<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>園城寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onjo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>山号 長等山（ながらさん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple: Mt. Nagara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), is a title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple: Mt. Nagara</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;), is a title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple: Nagarasan</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宗派 天台寺門宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigous school: Tendaijimon sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resigous school: Tendaijimon sect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious school: Tendaijimon sect</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>寺格 総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikaku (status of a Buddhist temple): Sohonzan (grand head temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikaku (status of a Buddhist temple): Sohonzan (grand head temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikaku (status of a Buddhist temple): Sohonzan (grand head temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本尊 弥勒菩薩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple): Miroku Bosatsu (Maitreya Bodhisattva)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple): Miroku Bosatsu (Maitreya Bodhisattva)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzon (principal image of Buddha): Miroku Bosatsu (Maitreya Bodhisattva)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>創建年 7世紀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Year of the foundation: In the seventh century</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founded: In the seventh century</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founded: In the seventh century</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>開基 大友与多王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding): Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding): Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding): Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>正式名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A formal name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A formal name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A formal name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>別称 三井寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name: Mii-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name: Mii-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name: Mii-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>札所等 西国三十三箇所14番西国薬師四十九霊場48番（別所・水観寺）近江三十三観音5番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) and so on: Stamp office for temple number 14 of the Saigoku Sanjusankasho (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage), Stamp office for temple number 48 of the Saigoku Yakushi 49 sacred places (Bessho (remote religious facilities from main temple facilities: Suikan-ji Temple), Stamp office for temple number 5 of the Omi 33 Kannon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) and so on: Stamp office for temple number 14 of the Saigoku Sanjusankasho (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage), Stamp office for temple number 48 of the Saigoku Yakushi 49 sacred places (Bessho (remote religious facilities from main temple facilities: Suikan-ji Temple), Stamp office for temple number 5 of the Omi 33 Kannon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) and so on: Stamp office for temple number 14 of the Saigoku Sanjusankasho (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage), Stamp office for temple number 48 of the Saigoku Yakushi 48 sacred places (Bessho (remote religious facilities from main temple facilities: Suikan-ji Temple), Stamp office for temple number 5 of the Omi 33 Kannon</e>
<cmt>数字修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>文化財 金堂、絹本著色不動明王像（黄不動）他8件（国宝）梵鐘他（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural properties: Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo (color painting of the God of Fire colored on silk) (Kifudo painting) and eight other works (National Treasures), and bonsho and other works (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural properties: Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo (color painting of the God of Fire colored on silk) (Kifudo painting) and eight other works (National Treasures), and bonsho and other works (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties: Kon-do Hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple), Kenbon Chakushoku Fudo Myoo zo (color painting on silk of the God of Fire) (Kifudo painting) and eight other works (National Treasures), and bonsho and other works (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>園城寺（おんじょうじ）は、滋賀県大津市にある、天台寺門宗の総本山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple is the head temple of the Tendaijimon Buddhist sect in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onjo-ji Temple is the head temple of the Tendaijimon Buddhist sect in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple is the head temple of the Tendaijimon Buddhist sect in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>山号を「長等山（ながらさん）」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sago is referred to &apos;Mt. Nagara&apos; (Nagarasan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sago is referred to as &apos;Mt. Nagara&apos; (Nagarasan).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sango is referred to as &apos;Nagarasan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>開基（創立者）は大友与多王、本尊は弥勒菩薩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding) is Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi, and honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) is Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding) is Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi, and honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) is Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding) is Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi, and honzon (principal image of Buddha) is Miroku Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>日本三不動の一である黄不動で著名な寺院で、観音堂は西国三十三箇所観音霊場の第14番札所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple is famous of its Kifudo painting which is one of the three most famous fudos in Japan, and its Kannon-do Hall (a temple dedicated to Kannon) is stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku Sanjyusankasho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple is famous of its Kifudo painting which is one of the three most famous fudos in Japan, and its Kannon-do Hall (a temple dedicated to Kannon) is the stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku Sanjyusankasho.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple is famous of its Kifudo painting which is one of the three most famous fudos in Japan, and its Kannon-do Hall (a temple dedicated to Kannon) is the stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku Sanjusankasho.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、近江八景の一つである「三井の晩鐘」でも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is well known for &apos;Mii no bansho&apos; (the evening bell at Mii-dera Temple) which is one of the Omi Hakkei (Eight Views of Omi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is well known for its &apos;Mii no bansho&apos; (the evening bell at Mii-dera Temple) which is one of the Omi Hakkei (Eight Views of Omi).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is well known for its &apos;Mii no bansho&apos; (the evening bell at Mii-dera Temple) which is one of the Omi Hakkei (Eight Views of Omi).</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお一般には「三井寺（みいでら）」として知られるため、本文では「三井寺」の呼称を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the name of &apos;Mii-dera Temple&apos; is used in this article, as it is generally known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the name used in this article, &apos;Mii-dera Temple,&apos; is its general name.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the name used in this article, &apos;Mii-dera Temple,&apos; is its general name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>三井寺は7世紀に大友氏の氏寺として草創され、9世紀に唐から帰国した留学僧円珍（天台寺門宗宗祖）によって再興された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple was firstly established as a Uji-dera Temple (temple built for praying clan&apos;s glory) in the 7th century, then restored in the 9th century by Enchin, ryugakuso (a priest who studied abroad), who had returned from Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mii-dera Temple was first established as a Uji-dera Temple (temple built for praying clan&apos;s glory) in the 7th century, then restored in the 9th century by Enchin, ryugakuso (a priest who studied abroad), who returned from Tang.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple was first established as a Uji-dera Temple (temple built for praying clan&apos;s glory) of Ouchi clan in the 7th century, then restored in the 9th century by Enchin, ryugakuso (a priest who studied abroad), who returned from Tang.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>三井寺は平安時代以降、皇室、貴族、武家などの幅広い信仰を集めて栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple had flourished by obtaining religious belief from wide range of classes including Imperial family, nobles, samurais, and so on since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mii-dera Temple flourished by obtaining followers from a wide range of classes including the Imperial family, nobles, samurai, and so on since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple flourished by obtaining followers from a wide range of classes including the Imperial Family, nobles, samurai, and so on since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、10世紀頃から比叡山延暦寺との対立抗争が激化し、比叡山の宗徒によって三井寺が焼き討ちされることが史上たびたびあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, confrontation with Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei-zan became intensified from around 10th century, and historically, Mii-dera Temple had been attacked and burned by devotees of Mt. Hiei-zan for several times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, conflicts with the Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei-zan intensified around the 10th century, and historically, Mii-dera Temple was attacked and burned by devotees of Mt. Hiei-zan several times.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, conflicts with the Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei intensified around the 10th century, and historically, Mii-dera Temple was attacked and burned by devotees of Mt. Hiei several times.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>近世には豊臣秀吉によって寺領を没収されて廃寺同然となったこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also once became virtually an abolished temple in early-modern times due to confiscation of its jiryo (temple estate) by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was once virtually an abolished temple in early-modern times due to its jiryo (temple estate) having been confiscated by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was once virtually an abolished temple in early-modern times due to its jiryo (temple estate) having been confiscated by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、こうした歴史上の苦難を乗り越えてその都度再興されてきたことから、三井寺は「不死鳥の寺」と称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Mii-dera Temple has been survived all these historical crises and restored every time, it is called &apos;Phoenix temple&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Mii-dera Temple has been survived all these historical crises and restored every time, it is called &apos;Phoenix temple&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Mii-dera Temple has been survived all these historical crises and restored every time, it is called &apos;Phoenix temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>三井寺の起源については、次のように伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the origin of Mii-dera Temple, there is the following tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the origin of Mii-dera Temple, there is the following tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the origin of Mii-dera Temple, there is the following tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大津京を造営した天智天皇は、念持仏の弥勒菩薩像を本尊とする寺を建立しようとしていたが、生前にはその志を果たせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Tenchi, who established Otsu-kyo, wanted to establish a temple of which honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) was statue of Miroku-bosatsu (Maitreya-bodhisattva), however, he could not accomplish his wish during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Tenchi, who established Otsu-kyo, wanted to establish a temple of which the honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) was the statue of Miroku-bosatsu (Maitreya-bodhisattva), however, he could not accomplish his wish during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Tenchi, who established Otsu-kyo, wanted to establish a temple of which the honzon was the statue of Miroku-bosatsu (Maitreya-bodhisattva), however, he could not accomplish his wish during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>(principal object of worship at a temple)既出のため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>天皇の子の大友皇子（弘文天皇）も壬申の乱のため、25歳の若さで没している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor&apos;s child, Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun) also died at an early age of 25 in Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor&apos;s child, Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun) also died at the early age of 25 in the Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor&apos;s child, Prince Otomo (Emperor Kobun) also died at the early age of 25 in the Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>大友皇子の子である大友与多王は、父の菩提のため、天智天皇所持の弥勒像を本尊とする寺の建立を発願した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi, who was a child of Prince Otomo, wished to build a temple for his father&apos;s bodai (pray to Buddha for the happiness of the dead) with Miroku-bosatsu-zo of the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi, who was a child of Prince Otomo, wished to build a temple for his father&apos;s bodai (pray to Buddha for the happiness of the dead) with Miroku-bosatsu-zo of the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi, who was a child of Prince Otomo, wished to build a temple for his father&apos;s bodai (pray to Buddha for the happiness of the dead) with Miroku-bosatsu statue of the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>壬申の乱で大友皇子と敵対していた天武天皇は、朱鳥元年（686年）この寺の建立を許可し、「園城寺」の寺号を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Tenmu, who was an enemy of Prince Otomo at Jinshin War, approved the restoration of this temple in 686 and named the temple &apos;Onjo-ji Temple&apos; as jigo (literally, &quot;temple name&quot;, which is the title given to a Buddhist temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Tenmu, who was an enemy of Prince Otomo at Jinshin War, approved the restoration of this temple in 686 and named the temple &apos;Onjo-ji Temple&apos; as jigo (literally, &quot;temple name&quot;, which is the title given to a Buddhist temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Tenmu, who was an enemy of Prince Otomo at Jinshin War, approved the restoration of this temple in 686 and named the temple &apos;Onjo-ji Temple&apos; as jigo (literally, &quot;temple name&quot;, which is the title given to a Buddhist temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>「園城」という寺号は、大友与多王が自分の「荘園城邑」（「田畑屋敷」）を投げ打って一寺を建立しようとする志に感じて名付けたものという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jigo &apos;Onjo&apos; was named by the Emperor Tenmu who was deeply impressed by the aspiration of Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi to establish a temple at the cost of his &apos;Shoen-jyoyu&apos; (a private estate and a castle)</e>
<cmt>文中に天武天皇は入っていませんが、「志に感じて」の主語は天武天皇であり、入れた方が訳しやすいので the Emperor Tenmu　が訳文に入っています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jigo &apos;Onjo&apos; was named by the Emperor Tenmu who was deeply impressed by the aspiration of Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi to establish a temple at the cost of his &apos;Shoen-jyoyu&apos; (a private estate and a castle)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jigo &apos;Onjo&apos; was named by the Emperor Tenmu who was deeply impressed by the aspiration of Otomo-no-Yota-no-Okimi to establish a temple at the cost of his &apos;Shoen-joyu&apos; (a private estate and a castle).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>なお、「三井寺」の通称は、この寺に涌く霊泉が天智・天武・持統の3代の天皇の産湯として使われたことから「御井」（みい）の寺と言われていたものが転じて三井寺となったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, it is said that the popular name of &apos;Mitsui-dera Temple&apos; was derived from a temple of &apos;Mii&apos; (a spring water for Emperors), because the sacred spring water was used for ubuyu (a baby&apos;s first bath) for three generations of emperors of the Emperor Tenchi, the Emperor Tenmu and the Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, it is said that the popular name of &apos;Mitsui-dera Temple&apos; was derived from a temple of &apos;Mii&apos; (a spring water for Emperors), because the sacred spring water was used for ubuyu (a baby&apos;s first bath) for three generations of emperors: Emperor Tenchi, the Emperor Tenmu and the Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, it is said that the popular name of &apos;Mitsui-dera Temple&apos; was derived from a temple of &apos;Mii&apos; (a spring water for Emperors), because the sacred spring water was used for ubuyu (a baby&apos;s first bath) for three generations of emperors: Emperor Tenchi, the Emperor Tenmu and the Empress Jito.</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>現在の三井寺には創建時にさかのぼる遺物はほとんど残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is almost no relic left which dated back to the time of its establishment in the current Mitsui-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is almost no relic left which dates back to the time of its establishment in the current Mitsui-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is almost no relic left which dates back to the time of its establishment in the current Mitsui-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、金堂付近からは、奈良時代前期にさかのぼる古瓦が出土しており、大友氏と寺との関係も史料から裏付けられることから、以上の草創伝承は単なる伝説ではなく、ある程度史実を反映したものと見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because old roof-tiles dated back to the early Nara period were excavated from the area around Kon-do Hall, and also relationship between Otomo clan and the temple is supported by historical material, it is possible to consider that the tradition about inauguration which described above is not just a legend but a story in which historical fact were reflected to some extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because old roof-tiles dating back to the early Nara period were excavated from the area around Kon-do Hall, and the fact that the relationship between Otomo clan and the temple is supported by historical material, it is possible to consider that the inauguration traditioin described above is not just a legend but a story in which historical fact was reflected to some extent.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because old roof-tiles dating back to the early Nara period were excavated from the area around Kon-do Hall, and the fact that the relationship between Otomo clan and the temple is supported by historical material, it is possible to consider that the inauguration tradition described above is not just a legend but a story in which historical fact was reflected to some extent.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>三井寺では、他宗で「管長」「別当」などと呼ばれる、一山を代表する僧のことを「長吏」（ちょうり）と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Mii-dera Temple, a representative priest of Issan is called &apos;chori&apos; (a chief administrator), whereas the post is called &apos;kantyo&quot; (a chief abbot) or &apos;betto&apos; (administrator of a Buddhist temple) in other temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Mii-dera Temple, a representative priest of Issan is called &apos;chori&apos; (a chief administrator), whereas the post is called &apos;kantyo&quot; (a chief abbot) or &apos;betto&apos; (administrator of a Buddhist temple) in other temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Mii-dera Temple, a representative priest of Issan is called &apos;chori&apos; (a chief administrator), whereas the post is called &apos;kancho&quot; (a chief abbot) or &apos;betto&apos; (administrator of a Buddhist temple) in other temples.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>貞観 (日本)元年（859年）、三井寺初代長吏に就任し、その後の三井寺の発展の基礎を築いたのが、智証大師円珍である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first chori of Mii-dera Temple was Chisho Daishi Enchin (859), who established a basis of development of Mii-dera Temple thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first chori of Mii-dera Temple was Chisho Daishi Enchin (859), who established the basis for the development of Mii-dera Temple thereafter.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first chori of Mii-dera Temple was Chisho Daishi Enchin (859), who established the basis for the development of Mii-dera Temple thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>円珍は、弘仁5年（814年）、讃岐国那珂郡（香川県善通寺市）に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enchin was born in Naka County, Sanuki Province (Zentsuji City, Kagawa Prefecture) in 814.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enchin was born in Naka County, Sanuki Province (Zentsuji City, Kagawa Prefecture) in 814.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enchin was born in Naka County, Sanuki Province (Zentsuji City, Kagawa Prefecture) in 814.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>俗名は和気広雄、母方の姓は佐伯氏で、円珍の母は弘法大師空海の姪にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His secular name was Hiroo WAKE and his mother, a Saeki clan, was a niece of Kobo-Daishi Kukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His secular name was Hiroo WAKE and his mother, a Saeki clan, was a niece of Kobo-Daishi Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His secular name was Hiroo WAKE and his mother, a Saeki clan, was a niece of Kobo-Daishi Kukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>幼時から学才を発揮し神童と呼ばれた広雄は、15歳で比叡山に登り、初代天台座主（てんだいざす）義真に入門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroo, gifted with academic ability from early age, was called a prodigy, and ascended Mt. Hiei at the age of 15 and joined the first Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Dendai sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroo, gifted with academic ability from an early age, was called a prodigy, and ascended Mt. Hiei at the age of 15 and joined the first Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Dendai sect).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroo, gifted with academic ability from an early age, was called a prodigy, and ascended Mt. Hiei at the age of 15 and joined the first Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>19歳の時に国家公認の正規の僧となり、円珍と改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At age 19, he became a priest officially recognized by the state, and changed his name to Enchin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At age 19, he became a priest officially recognized by the state, and changed his name to Enchin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At age 19, he became a priest officially recognized by the state, and changed his name to Enchin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その後、比叡山の規定に従って「十二年籠山行」（12年間、比叡山から下りずにひたすら修行する）を終えた後、大峯山や熊野三山をめぐって厳しい修行をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, following accomplishment of &apos;Jyuni-nen-rozangyo&apos; (ascetic practices without descending Mt. Hiei for twelve years) according to the rule of Mt. Hiei, he did ascetic practices at Mt. Omine and Kumano sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha).</e>
<cmt>十二年籠山行：意訳併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, following accomplishment of &apos;Jyuni-nen-rozangyo&apos; (ascetic practices without descending Mt. Hiei for twelve years) according to the rules of Mt. Hiei, he did ascetic practices at Mt. Omine and Kumano sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, following accomplishment of &apos;Juni-nen-rozangyo&apos; (ascetic practices without descending Mt. Hiei for twelve years) according to the rules of Mt. Hiei, he did ascetic practices at Mt. Omine and Kumano sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-Taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-Taisha and Kumano-Nachi-Taisha).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>このことから三井寺は修験道とも深いつながりを持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, Mii-dera Temple is deeply connected with Shugendo (Japanese ascetic and shamanistic practice in mountainous sites).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Mii-dera Temple is deeply connected with Shugendo (Japanese ascetic and shamanistic practice in mountainous sites).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Mii-dera Temple is deeply connected with Shugendo (Japanese ascetic and shamanistic practice in mountainous sites).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>仁寿3年（853年）には唐へ留学して6年間、各地で修行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Tang in 853 to study and trained himself in various places for six years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Tang in 853 to study and trained himself in various places for six years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Tang in 853 to study and trained himself in various places for six years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>青龍寺の法全（はっせん）から密教の奥義を伝授された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received instruction of esoteric point of Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) from Hassen of Seiryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received instruction on the esoteric points of Mikkyo (Esoteric Buddhism) from Hassen of Seiryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received instruction on the esoteric points of Esoteric Buddhism from Hassen of Seiryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>天安 (日本)2年（858年）、円珍は多くの経巻、図像、法具を携えて日本へ帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enchin returned to Japan in 858 with many scriptures, iconographies and hogu (Buddhist instruments).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enchin returned to Japan in 858 with many scriptures, iconographies and hogu (Buddhist instruments).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enchin returned to Japan in 858 with many scriptures, iconographies and hogu (Buddhist instruments).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>翌貞観元年（859年）、大友氏の氏寺であった三井寺に「唐院」（とういん）を設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year (859), he established &apos;To-in&apos; at Mii-dera Temple, Uji-dera Temple (a temple for praying clan&apos;s glory) of Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year (859), he established &apos;To-in&apos; at Mii-dera Temple, Uji-dera Temple (a temple for praying clan&apos;s glory) of Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year (859), he established &apos;To-in&apos; at Mii-dera Temple, Uji-dera Temple (a temple for praying clan&apos;s glory) of Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>寺を整備して修行の道場とするとともに、唐から請来した経典や法具を唐院に収蔵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He stored Buddhist scriptures and hogu, which he brought from Tang, in To-in, along with preparing it for the use of ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He stored Buddhist scriptures and hogu, which he brought from Tang, in To-in, and prepared them for use in ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He stored Buddhist scriptures and hogu, which he brought from Tang, in To-in, and prepared them for use in ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>貞観8年（866年）、太政官から円珍に伝法の公験（くげん、証明書）が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 866, he was awarded kugen (official documents) from Dajyokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 866, he was awarded kugen (official documents) from Dajyokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 866, he was awarded kugen (official documents) of Enchin&apos;s denpo (teachings) from Dajokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>顕教、密教に加えて修験道を兼学する円珍の伝法は、これによって政府の公認を得たわけであり、天台寺門宗ではこの時をもって開宗とみなしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enchin&apos;s denpo, which was combined with Mikkyo and Shugendo (Japanese ascetic and shamanistic practice in mountainous sites), had obtained official recognition by kugen, and that occasion is considered to be the foundation of the Sect by Tendaijimon sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enchin&apos;s denpo, which was combined with Mikkyo and Shugendo (Japanese ascetic and shamanistic practice in mountainous sites), had obtained official recognition by kugen, and that occasion is considered to be the foundation of the Sect by the Tendaijimon sect.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enchin&apos;s denpo, which was combined with Esoteric Buddhism and Shugendo (Japanese ascetic and shamanistic practice in mountainous sites), had obtained official recognition by kugen, and that occasion is considered to be the foundation of the Sect by the Tendaijimon sect.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>貞観10年（868年）、円珍は天台宗最高の地位である天台座主に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enchin was inaugurated as zasu (temple&apos;s head priest),the highest status of the Tendai sect, in 868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enchin was inaugurated as zasu (temple&apos;s head priest),the highest status of the Tendai sect, in 868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enchin was inaugurated as zasu (temple&apos;s head priest), the highest status of the Tendai sect, in 868.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>以後、没するまでの24年間、その地位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he had kept the post for 24 years until he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, he kept the post for 24 years until his death.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, he kept the post for 24 years until his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>円珍の没後、比叡山は円珍の門流と、慈覚大師円仁の門流との2派に分かれ、両者は事あるごとに対立するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Enchin died, Mt. Hiei was diverted into two branch groups of Enchin mon-ryu (school of a sect) and Jikaku Daishi Ennin mon-ryu, and two groups began to conflict whenever occasion arose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Enchin died, Mt. Hiei was diverted into two branch groups of Enchin mon-ryu (school of a sect) and Jikaku Daishi Ennin mon-ryu, and the two groups came into conflict whenever the occasion arose.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Enchin died, Mt. Hiei was diverted into two branch groups of Enchin school and Jikaku Daishi Ennin school, and the two groups came into conflict whenever the occasion arose.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>円珍の没後1世紀あまりを経た正暦4年（993年）には、円仁派の僧たちが比叡山内にあった円珍派の房舎を打ち壊す騒動があり、両派の対立は決定的となり、円珍派は比叡山を下りて、三井寺に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 993, about a century after Enchin died, there was a commotion that priests of Ennin-ha (the sect of Ennin) had demolished temple&apos;s quarters of Enchin-ha (the sect of Enchin) located in the area of Mt. Hiei, by this event, the confrontation between the two became conclusive and Enchin-ha descended Mt. Hiei and moved to Mii-derat Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 993, about a century after Enchin died, there was a commotion that priests of Ennin-ha (the sect of Ennin) had demolished the temple&apos;s quarters of Enchin-ha (the sect of Enchin) located in the area of Mt. Hiei, which cemented the conflict between the two, and Enchin-ha descended Mt. Hiei and moved to Mii-derat Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 993, about a century after Enchin died, there was a commotion that priests of Ennin school had demolished the temple&apos;s quarters of Enchin school located in the area of Mt. Hiei, which cemented the conflict between the two, and Enchin school descended Mt. Hiei and moved to Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>比叡山延暦寺を「山門」と別称するのに対し三井寺を「寺門」と称することから、両者の対立抗争を「山門寺門の抗争」などと呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei is called &apos;Sanmon gate&apos; whereas Mii-dera Temple is called &apos;Jimon,&apos; confrontation between them is called &apos;Sanmon-Jimon battle&apos; and the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei is called &apos;Sanmon gate&apos; whereas Mii-dera Temple is called &apos;Jimon,&apos; the conflict between them was termed &apos;Sanmon-Jimon battle&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei is called &apos;Sanmon gate&apos; whereas Mii-dera Temple is called &apos;Jimon,&apos; the conflict between them was termed &apos;Sanmon-Jimon battle&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>比叡山宗徒による三井寺の焼き討ちは永保元年（1081年）をはじめ、中世末期までに大規模なものだけで10回、小規模なものまで含めると50回にも上るという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the end of mediaeval period, the number of major attacking and burning such as the one in 1081 by devotees of Mt. Hiei to Mii-dera Temple reached 10, and the number reaches some 50 if minor ones are included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the end of the mediaeval period, roughly 10 major attacks and burnings such as the one in 1081 by devotees of Mt. Hiei to Mii-dera Temple took place, with the number reaching 50 if one countes all minor skirmishes as well.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the end of the mediaeval period, roughly 10 major attacks and burnings such as the one in 1081 by devotees of Mt. Hiei to Mii-dera Temple took place, with the number reaching 50 if one counts all minor skirmishes as well.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="52">
<j>三井寺は、平安時代には朝廷や貴族の尊崇を集め、中でも藤原道長、白河天皇らが深く帰依したことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple obtained adoration from Imperial Court and nobles during the Heian period, and it is well known that FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the Emperor Shirakawa were especially deeply devoted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mii-dera Temple was adored by the Imperial Court and nobles during the Heian period, and it is well known that FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the Emperor Shirakawa were especially deeply devoted.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple was adored by the Imperial Court and nobles during the Heian period, and it is well known that FUJIWARA no Michinaga and the Emperor Shirakawa were especially deeply devoted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>中世以降は源氏など武家の信仰も集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the medieval period, it obtained faith from samurai including Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the medieval period, samurai including Minamoto clan also became devotees.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the medieval period, samurai including Minamoto clan also became devotees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>源氏は、源頼義が三井寺に戦勝祈願をしたことから歴代の尊崇が篤く、源頼政が平家打倒の兵を挙げた時にはこれに協力し、平家を滅ぼした源頼朝も当寺に保護を加えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive Minamoto clan had paid adoration to Mii-dera Temple from the fact MINAMONO no Yoriyoshi had been prayed for victory to the temple, and the temple cooperated when MINAMOTO no Yorimasa raised an army to defeat the Taira family and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who defeated the Taira family protected the temple in return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive Minamoto clans had paid adoration to Mii-dera Temple from the fact MINAMONO no Yoriyoshi had been prayed for victory to the temple, and the temple cooperated when MINAMOTO no Yorimasa raised an army to defeat the Taira family and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who defeated the Taira family protected the temple in return.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Successive Minamoto clans had paid adoration to Mii-dera Temple from the fact MINAMONO no Yoriyoshi had been prayed for victory to the temple,&quot; doesn&apos;t make sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive Minamoto clans had paid adoration to Mii-dera Temple from the fact MINAMONO no Yoriyoshi had been prayed for victory to the temple, and the temple cooperated when MINAMOTO no Yorimasa raised an army to defeat the Taira family and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who defeated the Taira family protected the temple in return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>頼朝の意思を継いだ北条政子もこの方針を継承し、建保元年（1214年）に延暦寺に焼き払われた園城寺を大内惟義・佐々木広綱・宇都宮蓮生ら在京の御家人に命じて直ちに再建させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after Masako HOJO succeeded Yoritomo, she also followed this policy and ordered gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo period, including Koreyoshi OUCHI, Hirotsuna SASAKI, Rensho UTSUNOMIYA and so on in Kyoto, to restore Onjo-ji Temple which had been burned down by Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after Masako HOJO succeeded Yoritomo, she also followed this policy and ordered gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo period, including Koreyoshi OUCHI, Hirotsuna SASAKI, Rensho UTSUNOMIYA and so on in Kyoto, to restore Onjo-ji Temple which had been burned down by Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after Masako HOJO succeeded Yoritomo, she also followed this policy and ordered gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo period), including Koreyoshi OUCHI, Hirotsuna SASAKI, Rensho UTSUNOMIYA and so on in Kyoto, to restore Onjo-ji Temple which had been burned down by Enryaku-ji Temple in 1214.</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。)補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>しかし、園城寺で僧侶として育てられていた源頼家の子公暁が叔父である源実朝を暗殺するという事件を起こしたために、以後鎌倉幕府より一時冷遇を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Onjo-ji Temple had been temporarily received a cold treatment since Kugyo, a child of MINAMOTO no Yoriie and a priest raised at the temple, assassinated his uncle MINOMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Onjo-ji Temple temporarily received cold treatment since Kugyo, a child of MINAMOTO no Yoriie and a priest raised at the temple, assassinated his uncle MINOMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Onjo-ji Temple temporarily received cold treatment since Kugyo, a child of MINAMOTO no Yoriie and a priest raised at the temple, assassinated his uncle MINAMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>だが、北条時頼の信頼が厚かった隆弁が別当に就任すると再興され、続く南北朝の内乱でも北朝_(日本)・足利氏を支持したことから、室町幕府の保護を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Ryuben, who had been deeply trusted by Tokiyori HOJO, assumed betto (the head priest), Mii-dera Tmple was restored and, also was protected from the Muromach bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a return for supporting Ashikaga clan of the Northern Dynasty (Japan) during the successive domestic disturbance of Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Ryuben, who had been deeply trusted by Tokiyori HOJO, assumed betto (the head priest), Mii-dera Tmple was restored and, also was protected from the Muromach bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a return for supporting Ashikaga clan of the Northern Dynasty (Japan) during the successive domestic disturbance in the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Ryuben, who had been deeply trusted by Tokiyori HOJO, assumed betto (the head priest), Mii-dera Temple was restored and, also was protected from the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a return for supporting Ashikaga clan of the Northern Court (Japan) during the successive domestic disturbance in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>両幕府のこの厚遇は、強力な権門である延暦寺の勢力を牽制するために園城寺に対して一定の支援をすることが必要であると考えられていたからだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed those handsome treatment for Onjo-ji Temple from both bakufus resulted from the idea that a certain support was necessary to restrict Enryaku-ji Temple as kenmon (an influential family) with great power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the handsome treatment for the Onjo-ji Temple from both bakufus resulted from the idea that a certain support was necessary to restrict Enryaku-ji Temple from being kenmon (an influential family) with great power.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the handsome treatment for the Onjo-ji Temple from both bakufus resulted from the idea that a certain support was necessary to restrict Enryaku-ji Temple from being kenmon (an influential family) with great power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）、三井寺は豊臣秀吉の怒りに触れ、欠所（寺領の没収、事実上の廃寺）を命じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1595, because Mii-dera Temple offended Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, it received kessho (confiscation of jiryo [temple estate], actual abolishment of a temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1595, because Mii-dera Temple offended Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, it received kessho (confiscation of jiryo [temple estate], actual abolishment of a temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1595, because Mii-dera Temple offended Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, it received kessho (confiscation of jiryo (temple estate), actual abolishment of a temple).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>三井寺が何によって秀吉の怒りを買ったものかは諸説あって定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there are various theories about what made Hideyoshi angry against Mii-dera Temple, it cannot be determined to one theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there are various theories about what angered Hideyoshi, no one theory has been established.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there are various theories about what angered Hideyoshi, no one theory has been established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>この結果、三井寺の本尊や宝物は他所へ移され、金堂をはじめとする堂宇も強制的に移築された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) and other treasures were removed to other places, and temple buildings including Kon-do Hall were also forced to be relocated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) and other treasures were removed to other places, and temple buildings including Kon-do Hall were also forced to be relocated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, honzon (principal image of Buddha) and other treasures were removed to other places, and temple buildings including Kon-do Hall were also forced to be relocated.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>当時の三井寺金堂は比叡山に移され、延暦寺転法輪堂（釈迦堂）として現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kon-do Hall of Mii-dera Temple in those days were relocated to Mt. Hiei and it is existing as Enryaku-ji Temple Tenborin-do (Shaka-do Hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kon-do Hall of Mii-dera Temple was relocated to Mt. Hiei and today exists as Enryaku-ji Temple Tenborin-do (Shaka-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kon-do Hall of Mii-dera Temple was relocated to Mt. Hiei and today exists as Enryaku-ji Temple Tenborin-do (Shaka-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）、秀吉は自らの死の直前になって三井寺の再興を許可している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1598, just before his death, Hideyoshi approved restoration of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1598, just before his death, Hideyoshi approved restoration of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1598, just before his death, Hideyoshi approved restoration of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これは死期を悟った秀吉が、霊験あらたかな三井寺の祟りを恐れたためとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi feared the curse of Mii-dera Temple with miraculous virtue when he realized time of his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hideyoshi feared the curse of Mii-dera Temple with miraculous virtue when he realized time of his death.</e>
<cmt>Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi feared the curse of Mii-dera Temple with miraculous virtue when he realized time of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>秀吉の再興許可を受け、当時の三井寺長吏・道澄が中心となって寺の再興が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With restoration approval by Hideyoshi, Docho, chori (chief priest) of Mii-dera Temple at that time, proceeded the restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With restoration approved by Hideyoshi, Docho, chori (chief priest) of Mii-dera Temple at the time, proceeded with the restoration.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With restoration approved by Hideyoshi, Docho, chori (chief priest) of Mii-dera Temple at the time, proceeded with the restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>現在の三井寺の寺観は、ほぼこの頃に整えられたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikan of the present Mii-dera Temple was almost prepared in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikan of the present Mii-dera Temple was almost completely prepared in those days.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikan of the present Mii-dera Temple was almost completely prepared in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="67">
<j>明治維新後は天台宗寺門派を名乗っていたが、1946年以降は天台寺門宗総本山となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the temple had been under the name of the Jimon School of the Tendai Sect since Meiji Restoration, it became Sohonzan of Tendaijimon sect from 1946.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the temple had been under the name of the Jimon School of the Tendai Sect since Meiji Restoration, it was changed to the Sohonzan of Tendaijimon sect from 1946.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the temple had been under the name of the Jimon School of the Tendai Sect since Meiji Restoration, it was changed to the Sohonzan of Tendaijimon sect from 1946.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>伽藍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Garan (Buddhist tempe)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Garan (Buddhist tempe)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Garan (Buddhist temple)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>大門（重文）－仁王門とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimon-gate (the great outer gate) (Important Cultural Property): It is called Nio-mon gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimon-gate (the great outer gate) (Important Cultural Property): It is called Nio-mon gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimon-gate (the great outer gate) (Important Cultural Property): It is called Nio-mon gate.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>入母屋造の楼門（2階建ての門で、下層と上層の境には屋根の出をつくらないもの）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Romon (two-story gate) of irimoya-zukuri (building with a half-hipped roof) (Two-story gate without half-hipped roof between upper and lower stratums.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Romon (two-story gate) of irimoya-zukuri (building with a half-hipped roof) (Two-story gate without half-hipped roof between upper and lower stratums.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Romon (two-story gate) of irimoya-zukuri (building with a half-hipped roof) (Two-story gate without half-hipped roof between upper and lower stratums.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>もと近江の常楽寺（滋賀県湖南市）にあった門を慶長6年（1601年）、徳川家康が寄進したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a gate donated by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in 1601, which was originally located at Joraku-ji Temple in Omi Province (Konan City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was is a gate donated by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in 1601, which was originally located at Joraku-ji Temple in Omi Province (Konan City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was is a gate donated by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in 1601, which was originally located at Joraku-ji Temple in Omi Province (Konan City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>墨書銘等から室町時代の宝徳3年（1451年）の建立と推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed to have been erected in 1451 according to its bukushomei (ink inscriptions) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed to have been erected in 1451 according to its bukushomei (ink inscriptions) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed to have been erected in 1451 according to its bokushomei (ink inscriptions) and so on.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>釈迦堂（重文）－大門を入って金堂に至る道の右側にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka-do Hall (Important Cultural Property): It&apos;s on the right side on the way to Kon-do Hall after entering Daimon-gate (the great outer gate)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka-do Hall (Important Cultural Property): It&apos;s on the right side on the way to Kon-do Hall after entering Daimon-gate (the great outer gate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka-do Hall (Important Cultural Property): It&apos;s on the right side on the way to Kon-do Hall after entering Daimon-gate (the great outer gate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>天正年間（16世紀末）造営の御所清涼殿を下賜され移築したものと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Seiryoden (Literally &quot;Limpid Cool Hall,&quot; an imperial summer palace) constructed in the end of 16th century, and relocated an reconstructed after being granted as an Imperial gift.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Seiryoden (Literally &quot;Limpid Cool Hall,&quot; an imperial summer palace) that was constructed in the end of the 16th century, was relocated and reconstructed after being granted as an Imperial gift.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Seiryoden (Literally &quot;Limpid Cool Hall,&quot; an imperial summer palace) that was constructed in the end of the 16th century, was relocated and reconstructed after being granted as an Imperial gift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>金堂（国宝）－三井寺再興を許可した豊臣秀吉の遺志により、北政所が慶長4年（1599年）に再建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kon-do Hall (National Treasures): According to a will of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who approved restoration of Mii-dera Temple, it was restored by Kita no Mandokoro in 1599..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kon-do Hall (National Treasures): According to the will of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who approved restoration of Mii-dera Temple, it was restored by Kita no Mandokoro in 1599..</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kon-do Hall (National Treasures): According to the will of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who approved restoration of Mii-dera Temple, it was restored by Kita no Mandokoro in 1599.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>入母屋造、檜皮葺きの和様仏堂である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri is a Japanese style Buddhist temple with hiwadabuki (Japanese cypress bark thatch).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irimoya-zukuri is a Japanese style Buddhist temple with hiwadabuki (Japanese cypress bark thatch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri is a Japanese style Buddhist temple with hiwadabuki (Japanese cypress bark thatch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>鐘楼（重文）－金堂の左手前にあり、「三井の晩鐘」で知られる梵鐘を吊る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoro (bell twer) (Important Cultural Property): It is located in front of the left side of Kon-do Hall, in which bonsho (a Buddhist Temple bell) known as &apos;Mii no bansho&apos; (the evening bell at Mi) is being hung.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoro (bell twer) (Important Cultural Property): It is located in front of the left side of Kon-do Hall, in which bonsho (a Buddhist Temple bell) known as &apos;Mii no bansho&apos; (the evening bell at Mi) is hung.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoro (bell tower) (Important Cultural Property): It is located in front of the left side of Kon-do Hall, in which bonsho (a Buddhist Temple bell) known as &apos;Mii no bansho&apos; (the evening bell at Mii) is hung.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>この梵鐘は慶長7年（1602年）の鋳造で、平等院鐘、神護寺鐘とともに日本三名鐘に数えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This bonsho is founded in 1602 and is one of the three most famous bells in Japan, along with the ones of Byodoin Temple and Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This bonsho was founded in 1602 and is one of the three most famous bells in Japan, along with the ones of Byodoin Temple and Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This bonsho was founded in 1602 and is one of the three most famous bells in Japan, along with the ones of Byodoin Temple and Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="78">
<j>閼伽井屋（あかいや、重文）－金堂の西に接して建つ小堂で、慶長5年（1600年）、金堂と同じく北政所によって建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akaiya (Important Cultural Property): It is a small pagoda adjoining the left side of Kon-do Hall, which was erected in 1600 by Kita no Mandokoro as well as Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akaiya (Important Cultural Property): It is a small pagoda adjoining the left side of Kon-do Hall, which was erected in 1600 by Kita no Mandokoro as well as Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akaiya (Important Cultural Property): It is a small pagoda adjoining the left side of Kon-do Hall, which was erected in 1600 by Kita no Mandokoro as well as Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>堂内には三井寺の名の起こりとなった霊泉が湧出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a sacred fountain which is the origin of the name of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a sacred fountain which is the origin of the name of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a sacred fountain which is the origin of the name of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="80">
<j>一切経蔵（重文）－室町時代の建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issai Kyozo (Rinzo) (Important Cultural Property): Architecture during the Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issai Kyozo (Rinzo) (Important Cultural Property): Architecture during the Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issai Kyozo (Rinzo) (Important Cultural Property): Architecture during the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>毛利輝元の寄進により、慶長7年（1602年）、山口市の国清寺の経蔵を移築したものという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be Kyozo (sutra repository) of Kokusei-ji Temple in Yamaguchi City which was relocated and reconstructed in 1602 as a contribution of Terumoto MORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to be Kyozo (sutra repository) of Kokusei-ji Temple in Yamaguchi City which was relocated and reconstructed in 1602 as a contribution by Terumoto MORI.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to be Kyozo (sutra repository) of Kokusei-ji Temple in Yamaguchi City which was relocated and reconstructed in 1602 as a contribution by Terumoto MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>輪蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinzo (a warehouse to store Buddhist scriptures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinzo (a warehouse to store Buddhist scriptures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinzo (a warehouse to store Buddhist scriptures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="83">
<j>三重塔（重文）－鎌倉時代末期から室町時代初期の建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanju-no-to (three-story pagoda) (Important Cultural Property): An architecture from the end Kamakura period to the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanju-no-to (three-story pagoda) (Important Cultural Property): An architecture from the end of the Kamakura period to the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanju-no-to (three-story pagoda) (Important Cultural Property): An architecture from the end of the Kamakura period to the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>奈良県の比曽寺にあった塔を豊臣秀吉が伏見城に移築したものを、慶長6年（1601年）、徳川家康が再度移築させたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a pagoda of Hiso-ji Temple in Nara Prefecture which was firstly relocated and reconstructed to Fusimi-jo Castel by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, followed by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (1601).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a pagoda of Hiso-ji Temple in Nara Prefecture which was firstlrelocated and reconstructed in Fusimi-jo Castle by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, followed by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (1601).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a pagoda of Hiso-ji Temple in Nara Prefecture which was first relocated and reconstructed in Fushimi-jo Castle by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, followed by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (1601).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="85">
<j>唐院－灌頂堂（重文）、唐門（重文）、大師堂（重文）、長日護摩堂などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kara-mon gate: Kanjodo (The hall for holding the ceremony to pour holy water on the head of a monk) (Important Cultural Property), Kara-mon gate (Important Cultural Property), Daishi-do Hall (hall for the Great Teacher)(Important Cultural Property), 長日-goma-do Hall and so on.</e>
<cmt>長日読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kara-mon gate: Kanjodo (The hall for holding the ceremony to pour holy water on the head of a monk) (Important Cultural Property), Kara-mon gate (Important Cultural Property), Daishi-do Hall (hall for the Great Teacher)(Important Cultural Property), 長日-goma-do Hall and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kara-mon gate: Kanjodo (The hall for holding the ceremony to pour holy water on the head of a monk) (Important Cultural Property), Kara-mon gate (Important Cultural Property), Daishi-do Hall (hall for the Great Teacher) (Important Cultural Property), 長日-goma-do Hall and so on.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入しました。長日読み方不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>智証大師円珍が唐から帰国後、請来した経巻法具などを納めたところとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be the place where Chisho Daishi Enchin stored Buddhist scriptures, hogu and so on after he returned from Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to be where Chisho Daishi Enchin stored Buddhist scriptures, hogu and so on after he returned from Tang.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to be where Chisho Daishi Enchin stored Buddhist scriptures, hogu and so on after he returned from Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>現在は、宗祖円珍の廟所ならびに灌頂（密教の儀式）の道場として寺内でも最も重視されている区域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, this is the most important place in the temple precincts as byosho (mausoleum) of the founder Enchin and dojo (training hall) of kanjo (a consecration ceremony by pouring water onto the top of monk&apos;s head) (a ceremony of Mikkyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, this is the most important place in the temple precincts as byosho (mausoleum) of the founder Enchin and dojo (training hall) of kanjo (a consecration ceremony by pouring water onto the top of monk&apos;s head) (a ceremony of Mikkyo).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, this is the most important place in the temple precincts as byosho (mausoleum) of the founder Enchin and dojo (training hall) of kanjo (a consecration ceremony by pouring water onto the top of monk&apos;s head) (a ceremony of Esoteric Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="88">
<j>観音堂－寺域の南側、琵琶湖を望む高台に位置し、西国三十三箇所観音霊場の第14番札所として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannon-do Hall: It&apos;s located in the southern part of temple site and stands on high ground commanding a view of Lake Biwa, and it is known as stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku Sanjyusankasho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannon-do Hall: It&apos;s located in the southern part of temple site and stands on high ground, commanding a view of Lake Biwa, and it is known as the stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku Sanjyusankasho.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannon-do Hall: It&apos;s located in the southern part of temple site and stands on high ground, commanding a view of Lake Biwa, and it is known as the stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku Sanjusankasho.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>観音堂は元禄2年（1689年）に再建されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannon-do Hall was restored in 1689.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannon-do Hall was restored in 1689.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannon-do Hall was restored in 1689.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="90">
<j>毘沙門堂（重文）－観音堂の近くにある小堂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bishamon-do Temple (Important Cultural Property): It is a small pagoda nearby Kannon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bishamon-do Temple (Important Cultural Property): It is a small pagoda nearby Kannon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamon-do Temple (Important Cultural Property): It is a small pagoda nearby Kannon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>元和 (日本)2年（1616年）の建立と伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be erected in 1616.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have been erected in 1616.</e>
<cmt>Grannar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been erected in 1616.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="92">
<j>護法善神堂（千団子社）－三井寺の守護神である護法善神（鬼子母神）像を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goho zenjin (good dieties protecting dharma) (sen-dango-sha): It worships the statue of Goho zenjin (Kishimojin [Goddess of Children]), a guardian god of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goho zenjin (good dieties protecting dharma) (sen-dango-sha): The statue of Goho zenjin (Kishimojin [Goddess of Children]), a guardian god of Mii-dera Temple is worshiped here.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goho zenjin (good deities protecting dharma) (sen-dango-sha): The statue of Goho zenjin (Kishimojin (Goddess of Children)), a guardian god of Mii-dera Temple is worshiped here.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="93">
<j>新羅善神堂（しんらぜんじんどう、国宝）－三井寺の中心伽藍から北へ500メートルほど離れた場所にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall (National Treasures): It is located about 500meter north from the central Buddhist temple of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall (National Treasures): Located about 500 meter north from the central Buddhist temple of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall (National Treasures): Located about 500 meter north from the central Buddhist temple of Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>三井寺の鎮守神である新羅明神を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinra Myojin, a guardian god of Mii-dera Temple, is worshipped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinra Myojin, a guardian god of Mii-dera Temple, is worshipped.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinra Myojin, a guardian god of Mii-dera Temple, is worshipped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>「堂」と名が付くが、建築様式的には流造（ながれづくり）の神社本殿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the name contained &apos;do&apos; (hall), it is architecturally Honden (main shrine building) of Nagare-zukuri style (the front roof extends in a gentle curve into a projecting eave over the entrance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the name contained &apos;do&apos; (hall), it is architecturally Honden (main shrine building) of Nagare-zukuri style (the front roof extends in a gentle curve into a projecting eave over the entrance).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the name contained &apos;do&apos; (hall), it is architecturally Honden (main shrine building) of Nagare-zukuri style (the front roof extends in a gentle curve into a projecting eave over the entrance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>現存の建物は貞和3年（1347年）、足利尊氏の寄進によるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current structure was donated by Takauji ASHIKAGA in 1347.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current structure was donated by Takauji ASHIKAGA in 1347.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current structure was donated by Takauji ASHIKAGA in 1347.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>新羅明神は、唐に留学した円珍が日本へ帰国する際、船中に現われた神とされ、円珍に伝えられた経法を永遠に守護することを誓った神であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Shinra Myojin is a deity who appeared in the boat when Enchin returned to Japan after studying in Tang, and deity swore to safeguard the 経法 which had passed down to Enchin.</e>
<cmt>経法：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Shinra Myojin is a deity who appeared in the boat when Enchin returned to Japan after studying in Tang, and the deity swore to safeguard the 経法 which had passed down to Enchin.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Shinra Myojin is a deity who appeared in the boat when Enchin returned to Japan after studying in Tang, and the deity swore to safeguard the 経法 which had passed down to Enchin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>円珍が請来した経典法具を三井寺に保管することになったのも新羅明神の夢告によるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The storage of Buddhist scriptures and hogu of Enchin obtained from Tang was said to be decided by the oracle of Shinra Myojin in a dream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The storage of Buddhist scriptures and hogu of Enchin obtained from Tang was said to have been decided by the oracle of Shinra Myojin in a dream.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The storage of Buddhist scriptures and hogu of Enchin obtained from Tang was said to have been decided by the oracle of Shinra Myojin in a dream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>源頼義が三男の義光をこの神の前で元服させ、義光はそれ以来「新羅三郎」と呼ばれるようになったことはよく知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is well known that Yoshimitsu began to be called &apos;SHINRA Saburo&apos; after his father MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi celebrated his third son Yoshimitsu&apos;s genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) before this deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well known that Yoshimitsu began to be called &apos;SHINRA Saburo&apos; after his father MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi celebrated his third son Yoshimitsu&apos;s genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) before this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is well known that Yoshimitsu began to be called &apos;SHINRA Saburo&apos; after his father MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi celebrated his third son Yoshimitsu&apos;s genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) before this deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="100">
<j>勧学院客殿（国宝）－唐院の南隣に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakuin Kyakuden (guest hall) (National Treasures): It stands on the place adjoining the south side of To-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakuin Kyakuden (guest hall) (National Treasures): It stands on the place adjoining the south side of To-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakuin Kyakuden (guest hall) (National Treasures): It stands on the place adjoining the south side of To-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is erected in 1600.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was erected in 1600.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was erected in 1600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>桃山時代の書院造建築の代表作とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be a representative architecture of Shoin-zukuri style during the Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to represent architecture of the Shoin-zukuri style during the Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to represent architecture of the Shoin-zukuri style during the Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>障壁画は狩野光信を中心とする狩野派一門の作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shohekiga (paintings on the walls of fusuma of a building; pictures on partitions) is a work of Kano school sect led by Mitsunobu KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shohekiga (paintings on the walls of fusuma of a building; pictures on partitions) is a work of the Kano school sect led by Mitsunobu KANO.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shohekiga (paintings on the walls of fusuma of a building; pictures on partitions) is a work of the Kano school led by Mitsunobu KANO.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="104">
<j>光浄院客殿（国宝）－金堂の北方に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojoin Kyakuden (reception hall) (National Treasures): It stands on the place adjoining the north side of Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojoin Kyakuden (reception hall) (National Treasures): It stands on the place adjoining the north side of Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojoin Kyakuden (reception hall) (National Treasures): It stands on the place adjoining the north side of Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>勧学院客殿より1年あとの慶長6年（1601年）建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was erected in 1601 one year after the erection of Kangakuin Kyakuden (guest hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was erected in 1601 one year after the erection of Kangakuin Kyakuden (guest hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was erected in 1601 one year after the erection of Kangakuin Kyakuden (guest hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>規模、意匠など勧学院客殿と似る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It resembles Kangakuin Kyakuden in scale and design.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It resembles Kangakuin Kyakuden in scale and design.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It resembles Kangakuin Kyakuden in scale and design.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>障壁画はやはり狩野一門の作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shohekiga is also a work of Kano school sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shohekiga is also a work of the Kano school sect.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shohekiga is also a work of the Kano school.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="108">
<j>円満院－大門の北方（右）に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enman-in Temple: It stands in the north side (right) of Daimon-gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enman-in Temple: It stands in the north side (right) of Daimon-gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enman-in Temple: It stands in the north side (right) of Daimon-gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>円満院門跡とも称し、寛和3年（987年）村上天皇の第三皇子・悟円法親王によって創建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Enman-in Temple monzeki (successor of a temple), which was erected in 987 by Goenho Shinno (Imperial Prince Goenho) who was the third son of the Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Enman-in Temple monzeki (successor of a temple), which was erected in 987 by Goenho Shinno (Imperial Prince Goenho) who was the third son of the Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Enman-in Temple monzeki (successor of a temple), which was erected in 987 by Cloistered Imperial Prince Goenho who was the third son of the Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>江戸時代の画家円山応挙ゆかりの寺としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as a temple associated with Okyo MARUYAMA, a painter during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as a temple associated with Okyo MARUYAMA, a painter during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as a temple associated with Okyo MARUYAMA, a painter during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>宸殿（重文）は、慶長年間造営の御所のうち、東福門院の御局といわれる建物を移築したもので、仁和寺の金堂などとともに江戸時代初期の寝殿造宮廷建築の遺作として重要なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinden (Important Cultural Property) is a structure relocated and reconstructed 御局 of Tofukumon-in among goshos erected during the Keicho era, and it is an important posthumous architecture in Shinden-zukuri style during the early Edo period, along with Kon-do Hall of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>御局の読み方不明です。（みつぼねとおつぼねの２つがあるため。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinden (Important Cultural Property) is a structure relocated and reconstructed 御局 of Tofukumon-in among goshos erected during the Keicho era, and it is an important posthumous architecture in Shinden-zukuri style during the early Edo period, along with Kon-do Hall of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinden (Important Cultural Property) is a structure relocated and reconstructed Mitsubone of Tofukumon-in among goshos erected during the Keicho era, and it is an important posthumous architecture in Shinden-zukuri style during the early Edo period, along with Kon-do Hall of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>御局の読み方不明です。（みつぼねとおつぼねの２つがあるため、ここではみつぼねを採用しています。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>宸殿にあった障壁画の「住吉社頭図」6面（重文）と「風俗図」4面（重文）は1974～1975年に文部省買上げとなり、現在は京都国立博物館に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyoshi Shato-zu&apos; roku men (6 surfaces) (Important Cultural Property) and &apos;Fuzoku-zu&apos; yon men (four surfaces) (Important Cultural Property) of shoheki-ga of shinden, were purchased by the Ministry of Education from 1974 to 1975, and they are now possessed by Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyoshi Shato-zu&apos; roku men (6 surfaces) (Important Cultural Property) and &apos;Fuzoku-zu&apos; yon men (four surfaces) (Important Cultural Property) of shoheki-ga of shinden, were purchased by the Ministry of Education from 1974 to 1975, and they are now possessed by Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyoshi Shato-zu&apos; roku men (6 surfaces) (Important Cultural Property) and &apos;Fuzoku-zu&apos; yon men (four surfaces) (Important Cultural Property) of shoheki-ga of shinden, were purchased by the Ministry of Education from 1974 to 1975, and they are now possessed by Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>その他、円満院には円山応挙の「七難七福図」をはじめ7件の重要文化財が所蔵されていたが、現在はいずれも寺外に流出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides those, seven important cultural properties including &apos;Shichinan-shichifuku-zu&apos; (the Seven Misfortunes and Seven Fortunes) by Okyo MARUYAMA were possessed by Enman-in Temple, however, all of them are displaced out of the temple at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides those, seven important cultural properties including &apos;Shichinan-shichifuku-zu&apos; (the Seven Misfortunes and Seven Fortunes) by Okyo MARUYAMA were possessed by Enman-in Temple, however, all of them are displaced out of the temple at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides those, seven important cultural properties including &apos;Shichinan-shichifuku-zu&apos; (the Seven Misfortunes and Seven Fortunes) by Okyo MARUYAMA were possessed by Enman-in Temple, however, all of them are displaced out of the temple at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="114">
<j>法明院－境内最北にある子院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homyoin: It is a branch temple located in the northernmost area in precincts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homyoin: It is a branch temple located in the northernmost area in precincts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homyoin: It is a branch temple located in the northernmost area in precincts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>明治時代に日本美術の普及啓蒙に功績のあったアメリカ人アーネスト・フェノロサが長く滞在し、その墓があることで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that there is a grave of Ernest Fenollosa, who was an American with a great achievement for spread and enlightenment of Japan Art during his long stay in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that there is a grave of Ernest Fenollosa, who was an American that was well known for spreading Japanese Art during his long stay in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that there is a grave of Ernest Fenollosa, who was an American that was well known for spreading Japanese Art during his long stay in Japan in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>書院には円山応挙、池大雅らによる障壁画がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are shohekiga by Okyo MARUYAMA, IKE no Taiga and so on in shoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are shohekiga by Okyo MARUYAMA, IKE no Taiga and so on in shoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are shohekiga by Okyo MARUYAMA, IKE no Taiga and so on in shoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>黄不動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kifudo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kifudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kifudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>国宝指定名称は「絹本著色不動明王像」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name designated national treasure is &apos;Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo&apos; (color painting of the God of Fire colored on silk)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The designated national treasure is &apos;Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo&apos; (color painting of the God of Fire colored on silk)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The designated national treasure is &apos;Kenbon Chakushoku Fudo Myoo zo&apos; (color painting on silk of the God of Fire).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>高野山明王院の「赤不動」、青蓮院の「青不動」とともに日本三不動の一つに数えられる、古来著名な画像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the three most famous Fudo in Japan from ancient times, along with &apos;Aka Fudo&apos; (Red Fudo) of Koyasan Myoo-in Temple and &apos;Ao Fudo&apos; (Blue Fudo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the three most famous Fudo in Japan from ancient times, along with &apos;Aka Fudo&apos; (Red Fudo) of Koyasan Myoo-in Temple and &apos;Ao Fudo&apos; (Blue Fudo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the three most famous Fudo in Japan from ancient times, along with &apos;Aka Fudo&apos; (Red Fudo) of Myoo-in Temple in Mt. Koya and &apos;Ao Fudo&apos; (Blue Fudo) of Shoren-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>「金色（こんじき）不動明王」とも呼ばれるこの像は、承和 (日本)5年（838年）、比叡山で籠山修行中の円珍（当時25歳）の前に忽然と現われ、「自分は金色不動明王である。」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This image, which is also called &apos;Konjiki Fudo Myoo&apos; (Golden God of Fire), appeared suddenly in front of Enchin, who had been doing ascetic practices at Mt. Hiei, in 838 and said, &quot;I am Konjiki Fudo Myoo,&quot;</e>
<cmt>文が途中だったので、『　」と言った。』を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This image, which is also called &apos;Konjiki Fudo Myoo&apos; (Golden God of Fire), appeared suddenly in front of Enchin, who had been doing ascetic practices at Mt. Hiei, in 838 and said, &quot;I am Konjiki Fudo Myoo,&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This image, which is also called &apos;Konjiki Fudo Myoo&apos; (Golden God of Fire), appeared suddenly in front of Enchin (he was 25 years old at that time), who had been doing ascetic practices at Mt. Hiei, in 838 and said, &apos;I am Konjiki Fudo Myoo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>「仏法の真髄を伝える汝（円珍）を守護するために現われた」と告げたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the god told him &quot;I showed up to protect thou (Enchin) who transmits the essence of Buddhism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>本文に仏法のを「仏法の、と、「を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the god told him &quot;I showed up to protect thou (Enchin) who transmits the essence of Buddhism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the god told him &apos;I showed up to protect thou (Enchin) who transmits the essence of Buddhism.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>その後、この不動明王は、円珍が唐への航海の途上、海賊に襲われそうになった時に出現するなど、円珍の生涯の危機に際して現れたとされ、円珍の守護神的な性格をもっていたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Fudo Myoo was a kind of a guardian deity for Enchin and appeared on the occasion of crisis in Enchin&apos;s life after that, such as attacks by pirates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Fudo Myoo was a kind of a guardian deity for Enchin and appeared in times of crisis, such as when he was attacked by pirates.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Fudo Myoo was a kind of a guardian deity for Enchin and appeared in times of crisis, such as when he was attacked by pirates on the way to Tang.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="122">
<j>画面の大きさは178センチ×72センチ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A 178X72 centimeter painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A 178X72 centimeter painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A 178X72 centimeter painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>平安時代初期、9世紀頃の制作と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed to be the work of around the 9th century, during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed to be the work from around the 9th century, during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed to be the work from around the 9th century, during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>不動像は両眼をかっと見開き、上半身裸形、筋骨隆々とした姿に表わされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudo zo is expressed in its widely opened eyes, naked upper part of body, powerfully built form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudo zo is expressed by its widely opened eyes, naked upper part of body, powerfully built form.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudo zo is expressed by its widely opened eyes, naked upper part of body, powerfully built form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>背景を描かず、像は画面一杯に描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The figure fills the whole screen without background painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The figure fills the whole screen without any background painting.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The figure fills the whole screen without any background painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>像の足下には台座がなく、虚空を踏まえている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no pedestal under the figure, and it stands in an empty space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no pedestal under the figure, and it stands in an empty space.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no pedestal under the figure, and it stands in an empty space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>頭髪に弁髪をつくらない点など、通常の不動明王像とは図像的にかなり異なるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is much different from the other ordinary Fudo Myoo zo in some points like there is no bempatsu (a long rope of hair hanging down the left side of the face and the left shoulder of a sculpted figure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is very different from other ordinary Fudo Myoo zo such as it lacking a bempatsu (a long rope of hair hanging down the left side of the face and the left shoulder of a sculpted figure).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is very different from other ordinary Fudo Myoo zo such as it lacking a benpatsu (a long rope of hair hanging down the left side of the face and the left shoulder of a sculpted figure).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="128">
<j>三井寺では宗祖ゆかりのこの像を厳重な秘仏としており、出版物への写真掲載を厳しく制限している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue is recognized as a strict hibutu (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view) originated from the founder of the religious sect by Mii-dera Temple, and publication of the picture is strictly controlled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue is recognized as a strict hibutu (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view) originating from the founder of the religious sect by Mii-dera Temple, and publication of the picture is strictly controlled.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue is recognized as a strict hibutsu (Buddhist image normally withheld from public view) originating from the founder of the religious sect by Mii-dera Temple, and publication of the picture is strictly controlled.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>かつては伝法灌頂という密教の儀式を受けた者にのみ黄不動像の拝観が許されていたが、昭和時代以降、在家の一般信者も参加できる「結縁灌頂」という儀式が何度か実施され、その際に黄不動像拝観の機会が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although only those who had experienced a ceremony of Mikkyo named denpo-kanjo was allowed to have the honor of seeing Kifudo painting from the Showa period, the ceremony &quot;kechien-kanjo&quot;, in which ordinary believers are able to participate, were held several times, and those believers had opportunities to have the honor of seeing Kifudo painting on that occasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although only those who had gone through the ceremony of Mikkyo named denpo-kanjo were allowed to have the honor of seeing Kifudo painting from the Showa period, the ceremony &quot;kechien-kanjo&quot;, in which ordinary believers were able to participate, was held several times, and those believers were able to see the Kifudo painting on those occasions.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although only those who had gone through the ceremony of Esoteric Buddhism named denpo-kanjo were allowed to have the honor of seeing Kifudo painting, the ceremony &apos;kechien-kanjo,&apos; in which ordinary believers were able to participate, was held several times, and those believers were able to see the Kifudo painting on those occasions from the Showa period,.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。記号を修正しました。カンマの位置移動しました。from the Showa period,位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>20世紀後半以降、黄不動像が公開された機会は以下のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opportunities that Kifudo painting were opened to the public since the late 20th century are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opportunities that Kifudo painting were opened to the public since the late 20th century are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opportunities that Kifudo painting were opened to the public since the late 20th century are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="131">
<j>1954年－東京日本橋高島屋にて結縁灌頂と記念秘宝展開催。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1854: Kechien-kanjo (to have a good relationship with Buddha) and a commemorative exhibition of treasured articles were held at TAKASHIMAYA, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1854: Kechien-kanjo (to have a good relationship with Buddha) and a commemorative exhibition of treasured articles were held at TAKASHIMAYA, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1954: Kechien-kanjo (to have a good relationship with Buddha) and a commemorative exhibition of treasured articles were held at TAKASHIMAYA, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>数字修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="132">
<j>1973年－横浜高島屋にて結縁灌頂と記念秘宝展開催。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1973: Kechien-kanjo and a commemorative exhibition of treasured articles were held at TAKASHIMAYA, Yokohama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1973: Kechien-kanjo and a commemorative exhibition of treasured articles were held at TAKASHIMAYA, Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1973: Kechien-kanjo and a commemorative exhibition of treasured articles were held at TAKASHIMAYA, Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="133">
<j>1989年10月 - 1990年9月－東京国立博物館など4会場で「智証大師一千百年御遠忌記念三井寺秘宝展」開催。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October, 1989: September, 1990: &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; was held at four halls including Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October, 1989: September, 1990: &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; was held at four halls including the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1989: September 1990: &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; was held at four halls including the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="134">
<j>1990年－寺内で「智証大師一千百年御遠忌大法会」が行われ、11月6日～11月12日の7日間、結縁灌頂受者に限り黄不動像拝観が許可された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1990: &apos;Daihoe (great Buddhist memorial service) on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; was held at temple precincts, and only those who received kechien-kanjo were allowed to have the honor of seeing Kifudo painting for seven days from from November 6th to 12tn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1990: &apos;Daihoe (great Buddhist memorial service) on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; was held at temple precincts, and only those who received kechien-kanjo were allowed to have the honor of seeing the Kifudo painting for seven days from November 6th to the 12th.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1990: &apos;Daihoe (great Buddhist memorial service) on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; was held at temple precincts, and only those who received kechien-kanjo were allowed to have the honor of seeing the Kifudo painting for seven days from November 6th to the 12th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="135">
<j>1995年5月－奈良国立博物館開館百年記念「日本仏教美術名宝展」に黄不動像を1週間だけ展示。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May, 1995: Kifudo painting was exhibited only for a week at &apos;exhibition of treaures of Japanese Buddhist art&apos; of the 100th anniversary of opening day of Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May, 1995: Kifudo painting was exhibited for only a week at &apos;exhibition of treaures of Japanese Buddhist art&apos; during the 100th anniversary of the opening day for Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 1995: Kifudo painting was exhibited for only a week at &apos;exhibition of treasures of Japanese Buddhist art&apos; during the 100th anniversary of the opening day for Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>なお、特別展図録には黄不動像の写真は掲載されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the photo of Kifudo painting was not inserted in a pictorial record of the special exhibition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the Kifudo painting was not inserted in the pictorial record of the special exhibition.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the Kifudo painting was not inserted in the pictorial record of the special exhibition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="137">
<j>2008年11月 - 2009年5月 - 智証大師帰朝1150年記念「国宝三井寺展」（大阪市立美術館、サントリー美術館、福岡市博物館を巡回）に出展。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From November, 2008 to May, 2009: Kifudo painting was exhibited at &apos;exhibition of National Treasures of Mii-dera Temple of the 1150th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s return from abroad&apos; (circulated Osaka Municipal Museum of Art, Suntory Museum, Fukuoka City Museum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From November, 2008 to May, 2009: Kifudo painting was exhibited at &apos;exhibition of National Treasures of Mii-dera Temple of the 1150th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s return from abroad&apos; (circulated Osaka Municipal Museum of Art, Suntory Museum, Fukuoka City Museum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From November 2008 to May 2009: Kifudo painting was exhibited at &apos;exhibition of National Treasures of Mii-dera Temple of the 1150th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s return from abroad&apos; (circulated Osaka Municipal Museum of Art, Suntory Museum, Fukuoka City Museum).</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>三井寺の秘仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibutu of Mii-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibutu of Mii-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibutsu of Mii-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="138">
<j>三井寺は、歴史上、たび重なる焼き討ちの被害に遭ったにも関わらず、仏像、仏画、文書など多くの文化財を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Mii-dera Temple historically suffered attacking and burning set fire repeatedly, many Buddha statues, Buddhist paintings, documents and so on are preserved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Mii-dera Temple historically suffered from attacks and burnings set repeatedly, many Buddha statues, Buddhist paintings, documents and so on are preserved.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Mii-dera Temple historically suffered from attacks and burnings set repeatedly, many Buddha statues, Buddhist paintings, documents and so on are preserved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>また、建造物や障壁画にも近世以降の優れたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, there are many excellent architectures and shohekiga since the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there are many excellent architectures and shohekiga since the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there are many excellent architectures and shohekiga since the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="140">
<j>なお、建造物以外の文化財で、寺内で常時公開されているものは奈良時代の梵鐘（重文、通称弁慶引き摺り鐘）のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, among cultural properties other than architectures, only bonsho (Important Cultural Property, common name is &apos;a bell which had dragged by Benkei&apos;) is exhibited to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, among cultural properties other than architectures, only bonsho (Important Cultural Property, common name is &apos;a bell which had dragged by Benkei&apos;) is exhibited to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, among cultural properties other than architectures, only bonsho (Important Cultural Property, common name is &apos;a bell which had dragged by Benkei&apos;) of Nara period is exhibited to the public.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>黄不動像をはじめ、大師堂の智証大師像2体（中尊大師、御骨大師）と木造黄不動立像、新羅善神堂の新羅明神像、観音堂の如意輪観音像、護法善神堂の鬼子母神像などはいずれも秘仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kifudo painting down, two statues of Chisho Daishi (Chuson Daishi, Okotsu Daishi) and a wooden standing statue of Kifudo of Daishi-do Hall; a statue of Shinra Myojin of Shinra Zenjin-do Hall; a painting of Nyoirin Kannon statue of Kannon-do Hall; a statue of Kishimojin (Goddess of Children) of Goho zenjin-do Hall, and so on are all hibutu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Kifudo painting on down, two statues of Chisho Daishi (Chuson Daishi, Okotsu Daishi) and a wooden standing statue of Kifudo of Daishi-do Hall; a statue of Shinra Myojin of Shinra Zenjin-do Hall; a painting of Nyoirin Kannon statue of Kannon-do Hall; a statue of Kishimojin (Goddess of Children) of Goho zenjin-do Hall, and so on are all hibutu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Kifudo painting on down, two statues of Chisho Daishi (Chuson Daishi, Okotsu Daishi) and a wooden standing statue of Kifudo of Daishi-do Hall; a statue of Shinra Myojin of Shinra Zenjin-do Hall; a painting of Nyoirin Kannon statue of Kannon-do Hall; a statue of Kishimojin (Goddess of Children) of Goho zenjin-do Hall, and so on are all hibutsu.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>また、秘仏以外の仏像、仏画等の多くは東京・京都・奈良の国立博物館に寄託されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, many of Buddha statues, Buddhist paintings and so on except for hibutsu are deposited in national museums in Tokyo, Kyoto and Nara Prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, many Buddha statues, Buddhist paintings and so on except for hibutsu are placed in national museums in Tokyo, Kyoto and Nara Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, many Buddha statues, Buddhist paintings and so on except for hibutsu are placed in national museums in Tokyo, Kyoto and Nara Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="143">
<j>1989年10月から1990年9月まで東京国立博物館など4会場で開催された「智証大師一千百年御遠忌記念三井寺秘宝展」、1990年10月から11月に寺内で開催された「智証大師一千百年御遠忌大法会」、2008年11月から2009年5月まで大阪市立美術館など3会場で開催の「智証大師帰朝1150年記念国宝三井寺展」では、以上の秘仏すべてが一定期間公開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; at four halls including Tokyo National Museum held from October, 1989 to September, 1990, and &apos;Daihoe (great Buddhist memorial service) on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; at temple precincts held from December to November, and &apos;exhibition of National Treasures of Mii-dera Temple of the 1150th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s return from abroad exhibited at three museums including Osaka Municipal Museum of Art from November, 2008 to May, 2009, all hibutsu described above were opened to the public for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>18項目上では、1990年－寺内で「智証大師一千百年御遠忌大法会」が行われ、11月6日～11月12日の7日間と書かれていますが、ここでは、1990年10月から11月と書かれており、一致しないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; at four halls including Tokyo National Museum held from October, 1989 to September, 1990, and &apos;Daihoe (great Buddhist memorial service) on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; at temple precincts held from December to November, and exhibition of National Treasures of Mii-dera Temple of the 1150th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s return from abroad exhibited at three museums including Osaka Municipal Museum of Art from November, 2008 to May, 2009, all hibutsu described above were opened to the public for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; at four halls including Tokyo National Museum held from October 1989 to September 1990, and &apos;Daihoe (great Buddhist memorial service) on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; at temple precincts held from October to November 1990, and exhibition of National Treasures of Mii-dera Temple of the 1150th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s return from abroad exhibited at three museums including Osaka Municipal Museum of Art from November 2008 to May 2009, all hibutsu described above were opened to the public for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。カンマ削除しました。日付修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>なお、金堂本尊の弥勒菩薩像（弥勒如来とも）は、天智天皇の念持仏と伝え、唐からの請来像ともいうが、公開されたことがなく、写真も存在しないため、いかなる像であるかは不明と言うほかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, statue of Maitreya (or Miroku-nyorai) of Kondo honzon was said to be nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) of the Emperor Tenchi and also it is shorai-zo (bring in the scriptures or the statues of Buddha from a foreign country) from Tang, however, it had not been opened to the public and there is no picture, accordingly, it is totally unknown about the statue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the statue of Maitreya (or Miroku-nyorai) of Kondo honzon was said to be nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) of the Emperor Tenchi and also it is shorai-zo (bring in the scriptures or the statues of Buddha from a foreign country) from Tang, however, it had not been opened to the public and there is no picture, accordingly, the statue itself remains totally unknown.it is totally unknown about the statue.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the statue of Maitreya (or Miroku-nyorai) of Kondo honzon was said to be nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) of the Emperor Tenchi and also it is shorai-zo (bring in the scriptures or the statues of Buddha from a foreign country) from Tang, however, it had not been opened to the public and there is no picture, accordingly, the statue itself remains totally unknown.</e>
<cmt>重複削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="145">
<j>金堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kon-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kon-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kon-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="146">
<j>新羅善神堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="147">
<j>勧学院客殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinra Zenjin-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakuin Kyakuden (guest hall)</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="148">
<j>光浄院客殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojoin Kyakuden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojoin Kyakuden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojoin Kyakuden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="149">
<j>絹本著色不動明王像（黄不動）（既述）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo&apos; (Kifudo painting) (above-mentioned)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo&apos; (Kifudo painting) (above-mentioned)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Fudo Myoo zo&apos; (Kifudo painting) (above-mentioned)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="150">
<j>木造智証大師坐像（中尊大師）－唐院大師堂の中央の厨子に安置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden Chisho Daishi Zazo (the seated statue of Chisho Daishi) (Chuson Daishi) (the Great teacher of the principal statue of in a group of Buddhist statues): The statue is enshrined in zushi (a miniature shrine) placed in the middle of To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden Chisho Daishi Zazo (the seated statue of Chisho Daishi) (Chuson Daishi) (the Great teacher of the principal statue of in a group of Buddhist statues): The statue is enshrined in zushi (a miniature shrine) placed in the middle of To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden Chisho Daishi Zazo (the seated statue of Chisho Daishi) (Chuson Daishi) (the Great teacher of the principal statue of in a group of Buddhist statues): The statue is enshrined in zushi (a miniature shrine) placed in the middle of To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>秘仏で、毎年10月29日の円珍の命日にのみ開扉される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hibutu, and is opened to the public on the anniversary of Enchin&apos;s death, on 29 October, every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hibutu, and is opened to the public on the anniversary of Enchin&apos;s death, on 29 October, every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hibutsu, and is opened to the public on the anniversary of Enchin&apos;s death, on 29 October, every year.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>卵形の頭の形と細い眼が特徴の独特の風貌は、各地に残る円珍の肖像に共通のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic features of egg-shaped head and narrow eyes are common to other statues of Enchin in all areas of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristic features are an egg-shaped head and narrow eyes common to other statues of Enchin in all areas of the country.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristic features are an egg-shaped head and narrow eyes common to other statues of Enchin in all areas of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>この像はもと比叡山内の山王院（千手院）にあったと言われ、円仁（慈覚大師）門徒と円珍門徒の抗争激化のため、円珍門徒が比叡山を下りた正暦4年（993年）に三井寺に移されたものと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this statue had been initially placed in Sanno-in Temple (Sanju-in Temple) in Mt. Hiei, then it was transferred to Mii-dera Temple in 993 by followers of Enchin who descended Mt. Hiei due to intensified struggle between the followers of Ennin (Jikaku Daishi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this statue had been initially placed in Sanno-in Temple (Sanju-in Temple) in Mt. Hiei, then transferred to Mii-dera Temple in 993 by followers of Enchin who descended Mt. Hiei due to intensified struggle between the followers of Ennin (Jikaku Daishi).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this statue had been initially placed in Sanno-in Temple (Senju-in Temple) in Mt. Hiei, then transferred to Mii-dera Temple in 993 by followers of Enchin who descended Mt. Hiei due to intensified struggle between the followers of Ennin (Jikaku Daishi).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>ただし、作風的には10世紀後半頃のものと見られ、正暦4年頃に三井寺で新たに造像されたとの見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from its making method, it is thought to be made during around late 10th century, and there is another opinion that it was newly made at Mii-dera Temple in about 993.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, based on the method that it was made, it could be dated to around the late 10th century, and there is another opinion that it was newly made at Mii-dera Temple around 993.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, based on the method that it was made, it could be dated to around the late 10th century, and there is another opinion that it was newly made at Mii-dera Temple around 993.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>1989年～1990年の「智証大師一千百年御遠忌記念三井寺秘宝展」で公開されたほか、1986年に開催された「開創千二百年記念比叡山と天台の美術」展でも公開されたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the exhibition of &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; from 1989 to 1990, it was also opened to the public at the exhibition of &apos;Art of Mt. Hiei and Tendai sect on the 1200th anniversary of the foundation of the temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides the exhibition of &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; from 1989 to 1990, it was also opened to the public during the exhibition of &apos;Art of Mt. Hiei and Tendai sect on the 1200th anniversary of the foundation of the temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides the exhibition of &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; from 1989 to 1990, it was also opened to the public during the exhibition of &apos;Art of Mt. Hiei and Tendai sect on the 1200th anniversary of the foundation of the temple&apos; in 1986.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="156">
<j>木造智証大師坐像（御骨大師）－唐院大師堂内、中尊大師像の向かって左に安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden seated statue of Chisho Daishi (Okotsu Daishi): It is enshrined to the left of Chuson Daishi in To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden seated statue of Chisho Daishi (Okotsu Daishi): It is enshrined to the left of Chuson Daishi in To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden seated statue of Chisho Daishi (Okotsu Daishi): It is enshrined to the left of Chuson Daishi in To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>秘仏で、特別な行事の時以外、開扉はされない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hibutu and is not opened to the public except special rites or festivals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hibutu and not opened to the public except for special rites or festivals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hibutsu and not opened to the public except for special rites or festivals.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>荼毘に付した円珍の遺骨を納めるところから「御骨大師」と呼ばれて寺内で尊崇され、出版物への写真掲載は制限されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called &apos;Okotsu Daishi&apos; and worshiped by the reason it contains remains of Enchin by cremation,and publication of its photographs is limited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called &apos;Okotsu Daishi&apos; and worshiped for the reason it contains remains of Enchin by cremation, and publication of its photographs is limited.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &apos;Okotsu Daishi&apos; and worshiped for the reason it contains remains of Enchin by cremation, and publication of its photographs is limited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>中尊大師像より古く、9世紀末、円珍没後まもない頃の作と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue is assumed to be made before Chuson Daishi-zo, around 9th century, shortly after the death of Enchin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue is assumed to have been made before Chuson Daishi-zo, around the 9th century, shortly after the death of Enchin.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue is assumed to have been made before Chuson Daishi-zo, around the 9th century, shortly after the death of Enchin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="160">
<j>木造新羅明神坐像－新羅善神堂に安置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden shinra myojin zazo (seated statue of Shinra Myojin): It is enshrined in Shinra Zenjin-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden shinra myojin zazo (seated statue of Shinra Myojin): It is enshrined in Shinra Zenjin-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden shinra myojin zazo (seated statue of Shinra Myojin): It is enshrined in Shinra Zenjin-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>秘仏で、特別な行事の時以外、開扉はされない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hibutu and is not opened to the public except special rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hibutu and is not opened to the public except for special rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hibutsu and is not opened to the public except for special rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>円珍が日本へ帰国する際、船中に現われた神とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the deity appeared in the boat when Enchin returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the deity appeared in the boat when Enchin returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the deity appeared in the boat when Enchin returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>長いあごひげをたくわえ、目尻の下がった異様な相貌、異様に細く長い指など、きわめて特殊な像容を示し、日本彫刻史の中でも異彩を放っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a statue of peculiar looks with long beard, eyes slanting down outwards, strangely thin long fingers and so on, and it stands out prominently among sculpture history in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a peculiar statue with a long beard, eyes slanting down outwards, strange thin long fingers and so on, and stands out prominently among the history of sculpture in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a peculiar statue with a long beard, eyes slanting down outwards, strange thin long fingers and so on, and stands out prominently among the history of sculpture in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>平安時代後期、11世紀頃の制作と推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed to be made during the late Heian period, around the 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed to have been made during the late Heian period, around the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed to have been made during the late Heian period, around the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>1989年～1990年の「智証大師一千百年御遠忌記念三井寺秘宝展」で公開されたほか、1986年に開催された「開創千二百年記念比叡山と天台の美術」展でも公開されたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the exhibition of &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; from 1989 to 1990, it was also opened to the public at the exhibition of &apos;Art of Mt. Hiei and Tendai sect on the 1200th anniversary of the foundation of the temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides the exhibition of &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; from 1989 to 1990, it was also opened to the public during the exhibition of &apos;Art of Mt. Hiei and Tendai sect on the 1200th anniversary of the foundation of the temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides the exhibition of &apos;A commemorative exhibition of treasured articles of Mii-dera Temple on the 1100th anniversary of Chisho Daishi&apos;s death&apos; from 1989 to 1990, it was also opened to the public during the exhibition of &apos;Art of Mt. Hiei and Tendai sect on the 1200th anniversary of the foundation of the temple&apos; in 1986.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="166">
<j>五部心観2巻－両界曼荼羅のうち、金剛界曼荼羅の諸尊を表わした白描（はくびょう）図像の巻物である（白描とは、陰影や肥痩のない、均質な墨の線だけで表わした絵画のこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two Gobushinkan (Painting of the five parts of the Mandala): It is a Hakubyo plain sketch representing shoson (persons or things to be respected, such as Buddha) of Diamond World Mandala among Ryokai Mandala (Two World Mandala) (Hakubyo refers to a plain picture depicted by only lines black ink without shadow or thick-and-thin lines).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two Gobushinkan (Painting of the five parts of the Mandala): It is a Hakubyo plain sketch representing shoson (persons or things to be respected, such as Buddha) of Diamond World Mandala among Ryokai Mandala (Two World Mandala) (Hakubyo refers to a plain picture depicted by only lines black ink without shadow or thick-and-thin lines).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two Gobushinkan (Painting of the five parts of the Mandala): It is a Hakubyo plain sketch representing shoson (persons or things to be respected, such as Buddha) of Diamond World Mandala among Ryokai Mandala (Two World Mandala) (Hakubyo refers to a plain picture depicted by only lines black ink without shadow or thick-and-thin lines).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>2巻のうち1巻は唐時代の制作で、円珍が師の法全（はっせん）から授かったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the two was made during the period of Tang Dynasty, and was endowed to Enchin from his mentor, Hassen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the two was made during the Tang Dynasty, and was endowed to Enchin from his mentor, Hassen.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the two was made during the Tang Dynasty, and was endowed to Enchin from his mentor, Hassen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>もう1巻は平安時代に日本で写されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another one was copied in Japan during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another one was copied in Japan during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another one was copied in Japan during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="169">
<j>智証大師関係文書典籍－円珍に関わる資料46種が一括して国宝に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Books of documents related to Chisho Daishi: 46 kinds of materials related Enchin are designated to National Treasures all together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Books of documents related to Chisho Daishi: 46 kinds of materials related Enchin are all designated as National Treasures.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Books of documents related to Chisho Daishi: 46 kinds of materials related Enchin are all designated as National Treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>主なものとしては、円珍の系図、唐への過所、円珍自筆本、唐から請来した経典などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As main works, genealogy of Enchin, admittance to Tang, manuscript in his own hand, Buddhist scriptures obtained from Tang and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As main works, genealogy of Enchin, admittance to Tang, manuscript in his own hand, Buddhist scriptures obtained from Tang and so on.</e>
<cmt>Doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As main works, genealogy of Enchin, admittance to Tang, manuscript in his own hand, Buddhist scriptures obtained from Tang and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="171">
<j>木造不動明王立像－唐院大師堂の向かって右の厨子に安置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden Fudo-myoo ryuzo; mokuzo Fudo-myo-o ryuzo (the wooden standing statue of Fudo-myoo) - It is enshrined in a zushi on the right in To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden Fudo-myoo ryuzo; mokuzo Fudo-myo-o ryuzo (the wooden standing statue of Fudo-myoo) - It is enshrined in a zushi on the right in To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Fudo-myoo - It is enshrined in a zushi on the right in To-in Daishi Do.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>秘仏で、特別な行事の時以外、開扉はされない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hibutu and is not opened to the public except special rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hibutu and is not opened to the public except for special rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hibutsu and is not opened to the public except for special rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>原本である黄不動の画像をもとに、鎌倉時代に彫像として造られた像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was carved statue during the Kamakura period based on the kifudo painting of original book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was carved during the Kamakura period based on the kifudo painting of original book.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was carved during the Kamakura period based on the kifudo painting of original book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="174">
<j>木造如意輪観音坐像－西国観音霊場14番札所の観音堂の本尊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden seated Nyoirin Kannon: It&apos;s honzon of stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku kannon reijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden seated Nyoirin Kannon: It is the honzon of stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku kannon reijo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden seated Nyoirin Kannon: It is the honzon of stamp office for temple number 14 of Saigoku kannon reijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>秘仏で、開扉は33年に一度とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hibutu and is opened to the public once every 33 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hibutu and is opened to the public once every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hibutsu and is opened to the public once every 33 years.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="176">
<j>梵鐘（弁慶の引き摺り鐘）－金堂裏の霊鐘堂に所在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonsho (a bell which had dragged by Benkei): It is placed in a sacred bell tower behind Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonsho (a bell which had dragged by Benkei): It is placed in a sacred bell tower behind Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonsho (a bell which had dragged by Benkei): It is placed in a sacred bell tower behind Kon-do Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>「三井の晩鐘」の鐘とは別のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a different from the &apos;Mii no bansho.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is different from the &apos;Mii no bansho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is different from the &apos;Mii no bansho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>無銘だが、奈良時代にさかのぼる日本でも有数の古鐘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is unsigned, it is a prominent old bell in Japan date back to the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is unsigned, it is a prominent old bell in Japan dating back to the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is unsigned, it is a prominent old bell in Japan dating back to the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>伝承では、藤原秀郷がムカデ退治のお礼に琵琶湖の竜神から授かった鐘だと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By a tradition, it is said that FUJIWARA no Hidesato was given from the dragon god as a token of his gratitude for extermination of a scolopendrid.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to tradition, it is said that FUJIWARA no Hidesato was given from the dragon god as a token of his gratitude for exterminating a scolopendrid.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to tradition, it is said that FUJIWARA no Hidesato was given from the dragon god of Lake Biwa as a token of his gratitude for exterminating a scolopendrid.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>その後比叡山と三井寺の争いに際して、弁慶が奪って比叡山に引き摺り上げたが、鐘が「イノー」（「帰りたいよう」の意）と鳴ったので、弁慶が怒って谷底へ捨てたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some time later, on the occasion Benkei dragged it up to Mt. Hiei at a struggle between Mt. Hiei and Mii-dera Temple, Benkei was offended by the sound of &apos;Inoo (I want to go back home) that the bell made, and he threw away the bell to the bottom of a valley.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some time later, Benkei dragged it up to Mt. Hiei during a battle between Mt. Hiei and Mii-dera Temple, Benkei was offended by the sound of &apos;Inoo (I want to go back home) that the bell made, and he threw the bell to the bottom of a valley.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some time later, Benkei dragged it up to Mt. Hiei during a battle between Mt. Hiei and Mii-dera Temple, Benkei was offended by the sound of &apos;Inoo&apos; (I want to go back home) that the bell made, and he threw the bell to the bottom of a valley.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>現状、鐘の表面に見られる擦り傷やひびはその時のものと称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing scratches and cracks on the bell is said to be made on that occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing scratches and cracks on the bell are said to have been made on that occasion.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing scratches and cracks on the bell are said to have been made on that occasion.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>歴史的には、この鐘は文永元年（1264年）の比叡山による三井寺焼き討ちの際に強奪され、後に返還されたというのが史実のようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, this bell was robbed from Mii-dera Temple on the occasion of attacking and burning set fire by Mt. Hiei in 1264, and it was returned thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, this bell was robbed from Mii-dera Temple when it was attacked and burned by Mt. Hiei in 1264, and returned thereafter.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, this bell was robbed from Mii-dera Temple when it was attacked and burned by Mt. Hiei in 1264, and returned thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="183">
<j>以下は園城寺所有の重要文化財の一覧である（上に解説したものも重出している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is a list of Important Cultural Property which are owned by Onjo-ji Temple (some of them are cited again).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is a list of Important Cultural Property which are owned by Onjo-ji Temple (some of them are cited again).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is a list of Important Cultural Property which are owned by Onjo-ji Temple (some of them are cited again).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>絵画、彫刻等の大部分は東京・京都・奈良の国立博物館に寄託されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of paintings, sculptures and so on are deposited in national museums in Tokyo, Kyoto and Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the paintings, sculptures and so on are in national museums in Tokyo, Kyoto and Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the paintings, sculptures and so on are in national museums in Tokyo, Kyoto and Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="185">
<j>（建造物）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Architecture)</e>
<cmt>()補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>大門（仁王門）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimon-gate (Nio-mon gate)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimon-gate (Nio-mon gate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimon-gate (Nio-mon gate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>閼伽井屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akaiya (a well)</e>
<cmt>訳漏れしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>一切経蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issai-kyo (Complete Collection of Scriptures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issai-kyo (Complete Collection of Scriptures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issai-kyo (Complete Collection of Scriptures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>三重塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanju-no-to</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanju-no-to</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanju-no-to</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>食堂（釈迦堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikido (dining hall) (Shaka-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikido (dining hall) (Shaka-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikido (dining hall) (Shaka-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>毘沙門堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamon-do Hall</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>唐院大師堂・唐門・灌頂堂・四脚門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-in Daishi Do・Kara-mon gate・Kanjodo (The hall for holding the ceremony to pour holy water on the head of a monk)・Yotsuashimon Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-in Daishi Do・Kara-mon gate・Kanjodo (The hall for holding the ceremony to pour holy water on the head of a monk)・Yotsuashimon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To-in Daishi Do, Kara-mon gate, Kanjodo (The hall for holding the ceremony to pour holy water on the head of a monk), Yotsuashimon Gate</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>鐘楼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoro</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="194">
<j>（絵画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(paintings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(paintings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Paintings)</e>
<cmt>スタイル統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>絹本著色新羅明神像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Shinra Myozin zo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Shinra Myozin zo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Shinra Myozin zo</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>絹本著色天台大師像 2幅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Tendai Daishi (Chigi) zo Futano (double width)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Tendai Daishi (Chigi) zo Futano (double width)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Tendai Daishi (Chigi) zo Futano (double width)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>絹本著色不動明王像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo zo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Fudo Myoo zo</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>絹本著色不動明王二童子像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo Nidoji zo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo Nidoji zo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Fudo Myoo Nidoji zo</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>絹本著色不動明王八大童子像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo HachidaivDoji zo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Fudo Myoo HachidaivDoji zo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Fudo Myoo Hachidai Doji zo</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>絹本著色釈迦十六善神像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Shakyamuni (Buddha) and sixteen Zen-shin Buddhist deities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Shakyamuni (Buddha) and sixteen Zen-shin Buddhist deities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Shakyamuni (Buddha) and sixteen Zen-shin Buddhist deities</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>絹本著色涅槃像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Nehan zo (an image of the Buddha immediately after his death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Nehan zo (an image of the Buddha immediately after his death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Nehan zo (an image of the Buddha immediately after his death)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>絹本著色尊星王像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Sonjo-o zo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Sonjo-o zo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Sonjo-o zo</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>絹本著色多聞天像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Tamonten so (statue of Vaisravana Buddhist deity)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Tamonten so (statue of Vaisravana Buddhist deity)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Tamonten zo (statue of Vaisravana Buddhist deity)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>絹本著色閻魔天像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Emmaten zo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Emmaten zo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Enmaten zo</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>絹本著色水天像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Suiten zo (Varuna)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Suiten zo (Varuna)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Suiten zo (Varuna)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>絹本著色黄金剛童子像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kongodoji zo (child acolytes of Buddhism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kongodoji zo (child acolytes of Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Kongodoji zo (child acolytes of Buddhism)</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>絹本著色両界曼荼羅図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Ryokai Mandala (Two World Mandala)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Ryokai Mandala (Two World Mandala)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Ryokai Mandala (Two World Mandala)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>絹本著色尊勝曼荼羅図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Sonsho Mandala (Mandala composed of holy spirits of Mahavairocana&apos;s parietal region) Mandala</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Sonsho Mandala (Mandala composed of holy spirits of Mahavairocana&apos;s parietal region) Mandala</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Sonsho Mandala (Mandala composed of holy spirits of Mahavairocana&apos;s parietal region) Mandala</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>絹本著色八大仏頂曼荼羅図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenbon Chakusyoku Sonsho Mandala (Mandala composed of holy spirits of Mahavairocana&apos;s parietal region) Mandala</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenbon Chakusyoku Sonsho Mandala (Mandala composed of holy spirits of Mahavairocana&apos;s parietal region) Mandala</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenbon Chakushoku Hachidai Buccho Mandala (Mandala composed of holy spirits of Mahavairocana&apos;s parietal region) Mandala</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>光浄院客殿障壁画 松に滝図1面、菊花図5面、列仙図7面、花鳥図12面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojoin Kyakuden shohekiga: Matsu ni taki zu ichi men (1 surface of a pine tree and waterfall painting), Kikka zu go men (5 surfaces of chrysanthemum paintings), Ressen zu shiti men (7 surfaces of mountains paintings), Katyo zu juni men (12 surfaces of flowers and birds paintings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojoin Kyakuden shohekiga: Matsu ni taki zu ichi men (1 surface of a pine tree and waterfall painting), Kikka zu go men (5 surfaces of chrysanthemum paintings), Ressen zu shiti men (7 surfaces of mountains paintings), Katyo zu juni men (12 surfaces of flowers and birds paintings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojoin Kyakuden shohekiga: 1 surface of a pine tree and waterfall painting, 5 surfaces of chrysanthemum paintings, 7 surfaces of mountains paintings, 12 surfaces of flowers and birds paintings</e>
<cmt>英語訳のみにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>勧学院客殿障壁画 金地著色滝図3面、梅、桧及花卉図4面、桜、杉及花卉図4面、桧及花卉図4面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakuin Kyakuden shohekiga: Kinjichakushoku taki zu san men (3 surfaces of waterfall paintings), Ume, hinoki oyobi kaki zu yon men (4 surfaces of paintings of ume trees and hinoki cypresses, and paintings of flowers and grasses), Sakura, sugi oyobi kaki zu yon men (4 surfaces of paintings of cherry trees and Japanese cedars, and paintings of flowers and grasses), Hinoki oyobi kaki zu yon men (4 surfaces of hinoki cypresses paintings, and flowers and grasses paintings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakuin Kyakuden shohekiga: Kinjichakushoku taki zu san men (3 surfaces of waterfall paintings), Ume, hinoki oyobi kaki zu yon men (4 surfaces of paintings of ume trees and hinoki cypresses, and paintings of flowers and grasses), Sakura, sugi oyobi kaki zu yon men (4 surfaces of paintings of cherry trees and Japanese cedars, and paintings of flowers and grasses), Hinoki oyobi kaki zu yon men (4 surfaces of hinoki cypresses paintings, and flowers and grasses paintings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakuin Kyakuden shohekiga: 3 surfaces of waterfall paintings, 4 surfaces of paintings of ume trees and hinoki cypresses, and paintings of flowers and grasses, 4 surfaces of paintings of cherry trees and Japanese cedars, and paintings of flowers and grasses, 4 surfaces of hinoki cypresses paintings, and flowers and grasses paintings</e>
<cmt>英語訳のみにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>勧学院客殿障壁画 紙本著色松に山鳥、鴨、鴛鴦図及竹に雀図16面、竹に雀及芦に鷺図8面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakuin Kyakuden shohekiga: Shihon chakushoku matsu ni yamadori, kamo, oshidori zu oyobi take ni suzume zu jyuroku men (16 surfaces of paintings of copper pheasants, wild ducks and mandarin ducks, and paintings of bamboos and Japanese sparrows), Take ni suzume oyobi ashi ni sagi zu hachi men (8 surfaces of paintings of bamboos and Japanese sparrows and paintings of reeds and snowy herons)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakuin Kyakuden shohekiga: Shihon chakushoku matsu ni yamadori, kamo, oshidori zu oyobi take ni suzume zu jyuroku men (16 surfaces of paintings of copper pheasants, wild ducks and mandarin ducks, and paintings of bamboos and Japanese sparrows), Take ni suzume oyobi ashi ni sagi zu hachi men (8 surfaces of paintings of bamboos and Japanese sparrows and paintings of reeds and snowy herons)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakuin Kyakuden shohekiga: 16 surfaces of paintings of copper pheasants, wild ducks and mandarin ducks, and paintings of bamboos and Japanese sparrows, 8 surfaces of paintings of bamboos and Japanese sparrows and paintings of reeds and snowy herons</e>
<cmt>英語訳のみにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="213">
<j>（彫刻）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Sculpture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Sculpture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Sculpture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>木造如意輪観音坐像（観音堂安置）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden seated Nyoirin Kannon (enshrined in Kannon-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden seated Nyoirin Kannon (enshrined in Kannon-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden seated Nyoirin Kannon (enshrined in Kannon-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>木造愛染明王坐像（観音堂安置）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden seated statue of Aizenmyoo (enshrined in Kannon-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden seated statue of Aizenmyoo (enshrined in Kannon-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden seated statue of Aizenmyoo (enshrined in Kannon-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>木造護法善神立像（護法善神堂安置）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Goho zenjin (good dieties protecting dharma) (enshrined in Goho zenjin Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden standing statue of Goho zenjin (good dieties protecting dharma) (enshrined in Goho zenjin Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Goho zenjin (good deities protecting dharma) (enshrined in Goho zenjin Hall)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>木造黄不動尊立像（唐院安置）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Kifudo (enshrined in To-in)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden standing statue of Kifudo (enshrined in To-in)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Kifudo (enshrined in To-in)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>木造吉祥天立像（琵琶湖文化館寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Laksmi, Buddhist deity (deposited in Shiga Kenritsu Biwako Bunkakan [The Museum of Cultural Art, Shiga])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden standing statue of Laksmi, Buddhist deity (deposited in Shiga Kenritsu Biwako Bunkakan [The Museum of Cultural Art, Shiga])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Laksmi, Buddhist deity (deposited in the Museum of Cultural Art, Shiga)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>木造十一面観音立像（京都国立博物館寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon (deposited in Kyoto National Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon (deposited in Kyoto National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon (deposited in Kyoto National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>木造千手観音立像（奈良国立博物館寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Thousand Armed Kannon (deposited in Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden standing statue of Thousand Armed Kannon (deposited in Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden standing statue of Thousand Armed Kannon (deposited in Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>木造智証大師坐像（琵琶湖文化館寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden seated statue of Chisho Daishi (deposited in Shiga Kenritsu Biwako Bunkakan [The Museum of Cultural Art, Shiga])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden seated statue of Chisho Daishi (deposited in Shiga Kenritsu Biwako Bunkakan [The Museum of Cultural Art, Shiga])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden seated statue of Chisho Daishi (deposited in the Museum of Cultural Art, Shiga)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>木造不動明王坐像（奈良国立博物館寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wooden statue of Fudo Myoo (deposited in Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wooden statue of Fudo Myoo (deposited in Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wooden statue of Fudo Myoo (deposited in Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>木造訶梨帝母倚像（所在護法善神堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kariteimoizo (seated statue of Kariteimo) (kept in Goho zenjin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kariteimoizo (seated statue of Kariteimo) (kept in Goho zenjin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kariteimoizo (seated statue of Kariteimo) (kept in Goho zenjin-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>用語統一修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="224">
<j>（工芸品）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Artifact)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Artifact)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Artifact)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>金銅孔雀文磬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gilt bronze Kujaku Monkei (Buddhist Ritual Gong with Peacock Relief)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gilt bronze Kujaku Monkei (Buddhist Ritual Gong with Peacock Relief)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gilt bronze Kujaku Monkei (Buddhist Ritual Gong with Peacock Relief)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>銅鐘 大平年間（遼）銘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dosho (bronze bell): with an inscription of Taiei era (Liao in China)</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>梵鐘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonsho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonsho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonsho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="228">
<j>（書跡、歴史資料）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Calligraphy, Historical mateals)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Calligraphy, Historical mateals)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Calligraphy, Historical materials)</e>
<cmt>フォント修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>大蔵経 592帖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daizo-kyo Sutra (the Tripitaka) 592 jo (176X176cm)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daizo-kyo Sutra (the Tripitaka) 592 jo (176X176cm)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daizo-kyo Sutra (the Tripitaka) 592 jo (176X176 cm)</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>紙本著色園城寺境内古図 5幅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Color painting on paper of Onjo-ji Temple, five width</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>園城寺尺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple Shaku (ruler)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onjo-ji Temple Shaku (ruler)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onjo-ji Temple Shaku (ruler)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="232">
<j>算額 文政11年4月 堀池主計義竜他5名奉納 観音堂内に掲額</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangaku (Japanese votive tablets featuring mathematical puzzles): 1828 堀池主計義竜and other 5 people dedicated, the sangaku is set up in Kannon-do Hall</e>
<cmt>堀池主計義竜：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangaku (Japanese votive tablets featuring mathematical puzzles): 1828 堀池主計義竜and other 5 people dedicated, the sangaku is set up in Kannon-do Hall</e>
<cmt>Doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangaku (Japanese votive tablets featuring mathematical puzzles): May 1828 堀池主計義竜 and other 5 people dedicated, the sangaku is set up in Kannon-do Hall</e>
<cmt>日付補足しました。堀池主計義竜：読み方不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="233">
<j>御詠歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goeika (a Buddhist hymn)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goeika (a Buddhist hymn)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goeika (a Buddhist hymn)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>いで入るや</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the moon reflected in the lake (the moon indicates Boddisattva&apos;s heart)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the moon reflected in the lake (the moon indicates Boddisattva&apos;s heart)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the moon reflected in the lake (the moon indicates Boddisattva&apos;s heart)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>波間の月を</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ripples in the moonlight (carnal desire aroused)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ripples in the moonlight (carnal desire aroused)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ripples in the moonlight (carnal desire aroused)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>三井寺の</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple&apos;s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mii-dera Temple&apos;s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mii-dera Temple&apos;s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>鐘のひびきに</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">bell&apos;s sound (Zen&apos;s spirit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">bell&apos;s sound (Zen&apos;s spirit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">bell&apos;s sound (Zen&apos;s spirit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>あくる湖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">makes the whole lake shone bright (regain stability and a bodhisattva&apos;s way in the search for truth.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">makes the whole lake shone bright (regain stability and a bodhisattva&apos;s way in the search for truth.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">makes the whole lake shone bright (regain stability and a bodhisattva&apos;s way in the search for truth.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>前後の札所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudasho in front and behind</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudasho in front and behind</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudasho in front and behind</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>西国三十三箇所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigoku Sanjusankasho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigoku Sanjusankasho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigoku Sanjusankasho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>13 石山寺　--　14 三井寺（園城寺）　--　15 観音寺 (京都市東山区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">13 Ishiyama-dera Temple: 14 Mii-dera Temple (Onjo-ji Temple): 15 Kannon-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">13 Ishiyama-dera Temple: 14 Mii-dera Temple (Onjo-ji Temple): 15 Kannon-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">13 Ishiyama-dera Temple: 14 Mii-dera Temple (Onjo-ji Temple): 15 Kannon-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="242">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京阪石山坂本線三井寺駅より徒歩10分・別所駅 (滋賀県)より徒歩12分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Keihan Ishiyama Sakamoto Line, 10 minutes from Mii-dera Temple Station・12 minutes from Bessho Station (Shiga Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Keihan Ishiyama Sakamoto Line, 10 minutes from Mii-dera Temple Station・12 minutes from Bessho Station (Shiga Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Keihan Ishiyama Sakamoto Line, 10 minutes walk from Mii-dera Temple Station・12 minutes walk from Bessho Station (Shiga Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道東海道本線（琵琶湖線）大津駅より京阪バス三井寺バス停下車0分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan Railway Tokaido Main Line (Biwako Line), Otsu Station, change to Keihan Bus, 0 minute from Mii-dera Temple Stop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West Japan Railway Tokaido Main Line (Biwako Line), Otsu Station, change to Keihan Bus, 0 minute from Mii-dera Temple Stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan Railway Tokaido Main Line (Biwako Line), Otsu Station, change to Keihan Bus, 0 minute from Mii-dera Temple Stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>JR西日本湖西線大津京駅より京阪バス三井寺バス停下車0分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR West Japan Railway Company Kosei Railway Line, Otsukyo Station, change to Keihan Bus, 0 minute from Mii-dera Temple Stop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR West Japan Railway Company Kosei Railway Line, Otsukyo Station, change to Keihan Bus, 0 minute from Mii-dera Temple Stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR West Japan Railway Company Kosei Railway Line, Otsukyo Station, change to Keihan Bus, 0 minute from Mii-dera Temple Stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kanejan(id:78613), Bakkai(id:7233), Yard(id:59322), Nnh(id:474), China(id:10362), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Eskimbot(id:29676), 二八(id:10408), Urania(id:7213), D.h(id:79056), Ash Crow(id:26765), Mop(id:12061), Opponent(id:720), Ko-ken(id:49348), あお。(id:39226), ChibaRagi(id:68046), Yas(id:739), Davin(id:126560), ロリ(id:613), たね(id:10372), 与左衛門(id:159462), Chi-Ham(id:143515), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tiyoringo(id:70026), ネオン(id:59494), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Oilstreet(id:31325), Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), 悠卯斗(id:46277), Yonoemon(id:55450), 663highland(id:18755), Chibang(id:19967), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>