<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>清水寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>清水寺（きよみずでら）は、京都府京都市東山区清水にある寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple is a Buddhist temple in Kiyomizu, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomizu-dera Temple is a Buddhist temple in Kiyomizu, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple is a Buddhist temple in Kiyomizu, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号を音羽山と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sango ((literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Otowa-san (Mt. Otowa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sango ((literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Otowa-san (Mt. Otowa).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sango (literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Otowa-san (Mt. Otowa).</e>
<cmt>(削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本尊は千手観音、開基（創立者）は延鎮である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) of the temple is Senju Kannon (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy with a thousand arms), and the founder is the late Enchin, a Buddhist monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) of the temple is Senju Kannon (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy with a thousand arms), and the founder is the late Enchin, a Buddhist monk.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) of the temple is Senju Kannon (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy with a thousand arms), and the founder is the late Enchin, a Buddhist monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>もとは法相宗に属したが、現在は独立して北法相宗大本山を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although having belonged to the Hosso sect originally, the temple left the sect to become independent, with calling itself &quot;Daihonzan (head temple) of the Kita Hoso sect.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although having belonged to the Hosso sect originally, the temple left the sect to become independent, calling itself &quot;Daihonzan (head temple) of the Kita Hoso sect.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although having belonged to the Hosso sect originally, the temple left the sect to become independent, calling itself &quot;Daihonzan (head temple) of the Kita Hoso sect.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>西国三十三箇所観音霊場の第16番札所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the stamp office for temple number 16 of the Saigoku Sanjyusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the stamp office for temple number 16 of the Saigoku Sanjyusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the stamp office for temple number 16 of the Saigoku Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>清水寺は法相宗（南都六宗の一）系の寺院で、広隆寺、鞍馬寺とともに、平安京遷都以前からの歴史をもつ、京都では数少ない寺院の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple is not only a Buddhist temple belonging to a group of Hosso sect (one of Nanto rokushu (the six sects of Buddhism which flourished in ancient Nara)), but also one of only a few Buddhist temples with the history started before the period when the national capital was transferred to Heian-kyo, along with Koryu-ji Temple and Kurama-dera Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomizu-dera Temple is not only a Buddhist temple belonging to a group of the Hosso sect (one of the Nanto rokushu (the six sects of Buddhism which flourished in ancient Nara)), but also one of only a few Buddhist temples with history started before the period when the national capital was transferred to Heian-kyo, along with Koryu-ji Temple and Kurama-dera Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple is not only a Buddhist temple belonging to a group of the Hosso sect (one of the Nanto rokushu (the six sects of Buddhism which flourished in ancient Nara)), but also one of only a few Buddhist temples with history started before the period when the national capital was transferred to Heian-kyo, along with Koryu-ji Temple and Kurama-dera Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、石山寺（滋賀県大津市）、長谷寺（奈良県桜井市）などと並び、日本でも有数の観音霊場である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This temple is also ranked as one of eminent Kannon Pilgrimage along with Ishiyama-dera Temple in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture and Hase-dera Temple in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This temple is also ranked as one of the eminent Kannon Pilgrimage stops along with Ishiyama-dera Temple in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture and Hase-dera Temple in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This temple is also ranked as one of the eminent Kannon Pilgrimage stops along with Ishiyama-dera Temple in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture and Hase-dera Temple in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鹿苑寺（金閣寺）、嵐山などと並ぶ京都市内でも有数の観光地で、季節を問わず多くの参詣者が訪れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is known as one of best tourist sites in Kyoto City along with Rokuon-ji Temple (or Kinkaku-ji Temple) and Arashiyama, and therefore many people visit the temple in all seasons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is known as one of the best tourist sites in Kyoto City along with Rokuon-ji Temple (or Kinkaku-ji Temple) and Arashiyama, and therefore many people visit the temple in all seasons.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is known as one of the best tourist sites in Kyoto City along with Rokuon-ji Temple (or Kinkaku-ji Temple) and Arashiyama, and therefore many people visit the temple in all seasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>古都京都の文化財の一部としてユネスコ世界遺産に登録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is registered in the UNESCO World Heritage sites as a part of &quot;Historic Monuments of Ancient Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is registered in the UNESCO World Heritage sites as a part of the &quot;Historic Monuments of Ancient Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is registered in the UNESCO World Heritage sites as a part of the &quot;Historic Monuments of Ancient Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>創建伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradition for the foundation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foundation traditions</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foundation traditions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>清水寺の創建については、『群書類従』所収の藤原明衡撰の『清水寺縁起』、永正17年（1520年）制作の『清水寺縁起絵巻』（東京国立博物館蔵）にみえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the foundation of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, there are descriptions in &quot;Kiyomizu-dera Engi&quot; (The Origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple) selected by FUJIWARA no Akihira, the owner of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA), and &quot;Kiyomizu-dera Engi Emaki&quot; (&apos;The Picture Scroll of the Origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple,&apos; now it is owned by Tokyo National Museum) produced in 1520.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the foundation of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, there are descriptions in &quot;Kiyomizu-dera Engi&quot; (The Origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple) selected by FUJIWARA no Akihira, the owner of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; (Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA), and &quot;Kiyomizu-dera Engi Emaki&quot; (&apos;The Picture Scroll of the Origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple,&apos; now it is owned by Tokyo National Museum) produced in 1520.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the foundation of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, there are descriptions in &quot;Kiyomizu-dera Engi&quot; (The Origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple) selected by FUJIWARA no Akihira, the owner of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; (Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA), and &quot;Kiyomizu-dera Engi Emaki&quot; (&apos;The Picture Scroll of the Origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple,&apos; now it is owned by Tokyo National Museum) produced in 1520.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ほか、『今昔物語集』、『扶桑略記』の延暦十七年（798年）記などにも清水寺草創伝承が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (a collection of anecdotes), as well as a chapter of &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Brief History of Japan) mentioning the episode in 798 also introduces tradition about the foundation of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (a collection of anecdotes), as well as a chapter of &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Brief History of Japan) mentioning the episode in 798 also introduces tradition about the foundation of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (a collection of anecdotes), as well as a chapter of &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Brief History of Japan) mentioning the episode in 798 also introduces tradition about the foundation of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これらによれば、草創縁起は大略次のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to these books, the outline of the origin is as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to these books, the outline of the origin is as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to these books, the outline of the origin is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>宝亀9年（778年）、大和国興福寺の僧で子嶋寺で修行していた賢心（後に延鎮と改名）は、夢のお告げで北へ向かい、山城国愛宕郡八坂郷の東山、今の清水寺の地である音羽山に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 778, Kenshin (later Enchin), a Buddhist monk of Kofuku-ji Temple in Yamato Province, who had engaged in ascetic practices at Kojima-dera Temple, went north after he received a message from dream, reaching Mt. Higashi in Yasaka-kyo, Otagi-gun County, Yamashiro Province, now Mt. Otowa, the area Kiyomizu-dera Temple is situated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 778, Kenshin (later Enchin), a Buddhist monk of Kofuku-ji Temple in Yamato Province, who had engaged in ascetic practices at Kojima-dera Temple, went north after he received a message from a dream, reaching Mt. Higashi in Yasaka-kyo, Otagi-gun County, Yamashiro Province, now Mt. Otowa, the area where Kiyomizu-dera Temple is situated.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 778, Kenshin (later Enchin), a Buddhist monk of Kofuku-ji Temple in Yamato Province, who had engaged in ascetic practices at Kojima-dera Temple, went north after he received a message from a dream, reaching Mt. Higashi in Yasaka-kyo, Otagi County, Yamashiro Province, now Mt. Otowa, the area where Kiyomizu-dera Temple is situated.</e>
<cmt>住所修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>金色の水流を見出した賢心がその源をたどっていくと、そこにはこの山に篭って滝行を行い、千手観音を念じ続けている行叡居士（ぎょうえいこじ）という白衣の修行者がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tracing the path for the source of a golden current he found, he came across a practitioner of austerities, Gyoei-koji (a lay Buddhist, Gyoei) intently praying to Senju Kannon in white robe, who was confining himself to the mountain to practice religious austerities under the waterfall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tracing the path for the source of a golden current he found, he came across a practitioner of austerities, Gyoei-koji (a lay Buddhist, Gyoei) intently praying to Senju Kannon in a white robe, who was confining himself to the mountain to practice religious austerities under the waterfall.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tracing the path for the source of a golden current he found, he came across a practitioner of austerities, Gyoei-koji (a lay Buddhist, Gyoei) intently praying to Senju Kannon in a white robe, who was confining himself to the mountain to practice religious austerities under the waterfall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>年齢200歳になるという行叡居士は賢心に「私はあなたが来るのを長年待っていた。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 200-year-old Gyoei-koji said to Kenshin, &quot;I have waited for you long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 200-year-old Gyoei-koji said to Kenshin, &quot;I have waited for you long.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 200-year-old Gyoei-koji said to Kenshin, &quot;I have waited for you long.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「自分はこれから東国へ旅立つので、後を頼む」と言い残し、去っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I am leaving for Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) now, so I leave everything to you,&quot; and he left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I am leaving for Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region) now, so I leave everything to you,&quot; and he left.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I am leaving for Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region) now, so I leave everything to you,&quot; and he left.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>行叡は観音の化身であったと悟った賢心は、行叡が残していった霊木に千手観音像を刻み、行叡の旧庵に安置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Realizing that Gyoei was an incarnation of Kannon (Deity of Mercy), Kenshin carved a statue of Senju Kannon out of a sacred tree that Gyoei left so as to enshrine in the hermitage Gyoei had used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Realizing that Gyoei was an incarnation of Kannon (Deity of Mercy), Kenshin carved a statue of Senju Kannon out of a sacred tree that Gyoei left so as to enshrine in the hermitage Gyoei had used.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Realizing that Gyoei was an incarnation of Kannon (Deity of Mercy), Kenshin carved a statue of Senju Kannon out of a sacred tree that Gyoei left so as to enshrine in the hermitage Gyoei had used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これが清水寺の始まりであるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is believed to be the origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is believed to be the origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is believed to be the origin of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>その2年後の宝亀11年（780年）、鹿を捕えようとして音羽山に入り込んだ坂上田村麻呂（758年‐811年）は、修行中の賢心に出会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 780, two years later, SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro (758-811) who wandered into Mt. Otowa while chasing a deer happened to meet Kenshin being in the middle of ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 780, two years later, SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro (758-811) who wandered into Mt. Otowa while chasing a deer happened to meet Kenshin being in the middle of ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 780, two years later, SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro (758-811) who wandered into Mt. Otowa while chasing a deer happened to meet Kenshin being in the middle of ascetic practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>田村麻呂は妻の高子の病気平癒のため、薬になる鹿の生き血を求めてこの山に来たのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamuramaro told Kenshin that he came to the mountain to obtain blood of a living deer for his sick wife.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamuramaro told Kenshin that he came to the mountain to obtain blood of a living deer for his sick wife.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamuramaro told Kenshin that he came to the mountain to obtain blood of a living deer for his sick wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>延鎮より殺生の罪を説かれ、観音に帰依して観音像を祀るために自邸を本堂として寄進したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after being preached about a sin of killing by Enchin, Tamuramaro became a believer of Kannon and donated his residence as Hondo main hall (main sanctuary) to enshrine the statue of Kannon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after being preached about the sin of killing by Enchin, Tamuramaro became a believer of Kannon and donated his residence as the Hondo main hall (main sanctuary) to enshrine the statue of Kannon.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after being preached about the sin of killing by Enchin, Tamuramaro became a believer of Kannon and donated his residence as the Hondo main hall (main sanctuary) to enshrine the statue of Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後に征夷大将軍となり、東国の蝦夷平定を命じられた田村麻呂は、若武者と老僧（観音の使者である毘沙門天と地蔵菩薩の化身）の加勢を得て戦いに勝利し、無事に都に帰ることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tamuramaro--he had assumed the post of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) at that time-- later received orders to subjugate Ezo (inhabited area of Ainu tribe) in Togoku, he could win the battle with the support from a young samurai and an old monk (they are the incarnations of Bishamonten (Vaisravana) and Jizo Bosatsu (Ksitigarbha) respectively, and both of them are messengers of Kannon), and returned to the capital in safety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tamuramaro -- he had assumed the post of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) at that time -- later received orders to subjugate Ezo (inhabited area of the Ainu tribe) in Togoku, he could win the battle with the support from a young samurai and an old monk (they are the incarnations of Bishamonten (Vaisravana) and Jizo Bosatsu (Ksitigarbha) respectively, and both of them are messengers of Kannon), and returned to the capital in safety.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tamuramaro -- he had assumed the post of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) at that time -- later received orders to subjugate Ezo (inhabited area of the Ainu tribe) in Togoku, he could win the battle with the support from a young samurai and an old monk (they are the incarnations of Bishamonten (Vaisravana) and Jizo Bosatsu (Ksitigarbha) respectively, and both of them are messengers of Kannon), and returned to the capital in safety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>延暦17年（798年）、田村麻呂は延鎮（もとの賢心）と協力して本堂を大規模に改築し、観音像の脇侍として地蔵菩薩と毘沙門天の像を造り、ともに祀った、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Tamuramaro rebuilt the Hondo main hall on a large scale in cooperation with Enchin (former Kenshin), carving the statues of Jizo Bosatsu and Bishamonten regarded as Kyoji (attendant figures) of the statue of Kannon, and then enshrined them all together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Tamuramaro rebuilt the Hondo main hall on a large scale in cooperation with Enchin (former Kenshin), carving the statues of Jizo Bosatsu and Bishamonten regarded as Kyoji (attendant figures) of the statue of Kannon, and then enshrined them all together.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Tamuramaro rebuilt the Hondo main hall on a large scale in cooperation with Enchin (former Kenshin) in 798, carving the statues of Jizo Bosatsu and Bishamonten regarded as Kyoji (attendant figures) of the statue of Kannon, and then enshrined them all together.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>以上の縁起により、清水寺では行叡を元祖、延鎮を開山、田村麻呂を本願と位置づけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on these traditions, Kiyomizu-dera Temple recognizes Gyoei as the originator, Enchin as the Kaisan (founder of temple as the first chief priest), and Tamuramaro as the Hongan (promoter).</e>
<cmt>開山、本願ともに創立者の意味ですが、違いをだすために、本願を発起人と解釈し訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on these traditions, Kiyomizu-dera Temple recognizes Gyoei as the originator, Enchin as the Kaisan (founder of temple as the first chief priest), and Tamuramaro as the Hongan (promoter).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on these traditions, Kiyomizu-dera Temple recognizes Gyoei as the originator, Enchin as the Kaisan (founder of temple as the first chief priest), and Tamuramaro as the Hongan (promoter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>平安時代以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and after the Heian period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In and after the Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>延暦24年（805年）には太政官符により坂上田村麻呂が寺地を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reportedly, Daijokan (Grand Council of State) granted a temple land to SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro by issuing Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan) in 805.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reportedly, Daijokan (Grand Council of State) granted temple land to SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro by issuing Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan) in 805.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reportedly, Daijokan (Grand Council of State) granted temple land to SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro by issuing Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan) in 805.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>弘仁元年（810年）には嵯峨天皇の勅許を得て公認の寺院となり、「北観音寺」の寺号を賜ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is believed that the temple became the certified temple by the Imperial sanction, granted the Jigo (the name of a Buddhist temple) &apos;Kita-Kannon-ji Temple&apos; (literally, North-Kannon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is believed that the temple became the certified temple by Imperial sanction, granted the Jigo (the name of a Buddhist temple) &apos;Kita-Kannon-ji Temple&apos; (literally, North-Kannon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is believed that the temple became the certified temple by Imperial sanction by Emperor Saga in 810, granted the Jigo (the name of a Buddhist temple) &apos;Kita-Kannon-ji Temple&apos; (literally, North-Kannon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『枕草子』は「さわがしきもの」の例として清水観音の縁日を挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (an essay literature written in the Heian period) cites a festival day of Kiyomizu Kannon Temple as a good example of rollicking events.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (an essay literature written in the Heian period) cites a festival day of Kiyomizu Kannon Temple as a good example of rollicking events.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (an essay literature written in the Heian period) cites a festival day of Kiyomizu Kannon Temple as a good example of rollicking events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>『源氏物語』「夕顔」の巻や『今昔物語集』にも清水観音への言及がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chapter of &apos;Yugao&apos; in &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) and &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (a narrative literature) also mention Kiyomizu Kannon Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chapter of &apos;Yugao&apos; in &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) and &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (a narrative literature) also mention Kiyomizu Kannon Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chapter of &apos;Yugao&apos; in &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) and &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (a narrative literature) also mention Kiyomizu Kannon Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>など、平安時代中期には観音霊場として著名であったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These matters show that this temple had already become a famous Kannon Pilgrimage in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These matters show that this temple had already become a famous Kannon Pilgrimage stop in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These matters show that this temple had already become a famous Kannon Pilgrimage stop in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>清水寺の伽藍は康平6年（1063年）の火災（扶桑略記に言及）以来、近世の寛永6年（1629年）の焼失まで、記録に残るだけで9回の焼失を繰り返している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to records, from the burnt down in 1063, which is mentioned in &quot;Fuso ryakki,&quot; to that in the early-modern times 1629, the temple building of Kiyomizu-dera Temple was burnt down at least nine times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to records, starting with the burning down in 1063, which is mentioned in &quot;Fuso ryakki,&quot; to that in the early-modern times in 1629, the temple building of Kiyomizu-dera Temple was burnt down at least nine times.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to records, starting with the burning down in 1063, which is mentioned in &quot;Fuso ryakki,&quot; to that in the early-modern times in 1629, the temple building of Kiyomizu-dera Temple was burnt down at least nine times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>平安時代以来長らく興福寺の支配下にあったことから、興福寺と延暦寺のいわゆる「南都北嶺」の争いにもたびたび巻き込まれ、永万元年（1165年）には延暦寺の僧兵の乱入によって焼亡している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kiyomizu-dera Temple had been ruled by Kofuku-ji Temple for a long time since the Heian period, it was frequently involved in the conflict of &apos;Nanto Hokurei,&apos; conflict between Buddhism temples in Nara area and Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, burnt down due to the intrusion committed by warrior-monks of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1165.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kiyomizu-dera Temple had been ruled by the Kofuku-ji Temple for a long time since the Heian period, it was frequently involved in the conflicts of the &apos;Nanto Hokurei,&apos; conflict between Buddhist temples in the Nara area and Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, and was burnt down due to the intrusion committed by warrior-monks of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1165.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kiyomizu-dera Temple had been ruled by the Kofuku-ji Temple for a long time since the Heian period, it was frequently involved in the conflicts of the &apos;Nanto Hokurei,&apos; conflict between Buddhist temples in the Nara area and Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, and was burnt down due to the intrusion committed by warrior-monks of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1165.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>現在の本堂は上記寛永6年の火災の後、寛永10年（1633年）、徳川家光の寄進により再建されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current Hondo main hall is the structure rebuilt in 1633 after the above-mentioned fire in 1629, owing to the donation made by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current Hondo main hall is the structure rebuilt in 1633 after the above-mentioned fire in 1629, owing to the donation made by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current Hondo main hall is the structure rebuilt in 1633 after the above-mentioned fire in 1629, owing to the donation made by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>他の諸堂も多くはこの前後に再建されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other halls were also rebuilt around this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other halls were also rebuilt around this period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other halls were also rebuilt around this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern times</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>近代に入り、大正3年（1914年）には興福寺住職・法相宗管長であった大西良慶（1875年 - 1983年）が清水寺住職に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the modern times, Ryokei ONISHI (1875-1983), the chief priest of Kofuku-ji Temple and the chief abbot of the Hosso sect, assumed the post of the chief priest of Kiyomizu-dera Temple in 1914.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the modern times, Ryokei ONISHI (1875-1983), the chief priest of Kofuku-ji Temple and the chief abbot of the Hosso sect, assumed the post of the chief priest of Kiyomizu-dera Temple in 1914.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the modern times, Ryokei ONISHI (1875-1983), the chief priest of Kofuku-ji Temple and the chief abbot of the Hosso sect, assumed the post of the chief priest of Kiyomizu-dera Temple in 1914.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>大西は昭和40年（1965年）に法相宗から独立して北法相宗を開宗、初代管長となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leaving the Hosso sect, Onishi founded a new sect &quot;Kita Hoso sect&quot; to become the first chief abbot in 1965.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leaving the Hosso sect, Onishi founded a new sect, the &quot;Kita Hoso sect&quot; to become the first chief abbot in 1965.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leaving the Hosso sect, Onishi founded a new sect, the &quot;Kita Hoso sect&quot; to become the first chief abbot in 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>大西は昭和58年（1983年）、満107歳で没するまで70年近く清水寺貫主を務め、「中興の祖」と位置づけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onishi served as chief abbot of Kiyomizu-dera Temple for nearly 70 years until he died in 1983 at the age of 107, respected as &quot;Chuko-no-so&quot; (a restorer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onishi served as chief abbot of Kiyomizu-dera Temple for nearly 70 years until he died in 1983 at the age of 107, and respected as &quot;Chuko-no-so&quot; (a restorer).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onishi served as chief abbot of Kiyomizu-dera Temple for nearly 70 years until he died in 1983 at the age of 107, and respected as &quot;Chuko-no-so&quot; (a restorer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>大西は昭和41年（1966年）に月2回の北法相宗仏教文化講座を開始、昭和49年（1974年）には日中友好仏教協会を設立するなど、仏教を通じた国際交流、平和運動、文化活動などに尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onishi devoted himself to promote the international exchange, the peace movement, cultural activities, etc. through the Buddhism, which is shown in his achievements such as launching the bimonthly &quot;Hoso sect Buddhism culture course&quot; in 1966 and establishing &quot;The Japan-China Friendship Association of Buddhism&quot; in 1974.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onishi devoted himself to promote the international exchange, the peace movement, cultural activities, etc. through Buddhism, which is shown in his achievements such as launching the bimonthly &quot;Hoso sect Buddhism culture course&quot; in 1966 and establishing &quot;The Japan-China Friendship Association of Buddhism&quot; in 1974.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onishi devoted himself to promote the international exchange, the peace movement, cultural activities, etc. through Buddhism, which is shown in his achievements such as launching the bimonthly &quot;Hoso sect Buddhism culture course&quot; in 1966 and establishing &quot;The Japan-China Friendship Association of Buddhism&quot; in 1974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>境内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The precincts of Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The precincts of Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The precincts of Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>東大路通から清水寺までの約1.2キロの坂道は清水坂と称され、道の両側には観光客向けのみやげ物店などが軒を連ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sloping street of about 1.2Km ranging from Higashioji-dori Street to Kiyomizu-dera Temple is called Kiyomizu-zaka Slope, where many souvenir shops and others aimed at tourists stand side by side along both sides of the street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sloping street of about 1.2 km ranging from Higashioji-dori Street to Kiyomizu-dera Temple is called Kiyomizu-zaka Slope, where many souvenir shops and others aimed at tourists stand side by side along both sides of the street.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sloping street of about 1.2 km ranging from Higashioji-dori Street to Kiyomizu-dera Temple is called Kiyomizu-zaka Slope, where many souvenir shops and others aimed at tourists stand side by side along both sides of the street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>境内は標高242メートルの清水山（音羽山）中腹に石垣を築いて整地され、多くの建物が軒を接するように建ち並んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The land for the precincts was secured by constructing stone-wall at the half way up of 242m high Kiyomizu-yama Mountain (or Mt. Otowa), on which many structures stand closely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land for the precincts was secured by constructing a stone-wall half way up Kiyomizu-yama Mountain (or Mt. Otowa) at a height of 242m, on which many structures stand closely.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land for the precincts was secured by constructing a stone-wall half way up Mt. Kiyomizu (or Mt. Otowa) at a height of 242 m, on which many structures stand closely.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>入口の仁王門を過ぎ、西門、三重塔、鐘楼、経堂、田村堂（開山堂）、朝倉堂などを経て本堂に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After passing through the entrance &quot;Nio-mon gate&quot; (a Deva temple gate), visitors will reach Hondo main hall via &quot;Nishi-mon gate&quot; (the west gate), Three-Storied Pagoda, Shoro (a bell tower), Kyo-do Hall (Sutra Hall), Tamura-do Hall (or Kaisan-do Hall), Asakura-do Hall and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After passing through the entrance &quot;Nio-mon gate&quot; (a Deva temple gate), visitors will reach the Hondo main hall via &quot;Nishi-mon gate&quot; (the west gate), the Three-Storied Pagoda, Shoro (a bell tower), Kyo-do Hall (Sutra Hall), Tamura-do Hall (or Kaisan-do Hall), Asakura-do Hall and so on.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After passing through the entrance Nio-mon gate (a Deva temple gate), visitors will reach the Hondo main hall via Nishi-mon gate (the west gate), the Three-Storied Pagoda, Shoro (a bell tower), Kyo-do Hall (Sutra Hall), Tamura-do Hall (or Kaisan-do Hall), Asakura-do Hall and so on.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>本堂の先、境内の東側には北から釈迦堂、阿弥陀堂、奥の院が崖に面して建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ahead of Hondo main hall, in the east of the precincts, Shaka-do hall (a hall in which a statue of the historical Buddha, Shakamuni, is enshrined), Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) and Oku-no-in (inner sanctuary) in that order from the north stand facing toward precipice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beyond of the Hondo main hall, in the east of the precincts, Shaka-do hall (a hall in which a statue of the historical Buddha, Shakamuni, is enshrined), Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) and Oku-no-in (inner sanctuary) in that order from the north stand facing toward a precipice.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beyond of the Hondo main hall, in the east of the precincts, Shaka-do hall (a hall in which a statue of the historical Buddha, Shakamuni, is enshrined), Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) and Oku-no-in (inner sanctuary) in that order from the north stand facing toward a precipice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>本堂東側の石段を下りた先には寺名の由来でもある名水が3本の筧（かけい）から流れ落ちている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After going down the stone steps situated at the east side of Hondo main hall, visitors will find that famous pure water is dropping through three water pipe, which is the origin of the temple name; when Kiyomizu is written in Chinese character, it means pure water.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After going down the stone steps situated at the east side of the Hondo main hall, visitors will find that famous pure water is dropping through three water pipes, which are the origin of the temple name; when Kiyomizu is written in Chinese character, it means pure water.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After going down the stone steps situated at the east side of the Hondo main hall, visitors will find that famous pure water is dropping through three water pipes, which are the origin of the temple name; when Kiyomizu is written in Chinese character, it means pure water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>「音羽の滝」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The waterfall is called &apos;Otowa no taki Falls.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The waterfall is called &apos;Otowa no taki Falls.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The waterfall is called &apos;Otowa no taki Falls.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>音羽の滝からさらに南へ進むと、「錦雲渓」と呼ばれる谷を越えた先に塔頭寺院の泰産寺があり、「子安塔」と呼ばれる小さな三重塔がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With going ahead further to the south from &apos;Otowa no taki Falls,&apos; visitors will find a minor temple Taizan-ji Temple ahead of the valley called &apos;Kinunkei valley&apos; and a small three-storied pagoda called &apos;Koyasu-no-to pagoda.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heading further to the south from &apos;Otowa no taki Falls,&apos; visitors will find the minor temple of Taizan-ji Temple ahead of the valley called &apos;Kinunkei valley&apos; and a small three-storied pagoda called &apos;Koyasu-no-to pagoda.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heading further to the south from &apos;Otowa no taki Falls,&apos; visitors will find the minor temple of Taizan-ji Temple ahead of the valley called &apos;Kinunkei valley&apos; and a small three-storied pagoda called &apos;Koyasu-no-to pagoda.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>このほか、本堂の北に鎮守社の地主神社（じしゅじんじゃ）があり、さらに北には清水寺本坊の成就院がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, there is Jishu-jinja Shrine, a Chinju-sha shrine (Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) in the north of Hondo main hall, as well as Joju-in Temple, Honbo (main priest&apos;s residence) of Kiyomizu-dera Temple in the further north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is Jishu-jinja Shrine, a Chinju-sha shrine (Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) in the north of the Hondo main hall, as well as Joju-in Temple, Honbo (main priest&apos;s residence) of Kiyomizu-dera Temple further in the north.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is Jishu-jinja Shrine, a Chinju-sha shrine (Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) in the north of the Hondo main hall, as well as Joju-in Temple, Honbo (main priest&apos;s residence) of Kiyomizu-dera Temple further in the north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>本堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo main hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hondo main hall</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hondo main hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>国宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is designated as a National Treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is designated as a National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is designated as a National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>徳川家光の寄進により寛永10年（1633年）に再建されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current Hondo main hall is the structure rebuilt in 1633 owing to the donation made by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current Hondo main hall is the structure rebuilt in 1633 owing to the donation made by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current Hondo main hall is the structure rebuilt in 1633 owing to the donation made by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>「清水の舞台」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Kiyomizu no Butai&apos; (the stage of Kiyomizu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;Kiyomizu no Butai&apos; (the stage of Kiyomizu).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Kiyomizu no Butai&apos; (the stage of Kiyomizu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>屋根は寄棟造、檜皮葺きで、正面（南面）左右に入母屋造の翼廊が突き出し、外観に変化を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo main hall has the Yosemune-yane (the roof that descends from the ridge on four sides of a rectangular building) thatched with cypress bark, also having transepts of Irimoya-zukuri style (building with a half-hipped roof) on both sides of its south-facing facade, all of which provide its external appearance with unique feature.</e>
<cmt>「変化」ですが実際に変わるものではないため、特徴と考え訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hondo main hall has the Yosemune-yane (roof that descends from the ridge on four sides of a rectangular building) thatched with cypress bark, also having transepts of Irimoya-zukuri style (building with a half-hipped roof) on both sides of its south-facing facade, all of which provide its external appearance with unique features.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hondo main hall has the Yosemune-yane (roof that descends from the ridge on four sides of a rectangular building) thatched with cypress bark, also having transepts of Irimoya-zukuri style (building with a half-hipped roof) on both sides of its south-facing facade, all of which provide its external appearance with unique features.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>建物の前半部分は山の斜面にせり出すようにして建てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The front part of the structure has an appearance as if the part is pushed out over the slope of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The front part of the structure appears as if part of it is pushing out over the slope of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The front part of the structure appears as if part of it is pushing out over the slope of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>多くの長大な柱（139本という）が「舞台」と呼ばれるせり出し部分を支えている（釘は使われていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That part, which is called &apos;Butai&apos; (a stage), is supported by as many as 139 long and large pillars without using any nails.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That part, which is called the &apos;Butai&apos; (a stage), is supported by as many as 139 long and large pillars without using any nails.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That part, which is called the &apos;Butai&apos; (a stage), is supported by as many as 139 long and large pillars without using any nails.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>このような構造を「懸造（かけづくり）」、あるいは「舞台造」と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a structure is called &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; (overhang method of construction) or &apos;Butai-zukuri&apos; (the construction style like a stage).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a structure is called &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; (overhang method of construction) or &apos;Butai-zukuri&apos; (the construction style like a stage).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a structure is called &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; (overhang method of construction) or &apos;Butai-zukuri&apos; (the construction style like a stage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>観音菩薩は補陀洛山（ふだらくさん）に現われるという『法華経』「観世音菩薩普門品」（観音経）の所説に基づくものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why this Hondo main hall adopted this construction style is in the theory stated in &apos;Kanzeon Bosatsu Fumonhon&apos; (Kannon-gyo Sutra), a chapter in &quot;Hokke-kyo Sutra,&quot; which advocates that Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Bodhisattva) would come to Fudarakusan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why this Hondo main hall adopted this construction style is in the theory stated in &apos;Kanzeon Bosatsu Fumonhon&apos; (Kannon-gyo Sutra), a chapter in &quot;Hokke-kyo Sutra,&quot; which advocates that Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Bodhisattva) would come to Fudarakusan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why this Hondo main hall adopted this construction style is in the theory stated in &apos;Kanzeon Bosatsu Fumonhon&apos; (Kannon-gyo Sutra), a chapter in &quot;Hokke-kyo Sutra,&quot; which advocates that Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Bodhisattva) would come to Fudarakusan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>なお、同じく観音霊場である長谷寺や石山寺の本堂も同様の「懸造」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo main hall of Hase-dera Temple and Ishiyama-dera Temple, both of which are Kannon Pilgrimage, also adopt the similar &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hondo main hall of Hase-dera Temple and Ishiyama-dera Temple, both of which are Kannon Pilgrimage stops, also adopt a similar &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; style.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hondo main hall of Hase-dera Temple and Ishiyama-dera Temple, both of which are Kannon Pilgrimage stops, also adopt a similar &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>内々陣には、3基の厨子が置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are three bodies of Zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple) in the most inner sanctuary.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are three bodies of Zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple) in the inner most sanctuary.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are three bodies of Zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple) in the inner most sanctuary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>中央の厨子には本尊の千手観音立像、向かって右の厨子には毘沙門天立像、左の厨子には地蔵菩薩立像をそれぞれ安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A standing statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon is enshrined in the central Zushi, while a standing statue of Bishamonten is in the right-hand Zushi, as well as a standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu is in the left-hand Zushi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A standing statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon, is enshrined in the central Zushi, while a standing statue of Bishamonten is in the right-hand Zushi, as well as a standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu is in the left-hand Zushi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A standing statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon, is enshrined in the central Zushi, while a standing statue of Bishamonten is in the right-hand Zushi, as well as a standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu is in the left-hand Zushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>三尊とも秘仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three are hidden Buddhist statues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three are hidden Buddhist statues.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three are hidden Buddhist statues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>本尊厨子の左右には千手観音の眷属である二十八部衆像を安置し、内々陣左右端には風神・雷神像が安置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nijuhachi-bushu-zo,&quot; statues of the 28 Attendants of Senju Kannon, are enshrined on both sides of the central Zushi, and in addition, &quot;Fujin-zo statue&quot; (statue of Wind God) and &quot;Raijin-zo statue&quot; (statue of Thunder God) are enshrined on both far sides of the most inner sanctuary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nijuhachi-bushu-zo,&quot; statues of the 28 Attendants of Senju Kannon, are enshrined on both sides of the central Zushi, and in addition, &quot;Fujin-zo statue&quot; (statue of Wind God) and &quot;Raijin-zo statue&quot; (statue of Thunder God) are enshrined on both far sides of the most inner sanctuary.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijuhachi-bushu-zo, statues of the 28 Attendants of Senju Kannon, are enshrined on both sides of the central Zushi, and in addition, Fujin-zo statue (statue of Wind God) and Raijin-zo statue (statue of Thunder God) are enshrined on both far sides of the most inner sanctuary.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>思い切って物事を決断することを「清水の舞台から飛び降りるつもりで」と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Do boldly as if you jump down from the Kiyomizu-no-Butai&apos; is a common saying used when people make a bold decision.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Do boldly as if you were jumping down from the Kiyomizu-no-Butai&apos; is a common saying used when people make a bold decision.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Do boldly as if you were jumping down from the Kiyomizu-no-Butai&apos; is a common saying used when people make a bold decision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>清水寺の古文書調査によれば、実際に飛び降りた人が1694年から1864年の間に234件に上り、生存率は85.4パーセントであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The research of ancient documents conducted by Kiyomizu-dera Temple shows that 234 people actually jumped down from the Butai from 1694 to 1864 and 85.4% of them survived.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research of ancient documents conducted by Kiyomizu-dera Temple shows that 234 people actually jumped down from the Butai from 1694 to 1864 and 85.4% of them survived.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research of ancient documents conducted by Kiyomizu-dera Temple shows that 234 people actually jumped down from the Butai from 1694 to 1864 and 85.4% of them survived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>明治5年（1872年）に政府が飛び降り禁止令を出し、柵を張るなど対策を施したことで下火になったという</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of people who try to jump down from the Butai has reportedly decreased since 1872 because the government issued a prohibition on jumping down and took countermeasures such as establishing fence.</e>
<cmt>（・・・を下のセルに移動、下火に・・以下を上のセルに移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of people who try to jump down from the Butai has reportedly decreased since 1872 because the government issued a prohibition on jumping down and took countermeasures such as establishing a fence.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of people who try to jump down from the Butai has reportedly decreased since 1872 because the government issued a prohibition on jumping down and took countermeasures such as establishing a fence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>（これは写真に残っている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The fence is in a photo taken in those days.)</e>
<cmt>何が写真に残っているのか不明です。柵としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The fence remains in photos taken in those days.)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The fence remains in photos taken in those days.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="64">
<j>その他の建造物等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other structures, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other structures, etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other structures, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>奥の院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oku-no-in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oku-no-in</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oku-no-in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>- 本堂の全貌を見渡すことができる位置に建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Oku-no-in, visitors can enjoy the full picture of Hondo main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Oku-no-in, visitors can enjoy the full picture of the Hondo main hall.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Oku-no-in, visitors can enjoy the full picture of the Hondo main hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>本堂より小規模ながら、崖にせり出した懸造の建物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although being smaller than Hondo main hall, it adopts the &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; construction style, and therefore looks as if being pushed out over precipice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although being smaller than the Hondo main hall, it adopts the &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; construction style, and therefore looks as if it is being pushed out over the precipice.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although being smaller than the Hondo main hall, it adopts the &apos;Kake-zukuri&apos; construction style, and therefore looks as if it is being pushed out over the precipice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>本堂と同様に千手観音、毘沙門天、地蔵菩薩、二十八部衆、風神・雷神の諸仏を安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like Hondo main hall, statues of Senju Kannon, Bishamonten, Jizo Bosatsu, Nijuhachi-bushu (28 Attendants of Senju Kannon) and Fujin (Wind God) and Raijin (Thunder God) are enshrined there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like the Hondo main hall, statues of Senju Kannon, Bishamonten, Jizo Bosatsu, Nijuhachi-bushu (28 Attendants of Senju Kannon) and Fujin (Wind God) and Raijin (Thunder God) are enshrined there.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like the Hondo main hall, statues of Senju Kannon, Bishamonten, Jizo Bosatsu, Nijuhachi-bushu (28 Attendants of Senju Kannon) and Fujin (Wind God) and Raijin (Thunder God) are enshrined there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>ただし本尊は立像でなく坐像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the statue of Honzon is not a standing type, but a seated type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the statue of Honzon is not a standing type, but a seated type.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the statue of Honzon is not a standing type, but a seated type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="70">
<j>成就院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joju-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joju-in Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joju-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>- 境内北方にある、清水寺の本坊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joju-in Temple is the Honbo, main priest&apos;s residence of Kiyomizu-dera Temple situated in the north of precincts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joju-in Temple is the Honbo, main priest&apos;s residence of Kiyomizu-dera Temple situated in the north of the precincts.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joju-in Temple is the Honbo, main priest&apos;s residence of Kiyomizu-dera Temple situated in the north of the precincts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>池泉回遊式庭園は国の名勝に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chisen Kaiyu style garden (a style of Japanese garden with a path around a central pond and spring) is designated as a National Site of Scenic Beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chisen Kaiyu style garden (a style of Japanese garden with a path around a central pond and spring) is designated as a National Site of Scenic Beauty.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chisen Kaiyu style garden (a style of Japanese garden with a path around a central pond and spring) is designated as a National Site of Scenic Beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>秋季などに行われる特別公開の時期を除き、通常は非公開である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not open to the public as a general rule except certain periods such as the period for special viewing in autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not open to the public as a general rule except certain periods such as the period for special viewing in autumn.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not open to the public as a general rule except certain periods such as the period for special viewing in autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>なお、内部での撮影は原則として禁止となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, taking photos within the structure is prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, taking photos within the structure is prohibited.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, taking photos within the structure is prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="75">
<j>地主神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jishu-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jishu-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jishu-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>- 本堂の北にある、清水寺の鎮守社で縁結びの神として信仰を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jishu-jinja Shrine situated in the north of Hondo main hall is the Chinju-sha shrine of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, widely believed as a god of marriage (matchmaking).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jishu-jinja Shrine situated in the north of the Hondo main hall is the Chinju-sha shrine of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, widely believed to be a god of marriage (matchmaking).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jishu-jinja Shrine situated in the north of the Hondo main hall is the Chinju-sha shrine of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, widely believed to be a god of marriage (matchmaking).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>本殿、拝殿、総門は清水寺本堂と同じく寛永10年（1633年）の再建である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honden (main hall), Haiden (hall of worship) and So-mon gate (main gate) were rebuilt in 1633 like Hondo main hall of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honden (main hall), Haiden (hall of worship) and So-mon gate (main gate) were rebuilt in 1633 like the Hondo main hall of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honden (main hall), Haiden (hall of worship) and So-mon gate (main gate) were rebuilt in 1633 like the Hondo main hall of Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>ちなみに清水寺・仁王門前にある狛犬は地主神社のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the statue of Komainu (a pair of stone-carved guardian dogs) in front of the Nio-mon gate of Kiyomizu-dera Temple belongs to Jishu-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, the statue of Komainu (a pair of stone-carved guardian dogs) in front of the Nio-mon gate of Kiyomizu-dera Temple belongs to the Jishu-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, the statue of Komainu (a pair of stone-carved guardian dogs) in front of the Nio-mon gate of Kiyomizu-dera Temple belongs to the Jishu-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="79">
<j>坂上田村麻呂のゆかりからアテルイとモレを慰霊する石碑（1994年建立）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kiyomizu-dera Temple has a connection with SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, there is a stone monument erected in 1994 for performing the memorial service for Aterui and More (both of them were military leaders of Ezo in the Heian period, and were killed after being defeated by Tamuramaro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kiyomizu-dera Temple has a connection with SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, there is a stone monument erected in 1994 for performing the memorial service for Aterui and More (both of them were military leaders of Ezo in the Heian period, and were killed after being defeated by Tamuramaro).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kiyomizu-dera Temple has a connection with SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, there is a stone monument erected in 1994 for performing the memorial service for Aterui and More (both of them were military leaders of Ezo in the Heian period, and were killed after being defeated by Tamuramaro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>本尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzon</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>本堂本尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzon of Hondo main hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzon of the Hondo main hall</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzon of the Hondo main hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>清水寺本堂本尊の千手観音立像は33年に1度開扉の秘仏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standing statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of Hondo main hall of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, is a hidden Buddhist statue, kept in the Zushi whose door is opened once 33 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standing statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of the Hondo main hall of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, is a hidden Buddhist statue, kept in the Zushi whose door is opened once 33 years.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standing statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of the Hondo main hall of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, is a hidden Buddhist statue, kept in the Zushi whose door is opened once 33 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>この像については学術調査が行われたことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue has never been studied academically.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue has never been studied academically.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue has never been studied academically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>写真も公表されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, its photo has never been publicized, either.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, its photo has never been publicized either.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, its photo has never been publicized either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>ただし、秘仏本尊を模して造られた「お前立ち像」の写真は公表されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the photograph of &apos;Omaetachi-zo statue&apos; (the exhibited statue in place of the secret hidden one) produced by copying the Honzon, a hidden Buddhist statue has been publicized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the photograph of the &apos;Omaetachi-zo statue&apos; (the exhibited statue in place of the secret hidden one) produced by copying the Honzon, a hidden Buddhist statue has been publicized.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the photograph of the &apos;Omaetachi-zo statue&apos; (the exhibited statue in place of the secret hidden one) produced by copying the Honzon, a hidden Buddhist statue has been publicized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>本像は、42本の手のうち、左右各1本を頭上に伸ばして組み合わせ、化仏（けぶつ）を捧げ持つ特殊な形式の像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue has a unique style, because the statue with 42 arms extends a couple of its arms overhead to clasp its hands and lift up the Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue has a unique style, because the statue has 42 arms and extends a couple of its arms overhead to clasp its hands and lift up a Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue has a unique style, because the statue has 42 arms and extends a couple of its arms overhead to clasp its hands and lift up a Kebutsu (the Artificial Buddha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>このような形式の像を「清水寺形千手観音」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue with this style is called &apos;Kiyomizu Temple-styled Senju Kannon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue with this style is called &apos;Kiyomizu Temple-styled Senju Kannon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue with this style is called &apos;Kiyomizu Temple-styled Senju Kannon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>これを模した彫像、画像が日本各地に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are statues and portraits produced by copying this statue nationwide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are statues and portraits produced by copying this statue nationwide.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are statues and portraits produced by copying this statue nationwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>このような、脇手のうちの2本を頭上に掲げる形の千手観音については経典に典拠がなく、その由来は未詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no authority in the Buddhist scriptures about such a statue with a couple of its arm raising overhead, and therefore its origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no authority in the Buddhist scriptures about such a statue with a couple of its arm raising overhead, and therefore its origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no authority in the Buddhist scriptures about such a statue with a couple of its arm raising overhead, and therefore its origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>脇侍として毘沙門天像と地蔵菩薩像を安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kyoji, the statue of Bishamonten and that of Jizo Bosatsu are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kyoji, the statue of Bishamonten and that of Jizo Bosatsu are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kyoji, the statue of Bishamonten and that of Jizo Bosatsu are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>このうち地蔵菩薩像は、鎧で武装した上に袈裟を着け、兜をかぶり、剣を持つ特殊な形の像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jizo Bosatsu statue is unique, because the Jizo Bosatsu, the motif of the statue wears Kesa (Buddhist stole) over a suit of armor, having a helmet on and a sword in its hand.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jizo Bosatsu statue is unique because the Jizo Bosatsu, the motif of the statue wears Kesa (Buddhist stole) over a suit of armor, wearing a helmet and a sword in its hand.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jizo Bosatsu statue is unique because the Jizo Bosatsu, the motif of the statue wears Kesa (Buddhist stole) over a suit of armor, wearing a helmet and a sword in its hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>本堂本尊は、20世紀末以降では以下の機会に開帳された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Honzon of Hondo main hall has been unveiled during the periods mentioned below since the end of 20th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honzon of Hondo main hall has been unveiled during the periods mentioned below since the end of 20th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honzon of Hondo main hall has been unveiled during the periods mentioned below since the end of 20th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="91">
<j>2000年3月3日から同年12月3日まで（33年に一度の開帳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From March 3, 2000 to December 3 of the same year (Kaicho (unveiling) once 33 years)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From March 3, 2000 to December 3 of the same year (Kaicho (unveiling) once 33 years)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From March 3, 2000 to December 3 of the same year (Kaicho (unveiling) once 33 years)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>2008年9月1日から11月30日まで（西国三十三所巡礼の中興者とされる花山法皇一千年忌記念の結縁開帳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From September 1, 2008 to November 30 of the same year (This was the Kechien-Kaicho (unveiling to make a connection with Buddha) to commemorate the millenary of the Emperor Kazan&apos;s death, who is respected as a restorer of Saigoku Sanjusankasho Junrei (pilgrimage through 33 temples of Kansai Kannon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From September 1, 2008 to November 30 of the same year (This was the Kechien-Kaicho (unveiling to make a connection with Buddha) to commemorate the 1000th anniversary of Emperor Kazan&apos;s death, who is respected as a restorer of Saigoku Sanjusankasho Junrei (pilgrimage through 33 temples of Kansai Kannon).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From September 1, 2008 to November 30 of the same year (This was the Kechien-Kaicho (unveiling to make a connection with Buddha) to commemorate the 1000th anniversary of Emperor Kazan&apos;s death, who is respected as a restorer of Saigoku Sanjusankasho Junrei (pilgrimage through 33 temples of Kansai Kannon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>2009年3月1日から5月31日にも開帳予定）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaicho is also scheduled from March 1, 2009 to May 31of the same year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaicho is also scheduled from March 1, 2009 to May 31of the same year).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaicho is also scheduled from March 1, 2009 to May 31of the same year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>奥の院本尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzon of Oku-no-in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzon of Oku-no-in</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzon of Oku-no-in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>奥の院本尊の秘仏千手観音坐像（重要文化財）は、鎌倉時代の作で一木割矧造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Honzon of Oku-no-in, a seated statue of Senju Kannon that is also a hidden Buddhist statue (designated as an Important Cultural Property), was produced in the Kamakura period by the split-and-join method using wooden blocks from one tree.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honzon of Oku-no-in, a seated statue of Senju Kannon that is also a hidden Buddhist statue (designated as an Important Cultural Property), was produced in the Kamakura period by the split-and-join method using wooden blocks from one tree.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honzon of Oku-no-in, a seated statue of Senju Kannon that is also a hidden Buddhist statue (designated as an Important Cultural Property), was produced in the Kamakura period by the split-and-join method using wooden blocks from one tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>像高63.9センチメートル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue is 63.9cm in height.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue is 63.9 cm in height.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue is 63.9 cm in height.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>正面・右・左の3つの顔をもち、頭上に24の小面を乗せ、計27面をもつ特異な形の像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a unique appearance with 27 faces in total, three main faces (front face, right face and left face) and 24 small faces on its head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a unique appearance with 27 faces in total, three main faces (front face, right face and left face) and 24 small faces on its head.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a unique appearance with 27 faces in total, three main faces (front face, right face and left face) and 24 small faces on its head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>本面と左右脇面は額に縦の眼を有する三眼とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue has three eyes on each main face, two usual eyes and one vertical eye on the forehead.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue has three eyes on each main face, two usual eyes and one vertical eye on the forehead.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue has three eyes on each main face, two usual eyes and one vertical eye on the forehead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>膝前で組み合わせる宝鉢手は親指と人差し指で輪をつくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hohatsu-shu (hands for Hohatsu (A bowl used by Buddhist monks for meals, and as a begging bowl)), hands clasping in front of its knee, has a style making circles with thumbs and index fingers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hohatsu-shu (hands for Hohatsu (a bowl used by Buddhist monks for meals, and as a begging bowl)), hands clasping in front of its knees, has a style making circles with thumbs and index fingers.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Hohatsu-shu (hands for Hohatsu (a bowl used by Buddhist monks for meals, and as a begging bowl)), hands clasping in front of its knees, has a style making circles with thumbs and index fingers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>阿弥陀如来と同様の印相とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, features of those faces are similar to the features of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, features of those faces are similar to the features of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, features of those faces are similar to the features of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>光背に観音の三十三応現身を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Sanjusan Ogenshin (the images of the 33 reincarnations of Kannon) is displayed on the halo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Sanjusan Ogenshin (the images of the 33 reincarnations of Kannon) is displayed on the halo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Sanjusan Ogenshin (the images of the 33 reincarnations of Kannon) is displayed on the halo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>など、図像的に特異な点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, this statue has many peculiarities in terms of diagram and image.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, this statue has many peculiarities in terms of diagram and image.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, this statue has many peculiarities in terms of diagram and image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>作風には快慶風が強い、が作者を快慶と同定するには至っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While this statue includes lots of characteristics of a sculptor Kaikei, he has not yet been identified as author.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While this statue includes lots of characteristics of the sculptor Kaikei, he has not yet been identified as the creator.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While this statue includes lots of characteristics of the sculptor Kaikei, he has not yet been identified as the creator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>本像は2002年に重要文化財に指定され、翌2003年3月7日から12月7日まで243年ぶりに開帳された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue was designated as an Important Cultural Property in 2002, unveiled for the first time in 243years, from March 7, 2003 to December 7 of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue was designated as an Important Cultural Property in 2002, unveiled for the first time in 243 years, from March 7, 2003 to December 7 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue was designated as an Important Cultural Property in 2002, unveiled for the first time in 243 years, from March 7, 2003 to December 7 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>また、2008年8月から11月にかけて奈良国立博物館及び名古屋市博物館で開催された特別展「西国三十三所」に出陳された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it was exhibited in the special exhibitions &quot;Saigoku Sanjusankasho&quot; (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage) that were held at Nara National Museum and Nagoya City Museum from August to November 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it was exhibited in the special exhibitions &quot;Saigoku Sanjusankasho&quot; (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage) that were held at Nara National Museum and Nagoya City Museum from August to November 2008.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it was exhibited in the special exhibitions &apos;Saigoku Sanjusankasho&apos; (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage) that were held at Nara National Museum and Nagoya City Museum from August to November 2008.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural property</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>本堂 附厨子3基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo main hall including three bodies of Zushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hondo main hall including three bodies of Zushi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hondo main hall including three bodies of Zushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>文化財保護法第2条に基づき、建物とともに清水寺境内地も1993年9月1日付けで国宝に追加指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the second article of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, the precincts of Kiyomizu-dera Temple was additionally designated as a National Treasure along with the structure of Hondo main hall on September 1, 1993.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the second article of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, the precincts of Kiyomizu-dera Temple were additionally designated as a National Treasure along with the structure of the Hondo main hall on September 1, 1993.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the second article of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, the precincts of Kiyomizu-dera Temple were additionally designated as a National Treasure along with the structure of the Hondo main hall on September 1, 1993.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財（建造物）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Property (structures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property (structures)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property (structures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="107">
<j>仁王門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nio-mon gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nio-mon gate</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nio-mon gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>- 室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">established in the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>馬駐（うまとどめ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umatodome (hitching stables)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umatodome (hitching stables)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umatodome (hitching stables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>- 室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">established in the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in the Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>西門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishi-mon gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishi-mon gate</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishi-mon gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>三重塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-Storied Pagoda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-Storied Pagoda</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three-Storied Pagoda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>鐘楼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoro</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>- 慶長12年（1607年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">produced in 1607</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Produced in 1607</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Produced in 1607</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>経堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-do Hall</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>田村堂（開山堂）附厨子1基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamura-do Hall (or Kaizan-do Hall) including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamura-do Hall (or Kaizan-do Hall) including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamura-do Hall (or Kaizan-do Hall) including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>朝倉堂 附厨子1基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asakura-do Hall including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asakura-do Hall including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asakura-do Hall including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>鎮守堂（春日社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinju-do Hall (a guardian god hall, also called Kasuga-sha Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinju-do Hall (a guardian god hall, also called Kasuga-sha Shrine)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinju-do Hall (a guardian god hall, also called Kasuga-sha Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>本坊北総門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So-mon gate in the north of Honbo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So-mon gate in the north of Honbo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So-mon gate in the north of Honbo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>轟門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Todoroki-mon Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Todoroki-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Todoroki-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>釈迦堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka-do hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka-do hall</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka-do hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>阿弥陀堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amida-do Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida-do Hall</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida-do Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>奥の院 附厨子1基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oku-no-in including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oku-no-in including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oku-no-in including a body of Zushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>子安塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koyasu-no-to pagoda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koyasu-no-to pagoda</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koyasu-no-to pagoda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>地主神社本殿・拝殿・総門　地主神社境内地も社殿と一体をなして価値を形成するものとして重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Honden, Haiden and So-mon gate of Jishu-jinja Shrine as well as its precincts are also regarded as valuable properties along with the main building of a Shinto shrine, and therefore they were designated as an Important Cultural Property altogether.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the Honden, Haiden and So-mon gate of the Jishu-jinja Shrine as well as its precincts are also regarded as valuable properties along with the main building of the Shinto shrine, and therefore they were designated as an Important Cultural Property altogether.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the Honden, Haiden and So-mon gate of the Jishu-jinja Shrine as well as its precincts are also regarded as valuable properties along with the main building of the Shinto shrine, and therefore they were designated as an Important Cultural Property altogether.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>以上の建物のうち特記のないものは寛永年間（1630年代）の建立である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structures mentioned above without annotation were constructed during the Kanei period (in the 1630s).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structures mentioned above without annotation were constructed during the Kanei period (in the 1630s).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structures mentioned above without annotation were constructed during the Kanei period (in the 1630s).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財（美術工芸品）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Property (arts and crafts products)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property (arts and crafts products)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property (arts and crafts products)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="127">
<j>木造千手観音坐像（奥の院本尊）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokuzo Senju Kannon Zazo (wooden seated statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of Oku-no-in)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokuzo Senju Kannon Zazo (wooden seated statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of Oku-no-in)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokuzo Senju Kannon Zazo (wooden seated statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of Oku-no-in)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="128">
<j>木造十一面観音立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokuzo Juichimen Kannon Ryuzo (wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokuzo Juichimen Kannon Ryuzo (wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokuzo Juichimen Kannon Ryuzo (wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>- 本堂本尊の十一面千手観音立像とは別個の像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue and Juichimen Senju Kannon Ryuzo (standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon) that is the Honzon of Hondo main hall are different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue and Juichimen Senju Kannon Ryuzo (standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon) that is the Honzon of the Hondo main hall are different.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue and Juichimen Senju Kannon Ryuzo (standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon) that is the Honzon of the Hondo main hall are different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="130">
<j>木造伝・観音勢至菩薩立像（もと阿弥陀堂安置）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokuzo-den Kannon Seishi Bosatsu Ryuzo (wooden standing statue attributed to Kannon Bodhisattva and Mahasthamaprapta, previously enshrined in Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokuzo-den Kannon Seishi Bosatsu Ryuzo (wooden standing statue attributed to Kannon Bodhisattva and Mahasthamaprapta, previously enshrined in Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokuzo-den Kannon Seishi Bosatsu Ryuzo (wooden standing statue attributed to Kannon Bodhisattva and Mahasthamaprapta, previously enshrined in Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>木造大日如来坐像（もと真福寺大日堂安置）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokuzo Dainichi Nyorai Zazo (wooden seated statue of Dainichi Nyorai, previously enshrined in Dainichi-do Hall of Shinpuku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokuzo Dainichi Nyorai Zazo (wooden seated statue of Dainichi Nyorai, previously enshrined in Dainichi-do Hall of Shinpuku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokuzo Dainichi Nyorai Zazo (wooden seated statue of Dainichi Nyorai, previously enshrined in Dainichi-do Hall of Shinpuku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>木造毘沙門天立像（塔頭慈心院所有）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokuzo Bishamonten Ryuzo (wooden standing statue of Bishamonten, belonging to the sub-temple Jishin-in Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokuzo Bishamonten Ryuzo (wooden standing statue of Bishamonten, belonging to the sub-temple Jishin-in Temple)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokuzo Bishamonten Ryuzo (wooden standing statue of Bishamonten, belonging to the sub-temple Jishin-in Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>渡海船額（末吉船図3・角倉船図1）4面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four pictures of Tokai Sengaku (votive horse tablet praying for success in foreign trade, motif of three pictures among four; Sueyoshi Ship (the shogunate-licensed trading ship owned by the Sueyoshi family), motif of the other; Suminokura Ship (the shogunate-licensed trading ship owned by Ryoi SUMINOKURA.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four pictures of Tokai Sengaku (votive horse tablet praying for success in foreign trade, motif of three pictures among four; Sueyoshi Ship (the shogunate-licensed trading ship owned by the Sueyoshi family), motif of the other; Suminokura Ship (the shogunate-licensed trading ship owned by Ryoi SUMINOKURA)).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four pictures of Tokai Sengaku (votive horse tablet praying for success in foreign trade, motif of three pictures among four; Sueyoshi Ship (the shogunate-licensed trading ship owned by the Sueyoshi family), motif of the other; Suminokura Ship (the shogunate-licensed trading ship owned by Ryoi SUMINOKURA)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>板絵朝比奈草摺曳図（伝・長谷川久蔵筆）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Itae Asahina Kusazurihiki-zu (painting on the board of a samurai warrior, Asahina, attributed to Kyuzo HASEGAWA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Itae Asahina Kusazurihiki-zu (painting on the board of a samurai warrior, Asahina, attributed to Kyuzo HASEGAWA)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Itae Asahina Kusazurihiki-zu (painting on the board of a samurai warrior, Asahina, attributed to Kyuzo HASEGAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>京都市内の社寺に残る大絵馬では最古のもので、寛永6年（1629年）の旧本堂炎上の際、これ1点のみ焼け残ったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Itae is the oldest votive horse tablet among tablets remaining in shrines and temples in Kyoto city, which was the only tablet survived the fire burned down the former Hondo main hall in 1629.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Itae is the oldest votive horse tablet among tablets remaining in shrines and temples in Kyoto city, which was the only tablet that survived the fire that burned down the former Hondo main hall in 1629.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Itae is the oldest votive horse tablet among tablets remaining in shrines and temples in Kyoto City, which was the only tablet that survived the fire that burned down the former Hondo main hall in 1629.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>天正20年（1592年）の奉納銘がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This painting has a signature of 1592.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This painting has a signature from 1592.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This painting has a signature from 1592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>筆者は長谷川等伯の子・久蔵とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author is believed to be Kyuzo HASEGAWA, a child of Tohaku HASEGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author is believed to be Kyuzo HASEGAWA, a child of Tohaku HASEGAWA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author is believed to be Kyuzo HASEGAWA, a child of Tohaku HASEGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="138">
<j>鉄鰐口（もと阿弥陀堂所在）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsu Waniguchi (a steel gong, previously enshrined in Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsu Waniguchi (a steel gong, previously enshrined in Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsu Waniguchi (a steel gong, previously enshrined in Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>梵鐘 文明10年（1478年）銘（辺見抗米）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonsho with a signature of 1478 (produced by Komai HENMI)</e>
<cmt>辺見抗米が梵鐘にどのように関係あるのかわかりません。作者としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonsho with a signature from 1478 (produced by Komai HENMI)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonsho with a signature from 1478 (produced by Komai HENMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="140">
<j>重要文化財の仏像のうち、千手観音坐像は秘仏、その他の像は宝蔵殿に収蔵され非公開である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Buddha statues designated as the Important Cultural Property, the seated statue of Senju Kannon is the hidden Buddhist statue, while other statues are preserved at Hozoden (treasure hall) without being unveiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Buddha statues designated as Important Cultural Properties, the seated statue of Senju Kannon is the hidden Buddhist statue, while other statues are preserved at Hozoden (treasure hall) without being unveiled.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Buddha statues designated as Important Cultural Properties, the seated statue of Senju Kannon is the hidden Buddhist statue, while other statues are preserved at Hozoden (treasure hall) without being unveiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>本堂本尊の秘仏千手観音像は指定文化財ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hidden statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of Hondo main hall is not a designated cultural property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hidden statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of Hondo main hall is not a designated cultural property.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hidden statue of Senju Kannon, the Honzon of Hondo main hall is not a designated cultural property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="142">
<j>算額　明治25年　池内善之助、伊三郎奉納</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangaku (Japanese votive tablets featuring mathematical puzzles) donated by Zennosuke and Isaburo IKEUCHI in 1892</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangaku (Japanese votive tablets featuring mathematical puzzles) donated by Zennosuke and Isaburo IKEUCHI in 1892</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangaku (Japanese votive tablets featuring mathematical puzzles) donated by Zennosuke and Isaburo IKEUCHI in 1892</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="143">
<j>御詠歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goeika (song in praise of the Buddha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goeika (song in praise of the Buddha)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goeika (song in praise of the Buddha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>松風や</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Otowa enjoys wind blowing from a pine grove.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Otowa enjoys wind blowing from a pine grove.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Otowa enjoys wind blowing from a pine grove.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>音羽の滝の</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the mountain, there are &quot;Otowa no taki Falls&quot; with miraculous efficacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the mountain, there are &quot;Otowa no taki Falls&quot; with miraculous efficacy.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the mountain, there are &quot;Otowa no taki Falls&quot; with miraculous efficacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>清水を</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Water running the waterfalls is quite pure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Water running from the waterfalls is quite pure.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water running from the waterfalls is quite pure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>むすぶ心は</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple was established in such a precious location due to an unexpected meeting of three people, Gyoei, Kenshin and SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro who were guided by the Senju Kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomizu-dera Temple was established in such a precious location due to an unexpected meeting of three people, Gyoei, Kenshin and SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro who were guided by the Senju Kannon.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple was established in such a precious location due to an unexpected meeting of three people, Gyoei, Kenshin and SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro who were guided by the Senju Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>涼しかるらん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What magnificent power Senju Kannon possesses!</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What magnificent power Senju Kannon possesses!</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What magnificent power Senju Kannon possesses!</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>札所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudasho (stamp office)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudasho (stamp office)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudasho (stamp office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="149">
<j>西国三十三箇所観音霊場　第16番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 16 of Saigoku Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp office for temple number 16 of Saigoku Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 16 of Saigoku Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>法然上人二十五霊跡　第13番（阿弥陀堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 13 of Honen Shonin&apos;s 25 sacred sites (Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp office for temple number 13 of Honen Shonin&apos;s 25 sacred sites (Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 13 of Honen Shonin&apos;s 25 sacred sites (Amida-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>洛陽三十三所観音霊場　第10番（善光寺堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 10 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (the 33 Temples of Rakuyo Kannon Pilgrimage in Kyoto, Zenko-ji-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp office for temple number 10 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (the 33 Temples of Rakuyo Kannon Pilgrimage in Kyoto, Zenko-ji-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 10 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (the 33 Temples of Rakuyo Kannon Pilgrimage in Kyoto, Zenko-ji-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>洛陽三十三所観音霊場　第11番（奥の院）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 11 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Oku-no-in)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp office for temple number 11 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Oku-no-in)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 11 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Oku-no-in)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>洛陽三十三所観音霊場　第12番（本堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 12 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Hondo main hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp office for temple number 12 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Hondo main hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 12 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Hondo main hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>洛陽三十三所観音霊場　第13番（朝倉堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 13 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Asakura-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp office for temple number 13 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Asakura-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 13 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Asakura-do Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>洛陽三十三所観音霊場　第14番（泰産寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 14 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Taizan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp office for temple number 14 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Taizan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp office for temple number 14 of Rakuyo Sanjusankasho Kannon Pilgrimage (Taizan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="156">
<j>前後の札所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudasho before and after Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudasho before and after Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudasho before and after Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>西国三十三箇所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigoku Sanjusankasho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigoku Sanjusankasho</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigoku Sanjusankasho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>15 観音寺 (京都市東山区)　--　16 清水寺　--　17 六波羅蜜寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">number 15; Kannon-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City)--number 16; Kiyomizu-dera Temple--number 17; Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Number 15; Kannon-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City) -- Number 16; Kiyomizu-dera Temple -- Number 17; Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Number 15; Kannon-ji Temple (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City) -- Number 16; Kiyomizu-dera Temple -- Number 17; Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>雑学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Encyclopedic knowledge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Encyclopedic knowledge</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Encyclopedic knowledge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="159">
<j>今年の漢字</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanji (Chinese character) of the Year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanji (Chinese character) of the Year</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanji (Chinese character) of the Year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>バブル期より毎年漢字の日の12月12日（ただし事情によりずれる場合もある）に、財団法人日本漢字能力検定協会主催によりその年の世相を漢字一字で表現する「今年の漢字」が清水寺で発表される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the period of bubble economy, &quot;Kanji of the Year,&quot; one Chinese character representing the social conditions of the year, has been announced every year at Kiyomizu-dera Temple under the auspices of &quot;The Japan Kanji Aptitude Testing Foundation&quot; on December 12th, &quot;the day for Kanji&quot; (however, the day may be shifted according to circumstances).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the period of bubble economy, &quot;Kanji of the Year,&quot; one Chinese character representing the social conditions of the year, have been announced every year at Kiyomizu-dera Temple under the auspices of &quot;The Japan Kanji Aptitude Testing Foundation&quot; on December 12th, &quot;the day for Kanji&quot; (however, the day may be shifted according to circumstances).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the period of bubble economy, &apos;Kanji of the Year,&apos; one Chinese character representing the social conditions of the year, have been announced every year at Kiyomizu-dera Temple under the auspices of The Japan Kanji Aptitude Testing Foundation on December 12, &apos;the day for Kanji&apos; (however, the day may be shifted according to circumstances).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="161">
<j>新・世界七不思議</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The New Seven wonders of the World</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The New Seven wonders of the World</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The New Seven wonders of the World</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>スイスの財団が実施している「新・世界七不思議」を選ぶ取り組みで、京都市東山区の清水寺が日本で唯一、中国の万里の長城やフランスのエッフェル塔などとともに最終候補地に選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the project to select &apos;The New Seven wonders of the World&apos; carried out by a foundation in Switzerland, Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City became the only site in Japan that went through to the final selection along with other sites such as the Great Wall of China and the Eiffel Tower in France.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the project to select &apos;The New Seven wonders of the World&apos; carried out by a foundation in Switzerland, Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City became the only site in Japan that went through to the final selection along with other sites such as the Great Wall of China and the Eiffel Tower in France.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the project to select &apos;The New Seven wonders of the World&apos; carried out by a foundation in Switzerland, Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City became the only site in Japan that went through to the final selection along with other sites such as the Great Wall of China and the Eiffel Tower in France.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>それを記念して財団から賞状を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For commemorating the honor, Kiyomizu-dera Temple later received a letter of commendation from the foundation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To commemorate this honor, Kiyomizu-dera Temple later received a letter of commendation from the foundation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To commemorate this honor, Kiyomizu-dera Temple later received a letter of commendation from the foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="164">
<j>インターネットと電話による投票が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The site for &quot;The New Seven wonders of the World&quot; was decided by a vote through the Internet and telephone.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site for &quot;The New Seven wonders of the World&quot; was decided by a vote through the Internet and telephone.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site for &apos;The New Seven wonders of the World&apos; was decided by a vote through the Internet and telephone.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>2007年7月7日にリスボンで発表された最終結果では次選となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the final selection whose result was announced in Lisbon on July 7, 2007, Kiyomizu-dera Temple ranked second.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the final selection whose result was announced in Lisbon on July 7, 2007, Kiyomizu-dera Temple ranked second.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the final selection whose result was announced in Lisbon on July 7, 2007, Kiyomizu-dera Temple ranked second.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="166">
<j>清水寺が登場する文学作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary work in which Kiyomizu-dera Temple appears</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary work in which Kiyomizu-dera Temple appears</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary work in which Kiyomizu-dera Temple appears</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>平安時代以来、『源氏物語』、『枕草子』、『更級日記』、『梁塵秘抄』などの古典文学に言及された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple had appeared in various classical literatures such as &quot;Genji Monogatari,&quot; &quot;Makura no soshi,&quot; &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (Diary written by a daughter of Sugawara Takasue), &quot;Ryojin hisho&quot; (anthology of songs) since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomizu-dera Temple has appeared in various classical literatures such as &quot;Genji Monogatari,&quot; &quot;Makura no soshi,&quot; &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (Diary written by a daughter of Sugawara Takasue), and &quot;Ryojin hisho&quot; (anthology of songs) since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple has appeared in various classical literatures such as &quot;Genji Monogatari,&quot; &quot;Makura no soshi,&quot; &quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (Diary written by a daughter of Takasue SUGAWARA), and &quot;Ryojin hisho&quot; (anthology of songs) since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>『枕草子』は、「さはがしきもの」の例として清水寺の縁日の日を挙げており、平安時代、既に多くの参詣者を集めていたことが伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Makura no soshi&quot; cites a festival day of Kiyomizu-dera Temple as a good example of &apos;rollicking events,&apos; which shows that this temple had already become famous among pilgrims.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Makura no soshi&quot; cites a festival day of Kiyomizu-dera Temple as a good example of &apos;rollicking events,&apos; which shows that this temple had already become famous among pilgrims.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Makura no soshi&quot; cites a festival day of Kiyomizu-dera Temple as a good example of &apos;rollicking events,&apos; which shows that this temple had already become famous among pilgrims during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>近世には浄瑠璃、歌舞伎などにも清水寺が登場する作品がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early-modern times, Kiyomizu-dera Temple also appears in the works of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment), Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early-modern times, Kiyomizu-dera Temple also appears in the works of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a shamisen accompaniment), Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) and so on.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early-modern times, Kiyomizu-dera Temple also appears in the works of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a shamisen accompaniment), Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="170">
<j>清水寺貫主の大西良慶が、本寺を法相宗から独立させ北法相宗を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryokei ONISHI, the chief abbot of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, attained the independence of the main temple from the Hosso sect, and then founded the &quot;Kita Hoso sect.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryokei ONISHI, the chief abbot of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, attained independence of the main temple from the Hosso sect, and then founded the &quot;Kita Hoso sect.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryokei ONISHI, the chief abbot of Kiyomizu-dera Temple, attained independence of the main temple from the Hosso sect, and then founded the Kita Hoso sect.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>大西は晩年には日本最高齢者となったこともあり、日本初の五つ子の名付け親にもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onishi became the oldest person in Japan in his last years, which provided him with honor to give names to the first quintuplets born in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onishi became the oldest person in Japan in his last years, which provided him with honor to give names to the first quintuplets born in Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onishi became the oldest person in Japan in his last years, which provided him with honor to give names to the first quintuplets born in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="172">
<j>1985年、京都市が市内の観光寺院へ古都保存協力税の特別徴収義務者を依頼したが清水寺は拒否、他の寺と古都税騒動と呼ばれる政治事件を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kyoto City tried to designate the temples in the city where tourists frequently visit as the agent responsible to pay a special tax, so-called &quot;The Kyoto Old Capital Preservation Cooperation Tax&quot; in 1985, Kiyomizu-dera Temple rebuffed it and caused a political trouble called &quot;Koto-zei-sodo&quot; (dispute over the old capital tax) in concert with other temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kyoto City tried to designate the temples in the city where tourists frequently visit as agents responsible for paying a special tax, the so-called &quot;Kyoto Old Capital Preservation Cooperation Tax&quot; in 1985, Kiyomizu-dera Temple rebuffed it and caused political trouble called the &quot;Koto-zei-sodo&quot; (dispute over the old capital tax) in concert with other temples.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kyoto City tried to designate the temples in the city where tourists frequently visit as agents responsible for paying a special tax, the so-called &quot;Kyoto Old Capital Preservation Cooperation Tax&quot; in 1985, Kiyomizu-dera Temple rebuffed it and caused political trouble called the &quot;Koto-zei-sodo&quot; (dispute over the old capital tax) in concert with other temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="173">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京阪本線「清水五条駅」下車徒歩約25分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 25 minutes walk from &apos;Kiyomizu-gojo Station&apos; of Keihan Electric Railway Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 25 minutes walk from &apos;Kiyomizu-gojo Station&apos; of the Keihan Electric Railway Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 25 minutes walk from &apos;Kiyomizu-gojo Station&apos; of the Keihan Electric Railway Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>京都市営バス「清水道」及び京阪バス「五条坂」（市バス100、206）停留所下車徒歩約1５分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 15 minutes walk from either &apos;Kiyomizu-michi Bus Stop&apos; of Kyoto City Bus (line 100 or 206) or &apos;Gojozaka Bus Stop&apos; of Keihan Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 15 minutes walk from either &apos;Kiyomizu-michi Bus Stop&apos; of Kyoto City Bus (line 100 or 206) or &apos;Gojozaka Bus Stop&apos; of Keihan Bus</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 15 minutes walk from either &apos;Kiyomizu-michi Bus Stop&apos; of Kyoto City Bus (line 100 or 206) or &apos;Gojozaka Bus Stop&apos; of Keihan Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kanejan(id:78613), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Nnh(id:474), KMT(id:1772), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Lupinoid(id:68), Peter.nezumi(id:164884), Zenzai-Doji(id:98967), ＋－(id:17104), Amano3636(id:202075), Opponent(id:720), 眠(id:82369), ワイルドマン(id:198112), Cloudya(id:111115), BotMultichill(id:132395), Point136(id:211299), Shadow ump(id:112836), Maakun(id:16735), FlaBot(id:30804), 木島無名(id:29709), たね(id:10372), Tiyoringo(id:70026), TEy(id:32722), Komatta(id:52309), 南無観自在(id:180807), Goncyan(id:92158), Escarbot(id:59151), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Hatsune(id:26654), Nnn(id:26535), 倶楽部オータム(id:139861), Ilovekyoto(id:94930), JAnDbot(id:66507), JKT(id:80762), Yard(id:59322), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Reggaeman(id:6214), Urania(id:7213), Jinzo(id:209385), Araisyohei(id:378), D.h(id:79056), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Knife(id:10235), ムカイ(id:72972), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Nobuo Yamanaka(id:89419), MCHC(id:208548), Nkensei(id:26989), Kinori(id:443), Kftsang hk(id:37062), 怪蘇(id:45514), Rei-bot(id:94097), ChibaRagi(id:68046), Kurihaya(id:132524), Nopira(id:29335), Volfgang(id:98768), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tassi-(id:81774), New Japan(id:310406), Folivora(id:228582), RockHeaven(id:66567), LaaknorBot(id:220851), 沼田寅松(id:26068), Carkuni(id:79281), Hix2(id:115746), Wc(id:253787), Monado(id:53906), よしえもん(id:59920), Mooko(id:36162), VolkovBot(id:105371), CarsracBot(id:217884), BUNBUN(id:63624), Miya(id:1881), Mochi(id:9489), Pitan(id:171), 663highland(id:18755), Chibang(id:19967), 商事品川(id:68669), Cpro(id:28341), SieBot(id:126695), っ(id:4481), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>