<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長谷寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hase-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hase-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hase-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>山号 豊山（ぶざん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sango (literally, &quot;mountain name&quot;, which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple): Buzan</e>
<cmt>長谷寺のHP (http://www.hasedera.or.jp/2009/treasure/index.html）には豊山（ぶさん）とありますが、原文のまま（ぶざん）と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sango (literally &quot;mountain name&quot;, this is a title prefixed to the name of Buddhist temples): Buzan</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sango (literally &quot;mountain name&quot;, this is a title prefixed to the name of Buddhist temples): Buzan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宗派 真言宗豊山派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious school: the Buzan school of the Shingon sect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious school: the Buzan school of Shingon Buddhism</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious school: the Buzan school of Shingon Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>寺格 総本山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikaku (status of a Buddhist temple): Sohonzan (the head temple of a Buddhist sect)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikaku (status of a Buddhist temple): Sohonzan (head temple)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikaku (status of a Buddhist temple): Sohonzan (head temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本尊 十一面観音（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzon (principal image of Buddha): Eleven-faced Kannon (Goddess of Mercy) (an important cultural property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzon (principal image of Buddha): Eleven-faced Kannon, the Goddess of Mercy (an Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzon (principal image of Buddha): Eleven-faced Kannon, the Goddess of Mercy (an Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>創建年 奈良時代（8世紀前半）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of founding: the Nara period (the early part of the 8th century)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established: Nara period (early 8th century)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established: Nara period (early 8th century)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>開基 道明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiki (patron of a temple in its founding): Domyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founder: Domyo</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founder: Domyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>正式名 豊山 神楽院 長谷寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official name: Buzan Kagurain (神楽院) Hase-dera</e>
<cmt>神楽院の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official name: Buzan Kagurain Hase-dera</e>
<cmt>ArticleDeleted kanji</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official name: Buzan Kagurain Hase-dera</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>別称 花の御寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name: the flower temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other name: the Flower Temple</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other name: the Flower Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>札所等 西国三十三箇所8番真言宗十八本山16番神仏霊場 巡拝の道 第35番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) etc: the 8th of the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage, the 16th of Shingonshu juhachi honzan (18 Head Temple of Shingon sect) and the 35th of Shinbutsu Reijo Junpai no Michi (the road for pilgrimage to the sacred places of Gods or Buddha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudasho (temple on a pilgrimage route): 8th of the thirty-three-temple Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage; 16th of the eighteen-temple Shingon Head Temple Pilgrimage; 35th temple on the Sacred Places of Shinto and Buddhism Pilgrimage</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudasho (temple collecting and offering amulets): 8th of the thirty-three-temple Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage; 16th of the eighteen-temple Shingon Head Temple Pilgrimage; 35th temple on the Sacred Places of Shinto and Buddhism Pilgrimage</e>
<cmt>札所は、単に「巡礼路上にあるお寺」というより、「お守り札を納めたり貰ったりするお寺」という点に意義があると思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>文化財 本堂、長谷寺経、銅板法華説相図（国宝）木造十一面観音立像、仁王門ほか（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cultural properties: Hondo (main hall), Hase-dera kyo (sutra), Bronze Plaque Hokke Sesso Zu (a national treasure), the wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon, Nio-mon Gate (Deva gate) and so on (important cultural properties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural properties: the Hondo, or main hall; the Hase-dera sutra; the bronze plaque of the Hokke Sesso-zu (National Treasure); the wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon; the Nio (or Deva) Gate; etc (Important Cultural Properties)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties: the Hondo, or main hall; the Hase-dera sutra; the bronze plaque of the Hokke Sesso-zu (National Treasure); the wooden standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon; the Nio (or Deva) Gate; etc (Important Cultural Properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>長谷寺（はせでら）は、奈良県桜井市にある真言宗豊山派（ぶざんは）総本山の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hase-dera Temple is Sohonzan of the Buzan school of the Shingon sect in the Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hase-dera Temple, in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture, is the head temple of the Buzan school of Shingon Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hase-dera Temple, in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture, is the head temple of the Buzan school of Shingon Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>山号を豊山神楽院と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Sango is Buzan Kagurain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango is Buzan Kagurain.</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango is Buzan Kagurain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>本尊は十一面観音、開基（創立者）は道明上人とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Honzon is Eleven-faced Kannon and its Kaiki (founder) is regarded as Domyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its principal object of worship is the eleven-faced Kannon and its founder is regarded as Domyo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its principal object of worship is the eleven-faced Kannon and its founder is regarded as Domyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>西国三十三箇所観音霊場の第八番札所であり、日本でも有数の観音霊場として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also the 8th of the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage, which is one of the famous sacred places of Kannon in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also the eighth of the thirty-three temples that make up the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage, and is one of the most famous sacred places of Kannon in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also the eighth of the thirty-three temples that make up the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage, and is one of the most famous sacred places of Kannon in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>大和国と伊勢国を結ぶ伊勢参宮街道を見下ろす初瀬山の中腹に本堂が建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo stands on the mountainside of Mt. Hatsuse over the Ise Shrine Pilgrimage Road which tied the Yamato Province with the Ise Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hondo stands on the side of Mt. Hatsuse overlooking the Ise Shrine Pilgrimage Road which linked Yamato Province with Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hondo stands on the side of Mt. Hatsuse overlooking the Ise Shrine Pilgrimage Road which linked Yamato Province with Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>初瀬山は牡丹の名所であり、4月下旬～5月上旬は150種類以上、7,000株と言われる牡丹が満開になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt.Hatsuse is famous for peony which is said to be more than 150 different kinds and 7,000 flowers, and they are in full bloom from late April to early May.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Hatsuse is famous for peonies, of which it is said that more than 150 different kinds and 7,000 flowers are in full bloom from late April to early May.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Hatsuse is famous for peonies, of which it is said that more than 150 different kinds and 7,000 flowers are in full bloom from late April to early May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当寺は古くから「花の御寺」と称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, this temple has been called &apos;the flower temple&apos; since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the temple has been called &apos;the Flower Temple&apos; since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the temple has been called &apos;the Flower Temple&apos; since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また「枕草子」、「源氏物語」、「更級日記」など多くの古典文学にも登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is described in many classic literature such as &apos;Makura no soshi&apos; (the Pillow Book), &apos;Genji Monogatari&apos; (The Tale of Genji) and &apos;Sarashina Nikki&apos; (Sarashina Diary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is described in many classic works of literature such as &apos;Makura no soshi&apos; (The Pillow Book), &apos;Genji Monogatari&apos; (The Tale of Genji) and &apos;Sarashina Nikki&apos; (Sarashina Diary).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is described in many classic works of literature such as &apos;Makura no soshi&apos; (The Pillow Book), &apos;Genji Monogatari&apos; (The Tale of Genji) and &apos;Sarashina Nikki&apos; (Sarashina Diary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>中でも「源氏物語」にある玉鬘 (源氏物語)（たまかずら）の巻のエピソード中に登場する二本（ふたもと）の杉は現在も境内に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the two Japanese cedar trees which appear in the episode of Tamakazura (Jeweled Chaplet) on &apos;Genji Monogatari&apos; still remain in the precincts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two Japanese cedar trees which appear in the Tamakazura (Jeweled Chaplet) chapter of &apos;Genji Monogatari&apos; still remain in the precincts.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two Japanese cedar trees which appear in the Tamakazura (Jeweled Chaplet) chapter of &apos;Genji Monogatari&apos; still remain in the precincts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>起源と歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin and history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origins and History</e>
<cmt>ArticlePluralCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origins and History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>長谷寺の創建は奈良時代、8世紀前半と推定されるが、創建の詳しい時期や事情は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is guessed that the Hase-dera Temple was established in the early part of the 8th century during the Nara period, but the details on period and situation of its establishment are not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Hase-dera Temple was established in the early part of the 8th century during the Nara period, but details on the period and circumstances of its establishment are unknown.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Hase-dera Temple was established in the early part of the 8th century during the Nara period, but details on the period and circumstances of its establishment are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>寺伝によれば、天武朝の朱鳥元年（686年）、道明上人が初瀬山の西の丘（現在、本長谷寺と呼ばれている場所）に三重塔を建立、続いて神亀4年（727年）、徳道上人が東の丘（現在の本堂の地）に本尊十一面観音像を祀って開山したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a legend of the temple, Domyo Shonin had a three-storied pagoda built on the west hillside (the place which is called Motohase-dera Temple today) of Mt.Hatsuse in 686, and next, Tokudo Shonin enshrined Honzon of the Eleven-faced Kannon statue on the east hillside (the place where the present Hondo stands) and founded the temple on 727.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to temple legend, Domyo Shonin had a three-storied pagoda built on the west side of Mt. Hatsuse (the place known today as Motohase-dera Temple) in 686, and then, in 727, Tokudo Shonin founded the temple when he enshrined the statue of the Eleven-faced Kannon on the east side (where the present Hondo stands).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to temple legend, Domyo Shonin had a three-storied pagoda built on the west side of Mt. Hatsuse (the place known today as Motohase-dera Temple) in 686, and then, in 727, Tokudo Shonin founded the temple when he enshrined the statue of the Eleven-faced Kannon on the east side (where the present Hondo stands).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>が、これらのことについては正史に見えず、伝承の域を出ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these are not described in official history, so that they are regarded as legends.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these are not described in any official history and are thus regarded as legends.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these are not described in any official history and are thus regarded as legends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>長谷寺は平安時代中期以降、観音霊場として貴族の信仰を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hase-dera Temple had been worshipped by nobles as a sacred place of Kannon after the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the middle of the Heian period, Hase-dera Temple was worshipped by nobles as a sacred place of Kannon.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the middle of the Heian period, Hase-dera Temple was worshipped by nobles as a sacred place of Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>万寿元年（1024年）には藤原道長が参詣しており、中世以降は武士や庶民にも信仰を広めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinaga worshipped it in 1024 and it had been worshipped by samurai and common people after medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michinaga made a pilgrimage there in 1024, and from the medieval period onwards, samurai and commoners came to worship there.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinaga made a pilgrimage there in 1024, and from the medieval period onwards, samurai and commoners came to worship there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>長谷寺は東大寺（華厳宗）の末寺であったが、平安時代中期には興福寺（法相宗）の末寺となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hase-dera Temple was a branch temple of the Todai-ji Temple (the Kegon sect) and became a branch temple of the Kofuku-ji Temple (the Hosso sect) in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hase-dera Temple was originally a branch temple of Todai-ji Temple (the Kegon sect) but became a branch temple of Kofuku-ji Temple (the Hosso sect) in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hase-dera Temple was originally a branch temple of Todai-ji Temple (the Kegon sect) but became a branch temple of Kofuku-ji Temple (the Hosso sect) in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>16世紀以降は興教大師覚鑁（かくばん）によって興され頼瑜僧正により成道した新義真言宗の流れをくむ寺院となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the 16th century, it has been a temple of the Shingi Shingon sect which was begun by Kogyo Daishi Kakuban and completed by Raiyu Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the 16th century, it was a temple of the Shingi Shingon sect, which was begun by Kogyo Daishi Kakuban and completed by Raiyu, a priest with the highest rank of &apos;sojo&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the 16th century, it was a temple of the Shingi Shingon sect, which was begun by Kogyo Daishi Kakuban and completed by Raiyu, a priest with the highest rank of &apos;sojo&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>天正16年（1588年）、豊臣秀吉により根来山を追われた新義真言宗門徒が入山し、同派の僧正専誉により現在の真言宗豊山派が大成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1588 the believers of the Shingi Shingon sect who escaped from Mt. Negoro by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s attack entered Mt.Hatsuse and Sojo Senyo of its sect established the present Buzan school of the Shingo sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1588, believers of the Shingi Shingon sect who had escaped Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s attack on Mt. Negoro arrived at Mt. Hatsuse and Sojo Senyo of the same sect established the present Buzan school of Shingon Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1588, believers of the Shingi Shingon sect who had escaped Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s attack on Mt. Negoro arrived at Mt. Hatsuse and Sojo Senyo of the same sect established the present Buzan school of Shingon Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>十一面観音を本尊とし「長谷寺」を名乗る寺院は鎌倉の長谷寺をはじめ日本各地に多く、他と区別するため「大和国長谷寺」「総本山長谷寺」等と呼称することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many temples which Honzon are Eleven-faced Kannon and use the name &apos;Hase-dera Temple&apos; including the Hase-dera Temple in Kamakura, and therefore, in order to distinguish it from others, it is sometimes called &apos;the Hase-dera Temple in the Yamato Province,&apos; &apos;Sohonzan Hase-dera Temple&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many temples throughout Japan have an Eleven-faced Kannon as their principal object of worship use the name &apos;Hase-dera Temple&apos;, including Hase-dera Temple in Kamakura, and therefore, in order to distinguish the Nara temple from others, it is sometimes called &apos;Hase-dera Temple of Yamato Province&apos; or &apos;Sohonzan Hase-dera Temple&apos; amongst others.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many temples throughout Japan have an Eleven-faced Kannon as their principal object of worship use the name &apos;Hase-dera Temple&apos;, including Hase-dera Temple in Kamakura, and therefore, in order to distinguish the Nara temple from others, it is sometimes called &apos;Hase-dera Temple of Yamato Province&apos; or &apos;Sohonzan Hase-dera Temple&apos; amongst others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>伽藍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temple buildings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temple Buildings</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temple Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>入口の仁王門から本堂までは399段の登廊（のぼりろう、屋根付きの階段）を上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Noboriro (steps with roof) of 399 steps from the Nio-mon Gate, an entrance, to Hondo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Noboriro&apos; (enclosed stairway) rises 399 steps from the entrance at the Nio-mon Gate to the Hondo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Noboriro&apos; (enclosed stairway) rises 399 steps from the entrance at the Nio-mon Gate to the Hondo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>本堂の西方の丘には「本長谷寺」と称する一画があり、五重塔などが建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the west hillside of Hondo is the area called &apos;Motohase-dera&apos; where a five-storied pagoda and others are located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the hillside to the west of the Hondo is the area called &apos;Motohase-dera&apos;, which contains a five-storied pagoda other buildings.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the hillside to the west of the Hondo is the area called &apos;Motohase-dera&apos;, which contains a five-storied pagoda other buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>国宝の本堂のほか、仁王門、下登廊、繋屋、中登廊、蔵王堂、上登廊、三百余社、鐘楼、繋廊が重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo is designated to a national treasure and in addition, Nio-mon Gate, Shimo-Noboriro (lower Noboriro) (下登廊), 繋屋, Naka-Noboriro (中登廊), Zao-do Hall, Kami-Noboriro (上登廊), Sanbyakuyosha (more than 300 shrines) (三百余社), Shoro (a bell tower) and 繋廊 are also designated to important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>下登廊、繋屋、中登廊、上登廊、三百余社、繋廊の読み方、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hondo is designated a National Treasure and the Nio-mon Gate, Shimo-Noboriro (lower stairway), Tsunagiya (a building connecting the lower and middle stairways), Naka-Noboriro (middle stairway), Zaodo Hall, Kami-Noboriro (upper stairway), Sanbyakuyosha Shrine, Shoro (bell tower) and Tsunagiro (a corridor connecting the bell tower and the Hondo) are designated Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>Took pronunciation of &quot;繋屋&quot; from this website: http://www.mext.go.jp/b_menu/shingi/bunka/toushin/04112401/003.htmand although not in the original, added an explanation of &quot;繋屋&quot; and &quot;繋廊&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hondo is designated a National Treasure and the Nio-mon Gate, Shimo-Noboriro (lower stairway), Tsunagiya (a building connecting the lower and middle stairways), Naka-Noboriro (middle stairway), Zaodo Hall, Kami-Noboriro (upper stairway), Sanbyakuyosha Shrine, Shoro (bell tower) and Tsunagiro (a corridor connecting the bell tower and the Hondo) are designated Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>本堂（国宝）－本尊を安置する正堂（しょうどう）、相の間、礼堂（らいどう）から成る巨大な建築で、前面は京都の清水寺本堂と同じく懸造（かけづくり、舞台造とも）になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo (a national treasure): a magnificent building consisting of Shodo where Honzon is placed, Ainoma (Middle Room, located in between Honden main hall and Haiden oratory) and Rai-do hall (a worship hall), and its front is made in the kake-zukuri (overhang method of construction) style as well as the Hondo of the Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hondo (National Treasure): a magnificent building consisting of the Shodo, where the statue of Kannon stands; the Ainoma (Middle Room), located in between Honden main hall and Haiden oratory; and the Raido (worship hall); and the front is constructed in the kake-zukuri, or platform, style like the hondo of Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hondo (National Treasure): a magnificent building consisting of the Shodo, where the statue of Kannon stands; the Ainoma (Middle Room), located in between Honden main hall and Haiden oratory; and the Raido (worship hall); and the front is constructed in the kake-zukuri, or platform, style like the hondo of Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>本堂は奈良時代から室町時代の天文 (元号)5年（1536年）まで7回焼失している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo was burnt down seven times from the Nara period to 1536 during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hondo was burnt down seven times between the Nara period and 1536.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hondo was burnt down seven times between the Nara period and 1536.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>7回目の焼失後、豊臣秀長の援助で天正16年（1588年）に新しい堂が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the seventh fire, a new hall was completed in 1588 supported by Hidenaga TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the seventh fire, a new hall was completed in 1588 with Hidenaga TOYOTOMI&apos;s assistance.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the seventh fire, a new hall was completed in 1588 with Hidenaga TOYOTOMI&apos;s assistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その後、堂の雨漏りや傷みが激しいため、修理ではなく新築することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it leaked and was damaged heavily, so that it was decided to be newly built instead of repair.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, due to leaks and heavy damage, it was decided to again rebuild instead of repair it.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, due to leaks and heavy damage, it was decided to again rebuild instead of repair it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>徳川家光の寄進を得て、5年がかりの工事の後、慶安3年（1650年）に新築落慶したのが現・本堂である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving a donation by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the president Hondo was celebrated the construction in 1650 after five-years work of construction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a donation from Iemitsu TOKUGAWA and after five years work, the hondo, which still stands today, was completed</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a donation from Iemitsu TOKUGAWA and after five years work, the hondo, which still stands today, was completed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>高さ10メートル以上ある本尊・十一面観音像は、天文5年の本堂焼失の2年後に完成しており、慶安3年の新本堂建設工事は本尊を原位置から移動せずに行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Honzon Eleven-faced Kannon statue which is more than 10m high was completed two years after Hondo was burnt down in 1536, so that it remained in the same place when new Hondo was built in 1650.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eleven-faced Kannon statue, which is more than ten meters high, was completed two years after the hondo was burnt down in 1536, and was not moved when the new hondo was built in 1650.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eleven-faced Kannon statue, which is more than ten meters high, was completed two years after the hondo was burnt down in 1536, and was not moved when the new hondo was built in 1650.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>そのため、本堂は内陣の中にさらに内々陣（本尊を安置）がある複雑な構成となっており、内々陣は巨大な厨子の役目をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Hondo has such a complicated structure as having nainaijin (the most inner sanctuary where Honzon is placed) in naijin (inner sanctuary of a shrine or temple), and as a result, nainaijin plays a role of a big zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the hondo has a complicated structure, with a &apos;nainaijin&apos; (the innermost sanctuary where the principal object stands) within the &apos;naijin&apos; (inner sanctuary), and as a result, the nainaijin acts as a big &apos;zushi&apos; (a cupboard-like shrine with double doors used to store images of Buddha, sutras, etc).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the hondo has a complicated structure, with a &apos;nainaijin&apos; (the innermost sanctuary where the principal object stands) within the &apos;naijin&apos; (inner sanctuary), and as a result, the nainaijin acts as a big &apos;zushi&apos; (a cupboard-like shrine with double doors used to store images of Buddha, sutras, etc).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>近世前半の大規模本堂の代表作として、2004年12月、国宝に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a representative large Hondo in the early part of recent times, it was designated to a national treasure on December 2004.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deemed representative of large early-modern hondo, it was designated a National Treasure on December 2004.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deemed representative of large early-modern hondo, it was designated a National Treasure on December 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>ArticleCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The national treasures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasures</e>
<cmt>ArticleCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>本堂（既述）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hondo (mentioned above)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hondo (mentioned above)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hondo (mentioned above)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>銅板法華説相図－法華経の見宝塔品（けんほうとうほん）で、釈迦が説法していたところ、空中に巨大な宝塔が出現した場面を表現したもので、縦84センチ、横75センチの鋳銅の板に宝塔と諸仏が浮き彫り状に表わされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bronze Plaque Hokke Sesso ZU: Kenhotohon of Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra) which expresses the scene that a big pagoda appeared in the sky when Shakyamuni preached and in which a pagoda and some Buddha are expressed with embossed carving on a copper board of 84 long and 75 wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze plaque of the Hokke Sesso-zu: an embossed carving of a pagoda and several buddhas on a copper plate 84cm long and 75cm wide depicting the scene in &quot;The Emergence of the Treasure Tower&quot; chapter of the Lotus Sutra when a large pagoda appeared in the sky while Shakyamuni was preaching.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze plaque of the Hokke Sesso-zu: an embossed carving of a pagoda and several buddhas on a copper plate 84cm long and 75cm wide depicting the scene in &quot;The Emergence of the Treasure Tower&quot; chapter of the Lotus Sutra when a large pagoda appeared in the sky while Shakyamuni was preaching.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>銅板の下部には長文の銘が刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the lower part of copper plate, a long inscription is carved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lower part of the copper plate contains a long inscription.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lower part of the copper plate contains a long inscription.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>そこには「戌年」に「飛鳥浄御原で天下を治めた天皇」の病気平癒のため、僧・道明が作ったという意味のことが書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inscription shows that it was made by a priest Domyo in order to cure a disease of &apos;the Emperor who governed the world at &apos;Asukakiyomihara&apos; in &apos;the year of Dog.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inscription shows that it was made by the priest Domyo in order to cure a disease of &quot;the Emperor who governed the world at Asukakiyomihara&quot; in &quot;the Year of the Dog&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inscription shows that it was made by the priest Domyo in order to cure a disease of &quot;the Emperor who governed the world at Asukakiyomihara&quot; in &quot;the Year of the Dog&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この戌年について、寺伝では天武天皇の朱鳥元年（686年）とするが、研究者の間では干支が一巡した文武天皇2年（698年）の作と見る意見が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a temple legend says that this year of Dog was 686, many researchers regard that this was made in 698, after one cycle of the Oriental zodiac.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a temple legend says that this Year of the Dog was 686, many researchers regard that this was made in 698, one cycle of the Oriental zodiac later.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a temple legend says that this Year of the Dog was 686, many researchers regard that this was made in 698, one cycle of the Oriental zodiac later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>（奈良国立博物館に寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(A deposit in Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(on loan to the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(on loan to the Nara National Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>法華経、観普賢経、無量義経、阿弥陀経、般若心経、計34巻－鎌倉時代に制作された「装飾経」のセットで「長谷寺経」と通称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke-kyo Sutra, Kanfugenkyo (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra), Muryo gikyo (Sutra of Immeasurable Meanings), Amida Sutra, Hannya Shingyo (Heart Sutra), 34 volumes in total: a series of &apos; soshokukyo&apos; (decorative sutras) made in the Kamakura period and commonly called &apos;Hasedera-kyo Sutra.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lotus Sutra, Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra, Sutra of Immeasurable Meanings, Amida Sutra, Heart Sutra, 34 scrolls in total: a series of &apos;soshokukyo&apos; (decorative sutras) made in the Kamakura period and commonly called the &apos;Hasedera-kyo Sutras&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lotus Sutra, Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra, Sutra of Immeasurable Meanings, Amida Sutra, Heart Sutra, 34 scrolls in total: a series of &apos;soshokukyo&apos; (decorative sutras) made in the Kamakura period and commonly called the &apos;Hasedera-kyo Sutras&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>本文の用紙は金銀の切箔などで装飾し、巻き軸には水晶を用いるなど、装飾をこらしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the paper of sutras are decorated with kirihaku (decorative metal pattern on sculptures or paintings) of gold and silver and crystal is used for a roller, it has an ornate decoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sutras are ornately decorated with gold and silver leaf decorating the paper and crystal used for the rollers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sutras are ornately decorated with gold and silver leaf decorating the paper and crystal used for the rollers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The important cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>ArticleCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>木造十一面観音立像（本堂安置）附木造難陀龍王立像及び像内納入品、木造赤精童子立像及び像内納入品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of Eleven-Faced Kannon (placed at Hondo) with the wooden standing statue of Nanda Ryuo and its stored goods inside of the statue, and the wooden standing statue of Sekishou douji and its stored goods inside of the statue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of the Eleven-Faced Kannon (in the hondo) together with the wooden standing statue of the Dragon King Nanda (Nanda-ryuo) and stored goods inside the statue, and the wooden standing statue of Sekishou Douji (a synthesis of the Vairocana Buddha and the Shinto Sun Goddess, Amaterasu) and stored goods inside the statue</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of the Eleven-Faced Kannon (in the hondo) together with the wooden standing statue of the Dragon King Nanda (Nanda-ryuo) and stored goods inside the statue, and the wooden standing statue of Sekishou Douji (a synthesis of the Vairocana Buddha and the Shinto Sun Goddess, Amaterasu) and stored goods inside the statue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>長谷寺の本尊像については、神亀年間（720年代）、近隣の初瀬川に流れ着いた巨大な神木が大いなる祟りを呼び、恐怖した村人の懇願を受けて開祖徳道が祟りの根源である神木を観音菩薩像に作り替え、これを近くの初瀬山に祀ったという長谷寺開山の伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a legend on the foundation of the Hase-dera Temple, the origin of the Honzon statue in the Hase-dera Temple was as follows; in 720s a big sacred tree washed up on the riverside of the Hatsuse River and invited a big curse, village people scared and asked the founder Tokudo to made a statue of Kannon Bosatsu from that sacred tree which was the root of curse, and it was enshrined on Mt. Hatsuse near the village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a legend about the founding of Hase-dera Temple, in the 720s a big sacred tree washed up on the banks of the Hatsuse River and brought down a great curse, causing fear among the villagers, who asked the founder, Tokudo, to make a statue of the Bodhisattva Kannon from the sacred tree, which was the root of curse, and the statue was enshrined on Mt. Hatsuse near the village.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend about the founding of Hase-dera Temple, in the 720s a big sacred tree washed up on the banks of the Hatsuse River and brought down a great curse, causing fear among the villagers, who asked the founder, Tokudo, to make a statue of the Bodhisattva Kannon from the sacred tree, which was the root of curse, and the statue was enshrined on Mt. Hatsuse near the village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>伝承の真偽はともかく、当初像は「神木」等、何らかのいわれのある木材を用いて刻まれたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not sure that this legend is true or not, it seems that the statue was curved from a wood with some origins such as &apos;sacred tree&apos; at first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regardless of the veracity of this legend, it seems that the wood the original statue was carved from was some kind of &apos;sacred wood&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regardless of the veracity of this legend, it seems that the wood the original statue was carved from was some kind of &apos;sacred wood&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>現在の本尊像は天文7年（1538年）の再興。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present Honzon statue was the one which was rebuilt in 1538.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present statue was remade in 1538.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present statue was remade in 1538.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>仏像彫刻衰退期の室町時代の作品だが、10メートルを超える巨像を破綻なくまとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was made in the Muromachi period when Buddhist sculpture declined, but it is a fine big statue with over 10m high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was made in the Muromachi period, when Buddhist sculpture was in decline, it is a superb large statue over ten meters tall.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was made in the Muromachi period, when Buddhist sculpture was in decline, it is a superb large statue over ten meters tall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>国宝・重要文化財指定の木造彫刻の中では最大のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the wooden sculptures designated to national treasures or important cultural properties, it is the largest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the largest wooden sculpture to be designated either a National Treasure or Important Cultural Property.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the largest wooden sculpture to be designated either a National Treasure or Important Cultural Property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>本像は通常の十一面観音像と異なり、右手に地蔵菩薩の持つような錫杖を持ち、岩の上に立つ姿である（左手には通常の十一面観音像と同じく水瓶を持つ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike common Eleven-Faced Kannon statues, it has Shakujo (a priest&apos;s pewter staff) on the right hand as Jizo Bosatsu has and stands on a rock (it has Suibyo, water jug, on the left hand as well as common Eleven-Faced Kannon statues).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike usual Eleven-Faced Kannon statues, it holds a &apos;shakujo&apos; (priest&apos;s pewter staff) in the right hand similar to Jizo Bosatsu (Ksitigarbha Bodhisattva) and stands on a rock (like most Eleven-Faced Kannon statues, it has a &apos;suibyo&apos;, or water jug, in the left hand).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike usual Eleven-Faced Kannon statues, it holds a &apos;shakujo&apos; (priest&apos;s pewter staff) in the right hand similar to Jizo Bosatsu (Ksitigarbha Bodhisattva) and stands on a rock (like most Eleven-Faced Kannon statues, it has a &apos;suibyo&apos;, or water jug, in the left hand).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>伝承によれば、これは地蔵菩薩と同じく、自ら人間界に下りて衆生を救済して行脚する姿を表したものとされ、他の宗派（真言宗他派も含む）には見られない独特の形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the legend, this expresses the figure to go down to the world of mortals by himself and walk around with relieving all living things, and it is a unique style which is not seen in other sects (including other schools of the Shingon sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the legend, this signifies that Kannon, like Jizo, will come down to the world of mortals and walk around giving salvation to all living things and is a unique style which is not seen in other sects (including other schools of Shingon Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the legend, this signifies that Kannon, like Jizo, will come down to the world of mortals and walk around giving salvation to all living things and is a unique style which is not seen in other sects (including other schools of Shingon Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>この種の錫杖を持った十一面観音を「長谷寺式十一面観音（長谷型観音）」と呼称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eleven-Faced Kannon with this kind of Shakujo is called &apos;the Eleven-Faced Kannon in the Hase-dera style&apos; (Hase-style Kannon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eleven-Faced Kannon with this kind of shakujo are called &apos;Hase-dera-style Eleven-Faced Kannon (Hase-style Kannon)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eleven-Faced Kannon with this kind of shakujo are called &apos;Hase-dera-style Eleven-Faced Kannon (Hase-style Kannon)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>その他の重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other important cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>Capital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="58">
<j>仁王門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nio-mon Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nio-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nio-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="59">
<j>登廊5棟（下登廊、繋屋、中登廊、蔵王堂、上登廊）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The five buildings of Noboriro (Shimo-Noboriro, 繋屋, Naka-Noboriro, Zaodo-hall, Kami-Noboriro)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The five buildings of the &apos;noboriro&apos; covered stairway (Lower Stairway, Tsunagiya, Middle Stairway, Zaodo Hall, Upper Stairway)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The five buildings of the &apos;noboriro&apos; covered stairway (Lower Stairway, Tsunagiya, Middle Stairway, Zaodo Hall, Upper Stairway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="60">
<j>三百余社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanbyakuyosha (more than 300 shrines)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanbyakuyosha Shrine</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanbyakuyosha Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="61">
<j>鐘楼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoro</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="62">
<j>繋廊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">繋廊</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunagiro</e>
<cmt>Took pronunciation from this website: http://www.mext.go.jp/b_menu/shingi/bunka/toushin/04112401/003.htm</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunagiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>絹本著色阿弥陀来迎図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amidaraigozu (a picture of Amidabha coming on purple clouds to welcome the spirits of the dead), colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amidaraigozu (a picture of Amidabha coming on purple clouds to welcome the spirits of the dead) colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amidaraigozu (a picture of Amidabha coming on purple clouds to welcome the spirits of the dead) colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>絹本著色浄土曼荼羅図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The picture of Jodo Mandala (Pure Land Mandala), colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo Mandala (Pure Land Mandala) colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo Mandala (Pure Land Mandala) colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>紙本白描高雄曼荼羅図像（胎蔵界巻第一、三、四、五　金剛界巻第一、二）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihon Hakubyo Takao mandala zuzo (a picture of Takao mandala drawn with Hakubyo plain sketch on paper) (Garbhadhatu No.1, 3, 4, 5 and Vajradhatu No.1, 2)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihon Hakubyo Takao mandala zuzo, an ink sketch on paper of the Takao mandala (Womb Realm Nos.1, 3, 4, 5 and Diamond Nos.1, 2)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihon Hakubyo Takao mandala zuzo, an ink sketch on paper of the Takao mandala (Womb Realm Nos.1, 3, 4, 5 and Diamond Nos.1, 2)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>銅造十一面観音立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze standing statue of Eleven-faced Kannon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze standing statue of the Eleven-faced Kannon</e>
<cmt>Articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze standing statue of the Eleven-faced Kannon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>木造地蔵菩薩立像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden standing statue of Jizo Bosatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>木造不動明王坐像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden seated statue of Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the Five Wisdom Kings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden seated statue of Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the Five Wisdom Kings)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden seated statue of Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the Five Wisdom Kings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>金鼓　建久三年銘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konku (a kind of musical instrument) with an inscription of 1192</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konku (a kind of musical instrument), inscribed with the year &apos;1192&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konku (a kind of musical instrument), inscribed with the year &apos;1192&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>三鈷柄剣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sankoeken (three-pronged sword)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sankoeken (three-pronged sword)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankoeken (three-pronged sword)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>赤糸威鎧　大袖付、白糸威鎧　大袖付、鷹羽威鎧　大袖付、三目札鎧、藍韋威肩赤大袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akaito Odoshi Yoroi (Red-threaded Armor) with osode (large sleeves), Shiroito Odoshi Yoroi (White-threaded Armor) with osode, Takanoha (鷹羽) Odoshi Yoroi (Red-threaded Armor) with osode, Mitsumezane Yoroi (Armor made of small piece of iron or leather for armor with three line holes), and Aikawa Odoshi Kataaka Osode (Armor with leather of deer died with indigo and red large sleeves)</e>
<cmt>鷹羽の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akaito Odoshi Yoroi (red braided armor) with osode (large sleeves), Shiroito Odoshi Yoroi (white braided armor) with osode, Takanoha Odoshi Yoroi (Red-threaded Armor) with osode, Mitsumezane Yoroi (armor made of small pieces of iron or leather that have three rows of holes for lacing), and Aikawa Odoshi Kataaka Osode (deer skin armor died indigo with large red sleeves)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akaito Odoshi Yoroi (red braided armor) with osode (large sleeves), Shiroito Odoshi Yoroi (white braided armor) with osode, Takanoha Odoshi Yoroi (Red-threaded Armor) with osode, Mitsumezane Yoroi (armor made of small pieces of iron or leather that have three rows of holes for lacing), and Aikawa Odoshi Kataaka Osode (deer skin armor died indigo with large red sleeves)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>銅錫杖頭　2柄　各建長三年銘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two Doshakujoto (the head of a priest&apos;s pewter staff made of copper) each of which has an inscription of 1251</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two Doshakujoto (the head of a priest&apos;s pewter staff made of copper) each inscribed with the year &apos;1251 &apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two Doshakujoto (the head of a priest&apos;s pewter staff made of copper) each inscribed with the year &apos;1251 &apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>宋版一切経　2,766帖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soban Issaikyo (Sung Dynasty Edition of the Buddhist Canon) 2,766 quires</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soban Issaikyo (Sung Dynasty Edition of the Buddhist Canon), 2,766 quires</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soban Issaikyo (Sung Dynasty Edition of the Buddhist Canon), 2,766 quires</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>僻連抄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hekiren sho (Selected Stories on Hekiren)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hekirensho (Biased Treatise on Renga Linked Verse)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hekirensho (Biased Treatise on Renga Linked Verse)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>能満院所有</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Held by the Noman-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Held at Noman-in Temple</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Held at Noman-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>絹本著色地蔵十王像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of Jizo-juo, colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depiction of Jizo and the Ten Kings, colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depiction of Jizo and the Ten Kings, colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>絹本著色春日曼荼羅図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The picture of Kasuga Mandala (Mandala form that sprang from Kasuga-Taisha Shrine), colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga Mandala (mandala form that sprang from Kasuga-Taisha Shrine), colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga Mandala (mandala form that sprang from Kasuga-Taisha Shrine), colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="67">
<j>絹本著色十一面観音像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of Eleven-faced Kannon, colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depiction of the Eleven-faced Kannon, colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depiction of the Eleven-faced Kannon, colored on silk canvas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="68">
<j>黒漆四方殿舎利厨子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushitsu Shihoden (四方殿) Shari Zushi (The black lacquered container to hold the urn putting in the Buddha&apos;s ashes)</e>
<cmt>四方殿の読み方、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushitsu Shihoden Shari Zushi (black lacquered box to hold the urn containing the Buddha&apos;s ashes)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushitsu Shihoden Shari Zushi (black lacquered box to hold the urn containing the Buddha&apos;s ashes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="69">
<j>普門院所有</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Held by the Fumon-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Held by Fumon-in Temple</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Held by Fumon-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="70">
<j>木造不動明王坐像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden statue of the seated Fudo Myoo (Acalanatha, one of the Five Kings of Wisdom)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden statue of the seated Fudo Myoo (Acalanatha, one of the Five Kings of Wisdom)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden statue of the seated Fudo Myoo (Acalanatha, one of the Five Kings of Wisdom)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>奈良県桜井市初瀬731-1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">731-1, Hatsuse, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">731-1, Hatsuse, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">731-1, Hatsuse, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>近畿日本鉄道 近鉄大阪線・長谷寺駅から徒歩15分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">15 minutes walk from the Hasedera Station of the Kintetsu Osaka line of Kinki Nippon Railway Company</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">15 minutes walk from Hasedera Station on the Kinki Nippon Railway Company&apos;s Kintetsu Osaka line</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">15 minutes walk from Hasedera Station on the Kinki Nippon Railway Company&apos;s Kintetsu Osaka line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 いろはにほへと(id:89648), Yard(id:59322), たね(id:10372), しるふぃ(id:11247), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Yanahan(id:2437), Makotozushi(id:4545), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Shinkansen(id:13703), Aska-sacra(id:8180), ＋－(id:17104), Masyu(id:31065), Rusk(id:9895), たぬき(id:27723), Myochu(id:17622), Nnn(id:26535), EDUCA33E(id:69700), YurikBot(id:18605), Tawashi2006(id:95112), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Zxtdextra(id:218327), 663highland(id:18755), Woles(id:116374), Chibang(id:19967), かおる(id:8643), 一休(id:17559), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>