<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>慈眼院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jigen-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jigen-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jigen-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>慈眼院（じげんいん）は大阪府泉佐野市にある真言宗御室派の寺院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jigen-in Temple is a Shingon sect Omuro school temple located in the Izumisano City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jigen-in Temple is a Shingonshu sect Omuro school temple located in the Izumisano City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>統一リストより、Shingonshu sectとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jigen-in Temple is a Shingonshu sect Omuro school temple located in the Izumisano City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山号は大悲山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its sango (mountain name) is Mt. Daiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Mt. Daihi.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除、sangoの補足を一部修正、Mt. Daiji→Mt. Daihiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sango (literally, &quot;mountain name,&quot; which is the title prefixed to the name of a Buddhist temple) is Mt. Daihi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近世末までは、隣接する日根神社の神宮寺であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Jingu-ji Temple of adjacent Hine-jinja Shrine until the end of the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a Jingu-ji Temple (temples associated with shrines) of adjacent Hine-jinja Shrine until the end of the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>a Jingu-ji Templeとし、補足を追加しました。(用語集参照)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a Jingu-ji Temple (temples associated with shrines) of adjacent Hine-jinja Shrine until the end of the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>国宝の多宝塔は石山寺塔、金剛三昧院塔とともに日本の多宝塔の3名塔の一つとして知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tahoto pagoda (a &quot;multi-treasure&quot; pagoda), which is designated as National Treasures, is known as one of the three famous pagodas in Japan together with the pagoda of Ishiyama-dera Temple and that of Kongosanmaiin Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tahoto pagoda (a &quot;multi-treasure&quot; pagoda), which is designated as a national treasure, is known as one of the three famous pagodas in Japan together with the pagoda of Ishiyama-dera Temple and that of Kongosanmai-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、スペース削除、which is designated as National Treasures→which is designated as a national treasure、Kongosanmai-in Templeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tahoto pagoda (a &quot;multi-treasure&quot; pagoda), which is designated as a national treasure, is known as one of the three famous pagodas in Japan together with the pagoda of Ishiyama-dera Temple and that of Kongosanmai-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また境内が「日根荘遺跡」の一部として国の史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the precincts of a shrine, which is the part of &apos;the remains of Hinenosho (Shoen (manor) in Hineno district, Izumi Province)&apos;, is designated as the state&apos;s historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the precincts of the temple, which is the part of &apos;the remains of Hinenosho (Shoen [manor] in Hineno district, Izumi Province),&apos; is designated as the state&apos;s historic site.</e>
<cmt>the precincts of a shrine→the precincts of the templeに修正、全角アポストロフィー・クォーテーションを半角に修正、スペース削除、カッコ表記修正、カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the precincts of the temple, which is the part of &apos;the remains of Hinenosho (Shoen [manor] in Hineno district, Izumi Province),&apos; is designated as the state&apos;s historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>仏塔古寺十八尊第十二番。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 12th Butto Koji Juhachi Son (the 18 Historical Temples with Pagodas)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 12th Butto Koji Juhachi Son (the 18 Historical Temples with Pagodas).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加、スペース削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 12th Butto Koji Juhachi Son (the 18 Historical Temples with Pagodas).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>伝承によれば、天武天皇2年（673年）、天皇の勅願寺として、井堰山願成就寺無辺光院の名で覚豪阿闍梨により開創され、奈良時代の天平年間、聖武天皇の勅願寺となり、寺領１千石が加増されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the tradition, this temple was founded by Kakugo Ajari in 673 in the name of Iseki yama ganjojuji Temple (井堰山願成就寺) Muhenkoin, and it became Chokugan-ji Temple of the Emperor Shomu from 729 to 749 of Nara era, and was added 1,000 koku of Jiryo (land belonged to a temple).</e>
<cmt>井堰山願成就寺: 正しい読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the tradition, this temple was founded by Kakugo Ajari in 673 in the name of Ganjoju-ji Temple Muhenkoin on Mt. Iseki (井堰山願成就寺無辺光院), and it became a Chokugan-ji Temple (temple built at the order of an emperor) of the Emperor Shomu from 729 to 749 of the Nara period, and was added 1,000 koku of Jiryo (land belonged to a temple).</e>
<cmt>Iseki yama ganjojuji Temple (井堰山願成就寺) Muhenkoin→Ganjoju-ji Temple Muhenkoin on Mt. Iseki (井堰山願成就寺無辺光院)、a Chokugan-ji Templeとし補足追加、Nara era→the Nara periodに修正、スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the tradition, this temple was founded by Kakugo Ajari in 673 in the name of Ganjoju-ji Temple Muhenkoin on Mt. Iseki, and it became a Chokugan-ji Temple (temple built at the order of an emperor) of the Emperor Shomu from 729 to 749 of the Nara period, and was added 1,000 koku of Jiryo (land belonged to a temple).</e>
<cmt>漢字は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、弘仁6年（815年）、 空海（弘法大師）によって多宝塔、金堂をはじめとする諸堂が再興されたと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in 815, Kukai (Kobo Daishi (a posthumous title of the priest Kukai) reconstructed Tahoto pagoda, Kon-do hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple) and many other temple buildings afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in 815, Kukai (Kobo Daishi [a posthumous title of the priest Kukai]) reconstructed Tahoto pagoda, Kon-do hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple) and many other temple buildings afterwards.</e>
<cmt>カッコ表記修正、スペース削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in 815, Kukai (Kobo Daishi [a posthumous title of the priest Kukai]) reconstructed Tahoto pagoda, Kon-do hall (main hall of a Buddhist temple) and many other temple buildings afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>南北朝時代_(日本)の正平8年（1353年）、戦火を受けて焼失。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1353, the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, this temple was burned down because of war fires.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1353, the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, this temple was burned down because of war fires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1353, the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, this temple was burned down because of war fires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、後村上天皇と後亀山天皇の勅命により再興された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some years later, two emperors named Emperor Gomurakami and Emperor Gokameyama ordered the reconstruction of this temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some years later, two emperors named Emperor Gomurakami and Emperor Gokameyama ordered the reconstruction of this temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some years later, two emperors named Emperor Gomurakami and Emperor Gokameyama ordered the reconstruction of this temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>慈眼院の位置する日根（日根野）荘は、五摂家の1つである九条家の荘園であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hine (Hineno) sho, where there is Jigen-in Temple, was Shoen (manor in medieval Japan) of the Kujo family who was one of the Gosekke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hine (Hineno) sho, where there is Jigen-in Temple, was Shoen (manor in medieval Japan) of the Kujo family who was one of the Gosekke Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除、Gossekeの補足を追加しました。(用語集参照)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hine (Hineno) sho, where there is Jigen-in Temple, was Shoen (manor in medieval Japan) of the Kujo family who was one of the Gosekke Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>文亀元年（1501年）から4年間、前関白の九条政基が日根に滞在して領地の直接経営にあたり、日記「政基公旅引付」（宮内庁書陵部蔵）を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For 4 years from 1501, Masamoto KUJO, the former chief adviser to the Emperor, stayed Hine and managed there directly, and he recorded about those days in &quot; Masamoto ko tabi hikitsuke&quot; (the diary of Masamoto KUJO), (the Archives and Mausoleum Department of The Imperial Household Agency).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For four years from 1501, Masamoto KUJO, the former chief adviser to the Emperor, stayed Hine and managed there directly, and he recorded about those days in the &apos;Masamoto-ko Tabi Hikitsuke&apos; (The Diary of Masamoto KUJO) (property of the Imperial Household Archives).</e>
<cmt>4をスペルアウト、“ Masamoto ko tabi hikitsuke”→the &apos;Masamoto-ko Tabi Hikitsuke&apos;とし補足一部修正、スペース・カンマ削除、「宮内庁書陵部」の表記を修正、「蔵」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For four years from 1501, Masamoto KUJO, the former chief adviser to the Emperor, stayed Hine and managed there directly, and he recorded about those days in the &apos;Masamoto-ko Tabi Hikitsuke&apos; (The Diary of Masamoto KUJO) (property of the Imperial Household Archives).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>天正13年（1585年）には豊臣秀吉の根来寺攻めの兵火を受けて、金堂、多宝塔を除いた全山が焼失。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI attacked Negoro-ji Temple and this district, so all buildings, except for Kon-do hall and Tahoto pagoda of Jigen-in Temple, were destroyed by war fires.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI attacked Negoro-ji Temple and this district, so all buildings, except for Kon-do hall and Tahoto pagoda of Jigen-in Temple, were destroyed by war fires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI attacked Negoro-ji Temple and this district, so all buildings, except for Kon-do hall and Tahoto pagoda of Jigen-in Temple, were destroyed by war fires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後慶長7年（1602年）、豊臣秀頼によって伽藍の再興が始められ、奥之坊・山之坊・明王院・戒躰院・稲之坊・中之坊・下之坊・東方寺・上之坊・明神社・観音堂・毘沙門堂・護摩堂の堂宇が建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1602, the restoration of Buddhist temple was begun by Hideyori TOYOTOMI, and temple buildings of Okunobo, Yamanobo, Myoo-in Temple, 戒躰院, Inanobo, Nakanobo, Shimonobo, Toho-ji Temple, Kaminobo, Myojin jinja Shrine, Kannon-do hall, Bishamon-do Temple and Goma-do hall were founded.</e>
<cmt>戒躰院:　読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1602, the restoration of the Buddhist temple was begun by Hideyori TOYOTOMI, and temple buildings of Okunobo, Yamanobo, Myoo-in Temple, 戒躰院, Inanobo, Nakanobo, Shimonobo, Toho-ji Temple, Kaminobo, Myojin-sha Shrine, Kannon-do hall, Bishamon-do hall and Goma-do hall were founded.</e>
<cmt>Buddhist temple→the Buddhist temple、Myojin jinja Shrine→Myojin-sha Shrine、Bishamon-do Temple→Bishamon-do hallに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1602, the restoration of the Buddhist temple was begun by Hideyori TOYOTOMI, and temple buildings of Okunobo, Yamanobo, Myoo-in Temple, Kaishaku-in Temple, Inanobo, Nakanobo, Shimonobo, Toho-ji Temple, Kaminobo, Myojin-sha Shrine, Kannon-do hall, Bishamon-do hall and Goma-do hall were founded.</e>
<cmt>戒躰院の読み方は推測です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>寛文年間には岸和田藩藩主岡部氏により修復が行われ、寛文5年（1665年）、中之坊が仁和寺の性承門跡から現在の院号「慈眼院」を賜り、仁和寺の末寺となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kanbun era, this temple was repaired by the lord of Kishiwada domain named Okabe, and Nakanobo was given the present Ingo (a title given to a Buddhist) &apos;Jigen-in&apos; by Shojo Monzeki (successor of a temple) of Ninna-ji Temple in 1665, then this temple became a branch temple of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kanbun era, this temple was repaired by the lord of the Kishiwada Domain named the Okabe clan, and Nakanobo was given the present Ingo (a title given to a Buddhist temple) &apos;Jigen-in&apos; by Shojo Monzeki (successor of a temple) of Ninna-ji Temple in 1665, then this temple became a branch temple of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Kishiwada domain→the Kishiwada Domain、Okabe→the Okabe clan、Ingoの補足を修正、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kanbun era, this temple was repaired by the lord of the Kishiwada Domain named the Okabe clan, and Nakanobo was given the present Ingo (a title given to a Buddhist temple) &apos;Jigen-in&apos; by Shojo Monzeki (successor of a temple) of Ninna-ji Temple in 1665, then this temple became a branch temple of Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>伽藍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>多宝塔（国宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tahoto pagoda (National Treasures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tahoto pagoda (National Treasure)</e>
<cmt>(National Treasures)→(National Treasure)に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tahoto pagoda (National Treasure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>- 鎌倉時代、文永8年（1271年）建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founded in 1271, Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founded in 1271, Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founded in 1271, Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>高さ約10m。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Height is about 10 m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Height is about 10 meters.</e>
<cmt>m→metersとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Height is about 10 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>屋外にある木造多宝塔で国宝・重要文化財に指定されているものの中では日本最小。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the smallest one in Japan in wooden Tahoto pagodas in the outdoors, which are designated as National Treasures and Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the smallest one in Japan among the wooden Tahoto pagodas in the outdoors which are designated as National Treasures and Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>in wooden Tahoto pagodas→among the wooden Tahoto pagodasとし、カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the smallest one in Japan among the wooden Tahoto pagodas in the outdoors which are designated as National Treasures and Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>石山寺塔、金剛三昧院塔とともに日本の多宝塔の3名塔の一つとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the one of the three famous pagodas in Japan together with the pagoda of Ishiyama-dera Temple and that of Kongosanmaiin Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the one of the three famous pagodas in Japan together with the pagoda of Ishiyama-dera Temple and that of Kongosanmai-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>Kongosanmai-in Templeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the one of the three famous pagodas in Japan together with the pagoda of Ishiyama-dera Temple and that of Kongosanmai-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>初層内部には大日如来坐像（大阪府指定文化財）を安置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainichi Nyorai zazo (sitting statue of Mahavairocana) (the cultural property designated by Osaka Prefecture) is enshrined in the inside of first-layer of this pagoda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seated statue of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) (the cultural property designated by Osaka Prefecture) is enshrined in the inside of first-layer of this pagoda.</e>
<cmt>Dainichi Nyorai zazo (sitting statue of Mahavairocana)→The seated statue of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Dainichi Nyorai (Mahavairocana) (the cultural property designated by Osaka Prefecture) is enshrined in the inside of first-layer of this pagoda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>金堂（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kon-do hall (Important Cultural Properties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kon-do hall (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>(Important Cultural Properties)→(Important Cultural Property)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kon-do hall (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>- 鎌倉時代後期、 方3間、単層、寄棟造、本瓦葺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founded in the latter half of Kamakura Period, about 5.45 m square, single-layer, Yosemune-zukuri (a square or rectangular building, covered with a hipped roof) and Hongawarabuki (a style of tile roofing in which round and square tiles are laid down alternately).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founded in the latter half of the Kamakura period, about 5.45 meters square, single-layer, Yosemune-zukuri (a square or rectangular building, covered with a hipped roof) and Hongawarabuki (a style of tile roofing in which round and square tiles are laid down alternately).</e>
<cmt>the Kamakura period、m→metersとし、スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founded in the latter half of the Kamakura period, about 5.45 meters square, single-layer, Yosemune-zukuri (a square or rectangular building, covered with a hipped roof) and Hongawarabuki (a style of tile roofing in which round and square tiles are laid down alternately).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>毘沙門堂（一願薬師堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bishamon-do Temple (Ichigan Yakushi-do Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bishamon-do hall (Ichigan Yakushi-do hall)</e>
<cmt>Bishamon-do hall、Ichigan Yakushi-do hallとし、スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamon-do hall (Ichigan Yakushi-do hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>- 「柿経（笹塔婆）」安置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Kokerakyo (Sasatoba, a very small common type of memorial stupa that is made of bamboo grass) &apos; is enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokerakyo (Sasatoba, a very small common type of memorial stupa that is made of bamboo grass)&apos; is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokerakyo (Sasatoba, a very small common type of memorial stupa that is made of bamboo grass)&apos; is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>食野家十三重石塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A thirteen-storied stone pagoda of the Meshino family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A thirteen-story stone pagoda of the Meshino family</e>
<cmt>thirteen-storied→thirteen-storyに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A thirteen-story stone pagoda of the Meshino family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>- 江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founded in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founded in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founded in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>本邦洋式製革始祖碑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese and Western style leather monument of the earliest ancestor</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese and Western style leather monument of the earliest ancestor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese and Western style leather monument of the earliest ancestor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>- 明治時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founded in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founded in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founded in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>札所等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) and so on</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) and so on</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudasho (temples where amulets are collected) and so on</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>仏塔古寺十八尊 第12番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 12th Butto Koji Juhachi Son (the 18 Historical Temples with Pagodas)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 12th Butto Koji Juhachi Son</e>
<cmt>既出のため、Butto Koji Juhachi Sonの補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 12th Butto Koji Juhachi Son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>和泉西国三十三箇所 客番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage in the West Izumi Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The extra sacred site of Izumi Saigoku Sanjusankasho (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage in the West Izumi Province)</e>
<cmt>「客番」→訳漏れのため訳出、英訳表記の前にIzumi Saigoku Sanjusankashoを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The extra sacred site of Izumi Saigoku Sanjusankasho (the 33 temples that are visited during the Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage in the West Izumi Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>新大阪百景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin Osaka Hyakkei (New Hundred Sights of Osaka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin Osaka Hyakkei (New Hundred Sights of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Osaka Hyakkei (New Hundred Sights of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>〒598-0021 大阪府泉佐野市日根野626</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">626, Hineno, Izumisano City, Osaka Prefecture, 598-0021</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">626, Hineno, Izumisano City, Osaka Prefecture, 598-0021</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">626, Hineno, Izumisano City, Osaka Prefecture, 598-0021</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>拝観情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Information to have the honor of seeing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Information for visitors</e>
<cmt>to have the honor of seeing→for visitorsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Information for visitors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>開門時間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opening hours</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opening hours</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opening hours</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>- 800～1700（要予約）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 8:00 to 17:00 (Reservation is required.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 8:00 to 17:00 (Reservation is required.)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 8:00 to 17:00 (Reservation is required.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>- 南海電鉄 泉佐野駅または阪和線 日根野駅から南海バス「犬鳴山」行きで8分、「東上」下車すぐ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Take Nankai Bus bound for &apos; Inunakiyama &apos; from Nankai Dentetsu Izumisano station or Hanwa Line Hineno station to &apos; Tojo&apos;; for eight minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take Nankai Bus bound for &apos;Inunakiyama&apos; from Nankai Dentetsu Izumisano Station or Hanwa Line Hineno Station to &apos;Tojo&apos;; for eight minutes.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、stationの頭文字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take Nankai Bus bound for &apos;Inunakiyama&apos; from Nankai Dentetsu Izumisano Station or Hanwa Line Hineno Station to &apos;Tojo&apos;; for eight minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="43">
<j>周辺情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Information for nearby spots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Information for nearby spots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Information for nearby spots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>日根神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hine-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hine-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hine-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>- 延喜式神名帳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engishiki jimmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engishiki jinmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan)</e>
<cmt>jimmyocho→jinmyochoに修正、スペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engishiki jinmyocho (a register of shrines in Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>慈眼院の旧下之坊が日根神社の社務所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Shimonobo of Jigen-in Temple is a shrine office of Hine-jinja Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old Shimonobo of Jigen-in Temple is a shrine office of Hine-jinja Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old Shimonobo of Jigen-in Temple is a shrine office of Hine-jinja Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="47">
<j>総福寺天満宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sofuku-ji Temple Tenman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sofuku-ji Temple Tenman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sofuku-ji Temple Tenman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>- 本殿が重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honden is designated as Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honden (main hall) is designated as an important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>Hondenの補足を追加、Important Cultural Properties→an important cultural propertyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honden (main hall) is designated as an important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), Megane wa(id:244800), Seibuabina(id:37532), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>