<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>嘉喜門院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakimon-in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakimon-in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakimon-in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>嘉喜門院（かきもんいん、生没年未詳）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の女院・女流歌人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakimon-in (dates of birth and death unknown) was Nyoin (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor) and a female waka poet in the period of (Japanese) Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakimon-in (dates of birth and death unknown) was Nyoin (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor) and a female waka poet in the period of (Japanese) Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakimon-in (dates of birth and death unknown) was Nyoin (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor) and a female waka poet in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>南北の表記を変更&quot;the period of (Japanese) Northern and Southern Courts&quot; -&gt; &quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan)&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後村上天皇の女御であり、長慶天皇・後亀山天皇の双方あるいは少なくとも一方の生母と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the nyogo (a court title given to a consort of the Emperor) of Emperor Gomurakami, and seems to have given birth to both Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama, or at least one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the nyogo (a court title given to a consort of the Emperor) of Emperor Gomurakami, and seems to have given birth to both Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama, or at least one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the nyogo (a court title given to a consort of the Emperor) of Emperor Gomurakami, and seems to have given birth to both Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama, or at least one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正平 (日本)23年（1368年）の後村上天皇崩御後、出家し、院号宣下を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Gomurakami passed away in 1368, she retired into priesthood and was given a title of nyoin.</e>
<cmt>次の語は訳文中で名詞として使用しなかったため、terms欄から削除しました。院号宣下→imperial edict of the In title</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Gomurakami passed away in 1368, she retired into priesthood and was given a title of nyoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Gomurakami passed away in 1368, she retired into priesthood and was given a title of nyoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>名は、江戸時代作成の系図以来、勝子（しょうし）とされることが一般的であるが、確証はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real name has been generally considered Shoshi since a genealogy was made in the Edo period, but there is no evidence to prove it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name has been generally considered Shoshi since a genealogy was made in the Edo period, but there is no evidence to prove it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name has been generally considered Shoshi since a genealogy was made in the Edo period, but there is no evidence to prove it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、出自についても諸説あり定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there are various opinions about her origins, but they are not reliable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there are various opinions about her origins, but they are not reliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there are various opinions about her origins, but they are not reliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>琵琶の名手とも伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was known as a good biwa (a Japanese lute) player.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was known as a good biwa (a Japanese lute) player.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was known as a good biwa (a Japanese lute) player.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origins</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>父は、近衛経忠とされることが多いが、阿野実為、一条経通、二条師基、坊門経忠（坊門清忠のことか?）ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father is generally considered Tsunetada KONOE, but there are a few more possible fathers like Sanetame ANO, Tsunemichi ICHIJO, Moromoto NIJO, and Tsunetada BOMON (or Kiyotada BOMON?).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father is generally considered Tsunetada KONOE, but there are a few more possible fathers like Sanetame ANO, Tsunemichi ICHIJO, Moromoto NIJO, and Tsunetada BOMON (or Kiyotada BOMON?).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father is generally considered Tsunetada KONOE, but there are a few more possible fathers like Sanetame ANO, Tsunemichi ICHIJO, Moromoto NIJO, and Tsunetada BOMON (or Kiyotada BOMON?).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このうち、二条師基については、実の親子ではなく、後村上天皇の女御になるにあたって猶子となったとの見解も有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a dominant view that Moromoto NIJO was not her real father but adopted her when she became the nyogo of Emperor Gomurakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a dominant view that Moromoto NIJO was not her real father but adopted her when she became the nyogo of Emperor Gomurakami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a dominant view that Moromoto NIJO was not her real father but adopted her when she became the nyogo of Emperor Gomurakami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>いずれも藤原氏であり、一条経通以外は南朝 (日本)において重きをなした人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of them were from the Fujiwara clan, and leading figures in the Southern Court (in Japan) except Tsunemichi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of them were from the Fujiwara clan, and leading figures in the Southern Court (in Japan) except Tsunemichi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of them were from the Fujiwara clan, and leading figures in the Southern Court (in Japan) except Tsunemichi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これに対し、一条経通は一貫して北朝 (日本)側にいた人物だが、長男の一条内嗣が南朝に出仕している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemichi ICHIJO belonged to the Northern Court (in Japan), but his eldest son Uchitsugu ICHIJO served the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemichi ICHIJO belonged to the Northern Court (in Japan), but his eldest son Uchitsugu ICHIJO served the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemichi ICHIJO belonged to the Northern Court (in Japan), but his eldest son Uchitsugu ICHIJO served the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>『大日本史』巻85（后妃列伝12）によると、『新葉和歌集』巻16（雑1）にある、嘉喜門院が女御となるときに「福恩寺前関白内大臣」と呼ばれる人物が「禁中月」という題で詠んだ歌がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Dainihonshi (Great History of Japan)&quot; vol. 85 (Biographies of Consorts vol. 12) said that a poem on the given theme of &apos;the moon seen from the Imperial court&apos; was composed by a person called &apos;Fukuonji former Chancellor Inner Minister&apos; when Kakimon-in became the nyogo, and it was collected in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu (Collection of New Leaves)&quot; vol.16 (Miscellaneous 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainihonshi (Great History of Japan) vol. 85 (Biographies of Consorts vol. 12) said that a poem on the given theme of &apos;the moon seen from the Imperial court&apos; was composed by a person called &apos;Fukuonji former Chancellor Inner Minister&apos; when Kakimon-in became the nyogo, and it was collected in Shinyo Wakashu (Collection of New Leaves) vol.16 (Miscellaneous 1).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan) vol. 85 (Biographies of Consorts vol. 12) said that a poem on the given theme of &apos;the moon seen from the Imperial court&apos; was composed by a person called &apos;Fukuonji former Chancellor Inner Minister&apos; when Kakimon-in became the nyogo, and it was collected in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; (Collection of New Leaves) vol.16 (Miscellaneous 1).</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>嘉喜門院の后（中宮）への昇格を期待する意であると解釈し、これを根拠としてこの人物を嘉喜門院の父と推定するが、それが誰なのかは未知であると述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poem was interpreted as an expectation for Kakimon-in&apos;s being raised to the Empress (an Imperial consort), so the history book made a supposition that the person who made the poem was Kakimon-in&apos;s father, but it also said that it was not certain who the person was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poem was interpreted as an expectation for Kakimon-in&apos;s being raised to the Empress (an Imperial consort), so the history book made a supposition that the person who made the poem was Kakimon-in&apos;s father, but it also said that it was not certain who the person was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poem was interpreted as an expectation for Kakimon-in&apos;s being raised to the Empress (an Imperial consort), so the history book made a supposition that the person who made the poem was Kakimon-in&apos;s father, but it also said that it was not certain who the person was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『系図纂要』は近衛経忠の子近衛経家を「福恩寺関白」とし、嘉喜門院の父とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Keizu Sanyo (a collection of genealogies),&quot; Tsuneie KONOE, a son of Tadatsune KONOE, was the &apos;Fukuonji Chancellor&apos; and also Kakimon-in&apos;s real father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Keizu Sanyo (a collection of genealogies), Tsuneie KONOE, a son of Tadatsune KONOE, was the &apos;Fukuonji Chancellor&apos; and also Kakimon-in&apos;s real father.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Keizu Sanyo&quot; (a collection of genealogies), Tsuneie KONOE, a son of Tadatsune KONOE, was the &apos;Fukuonji Chancellor&apos; and also Kakimon-in&apos;s real father.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また『古事類苑』帝王部も近衛経家を父と記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section of Emperors in &quot;Kojiruien (an encyclopedia of ancient literature)&quot; also says that Tsuneie KONOE was her father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section of Emperors in Kojiruien (an encyclopedia of ancient literature) also says that Tsuneie KONOE was her father.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section of Emperors in &quot;Kojiruien&quot; (an encyclopedia of ancient literature) also says that Tsuneie KONOE was her father.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、近衛経家を父と主張する説は現在は存在しないようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the view that Tsuneie KONOE was her father seems not to exist today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the view that Tsuneie KONOE was her father seems not to exist today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the view that Tsuneie KONOE was her father seems not to exist today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>『国史大辞典』の「後亀山天皇」項では、『帝王系図』吹上本の付紙を根拠に、天皇の生母が阿野実為の娘であることをほぼ確実とする一方で、この人物が嘉喜門院と同一人物ではない可能性のあることを示唆する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on a snip of paper pasted to a page of the Fukiage bon, the entry of &apos;Emperor Gokameyama&apos; in &quot;Kokushi Daijiten (Great Dictionary of National History)&quot; says that probably the Emperor&apos;s real mother was a daughter of Sanetame ANO, suggesting that the woman might have been the Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on a snip of paper pasted to a page of the Fukiage bon, the entry of &apos;Emperor Gokameyama&apos; in Kokushi Daijiten (Great Dictionary of National History) says that probably the Emperor&apos;s real mother was a daughter of Sanetame ANO, suggesting that the woman might have been the Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on a snip of paper pasted to a page of the Fukiage bon of &quot;Teio Keizu&quot; (Genealogical Table of Emperor), the entry of &apos;Emperor Gokameyama&apos; in &quot;Kokushi Daijiten&quot; (Great Dictionary of National History) says that probably the Emperor&apos;s real mother was a daughter of Sanetame ANO, suggesting that the woman might have not been the Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>of &quot;Teio Keizu&quot; (Genealogical Table of Emperor)補足not補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>一方、嘉喜門院と阿野実為とが親しい間柄であるのは『嘉喜門院集』の成立経緯を記した冒頭部から伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the opening lines of &quot;Kakimon-in shu (Kakimon-in Collection),&quot; which explained how the collection was compiled, we can tell that a close relationship existed between Kakimon-in and Sanetame ANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the opening lines of Kakimon-in shu (Kakimon-in Collection), which explained how the collection was compiled, we can tell that a close relationship existed between Kakimon-in and Sanetame ANO.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the opening lines of &quot;Kakimon-in shu&quot; (Kakimon-in Collection), which explained how the collection was compiled, we can tell that a close relationship existed between Kakimon-in and Sanetame ANO.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歌人として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a poet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a poet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a poet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>嘉喜門院の歌は、『新葉和歌集』と『嘉喜門院集』に見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poems composed by Kakimon-in can be seen in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Kakimon-in shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poems composed by Kakimon-in can be seen in Shinyo Wakashu and Kakimon-in shu.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poems composed by Kakimon-in can be seen in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Kakimon-in shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『新葉和歌集』に収録された嘉喜門院の歌17首、および、嘉喜門院との贈答歌5首の計22首は『嘉喜門院集』から採られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 22 poems collected in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; were selected from &quot;Kakimon-in shu&quot;: 17 poems from &quot;Kakimon-in shu&quot; and 5 exchanged poems with Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 22 poems collected in Shinyo Wakashu were selected from Kakimon-in shu: 17 poems from Kakimon-in shu and 5 exchanged poems with Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 22 poems collected in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; were selected from &quot;Kakimon-in shu&quot;: 17 poems from Kakimon-in shu and 5 exchanged poems with Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>歌風は、オーソドックスな二条流で、哀愁を帯びたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style of her poems was the Nijo style and most of them were tinged with sadness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style of her poems was the Nijo style and most of them were tinged with sadness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style of her poems was the Nijo style and most of them were tinged with sadness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『新葉和歌集』の撰者である宗良親王は、先立った後村上天皇を偲んで歌われた長慶天皇との贈答歌が特に秀逸であると評する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Munenaga, an anthologist of &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; commented that an exchanged poem with Emperor Chokei, which was composed to reminisce about late Emperor Gomurakami, was especially excellent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Munenaga, an anthologist of Shinyo Wakashu commented that an exchanged poem with Emperor Chokei, which was composed to reminisce about late Emperor Gomurakami, was especially excellent.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Munenaga, an anthologist of &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; commented that an exchanged poem with Emperor Chokei, which was composed to reminisce about late Emperor Gomurakami, was especially excellent.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>嘉喜門院集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakimon-in shu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakimon-in shu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakimon-in shu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>『嘉喜門院集』は、宗良親王が『新葉和歌集』を撰集する際の資料として、天授 (日本)3年（1377年）7月13日 (旧暦)に嘉喜門院がこれまでに詠んだ和歌の記録を求められたのに応じて、まとめられた私家集である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kakimon-inshu&quot; is Shikashu (a private poetry collection) which was compiled when Kakimon-in was asked to submit a list of her poems on July 13, 1377 by Imperial Prince Munenaga because he wanted to select poems for &quot;Shinyo Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakimon-inshu is Shikashu (a private poetry collection) which was compiled when Kakimon-in was asked to submit a list of her poems on July 13, 1377 by Imperial Prince Munenaga because he wanted to select poems for Shinyo Wakashu.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kakimon-in shu&quot; is Shikashu (a private poetry collection) which was compiled when Kakimon-in was asked to submit a list of her poems on August 25, 1377 by Imperial Prince Munenaga because he wanted to select poems for &quot;Shinyo Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ歴に&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>阿野実為が清書をし、宗良親王に提出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetame ANO made a fair copy, and handed it to Imperial Prince Munenaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetame ANO made a fair copy, and handed it to Imperial Prince Munenaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetame ANO made a fair copy, and handed it to Imperial Prince Munenaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>全体の構成は、大きく3つに分かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is roughly divided into three sections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is roughly divided into three sections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is roughly divided into three sections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>最初の部分は「袖書」と呼ばれ、この歌集の成立事情と、嘉喜門院と阿野実為の贈答歌各2首、そして、「内の御方」（長慶天皇）の歌2首が掲載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first section is called &apos;sodegaki (side notes),&apos; in which there is an explanation how this collection came into existence, and 2 exchanged poems between Kakimon-in and Sanetame ANO, and 2 poems composed by &apos;uchino onkata&apos; (Emperor Chokei) were collected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first section is called &apos;sodegaki (side notes),&apos; in which there is an explanation how this collection came into existence, and 2 exchanged poems between Kakimon-in and Sanetame ANO, and 2 poems composed by &apos;uchino onkata&apos; (Emperor Chokei) were collected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first section is called &apos;sodegaki&apos; (side notes), in which there is an explanation how this collection came into existence, and 2 exchanged poems between Kakimon-in and Sanetame ANO, and 2 poems composed by &apos;uchino onkata&apos; (Emperor Chokei) were collected.</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>2つめの部分が本体で、全102首。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second section is a main part, which contains 102 poems in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second section is a main part, which contains 102 poems in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second section is a main part, which contains 102 poems in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>贈答歌が14組含まれるため、嘉喜門院自身の歌は88首、他人の歌が14首収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of them, there are 14 exchanged poems, so the poems made by Kakimon-in herself were 88, and 14 poems composed by others were collected together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of them, there are 14 exchanged poems, so the poems made by Kakimon-in herself were 88, and 14 poems composed by others were collected together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of them, there are 14 exchanged poems, so the poems made by Kakimon-in herself were 88, and 14 poems composed by others were collected together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>以上が宗良親王に提出された部分だと推定され、この後には宗良親王からの返書が収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is conjectured that these poems were the ones submitted to Imperial Prince Munenaga, and there is an answer from him after these poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is conjectured that these poems were the ones submitted to Imperial Prince Munenaga, and there is an answer from him after these poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is conjectured that these poems were the ones submitted to Imperial Prince Munenaga, and there is an answer from him after these poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>上記の宗良親王の評はここに記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Munenaga&apos;s comment mentioned above was collected here too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Munenaga&apos;s comment mentioned above was collected here too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Munenaga&apos;s comment mentioned above was collected here too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>最期の部分は「詠三十首和歌」と呼ばれ、30首が掲載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last section is called &apos;Thirty Poems for Singing&apos; and contains 30 poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last section is called &apos;Thirty Poems for Singing&apos; and contains 30 poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last section is called &apos;Thirty Poems for Singing&apos; and contains 30 poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この30首は、嘉喜門院が手本とするために収集した他人作の歌ものと見られていたが、これらの歌も嘉喜門院作とする説が有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These 30 poems had been considered poems made by other people for Kakimon-in to practice composing poems, but now the view that these poems were composed by Kakimon-in is dominant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These 30 poems had been considered poems made by other people for Kakimon-in to practice composing poems, but now the view that these poems were composed by Kakimon-in is dominant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These 30 poems had been considered poems made by other people for Kakimon-in to practice composing poems, but now the view that these poems were composed by Kakimon-in is dominant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>子女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Children</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>諸系図で嘉喜門院の子とされることがあるのは、長慶天皇（寛成親王）と後亀山天皇（熙成親王）の他、泰成親王と良子内親王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to some genealogies, the following people are considered Kakimon-in&apos;s children: Emperor Chokei (Imperial Prince Yutanari), Emperor Gokameyama (Imperial Prince Hironari), Imperial Prince Yasunari, and Imperial Princess Ryoshi/Nagako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some genealogies, the following people are considered Kakimon-in&apos;s children: Emperor Chokei (Imperial Prince Yutanari), Emperor Gokameyama (Imperial Prince Hironari), Imperial Prince Yasunari, and Imperial Princess Ryoshi/Nagako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some genealogies, the following people are considered Kakimon-in&apos;s children: Emperor Chokei (Imperial Prince Yutanari), Emperor Gokameyama (Imperial Prince Hironari), Imperial Prince Yasunari, and Imperial Princess Ryoshi/Nagako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>嘉喜門院が天皇の生母であるというのは、『新葉和歌集』と『嘉喜門院集』に収録された和歌と詞書の解釈によるところが大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view that Kakimon-in was Emperor&apos;s real mother is mostly based on the interpretations of waka poem and foreword collected in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Kakimon-in shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>legendは絵巻物の詞書</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The view that Kakimon-in was Emperor&apos;s real mother is mostly based on the interpretations of waka poem and foreword collected in Shinyo Wakashu and Kakimon-in shu.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The view that Kakimon-in was Emperor&apos;s real mother is mostly based on the interpretations of waka poem and foreword collected in &quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Kakimon-in shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>江戸時代から明治時代にかけて、これらの歌集に登場する「内の御方」（今上天皇）は後亀山天皇であるとの見解が支配的であったため、この頃に書かれた系図や歴史書は、後亀山天皇の生母を嘉喜門院としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Edo to Meiji period, it had been a dominant view that the word &apos;uchino onkata&apos; (means the present Emperor) which appeared in the collections of poetry referred to Emperor Gokameyama, so the genealogies and history books written around this time said that Emperor Gokameyama&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Edo to Meiji period, it had been a dominant view that the word &apos;uchino onkata&apos; (means the present Emperor) which appeared in the collections of poetry referred to Emperor Gokameyama, so the genealogies and history books written around this time said that Emperor Gokameyama&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Edo to Meiji period, it had been a dominant view that the word &apos;uchino onkata&apos; (means the present Emperor) which appeared in the collections of poetry referred to Emperor Gokameyama, so the genealogies and history books written around this time said that Emperor Gokameyama&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>他方、長慶天皇と後亀山天皇が同母兄弟なのかに関しては、それを裏付ける確証がないことから否定的な見方が有力であった中で、塙保己一のように早くから同母兄弟であることを主張する人もあった（ただし、塙は後亀山天皇を兄、長慶天皇を弟と主張していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the matter whether Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama were brothers, there is no evidence to prove it and most people denied it, however there are some scholars like Hokiichi HANAWA who claimed that these Emperors were brothers from early on (according to HANAWA, Emperor Gokameyama was an older brother and Emperor Chokei was a younger brother).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the matter whether Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama were brothers, there is no evidence to prove it and most people denied it, however there are some scholars like Hokiichi HANAWA who claimed that these Emperors were brothers from early on (according to HANAWA, Emperor Gokameyama was an older brother and Emperor Chokei was a younger brother).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the matter whether Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama were brothers, there is no evidence to prove it and most people denied it, however there are some scholars like Hokiichi HANAWA who claimed that these Emperors were brothers from early on (according to HANAWA, Emperor Gokameyama was an older brother and Emperor Chokei was a younger brother).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その後、長慶天皇の即位の有無をめぐる研究が進む中で、両歌集の今上天皇は後亀山天皇ではなく、長慶天皇であるとの説が有力化し、長慶天皇の生母を嘉喜門院とする系図や歴史書が増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later a research on Emperor Chokei&apos;s succession to the throne was making progress, and the opinion that the Emperor appeared in the both collections of poetry did not indicate Emperor Gokameyama but Emperor Chokei became dominant, which encouraged people to make genealogies and history books saying that Emperor Chokei&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, research on Emperor Chokei&apos;s succession to the throne made progress, and the opinion that the Emperor appeared in the both collections of poetry did not indicate Emperor Gokameyama but Emperor Chokei became dominant, which encouraged people to make genealogies and history books saying that Emperor Chokei&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>Cut &quot;a&quot;. &quot;Was making&quot;-&quot;made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, research on Emperor Chokei&apos;s succession to the throne made progress, and the opinion that the Emperor appeared in the both collections of poetry did not indicate Emperor Gokameyama but Emperor Chokei became dominant, which encouraged people to make genealogies and history books saying that Emperor Chokei&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>そして、後亀山天皇の生母を嘉喜門院とするこれまでの資料と、新たに長慶天皇の生母を嘉喜門院とする説とが合成されて、両人とも嘉喜門院の子とされることが一般化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And conventional materials which said that Kakimon-in was a real mother of Emperor Gokameyama was put together with the new opinion that Emperor Chokei&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in too, and now it is generally considered that both of them were Kakimon-in&apos;s sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And conventional materials which said that Kakimon-in was a real mother of Emperor Gokameyama was put together with the new opinion that Emperor Chokei&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in too, and now it is generally considered that both of them were Kakimon-in&apos;s sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And conventional materials which said that Kakimon-in was a real mother of Emperor Gokameyama was put together with the new opinion that Emperor Chokei&apos;s real mother was Kakimon-in too, and now it is generally considered that both of them were Kakimon-in&apos;s sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ただし、後亀山天皇が嘉喜門院の子であるか否かに関する確証は無いのが現状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there is no evidence so far to prove whether Emperor Gokameyama was really Kakimon-in&apos;s son or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there is no evidence so far to prove whether Emperor Gokameyama was really Kakimon-in&apos;s son or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there is no evidence so far to prove whether Emperor Gokameyama was really Kakimon-in&apos;s son or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Oxhop(id:2551), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>