<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>無名草子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mumyo Zoshi (Story Without a Name)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mumyo Zoshi (Story Without a Name)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mumyo Zoshi (Story Without a Name)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>無名草子（むみょうぞうし）は鎌倉時代初期の古典で、文芸評論書としては最古。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mumyo Zoshi (Story Without a Name) is a classic literature in the early Kamakura Period, and the oldest critique of literature in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mumyo Zoshi (Story Without a Name) is a classic from the early Kamakura Period, and the oldest critique of literature in Japan.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary/ grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mumyo Zoshi (Story Without a Name) is a classic from the early Kamakura Period, and the oldest critique of literature in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『無名物語』、『建久物語』などの異名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Mumyo Monogatari&quot; or &quot;Kenkyu Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Mumyo Monogatari&quot; or &quot;Kenkyu Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Mumyo Monogatari&quot; or &quot;Kenkyu Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>女性の立場から述べる王朝物語評論。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a critique of Ocho monogatari (tales of Heian and Kamakura period) from a female perspective.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a critique of Ocho Monogatari (tales of the Heian and Kamakura periods) from a female perspective.</e>
<cmt>capital, plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a critique of Ocho Monogatari (tales of the Heian and Kamakura periods) from a female perspective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>作者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Author</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Author</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Author</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>通説では藤原俊成女（越部禅尼）が作者とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A prevailing theory states that the author of Mumyo zoshi is Daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshinari (Koshibe no zenni).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A prevailing theory states that the author of Mumyo Zoshi is the daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshinari (KOSHIBE no Zenni).</e>
<cmt>capital/article/lower case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A prevailing theory states that the author of Mumyo Zoshi is the daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshinari (KOSHIBE no Zenni).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Completion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Completion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>建久7年（1196年）から建仁2年（1202年）頃の成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in the period between 1196 and 1202.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in the period between 1196 and 1202.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in the period between 1196 and 1202.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>若くして皇嘉門院の母北政所に仕えた八十三歳の老尼と、東山の麓に住む若い女房たちの対話形式をとり、「序」「物語批評」「歌集批評」「女性批評」の四部からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It takes a style of dialogue between a 83-year-old nun who, at a young age, served Kokamonin&apos;s mother, Kita no Mandokoro, and young court ladies living at the foot of Higashiyama with four chapters of &quot;Preface,&quot; &quot;Critique of Monogatari (tales),&quot; &quot;Critique of Kashu (collection of poetry),&quot; and &quot;Critique of Women.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It takes the style of a dialogue between an 83-year-old nun who, at a young age, served Kokamonin&apos;s mother, Kitanomandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor), and young court ladies living at the foot of Mt. Higashiyama with four chapters of &quot;Preface,&quot; &quot;Critique of Monogatari (tales),&quot; &quot;Critique of Kashu (collection of poetry),&quot; and &quot;Critique of Women.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammaradded the explanation of Kitanomandokorovocab/ Higashiyama-Mt. Higashiyama</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes the style of a dialogue between an 83-year-old nun who, at a young age, served Kokamonin&apos;s mother, Kitanomandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor), and young court ladies living at the foot of Mt. Higashiyama with four chapters of &quot;Preface,&quot; &quot;Critique of Monogatari (tales),&quot; &quot;Critique of Kashu (collection of poetry),&quot; and &quot;Critique of Women.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>「物語批評」では源氏物語の各巻や登場人物、印象的な場面に関する短評を先頭に、『狭衣物語』『夜半の寝覚』『みつの浜松（浜松中納言物語）』『とりかへばや物語』ら中古の作り物語についての議論を交わす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Critique of Monogatari&quot; starts with a short review of chapters, characters, and impressive scenes of &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; followed by discussions of tsukuri monogatari (fictional tales) in the Heian Period, such as &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari (The Tale of Sagoromo),&quot; &quot;Yowanonezame (Awaken at the midnight),&quot; &quot;Mitsu no Hamamatsu (Hamamatsu Chunagon Monogatari (The Tale of Hamamatsu Chunagon)),&quot; and &quot;Torikaebaya Monogatari (The Changelings).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Critique of Monogatari&quot; starts with a short review of chapters, characters, and impressive scenes of &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; followed by discussions of tsukuri monogatari&quot; (fictional tales) in the Heian Period, such as &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Sagoromo), &quot;Yowa no Nezame&quot; (Awaken at the midnight), &quot;Mitsu no Hamamatsu&quot; (Hamamatsu Chunagon Monogatari [The Tale of Hamamatsu Chunagon]), and &quot;Torikaebaya Monogatari&quot; (The Changelings).</e>
<cmt>changed from Yowanonezame to Yowa no Nezame (to consolidate the style) punctuation rules</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Critique of Monogatari&quot; starts with a short review of chapters, characters, and impressive scenes of &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; followed by discussions of tsukuri monogatari&quot; (fictional tales) in the Heian Period, such as &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Sagoromo), &quot;Yowa no Nezame&quot; (Awaken at the midnight), &quot;Mitsu no Hamamatsu&quot; (Hamamatsu Chunagon Monogatari [The Tale of Hamamatsu Chunagon]), and &quot;Torikaebaya Monogatari&quot; (The Changelings).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ついで『伊勢物語』『大和物語』などの歌物語・歌集に移り、『万葉集』以下、勅撰七代集・私撰集・歌合の類に触れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next chapter, discussions focus on poetry stories and collections of poetry, such as &quot;Ise Monogatari (The tales of Ise)&quot; and &quot;Yamato Monogatari (Tales of Yamato),&quot; and shift to &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (the oldest anthology of Japanese poetry), seven major imperial anthologies of poetry, personal anthologies, and poetry contests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next chapter, discussions focus on poetry stories and collections of poetry, such as &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise) and &quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Yamato), and shift to &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (the oldest anthology of Japanese poetry), seven major imperial anthologies of poetry, personal anthologies, and poetry contests.</e>
<cmt>punctuation rulescapital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next chapter, discussions focus on poetry stories and collections of poetry, such as &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise) and &quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Yamato), and shift to &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (the oldest anthology of Japanese poetry), seven major imperial anthologies of poetry, personal anthologies, and poetry contests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>最後の「女性論」では、清少納言・紫式部・和泉式部・小式部内侍・大和宣旨・小侍従ら宮廷の花を語るが、中でも作者が賛美したかったのは、伊勢 (歌人)・選子内親王・藤原定子・藤原歓子の四人であったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last chapter on women, stars in the Imperial court such as Sei Shonagon, Murasaki Shikibu, Izumi Shikibu, Koshikibu no Naishi, Yamato no senji, and Kojiju are the topics of discussion, but the author seems to give the highest praise for Ise, Imperial Princess Senshi, FUJIWARA no Teishi, and FUJIWARA no Kanshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last chapter on women, stars in the Imperial court such as Sei Shonagon, Murasaki Shikibu, Izumi Shikibu, Koshikibu no Naishi, Yamato no Senji, and Kojiju are the topics of discussion, but the author seems to give the highest praise to Ise, who was a poet, Imperial Princess Senshi, FUJIWARA no Teishi, and FUJIWARA no Kanshi.</e>
<cmt>changed from senji to Senji (to consolidate the style) capitals, prepositionadded the translation for 歌人</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last chapter on women, stars in the Imperial court such as Sei Shonagon, Murasaki Shikibu, Izumi Shikibu, Koshikibu no Naishi, Yamato no Senji, and Kojiju are the topics of discussion, but the author seems to give the highest praise to Ise, who was a poet, Imperial Princess Senshi, FUJIWARA no Teishi, and FUJIWARA no Kanshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>いずれも、確固たる生き方をした女性だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of four women had her own attitude to her life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of the four women had her own attitude toward her life.</e>
<cmt>article/vocab</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of the four women had her own attitude toward her life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして男性論は『大鏡』の類に任せるとして、筆を置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book is concluded by stating that it leaves the critique on men to other tales like &quot;Okagami&apos; (The Great Mirror).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book is concluded by stating that it leaves the critique of men to other tales like &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror).</e>
<cmt>grammarpunctuation rules</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book is concluded by stating that it leaves the critique of men to other tales like &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>無名草子は散逸物語の研究資料としてのみならず、中世初期に於ける人々の中古文学享受史が伺える貴重な作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mumyo zoshi is a valuable literature not only for researches on scattered and lost tales but also for understanding how people in the early Medieval Period accepted the Heian literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mumyo Zoshi is a valuable literary work not only for research on scattered and lost tales but also for understanding how people in the early Medieval Period accepted the Heian literature.</e>
<cmt>capital/ vocab/ grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mumyo Zoshi is a valuable literary work not only for research on scattered and lost tales but also for understanding how people in the early Medieval Period accepted the Heian literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yume149(id:17504), YOSHI438(id:174755), SK(id:64397), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), 松茸(id:27535), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>