<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平治物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiji Monogatari (The Tale of Heiji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiji Monogatari (The Tale of Heiji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiji Monogatari (The Tale of Heiji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『平治物語』（へいじものがたり）は平治の乱の顛末を描いた軍記物語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; is a war chronicle concerning the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; is a war chronicle concerning the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; is a war chronicle concerning the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>作者不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平治元年（1159）、後白河上皇方最大の武力勢力であった平清盛が熊野参詣に出かけた隙を狙って、かねてから信西（信西）と後白河の寵愛をめぐって権力争いを起こしていた藤原信頼が、保元の乱での賞与などで平家の圧迫に不満を覚えていた源義朝を語らって挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1159, when TAIRA no Kiyomori, who led the strongest army of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, paid a visit to the Kumano Shrine, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, who had been involved in the struggle for winning Goshirakawa&apos;s favor against Shinzei, got together with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, who had been dissatisfied with the oppression by the Taira family, above all the inadequate reward in the Hogen War, raised an army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1159, when TAIRA no Kiyomori, who led the strongest army of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, visited the Kumano Shrine, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori (who had been involved in the struggle to win Goshirakawa&apos;s favor against Shinzei) got together with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (who had been dissatisfied with the oppression by the Taira family, particularly the inadequate reward in the Hogen War) and raised an army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1159, when TAIRA no Kiyomori, who led the strongest army of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa, visited the Kumano-jinja Shrine, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori (who had been involved in the struggle to win Goshirakawa&apos;s favor against Shinzei) raised an army, getting together with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (who had been dissatisfied with the oppression by the Taira family, particularly the inadequate reward in the Hogen War).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>上皇を大内裏で監禁、通憲を殺害し一度は権勢を握る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They confined the retired Emperor to the Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace), killing Michinori and holding power for a while, but TAIRA no Kiyomori, who came back from Kumano, defeated them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They confined the retired Emperor to the Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace), killing Michinori and holding power for a while, but TAIRA no Kiyomori, who came back from Kumano, defeated them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They confined the Retired Emperor to the Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace), killing Michinori, and held power for a while.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、熊野から引き返した平清盛に敗れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, TAIRA no Kiyomori, who came back from Kumano, defeated them.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>信頼は処刑、義朝も暗殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunori was executed, and Yoshitomo was assassinated too.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunori was executed, and Yoshitomo was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunori was executed, and Yoshitomo was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以降、平家政権の全盛や没落、鎌倉幕府の成立などまでを描いた諸本も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many manuscripts contains the descriptions of the glory and fall of the Taira Government since then, and establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many manuscripts since then have contained descriptions of the glory and fall of the Taira Government, as well as the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many manuscripts since then have contained descriptions of the glory and fall of the Taira Government, as well as the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>『保元物語』や『平家物語』と同様、和漢混淆文で叙述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Hogen War) and &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heike), it was written in the mixed writing of Japanese and Chinese</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like &quot;Hogen Monogatari (The Tale of the Hogen War&quot;) and &quot;Heike Monogatari (The Tale of Heike&quot;), it was written in a mixture of Japanese and Chinese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well as &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Hogen War) and &quot;Heike Monogatari &quot;(The Tale of Heike), it was written in a mixed writing of Japanese and Chinese.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>諸本によって内容に異同は大きいが、悪源太義平（源義平）の武勇譚や、源義経の母である常盤御前（常葉とも）が、老いた母のために清盛のもとへと赴く哀憐の話が中心を占めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the contents are different among the transcription and published books, most of the story consists of a heroic episode of Akugenta Yoshihira (Wicked Genta, Yoshihira) (MINAMOTO no Yoshihira) and a pitiful story in which Tokiwa Gozen (the name 常盤 is also written with the characters 常葉), the mother of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, visits Kiyomori on behalf of her old mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the contents vary among the transcriptions and published books, most of the story consists of a heroic episode of Akugenta Yoshihira (Wicked Genta, Yoshihira) (MINAMOTO no Yoshihira) and a pitiful story in which Tokiwa Gozen (the name 常盤 is also written with the characters 常葉), the mother of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, visits Kiyomori on behalf of her aged mother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the contents vary among the transcriptions and published books, most of the story consists of a heroic episode of Akugenta Yoshihira (Wicked Genta, Yoshihira) (MINAMOTO no Yoshihira) and a pitiful story in which Tokiwa Gozen (the name 常盤 is also written with the characters 常葉), the mother of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, visits Kiyomori on behalf of her aged mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『保元物語』と同様に源氏に対して同情的な内容であるのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characterized by the sympathetic tone to the Minamoto Clan as well as &quot;Hogen Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characterized by the sympathetic tone toward the Minamoto Clan, as is also the case in &quot;Hogen Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characterized by the sympathetic tone toward the Minamoto Clan, as is also the case in &quot;Hogen Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>成立・作者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The writing process and authorship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The writing process and authorship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The writing process and authorship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>『平治物語』については、成立・作者に関しては、確かな資料は多くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are not so many reliable materials concerning the writing process of &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; and its author.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There aren&apos;t many reliable materials concerning the authorship and writing process of &quot;Heiji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There aren&apos;t many reliable materials concerning the authorship and writing process of &quot;Heiji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし、成立に関していえば、第1類本である学習院大学図書館蔵本が源頼朝の死（正治元年・1199）に関する記事を含んでいるので、これ以降であることは確実。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is no doubt that the work was completed after 1199, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo died, because the manuscript, which belongs to the Group One and is owned by Gakushuin University Library, contains the article concerning the death of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is certain that the work was completed after 1199, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo died, because the manuscript, which is in the possession of Group One (another is owned by Gakushuin University Library), contains an article concerning the death of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>OWNERSHIP?SF: Interpretation is wrong.However, it is certain that the work was completed after 1199, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo died, because the manuscript of the first edition which is owned by Gakushuin University Library contains an article concerning the death of Yoritomo.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is certain that the work was completed at least after 1199, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo passed away, because the manuscript of the first edition which is owned by Gakushuin University Library contains an article concerning the death of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この頼朝の死を含まない本文もあるが、永積安明の説によって、第1類本がもっとも古態本文であることがほぼ承認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are manuscripts which do not contain the description of Yoritomo&apos;s death, according to Yasuaki NAGAZUMI, it is almost certain that the manuscripts which belong to the Group One are the oldest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are manuscripts that don&apos;t contain descriptions of Yoritomo&apos;s death, according to Yasuaki NAGAZUMI it is almost certain that the manuscripts held by Group One are the oldest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are manuscripts that don&apos;t contain descriptions of Yoritomo&apos;s death, Yasuaki NAGAZUMI claimed that it is almost certain that the manuscripts belonging to the Group One are the oldest.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、石井行雄によって『春華秋月抄草』（宗性作）の寛元4年（1246）の執筆箇所に、物語古態本の断片が存在することが確認されており、すくなくともこの年以前には成立していたと目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukio ISHII confirmed that the fragment of the oldest manuscript of the story was included in the article dated 1246 in &quot;Shunka shugetsu shoso&quot; (a book written by Sosho), so it is considered that the work was completed at least in this year or before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukio ISHII confirmed that the fragment of the oldest manuscript of the story was included in the article dated 1246 in &quot;Shunka shugetsu shoso&quot; (a book written by Sosho), so it&apos;s considered that the work was completed at least in that year, if not before.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukio ISHII confirmed that the fragment of the oldest manuscript of the story was included in the article dated 1246 in &quot;Shunka shugetsu shoso&quot; (a book written by Sosho), therefore it is considered that the work was completed at least before 1246.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは絵巻である『平治物語絵詞』の書風を、藤原教家の晩年、建長年間（1249-1255）のものであると認定した松原茂の説とも合致している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This view agrees with an opinion of Shigeru MATSUBARA, who identified the handwriting written in &quot;Heiji Monogatari Ekotoba&quot; (illustrated stories of Heiji Rebellion) with that of FUJIWARA no Noriie in his later years, between 1249 and 1255.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This view is in agreement with an opinion by Shigeru MATSUBARA, who identified the handwriting written in &quot;Heiji Monogatari Ekotoba&quot; (illustrated stories of the Heiji Rebellion) with that of FUJIWARA no Noriie in his later years, between 1249 and 1255.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This view is in agreement with an opinion by Shigeru MATSUBARA, who identified the handwriting written in &quot;Heiji Monogatari Ekotoba&quot; (illustrated stories of the Heiji Rebellion) with that of FUJIWARA no Noriie in his later years, between 1249 and 1255.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>以上の説によれば13世紀半ばには成立していたという点は動かないと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the above, it seems to be certain that the work was completed by the mid-thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the above, it appears certain that the work was completed by the mid-thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the above, it appears certain that the work was completed by the mid-13th century.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして『普通唱導集』（永仁5年・1297）には保元・平家と並んで琵琶法師の語りが広まっていたことが記されており、13世紀後半には物語は広く浸透してものと判断される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Futsu-shodo shu&quot; (a selecton of ordinary advocate) (1297) has a record that the storytelling done by a biwa-playing minstrel had spread as well as Hogen and Heike Monogatari, so it is estimated that the story came to be known to everybody by the late thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Futsu-shodo shu&quot; (a selection of ordinary advocates) (1297) contains a record that the storytelling by a biwa-playing minstrel had spread as well as the Hogen and Heike monogatari, so it is estimated that by the late thirteenth century the story was known to everyone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Futsu-shodo shu&quot; (a selection of ordinary advocates) (1297) contains a record that the storytelling by a biwa-playing minstrel had spread as well as the Hogen Monogatari and Heike Monogatari, so it is estimated that by the late 13th century the story was widely known.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しアラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>作者については、近世までは『保元物語』と同一とみる理解が通説であったが、近年は別人であると考えるのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was common view that the author of the story was the same as that of &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; until the early modern times, but these past few years it is generally considered that these two works were written by the different authors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a common view that the author of the story was the same as that of &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; until the early modern times, but in recent years it has generally been assumed that the two works were written by different authors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a common view that the author of the story was the same as that of &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; until the early-modern times, but in recent years it has generally been assumed that the two works were written by different authors.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>誰であるかは不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the author is still unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the authorship remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the authorship remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、成立・作者にかんしては『保元物語』の保元物語成立・保元物語作者と重なる点がおおいので、そちらも参照されたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See also The writing process of &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; to get to know the writing process and authorship; there are a lot of overlaps between Hogen Monogatari and Heiji Monogatari, especially about the writing process and the authorship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See the section on the writing process of &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; to learn more about the writing process and authorship; there are many overlaps between Hogen Monogatari and Heiji Monogatari, particularly in regard to the writing process and authorship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See the section on the writing process of &quot;Hogen Monogatari&quot; to learn more about the writing process and authorship; there are many overlaps between Hogen Monogatari and Heiji Monogatari, particularly in regard to the writing process and authorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Rupert660(id:93405), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Zerozeros(id:189962), Ktmchi(id:113301), Yas(id:739), Chujuki(id:243505), NDR(id:5500), Kiev(id:13022), Yuming(id:17854), DorganBot(id:149946), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>