<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>虎御前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tora Gozen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tora Gozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tora Gozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>虎御前（とらごぜん、安元元年（1175年） - ?）は、富士の巻狩りの際に起こった曽我兄弟の仇討ちで有名な「曽我物語」のヒロインで曽我兄弟の兄・曾我祐成の恋人で、この物語を色づけ深みを持たせる役割をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Sogamonogatari&quot; (the tale of Soga) that deals with the famous story of the Soga brothers&apos; revenge that happened in the Fuji no Makigari (Hunting session at Mt. Fuji), Tora Gozen (1174-?) is a heroin and a lover of the elder of the brothers, SOGA no Sukenari, the role added the depth and color to the story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sogamonogatari&quot; (the tale of Soga) that deals with the famous story of the Soga brothers&apos; revenge that happened in Fuji no Makigari (Hunting session at Mt. Fuji), Tora Gozen (1174-?) is a heroin and a lover of the elder of the brothers, SOGA no Sukenari, the role added depth and color to the story.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;Sogamonogatari&apos; (the tale of Soga) that deals with the famous story of the Soga brothers&apos; revenge that happened in Fuji no Makigari (Hunting session at Mt. Fuji), Tora Gozen (1175-?) is a heroin and a lover of the elder of the brothers, SOGA no Sukenari, the role added depth and color to the story.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。1174を1175に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>お虎さん、虎女（とらじょ）とも呼ばれる、また俳句などでは虎御前と書いて「とらごぜ」と読ませることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is also called O-tora san or Torajo; in haiku she is sometimes referred to as &quot;Toragoze&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is also called O-tora san or Torajo; in haiku she is sometimes referred to as &quot;Toragoze.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is also called O-tora san or Torajo; in haiku she is sometimes referred to as &apos;Toragoze.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>十郎祐成と弟の曾我時致は早くから父の仇を討とうと考えていたので妻を持つことを考えなかったが、五郎の勧めもあり妻を持つことになった十郎は自分が死んだ後のことを考え遊女を選んだといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juro Sukenari and his younger brother Tokimune SOGA had determined early on to take revenge for their father&apos;s death, so they had no intention to marry, but when Goro suggested Juro to have a wife, Juro chose a courtesan thinking about matters that would occur after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juro Sukenari and his younger brother Tokimune SOGA had determined early on to take revenge for their father&apos;s death, so they had no intention to marry, but when Goro suggested Juro have a wife, Juro chose a courtesan thinking about matters that would occur after his death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juro Sukenari and his younger brother Tokimune SOGA had determined early on to take revenge for their father&apos;s death, so they had no intention to marry, but when Goro suggested Juro have a wife, Juro chose a courtesan thinking about matters that would occur after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>虎は大磯町の遊女であった、虎と十郎は遭うべくして出会い直ぐに恋に落ちる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tora was a courtesan in Oiso-machi, with whom Juro was destined to fall in love immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tora was a courtesan in Oiso-machi, with whom Juro was destined to fall in love with immediately.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tora was a courtesan in Oiso-machi, with whom Juro was destined to fall in love with immediately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>虎17歳、十郎20歳の時であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tora was seventeen and Juro was twenty years old when they met.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tora was seventeen and Juro was twenty years old when they met.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tora was seventeen and Juro was twenty years old when they met.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして虎が19歳の年、建久4年（1193年）5月28日 (旧暦)に源頼朝が催した富士の裾野での狩りに夜陰に乗じて忍び込んだ兄弟は、父の仇の工藤祐経を討ち取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tora was nineteen, in May 28 1193 (old lunar calendar), the brothers sneaked under the darkness of night into the hunting grounds at the foot of Mt. Fuji that was held by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and executed their revenge on Suketsune KUDO for their father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tora was nineteen, in May 28 1193 (old lunar calendar), the brothers sneaked under the darkness of night into the hunting grounds at the foot of Mt. Fuji held by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and executed their revenge on Suketsune KUDO for their father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tora was nineteen, in May 28 1193 (old lunar calendar), the brothers sneaked under the darkness of night into the hunting grounds at the foot of Mt. Fuji held by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and executed their revenge on Suketsune KUDO for their father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、十郎はその場で新田忠常に切り殺され、五郎も生け捕りになった後頼朝直々に取り調べられて処刑される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Juro was slain at the site by Tadatsune NITTA and Goro was caught alive and investigated by Yoritomo himself before executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Juro was slain on the site by Tadatsune NITTA and Goro was caught alive and investigated by Yoritomo himself before executed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Juro was slain on the site by Tadatsune NITTA and Goro was caught alive and investigated by Yoritomo himself before executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>俳句の季語に「虎が雨（とらがあめ）」という言葉があるが、旧暦の5月28日に降る雨に後世の人びとが虎女の悲しみを重ねたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Toragaame (Tora&apos;s rain)&quot; is a kigo (season word) for haiku that came from a sympathy of people in the following generations with Torajo&apos;s sorrow that was reflected on the rain in May 28 of the old lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Toragaame (Tora&apos;s rain)&quot; is a kigo (season word) for haiku that came from the sympathy of the people in the following generations with Torajo&apos;s sorrow that was reflected in the rain in May 28 of the old lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toragaame (Tora&apos;s rain)&apos; is a kigo (season word) for haiku that came from the sympathy of the people in the following generations with Torajo&apos;s sorrow that was reflected in the rain in May 28 of the old lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>兄弟が死んだ後、残された虎女は曽我の母のもとを訪ね兄弟を弔い出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the brothers died, surviving Torajo visited their mother to mourn for them, and she became a nun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the brothers died, the surviving Torajo visited their mother to mourn for them, and she became a nun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the brothers died, the surviving Torajo visited their mother to mourn for them, and she became a nun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>BiographyをCareerに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>虎女の出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torajo&apos;s origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torajo&apos;s origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torajo&apos;s origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>虎女は「吾妻鏡」にも出てくることから実在した女性とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torajo also appears in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), so she is considered to be a existed woman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torajo also appears in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), so she is considered to be an existing woman.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torajo also appears in &apos;Azuma Kagami&apos; (The Mirror of the East), so she is considered to be an existing woman.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>虎女の出自については諸説あるが、重須本「曽我物語」では、虎女の母は平塚市の遊女夜叉王で父は都を逃れて相模国海老名郷にいた宮内判官家永だとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several theories on her origin; according to an alternative version Omosuhon &quot;Sogamonogatari,&quot; Torajo&apos;s mother was a courtesan in Hiratsuka City named Yashao and her father was Kunai hogan Ienaga who escaped from the capital to Ebina-go, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>重須本Omosuhon　宮内判官家永 Kunai hogan Ienaga 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several theories on her origin; according to an alternative version Omosuhon &quot;Sogamonogatari,&quot; Torajo&apos;s mother was a courtesan in Hiratsuka City named Yashao and her father was Kunai hogan Ienaga who escaped from the capital to Ebina-go, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several theories on her origin; according to an alternative version Omosuhon &apos;Sogamonogatari,&apos; Torajo&apos;s mother was a courtesan in Hiratsuka City named Yashao and her father was Kunai hogan Ienaga who escaped from the capital to Ebina-go, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>虎女は平塚で生まれ大磯町の長者のもとで遊女になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torajo was born in Hiratsuka and became a courtesan under a choja (female controller) in Oiso-machi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torajo was born in Hiratsuka and became a courtesan under a choja (female controller) in Oiso-machi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torajo was born in Hiratsuka and became a courtesan under a choja (female controller) in Oiso-machi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>虎の母夜叉王がいた平塚の遊女宿は現在の平塚市の黒部が丘あたりにあったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The brothel in Hiratsuka to which Tora&apos;s mother Yashao belonged is said to be located in present-day Kurobeoka, Hiratsuka City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brothel in Hiratsuka to which Tora&apos;s mother Yashao belonged is said to be located in present-day Kurobeoka, Hiratsuka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brothel in Hiratsuka to which Tora&apos;s mother Yashao belonged is said to be located in present-day Kurobeoka, Hiratsuka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大磯の長者は高麗山の近く（現在の平塚市山下）であるので余り離れた場所ではない、花水川が間にあるが歩いても一時間は掛からない距離関係である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The choja in Oiso was placed near Komayama Mountain (present-day Yamashita, Hiratsuka-City), so it was not so distant from Kurobeoka; the distance between these places is less than an hour on foot even there is Hanamizugawa River in between.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The choja in Oiso was placed near Komayama Mountain (present-day Yamashita, Hiratsuka-City), so it was not so distant from Kurobeoka; the distance between these places is less than an hour on foot there is even the Hanamizugawa River in between.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The choja in Oiso was placed near Mt. Koma (present-day Yamashita, Hiratsuka-City), so it was not so distant from Kurobeoka; the distance between these places is less than an hour on foot there is even the Hanamizugawa River in between.</e>
<cmt>Komayama MountainをMt. Komaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>虎御前の名前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name of Tora Gozen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name of Tora Gozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name of Tora Gozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>寅年の寅の日の寅の刻に生まれたので三寅御前と名づけたと「曽我物語」にあるが、実際は虎女は未（ひつじ）年の生まれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Sogamonogatari,&quot; she was named Mitora (three tigers) Gozen because she was born on the time, day, and year of Tiger, she was actually born in the year of the Sheep.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Sogamonogatari,&quot; she was named Mitora (three tigers) Gozen because she was born on the time, day, and year of Tiger, she was actually born in the year of the Sheep.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Sogamonogatari,&apos; she was named Mitora (three tigers) Gozen because she was born on the time, day, and year of Tiger, she was actually born in the year of the Sheep.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは計算すれば直ぐに判ることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be found out with a quick calculation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be determined with a quick calculation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be determined with a quick calculation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なぜ虎という名前をつけたかは本当のところはわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The true reason why she was named Tora is therefore unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The true reason why she was named Tora is therefore unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The true reason why she was named Tora is therefore unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>虎が生まれた場所は近くにもろこしが原があり、その向こうには高麗山があるという異国の面影があった、唐（もろこし）とくれば枕詞は虎であるがその為かどうかも判らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place where Tora was born was near a corn field and Komayama Mountain was beyond the field; such an exotic scenery can be associated with Morokoshi (China) and its Makura word (Poetic epithet convention) is Tora, but it is uncertain whether such association is the reason of her name or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The place where Tora was born was near a corn field and Komayama Mountain was beyond the field; such exotic scenery can be associated with Morokoshi (China) and its Makura word (Poetic epithet convention) is Tora, but it is uncertain whether such association is the reason for her name or not.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The place where Tora was born was near a corn field and Komayama Mountain was beyond the field; such exotic scenery can be associated with Morokoshi (China) and its Makura word (Poetic epithet convention) is Tora, but it is uncertain whether such association is the reason for her name or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>虎御前の御前は当時遊女や白拍子などにつけて呼ぶ呼称である、静御前、巴御前などと同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gozen in &quot;Tora Gozen&quot; is a designation given to courtesan and Shirabyoshi (women who play Japanese traditional dance) at that time, such as Shizuka Gozen and Tomoe Gozen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gozen in &quot;Tora Gozen&quot; is a designation given to courtesan and Shirabyoshi (women who play Japanese traditional dance) at that time, such as Shizuka Gozen and Tomoe Gozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozen in &quot;Tora Gozen&quot; is a designation given to courtesan and Shirabyoshi (women who play Japanese traditional dance) at that time, such as Shizuka Gozen and Tomoe Gozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>当時の呼び方として「ごぜん」ではなく短く「ごぜ」としたようで後の瞽女（ごぜ）に通ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, they were called &quot;Goze&quot; instead of &quot;Gozen,&quot; that was later let to Goze (blind female musicians).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, they were called &quot;Goze&quot; instead of &quot;Gozen,&quot; that was later Goze (blind female musicians).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, they were called &apos;Goze&apos; instead of &apos;Gozen,&apos; that was later Goze (blind female musicians).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>虎女の生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torajo&apos;s life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torajo&apos;s life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torajo&apos;s life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>夫、十郎（当時は戸籍などないので、明確な婚姻の定義は無いが虎は十郎の妻としてその生涯を送った）の死後、兄弟の母を曽我の里に訪ねたあと箱根に登り箱根権現の別当の手により出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her husband Juro died (there was no system of family registration at that time, so no distinct definition of marriage existed either, but Tora spent her life as Juro&apos;s wife), she visited the brothers&apos; mother in the village of Soga before she climbed the Hakone to became a nun by Betto (superintendent) of Hakone gongen (sacred mountain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her husband Juro died (there was no system of family registration at that time, so no distinct definition of marriage existed either, but Tora spent her life as Juro&apos;s wife), she visited the brothers&apos; mother in the village of Soga before she climbed the Hakone to became a nun by Betto (superintendent) of Hakone gongen (sacred mountain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her husband Juro died (there was no system of family registration at that time, so no distinct definition of marriage existed either, but Tora spent her life as Juro&apos;s wife), she visited the brothers&apos; mother in the village of Soga before she climbed the Hakone to became a nun by Betto (superintendent) of Hakone gongen (sacred mountain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その後亡夫の供養のため信州の善光寺に参る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then she visited Zenko-ji Temple in Shinshu to hold a memorial service for the deceased husband.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then she visited Zenko-ji Temple in Shinshu to hold a memorial service for her deceased husband.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then she visited Zenko-ji Temple in Shinshu to hold a memorial service for her deceased husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>大磯町にもどった後高麗山の北側の山下に庵を結び菩薩地蔵を安置し夫の供養に明け暮れる日々を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returned to Oiso-machi, she build herself a hermitage in Yamashita on the north side of Komayama Mountain where she placed Bosatsu Jizo and spent all her time praying for her deceased husband</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returned to Oiso-machi, she build herself a hermitage in Yamashita on the north side of Komayama Mountain where she placed a Bosatsu Jizo and spent all her time praying for her deceased husband</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returned to Oiso-machi, she build herself a hermitage in Yamashita on the north side of Mt. Koma where she placed a Bosatsu Jizo and spent all her time praying for her deceased husband.</e>
<cmt>Komayama MountainをMt. Komaに変更しました。ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>事が山下（現、平塚市）に現存する高麗寺の末寺であった荘巌寺に伝わる「荘巌寺虎御前縁起」に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is described in &quot;Shoganji Toragozen Engi&quot; that has been handed down at Shoganji which still exists today in Yamashita (in present-day Hiratsuka City) and was a branch temple of Korai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is described in &quot;Shoganji Toragozen Engi&quot; handed down at Shoganji and still exists today in Yamashita (in present-day Hiratsuka City) and was a branch temple of Korai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is described in &apos;Shoganji Toragozen Engi&apos; handed down at Shoganji and still exists today in Yamashita (in present-day Hiratsuka City) and was a branch temple of Korai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>虎女は兄弟の供養を片時も忘れることなく「曽我物語」の生成に深く関わりながらその小庵で63年と言われるその生涯を閉じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torajo never ceased to pray for the soul of the brothers and deeply related to generation of &quot;Sogamonogatari&quot; until she died at the age of 63 at her hermitage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torajo never ceased to pray for the soul of the brothers and deeply related to the generation of &quot;Sogamonogatari&quot; until she died at the age of sixty-three at her hermitage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torajo never ceased to pray for the soul of the brothers and deeply related to the generation of &apos;Sogamonogatari&apos; until she died at the age of sixty-three at her hermitage.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>（虎女の生涯は嘉禄3年1227年2月13日 (旧暦)没、享年53と言われてきたが最近の研究でその没年は嘉禎4年西暦1238年とされる、ノートに注を付記）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Torajo had been said to die in February 13, 1227 (old lunar calendar) at the age of 53, but the recent researches found out that she died in 1238; see notes.)</e>
<cmt>「ノートに注を付記」は意味不明ですが see notes としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Torajo said to have died in February 13, 1227 (old lunar calendar) at the age of fifty-three, but the recent research revealed that she died in 1238; see notes.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Torajo said to have died in June 4, 1225 at the age of fifty-three, but the recent research revealed that she died in 1238; see notes.)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>遊女考（参考）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consideration for courtesans (reference)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consideration for courtesans (reference)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consideration for courtesans (reference)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>現代人は遊女というと江戸時代の零落した女性が行き着く暗くマイナスなイメージを強く持つが、室町時代以前の遊女はむしろ知識人であり歌舞などの技芸を厳しく長者と言われる元締めのような存在の女性から躾けられ、時には教養も身につけた女性たちで、神聖な存在として巫女の代わりをするようなこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People today have a dark and negative image on courtesans who were in the Edo Period ruined women, but in days prior to Muromachi Period, courtesans were rather intelligent women who were strictly trained in singing and dancing by a female controller called Choja, and some of them acquired some culture, so they were sometimes regarded sacred women and played a role of miko (shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People today have a dark and negative image on courtesans who lived during ithe Edo Period as ruined women, but in days prior to the Muromachi Period, courtesans were rather intelligent women who were strictly trained in singing and dancing by a female controller called Choja, and some of them acquired some culture, so they were sometimes regarded as sacred women and played the role of miko (shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People today have a dark and negative image on courtesans who lived during in the Edo Period as ruined women, but in days prior to the Muromachi Period, courtesans were rather intelligent women who were strictly trained in singing and dancing by a female controller called Choja, and some of them acquired some culture, so they were sometimes regarded as sacred women and played the role of miko (shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt>itheをin theに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>遊女が自らの性で商売するだけの存在になったは戦国時代 (日本)以降のようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that courtesans became mere prostitutes after the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that courtesans became mere prostitutes after the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that courtesans became mere prostitutes after the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ef3(id:84901), Lupinoid(id:68), 味っ子(id:17086), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Nevylax(id:38464), Shigenaga.S(id:30574), 小者(id:172526), Hat2867(id:67840), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>