<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本藩人物誌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honpanjinbutsushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honpanjinbutsushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honpan Jinbutsushi (brief accounts of the Shimazu clan and its chief retainers mainly during the Sengoku period [period of warring states])</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本藩人物誌（ほんぱんじんぶつし）は、戦国時代 (日本)を中心に、15世紀中頃から17世紀中頃までの約200年間にわたる島津氏の一族及び主な家臣などの略記をいろは順に全13巻にまとめたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honpanjinbutsushi was thirteen volumes of brief accounts of the Shimazu clan and its chief retainers for 200 years from the middle of 15 century to the middle of 17 century mainly during the Warring States period (middle 15c. - middle 16c.) arranged in the traditional Japanese alphabetical order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honpanjinbutsushi was thirteen volumes of brief accounts of the Shimazu clan and its chief retainers for 200 years from the middle of 15 century to the middle of 17 century mainly during the Warring States period (middle 15c. - middle 16c.) arranged in the traditional Japanese alphabetical order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honpan Jinbutsushi is thirteen volumes of brief accounts of the Shimazu clan and its chief retainers for 200 years from the middle of 15th century to the middle of 17th century mainly during the Sengoku period arranged in the traditional Japanese alphabetical order.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>著者は福崎正澄とされているがその経歴は不明であり、成立年代も不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Masazumi FUKUZAKI wrote the book but both his career and the year of creation were unknown.</e>
<cmt>「正澄」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Masazumi FUKUZAKI wrote the book but both his career and the year of creation were unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to be written by Masazumi FUKUZAKI but both his career and the year of creation are unknown.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>巻の12末尾に道釈（僧侶）及び女子伝を、巻の13には島津氏に敵対又は謀反を起こした人物をまとめた国賊伝を記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of Vol. 12, items of monks and women were organized, and Vol. 13 was a book of traitors with the items of those who opposed to and who rebelled against the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of Vol. 12, items of monks and women were organized, and Vol. 13 was a book of traitors with the items of those who opposed to and who rebelled against the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Records related to priests of Doshaku (Buddhism and Taoism) and women are written at the end of the volume 12, traitors who opposed or revolted against Shimazu clan in the volume 13.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鹿児島大学附属図書館が所蔵している写本は、島津久光が天保10年（1839年）から翌年にかけて書写したもので、昭和26年（1951年）に同館が玉里島津家から購入したものである。（玉里文庫本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A handwritten copy possessed by the Kagoshima University Library was written by Hisamitsu SHIMAZU from 1839 to 1840, which the library bought from the Tamazato Shimazu clan in 1951.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A handwritten copy possessed by the Kagoshima University Library was written by Hisamitsu SHIMAZU from 1839 to 1840, which the library bought from the Tamazato Shimazu clan in 1951.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A handwritten copy possessed by the Kagoshima University Library was written by Hisamitsu SHIMAZU from 1839 to 1840, the following year, which the library bought from the Tamazato-shimazu family in 1951 (known as Tamazato bunko-bon [the books originally owned by Tamazato-shimazu family]).</e>
<cmt>原文が不適切に分断されていたため、「（玉里文庫本）」を本文章に含めました。原文には 「島津家文書本」とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「玉里文庫本」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、鹿児島県立図書館の所蔵本を底本にしたものが、昭和48年（1973年）、鹿児島県史料集第13集として刊行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documents of the Shimazu clan: Those based on the books possessed by the Kagoshima Prefectural Library have been published as &apos;Kagoshimaken Shiryo Dai 13 shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents of the Shimazu clan: Those based on the books possessed by the Kagoshima Prefectural Library have been published as &apos;Kagoshimaken Shiryo Dai 13 shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those based on the books possessed by the Kagoshima Prefectural Library has been published as &apos;Kagoshimaken Shiryo Dai 13 shu&apos; (volume 13 of Historical Records of Kagoshima Prefecture) since 1973.</e>
<cmt>不適切に分断されていた原文、訳文を修正しました。訳漏れ。「昭和48年(1973年）」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), 紹益(id:202652), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>