<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>椎本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiigamoto (Beneath the Oak)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiigamoto (Beneath the Oak)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiigamoto (Beneath the Oak)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>椎本（しいがもと）は、『源氏物語』五十四帖の巻名のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiigamoto is one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiigamoto is one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiigamoto is one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第46帖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the forty-sixth chapter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the forty-sixth chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the forty-sixth chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第三部の一部「宇治十帖」の第2帖にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the second chapter in &apos;Uji Jujo&apos; (The Ten Quires of Uji), a part of the third section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the second chapter in &apos;Uji Jujo&apos; (The Ten Quires of Uji), part of the third section.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the second chapter in &apos;Uji Jujo&apos; (The Ten Quires of Uji), part of the third section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>巻名は、薫が故八の宮を偲んで詠んだ和歌「立ち寄らむ陰とたのみし椎が本むなしき床になりにけるかな」に因む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The title of this chapter came from a waka poem which was composed by Kaoru when he remembered late Hachi no Miya, &apos;The oak tree on which I depended under spreading shade does not exist any more, and I will live in emptiness and silence.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title of this chapter came from a waka poem which was composed by Kaoru when he remembered late Hachi no Miya, &apos;The oak tree on which I depended, spreading shade does not exist any more, and I will live in emptiness and silence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of this chapter came from a waka poem which was composed by Kaoru when he remembered late Hachi no Miya, &apos;The oak tree on which I depended, spreading shade does not exist any more, and I will live in emptiness and silence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>この帖に登場する夕霧 (源氏物語)所有の別荘は、宇治川の岸辺、京の向こう岸にあることから平等院がモデルというのが通説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly said that the second residence owned by Yugiri which appears in this chapter was modeled after Byodoin Temple because in the tale it is located on the shore of the Uji-gawa river, the opposite side of the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly said that the second residence owned by Yugiri, appearing in this chapter, was modeled after the Byodoin Temple because in the tale it is located on the shore of the Uji-gawa river, the opposite side of the capital.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly said that the second residence owned by Yugiri (The Tale of Genji), appearing in this chapter, was modeled after the Byodoin Temple because in the tale it is located on the shore of the Uji-gawa River, the opposite side of the capital.</e>
<cmt>(The Tale of Genji)　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>薫23歳の春二月から24歳の夏の話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru, age twenty-three of spring (February) to the summer of twenty-four.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru, age twenty-three in spring (February) to the summer of twenty-four.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru, age twenty-three in spring (February) to the summer of twenty-four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>2月20日 (旧暦)ごろ、匂宮は初瀬詣で（長谷寺参詣）の帰りに宇治の夕霧 (源氏物語)の別荘に立ち寄った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around February 20th (old lunar calendar), when Nioumiya pays a visit to the Hasedera Temple, he drops in at Yugiri&apos;s second house in Uji on his way home.</e>
<cmt>原文の「初瀬詣で（長谷寺参詣）」の箇所は「長谷寺参詣」とひとまとめにして訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around February 20th (old lunar calendar), when Nioumiya pays a visit to the Hasedera Temple, he drops in at Yugiri&apos;s second house in Uji on his way home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around February 20 (old lunar calendar), when Nioumiya pays a visit to Hatsuse (to Hase-dera Temple), he drops in at Yugiri&apos;s (The Tale of Genji) second house in Uji on his way home.</e>
<cmt>初瀬詣で（長谷寺参詣）→pays a visit to Hatsuse (to Hase-dera Temple)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宇治の姫君たちに関心があったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he is interested in the princesses in Uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he is interested in the princesses in Uji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he is interested in the princesses in Uji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>匂宮は薫や夕霧の子息たちと碁や双六をしたり琴を弾いたりして楽しんでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nioumiya enjoys playing a game of go, sugoroku (Japanese backgammon) and the koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) with Kaoru and Yugiri&apos;s sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nioumiya enjoys playing the game of go, sugoroku (Japanese backgammon) and the koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) with Kaoru and Yugiri&apos;s sons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nioumiya enjoys playing the game of go, sugoroku (Japanese backgammon) and the koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) with Kaoru and Yugiri&apos;s sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宇治川を挟んだ対岸にある八の宮邸にもそのにぎやかな管弦の音が響き、八の宮は昔の宮中での栄華の日々を思い出さずにはいられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachi no Miya, who lives on the other side of the Uji-gawa river, hears the sound of wind and string instruments, and cannot help remembering the old glorious days at the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachi no Miya, who lives on the other side of the Uji-gawa river, hears the sound of some wind and string instruments, and cannot help remembering the old glorious days at the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachi no Miya, who lives on the other side of the Uji-gawa River, hears the sound of some wind and string instruments, and cannot help remembering the old glorious days at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Uji-gawa River としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>翌日、八の宮から薫に贈歌があり、それを見た匂宮が代わりに返歌をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following day, Hachi no Miya sends Kaoru a poem, but Nioumiya, who happens to see it, replies the poem instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following day, Hachi no Miya sends Kaoru a poem, but Nioumiya, who happens to see it, replies to the poem instead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following day, Hachi no Miya sends Kaoru a poem, but Nioumiya, who happens to see it, replies to the poem instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>匂宮は帰京後もしばしば宇治に歌を送るようになり、八の宮はその返歌を常に中の君に書かせるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nioumiya has returned to the capital, he has come to send poems to Uji frequently, but Hachi no Miya always has Naka no Kimi reply to the poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nioumiya has returned to the capital, he frequently sends poems to Uji, but Hachi no Miya always has Naka no Kimi reply to his poems.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nioumiya has returned to the capital, he frequently sends poems to Uji, but Hachi no Miya always has Naka no Kimi reply to his poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>今年が重い厄年にあたる八の宮は、薫に姫君たちの後見を托す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is Hachi no Miya&apos;s unlucky year, so he asks Kaoru to look after his princesses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is Hachi no Miya&apos;s unlucky year, so he asks Kaoru to look after his princesses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is Hachi no Miya&apos;s unlucky year, so he asks Kaoru to look after his princesses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一方で姫君たちに、軽々しく結婚して宇治を離れ俗世に恥をさらすな、この山里に一生を過ごすのがよいと戒め、宇治の山寺に参籠しに出かけ、そこで亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also warns his daughters not to marry a man thoughtlessly, leave Uji, and disgrace themselves in public, then he visits a temple on a mountain and passes away there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also warns his daughters not to marry a man thoughtlessly, leave Uji, and disgrace themselves in public, then he visits a temple on a mountain and passes away there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also warns his daughters not to marry a man thoughtlessly, leave Uji, and disgrace themselves in public, then he visits a temple on a mountain and passes away there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>8月20日 (旧暦)のころである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an incident which has happened around August 20 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an incident that happened around August 20 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an incident that happened around August 20 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>訃報を知った姫君たちは、父の亡骸との対面を望むが、阿闍梨に厳しく断られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The princesses, who are let to know the death of their father, hope to see his remains, but Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) refuses their offer absolutely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The princesses, who are told about the death of their father, hoped to see his remains, but Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) refuses their request absolutely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The princesses, who are told about the death of their father, hoped to see his remains, but Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest) refuses their request absolutely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>薫や匂宮が弔問に八の宮邸を訪れるが、悲しみに沈む姫君たちはなかなか心を開かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru and Nioumiya visit the Hachi no Miya&apos;s residence to make a call of condolence, but the daughters feel so sad that they will not open up to anybody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru and Nioumiya visit the Hachi no Miya&apos;s residence to make a call of condolence, but the daughters feel so sad that they will not open up to anybody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru and Nioumiya visit the Hachi no Miya&apos;s residence to make a call of condolence, but the daughters feel so sad that they will not open up to anybody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>年の暮れの雪の日、宇治を訪れた薫は大君と対面する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One snowy day, at the end of the year, Kaoru visits Uji and sees Oigimi (oldest sister).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One snowy day, at the end of the year, Kaoru visits Uji and sees Oigimi (oldest sister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One snowy day, at the end of the year, Kaoru visits Uji and sees Oigimi (oldest sister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>匂宮と中の君の縁談を持ち上げつつ、おのが恋心をも訴え、京に迎えたいと申し出るが、大君は取り合わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He speaks to her about marriage arrangement between Nioumiya and Naka no Kimi, also revealing to her that he has been in love with her and wants her to move to the capital, but Oigimi will not take his words seriously.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He speaks to her about marriage arrangements between Nioumiya and Naka no Kimi, also revealing to her that he has been in love with her and wants her to move to the capital, but Oigimi does not take his words seriously.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He speaks to her about marriage arrangements between Nioumiya and Naka no Kimi, also revealing to her that he has been in love with her and wants her to move to the capital, but Oigimi does not take his words seriously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>翌年の春、匂宮の中の君への思いはますます募るようになり、夕霧の六の君との縁談にも気が進まない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following spring, Nioumiya comes to love Naka no Kimi more and more, and he is in no mood for the proposal of marriage with Yugiri&apos;s Roku no Kimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following spring, Nioumiya comes to love Naka no Kimi more and more, and he is in no mood for the proposal of marriage with Yugiri&apos;s Roku no Kimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following spring, Nioumiya comes to love Naka no Kimi more and more, and he is in no mood for the proposal of marriage with Yugiri&apos;s Roku no Kimi (Yugiri&apos;s sixth daughter).</e>
<cmt>六の君の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、自邸の三条宮が焼失した後始末などで、薫も久しく宇治を訪ねていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru&apos;s residence, Sanjo no Miya has been burnt in a fire, so he gets busy with taking care of the aftermath, and has not visited Uji for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru&apos;s residence, Sanjo no Miya was burnt down, so he gets busy taking care of the aftermath, and has not visited Uji for a long time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kaoru&apos;s residence, Sanjo no Miya was burnt down, so he gets busy taking care of the aftermath, and has not visited Uji for a long time.</e>
<cmt>meanwhile　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>夏、宇治を訪れた薫は、喪服姿の姫君たちを垣間見て、大君の美しさにますます惹かれてゆくのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In summer, when Kaoru visits Uji, he catches a glimpse of the princesses in the mourning clothes, and is attracted by the beauty of Oigimi more than ever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In summer, when Kaoru visits Uji, he catches a glimpse of the princesses in the mourning clothes, and is attracted by the beauty of Oigimi more than ever.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In summer, when Kaoru visits Uji, he catches a glimpse of the princesses in the mourning clothes, and is attracted by the beauty of Oigimi more than ever.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>