<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>続古事談</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoku Kojidan (collection of narratives complied in the Kamakura period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoku Kojidan</e>
<cmt>omit explanation because it appears immediately below</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoku Kojidan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>続古事談（ぞくこじだん）は鎌倉時代初期の説話集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Zoku Kojidan is a collection of narratives complied in the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zoku Kojidan is a collection of narratives complied during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Zoku Kojidan&quot; is a collection of narratives complied during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>The Zoku Kojidan にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>編者不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compiler is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compiler is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compiler is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>跋文によれば建保7年（1219年、同年承久と改元）4月23日成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to its postscript, this came into existence on June 14, 1219.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Afterword, this collection was completed on June 14, 1219.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Afterword, this collection was completed on June 14, 1219.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>全六巻のうち、現存本は巻三を欠く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This originally consisted of six volumes, but the third volume is missing from the existing series at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally consisting of six volumes, it is presently missing the third volume.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally consisting of six volumes, it is presently missing the third volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>185話収載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This collection contains 185 stories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection contains 185 narratives.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection contains 185 narratives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>構成は『古事談』を範とし、「王道后宮・臣節・（欠巻）・神社仏寺・諸道・漢朝」の各巻からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure of text follows the &quot;Kojidan&quot; (a collection of narratives authored by MINAMOTO no Akikane between 1212 and 1215), and the series consists of the following volumes: &apos;the rule of right based on benevolence,&apos; &apos;loyalty,&apos; the third volume is missing, &apos;shrines and temples,&apos; &apos;accomplishments,&apos; and &apos;the Han dynasty.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its structure resembles the &quot;Kojidan&quot; (a collection of narratives authored by MINAMOTO no Akikane between 1212 and 1215), and consists of the following volumes: &apos;The Rule of Right Based on Benevolence,&apos; &apos;Loyalty,&apos; (missing), &apos;Shrines and Temples,&apos; &apos;Accomplishments,&apos; and &apos;The Han Dynasty.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its structure follows the example of &quot;The Kojidan&quot; (a collection of narratives authored by MINAMOTO no Akikane between 1212 and 1215), and consists of the following volumes: &apos;The Rule of Right Based on Benevolence,&apos; &apos;Loyalty,&apos; (missing), &apos;Shrines and Temples,&apos; &apos;Accomplishments,&apos; and &apos;The Han Dynasty.&apos;</e>
<cmt>resembles をfollows the example of に修正しました。※ resemble「似たような特徴を持っている (have a similar appearance to or features in common with)」では「範とする」すなわち「倣って」の意味が弱いように感じられたため、上記のとおり訳しました。http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/orexxsemble?view=uk統一リスト（レビュー結果：2009/06/30）を参考にthe &quot;Kojidan&quot; を &quot;The Kojidan&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>うち漢朝部は『古事談』に無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these volume names, only &apos;the Han dynasty&apos; does not exist in the &quot;Kojidan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these volume, only &apos;The Han Dynasty&apos; does not exist in the &quot;Kojidan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these volume, only &apos;The Han Dynasty&apos; does not exist in the &quot;Kojidan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>所収の説話伝承は『中右記』『長秋記』『中外抄』『富家語』などを出典としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stories and legends contained in this collection are originally from the &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), the &quot;Choshuki&quot; (the diary of MINAMOTO no Morotoki), the &quot;Chugaisho&quot; (the analects of FUJIWARA no Tadazane), the &quot;Fukego&quot; (the analects of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu), and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stories and legends contained in this collection are originally from the &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (the Diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), the &quot;Choshuki&quot; (the Diary of MINAMOTO no Morotoki), the &quot;Chugaisho&quot; (the Analects of FUJIWARA no Tadazane), the &quot;Fukego&quot; (the Analects of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu), among others.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stories and legends contained in this collection are originally from &quot;The Chuyuki&quot; (the Diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), &quot;The Choshuki&quot; (the Diary of MINAMOTO no Morotoki), &quot;The Chugaisho&quot; (the Analects of FUJIWARA no Tadazane), &quot;The Fukego&quot; (the Analects of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu), among others.</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（レビュー結果：2009/06/30）を参考に、書名の定冠詞を大文字にしてクォーテーション内に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>日記・故実書の利用は『古事談』に似ているが、文体は和文（仮名文）で儒教の教訓性を持つ説話が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Zoku Kojindan is similar to the Kojindan in regard to the use of diaries and books of ancient practices and customs, but the literary style of the Zoku Kojindan is Japanese kana text, and stories in this collection tend to have teachings of Confucius.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Zoku Kojindan shows similarity to the Kojindan in regard to the use of diaries and books of ancient practices and customs, the Zoku Kojindan uses Japanese Kana characters, and its stories tend to include teachings of Confucius.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;The Zoku Kojidan&quot; shows similarity to &quot;The Kojidan&quot; in regard to the use of diaries and books of ancient practices and customs, &quot;The Zoku Kojidan&quot; uses Japanese Kana characters, and its stories tend to include teachings of Confucius.</e>
<cmt>the Zoku Kojindan、the Kojindan を各々&quot;The Zoku Kojidan&quot;、&quot;The Kojidan&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>承久の乱前夜において尚古傾向と末代意識が強く、理想的な帝王の姿を説くのは後鳥羽天皇への諫言が込められているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this was complied on the eve of the Jokyu War, it has a strong inclination toward the respect of old political systems and the pessimism due to the theory of the latter days of Buddhism, and it is believed that it remonstrates with Emperor Gotoba by preaching an ideal emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this work was complied during the eve of the Jokyu War, it has a strong tendency to respect old political systems, and to remonstrate Emperor Gotoba by preaching the ideal emperor.</e>
<cmt>rewording;does the original English translation correspond to the Japanese text? how does pessimism due to latter days of Buddhism fit into this?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this work was complied during the eve of the Jokyu War, it has a strong tendency to respect old political systems, and to remonstrate Emperor Gotoba by preaching the ideal emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>1994年に和泉書院から注釈書『続古事談注解』が刊行されているが相当に高価。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1994, Izumi Shoin Publishing released the &quot;Shoku Kojidan Chukai&quot; (annotated edition of the Zoku Kojidan), which is very expensive.</e>
<cmt>この書名は「ぞくこじだんちゅうかい」ではなく「しょくこじだんちゅうかい」という読みが正式のようです。http://www.izumipb.co.jp/izumi/modules/bmc/detail.php?book_id=5046&amp;prev=search</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1994, Izumi Shoin Publishing released the &quot;Shoku Kojidan Chukai&quot; (An Annotated Edition of the Zoku Kojidan), which is priced rather expensively.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1994, Izumi Shoin Publishing released &quot;The Shoku Kojidan Chukai&quot; (An Annotated Edition of the Zoku Kojidan), which is priced rather expensively.</e>
<cmt>the &quot;Shoku Kojidan Chukai&quot; を&quot;The Shoku Kojidan Chukai&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>2002年におうふうで播摩光寿ほか編『続古事談』が、2005年に岩波書店で最終回配本「古事談、続古事談　新日本古典文学大系41」が刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2002, the &quot;Zoku Kojidan&quot; (edited by Mitsutoshi HARIMA and so on) was released from Ohfu Co., Ltd., and the last volume of &apos;The Kojidan and the Zoku Kojidan, the New Japanese Classis Literature Systematic Edition 41&apos; was released from Iwanami Shoten Publishers in 2005.</e>
<cmt>「おうふう」のローマ字表記は当該企業のウェブサイト上の表記より採用いたしました。http://www.ohfu.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Zoku Kojidan&quot; (edited by Mitsutoshi HARIMA, etc.) was published by Ohfu Co., Ltd. in 2002, and the last volume of the series &quot;The Kojidan and The Zoku Kojidan, The New Japanese Classic Literature Compendium Edition 41&apos; was published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers in 2005.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Zoku Kojidan&quot; (edited by Mitsutoshi HARIMA, etc.) was published by Ohfu Co., Ltd. in 2002, and the last volume of the series &apos;The Kojidan and The Zoku Kojidan, The New Japanese Classic Literature Compendium Edition 41&apos; was published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers in 2005.</e>
<cmt>the Zoku Kojindan を &quot;The Zoku Kojidan&quot;に修正しました。&quot;The Kojidan and The Zoku Kojidan, を&apos; The Kojidan and The Zoku Kojidan, に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yume149(id:17504), 松茸(id:27535), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>