<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>掛詞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakekotoba (Pivot Word)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakekotoba (Pivot Word)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakekotoba</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>掛詞（かけことば）とは、和歌などにおける修辞用法の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakekotoba (a pivot word) is a rhetorical device in waka poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakekotoba (a pivot word) is a rhetorical device used in waka poetry.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;used&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakekotoba (a pivot word) is a rhetorical device used in waka poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同じ音、あるいは類似した音を有するものに、2つ以上の意味を込めて表現する方法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakekotoba is a trope in which a pivot word that has homophonous or analogously sounding words is expressed in such a way that it has more than two meanings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakekotoba is a figure of speech in which a pivot word that has homophonous or analogous-sounding words is expressed in such a way that it has two or more meanings.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;trope&quot; to &quot;a figure of speech&quot;; &quot;2つ以上&quot;: two or more; more than one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakekotoba is a figure of speech in which a pivot word that has homophonous or analogous-sounding words is expressed in such a way that it has two or more meanings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>古来より用いられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been used from of old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This linguistic device has been used from time immemorial.</e>
<cmt>Extended sentence to reduce fragmentation and fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This linguistic device has been used from time immemorial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>掛詞となる語は、ほとんどの場合平仮名で書かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words used as the pivot word are in most cases written in hiragana (Japanese phonetic alphabet).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words used as a pivot word are almost always written in hiragana (Japanese phonetic alphabet).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words used as a pivot word are almost always written in hiragana (Japanese phonetic alphabet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>「逢坂山」…「逢う」/「逢坂」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Ausaka-yama&apos;: &apos;au&apos; (to meet)/&apos;Ausaka&apos; (Osaka).</e>
<cmt>日英とも句点を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Ausaka-yama&apos;: &apos;au&apos; (to meet)/&apos;Ausaka&apos; (Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ausaka-yama: &apos;au&apos; (to meet)/&apos;Ausaka&apos; (Osaka).</e>
<cmt>文頭の &apos;　は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「まつ」…「松」/「待つ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Matsu&apos;: &apos;matsu&apos; (pine tree)/&apos;matsu&apos; (to wait).</e>
<cmt>日英とも句点を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Matsu&apos;: &apos;matsu&apos; (pine tree)/&apos;matsu&apos; (to wait).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsu: &apos;matsu&apos; (pine tree)/&apos;matsu&apos; (to wait).</e>
<cmt>文頭の &apos;　は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「みお（を）つくし」…「身を尽くし」/「澪標」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Mi(w)otsukushi&apos;: &apos;mi (w)o tsukushi&apos; (to dedicate oneself)/&apos;mi(w)otsukushi&apos; (channel buoys).</e>
<cmt>日英とも句点を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Mi(w)otsukushi&apos;: &apos;mi (w)o tsukushi&apos; (to dedicate oneself)/&apos;mi(w)otsukushi&apos; (channel buoys).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mi(w)otsukushi: &apos;mi (w)o tsukushi&apos; (to dedicate oneself)/&apos;mi(w)otsukushi&apos; (channel buoys).</e>
<cmt>文頭の &apos;　は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>花の色は移りにけりな いたずらに 我が身「よにふるながめ」せし間に…「夜に降る長雨」/「世に経る 眺め」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hana no iro ha utsurinikerina itazurani wagami &apos;yonifuru nagame&apos; seshi mani&quot; (The color of the cherry blossoms has faded; I have vainly passed the time in the world while watching the rain falling): &apos;the long spell of rain in the evening&apos;/&apos;pass the time in the world (while) watching.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the poem, &quot;Hana no iro ha utsurinikerina itazurani wagami &apos;yonifuru nagame&apos; seshi mani,&quot; the &quot;yonifuru nagame&quot; is interpreted twice. One interpretation is &quot;the long spell of rain in the evening&quot; and the other is &quot;pass the time in the world (while) watching,&quot; which lets the poem carry both meanings as: &quot;The color of the cherry blossoms has faded, and I have vainly passed the time in the world while watching the rain falling.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Translation 1 is very well done, but not clear on what is significant, so I wrote it out for better clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the poem, &quot;Hana no iro ha utsurinikerina itazurani wagami &apos;yonifuru nagame&apos; seshi mani,&quot; the &quot;yonifuru nagame&quot; is interpreted twice. One interpretation is &quot;the long spell of rain in the evening&quot; and the other is &quot;pass the time in the world (while) watching,&quot; which lets the poem carry both meanings as: &quot;The color of the cherry blossoms has faded, and I have vainly passed the time in the world while watching the rain falling.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大江山「いくののみち」の遠ければ まだ「ふみもみず」天の橋立…「行く野の道」/「朝来市（地名）の道」、「文（手紙）も見ず」/「踏みもみず（踏破もせず）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Oeyama &apos;ikunonomichi&apos; no tookereba mada &apos;fumimomizu&apos; ama no hashidate&quot; (Mt. Oe and the road that goes to Ikuno are far away; so I have neither seen the letter, nor trod there, from Amanohashidate): &apos;iku no no michi&apos; (the road that goes through a field)/&apos;Ikuno no michi&apos; (the road that goes to Ikuno which is a place name, the present Asago City); &apos;fumi (letter) mo mizu&apos; (have seen no letter)/&apos;fumimomizu (have not trod).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes more than one kakekotoba is employed in a poem, such as, &quot;Oeyama &apos;ikunonomichi&apos; no tookereba mada &apos;fumimomizu&apos; ama no hashidate,&apos; where &quot;ikunonomichi&quot; and &quot;fumimomizu&quot; both have double meanings. In this case, &quot;ikunonomichi&quot; can mean &quot;the road that goes through a field&quot; or &quot;the road leading to Ikuno&quot; (Ikuno is a place name for the current Asago City). Additionally, &quot;fumimomizu&quot; can mean &quot;have seen no letter&quot; or &quot;have not travelled by foot.&quot; Putting them all together, the poem can be interpreted as: &quot;Mt. Oe and the road that leads to Ikuno through the field are far away, so I have neither seen a letter, nor travelled there from Amanohashidate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>translation 1 lacks an explanation for what is significant, so I wrote it out for better clarity; added the second meaning of &quot;fumimomizu&quot; &quot;through the field&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes more than one kakekotoba is employed in a poem, such as, &quot;Oeyama &apos;ikunonomichi&apos; no tookereba mada &apos;fumimomizu&apos; ama no hashidate,&apos; where &quot;ikunonomichi&quot; and &quot;fumimomizu&quot; both have double meanings. In this case, &quot;ikunonomichi&quot; can mean &quot;the road that goes through a field&quot; or &quot;the road leading to Ikuno&quot; (Ikuno is a place name for the current Asago City). Additionally, &quot;fumimomizu&quot; can mean &quot;have seen no letter&quot; or &quot;have not traveled by foot.&quot; Putting them all together, the poem can be interpreted as: &quot;Mt. Oe and the road that leads to Ikuno through the field are far away, so I have neither seen a letter, nor traveled there to Amanohashidate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>To Amanohashidate に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>英語における掛詞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakekotoba in English</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakekotoba in English</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakekotoba in English</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本語における掛詞と同じ手法を用いた修辞は、英語においてはほとんど見られない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rhetorical device with the Japanese kakekotoba is hardly found in English.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rhetorical device with the Japanese kakekotoba is rarely found in English.</e>
<cmt>&quot;hardly&quot;→&quot;rarely&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rhetorical device with the Japanese kakekotoba is rarely found in English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>但し、英語においても、以下のような同音もしくは類似音を利用した技巧が使われることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As is shown below, however, figures of speech that use homophones or similar sounds are sometimes employed in English.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As is shown below, however, figures of speech that use homophones or similar sounds are sometimes employed in English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As is shown below, however, figures of speech that use homophones or similar sounds are sometimes employed in English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>Spring forward, fall backward.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spring forward, fall backward. In adjusting a clock for the daylight saving time, one puts it forward in spring and puts it backward in fall; one springs forward and falls backward.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spring forward, fall backward. In adjusting a clock for daylight saving time, time is put forward in the spring and backward in the fall, so one &quot;springs forward&quot; and &quot;falls backward.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spring forward, fall backward:</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>夏時間の調整、春には時計の針を進める、秋には戻す / 前に飛び出す、後ろに倒れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In adjusting a clock for daylight saving time, time is put forward in the spring and backward in the fall, so one &quot;springs forward&quot; and &quot;falls backward.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文を分けたのに応じて、英文も分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>Two is the oddest prime number, since it is the only even one.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two is the oddest prime number, since it is the only even one. This is a joke playing on the homophony of odd (as in the odd number as opposed to the even number) and odd (strange).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another example is: &quot;Two is the oddest prime number, since it is the only even one.&quot; This is a joke playing on the homophony of &quot;odd&quot; as an odd number as opposed to an even number, and &quot;odd&quot; as in &quot;strange.&quot;</e>
<cmt>replaced parenthesis with quotation marks and fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two is the oddest prime number, since it is the only even one:</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>偶数(even)奇数(odd)と奇妙(odd)を掛けたジョーク。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a joke playing on the homophony of odd (as in the odd number as opposed to the even number) and odd (strange).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a joke playing on the homophony of odd (as in the odd number as opposed to the even number) and odd (strange).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a joke playing on the homophony of &quot;odd&quot; as an odd number as opposed to an even number, and &quot;odd&quot; as in &quot;strange.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文を分けたのに応じて、英文も分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>最後のoneは代名詞で幾多の素数の中の一つのもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word, &quot;one&quot; that appears at the end is a pronoun referring to a prime number among many.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the word &quot;one&quot; that appears at the end is a pronoun referring to a prime number.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Furthermore&quot; to help indicate that the explanation is continuing from the previous sentence; eliminated &quot;among many&quot; as it was unecessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the word &quot;one&quot; that appears at the end is a pronoun referring to a prime number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>（意味は：数字の2は最も奇妙(odd/数学的には奇数を意味する単語)な素数である、何故ならば唯一の偶数の素数(代名詞one）であるから。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The joke means that: the number &quot;2&quot; is the oddest (meaning &apos;strangest&apos; as well as a mathematical odd number) prime number, because it is the only even prime number (which is indicated by &quot;one&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The meaning of the joke is that the prime number &quot;two&quot; is the oddest, meaning &quot;strangest&quot; as well as a mathematical &quot;odd&quot; number because it is the only even prime number).</e>
<cmt>shortened explanation slightly as some of it was uneeded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The meaning of the joke is that the prime number &quot;two&quot; is the oddest, meaning &quot;strangest&quot; as well as a mathematical &quot;odd&quot; number because it is the only even prime number).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>（最初に2、最後にoneを置くのも洒落の類とみなせば二重の掛詞となる。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It starts with 2 and ends with &quot;one.&quot; If this can be taken as a kind of pun, it follows that it contains double kakekotoba).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The sentence starts with &quot;two&quot; and ends with &quot;one.&quot; Taking this as a pun, it follows that it contains a double kakekotoba).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The sentence starts with &quot;two&quot; and ends with &quot;one&quot;; taking this as a pun, it follows that it contains a double kakekotoba).</e>
<cmt>一つの文章にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>詩において、節の最後を、語尾が同音節である単語(fallとhallなど)で揃える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In poetry stanzas often end with words whose last syllables are the same (e.g., fall and hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In poetry, stanzas often end with words that have the same final syllables (e.g. fall and hall).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In poetry, stanzas often end with words that have the same final syllables (e.g. fall and hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>(押韻)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Rhyme)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Rhyme)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Rhyme)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>よく知られている言葉を、綴りが似た言葉に置き換える言葉遊び。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known words are replaced by words whose spellings are similar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known words are replaced by word that have similar spellings.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known words are replaced by word that have similar spellings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>不思議の国のアリスはこの技法を多用していることで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alice&apos;s Adventures in Wonderland is famously replete with such a literary technique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alice&apos;s Adventures in Wonderland is famously replete with such literary techniques.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alice&apos;s Adventures in Wonderland is famously replete with such literary techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>シェークスピアの戯曲やマザーグースなどの著名な一節を引用して、別の意味を連想させる手法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Below is a technique in which a famous passage from Shakespeare&apos;s dramas or the Mother Goose is cited to associate it with another meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Below is a technique in which a famous passage from Shakespeare&apos;s dramas and &quot;Mother Goose&quot; is cited to suggest a separate meaning.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Below is a technique in which a famous passage from Shakespeare&apos;s dramas and &quot;Mother Goose&quot; is cited to suggest a separate meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>例えば、アメリカ映画のオール・ザ・キングスメンについて、タイトルを直訳すると「王の全ての家来」であるが、これはマザーグースにおけるハンプティ・ダンプティからの引用であり、権力者の悲劇的な結末をタイトルから連想させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, All the King&apos;s Men, which is the title of an American film, literally means &apos;all the subjects of the king.&apos; This is a citation from Humpty Dumpty in the Mother Goose, by way of which the title suggests the tragic end of a powerful man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the American film title &quot;All the King&apos;s Men,&quot; which literally means &quot;all the subjects of the king,&quot; is a citation from Humpty Dumpty through which the title suggests the tragic end of a powerful man.</e>
<cmt>connected the two sentences to work as one; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the American film title &quot;All the King&apos;s Men,&quot; which literally means &quot;all the subjects of the king,&quot; is a citation from Humpty Dumpty through which the title suggests the tragic end of a powerful man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、アガサ・クリスティーの推理小説も、マザーグースからの引用が多いことで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agatha Christie&apos;s detective novels are renowned for many citations from the Mother Goose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agatha Christie&apos;s detective novels are renowned for many citations from &quot;Mother Goose.&quot;</e>
<cmt>added quotation marks for Mother Goose and fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agatha Christie&apos;s detective novels are renowned for many citations from &quot;Mother Goose.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、日本語に翻訳されると、原文におけるこれらの技法が十分に伝わらないことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These techniques are sometimes not fully captured in Japanese translations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These techniques are sometimes not fully captured in Japanese translations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These techniques are sometimes not fully captured in Japanese translations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 5816K(id:102574), HOTUMA(id:112649), Namazu-tron(id:135120), PaPaPaPa(id:87231), NORN(id:52924), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>