<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>空蝉（源氏物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utsusemi (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utsusemi (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utsusemi (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>空蝉（うつせみ）とは、カメムシ目の昆虫であるセミの羽化時の脱皮殻のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utsusemi is the cast-off skin of a cicada (order: Pentatomidae), when it hatches out.</e>
<cmt>2つに分かれていたセルを統合</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utsusemi is the cast-off skin of a cicada (order: Pentatomidae), when it hatches.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utsusemi is the cast-off skin of a cicada (order: Pentatomidae), when it hatches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>『源氏物語』五十四帖の巻の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第3帖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the third chapter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the third chapter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the third chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>『源氏物語』に登場する女性の一人に対する通称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also a nickname for the woman who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also a nickname for the woman who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also a nickname for the woman who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>十代の頃の光源氏が知り合い、影響を受けた女性たちの一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is one of the women whom Hikaru Genji gets to know in his teens and is influenced by.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is one of the women whom Hikaru Genji gets to know while in his teens and is influenced by.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is one of the women whom Hikaru Genji gets to know while in his teens and is influenced by.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>名前の由来は、求愛に対して一枚の着物を残し逃げ去ったことを、源氏がセミの抜け殻によそえて送った和歌から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name came from the waka poem which Genji sends her with a cicada shell because she made away from his courtship leaving a kimono (Japanese traditional clothing) behind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name came from a waka poem that Genji sends her with a cicada shell because she left his courtship leaving a kimono (Japanese traditional clothing) behind.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name came from a waka poem that Genji sends her with a cicada shell because she left his courtship leaving a kimono (Japanese traditional clothing) behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>主だった登場は「帚木」「空蝉」「関屋」の3巻のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly she appears in the three chapters of &apos;Hahakigi&apos; (The Broom Tree), &apos;Utsusemi,&apos; and Sekiya&apos; (The Gatehouse).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainly she appeared in the three chapters of &apos;Hahakigi&apos; (The Broom Tree), &apos;Utsusemi,&apos; and Sekiya&apos; (The Gatehouse).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainly she appeared in the three chapters of &apos;Hahakigi&apos; (The Broom Tree), &apos;Utsusemi,&apos; and &apos;Sekiya&apos; (The Gatehouse).</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>空蝉を忘れられない源氏は、彼女のつれないあしらいにも却って思いが募り、再び紀伊守邸へ忍んで行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genji, who cannot forget Utsusemi, loves her more than ever in spite of her indifferent attitude, and pays a secret visit to the residence of Kii no kami (Governor of Kii Province) again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji, who cannot forget Utsusemi, loves her more than ever in spite of her indifferent attitude, and pays a secret visit to the residence of Kii no kami (Governor of Kii Province) again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji, who cannot forget Utsusemi, loves her more than ever in spite of her indifferent attitude, and pays a secret visit to the residence of Kii no kami (Governor of Kii Province) again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そこで継娘（軒端荻）と碁を打ち合う空蝉の姿を覗き見し、決して美女ではないもののたしなみ深い空蝉をやはり魅力的だと改めて心惹かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He catches a glimpse of Utsusemi having a game of go with her stepdaughter, Nokiba no Ogi, and he considers that she is not necessarily beautiful but very temperate, being attracted by her again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He catches a glimpse of Utsusemi playing a game of go with her stepdaughter, Nokiba no Ogi, and he considers that she is not necessarily beautiful, but very temperate, and he is attracted to her again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He catches a glimpse of Utsusemi playing a game of go with her stepdaughter, Nokiba no Ogi, and he considers that she is not necessarily beautiful, but very temperate, and he is attracted to her again.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし源氏の訪れを察した空蝉は薄衣一枚を脱ぎ捨てて逃げ去ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Utsusemi, who notices Genji&apos;s visit, escapes from him leaving her thin robes behind.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Utsusemi, who notices Genji&apos;s visit, escapes from him leaving her thin robes behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Utsusemi, who notices Genji&apos;s visit, escapes from him leaving her thin robes behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>心ならずも後に残された軒端荻と契った源氏はその薄衣を代わりに持ち帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genji unwillingly has a relationship with Nokiba no Ogi, who is left behind, and brings her thin robes home with him instead.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji unwillingly has a relationship with Nokiba no Ogi, who is left behind, and brings her thin robes home with him instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji unwillingly has a relationship with Nokiba no Ogi, who is left behind, and brings her thin robes home with him instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>源氏は女の抜け殻のような衣にことよせて空蝉へ歌を送り、空蝉も源氏の愛を受けられない己の境遇のつたなさを密かに嘆いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sends her a poem on the robes which looks like a cast-off skin of a woman, while Utsusemi secretly laments her insecure circumstances that she cannot accept Genji&apos;s love.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sends her a poem about the robes which looks like a cast-off skin of a woman, while Utsusemi secretly laments her insecure circumstances that she cannot accept Genji&apos;s love.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sends her a poem about the robes which looks like a cast-off skin of a woman, while Utsusemi secretly laments her insecure circumstances that she cannot accept Genji&apos;s love.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>境遇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Circumstances</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>中級貴族の娘として生まれ育ち、宮仕えを希望したこともあったが、伊予の介（伊予国（現在の愛媛県）の国守の次官）を務める男の元に年の離れた後妻として嫁いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born and brought up as a daughter of the middle-class court noble, and hoped to serve in the Imperial Court once, but she gets married to Iyo no suke (assistant governor of Iyo Province (the present Aichi Prefecture)), who is much older than she.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born and brought up as the daughter of a middle-class court noble, and hoped to serve in the Imperial Court once, but she gets married to Iyo no suke (assistant governor of Iyo Province - the present Aichi Prefecture), who is much older than she.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born and brought up as the daughter of a middle-class court noble, and hoped to serve in the Imperial Court once, but she gets married to Iyo no suke (assistant governor of Iyo Province - the present Aichi Prefecture) as his second wife, who is much older than she.</e>
<cmt>as his second wife補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>当時、女性の地位は父か夫の位に順ずるので、彼女は貴族としては中級の身分であり、上流中の上流の源氏とは身分がつりあわなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status of woman in those days was up to the status of her father or husband, and she is a middle-class court noble, so there is a difference in degree between Genji, who belongs to the highest class, and her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status of woman in those days was dependent upon the status of her father or husband, and she was a middle-class court noble, so there was a difference in degree between Genji, who belongs to the highest class, and her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of woman in those days was dependent upon the status of her father or husband, and she was a middle-class court noble, so there was a difference in degree between Genji, who belongs to the highest class, and her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>作中に伊予介の娘（軒端荻）が登場するが、前妻の娘であった彼女と空蝉はほとんど同年輩と言う、かなりの年の差結婚である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gets married to the man who is much older than she, and his daughter by a previous marriage (Nokiba no Ogi) in the work is almost as old as Utsusemi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gets married to a man who is much older than her, and his daughter by a previous marriage (Nokiba no Ogi) is almost as old as Utsusemi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gets married to a man who is much older than her, and his daughter by a previous marriage (Nokiba no Ogi) is almost as old as Utsusemi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>夫との間に子供は出来なかったようで、年の離れた幼い弟（小君）を一人手元に置いて我が子のように養育していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They do not have a child, so she keeps her little brother (Kogimi), who is much younger than she, and brings up him as if he were her own son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They do not have any children, so she keeps her little brother (Kogimi), who is much younger than her, and brings him up as if he were her own son.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They do not have any children, so she keeps her little brother (Kogimi), who is much younger than her, and brings him up as if he were her own son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この子は後に源氏に仕えて、夫との死別の後はその縁と言う触れ込みで源氏に引き取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The child later serves Genji, and after her husband dies, Genji takes in him publicly stating that the child has worked for him, so he has responsibility..</e>
<cmt>「その縁」は、「その子どもが源氏に仕えてきたのだから、源氏には引き取る責任がある」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The child later serves Genji, and after her husband dies, Genji takes him in publicly stating that the child has worked for him, so he has responsibility..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The child later serves Genji, and after her husband dies, Genji takes him in publicly stating that the child has worked for him, so he has responsibility.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>空蝉は後ろ盾となる父を早くに亡くし、後妻を探していた伊予の介の元に妻として引き取られて、地味で堅実な生活を送っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Utsusemi was little, she lost her father who was supposed to be her supporter, so she was taken to wife by Iyo no suke, who was looking for the second wife, and has led a quiet and steady life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Utsusemi was little, she lost her father who was supposed to be her supporter, so she was taken to wife by Iyo no suke, who was looking for a second wife, and she led a quiet and stable life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Utsusemi was little, she lost her father who was supposed to be her supporter, so she was taken to wife by Iyo no suke, who was looking for a second wife, and she led a quiet and stable life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>あるとき、彼女の噂を聞いていたことから方違先で興味本位に忍んできた源氏と情を通じてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, she has a relationship with Genji, who has heard a rumor about her and sneaks into her residence out of curiosity when he is in katatagae (to stay the night in a place situated at another point of the compass when one&apos;s destination from home lies in an ill-starred direction).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, she has a relationship with Genji, who has heard a rumor about her and he sneaks into her residence out of curiosity when he is in katatagae (to stay the night in a place situated at another point on the compass when one&apos;s destination from home lies in an ill-starred direction).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, she has a relationship with Genji, who has heard a rumor about her and he sneaks into her residence out of curiosity when he is in katatagae (to stay the night in a place situated at another point on the compass when one&apos;s destination from home lies in an ill-starred direction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>魅力的な源氏の求愛に惹かれ悩みながらも、身分が釣り合わない立場であることを理解していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is attracted by Genji&apos;s charm and his courtship, but at the same time she is afflicted because she understands that they belong to the different classes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is attracted to Genji&apos;s charm and his courtship, but at the same time she is afflicted because she understands that they belong to different classes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is attracted to Genji&apos;s charm and his courtship, but at the same time she is afflicted because she understands that they belong to different classes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>逢瀬の後はいくら掻き口説かれても靡こうとはせず、その後夫に従って京を離れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So after they sleep together, she will not give her heart to him, and she leaves the capital following her husband.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So even after they sleep together, she did not give her heart to him, and she leaves the capital following her husband.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So even after they sleep together, she did not give her heart to him, and she leaves the capital following her husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>皮肉にも、驕慢な貴公子であった源氏にとって、空蝉の拒絶が彼女を忘れられない存在にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironically, it is her refusal that makes her an unforgettable figure for Genji, who is a proud-hearted noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironically, it is her rejection that makes her an unforgettable figure for Genji, who is a proud-hearted noble.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironically, it is her rejection that makes her an unforgettable figure for Genji, who is a proud-hearted noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>源氏は彼女の弟を手元に引き取り、後には尼となった彼女を二条東院に迎えて住まわせることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genji takes in her younger brother, and later invites Utsusemi, who has become a nun, to the Nijohigashi no In residence in order to have her live there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji takes in her younger brother, and later invites Utsusemi, who has become a nun, to the Nijohigashi no In residence in order to have her live there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji takes in her younger brother, and later invites Utsusemi, who has become a nun, to the Nijohigashi no In residence in order to have her live there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>控えめで、容貌も非常に地味な女性であったが、小柄で立ち振る舞いが水際立っており趣味も良かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though she is modest and looks plain, she is small, so her behavior stands out splendidly and she has good taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though she is modest and looks plain, she is small, so her behavior stands out splendidly and she has good taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though she is modest and looks plain, she is small, so her behavior stands out splendidly and she has good taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>求愛に対しても、悩み迷いながらも最後まで品良く矜持を守り通し、貴公子である源氏を感心させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even when Genji makes advances to her, she maintains her honor gracefully to the last though she is afflicted, which makes Genji, a young noble, deeply impressed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even when Genji makes an advance to her, she maintains her honor gracefully to the last though she is afflicted, which makes Genji, a young noble, deeply impressed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even when Genji makes an advance to her, she maintains her honor gracefully to the last though she is afflicted, which makes Genji, a young noble, deeply impressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>彼女のモデルに関しては、境遇や身分が似ているため、作者である紫式部自身がモデルではないかと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that her model would be the author, Murasaki Shikibu, because of resemblances to her circumstances and status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that her model would be the author, Murasaki Shikibu, because of the resemblance to her circumstances and status.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that her model would be the author, Murasaki Shikibu, because of the resemblance to her circumstances and status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), アレシンロ(id:170344), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Manop(id:78964), พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Masyu(id:31065), Nlkl(id:88201), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), Tropopause(id:95729), Ｋｓ(id:15319), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>