<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>顕註密勘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenchumikkan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenchumikkan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenchumikkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>顕註密勘（けんちゅうみっかん）とは、鎌倉時代前期に藤原定家によって書かれた『古今和歌集』の注釈書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kenchumikkan&quot; is a book written by Teika FUJIWARA in the early Kamakura Period, which is a collection of Commentaries on Kokin Wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kenchumikkan&quot; is a book written by Teika FUJIWARA in the early Kamakura Period, which is a collection of commentaries on Kokin Wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kenchumikkan&quot; is a book written by FUJIWARA no Teika in the early Kamakura Period, which is a collection of commentaries on &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>Teika FUJIWARA をFUJIWARA no Teika に修正しました。Kokin Wakashu にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>全3巻8冊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book consists of three series in eight volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book consists of three series in eight volumes.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book consists of three series in eight volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古今秘註抄（こきんひちゅうしょう）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book is also called as &quot;Kokinhichusho&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book is also called &quot;Kokinhichusho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book is also called &quot;Kokinhichusho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>承久3年3月21日 (旧暦)（1221年4月15日）の日付が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book has a date of March 21, 1221(old lunar calendar) (April 15, 1221 of solar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book has a date of March 21, 1221(old lunar calendar) (April 15, 1221 of the solar calendar).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book has a date of April 24, 1221.</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（その他　2010/02/19）の指示に従い、March 21, 1221(old lunar calendar) (April 15, 1221 of the solar calendar) をApril 24, 1221 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>元は六条藤家の顕昭によって書かれた『古今和歌集』の用語に対する注釈書を対立関係にあった御子左家の藤原定家が秘かに見る機会を得て春歌上巻の部分を写し、これに自説（藤原俊成以来の御子左家の歌道家学）を「密勘」として書き加えた物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book was written by Teika FUJIWARA of the Mikohidari family who had had a chance to secretly read commentaries on Kokin Wakashu originally made by Kensho FUJIWARA of the rival Rokujo Toke (Rokujo Fujiwara family), transcribed the commentaries in its first volume of Spring Poetry part and added his own reviews (based on the Mikohidari family&apos;s poetry school established by FUJIWARA no Toshinari) as &quot;mikkan&quot; (personal views), to thereby complete his own version.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book was written by Teika FUJIWARA of the Mikohidari family who had had a chance to secretly read commentaries on Kokin Wakashu originally made by Kensho FUJIWARA of the rival Rokujo Toke (Rokujo Fujiwara family), who transcribed the commentaries in its first volume of the Spring Poetry part and added his own reviews (based on the Mikohidari family&apos;s poetry school established by FUJIWARA no Toshinari) as &quot;mikkan&quot; (personal views), to thereby complete his own version.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book was written by FUJIWARA no Teika of the Mikohidari family who had had a chance to secretly read commentaries on &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; originally made by Kensho of the rival Rokujo Toke (Rokujo Fujiwara family), who transcribed the commentaries in its first volume of the Spring Poetry part and added his own reviews (based on the Mikohidari family&apos;s poetry school established by FUJIWARA no Toshinari) as &apos;mikkan&apos; (personal views), to thereby complete his own version.</e>
<cmt>原文「として書き加えた者である」を「として書き加えた物である」に修正しました。Teika FUJIWARA をFUJIWARA no Teika に修正しました。Kokin Wakashu にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。Kensho FUJIWARA の FUJIWARA を削除しました。&quot;mikkan&quot; をシングルクォーテーションに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>顕昭と定家の説に大きな違いはないものの、考証主義的な六条藤家と芸術的解釈の御子左家の観点の違いが反映された部分も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there is no significant difference between Kensho&apos;s views and Teika&apos;s, some parts reflect differences in the bases of viewpoints between the Rokujo Toke who weighed much in the historical authenticity and the Mikohidari family who weighed much in the artistic interpretation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is no significant difference between Kensho&apos;s views and Teika&apos;s, some parts reflect differences in the bases of viewpoints between the Rokujo Toke who favored the historical authenticity and the Mikohidari family who favored the artistic interpretation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is no significant difference between Kensho&apos;s views and Teika&apos;s, some parts reflect differences in the bases of viewpoints between the Rokujo Toke who favored the historical authenticity and the Mikohidari family who favored the artistic interpretation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>定家は跋に「返々も窓のほかに出され侍まじ」と記して子孫に対してこの書の門外不出を求めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teika left a note in the end of the book, &quot;Make sure not to take this book outside the window&quot; which instructed his posterity never to allow the book to be taken out of the house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teika left a note in the end of the book, &quot;Make sure not to take this book outside the window&quot; which instructed his future generations never to allow the book to be taken out of the house.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teika left a note in the end of the book, &apos;Make sure not to take this book outside the window&apos; which instructed his future generations never to allow the book to be taken out of the house.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテーションに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>六条藤家と御子左家の学説の違いが示された書として流布され、江戸時代には公刊されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book, however, came to go about as a book showing differences between the theories of the Rokujo Toke and the Mikohidari family and then it was publicly printed in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book, however, became a book showing the differences between the theories of the Rokujo Toke and the Mikohidari family and then it was publicly printed in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book, however, became a book showing the differences between the theories of the Rokujo Toke and the Mikohidari family and then it was publicly printed in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>