<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浦島太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima Taro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urashima Taro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urashima Taro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浦島太郎（うらしまたろう）は、日本各地にある龍宮伝説の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima Taro is one of the Ryugu (Dragon Palace) legend which is spread all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urashima Taro is one of the Ryugu (Dragon Palace) legends which appear all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urashima Taro is one of the Ryugu (Dragon Palace) legends which appear all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、日本の説話（おとぎばなし）の一つで、その主人公の名前でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also one of the Japanese setsuwa (anecdotes), and the name of the main character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also a Japanese setsuwa (folk tale), and the name of the main character within it.</e>
<cmt>The word &apos;anecdote&apos; suggests a small aside or tale from personal experience.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also a Japanese setsuwa (folk tale), and the name of the main character within it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>現在一般的に流通しているストーリーはおおむね以下のようなものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plot which is widely known today is mainly as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The outline of the plot, which is widely known in Japan today, is as follows.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The outline of the plot, which is widely known in Japan today, is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>漁師の浦島太郎は、子どもがカメをいじめているところに遭遇する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima Taro, a fisherman, happened to see children treating a turtle cruelly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urashima Taro, a fisherman, happened to see children treating a turtle cruelly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urashima Taro, a fisherman, happened to see children treating a turtle cruelly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>太郎が亀を助けると、亀は礼として太郎を竜宮城に連れて行く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Taro saved the turtle, it took him to the Ryugu-jo castle as a token of it&apos;s thanks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Taro saved the turtle, it took him to Ryugu-jo Castle as a token of it&apos;s gratitude.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Taro saved the turtle, it took him to Ryugu-jo Castle as a token of it&apos;s gratitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>竜宮城では乙姫（一説には東海竜王の娘：竜）が太郎を歓待する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Ryugu-jo castle, Otohime (according to one theory, a daughter of Tokai Ryuo (Dragon King of the East): dragon) welcomed Taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Ryugu-jo Castle, the dragon Otohime (according to one theory, a daughter of Tokai Ryuo, Dragon King of the East) welcomed Taro.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Ryugu-jo Castle, the dragon Otohime (according to one theory, a daughter dragon of Tokai Ryuo, Dragon King of the East) welcomed Taro.</e>
<cmt>竜を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しばらくして太郎が帰る意思を伝えると、乙姫は「決して開けてはならない」としつつ玉手箱を渡す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, Taro told her that he would go home, then Otohime gave him a casket, saying, &apos;Don&apos;t ever open this.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, Taro told her that he would go home, at which point Otohime gave him a casket, saying &apos;Don&apos;t ever open this&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, Taro told her that he would go home, at which point Otohime gave him a casket, saying &apos;Don&apos;t ever open this.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>太郎が亀に連れられ浜に帰ると、太郎が知っている人は誰もいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Taro came back to the beach with the turtle, there was nobody whom Taro knew.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Taro arrived back at the beach with the turtle, there was nobody whom Taro knew.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Taro arrived back at the beach with the turtle, there was nobody whom Taro knew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>太郎が玉手箱を開けると、中から煙が発生し、煙を浴びた太郎は老人の姿に変化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taro opened the casket, which gave off smoke from inside, and Taro, who was wrapped in smoke, changed into an old man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taro then opened the casket, and the smoke which billowed out began to envelop him, turning him into an old man.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taro then opened the casket, and the smoke which billowed out began to envelop him, turning him into an old man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>浦島太郎が竜宮城で過ごした日々は数日だったが、地上では700年が経っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The days which Urashima Taro spent in Ryugu-jo castle were only a few days, but in reality, 700 years had passed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urashima Taro had spent only a few days in Ryugu-jo Castle, but in that time 700 years had passed.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urashima Taro had spent only a few days in Ryugu-jo Castle, but in that time 700 years had passed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、浦島太郎のその後については文献や地方によって諸説あり、定説と呼ぶべきものはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is nothing to be called a widely accepted legend, because each region has different literature on Urashima Taro&apos;s later days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no widely accepted version of the legend because in each region the story continues differently.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural as it sounds like &apos;chokuyaku&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no widely accepted version of the legend because in each region the story continues differently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>バリエーション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Variation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Variations</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>『日本書紀』による話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story collected in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story collected in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story collected in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>現存文献で浦島子の登場する最古の事例であり『日本書紀』「雄略天皇二477年条」で、蓬莱山へ行ったという発端部分だけが記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the oldest extant literature in which Urashima appears, and &apos;An article of 477, during the reign of Emperor Yuryaku&apos; in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; contains only the beginning of the story in which Urashima went to Mt. Horai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the oldest extant piece of literature in which Urashima appears, and &apos;Article 477 during the reign of Emperor Yuryaku&apos; in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; contains only the beginning of the story, in which Urashima went to Mt. Horai.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the oldest extant piece of literature in which Urashima appears, and &apos;Article 477 during the reign of Emperor Yuryaku&apos; in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; contains only the beginning of the story, in which Urashima went to Mt. Horai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その内容は表現も構成も神仙思想を元に古代中国で流行した神仙伝奇小説に似ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contents is based on Taoist immortality thought both in expression and structure, and it resembles Taoism fantastic novel which was widely known in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The content is based on concepts of Taoist immortality both in expressions used and the structure of the piece, and it resembles Taoist fantastic novels which were widely known in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The content is based on concepts of Taoist immortality both in expressions used and the structure of the piece, and it resembles Taoist fantastic novels which were widely known in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この物語が不老不死への願望から生じた作品だったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that this story was created from a yearning for eternal youth and immortality.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that this story was created out of a yearning for eternal youth and immortality.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that this story was created out of a yearning for eternal youth and immortality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>『丹後国風土記』にある話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story collected in &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki&quot; (the records of Tango Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story collected in &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of Tango Province)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story collected in &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (Records of Tango Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>『丹後国風土記』（現在は逸文のみが残存）にある「筒川嶼子 水江浦嶼子」が原型とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that &apos;Shimako TSUTSUKAWA and Mizunoe no ura no Shimako&apos; in &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki&quot; (the records of Tango Province) (the text is partly survived now) was a model.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the model of the story in the Records of Tango Province (of which only part survives today) was Shimako TSUTSUKAWA and Mizunoe no ura no Shimako.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the model of the story in the Records of Tango Province (of which only part survives today) was Shimako TSUTSUKAWA and Mizunoe no ura no Shimako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ほぼ同時代に書かれた『日本書紀』『万葉集』にも記述が見られるが、『丹後国風土記』逸文が内容的に一番詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves), which were written in the almost same time, contained the story, but the surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki&quot; gives us more detailed contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves), written around the same time, contain the story, but the surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki&quot; provides more detail.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves), written around the same time, contain the story, but the surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki&quot; provides more detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>万葉集巻九による話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story collected in the ninth volume of Manyoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story collected in the ninth volume of Manyoshu</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story collected in the ninth volume of Manyoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>『万葉集』巻九の高橋虫麻呂作の長歌（歌番号1740）に「詠水江浦嶋子一首」として、浦島太郎の原型というべき以下の内容が歌われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the ninth volume of &quot;Manyoshu,&quot; a long poem composed by TAKAHASHI no Mushimaro (poem No. 1740) express the following contents which should be called a prototype of Urashima Taro as &apos;a poem concerning Mizunoe no Ura Shimako.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ninth volume of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; a long poem composed by TAKAHASHI no Mushimaro (poem 1740, &apos;a poem concerning Mizunoe no Ura Shimako&apos;) expresses the following, and which could be called a precursor of Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ninth volume of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; a long poem composed by TAKAHASHI no Mushimaro (poem 1740, &apos;a poem concerning Mizunoe no Ura Shimako&apos;) expresses the following, and which could be called a precursor of Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>「浦島太郎」という名前は中世から登場し、それ以前は水江浦嶼子を略して「浦島子」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; could be seen since the Medieval times, and before that the character was called &apos;Ura Shimako,&apos; which was a shortened name for Mizunoe no ura no Shimako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; appeared in Medieval times, but before that the character was called &apos;Ura Shimako&apos;, which was a shortened version of Mizunoe no ura no Shimako.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; appeared in Medieval times, but before that the character was called &apos;Ura Shimako,&apos; which was a shortened version of Mizunoe no ura no Shimako.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>『御伽草子』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Otogi zoshi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Otogi zoshi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Otogi zoshi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>「浦島太郎」として現在伝わる話の型が定まったのは、室町時代に成立した短編物語『御伽草子』による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A short story in &quot;Otogi zoshi,&quot; which was completed in the Muromachi period, fixed the present text of &apos;Urashima Taro.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The short story in &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot;, completed in the Muromachi Period, established the present text of &apos;Urashima Taro&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The short story in &quot;Otogi zoshi,&quot; completed in the Muromachi Period, established the present text of &apos;Urashima Taro.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ,ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後は良く知られた昔話として様々な媒体で流通することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the story came to be familiar to everybody in various media as a well known old tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, the story came to be widely known in Japan through various media as a traditional tale.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, the story came to be widely known in Japan through various media as a traditional tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>亀の恩返し（報恩）と言うモチーフを取るようになったのも『御伽草子』以降のことで、乙姫、竜宮城、玉手箱が登場するのも中世であり、『御伽草子』の出現は浦島物語にとって大きな変換点であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A motif of turtle&apos;s returning of a favor (gratitude) was fixed after &quot;Otogi zoshi,&quot; and moreover, the characters and items of Otohime, Ryugu-jo castle, and tamatebako (Urashima&apos;s casket) appeared in the Medieval period, therefore an appearance of &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; was a big change to the tale of Urashima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The motif of the turtle returning the favor in gratitude was established after &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot;, and moreover, Otohime, Ryugu-jo Castle, and the tamatebako (Urashima&apos;s casket) appeared in the Medieval period, and so the appearance of &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; marked a considerable change in the tale of Urashima.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The motif of the turtle returning the favor in gratitude was established after &quot;Otogi zosh,i&quot; and moreover, Otohime, Ryugu-jo Castle, and the tamatebako (Urashima&apos;s casket) appeared in the Medieval period, and so the appearance of &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; marked a considerable change in the tale of Urashima.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>『御伽草子』では龍宮は海中ではなく、島か大陸にあるように書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Otogi zoshi,&quot; Ryugu was described not as somewhere in the sea but on an island or a continent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; Ryugu was described not as somewhere in the sea but on an island or continent.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; Ryugu was described not as somewhere in the sea but on an island or continent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>春の庭、夏の庭、秋の庭、冬の庭の話はメインストーリーの付け足し程度に書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gardens of spring, summer, autumn, and winter were just subplots, which were added to the main plot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elements such as the spring, summer, autumn, and winter gardens were subplots, and were added to the main plot.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elements such as the spring, summer, autumn, and winter gardens were subplots, and were added to the main plot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>「鶴亀」バージョン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A variation of &apos;crane and tortoise&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;crane and tortoise&apos; variation</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;crane and tortoise&apos; variation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>室町以降の『御伽草子』系の一部に浦島説話の変形版があり、以下のように結末を結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; which was created after the Muromachi period contained a variation of Urashima story, and its ending is as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A part of &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; created after the Muromachi Period contained a variation of the Urashima story, and its ending is as follows.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A part of &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; created after the Muromachi Period contained a variation of the Urashima story, and its ending is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>一説に、ここから「亀は万年の齢を経、鶴は千代をや重ぬらん」と謡う能楽の「鶴亀」などに受け継がれ、さらに、鶴亀を縁起物とする習俗がひろがったとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, a Noh play, &apos;Tsurukame&apos; (a crane and a turtle), in which &apos;a turtle spent ten thousand years, while a crane had a life of thousand years&apos; was created from this variation, and furthermore, it is said that manners and customs which take a turtle and a crane as a good luck charm has been spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, a Noh play called &apos;Tsurukame&apos; (Crane and Turtle), in which a turtle lived for ten thousand years, while a crane had a life of a thousand years, was created from this version of the story, and the custom of having a turtle or crane as a good luck charm spread as a result of this.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, a Noh play called &apos;Tsurukame&apos; (Crane and Turtle), in which a turtle lived for ten thousand years, while a crane had a life of a thousand years, was created from this version of the story, and the custom of having a turtle or crane as a good luck charm spread as a result of this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>横浜市神奈川区に伝わる話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story which has been handed down in Kanagawa Ward, Yokohama City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The version of the story handed down in Kanagawa, Yokohama City</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The version of the story handed down in Kanagawa Ward, Yokohama City</e>
<cmt>Wardを追加</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>昔、相模国三浦郡に浦島太夫とよばれる人がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once upon a time, there was a man called Urashima Tayu in Miura-gun County, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once upon a time, there was a man called Urashima Tayu in Miura-gun County, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once upon a time, there was a man called Urashima Tayu in Miura-gun County, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>彼は仕事のため丹後国に赴任していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came to Tango Province to start a new job.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came to Tango Province to start a new job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came to Tango Province to start a new job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その息子太郎は、亀が浜辺で子ども達にいじめられているところに出会う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, Taro happened to see a turtle being bullied by children on the beach.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, Taro, happened to see a turtle being treated badly by children on the beach.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, Taro, happened to see a turtle being treated badly by children on the beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>（全国版と同じなので中略）老人になった太郎はある漁師から両親の墓が武蔵国白幡にあると聞いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(A middle part is omitted for it is the same as a widely known variation) Taro, who became an old man, heard from a fisherman that his parents&apos; grave was in Shirahata, Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The middle part is omitted as it is the same as the widely-known variation) Taro, who had become an old man, heard from a fisherman that his parents&apos; grave was in Shirahata, Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The middle part is omitted as it is the same as the widely-known variation) Taro, who had become an old man, heard from a fisherman that his parents&apos; grave was in Shirahata, Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>この情報を聞いた太郎は急いで子安の浜に行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing this information, Taro hurried to Koyasu beach.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing this information, Taro hurried to Koyasu beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing this information, Taro hurried to Koyasu beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>子安に着いた太郎は両親の墓を探したが、なかなか見つけられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taro arrived at Koyasu, looking for his parents&apos; grave, but he could not find it easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taro arrived at Koyasu, and looked for his parents&apos; grave, but it could not be found.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taro arrived at Koyasu, and looked for his parents&apos; grave, but it could not be found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>それを見かねた乙姫は、マツに明かりを照らして場所を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otohime, who could not look on with indifference, put a light to a pine tree and showed him where it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otohime, wanting to help him, put a light to a pine tree and showed him where it was.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otohime, wanting to help him, put a light to a pine tree and showed him where it was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>やっとのことで墓を見つけた太郎はその地に庵をつくり、太郎はそこに住んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taro finally found the grave, and built a hermitage to live there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taro finally found the grave, and built a hermitage in order to live there.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taro finally found the grave, and built a hermitage in order to live there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この寺は後に観福寿寺と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This temple was later came to be called Kanfukuju-ji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This temple later came to be called Kanfukuju-ji.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This temple later came to be called Kanfukuju-ji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>沖縄に伝わる話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story which has been handed down in Okinawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The version of the story handed down in Okinawa</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The version of the story handed down in Okinawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>本土のものと若干道具立てが異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is slightly different from a story told in the mainland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This has minor differences from that told on the mainland.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This has minor differences from that told on the mainland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>昔、南風原町与那覇村に正直者の漁師が居て、ある日与那原町の浜で髢（かもじ。髪の毛）を拾った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once upon a time, there was an honest fisherman in Yonaha village in Haebaru town, and he picked up kamoji (a switch) on the beach in Yonabaru town.</e>
<cmt>２つに分かれていたので統合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once upon a time, there was an honest fisherman in Yonaha village in Haebaru town, who picked up a kamoji (hairpiece) on the beach in Yonabaru town.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once upon a time, there was an honest fisherman in Yonaha village in Haebaru town, who picked up a kamoji (hairpiece) on the beach in Yonabaru town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>探している娘を見つけて渡すと感謝され、竜宮に招待したいと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He handed the kamoji to a girl who was looking for it, and she thanked him and told that she wanted to invite him to Ryugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He handed the kamoji to a girl who was looking for it, and she thanked him and said that she wanted to invite him to Ryugu.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He handed the kamoji to a girl who was looking for it, and she thanked him and said that she wanted to invite him to Ryugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>漁師が娘と一緒に歩くと海が二つに割れて道が開け、竜宮に通じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the fisherman began to walk with the girl, the sea was divided and a path to the Ryugu appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the fisherman began to walk with the girl, the sea divided and a path to the Ryugu appeared.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the fisherman began to walk with the girl, the sea divided and a path to the Ryugu appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>娘は乙姫と素性を明かし、漁師は竜宮で歓待の日々を過ごすこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The girl called herself Otohime, and the fisherman spent his days in Ryugu, receiving hospitable treatment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The girl called herself Otohime, and the fisherman spent his days in Ryugu, receiving warm and friendly treatment.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The girl called herself Otohime, and the fisherman spent his days in Ryugu, receiving warm and friendly treatment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>三ヵ月ほど経つと漁師は故郷が恋しくなり、娘から紙包みを渡されるが「開けないように」と念を押される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When three months passed, the fisherman missed his home, and he was given a paper parcel by the girl, being warned &apos;not to open it.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When three months had passed the fisherman began to miss home, and he was given a paper parcel by the girl, being warned not to open it.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When three months had passed the fisherman began to miss home, and he was given a paper parcel by the girl, being warned not to open it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>やがて漁師が郷里に帰り着くと辺りは変わり果て、人間でおよそ三十三代かかるほどの年月が経っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long the fisherman returned home to find that his neighborhood was completely changed, and he spent many years which was equivalent to about 33 generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long the fisherman returned home to find that his neighborhood was completely changed, and he lived there for many years, equivalent to about thirty-three generations.</e>
<cmt>Style, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long the fisherman returned home to find that his neighborhood was completely changed, and he lived there for many years, equivalent to about thirty-three generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>漁師は開けるなと言われた紙包みを開いたが、中には髢が一束入っているのみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fisherman opened the paper parcel, which he was not supposed to open, but inside there was only a bundle of kamoji.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fisherman opened the paper parcel, which he was not supposed to open, but inside there was only a bundle of kamoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fisherman opened the paper parcel, which he was not supposed to open, but inside there was only a bundle of kamoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>そして煙が沸き立ち、彼は白髪の老爺と化して倒れ死んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then smoke rose, and he became an old man with white hair, fell down, and died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that moment smoke enveloped him, and he became an old man with white hair, fell down, and died.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that moment smoke enveloped him, and he became an old man with white hair, fell down, and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>地元の者が老爺に敬意を払い墓を建て祀ったのが、穏作根嶽（うさんにだき）であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the local people showed their respects to the old man and made a grave, which was called Usan Nidaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the local people paid their respects to the old man and made a grave, which was called Usan Nidaki.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the local people paid their respects to the old man and made a grave, which was called Usan Nidaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>近代における改変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A change in modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in modern times</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>竜宮城に行ってからの浦島太郎の行状は、子どもに話すにはふさわしくない内容が含まれているので、童話においてはこの部分は改変されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The behavior of Urashima Taro after he went to Ryugu-jo castle was not appropriate to tell children, so this part was changed in a story for children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The behavior of Urashima Taro after he went to Ryugu-jo Castle was not appropriate for a childrens&apos; story, so this part was changed when told to children.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The behavior of Urashima Taro after he went to Ryugu-jo Castle was not appropriate for a children&apos;s story, so this part was changed when told to children.</e>
<cmt>childrens&apos;→children&apos;s</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>これは、明治時代に国定教科書向きに書き換えられたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the story was rewritten for a national textbook during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the story was rewritten for a national textbook during the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the story was rewritten for a national textbook during the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>歴史・解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History and Interpretation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and Interpretation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and interpretation</e>
<cmt>小文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>『丹後国風土記』を基にして解釈すれば、主人公は風流な男である浦島子と神仙世界の美女である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an interpretation of the story which is based on &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki,&quot; the main characters are a tasteful man called Ura Shimako and a beautiful woman in a world of supernatural beings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an interpretation of the story in &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki&quot;, the main characters are a man of refinement called Ura Shimako and a beautiful woman in a world of supernatural beings.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an interpretation of the story in &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki,&quot; the main characters are a man of refinement called Ura Shimako and a beautiful woman in a world of supernatural beings.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>その二人の恋が官能的に描かれて異界（蓬莱山）と人間界との3年対300年という時間観念を鮮明に持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their love was described erotically, and the story showed us a vivid contrast of sense of time, for example, three years in a supernatural world (Mt. Horai) are equivalent to three hundred years in a world of human beings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their love was described erotically, and the story showed us a vivid contrast in the sense of time, three years in the supernatural world (Mt. Horai) being equivalent to three hundred years in the world of human beings.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their love was described erotically, and the story showed us a vivid contrast in the sense of time, three years in the supernatural world (Mt. Horai) being equivalent to three hundred years in the world of human beings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その語り口は、古代にあっては非常に真新しい思想と表現であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of narrating the story was very unconventional in the ancient times and it expressed a new idea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of narrating the story was very unconventional for the period and it expressed a new concept.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way of narrating the story was very unconventional for the period and it expressed a new concept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>神婚神話や海幸山幸神話などとはまったく異質であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was totally different from a myth dealing with marriages between gods, or a legend of Umisachi Yamasachi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was totally different from myths dealing with marriages between gods, or the legend of Umisachi Yamasachi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was totally different from myths dealing with marriages between gods, or the legend of Umisachi Yamasachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>結末が老や死ではなく肉体が地上から消え去るという神仙的な尸解譚になっているのもそのためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore the story does not end with the main character&apos;s growing old or death, but his body disappears from this world, which is like a legend of a Taoist immortal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story does not end with the main character growing old and dying, but rather his body disappears from this world, which is like legends telling of Taoist immortals.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story does not end with the main character growing old and dying, but rather his body disappears from this world, which is like legends telling of Taoist immortals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>『丹後国風土記』逸文によれば、その記事は連（むらじ）の伊預部馬養（いよべのうまかい）という人物が書いた作品を本にしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki,&quot; the article was a compilation of works written by IYOBE no Umakai in Muraji (one of the highest family names).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki&quot;, the article was a compilation of works written by IYOBE no Umakai (one of the highest regarded family names) in Muraji.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki,&quot; the article was a compilation of works written by IYOBE no Umakai (one of the highest regarded family names) in Muraji.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>この人物は7世紀後半の学者官僚で『律令』選定、史書編纂に係わり皇太子学士を勤め、『壊風藻』に神仙思想を基にした漢詩を残す当代一級の知識人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The man was the greatest intellectual in those days, who was a scholar and a government official in the late 7th century, selecting &quot;Ritsuryo&quot; (a law), being involved in compilation of history books, working as Kotaishigakushi (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince), leaving Chinese poems based on Taoist immortality thought in &quot;Kaifuso&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was regarded as the greatest intellectual of the day, and was a scholar and government official in the late 7th century, selecting &quot;Ritsuryo&quot; (a kind of law), being involved in the compilation of history books, working as Kotaishigakushi (an official in charge of the education of the Crown Prince), and who left Chinese poems based on concepts of Taoist immortality in &quot;Kaifuso&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation, grammar. I&apos;m not sure what the term &apos;selecting&apos; a law refers to. This may need clarification.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was regarded as the greatest intellectual of the day, and was a scholar and government official in the late 7th century, selecting &quot;Ritsuryo&quot; (a kind of law), being involved in the compilation of history books, working as Kotaishigakushi (an official in charge of the education of the Crown Prince), and who left Chinese poems based on concepts of Taoist immortality in &quot;Kaifuso&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>『雄略記』や『丹後国風土記』、『万葉集』「巻九」などに見られる8世紀の浦島物語の原話は伊預部馬養によって描かれた神仙伝奇小説であった可能性が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a great possibility that the original story of Urashima Monogatari in 8th century which can be seen &quot;Yuryaku-ki,&quot; &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki,&quot; the ninth volume of &quot;Manyoshu,&quot; and so on was written by IYOBE no Umakai as a bizarre novel based on Taoist immortality thought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a great possibility that the original story of Urashima Monogatari in the 8th century, which can be seen in &quot;Yuryaku-ki&quot;, &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki&quot;, and the ninth volume of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; among other sources, was written by IYOBE no Umakai as a bizarre novel based on concepts of Taoist immortality.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a great possibility that the original story of Urashima Monogatari in the 8th century, which can be seen in &quot;Yuryaku-ki,&quot; &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki,&quot; and the ninth volume of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; among other sources, was written by IYOBE no Umakai as a bizarre novel based on concepts of Taoist immortality.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>平安時代になると浦島物語の舞台の丹後地方で、浦島明神という神社が浦島子を祀り人々の信仰を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the early Heian period came, a shrine called Urashima Myojin worshiped Ura Shimako and people believed in the god at Tango region, which is a setting of Urashima Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Heian Period, people worshipped Ura Shimako at a shrine called Urashima Myojin in the Tango region, the setting of Urashima Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Heian Period, people worshipped Ura Shimako at a shrine called Urashima Myojin in the Tango region, the setting of Urashima Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>中央の浦島物語と呼応する形で出てきたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the faith appeared in response to the Urashima Monogatari in the central area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that this expression of faith appeared in response to Urashima Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that this expression of faith appeared in response to Urashima Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="57">
<j>平安時代以降も漢文伝として書き継がれてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Heian period, it has been written as kanbunden (biography in classical Chinese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Heian Period it was written as a kanbunden (biography in classical Chinese).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Heian Period it was written as a kanbunden (biography in classical Chinese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="58">
<j>10世紀初頭：『続浦島子伝記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The early 10th century: &quot;Zoku Ura Shimako no denki&quot; (a biography of Ura Shimako, second series)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The early 10th century: &quot;Zoku Ura Shimako no Denki&quot; (a biography of Ura Shimako, second series)</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The early 10th century: &quot;Zoku Ura Shimako no Denki&quot; (a biography of Ura Shimako, second series)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>11世紀後半：「浦島子伝」（『本朝神仙伝』 所収）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The late 11th century: &apos;Ura Shimako den&apos; (a biography of Ura Shimako) (collected in &quot;Honcho shinsen den&quot; (Lives of Japanese Spirit Immortals)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The late 11th century: &apos;Ura Shimako Den&apos; (a biography of Ura Shimako), collected in &quot;Honcho Shinsen Den&quot; (Lives of Japanese Spirit Immortals)</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The late 11th century: &apos;Ura Shimako Den&apos; (a biography of Ura Shimako), collected in &quot;Honcho Shinsen Den&quot; (Lives of Japanese Spirit Immortals)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="60">
<j>11世紀末：「浦島子伝」（『扶桑略記』 所収）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of the 11th century: &apos;Ura Shimako den&apos; (collected in &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Brief History of Japan))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end of the 11th century: &apos;Ura Shimako Den&apos;, collected in &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Brief History of Japan)</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, double parentheses avoided.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end of the 11th century: &apos;Ura Shimako Den&apos;, collected in &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Brief History of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="61">
<j>13世紀初期：「浦島子伝」（『古事談』 所収） など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The early 13th century: &apos;Ura Shimako den&apos; (collected in &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The early 13th century: &apos;Ura Shimako Den&apos;, collected in &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past)</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, double parentheses avoided.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The early 13th century: &apos;Ura Shimako Den&apos;, collected in &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="62">
<j>12世紀以降になると、『俊頼髄脳』をはじめ『奥儀抄』、『和歌童蒙抄』など歌論書に浦島物語が登場し、仮名で書かれ宮廷や貴族達の間に浦島物語が広く浸透した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the 12th century, Urashima Monogatari appeared in books on a theory of waka poetry such as &quot;Toshiyori Zuino&quot; (Toshiyori&apos;s Poetic Essentials), &quot;Ogisho,&quot; &quot;Waka domosho&quot; (A waka handbook for beginners), and they were written in kana (the Japanese syllabaries), being widely read among nobles in the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the 12th century, Urashima Monogatari appeared in books about waka poetry such as &quot;Toshiyori Zuino&quot; (Toshiyori&apos;s Poetic Essentials), &quot;Ogisho&quot;, and &quot;Waka domosho&quot; (a waka handbook for beginners), and they were written in kana (the Japanese syllabaries), being widely read among nobles in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the 12th century, Urashima Monogatari appeared in books about waka poetry such as &quot;Toshiyori Zuino&quot; (Toshiyori&apos;s Poetic Essentials), &quot;Ogisho,&quot; and &quot;Waka domosho&quot; (a waka handbook for beginners), and they were written in kana (the Japanese syllabaries), being widely read among nobles in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="63">
<j>中世になると、『御伽草子』の「浦島太郎」をはじめ絵巻・能・狂言の題材になり、読者・観客を得て大衆化していき、江戸時代に受け継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Medieval period began, &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; made a good theme for picture scrolls, Noh plays, and Kyogen (farce played during a No play cycle) as well as &quot;Otogi zoshi,&quot; and the story required readers and audiences, becoming popularized, and was passed down to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Medieval period, the &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; from &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; became a theme for picture scrolls, Noh plays, and Kyogen (a farce played during a Noh play cycle), and the story reached a much wider audience, becoming further popularized during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Medieval period, the &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; from &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; became a theme for picture scrolls, Noh plays, and Kyogen (a farce played during a Noh play cycle), and the story reached a much wider audience, becoming further popularized during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>明治期には巌谷小波が前代の物語を恩返しに主眼を置いた子供向けの読み物に改作し、ダイジェスト版が明治43年から35年間、国定教科書の教材になり定着していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Meiji Period, Sazanami IWAYA changed the former story into the one for children, focusing on returning of a favor, and a summary of the story had been on a national text book and spread for 35 years since 1910.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Period, Sazanami IWAYA changed the established story into one for children, focusing on the returning of the favor, and the summary of the story appeared in national textbooks for 35 years from 1910.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji Period, Sazanami IWAYA changed the established story into one for children, focusing on the returning of the favor, and the summary of the story appeared in national textbooks for 35 years from 1910.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="65">
<j>1300年もの長い歴史を持ち、各種の文献にさまざまな形で残された話は他に例がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except this story, there is no example which has a long history of 1300 years, being left in different forms in various literatures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from this story, there are no examples of stories which have a history spanning 1300 years, and appear in different forms in various works.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from this story, there are no examples of stories which have a history spanning 1300 years, and appear in different forms in various works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>謎と背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mysteries and the Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background and Certain Mysteries</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background and Certain Mysteries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>浦島太郎がいた蓬莱山（竜宮城）とは仙人が住むという伝説の山であり、古代中国の不老不死を願う神仙思想が背景にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Horai (or Ryugu-jo castle) where Urashima Taro stayed was a legendary mountain in which sennin (immortal mountain wizard) lived, and behind the story, there was the Taoist immortality thought that hoped for eternal youth and immortality in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Horai (or Ryugu-jo Castle) where Urashima Taro stayed, was a legendary mountain on which sennin (immortal mountain wizards) lived, and behind the story were concepts concerning Taoist immortality in which eternal youth and immortality were prized in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Horai (or Ryugu-jo Castle) where Urashima Taro stayed, was a legendary mountain on which sennin (immortal mountain wizards) lived, and behind the story were concepts concerning Taoist immortality in which eternal youth and immortality were prized in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>海のかなたの東方に、仙人が住む孤島があり不老不死の薬があるという島である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an isolated island located to the far east of the sea, and sennin lived there with an elixir of life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an isolated island located at the far to the east, and the sennin lived there, knowing of the elixir of life.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an isolated island located at the far to the east, and the sennin lived there, knowing of the elixir of life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>神仙思想は古代中国の陰陽五行説ともつながり、劇中登場する亀の色の五色も五行思想からきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taoist immortality thought has something to do with the doctrine of Yin and Yang and the Five Agents or Elements in ancient Chinese cosmology, and the five colors of the turtle in the tale were derived from Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concepts of Taoist immortality are connected to the doctrine of Yin and Yang and the Five Agents or Elements in ancient Chinese cosmology, and the five colors of the turtle in the tale were derived from this Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concepts of Taoist immortality are connected to the doctrine of Yin and Yang and the Five Agents or Elements in ancient Chinese cosmology, and the five colors of the turtle in the tale were derived from this Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その蓬莱山が後の時代に竜宮城へと変化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mt. Horai has been changed into the Ryugu-jo castle in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Horai was changed into Ryugu-jo Castle in later years.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Horai was changed into Ryugu-jo Castle in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>またその内容から神仙思想を基にして古代日本の貴族が書いた官能小説ともとれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the contents of the story, it is also regarded as a pornographic novel which was based on Taoist immortality thought and written by an ancient Japanese court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the content of the story, it is also regarded as a pornographic novel based on concepts of Taoist immortality written by an ancient Japanese court noble.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the content of the story, it is also regarded as a pornographic novel based on concepts of Taoist immortality written by an ancient Japanese court noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="71">
<j>浦島太郎と似た説話に、ホデリ・山幸神話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoderi, myth of Yamasachi, is a similar tale to Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoderi, the myth of Yamasachi, is a similar tale to Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoderi, the myth of Yamasachi, is a similar tale to Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>その劇中、天皇の祖神、山幸彦が「塩土老翁」（しおつつのおじ）という神に「無目籠」（まなしかたま）という水の入らないかごに乗せられ、海神の宮（わだつみのみや）に行き、海神（わだつみ）の娘、豊玉姫（とよたまひめ）と結婚し3年間暮らし生まれ故郷に戻り禁（タブー）を破る話の大筋がそっくりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main plot is quite similar to Urashima Monogatari; Yamasachihiko, the deity from which the Imperial family is descended, was put in a waterproof palanquin called &apos;Manashikatama&apos; by &apos;Shiotsutsunooji,&apos; and went to Wadatsumi no miya (a palace of a tutelary of the sea), getting married to Toyotamahime, a daughter of Wadatsumi, spending three years there, and returning to his home to break a taboo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main plot is quite similar to Urashima Monogatari; Yamasachihiko, the deity from which the Imperial family is descended, was put in a waterproof palanquin called &apos;Manashikatama&apos; by the god Shiotsutsunooji and taken to Wadatsumi no miya (a palace of the tutelary deity of the sea), and there gets married to Toyotamahime, a daughter of Wadatsumi, and after spending three years there he returns home and breaks a taboo.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main plot is quite similar to Urashima Monogatari; Yamasachihiko, the deity from which the Imperial family is descended, was put in a waterproof palanquin called &apos;Manashikatama&apos; by the god Shiotsutsunooji and taken to Wadatsumi no miya (a palace of the tutelary deity of the sea), and there gets married to Toyotamahime, a daughter of Wadatsumi, and after spending three years there he returns home and breaks a taboo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また『歴史書』に著される山幸彦の孫の初代神武天皇がヤマトに向かう際、亀に乗り釣竿を持った男が水先案内人になる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, according to &quot;History books,&quot; when the first Emperor Jinmu, a grandchild of Yamasachihiko, went to Yamato, a man with a fishing rod riding on the back of the turtle was a pilot.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, according to history books, when the first Emperor Jinmu, a grandchild of Yamasachihiko, came to Yamato, a man with a fishing rod was riding on the back of a turtle.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity, punctuation. I have assumed 『歴史書』is not the title of a book.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, according to &quot;Rekishi-sho&quot;(a history book), when the first Emperor Jinmu, a grandchild of Yamasachihiko, came to Yamato, a man with a fishing rod was riding on the back of a turtle.</e>
<cmt>「歴史書」の訳語</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>この2人の人物は不思議と浦島太郎に似ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two characters are strangely similar to Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two characters are strangely similar to Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two characters are strangely similar to Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="75">
<j>浦島太郎のモデルとなったとされる人物として、『歌集』に「墨吉」（すみのえ）の人の記述があり、これは今も大阪の住吉にあり住吉三神に祭られている住吉三神の事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;A Collection of Poetry&quot; contains a description of a person in &apos;Suminoe,&apos; who is considered a model for Urashima Taro, and he is still worshiped as Sumiyoshi Myojin, one of Sumiyoshi Sanjin (Sumiyoshi three deities), in Sumiyoshi, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処ウェブを参照したところ、赤字の住吉三神は「住吉明神」となっていました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;A Collection of Poetry&quot; contains a description of a person called &apos;Suminoe&apos;, who is considered to be a model for Urashima Taro, and who is still worshipped as Sumiyoshi Myojin, one of the Sumiyoshi Sanjin (Sumiyoshi three deities), in Sumiyoshi, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;A Collection of Poetry&quot; contains a description of a person called &apos;Suminoe,&apos; who is considered to be a model for Urashima Taro, and who is still worshipped as Sumiyoshi Myojin, one of the Sumiyoshi Sanjin (Sumiyoshi three deities), in Sumiyoshi, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>別名、「塩土老翁」といい大変長命長生きであったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His another name was &apos;Shiotsutsunooji&apos; and said to have lived for a long time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His other name was &apos;Shiotsutsunooji&apos; and he is said to have lived for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His other name was &apos;Shiotsutsunooji&apos; and he is said to have lived for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>そのモデルとされる武内宿禰も大変に長生きである（しかしながら人間の寿命をはるかに超越しているため多分にフィクションともとれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The model of this character, TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, also lived to a great age (however, they lived for much longer than human being&apos;s life span, therefore it is also taken as a fiction).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The model of this character, TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, lived to a great age (however, as they lived much longer than a human life span, it is taken to be fiction).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The model of this character, TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, lived to a great age (however, as they lived much longer than a human life span, it is taken to be fiction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>浦島太郎、塩土老翁、武内宿禰、この3者は長生きで繋がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three characters, Urashima Taro, Shiotsutsunooji, and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, are related to each other in that they lived for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three characters, Urashima Taro, Shiotsutsunooji, and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, share the same characteristic in that they lived for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three characters, Urashima Taro, Shiotsutsunooji, and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, share the same characteristic in that they lived for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="79">
<j>住吉明神から塩土老翁、「老翁」の字が老人になった浦島太郎にそっくりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letters &apos;老翁&apos; (old man) are closely associated with Urashima Taro, who became an old man.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文の言葉のつながり方がおかしいのですが、ウェブを参照しても同様の文のため、訳せる範囲で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letters &apos;老翁&apos; (old man) are closely associated with Urashima Taro, who became an old man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letters &apos;老翁&apos; (old man) are closely associated with Urashima Taro, who became an old man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>住吉明神、塩土老翁、浦島太郎の3者は長寿、老人のイメージで繋がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyoshi Myojin, Shiotsutsunooji, Urashima Taro share a common feature of long life and an image of an old man.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyoshi Myojin, Shiotsutsunooji, and Urashima Taro share the common feature of being represented by an image of an old man, in addition to their long life.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word order, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyoshi Myojin, Shiotsutsunooji, and Urashima Taro share the common feature of being represented by an image of an old man, in addition to their long life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>また塩土老翁はヤマト王権の天孫降臨を導びき、神武天皇の東征をうながした謎の神であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Shiotsutsunooji led the descent of the Sun-Goddess&apos;s grandson in Yamato regal power, and it is said that he was a mysterious god that encouraged Emperor Jinmu&apos;s military expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Shiotsutsunooji oversaw the descent to earth of the Sun-Goddess&apos;s grandson in the Yamato regal system, and it is said that he was a mysterious god that encouraged Emperor Jinmu&apos;s military expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Shiotsutsunooji oversaw the descent to earth of the Sun-Goddess&apos;s grandson in the Yamato regal system, and it is said that he was a mysterious god that encouraged Emperor Jinmu&apos;s military expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>また武内宿禰は古代豪族、臣の祖とされ応神天皇の東征を導いたともされ、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune is considered the founder of Omi, a powerful family in ancient times, and led Emperor Ojin&apos;s military expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune is considered the founder of Omi, a powerful family in ancient times, and led Emperor Ojin&apos;s military expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune is considered the founder of Omi, a powerful family in ancient times, and led Emperor Ojin&apos;s military expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>浦島もどき：神武天皇の案内役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima-like: a guide for Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like Urashima: a guide for Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>The term 浦島もどき is a little unclear. It may be better to alter the structure of the sentence to illustrate more clearly the emphasis that the two characters are similar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Urashima: a guide for Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="84">
<j>塩土老翁：神武東征を促し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiotsutsunooji: the one who encouraged Emperor Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiotsutsunooji: encouraged Emperor Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiotsutsunooji: encouraged Emperor Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="85">
<j>武内宿禰：応神天皇の東征を導く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune: the one who led Emperor Ojin&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune: led Emperor Ojin&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune: led Emperor Ojin&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="86">
<j>この三者は不思議と同じイメージで繋がっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three people are related to each other in the same image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three people are represented by similar images.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three people are represented by similar images.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>神武東征と応神天皇の東征はルートも似ており神武と応神天皇も同一人物ではないかとの見方も見て取れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Jinmu and Emperor Ojin took the similar route to the east, therefore there is a view that these two emperors were considered the same person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Jinmu and Emperor Ojin took a similar route to the east, and there is a view that these two emperors could have been the same person.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Jinmu and Emperor Ojin took a similar route to the east, and there is a view that these two emperors could have been the same person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="88">
<j>蘇我氏と浦島にも「海」という接点が見えてくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sea&apos; is something that connects the Soga clan with Urashima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sea is an element that connects the Soga clan with Urashima.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sea is an element that connects the Soga clan with Urashima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>7世紀に全盛期を迎えた蘇我氏は、縄文時代から生産されてきた翡翠（硬玉）を独占的に生産していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Soga clan, who was at the height of their prosperity in the 7th century, had monopolistically produced green jadeite since the Jomon period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Soga clan, who were at the height of their prosperity in the 7th century, had been the sole producers of green jadeite since the Jomon Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Soga clan, who were at the height of their prosperity in the 7th century, had been the sole producers of green jadeite since the Jomon Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>ヒスイは海底からもたらされるため海神からもたらされる神宝と考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because green jadeite is brought from the bottom of the sea, it was considered sacred treasure given by the god of the sea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because green jadeite is brought from the bottom of the sea, it was considered to be sacred treasure given by the god of the sea.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because green jadeite is brought from the bottom of the sea, it was considered to be sacred treasure given by the god of the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>蘇我氏が海の神宝ヒスイにこだわった所に浦島太郎とのかすかな接点が見出せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A slight connection can be found in that the Soga clan had an obsession with green jadeite, or the sacred treasure in the sea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A slight connection can be found with Urashima Taro in that the Soga clan had an obsession with green jadeite, or the sacred treasure in the sea.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A slight connection can be found with Urashima Taro in that the Soga clan had an obsession with green jadeite, or the sacred treasure in the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>それがゆえか浦島そっくりな山幸彦も劇中で海神からヒスイをもらっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That might be why, Yamasachihiko, who was quite similar to Urashima, was also given green jadeite by the god of the sea in the story.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This may be the reason Yamasachihiko, who was quite similar to Urashima, was also given green jadeite by the god of the sea in the story.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This may be the reason Yamasachihiko, who was quite similar to Urashima, was also given green jadeite by the god of the sea in the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="93">
<j>蘇我氏の祖の武内宿禰は応神天皇の母、神功皇后の忠臣として活躍し神功皇后はトヨの海の神と強く結ばれ「豊浦宮」（とゆらのみや）に拠点を構えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, the founder of the Soga clan, worked as a loyal subject of Emperor Jingu, the mother of Emperor Ojin, while Empress Jingu was firmly bound with the sea god of Toyo, creating a strongpoint at &apos;Toyura no miya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, the founder of the Soga clan, worked as a loyal subject to Emperor Jingu, the mother of Emperor Ojin, while Empress Jingu was strongly connected to the sea god of Toyo and created a stronghold at &apos;Toyura no miya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, the founder of the Soga clan, worked as a loyal subject to Emperor Jingu, the mother of Emperor Ojin, while Empress Jingu was strongly connected to the sea god of Toyo and created a stronghold at &apos;Toyura no miya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>それは「トヨの港の宮」とも呼ばれ、そこから神功皇后はトヨの女王と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was also called &apos;Toyo no minato no miya,&apos; Empress Jingu was called Queen of Toyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it was also called &apos;Toyo no minato no miya,&apos; Empress Jingu was called Queen of Toyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it was also called &apos;Toyo no minato no miya,&apos; Empress Jingu was called Queen of Toyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>蘇我氏のルーツと神功皇后との係わり、神功皇后と武内宿禰の関係性が浦島太郎伝説から読み取れるともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that the origins of the Soga clan, their relationships with Empress Jingu, and relationships between Empress Jingu and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune can be read from the legend of Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that the origins of the Soga clan, their relationships with Empress Jingu, and relationships between Empress Jingu and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune can be worked out from the legend of Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that the origins of the Soga clan, their relationships with Empress Jingu, and relationships between Empress Jingu and TAKENOUCHI no Sukune can be worked out from the legend of Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="96">
<j>歴史作家・関裕二の最近の研究によると古代文書のことごとくが浦島に饒舌なのはこの人物の背後に歴史の闇の存在が指摘できるからであるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the recent study conducted by Yuji SEKI, an author of history novels, most of the ancient documents mention especially Urashima a lot because it can be pointed out that there is darkness of history behind this character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a recent study conducted by Yuji SEKI, an author of historical novels, the fact that most of the ancient documents frequently mention Urashima particularly means that it can be interpreted that he was a significant, if shadowy, figure.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a recent study conducted by Yuji SEKI, an author of historical novels, the fact that most of the ancient documents frequently mention Urashima particularly means that it can be interpreted that he was a significant, if shadowy, figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>『日本書紀』は太郎を5世紀後半の雄略天皇のころの話であるといい、300年後（この場合は300年）の8世紀に生まれ故郷に戻るとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; tells us that the story of Taro happened around the late 5th century, the reign of Emperor Yuryaku, and 300 years later (in this case 300 years), during the 8th century, he returned to his home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; tells us that the story of Taro happened around the late 5th century, during the reign of Emperor Yuryaku, and 300 years later (in this case really 300 years), in the 8th century, he returned to his birthplace.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; tells us that the story of Taro happened around the late 5th century, during the reign of Emperor Yuryaku, and 300 years later (in this case really 300 years), in the 8th century, he returned to his birthplace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>この5世紀と8世紀の間が重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interval between 5th and 8th centuries is important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interval between 5th and 8th centuries is important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interval between 5th and 8th centuries is important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>この時代、雄略天皇が改革事業を推し進め「強い天皇家」を目指し蘇我氏が補佐役として政権を築くが、後に勃興した貴族に政権を奪われてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this period, Emperor Yuryaku tried to carry out a reform project, aiming at &apos;a powerful Imperial family,&apos; and the Soga clan supported him, establishing political power, but later their political power was taken by court nobles rising suddenly to power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this period Emperor Yuryaku tried to carry out a project of reforms, aiming to create &apos;a powerful Imperial family&apos;, and the Soga clan supported him, thus establishing their political power, however, later this political power was taken by the sudden rise to prominence of other court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this period Emperor Yuryaku tried to carry out a project of reforms, aiming to create &apos;a powerful Imperial family,&apos; and the Soga clan supported him, thus establishing their political power, however, later this political power was taken by the sudden rise to prominence of other court nobles.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>浦島太郎の300年とは、雄略天皇の改革と蹉跌の時代であるとも推測できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be conjectured that the 300 years of Urashima Taro was also the period of Emperor Yuryaku&apos;s reform and stumbling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be conjectured that the relevance of the 300 years in the Urashima Taro story reflects the period of time of Emperor Yuryaku&apos;s reforms and the ensuing difficulties.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be conjectured that the relevance of the 300 years in the Urashima Taro story reflects the period of time of Emperor Yuryaku&apos;s reforms and the ensuing difficulties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>心理学的解題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A psychological Bibliographical Introduction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Psychological synopsis</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Psychological synopsis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>心理学的には、浦島太郎の伝説は非常に日本的な風土を表していると分析される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Psychologically, it is analyzed that the legend of Urashima Taro expresses the features of Japan very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be suggested that the legend of Urashima Taro reflects the psychological features of Japan very closely.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be suggested that the legend of Urashima Taro reflects the psychological features of Japan very closely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>それによると、水底のヘビや竜は母親を象徴するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the analysis, a snake or a dragon at the bottom of the sea is a symbol of a mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to such an analysis, a snake or dragon at the bottom of the sea can be seen as a mother symbol.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to such an analysis, a snake or dragon at the bottom of the sea can be seen as a mother symbol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>西洋の説話では、竜退治囚われの姫を救出して結婚する、という筋書きになる（古代バビロニア神話の女神ティアマト、ギリシア神話のアンドロメダにまつわる物語を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Western tale, the main character cleared a dragon, saved a princess in captivity, and got married to her. (See also the tales concerning Tiamat, the goddess in the ancient Babylonian myth, and also Andromeda, the goddess in the Greek myth.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Western tales, the main character vanquished a dragon, saved a princess from captivity, and got married to her (see also the tales concerning Tiamat, the goddess in the ancient Babylonian myth, and the goddess Andromeda in the Greek myth).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Western tales, the main character vanquished a dragon, saved a princess from captivity, and got married to her (see also the tales concerning Tiamat, the goddess in the ancient Babylonian myth, and the goddess Andromeda in the Greek myth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>これは象徴的な母親殺しであるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this is a symbolical matricide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this represents a symbol of matricide.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this represents a symbol of matricide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>つまり、母親の影響を廃して男子は独立する、ということを意味するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In short, it means that a man becomes independent, driving away an influence of mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In short, it means that a man becomes independent by driving away the influence of his mother.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In short, it means that a man becomes independent by driving away the influence of his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>それに対して浦島太郎はその竜の住み処で姫と暮らしてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Urashima Taro lived in the residence of the dragon with the princess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Urashima Taro lived in the residence of the dragon with the princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Urashima Taro lived in the residence of the dragon with the princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>これは、男性が母親の影響を断ち切ることなく成人してしまう日本的なあり方を示しているというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This indicates that men become adults without cutting off influences of mother, which is very typical way of boy&apos;s growing up to a man in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This indicates that men become adults without breaking from the influence of his mother, which is very typical way of a boy becoming a man in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that men become adults without breaking from the influence of his mother, which is very typical way of a boy becoming a man in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>ゆかりの神社仏閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines and Temples Noted in Connection with Urashima Taro</e>
<cmt>「浦島太郎」という言葉を補って訳しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines and Temples Noted in Connection with Urashima Taro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines and Temples Noted in Connection with Urashima Taro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>観福寿寺（神奈川県横浜市神奈川区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanfukuju-ji Temple (Kanagawa Ward, Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanfukuju-ji Temple (Kanagawa Ward, Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanfukuju-ji Temple (Kanagawa Ward, Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>- 明治に焼失。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was burnt down in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This temple was burnt down in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This temple was burnt down in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>また、乙姫が枝に光を照らしたマツも大正時代に枯死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A pine tree to which Otohime put a light also died during the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pine tree to which Otohime put a light also died during the Taisho Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pine tree to which Otohime put a light also died during the Taisho Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>慶運寺に聖観世音菩薩像が現在も残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An image of Sho Kanzeon Bosatsu (Avalokitesvara-bodhisattva) has remained until today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of Sho Kanzeon Bosatsu (Avalokitesvara-bodhisattva) still remains today.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of Sho Kanzeon Bosatsu (Avalokitesvara-bodhisattva) still remains at Keiun-ji temple today.</e>
<cmt>at Keiun-ji templeを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>浦嶋神社（京都府与謝郡伊根町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima-jinja Shrine (Ine-cho, Yosa-gun, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urashima-jinja Shrine (Ine-cho, Yosa-gun, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urashima-jinja Shrine (Ine-cho, Yosa-gun, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>- 浦島伝説の中では最も古いとされる『丹後国風土記』逸文ゆかりの地域にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in the area noted in connection with a surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no kuni Fudoki,&quot; which is considered the oldest legend of Urashima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine is located in an area noted in connection with a surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki&quot;, which is considered the oldest legend concerning Urashima.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shrine is located in an area noted in connection with a surviving fragment of &quot;Tango no Kuni Fudoki,&quot; which is considered the oldest legend concerning Urashima.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>社伝では天長2年（825年）に創建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the shrine&apos;s biography, it was build in 825.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to shrine records, it was built in 825.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to shrine records, it was built in 825.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>丹後半島にはこのほかにも浦島伝説に基づく神社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tango Peninsula also has other shrines based on the Urashima legend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tango Peninsula also contains other shrines based on the Urashima legend.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tango Peninsula also contains other shrines based on the Urashima legend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>浦島神社（香川県三豊市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima-jinja Shrine (Mitoyo City, Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urashima-jinja Shrine (Mitoyo City, Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urashima-jinja Shrine (Mitoyo City, Kagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="114">
<j>- 荘内半島一帯には,太郎が生まれたという生里,箱から出た煙がかかった紫雲出山ほかたくさんの浦島伝説に基づく地名が点在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Shonai Peninsula, there are many place-names based on the Urashima legend such as Namari, where Taro was born, and Mt. Shiudeyama, which the smoke rising from the casket wrapped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Shonai Peninsula, there are many place-names based on the Urashima legend, such as Namari, where Taro was born, and Mt. Shiudeyama, the smoke from which rose from the casket in the tale.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the Shonai Peninsula, there are many place-names based on the Urashima legend, such as Namari, where Taro was born, and Mt. Shiudeyama, the smoke from which rose from the casket in the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>太郎が助けた亀が祀られている亀戎社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kameebisuha, where the turtle that Taro saved has been worshiped, is also located in the same city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kameebisuha, where the turtle that Taro saved has been worshipped, is also located in the same city.</e>
<cmt>Spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameebisusha, where the turtle that Taro saved has been worshipped, is also located in the same city.</e>
<cmt>Kameebisuha→Kameebisusha</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>寝覚の床・臨川寺（長野県上松町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nezame no Toko (wake-up bed)/Rinsen-ji Temple (Agematsu Machi, Nagano Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nezame no Toko (wake-up bed)/Rinsen-ji Temple (Agematsu Machi, Nagano Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nezame no Toko (wake-up bed)/Rinsen-ji Temple (Agematsu Machi, Nagano Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="116">
<j>- 寝覚の床は竜宮城から戻った浦島太郎が玉手箱を開けた場所といわれ,中央の岩の上には浦島堂が建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nezame no Toko is said to be a place where Urashima Taro, who just came back from Ryugu-jo castle, opened the casket, and on the central rock, the Urashimado Shrine stands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nezame no Toko is said to be the place where Urashima Taro, just back from Ryugu-jo Castle, opened the casket, and Urashimado Shrine stands on a rock in the center.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nezame no Toko is said to be the place where Urashima Taro, just back from Ryugu-jo Castle, opened the casket, and Urashimado Shrine stands on a rock in the center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>臨川寺は、浦島太郎が使っていたとされる釣竿を所蔵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinsen-ji Temple owns a fishing rod which is said to have been used by Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinsen-ji Temple owns a fishing rod which is said to have been used by Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinsen-ji Temple owns a fishing rod which is said to have been used by Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>境内からは景勝寝覚の床を見下ろす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the precincts, you can see picturesque scenery, Nezame no Toko, below your eyes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the precincts you can look down over the picturesque scenery of Nezame no Toko.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the precincts you can look down over the picturesque scenery of Nezame no Toko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>派生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Derivation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Derivation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Derivation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>唱歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Song for School Children</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Song for School Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Song for School Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>文部省唱歌「浦島太郎」は、1900年の『幼年唱歌』に掲載された「うらしまたろう」（作詞・石原和三郎、作曲・田村虎蔵）と、1911年の『尋常小学唱歌』に掲載された「浦島太郎」（作詞・乙骨三郎、作曲者不明）とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two kinds of &apos;Urashima Taro,&apos; songs authorized by the Ministry of Education: &apos;Utashima Taro&apos; published in &quot;Yonen Shoka&quot; (songs for little children) in 1900 (words by Kazusaburo ISHIHARA, music by Torazo TAMURA) and another &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; published in &quot;Jinjo Shogaku Shoka&quot; (songs collected for common elementary education) in 1911 (words by Saburo Otsukotsu, musical composed is unknown).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two kinds of &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; songs authorized by the Ministry of Education: &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; published in &quot;Yonen Shoka&quot; (songs for little children) in 1900 (words by Kazusaburo ISHIHARA, music by Torazo TAMURA) and another &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; published in &quot;Jinjo Shogaku Shoka&quot; (songs collected for common elementary education) in 1911 (words by Saburo Otsukotsu, music by a person unknown).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two kinds of &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; songs authorized by the Ministry of Education: &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; published in &quot;Yonen Shoka&quot; (songs for little children) in 1900 (words by Kazusaburo ISHIHARA, music by Torazo TAMURA) and another &apos;Urashima Taro&apos; published in &quot;Jinjo Shogaku Shoka&quot; (songs collected for common elementary education) in 1911 (words by Saburo Otsukotsu, music by a person unknown).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>現在でも歌われている「昔々浦島は助けた亀に連れられて」で始まる歌は、『尋常小学唱歌』の「浦島太郎」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The song which is sung even today begins with the words, &apos;once upon a time, Urashima was brought by the turtle which he saved,&apos; and it is the &quot;Jinjo Shogaku Shoka&quot; version of &apos;Urashima Taro.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The song, which is sung even today, is the &quot;Jinjo Shogaku Shoka&quot; version of &apos;Urashima Taro&apos;, and begins with the words &apos;once upon a time Urashima was brought hither by the turtle he saved&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The song, which is sung even today, is the &quot;Jinjo Shogaku Shoka&quot; version of &apos;Urashima Taro,&apos; and begins with the words &apos;once upon a time Urashima was brought hither by the turtle he saved&apos;.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>ウラシマ効果</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima Effect (Time Dilation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urashima Effect (Time Dilation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urashima Effect (Time Dilation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>物理学者アルベルト・アインシュタインの相対性理論によれば、運動している物体の経過時間は、静止している物体の経過時間に比べて相対的に遅くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the theory of relativity advocated by a physicist, Albert Einstein, the elapsed time of objects in motion is relatively later than that of objects at rest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the theory of relativity advocated by the physicist Albert Einstein, the elapsed time of objects in motion is relatively slower than that of objects at rest.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the theory of relativity advocated by the physicist Albert Einstein, the elapsed time of objects in motion is relatively slower than that of objects at rest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>この現象は日常的には判らないが、光速に近づくと顕著になる（理論的には、光速に達すると時間は止まってしまうことになる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This phenomenon is not observed in daily life, but when the objects reach a velocity of light, it becomes more conspicuous. (Theoretically, time stops when it reaches the light velocity.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This phenomenon is not observed in daily life, but when objects reach the velocity of light, it becomes more conspicuous; theoretically, time stops when it reaches the velocity of light.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phenomenon is not observed in daily life, but when objects reach the velocity of light, it becomes more conspicuous; theoretically, time stops when it reaches the velocity of light.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>そのため、光速に近い速度の宇宙船に乗って宇宙旅行をして帰還すると、地上では宇宙船での何倍もの時間が経過しており、宇宙船の乗組員は、さながら浦島太郎の様相を呈することのなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, people who get on a spacecraft reaching almost a speed of light, enjoy space travel, and return to the earth, they find that time already passed on earth much more than in the spacecraft, so the crews of the spacecraft look as if they were Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, people who are on a spacecraft reaching almost the speed of light enjoy space travel, and on returning to the earth they find that time passed on earth much faster than on the spacecraft, so the crew of the spacecraft feel as if they were Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, people who are on a spacecraft reaching almost the speed of light enjoy space travel, and on returning to the earth they find that time passed on earth much faster than on the spacecraft, so the crew of the spacecraft feel as if they were Urashima Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>そのため、この効果のことを俗にウラシマ効果と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why this effect is commonly called Urashima effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why this effect is commonly called the Urashima Effect.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why this effect is commonly called the Urashima Effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>（物理学用語ではなく、ふつう「ウラシマ」と片仮名表記する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is not a physical term, and generally written in the katakana syllabary as &apos;ウラシマ&apos; (Urashima).</e>
<cmt>表記が問題になっているため、訳文中にカタカナを使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is not a physical term, and generally written in the katakana syllabary as &apos;ウラシマ&apos; (Urashima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is not a physical term, and generally written in the katakana syllabary as &apos;ウラシマ&apos; (Urashima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>複数のSF作家（豊田有恒など）がこの話を浦島太郎が宇宙人に攫われ、亀（宇宙船）に乗って、竜宮城（異星）へ光速移動したために地球との時間の進み方にずれが生じたとする解釈を提示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several science-fiction writers (such as Aritsune TOYOTA) made an interpretation of this story; Urashima Taro was caught by aliens, and brought to the Ryugu-jo castle (other planet) on the back of the turtle (spacecraft) at a velocity of light, therefore time passed in a different way on earth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several science-fiction writers, such as Aritsune TOYOTA, have made an interpretation of this story; Urashima Taro was caught by aliens, and brought to Ryugu-jo Castle (other planet) on the back of a turtle (spacecraft) at the velocity of light, therefore time passed in a different way to that on earth.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several science-fiction writers, such as Aritsune TOYOTA, have made an interpretation of this story; Urashima Taro was caught by aliens, and brought to Ryugu-jo Castle (other planet) on the back of a turtle (spacecraft) at the velocity of light, therefore time passed in a different way to that on earth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="127">
<j>詳細はウラシマ効果、双子のパラドックスを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See also see Urashima effect (time dilation) and a paradox of twins for further details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See also see Urashima effect (time dilation) and the paradox of twins for further details.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See also see Urashima effect (time dilation) and the paradox of twins for further details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>「浦島太郎（花子）状態」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urashima Taro (Hanako) Condition&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Urashima Taro (Hanako) Condition&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Urashima Taro (Hanako) Condition&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="128">
<j>竜宮城から故郷に戻るとまったく見知らぬ土地になっていたという浦島太郎の立場になぞらえ、長い間離れていた所に久しぶりに戻ると別世界になっており面食らうことを、古くは「今浦島」現在では「浦島太郎である」「浦島太郎状態にある」などと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to Urashima Taro, who returned to his home from Ryugu-jo Castle, and found that his neighborhood became total strange place, those who have been away for a long time return to their home to found that it has been totally changed are called &apos;Ima Urashima&apos; (now Urashima) in the past, and today called &apos;the person is Urashima Taro&apos; or &apos;the person is in a state of Urashima Taro.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to Urashima Taro, who returned home from Ryugu-jo Castle to find that his neighborhood had become a completely unfamiliar place, those who have been away for a long time and who return to their home to find that it has totally changed were called &apos;Ima Urashima&apos; (Urashima of the present) in the past, and today &apos;the person is Urashima Taro&apos; or &apos;the person is in a state of Urashima Taro&apos; is used.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to Urashima Taro, who returned home from Ryugu-jo Castle to find that his neighborhood had become a completely unfamiliar place, those who have been away for a long time and who return to their home to find that it has totally changed were called &apos;Ima Urashima&apos; (Urashima of the present) in the past, and today &apos;the person is Urashima Taro&apos; or &apos;the person is in a state of Urashima Taro&apos; is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>女性の場合は浦島花子（うらしまはなこ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the person is female, she is called Urashima Hanako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the person is female, she is called Urashima Hanako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the person is female, she is called Urashima Hanako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>「日本国外に住み日本の流行に疎くなったり違和感を覚えてしまう」「出向先から戻って本社の変貌ぶりにまごつく」「世間から離れていたために時事ニュースや新しい技術を知らず、時代に取り残されたと感じる」などの状態を自虐的に表現する際に用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expression is masochistically used when &apos;the person has lived abroad and become ignorant of Japanese fashion or felt awkward,&apos; &apos;the person who has just returned from his or her place of assignment gets confused by changes in the head office,&apos; or &apos;the person who has been away from the society and not known current affairs news or new technologies feels that he or she has been left behind.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expression is used in a masochistic way about &apos;a person who has lived abroad and become ignorant of Japanese fashion or felt awkward&apos;, &apos;a person who has just returned from his or her place of assignment and who gets confused by changes at the head office&apos;, or &apos;a person who has been away from society and who doesn&apos;t know about current affairs or new technologies and feels that he or she has been left behind&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression is used in a masochistic way about &apos;a person who has lived abroad and become ignorant of Japanese fashion or felt awkward,&apos; &apos;a person who has just returned from his or her place of assignment and who gets confused by changes at the head office,&apos; or &apos;a person who has been away from society and who doesn&apos;t know about current affairs or new technologies and feels that he or she has been left behind.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="131">
<j>精神病院に長期間社会的入院を強いられていた患者が、退院した場合このような困難を経験することがあり、退院の際には入念なカウンセリングとトレーニングを受ける必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a patient who has been forced into social hospitalization in a mental hospital for a long period of time leaves the hospital, he or she sometimes experiences such troubles, so it is needed to receive careful counseling and training when he or she leaves the hospital</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a patient who has been forced into &apos;social hospitalization&apos; in a mental hospital for a long period of time leaves the hospital, he or she sometimes experiences such troubles, so it is necessary for them to receive careful counseling and training when leaving the hospital.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a patient who has been forced into &apos;social hospitalization&apos; in a mental hospital for a long period of time leaves the hospital, he or she sometimes experiences such troubles, so it is necessary for them to receive careful counseling and training when leaving the hospital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>これは長期間服役して出所した受刑者にもありえることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This also applies to a prisoner who has been released from the prison after serving a long sentence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This also applies to a prisoner who has been released from prison after serving a long sentence.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This also applies to a prisoner who has been released from prison after serving a long sentence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Eskimbot(id:29676), Tgmsito(id:15714), Kaihsu(id:219), Greenland4(id:114494), Hykw-a4(id:14184), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Yelm(id:33836), Dr jimmy(id:111486), TY(id:1386), Bact(id:20497), Bit(id:2197), Ｋｓ(id:15319), FlaBot(id:30804), Kouko0515(id:100370), GENMEI(id:31879), Excavator(id:25917), とらでじこ(id:11570), MlolM(id:24777), Nallimbot(id:230812), Areare(id:119960), Misakawa(id:208485), Hagaren(id:161278), Miketukunibito(id:9680), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), McBot(id:159617), Nekosuki600(id:21263), ウッでやんす高橋(id:11540), 唐棣色(id:64681), けんち(id:5147), 小太刀(id:18154), 特急東海(id:1014), BOTarate(id:185620), Suguri F(id:11127), Aotake(id:34929), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Punipico(id:25163), D.h(id:79056), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Tjan(id:17305), Qazzx(id:8772), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Su-no-G(id:52744), Kinori(id:443), Yan-er(id:125983), Chiew(id:39745), Loveless(id:129239), 曼珠沙華(id:26417), Belle Equipe(id:39537), Izayohi(id:13095), クロウ(id:21337), Law soma(id:45202), 表現等規制委員会(id:61918), Cooks(id:136468), Kamitani(id:30757), Kwakkun(id:19105), 新茶(id:157775), Bay Flam(id:34111), N yotarou(id:60870), Unamu(id:14627), Louperibot(id:128971), Trib(id:1441), Ogaki(id:173354), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>