<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>在原棟梁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ARIWARA no Muneyana</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ARIWARA no Muneyana</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ARIWARA no Muneyana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>在原 棟梁（ありわら の むねやな、生年不詳 - 昌泰元年（898年））は、平安時代前期の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ARIWARA no Muneyana (year of birth unknown-898) was kajin (a waka poet) in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ARIWARA no Muneyana (year of birth unknown-898) was kajin (a waka poet) in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ARIWARA no Muneyana (year of birth unknown - 898) was a waka poet in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>waka poet のみの表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は「むねはり」ともよむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first name is also called &quot;Munehari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first name is also called &quot;Munehari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first name is also called &quot;Munehari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は六歌仙・三十六歌仙の一人である在原業平。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was ARIWARA no Narihira who was one of Rokkasen (six best waka poets) and one of the 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was ARIWARA no Narihira who was one of Rokkasen (six best waka poets) and one of the 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was ARIWARA no Narihira who was one of Rokkasen (six best waka poets) and one of the Sanjurokkasen (36 Immortal Poets).</e>
<cmt>三十六歌仙　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に中古三十六歌仙の一人在原元方・藤原滋幹母（ふじわらしげもとのはは）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children include one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets ARIWARA no Motokata and the mother of FUJIWARA Shigemoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children include one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets ARIWARA no Motokata and the mother of FUJIWARA Shigemoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children include one of the Chuko sanjurokkasen (medieval 36 Immortal Poets) ARIWARA no Motokata and the mother of FUJIWARA no Shigemoto.</e>
<cmt>中古三十六歌仙　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>棟梁も中古三十六歌仙の一人に選ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneyana was also selected as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneyana was also selected as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneyana was also selected as one of the Chuko sanjurokkasen.</e>
<cmt>中古三十六歌仙　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>平城天皇の孫である在原業平の子であるが、官位に恵まれず従五位上筑前国守にとどまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his father was a grandchild of the Emperor Heizei, Muneyana&apos;s official court rank was not high and it remained Jugoinojo Chikuzen no kuni no Kami (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, an officer in charge of regional administration in Chikuzen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his father was a grandchild of the Emperor Heizei, Muneyana&apos;s official court rank was not high and it remained Jugoinojo Chikuzen no kuni no Kami (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, an officer in charge of regional administration in Chikuzen).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his father was a grandchild of the Emperor Heizei, Muneyana&apos;s official court rank was not high and it remained Jugoinojo Chikuzen no kuni no Kami (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, an officer in charge of regional administration in Chikuzen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>勅撰和歌集では、『古今和歌集』に4首、『後撰和歌集』に2首、『続後拾遺和歌集』に1首が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command): four poems for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), two poems for &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (the later selected collection of Japanese poetry), one poem for &quot;Shokugoshui wakashu&quot; (a kind of anthology of poems collected by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His waka poems were selected for chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command): four poems for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), two poems for &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (the later selected collection of Japanese poetry), and one poem for &quot;Shokugoshui wakashu&quot; (a kind of anthology of poems collected by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His waka poems were selected for Chokusen Wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command): four poems for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), two poems for &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry), and one poem for &quot;Shokugoshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Collection of Gleaning Continued).</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), ArthurBot(id:265089), Ks8823(id:130146), 与左衛門(id:159462), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>