<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>風雅和歌集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuga Wakashu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuga Wakashu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuga Wakashu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>風雅和歌集（ふうがわかしゅう）は第17勅撰集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuga Wakashu is the seventeenth Imperial anthology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuga Wakashu is the seventeenth Imperial anthology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuga Wakashu is the seventeenth Imperial anthology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>20巻、総歌数2211首。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of twenty volumes, including 2211 poems in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of twenty volumes, including 2211 poems in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of twenty volumes, including 2211 poems in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>構成上、先行する『玉葉和歌集』と異なるのは、春・秋を各三巻に増大した代わり、雑歌を玉葉の五巻から三巻に縮め、また賀歌を掉尾に置き換えたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure of the collection is different from preceding anthology &quot;Gyokuyo Wakashu&quot; (Jeweled Leaves Collection) in that it reduced five volumes of miscellaneous poems to three, increasing each volume of Spring and Winter to three books instead, and Gaka (Celebration Poetry) was replaced with Chobi.</e>
<cmt>掉尾の定訳不明のため、ローマ字表記にとどめてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure of the collection is different from the preceding anthology &quot;Gyokuyo Wakashu&quot; (Jeweled Leaves Collection) in that it reduced five volumes of miscellaneous poems to three, increasing each volume of Spring and Winter to three books instead, and Gaka (Celebration Poetry) was replaced with Chobi.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The differences in structure of the collection between Fuga Wakashu and the preceding anthology &quot;Gyokuyo Wakashu&quot; (Jeweled Leaves Collection) is that the compilers reduced five volumes of miscellaneous poems to three, increasing each volume of Spring and Autumn to three books instead, and moreover, a volume of Gaka (Celebration Poetry) was replaced with Chobi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>春・秋の歌各三巻という構成は『後撰和歌集』を模した可能性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is pointed out that the structure which has three volumes of either Spring and Winter would have been modeled after &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is pointed out that the structure which has three volumes for Spring and Winter would have been modeled after &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (A later collection of selected Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is pointed out that the structure which has three volumes for Spring and Autumn would have been modeled after &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (A later collection of selected Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>「秋」Winter→Autumn</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>貞和二年（1346年）頃、風雅集編纂のために貞和百首が詠進され、選考資料となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1346, 100 poems of Jowa were offered for reference in order to compile Fugashu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1346, 100 poems of Jowa were offered for reference in order to compile Fugashu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1346, 100 poems of Jowa were offered for reference in order to compile Fugashu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>北朝 (日本)の貞和二年（1346）十一月九日、竟宴が催され、同四年頃までに成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 9, 1346, a party after poetry&apos;s selection was held in the Northern Dynasty, so the anthology should have been completed by around 1348.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 9, 1346, a party after poetry selection was held in the Northern Dynasty, so the anthology should have been completed by around 1348.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 30, 1346 (Japanese Northern Dynasty), a party after poetry selection was held, therefore the anthology should have been completed by around 1348.</e>
<cmt>貞和は北朝の年号なので、（Japanese Northern Dynasty）としました。FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>学芸諸般に優れた花園天皇の監修のもと、光厳天皇が親撰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the supervision of Emperor Hanazono, who was excellent in various arts and sciences, Emperor Kogen selected poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the supervision of Emperor Hanazono, who was excellent in various arts and sciences, Emperor Kogen selected poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kogen selected poems under the supervision of Emperor Hanazono, who was excellent in arts and sciences.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正親町公蔭（京極為兼の養子）・藤原為基・冷泉為秀らが寄人を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinkage OGIMACHI (an adopted son of Tamekane KYOGOKU), FUJIWARA no Tamemoto, and Tamehide REIZEI were chosen members of compiling work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinkage OGIMACHI (an adopted son of Tamekane KYOGOKU), FUJIWARA no Tamemoto, and Tamehide REIZEI were chosen members for compiling work.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinkage OGIMACHI (an adopted son of Tamekane KYOGOKU), FUJIWARA no Tamemoto, and Tamehide REIZEI were chosen as members of the compiling work.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>真名序・仮名序は共に花園法皇の筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both manajo (a preface written in Chinese) and kanajo (Japanese preface) were written by Cloistered Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both manajo (a preface written in Chinese) and kanajo (Japanese preface) were written by Cloistered Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both manajo (a preface written in Chinese) and kanajo (Japanese preface) were written by Cloistered Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>二人の上皇が深く関わった、二十一代集の中でも特異な集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This anthology is distinctive among the Nijuichidai-shu (the twenty-one collections of waka compiled by imperial command) in that two Retired Emperors were involved in compilation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This anthology is distinctive among the Nijuichidai-shu (the twenty-one collections of waka compiled by imperial command) in that two Retired Emperors were involved in compilation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a unique anthology among the Nijuichidai-shu (the twenty-one collections of waka compiled by imperial command) because two Retired Emperors were involved in compilation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>仮名序によると、本来、「正しき風」（由緒正しい和歌の道）という意の「正風和歌集」に命名すべきところを、呉音で「傷風」に通じるのを忌み「風雅」に改めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the kanajo, it was originally planned to be called &apos;Shofu (正風) Wakashu&apos; which means &apos;right wind&apos; (historic pass for waka poetry), but it also could be called &apos;Shofu (傷風)&apos; in the Wu reading, so they changed it into &apos;Fuga.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the kanajo, it was originally planned to be called &apos;Shofu (正風) Wakashu&apos; which means &apos;right wind&apos; (historic pass for waka poetry), but it also could be called &apos;Shofu (傷風)&apos; in the Wu reading, so they changed it into &apos;Fuga.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the kanajo, it was originally planned to be called &apos;Shofu (正風) Wakashu&apos; which means &apos;right wind&apos; (historic pass for waka poetry), but it also could be called &apos;Shofu (傷風)&apos; (literally injured wind) in the Wu reading, so they changed it into &apos;Fuga&apos; to avoid the negative meaning.</e>
<cmt>「傷風」に英語の説明を付け加え、「忌み」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>持明院統の天皇による勅撰集では『玉葉集』に次ぎ、完成された京極派の歌風を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Imperial anthologies compiled by the Emperor from Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu), it inherited the perfect style of the Kyogoku school of poetry, following &quot;Gyokuyo shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Imperial anthologies compiled by the Emperor from Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu), it inherited the perfect style of the Kyogoku school of poetry, following &quot;Gyokuyo shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Imperial anthologies compiled by the Emperor from Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu), it inherited the perfect style of the Kyogoku school of poetry, following &quot;Gyokuyo shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>前期京極派の庇護者兼主将、伏見天皇（85首）と西園寺しょう子（68首）を筆頭に、上位入集歌人は花園院（54首）・京極為兼（52首）・京極為子（39首）の順に並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poems selected most were composed by Emperor Fushimi (85 poems), a patron and captain of early Kyogoku group, and the second most were by Shoshi SAIONJI (68 poems), followed by Hanazonoin (54 poems), Tamekane KYOGOKU (52 poems), and Tameko KYOGOKU (39 poems).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poems selected most were composed by Emperor Fushimi (85 poems), a patron and captain of the early Kyogoku group, and the second most were by Shoshi SAIONJI (68 poems), followed by Hanazonoin (54 poems), Tamekane KYOGOKU (52 poems), and Tameko KYOGOKU (39 poems).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poems selected most were composed by Emperor Fushimi (85 poems), a patron and captain of the early Kyogoku group, and the ones selected second most were by Shoshi SAIONJI (68 poems); the following are other poets whose poems dominate the top ranks: Hanazonoin (54 poems), Tamekane KYOGOKU (52 poems), and Tameko KYOGOKU (39 poems).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>花園院のほか、後伏見天皇・光厳院・徽安門院ら後期京極派の代表歌人も30首以上の入集を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More than thirty poems composed by representative poets of late Kyogoku group such as Emperor Gofushimi, Gokogenin, and Kianmonin were selected, as well as Hanazonoin&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More than thirty poems composed by representative poets of the later Kyogoku group, such as Emperor Gofushimi, Gokogenin, and Kianmonin were selected, as well as Hanazonoin&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More than 30 poems composed by representative poets of the later Kyogoku group such as Emperor Gofushimi, Kogonin, and Kianmonin were selected, as well as Hanazonoin&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお前代歌人では紀貫之・藤原俊成・藤原定家・後鳥羽天皇らが勅撰集の慣例に沿って尊重されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, poets in earlier period such as KI no Tsurayuki, FUJIWARA no Toshinari, FUJIWARA no Teika, Emperor Gotoba were treated with respect by custom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, poets in the earlier period such as KI no Tsurayuki, FUJIWARA no Toshinari, FUJIWARA no Teika, Emperor Gotoba were treated with respect by custom.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, poets who lived in the earlier period such as KI no Tsurayuki, FUJIWARA no Toshinari, FUJIWARA no Teika, Emperor Gotoba were treated with respect in accordance with custom of imperial anthology.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>玉葉・風雅は共に清新自然な風体を特色とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both anthologies of Gyokuyo and Fuga are characterized by its fresh and natural style, but Fuga shu are more intense, illustrating the distinctive character of dealing with contemplation of delicate nature and calm mind, reflecting the deep emotions of those who lived in a turbulent age of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both anthologies of Gyokuyo and Fuga are characterized by a fresh and natural style, but Fuga shu are more intense, illustrating the distinctive character of dealing with contemplation of delicate nature and calm mind, reflecting the deep emotions of those who lived in the turbulent age of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both anthologies of Gyokuyo and Fuga are characterized by the fresh and natural style.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>風雅集においてその純度は一層高く、繊細な自然観照と深沈な心境の描写を本領とし、南北朝の乱世に生きる人々の感慨を映している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuga shu, however, is more intense, and its distinctive characters are contemplation of delicate nature and description of calm mind, which reflect the deep emotions of those who lived in the turbulent age of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>閑寂な境界を現出した冬歌や、内省的な述懐歌に秀歌が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It contains a lot of Winter Poetry which presents the boundary of tranquility, excellent introspective Reminiscence Poetry, and even love poems have a feeling of melancholy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It contains a lot of Winter Poetry which presents the boundary of tranquility, excellent introspective Reminiscence Poetry, and even the love poems have a feeling of melancholy.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It contains a lot of Winter Poetry which express the boundary of tranquility and excellent introspective Reminiscence Poetry.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>恋歌にさえ孤独な哀感が漂う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even the love poems create melancholic atmosphere of loneliness.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>玉葉集同様、岩佐美代子氏による全注釈が笠間書院にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as Gyokuyo shu, an complete annotated edition of the anthology by Miyoko IWASA was published by Kasama Shoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well as Gyokuyo shu, a complete annotated edition of the anthology by Miyoko IWASA was published by Kasama Shoin.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A complete annotated edition of the anthology by Miyoko IWASA was published by Kasama Shoin, as well as Gyokuyo shu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また岩佐編で、次田香澄『玉葉集風雅集攷』もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there is a book called &quot;Gyokuyo Fugashu ko&quot; written by Kasumi TSUGITA and edited by IWASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there is a book called &quot;Gyokuyo Fugashu ko&quot; written by Kasumi TSUGITA and edited by IWASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there is a book called &quot;Gyokuyo Fugashu ko&quot; written by Kasumi TSUGITA and edited by IWASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Loveless(id:129239), Yume149(id:17504), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), SK(id:64397), 水野白楓(id:22811), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>