<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一代要記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichidai Yoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichidai Yoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichidai Yoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一代要記（いちだいようき）は、年代記の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichidai Yoki is one of the chronicles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichidai Yoki is one of the chronicles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichidai Yoki is one of the chronicles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>著者不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilers are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compilers are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compilers are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後宇多天皇の時に成立し、鎌倉時代末から南北朝時代 (日本)初期まで書き継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was brought into existence during the reign of Emperor Gouda, and had been written from the late Kamakura period to the beginning of the period of (Japanese) Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed during the reign of Emperor Gouda, and had been written from the late Kamakura period to the beginning of the period of (Japanese) Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>&quot;brought into existence&quot;-&quot;completed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed during the reign of Emperor Gouda, and had been written from the late Kamakura period to the beginning of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>南北朝の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>水戸徳川家による『大日本史』の史料探索中、延宝年間に金沢文庫本を発見し、10冊に書写して世間に流布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Mito Tokugawa family was searching for historical materials in &quot;Dainihon shi (Great History of Japan)&quot; during the Enpo era, the chronicle was found in the Kanazawa library and they made ten copies of the manuscript, which circulated among people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Mito Tokugawa family was searching for historical materials in Dainihon shi (Great History of Japan) during the Enpo era, the chronicle was found in the Kanazawa library and they made ten copies of the manuscript, which were put into circulation.</e>
<cmt>I thought &quot;which were put into circulation&quot; would read more naturally here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Mito Tokugawa family was searching for historical materials in &quot;Dainihon shi&quot; (Great History of Japan) during the Enpo era, the chronicle was found in the Kanazawa library and they made ten copies of the manuscript, which were put into circulation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>春夏秋冬の全4冊から成り（流布本は10巻）、その内訳は春冊が神代～醍醐天皇、夏冊が朱雀天皇～高倉天皇、秋冊が安徳天皇～後嵯峨天皇、冬冊が後深草天皇～花園天皇となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of four volumes of spring, summer, autumn, and winter (the popular edition consists of ten volumes): the volume of spring covers the periods from a mythological age to the reign of Emperor Daigo, the summer covers the reigns of Emperor Suzaku to Emperor Takakura, the autumn covers the reigns of Emperor Antoku to Emperor Gosaga, the winter covers the reigns of Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of four volumes of spring, summer, autumn, and winter (the popular edition consists of ten volumes): the volume of spring covers the periods from a mythological age to the reign of Emperor Daigo, the summer covers the reigns of Emperor Suzaku to Emperor Takakura, the autumn covers the reigns of Emperor Antoku to Emperor Gosaga, and the winter covers the reigns of Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>&quot;And the winter&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of four volumes of spring, summer, autumn, and winter (the popular edition consists of ten volumes): the volume of spring covers the periods from a mythological age to the reign of Emperor Daigo, the summer covers the reigns of Emperor Suzaku to Emperor Takakura, the autumn covers the reigns of Emperor Antoku to Emperor Gosaga, and the winter covers the reigns of Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、中間及び尾部を欠くため最後は明らかではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the middle and ending parts are missing so it is not clear when the last article was finished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the middle and ending parts are missing so it is not clear when the last article was finished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the middle and ending parts are missing so it is not clear when the last article was finished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>内容は書名のとおり、各天皇ごとに諡号あるいは追号を掲げて、略歴や在位中の出来事の摘要を編年体で記し、さらに太上天皇・皇太子・後宮・斎宮・摂関・大臣・大納言・参議・蔵人頭・皇子女などの各項を設けて、該当者の人名を記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the title of the book suggests, the book mentions each Emperor&apos;s posthumous name or the name bestowed after death which is followed by a brief biography, and the incidents that took place during his reign were written briefly in chronological order, and moreover there are categories of abdicated Emperor, Crown Prince, consorts of Emperor, the high priestess of Ise, Sekkan (Regent and Chancellor), Otodo (Minister), Dainagon (Major Councillor), Sangi (Councillor), Kuroudono kami, Prince and Princess, in which the name of the person in question is mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the title of the book suggests, the book mentions each Emperor&apos;s posthumous name or the name bestowed after death which is followed by a brief biography, and the incidents that took place during his reign were written briefly in chronological order, and moreover there are categories of abdicated Emperor, Crown Prince, consorts of Emperor, the high priestess of Ise, Sekkan (Regent and Chancellor), Otodo (Minister), Dainagon (Major Councillor), Sangi (Councillor), Kuroudono kami, Prince and Princess, in which the name of the person in question is mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the title of the book suggests, the book mentions each Emperor&apos;s posthumous name or the name bestowed after death which is followed by a brief biography, and the incidents that took place during his reign were written briefly in chronological order, and moreover there are categories of abdicated Emperor, Crown Prince, consorts of Emperor, the high priestess of Ise, Sekkan (Regent and Chancellor), Otodo (Minister), Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Sangi (Councillor), Kuroudono kami, Prince and Princess, in which the name of the person in question is mentioned.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Major Councillor&quot;→&quot;chief councilor of state&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>各天皇と皇子女が系線で結ばれ、一大皇室系図になっている特徴があるが、流布本の中には系線が略されているものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A genealogical table of Imperial family is featured in the book, in which Emperor and his sons and daughters are connected with lines, but in some popular editions the lines are omitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A genealogical table of Imperial family is featured in the book, in which the emperor and his sons and daughters are connected with lines, but in some popular editions the lines are omitted.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The emperor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A genealogical table of Imperial family is featured in the book, in which the emperor and his sons and daughters are connected with lines, but in some popular editions the lines are omitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>流布本の祖本である金沢文庫本は東山文庫に現存し、その断簡は高松宮が所蔵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book collected in the Kanazawa library, which was the original manuscript of the popular edition, is still extant in the Higashiyama library, and some fragments of the book are owned by Takamatsu no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book collected in the Kanazawa library, which was the original manuscript of the popular edition, is still extant in the Higashiyama library, and some fragments of the book are owned by Takamatsu no Miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book collected in the Kanazawa library, which was the original manuscript of the popular edition, is still extant in the Higashiyama library, and some fragments of the book are owned by Takamatsu no Miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、高松藩主松平頼恕は国学者の友安三冬らに命じて、本書の後を継ぐ『歴朝要紀』を編纂させ、朝廷に献上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorihiro MATSUDAIRA, Lord of Takamatsu Domain, ordered Mifuyu TOMOYASU, a scholar of Kokugaku (National Learning), to compile a sequel to this book called &quot;Rekicho Yoki&quot; and presented it to the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorihiro MATSUDAIRA, Lord of Takamatsu Domain, ordered Mifuyu TOMOYASU, a scholar of Kokugaku (National Learning), to compile a sequel to this book called Rekicho Yoki and he presented it to the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks. &quot;And he presented it&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorihiro MATSUDAIRA, Lord of Takamatsu Domain, ordered Mifuyu TOMOYASU, a scholar of Kokugaku (National Learning), to compile a sequel to this book called &quot;Rekicho Yoki&quot; and he presented it to the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>