<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五代帝王物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godai Teio Monogatari (Stories of Five Reigns and Their Emperors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godai Teio Monogatari (Stories of Five Reigns and Their Emperors)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godai Teio Monogatari (Stories of Five Reigns and Their Emperors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>『五代帝王物語』（ごだいていおうものがたり）は、鎌倉時代後期に書かれた編年体の歴史物語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godai Teio Monogatari is a historical tale which was written in the late Kamakura period and arranged in chronological order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godai Teio Monogatari is a historical tale which was written in the late Kamakura period and arranged in chronological order.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godai Teio Monogatari is a historical tale which was written in the late Kamakura period and arranged in chronological order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『五代記』・『五代王記』・『五代帝王記』などの異名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Godaiki,&quot; &quot;Godaioki,&quot; or &quot;Godai Teioki,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Godaiki,&quot; &quot;Godaioki,&quot; or &quot;Godai Teioki,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Godaiki,&quot; &quot;Godaioki,&quot; or &quot;Godai Teioki,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>作者は未詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>題名の「五代」とは、後堀河天皇・四条天皇・後嵯峨天皇・後深草天皇・亀山天皇の各天皇を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &apos;Godai&apos; included in the title refers to Emperor Gohorikawa, Emperor Shijo, Emperor Gosaga, Emperor Gofukakusa, and Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;Godai&apos; included in the title refers to Emperor Gohorikawa, Emperor Shijo, Emperor Gosaga, Emperor Gofukakusa, and Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Godai&apos; included in the title refers to the Emperor Gohorikawa, the Emperor Shijo, the Emperor Gosaga, the Emperor Gofukakusa, and the Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>Emperorの前にtheを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『六代勝事記』の後を継ぐ形式で執筆されているが、実際には最初の2代の天皇の記事が少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It followed the style of &quot;Rokudai Shojiki&quot; (war tales concerning six Emperors), but in fact, it does not have much articles about the first two Emperors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It followed the style of &quot;Rokudai Shojiki&quot; (war tales concerning six Emperors), but in fact, it does not have many articles about the first two Emperors.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It followed the style of &quot;Rokudai Shojiki&quot; (war tales concerning six Emperors), but in fact, it does not have many articles about the first two Emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>最後の亀山天皇の記事も後嵯峨法皇の葬儀に関する一連の行事とともに終えていることから、後嵯峨天皇（法皇）の側近による作品だと言う説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article about the last Emperor Kameyama ends with a series of event concerning Emperor Gosaga&apos;s funeral service, so there is an opinion that it was written by Emperor (Cloistered Emperor) Gosaga&apos;s close aide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The article about the last Emperor Kameyama ends with a series of events concerning Emperor Gosaga&apos;s funeral service, so there is an opinion that it was written by Emperor (Cloistered Emperor) Gosaga&apos;s close aide.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The article about the last Emperor Kameyama ends with a series of events concerning the Emperor Gosaga&apos;s funeral service, so there is an opinion that it was written by the Emperor (Cloistered Emperor) Gosaga&apos;s close aide.</e>
<cmt>Emperorの前にtheを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、のちに伏見天皇となる伏見天皇の存在（後深草天皇の子、亀山天皇の皇太子（後宇多天皇）の即位後、後深草上皇の働きかけで皇太子に立てられた）を知りながら、その存在を過小に書いていることから、著者を亀山天皇とその子孫である大覚寺統を支持していたと見る向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is a view that the author was somebody who supported Emperor Kameyama and his descendants, Daikakuji-to (Imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama), because the author did not pay much attention to Emperor Fushimi (a son of Emperor Gofukakusa; after the enthronement of the Crown Prince of Emperor Kameyama, he was made a new Crown Prince by retired Emperor Gofukakusa), although the author knew that he would be an Emperor later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there is a view that the author was somebody who supported Emperor Kameyama and his descendants, Daikakuji-to (Imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama), because the author did not pay much attention to Emperor Fushimi (a son of Emperor Gofukakusa; after the enthronement of the Crown Prince of Emperor Kameyama, he was made a new Crown Prince by retired Emperor Gofukakusa), although the author knew that he would be an Emperor later.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there is a view that the author was somebody who supported the Emperor Kameyama and his descendants, Daikakuji-to (Imperial lineage starting with the Emperor Kameyama), because the author did not pay much attention to the Emperor Fushimi (a son of the Emperor Gofukakusa; after the enthronement of the Crown Prince of the Emperor Kameyama, he was made a new Crown Prince by the retired Emperor Gofukakusa), although the author knew that he would be an Emperor later.</e>
<cmt>Emperorの前にtheを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、のちに『増鏡』が執筆された折に『五代帝王物語』を参照して描かれたと考えられる部分が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror), which was written in later years, contain a part that seems to be written, referring to &quot;Godai Teio Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror), which was written later, contains a part that seems to be written, referring to &quot;Godai Teio Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror), which was written later, contains a part that seems to be written, referring to &quot;Godai Teio Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), はやぶさ(id:236661), 頭痛(id:201680), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>