<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>百首歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Set of a Hundred Poems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Set of a Hundred Poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Set of a Hundred Poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>百首歌（ひゃくしゅうた）は、数を定めて詠う和歌（定数和歌）のひとつで、100首を単位として詠まれるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The set of a hundred poems consists of a unit of 100 poems, being a type of waka composed to make up a set of a predetermined number (set of waka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Set of One Hundred Poems (百首歌 Hyakushuta) consists of one hundred poems as a unit, which are a type of waka composed with a predetermined number.</e>
<cmt>added kanji and reading in parenthesis; capitalized &quot;The Set of One Hundred Poems&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakushuuta (The Set of One Hundred Poems, 百首歌) consists of one hundred poems as a unit, which are a type of waka composed with a predetermined number.</e>
<cmt>文頭の表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>単に百首ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also simply referred to as the one hundred poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also simply referred to as &quot;One Hundred Poems.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing and added quotation marks to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also simply referred to as &quot;One Hundred Poems.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1人で100首を詠んだものと、複数の人が詠んだものを100首集めたものに分けることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The set of a hundred poems can be broken down into 2 types including the set of one hundred poems composed by an individual poet and the other which is a collection of a hundred poems composed by a number of poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Set of One Hundred Poems can be broken down into two types, including a set of poems composed by an individual poet and a set which is a collection of poems by a number of poets.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally and less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Set of One Hundred Poems can be broken down into two types, including a set of poems composed by an individual poet and a set which is a collection of poems by a number of poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1人で詠んだ百首歌は960年（天徳4年）曾禰好忠の家集「曾丹集」のなかの『百ちの歌』に始まるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the first set of a hundred poems by individual poet was百ちの歌 composed in 960 which was included in Sotanshu, the personal collection of poetry of SONE no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>『百ちの歌』　－読み・定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the first set of one hundred poems by an individual poet was &quot;Hyakuchi no Uta&quot; (百ちの歌) composed in 960 as part of the Sotanshu, the personal poetry collection of SONE no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>I do not know how to read &quot;百ちの歌&quot; either, but simply putting the kanji in the middle of the sentence does nothing but confuse an English reader, so I made a guess at the reading and added parenthesis; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the first set of one hundred poems by an individual poet was &quot;Hyakuchi no Uta&quot; (百ちの歌) composed in 960 as part of the &apos;Sotanshu,&apos; the personal poetry collection of SONE no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>複数の歌人による百首歌は、1105年（長治2年）～1106年（長治3年）頃堀河天皇に奏覧された「堀河院御時百首和歌」が最初とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the first set of a hundred poems written by a number of poets was the One Hundred Waka of the Horikawa-In Era submitted to Emperor Horikawa around 1105 to 1106.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first set of one hundred poems written by a number of poets is presumed to be the &quot;One Hundred Waka of the Horikawa-in Era,&quot; which was submitted to Emperor Horikawa at around 1105 to 1106.</e>
<cmt>fixed to avoid redundancy with the previous sentence; fixed grammar to read more naturally; added parenthesis for the title of the collection of poems</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first set of one hundred poems written by a number of poets is presumed to be the &apos;One Hundred Waka of the Horikawa-in Era,&apos; which was submitted to Emperor Horikawa at around 1105 to 1106.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原公実ら16人によって進詠されたもので以後の組題による百首歌の手本となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The One Hundred Waka of the Horikawa-In Era consisted of waka written by 16 poets including FUJIWARA no Kinzane which became the model for the subsequent sets of a hundred poems on set topics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This collection of one hundred poems consisted of waka written by 16 poets, including FUJIWARA no Kinzane, and became the model for subsequent collections with set topics.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; added commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This collection of one hundred poems consisted of waka written by 16 poets, including FUJIWARA no Kinzane, and became the model for subsequent collections with set topics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>中世以後は、勅撰和歌集を撰出する際の基礎資料として主要な歌人に百首を詠進させるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequent to the medieval times, it became a practice for leading poets of the time to submit 100 poems as baseline material when selecting waka for the Chokusen Wakashu (waka anthology compiled by Imperial command), whereas, the one hundred poem sequences written by an individual poet were composed for the other purposes such as training and to dedicate to shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following medieval times, it became a practice for leading poets to submit one hundred poems as baseline material when selecting waka for the Chokusen Wakashu (Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry compiled by Imperial command). One hundred poem sequences written by an individual poet, on the other hand, were composed for other purposes, such as training and dedicating them to shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>I could not comfortably keep this as one sentence, so I split it into two and fixed the grammar accordingly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following medieval times, it became a practice for leading poets to submit one hundred poems as baseline material when selecting waka for the Chokusen Wakashu (Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>NCのコメントに応じて、原文を分け、英文も分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一方、個人による百首は作歌の練習や社寺への奉納などの目的で詠まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One hundred poem sequences written by an individual poet, on the other hand, were composed for other purposes, such as training and dedicating them to shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>NCのコメントに応じて、原文を分け、英文も分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), 水澤蒼一郎(id:220700), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>