<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御製</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyosei (Poems or Songs Written by the Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyosei (Poems or Songs Written by the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyosei</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、補足は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御製（ぎょせい）とは、天皇や皇帝、また皇族が手ずから書いたり作ったりした文章（政令の類は除く）・詩歌・絵画などをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyosei refers to documents (except for decrees), poems and paintings that have been personally written or created by the emperors and royal family members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyosei refers to documents (aside from decrees), poems and paintings that have been personally written or created by emperors or royal family members.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyosei refers to documents (aside from decrees), poems and paintings that have been personally written or created by emperors or royal family members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では、御製というと一般に天皇が詠んだ和歌のことをいうことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, however, gyosei generally refers to the poems composed by the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within Japan, the term gyosei is generally used to refer to waka (poems) composed by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>added waka parethesis around (poems); eliminated &quot;however&quot; since there is no direct contrast with the previous sentence being made</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Japan, the term gyosei is generally used to refer to waka (poems) composed by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>代表的な作品として唐の太宗 (唐)の手になる大慈恩寺・大雁塔に刻された「聖教序」（御製御書）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative gyosei include Shuji Shogyojo (the writing in the emperor&apos;s hand) by Taiso, Tang tai zong (Tang) which was engraved on Daigando at Daijion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exemplary works of gyosei include the Shuji Shogyojo (writing done by the emperor&apos;s hand) by Taiso and Tang Tai Zong (Tang) that was engraved on the Daigando at the Daijon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exemplary works of gyosei include the &apos;Shogyojo&apos; (writing done by the emperor&apos;s hand) by Taiso (Tang tai zong), that was engraved on the Daiganto at the Daijion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本では天皇および皇室、皇族に関する敬語の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan gyosei is an honorific expressions used in relation to the emperor, Imperial Family and royalties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, gyosei is an honorific expression used in reference to the emperor, Imperial family and other royalites.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar errors; added comma; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, gyosei is an honorific expression used in reference to the emperor, Imperial Family and other royalties.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Uhock(id:86695), Phew(id:74086), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Dream100(id:41924), 愛国の歌人(id:173428), Ziksy(id:84091), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>