<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>将門記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomonki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomonki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomonki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『将門記』（しょうもんき）は、10世紀半ばに東国でおこった平将門の乱の顛末を描いた初期軍記物語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shomonki&quot; is an early war chronicle that describes details of the TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War which occurred in the Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) in thee middle of Tenth Century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shomonki&quot; is an early war chronicle that details TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War, which occurred in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region) in the middle of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shomonki&quot; is an early war chronicle that details TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War, which occurred in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region) in the middle of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outlines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他のトピックと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>将門記の原本とされるものは残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No original copy of Shomonki remained.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No original copy of Shomonki remains in existence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no extant copies of the Shomonki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『大須観音本』と『楊守敬旧蔵本』の二つの写本があるが、いずれも冒頭部分が失われており、本来の題名はわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two manuscripts, &quot;Osukannon bon&quot; and &quot;Yang Shoujing kyuzobon&quot; (book once possessed by Yang Shoujing), the beginning part of both books were lost and, therefore, original names cannot be identified.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two manuscripts, &quot;Osukannon bon&quot; and &quot;Yang Shoujing kyuzobon&quot; (a book once possessed by Yang Shoujing), but the beginning parts of both books were lost; consequently, the original names cannot be identified.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two manuscripts are extant, the &quot;Osukannon bon&quot; and the &quot;Yang Shoujing kyuzobon&quot; (so named because it was once owned by Yang Shoujing), but the beginning sections of both manuscripts have been lost, and consequently, the original titles cannot be verified.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代頃には「将門合戦章」、「将門合戦状」と呼ばれたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the Kamakura Period, it seems that it was called &quot;Shomon Kassen Sho [将門合戦章 正しい読み不明]&quot; or &quot;Shomon Kassen Jo [将門合戦状 正しい読み不明].&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apparently, around the Kamakura period it was called &quot;Shomon Kassen Sho [将門合戦章 正しい読み不明]&quot; or &quot;Shomon Kassen Jo [将門合戦状 正しい読み不明].&quot;</e>
<cmt>c</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that during the Kamakura period, it was referred to as the &quot;Shomon kassen sho&quot; or the &quot;Shomon kassen jo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>平将門が一族の私闘から国家への反逆に走って最後に討ち取られるまでと、死後に地獄から伝えたという｢冥界消息｣が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story in which TAIRA no Masakado escalated from strife within the family to revolt against the state and finally he was killed and &quot;information from underworld&quot; which Masakado conveyed from hell after his death are recorded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story is a record of TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s escalation from strife within the family to revolt against the state and his ultimate death and &quot;information from the underworld,&quot; which Masakado conveyed from hell after his death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book chronicles TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s downward spiral from intra-family strife to full-fledged rebellion against the state, also depicting his final moments and death and even beyond, recording as it does the so-called &quot;message from the underworld&quot; he is said to have sent after his death from hell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>『真福寺本』は名古屋市の真福寺に伝わるもので、1099年に書き写したという意味の奥書がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sinpukuji bon&quot; has been handed down by the Shinpuku-ji Temple and it has a postscript that it was transcribed in 1099.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shinpukuji bon&quot; has been handed down by the Shinpuku-ji Temple, and it bears a postscript stating that it was transcribed in 1099.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shinpukuji bon&quot; has been handed down by the Shinpuku-ji Temple in Nagoya City, and it bears a postscript stating that it was transcribed in 1099.</e>
<cmt>名古屋市　追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>整った字体や文章で誤字や訂正も少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form of character is well balanced and error and correction is not many.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The character formation is well balanced, and there are few errors or corrections.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese characters are well-formed and the composition as a whole well-ordered, with few errors or corrections.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『楊守敬旧蔵本』は、明治時代初期に来日した清国の楊守敬が所持していたとされるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yang Shoujing kyuzobon&quot; is told that it was possessed by Yang Shoujin from Quin, who came to Japan at the beginning of the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yang Shoujing kyuzobon&quot; is said to have been held by Yang Shoujin from Quin, who came to Japan at the beginning of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Yang Shoujin kyuzobon&quot; is said to have been owned by Yang Shoujing of Qing-dynasty China; Yang came to Japan at the beginning of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>真福寺本に比べて欠落部分が多く、筆蹟も奔放で訂正加筆が目立ち、内容も異なる部分が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to Shinpukuji-bon, many parts are missing and handwriting is wild and corrections are remarkable and there are many different parts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to Shinpukuji-bon, many parts are missing and the handwriting is wild; the corrections are remarkable, and there are many different parts.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to the Shinpukuji bon, there are many missing sections and the handwriting is extravagant and unrestrained; later corrections and additions stand out dramatically from the rest of the text, and many sections actually differ in content as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>研究者によっては真福寺本より数十年古いとする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, certain researchers have opinion that it is older than Shinpukuji bon for several tens of years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, certain researchers have offered the opinion that it&apos;s several decades older than Shinpukuji bon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, certain researchers have offered the opinion that it&apos;s several decades older than Shinpukuji bon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>いずれも巻首部分が欠落しているが、抄本将門記略などから、将門一族の対立抗争の経緯が叙述されていたものと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first page of the book is missing in both books, but, judging from Shohon Shomonki Ryaku (abridged version of Shomonki), it is surmised that details of conflicts in Masakado&apos;s family was described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first page of the book is missing in both books, but judging from Shohon Shomonki Ryaku (abridged version of Shomonki) it is surmised that the details of conflicts in Masakado&apos;s family were described.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The initial section is missing from both manuscripts, but judging from the Shohon shomonki ryaku (an abridged version of the Shomonki), it is possible to infer that the beginning of the book described the details of internecine strife in Masakado&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>文体は両本とも、和風の強い変体漢文で記された巻本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of them are bound books written in strongly japanized variant of Chinese language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of them are bound books written in a strongly Japanese-inflected variant of Chinese.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of literary style, both manuscripts are written in an abnormal kanbun (Sino-Japanese) script that shows strong influence from Japanese.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>作者・成立年代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Author and the time of formation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Author and the time of formation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Who wrote it and when</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>作者・成立年代も不明で、諸説入り乱れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author and the time of formation are not known, and there are many contradicting views.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author and time of formation aren&apos;t known, and there are many contradicting views in this regard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neither the author nor the date of writing is known, and opposing theories abound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>平将門の乱の一部始終を詳細に書き綴っていること、仏教的な世界観や挿話がある点から、将門の近くにいた僧侶が作者であるとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view that the author is a priest who was close to Masakado because every details of the TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War were fully described and there are a view of the world from and episodes based on Buddhist point of view..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a view that the author was a priest who was close to Masakado, because every detail of TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War is fully described and there are views of the world from and episodes based on the Buddhist perspective.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory holds that the author must have been a Buddhist priest who was close to Masakado, because the author gave a very detailed account of TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s Rebellion and because both the general worldview expressed and certain specific episodes reveal a Buddhist perspective.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>公文書類に基づいた記述があることに注目して、朝廷にいた貴族ではないかとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another view that the author is a noble in the Imperial Court because there are descriptions based on official documents.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another view that the author was a noble in the Imperial Court, because there are descriptions based on official documents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory argues that, because some descriptions are based on official documents, the author may well have been a nobleman in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その他もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are still different views.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are still different views.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are still different views.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>成立年代も、巻末に「天慶3年6月記文｣とあることで、将門死去の直後に書かれたとする説が明治時代以来支配的であったが、昭和に入り、この記年は冥界消息に付随する虚構であるとの指摘がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the time of formation, as it is written at the end of the book as &quot;written in June 940&quot;, the view that it was written immediately after Masakado&apos;s death was dominant since the Meiji Era, but, after it became Showa, it was pointed that this indication of year is a fiction attached to the information from year the underworld.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the time of its creation, since it is written at the end of the book as &quot;written in June 940,&quot; the view that it was written immediately after Masakado&apos;s death has predominated since the Meiji period, but since the dawn of the Showa period it has been pointed that this indication of year is a piece of fiction attached to the information from the year of the underworld.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for when it was written, at the very end of the manuscripts there is a note that it was &quot;written in the sixth month of 940,&quot; so the theory that it was written immediately after Masakado&apos;s death predominated beginning in the Meiji period, but since entering the Showa period, the viewpoint has emerged that argues this date was actually a fabrication that is supposed to be attached to Masakado&apos;s message from the underworld.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>他に、末法を示す記述が見られる点から、1052年以降の成立ではないかとする研究者もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are researchers who consider that the formation was on or after 1052 because there is a description showing Mappo (Age of the Final Dharma).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are researchers who consider that the work was created in or after 1052, because there is a description showing Mappo (Age of the Final Dharma).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some researchers, noting that the work also depicts Mappo (the final, decadent age in Buddhist cosmology), believe that it must have been written no earlier than 1052.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>多くの大学受験参考書では鎌倉時代の成立とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many study aids for university entrance test say formation was in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many study aids for the university entrance exam say it was created in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many university entrance exam study guides claim it was written during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>八幡神と武家政権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachimanjin (the god of Hachiman-gu Shrine) and military government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachimanjin (the god of Hachiman-gu Shrine) and military government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachimanjin (the god of Hachiman-gu Shrine) and military government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>平将門は『将門記』では939年に上野国の国庁で八幡大菩薩よりの神託をうけて「新皇」を自称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shomonki&quot;, TAIRA no Masakado received an oracle from Hachiman Daibosatsu (Great Bodhisattava Hachiman) in 939 at the kokucho (office of local government) and called himself &quot;Shinno&quot; (new emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shomonki,&quot; TAIRA no Masakado received an oracle from Hachiman Daibosatsu (Great Bodhisattva Hachiman) in 939 at the kokucho (office of local government) and called himself &quot;Shinno&quot; (new emperor).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shomonki,&quot; TAIRA no Masakado received an oracle from Hachiman Daibosatsu (Great Bodhisattva Hachiman) in 939 at the kokucho (office of local government) and called himself &quot;Shinno&quot; (new emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>このように八幡神は武家を王朝的秩序から解放し、天照大神とは異なる世界を創る大きな役割があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown here, Hachimanjin had an important role to release samurai from the order of Imperial Court and create a world which is different from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown here, Hachimanjin had an important role in releasing samurai from the orders of the Imperial Court and creating a world that was different from that of Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown here, Hachimanjin had an important role in releasing samurai from the orders of the Imperial Court and creating a world that was different from that of Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>武家が守護神として八幡神を奉ずる理由であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the reason why samurai believed in Hachimanjin as a guardian god.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason samurai believed in Hachimanjin as a guardian god.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was why the warrior class believed in the god Hachiman and took him to be a guardian deity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 エコとんぼ(id:235781), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Lobbyonce(id:195963), Rupert660(id:93405), Nakadati(id:26815), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Ko-ken(id:49348), 水野白楓(id:22811), 相馬小次郎(id:188976), こぶまき(id:38278), Memosa(id:131221), 蔭人(id:80171), MASAKADO(id:205056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>