<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本後紀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon Skoki History Book</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC%E5%BE%8C%E7%B4%80&amp;stype=1&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonkoki History Book</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonkoki History Book</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本後紀（にほんこうき）は、平安時代初期に編纂された勅撰史書で、続日本紀に続く六国史の第三にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonkoki History Book is a collection of history books by Imperial command and was compiled in the early Heian era after Shoku-Nihongi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan), being the third volume of Rikkokushi (Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt>続日本紀の訳語は〔新和英大事典（研究社）〕六国史の訳語は〔ルミナス和英辞典（研究社）〕</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonkoki History Book&quot; is a collection of histories created by Imperial command; it was compiled in the early Heian era after Shoku-Nihongi (&quot;Continuation of &apos;Chronicles of Japan&apos;),&quot; being the third volume of Rikkokushi (Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonkoki History Book is a collection of histories created by imperial command; it was compiled in the early Heian period after Shoku-Nihongi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan), being the third volume of Rikkokushi (Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt>era →period　（他の「記事と統一）　&quot;&quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>承和 (日本)7年 (840年) に完成し、延暦11年 (792年) から天長10年 (833年) に至る42年間を記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in 840, and contains records of the events which had taken place for 42 years, from 792 to 833.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completed in 840, it contains records of events that occurred over a period of 42 years, from 792 to 833.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Completed in 840, it contains records of events that occurred over a period of 42 years, from 792 to 833.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>編者は藤原緒嗣ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Otsugu and others compiled it.</e>
<cmt>http://spysee.jp/藤原緒嗣</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Otsugu and others compiled it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Otsugu and others compiled it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>編年体、漢文、全40巻（現存10巻）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was arranged in chronological order, written in Chinese, and a 40-volume book (10 of them are extant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Written in Chinese, it was arranged in chronological order and comprised 40-volumes, 10 of which are extant.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Written in Chinese, it was arranged in chronological order and comprised 40-volumes, 10 of which are extant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>編纂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compilation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compilation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compilation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>序文によれば、弘仁10年 (819年)、嵯峨天皇が、藤原冬嗣、藤原緒嗣、藤原貞嗣、良岑安世に勅して編纂を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the preface, Saga Emperor ordered FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, FUJIWARA no Otsugu, FUJIWARA no Sadatsugu, and YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo to compile the history book in 819.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E5%B5%AF%E5%B3%A8%E5%A4%A9%E7%9A%87&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2http://spysee.jp/藤原冬嗣http://spysee.jp/藤原貞嗣http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E8%89%AF%E5%B2%91%E5%AE%89%E4%B8%96&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2「○○天皇」という表記は、「○○emperor」よりも「emperor ○○」の方が多いようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the preface, in 819 Emperor Saga ordered FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, FUJIWARA no Otsugu, FUJIWARA no Sadatsugu and YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo to compile the history book.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the preface, in 819 Emperor Saga ordered FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, FUJIWARA no Otsugu, FUJIWARA no Sadatsugu and YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo to compile the history book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>未了のまま緒嗣を除く三人が死んだため、後に淳和天皇が詔して清原夏野、直世王、藤原吉野、小野岑守、坂上今継、島田清田に続行を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because all of them except Otsugu died before completing the work, Junna Emperor ordered KIHOYARA no Natsuno, Naoyo-o, FUJIWARA no Yoshino, ONO no Minemori, SAKANOUE no Imatsugu, and SHIMADA no Kiyota to continue it.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E6%B7%B3%E5%92%8C%E5%A4%A9%E7%9A%87&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E6%B8%85%E5%8E%9F%E5%A4%8F%E9%87%8E&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2http://spysee.jp/藤原吉野http://spysee.jp/小野岑守http://chiezou.jp/word/島田+清田</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because all of them except Otsugu died before completing the work, Junna Emperor ordered KIHOYARA no Natsuno, Naoyo-o, FUJIWARA no Yoshino, ONO no Minemori, SAKANOUE no Imatsugu and SHIMADA no Kiyota to continue the project.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because all of them except Otsugu died before the work could be completed, Emperor Junna ordered KIYOHARA no Natsuno, Naoyo-o, FUJIWARA no Yoshino, ONO no Minemori, SAKANOUE no Imatsugu and SHIMADA no Kiyota to continue the project.</e>
<cmt>Emperor Junnaとしました。 KIYOHARAとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仁明天皇の代になってさらに詔して藤原緒嗣、源常、藤原吉野、藤原良房、朝野鹿取に遂行を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of Ninmyo Emperor, more people such as FUJIWARA no Otsugu, MINAMOTO no Tokiwa, FUJIWARA no Yoshino, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, and ASANO no Katori were called to carry out the work.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E4%BB%81%E6%98%8E%E5%A4%A9%E7%9A%87&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2http://spysee.jp/%E6%BA%90%E5%B8%B8http://spysee.jp/藤原良房http://www.shogakukan.co.jp/koten/86.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of Emperor Ninmyo, more people such as FUJIWARA no Otsugu, MINAMOTO no Tokiwa, FUJIWARA no Yoshino, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and ASANO no Katori were called to carry out the work.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Ninmyo, more people such as FUJIWARA no Otsugu, MINAMOTO no Tokiwa, FUJIWARA no Yoshino, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and ASANO no Katori were called to carry out the work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>さらに後、布瑠高庭と山田古嗣を加え、承和7年12月9日（841年1月5日）にようやく完成を報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, FURU no Takaniwa and YAMATA no Furutsugu joined the compilation, and at last the book was completed on January 5, 841.</e>
<cmt>http://www.maff.go.jp/chushi/a/kyoku/jigyou/suiri/yoshino/3/colum1.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, FURU no Takaniwa and YAMATA no Furutsugu joined the compilation, and at last the book was completed on January 5, 841.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, FURU no Takaniwa and YAMATA no Furutsugu joined the compilation, and at last the book was completed on January 5, 841.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>編纂までにかかった期間は21年間、三代の天皇にわたる事業にずっと携わったのは、藤原緒嗣一人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took 21 years to compile the book, and it was only FUJIWARA no Otsugu who had been involved in the whole project over the 3 generations of the emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took 21 years to compile the book, but only FUJIWARA no Otsugu had been involved in the whole project over the three generations of emperors.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took 21 years to compile the book, but only FUJIWARA no Otsugu had been involved in the whole project over the three generations of emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『続日本紀』の後をうけて、桓武天皇の治世の途中から、平城天皇、嵯峨天皇、淳和天皇の治世を記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following &quot;Shoku-Nihongi,&quot; the book contains records of the reigns of Kanmu Emperor, Heizei Emperor, Saga Emperor, and Junna Emperor.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E5%B9%B3%E5%9F%8E%E5%A4%A9%E7%9A%87&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following &quot;Shoku-Nihongi,&quot; the book contains records of the reigns of emperors Kanmu, Heizei, Saga and Junna.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following &quot;Shoku-Nihongi,&quot; the book contains records of the reigns of emperors Kanmu, Heizei, Saga and Junna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>15世紀初め頃までは40巻揃っていたが、その後散逸し、塙保己一の門人、稲山行教が10巻分の写本を三条西家で発見（異説として柳原紀光の校訂本説もある）し、初めて刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until around the early 15th century, the whole 40 volumes of Nihonkoki History Book had existed, but afterward some volumes were dispersed and lost. Yukinori INAYAMA, one of the disciples of Hokinoichi HANAWA, found 10 volumes of the manuscript at the SANJONISHI Family residence and published them for the first time. (There is a different view that the published volumes were based on Norimitsu/Motomitsu YANAGIHARA&apos;s recension)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処http://spysee.jp/塙保己一http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E4%B8%89%E6%9D%A1%E8%A5%BF&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2http://spysee.jp/柳原紀光</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until about the early fifteenth century, all 40 volumes of Nihonkoki History Book were in existence, but eventually certain volumes were dispersed and lost; however, Yukinori INAYAMA, one of the disciples of Hokinoichi HANAWA, found 10 volumes of the manuscript at the residence of the SANJONISHI Family and published them for the first time. There is an opposing view that the published volumes were based on Norimitsu/Motomitsu YANAGIHARA&apos;s recension.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until about the early fifteenth century, all 40 volumes of Nihonkoki History Book were in existence, but eventually certain volumes were dispersed and lost; however, Yukinori INAYAMA, one of the disciples of Hokinoichi HANAWA, found 10 volumes of the manuscript at the residence of the Sanjonishi family and published them for the first time (There is an opposing view that the published volumes were based on Norimitsu/Motomitsu YANAGIHARA&apos;s recension.).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>現存分は巻5・8・12・13（桓武）、14・17（平城）、20・21・22・24（嵯峨）の10巻で、淳和天皇の代はまったく欠けてしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10 Existing volumes are Vol. 5, 8, 12, 13 (Kanmu), 14, 17 (Heizei), 20, 21, 22, 24 (Saga), and all the volumes about Junna Emperor are missing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 10 existing volumes are numbers 5, 8, 12, 13 (Kanmu), 14, 17 (Heizei), 20, 21, 22 and 24 (Saga); all the volumes about Emperor Junna are missing.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 10 existing volumes are numbers 5, 8, 12, 13 (Kanmu), 14, 17 (Heizei), 20, 21, 22 and 24 (Saga); all the volumes about Emperor Junna are missing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>六国史等の抜粋版である『日本紀略』と、六国史の項目分類である『類聚国史』の引用から本文をある程度復元できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possible to some extent to restore the text by gathering quotations from &quot;Nihonki ryaku (The Abbreviated History of Japan),&quot; extracts from Rikkokushi, and &quot;Ruiju kokushi (History book),&quot; a categorized Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt>「日本紀略」の訳語出典→研究社Online Dictionaryhttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E9%A1%9E%E8%81%9A%E5%9B%BD%E5%8F%B2&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is to some extent possible to restore the text by gathering quotations from &quot;Nihonki ryaku (The Abbreviated History of Japan),&quot; extracts from Rikkokushi and &quot;Ruiju kokushi (History Book),&quot; a categorized Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is to some extent possible to restore the text by gathering quotations from &quot;Nihongi ryaku (The Abbreviated History of Japan),&quot; extracts from Rikkokushi and &quot;Ruiju kokushi (History Book),&quot; a categorized Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt>Nihongi ryakuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>各所の逸文を収集したものに『日本逸史』『日本後紀逸文』があり、これを踏まえて、下記の集英社訳注日本史料や講談社学術文庫が出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon isshi History Book&quot; and &quot;Unknown or Lost Writings of &apos;Nihonkoki History Book&apos;&quot; are the collections of the lost texts of &quot;Nihonkoki History Book,&quot; and based on them the following books were published: Japanese historical records commentary, Shueisha Inc. and Academic paperback library, Kodansha Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC%E9%80%B8%E5%8F%B2&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E9%80%B8%E6%96%87&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2http://www.shueisha.co.jp/http://www.kodansha.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon isshi History Book&quot; and &quot;Unknown or Lost Writings of the Nihonkoki History Book&quot; are the collections of the lost texts of &quot;Nihonkoki History Book,&quot; and based on them the following books were published: Japanese Historical Records Commentary (Shueisha Inc.) and Academic Paperback Library (Kodansha Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon isshi History Book&quot; and &quot;Unknown or Lost Writings of the Nihonkoki History Book&quot; are the collections of the lost texts of Nihonkoki History Book, and with them as a basis the following books were published: &quot;Japanese Historical Records Commentary,&quot; from Shueisha Inc., and &quot;Academic Paperback Library,&quot; from Kodansha Ltd.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>内容には藤原緒嗣の意見がもっとも反映されたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the contents of the book reflected opinions of FUJIWARA no Otsugu most.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the contents of the book generally reflected the opinions of FUJIWARA no Otsugu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the contents of the book generally reflected the opinions of FUJIWARA no Otsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天皇・廷臣の死亡記事に短い伝記（薨伝）を付けたことは『続日本紀』にならい、後続の史書と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just like &quot;Shoku-Nihongi,&quot; short biographies called Koden was added to the obituaries of the emperors and retainers of Imperial Court, which was the same style of the following history books.</e>
<cmt>http://www001.upp.so-net.ne.jp/densetutanbo/tamuramaro/ryakuden.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As was the case with &quot;Shoku-Nihongi,&quot; short biographies called koden were added to the obituaries of the emperors and retainers of the Imperial Court, which was the same approach seen in the subsequent history books.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As was the case with &quot;Shoku-Nihongi,&quot; short biographies called koden were added to the obituaries of the emperors and retainers of the Imperial Court, which was the same approach seen in the subsequent history books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし本書の薨伝は一方的・公式的な礼賛や非難に流れず、独特の批評や感想を交えた興味深い記述が多く、六国史の中では批判精神を堅持したものとして異色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Koden in this book was neither a mere praise nor a criticism, but an interesting description interweaved with a unique comment and impression, and because of its critical spirit, the book was unusual among Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the koden in this book was neither simple praise nor criticism; instead it was an interesting description interwoven with a unique comment and impression, and because of its critical spirit the book was unusual among Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the koden in this book was neither mere praise nor criticism, but was instead full of interesting descriptions interwoven with unique comments and impressions, and because of its critical spirit the book was unusual among Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt>「(記述が）多く」の意味見合いを訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>また六国史の中では前後の史書に比べ和歌を多く収録していたことが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is known that compared with the volumes compiled before and after the book, it contained more Waka/Yamatouta poems than the other volumes of Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is known that compared with the volumes compiled before and after the book, it contained more Waka/Yamatouta poems than the other volumes of Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is known that compared with the volumes compiled before and after the book, it contained more Waka/Yamatouta poems than the other volumes of Rikkokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Lonicera(id:20638), Safkan(id:423), Auf(id:633), Kinori(id:443), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>