<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊勢物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise Monogatari (The Tales of Ise)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise Monogatari (The Tales of Ise)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise Monogatari</e>
<cmt>(The Tales of Ise)説明が続くので、削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『伊勢物語』（いせものがたり）は、平安時代初期に成立した歌物語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise) is a poem-tale completed in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise) is a poetry narrative completed in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise) is a poetry narrative completed in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『在五が物語』、『在五中将物語』、『在五中将の日記』とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Zaigo), &quot;Zaigo Chujo Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Lieutenant General Zaigo) or &quot;Zaigo Chujo no Nikki&quot; (the Dairy of Lieutenant General Zaigo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Zaigo), &quot;Zaigo Chujo Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Lieutenant General Zaigo) or &quot;Zaigo Chujo no Nikki&quot; (the Dairy of Lieutenant General Zaigo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Zaigo), &quot;Zaigo Chujo Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Lieutenant General Zaigo) or &quot;Zaigo Chujo no Nikki&quot; (the Dairy of Lieutenant General Zaigo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>全125段からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; consists of 125 chapters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; consists of 125 chapters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; consists of 125 chapters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ある男の元服から死にいたるまでを和歌と歌に添えた物語によって描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It tells of the story of a man from his coming of age to death through verses and songs with accompanying prose narratives.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It tells the story of a man from his coming of age to death through verses and songs with accompanying prose narratives.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It tells the story of a man from his coming of age to death through verses and songs with accompanying prose narratives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>歌人在原業平の和歌を多く採録し、主人公を業平の異名で呼んだりしている（第63段）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It includes many of waka poems by the poet ARIWARA no Narihira and the hero is called by his cognomen (Chapter 63).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It includes many waka poems by the poet ARIWARA no Narihira and the hero is called by his cognomen (Chapter 63).</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It includes many waka poems by the poet ARIWARA no Narihira and the hero is called by his cognomen (Chapter 63).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>したがって主人公には業平の面影がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His image is therefore reflected on the hero.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His image is therefore reflected in the hero.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His image is therefore reflected in the hero.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし作中に業平の実名は出ず、また業平に伝記的に帰せられない和歌や挿話も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless he does no appear under his real name in the text and there are a number of poems and episodes that cannot be ascribed to his biography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, he does no appear under his real name in the tex,t and there are a number of poems and episodes that cannot be ascribed to his biography.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, he does no appear under his real name in the text and there are a number of poems and episodes that cannot be ascribed to his biography.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>中には業平没後の史実に取材した話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some tales are based on historical events that took place after his death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some tales are based on historical events that took place after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some tales are based on historical events that took place after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>作品の最終的な成立もそれ以降ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This suggests that the text was finalized after it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This suggests that the text was finalized after his death.</e>
<cmt>antecedent</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This suggests that the text was finalized after his death.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>書名の文献上の初見は『源氏物語』（絵合の巻）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first document that refers to the title is &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) (&quot;Eawase no Maki&quot; or the Chapter on A Picture Contest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first document that refers to the title is &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) (&quot;Eawase no Maki&quot; or the Chapter on A Picture Contest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first document that refers to the title is &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) (&quot;Eawase no Maki&quot; or the Chapter on A Picture Contest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>作者と成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Author and the Time of Completion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Author and Time of Completion</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Author and time of completion</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>作者、成立共に未詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author and the time of completion still remain uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author and the time of completion still remain uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author and the time of completion still remain uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>物語の成立当時から古典教養の中心であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the time of its completion it had played a central role in classical education.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the time of its completion it has played a central role in classical education.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the time of its completion it has played a central role in classical education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>各章段が一話をなし分量も手ごろである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each chapter contains a single tale with handy length.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each chapter contains a single tale of handy length.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each chapter contains a single tale of handy length.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>都人に大変親しまれたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; was probably very popular among the nobility in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; was probably very popular among the nobility in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; was probably very popular among the nobility in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>『源氏物語』には『伊勢物語』を「古い」とする記述が見られ、注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is noteworthy that &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; refers to &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; as &quot;outdated.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is noteworthy that &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; refers to &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; as &quot;outdated.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is noteworthy that &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; refers to &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; as &apos;outdated.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一体作中のどの時点からどの位古いとするのかは説が分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opinions differs as to how &quot;outdates&quot; it was from which point of time in the text. They still remain unresolved.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opinions differs as to how &quot;outdated&quot; it was from which point of time in the text. This issue still remains unresolved.</e>
<cmt>antecedent</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opinions differs as to how &apos;outdated&apos; it was from which point of time in the text.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>なお決着を見ていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This issue still remains unresolved.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>作者については当時から多く意見があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There have been many speculations about the authorship of &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have been many speculations about the authorship of &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have been many speculations about the authorship of &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『伊勢物語』の作者論は、作品そのものの成立論と不即不離の関係にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The question of its authorship is inextricably linked to the question of its textual formation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The question of its authorship is inextricably linked to the question of its textual formation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The question of its authorship is inextricably linked to the question of its textual formation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>古く『古今和歌集』と『後撰和歌集』の成立時期の前・間・後のいずれの時期で成立したか説が分かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In former times the controversy over the completion of the text was divided into three: before, during or after the composition of &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (A Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In former times the controversy over the completion of the text was divided into three: before, during, or after the composition of &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (A Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In former times the controversy over the completion of the text was divided into three: before, during, or after the composition of &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (A Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;→)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作者について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Authorship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Authorship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Authorship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="21">
<j>藤原清輔の歌学書『袋草子』や『古今集注』の著者顕昭さらに藤原定家の流布本奥書に業平であろうと記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke&apos;s &quot;Fukurozoshi&quot; (Notes in a Folder, the Collection of Poetic Lore&quot; on poetics, Kensho&apos;s &quot;Kokinshu Chu&quot; (Commentary of the Kokinshu) and in the postscript to vulgate copies of the manuscript transcribed by FUJIWARA no Sadaie, Narihira is suggested as the author of &quot;The Tales of Ise.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke&apos;s &quot;Fukurozoshi&quot; (Notes in a Folder, the Collection of Poetic Lore&quot; on poetics, Kensho&apos;s &quot;Kokinshu Chu&quot; (Commentary of the Kokinshu) and in the postscript to vulgate copies of the manuscript transcribed by FUJIWARA no Sadaie, Narihira is suggested as the author of &quot;The Tales of Ise.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke&apos;s &quot;Fukurozoshi&quot; (Notes in a Folder, the Collection of Poetic Lore on poetics), Kensho&apos;s &quot;Kokinshu Chu&quot; (Commentary of the Kokinshu) and in the postscript to vulgate copies of the manuscript transcribed by FUJIWARA no Sadaie, Narihira is suggested as the author of &quot;The Tales of Ise.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに朱雀院の蔵書塗籠本にも同様の記述があったとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reportedly a similar mention was made in &quot;nurigome-bon&quot; (the manuscript of &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; in possession of Emperor Suzaku).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reportedly a similar mention was made in &quot;nurigome-bon&quot; (the manuscript of &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; in the possession of Emperor Suzaku).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reportedly a similar mention was made in &quot;Nurigome-bon&quot; (the manuscript of &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; in the possession of Emperor Suzaku).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また伊勢物語という題名から作者を延喜歌壇の紅一点の伊勢であるからとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another ascribed its authorship to Ise who was the only female poet in the poetry circle in the Engi era based on the title of &quot;The Tales of Ise.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another ascribed its authorship to Ise, who was the only female poet in the poetry circle in the Engi era, based on the title of &quot;The Tales of Ise.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another ascribed its authorship to Ise, who was the only female poet in the poetry circle in the Engi era, based on the title of &quot;The Tales of Ise.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>二条家の所蔵流布本の奥書に伊勢の補筆という記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The postscript to the vulgate copy in possession of the Nijo family of the manuscript copied by FUJIWARA no Sadaie mentions that it was supplemented by Ise.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The postscript to the vulgate copy in the possession of the Nijo family of the manuscript copied by FUJIWARA no Sadaie mentions that it was supplemented by Ise.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The postscript to the vulgate copy in the possession of the Nijo family of the manuscript copied by FUJIWARA no Sadaie mentions that it was supplemented by Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし明らかに『古今和歌集』との関係が強い章段も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is clear, however, that some chapters of the text are closely related to &quot;Kokin Wakashu.&quot; Recently, therefore,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is clear, however, that some chapters of the text are closely related to &quot;Kokin Wakashu.&quot; Recently, therefore,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is clear, however, that some chapters of the text are closely related to &quot;Kokin Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Recently, therefore,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>近年ではそのような業平の伝説や、『業平集』とは一線を画す必要があると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, therefore, many have considered it necessary to dissociate the text from the legendary authorship of Narihira and &quot;Narihirashu&quot; (Collection of Poems of ARIWARA no Narihira).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, therefore, many have considered it necessary to dissociate the text from the legendary authorship of Narihira and &quot;Narihirashu&quot; (Collection of Poems of ARIWARA no Narihira).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, therefore, many have considered it necessary to dissociate the text from the legendary authorship of Narihira and &quot;Narihirashu&quot; (Collection of Poems of ARIWARA no Narihira).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>現在は概ね片桐洋一の唱えた「段階的成長」説が主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of &quot;gradual development&quot; which Yoichi KATAGIRI has advanced is predominant at the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the theory of &quot;gradual development,&quot; which Yoichi KATAGIRI has advanced, is predominant.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the theory of &apos;gradual development,&apos; which Yoichi KATAGIRI has advanced, is predominant.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>元来業平の歌集や家に伝わっていた話が、後人の補足などによって段階的に現在の125段に成長していったという仮説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a hypothesis that tales which were included in the collection of poems of Narihira or had been handed down in his family gradually developed into the 125 chapters as we now know them through the addition of supplementary chapters by later redactors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One hypothesis states that tales that were included in the collection of poems of Narihira or had been handed down in his family gradually developed into the 125 chapters as we now know them, through the addition of supplementary chapters by later redactors.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One hypothesis states that tales that were included in the collection of poems of Narihira or had been handed down in his family gradually developed into the 125 chapters as we now know them, through the addition of supplementary chapters by later redactors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ただし増補があったとするには、現行の125段本以外の本がほぼ確認できないという弱みがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The assumption of the later addition of chapters is however questionable as no manuscript with more than 125 chapters has been confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The assumption of the later addition of chapters is, however, questionable, as no manuscript with more than 125 chapters has been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The assumption of the later addition of chapters is, however, questionable, as no manuscript with more than 125 chapters has been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>最終的に秩序だって整理されたとするならば、その整理者をいわゆる作者とすべきではないか、という指摘も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As some have pointed out, if the text had been orderly arranged at the final stage, the person who did this editing must be regarded as the author.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As some have pointed out, if the text had been orderly arranged at the final stage, the person who did this editing must be regarded the author.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As some have pointed out, if the text had been orderly arranged at the final stage, the person who did this editing must be regarded the author.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>近代以前の作品の有り方は、和歌にせよ散文にせよそれ以前の作品を踏まえるのが前提であると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary works, whether poetry or prose, before pre-modern times are assumed to have been based on earlier works.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary works, whether poetry or prose, before pre-modern times are assumed to have been based on earlier works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary works, whether poetry or prose, before pre-modern times are assumed to have been based on earlier works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>現代的な著作物の観念から見た作者とは分けて考える必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is necessary therefore to consider pre-modern authorship in different light from the authors of modern writings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is therefore necessary to consider pre-modern authorship in different light from the authors of modern writings.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is therefore necessary to consider pre-modern authorship in different light from the authors of modern writings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そのような場合も含めて、個人の作者として近年名前が挙げられる事が多いのは、紀貫之らである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making allowances for such cases, KI no Tsurayuki and others have been lately often mentioned as individual authors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making allowances for such cases, in recent years KI no Tsurayuki and others have often been mentioned as individual authors.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making allowances for such cases, in recent years KI no Tsurayuki and others have often been mentioned as individual authors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし作者論は現在も流動的な状況にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nonetheless, the question of the authorship of the text is still in a state of flux.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nonetheless, the question of the authorship of the text is still in a state of flux.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nonetheless, the question of the authorship of the text is still in a state of flux.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内容・構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Content and Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Content and Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Content and structure</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>数行程度（長くて数十行、短くて2～3行）の短章段の連鎖からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tale of Ise is structured as a chain of short chapters with several lines (several dozen at their longest and a few lines at their shortest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tale of Ise is structured as a chain of short chapters with several lines (several dozen at the longest and a few lines at the shortest).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tale of Ise is structured as a chain of short chapters with several lines (several dozen at the longest and a few lines at the shortest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>主人公の男が己の思いを詠み上げた独詠歌や、他者と詠み交わした贈答歌が各段の中核をなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A central piece of each chapter is constituted by &quot;dokueika&quot; (waka composed without a specific addressee in mind) in which the hero expresses his sentiments or &quot;zotoka&quot; (poems composed with a specific addressee in mind) which he exchanges with others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A central piece of each chapter is constituted by &quot;dokueika&quot; (waka composed without a specific addressee in mind) in which the hero expresses his sentiments or &quot;zotoka&quot; (poems composed with a specific addressee in mind) which he exchanges with others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A central piece of each chapter is constituted by dokueika (waka composed without a specific addressee in mind) in which the hero expresses his sentiments or zotoka (poems composed with a specific addressee in mind) which he exchanges with others.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>在原業平（825-880）の和歌を多く含み、業平の近親や知己も登場するけれども、主人公が業平と呼ばれることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hero is never called Narihira although many waka poems by ARIWARA no Narihira (825-880) are cited and his close relatives and acquaintances appear in the text.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hero is never called Narihira although many waka poems by ARIWARA no Narihira (825-880) are cited and his close relatives and acquaintances appear in the text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hero is never called Narihira although many waka poems by ARIWARA no Narihira (825-880) are cited and his close relatives and acquaintances appear in the text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>（各章段は「昔、男…」と始まることが多い。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Chapters often begin with the following sentence: &quot;Once upon a time, a man …&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Chapters often begin with the following sentence: &quot;Once upon a time, a man …&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Chapters often begin with the following sentence: &apos;Once upon a time, a man///.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>王統の貴公子であった業平とは関わらないような田舎人を主人公とする話（23段いわゆる「筒井筒」など）も含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some tales (e.g., Chapter 23 on the so-called &quot;Tsutsu Izutsu&quot; (lit. a well curb), countrymen who have nothing to do with Narihira who is a nobleman of imperial lineage are made into the protagonists.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some tales (e.g., Chapter 23 on the so-called &quot;Tsutsu Izutsu&quot; (lit. a well curb), countrymen who have nothing to do with Narihira, who is a nobleman of imperial lineage, are made into the protagonists.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some tales (e.g., Chapter 23 on the so-called &apos;Tsutsu Izutsu&apos; (lit. a well curb)), countrymen who have nothing to do with Narihira, who is a nobleman of imperial lineage, are made into the protagonists.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>よって、主人公を業平と断言することははばかられ、業平の面影があるとか、業平らしき男、と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For these reasons one hesitates to assert that the hero is Narihira and prefers to state that he has something of Narihira or he is a man like Narihira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For these reasons, one hesitates to assert that the hero is Narihira and prefers to state that he has something of Narihira or he is a man like Narihira.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For these reasons, one hesitates to assert that the hero is Narihira and prefers to state that he has something of Narihira or he is a man like Narihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>また、章段の冒頭表現にちなんで、「昔男」と呼ぶことも、古くから行われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has been referred to from of old as &quot;once- upon-a-time man&quot; based on the opening line of chapters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has been referred to from days of old as &quot;once-upon-a-time man&quot; based on the opening line of chapters.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;days&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has been referred to from days of old as &apos;once-upon-a-time man&apos; based on the opening line of chapters.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>各話の内容は男女の恋愛を中心に、親子愛、主従愛、友情、社交生活など多岐にわたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chapters cover broad subjects from heterosexual love, parent-child love to master-subject love to friendship and social life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chapters cover broad subjects from heterosexual love, to parent-child love, to master-subject love, to friendship and social life.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chapters cover broad subjects from heterosexual love, to parent-child love, to master-subject love, to friendship and social life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>主人公だけでなく、彼と関わる登場人物も匿名の「女」や「人」であることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only the hero but also many characters who associate with him are referred to as a &quot;woman&quot; or &quot;person.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only the hero but also many characters who associate with him are referred to as a &quot;woman&quot; or &quot;person.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only the hero but also many characters who associate with him are referred to as a &apos;woman&apos; or &apos;person.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そのため単に業平の物語であるばかりでなく、普遍的な人間関係の諸相を描き出した物語となりえている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Which is why &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; does not merely remain as a narrative about Narihira but can be a universal narrative that describes many aspects of human relations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Which is why &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; does not merely remain as a narrative about Narihira but can be a universal narrative that describes many aspects of human relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Which is why &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; does not merely remain as a narrative about Narihira but can be a universal narrative that describes many aspects of human relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>複数の段が続き物の話を構成している場合もあれば、1段ごとに独立した話となっている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At times, multiple chapters constitute a serialized story and at times, a single chapter tells of an independent story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At times, multiple chapters constitute a serialized story and at times, a single chapter tells an independent story.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At times, multiple chapters constitute a serialized story and at times, a single chapter tells an independent story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>後者の場合でも、近接する章段同士が語句を共有したり内容的に同類であったりで、ゆるやかに結合している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the latter case, however, adjacent chapters are loosely connected by sharing common words, phrases or contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the latter case, however, adjacent chapters are loosely connected by sharing common words, phrases, or contents.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the latter case, however, adjacent chapters are loosely connected by sharing common words, phrases, or contents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>現存の伝本では、元服直後を描く冒頭と、死を予感した和歌を詠む末尾がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the extant manuscripts, the text begins with the hero who has just undergone the ceremony of coming-of-age celebration and ends with his writing a waka poem anticipatory of his death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the extant manuscripts, the text begins with the hero just having undergone the ceremony of coming-of-age celebration and ends with his writing a waka poem anticipatory of his death.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the extant manuscripts, the text begins with the hero just having undergone the ceremony of coming-of-age celebration and ends with his writing a waka poem anticipatory of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この間に、二条后との悲恋や、東国へ流離する「東下り（あずまくだり）」、伊勢の斎宮との交渉や惟喬親王との主従愛を描く挿話が置かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between these two episodes are inserted the following episodes: the hero&apos;s tragic love affair with Nijo no Kisaki, &quot;Azuma Kudari&quot; where he journeys into Eastern provinces, his amour with Ise Saigu (Vestal Virgin of Ise), the master-subject love between Imperial Prince Koretaka and him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between these two episodes are inserted the following episodes: the hero&apos;s tragic love affair with Nijo no Kisaki, &quot;Azuma Kudari&quot; where he journeys into Eastern provinces, his amour with Ise Saigu (Vestal Virgin of Ise), and the master-subject love between Imperial Prince Koretaka and him.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between these two episodes are inserted the following episodes: the hero&apos;s tragic love affair with Nijo no Kisaki, &apos;Azuma Kudari&apos; where he journeys into Eastern provinces, his amour with Ise Saigu (Vestal Virgin of Ise), and the master-subject love between Imperial Prince Koretaka and him.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>後半には老人となった男が登場するという、ゆるやかな一代記的構成をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter part of the text the hero appears as an old man, which imparts a broad structure of biography to the narrative.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter part of the text the hero appears as an old man, which imparts a broad structure of biography to the narrative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter part of the text the hero appears as an old man, which imparts a broad structure of biography to the narrative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>一代記というフレームに、愛情のまことをちりばめた小話が列をなしてる様を櫛にたとえて櫛歯式構成という学者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scholars has described such a structure as the &quot;comb-teeth organization&quot; by way of the metaphor of the comb in which the framework of biography is filled with a row of teeth that are individual episodes recounting the truths of love.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A scholars has described such a structure as the &quot;comb-teeth organization&quot; by way of the metaphor of the comb in which the framework of biography is filled with a row of teeth that are individual episodes recounting the truths of love.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A scholars has described such a structure as the &quot;comb-teeth organization&quot; by way of the metaphor of the comb in which the framework of biography is filled with a row of teeth that are individual episodes recounting the truths of love.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>作中紀氏との関わりの多い人物が多く登場する事で知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many characters associated with the Ki clan famously appear in the text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many characters associated with the Ki clan famously appear in the text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many characters associated with the Ki clan famously appear in the text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>在原業平は紀有常（実名で登場）の娘を妻としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ARIWARA no Narihira was married to the daughter of KI no Aritsune (who appears under his real name in the narrative).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ARIWARA no Narihira was married to the daughter of KI no Aritsune (who appears under his real name in the narrative).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ARIWARA no Narihira was married to the daughter of KI no Aritsune (who appears under his real name in the narrative).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>その有常の父紀名虎の娘が惟喬親王を産んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The daughter of Aritsune&apos;s father named KI no Natora gave birth to Imperial Prince Koretaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The daughter of Aritsune&apos;s father, named KI no Natora, gave birth to Imperial Prince Koretaka.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The daughter of Aritsune&apos;s father, named KI no Natora, gave birth to Imperial Prince Koretaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>作中での彼らは古記録から考えられる以上に零落した境遇が強調されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The text underscores that the Ki clan are in more reduced circumstances than ancient records would tell us.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The text underscores that the Ki clan are in more reduced circumstances than ancient records would tell us.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The text underscores that the Ki clan are in more reduced circumstances than ancient records would tell us.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>何らかの意図で藤原氏との政争に敗れても、優美であったという紀氏の有り様を美しく描いているとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This can be taken as the aesthetic rendering of the clan who remained graceful even though, for some reasons, they failed to defeat the Fujiwara clan in their political strife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be taken as the aesthetic rendering of the clan who remained graceful even though, for some reason, they failed to defeat the Fujiwara clan in their political strife.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be taken as the aesthetic rendering of the clan who remained graceful even though, for some reason, they failed to defeat the Fujiwara clan in their political strife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>なお、斎宮との交渉を描く章段を冒頭に置く本もかつては存在したらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that manuscripts that began with the episode of the hero&apos;s liaison with the Vestal Virgin of Ise once existed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that manuscripts that began with the episode of the hero&apos;s liaison with the Vestal Virgin of Ise once existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that manuscripts that began with the episode of the hero&apos;s liaison with the Vestal Virgin of Ise once existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>だが藤原定家はそのような本を改ざんされた本と非難している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadaie however criticized that they were interpolated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sadaie, however, criticized that they were interpolated.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadaie, however, criticized that they were interpolated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>伝本も確認できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No such manuscripts moreover have been identified.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No such manuscripts moreover have been identified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No such manuscripts moreover have been identified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>書名の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Origin of the Title</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Origin of the Title</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the title</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="59">
<j>古来諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many opinions about the origin of the title.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many opinions about the origin of the title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many opinions about the origin of the title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>現在は、第69段の伊勢国を舞台としたエピソード（在原業平と想定される男が、伊勢斎宮と密通してしまう話）に由来するという説が最も有力視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the present, however, one of the most cogent theories is that the title derives from the 69th chapter set in Ise Province (where a man supposed to be ARIWARA no Narihira commits adultery with the Vestal Virgin of Ise).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the present, however, one of the most cogent theories is that the title derives from the 69th chapter set in Ise Province (where a man supposed to be ARIWARA no Narihira commits adultery with the Vestal Virgin of Ise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the present, however, one of the most cogent theories is that the title derives from the 69th chapter set in Ise Province (where a man supposed to be ARIWARA no Narihira commits adultery with the Vestal Virgin of Ise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>その場合、この章段がこの作品の白眉であるからとする理解と、本来はこの章段が冒頭にあったからとする理解とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory assumes, on the one hand, that the chapter is a highlight of the text, and, on the other, that it was originally an opening episode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory assumes, on the one hand, that the chapter is a highlight of the text, and, on the other, that it was originally an opening episode.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory assumes, on the one hand, that the chapter is a highlight of the text, and, on the other, that it was originally an opening episode.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>前者は、二条后や東下りなど他の有名章段ではなくこの章段が選ばれた必然性がいまひとつ説明できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former interpretation cannot really explain why this chapter rather than famous chapters like &quot;Nijo no Kisaki&quot; or &quot;Azumakudari&quot; had to be selected.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former interpretation cannot really explain why this chapter rather than famous chapters like &quot;Nijo no Kisaki&quot; or &quot;Azumakudari&quot; had to be selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former interpretation cannot really explain why this chapter rather than famous chapters like &quot;Nijo no Kisaki&quot; or &quot;Azumakudari&quot; had to be selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>後者は、そのような形態の本はむしろ書名に合わせるために後世の人間によって再編されたものではないかとの批判もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter has met the criticism that such a form of texts would have been re-edited by later redactors to justify the title.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter has met the criticism that such a form of texts would have been re-edited by later redactors to justify the title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter has met the criticism that such a form of texts would have been re-edited by later redactors to justify the title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>最終的な決着はついていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The controversy around the title has not been fully settled.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The controversy around the title has not been fully settled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The controversy around the title has not been fully settled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>また、業平による伊勢斎宮との密通は、当時の貴族社会へ非常に重大な衝撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narihira&apos;s adulterous relationship with the Saigu of Ise had a grave impact on the aristocratic society of the day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narihira&apos;s adulterous relationship with the Saigu of Ise had a grave impact on the aristocratic society of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narihira&apos;s adulterous relationship with the Saigu of Ise had a grave impact on the aristocratic society of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>（当時、伊勢斎宮と性関係を結ぶこと自体が完全な禁忌であった。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In the Heian period sexual intercourse with Saigu itself was an absolute taboo).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In the Heian period sexual intercourse with Saigu itself was an absolute taboo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In the Heian period sexual intercourse with Saigu itself was an absolute taboo.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>この事件の暗示として「伊勢物語」の名称が採られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an allusion to this event the title of &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; was adopted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an allusion to this event the title &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; was adopted.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an allusion to this event the title &apos;Ise Monogatari&apos; was adopted.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>そのような説も提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a theory has also been suggested.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a theory has also been suggested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a theory has also been suggested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>だが虚構の物語を史実に還元するものであるとして強く批判されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been however severely criticized on the ground that it reduces the fictional narrative to a historical fact.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been, however, severely criticized on the ground that it reduces the fictional narrative to a historical fact.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been, however, severely criticized on the ground that it reduces the fictional narrative to a historical fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>さらに、作者が女流歌人の伊勢にちなんだとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is moreover a theory that the text was called as such because the author was Ise who was a female poet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is moreover a theory that the text was called as such because the author was Ise who was a female poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is moreover a theory that the text was called as such because the author was Ise who was a female poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>｢妹背（いもせ）物語」の意味だとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is yet another conjecture that &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; in fact meant &quot;Imose Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Imose).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is yet another conjecture that &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; in fact meant &quot;Imose Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Imose).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is yet another conjecture that &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; in fact meant &apos;Imose Monogatari&apos; (the Tales of Imose).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また、源氏物語（総角 (源氏物語)の巻）には、『在五が物語』（在五は、在原氏の第五子である業平を指す）という書名が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; (the chapter on Agemaki of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot;) cites the title called &quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Zaigo, who refers to Narihira who was the fifth son of the Ariwara clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; (the chapter on Agemaki of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot;) cites the title called &quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Zaigo, who refers to Narihira who was the fifth son of the Ariwara clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; (the chapter on Agemaki of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot;) cites the title called &quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Zaigo, who refers to Narihira who was the fifth son of the Ariwara clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>『伊勢物語』の（ややくだけた）別称だったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari is regarded as (a little casual) name of &quot;Ise Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari is regarded (a little casual) name of &quot;Ise Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Zaigo ga Monogatari&quot; is regarded (a little casual) name of &quot;Ise Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>後世への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence of &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; on Later Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence of &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; on Later Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence of &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; on later works</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>「いろごのみ」の理想形を書いたものとして、『源氏物語』など後代の物語文学や、和歌に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a document on the ideal of &quot;irogonomi&quot; (heroic love-making) &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; was very influential on later prose narratives such as &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; as well as waka poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a document on the ideal of &quot;irogonomi&quot; (heroic love-making) &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; was very influential on later prose narratives such as &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; as well as waka poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a document on the ideal of &apos;irogonomi&apos; (heroic love-making) &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; was very influential on later prose narratives such as &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; as well as waka poems.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>やや遅れて成立した歌物語、『大和物語』（950年頃成立）にも、共通した話題がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Common themes are found in &quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Yamamoto) that was completed slightly later (in ca. 950).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common themes are found in &quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Yamamoto) that was completed slightly later (in ca. 950).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common themes are found in &quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Yamamoto) that was completed slightly later (in ca. 950).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>『後撰和歌集』や『拾遺和歌集』にも『伊勢物語』から採録されたと考えられる和歌が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka poems that are considered to have been taken from &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; are included in &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka poems that are considered to have been taken from &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; are included in &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka poems that are considered to have been taken from &quot;The Tales of Ise&quot; are included in &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>中世以降おびただしい数の注釈書が書かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since medieval times innumerable commentaries were written.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since medieval times innumerable commentaries were written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since medieval times innumerable commentaries were written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>それぞれ独自の伊勢物語理解を展開し、それが能『井筒 (能)』などの典拠となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They each developed their own interpretations of the text and provided sources for later works such as &quot;Noh Izutsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They each developed their own interpretations of the text and provided sources for later works such as &quot;Noh Izutsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They each developed their own interpretations of the text and provided sources for later works such as &quot;Noh Izutsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>近世以降は、『仁勢物語』（にせものがたり）をはじめとする多くのパロディ作品の元となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After pre-modern times, the text became the basis of parodies like &quot;Nise Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Pseudo-Ise).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After pre-modern times, the text became the basis of parodies such as &quot;Nise Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Pseudo-Ise).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After pre-modern times, the text became the basis of parodies such as &quot;Nise Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Pseudo-Ise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>現代でも『江勢物語』（えせものがたり、清水義範著）といった模倣が生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In our times too, it gave rise to mock &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; like &quot;Ese Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Ese by Yoshinori SHIMIZU).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In our times too, it gave rise to mock &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; such as &quot;Ese Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Ese by Yoshinori SHIMIZU).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In our times too, it gave rise to mock &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; such as &quot;Ese Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Ese by Yoshinori SHIMIZU).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 月下薄氷(id:47743), Suguri F(id:11127), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Yukawaguchi(id:247744), Charon(id:9162), Jazzy(id:3202), Aiko17(id:28386), Kiev(id:13022), Sshima(id:27978), Masyu(id:31065), Janus01(id:69663), さららゆら(id:12274), 名無し(id:7386), Shimoxx(id:9332), Avxz(id:123412), FlaBot(id:30804), Tiger aki(id:29320), Izayohi(id:13095), SK(id:64397), Transpassive(id:12204), Aney(id:10520), STBot(id:137943), PixelBot(id:166734), しまながし(id:90740), Aphaia(id:3132), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), Peachkiller(id:99202), 榎(id:91458), Carkuni(id:79281), VolkovBot(id:105371), 頭痛(id:201680), Corwin(id:973), Alexbot(id:157199), Fir(id:10210), Terotako(id:11853), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>