<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐竹本三十六歌仙絵巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (hand scrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets)&quot;</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>佐竹本三十六歌仙絵巻（さたけぼんさんじゅうろっかせんえまき）は、鎌倉時代・13世紀に制作された絵巻物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets)&quot; were made in the 13th century, Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets)&quot; were made in the 13th century, Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (hand scrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets)&quot; were made in the 13th century, Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉時代の肖像画、歌仙絵を代表する作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the most famous illustrated scroll of celebrated poets, or portraits made in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the most famous illustrated scroll of celebrated poets, or portraits made in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the most famous illustrated scroll of celebrated poets, or portraits made in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>元は上下2巻の巻物で、各巻に18名ずつ、計36名の歌人の肖像が描かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were originally two-volume scrolls with portraits of 36 poets, 18 in each volume.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were originally two-volume scrolls with portraits of 36 poets, 18 in each volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were originally two-volume scrolls with portraits of 36 poets, 18 in each volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1919年（大正8年）に各歌人ごとに切り離され、掛軸装に改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, the scrolls were divided into sections of each poet and redecorated to hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, the scrolls were divided into sections of each poet and redecorated to hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, the scrolls were divided into sections of each poet and redecorated to hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原公任（966 – 1041）は11世紀初め頃に私撰集「三十六人撰」を撰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinto (966 – 1041) edited a personal collection of poetry &quot;Sanjurokuninsen (Thirty-six Master Poets Collection)&quot; in the early 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinto (966 – 1041) edited a personal collection of poetry &quot;Sanjurokuninsen (Thirty-six Master Poets Collection)&quot; in the early 11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinto (966 –1041) edited a personal collection of poetry &apos;Sanjurokuninsen&apos; (Thirty-six Master Poets Collection) in the early 11th century.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更し、（）を外に出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは、『万葉集』の時代から、平安時代中期までの歌人36名の秀歌を集めて歌合形式としたもので、これら36名を後に「三十六歌仙」と称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This collection is in the form of poetry competition of excellent poems by 36 poets from &quot;Manyoshu (the first major anthology of early Japanese poetry)&quot; to the mid-Heian Period, who were later called Sanju-roku Kasen (the thirty-six immortal poets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This collection is in the form of a poetry competition of excellent poems by 36 poets from &quot;Manyoshu (the first major anthology of early Japanese poetry)&quot; to the mid-Heian Period, who were later called Sanju-roku Kasen (the thirty-six immortal poets).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This collection is in the form of a poetry competition of excellent poems by 36 poets from &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (the first major anthology of early Japanese poetry) to the mid-Heian Period, who were later called &apos;Sanju-roku Kasen&apos; (the thirty-six immortal poets).</e>
<cmt>(　)を&quot;&quot;の外に出しました。&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>本絵巻はこの三十六歌仙の肖像画にその代表歌と略歴を添え、巻物形式としたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki was handscrolls consisting of portraits, famous poems, and biographies of the thirty-six poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki were handscrolls consisting of portraits, famous poems, and biographies of the thirty-six poets.</e>
<cmt>verb conjugation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki were hand scrolls consisting of portraits, famous poems, and biographies of the thirty-six poets.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>上巻・下巻ともに18名の歌人を収録する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of Volume One and Two included 18 poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of Volume One and Two included 18 poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of Volume One and Two included 18 poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>下巻巻頭には和歌の神とされる住吉明神（住吉大社）の景観が描かれた図があり、上巻巻頭にも、現在は失われているが、玉津姫明神または賀茂御祖神社の景観図があったものと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume Two began with a landscape of Sumiyoshi Myojin (Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine) that enshrined the deity of Waka (Japanese poem), and it is assumed that Volume One also started with a landscape of Tamatsuhime Myojin or Kamomioya Shrine, although it had been lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume Two began with a landscape of Sumiyoshi Myojin (Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine) that enshrined the deity of Waka (Japanese poem), and it is assumed that Volume One also started with a landscape of Tamatsuhime Myojin or Kamomioya Shrine, although it has been lost.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume Two began with a landscape of Sumiyoshi Myojin (Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine) that enshrined the deity of Waka (Japanese poem), and it is assumed that Volume One also started with a landscape of Tamatsuhime Myojin or Kamomioya Shrine, although it has been lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>技法・寸法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Technique and size</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Technique and size</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Technique and size</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>紙本著色。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Colored on paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Colored on paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Colored on paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>元は巻子装で上下2巻からなっていたが、上述のように1919年、上巻は18枚、下巻は19枚に分割され、計37幅の掛幅装に改装されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally two-volume handscrolls, but as described above, in 1919 Volume One was divided into 18 pieces and Volume Two into 19 pieces, and redecorated to 37 hanging scrolls in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally two volumes, but as described above, in 1919 Volume One was divided into 18 pieces and Volume Two into 19 pieces, and redecorated to 37 hanging scrolls in total.</e>
<cmt>two volumes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally two volumes, but as described above, in 1919 Volume One was divided into 18 pieces and Volume Two into 19 pieces, and redecorated to 37 hanging scrolls in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>寸法は縦が約36センチメートル、横は各幅によって差があり一定しないが、60 - 80センチメートル前後である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The height of a hanging scroll is about 36 cm, but the width varies from scroll to scroll, from 60 cm to 90 cm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The height of a hanging scroll is about 36 cm, but the width varies from scroll to scroll, from 60 cm to 90 cm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The height of a hanging scroll is about 36 cm, but the width varies from scroll to scroll, from 60 cm to 90 cm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>画風・作者・年代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Painting style, author, date</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Painting style, author, date</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Painting style, author, date</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>各画面は、まず歌仙の位署（氏名と官位）を記した後、略歴を数行にわたって記し、代表歌1首を2行書きにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each section of poet started with writing the poet&apos;s rank and name in a row, and then his/her biography in several rows and a poem in two rows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each poet&apos;s section started with writing the poet&apos;s rank and name in a row, and then his/her biography in several rows and a poem in two rows.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each poet&apos;s section started with writing the poet&apos;s rank and name in a row, and then his/her biography in several rows and a poem in two rows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それに続いて紙面の左方に歌仙の肖像を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were followed by a portrait of the poet on the left of the sheet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were followed by a portrait of the poet on the left of the sheet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were followed by a portrait of the poet on the left of the sheet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>上巻・下巻の構成はそれぞれ次のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poets included in Volumes One and Two were as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poets included in Volumes One and Two were as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poets included in Volumes One and Two were as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>上巻 - 人麿、躬恒、家持、業平、素性、猿丸、兼輔、敦忠、公忠、斎宮、宗于、敏行、清正、興風、是則、小大君、能宣、兼盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume One: Hitomaro, Mitsune, Yakamochi, Narihira, Sosei, Sarumaru, Kanesuke, Atsutada, Kintada, Saigu, Toshiyuki, Muneyuki, Kiyotada, Okikaze, Korenori, Kodai no Kimi, Yoshinobu, Kanemori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume One: Hitomaro, Mitsune, Yakamochi, Narihira, Sosei, Sarumaru, Kanesuke, Atsutada, Kintada, Saigu, Toshiyuki, Muneyuki, Kiyotada, Okikaze, Korenori, Kodai no Kimi, Yoshinobu, Kanemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume One: Hitomaro, Mitsune, Yakamochi, Narihira, Sosei, Sarumaru, Kanesuke, Atsutada, Kintada, Saigu, Toshiyuki, Muneyuki, Kiyotada, Okikaze, Korenori, Kodai no Kimi, Yoshinobu, Kanemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>下巻 - （住吉明神）、貫之、伊勢、赤人、遍照、友則、小町、朝忠、高光、忠岑、頼基、重之、信明、順、元輔、元真、仲文、忠見、中務</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume Two: (Sumiyoshi Myojin), Tsurayuki, Ise, Akahito, Henjo, Tomonori, Komachi, Asatada, Takamitsu, Tadamine, Yoritomo, Shigeyuki, Saneakira, Shitago, Motosuke, Motozane, Nakafumi, Tadami, Nakatsukasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume Two: (Sumiyoshi Myojin), Tsurayuki, Ise, Akahito, Henjo, Tomonori, Komachi, Asatada, Takamitsu, Tadamine, Yoritomo, Shigeyuki, Saneakira, Shitago, Motosuke, Motozane, Nakafumi, Tadami, Nakatsukasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume Two: (Sumiyoshi Myojin), Tsurayuki, Ise, Akahito, Henjo, Tomonori, Komachi, Asatada, Takamitsu, Tadamine, Yoritomo, Shigeyuki, Saneakira, Shitago, Motosuke, Motozane, Nakafumi, Tadami, Nakatsukasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>古来、絵の筆者は藤原信実（1176 - 1265）、文字の筆者は九条良経（1169 - 1206）と伝承するが、確証はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been believed that portraits were drawn by FUJIWARA no Nobuzane (1176 - 1265) and texts were by Yoshitsune KUJO (1169 - 1206), but there is no evidence for it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was believed that portraits were drawn by FUJIWARA no Nobuzane (1176 - 1265) and texts were by Yoshitsune KUJO (1169 - 1206), but there is no evidence for it.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was believed that portraits were drawn by FUJIWARA no Nobuzane (1176 - 1265) and texts were by Yoshitsune KUJO (1169 - 1206), but there is no evidence for it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>絵の筆者は数人の手に分かれており、信実筆の可能性が高い後鳥羽天皇像（水無瀬神宮蔵、国宝）よりは様式的に時代が下るものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed that several people involved in drawing portraits, and their painting style was that of later period than the style employed in the portrait of the Emperor Gotoba (Minase-jingu Shrine collection, National Treasure) that is highly likely to be the work of Nobuzane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed that several people were involved in drawing portraits, and their painting style was that of a later period than the style employed in the portrait of the Emperor Gotoba (Minase-jingu Shrine collection, National Treasure) that is highly likely to be the work of Nobuzane.</e>
<cmt>added “were”; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed that several people were involved in drawing portraits, and their painting style was that of a later period than the style employed in the portrait of the Emperor Gotoba (Minase-jingu Shrine collection, National Treasure) that is highly likely to be the work of Nobuzane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、文字は13世紀前半の作である承久本『北野天神縁起絵巻』（国宝）の第3巻1・2段の詞書の書風に近いことが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also pointed out that the handwriting style of the text is close to that of the first and second chapter of Volume Three of the Jokyu version of &quot;Kitano Tenjin Emaki (an illustrated history of Kitano shrine)&quot; (National Treasure) written in the early 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also pointed out that the handwriting style of the text is close to that of the first and second chapter of Volume Three of the Jokyu version of &quot;Kitano Tenjin Emaki (an illustrated history of Kitano shrine)&quot; (National Treasure) written in the early 13th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also pointed out that the handwriting style of the text is close to that of the first and second chapter of Volume Three of the Jokyu version of &quot;Kitano Tenjin Emaki&quot; (an illustrated history of Kitano shrine) (National Treasure) written in the early 13th century.</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>以上の画風・書風の検討、また男性歌人像の装束の胸部や両袖部の張りの強さを強調した描き方などから、佐竹本の制作年代は鎌倉時代中期、13世紀と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the study of painting and handwriting style described above as well as the tenseness in drawing of chest and sleeves of male poets, it is estimated that the Satake version handscrolls were made in the mid-Kamakura Period in the 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the study of painting and handwriting style described above as well as the tenseness in drawing of chest and sleeves of male poets, it is estimated that the Satake version handscrolls were made in the mid-Kamakura Period in the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the study of painting and handwriting style described above as well as the tenseness in drawing of chest and sleeves of male poets, it is estimated that the Satake version hand scrolls were made in the mid-Kamakura Period in the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>なお、佐竹本の位署・略歴等の文字には誤字脱字の多いことが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also noted that there are many errors and omissions in rank, name, and biography of poets in the Satake version.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also noted that there are many errors and omissions in rank, name, and biography of poets in the Satake version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also noted that there are many errors and omissions in rank, name, and biography of poets in the Satake version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>描かれている歌人たちは、『万葉集』の時代から、下っても10世紀頃までの人物であり、当然ながら、現実のモデルを前に制作された肖像ではなく理想化された肖像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poets included in the handscrolls were from the days of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; to the 10th century at the latest; their portraits were, therefore, idealized version instead of realistic portraits of living people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poets included in the handscrolls were from the days of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; to the 10th century at the latest; their portraits were, therefore, idealized versions instead of realistic portraits of living people.</e>
<cmt>versions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poets included in the hand scrolls were from the days of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; to the 10th century at the latest; their portraits were, therefore, idealized versions instead of realistic portraits of living people.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>画面には歌人の姿のみを描き、背景や調度品等は一切描かないのが原則である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, such portrait should depict only the figure of a poet without any scenery or furnishings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, such portraits should depict only the figure of a poet without any scenery or furnishings.</e>
<cmt>portraits</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, such portraits should depict only the figure of a poet without any scenery or furnishings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>ただし、中で身分の高い斎宮女御徽子のみは繧繝縁（うんげんべり）の上畳（あげだたみ）に座し、背後に屏風、手前に几帳を置いて、格の高さを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only exception is the portrait of the High priestess (Saigu) Kishi; she is sitting on a tatami mat with ugen-beri (a hem made of silk fabrics colored in one color with sequential layers from light to dark) with a folding screen at the back and a kicho (a curtained frame put up to screen royal personages or noble ladies from direct view of those around them) at the front to indicate her noble status.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文は「徽子女王」でしたがWeb上標記の「斎宮女御徽子」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only exception is the portrait of the High priestess (Saigu) Kishi; she is sitting on a tatami mat with ugen-beri (a hem made of silk fabrics colored in one color with sequential layers from light to dark) with a folding screen at the back and a kicho (a curtained frame put up to screen royal personages or noble ladies from direct view of those around them) at the front to indicate her noble status.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only exception is the portrait of the High priestess (Saigu) Kishi; she is sitting on a tatami mat with ugen-beri (a hem made of silk fabrics colored in one color with sequential layers from light to dark) with a folding screen at the back and a kicho (a curtained frame put up to screen royal personages or noble ladies from direct view of those around them) at the front to indicate her noble status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>36名の歌人の男女別内訳は女性5名、男性31名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">36 portraits include 5 female and 31 male poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">36 portraits include 5 female and 31 male poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">36 portraits include 5 female and 31 male poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>女性歌人は上記の斎宮女御のほか、小大君、小野小町、中務、伊勢で、小大君、小野小町、中務は唐衣に裳の正装であるが、伊勢は唐衣を略す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Female poets are the High priestess Kishi, Kodai no Kimi, Ono no Komachi, Nakatsukasa, and Ise; among them, Kodai no Kimi, Ono no Komachi, and Nakatsukasa dress up in karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket) and mo (long pleated skirts), while Ise doesn&apos;t wear karaginu.</e>
<cmt>(歌人)は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Female poets are the High priestess Kishi, Kodai no Kimi, Ono no Komachi, Nakatsukasa, and Ise; among them, Kodai no Kimi, Ono no Komachi, and Nakatsukasa dress up in karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket) and mo (long pleated skirts), while Ise doesn&apos;t wear karaginu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Female poets are the High priestess Kishi, Kodai no Kimi, Ono no Komachi, Nakatsukasa, and Ise; among them, Kodai no Kimi, Ono no Komachi, and Nakatsukasa dress up in karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket) and mo (long pleated skirts), while Ise doesn&apos;t wear karaginu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>女性歌人のうち、斎宮女御は慎み深く袖で顔を隠している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these female poets, the High priestess discreetly hides her face with her sleeve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these female poets, the High priestess discreetly hides her face with her sleeve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these female poets, the High priestess discreetly hides her face with her sleeve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、絶世の美女とされた小野小町は顔貌が見えないように後向きに描かれ、容姿については鑑賞者の想像にゆだねる形となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ono no Komachi who is known as a rare beauty turns backward and doesn&apos;t show her face to leave it to the viewer&apos;s imagination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ono no Komachi, who is known as a rare beauty, turns backward and doesn&apos;t show her face to leave it to the viewer&apos;s imagination.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ono no Komachi, who is known as a rare beauty, turns backward and doesn&apos;t show her face to leave it to the viewer&apos;s imagination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>男性歌人像は束帯姿18、直衣（のうし）姿7、狩衣（かりぎぬ）姿2、褐衣（かちえ）姿2、僧侶2となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Male poets include 18 in sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress), 7 in noshi (everyday clothes for nobles), 2 in kariginu (informal clothes for court nobles), 2 in kachi-e (similar clothes to kariginu), and 2 in clothes for Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Male poets include 18 in sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress), 7 in noshi (everyday clothes for nobles), 2 in kariginu (informal clothes for court nobles), 2 in kachi-e (similar clothes to kariginu), and 2 in clothes for Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt>priests</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Male poets include 18 in sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress), 7 in noshi (everyday clothes for nobles), 2 in kariginu (informal clothes for court nobles), 2 in kachi-e (similar clothes to kariginu), and 2 in clothes for Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>男性像では藤原興風、藤原朝忠は後向きの体勢で描かれ、藤原仲文は脚を立膝とするなど、単調になりがちな画面に変化をつけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, FUJIWARA no Okikaze and FUJIWARA no Asatada turn backwards while FUJIWARA no Nakafumi sits with one knee drawn up, in order to add a variety to rather monotonous series of portraits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, FUJIWARA no Okikaze and FUJIWARA no Asatada turn backwards while FUJIWARA no Nakafumi sits with one knee drawn up, in order to add a variety to rather monotonous series of portraits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, FUJIWARA no Okikaze and FUJIWARA no Asatada turn backwards while FUJIWARA no Nakafumi sits with one knee drawn up, in order to add a variety to rather monotonous series of portraits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、凡河内躬恒の図は当初のものが失われ、江戸時代・狩野探幽筆のものに代わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be noted that the original portrait of OSHIKOCHI no Mitsune was lost and substituted with the one by Tanyu KANO in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted that the original portrait of OSHIKOCHI no Mitsune was lost and substituted with the one by Tanyu KANO in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted that the original portrait of OSHIKOCHI no Mitsune was lost and substituted with the one by Tanyu KANO in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>紀貫之の文字の部分も後補である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Text by KI no Tsurayuki was also added in a later date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Text by KI no Tsurayuki was also added at a later date.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Text by KI no Tsurayuki was also added at a later date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>三十六歌仙は、近世に至るまで画帖、額絵などさまざまな形で絵画化され、遺品も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thirty-six immortal poets had been portrayed up to the early-modern times in various formats such as gajo (an album of paintings) and framed pictures, and many of those were articles of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thirty-six immortal poets had been portrayed up to early-modern times in various formats such as gajo (an album of paintings) and framed pictures, and many of those were articles of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thirty-six immortal poets had been portrayed up to early-modern times in various formats such as gajo (an album of paintings) and framed pictures, and many of those were articles of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>佐竹本三十六歌仙絵巻は、上畳本三十六歌仙絵巻と並んで三十六歌仙図のうちでも最古の遺品であり、鎌倉時代の大和絵系肖像画を代表する作品と評されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satake version is one of the earliest extant examples of the illustrated handscroll of thirty-six immortal poets along with the Agedatami version, and therefore it is evaluated as a representative work of portraits in the Yamato-e style (classical Japanese style painting) in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satake version is one of the earliest extant examples of the illustrated handscroll of thirty-six immortal poets along with the Agedatami version, and therefore it is evaluated as a representative work of portraits in the Yamato-e style (classical Japanese style painting) in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satake version is one of the earliest extant examples of the illustrated handscroll of thirty-six immortal poets along with the Agedatami version, and therefore it is evaluated as a representative work of portraits in the Yamato-e style (classical Japanese style painting) in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>伝来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>旧秋田藩主・佐竹侯爵家に伝来したことから「佐竹本」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called &quot;Satake version&quot; because it is a hereditary article in the family of Marquis Satake, a former lord of Akita Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called &quot;Satake version&quot; because it is a hereditary article in the family of Marquis Satake, a former lord of Akita Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &apos;Satake version&apos; because it is a hereditary article in the family of Marquis Satake, a former lord of Akita Domain.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>大坂在住の文人・木村兼葭堂（1736 - 1802年）の『蒹葭堂雑録』によると、元は下鴨神社に伝来したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kenkado Zatsuroku&quot; by Osaka-based man of literature, Kenkado KIMURA (1736-1802), the Satake version was originally a hereditary article of the Shimogamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kenkado Zatsuroku&quot; by Osaka-based man of literature, Kenkado KIMURA (1736-1802), the Satake version was originally a hereditary article of the Shimogamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Kenkado Zatsuroku&quot; by Osaka-based man of literature, Kenkado KIMURA (1736-1802), the Satake version was originally a hereditary article of the Shimogamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>絵巻の分割と所有者の変転</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Division of the handscrolls and change of owners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Division of the handscrolls and change of owners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Division of the hand scrolls and change of owners</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>この絵巻は前述のとおり、佐竹侯爵家に伝来したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, the handscrolls were in the hand of the family of Marquis Satake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, the handscrolls were in the hands of the family of Marquis Satake.</e>
<cmt>hands</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, the hand scrolls were in the hands of the family of Marquis Satake.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1917年（大正6年）、東京両国の東京美術倶楽部で佐竹家の所蔵品の売立てが行われ、三十六歌仙絵巻は東京と関西の古美術業者9店が合同で35万円3千円で落札した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1917, the collection of the Satake family was put up for auction at the Tokyo Bijutsu Club in Ryogoku, Tokyo, and nine antique dealers in Tokyo and Kansai regions jointly bought the handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets for \353,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1917, the collection of the Satake family was put up for auction at the Tokyo Bijutsu Club in Ryogoku, Tokyo, and nine antique dealers in Tokyo and Kansai regions jointly bought the handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets for 353,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>Deleted “\” and added “yen”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1917, the collection of the Satake family was put up for auction at the Tokyo Bijutsu Club in Ryogoku, Tokyo, and nine antique dealers in Tokyo and Kansai regions jointly bought the hand scrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets for 353,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>単純には比較できないが、当時の1万円は21世紀初頭現在の約1億円に相当するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a simple comparison is not accurate, it can be roughly estimated that a ten-thousand yen at that time is equivalent to 100 million yen at today&apos;s price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a simple comparison is not accurate, it can be roughly estimated that ten-thousand yen at that time is equivalent to 100 million yen at today&apos;s price.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a simple comparison is not accurate, it can be roughly estimated that ten-thousand yen at that time is equivalent to 100 million yen at today&apos;s price.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>あまりの高額のため、業者1社では落札できなかったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it can be assumed that the handscrolls were too expensive for one dealer to buy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it can be assumed that the handscrolls were too expensive for one dealer to buy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it can be assumed that the hand scrolls were too expensive for one dealer to buy.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>同年、この絵巻を購入したのは実業家の山本唯三郎（1873 - 1927年）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, an industrialist Tadasaburo YAMAMOTO (1873-1927) bought the handscrolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, industrialist Tadasaburo YAMAMOTO (1873-1927) bought the handscrolls.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, industrialist Tadasaburo YAMAMOTO (1873-1927) bought the hand scrolls.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>山本は松昌洋行という貿易商社を起こし、中国で材木の輸出、石炭の輸入などの事業を行い、後に海運業で財を成した人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamamoto was the founder of a trade firm called Shosho Yoko to export lumber and import coal in China, and a fortune in the shipping industry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamamoto was the founder of a trade firm called Shosho Yoko to export lumber and import coal in China, and made a fortune in the shipping industry.</e>
<cmt>added “made”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamamoto was the founder of a trade firm called Shosho Yoko to export lumber and import coal in China, and made a fortune in the shipping industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>朝鮮半島へ虎狩りに行ったことから「虎大尽」の異名を取り、数々の武勇談や奇行に満ちた人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a nickname &quot;Toradaijin (Tiger Millionaire)&quot; because he went to the Korean Peninsula for tiger hunting, and he was a man full of heroic exploits and amusing anecdotes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a nickname &quot;Toradaijin (Tiger Millionaire)&quot; because he went to the Korean Peninsula for tiger hunting, and he was a man full of heroic exploits and amusing anecdotes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a nickname &apos;Toradaijin&apos; (Tiger Millionaire) because he went to the Korean Peninsula for tiger hunting, and he was a man full of heroic exploits and amusing anecdotes.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更し、(　）を外に出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>第一次大戦の終戦による経済状況の悪化に伴い、山本は早くも1919年にはこの絵巻を手放さざるをえなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the economic decline after the World War I, Yamamoto was already required to give up the handscrolls in 1919.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the economic decline after World War I, Yamamoto was already required to give up the handscrolls in 1919.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the economic decline after World War I, Yamamoto was already required to give up the hand scrolls in 1919.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>ところが、時節柄、高価な絵巻を1人で買い取れる収集家はどこにもいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a sever economic situation, however, none of antique collectors could buy such an expensive handscroll by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a severe economic situation, however, no antique collector could buy such an expensive handscroll by himself.</e>
<cmt>spelling; expressions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a severe economic situation, however, no antique collector could buy such an expensive hand scroll by himself.</e>
<cmt>handscrollをhand scrollに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>この絵巻の買い取り先を探していた服部七兵衛、土橋嘉兵衛らの古美術商は、当時、茶人・美術品コレクターとして高名だった、実業家益田孝（号鈍翁）のところへ相談に行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antique dealers such as Shichibe HATTORI and Kahee TSUCHIHASHI were looking for someone who could buy the handscrolls, and visited Takashi MASUDA (pen name Donno), industrialist and a renowned master of the tea ceremony and art collector, for consultation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antique dealers such as Shichibe HATTORI and Kahee TSUCHIHASHI were looking for someone who could buy the handscrolls, and visited Takashi MASUDA (pen name Donno), industrialist, renowned master of the tea ceremony and art collector, for consultation.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antique dealers such as Shichibe HATTORI and Kahee TSUCHIHASHI were looking for someone who could buy the hand scrolls, and visited Takashi MASUDA (pen name Donno), industrialist, renowned master of the tea ceremony and art collector, for consultation.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>大コレクターとして知られた益田もさすがにこの絵巻を一人で買い取ることはできず、彼の決断で、絵巻は歌仙一人ごとに分割して譲渡することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Masuda was known as the leading collector of the time, he couldn&apos;t afford the handscrolls by himself, so he decided to divide the handscrolls into each portrait of poet to distribute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Masuda was known as the leading collector of the time, he couldn&apos;t afford the handscrolls by himself, so he decided to divide the handscrolls into each poet&apos;s portrait to distribute.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Masuda was known as the leading collector of the time, he couldn&apos;t afford the hand scrolls by himself, so he decided to divide the hand scrolls into each poet&apos;s portrait to distribute.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>益田は実業家で茶人の高橋義雄（号箒庵）、同じく実業家で茶人の野崎廣太（号幻庵）を世話人とし、絵巻物の複製などで名高い美術研究家の田中親美を相談役とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuda appointed industrialists/masters of the tea ceremony Yoshio TAKAHASHI (pen name Soan) and Kota NOZAKI (pen name Genan) as mediators, and a renowned art scholar known for reproduction of handscrolls, Shinbi TANAKA, as an advisor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuda appointed industrialists/masters of the tea ceremony Yoshio TAKAHASHI (pen name Soan) and Kota NOZAKI (pen name Genan) as mediators, and a renowned art scholar known for reproduction of handscrolls, Shinbi TANAKA, as an advisor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuda appointed industrialists/masters of the tea ceremony Yoshio TAKAHASHI (pen name Soan) and Kota NOZAKI (pen name Genan) as mediators, and a renowned art scholar known for reproduction of hand scrolls, Shinbi TANAKA, as an advisor.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>三十六歌仙絵巻を37枚（下巻冒頭の住吉明神図を含む）に分割し、くじ引きで希望者に譲渡することとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuda then divided the handscrolls of 36 poets into 37 pictures (including the picture of Sumiyoshi Myojin Shrine at the top of Volume Two) and tried to distribute each separated picture to 37 renderers by lottery.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuda then divided the handscrolls of 36 poets into 37 pictures (including the picture of Sumiyoshi Myojin Shrine at the top of Volume Two) and tried to distribute each separated picture to 37 renderers by lottery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuda then divided the hand scrolls of 36 poets into 37 pictures (including the picture of Sumiyoshi Myojin Shrine at the top of Volume Two) and tried to distribute each separated picture to 37 renderers by lottery.</e>
<cmt>handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="51">
<j>抽選会は1919年12月20日、東京の御殿山（現・品川区北品川）にあった益田の自邸で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lottery was held on December 20, 1919, at the Masuda&apos;s residence in Gotenyama (present-day Kitashinagawa, Shinagawa Ward), Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lottery was held on December 20, 1919, at the Masuda&apos;s residence in Gotenyama (present-day Kitashinagawa, Shinagawa Ward), Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lottery was held on December 20, 1919, at the Masuda&apos;s residence in Gotenyama (present-day Kitashinagawa, Shinagawa Ward), Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この抽選会が行われた建物は「応挙館」と呼ばれ、後に東京国立博物館の構内に移築されて現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The building was called &quot;Okyokan&quot; and later brought over to the Tokyo National Museum where the building still exists today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building was called &quot;Okyokan&quot; and later brought over to the Tokyo National Museum where the building still exists today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building was called &apos;Okyokan&apos; and later brought over to the Tokyo National Museum where the building still exists today.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>抽選会には益田自身も参加し、また、旧所蔵者の山本唯三郎にも1枚が譲渡されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuda himself participated in the lottery, and it was decided that one of the pictures was given to its former owner Tadasaburo Yamamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuda himself participated in the lottery, and it was decided that one of the pictures was given to its former owner Tadasaburo Yamamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuda himself participated in the lottery, and it was decided that one of the pictures was given to its former owner Tadasaburo Yamamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>益田は、三十六歌仙の中でも最も人気が高く、最高値の4万円が付けられていた「斎宮女御」の入手をねらっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuda aimed to obtain the picture of the High priestess that was the most sought-after among 36 poets with the highest price of \40,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuda aimed to obtain the picture of the High priestess that was the most sought-after among 36 poets with the highest price of 40,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>Deleted “\” and added “yen”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuda aimed to obtain the picture of the &apos;High priestess&apos; that was the most sought-after among 36 poets with the highest price of 40,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>&apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>通説では、くじ引きの結果、益田にはもっとも人気のない「僧侶」の絵が当たってしまい、すっかり不機嫌になってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the prevailing story, Masuda was allotted to the least popular picture of a Buddhist priest and became completely displeased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the prevailing story, Masuda was allotted the least popular picture of a Buddhist priest and was completely displeased.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the prevailing story, Masuda was allotted the least popular picture of a &apos;Buddhist priest&apos; and was completely displeased.</e>
<cmt>&apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>それで、「斎宮女御」のくじを引き当てた人物が「自分の引き当てた絵と交換しましょう」と益田に提案し、益田は「斎宮女御」を入手して満足そうであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A participant who won the picture of the High priestess offered to exchange it for the picture Masuda was allotted, and Masuda looked very satisfied with the picture of his dream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A participant who won the picture of the High priestess offered to exchange it for the picture Masuda was allotted, and Masuda looked very satisfied with the picture of his dream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A participant who won the picture of the &apos;High priestess&apos; offered to exchange it for the picture Masuda was allotted, and Masuda looked very satisfied with the picture of his dream.</e>
<cmt>&apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>もっとも、翌12月21日付け「東京朝日新聞」でこの絵巻売却の件が報道されたのを見ると、益田が最初に引き当てたのは僧侶像ではなく「源順像」だったことになっており、細かい点についての真相は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an article of Tokyo Asahi Shimbun on the following day of the lottery, however, the picture Masuda was allotted first was the portrait of MINAMOTO no Shitago, not a picture of a priest; the details of what actually happened on the day of lottery remained unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an article of Tokyo Asahi Shimbun on the day after the lottery, however, the picture Masuda was allotted first was the portrait of MINAMOTO no Shitago, not a picture of a priest; the details of what actually happened on the day of lottery remained unknown.</e>
<cmt>following-&gt;after</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an article of Tokyo Asahi Shimbun on the day after the lottery, however, the picture Masuda was allotted first was the &apos;portrait of MINAMOTO no Shitago&apos;, not a picture of a priest; the details of what actually happened on the day of lottery remained unknown.</e>
<cmt>&apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="58">
<j>これら37分割された歌仙像は、その後も社会経済状況の変化、第二次大戦終了後の社会の混乱等により、次々と所有者が変わり、公立・私立の博物館・美術館の所蔵となっているものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These 37 pieces were transferred from one owner to the other due to changes in the socioeconomic conditions and social turmoil after the World War II, and many of the pictures were in collections of public or private museums.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These 37 pieces were transferred from one owner to the other due to changes in the socioeconomic conditions and social turmoil after World War II, and many of the pictures were in collections of public or private museums.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These 37 pieces were transferred from one owner to the other due to changes in the socioeconomic conditions and social turmoil after World War II, and many of the pictures were in collections of public or private museums.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>1984年11月3日、NHKテレビで、三十六歌仙絵巻の分割とその後の流転をテーマにしたドキュメンタリー番組「絵巻切断」が放送され、関連書籍が発行されたことにより、この件はさらなる注目を集めることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 3, 1984, NHK broadcasted a documentary program entitled &quot;Emaki Setsudan (Divided Handscroll)&quot; on how the handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets were divided into pieces and their vicissitudes, and related books were published, resulting in further attention to this subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 3, 1984, NHK broadcast a documentary program entitled &quot;Emaki Setsudan (Divided Handscroll)&quot; on how the handscrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets were divided into pieces and their vicissitudes, and related books were published, resulting in further attention to this subject.</e>
<cmt>verb conjugation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 3, 1984, NHK broadcast a documentary program entitled &apos;Emaki Setsudan&apos; (Divided Handscroll) on how the hand scrolls of the thirty-six immortal poets were divided into pieces and their vicissitudes, and related books were published, resulting in further attention to this subject.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更し、()を外に出しました。handscrollsをhand scrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>1986年には当時、東京・赤坂にあったサントリー美術館で「開館25周年記念展 三十六歌仙絵」が開催され、佐竹本三十六歌仙絵37点のうち、20点が出品された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1986, the Suntory Museum of Art that was in Akasaka, Tokyo at the time held &quot;An Exhibition Commemorating the 25th Anniversary - Portraits of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets&quot; in which 20 out of 37 pieces of Satake version were exhibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1986, the Suntory Museum of Art that was in Akasaka, Tokyo, at the time held &quot;An Exhibition Commemorating the 25th Anniversary - Portraits of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets&quot; in which 20 out of 37 pieces of Satake version were exhibited.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1986, the Suntory Museum of Art that was in Akasaka, Tokyo, at the time held &apos;An Exhibition Commemorating the 25th Anniversary - Portraits of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets&apos; in which 20 out of 37 pieces of Satake version were exhibited.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>佐竹本三十六歌仙絵巻断簡の一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of pieces of Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of pieces of Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of pieces of Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>1919年当時の所有者については、参考文献に挙げた『秘宝三十六歌仙の流転 絵巻切断』による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The information of owners in 1919 is based on &quot;Hiho Sanju-roku Kasen no Ruten: Emaki Setsudan&quot; in References.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Information about owners in 1919 is based on &quot;Hiho Sanju-roku Kasen no Ruten: Emaki Setsudan&quot; in References.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Information about owners in 1919 is based on &quot;Hiho Sanju-roku Kasen no Ruten: Emaki Setsudan&quot; in References.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ReijiYamashina(id:29567), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>