<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>総角 (源氏物語)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agemaki (Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agemaki (Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agemaki (Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>総角（あげまき）は、『源氏物語』五十四帖の巻の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agemaki is the name of one of the fifty-four quires of &quot;Genji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agemaki is the name of one of the fifty-four quires of &quot;Genji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agemaki is the name of one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;Genji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>quires→chapters他の記事と合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第47帖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the forty-seven quire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the forty-seven quire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the forty-seventh chapter.</e>
<cmt>forty-seven quire→forty-seventh chapter他の記事と合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第三部の一部「宇治十帖」の第3帖にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It corresponds to the third quire of &apos;Uji jujo (The Ten Quires of Uji),&apos; a part of the third volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It corresponds to the third quire of &apos;Uji jujo (The Ten Quires of Uji),&apos; a part of the third volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the third chapter of &apos;Uji jujo&apos; (The Ten Quires of Uji), which is a part of the third section.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>巻名は薫が一周忌法要に事寄せて大君に詠んだ和歌「あげまきに 長き契りをむすびこめ おなじところに よりもあはなむ」（あなたが縒り結んでいる総角結びのように、あなたと私が長く寄り添えるようになりたいものだ）に因む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was named after the waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) made by Kaoru (a character of Genji Monogatari) for Oigimi (oldest daughter of Hachi no miya) at the time of the Buddhist memorial service for the first anniversary of her father&apos;s death, that is, &apos;We knot these braids in trefoil. As braided threads may our fates be joined, may we be together always.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was named after waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) made by Kaoru (a character of Genji Monogatari) for Oigimi (oldest daughter of Hachi no miya) at the time of the Buddhist memorial service for the first anniversary of her father&apos;s death, that is, &apos;We knot these braids in trefoil. As braided threads may our fate be joined, may we be together always.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of this chapter was derived from the waka poem, which Kaoru made for Oigimi (oldest daughter of Hachi no miya) at a memorial service on the first anniversary of the death of her father: &apos;I hope that we will stay together for long just like these trefoil knots which you tie.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>薫24歳の秋八月から冬十二月の話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the story from the August in fall to the December in winter when Kaoru was twenty-four years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a story that takes place from August in fall to December in winter when Kaoru was twenty-four years old.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a story which covers from August in fall to December in winter when Kaoru was 24 years old.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>秋八月、宇治八の宮の一周忌法要が営まれ、薫はこまごまと心をくばった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the August of fall, a Buddhist memorial service for the first anniversary of Uji Hachi no miya (the Eighth Prince) was performed, to which Kaoru paid great attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of August in fall, a Buddhist memorial service for the first anniversary of Uji Hachi no miya (the Eighth Prince) was performed, to which Kaoru paid great attention.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August in fall, a Buddhist memorial service for the first anniversary of Uji Hachi no miya (the Eighth Prince) was performed, and Kaoru took care of various things.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その夜、薫は大君に近づき意中を訴えるが、大君に拒まれ、そのまま夜通し語り合って別れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that night, Kaoru approached Oigimi and showed his love, but was rejected by her and left after staying up all night talking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that night, Kaoru approached Oigimi and showed his love, but was rejected by her and left after staying up all night talking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that night, Kaoru approached Oigimi and confessed his love, but she refused him, and after they talked all night long, they parted.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大君は父宮の遺志を継ぎ宇治の主として独身を貫く決意をしており、その一方で妹の中の君を薫と結婚させようと考えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oigimi had become celibate for good as a master of the Uji residence followed by her late father&apos;s will, and thought to make her sister Naka no kimi get married with Kaoru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oigimi had become celibate for good as a master of the Uji residence following her late father&apos;s will, and thought to make her sister Naka no kimi get married with Kaoru.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oigimi had decided to become celibate for good as a master of the Uji residence, following her late father&apos;s will, but, on the other hand, she was planning to marry her younger sister, Naka no kimi, to Kaoru.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大君の衣服には薫の強い香が染み付いており、中の君は薫との仲を疑う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kaoru&apos;s strong smell clung to the clothes of Oigimi, Naka no kimi doubted the relation between them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kaoru&apos;s strong smell clung to the clothes of Oigimi, Naka no kimi doubted the relation between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the clothes of Oigimi gave off strong scent of Kaoru, Naka no kimi doubted the relationship between them.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>一周忌が済んで間もなく宇治市を訪れた薫は、大君の結婚を望む老女房の弁たちの手引きで大君の寝所に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru visited Uji soon after finishing the first anniversary and entered into the bedroom of Oigimi by a help of old maid of Ben (a name of character) who wished Oigimi&apos;s marriage, but Oigimi noticed Kaoru&apos;s breath quickly and hid with leaving Naka no kimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru visited Uji soon after finishing the first anniversary and entered Oigimi&apos;s bedroom with the help of an old maid of Ben (a name of character) who wished for Oigimi&apos;s marriage, but Oigimi quickly noticed Kaoru&apos;s breath and hid leaving Naka no kimi.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly after the memorial service for the first anniversary, Kaoru, who visited Uji, entered Oigimi&apos;s bedroom with the help of old maids such as Ben (a name of character), who wished for her marriage.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、大君はいち早く気配を察し中の君を残して隠れてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Oigimi noticed right away, and went out of sight, leaving Naka no kimi alone.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>薫は、後に残された中の君に気付き、二人そのまま語り明かすことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru noticed left Naka no kimi and stayed up all night talking together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru noticed Naka no kimi and stayed up all night talking with her.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru noticed Naka no kimi left behind, and stayed up all night talking with her.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>大君の意思を知った薫は中の君を匂宮と結婚させようと考える</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru, who knew Oigimi&apos;s intention, thought to make Naka no kimi marry Nioumiya, brought him to Uji secretly on a night in September and made him see her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru, who knew Oigimi&apos;s intentions, thought to make Naka no kimi marry Nioumiya and brought him to Uji secretly on a night in September and made him see her.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru, who knew Oigimi&apos;s intention, thought of marrying Naka no kimi to Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>九月のある夜ひそかに匂宮を宇治に案内し、中の君と逢わせてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One night in September, he brought Nioumiya secretly to Uji, and made him see her.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>薫は事実を打ち明け大君に結婚を迫るが、大君は承知しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru told the truth to Oigimi and demanded marriage, but she did not accept it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru told the truth to Oigimi and demanded she marry him, but she did not accept it.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru told the truth to Oigimi, and urged her to marry him, but she did not accept it.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>匂宮は三日間中の君の元に通い続けたが、その後は身分柄思うように宇治を訪問することができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nioumiya continued to visit Naka no kimi for three days, but he could hardly visit Uji after that because of his high status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nioumiya continued to visit Naka no kimi for three days, but he could hardly visit Uji after that because of his high status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nioumiya kept visiting Naka no kimi for three days, but after that he could not visit Uji as he liked due to his social status.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>大君と中の君は、匂宮の訪れが途絶えたことを嘆き悲しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oigimi and Naka no kimi wailed in sorrow about getting scarce of Nioumiya&apos;s visit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oigimi and Naka no kimi wailed in sorrow about Nioumiya&apos;s visit becoming fewer.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nioumiya stopped visiting Uji, so Oigimi and Naka no kimi wailed about it.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>十月、匂宮は淀川に舟遊びや紅葉狩りを催して中の君に会おうと計画した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October, Nioumiya planned to see Naka no kimi by going boating and leaf-viewing to the Yodo River, but he could not achieve his aim because too many people gathered with alacrity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, Nioumiya planned to see Naka no kimi by going boating and leaf-viewing on the Yodo River, but he could not achieve his aim because too many people gathered with alacrity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, Nioumiya planned to go boating on the Yodo-gawa River and arranged an excursion to view the autumn leaves in order to see Naka no kimi.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、多くの人が集まり盛大になりすぎ、かえって目的を果たせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many people came and the gathering became too splendid, so he could not achieve his aim.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>今上帝 (源氏物語)は匂宮の遠出をやめさせるために、夕霧 (源氏物語)の六の君との結婚を取り決める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinjo no Mikado (an emperor in Genji Monogatari) decided to make Nioumiya get married with Roku no kimi (a character of Genji Monogatari), a daughter of Yugiri (a character of Genji Monogatari), in order to stop his trip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinjo no Mikado (an emperor in Genji Monogatari) decided to make Nioumiya marry Roku no kimi (a character in Genji Monogatari), a daughter of Yugiri (a character in Genji Monogatari), in order to stop his visits.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinjo no Mikado decided to marry Nioumiya to Roku no kimi, a daughter of Yugiri, in order to stop his trip.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。（源氏物語）はリンク先の言葉のため、訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>これを聞いた大君は心労のあまり病に臥した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oigimi heard this, fell sick in bed because of the strain of worry and died at home with Kaoru on November in spite of his great care as if vegetation dried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oigimi heard this, fell sick in bed because of the strain of worry and died at home with Kaoru in November in spite of his great care, she withered away like vegetable dries out.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oigimi, who heard this, fell sick in bed as a result of excessive anxiety.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>薫の懸命の看病もむなしく、十一月、薫に看取られる中で草木の枯れていくように息絶えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, despite Kaoru&apos;s care lavished on her, she passed away with Kaoru at her side as if plants and trees had died off.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>26歳だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was twenty-six years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was twenty-six years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was twenty-six years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その日は豊明節会の日で、宇治は吹雪の夜であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the day of Toyoakari no sechie (one of the ceremonies at a seasonal holiday) and the night of snowstorm in Uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the day of Toyoakari no sechie (one of the ceremonies at a seasonal holiday) and the night of a snowstorm in Uji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the day of Toyoakari no sechie (one of the ceremonies at a seasonal holiday), and a snowstorm rages in Uji at night.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>大君と結ばれぬまま終わった薫は深い悲嘆に沈み、宇治に籠って喪に服した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru, who could not marry Oigimi, wailed in sorrow and went into mourning with staying in Uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru, who could not marry Oigimi, wailed in sorrow and went into mourning staying in Uji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru, who could not marry Oigimi, grieved deeply, and secluded himself in Uji to be in mourning.</e>
<cmt>FBに準じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>匂宮は、中の君を京の二条院に引き取る決意をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nioumiya decided to take in Naka no kimi to the Nijoin (a name of residence) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nioumiya decided to take Naka no kimi to the Nijoin (name of residence) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nioumiya decided to take Naka no kimi to the Nijoin (name of residence) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), Rusk(id:9895), Nnh(id:474), 健ちゃん(id:60346), 김용자(id:183966), Roter Stern Leipzig ’99 e.V.(id:82059), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Mikomaid(id:56139), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>