<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>救済 (連歌師)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gusai (the Renga master)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gusai (the Renga master)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gusai (the Renga master)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>救済（ぐさい・きゅうせい・きゅうぜい、正応元年（1283年）？ － 天授 (日本)2年/永和 (日本)2年（1376年）？）は鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけての地下（じげ）の連歌師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gusai (also known as Kyusei or Kyuzei, born 1283, died roughly 1376) was a non-courtier Renga (linked verse) master who lived from the end of the Kamakura period into the Nanbokucho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gusai (also known as Kyusei or Kyuzei, born 1283, died roughly 1376) was a non-courtier Renga (linked verse) master who lived from the end of the Kamakura period into the Nanbokucho period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gusai (also known as Kyusei or Kyuzei, 1283 - 1376) was a non-courtier Renga (linked verse) master who lived from the end of the Kamakura period into the Northern and Southern Court period.</e>
<cmt>Nanbokucho修正</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>和歌を冷泉為相に、連歌を善阿に学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To acquire proficiency in waka, he learned the poetic style of Reizei Tamesuke, and to master Renga, he studied the techniques of Zen&apos;a.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To acquire proficiency in waka, he learned the poetic style of Reizei Tamesuke, and to master Renga, he studied the techniques of Zen&apos;a.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To acquire proficiency in waka, he learned the poetic style of Tamesuke REIZEI, and to master Renga, he studied the techniques of Zena.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>二条良基と協力して1356年に連歌集「莬玖波集」を編纂し、1372年には連歌を読むにあたっての法則を定めた「応安新式」を制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He collaborated with Yoshimoto NIJO to compile a Renga anthology called the &quot;Tsukuba shu&quot; in 1356, and in 1372 he established the rules for composing Renga and set them down in the &quot;Oan shinshiki&quot; (The New Form of the Oan era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He collaborated with Yoshimoto NIJO to compile a Renga anthology called the Tsukuba shu in 1356, and in 1372 he established the rules for composing Renga and set them down in the Oan shinshiki (The New Form of the Oan era).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He collaborated with Yoshimoto NIJO to compile a Renga anthology called the &apos;Tsukuba shu&apos; in 1356, and in 1372 he established the rules for composing Renga and set them down in the &apos;Oan shinshiki&apos; (The New Form of the Oan era).</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>句風は特定の風体に偏らず、言葉のこまやかな使い方と心情の深さ、付け句の緊迫感に優れていると評価された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He did not favor any specific style for the manner of writing verses in his poetry, and is instead considered to have excelled in achieving delicate word-play and true depth of feeling, and in his tsukeku (seventeen-syllable linking verse) a sense of artistic tension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not favor any specific style for the manner of writing verses in his poetry, and is instead considered to have excelled in achieving delicate word-play and true depth of feeling, and in his tsukeku (seventeen-syllable linking verse) a sense of artistic tension.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not favor any specific style for the manner of writing verses in his poetry, and is instead considered to have excelled in achieving delicate word-play and true depth of feeling, and in his tsukeku (seventeen-syllable linking verse) a sense of artistic tension.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>門弟に二条良基のほかに、周阿・永運・素阿・利阿らがおり、室町時代初期の連歌界の周流をなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to his main pupil Yoshimoto NIJO, his disciples (pupils) included Shu&apos;a, Eiun,, So&apos;a, and Ri&apos;a, and Sadafumi&apos;s poetic style also influenced the development and spread of Renga circles in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to his main pupil Yoshimoto NIJO, his disciples (pupils) included Shu&apos;a, Eiun,, So&apos;a, and Ri&apos;a, and Sadafumi&apos;s poetic style also influenced the development and spread of Renga circles in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to his main pupil Yoshimoto NIJO, his disciples (pupils) included Shua, Eiun,, Soa, and Ria, and Sadafumi&apos;s poetic style also influenced the development and spread of Renga circles in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>「莬玖波集」に入集しているほか、「文和千句」「紫野千句」「侍公周阿百番連歌合」などにも句が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the poems of his in the &quot;Tsukuba shu,&quot; his poetry was also included in the &quot;Bunwa senku&quot; (One Thousand Verses from the Bunwa era), the &quot;Murasakino senku&quot; (One Thousand Verses from Murasakino (the Purple Fields)), and the &quot;Jiko shu&apos;a hyakuban renga awase&quot; (The Jiko Shu&apos;a&apos;s hundred-verse Renga contest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the poems of his in the Tsukuba shu, his poetry was also included in the Bunwa senku (One Thousand Verses from the Bunwa era), the Murasakino senku (One Thousand Verses from Murasakino (the Purple Fields)), and the Jiko shu&apos;a hyakuban renga awase (The Jiko Shu&apos;a&apos;s hundred-verse Renga contest).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the poems of his in the &apos;Tsukuba shu,&apos; his poetry was also included in the &apos;Bunwa senku&apos; (One Thousand Verses from the Bunwa era), the &apos;Murasakino senku&apos; (One Thousand Verses from Murasakino (the Purple Fields)), and the &apos;Jiko shua hyakuban renga awase&apos; (The Jiko Shua&apos;s hundred-verse Renga contest).</e>
<cmt>人名を修正&apos;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Novo(id:87875), 代言人(id:33675), Hatsune(id:26654), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>