<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宝物集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hobutsu shu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hobutsu shu (A Collection of Treasures)</e>
<cmt>Added English translation in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hobutsu shu (A Collection of Treasures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宝物集（ほうぶつしゅう）は平安時代末期の仏教説話集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hobutsu shu (A Collection of Treasures) is a Buddhist setsuwa (anecdotes) collection from the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hobutsu shu is a Buddhist setsuwa (anecdotes) collection from the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Cut English translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hobutsu shu is a Buddhist setsuwa (anecdotes) collection from the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>著者は平康頼（たいらのやすより）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author was TAIRA no Yasuyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author was TAIRA no Yasuyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author was TAIRA no Yasuyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>別名は「康頼宝物集」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Yasuyori&apos;s Collection of Treasures&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as Yasuyori&apos;s Collection of Treasures.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks from title.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Yasuyori&apos;s Collection of Treasures.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>治承年間（1177～1181）の成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written during the Jisho period (1177-1181).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was written during the Jisho period (1177-1181).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written during the Jisho period (1177-1181).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>本によって一巻・二巻・三巻・七巻の違いがあり、本文の異同も甚だしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are different texts of 1, 2, 3 and 7 volumes, and the contents are extremely different between them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are different texts of 1, 2, 3 and 7 volumes, and the contents are extremely different between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are different texts of 1, 2, 3 and 7 volumes, and the contents are extremely different between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>原型に近いのは一巻本だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the text with one volume is closest to the original.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the one volume text is closest to the original.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;text with one volume&quot; to &quot;one volume text&quot; to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the one volume text is closest to the original.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>嵯峨釈迦堂（清涼寺）での僧俗の対話形式をとり、多数の説話を援引し、仏法こそが至高の宝物であると語る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in the form of a dialogue between a monk and a layman at the Saga Shakado (Shaka Hall) (in Seiryo-ji Temple), where in the course of citing a large number of setsuwa, they discuss how the Buddhist law is the greatest of all treasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in the form of a dialogue between a monk and a layman at the Saga Shakado (Shaka Hall) in Seiryo-ji Temple, where in the course of citing a large number of setsuwa, they discuss how Buddhist law is the greatest of all treasures.</e>
<cmt>Took &quot;in Seiryo-ji Temple&quot; out of parenthesis. Removed &quot;the&quot; from &quot;Buddhist&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in the form of a dialogue between a monk and a layman at the Saga Shakado (Shaka Hall) in Seiryo-ji Temple, where in the course of citing a large number of setsuwa, they discuss how Buddhist law is the greatest of all treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>概して四部に分けることができ、第1部と第2部は、全体から見る序章のようなものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can largely be divided into 4 parts, with parts 1 and 2 as a kind of introduction when seen from the whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can largely be divided into 4 parts, with parts 1 and 2 acting as a kind of introduction when taken as a whole.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;acting&quot; before &quot;as a kind of&quot; to make the sentence read a bit smoother. Changed &quot;when seen from the whole&quot; to &quot;when taken as a whole&quot; for the same reason.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can largely be divided into 4 parts, with parts 1 and 2 acting as a kind of introduction when taken as a whole.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>第3部から、「この世で一番の宝物は何か？」ということが議論になり、最終的には第4部で「仏法こそが第一の宝」だということに落ち着く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The discussion about &apos;what is the most precious treasure in the world?&apos; starts from part 3, and by the end in part 4, it is settled that &apos;the greatest treasure is simply the Buddhist law&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The discussion about &apos;what is the most precious treasure in the world?&apos; starts from part 3, and by the end of part 4, they have decided that &apos;the greatest treasure is simply the Buddhist law&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Despite the Japanese reading 「落ち着く」, I feel that &quot;they have decided that&quot; reads more naturally here. Changed &quot;in part 4&quot; to &quot;of part 4&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The discussion about &apos;what is the most precious treasure in the world?&apos; starts from part 3, and by the end of part 4, they have decided that &apos;the greatest treasure is simply the Buddhist law.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>世間で大切だとされているものは功罪半ばして、幸せになる反面、不幸せにもなるのだから、何よりも尊いものは世俗を越えた仏法だ、という教えを説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It preaches that things commonly regarded as precious have both merits and demerits, and while they make people happy, also make them unhappy, so that better than anything else is the Buddhist law that stands aloof from the trivia of life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It preaches that things commonly regarded as precious have both merits and demerits, and while they can make people happy, they can also make them unhappy, so above all else is the Buddhist law that stands aloof from the trivialities of life.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;better than anything else&quot; to &quot;above all else&quot; and corrected &quot;trivia&quot; to &quot;trivialities&quot;. Finally added &quot;can&quot; and removed &quot;that&quot; from &quot;so that&quot; to make the sentence read a bit smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It preaches that things commonly regarded as precious have both merits and demerits, and while they can make people happy, they can also make them unhappy, so above all else is the Buddhist law that stands aloof from the trivialities of life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>作者平康頼（法名性照）は後白河院の北面の武士で、検非違使兼衛門府に任ぜられたが、安元三年（1177）、鹿ケ谷の陰謀に預かり、事敗れて鬼界ヶ島（薩摩沖の硫黄島）に流刑されたが、翌年、中宮平徳子平産のための大赦によって召還され帰京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author TAIRA no Yasuyori (Buddhist name, Shosho) was a member of the Northern Guard for the retired emperor Go-Shirakawa, and was also appointed to the Imperial Police and the gate guards at the same time; however, in 1177, he participated in the Shishigatani plot, which was exposed, and was exiled to Kikaigashima island (Iwojima island off the Satsuma coast), though he was recalled to Kyoto the next year in an amnesty due to Empress TAIRA no Tokuko&apos;s healthy childbirth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author TAIRA no Yasuyori (Buddhist name, Shosho) was a member of the Northern Guard for the retired emperor Go-Shirakawa, and was also appointed to the Imperial Police and the gate guards at the same time, however, in 1177, he was exposed as a participant in the Shishigatani plot (a failed uprising against the rule of Taira no Kiyomori), and was exiled to Kikaigashima island (Iwojima island off the Satsuma coast), though he was recalled to Kyoto the next year in an amnesty due to Empress TAIRA no Tokuko&apos;s healthy childbirth.</e>
<cmt>Removed semi colon for comma. Changed &quot;he participated in the Shishigatani plot, which was exposed&quot; to &quot;he was exposed as a participant in the Shishigatani plot&quot; to read a bit smoother. Added a brief explanation of the Shishigatani plot.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author TAIRA no Yasuyori (Buddhist name, Shosho) was a member of the Northern Guard for the retired emperor Goshirakawa, and was also appointed to the Imperial Police and the gate guards at the same time, however, in 1177, he was exposed as a participant in the Shishigatani plot (a failed uprising against the rule of Taira no Kiyomori), and was exiled to Kikaigashima island (Iwojima island off the Satsuma coast), although he was recalled to Kyoto the next year in an amnesty due to Empress TAIRA no Tokuko&apos;s healthy childbirth.</e>
<cmt>人名のスペルを修正&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後は東山 (京都府)双林寺に住み、この説話集を編んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he lived in Sorin-ji Temple in Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture), and compiled this setsuwa collection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he lived in Sorin-ji Temple in Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture), where he compiled this setsuwa collection.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;and&quot; to &quot;where he&quot; to read a bit more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he lived in Sorin-ji Temple in Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture), where he compiled this setsuwa collection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>「新日本古典文学大系」（岩波書店）所収。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is included in &apos;Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei&apos; (Iwanami Shoten).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is included in Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (published by Iwanami Shoten), a collection of classical Japanese literature.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks from title. Added &quot;published by&quot; to explain what Iwanami Shoten is. Added brief explanation of Shin Nihon Koten Bunagaku.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is included in Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (published by Iwanami Shoten), a collection of classical Japanese literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yume149(id:17504), ぴこハンマー(id:15127), Haruno Akiha(id:107628), Suisui(id:69), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>