<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大江嘉言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OE no Yoshitoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OE no Yoshitoki</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Yoshitoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大江嘉言（おおえ・の・よしとき。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Yoshitoki</e>
<cmt>追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>？ － 寛弘6年（1009年）？）は、平安時代中期の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OE no Yoshitoki (year of birth unknown-1009?) was kajin (a waka poet) in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアの「大江嘉言」には、この文の冒頭に「生年不詳」とあったので、加えて訳しました。上段と合わせて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OE no Yoshitoki (year of birth unknown-1009?) was kajin (a waka poet) in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Yoshitoki (year of birth unknown - c. 1009) was a waka poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>c.を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は大江仲宣で、嘉言は大江千古の曾孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was OE no Nakanobu and his great-grandfather was OE no Chifuru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was OE no Nakanobu and his great-grandfather was OE no Chifuru.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was OE no Nakanobu and his great-grandfather was OE no Chifuru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一時弓削氏を称したこともあるが、後に大江氏に復姓している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he once called himself one of the Yuge clan, later he resumed his former surname of OE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he once called himself one of the Yuge clan, later he resumed his former surname of OE.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he once called himself one of the Yuge clan, later he resumed his former surname of OE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>中古三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is regarded as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is regarded as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is regarded as one of the Chuko sanjurokkasen (medieval 36 Immortal Poets).</e>
<cmt>中古三十六歌仙　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>992年（正暦3年）文章生（もんじょしょう）となり、弾正少忠となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 992, he became monjosho (a student of literary studies in the Imperial University) and then Danshoshochu (Judge of Inspection and police ministry).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 992, he became monjosho (a student of literary studies in the Imperial University) and then Danshoshochu (Judge of Inspection and police ministry).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 992, he became monjosho (a student of literary studies in the Imperial University) and then Danshoshochu (judge of inspection and police ministry).</e>
<cmt>弾正少忠 補足を一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1009年（寛弘6年）対馬守として現地に赴任し同地で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1009, he went to Tsushima Province as Tsushima no Kami and died there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1009, he went to Tsushima Province as Tsushima no Kami and died there.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1009, he went to Tsushima Province as Tsushima no Kami (Governor of Tsushima Province) and died there.</e>
<cmt>対馬守　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>歌合に作者として出詠するほか、藤原長能・源道済・能因法師などと交流があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in Uta awase (poetry competitions) as a poet and interacted with FUJIWARA no Nagato, MINAMOTO no Michinari, Noin Priest and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in Uta awase (poetry competitions) as a poet and interacted with FUJIWARA no Nagato, MINAMOTO no Michinari, the priest Noin, and others.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in Uta-awase (poetry competitions) as a poet and interacted with FUJIWARA no Nagato, MINAMOTO no Michinari, the priest Noin, and others.</e>
<cmt>Uta-awase とハイフンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「能因集」に嘉言が対馬守として下向する際の贈答歌や、嘉言を追悼する歌が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Noin shu&quot; includes Zotoka (poetry exchanged between a man and a woman) in his leaving the capital as Tsushima no Kami and elegies on his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Noin shu&quot; includes Zotoka (poetry exchanged between a man and a woman) about his leaving the capital as Tsushima no Kami and elegies on his death.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Noin shu&quot; includes Zotoka (poetry exchanged between a man and a woman) about his leaving the capital as Tsushima no Kami and elegies on his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「拾遺和歌集」以下の勅撰和歌集に入集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) when and after &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (the third imperial anthology) was compiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) starting when &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (the third imperial anthology) was compiled and onwards.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His waka poems were selected for chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) starting when &apos;Shui Wakashu&apos; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) was compiled and onwards.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>家集に「大江嘉言集」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He privately compiled &quot;OE no Yoshitoki shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He privately compiled &quot;OE no Yoshitoki shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He privately compiled &apos;OE no Yoshitoki shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mercenario97(id:206084), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), 沢田(id:40580), 代言人(id:33675), 松茸(id:27535), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>