<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紫式部日記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Murasaki Shikibu Diary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Murasaki Shikibu Diary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Murasaki Shikibu Diary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『紫式部日記』（むらさきしきぶにっき）は、紫式部によって記された日記とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Murasaki Shikibu Diary&quot; is a diary which was written by Murasaki Shikibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Murasaki Shikibu Diary&quot; was written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Murasaki Shikibu Diary&quot; is said to have been written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>「～とされる」のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>写本は宮内庁書陵部蔵の黒川本が最もよいとされているが一部記載については他の写本がすぐれているとも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurokawabon, the manuscript owned by the Imperial Household Agency, is considered best, but some people say that the other manuscript is partly better than that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurokawabon, the manuscript owned by the Imperial Household Agency, is considered best, but some people say that the other manuscript is partly better than that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people regard Kurokawa bon, the manuscript owned by the Imperial Household Agency, as the best manuscript, but it is said that there is a manuscript which has partly better contents than Kurokawabon.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>写本の表紙の表題は『紫日記』とあり、内容にも紫式部の名の記載ははなく、いつから『紫式部日記』とされたかは不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The title on the cover of the manuscript says &quot;Murasaki Diary,&quot; but the contents of the diary do not contain the author&apos;s name, Murasaki Shikibu, therefore it is unknown when it came to be called &quot;The Murasaki Shikibu Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title on the cover of the manuscript says &quot;Murasaki Diary&quot; but the diary does not contain the author&apos;s name, Murasaki Shikibu, so it is unknown when it came to be called &quot;The Murasaki Shikibu Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title on the cover of the manuscript says &quot;Murasaki Diary,&quot; but the diary does not contain the author&apos;s name, Murasaki Shikibu, so it is unknown since when it has been called &quot;The Murasaki Shikibu Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>全2巻であり1巻は記録的内容、2巻は手紙と記録的内容である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of two volumes in total, and the first volume includes records, while the second volume contains both letters and records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of two volumes in total, and the first volume includes records, while the second volume contains both letters and records.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of two volumes in total: The first volume is a collection of records, and the second volume contains both letters and records.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『源氏物語』の作者が紫式部であるという通説は、伝説とこの『紫日記』にでてくる記述に基づいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The common view that the author of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; is Murasaki Shikibu is based on a legend and the description written in this &quot;Murasaki Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The common view that Murasaki Shikibu authored &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; is based on a legend and the description written in this &quot;Murasaki Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The common view that Murasaki Shikibu authored &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; is based on a legend and the description written in this &quot;Murasaki Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>内容構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>寛弘7年（1010年）に完成されたとするのが通説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is widely considered that the diary was completed in 1010.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is widely considered that the diary was completed in 1010.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is widely considered that the diary was completed in 1010.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中宮藤原彰子の出産が迫った寛弘5年（1008年）秋から同7年正月にかけての諸事が書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She kept the diary from the autumn of 1008, when the Empress FUJIWARA no Shoshi was about to have a baby, to the New Year of 1010.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She kept the diary from the autumn of 1008, when the Empress FUJIWARA no Shoshi was about to have a baby, to the New Year of 1010.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diary covers the incidents ranging in date from the autumn of 1008, when the Empress FUJIWARA no Shoshi was nearing her confinement, to the New Year of 1010.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>史書では明らかにされていない人々の生き生きとした行動がわかり、歴史的価値もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the diary she described lives of people vividly, which other historical materials do not show us, therefore it is historically valuable, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the diary she described lives of people vividly, which other historical materials do not show us, so the work has historical value.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the diary she described people vividly, which other historical materials did not do, so the work also has historical value.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>自作『源氏物語』に対しての世人の評判や、宮中の同僚であった和泉式部・赤染衛門、ライバル清少納言らの人物評や自らの人生観について述べた消息文などもみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It contains gossips about &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; private letters in which she described her view of life, and comments about her colleagues at the Imperial court such as Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon, and her rival Seisho Nagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It contains gossips about &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; private letters in which she described her view of life, and comments about her colleagues at the Imperial Court such as Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon and her rival, Seisho Nagon.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It contains gossips about &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; private letters in which she described her view of life, and comments about her colleagues at the Imperial Court such as Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon and her rival, Seisho Nagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>和泉式部に対しては先輩として後輩の才能を評価しつつもその情事の奔放さに苦言を呈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She appreciated the talented younger colleague, Izumi Shikibu, but at the same time gave her the frank opinion about her unrestrained love affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She appreciated the talented younger colleague, Izumi Shikibu, but at the same time she offered frank opinions about her unrestrained love affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She appreciated the talented younger colleague, Izumi Shikibu, but also gave frank advice about her unrestrained love affairs.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>先輩に当たる赤染衛門には後輩として尊敬の意を見せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To the older colleague, Akazome Emon, she showed her respect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the older colleague, Akazome Emon, she showed her respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She showed her respect to the senior colleague, Akazome Emon.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>特に清少納言への評では徹底的に扱き下ろしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She severely criticized especially Seisho Nagon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She could be severely critical, particularly of Seisho Nagon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She could be severely critical, particularly of Seisho Nagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「清少納言と言うのはとても偉そうに威張っている人である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sei Shonagon is a woman who assumes an air of importance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sei Shonagon is a woman who assumes an air of importance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sei Shonagon is a woman who assumes an air of importance.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文にかっこ、訳文にクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「さも頭が良いかのように装って漢字を書きまくっている。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She thinks herself so clever and litters her writings with Chinese characters, but if you examine them closely, you will find that most of them were written with awkward brushstrokes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She thinks herself so clever and litters her writings with Chinese characters, but one close examination one will find that most of them have been written with awkward brushstrokes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She thinks herself so clever and litters her writings with Chinese characters.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。FBに従って修正しました。原文にかっこ、訳文にクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「けれども、その中身を見れば稚拙なところが多い。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if you take a look at them, you will find that most of them have been written with awkward brushstrokes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文にかっこ、訳文にクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「他人より優れているように振舞いたがる人間は後々見劣りするであろう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who want to act as if they were superior to the others would come to a bad end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who want to act as if they are superior to others will come to a bad end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who want to act as if they were superior to others will lose by comparison with others.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文にかっこ、訳文にクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>「(中略)そういう人間の行末が果たして良いものであろうか」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(…) How can the future turn out well for them?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(...) How can the future turn out well for them?&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(...) &apos;How could the future turn out well for such a woman?&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文にかっこ、訳文にクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>13世紀（鎌倉時代）には『紫式部日記絵巻』という紙本着色の絵巻物が著された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the thirteenth century (the Kamakura period), an illustrated scroll called &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Nikki Emaki&quot; was made, which was written on paper with colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the thirteenth century (the Kamakura period), an illustrated scroll called &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Nikki Emaki&quot; was made, being written on paper with colors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the 13th century (the Kamakura period), an illustrated scroll of color painting on paper called &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Nikki Emaki&quot; was made.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>作者は不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known who the author was.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known who the author was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、『栄花物語』と一部文章が全く同じであり、同物語のあとがきには日記から筆写した旨記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) contains exactly the same writing as the diary, and in its afterword the author wrote that the part of the tale was transcribed from the diary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A part of &quot;Eiga Monogatari (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes)&quot; contains exactly the same writing as the diary, and in its afterword the author writes that part of the tale was transcribed from the diary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A part of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) contains exactly the same writing as the diary, and in its afterword the author writes that part of the tale was transcribed from the diary.</e>
<cmt>&quot;の場所を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nnh(id:474), Carbuncle(id:346), Eskimbot(id:29676), Ideal(id:236), MIO(id:31681), Rai koku(id:1661), 青山コロハ(id:118527), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Kiev(id:13022), Kamawanu(id:20537), Yuming(id:17854), Kurz(id:1601), TY(id:1386), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), Samine(id:58028), 捕澤(id:23785), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>