<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>正風俳諧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shofu-haikai (the right style haikai poetry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shofu-haikai (the right style haikai poetry)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shofu-haikai (the right style haikai poetry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正風俳諧（しょうふうはいかい）とは、松尾芭蕉が大成した俳諧の概念をさすことばである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shofu-haikai is the word for the concept of haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) which Basho MATSUO completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shofu-haikai is the word for the concept of haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) which Basho MATSUO completed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shofu-haikai&quot; is the word for the concept of haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) which Basho MATSUO completed.</e>
<cmt>Shofu-haikai にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>もともとは、天文9年（1540年）の秋、荒木田守武が俳諧式目の制定と同時に初めて名付けたことばである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally the name that Moritake ARAKIDA coined at the same time when he set haikai rules in the autumn of 1540.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally the name that Moritake ARAKIDA coined at the same time when he set haikai rules in the autumn of 1540.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally the name that Moritake ARAKIDA coined at the same time when he set haikai rules in the autumn of 1540.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、俳諧という、自然と人生に基礎を置く民衆的な文学を、形式・内容共に純芸術と完成せしめたのは松尾芭蕉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless it was Basho MATSUO who brought haikai, popular literature based on the nature and human life, to the high art in its form and substance.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless it was Basho MATSUO who brought haikai, popular literature based on the nature and human life, to the high art in its form and substance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, it was Basho MATSUO who brought haikai, popular literature based on the nature and human life, to the high art in its form and substance.</e>
<cmt>Nevertheless の後にカンマを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>芭蕉が主体たる蕉門俳諧は芭蕉自身諸国を行脚し、深く自然と人生に思いを秘め「正風」を弘めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basho was the core of Shomon (Basho School) Haikai, and he traveled to various parts of the country to spread &quot;Shofu (right style)&quot; with deep thought over the nature and human life.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basho was the core of Shomon (Basho School) Haikai, and he traveled to various parts of the country to spread &quot;Shofu (right style)&quot; with deep thought over the nature and human life.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basho was the core of Shomon (Basho School) Haikai, and he traveled to various parts of the country to spread &apos;Shofu&apos; (right style) with deep thought over the nature and human life.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shofu (right style)&quot; を &apos;Shofu&apos; (right style) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのことから、芭蕉の俳諧を指すことばとして用いられるようになり、蕉風俳諧とも書かれるようにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore the word Shofu-haikai came to be used as a word that means Haikai of Basho, and the Chinese character for &apos;sho&apos; of Shofu was sometimes written as &apos;sho&apos; of Basho.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore the word Shofu-haikai came to be used as a word that means Haikai of Basho, and the Chinese character for &apos;sho&apos; of Shofu was sometimes written as &apos;sho&apos; of Basho.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore the word Shofu-haikai came to be used as a word that means Haikai of Basho, and the Chinese character for &apos;sho&apos; of Shofu was sometimes written as &apos;sho&apos; of Basho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>下記は、芭蕉不滅の名言である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the golden and everlasting saying of Basho</e>
<cmt>13行目にあった「とは芭蕉不滅の名言である。」を10行目に移動し、「下記は、芭蕉不滅の名言である。」に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>「正風俳諧は万葉集の心なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shofu-haikai is the spirit of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (the oldest anthology of tanka, thirty-one syllables&apos; poem).</e>
<cmt>用語集定訳　短歌＝Tanka (thirty-one syllables&apos; poem)を補足で入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shofu-haikai is the spirit of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (the oldest anthology of tanka, thirty-one syllables&apos; poem).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shofu-haikai is the spirit of Manyoshu (the oldest anthology of tanka, thirty-one-syllable poem).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shofu-haikai is the spirit of Manyoshu&quot; を&apos;Sho-fu-haikai is the spirit of Manyoshu に修正しました。thirty-one syllables&apos; poem をthirty-one-syllable poem に修正しました（※）。※用語集では thirty-one syllables&apos; poem となっておりますが、他のサイトを検索したところ、欧米では &apos;thirty-one-syllable poem&apos; あるいは &apos;31-syllable poem&apos; という表記が一般的なようです。よって他の表記と併せて &apos;thirty-one-syllable poem&apos;　と表記させていただきました。参考：http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/5793http://www.americantanka.com/about.htmlhttp://www.uk.emb-japan.go.jp/en/event/tanka.htmlhttp://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/asia/asia_features/japan/japanese_art_design/原文の末尾に閉じ括弧及び訳文に&apos; &apos;を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「されば貴となく賎となく味うべき道なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is the way everybody should appreciate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is the way that everybody should appreciate.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is the way that everybody should appreciate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文されば貴となく賎となく味うべき道なり。の末尾に閉じカッコ（」）を追記しました。文末に &apos; を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>18世紀後半の天明期に、与謝蕪村は、あくまでも正風の真髄を護持しながらも、用語を広く自由に、近代的な感覚、即ち真実を踏まえての自然への感動と、生活への感動とを盛り上げ偉大なる「革新」を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tenmei era in the latter half of the nineteenth century, Buson YOSA tried to make a great &apos;innovation&apos; by keeping the essence of Shofu but allowing freer use of words and raised modern sense, in other words excitement towards nature and daily life grounded in the reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tenmei era in the latter half of the nineteenth century, Buson YOSA tried to make a great &apos;innovation&apos; by keeping the essence of Shofu but allowing freer use of words and raised a modern sense, in other words, excitement towards nature and daily life grounded in reality.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tenmei era in the latter half of the eighteenth century, Buson YOSA tried to make a great &apos;innovation&apos; by keeping the essence of Shofu but allowing freer use of words and raised a modern sense, in other words, excitement towards nature and daily life grounded in reality.</e>
<cmt>the nineteenth century をthe eighteenth century に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、20世紀初頭の明治期に至って、正岡子規をはじめとする、松瀬青々、河東碧梧桐、内藤鳴雪、高浜虚子、たちは新聞『日本』に拠って、新派ホトトギス (雑誌)なる結社をおこし、正風打倒を目標とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Meiji period in the beginning of twentieth century, led by Shiki MASAOKA, Seisei MATSUSE, Hekigoto KAWAHIGASHI, Meisetsu NAITO, and Kyoshi TAKAHAMA organized an association New Hototogisu (name of magazine) based on &quot;Japan&quot; (a newspaper) and targeted to overthrow Shofu.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Meiji period in the beginning of twentieth century, led by Shiki MASAOKA, Seisei MATSUSE, Hekigoto KAWAHIGASHI, Meisetsu NAITO, and Kyoshi TAKAHAMA organized an association, New Hototogisu (name of magazine) based on &quot;Japan&quot; (a newspaper) and targeted to overthrow Shofu.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Meiji period in the beginning of twentieth century, led by Shiki MASAOKA, Seisei MATSUSE, Hekigoto KAWAHIGASHI, Meisetsu NAITO, and Kyoshi TAKAHAMA organized an association, New Hototogisu (name of magazine) based on &quot;Japan&quot; (a newspaper) and targeted to overthrow Shofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、それ以後の俳句は、必ずしも正風を継承しているとはいえなくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently haiku in later ages cannot be necessarily said to have succeeded Shofu.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently haiku in the later ages cannot necessarily be said to have succeeded Shofu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently haiku in the later ages cannot necessarily be said to have succeeded Shofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), ねこぱんだ(id:35119), Mishika(id:276), 雲夢園(id:287326), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>