<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本文徳天皇実録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Veritable Records of Emperor Montoku of Japan (Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku (Veritable Records of Emperor Montoku of Japan)</e>
<cmt>Moved the English translation into parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku (Veritable Records of Emperor Montoku of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本文徳天皇実録（にほんもんとくてんのうじつろく）は、平安時代の日本で編纂された歴史書で、六国史の第五にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Veritable Records of Emperor Montoku of Japan (Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku) is a history compiled in Japan during the Heian period, the fifth among the Six National Histories (Rikkokushi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku is a history compiled in Japan during the Heian period, and is the fifth among the six Rikkokushi (National Histories of Japan, six historical compilations chronicling the mythology and history of Japan between the Nara and Heian periods)</e>
<cmt>Added a longer explanation for Rikkokushi.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku is a history compiled in Japan during the Heian period, and is the fifth among the six Rikkokushi (National Histories of Japan, six historical compilations chronicling the mythology and history of Japan between the Nara and Heian periods).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>文徳天皇の代、嘉祥3年（850年）から天安 (日本)2年（858年）までの8年間を扱う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It covers the reign of Emperor Montoku, eight years from 850 to 858.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It covers the eight years of the reign of Emperor Montoku from 850 to 858.</e>
<cmt>Changed to &quot;eight years of the reign of&quot; to read a little smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It covers the eight years of the reign of Emperor Montoku from 850 to 858.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>略して文徳実録ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Montoku Jitsuroku for short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can also be abbreviated to Montoku Jitsuroku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;For short&quot; felt a little to casual so I replaced it with &quot;abbreviated to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can also be abbreviated to Montoku Jitsuroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>編年体、漢文、全10巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written in an annalistic style, in Sino-Japanese (kanbun), having 10 volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was written in an annalistic style, in Sino-Japanese (kanbun), and comprised 10 volumes.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;having&quot; to &quot;comprised&quot; to make it read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written in an annalistic style, in Sino-Japanese (kanbun), and comprised 10 volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>編纂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compilation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compilation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compilation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>序文によれば、本書の編纂は清和天皇が貞観 (日本)13年（871年）、藤原基経、南淵年名、都良香、大江音人らに編纂を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the preface, in 871 Emperor Seiwa ordered FUJIWARA no Mototsune, MINABUCHI no Toshina, MIYAKO no Yoshika, and OE no Otondo to compile it.</e>
<cmt>[本書の編纂は～編纂を命じた」と「編纂」が重複するため、最初を削りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the preface, in 871 Emperor Seiwa ordered FUJIWARA no Mototsune, MINABUCHI no Toshina, MIYAKO no Yoshika, and OE no Otondo to compile it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the preface, in 871 Emperor Seiwa ordered FUJIWARA no Mototsune, MINABUCHI no Toshina, MIYAKO no Yoshika, and OE no Otondo to compile it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>年名と音人（共に877年没）の死後、元慶2年（878年）に菅原是善を加え、基経・良香との3人で翌年879年に完成成立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the deaths of Toshina and Otondo (both died in 877), SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi joined in 878, and in 879, he, Mototsune, and Yoshika completed the compilation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the deaths of Toshina and Otondo (both died in 877), SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi joined in 878, and in 879, he, Mototsune, and Yoshika completed the compilation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the deaths of Toshina and Otondo (both died in 877), SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi joined in 878, and in 879, he, Mototsune, and Yoshika completed the compilation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、『菅家文章』によれば、菅原是善の子菅原道真が父に代わって序文を執筆したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, according to &quot;Literary Drafts of the Sugawara Family&quot;, SUGAWARA no Michizane, the son of SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi, is said to have written the preface on behalf of his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, according to &quot;Literary Drafts of the Sugawara Family&quot;, SUGAWARA no Michizane, the son of SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi, is said to have written the preface on behalf of his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, according to &quot;Literary Drafts of the Sugawara Family,&quot; SUGAWARA no Michizane, the son of SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi, is said to have written the preface on behalf of his father.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>書名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Title</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Title</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Title</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本のそれまでの正史は、いずれも「紀」と命名されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of the Japanese official histories before this were named &apos;chronicles&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of the Japanese official histories before this were named &apos;chronicles&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of the Japanese official histories before this were named &apos;chronicles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>日本が範とした中国においては、正史はある王朝が倒れた後に、新たな王朝が前代の王朝の歴史をまとめるという形で作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, which Japan took as a model, the official history of a dynasty was compiled after it had fallen, by the next dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, which Japan took as a model, the official history of a dynasty was compiled after it had fallen by the succeeding dynasty.</e>
<cmt>I felt &quot;succeeding&quot; was more appropriate than &quot;next&quot; in this context.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, which Japan took as a model, the official history of a dynasty was compiled after it had fallen by the succeeding dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これに対して実録とはもともとある皇帝一代ごとに、その事蹟を書き記したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, veritable records were originally the records of one emperor&apos;s deeds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, veritable records originally only recorded the deeds of each emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Each&quot; seems more accurate than &quot;one&quot; for 「ごとに」 in this context. Changed &quot;records of&quot; to &quot;recorded&quot;(書き記した) to avoid repetition of &quot;records&quot; and to bring it a bit closer to the original Japanese. Added &quot;only&quot; to make it read a bit smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, veritable records originally only recorded the deeds of each emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>日本の正史は、日本書紀はともかく、続日本紀以降は「むしろ一つの王朝の歴代の君主の統治記録としての性格」を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official histories of Japan, on the other hand, excepting the Chronicles of Japan (Nihon Shoki), took on the character of &apos;records of the reigns of successive emperors&apos; after the Chronicle of Japan Continued (Shoku Nihongi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for the first Rikkokushi (Nihon Shoki, The Chronicles of Japan), and the second (Shoku Nihongi, The Chronicles of Japan, Continued), all National Histories of Japan were concerned only with recording the reigns of each successive emperor.</e>
<cmt>Added some explanation for Nihon Shoki and Shoku Nihongi as to their place in the Rikokushi to make it less confusing. Changed &quot;official&quot; to &quot;National&quot; in keeping with how Rikkokushi has been translated elsewhere in the text. Although &quot;concerned with&quot; is a bit of a liberal translation of 「性格」 I thought it fit better than &quot;character&quot; in this context.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for the first Rikkokushi (Nihon Shoki, The Chronicles of Japan), and the second (Shoku Nihongi, The Chronicles of Japan, Continued), all National Histories of Japan were concerned only with recording the reigns of each successive emperor.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>こうした流れをくむ文徳実録が「実録」という書名を採用したことは、日本の史書が中国の実録を模していったことの表れであるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fact that the Veritable Records of Emperor Montoku used the title &apos;veritable records&apos; against such a background, it can be seen to have imitated the veritable records of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that these records of Emperor Montoku used the title &apos;veritable records&apos; in such a way can be seen as a direct imitation of the &apos;veritable records&apos; of China.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In the fact&quot; to &quot;the fact&quot;. Removed the first &quot;veritable records&quot; to avoid repetition. Changed &quot;against such a background&quot; to &quot;in such a way&quot; which makes a bit more sense here, and &quot;imitated&quot; to &quot;direct imitation&quot; to read a bit more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that these records of Emperor Montoku used the title &apos;veritable records&apos; in such a way can be seen as a direct imitation of the &apos;veritable records&apos; of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>六国史中、最も期間が短い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It covers the shortest period among the Six National Histories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It covers the shortest period among the Six National Histories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It covers the shortest period among the Six National Histories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>政治関係が少なく、下級貴族の人物伝が多いのが特徴という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unique in containing little political material, but a large number of biographies of lower-ranking nobles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unique in containing little political material, but a large number of biographies of lower-ranking nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unique in containing little political material, but a large number of biographies of lower-ranking nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは従前の国史が官人の卒伝を四位までとしたのに比し五位にまで拡大していることによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is due to the fact that previous official histories had only recorded the biographies of officials up to the fourth rank, but this one expanded that up to the fifth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is due to the fact that previous National Histories had only recorded the biographies of officials up to the fourth rank, but this one expanded that up to the fifth.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;official&quot; to &quot;National&quot; as above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is due to the fact that previous National Histories had only recorded the biographies of officials up to the fourth rank, but this one expanded that up to the fifth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「弘仁・貞観文化」から「貞観文化」への過渡期を詳述し六国史の中ではもっとも人間臭い伝記を収めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It describes in detail the transitional period from the &apos;Konin-Jogan Culture&apos; to the &apos;Jogan Culture&apos;, and among the Six National Histories it contains the most human-like biographies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It describes in detail the transitional period from the Konin-Jogan culture to the Jogan culture, and among the Six National Histories it contains the most human-like biographies.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks. I wasn&apos;t sure if &quot;culture&quot; should be capitalised here so I removed them.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It describes in detail the transitional period from the Konin-Jogan culture to the Jogan culture, and among the Six National Histories it contains the most human-like biographies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Lonicera(id:20638), 春秋君(id:174988), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>