<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>夢浮橋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yume no Ukihashi (The Floating Bridge of Dream)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yume no Ukihashi (The Floating Bridge of Dreams)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yume no Ukihashi</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>夢浮橋（ゆめのうきはし）は、『源氏物語』五十四帖の第54帖（最後の巻）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yume no Ukihashi is the chapter 54 (the fianl chapter) of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yume no Ukihashi is chapter 54 (the final chapter) of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ume no Ukihashi is the 54th (last) chapter of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第三部の一部「宇治十帖」の最後、第10帖にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It coincides with the chapter 10, the final chapter of &quot;Uji jujo&quot; (ten chapters of Uji), a part of Part 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It coincides with chapter 10, the final chapter of &quot;Uji jujo&quot; (ten chapters of Uji), Part 3.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the tenth (last) chapter of &apos;Uji jujo&apos; (The Ten Quires of Uji), a part of the tale&apos;s third section.</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>例外はあるにせよ、源氏物語の多くの巻はストーリー上のそれなりの区切りと見られるところで終わっていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though there are some exceptions, many of the chapters of The Tale of Genji ended at the point where the story was more or less completed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though there are some exceptions, many of the chapters of The Tale of Genji ended at the point where the story was more or less completed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are some exceptions, many of the chapters of The Tale of Genji ended at the point where the story was more or less completed.</e>
<cmt>although としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、この巻は源氏物語の最終巻の終わり、つまり源氏物語全体の終わりであるにもかかわらず特にストーリー上の区切りでも何でもないところでいきなり終わっているように見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this chapter, which is the final chapter of The Tale of Genji, namely the end of the whole of The Tale of Genji, seems to have ended suddenly at the point where the story was not completed at all.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this chapter, which is the final chapter of The Tale of Genji, namely the end of the whole of The Tale of Genji, seems to have ended suddenly at the point where the story was not completed at all.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this chapter, which is the final chapter of The Tale of Genji, namely the end of the whole of The Tale of Genji, seems to have ended suddenly at the point where the story was not completed at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このために「終わることなく終わりを告げる」等と評されており、作者が構想通りここで完結するように書き進められてきて予定通り完結させたのか、それとももっと先まで書き進める構想はあったが何らかの事情でここで中断してしまったのか議論になることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, this chapter is commented as the one which &quot;tells the end without ending&quot;, and it sometimes generates the arguments whether the author went on writing with the idea of ending at this point and completed as planned or stopped writing halfway through for any reason though she intended to continue writing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, this chapter is commented as the one which &quot;tells the end without ending,&quot; and it sometimes generates the arguments whether the author went on writing with the idea of ending at this point and completed as planned or stopped writing halfway through for some reason though she intended to continue writing.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, this chapter is commented as the one which &apos;tells the end without ending,&apos; and it sometimes generates the arguments whether the author went on writing with the idea of ending at this point and completed as planned or stopped writing halfway through for some reason though she intended to continue writing.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、これに関連してこの巻が「とぞ本にはべめる」（と本に書いてある）という独特の終わり方をしている点も注目されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, the fact that this chapter ended with the unique phrase &quot;tozo hon ni habemeru&quot; (written in a book) is also noteworthy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the fact that this chapter ended with the unique phrase &quot;tozo hon ni habemeru&quot; (written in a book) is also noteworthy.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the fact that this chapter ended with the unique phrase &apos;tozo hon ni habemeru&apos; (written in a book) is also noteworthy.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>巻名について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Title of the chapter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Title of the chapter</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Title of the chapter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>源氏物語の多くの巻名のほとんどが本文中にある言葉（特に歌の中にある言葉）から取られているのに対してこの「夢浮橋」という言葉は本文中に見られない言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While most of the chapter titles of The Tale of Genji were named after the words used in respective texts (especially the words used in waka poems), this title &quot;Yume no Ukihashi&quot; is not seen in the text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While most of the chapter titles of The Tale of Genji were named after the words used in respective texts (especially the words used in waka poems), this title &quot;Yume no Ukihashi&quot; is not seen in the text.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While most of the chapter titles of The Tale of Genji were named after the words used in respective texts (especially the words used in waka poems), this title &apos;Yume no Ukihashi&apos; is not seen in the text.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>藤原定家の古注釈『源氏物語奥入』では出典未詳の古歌「世の中は夢の渡りの浮橋かうちわたりつつものをこそ思へ」に関連するとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Genji monogatari Okuiri&quot;, an ancient commentary written by FUJIWARA no Teika, this title related to an anonymous ancient waka poem &quot;Yononakaha yumenowatarino ukihashika uchiwataritsutsu monookosoomoe&quot; (The world is something like a floating bridge of dream and I am lost in thought while crossing it).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Genji monogatari Okuiri,&quot; an ancient commentary written by FUJIWARA no Teika, this title related to an anonymous ancient waka poem &quot;Yononakaha yumenowatarino ukihashika uchiwataritsutsu monookosoomoe&quot; (The world is something like a floating bridge of dreams and I am lost in thought while crossing it).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Genji monogatari Okuiri,&quot; an ancient commentary written by FUJIWARA no Teika, this title related to an anonymous ancient waka poem &apos;Yononakaha yumenowatarino ukihashika uchiwataritsutsu monookosoomoe&apos; (The world is something like a floating bridge of dreams and I am lost in thought while crossing it).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、本帖は「法の師」という異名で呼ばれることがあるが、この「法の師」という言葉は本帖中の薫の歌のなかに存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, this chapter is sometimes called &quot;Norinoshi, its another name, and the word &quot;Norinoshi&quot; exists in Kaoru&apos;s waka poem used in the text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, this chapter is sometimes called &quot;Norinoshi,&quot; and the word &quot;Norinoshi&quot; exists in Kaoru&apos;s waka poem used in the text.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, this chapter is sometimes called &apos;Norinoshi,&apos; and the word &apos;Norinoshi&apos; exists in Kaoru&apos;s waka poem used in the text.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline of the cahpter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline of the chapter</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>薫28歳の夏の話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tale in the summer when Kaoru was 28 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tale tells of the summer when Kaoru was 28 years old.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tale tells of the summer when Kaoru was 28 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>薫は比叡山の奥・横川（よかわ）を訪ね、小野で出家した女について僧都に詳しく尋ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru visited Yokawa, deep Mt. Hiei, and asked sozu in detail about a woman who had become a nun at On.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru visited Yokawa, deep in Mt. Hiei, and asked sozu in detail about a woman who had become a nun at On.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru visited Yokawa, deep in Mt. Hiei, and asked sozu (a prelate) in detail about a woman who had become a priest at Ono.</e>
<cmt>僧都　に補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「その女は浮舟 (源氏物語)に違いない」と確信した薫は夢のような気がして涙を落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru was convinced that a woman in question was Ukifune (The Tale of Genji), felt as if he had a bad dream and shed tears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru was convinced that the woman in question was Ukifune (The Tale of Genji), and felt as if he had had a bad dream and shed tears.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru was convinced that the woman in question was Ukifune (The Tale of Genji), and felt as if he had had a bad dream and shed tears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その様子を見て、僧都は浮舟を出家させたことを後悔した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he saw the look of kaoru, sozu regretted that he had made Ukifune a nun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he saw Kaoru&apos;s look, sozu regretted that he had made Ukifune a nun.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he saw Kaoru&apos;s look, sozu regretted that he had made Ukifune a priest.</e>
<cmt>nun →priest　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>薫は僧都に浮舟のいる小野への案内を頼むが「今は難しいが来月なら御案内しましょう」と述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kaoru asked him to guide to Ono where Ukifune resided, sozu said &quot;it is difficult now, but I will guide you some time in the next month&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kaoru asked him to guide him to Ono where Ukifune resided, sozu said &quot;it is difficult now, but I will guide you some time in the next month.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kaoru asked him to guide him to Ono where Ukifune resided, sozu said &apos;it is difficult now, but I will guide you some time in the next month.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>薫は浮舟への口添え文を僧都に懇願して書いてもらう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After imploring sozu to write a letter of good word for Ukifune, Kaoru was given a letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After imploring sozu to write a letter of good word for Ukifune, Kaoru was given a letter.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After imploring sozu to write a letter of good word for Ukifune, Kaoru was given a letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>その夜、横川から下山する薫一行の松明の火が（浮舟がいる）小野の庵からも見えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same night, lights of Kaoru&apos;s party, who were then descending from Yokawa, were visible from hermitage at Ono (where Ukifune resided).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same night, lights of Kaoru&apos;s party, who were then descending from Yokawa, were visible from the hermitage at Ono (where Ukifune resided).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same night, lights of Kaoru&apos;s party, who were then descending from Yokawa, were visible from the hermitage at Ono (where Ukifune resided).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>妹尼たちが薫の噂をする中、浮舟は薫との思い出を払うように念仏を唱える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While imoutoama and others were chatting about Kaoru, Ukifune was intoning nenbutsu (invocation of Amida Buddha) in order to forget the memory of Kaoru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While imoutoama and others were chatting about Kaoru, Ukifune was intoning nenbutsu (invocation of Amida Buddha) in order to forget the memory of Kaoru.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While imoutoama and others were chatting about Kaoru, Ukifune was intoning nenbutsu (invocation of Amida Buddha) in order to forget the memory of Kaoru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>翌日、薫の使者として　浮舟の異父弟・小君が小野を訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following day, Ogimi, Ukifune&apos;s younger brother with the same father, visited Ono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the following day, Ogimi, Ukifune&apos;s younger brother with the same father, visited Ono.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the following day, Ogimi, Ukifune&apos;s younger maternal half-brother, visited Ono.</e>
<cmt>異父弟　の表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>朝早くに僧都から前日の事情を知らせる文が届いており、妹尼たちが浮舟の素性に驚いていたところだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He visited when imoutoama and others were surprised to know Ukifune&apos;s background since they had received in the early morning the letter from sozu informing what happened the day before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He visited when imoutoama and others were surprised to know Ukifune&apos;s background since they had received in the early morning the letter from sozu informing what happened the day before.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He visited when imoutoama and others were surprised to know Ukifune&apos;s background since they had received in the early morning the letter from sozu informing what happened the day before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>小君が持参した僧都の文には、薫との復縁と還俗の勧めをほのめかしてあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letter of sozu brought by Ogimi gave Ukifune a hint that she should restore her relationship with Kaoru and return to a secular life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letter of sozu brought by Ogimi gave Ukifune a hint that she should restore her relationship with Kaoru and return to a secular life.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letter of sozu brought by Ogimi gave Ukifune a hint that she should restore her relationship with Kaoru and return to a secular life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>簾越しに異父弟の姿を見た浮舟は動揺する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune, who had seen her younger brother with the same father over a bamboo screen, became unsettled.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune, who had seen her younger brother with the same father over a bamboo screen, became unsettled.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune, who had seen her younger maternal half-brother over a bamboo screen, became unsettled.</e>
<cmt>異父弟　の表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、結局は心を崩さず、妹尼のとりなしにも応ぜず、小君との対面も拒み、薫の文にも「（宛先が）人違いだったらいけない」と言って受け取ろうとしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, however, she didn&apos;t open her heart, didn&apos;t accept the mediation of imoutoama, refused to meet Ogimi and refused to receive Kaoru&apos;s letter by saying &quot;an addressee is wrong&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, however, she didn&apos;t open her heart, didn&apos;t accept the mediation of imoutoama, refused to meet Ogimi and refused to receive Kaoru&apos;s letter by saying &quot;the addressee is wrong.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, however, she didn&apos;t open her heart, didn&apos;t accept the mediation of imoutoama, refused to meet Ogimi and refused to receive Kaoru&apos;s letter by saying &apos;the addressee is wrong.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>むなしく帰京した小君から「対面できず、お返事も下さらなかった」と聞いた薫は（自分が浮舟を宇治に隠していたように）「他の誰かが浮舟を小野に隠しているのではないか」と思うのだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he heard from Ogimi, who returned to Kyoto in vain, his report saying &quot;I couldn&apos;t meet Ukifune and she didn&apos;t give her response&quot;, Kaoru suspected that someone else hid Ukifune in Uji (as he hid Ukifune in Uji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he heard from Ogimi, who returned to Kyoto in vain, his report saying &quot;I couldn&apos;t meet Ukifune and she didn&apos;t give her response,&quot; Kaoru suspected that someone else hid Ukifune in Uji (as he hid Ukifune in Uji).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he heard from Ogimi, who returned to Kyoto in vain, his report saying &apos;I couldn&apos;t meet Ukifune and she didn&apos;t give her response,&apos; Kaoru suspected that someone else hid Ukifune in Uji (as he hid Ukifune in Uji).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), きまま(id:183217), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>