<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>茶湯一会集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chanoyu Ichie Shu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chanoyu Ichie Shu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chanoyu Ichie Shu (Collection on the Oneness of Chanoyu)</e>
<cmt>説明補足</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>茶湯一会集(ちゃのゆいちえしゅう)は、江戸時代末期の彦根藩主井伊直弼(茶号/宗観)の著による茶書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chanoyu Ichie Shu (Collection on the Oneness of Chanoyu)&quot; is a book on tea ceremony written by Naosuke II (appellation in tea ceremony: Sokan), the lord of the Hikone Domain in the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chanoyu Ichie Shu (Collection on the Oneness of Chanoyu)&quot; is a book on tea ceremony written by Naosuke II (title in tea ceremony: Sokan), the lord of the Hikone Domain in the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Word usage.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chanoyu Ichie Shu (Collection on the Oneness of Chanoyu)&quot; is a book on tea ceremony written by Naosuke II (title in tea ceremony: Sokan), the lord of the Hikone Domain in the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>茶道における「一期一会」の理念を広めており、茶の湯における主客の深い心構えを提唱している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book propagates the concept of &quot;Ichigo ichie&quot; at tea ceremony and proposes the thoughtful attitude of the host at the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book propagates the concept of &quot;Ichigo ichie&quot; which advocates a thoughtful attitude from the host during a tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book propagates the concept of &apos;Ichigo ichie&apos; (meeting only once in a lifetime) which advocates a thoughtful attitude from the host during a tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>一期一会の説明補足&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>二十三ヵ条にわたる本文の冒頭に「一期一会」の思想を、『本日の出会いは、再び同じ出会いではないと考え、主人は全てのことに、気を配り、客も亭主の趣向を何一つおろそかにせず、心に留めて、双方が誠意をもって交わるべきである』と主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of this book of 23 articles, Ii stated the idea of ichigo ichie: &quot;We should keep in mind that an encounter today can never be experienced again. The host should pay attention to every single matter and guests should never neglect the host&apos;s care. Both should communicate with the earnestness.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of this book consisting of 23 articles, Ii states the idea of ichigo ichie: &quot;We should keep in mind that an encounter today can never be experienced again. The host should pay attention to every single matter and guests should never neglect the host&apos;s care. Both should communicate in earnest.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of this book consisting of 23 articles, Ii states the idea of &apos;ichigo ichie&apos;: &quot;We should keep in mind that an encounter today can never be experienced again, so the host should pay attention to every single matter and guests should never neglect the host&apos;s care; both should communicate in earnest.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文が一文のため、訳文も一文に変更しました。「一期一会」に &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>激動の幕末にあって、静寂の極致のような茶室での心を、時の為政者である直弼が残していることは興味深く後世における本書の魅力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is quite interesting that Ii, a statesman at the time of political turmoil at the end of Tokugawa Shogunate, wrote a book on the desirable attitude of absolute stillness for tea ceremony, which makes the book attractive to people down the ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is quite interesting that Ii, a statesman at the time of political turmoil at the end of Tokugawa Shogunate, wrote a book advocating absolute stillness during a tea ceremony, which continues to make the book attractive to people throughout the ages.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is quite interesting that Ii, a statesman at the time of political turmoil at the end of Tokugawa Shogunate, wrote a book advocating absolute stillness during a tea ceremony, which continues to make the book attractive to people throughout the ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Completion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conclusion</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conclusion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>成立は、本文中の記述から安政5年と考えられ、桜田門外で非業の死を遂げる2年前とみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The description in the book indicates that Chanoyu Ichie Shu was completed in 1858, two years before Ii assassinated in the Sakuradamongai Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descriptions in the book indicate that Chanoyu Ichie Shu was completed in 1858, two years before Ii was assassinated in the Sakuradamongai Incident.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descriptions in the book indicate that Chanoyu Ichie Shu was completed in 1858, two years before Ii was assassinated in the Sakuradamongai Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>封建国家が変質を遂げる過程での出来事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident occurred in the course of change of the feudal nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident occurred during the course of change in the feudal nation.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident occurred during the course of change in the feudal nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>原典</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Original manuscript</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Original manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Original manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>原本は彦根市の井伊家に、草稿と清書本の二本が伝来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the original manuscript of Chanoyu Ichie Shu, its draft manuscript and a clean copied book are kept by the Ii family in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original manuscript of Chanoyu Ichie Shu, its draft manuscript and a clean copy, are both kept by the Ii family in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original manuscript of Chanoyu Ichie Shu, its draft manuscript and a clean copy, are both kept by the Ii family in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mixtures(id:29234), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), MCHC(id:208548), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>