<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蕉風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shofu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shofu (a style of Haikai)</e>
<cmt>説明補足</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>蕉風（しょうふう）とは、松尾芭蕉を祖とする俳諧の流派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shofu is a style of the Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) with Basho MATSUO as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shofu is a style of Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse), the originator of which is Basho MATSUO.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shofu is a style of Haikai (17-syllable verse), the originator of which is Basho MATSUO.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正風とも書き、蕉門ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanji characters for Shofu are 蕉風 or 正風, and it is also called Shomon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kanji (Chinese characters) for Shofu are &quot;蕉風&quot; or &quot;正風&quot;, and it can also be called Shomon.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kanji (Chinese characters) for Shofu are &quot;蕉風&quot; or &quot;正風&quot;, and it can also be called Shomon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>松尾芭蕉は、当初談林派の俳諧であったが、それまでの日本における詩歌を基にしながらも、日常的なものを素材とする独自の俳諧の流儀を生み出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basho MATUSO started as a haikai poet of the Danrin school, but gradually he produced his own style of haikai on ordinary things with the basis of traditional Japanese poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basho MATSUO started as a haikai poet of the Danrin school, but gradually he produced his own style of haikai on ordinary things with a basis in traditional Japanese poetry.</e>
<cmt>Spelled &quot;MATSUO&quot; in previous cell.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basho MATSUO started as a haikai poet of the Danrin school, but gradually he produced his own style of haikai on ordinary things with a basis in traditional Japanese poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>俳諧における蕉風の理念は、「侘び」・「寂び」・「しをり」・「ほそみ」・「かろみ」などの言葉で表される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principle of Shofu style of haikai is represented by the terms such as Wabi, Sabi (these two imply the beauty of simplicity), Shiori (a capacity for empathy), Hosomi (understatement), or Karomi (a light tone).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principle of the Shofu style of haikai is represented by terms such as Wabi, Sabi (these two imply the beauty of simplicity), Shiori (a capacity for empathy), Hosomi (understatement), or Karomi (a light tone).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principle of the Shofu style of haikai is represented by terms such as Wabi, Sabi (these two imply the beauty of simplicity), Shiori (a capacity for empathy), Hosomi (understatement), or Karomi (a light tone).</e>
<cmt>原文には「」がついてますが、括弧書きがあり、&apos; &apos; をつけるとかえって見づらくなると思い、訂正していません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>