<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>愛宕百韻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atagohyakuin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atagohyakuin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atago Hyakuin (a linked verse of Mitsuhide AKECHI and others)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>愛宕百韻（あたごひゃくいん）は、本能寺の変の直前に愛宕山 (京都市)で明智光秀が張行した連歌である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atagohyakuin was a linked verse known as Renga, which was composed by a warrior Mitsuhide AKECHI and others at Mt. Atago in Kyoto immediately before his coup the Incident of Honnoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atagohyakuin was a linked verse known as Renga, which was composed by a warrior Mitsuhide AKECHI and others at Mt. Atago in Kyoto immediately before his coup, the Incident of Honnoji.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atago Hyakuin was a linked verse known as Renga, which was composed by Mitsuhide AKECHI and others at Mt. Atago in Kyoto immediately before his coup, the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「明智光秀張行百韻」とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Akechi Mitsuhide Chogyo Hyakuin&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as &apos;Akechi Mitsuhide Chogyo Hyakuin&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Akechi Mitsuhide Chogyo Hyakuin&apos; (100 verses composed by Mitsuhide AKECHI and others).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天正10年（1582年）5月24日 (旧暦)（あるいは28日）、明智光秀が山城国愛宕山の威徳院で、明智光慶、東行澄、里村紹巴、里村昌叱、猪苗代兼如、里村心前、宥源、行祐と巻いた百韻である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a poem of a hundred links composed on June 24 or 28, 1582 by Mitsuhide AKECHI, Mitsuyoshi AKECHI, Gyocho AZUMA, Joha SATOMURA, Shoshitsu SATOMURA, Kennyo INAWASHIRO, Shinzen SATOMURA, Yugen, and Gyoyu at Itokuin Temple on Mt. Atago in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>「東行澄」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a poem of a hundred links composed on June 24 or 28, 1582, by Mitsuhide AKECHI, Mitsuyoshi AKECHI, Gyocho AZUMA, Joha SATOMURA, Shoshitsu SATOMURA, Kennyo INAWASHIRO, Shinzen SATOMURA, Yugen, and Gyoyu at Itokuin Temple on Mt. Atago in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a poem of 100 links composed on June 24 (or 28), 1582, by Mitsuhide AKECHI, Mitsuyoshi AKECHI, Gyocho AZUMA, Joha SATOMURA, Shoshitsu SATOMURA, Kennyo INAWASHIRO, Shinzen SATOMURA, Yugen, and Gyoyu at Itokuin Temple on Mt. Atago in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>発句は光秀の「ときは今 あめが下しる 五月かな」、脇は威徳院行祐の「水上まさる 庭の夏山」、第三は里村紹巴の「花落つる 池の流を せきとめて」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opening stanza was composed by Mitsuhide AKECHI &apos;Toki wa Ima Ame ga Shitashiru Satsuki kana&apos;; the second stanza was composed by Itokuin Gyoyu &apos;Minakami masaru Niwa no Natsuyama&apos;; and the third stanza was composed by Joha SATOMURA &apos;Hana otsuru Ike no nagare wo Sekitomete.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opening stanza was composed by Mitsuhide AKECHI &apos;Toki wa Ima Ame ga Shitashiru Satsuki kana&apos;; the second stanza was composed by Itokuin Gyoyu &apos;Minakami masaru Niwa no Natsuyama&apos;; and the third stanza was composed by Joha SATOMURA &apos;Hana otsuru Ike no nagare wo Sekitomete.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first line was &apos;Toki wa Ima Ame ga Shita-shiru Satsuki kana&apos; (It is May, a rainy season) composed by Mitsuhide AKECHI; the second &apos;Minakami masaru Niwa no Natsuyama&apos; (river flow flashes in the garden on summer mountain) composed by Itokuin Gyoyu; and the third &apos;Hana otsuru Ike no nagare wo Sekitomete&apos; (falling flowers keep back the flow of the pond) composed by Joha SATOMURA.</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、句の英訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>発句は、その姓の「土岐」をいいかけて、「雨が下」に「天が下」をいいかけて、主人織田信長の殺害という宿願の祈請のものであるといい、紹巴はこのために責問を受けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opening stanza is considered that Mitsuhide used the word &apos;Toki&quot;, meaning &apos;Now, its (a time)&apos;, to imply his surname &apos;the Toki clan&apos;, and &apos;Ame ga Shita&apos;, meaning &apos;it&apos;s raining&apos;, to imply &apos;Tennka&apos;, the whole country, to show his long-held wish of killing his master Nobunaga ODA--for which Joha SATOMURA was demanded an explanation later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that for the opening stanza Mitsuhide used the word &apos;Toki&quot;, meaning &apos;Now, its (a time)&apos;, to imply his surname &apos;the Toki clan&apos;, and &apos;Ame ga Shita&apos;, meaning &apos;it&apos;s raining&apos;, to imply &apos;Tennka&apos;, the whole country, to show his long-held wish of killing his master Nobunaga ODA--for which Joha SATOMURA demanded an explanation later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first line is supposed to include the word &apos;Toki&apos; (meaning &apos;It is&apos;) also implied Mitsuhide&apos;s surname, and &apos;Ame ga Shita&apos; also meant &apos;Tenka&apos; (the whole country), to show his long-held wish of killing his master Nobunaga ODA for which Joha demanded an explanation later.</e>
<cmt>原文には 「土岐氏」とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「土岐」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また発句の「あめが下なる」を「あめが下しる」に改めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that &apos;Ame ga Shitanaru&apos;, meaning &apos;it has been raining&apos; to imply that &apos;(Mitsuhide) have took the whole country&apos;, in the opening stanza was rewrote &apos;Ame ga Shitanaru&apos;, meaning &apos;it&apos;s raining&apos; to imply that &apos;(Mitsuhide) is going to take the whole country.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that &apos;Ame ga Shitanaru&apos;, meaning &apos;it has been raining&apos; implies that &apos;(Mitsuhide) took the whole country&apos;, in the opening stanza was rewritten &apos;Ame ga Shitanaru&apos;, meaning &apos;it&apos;s raining&apos; to imply that &apos;(Mitsuhide) is going to take the whole country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>verb conjugation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that &apos;Ame ga Shita-shiru&apos; (to have the meaning &apos;coming into power&apos; as well) in the first line was changed from &apos;Ame ga Shita-naru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>続群書類従に収める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This verse is contained in &apos;Shoku Gunshoruiju.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This verse is contained in &apos;Shoku Gunshoruiju.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This verse is contained in Zoku-Gunsho Ruiju (The Library of Historical Documents, Continued).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>