<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都学派四天王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Big Four of the Kyoto School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Big Four of the Kyoto School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Big Four of the Kyoto School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都学派四天王（きょうとがくはしてんのう）とは高坂正顕、西谷啓治、高山岩男、鈴木成高の京都学派に属する四人の学者のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Big four of the Kyoto School refers to the following four scholars who belonged to the Kyoto School: Masaaki KOSAKA, Keiji NISHITANI, Iwao KOYAMA and Shigetaka SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Big Four refers to the following four scholars who belonged to the Kyoto School: Masaaki KOSAKA, Keiji NISHITANI, Iwao KOYAMA and Shigetaka SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Big Four of the Kyoto school refers to the following four scholars who belonged to the Kyoto School: Masaaki KOSAKA, Keiji NISHITANI, Iwao KOYAMA and Shigetaka SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>戦後、戦争協力の廉で京都大学を離れた（高坂正顕、西谷啓治は後に京都大学に復帰）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World War II, they were purged from Kyoto University on charges of giving assistance for the war (Masaaki KOSAKA and Keiji NISHITANI were later reinstated at Kyoto University).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War II, they were purged from Kyoto University on charges of having assisted the war effort (Masaaki KOSAKA and Keiji NISHITANI were later reinstated at Kyoto University).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II, they were purged from Kyoto University on charges of having assisted the war effort (Masaaki KOSAKA and Keiji NISHITANI were later reinstated at Kyoto University).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>戦時下の1942年から翌年にかけて 『中央公論』誌上で三回にわたり掲載され、大東亜戦争を「世界史の哲学」の立場から思想的に位置付けようと試みた「世界史的立場と日本」座談会（「世界史的立場と日本」1942年一月号、「東亜共栄圏の倫理性と歴史性」1942年四月号、「総力戦の哲学」1943年一月号）の出席者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were participants in the symposiums on &apos;The World-historic position and Japan&apos;, which was reported on three times in &quot;Chuo koron&quot; from 1942 to the next year, during wartime (&apos;The World-historic Position and Japan&apos; in the January 1942 issue, &apos;The Ethics and Historic Position of the East Asia Co-prosperity Sphere&apos; in the April 1942 issue and &apos;The Philosophy of Total War&apos; in the January 1943 issue); in these they had tried to determine what the ideological standing of the Greater East Asia War was from the point of view of the &apos;philosophy of world history&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were participants in the symposiums on &apos;The World Historic Position and Japan&apos;, which appeared three times in &quot;Chuo koron&quot; from 1942 to the following year, during the war: &apos;The World Historic Position and Japan&apos; in the January 1942 issue, &apos;The Ethics and Historical Position of the East Asia Co-prosperity Sphere&apos; in the April 1942 issue and &apos;The Philosophy of Total War&apos; in the January 1943 issue; in these they had tried to determine what the ideological standing of the Greater East Asia War was from the point of view of the &apos;philosophy of world history&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war, they were participants in the symposiums on &apos;The World Historic Position and Japan&apos; (&apos;The World Historic Position and Japan&apos; in the January 1942 issue, &apos;The Ethics and Historical Position of the East Asia Co-prosperity Sphere&apos; in the April 1942 issue and &apos;The Philosophy of Total War&apos; in the January 1943 issue), which appeared three times in &quot;Chuo koron&quot; magazine from 1942 to the following year and in these they had tried to determine what the ideological standing of the Greater East Asia War was from the point of view of the &apos;philosophy of world history.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>大東亜戦争中に京都学派と大日本帝国海軍との間で定期的に行われ、東條内閣打倒や大日本帝国陸軍の方針の是正が話し合われた秘密会合の常連出席者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were regular participants of closed-door meetings during the Greater East Asia War that were periodically held between the Kyoto School and the Imperial Japanese Navy and the topics were about the overthrow of the Tojo cabinet and the rectification of the course of the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were regular participants of closed-door meetings during the Greater East Asia War that were periodically held between the Kyoto School and the Imperial Japanese Navy, topics being about the overthrow of the Tojo cabinet and the restoration of the course of the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were regular participants of closed-door meetings during the Greater East Asia War that were periodically held between the Kyoto School and the Imperial Japanese Navy, topics being about the overthrow of the Tojo cabinet and the restoration of the course of the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>「世界史の哲学」は大日本帝国陸軍の皇道派により国体思想として攻撃されていたが、大川周明『近世欧羅巴植民史』の亜流とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the &apos;philosophy of world history&apos; was criticized as the ideology of kokutai (national polity) by the Kodo-ha (&apos;Imperial Way&apos; faction) of the Imperial Japanese Army, there is another theory that it was an echo of Shumei OKAWA&apos;s &quot;Colonization in Early-modern European History&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the &apos;philosophy of world history&apos; was criticized as being the ideology of the kokutai (national polity) by the Kodo-ha (&apos;Imperial Way&apos; faction) of the Imperial Japanese Army, there is another view that it was heavily based on Shumei OKAWA&apos;s &quot;Colonization in Early-modern European History&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the &apos;philosophy of world history&apos; was criticized as being the ideology of the kokutai (national polity) by the Kodo-ha (&apos;Imperial Way&apos; faction) of the Imperial Japanese Army, there is another view that it was heavily based on Shumei OKAWA&apos;s &quot;Colonization in Early-modern European History.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 廿粁(id:219234), Straysheep(id:42448), Satooya(id:213741), Mooko(id:36162), Amikake3(id:89826), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>