<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鞍馬天狗 (小説)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurama Tengu (novel)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurama Tengu (novel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurama Tengu (novel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『鞍馬天狗』（くらまてんぐ）は、大佛次郎の大正・昭和期における時代小説、およびその主人公の名前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; is the title of the series of historical novels written by Jiro OSARAGI in Taisho and Showa periods, as well as the name of its protagonist.</e>
<cmt>シリーズものですのでthe series ofを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; is the title of the series of historical novels written by Jiro OSARAGI in Taisho and Showa periods, as well as the name of its protagonist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; is the title of the series of historical novels written by Jiro OSARAGI in Taisho and Showa periods, as well as the name of its protagonist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>幕末期を舞台に「鞍馬天狗」を名乗る勤王志士の活躍を描いたもので、大衆小説の代表作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The novels, one of the most famous popular fictions in Japan, depicts the activities of a royalist who called himself &apos;Kurama Tengu (a long-nosed goblin who lives on Mt. Kurama)&apos; at the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「大衆小説の代表作」を「最も有名な大衆小説の一つ」としました。「鞍馬天狗」のイメージがEnglish readersに感じられるよう、「鞍馬山に住む鼻の長いgoblin」という説明をかっこの中に入れて加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The novels, one of the most famous popular fictions in Japan, depicts the activities of a royalist who called himself &apos;Kurama Tengu (a long-nosed goblin who lives on Mt. Kurama)&apos; at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The novels, one of the most famous popular fictions in Japan, depicts the activities of a royalist who called himself &apos;Kurama Tengu&apos; (a long-nosed goblin who lives on Mt. Kurama) at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>1924年（大正13年）の誕生以降、1965年（昭和40年）まで長編・短編併せて計47作が発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since its birth in 1924 until 1965 a total of 47 works of long novels and short stories were published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since its birth in 1924 until 1965 a total of 47 long novels and short stories have been published.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it started in 1924, a total of 47 long novels and short stories have been published until 1965.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>何度も映画化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; was filmed many times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処主語を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; was made into a movie many times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was made into a movie many times.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>特にアラカンこと嵐寛寿郎が主役の映画作品は有名であり、一般に思い浮かべられる鞍馬天狗像は嵐寛寿郎の演じたものの影響が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially the movies starring Arakan or Kanjuro ARASHI were so famous that the generally recalled image of Kurama Tengu was greatly influenced by the one by Kanjuro ARASHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文通り訳しましたが、英語としてはby the oneはないほうがいいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially the movies starring Arakan or Kanjuro ARASHI were so famous and the generally recalled image of Kurama Tengu was greatly influenced by the movie that starred Kanjuro ARASHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movies starring Arakan, or Kanjuro ARASHI, were so famous that the image of Kurama Tengu recalled for many was greatly influenced by the acting of Kanjuro ARASHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>本項では映画版、テレビドラマ版についても記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here we describe their film versions and television drama versions, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here we describe their film versions and television drama versions, as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here we describe both the film versions and television drama versions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>舞台背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>幕末期を舞台にしており、生麦事件・蛤御門の変といった歴史上の事件を背景としたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The series was set in the end of Edo period, and some stories have historical events such as Namamugi Incident and Conspiracy of Hamaguri-gomon Gate as their backgrounds.</e>
<cmt>主語として「シリーズは」を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The series was set at the end of the Edo period, and some stories include historical events such as the Namamugi Incident and the Conspiracy of the Hamaguri-gomon Gate as backgrounds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The series was set at the end of the Edo period, and some stories include historical events such as the Namamugi Incident and the Conspiracy of the Hamaguri-gomon Gate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>作品同士の関連性は、初期を除けば明確なつながりは見えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except some early ones, all the stories are not clearly connected each other.</e>
<cmt>「関連性」と「つながり」は重複していますので、「つながり」のみにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for some early ones, all the stories are not clearly connected to each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for some early ones, the stories are not clearly connected to each other.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>（「ポケット」連載分は一連につながっている所がある。また『鞍馬天狗倒れず』は『天狗倒し』の続きとなっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Some of the stories published consecutively in the magazine Pocket made a series).</e>
<cmt>「ポケット」に「雑誌の」を加えました。また「ポケット」は雑誌名ですので、””をつけるかわりにイタリックにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Some of the stories published consecutively in the magazine &quot;Pocket&quot; were a series).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Some of the stories published consecutively in the magazine &apos;Pocket&apos; were a series. &quot;Kurama Tengu Taorezu&quot; (Kurama Tengu is not defeated) follows &quot;Tengu Daoshi&quot; (Defeating Tengu)).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーション、半角カッコにしました。FBに基づいて修正しました。Kurama Tengu Taorezuにダブルクォーテーションを付けました。セル19は（）内に含まれるのでセル18に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>『角兵衛獅子』『天狗廻状』のように京都・大阪市が中心的な舞台となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cities of Kyoto and Osaka were the central cites of the stories such as &quot;Kakubeejisi (traveling entertainers who wear lion masks and perform tumbling acts)&quot; and &quot;Tengu Kaijo (a circular on Tengu).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「角兵衛獅子」と「廻状」の意味をEnglish readersのため、カッコに入れて加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cities of Kyoto and Osaka were the central cites of stories such as; &quot;Kakubeejisi&quot; (traveling entertainers who wear lion masks and perform tumbling acts) and &quot;Tengu Kaijo&quot; (a circular on Tengu).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cities of Kyoto and Osaka were the central cites of stories such as; &quot;Kakubei Jishi&quot; (traveling entertainers who wear lion masks and perform tumbling acts) and &quot;Tengu Kaijo&quot; (a circular on Tengu).</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、作品によっては江戸・横浜市の関東地方、果ては松前町 (北海道)といった場所も舞台となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But some stories took place in Kanto area including Edo and Yokohama city, and others took place in the far towns such as Matsumae (Hokkaido).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But some stories took place in the Kanto area including Edo and Yokohama city, and others took place in far towns such as Matsumae (Hokkaido).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But some stories took place in the Kanto region including Edo and Yokohama City, and others took place in far-away towns such as Matsumae-cho (Hokkaido).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、戦後発表された作品には明治を舞台にしたものも見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also some works that were published after the World War II describing the events in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>戦後は「二次大戦後」としました。以下同様です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also some works that were published after the World War II describing events during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also some works that were published after the World War II describing events during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物としての鞍馬天狗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurama Tengu as a person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurama Tengu as a person</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurama Tengu as a person</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>普段は倉田典膳（くらたでんぜん）と名乗るが本名ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He usually called himself Denzen KURATA which was not his real name.</e>
<cmt>読み方は、原文に従い「でんぜん」としております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He usually called himself Denzen KURATA which was not his real name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He usually called himself Denzen KURATA which was not his real name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また作品によっては館岡弥吉郎（たておかやきちろう）、海野雄吉（うんのゆうきち）とも名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some works he called himself Yakichiro TATEOKA, or Yukichi UNNO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some works he called himself Yakichiro TATEOKA, or Yukichi UNNO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some works he called himself Yakichiro TATEOKA, or Yukichi UNNO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その容姿は、『角兵衛獅子』に「身長五尺五寸ぐらい。中肉にして白皙、鼻筋とおり、目もと清（すず）し。」という描写がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his features and figure, he was depicted in &quot;Kakubeejisi&quot; as &apos;a man of about 165 cm in height, medium build, with a fair-complexioned face, a well-formed nose, and beautiful eyes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>容姿の描写は、切るとおさまりが悪かったため一文として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his features and figure, he was depicted in &quot;Kakubeejisi&quot; as &apos;a man of about 165 cm in height, medium build, with a fair-complexion, a well-formed nose, and beautiful eyes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding his features and figure, he was depicted in &quot;Kakubei Jishi&quot; as &apos;a man of about 165 cm in height, medium build, with a fair-complexion, a well-formed nose and beautiful eyes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>宗十郎頭巾に紋付の着流し姿をしたイメージは、アラカン主演の映画における姿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His typical image in a Sojuro hood and a kimono with the family crest, but without a formal haori nor a hakama was that of Arakan, the starring actor of the films.</e>
<cmt>「アラカン主演の映画における姿」を、「映画における主演俳優アラカンの姿」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typically he wore a Sojuro hood and a kimono with the family crest, but without a formal haori nor a hakama played by Arakan, the starring actor of the films.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typically he wore a Sojuro hood and a kimono with the family crest, but without a formal haori (a Japanese half-coat) nor a hakama (pleated and divided skirt made in fine stripes) in films starring Arakan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>日本の未来を思う討幕派の志士ではあるが、幕府側である勝海舟と繋がったり、新選組の近藤勇とも奇妙な交友関係をもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he was a royalist who seriously ponders about Japanese future, he was sometimes connected with Kaishu KATSU who worked for the Government, and had a strange friendship with Isami KONDO of Shinsengumi, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he was a royalist who seriously pondered about the future of Japan, he was sometimes connected with Kaishu KATSU who worked for the Government, and also had a strange friendship with Isami KONDO of Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though he was a royalist who was worried about the future of Japan, he was sometimes connected with Kaishu KATSU, who worked for the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and also had a strange friendship with Isami KONDO of Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（実際小説で近藤勇と一対一で対峙するのは『角兵衛獅子』1作のみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(His one-on-one battle with Isami KONDO was actually depicted only in &quot;Kakubeejisi&quot; in all the original works).</e>
<cmt>英語として自然なように「原作小説すべてのうちで近藤勇と一対一で戦うのは実際『角兵衛獅子』の中でのみ描かれている」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(His one-on-one battle with Isami KONDO was actually depicted only in &quot;Kakubeejisi&quot; in all the original works).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Among the original novels, his one-on-one battle with Isami KONDO was actually depicted only in &quot;Kakubei Jishi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、明治維新後は明治政府に対して否定的な部分を持つなど、権力の批判者であることを貫いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was always critical to authority; after the Meiji Restoration he was sometimes negative against the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was quite critical of authority; after the Meiji Restoration he was sometimes negative against the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was quite critical of authority; after the Meiji Restoration he was sometimes negative against the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>剣は一刀流の凄腕。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a crackerjack of swordsmanship of the Itto school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a crackerjack swordsmanship of the Itto school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a top swordsman in the Itto school.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>時には火縄銃弾丸重量による分類も使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes he also used matchlocks according to the classification of their bullet weight.</e>
<cmt>原文はそのままでは意味がわかりにくく、「火縄銃を、弾丸重量による分類に従って使用した」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes he also used matchlocks according to the classification of their bullet weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes he also used Tanzutsu (pistol).</e>
<cmt>「火縄銃弾丸重量」はWebでは「短筒」のリンク先ですので、「短筒」と直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その素性は謎が多く、天狗党の生き残りではないかと言われたこともあるが定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His past remained in mystery; a rumor said that he was probably a survivor of the Tengu Party, but unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His past remained in mystery; there was a rumor that he was probably a survivor of the Tengu Party, but unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His past remained in mystery; there was a rumor that he was probably a survivor of the Tengu-to (Tengu Party), but this is unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>作者は鞍馬天狗の最後は『パリ燃ゆ』の舞台であるパリ・コミューンの市街戦で戦死させる構想を持っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author seemed to have a plan that Kurama Tengu would be killed in a street fighting during the Paris Commune that was also the stage of OSARAGI&apos;s another work &quot;Pari Moyu (Paris Burns).&quot;</e>
<cmt>English readersのために、「パリ燃ゆ」に（大仏の作品）を付け加えました。「パリ燃ゆ」の定訳を見つけられませんでしたので、現代語訳である「パリが燃える」の英訳としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author seemed to have a plan that Kurama Tengu would be killed in a street fight during the Paris Commune that was also the stage of OSARAGI&apos;s another work &quot;Pari Moyu (Paris Burns).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author seemed to have a plan that Kurama Tengu would be killed in a street fight during the Paris Commune that was also the stage of Osaragi&apos;s another work &quot;Pari Moyu&quot; (Paris Burns).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置、および用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>鞍馬天狗と関わる人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who were associated with Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who were associated with Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who were associated with Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>杉作（すぎさく）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugisaku,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugisaku,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugisaku,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>鞍馬天狗を小父さんと慕う少年（実は、女の子）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a boy (actually a girl) who loved Kurama Tengu calling him pop.</e>
<cmt>前項に続く杉作の描写であろうと推測し、小文字で始めました。黒姫の吉兵衛も同様です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">a boy (actually a girl) who loved Kurama Tengu calling him pop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">a boy (actually a girl) who loved Kurama Tengu calling him pop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>黒姫の吉兵衛（くろひめのきちべえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurohime no Kichibee,</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA no Michinagaのように、「の」が間に入る場合は日本語の語順通りとしましたが、「黒姫の」は姓というより「黒姫出身の」や「黒姫にまつわる」などの意味ですので、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurohime no Kichibee,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurohime no Kichibei,</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>元盗賊で鞍馬天狗の右腕的存在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">who once was a thief, and now a right-hand of Kurama Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">who once was a thief, and now a right-hand of Kurama Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">who once was a thief, and now a right-hand of Kurama Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>作品一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the works of Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the works of Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the works of Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>短編と長編は福島行一の分け方による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification into long novels and short stories was done by Koichi FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classification into long novels and short stories was done by Koichi FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classification into long novels and short stories was done by Koichi FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>半角スペースにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>映画版</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movie versions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movie versions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movie versions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>鞍馬天狗の映画版は、1924年の実川延笑主演の『女人地獄』に始まり、1965年の市川雷蔵 (8代目)主演の『新 鞍馬天狗 五条坂の決闘』まである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movie versions of Kurama Tengu began in 1924 as &quot;Nyonin Jigoku (Hell with Women)&quot; starring Ensho JITSUKAWA, and finished in 1965 as &quot;The New Kurama Tengu, Gojozaka no Ketto (The Dual at the Slope of Gojo)&quot; starring Raizo ICHIKAWA (the eighth).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movie versions of Kurama Tengu began in 1924 as &quot;Nyonin Jigoku&quot; (Hell with Women) starring Ensho JITSUKAWA, and finished in 1965 as &quot;The New Kurama Tengu, Gojozaka no Ketto&quot; (The Dual at the Slope of Gojo) starring Raizo ICHIKAWA (the eighth).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movie versions of Kurama Tengu start from &quot;Nyonin Jigoku&quot; (Hell with Women) starring Ensho JITSUKAWA in 1924 to &quot;Shin Kurama Tengu, Gojozaka no Ketto&quot; (The Dual at the Slope of Gojo, The New Kurama Tengu) starring Raizo ICHIKAWA (the eighth Kurama Tengu) in 1965.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>延べ60本近く製作され、天狗は様々な俳優が演じてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A total of nearly sixty movies were produced, and various actors played the role of Tengu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A total of nearly sixty movies were produced, and various actors played the role of Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A total of nearly sixty movies were produced, and various actors played the role of Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>特に原作からは『角兵衛獅子』、『天狗廻状』が多く映画化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, &quot;Kakubeejisi&quot; and &quot;A Circular on Tengu&quot; were made into films repeatedly from the original novels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, &quot;Kakubeejisi&quot; and &quot;A Circular on Tengu&quot; were repeatedly made into films from the original novels.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the original novels, &quot;Kakubei Jishi&quot; and &quot;Tengu Kaijo&quot; were made into films several times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>その内40本以上はアラカンこと嵐寛寿郎（当初は嵐長三郎名義）が演じており、アラカンの鞍馬天狗が最も有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More than forty films of them starred Kanjuro ARASHI (at first in the name of Chozaburo ARASHI); thus Kurama Tengu by Arakan was the most famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More than forty films starred Kanjuro ARASHI (at first by the name of Chozaburo ARASHI); thus Kurama Tengu by Arakan was the most famous.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurama Tengu by Arakan was the most famous because more than forty films starred Kanjuro ARASHI (at that time known by the name of Chozaburo ARASHI).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、戦前撮られた『鞍馬天狗』には紛失・消失してしまい、現在では観られないものが多々ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But many of the &quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; films taken before the World War II were lost or disappeared, and are unable to be watched now.</e>
<cmt>原文どおり訳しましたが、英語ではwere lost or disappearedは重複となり不自然で、were lostだけのほうがいいのではないかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But many of the &quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; films produced before World War II were lost, and are unable to be watched now.</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But many of the &quot;Kurama Tengu&quot; films produced before World War II were lost, and are unable to be watched now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>アラカンと鞍馬天狗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arakan and Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arakan and Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arakan and Kurama Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>マキノ入社直後、嵐はマキノ省三から「このなかからやりたい役を選べ」と雑誌『少年倶楽部』昭和2年（1927年）3月号を渡される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after having joined the company of Makino, ARASHI was handed the 1927 March issue of the Shonen Club (Boys&apos; Club) magazine by Shozo MAKINO who said, &quot;Choose a role that you want to play from the stories here.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after having joined the company of Makino, ARASHI was handed the 1927 March issue of the Shonen Club (Boys&apos; Club) magazine by Shozo MAKINO who said, &quot;Choose a role that you want to play from the stories here.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after having joined the company of Makino, Arashi was handed the 1927 March issue of the Shonen Club (Boys&apos; Club) magazine by Shozo MAKINO who said, &apos;Choose a role that you want to play from the stories here.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語表記およびクォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>嵐は『角兵衛獅子』を読み、鞍馬天狗をやりたいと伝えたことにより、『鞍馬天狗余聞・角兵衛獅子』で映画デビューを果たす事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reading &quot;Kakubeejisi,&quot; he told that he wanted to play Kurama Tengu, and thus ARASHI made his screen debut in &quot;A Side Story of Kurama Tengu, Kakubeejisi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reading &quot;Kakubeejisi,&quot; he said that he wanted to play Kurama Tengu, and thus ARASHI made his screen debut in &quot;A Side Story of Kurama Tengu, Kakubeejisi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reading &quot;Kakubei Jishi,&quot; he said that he wanted to play Kurama Tengu, and thus Arashi made his screen debut in &quot;Kurama Tengu Yobun, Kakubei Jishi&quot; (A Side Story of Kurama Tengu, Kakubei Jishi).</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その後、嵐のはまり役として寛プロ・東亜キネマ・新興・日活・東宝・東映とまたに駆けて40本以上もの鞍馬天狗映画に出演した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then it became the best fit role for ARASHI, who performed Kurama Tengu in more than forty movies produced by several film studios: Kan Production, Toa Kinema, Shinko, Nikkatsu, Toho, and Toei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then it became the most suitable role for ARASHI, who performed Kurama Tengu in more than forty movies produced by several film studios: Kan Production, Toa Kinema, Shinko, Nikkatsu, Toho, and Toei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, Arashi was considered most suitable for the role and performed Kurama Tengu in more than forty movies produced by several film studios: Kan Pro (production), Toa Kinema, Shinko (Shinko Kinema Production), Nikkatsu (Nikkatsu Corporation), Toho (Toho Co., Ltd.), and Toei (Toei Company, Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>嵐扮する鞍馬天狗が敵を次々と切り倒すその壮快なチャンバラ劇は長きに渡り大衆を魅了し続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those films with exciting sword fights in which Kurama Tengu by ARASHI slashed down his enemies one after another kept charming the populace for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those films with the exciting sword fights in which Kurama Tengu played by ARASHI slashed down his enemies one after another continued to charm audiences for a long time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those films with the exciting sword fights in which Kurama Tengu played by Arashi slashed down his enemies one after another continued to charm audiences for a long time.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、原作者である大佛はこれに不満を抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, OSARAGI, the original author, was discontented with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, OSARAGI, the original author, was discontented with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Osaragi, the original author, was dissatisfied with this.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1954年、大佛は著作権無視、原作を書き換えて題名だけ盗んでいる、映画の鞍馬天狗は人を斬りすぎて原作者の意向を無視している等との理由を挙げて非難し、嵐が演ずる鞍馬天狗の中止を要求。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1954 OSARAGI demanded that ARASHI stop performing Kurama Tengu, blaming the films that his copyright was ignored, his titles were stolen while their original contents were rewritten, and Kuram Tengu in the films slashed too many people with his sword against OSARAGI&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>「理由を挙げて」は英語の中では文中に既に含まれているとして訳出しませんでした。「非難して」の目的語としてthe filmsを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1954 OSARAGI demanded that ARASHI stop performing Kurama Tengu, claiming that his copyright was ignored, his titles were stolen while their original contents were rewritten, and Kuram Tengu in the films slashed too many people with his sword which was against OSARAGI&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1954 Osaragi demanded that Arashi stop performing Kurama Tengu, claiming that his copyright was ignored, his titles were stolen and the original content was rewritten, and Kurama Tengu in the films slashed too many people with his sword, which was against Osaragi&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>そして大佛は自ら「天狗ぷろだくしょん」を設立してプロデューサーに就任し、同年より小堀明男の主演による『新鞍馬天狗』シリーズの製作を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, OSARAGI himself established &apos;Tengu Production,&apos; took up the position of producer, and began producing &quot;The New KuramaTengu&quot; series starring Akio KOBORI in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, OSARAGI himself established &apos;Tengu Productions,&apos; took up the position of producer, and began producing &quot;The New KuramaTengu&quot; series starring Akio KOBORI in the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, Osaragi himself established &apos;Tengu Productions,&apos; took up the position of producer, and began producing &quot;Shin Kurama Tengu&quot; series starring Akio KOBORI in the same year.</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この作品にはアラカンの鞍馬天狗なら5本は撮れると言われた程の資金が毎回投入されたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that for each movie a large amount of money which would be equal to take five Kurama Tengu movies by Arakan was funded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that for each movie a large amount of money equal to the costs of filming five Kurama Tengu movies by Arakan, was funded.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that a huge sum of money equal to the costs of filming five Kurama Tengu movies by Arakan, was used for each movie.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>この『新鞍馬天狗』は、原作者自ら手掛ける映画作品として当初話題にはなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The New Kurama Tengu&quot; was much talked about at first as the film taken by the author himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The New Kurama Tengu&quot; was much talked about at first since the film was produced by the author himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Kurama Tengu attracted much attention at first since the film was produced by the author himself.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし、いざ完成した作品は、小堀の天狗姿が常に嵐と比較されて酷評ばかりされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But once the film was on screen, KOBORI was always compared with that of ARASHI as the figure of Tengu and was severely criticized.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But once the film was on screen, KOBORI was always compared with that of ARASHI as the character of Tengu, and was severely criticized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But once the film was on screen, Kobori as the character of Tengu was always compared with Arashi and severely criticized.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>近藤勇役に当時既に五十代で老け役も演じていた志村喬を起用するなど配役に無理があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an obvious miscast that Kyo SHIMURA who was already in his fifties and had been performing an old man was appointed for the role of Isami KONDO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an obvious miscast when Kyo SHIMURA, already in his fifties and had been performing old man roles, was appointed for the role of Isami KONDO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an obvious mistake in casting when Kyo SHIMURA, already in his fifties and had been performing grandfatherly roles was selected for the role of Isami KONDO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>その上、ストーリーもクライマックスで、天狗が敵に拳銃を構えるだけ構えて大儀を唱えて挙句に戦うことなく退散してしまうなど、大衆が好む時代劇の骨法や様式を完全に無視したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, at the climax of the story, Tengu only pointed his gun at his enemy, preached his good cause, and retreated without fighting; the frame and the style of a historical drama that the populace loved were completely ignored.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, at the climax of the story, Tengu only pointed his gun at his enemy, preached his good cause, and retreated without fighting; the frame and style of the historical drama that the populace loved, were completely ignored.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, at the climax of the story, Tengu only pointed his gun at his enemy, preached about the good cause and retreated without fighting which completely ignored the framework and style of historical drama that the spectators loved.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その爽快感も全く欠落した内容は、ある意味で大佛の自己満足にしか過ぎない代物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Without stirring any sense of excitement, the contents were, in a sense, nothing but OSARAGI&apos;s complacency.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Without stirring any sense of excitement, the contents were, in a sense, nothing but OSARAGI&apos;s complacency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Without stirring any sense of excitement, the contents were, in a sense, nothing but for Osaragi&apos;s self-satisfaction.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>この様な作品が成功する道理は当然無く、興行面で不振を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course there was no reason for such a product to be successful, and it was a terrible box-office failure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course there was no reason for such a product to be successful, and it was a terrible box-office failure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course there was no reason for such a product to be successful, and it was a terrible box-office failure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>「日本映画史に残る大失敗作」「大佛が作家としての自身のキャリアに自ら疵を付けた」と酷評された程の悲惨な結果に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Severely criticized as &apos;the flop that would remain in the Japanese movie history,&apos; or &apos;OSARAGI stained his own career as a writer,&apos; it came to a miserable end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Severely criticized as &apos;the flop that would go down in Japanese movie history,&apos; or &apos;OSARAGI stained his own career as a writer,&apos; it came to a miserable end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It came to a miserable end when it was severely criticized as &apos;the flop that would go down in Japanese movie history,&apos; or &apos;Osaragi stained his own career as a writer.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>天狗役を演じた小堀にとってもまた、巻き添えを食らう形で俳優キャリアの疵となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KOBORI who performed Tengu was also embroiled to get stained on his career as an actor.</e>
<cmt>「巻き添えを食らう形で」は「巻き添えを食らい」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KOBORI who performed Tengu was also embroiled and it stained his acting career.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also hampered the acting career of Kobori, who performed Tengu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>大佛プロデュース・小堀主演の『新鞍馬天狗』の興行成績は惨憺たるもので、作を重ねる毎に映画館サイドからの大佛に対する不満・怨嗟・抗議の声だけが増えてゆく始末であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The New Kurama Tengu&quot; produced by OSARAGI, starring KOBORI was a box-office bomb, and each film made movie theater owners shout their dissatisfaction, grudge, and protest more and more loudly against OSARAGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The New Kurama Tengu&quot; produced by OSARAGI, starring KOBORI was a box-office bomb, and each film made movie theater owners shout their dissatisfaction, grudge, and protest more and more loudly against OSARAGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Kurama Tengu&apos; produced by Osaragi, starring Kobori was a box-office bomb, and each film made movie theater owners increasingly vocal about their dissatisfaction, grudges, and protests against Osaragi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>結局、大駄作という酷評を覆す事はできず、全10作を予定するも、第3作『新鞍馬天狗 夕立の武士』を最後に打ち切りとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, OSARAGI could not overturn the harsh criticism as a perfect trash, nor shoot ten films as scheduled but dropped; the third film &quot;The New Kurama Tengu, The Samurai in the Shower&quot; was the last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, OSARAGI could not overturn the harsh criticism of his films being trash, nor shoot ten films as scheduled but he dropped; the third film &quot;The New Kurama Tengu, The Samurai in the Shower,&quot; was the last.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Osaragi could not disprove the harsh criticism of his films being trash and did not shoot the ten films as scheduled but finished with the third film &quot;Shin Kurama Tengu, Yudachi no Bushi&quot; (The New Kurama Tengu, The Samurai in the Shower).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この『新鞍馬天狗』で3度も煮え湯を飲まされる格好になった映画館サイドは、その損失補填を理由に大佛にアラカンの鞍馬天狗の復活を強硬に要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movie theater owners who had lost a huge amount of money three times demanded strongly the revival of Arakan as the Kurama Tengu from OSARAGI to compensate their damages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movie theater owners who had lost huge amounts of money three times demanded strongly the revival of Arakan as the Kurama Tengu from OSARAGI to compensate for their damages.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movie theater owners who had lost huge sums of money three times over &quot;Shin Kurama Tengu&quot; strongly demanded from Osaragi the revival of Arakan as Kurama Tengu to compensate for their damages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>さすがの大佛もこれは呑まざるを得ず、ここにアラカンの鞍馬天狗が復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the great author OSARAGI had to accept their proposal, and thus the Kurama Tengu by Arakan came back.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「さすがの」をthe great authorとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even the great author OSARAGI had to accept their proposal, and thus the Kurama Tengu played by Arakan returned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even the great author Osaragi had to accept their proposal, and thus the Kurama Tengu played by Arakan returned.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>だが、そこまでの経緯が経緯ゆえにもはや嵐自身も乗り気ではなく、僅か2作品で打ち止めとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But because of these circumstances, ARASHI was not much enthusiastic; only two films were made, and that was the end of it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But because of these circumstances, ARASHI was not very enthusiastic; only two films were made, and that was the end of it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But because of these circumstances, Arashi was not very enthusiastic; only two films were made, and that was the end of it.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>その後、映画では東千代之介と市川雷蔵が天狗を演じたものの、いずれも長続きせずに終わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Chiyonosuke AZUMA and Raizo ICHIKAWA performed the Tengu in the movies, but neither of them were produced many times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Chiyonosuke AZUMA and Raizo ICHIKAWA performed Tengu in the movies, but neither of them were produced many times.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞 the 不要</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Chiyonosuke AZUMA and Raizo ICHIKAWA performed Tengu in the movies, but neither of them made many films.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 白拍子花子(id:244805), Yukkey(id:83337), 水原怜雅(id:62300), 竃馬(id:102733), ととりん(id:31982), Game-M(id:86301), モンゴルの白い虎(id:134187), Piekawa(id:185375), Point136(id:211299), Nokia(id:129005), よもすがら(id:212112), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Riden(id:27573), Mikomaid(id:56139), MiraModreno(id:212669), 彩華1226(id:64711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>