<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天羽々矢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amanohabaya (arrow)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amanohabaya</e>
<cmt>took out (arrow) as Amanohabaya doesn&apos;t mean only arrow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amanohabaya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天羽々矢（あまのはばや）は、記紀神話に現れる矢。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amanohabaya is an arrow described in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amanohabaya is an arrow described in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amanohabaya is an arrow described in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「羽々」の意味は不詳だが、「羽のように大きい」もしくは「大蛇」と解する説が有力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meaning of &quot;haba&quot; is unknown, although prevailing theories state that the word means &quot;big as a feather&quot; or &quot;a large snake.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of &quot;haba&quot; is unknown, although prevailing theories state that the word means &quot;big for a feather&quot; or &quot;a large snake.&quot;</e>
<cmt>vocabulary (preposition)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning of &quot;haba&quot; is unknown, although prevailing theories state that the word means &quot;big for a feather&quot; or &quot;a large snake.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>高皇産霊神（たかみむすひのかみ）が、天稚彦（あめわかひこ）を葦原中国（あしはらのなかつくに）に下す際に、天鹿児弓（あまのかごゆみ）と共に天稚彦に与えた（詳しい経緯は葦原中国平定を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takamimusubi-no-kami sent Amewakahiko down to the Ashihara no nakatsukuni (Literally, &quot;Central Land of Reed Plains&quot;, which refers to the human world), Amanohabaya was given to Amewakahiko together with Amakagonoyumi (bow) (for details, refer to &quot;pacification of Ashihara no Nakatsukuni&quot;).</e>
<cmt>タカミムスビ、アメノワカヒコなどのカタカナはweb表記の漢字に修正しました。以下同様</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takamimusuhi no Kami (the god Takamimusuhi) sent Amewakahiko down to the Ashihara no Nakatsukuni (literally, the Central Land of Reed Plains, which refers to the human world), Amanohabaya was given to Amewakahiko together with the bow called Amanokagoyumi (for details, refer to &quot;pacification of Ashihara no Nakatsukuni&quot;).</e>
<cmt>additional explanation and corrected pronunciation for 高皇産霊神capitals/ punctuationcorrected pronunciation for 天鹿児弓changing words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takamimusuhi no Kami (the god Takamimusuhi) sent Amewakahiko down to the Ashihara no Nakatsukuni (literally, the Central Land of Reed Plains, which refers to the human world), Amanohabaya was given to Amewakahiko together with the bow called Amanokagoyumi (for details, refer to &quot;pacification of Ashihara no Nakatsukuni&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>神武東征に望む神武天皇に対し、長髄彦（ながすねひこ）は饒速日命（にぎはやひのみこと）が所持する天羽々矢を示し、自分が天津神に仕えていることを証明するが、饒速日命の手によって殺害される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Jinmu set off for the eastern expedition, Nagasunehiko showed Amanohabaya owned by Nigihayahi no Mikoto to the Emperor to prove that he was serving Amatsu kami (god of heaven), but Nagasunehiko was killed by Nigihayahi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Jinmu set off on the eastern expedition, Nagasunehiko showed Amanohabaya owned by Nigihayahi no Mikoto to the emperor to prove that he was serving Amatsu Kami (god of heaven), but Nagasunehiko was killed by Nigihayahi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>preposition/capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Jinmu set off on the eastern expedition, Nagasunehiko showed Amanohabaya owned by Nigihayahi no Mikoto to the emperor to prove that he was serving Amatsu Kami (god of heaven), but Nagasunehiko was killed by Nigihayahi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SKD(id:16685), Nnh(id:474), Singing(id:134656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>