<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>詞花和歌集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shika Wakashu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shika Wakashu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shika Wakashu (Shika Collection of Japanese Poems)</e>
<cmt>題名の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>詞花和歌集（しかわかしゅう）は、八代集の第六にあたる勅撰和歌集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shika Wakashu is the sixth Chokusen Wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) of Hachidai shu (the eight Imperial anthologies of Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shika Wakashu is the sixth Chokusen Wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by imperial command) of the Hachidai shu (the eight imperial anthologies of Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shika Wakashu is the sixth Chokusen Wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) of the Hachidaishu (the eight Imperial anthologies of Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天養元年（1144）に崇徳天皇が下命し、藤原顕輔（1090～1155年）が撰者となって編集、仁平元年（1151）になって完成奏覧された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1144, Emperor Sutoku ordered FUJIWARA no Akisuke (1090-1155) to compile the anthology, which was completed in 1151 and submitted to the Emperor for inspection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1144, Emperor Sutoku ordered FUJIWARA no Akisuke (1090-1155) to compile the anthology, which was completed in 1151 and submitted to the Emperor for inspection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1144, Emperor Sutoku ordered FUJIWARA no Akisuke (1090 - 1155) to compile the anthology, and he finished and submitted it to the Emperor for inspection in 1151.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>十巻、総歌数415首。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of ten volumes, including 415 poems in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of ten volumes and contains a total of 415 poems.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of ten volumes and contains a total of 415 poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、『金葉和歌集』三奏本があまり流布しなかったため、金葉三奏本との間でかなり重複がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sanso bon (the third revised edition) of &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot; (Kinyo Collection of Japanese Poems) did not circulate a lot, so many poems collected in Shika Wakashu overlapped with those in Kinyo Sanso bon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sanso bon (the third revised edition) of &quot;Kinyo Wakashu (Kinyo Collection of Japanese Poems)&quot; did not circulate a lot, so many poems collected in Shika Wakashu overlapped those in Kinyo Sanso bon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanso bon (the third revised edition) of &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot; (Kinyo Collection of Japanese Poems) did not circulate widely, so many poems collected in Shika Wakashu overlapped the ones in Kinyo Sanso bon (Sanso bon of &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>『詞花集』の歌は清新な叙景歌に特色があるほか、詠懐調の歌も多く見られ、その歌風は多様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style of poetry in &quot;Shika shu&quot; is diverse; it is characterized by the fresh descriptive poems, but it also contains a lot of poems in which poets expressed their feelings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style of poetry in &quot;Shika shu&quot; is diverse, being characterized by the fresh descriptive poems, but it also contains many poems in which the authors expressed their feelings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style of poetry in &quot;Shika shu&quot;(Shika Wakashu) is diverse; it is characterized by the fresh descriptive poems, and many poems in which the authors expressed their feelings.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>金葉と詞花は、第五、第六勅撰和歌集で、その命名の義も構成も、全く同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinyo is the fifth Imperial anthology and Shika is the sixth, and these two books have the same structure and the same meaning in the titles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinyo is the fifth imperial anthology and Shika is the sixth; these two books have the same structure and the same meaning in their titles.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinyo is the fifth Imperial anthology and Shika is the sixth; these two works have the same structure and their meanings of the titles are the same.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>古今以来、二十巻という勅撰集の慣例を破り、羈旅・哀傷・神祇歌を省き、恋歌を二巻に縮めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditionally the Imperial anthology had consisted of twenty volumes since the time of Kokin Wakashu, but they broke the custom, omitting the categories of Journey, Elegies, Gods of Heaven and Earth, and reducing the volumes of Love to two.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditionally, the imperial anthology had consisted of 20 volumes since the time of Kokin Wakashu, but they broke from the custom, omitting the categories of Journey, Elegies, and Gods of Heaven and Earth, and reduced the volumes of Love to two.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditionally, the Imperial anthology had consisted of 20 volumes since the time of Kokin Wakashu, but they broke the custom and omitted the categories of Journey, Elegies, and Gods of Heaven and Earth, reducing the volumes of Love to two.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アラビア数字にし表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>素朴な構成だが、その分選歌には厳しく、珠玉の詞華選といった感じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the structure was simple, the poems were selected meticulously, so every poem is like a gem.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the structure was simple, the poems were selected meticulously, so each poem is a gem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the structure was simple, the poems were selected meticulously, therefore they look like selected gems of written expression.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>『詞花集』と『金葉集』との違いでもっとも顕著なのは、『金葉集』の近代重視に対し、『詞花集』では、最多入集歌人が曾禰好忠（17首）・和泉式部（16首）であることが示すとおり、中頃（後拾遺和歌集時代）の歌人を重視する方針をとる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most notable difference between &quot;Shika shu&quot; and &quot;Kinyo shu&quot; is that &quot;Kinyo shu&quot; considered the contemporary poets as important, while &quot;Shika shu&quot; treated the poets around the period of Goshui Wakashu (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry) with respect, which is illustrated by the fact that the poems composed by the poets such as SONE no Yoshitada (17 poems) and Izumi Shikibu (16 poems) were selected a lot.</e>
<cmt>「近代」は「同時代」の意だと解釈しました。後拾遺和歌集→1086年成立。「中頃」の意味が曖昧なため、訳文では（　）内に表記されている「後拾遺和歌集時代」という言葉を使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most significant difference between &quot;Shika shu&quot; and &quot;Kinyo shu&quot; is that &quot;Kinyo shu&quot; considered the contemporary poets to be important while &quot;Shika shu&quot; treated the poets around the period of Goshui Wakashu (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry) with respect, as illustrated by the fact that the poems composed by poets such as SONE no Yoshitada (17 poems) and Izumi Shikibu (16 poems) were frequently selected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most significant difference between &quot;Shika shu&quot; and &quot;Kinyo shu&quot; is that &quot;Kinyo shu&quot; considered the contemporary poets to be important while &quot;Shika shu&quot; treated the poets around the period of Goshui Wakashu (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry) with respect; it is illustrated by the fact that the poets whose poems were selected most were SONE no Yoshitada (17 poems) and Izumi Shikibu (16 poems).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一方、当代の歌人については同一歌人を極力避けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the selector tried to avoid the poems by the contemporary poets, selecting only one poem per a poet in principle (a few exceptions are, of course, poems by Emperor Sutoku and Akisuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the selector tried to avoid the poems by the contemporary poets, selecting in principle only one poem per poet (but with a few exceptions, of course, such as the poems by Emperor Sutoku and Akisuke).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the selector tried to avoid selecting the poems by the same contemporary poets.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>原則的に一人一首とした（わずかな例外は、当然なことながら崇徳院と顕輔）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, only one poem was selected per poet (but with a few exceptions, of course, such as the poems by Emperor Sutoku and Akisuke).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Loveless(id:129239), Yume149(id:17504), SK(id:64397), さららゆら(id:12274), Modeha(id:1276), Kiev(id:13022), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>