<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>とりかへばや物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torikaebaya Monogatari (The Changelings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torikaebaya Monogatari (The Changelings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torikaebaya Monogatari (The Changelings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『とりかへばや物語』（とりかえばやものがたり）は平安時代後期に成立した物語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Torikaebaya Monogatari&quot; is a narrative which was completed in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Torikaebaya Monogatari&quot; is a narrative that was completed in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Torikaebaya Monogatari&quot; is a narrative that was completed in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>作者は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「とりかへばや」とは「取り替えたいなあ」と言う意の古語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torikaebaya&apos; is an archaic word whose meaning is &apos;I wish I could change something.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torikaebaya&apos; is an archaic word whose meaning is &apos;I wish I could change something.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torikaebaya&apos; is an archaic word whose meaning is &apos;I wish I could change something.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>関白左大臣には2人の子供がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpaku Sadaijin (Imperial Regent and Minister of the Left) has two children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpaku Sadaijin (Imperial Regent and Minister of the Left) has two children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpaku Sadaijin (Imperial Regent and Minister of the Left) has two children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1人は内気で女性的な性格の男児、もう1人は快活で男性的な性格の女児。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is a boy who is diffident and feminine, while the other is a cheerful girl who is rather mannish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is a boy who is diffident and feminine, while the other is a cheerful girl who is somewhat mannish.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One is a boy who is diffident and feminine, while the other is a cheerful girl who is like a boy.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>父は2人を「取り替えたいなあ」と嘆いており、この天性の性格のため、男児は「姫君」として、女児は「若君」として育てられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father feels sad, saying &apos;I wish I could exchange them,&apos; and because of the inborn personalities, the boy is brought up as &apos;a Princess&apos; and the girl as &apos;a Prince.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The father feels sad, saying, &apos;I wish I could exchange them,&apos; but because of their inborn personalities the boy is brought up as a &apos;princess&apos; and the girl as a &apos;prince.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The father feels sad, saying, &apos;I wish I could exchange their personalities,&apos; and because of their inborn characters the boy is brought up as a &apos;princess&apos; and the girl is treated as a &apos;young prince.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。他セルと用語を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>男装の女児である「若君」は男性として宮廷に出仕するや、あふれる才気を発揮し、若くして出世街道を突き進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as the girl in male dress enters the Imperial court as &apos;a young Prince,&apos; she shows her ability, taking the high road to success, though she is still young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as the girl in male dress enters the Imperial Court as &apos;a young prince,&apos; she shows her ability and takes the high road to success, though she is still young.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as the girl wearing male clothes enters the Imperial Court as &apos;a young prince,&apos; she shows her ability and takes the high road to success, while she is still young.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、女装の男児である「姫君」も女性として後宮に出仕を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The boy in female dress also enters the service of a consort of the Emperor as &apos;a Princess.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The boy in female dress also enters the service of a consort of the Emperor as a &apos;princess.&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boy in female clothes also enters the service of a consort of the Emperor as a &apos;princess.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>その後「若君」は右大臣の娘と結婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later the &apos;young Prince&apos; gets married to a daughter of the Minister of the Right, but the wife, who does not know the truth, becomes intimate with her husband&apos;s best friend, Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain), and their marriage collapses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the &apos;young Prince&apos; marries a daughter of the Minister of the Right, but the wife, being unaware of the truth, becomes intimate with her husband&apos;s best friend, Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain), and consequently their marriage collapses.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the &apos;young prince&apos; marries a daughter of the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、事情を知らない妻は「若君」の親友宰相中将と通じ、夫婦の仲は破綻する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the wife, who is unaware of the truth, becomes intimate with her husband&apos;s best friend, Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain), and consequently their marriage collapses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。FBに従って修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一方「姫君」は主君女東宮に恋慕し密かに関係を結んで、それぞれ次第に自らの天性に苦悩し始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the &apos;Princess&apos; falls in love with his master, a consort of the Emperor, having relations with her, and both of them began to agonize over thier innate characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the &apos;princess&apos; falls in love with his master, a consort of the Emperor, and has relations with her, and both of them begin to agonize over their innate characteristics.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the &apos;princess&apos; falls in love with his master, a consort of the Emperor, and has relations with her, and both of them begin to agonize over their innate characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして、とうとう「若君」が宰相中将に素性を見破られてしまうことで、事態は大きく変化していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last, Saisho no Chujo revealed what the &apos;young Prince&apos; really is, and the situation is changing noticeably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At last, Saisho no Chujo reveals what the &apos;young prince&apos; really is, and the situation changes noticeably.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At last, Saisho no Chujo reveals what the &apos;young prince&apos; really is, which changes the situation noticeably.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>宰相中将の子を妊娠し進退窮まった「若君」は、宰相中将に匿われて女の姿に戻り密かに出産する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;young Prince,&apos; who has been pregnant by Saisho no Chujo, are driven to the wall, and comes to be in female dress again, giving birth to a baby secretly sheltered by him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;young prince,&apos; who is pregnant by Saisho no Chujo, is driven to the wall and comes to be in female dress again, eventually giving birth to a baby that is sheltered in secret.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;young prince,&apos; who is pregnant by Saisho no Chujo and in a dilemma, comes to wear female dress again, and eventually gives birth to a baby, being sheltered by Saisho no Chujo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一方「姫君」も元の男性の姿に戻り、行方知れずとなっていた「若君」を探し当てて宰相中将の下からの逃亡を手助けする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;Princess&apos; also comes back to wear male dress, and he finds out the &apos;young Prince,&apos; who has been lost, and helps her escape from Saisho no Chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;princess&apos; also returns to male dress; he finds the &apos;young prince,&apos; who has been lost, and helps her escape from Saisho no Chujo.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having begun to wear male clothes again, the &apos;princess&apos; finds the lost &apos;young prince&apos; and helps &apos;him&apos; to escape from Saisho no Chujo.</e>
<cmt>「若君」が誰に探し当てられ手助けされたかがわかるように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後2人は、周囲に悟られぬよう互いの立場を入れ替える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then they exchange their positions secretly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The secretly exchange their positions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They secretly exchange their positions.</e>
<cmt>they としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>本来の性に戻った2人は、それぞれ自らの未来を切り開き、関白・中宮という人臣の最高位に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they get their original gender back, they carve out their future, attaining the highest social position, Kanpaku (Chancellor) and Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor), respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they get their original gender identities back, they carve out their future and attain their highest social positions of Kanpaku (Chancellor) and Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor), respectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they get their original gender identities back, they carve out their future and attain their highest social positions respectively: He became Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), while she became Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>成立過程</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The writing process</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The writing process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The writing process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>とりかへばや物語の原型は1180年以前に成立したと考えられているが、その後後世の手により改作が加えられ、現在の形のものが伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the original story of Torikaebaya Monogatari was made before 1180, and later it was rewritten by the posterity, which has been passed down until today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the original story of Torikaebaya Monogatari was created before 1180 but that it was ultimately rewritten through posterity, having been passed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the original story of Torikaebaya Monogatari was created before 1180 but that it was ultimately rewritten through posterity, having been passed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この経緯については、13世紀初頭に成立した無名草子や同世紀後半に成立した風葉和歌集の記述から推測可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possible to conjecture the process of writing by both Mumyozoshi (critique of tales), which was completed at the beginning of the thirteenth century and Fuyo Wakashu (Fuyo collection of poetry), which was compiled at the end of the same century, and Hiromichi SUZUKI and other people studied historical evidence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible to assume that the process of writing was by both Mumyozoshi (critique of tales), which was completed at the beginning of the thirteenth century, and Fuyo Wakashu (Fuyo collection of poetry), which was compiled at the end of the same century; accordingly, Hiromichi SUZUKI and others have studied the historical evidence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible to assume the process of writing by the descriptions of both Mumyozoshi (critique of tales), which was completed at the beginning of the 13th century, and Fuyo Wakashu (collection of Japanese poems based on fictional stories), which was compiled at the end of the same century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに従って修正しました。アラビア数字にし用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>鈴木弘道らによる考証がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromichi SUZUKI and others have studied the historical evidence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>作品の意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Significance of the work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The significance of the work</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The significance of the work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>この作品は、男性と女性が入れ替わるという非現実的な設定である反面、2人を中心とする人間関係の描写は現実的かつ重層的であり、現在でも十分に味わい深く鑑賞できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The setting of this story in which a man and woman exchange their roles is not realistic, but the portrayal of characters, especially these two people, is realistic and multilayered, so it is really wroth reading even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The setting of this story in which a man and woman exchange their roles is not realistic, but the portrayal of the characters, particularly these two people, is realistic and multilayered, so it&apos;s truly worth reading today.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The setting for this story in which a man and woman exchange their roles is not realistic, but the portrayal of the characters, particularly these two people, is realistic and multilayered, so it&apos;s truly worth reading even today.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>特に男装の女児である「若君」が宰相中将に素性を知られ身を許してしまうシーンは、本作品のクライマックスの一つでもあり、本作品が「退廃的」と批評される一因ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene in which Saisho no Chujo reveals the truth about the &apos;young Prince,&apos; the lady in the male dress and has a relationship with her is one of the climax of this work, which is one of the reasons why this work is considered &apos;decadent.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene in which Saisho no Chujo reveals the truth about the &apos;young prince,&apos; being the lady in the male dress, and has a relationship with her is one of the climactic scenes of this work, but it&apos;s also one of the reasons this work is considered &apos;decadent.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene in which Saisho no Chujo reveals the truth about a lady in the male clothes, or &apos;young prince,&apos; and has a relationship with her is one of the climactics in this work, but it&apos;s also one of the reasons why this work is considered &apos;decadent.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この点が、当時書かれた数量に対して現存作品の少ないジャンルであるにも関らず、人々へ強い印象を残し、当時、数多く作られた物語の中で本作品を現在まで命脈を保たせる原因となったのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, this work left a strong impression on the people and could survive among the many stories which had been written in those days, even though this story belongs to the genre which has not survived well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, the work has left a strong impression on people and therefore survived among the many stories that had been written in those days, even though the story belongs to a genre that hasn&apos;t survived well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, the work has left a strong impression on people, and therefore survived among the many stories that had been written in those days, even though the story belongs to a genre that hasn&apos;t survived well.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>また、古くから読み続けられてきた作品ではあるが、近代の一時期批判的に扱われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though having been read for a long time, it was critically treated for a certain time of the modern period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though having been read for a long time, it was treated critically for a certain time in the modern period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though people have read the story since old days, it was treated critically for a certain period of time in the modern times.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>明治時代の国文学史上では例えば藤岡作太郎から「怪奇」「読者の心を欺く」「小説になっていない」「嘔吐を催す」などと評される事もあったが、近年ジェンダーの視点から再評価された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Meiji period, Sakutaro FUJIOKA criticized the story as &apos;bizarre,&apos; &apos;betraying readers,&apos; &apos;even not a novel,&apos; and &apos;making people sick,&apos; but now it is revalued from the gender point of view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, Sakutaro FUJIOKA criticized the story as &apos;bizarre,&apos; &apos;betraying readers,&apos; &apos;even not a novel&apos; and &apos;making people sick,&apos; but now it is reconsidered from the perspective of gender.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the history of Japanese literature in the Meiji period, Sakutaro FUJIOKA criticized the story saying &apos;bizarre,&apos; &apos;something that betrays readers,&apos; &apos;it is not even a novel&apos; and &apos;it makes people feel sick,&apos; but now the work is revalued from the perspective of gender.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>当時の社会ならではの制約・お約束的展開はあるものの、本来的個人的性質と社会的に期待される役割との差異を浮き彫りにする本作品は、ジェンダーという枠を越えて、近代的小説に近い重要な要素を持つと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it contains a conventional and banal plot which was often seen in those days, it is said that this work has an important element which makes this story more like a modern novel beyond the matter of gender, exposing the difference between a human&apos;s innate nature and a social role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it contains a conventional and banal plot that was often seen in those days, the work is said to have an important element that makes the story more like a modern novel beyond the matter of gender, exposing the difference between a human&apos;s innate nature and his or her social role.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it contains a conventional and banal plot that was often seen in those days, the work is said to have an important element that makes the story more like a modern novel beyond the matter of gender, exposing the difference between a human&apos;s innate nature and his or her social role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>現代語訳・アレンジ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern translation and adaptation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern translations and adaptations</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern translations and adaptations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>現在手に入るとりかへばや物語の現代語訳としては、中村真一郎によるちくま文庫版、田辺聖子による講談社少年少女古典文学館版などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The modern translations of Torikaebaya Monogatari which are available today are the one in Chikuma Library, translated by Shinichiro NAKAMURA, and the Kodansha Japanese Classics for Boys and Girls edition translated by Seiko TANABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The modern translations of Torikaebaya Monogatari that are available today are the one in Chikuma Library, translated by Shinichiro NAKAMURA, and the Kodansha Japanese Classics for Boys and Girls edition translated by Seiko TANABE.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The modern translations of Torikaebaya Monogatari that are available today are Chikuma Library edition translated by Shinichiro NAKAMURA, and the Kodansha Japanese Classics for Boys and Girls edition translated by Seiko TANABE.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>講談社学術文庫版は、原文とともに現代語訳が付されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The edition of the Academic Paperback Library, Kodansha Ltd. contains the modern translation along with the original text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The edition of the Academic Paperback Library (Kodansha Ltd.) contains a modern translation along with the original text.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Academic Paperback Library (Kodansha Ltd.) edition contains a modern translation together with the original text.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、氷室冴子の小説『ざ・ちぇんじ!』は、とりかへばや物語を少女小説にアレンジしたものであり、山内直実によって漫画化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A novel, &quot;The Change!,&quot; which was written by Saeko HIMURO is an adaptation of Torikaebaya Monogatari for young girls and it was also adapted for a comic book by Naomi YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A novel, &quot;The Change!,&quot; by Saeko HIMURO, is an adaptation of Torikaebaya Monogatari for young girls; it was also adapted as a comic book by Naomi YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Change!,&quot; a novel written by Saeko HIMURO, is an adaptation of Torikaebaya Monogatari for young girls; it was also adapted as a comic book by Naomi YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>唐十郎による〈唐版 とりかえばや物語〉『きみと代わる日』（主婦と生活社）も1998年に発行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juro KARA adapted Torikaebaya Monogatari for a novel, &quot;The Day When We Switch Our Roles,&quot; (Shufu To Seikatsu Sha Co.,LTD) and published it in 1998.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juro KARA adapted Torikaebaya Monogatari for a novel, &quot;The Day We Switched Our Roles,&quot; (Shufu To Seikatsu Sha Co., Ltd.) and published it in 1998.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juro KARA adapted Torikaebaya Monogatari for a novel called &quot;The Day We Switched Our Roles&quot; (Shufu To Seikatsu Sha Co., Ltd.), and published it in 1998.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lumi(id:101666), MystBot(id:224584), マクガイア(id:33346), Bellcricket(id:37640), Sketch(id:102), 具利己(id:135882), Kiev(id:13022), Yuming(id:17854), Masyu(id:31065), さららゆら(id:12274), Xqbot(id:273540), 頭痛(id:201680), ねこぱんだ(id:35119), Marcosx(id:258596), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), 捕澤(id:23785), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>