<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後拾遺和歌集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshui Wakashu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshui Wakashu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshui Wakashu (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry)</e>
<cmt>他と合わせ、タイトルの補足をいれました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>後拾遺和歌集（ごしゅういわかしゅう）は八代集の第四、『拾遺和歌集』の後継たるべく編まれた勅撰和歌集である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshui Wakashu is the fourth Chokusen Wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) of the Hachidaishu (the eight Imperial anthologies of Japanese poetry), following &quot;Shui Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshui Wakashu is the fourth Chokusen Wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by imperial command) of the Hachidaishu (the eight imperial anthologies of Japanese poetry), following &quot;Shui Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshui Wakashu is the fourth Chokusen Wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) of the Hachidaishu (the eight Imperial anthologies of Japanese poetry), and it came out after &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>勅命は白河天皇、撰者は藤原通俊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By order of Emperor Shirakawa, FUJIWARA no Michitoshi selected poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By order of Emperor Shirakawa, FUJIWARA no Michitoshi selected the poems.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Shirakawa gave an order, and FUJIWARA no Michitoshi selected the poems.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>承保二年（1075年）奉勅、応徳3年（1086年）9月16日 (旧暦)完成を見、同年10月奏覧された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1075, he received the Imperial decree, completed on September 16 (in old calendar), 1086, submitted it to the Emperor for inspection in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1075, he received the imperial decree, completed the work on September 16 (in the old calendar) of 1086, and submitted it to the Emperor for inspection in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1075, he received the imperial decree, completed the work on September 16 (in the old calendar) of 1086, and submitted it to the Emperor for inspection in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>二十巻、総歌数1218首（新編国歌大観本）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of twenty volumes, including about 1218 poems in total (A New Version of Comprehensive National Poems).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of 20 volumes, comprising a total of approximately 1218 poems (A New Version of Comprehensive National Poems).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of twenty volumes, comprising a total of approximately 1218 poems (A New Version of Comprehensive National Poems).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>構成は古今和歌集を基とし、春（上・下）、夏、秋（上・下）、冬、賀、別、羇旅、哀傷、恋（四巻）、雑（六巻）からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poems were classified into the following categories based on Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry): Spring (two volumes), Summer, Autumn (two volumes), Winter, Celebration, Separation, Journey, Elegies, Love (four volumes), and Miscellaneous (six volumes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poems were classified into the following categories based on Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry): Spring (two volumes), Summer, Autumn (two volumes), Winter, Celebration, Separation, Journey, Elegies, Love (four volumes), and Miscellaneous (six volumes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poems were classified into the following categories based on Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry): Spring (two volumes), Summer, Autumn (two volumes), Winter, Celebration, Separation, Journey, Elegies, Love (four volumes), and Miscellaneous (six volumes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>巻二十（雑歌六）に収める「神祇」「釈教」の分類は勅撰集における初見。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The categories of &apos;Gods of Heaven and Earth&apos; and &apos;Shakyamuni&apos;s Teachings&apos; in the twentieth volume (Zoka (Other Poetry) Six) first appeared in the Imperial anthologies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The categories of &apos;Gods of Heaven and Earth&apos; and &apos;Shakyamuni&apos;s Teachings&apos; in the twentieth volume (Zoka (Other Poetry) Six) first appeared in the imperial anthologies.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These categories of &apos;Gods of Heaven and Earth&apos; and &apos;Shakyamuni&apos;s Teachings&apos; in the 20th volume (Zoka (Miscellaneous poems) volume six) appeared in the Imperial anthology for the first time.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アラビア数字にしました。(Miscellaneous poems, volume six)→(Miscellaneous poems） volume six)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>選歌範囲は『古今』『後撰和歌集』以後、村上天皇朝から白河朝までの約130年間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It contains poems which had been composed for about 130 years, after &quot;Kokin&quot; and &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry), which means from the reigns of Emperor Murakami to Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It contains poems that were about 130 years old, after &quot;Kokin&quot; and &quot;Gosen Wakashu (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry&quot;), meaning from the reign of Emperor Murakami to that of Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It covers the poems which had been composed for about 130 years, the period after &quot;Kokin&quot; and &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry), which is equivalent to the reign of Emperor Murakami (946 - 967) to that of Emperor Shirakawa (1073 - 1087).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションの位置を変えグレゴリオ暦を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>この歌集は、絢爛たる王朝文化が衰退しはじめた頃、華やかなりし昔を振り返ったともいうべきものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the time when the gorgeous Dynastic culture began to decline, the selector compiled this collection of poetry, reminiscing fondly about the flowery old days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the time when the gorgeous dynastic culture began to decline, the selector compiled this collection of poetry, reminiscing in fond but flowery terms about the old days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the time when the magnificent dynastic culture began to decline, the selector compiled this collection of poetry, looking back on the splendid past.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>主な歌人は、和泉式部（67首）・相模 (歌人)（39首）・赤染衛門（32首）・能因（31首）・伊勢大輔（26首）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major poets are Izumi Shikibu (67 poems), Sagami (39 poems), Akazome Emon (32 poems), Noin (31 poems), ISE no Taifu (26 poems).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major poets in the collection are Izumi Shikibu (67 poems), Sagami (39 poems), Akazome Emon (32 poems), Noin (31 poems) and ISE no Taifu (26 poems).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major poets in the collection are Izumi Shikibu (sixty-seven poems), Sagami (thirty-nine poems), Akazome Emon (thirty-two poems), Noin (thirty-one poems) and ISE no Taifu (twenty-six poems).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一条天皇朝前後の宮廷で活躍した才女歌人が上位を占め、女流の比重も三割と大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Intelligent female poets who were actively involved in the Imperial court before and after the reign of Emperor Ichijo ranked high, and as many as thirty percent of the poets in the collection were female.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Intelligent female poets who were actively involved in the Imperial Court before and after the reign of Emperor Ichijo ranked high, and up to 30% of the poets in the collection were females.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Talented female poets who were actively involved in the Imperial Court before and after the reign of Emperor Ichijo ranked high, and up to 30 percent of the poets in the collection were female.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ほかに、清原元輔・大中臣能宣・源道済・藤原長能・同藤原公任ら後撰・拾遺時代の歌人も重視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poets from the period of Gosen (Wakashu) and Shui (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) were considered important: KIYOHARA no Motosuke, ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, MINAMOTO no Michinari, FUJIWARA no Nagato, and FUJIWARA no Kinto.</e>
<cmt>「同藤原公任」はウィキペディアを参照したところ、「同公任」となっていました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poets from the period of Gosen (Wakashu) and Shui (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) were considered important: KIYOHARA no Motosuke, ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, MINAMOTO no Michinari, FUJIWARA no Nagato, and FUJIWARA no Kinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poets from the period of Gosen (Wakashu) and Shui (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) were considered important: KIYOHARA no Motosuke, ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, MINAMOTO no Michinari, FUJIWARA no Nagato, and FUJIWARA no Kinto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>和泉式部の激情がほとばしる恋歌から、赤染衛門の細やかな思い遣りの贈答歌、能因・良暹ら僧侶歌人の旅情豊かな歌、曾禰好忠の大胆な型破りの歌まで、その作者・作風ともに多様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poets and the style of poetry are diverse: Izumi Shikibu&apos;s love poem in which she expressed her passion, Akazome Emon&apos;s delicate zotoka (poetry exchanged between man and woman), poems appealing to the travelers&apos; sentiments which were composed by priest poets such as Noin and Ryozen, and SONE no Yoshitada&apos;s bold and unconventional poem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poets and style of poetry are diverse: Izumi Shikibu&apos;s love poem, in which she expressed her passion; Akazome Emon&apos;s delicate zotoka (poetry exchanged between a man and a woman); poems appealing to travelers&apos; sentiments, which were composed by priest poets such as Noin and Ryozen; and SONE no Yoshitada&apos;s bold and unconventional poem.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poets and styles of poetry are diverse: Izumi Shikibu wrote love poems in which she expressed her passion; Akazome Emon composed delicate zotoka (poetry exchanged between a man and a woman); poems appealing to travelers&apos; sentiments were composed by priest poets such as Noin and Ryozen; and SONE no Yoshitada made bold and unconventional poems.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、詠歌背景を詳しく説明する長文の詞書が多く、散文的特色が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some pointed out that the collection is distinctive in that it contains a lot of long forewords to poems explaining where and why they were composed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some pointed out that the collection was distinctive in that it contained numerous lengthy forewords to poems explaining where and why they were composed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some pointed out that the collection contained numerous lengthy forewords to poems explaining where and why they were composed, so it has prosaic character.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>『後拾遺集』は、格調よりも率直な情感を重んじ過ぎたため、撰者が若輩の歌人であったこともあいまって撰進当時から批判の声が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The selector of &quot;Goshui shu&quot; was young, taking frank sentiments too seriously rather than the refined style, so many people criticized the anthology when it was made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The selector of &quot;Goshui shu,&quot; who was young, considered frank sentiments too seriously but downplayed the refined style, so upon its introduction many people criticized the anthology.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The selector of &quot;Goshui shu,&quot; who was young, considered frank sentiments too seriously but downplayed the refined style, so upon its introduction many people criticized the anthology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>たとえば、歌壇の重鎮でありながら撰者の任に漏れた大納言源経信（1016～1097年）は、『難後拾遺』を著して論難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Dainagon (Major Counselor) MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu (1016-1097), who was not chosen selector, though he was a leading figure in the poetry circles, wrote a book &quot;Nan Goshui&quot; (A Criticism on Goshui Wakashu) to criticize it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Dainagon (Major Counselor) MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu (1016-1097), who had not been chosen as the selector, though he was a leading figure in poetry circles, wrote a book titled &quot;Nan Goshui&quot; (A Criticism on Goshui Wakashu) to criticize it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Dainagon (chief councilor of state) MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu (1016 - 1097), who was a leading figure in poetry circles but had not been chosen as the selector, wrote a book titled &quot;Nan Goshui&quot; (A Criticism on Goshui Wakashu) in order to criticize the anthology.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。統一リストに合わせ、スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>通俊は歌壇の先輩たちに協力を求め、草稿本は周防内侍・康資王母・源経信らの内覧を経た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michitoshi asked his seniors in the poetry circles to help him, so SUO no Naishi, the mother of Prince Yasusuke, and MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu conducted preliminary inspection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michitoshi had asked his seniors in the poetry circles to help him, so SUO no Naishi, the mother of Prince Yasusuke, and MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu conducted the preliminary inspection.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michitoshi had asked his seniors in the poetry circles to help him, so the draft was checked in advance by SUO no Naishi, the mother of Prince Yasusuke, and MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>特に経信とは『後拾遺問答』を取り交わし、経信の意見が選歌の入れ替えに影響した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He exchanged &quot;Goshui Mondo&quot; (A dialogue on Goshui Wakashu) with Tsunenobu, and his opinion had an influence on replacing poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He exchanged &quot;Goshui Mondo (A dialogue on Goshui Wakashu&quot;) with Tsunenobu, and his opinion influenced the replacement of poems.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He exchanged &quot;Goshui Mondo&quot; (A dialogue on Goshui Wakashu) with Tsunenobu, and his opinion had an influence on the reselection of poems.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一旦完成奏覧された後も、『難後拾遺』を重く見た通俊は、修訂を加えて再奏本を作成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after it was completed and submitted to the Emperor, Toshimichi, who took &quot;Nan Goshui&quot; seriously, revised the anthology and submitted it again to the Emperor for inspection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after it was completed and submitted to the Emperor, Toshimichi, who took &quot;Nan Goshui&quot; seriously, revised the anthology and again submitted it to the Emperor for inspection.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after it was completed and submitted to the Emperor, Michitoshi took &quot;Nan Goshui&quot; seriously and revised the anthology again in order to submit it to the Emperor for inspection.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>津守国基の歌が『後拾遺集』に三首も入っているのは、通俊に賄賂として鰺（アジ）を贈った為だと風評され、「小鰺集」の異名を得たという（袋草紙）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three poems composed by TSUMORI no Kunimoto were selected for &quot;Goshui shu,&quot; and there was a rumor that TSUMORI no Kunimoto bribed Toshimichi with horse mackerel to select his poems, so the anthology was nicknamed &apos;Koaji shu&apos; (a collection of horse mackerel) (according to Fukurozoshi, an essay on tanka poet compiled by FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three poems composed by TSUMORI no Kunimoto had been selected for &quot;Goshui shu,&quot; and there was a rumor that TSUMORI no Kunimoto bribed Toshimichi with horse mackerel to select his poems, so the anthology was nicknamed &apos;Koaji shu&apos; (a collection of horse mackerel) (according to Fukurozoshi, an essay on tanka poetry compiled by FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three poems composed by TSUMORI no Kunimoto had been selected for &quot;Goshui shu,&quot; because TSUMORI no Kunimoto was said to have bribed Michitoshi with horse mackerel to select his poems, so the anthology was nicknamed &apos;Koaji shu&apos; (a collection of horse mackerel) (according to Fukurozoshi, an essay on tanka poetry compiled by FUJIWARA no Kiyosuke).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), SK(id:64397), さららゆら(id:12274), Modeha(id:1276), Nnh(id:474), Yume149(id:17504), Kiev(id:13022), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>