<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五山文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Literature of the Five Mountains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Literature of the Five Mountains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Literature of the Five Mountains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五山文学（ござんぶんがく）は、鎌倉時代末期から室町時代にかけて禅宗寺院で行われた漢文学である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Literature of the Five Mountains (Gozan Bungaku) was literature in Chinese developed in Zen temples from the late Kamakura period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>漢文学・・・文字通りに訳すと中国の文学とまぎらわしいので、literature in Chinese (中国語で書かれた文学）としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Literature of the Five Mountains (Gozan Bungaku) was literature in Chinese developed in Zen temples from the late Kamakura period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozan Bungaku (the Literature of the Five Mountains) was literature in Chinese developed in Zen temples from the late Kamakura period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Literature of the Five Mountains (Gozan Bungaku)→Gozan Bungaku (the Literature of the Five Mountains)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>五山文学こそは、五山文化の中心であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gozan Bungaku was, literally, the center of Gozan culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gozan Bungaku was, literally, the center of Gozan culture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozan Bungaku was, literally, the center of Gozan culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>北宋元 (王朝)禅林においても文学が占める位置は非常に大きかったが、入宋僧や入元僧らにより、その禅風が伝来すると、こぞって文学志向が高揚することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literature occupied a very important place in Zen temples of the Northern Sung and Yuan (dynasties), and after the Zen style was introduced to Japan by monks who had been to the Sung and Yuan, there was a collective rise in literary aspirations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literature occupied a very important place in the Zen temples of the Northern Song and Yuan dynasties, and once the Zen style was introduced to Japan by monks who had been to the Song and Yuan, there was a collective rise in literary aspirations.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literature occupied a very important place in the Zen temples of the Northern Song and Yuan dynasties, and once the Zen style was introduced to Japan by monks who had been to the Song and Yuan, there was a collective rise in literary aspirations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉五山や京都五山（京五山）では、幕府の外交文書を起草するという必要性も伴い、四六文を用いた法語や漢詩を作る才が重視されたことも関係して、五山文学が栄えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related to the fact, that, in addition to the necessity of drafting the Shogunate&apos;s diplomatic documents, it was also considered important to be able to compose Zen instructional literature (Hogo) and Chinese poems written in a style of alternating 4 and 6 character lines (shirokubun), the Literature of the Five Mountains flourished in the five great Zen temples of Kamakura and Kyoto (the Kamakura Gozan and the Kyoto Gozan).</e>
<cmt>京都五山＝京五山なので、あえて訳仕分けはしておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, and in addition to the necessity of drafting the shogunate&apos;s diplomatic documents, it was considered important to compose Zen instructional literature (hogo) and Chinese poems written in a style of alternating four- and six-character lines (shirokubun), whereby the Literature of the Five Mountains flourished in the five great Zen temples of Kamakura and Kyoto (Kamakura Gozan and Kyoto Gozan).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, and in addition to the necessity of drafting the shogunate&apos;s diplomatic documents, it was considered important to compose hogo (Zen instructional literature) and Chinese poems written in shirokubun (a style of alternating four- and six-character lines), whereby the Literature of the Five Mountains flourished in Kamakura Gozan and Kyoto Gozan (the five great Zen temples of Kamakura and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Zen instructional literature (hogo)→hogo (Zen instructional literature)a style of alternating four- and six-character lines (shirokubun)→shirokubun (a style of alternating four- and six-character lines)five great Zen temples of Kamakura and Kyoto (Kamakura Gozan and Kyoto Gozan)→Kamakura Gozan and Kyoto Gozan (five great Zen temples of Kamakura and Kyoto)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>禅の法語をはじめ、詩文、日記、論説などの分野に及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting with Zen instructional literature, it covered such fields as poems and prose, diaries, discourses, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting with Zen instructional literature, it covered such fields as poetry and prose, diaries, discourse, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting with Zen instructional literature, it covered such fields as poetry and prose, diaries, discourse, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>代表的な詩文集に、義堂周信の『空華集』、絶海中津の『蕉堅稿』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As representative miscellanies of prose and poetry, there are &quot;Kugeshu&quot; (Sky Flowers Collection) by Gido Shushin, &quot;Shokenko&quot; by Zekkai Chushin, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representative miscellanies of prose and poetry include &quot;Kugeshu (Sky Flowers Collection),&quot; by Gido Shushin, &quot;Shokenko,&quot; by Zekkai Chushin, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representative miscellanies of prose and poetry include &quot;Kugeshu (Sky Flowers Collection),&quot; by Gido Shushin, &quot;Shokenko,&quot; by Zekkai Chushin, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、漢文学の盛行に伴って、木版出版も起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wood-block printing also arose as literature in Chinese became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wood-block printing also emerged as literature in Chinese became popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wood-block printing also emerged as literature in Chinese became popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>とりわけ、14世紀後半、京都の天龍寺雲居庵や、臨川寺で、春屋妙葩らが盛んに出版活動を展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the late 14 century, Shun&apos;oku Myoha and others actively expanded printing at Unkyo-an in Tenryu-ji Temple or at Rinsen-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly in the late fourteenth century, Shun&apos;oku Myoha and others actively expanded the activity of printing at Unkyo-an in Tenryu-ji Temple and at Rinsen-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly in the late fourteenth century, Shunoku Myoha and others actively expanded the activity of printing at Unkyo-an in Tenryu-ji Temple and at Rinsen-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Shun&apos;oku→Shunoku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらの木版印刷を五山版と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These wood-block printings are called Gozanban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These wood-block printings are called &quot;gozanban.&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These wood-block printings are called &quot;gozanban.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その大多数は、日本に伝わった宋版や元版を覆刻したものであり、古様を伝えるものも多く、版本学的な資料価値が非常に高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them were the reprinted editions of Sung or Yuan printings introduced into Japan, and many of them show the past, and they are of great value as materials in studying woodblock printing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them were the reprinted editions of the Song or Yuan printings that had been introduced into Japan; many of them depict the past, and they are of great value as materials in studying woodblock printing.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them were the reprinted editions of the Song or Yuan printings that had been introduced into Japan; many of them depict the past, and they are of great value as materials in studying woodblock printing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ねこぱんだ(id:35119), トホホ川(id:50502), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 遠藤(id:30275), D.h(id:79056), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>