<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寛和二年内裏歌合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanna ninen dairi Utaawase (Utaawase held at the Imperial Palace in the Kanna period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanna ninen dairi Utaawase (Utaawase held at the Imperial Palace in the Kanna period)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanna ninen dairi Utaawase (Utaawase held at the Imperial Palace in the Kanna period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寛和二年内裏歌合（かんなにねんだいりうたあわせ）は、寛和2年6月10日 (旧暦)（986年7月19日）、花山天皇によって行われた歌合。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanna nine dairi Utaawase is an utaawase (poetry contest) held by Emperor Kazan on 19th July 986.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanna ninen dairi Utaawase is an utaawase (poetry contest) held by Emperor Kazan on the 19th of July, 986.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kanna ninen dairi Utaawase is an utaawase&quot; (poetry contest) held by Emperor Kazan on July 24, 986.</e>
<cmt>Kanna ninen dairi Utaawase にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。 19th of July, 986 をJuly 24, 986 に修正しました。※　7月19日はユリウス暦でした。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>花山天皇は和歌に対する関心が深く、前年の寛和元年8月10日にも歌合を開催している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kazan was deeply interested in waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and held another utaawase on 2nd July 985.</e>
<cmt>原文の旧暦の日付を計算で現在の暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kazan was deeply interested in waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and held another utaawase on the 2nd of July, 985.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kazan was deeply interested in waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and held another utaawase on September 2, 985.</e>
<cmt>September 2, 985 に修正しました。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>判者は天皇の外戚権中納言藤原義懐が務め、講師は左方は当時21歳の藤原公任が抜擢された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanja (referee) was FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, a maternal relative of Emperor and Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), and FUJIWARA no Kinto who was 21 years old at that time was elected to be koji (presenter of a poem) of the left side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanja (referee) was FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, a maternal relative of the Emperor and Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), and FUJIWARA no Kinto who was 21 years old at that time was elected to be koji (presenter of a poem) of the left side.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanja (referee) was FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, a maternal relative of the Emperor and Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), and FUJIWARA no Kinto who was 21 years old at that time was elected to be koji (presenter of a poem) of the left side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>公任は当時の関白藤原頼忠の子であるが、幼くしてその才能は認められ、前年の歌合にも参加していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinto is a son of FUJIWARA no Yoritada, the then Kanpaku (chief advise to the Emperor) whose talent was admitted from his childhood, and participated in the utaawase of previous year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinto was a son of FUJIWARA no Yoritada, the then Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) whose talent was recognized from his childhood, and participated in the utaawase of the previous year.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinto was a son of FUJIWARA no Yoritada, the then Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) whose talent was recognized from his childhood, and participated in the utaawase of the previous year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>右方は藤原長能が務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koji of the right side was FUJIWARA no Nagato.</e>
<cmt>原文では「右方」とのみありますが、「右方の講師」と補足し訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koji of the right side was FUJIWARA no Nagato.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koji of the right side was FUJIWARA no Nagato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>講師以外で参加した歌人として知られているのは、大中臣能宣・藤原惟成・藤原実方・曾禰好忠・藤原敦信・藤原明理・藤原道綱・藤原道長・藤原斉信らである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other kajin (waka poet) who are know to have participated include ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, FUJIWARA no Koreshige, FUJIWARA no Sanekata, SONE no Yoshitada, FUJIWARA no Atsunobu, FUJIWARA no Akimasa, FUJIWARA no Michitsuna, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and FUJIWARA no Tadanobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other kajin (waka poet) who are known to have participated include ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, FUJIWARA no Koreshige, FUJIWARA no Sanekata, SONE no Yoshitada, FUJIWARA no Atsunobu, FUJIWARA no Akimasa, FUJIWARA no Michitsuna, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and FUJIWARA no Tadanobu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other kajin (waka poet) who are known to have participated include ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, FUJIWARA no Koreshige, FUJIWARA no Sanekata, SONE no Yoshitada, FUJIWARA no Atsunobu, FUJIWARA no Akimasa, FUJIWARA no Michitsuna, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and FUJIWARA no Tadanobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>能宣・好忠ら著名な歌人に加えて、道長・斉信ら天皇とほぼ同世代の若手貴族が参加していることが特徴として挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to famous kajin such as Yoshinobu and Yoshitada, it is remarkable that Michinaga and Tadanobu, young nobles of almost same generation as Emperor took part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to famous kajin such as Yoshinobu and Yoshitada, it is remarkable that Michinaga and Tadanobu, young nobles of almost the same generation as the Emperor took part.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to famous kajin such as Yoshinobu and Yoshitada, it is remarkable that Michinaga and Tadanobu, young nobles of almost the same generation as the Emperor took part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>和歌は20題20番であるが、歌題は四季の景物18と「祝」「恋」の人事題各1題ずつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participants were required to make twenty poems for twenty Kadai (subject of waka Japanese poem), including eighteen subjects related to four seasons and two subjects about human affairs, &quot;celebration&quot; and &quot;love affairs&quot; respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participants were required to make twenty poems for twenty Kadai (subject of waka Japanese poem), including eighteen subjects related to four seasons and two subjects about human affairs, &quot;celebration&quot; and &quot;love affairs&quot; respectively.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participants were required to make twenty poems for twenty Kadai (subject of waka Japanese poem), including eighteen subjects related to natural features of four seasons and two subjects about human affairs, &apos;celebration&apos; and &apos;love affairs&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>「の景物」訳漏れのためnatural features of を追記しました。出典http://tangorin.com/words/景物ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテーションに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>四季の季題と人事題が同時に出された歌合の最古の記録である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the oldest record of utaawase at which seasonal and human affairs subjects were presented at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the oldest record of utaawase at which seasonal and human affairs subjects were presented at the same time.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the oldest record of utaawase at which seasonal and human affairs subjects were presented at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>和歌は類聚歌合10巻本と20巻本に所収されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poems are included in 10 volumes version and 20 volumes version of Ruiju Utaawase (Poetry Match on Related Themes).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poems are included in a 10 volumes version and a 20 volumes version of Ruiju Utaawase (Poetry Match on Related Themes).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poems are included in a 10 volumes version and a 20 volumes version of Ruiju Utaawase (Poetry Match on Related Themes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一部の勝敗に関する記述が不明で作者が諸説あるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statement about the outcome of the match is not clear in some parts, and there are some poems about which there are various opinions about author.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statement about the outcome of the match is not clear in some parts, and there are some poems about which there are various opinions about the author.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statement about the outcome of the match is not clear in some parts, and there are some poems about which there are various opinions about the author.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>この歌合からわずか13日後、花山天皇は突如出家をして退位、義懐・惟成もこれに続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only thirteen days after this utaawase, Emperor Kazan suddenly abdicated the throne to become a priest, followed by Yoshichika and Koreshige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only thirteen days after this utaawase, Emperor Kazan suddenly abdicated the throne to become a priest, followed by Yoshichika and Koreshige.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only thirteen days after this utaawase, Emperor Kazan suddenly abdicated the throne to become a priest, followed by Yoshichika and Koreshige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>7歳の一条天皇が即位し、政権も小野宮流から九条流に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Ichijo who was seven years old at that time ascended the throne, and political power shifted from Onomiya line to Kujo line.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Ichijo who was seven years old at that time ascended the throne, and political power shifted from the Onomiya line to the Kujo line.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Ichijo who was seven years old at that time ascended the throne, and political power shifted from the Onomiya line to the Kujo line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>摂関政治の大きな画期となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a big milestone of regency.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a big milestone of the regency.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a big milestone of the sekkan (regents and advisers) government.</e>
<cmt>摂関政治the regency をthe sekkan (regents and advisers) government に修正しました（※）。※ regency は「摂政（時代）」のみで「関白」の意味を含んでいないように思われます。http://eow.alc.co.jp/regency/UTF-8/sekkan government という定訳が以下のサイトにありましたので、これに (regents and advisers) を追記して訳してみました。出典http://books.google.com/books?id=UudGTW6nK2AC&amp;pg=PA35&amp;dq=Sekkan+government&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=Sekkan%20government&amp;f=falsehttp://tangorin.com/words/摂関</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>