<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本書紀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本書紀（にほんしょき、やまとぶみ）は、奈良時代に成立した日本の歴史書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki (also referred to as Yamatobumi) is a Japanese history book established in Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonshoki (also referred to as Yamatobumi) is a Japanese history book established in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki (also referred to as Yamatobumi) is a Japanese history book established in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本における伝存最古の正史で、六国史の第一にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the existing oldest official history in Japan, and the first of Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the oldest existing official history in Japan, and the first of Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the oldest existing official history in Japan, and the first of Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>舎人親王らの撰で、養老4年（720年）に完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Selected by Imperial Prince Toneri, et al., it was completed in 720.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selected by Imperial Prince Toneri, et al., it was completed in 720.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selected by Imperial Prince Toneri, et al., it was completed in 720.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本神話から持統天皇の時代までを扱う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It covers from Japanese Mythology to the era of Emperor Jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It covers from Japanese Mythology to the era of Emperor Jito.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It covers from Japanese Mythology to the era of Emperor Jito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>漢文・編年体をとる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It takes the form of classical Chinese and chronological order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It takes the form of classical Chinese and is in chronological order.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes the form of classical Chinese and is in chronological order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>全30巻、系図1巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty volumes in total plus one volume of genealogy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty volumes in total plus one volume of genealogy.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty volumes in total plus one volume of genealogy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>系図は失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The genealogy has been lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The genealogy has been lost.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The genealogy has been lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>成立過程</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Process of establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Process of establishment</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Process of establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>日本書紀成立の経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background of establishing Nihonshoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background of establishing Nihonshoki</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background of establishing Nihonshoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『古事記』と異なり『日本書紀』には、その成立の経緯が書かれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; does not describe the background of its establishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; does not describe the background of its establishment.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; does not describe the background of its establishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし後に成立した『続日本紀』の記述により、成立の経緯を知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, later-established &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describes how &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the later-established &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describes how &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the later-established &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describes how &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『続日本紀』の養老四年(AD720)五月癸酉条には、以下のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An article of Mizunoto-Tori, May 720 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article by Mizunoto-Tori, May 720 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describes,</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article by Mizunoto-Tori, May 720 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; describes as follows:</e>
<cmt>セル２０の原文を移動しました。合わせて訳文も修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>「先是一品舎人親王奉勅修日本紀 至是功成奏上 紀卅卷系圖一卷」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;先是一品舎人親王奉勅修日本紀 至是功成奏上 紀卅卷系圖一卷.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;先是一品舎人親王奉勅修日本紀 至是功成奏上 紀卅卷系圖一卷.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">先是一品舎人親王奉勅修日本紀 至是功成奏上 紀卅卷系圖一卷.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その意味は下記のことである（ここに『日本書紀』ではなく『日本紀』とあることについては書名を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means as follows (for the reason why the title is &quot;Nihongi&quot; instead of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; refer to the title):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What this means is as follows (for the reason why the title is &quot;Nihongi&quot; instead of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; refer to the title):</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What this means is as follows (for the reason why the title is &quot;Nihongi&quot; instead of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; refer to the title):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>「以前から、一品舍人親王、天皇の命を受けて日本紀の編纂に当たっていたが、この度完成し、紀三十巻と系図一巻を撰上した」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihongi has been edited at the behest of Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) Imperial Prince Toneri, now it is completed and thirty volumes of the history and one volume of genealogy are compiled and offered to the Emperor.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihongi has been edited at the behest of Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) Imperial Prince Toneri, now it is completed and thirty volumes of the history and one volume of genealogy are compiled and offered to the Emperor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihongi has been edited at the behest of Ippon (First Order of an Imperial Prince) Imperial Prince Toneri, now it is completed and thirty volumes of the history and one volume of genealogy are compiled and offered to the Emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>記述の信頼性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reliability of description</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reliability of description</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reliability of description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>中国の史書、『晋書』安帝 (東晋)には、266年に倭国の関係記事があり、その後は5世紀の初めの413年（東晋・義熙9年）に倭国が貢ぎ物を献じたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the articles of Emperor An in &quot;Jin shu&quot; (History of the Jin Dynasty), a history book in China, there is a description on Wakoku (Japan) in 266, and also another description that Wakoku paid a tribute in 413.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the articles of Emperor An in &quot;Jin shu&quot; (History of the Jin Dynasty), a history book in China, there is a description on Wakoku (Japan) in 266, and also another description that Wakoku paid a tribute in 413.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the articles of Emperor An in &quot;Jin shu&quot; (History of the Jin Dynasty), a history book in China, there is a description on Wakoku (Japan) in 266, and also another description that Wakoku paid a tribute in 413.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この間は中国の史書に記述がなく、考古学的文字記録は無いことから、「謎の4世紀」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, there is no description in history books in China and no record of archaeology, so that it is called &apos;the mysterious fourth century.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, there is no description in history books in China and no record of archeology, so that it is called &apos;the mysterious fourth century.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, there is no description in history books in China and no record of archeology, so that it is called &apos;the mysterious fourth century.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>倭の五王の上表文や隅田八幡神社鏡銘、埼玉県稲荷山古墳出土鉄剣銘文などから、5世紀代には文字が日本で使用されていると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from Johyobun (memorial to the Emperor) of the five kings of Wa, an inscription of the mirror of Sumidahachiman-jinja Shrine, and an inscription of iron sword which was excavated from Inariyama-kofun Tumulus in Saitama Prefecture, et al., it is thought that letters were used in Japan in the fifth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from Johyobun (memorial to the Emperor) of the five kings of Wa, an inscription of the mirror of Sumidahachiman-jinja Shrine, and an inscription on an iron sword which was excavated from Inariyama-kofun Tumulus in Saitama Prefecture, et al., it is thought that characters were used in Japan in the fifth century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from Johyobun (memorial to the Emperor) of the five kings of Wa, an inscription of the mirror of Sumidahachiman-jinja Shrine, and an inscription on an iron sword which was excavated from Inariyama-kofun Tumulus in Saitama Prefecture, et al., it is thought that characters were used in Japan in the fifth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、当時朝廷内で常時文字による記録がとられていたかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is not clear whether letters were always used for recording in the Imperial Court in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not clear whether characters were always used for recording in the Imperial Court in those days.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not clear whether characters were always used for recording in the Imperial Court in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>金錯銘鉄剣の発見により、雄略天皇の実在は確実であるとして、その前後、特に仁徳天皇以降の国内伝承にある程度の証拠能力を認めてもよいとする意見も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that the discovery of kinsakumei tekken (an iron sword with gold-inlaid inscriptions) made the existence of the Emperor Yuryaku certain and that the traditions around him, especially after the Emperor Nintoku, has an reality to some extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say that the discovery of kinsakumei tekken (an iron sword with gold-inlaid inscriptions) made the existence of the Emperor Yuryaku certain and that the traditions around him, especially after Emperor Nintoku, has an reality to some extent.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that the discovery of kinsakumei tekken (an iron sword with gold-inlaid inscriptions) made the existence of the Emperor Yuryaku certain and that the traditions around him, especially after Emperor Nintoku, has an reality to some extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一方、実証主義的観点から、記紀や『上宮記』を全面的に信用することは出来ないとして、継体天皇以前の大王の名や系図等は信頼性に乏しいという慎重な意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is another cautious opinion that because kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki) and &quot;Joguki&quot; (Record of the Crown Prince) can not be relied on completely from the viewpoint of positivism, the names and family trees of Okimi (king) before the Emperor Keitai are unreliable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there is another cautious opinion that because kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki) and &quot;Joguki&quot; (Record of the Crown Prince) can not be relied on completely from the viewpoint of positivism, the names and family trees of Okimi (king) before the Emperor Keitai are unreliable.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there is another cautious opinion that because the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki, and &quot;Joguki&quot; (Record of the Crown Prince) can not be relied on completely from the viewpoint of positivism, the names and family trees of Okimi (king) before the Emperor Keitai are unreliable.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>稲荷山古墳から発見された金錯銘鉄剣の銘によれば5世紀中葉の地方豪族が8世代にもわたる系図を作成したのは事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the inscription of kinsakumei tekken discovered from Inariyama-kofun, it is true that local Gozoku (local ruling family) in the middle of the fifth century made a family tree for eight generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the inscription of kinsakumei tekken discovered from Inariyama-kofun, it is true that local Gozoku (local ruling family) in the middle of the fifth century made a family tree for eight generations.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the inscription of kinsakumei tekken discovered from Inariyama-kofun, it is true that local Gozoku (local ruling family) in the middle of the fifth century made a family tree for eight generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただし、それが正確な史実であるかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is not sure whether it is an accurate historical fact or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not certain whether it is historically accurate or not.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not certain whether it is historically accurate or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>同様に、4世紀後半以前の皇室の祖先については、事実を正確に記録していたかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same way, it is not sure that it recorded the fact accurately about the ancestors of Imperial family before the latter part of the fourth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same way, it is not certain that it recorded the facts accurately about the ancestors of the Imperial family before the latter part of the fourth century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same way, it is not certain that it recorded the facts accurately about the ancestors of the Imperial Family before the latter part of the fourth century.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>『隋書』卷八十一 列傳第四十六 東夷 に以下のような記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the following description on the eastern barbarians in the 46th of heroes&apos; biographies of the 81st volume of &quot;Zuisho&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is the following description on the eastern barbarians in the 46th of heroes&apos; biographies of the 81st volume of &quot;Zuisho&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is the following description on the eastern barbarians in the 46th of heroes&apos; biographies of the 81st volume of &quot;Zuisho&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>「無文字唯刻木結繩敬佛法於百濟求得佛經始有文字」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;無文字唯刻木結繩敬佛法於百濟求得佛經始有文字.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;無文字唯刻木結繩敬佛法於百濟求得佛經始有文字.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">無文字唯刻木結繩敬佛法於百濟求得佛經始有文字.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>文字なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They do not have letters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They do not have characters.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They do not have characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ただ木を刻み縄を結ぶのみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They only cut woods and tie ropes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They only cut wood and tie ropes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They only cut wood and tie ropes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>百済において仏法を敬い、仏経を求得し、初めて文字あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they admired Buddhism and got Buddhism sutras in Baekje, they got letters for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they admired Buddhism and got Buddhist sutras in Baekje, they received characters for the first time.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they admired Buddhism and got Buddhist sutras in Baekje, they received characters for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この記述を根拠として、朝廷内での文字の常用はおそらく西暦600年前後、厩戸皇子（聖徳太子）の頃であり、継体天皇即位の頃については文字としての記録は無く、口頭での言い伝えとして大和朝廷周辺に記憶があったのみであるとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this description, there is a theory that letters probably began to be used commonly in the Imperial Court around 600 at the era of Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku) and that there was no record of letters around the time of the enthronement of Emperor Keitai, which was only remembered as a tradition by the people of Yamato Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this description, there is a theory that characters probably began to be used commonly in the Imperial Court around 600 during the era of Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku) and that there were no records of characters around the time of the enthronement of Emperor Keitai, which was only remembered as a tradition by the people of the Yamato Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this description, there is a theory that characters probably began to be used commonly in the Imperial Court around 600 during the era of Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku) and that there were no records of characters around the time of the enthronement of Emperor Keitai, which was only remembered as a tradition by the people of the Yamato Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>現代の研究では、『古事記』や『日本書紀』の継体天皇以前の記述、特に編年は正確さを保証できないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In today&apos;s researches, the descriptions on the events before the Emperor Keitai in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; especially the year of edition, are thought to be inaccurate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In today&apos;s researches, the descriptions on the events before the Emperor Keitai in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; especially the year of edition, are thought to be inaccurate.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In today&apos;s researches, the descriptions on the events before the Emperor Keitai in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; especially the year of edition, are thought to be inaccurate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そのことは継体天皇の没年が『古事記』と『日本書紀』で三説があげられ、『書紀』の編者は外国資料である『百済本記』に基づき531年説を本文に採用したことからも推察することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This can be guessed by the fact that there are three kinds of descriptions on the year of the Emperor Keitai&apos;s death in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and that the editor of &quot;Shoki&quot; adopted the theory of 531 based on a foreign material, &quot;Original records of Baekje.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be guessed by the fact that there are three kinds of descriptions on the year of Emperor Keitai&apos;s death in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and that the editor of &quot;Shoki&quot; adopted the theory of 531 based on a foreign material, &quot;Original records of Baekje.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be guessed by the fact that there are three kinds of descriptions on the year of Emperor Keitai&apos;s death in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and that the editor of &quot;Shoki&quot; adopted the theory of 531 based on a foreign material, &quot;Original records of Baekje.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>皇室の歴代や系図の成立過程については、継体の系図を記録した『上宮記』や、現在は伝わらない聖徳太子による国史の成立以前にも各種の系図は存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were various family trees of the past Imperial family such as &quot;Joguki&quot; which recorded the family tree of the Emperor Keitai and others before the establishment of national history by Prince Shotoku which does not exist now.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were various family trees of the past Imperial family such as &quot;Joguki&quot; which recorded the family tree of the Emperor Keitai and others before the establishment of national history by Prince Shotoku which does not exist now.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were various family trees of the past Imperial family such as &quot;Joguki&quot; which recorded the family tree of the Emperor Keitai and others before the establishment of national history by Prince Shotoku which does not exist now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>が、様々な系図に祖先として伝説上の人物を書いたもので正確な内容ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these are not accurate because only the names of legendary people were written as ancestors on various family trees.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these are not accurate because only the names of legendary people were written as ancestors on various family trees.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these are not accurate because only the names of legendary people were written as ancestors on various family trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これらを参考にして『上宮記』や『古事記』、『日本書紀』が作られたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that &quot;Joguki,&quot; &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; were written based on these.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say that &quot;Joguki,&quot; &quot;Kojiki,&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; were written based on these.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that &quot;Joguki,&quot; &quot;Kojiki,&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; were written based on these.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>仮に推古朝の600年頃に『上宮記』が成立したとするなら、継体天皇（オホド王）が崩御した継体天皇25年（531年）は、当時から70年前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If &quot;Joguki&quot; was established around 600 in the era of Empress Suiko, the year when the Emperor Keitai (King Ohodo) died, that is, 531, was 70 years earlier from that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If &quot;Joguki&quot; was established around 600 in the era of Empress Suiko, the year when Emperor Keitai (King Ohodo) died, that is, 531, was 70 years earlier than that.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If &quot;Joguki&quot; was established around 600 in the era of Empress Suiko, the year when Emperor Keitai (King Ohodo) died, that is, 531, was 70 years earlier than that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>なお、記紀編纂の基本史料となった『帝紀』、『旧辞』は7世紀頃の成立と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is thought that &quot;Teiki&quot; (a genealogy of the imperial family) and &quot;Kyuji&quot; (a record of stories current at court) which were the basic historical materials for the compilation of Kiki were established around the seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is thought that &quot;Teiki&quot; (a genealogy of the imperial family) and &quot;Kyuji&quot; (a record of stories current at court) which were the basic historical materials for the compilation of Kiki were established around the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is thought that &quot;Teiki&quot; (a genealogy of the Imperial Family) and &quot;Kyuji&quot; (a record of stories current at court) which were the basic historical materials for the compilation of Kojiki and the Nihonshoki were established around the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>『日本書紀』には推古天皇28年（620年）に、「是歲 皇太子、島大臣共議之 錄天皇記及國記 臣 連 伴造 國造 百八十部并公民等本記」（皇太子は厩戸皇子（聖徳太子）、島大臣は蘇我馬子）という記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; there is a following record of 620, &quot;是歲 皇太子,島大臣共議之 錄天皇記及國記 臣 連 伴造 國造 百八十部并公民等本記&quot; (the prince referred to Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku) and Shima-daijin referred to SOGA no Umako).</e>
<cmt>島大臣の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; there is a following record of 620, &quot;是歲 皇太子,島大臣共議之 錄天皇記及國記 臣 連 伴造 國造 百八十部并公民等本記&quot; (the prince referred to Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku) and Shima-daijin referred to SOGA no Umako).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; there is a following record of 620, &apos;是歲 皇太子,島大臣共議之 錄天皇記及國記 臣 連 伴造 國造 百八十部并公民等本記&apos; (the prince referred to Prince Umayado (Prince Shotoku) and Shima-daijin referred to SOGA no Umako).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>当時のヤマト王権に史書編纂に資する正確かつ十分な文字記録があったと推定しうる根拠は乏しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are few reasons for the assumption that the Yamato dynasty at that time had accurate and enough records which could contribute to the compilation of history books.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are few reasons for the assumption that the Yamato dynasty at that time had accurate and enough records which could contribute to the compilation of history books.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are few reasons for the assumption that the Yamato dynasty at that time had accurate and enough records which could contribute to the compilation of history books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その編纂が仮に事実であったとしても、口承伝承に多く頼らざるを得なかったと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if that compilation had been true, it is guessed that it have had to largely rely on oral traditions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if that compilation had been true, it is guessed that it had to have largely relied on oral traditions.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if that compilation had been true, it is guessed that it had to have largely relied on oral traditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>なお、『日本書紀』によれば、この時聖徳太子らが作った歴史書『国記』、『天皇記』は蘇我蝦夷・蘇我入鹿が滅ぼされた時に大部分焼失したが、焼け残ったものは天智天皇に献上されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; most of the history books, &quot;Kokki&quot; (a National Record) and &quot;Tennoki&quot; (a Record of the Emperors), which were written by Prince Shotoku et al., were burnt down when Soga no Emishi and Soga no Iruka were killed, but others which escaped a fire were presented to the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; most of the history books, &quot;Kokki&quot; (a National Record) and &quot;Tennoki&quot; (a Record of the Emperors), which were written by Prince Shotoku et al., were burnt down when Soga no Emishi and Soga no Iruka were killed, but others which escaped the fire were presented to the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; most of the history books, &quot;Kokki&quot; (a National Record) and &quot;Tennoki&quot; (a Record of the Emperors), which were written by Prince Shotoku et al., were burnt down when Soga no Emishi and Soga no Iruka were killed, but others which escaped the fire were presented to the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="42">
<j>また、かつて百済三書は六世紀後半の威徳王の時代に対倭国政策の必要から倭王に提出するために百済で編纂されたと見られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, at one time the three books of Baekje (百済三書) were regarded to be edited in Baekje during the era of King Widok in the latter part of the sixth century in order to submit to the king of Wa (Japan) from necessity for diplomatic policy against Wakoku.</e>
<cmt>百済三書の定訳不明です。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, at one time the three books of Baekje (百済三書) were regarded to be edited in Baekje during the era of King Widok in the latter part of the sixth century in order to submit to the king of Wa (Japan) from necessity for diplomatic policy against Wakoku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, at one time the three books of Baekje (百済三書) were regarded to be edited in Baekje during the era of King Widok in the latter part of the sixth century in order to submit to the king of Wa (Japan) from necessity for diplomatic policy against Wakoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>日本書紀の編者はその原文を価値あるものとして重んじていたと考えられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was thought that the editor of Nihonshoki put a high value on those original texts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was thought that the editor of Nihonshoki put a high value on those original texts.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was thought that the editor of Nihonshoki put a high value on those original texts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>だからこそ百済三書に基づいてる日本書紀の記事を厳正に選び、これを繋ぎ合せていくと、日朝関係の実像が客観的に復元できると固く信じられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was firmly believed that if descriptions of Nihonshoki based on the three books of Baekje were strictly chosen and combined, the real figure of the relationship between Japan and Korea could be objectively restored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was firmly believed that if descriptions of Nihonshoki based on the three books of Baekje were strictly chosen and combined, the real figure of the relationship between Japan and Korea could be objectively restored.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was firmly believed that if descriptions of Nihonshoki based on the three books of Baekje were strictly chosen and combined, the real figure of the relationship between Japan and Korea could be objectively restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし、そのように高い信用性をもつと考えられた記事の中に、百済王の言葉として、自分は天皇の「黎民」と「封」建された領土とを治めている、自分たちの国は天皇に「調」を貢いで仕えまつる「官家（みやけ）」の国、元来の天皇の「封」域を侵して「新羅の折れる」加羅諸国を天皇の命令で「本貫に還し属け」てほしいなど、自分は天皇の「蕃」（藩屏）をなす「臣」などこの種の表現があふれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among those descriptions which were considered to be highly reliable, there are a lot of words of King of Baekje which show that he was a &apos;follower&apos; who protected the emperor as follows; He governs &apos;the people&apos; of the emperor and &apos;allotted&apos; land, His country is a country of &apos;Miyake&apos; which makes &apos;cho&apos; (tributes) and serves the emperor and He hopes that the emperor will make Kaya countries which were originally &apos;allotted&apos; land of emperor but &apos;invaded&apos; by Silla &apos;belong to the home place again&apos; by an imperial order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among those descriptions which were considered to be highly reliable, there are a lot of words of King of Baekje which show that he was a &apos;follower&apos; who protected the emperor as follows; He governs &apos;the people&apos; of the emperor and &apos;allotted&apos; land, His country is a country of &apos;Miyake&apos; which makes &apos;cho&apos; (tributes) and serves the emperor and He hopes that the emperor will make Kaya countries which were originally &apos;allotted&apos; land of the emperor but &apos;invaded&apos; by Silla &apos;belong to the home place again&apos; by an imperial order.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, among those descriptions which were considered to be highly reliable, there are a lot of words of King of Baekje which show that he was a &apos;follower&apos; who protected the emperor as follows; He governs &apos;the people&apos; of the emperor and &apos;allotted&apos; land, His country is a country of &apos;Miyake&apos; which makes &apos;cho&apos; (tributes) and serves the emperor and He hopes that the emperor will make Kaya countries which were originally &apos;allotted&apos; land of the emperor but &apos;invaded&apos; by Silla &apos;belong to the home place again&apos; by an imperial order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>地の文には、百済王が、天皇から全羅北道の地を「賜」与されたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a descriptive part, there is a description that the King of Baekje was &apos;given&apos; the land of North Jeolla Province by the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a another part, there is a description that says the King of Baekje was &apos;given&apos; the land of North Jeolla Province by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In another part, there is a description that says the King of Baekje was &apos;given&apos; the land of North Jeolla Province by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>a削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>百済三書の中でも最も記録性に富むのは『百済本記』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the three books of Baekje, &quot;Original records of Baekje&quot; has the largest amount of records.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the three books of Baekje, &quot;Original records of Baekje&quot; has the largest amount of records.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the three books of Baekje, &quot;Original records of Baekje&quot; has the largest amount of records.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>それに基づいた『継体紀』『欽明紀』の記述には、「日本の天皇が朝鮮半島に広大な領土を有っていた」としなければ意味不通になる文章が非常に多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many descriptions of &quot;the Keitai section&quot; and &quot;the Kinmei section&quot; based on it turn to be nonsense without an assumption that &apos;Japanese emperor had a large land in Korean Peninsula.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many descriptions of &quot;the Keitai section&quot; and &quot;the Kinmei section&quot; based on it turn out to be nonsense without the assumption that the &apos;Japanese emperor had a large land in the Korean Peninsula.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many descriptions of &quot;the Keitai section&quot; and &quot;the &quot;Kinmei section&quot; based on it turn out to be nonsense without the assumption that the &apos;Japanese emperor had a large land in the Korean Peninsula.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>「百済本記に云はく、安羅を以て父とし、日本府を以て本とす、と」とあるように「任那日本府」もその中に表れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a description that &apos;Original records of Baekje wrote that Alla is the father country and Japan is the home country&apos; shows, &apos; the Japanese Mimana Government&apos; is also described in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A description that says &apos;Original records of Baekje wrote that Alla is the father country and Japan is the home country&apos; shows, &apos;the Japanese Mimana Government&apos; is also described in it.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A description that says &apos;Original records of Baekje wrote that Alla is the father country and Japan is the home country&apos; shows, &apos;the Japanese Mimana Government&apos; is also described in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>百済王に「賜」与したとか、新羅王が「封」域を侵したという地の古地名を考証し、その最も北に線を引いたもの、それがかつての日本における「任那境域の縮小過程」図の「370年ころ」の「直轄領土」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The direct control territory&apos; &apos;around 370&apos; in the picture of &apos;the shrinking process of the territory of Minama&apos; in Japan was determined by studying a story of &apos;the present&apos; to King Baekje and an old place name of the &apos;allotted&apos; land which King Silla invaded and putting the border on most northerly line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The directly controlled territory &apos;around 370&apos; in the picture of &apos;the shrinking process of the territory of Minama&apos; in Japan was determined by studying a story of &apos;the present&apos; to King Baekje and an old place name of the &apos;allotted&apos; land which King Silla invaded and putting the border on the most northerly line.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The directly controlled territory &apos;around 370&apos; in the picture of &apos;the shrinking process of the territory of Minama&apos; in Japan was determined by studying a story of &apos;the present&apos; to King Baekje and an old place name of the &apos;allotted&apos; land which King Silla invaded and putting the border on the most northerly line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>その直轄地域とは全羅道、忠清道の南半分、慶尚道の西半分の広大な地域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That direct control territory was a vast area including Jeolla-do, the southern half of Chungcheong-do and the western half of Gyeongsang-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That directly controlled territory was a vast area including Jeolla-do, the southern half of Chungcheong-do and the western half of Gyeongsang-do.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That directly controlled territory was a vast area including Jeolla-do, the southern half of Chungcheong-do and the western half of Gyeongsang-do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>それは百済三書に依拠しており、それだけに長く信用されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those depend on the three books of Baekje and therefore, they have been relied on for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those depend on the three books of Baekje and therefore, they have been relied on for a long time.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those depend on the three books of Baekje and therefore, they have been relied on for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし、それまで日本で信じられてきた通説は誤りに基づいていたことが判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was cleared that the common view which had been believed in Japan was wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it became clear that the common view which had been believed in Japan was wrong.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it became clear that the common view which had been believed in Japan was wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>『神功紀』『応神紀』の注釈に引用された『百済記』に「新羅、貴国に奉らず。貴国、沙至比跪（さちひこ）を遣して討たしむ」、「阿花王立つ、貴国に礼なし」、（木刕満致は）「我が国に来入りて、貴国に往還ふ」「日本の貴国」などと記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Records of Baekje&quot; which was cited for the notes of &quot;the Jingu section&quot; and &quot;the Ojin section,&quot; there are descriptions such as &apos;Silla did not serve &quot;貴国.&quot; &quot;貴国&quot; dispatched Sachihiko and made him conquer,&apos; &apos;Akueo 立つ, but &quot;貴国&quot;に礼なし,&apos; and (Manchi MOKURA) &apos;came to our country, and went and came to &quot;貴国,&quot; and &apos;&quot;貴国&quot; of Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「の定訳、読み方不明です。阿花王立つ、貴国に礼なし」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Records of Baekje&quot; which was cited for the notes of &quot;the Jingu section&quot; and &quot;the Ojin section,&quot; there are descriptions such as &apos;Silla did not serve &quot;貴国.&quot; &quot;貴国&quot; dispatched Sachihiko and made him conquer,&apos; &apos;Akueo 立つ, but &quot;貴国&quot;に礼なし,&apos; and (Manchi MOKURA) &apos;came to our country, and went and came to &quot;貴国,&quot; and &apos;&quot;貴国&quot; of Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Records of Baekje&quot; which was cited for the notes of &quot;the Jingu section&quot; and &quot;the Ojin section,&quot; there are descriptions such as &apos;Silla did not serve &quot;貴国.&quot; &quot;貴国&quot; dispatched Sachihiko and made him conquer,&apos; &apos;Akueo 立つ, but &quot;貴国&quot;に礼なし,&apos; and (Manchi MOKURA) &apos;came to our country, and went and came to &quot;貴国,&quot; and &apos;&quot;貴国&quot; of Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この「貴国」を「二人称的称呼」（あなたのおくに）とそれまでの日本の学者は誤解していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The previous Japanese scholars thought wrongly that this &quot;貴国&quot; showed &apos;your country.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The previous Japanese scholars thought wrongly that this &quot;貴国&quot; showed &apos;your country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The previous Japanese scholars thought wrongly that this &quot;貴国&quot; showed &apos;your country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>総ての説明はここから始っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All explanations were based on this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All explanations were based on this.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All explanations were based on this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>しかし日本書紀本文では第三者相互の会話でも日本のことを「貴国」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the text of Nihonshoki, Japan is called &apos;貴国&apos; even in the conversation between third parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the text of Nihonshoki, Japan is called &apos;貴国&apos; even in the conversation between third parties.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the text of Nihonshoki, Japan is called &apos;貴国&apos; even in the conversation between third parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>貴国とは、「可畏（かしこき）天皇」「聖（ひじり）の王」が君臨する「貴（とうとき）国」「神（かみの）国」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;貴国&quot; refers to the &apos;noble country&apos; or &apos;divine land&apos; reigned by &apos;august emperor&apos; or &apos;saint king.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;貴国&quot; refers to the &apos;noble country&apos; or &apos;divine land&apos; reigned by the &apos;august emperor&apos; or &apos;saint king.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;貴国&quot; refers to the &apos;noble country&apos; or &apos;divine land&apos; reigned by the &apos;august emperor&apos; or &apos;saint king.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>「現神」が統治する「神国」という意識は、百済三書の原文にもある「日本」「天皇」号の出現と揆（原文まま）を一にしており、それは天武の時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The consciousness of &apos;Shinkoku (divine land)&apos; controlled by &apos;a living god&apos; appeared in the same period of the appearance of the terms of &apos;Japan&apos; and &apos;emperor&apos; in the text of the three books of Baekje and it was the era of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The consciousness of &apos;Shinkoku (divine land)&apos; controlled by &apos;a living god&apos; appeared in the same period of the appearance of the terms of &apos;Japan&apos; and &apos;emperor&apos; in the text of the three books of Baekje and it was the era of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The consciousness of &apos;Shinkoku&apos; (divine land) controlled by &apos;a living god&apos; appeared in the same period of the appearance of the terms of &apos;Japan&apos; and &apos;emperor&apos; in the text of the three books of Baekje and it was the era of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>六世紀後半はもちろんのこと「推古朝」にも存在していないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that it did not exist not only in the latter part of the sixth century but also in the era of &apos;the Empress Suiko.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that it not only didn&apos;t it exist in the latter part of the sixth century but also in the era of &apos;the Empress Suiko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that it not only didn&apos;t exist in the latter part of the sixth century but also in the era of &apos;the Empress Suiko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>it削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="61">
<j>百済三書の実態について今日では次のように考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the actual condition of the three books of Baekje is thought as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the actual condition of the three books of Baekje is thought of as follows.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the actual condition of the three books of Baekje is thought of as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="62">
<j>百済三書の記事の原形は百済王朝の史籍に遡ると推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is guessed that the original form of the text of the three books of Baekje went back to the history books of the Baekje Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is guessed that the original form of the text of the three books of Baekje went back to the history books of the Baekje Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is guessed that the original form of the text of the three books of Baekje went back to the history books of the Baekje Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>七世紀末～八世紀初めに、滅亡後に移住した百済の王族、貴族が、持ってきた本国の史書から改めて編纂し直して天皇の官府に進めたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the royal family and nobles of Baekje who moved to Japan after it was subverted from the end of the seventh century to the beginning of the eighth century compiled the history book of their home country again and presented to the government of the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the royal family and nobles of Baekje who moved to Japan after it was subverted from the end of the seventh century to the beginning of the eighth century compiled the history book of their home country again and presented it to the government of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the royal family and nobles of Baekje who moved to Japan after it was subverted from the end of the seventh century to the beginning of the eighth century compiled the history book of their home country again and presented it to the government of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>そして日本書紀の編纂者はこれに大幅に手を加えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the compiler of Nihonshoki greatly arranged this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the compiler of Nihonshoki greatly arranged this.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the compiler of Nihonshoki greatly arranged this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>仮に百済三書の「原文」にまで遡ることができたとしても、用字用語や評価、意味付けは、7、8世紀の交の日本において理解しなければならず、すぐに百済の原史籍の内容に遡ることは出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if &apos;the original text&apos; of the three books of Baekje could be gone back, terms and meanings have to be understood in the context of Japan of &apos;交&apos; in the seventh and eighth centuries and it is impossible to quickly go back to the contents of the original history book of Baekje.</e>
<cmt>「交の日本」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if &apos;the original text&apos; of the three books of Baekje went back that far, terms and meanings have to be understood in the context of the Japan of &apos;交&apos; in the seventh and eighth centuries and it is impossible to quickly go back to the contents of the original history book of Baekje.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if &apos;the original text&apos; of the three books of Baekje went back that far, terms and meanings have to be understood in the context of the Japan of &apos;交&apos; in the seventh and eighth centuries and it is impossible to quickly go back to the contents of the original history book of Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>記事当代の記録を推測するのは至難である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is very difficult to guess the background of the records when those were described.</e>
<cmt>原文の「記録を推測する」は不自然な日本語ですが、「記録の背景を推測する」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is very difficult to guess the background of the records when those were described.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is very difficult to guess the background of the records when those were described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>とにかく7、8世紀の交の意味付けはこれを徹底的に排し、百済王朝側の正当化の論理に十分用心して、客観的事実のみから蓋然性の範囲を推測しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, the meanings of &apos;交&apos; in the seventh and eighth centuries have to be cut off overwhelmingly and the probability has to be guessed only by objective facts with taking enough precaution against the legitimization of the Baekje Dynasty side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyway, the meanings of &apos;交&apos; in the seventh and eighth centuries have to be cut off overwhelmingly and the probability has to be guessed only by objective facts with taking enough precaution against the legitimization of the Baekje Dynasty side.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyway, the meanings of &apos;交&apos; in the seventh and eighth centuries have to be cut off overwhelmingly and the probability has to be guessed only by objective facts with taking enough precaution against the legitimization of the Baekje Dynasty side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>7世紀末以後の亡命した百済王族・貴族は、残らず全て天皇の臣下として組織されていたということがその理由である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because all royal family and nobles who exiled after the end of the seventh century were organized as the followers of emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because all royal family and nobles who were exiled after the end of the seventh century were organized as the followers of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because all royal family and nobles who were exiled after the end of the seventh century were organized as the followers of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>8世紀半ばごろまで難波の百済郡には、「天皇」が藩屏として冊立する「百済王」の「小百済国」的実体が存続していた可能性さえ考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be thought that there was a &apos;small Baekje country&apos; of &apos;King Baekje&apos; who was installed as hanpei (protector of the emperor) by &apos;emperor&apos; at the Kudara County of Nanba until the middle of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be thought that there was a &apos;small Baekje country&apos; of &apos;King Baekje&apos; who was installed as hanpei (protector of the emperor) by the &apos;emperor&apos; at the Kudara County of Nanba until the middle of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be thought that there was a &apos;small Baekje country&apos; of &apos;King Baekje&apos; who was installed as hanpei (protector of the emperor) by the &apos;emperor&apos; at the Kudara County of Nanba until the middle of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>根本的な事実である律令国家体制下の編纂という時代の性質、編纂の主体が置かれていた天皇の臣下という立場の性質、政治的な地位の保全への期待という思想性、それらを無視して百済三書に基づく日本書紀の記述を読むことは全くもって不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is totally impossible to understand the descriptions of Nihonshoki based on the three books of Baekje without regard to the backgrounds such as the period under the system of the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, the position as a follower of the emperor who led compilation, and the expectation to maintain their political status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is totally impossible to understand the descriptions of Nihonshoki based on the three books of Baekje without regard to the backgrounds such as the period under the system of the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, the position as a follower of the emperor who led the compilation, and the expectation to maintain their political status.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is totally impossible to understand the descriptions of Nihonshoki based on the three books of Baekje without regard to the backgrounds such as the period under the system of the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, the position as a follower of the emperor who led the compilation, and the expectation to maintain their political status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>天皇が百済王に「賜」わったという地は、忠清道の洪城、維鳩、公州付近から全羅道の栄山江、蟾津江流域にまで及んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The land which was &apos;given&apos; to the King Baekje by the emperor was a vast area from Hongseong, Yugu and Gongju in Chungcheong-do to the watershed areas of Yeongsan River and Seomjin River in Jeolla-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land which was &apos;given&apos; to King Baekje by the emperor was a vast area from Hongseong, Yugu, and Gongju in Chungcheong-do to the watershed areas of Yeongsan River and Seomjin River in Jeolla-do.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land which was &apos;given&apos; to King Baekje by the emperor was a vast area from Hongseong, Yugu, and Gongju in Chungcheong-do to the watershed areas of Yeongsan River and Seomjin River in Jeolla-do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これは、滅亡時の百済王が独立して、かつ正当に統治していた国家の領土とほぼ一致している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This almost corresponded the territory of the nation which the King Baekje had reigned independently and legitimately when Baekje was subverted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This almost corresponded to the territory of the nation which King Baekje had reigned independently and legitimately when Baekje was subverted.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This almost corresponded to the territory of the nation which King Baekje had reigned independently and legitimately when Baekje was subverted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>しかし7,8世紀の交の在日百済王族、貴族は、それを天皇から委任された統治と表現せざるを得ない臣下の立場に置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the royal family and nobles of Baekje of &apos;交&apos; who stayed in Japan in the seventh and eighth centuries stood on the position of followers who have had to express it as a delegation of the sovereignty by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>「交の」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the royal family and nobles of Baekje of &apos;交&apos; who stayed in Japan in the seventh and eighth centuries stood on the position of followers who have had to express it as a delegation of the sovereignty by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the royal family and nobles of Baekje of &apos;交&apos; who stayed in Japan in the seventh and eighth centuries stood on the position of followers who have had to express it as a delegation of the sovereignty by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>このような観念を実体化して「高麗、百済、新羅、任那」は「海表の蕃屏として」「元より賜はれる封の限」をもつ「官家を置ける国」だった（『継体紀』）などというのは完全に虚構の歴史である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is completely a fictional history which gives substance to these ideas and considers that &apos;Goryeo, Baekje, Silla and Minama&apos; were &apos;the country which had a local government (官家)&apos; that had a land given by Japan (元) &apos;as follower of 海表&apos; (&quot;the Keitai section&quot;).</e>
<cmt>官家、海表の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is completely a fictional history which gives substance to these ideas and considers that &apos;Goryeo, Baekje, Silla and Minama&apos; were &apos;the country which had a local government (官家)&apos; that had land given by Japan (元) &apos;as followers of 海表&apos; (&quot;the Keitai section&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is completely a fictional history which gives substance to these ideas and considers that &apos;Goryeo, Baekje, Silla and Minama&apos; were &apos;the country which had a local government (官家)&apos; that had land given by Japan (元) &apos;as followers of 海表&apos; (&quot;the Keitai section&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>「直轄領」と「保護国」とをもつ「東夷の小帝国」と換言しても事実認識に変化はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no disparity in saying it as &apos;a small empire of eastern barbarians&apos; which has &apos;direct control territory&apos; and &apos;a protected state.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no disparity in saying it as &apos;a small empire of eastern barbarians&apos; which has &apos;directly controlled territory&apos; and &apos;a protected state.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no disparity in saying it as &apos;a small empire of eastern barbarians&apos; which has &apos;directly controlled territory&apos; and &apos;a protected state.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="76">
<j>日本書紀の朝鮮関係資料には混乱偽造があると考えられているため、実に様々な意見が提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it is thought that some historical materials related to Korea in Nihonshoki were confused or forged, there are so many opinions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it is thought that some historical materials related to Korea in Nihonshoki were confused or forged, there are so many opinions.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it is thought that some historical materials related to Korea in Nihonshoki were confused or forged, there are so many opinions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>日本書紀における朝鮮半島に対する記述に対しては疑問が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some questions arise against the descriptions on Korean Peninsula in Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some questions arise against the descriptions of the Korean Peninsula in Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some questions arise against the descriptions of the Korean Peninsula in Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>上垣外憲一は、大和の権威を高めるために編纂されたのは周知の事実だが特に朝鮮半島関係の造作は著しいと指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenichi KAMIGAITO has pointed out that it is common knowledge that it was compiled in order to rise the authority of Yamato and there are many fiction related to Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenichi KAMIGAITO has pointed out that it is common knowledge that it was compiled in order to raise the authority of Yamato and there are many fictional elements related to the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenichi KAMIGAITO has pointed out that it is common knowledge that it was compiled in order to raise the authority of Yamato and there are many fictional elements related to the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>その背景として日本書紀の編纂が白村江の戦いで新羅に敗れてから間もないため、言葉の上だけでも朝鮮半島に威張りたいという心理があったと指摘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He pointed out that on the background there was a feeling to stand on its dignity at least on words because Nihonshoki was compiled soon after Japan was defeated by Silla at the Battle of Hakusukinoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He pointed out that as background reference, there was a need to save dignity at least in words because Nihonshoki was compiled soon after Japan was defeated by Silla at the Battle of Hakusukinoe.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He pointed out that as background reference, there was a need to save dignity at least in words because Nihonshoki was compiled soon after Japan was defeated by Silla at the Battle of Hakusukinoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>山内弘一は大和朝廷が中国から導入した自身を中心とし周辺国を蔑む天下的世界認識や華夷思想によって朝鮮半島の新羅を「蕃国」と位置づけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koichi YAMAUCHI has pointed out as follows; the Yamato Dynasty positioned Silla of Korean Peninsula as &apos;barbarian country&apos; by the recognition of the world which put itself on the center and despised surrounding countries and the Sinocentrism which were introduced by China. And since such recognition of the world also existed in Silla which accepted Chinese Civilization, it was merely a subjective recognition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koichi YAMAUCHI has pointed out the following; the Yamato Dynasty positioned Silla of the Korean Peninsula as a &apos;barbarian country&apos; by the recognition of the world which put itself on the center and despised surrounding countries and the Sinocentrism which were introduced by China. And since such recognition of the world also existed in Silla which accepted Chinese Civilization, it was merely a subjective recognition.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koichi YAMAUCHI has pointed out the following; the Yamato Dynasty positioned Silla of the Korean Peninsula as a &apos;barbarian country&apos; by the recognition of the world which put itself on the center and despised surrounding countries and the Sinocentrism which were introduced by China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>このような天下的世界認識は中華文明を同様に受容した新羅にも存在するため、所詮は主観的な認識の次元だと指摘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And since such recognition of the world also existed in Silla which accepted Chinese Civilization, it was merely a subjective recognition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>中国人学者の沈仁安は日本書紀の信頼性を検証した結果、朝鮮の正史である三国史記を以て日本書紀の記述を訂正することは相反しないと指摘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ren&apos;an SHEN, a Chinese scholar, verified the reliability of Nihonshoki, and as a result, he has pointed out that it is not wrong to correct the descriptions of Nihonshoki by Samguk Sagi (History of the Three Kingdoms) which is the official history of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ren&apos;an SHEN, a Chinese scholar, verified the reliability of Nihonshoki, and as a result, he has pointed out that it is not wrong to correct the descriptions of Nihonshoki with Samguk Sagi (History of the Three Kingdoms) which is the official history of Korea.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ren&apos;an SHEN, a Chinese scholar, verified the reliability of Nihonshoki, and as a result, he has pointed out that it is not wrong to correct the descriptions of Nihonshoki with Samguk Sagi (History of the Three Kingdoms) which is the official history of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>鈴木英夫は『日本書紀』編纂時に白村江の敗戦を契機とする八世紀代律令国家の新羅「蕃国」視によって、「在安羅諸倭臣」は百済王の統制に服し、倭王権の派遣軍は百済の「傭兵」的性格を帯びていたという事実が誇張・拡大されて「任那日本府」の存在や倭王権の「官家」たる百済・「任那」の従属を核とする内容の史的構想が成立したと指摘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideo SUZUKI has pointed out as follows; after the defeat at the Battle of Hakusukinoe, the vision to see Silla as &apos;barbarian country&apos; by the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes in the eighth century exaggerated the fact that &apos;Japanese followers of Alla&apos; were controlled by King Baekje and that the dispatched army of Yamato Dynasty was a kind of &apos;mercenary&apos; of Baekje, and as a result, the historical idea centering on the existence of &apos;Japanese government at Minama&apos; and the subordinance of Baekje and &apos;Minama&apos; which were &apos;官家&apos; of Yamato Dynasty was established.</e>
<cmt>「官家」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideo SUZUKI has pointed out the following; after the defeat at the Battle of Hakusukinoe, the vision to see Silla as a &apos;barbarian country&apos; by the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes in the eighth century exaggerated the fact that &apos;Japanese followers of Alla&apos; were controlled by King Baekje and that the dispatched army of the Yamato Dynasty was a kind of &apos;mercenary&apos; of Baekje, and as a result, the historical idea centering on the existence of a &apos;Japanese government at Minama&apos; and the subordinance of Baekje and &apos;Minama&apos; which were &apos;官家&apos; of the Yamato Dynasty was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideo SUZUKI has pointed out the following; after the defeat at the Battle of Hakusukinoe, the vision to see Silla as a &apos;barbarian country&apos; by the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes in the eighth century exaggerated the fact that &apos;Japanese followers of Alla&apos; were controlled by King Baekje and that the dispatched army of the Yamato Dynasty was a kind of &apos;mercenary&apos; of Baekje, and as a result, the historical idea centering on the existence of a &apos;Japanese government at Minama&apos; and the subordinance of Baekje and &apos;Minama&apos; which were &apos;官家&apos; of the Yamato Dynasty was established when &quot;Ninhonshoki&quot; was compiled.</e>
<cmt>when &quot;Ninhonshoki&quot; was compiled補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>直木孝次郎は何もかも失った大和とは対照的に新羅は唐をも破って朝鮮統一をしてしまったために大和は新羅から先進的な政治体制や文化を学ぶ一方で相当な危機感を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojiro NAOKI has pointed out as follows; as opposed to Yamato which lost everything, Silla defeated even Tang and achieved the integration of Korea, so that Yamato had a lot of sense of crisis while it learned advanced political system and culture from Silla. The nationalism caused by such sense of crisis appeared visibly at the time of compilation of Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojiro NAOKI has pointed out the following; as opposed to Yamato which lost everything, Silla defeated even the Tang and achieved the integration of Korea, so that Yamato had a sense of crisis while it learned about advanced political systems and culture from the Silla. The nationalism caused by such a sense of crisis appeared visibly at the time of compilation of Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojiro NAOKI has pointed out the following; as opposed to Yamato which lost everything, Silla defeated even the Tang and achieved the integration of Korea, so that Yamato had a sense of crisis while it learned about advanced political systems and culture from the Silla.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>こうした危機感から生まれたナショナリズムが、日本書紀編纂の際に形となって表れたと指摘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nationalism caused by such a sense of crisis appeared visibly at the time of compilation of Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>堀敏一は日本書紀が朝鮮諸国の「朝貢」を記しているが、中華意識では到来するものすべてが朝貢だと指摘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshikazu HORI has pointed out that there is a description on &apos;paying tribute to the court&apos; by Korean countries in Nihonshoki, but all people coming from other countries were considered to be paying tribute to the court in Chinese consciousness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshikazu HORI has pointed out that there is a description on &apos;paying tribute to the court&apos; by Korean countries in Nihonshoki, but all people coming from other countries were considered to be paying tribute to the court in Chinese consciousness.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshikazu HORI has pointed out that there is a description on &apos;paying tribute to the court&apos; by Korean countries in Nihonshoki, but all people coming from other countries were considered to be paying tribute to the court in Chinese consciousness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>書名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Title</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Title</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Title</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>もとの名称が『日本紀』だったとする説と、初めから『日本書紀』だったとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that original name was &quot;Nihongi&quot; and another that it had been &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; from the first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that the original name was &quot;Nihongi&quot; and another that it had been &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; from the start.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that the original name was &quot;Nihongi&quot; and another that it had been &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; from the start.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>『日本紀』とする説は、『続日本紀』の上記養老四年五月癸酉条記事に、「書」の文字がなく日本紀と書かれていることを重視する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of &quot;Nihongi&quot; emphases that there is no letter of &apos;sho&apos; (書) in the above description on Mizunoto-Tori (kiyu), June 720 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; but letters of Nihongi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of &quot;Nihongi&quot; emphases that there is no character of &apos;sho&apos; (書) in the above description on Mizunoto-Tori (kiyu), June 720 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; but characters for Nihongi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of &quot;Nihongi&quot; emphases that there is no character of &apos;sho&apos; (書) in the above description on Mizunoto-Tori (kiyu), June 720 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; but characters for Nihongi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>中国では紀伝体の史書を「書」（『漢書』『後漢書』など）と呼び、帝王の治世を編年体にしたものを「紀」（『漢紀』『後漢紀』）と呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, history books written in Kidentai (biographical historiography) were called &apos;sho&apos; (such as &quot;Kanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Han Dynasty), &quot;Gokanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Later Han Dynasty)), while other history books in which the reign of emperor was recorded in chronological order were called &apos;ki&apos; (紀) (such as &quot;Records of the Han Dynasty&quot; and &quot;Records of Later Han&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, history books written in Kidentai (biographical historiography) were called &apos;sho&apos; (such as &quot;Kanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Han Dynasty), &quot;Gokanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Later Han Dynasty)), while other history books in which the reign of the emperor was recorded in chronological order were called &apos;ki&apos; (紀) (such as &quot;Records of the Han Dynasty&quot; and &quot;Records of Later Han&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, history books written in Kidentai (biographical historiography) were called &apos;sho&apos; (such as &quot;Kanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Han Dynasty), &quot;Gokanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Later Han Dynasty)), while other history books in which the reign of the emperor was recorded in chronological order were called &apos;ki&apos; (紀) (such as &quot;Records of the Han Dynasty&quot; and &quot;Records of Later Han&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>この用法に倣ったとすれば、『日本書紀』は「紀」にあたるものなので、『日本紀』と名づけられたと推測できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If following this usage, it can be guessed that &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was named &quot;Nihongi&quot; because it belonged to &apos;ki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If following this usage, it can be guessed that &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was named &quot;Nihongi&quot; because it belonged to &apos;ki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If following this usage, it can be guessed that &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was named &quot;Nihongi&quot; because it belonged to &apos;ki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>『日本書紀』に続いて編纂された『続日本紀』『日本後紀』『続日本後紀』がいずれも書名に「書」の文字を持たないこともこの説を支持していると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the fact that any of &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; &quot;Nihonkoki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan) and &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued) does not have a letter of &apos;sho&apos; in the title, supports this theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the fact that any of &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; &quot;Nihonkoki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan), and &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued) does not have the character for &apos;sho&apos; in the title, supports this theory.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the fact that any of &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; &quot;Nihonkoki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan), and &quot;Shoku Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan Continued) does not have the character for &apos;sho&apos; in the title, supports this theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>この場合、「書」の字は後世に挿入されたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, a letter of &apos;sho&apos; can be regarded as being added in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the character for &apos;sho&apos; can be regarded as being added in later years.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, the character for &apos;sho&apos; can be regarded as being added in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>『日本書紀』とする説は、古写本と奈良時代・平安時代初期のように成立時期に近い時代の史料がみな『日本書紀』と記していることを重視する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; emphases that the term of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was used in old manuscripts and all historical sources around this time of establishment, that is, the Nara period and the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; emphases that the term of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was used in old manuscripts and all historical sources around this time of establishment, that is, the Nara period and the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; emphases that the term of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was used in old manuscripts and all historical sources around this time of establishment, that is, the Nara period and the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>例えば、『弘仁私記』序、『釈日本紀』引用の「延喜講記」などには『日本書紀』との記述が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the term of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; appears in some documents such as the preface of &quot;Koninshiki&quot; and &apos;Engikoki&apos; (延喜講記) which was cited from &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (annotated text of the Nihon Shoki).</e>
<cmt>「延喜講記」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the term of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; appears in some documents such as the preface of &quot;Koninshiki&quot; and &apos;Engikoki&apos; (延喜講記) which was cited from &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (annotated text of the Nihon Shoki).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the term of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; appears in some documents such as the preface of &quot;Koninshiki&quot; and &apos;Engikoki&apos; (延喜講記) which was cited from &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (annotated text of the Nihon Shoki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>初出例は『令集解』所引の「古記」とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first appearance is regarded to be in &apos;Koki&apos; (Ancient records) of &quot;Ryonoshuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first appearance is regarded to be in &apos;Koki&apos; (Ancient records) of &quot;Ryonoshuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first appearance is regarded to be in &apos;Koki&apos; (Ancient records) of &quot;Ryonoshuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>「古記」は天平10年（738年）の成立とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koki&apos; is regarded to be established in 738.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koki&apos; is regarded to be established in 738.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koki&apos; is regarded to be established in 738.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>『書紀』が参考にした中国史書は、『漢書』『後漢書』のように全体を「書」としその一部に「紀」を持つ体裁をとる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese history books such as &quot;Kanjo&quot; and &quot;Gokanjo&quot; which &quot;Shoki&quot; referred to were usually called &apos;sho&apos; as a whole including &apos;ki&apos; in some parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese history books such as &quot;Kanjo&quot; and &quot;Gokanjo&quot; which &quot;Shoki&quot; referred to were usually called &apos;sho&apos; as a whole including &apos;ki&apos; in some parts.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese history books such as &quot;Kanjo&quot; and &quot;Gokanjo&quot; which &quot;Shoki&quot; referred to were usually called &apos;sho&apos; as a whole including &apos;ki&apos; in some parts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>そこでこの説の論者は、現存する『書紀』は、中国の史書にあてはめると『日本書』の「紀」にあたるものとして、『日本書紀』と名づけられたと推測する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, supporters of this theory guess that the existing &quot;Shoki&quot; was named &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; because it corresponded to the &apos;ki&apos; of &quot;Nihon-sho, &quot;following the naming of Chinese history book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, supporters of this theory guess that the existing &quot;Shoki&quot; was named &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; because it corresponded to the &apos;ki&apos; of &quot;Nihon-sho,&quot; following the naming of Chinese history book.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, supporters of this theory guess that the existing &quot;Shoki&quot; was named &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; because it corresponded to the &apos;ki&apos; of &quot;Nihon-sho,&quot; following the naming of Chinese history book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="99">
<j>なお、一部には、『日本紀』と『日本書紀』とは別の書であると考える研究者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, some researchers think that &quot;Nihongi&quot; is a different book from &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, some researchers think that &quot;Nihongi&quot; is a different book from &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, some researchers think that &quot;Nihongi&quot; is a different book from &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>『万葉集』には双方の書名が併用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) both titles were used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) both titles were used.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) both titles were used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>原資料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Source materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Source materials</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Source materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>日本書紀の資料は記事内容の典拠となった史料と修辞の典拠となった漢籍類（三国志、漢書、後漢書、淮南子等）に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The materials of Nihonshoki are classified into historical materials which became the authority of contents and Chinese classic books (Sangokushi (Three Kingdom Saga), Kanjo, Gokanjo, Huainanzi (The Masters/Philosophers of Huainan) and so on) which became the authority of rhetoric.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The materials of Nihonshoki are classified into historical materials which became the authority of contents and Chinese classic books (Sangokushi (Three Kingdom Saga), Kanjo, Gokanjo, Huainanzi (The Masters/Philosophers of Huainan) and so on) which became the authority on rhetoric.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The materials of Nihonshoki are classified into historical materials which became the authority of contents and Chinese classic books (Sangokushi (Three Kingdom Saga), Kanjo, Gokanjo, Huainanzi (The Masters/Philosophers of Huainan) and so on) which became the authority on rhetoric.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>さらに史料には以下のようなものが含まれると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is thought that historical materials include following.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is thought that historical materials include the following.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is thought that historical materials include the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>帝紀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teiki (records of Emperor&apos;s family tree)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teiki (records of Emperor&apos;s family tree)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teiki (records of Emperor&apos;s family tree)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>旧辞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyuji (mythical tradition)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyuji (mythical tradition)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyuji (mythical tradition)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>諸氏に伝えられた先祖の記録（墓記）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The records of ancestors which were transmitted by various clans (epitaph)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The records of ancestors which were transmitted by various clans (epitaph)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The records of ancestors which were transmitted by various clans (epitaph)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>地方に伝えられた物語（風土記）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stories which were transmitted in local regions (fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stories which were transmitted in local regions (fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.))</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stories which were transmitted in local regions (fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>政府の記録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Records of government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Government records</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Government records</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>個人の手記（『伊吉連博徳書』、『難波吉士男人書』、『高麗沙門道顯日本世記』、（釈日本紀に挙げられている『安斗宿禰智徳日記』、『調連淡海日記』））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Individual notes (&quot;Iki no Muraji Hakatoko no Fumi&quot; (The Book of Iki no Muraji Hakatoko), &quot;Naniwa no Kishi Ohito no Fumi (The Book of Naniwa no Kishi Ohito) (難波吉士男人書) and &quot;Korai Samon Doken Nippon Seiki&quot; (高麗沙門道顯日本世記), (&quot;The Diary of Ato no Sukune no Chitoko&quot; and &quot;The Diary of Tsuki no Muraji Omi&quot; which appear in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot;))</e>
<cmt>「難波吉士男人書、高麗沙門道顯日本世記」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Individual notes (&quot;Iki no Muraji Hakatoko no Fumi&quot; (The Book of Iki no Muraji Hakatoko), &quot;Naniwa no Kishi Ohito no Fumi (The Book of Naniwa no Kishi Ohito) (難波吉士男人書), and &quot;Korai Samon Doken Nippon Seiki&quot; (高麗沙門道顯日本世記), (&quot;The Diary of Ato no Sukune no Chitoko&quot; and &quot;The Diary of Tsuki no Muraji Omi&quot; which appear in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot;))</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Individual notes (&quot;Iki no Muraji Hakatoko no Fumi&quot; (The Book of Iki no Muraji Hakatoko), &quot;Naniwa no Kishi Ohito no Fumi (The Book of Naniwa no Kishi Ohito) (難波吉士男人書), and &quot;Korai Samon Doken Nippon Seiki&quot; (高麗沙門道顯日本世記), (&quot;The Diary of Ato no Sukune no Chitoko&quot; and &quot;The Diary of Tsuki no Muraji Omi&quot; which appear in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot;))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>寺院の縁起</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engi (writing about the history) of temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engi (writing about the history) of temples</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engi (writing about the history) of temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>海外（特に百済）の記録（『百済記』、『百済新撰』、『百済本記』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overseas (especially in Baekje) records (&quot;Records of Baekje,&quot; &quot;The New Selection of Baekje&quot; (百済新撰) and &quot;Original records of Baekje&quot;)</e>
<cmt>「百済新撰」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overseas (especially in Baekje) records (&quot;Records of Baekje,&quot; &quot;The New Selection of Baekje&quot; (百済新撰), and &quot;Original records of Baekje&quot;)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overseas (especially in Baekje) records (&quot;Records of Baekje,&quot; &quot;The New Selection of Baekje&quot; (百済新撰), and &quot;Original records of Baekje&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>なお、『日本書紀』によれば、推古天皇28年（620年）に聖徳太子や蘇我馬子によって編纂されたとされる『天皇記』・『国記』の方がより旧い史書であるが、皇極天皇4年（645年）の乙巳の変とともに焼失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; &quot;Tennoki&quot; (a Record of the Emperors) and &quot;Kokki&quot; which were regarded to be compiled by Prince Shotoku and SOGA no Umako in 620 were older history books, but they were burnt down at the Isshi no hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) in 645.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; &quot;Tennoki&quot; (a Record of the Emperors), and &quot;Kokki&quot; which were regarded to be compiled by Prince Shotoku and SOGA no Umako in 620 were older history books, but they were burnt at the Isshi no hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) in 645.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; &quot;Tennoki&quot; (a Record of the Emperors), and &quot;Kokki&quot; which were regarded to be compiled by Prince Shotoku and SOGA no Umako in 620 were older history books, but they were burnt at the Isshi no hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) in 645.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>『日本書紀』は本文に添えられた注の形で多くの異伝、異説を書き留めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; records many heresies in the form of notes which added to the main text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; records many heresies in the form of notes which added to the main text.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; records many heresies in the form of notes which added to the main text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>「一書に曰く」の記述は異伝、異説を記した現存しない書が『日本書紀』の編纂に利用されたことを示すと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the descriptions of &apos;a book says&apos; show that the defunct books written heresies were used for the compilation of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the descriptions of &apos;a book says&apos; show that the defunct books written heresies were used for the compilation of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the descriptions of &apos;a book says&apos; show that the defunct books written heresies were used for the compilation of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="115">
<j>なお、『日本書紀』では既存の書物から記事を引用する場合「一書曰」、「一書云」、「一本云」、「別本云」、「旧本云」、「或本云」などと書名を明らかにしないことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, although some articles of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; were cited from other books, their titles were not usually cleared and only phrases such as &apos;a book says,&apos; &apos;another book says&apos; or &apos;an old book says&apos; were written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, although some articles of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; were cited from other books, their titles were not usually clear and only phrases such as &apos;a book says,&apos; &apos;another book says&apos; or &apos;an old book says&apos; were written.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, although some articles of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; were cited from other books, their titles were not usually clear and only phrases such as &apos;a book says,&apos; &apos;another book says&apos; or &apos;an old book says&apos; were written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>但し一部には書名を明らかにしているものがあり、書名をあげて引用されている文献として次のようなものがあるが、いずれも現存しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the titles of some books were clearly written and some articles were cited from those books as follows, but any of which does not exist now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the titles of some books were clearly written and some articles were cited from those books as follows, but none of which exist now.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the titles of some books were clearly written and some articles were cited from those books as follows, but none of which exist now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="117">
<j>『日本旧記』（雄略天皇21年（477年）3月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Old Records of Japan&quot; (May 477)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Old Records of Japan&quot; (May 477)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Old Records of Japan&quot; (May 477)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="118">
<j>『高麗沙門道顯日本世記』（斉明天皇6年（660年）5月、斉明天皇7年（661年）4月、11月、天智天皇9年（669年）10月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Korai Samon Doken Nippon Seiki&quot; (June 660, May and November 661 and November 669)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Korai Samon Doken Nippon Seiki&quot; (June 660, May and November 661 and November 669)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Korai Samon Doken Nippon Seiki&quot; (June 660, May and November 661 and November 669)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="119">
<j>『伊吉連博徳』（斉明天皇5年（659年）7月、斉明天皇7年（661年）5月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Iki no Muraji Hakatoko&quot; (July 659 and June 661)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Iki no Muraji Hakatoko&quot; (July 659 and June 661)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Iki no Muraji Hakatoko&quot; (July 659 and June 661)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="120">
<j>『難波吉士男人書』（斉明天皇5年（659年）7月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Naniwa no Kishi Ohito no Fumi&quot; (July 659)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Naniwa no Kishi Ohito no Fumi&quot; (July 659)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Naniwa no Kishi Ohito no Fumi&quot; (July 659)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="121">
<j>『百済記』（神功皇后摂政47年（247年）4月、神功皇后摂政62年（250年）2月、応神天皇8年（277年）3月、応神天皇25年（294年）、雄略天皇20年（476年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Records of Baekje&quot; (May 247, March 250, April 277, in 294 and 476)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Records of Baekje&quot; (May 247, March 250, April 277, in 294 and 476)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Records of Baekje&quot; (May 247, March 250, April 277, in 294 and 476)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="122">
<j>『百済新撰』（雄略天皇2年（458年）7月、雄略天皇5年（461年）7月、武烈天皇4年（502年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The New Selection of Baekje&quot; (July 458, July 461 and in 502)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The New Selection of Baekje&quot; (July 458, July 461 and in 502)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The New Selection of Baekje&quot; (July 458, July 461 and in 502)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="123">
<j>『百済本記』（継体天皇3年（509年）2月、継体天皇7年（513年）6月、継体天皇9年（515年）2月、継体天皇25年（531年）12月、欽明天皇5年（544年）3月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Original records of Baekje&quot; (March 509, July 513, March 515, December 531 and April 544)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Original records of Baekje&quot; (March 509, July 513, March 515, December 531 and April 544)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Original records of Baekje&quot; (March 509, July 513, March 515, December 531 and April 544)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="124">
<j>『譜第』（顕宗天皇即位前紀）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fudai&quot; (hereditary) (a record before the enthronement of the Emperor Kenzo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fudai&quot; (hereditary) (a record before the enthronement of the Emperor Kenzo)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fudai&quot; (hereditary) (a record before the enthronement of the Emperor Kenzo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="125">
<j>『晋起居注』（神功皇后摂政66年（267年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Kikochu&quot; (in 267)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin Kikochu&quot; (in 267)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Kikochu&quot; (in 267)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>編纂方針</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Policy of compilation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Policy of compilation</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Policy of compilation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="126">
<j>『日本書紀』の編纂は国家の大事業であり、皇室や各氏族の歴史上での位置づけを行うという、極めて政治的な色彩の濃厚なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilation of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was a big national project and also a very political project to characterize imperial family and various clans in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compilation of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was a big national project and also a very political project to characterize the imperial family and various clans in history.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compilation of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was a big national project and also a very political project to characterize the Imperial Family and various clans in history.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>編集方針の決定や原史料の選択は、政治的に有力者が主導したものと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is guessed that the decision of editorial policy and selection of original historical materials were politically led by an influential person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is guessed that the decision of editorial policy and selection of original historical materials were politically led by an influential person.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is guessed that the decision of editorial policy and selection of original historical materials were politically led by an influential person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>文体・用語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style and terms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style and terms</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style and terms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="128">
<j>『日本書紀』の文体・用語など文章上の様々な特徴を分類して研究・調査がされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various researches which classify various characteristics such as styles and terms of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various researches which classify various characteristics such as styles and terms of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various researches which classify various characteristics such as styles and terms of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>その結果によると、全三十巻のうち巻一・二の神代紀と巻二十八・二十九・三十の天武天皇・持統天皇紀の実録的な部分を除いた後の二十五巻は、大別して二つに分けられるといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to those researches, the 25 volumes, that is, the rest of total 30 volumes from which Jindaiki (Records of period of gods) in the first and second volume and the authentic records of the section of Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito in the 28th, 29th and 30th volumes are excluded, are roughly classified into the two categories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to those researches, the 25 volumes, that is, the rest of the total 30 volumes from which Jindaiki (Records of the period of the gods) in the first and second volume and the authentic records of the section of Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito in the 28th, 29th and 30th volumes are excluded, are roughly classified into the two categories.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to those researches, the 25 volumes, that is, the rest of the total 30 volumes from which Jindaiki (Records of the period of the gods) in the first and second volume and the authentic records of the section of Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito in the 28th, 29th and 30th volumes are excluded, are roughly classified into the two categories.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>その一は、巻三の神武天皇紀から巻十三の允恭天皇・安康天皇紀までである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first is from the section of Emperor Jinmu in the third volume to the section of Emperor Ingyo and Emperor Anko in the 13th volume.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first is from the section of Emperor Jinmu in the third volume to the section of Emperor Ingyo and Emperor Anko in the 13th volume.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first is from the section of Emperor Jinmu in the third volume to the section of Emperor Ingyo and Emperor Anko in the 13th volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>その二は、巻十四の雄略天皇紀から巻二十一の用明天皇・崇峻天皇紀まである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second is from the section of Emperor Yuryaku in the 14th volume to the section of Emperor Yomei and Emperor Sushun in the 21st volume.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second is from the section of Emperor Yuryaku in the 14th volume to the section of Emperor Yomei and Emperor Sushun in the 21st volume.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second is from the section of Emperor Yuryaku in the 14th volume to the section of Emperor Yomei and Emperor Sushun in the 21st volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>残る巻二十二・二十三の推古天皇・舒明天皇紀はその一に、巻二十四の皇極天皇紀から巻二十七の天智天皇紀まではその二に付加されるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is regarded that the sections of Empress Suiko and Emperor Jomei in the rest 22nd and 23rd volumes are added to the first, and the sections from the Emperor Kogyoku in the 24th volume to the Emperor Tenchi in the 27th volume are added to the second.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is regarded that the sections of Empress Suiko and Emperor Jomei in the remaining 22nd and 23rd volumes are added to the first, and the sections from Emperor Kogyoku in the 24th volume to Emperor Tenchi in the 27th volume are added to the second.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is regarded that the sections of Empress Suiko and Emperor Jomei in the remaining 22nd and 23rd volumes are added to the first, and the sections from Emperor Kogyoku in the 24th volume to Emperor Tenchi in the 27th volume are added to the second.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>巻十三と巻十四の間、つまり雄略天皇紀の前後に古代史の画期があったと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is guessed that there was a border of ancient history between the 13th volume and the 14th volume, that is, before and after the section of Emperor Yuryku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is guessed that there was a border of ancient history between the 13th volume and the 14th volume, that is, before and after the section of Emperor Yuryku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is guessed that there was a border of ancient history between the 13th volume and the 14th volume, that is, before and after the section of Emperor Yuryaku.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="134">
<j>ところで『日本書紀』は純漢文体であると思われてきたが、最近の研究から語彙や語法に倭習が多くみられることが分かってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; has been thought to be written in genuine Chinese writing style, but recent researches show that there are many grammatical deviations affected by Japanese in vocabulary and usage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; has been thought to be written in genuine Chinese writing style, but recent researches show that there are many grammatical deviations affected by Japanese in vocabulary and usage.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; has been thought to be written in genuine Chinese writing style, but recent researches show that there are many grammatical deviations affected by Japanese in vocabulary and usage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>とくに大化の改新について書かれた巻二十四、巻二十五に倭習が多数ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the 24th and 25th volumes which describe on the Taika Reforms there are many grammatical deviations affected by Japanese.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the 24th and 25th volumes which describe the Taika Reforms there are many grammatical deviations affected by Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the 24th and 25th volumes which describe the Taika Reforms there are many grammatical deviations affected by Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>蘇我氏を逆臣として誅滅を図ったクーデターに関しては、元明天皇（天智天皇の子）、藤原不比等（藤原鎌足の子）の意向を受けて「加筆」されたのではないかと考える学者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some scholars think that the description on the coup which aimed to kill the Soga clan as treacherous retainer was &apos;added,&apos; following the intentions of the Emperor Genmei (a child of the Emperor Tenchi) and FUJIWARA no Fuhito (a child of FUJIWARA no Kamatari).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some scholars think that the description of the coup which aimed to kill the Soga clan as treacherous retainers was &apos;added,&apos; following the intentions of Emperor Genmei (a child of the Emperor Tenchi) and FUJIWARA no Fuhito (a child of FUJIWARA no Kamatari).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some scholars think that the description of the coup which aimed to kill the Soga clan as treacherous retainers was &apos;added,&apos; following the intentions of Emperor Genmei (a child of the Emperor Tenchi) and FUJIWARA no Fuhito (a child of FUJIWARA no Kamatari).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="137">
<j>『日本書紀』は、欽明13年10月（）に百済の聖明王、釈迦仏像と経論を献ずる、としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; there is a description that Shomyoo of Baekje presented the statue of Buddha and sutras on November 552.</e>
<cmt>「欽明13年10月（）」の()内には西暦が入ると判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; there is a description that Shomyoo of Baekje presented a statue of Buddha and sutras on November 552.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; there is a description that Shomyoo of Baekje presented a statue of Buddha and sutras on November 552.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>しかし『上宮聖徳法王帝説』や『元興寺縁起』は、欽明天皇の戊午年10月12日 (旧暦)（同年が欽明天皇治世下にないため（宣化3年）と推定されている）に仏教公伝されることを伝えており、こちらが通説になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; (Biography of Shotoku Taishi) and &quot;The Origin of Gango-ji Temple,&quot; official introduction of Buddhism was on October 12 in the Bogo year (in old lunar calendar, and it is guessed to be in 537 because it was not under the reign of the Emperor Kinmei), which is commonly believed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; (Biography of Shotoku Taishi) and &quot;The Origin of Gango-ji Temple,&quot; official introduction of Buddhism was on October 12 in the Bogo year (in the old lunar calendar, and it is guessed to be in 537 because it was not under the reign of the Emperor Kinmei), which is commonly believed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; (Biography of Shotoku Taishi) and &quot;The Origin of Gango-ji Temple,&quot; official introduction of Buddhism was on October 12 in the Bogo year (in the old lunar calendar, and it is guessed to be in 537 because it was not under the reign of the Emperor Kinmei), which is commonly believed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>このように『日本書紀』には、改変したと推測される箇所があることが、いまや研究者の間では常識となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, it is commonly known among researchers that some parts of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; can be guessed to be altered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, it is commonly known among researchers that some parts of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; can be guessed to be altered.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, it is commonly known among researchers that some parts of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; can be guessed to be altered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>紀年・暦年の構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The framework of calendars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The framework of calendars</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The framework of calendars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>暦日に関する研究は、天文学者の小川清彦 (天文学者)により戦前に既に完成していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The research on calendar was already completed by Kiyohiko OGAWA (an astronomer) before the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The research on calendars was already completed by Kiyohiko OGAWA (an astronomer) before the war.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The research on calendars was already completed by Kiyohiko OGAWA (an astronomer) before the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>が、当時の状況はその研究の公表を許さず、戦後ようやく発表されたのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the situation at that time did not allow him to release it, so that it was finally disclosed after the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the situation at that time did not allow him to release it, so that it was finally disclosed after the war.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the situation at that time did not allow him to release it, so that it was finally disclosed after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>『日本書紀』は、完全な編年体史書で、神代紀を除いたすべての記事は、年・月・日（干支）の様式で記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; is a history book written in a complete chronological order and all articles except Jindaiki are described in the style of year, month and date (shown by the Oriental zodiac).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; is a history book written in a complete chronological order and all articles except Jindaiki are described in the style of year, month and date (shown by the Oriental zodiac).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; is a history book written in a complete chronological order and all articles except Jindaiki are described in the style of year, month and date (shown by the Oriental zodiac).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>記事のある月は、その月の一日の干支を書き、それに基づいてその記事が月の何日に当たるかを計算できるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first day of a month based on the Oriental zodiac is written in an article, which makes it possible to calculate the date of the article based on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first day of a month based on the Oriental zodiac is written in an article, which makes it possible to calculate the date of the article based on it.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first day of a month based on the Oriental zodiac is written in an article, which makes it possible to calculate the date of the article based on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>たとえば憲法十七条の制定は「推古十二年夏四月丙寅朔戊辰（へいいんさくぼしん）」であるが、これは四月一日の干支が丙寅であって、戊辰は三日であることを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the establishment of the Seventeen Article Constitution was on &apos;heiin saku (first day of the month) boshin, April 604,&apos; which showed that the Oriental zodiac of April 1 was heiin and that boshin was the third.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the establishment of the Seventeen Article Constitution was on &apos;heiin saku (first day of the month) boshin, April 604,&apos; which showed that the Oriental zodiac of April 1 was heiin and that boshin was the third.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the establishment of the Seventeen Article Constitution was on &apos;heiin saku (first day of the month) boshin, April 604,&apos; which showed that the Oriental zodiac of April 1 was heiin and that boshin was the third.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>また、小川の研究は、中国の元嘉暦と儀鳳暦の二つが用いられていることを明らかにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the research of Ogawa cleared that the two kinds of calendars of Genka reki (Genka calendar) and Giho reki (Giho calendar) of China were used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the research of Ogawa made clear that the two kinds of calendars of Genka reki (Genka calendar) and Giho reki (Giho calendar) of China were used.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the research of Ogawa made clear that the two kinds of calendars of Genka reki (Genka calendar) and Giho reki (Giho calendar) of China were used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>神武即位前紀の甲寅（こういん）年十一月丙戌（へいじゅつ）朔から仁徳八十七年十月癸未（きび）朔までが儀鳳暦、安康天皇紀三年八月甲申（こうしん）朔から天智紀六年閏十一月丁亥（ていがい）朔までが元嘉暦と一致するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to that research, the articles from heijutsu saku, November of koin year to kibi saku, October 399 were based on Giho reki, and those from koshin saku, September 456 to teigai saku, December 667 were based on Genka reki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to that research, the articles from heijutsu saku, November of koin year to kibi saku, October 399 were based on Giho reki, and those from koshin saku, September 456 to teigai saku, December 667 were based on Genka reki.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to that research, the articles from heijutsu saku, November of koin year to kibi saku, October 399 were based on Giho reki, and those from koshin saku, September 456 to teigai saku, December 667 were based on Genka reki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>元嘉暦が古く、暦が新しいにもかかわらず、『日本書紀』は、新しい暦を古い時代に、古い暦を新しい時代に採用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Genka reki was older than Giho reki, new calendar was adopted for older age and old calendar was adopted for new age in &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「暦が新しいにもかかわらず」の「暦」は文脈から「儀鳳暦」を指すと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Genka reki was older than Giho reki, the new calendar was adopted for the older age and old calendar was adopted for the new age in &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Genka reki was older than Giho reki, the new calendar was adopted for the older age and old calendar was adopted for the new age in &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>既述のように二組で撰述したと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, it is guessed that Nihonshoki was compiled by two groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, it is guessed that Nihonshoki was compiled by two groups.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, it is guessed that Nihonshoki was compiled by two groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="149">
<j>元嘉暦とは、中国・南朝の宋の何承天（かしょうてん）がつくった暦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genka reki was established by He Chengtian in Sung of the Southern Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genka reki was established by He Chengtian in Sung of the Southern Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genka reki was established by He Chengtian in Sung of the Southern Dynasty in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>元嘉二十二年（445年）から施行され、百済にも日本にもかなり早く伝来したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was implemented since 445 and it is said to be transmitted to Baekje and Japan at a very early stage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was implemented since 445 and it is said to be transmitted to Baekje and Japan at a very early stage.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was implemented since 445 and it is said to be transmitted to Baekje and Japan at a very early stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>儀鳳暦とは、唐の李淳風（りじゅんほう）がつくって高宗の麟徳（りんとく）二年（天智天皇4年665年）から用いられはじめた麟徳暦のことを指すと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that Giho reki refers to Linde Calendar which was devised by Ri junho in Tang and began to be used since 665.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Giho reki refers to the Linde Calendar which was devised by Ri junho in the Tang and began to be used since 665.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Giho reki refers to the Linde Calendar which was devised by Ri junho in the Tang and began to be used since 665.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>讖緯（しんい）の説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinisetsu (a theory on the method for prophecy or a book describing it)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinisetsu (a theory on the method for prophecy or a book describing it)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinisetsu (a theory on the method for prophecy or a book describing it)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="152">
<j>神武天皇の即位を紀元前660年に当たる辛酉（かのととり、しんゆう）の年を起点として紀年を立てている理由は、中国から伝えられた讖緯説を採用したためという学説が、明治に那珂通世（なかみちよ）によりうちたてられ、学界で広く受け入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Michiyo NAKA established a theory that the enthronement of Emperor Jinmu was defined in the kanototori year which corresponded to 660 B.C. because shinisetsu was introduced from China and adopted in Japan, which has been accepted in academic world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, Michiyo NAKA established a theory that the enthronement of Emperor Jinmu was defined in the kanototori year which corresponded to 660 B.C. because shinisetsu was introduced from China and adopted in Japan, which has been accepted in academic world.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Michiyo NAKA established a theory that the enthronement of Emperor Jinmu was defined in the kanototori year which corresponded to 660 B.C. because shinisetsu was introduced from China and adopted in Japan, which has been accepted in academic world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>三善清行による「革命勘文」（『群書類従』　第貮拾六輯 雜部　所収）で引用された『易緯』での鄭玄の注「天道不遠 三五而反 六甲爲一元 四六二六交相乗 七元有三變　三七相乗 廿一元爲一蔀 合千三百廿年」から一元60年、二十一元1260年を一蔀とし、そのはじめの辛酉の年に王朝交代という革命が起こるとするいわゆる緯書での辛酉革命の思想によるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was based on the idea of Shinyu kakumei (a prediction of revolution in Kanototori of the Chinese astrological calendar) in isho (Chinese books which describe predictions and others), that is, a revolution to change dynasty would occur in the first Kanototori year considering 60 years as one cycle (元) and 1260 years of 21 cycles as one period (蔀), in accordance with the note of Zheng Xuan, &apos;天道不遠 三五而反 六甲爲一元 四六二六交相乗 七元有三變 三七相乗 廿一元爲一蔀 合千三百廿年,&apos; in &quot;Yi wei&quot; which was cited in &apos;kakumeikanmon&apos; (in zatubu (overall section) in the 26th section of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA)) by Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>元、蔀、「天道不遠 三五而反 六甲爲一元 四六二六交相乗 七元有三變　三七相乗 廿一元爲一蔀 合千三百廿年」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was based on the idea of Shinyu kakumei (a prediction of revolution in Kanototori of the Chinese astrological calendar) in isho (Chinese books which describe predictions and others), that is, a revolution to change the dynasty would occur in the first Kanototori year considering 60 years as one cycle (元) and 1260 years of 21 cycles as one period (蔀), in accordance with the note from Zheng Xuan, &apos;天道不遠 三五而反 六甲爲一元 四六二六交相乗 七元有三變 三七相乗 廿一元爲一蔀 合千三百廿年,&apos; in &quot;Yi wei&quot; which was cited in &apos;kakumeikanmon&apos; (in zatubu (overall section) in the 26th section of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA)) by Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was based on the idea of Shinyu kakumei (a prediction of revolution in Kanototori of the Chinese astrological calendar) in isho (Chinese books which describe predictions and others), that is, a revolution to change the dynasty would occur in the first Kanototori year considering 60 years as one cycle (元) and 1260 years of 21 cycles as one period (蔀), in accordance with the note from Zheng Xuan, &apos;天道不遠 三五而反 六甲爲一元 四六二六交相乗 七元有三變 三七相乗 廿一元爲一蔀 合千三百廿年,&apos; in &quot;Yi wei&quot; which was cited in &apos;kakumeikanmon&apos; (in zatsubu (overall section) in the 26th section of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA)) by Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>この思想で考えると斑鳩の地に都を置いた推古天皇9年（601年）の辛酉の年より二十一元遡った辛酉の年を第一蔀のはじめの年とし、日本の紀元を第一の革命と想定して、神武の即位をこの年に当てたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this idea, the Kanototori year, which was the first year of the former 21 cycles from the Kanototori year of 601 when a capital was placed at Ikaruga, was defined as the first year of the first period and the year of the enthronement of Emperor Jinmu on the assumption that the beginning of Japan was the first revolution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this idea, the Kanototori year, which was the first year of the former 21 cycles from the Kanototori year of 601 when a capital was placed at Ikaruga, was defined as the first year of the first period and the year of the enthronement of Emperor Jinmu on the assumption that the beginning of Japan was the first revolution.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this idea, the Kanototori year, which was the first year of the former 21 cycles from the Kanototori year of 601 when a capital was placed at Ikaruga, was defined as the first year of the first period and the year of the enthronement of Emperor Jinmu on the assumption that the beginning of Japan was the first revolution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>異説では、那珂通世の計算には誤認があり、一蔀は「革命勘文」の引用のとおり1320年が正しく従って逆算起点は斉明天皇7年（661年）の辛酉の年になるともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a heresy, the calculation of Michiyo NAKA is wrong and one period is correctly 1320 years as cited in &apos;kakumeikanmon,&apos; so that the first year of back calculation corresponds to the Kanototori year of 661.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to another view, the calculation of Michiyo NAKA is wrong and one period is correctly 1320 years as cited in &apos;kakumeikanmon,&apos; so that the first year of back calculation corresponds to the Kanototori year of 661.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to another view, the calculation of Michiyo NAKA is wrong and one period is correctly 1320 years as cited in &apos;kakumeikanmon,&apos; so that the first year of back calculation corresponds to the Kanototori year of 661.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>紀年論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinenron (a way of counting years)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinenron (a way of counting years)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinenron (a way of counting years)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="156">
<j>古い時代の天皇の寿命が異常に長い事から、『日本書紀』の年次は古くから疑問視されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the length of life of emperors in ancient times was extremely long, the dates of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; has been questioned since old days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the length of life of emperors in ancient times was extremely long, the dates of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; has been questioned since old days.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the length of life of emperors in ancient times was extremely long, the dates of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; has been questioned since old days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>今日の学説では、初代神武天皇の即位年を辛酉（紀元前660年）とすることによって、年代を古くに引き上げたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to today&apos;s theory, it is considered that the dates were altered into older dates by defining the year of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s enthronement as Kanototori (660 B.C.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to today&apos;s theory, it is considered that the dates were altered into older dates by defining the year of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s enthronement as Kanototori (660 B.C.).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to today&apos;s theory, it is considered that the dates were altered into older dates by defining the year of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s enthronement as Kanototori (660 B.C.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>そこでこの紀年がどのように構成されているか、明らかにしようとする試みが紀年論である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Kinenron aims to clear this way of counting years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Kinenron aims to clear this way of counting years.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Kinenron aims to clear this way of counting years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>また応神紀には『三国史記』と対応する記述があり、干支2順、120年繰り下げると、『三国史記』と年次が一致する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is a description which corresponds to &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) in the section of Emperor Ojin, and the dates would correspond to &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; if they go back to two cycles of the Oriental zodiac, that is, 120 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is a description which corresponds to &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) in the section of Emperor Ojin, and the dates would correspond to &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; if they go back to two cycles of the Oriental zodiac, that is, 120 years.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is a description which corresponds to &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) in the section of Emperor Ojin, and the dates would correspond to &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; if they go back to two cycles of the Oriental zodiac, that is, 120 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>したがってこのあたりで、年次は120年古くに設定されているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the dates were defined 120 years earlier around this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that the dates were defined 120 years earlier around this period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the dates were defined 120 years earlier around this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>しかしこれも、あくまで『三国史記』の原型となった朝鮮史書を参考にした記事だけに該当するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this calculation only corresponds to the articles which referred to Korean history books from which &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; originated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this calculation only corresponds to the articles which referred to Korean history books from which &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; originated.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this calculation only corresponds to the articles which referred to Korean history books from which &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; originated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>前後の日本伝承による記事には当然適用されるわけではないし、その前の神功紀で引用される『三国志 (歴史書)』の年次との整合性もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course this does not correspond to the articles based on Japanese traditions around it, and it is inconsistent with the date of &quot;Sanguo Zhi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) which is cited in the former section of Emperor Jingu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course this does not correspond to the articles based on Japanese traditions around it, and it is inconsistent with the date of &quot;Sanguo Zhi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) which is cited in the former section of Emperor Jingu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course this does not correspond to the articles based on Japanese traditions around it, and it is inconsistent with the date of &quot;Sanguo Zhi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) which is cited in the former section of Emperor Jingu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="163">
<j>一方、『古事記』は年次を持たないが、文注の形で一部の天皇について崩御年干支が記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;Kojiki&quot; does not record date, but the Oriental zodiac of the year of death of some emperors are described in the form of notes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, &quot;Kojiki&quot; does not record a date, but the Oriental zodiac of the year of death of some emperors are described in the form of notes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;Kojiki&quot; does not record a date, but the Oriental zodiac of the year of death of some emperors are described in the form of notes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>『日本書紀』の天皇崩御年干支と、古い時代は一致しないが、以下は一致する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That Oriental zodiac in old days do not correspond to that of the year of emperors&apos; death in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; except following emperors.</e>
<cmt>セル２３６を結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oriental zodiacs in the past do not correspond to the year of the emperors&apos; deaths in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; except the following emperors.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oriental zodiacs in the past do not correspond to the year of the emperors&apos; deaths in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; except the following emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="165">
<j>第27代 安閑天皇（乙卯、安閑天皇4年（535年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 27th Emperor Ankan (Kinotou in 535)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 27th Emperor Ankan (Kinotou in 535)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 27th Emperor Ankan (Kinoto in 535)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="166">
<j>第31代 用明天皇（丁未、用明天皇2年（587年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 31st Emperor Yomei (Hinotohitsuji in 587)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 31st Emperor Yomei (Hinotohitsuji in 587)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 31st Emperor Yomei (Hinotohitsuji in 587)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="167">
<j>第32代 崇峻天皇（壬子、崇俊天皇5年（592年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 32nd Emperor Sushun (Mizunoene in 592)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 32nd Emperor Sushun (Mizunoene in 592)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 32nd Emperor Sushun (Mizunoene in 592)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="168">
<j>第33代 推古天皇（戊子、推古天皇36年（628年））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 33rd Empress Suiko (Tsuchinoene in 628)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 33rd Empress Suiko (Tsuchinoene in 628)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 33rd Empress Suiko (Tsuchinoene in 628)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>このあたりの年次は実年代を反映しているとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be also thought that the date around this period reflected the real date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can also be thought that the date around this period reflected the real date.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can also be thought that the date around this period reflected the real date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>また『古事記』の天皇崩御年干支を基に、『日本書紀』の年次を探ろうとする考えもあるが、前述の理由により多くの学者の支持を得られていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is another idea to define the dates in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; based on the Oriental zodiac of the year of emperors&apos; death in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; but it is not supported by many scholars for above reasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is another idea to define the dates in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; based on the Oriental zodiac of the year of emperors&apos; deaths in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; but it is not supported by many scholars for the above reasons.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is another idea to define the dates in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; based on the Oriental zodiac of the year of emperors&apos; deaths in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; but it is not supported by many scholars for the above reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>本文と一書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main text and heresies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main text and heresies</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main text and heresies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="171">
<j>本文の後に注の形で「一書に曰く」として多くの異伝を書き留めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many heresies in the form of notes after the main text such as &apos;a books says.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many heresies in the form of notes after the main text such as &apos;a books says.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many heresies in the form of notes after the main text such as &apos;a books says.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>中国では、清の時代になるまで本文中に異説を併記した歴史書はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China there had been no history book in which heresies were described in the main text until in the Ching period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China there had been no history book in which heresies were described in the main text until in the Ching period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China there had been no history book in which heresies were described in the main text until in the Ching period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>当時の常識では、世界にも類をみない画期的な歴史書だったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said to have been a revolutionary history book in the world by common sense in those days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said to have been a revolutionary history book for the world by the common sense of that period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said to have been a revolutionary history book for the world by the common sense of that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>あるいは、それゆえに現存するものは作成年代が古事記などよりもずっと新しいものであるという論拠ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, this is the reason for the theory that the existing one was written much later than Kojiki and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or, this is the reason for the theory that the existing one was written much later than Kojiki and others.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or, this is the reason for the theory that the existing one was written much later than Kojiki and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="175">
<j>なお、日本書紀欽明天皇2年3月条には、分注において皇妃・皇子に付いて本文と異なる異伝を記した後、『帝王本紀』について「古字が多くてわかりにくいためにさまざまな異伝が存在するのでどれが正しいのか判別しがたい場合には一つを選んで記し、それ以外の異伝についても記せ」と命じられた事を記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in the notes of the section of April 541 in Nihonshoki, there is a description on the order &apos;to choose one tradition and write other heresies when there were too many heresies to judge true one and it is difficult to choose one because of too many old characters&apos; about &quot;Teio Honki&quot; (The Chronicle of Emperors) after the notes on heresies about empresses and princes.</e>
<cmt>「分注」は「文注」の誤記と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in the notes of the section of April 541 in Nihonshoki, there is a description on the order &apos;to choose one tradition and write other heresies when there were too many heresies to judge which ones were true and it is difficult to choose one because of too many old characters&apos; about &quot;Teio Honki&quot; (The Chronicle of Emperors) after the notes on heresies about empresses and princes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in the notes of the section of April 541 in Nihonshoki, there is a description on the order &apos;to choose one tradition and write other heresies when there were too many heresies to judge which ones were true and it is difficult to choose one because of too many old characters&apos; about &quot;Teio Honki&quot; (The Chronicle of Emperors) after the notes on heresies about empresses and princes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>この部分の記述がどの程度事実を反映しているのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known that to what extent these descriptions reflect the fact.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known to what extent these descriptions reflect fact.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known to what extent these descriptions reflect fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>が、正しいと判断した伝承を一つだけ選ぶのではなく本文と異なる異伝も併記するという編纂方針が現在見られる日本書紀全般の状況とよく合っていることはしばしば注目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it often gathers attention that such a policy of compilation as describing heresies rather than choosing one tradition which was judged to be right corresponds to the overall situation of Nihonshoki which can be seen today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it often gathers attention that such a policy of compilation as describing heresies rather than choosing one tradition which was judged to be right corresponds to the overall situation of Nihonshoki which can be seen today.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it often gathers attention that such a policy of compilation as describing heresies rather than choosing one tradition which was judged to be right corresponds to the overall situation of Nihonshoki which can be seen today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="178">
<j>系図1巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One volume of genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One volume of genealogy</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One volume of genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>続日本紀にある日本書紀の完成記事には「紀卅卷系圖一卷」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article about the establishment of Nihonshoki in Shoku Nihongi, there is a description that &apos;30 volumes of Ki and one volume of genealogy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article about the establishment of Nihonshoki in Shoku Nihongi, there is a description that says &apos;30 volumes of Ki and one volume of genealogy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article about the establishment of Nihonshoki in Shoku Nihongi, there is a description that says &apos;30 volumes of Ki and one volume of genealogy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>成立時の日本書紀には現在伝えられている30巻の他に系図1巻が存在したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that there was one volume of genealogy other than existing 30 volumes in Nihonshoki when it was established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that there was one volume of genealogy other than the existing 30 volumes in Nihonshoki when it was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that there was one volume of genealogy other than the existing 30 volumes in Nihonshoki when it was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>日本書紀の「紀卅卷」が現在までほぼ完全に伝わっているのに対して系図は全く伝わっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While &apos;30 volumes of Ki&apos; of Nihonshoki has been transmitted almost completely until today, the genealogy has not been left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the &apos;30 volumes of Ki&apos; of Nihonshoki has been transmitted almost completely until today, the genealogy has not been left.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the &apos;30 volumes of Ki&apos; of Nihonshoki has been transmitted almost completely until today, the genealogy has not been left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>弘仁私記にはこの系図について、「図書寮にも民間にも見えない」としてすでに失われたかのような記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Koninshiki (a lecture written by O no Hitonaga), there is a description on this genealogy that &apos;it can be seen neither in Zushoryo (the Bureau of Drawings and Books) nor private libraries,&apos; which shows that it had been already lost.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Koninshiki (a lecture written by O no Hitonaga), there is a description on this genealogy that &apos;it can be seen neither in Zushoryo (the Bureau of Drawings and Books) nor private libraries,&apos; which shows that it had been already lost.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Koninshiki (a lecture written by O no Hitonaga), there is a description on this genealogy that &apos;it can be seen neither in Zushoryo (the Bureau of Drawings and Books) nor private libraries,&apos; which shows that it had been already lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>が、鎌倉時代に存在する書物を集めた記録では「舎人親王撰　帝王系図一巻」とあり、このころまでは存在したとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among the records which gathered books existing in the Kamakura period, there is a record that &apos;Selected by Imperial Prince Toneri, one volume of imperial genealogy,&apos; so that it can be thought that it had existed until this time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among the records which gathered books existing in the Kamakura period, there is a record that &apos;Selected by Imperial Prince Toneri, one volume of imperial genealogy,&apos; so that it can be thought that it had existed until this time.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, among the records which gathered books existing in the Kamakura period, there is a record that &apos;Selected by Imperial Prince Toneri, one volume of imperial genealogy,&apos; so that it can be thought that it had existed until this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>「新撰姓氏禄」には、ところどころ「日本紀合」という記述があるが、これは失われた系図部分と照合したものであると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;Shinsen Shojiroku&apos; (New Selection and Record of Hereditary Titles and Family Names) there are some descriptions of &apos;日本紀合&apos; (Nihongi go) which is thought to be the part verified by the lost part of genealogy.</e>
<cmt>「日本紀合」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;Shinsen Shojiroku&apos; (New Selection and Record of Hereditary Titles and Family Names) there are some descriptions of &apos;日本紀合&apos; (Nihongi go) which is thought to be the part verified by the lost part of the genealogy.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;Shinsen Shojiroku&apos; (New Selection and Record of Hereditary Titles and Family Names) there are some descriptions of &apos;日本紀合&apos; (Nihongi go) which is thought to be the part verified by the lost part of the genealogy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>この「系図一巻」がどのような内容を持っていたのかについては様々に推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various assumptions about what contents this &apos;one volume of genealogy&apos; included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various assumptions about what contents this &apos;one volume of genealogy&apos; included.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various assumptions about what contents this &apos;one volume of genealogy&apos; included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>例えば日本書紀には初出の人物についてはその系譜を期すのが通例であるにも関わらずこれらの無い人物が若干存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, although a genealogy is usually written for a person who appeared for the first time in Nihonshoki, there are some people who had no genealogies.</e>
<cmt>「期す」は「記す」の誤記と判断しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, although a genealogy is usually written for a person who appeared for the first time in Nihonshoki, there are some people who had no genealogies.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, although a genealogy is usually written for a person who appeared for the first time in Nihonshoki, there are some people who had no genealogies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>これらについては系図に記載があるために記載を譲ったためであると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that they are omitted because they are explained in the genealogy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that they are omitted because they are explained in the genealogy.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that they are omitted because they are explained in the genealogy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>また、記紀ともに現存の本文には見えない応神天皇から継体天皇に至る系譜についてもこの失われた「系図1巻」には書かれていたのではないかとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in another theory, the genealogy from the Emperor Ojin to the Emperor Keitai which is not seen in the existing texts of kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki) is regarded to have been written in this lost &apos;one volume of genealogy.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in another theory, the genealogy from the Emperor Ojin to the Emperor Keitai which is not seen in the existing texts of kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki) is regarded to have been written in this lost &apos;one volume of genealogy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in another theory, the genealogy from the Emperor Ojin to the Emperor Keitai which is not seen in the existing texts of the Kojiki and Nihonshoki is regarded to have been written in this lost &apos;one volume of genealogy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="189">
<j>太歳（大歳）記事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The articles on tai sui (an imaginary star directly opposite to Jupiter)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The articles on tai sui (an imaginary star directly opposite to Jupiter)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The articles on tai sui (an imaginary star directly opposite to Jupiter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>日本書紀には各天皇の即位の年の末尾に「この年大歳（大歳）」としてその年の干支を記した記事があり、「大歳（大歳）記事」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nihonshoki there are some articles in which the Oriental zodiac of the year is written at the end of the year of enthronement of each emperor, and those are called &apos;the articles on tai sui.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nihonshoki there are some articles in which the Oriental zodiac of the year is written at the end of the year of enthronement of each emperor, and those are called &apos;the articles on tai sui.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nihonshoki there are some articles in which the Oriental zodiac of the year is written at the end of the year of enthronement of each emperor, and those are called &apos;the articles on tai sui.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>日本書紀が参考にした中国の史書にも「続日本紀」などのこれ以後の日本の史書にもこのような記事は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such articles can be seen neither Chinese history books which Nihonshoki referred to nor later Japanese history books such as &apos;Shoku Nihongi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such articles can be seen in neither Chinese history books which Nihonshoki referred to nor later Japanese history books such as &apos;Shoku Nihongi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such articles can be seen in neither Chinese history books which Nihonshoki referred to nor later Japanese history books such as &apos;Shoku Nihongi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>この記事がどのような意味合いを持つものなのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not clear what meanings these articles have.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clear what meanings these articles have.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clear what meanings these articles have.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>ほとんどの天皇については即位元年の末尾にこの大歳記事があるが、以下のようにいくつか例外が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article of tai sui exists in the end of the first year of enthronement for almost all emperors, but there are some exceptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article of tai sui exists in the end of the first year of enthronement for almost all emperors, but there are some exceptions.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This article of tai sui exists in the end of the first year of enthronement for almost all emperors, but there are some exceptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>このような例外が存在する理由についてはさまざまな推測がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various speculations on the reason for these exceptions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various speculations on the reason for these exceptions.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various speculations on the reason for these exceptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>中には皇統譜が書き換えられた痕跡ではないかとする見解もあるが、広い賛同は得ていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that this might be a trace that Kotofu (the genealogy of the Imperial Family) was revised, which is not widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say that this might be a trace that Kotofu (the genealogy of the Imperial Family) was revised, which is not widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that this might be a trace that Kotofu (the genealogy of the Imperial Family) was revised, which is not widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="196">
<j>神武天皇については東征を始めた年にあり、即位元年にはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the Emperor Jinmu, it is not written in the year of his enthronement but the year when he began Eastern expedition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the Emperor Jinmu, it is not written in the year of his enthronement but the year when he began his Eastern expedition.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the Emperor Jinmu, it is not written in the year of his enthronement but the year when he began his Eastern expedition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="197">
<j>綏靖天皇については即位前紀の神武天皇崩御の年と自身の即位元年にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the Emperor Suizei, it is described both in the year of the Emperor Jinmu&apos;s death before enthronement (即位前紀) and the first year of his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>「即位前紀」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the Emperor Suizei, it is described both in the year of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s death before enthronement (即位前紀) and the first year of his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the Emperor Suizei, it is described both in the year of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s death before enthronement (即位前紀) and the first year of his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="198">
<j>神功皇后については摂政元年、摂政十三年、摂政六九年にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the Empress Jingu, it is described in the first, 13th and 69th year of Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the Empress Jingu, it is described in the first, 13th and 69th year of Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the Empress Jingu, it is described in the first, 13th and 69th year of Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="199">
<j>継体天皇については元年と二五年にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the Emperor Keitai, it is described in the first and the 25th year of his enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the Emperor Keitai, it is described in the first and the 25th year of his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the Emperor Keitai, it is described in the first and the 25th year of his enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="200">
<j>天武天皇については元年にはなく二年にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the Emperor Tenmu, it is described in the second year of his enthronement instead of the first year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the Emperor Tenmu, it is described in the second year of his enthronement instead of the first year.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the Emperor Tenmu, it is described in the second year of his enthronement instead of the first year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>諱と諡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imina (personal name) and okurina (a posthumous name)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imina (personal name) and okurina (a posthumous name)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imina (personal name) and okurina (a posthumous name)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="201">
<j>天皇の名には、天皇在世中の名である諱（いみな）と、没後に奉られる諡（おくりな）とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An emperor has imina, the name during the reign, and okurina which is given after the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An emperor has imina, the name during the reign, and okurina which is given after the death.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An emperor has imina, the name during the reign, and okurina which is given after the death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>現在普通に使用されるのは『続日本紀』に記述される奈良時代、天平宝字6年（762年）～同8年（764年）、淡海三船による神武天皇から持統天皇までの41代、及び元明天皇・元正天皇へ一括撰進された漢風諡号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese-style posthumous names which are commonly used today are those of the 41 emperors from Emperor Jinmu to Empress Jito and Emperor Genmei and Gensho dedicated by OMI no Mifune in a lump from 762 to 764 during the Nara period which are described in &quot;Shoku Nihongi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese-style posthumous names which are commonly used today are those of the 41 emperors from Emperor Jinmu to Empress Jito and Emperor Genmei and Gensho dedicated by OMI no Mifune in a lump from 762 to 764 during the Nara period which are described in &quot;Shoku Nihongi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese-style posthumous names which are commonly used today are those of the 41 emperors from Emperor Jinmu to Empress Jito and Emperor Genmei and Gensho dedicated by OMI no Mifune in a lump from 762 to 764 during the Nara period which are described in &quot;Shoku Nihongi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>が、『日本書紀』の本来の原文には当然漢風諡号はなく、天皇の名は諱または和風諡号によってあらわされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, naturally there is no Chinese-style posthumous name in the original text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and emperors&apos; names are written by imina or Japanese-style posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, naturally there is no Chinese-style posthumous name in the original text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and emperors&apos; names are written by imina or Japanese-style posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, naturally there is no Chinese-style posthumous name in the original text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and emperors&apos; names are written by imina or Japanese-style posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>15代応神天皇から26代継体天皇までの名は、おおむね諱、つまり在世中の名であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names from the 15th Emperor Ojin to the 26th Emperor Keitai are considered to be imina, that is, the names during the reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names from the 15th Emperor Ojin to the 26th Emperor Keitai are considered to be imina, that is, the names during their reign.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names from the 15th Emperor Ojin to the 26th Emperor Keitai are considered to be imina, that is, the names during their reign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>その特徴は、ホムタ・ハツセなどの地名、ササギなどの動物名、シラカ・ミツハなどの人体に関する語、ワカ・タケなどの素朴な称、ワケ・スクネなどの古い尊称などを要素として単純な組み合わせから成っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are characteristically combined with various simple factors including place names such as Homuta and Hatsuse, animal names such as a wren, the words related to human body such as gray hair and Mitsuha, simple titles such as waka and take, and old honorific titles such as wake and sukune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are characteristically combined with various simple factors including place names such as Homuta and Hatsuse, animal names such as a wren, words related to the human body such as gray hair and Mitsuha, simple titles such as waka and take, and old honorific titles such as wake and sukune.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are characteristically combined with various simple factors including place names such as Homuta and Hatsuse, animal names such as a wren, words related to the human body such as gray hair and Mitsuha, simple titles such as waka and take, and old honorific titles such as wake and sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Constituent structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Constituent structure</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Constituent structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="206">
<j>卷第一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 1</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 1</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 1</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="207">
<j>神代上（かみのよのかみのまき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiyo no kami no maki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyo no kami no maki</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyo no kami no maki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="208">
<j>第一段、天地のはじめ及び神々の化成した話（天地開闢 (日本神話)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first section: the story about the beginning of the world and the birth of gods (creation of heaven and earth (Japanese Mythology))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first section: the story about the beginning of the world and the birth of the gods (creation of heaven and earth (Japanese Mythology))</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first section: The story about the beginning of the world and the birth of the gods (creation of heaven and earth (Japanese Mythology))</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="209">
<j>第二段、世界起源神話の続き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second section: the continuation of the mythology of the world&apos;s origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second section: the continuation of the mythology of the world&apos;s origin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second section: The continuation of the mythology of the world&apos;s origin</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="210">
<j>第三段、男女の神が八柱、神世七世（かみのよななよ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third section: eight pillars of male and female gods and seven generations of (celestial) gods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third section: eight pillars of male and female gods and seven generations of (celestial) gods</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third section: Eight pillars of male and female gods and seven generations of (celestial) gods</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="211">
<j>第四段、国産みの話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth section: the story of kuni-umi (the birth of (the land) of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth section: the story of kuni-umi (the birth of (the land) of Japan)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth section: The story of kuni-umi (the birth of (the land) of Japan)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="212">
<j>第五段、国産みに次いで山川草木・月日などを産む話（神産み）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifth section: the story of the birth of mountains, rivers, grasses, trees, month and date (kamiumi (bearing gods between Izanagi and Izanami)) after kuni-umi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth section: the story of the birth of mountains, rivers, grasses, trees, month and dates (kamiumi (bearing gods between Izanagi and Izanami)) after kuni-umi</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth section: The story of the birth of mountains, rivers, grasses, trees, month and dates (kamiumi (bearing gods between Izanagi and Izanami)) after kuni-umi</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="213">
<j>第六段、イザナギが崩御し、スサノオは根の国に行く前に天照大神に会いに行く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixth section: Izanagi died and Susanoo (Deity in Japanese Mythology) went to see Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) before going to Nenokuni (Land of the Roots).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixth section: Izanagi died and Susanoo (Deity in Japanese Mythology) went to see Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) before going to Nenokuni (Land of the Roots).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth section: Izanagi died and Susanoo (Deity in Japanese Mythology) went to see Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) before going to Nenokuni (Land of the Roots).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>アマテラスはスサノオとうけいし、互いに相手の持ち物から子を産む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amaterasu Omikami made a pledge with Susanoo and gave a birth from belongings of the other.</e>
<cmt>wikipediaを参考に「うけい」は「誓約」と置き換えて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amaterasu Omikami made a pledge with Susanoo and gave birth from the belongings of the other.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amaterasu Omikami made a pledge with Susanoo and gave birth from the belongings of the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>（アマテラスとスサノオの誓約）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(A pledge of Amaterasu and Susanoo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(A pledge of Amaterasu and Susanoo)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(A pledge of Amaterasu and Susanoo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="216">
<j>第七段、スサノオは乱暴をはたらき、アマテラスは天の岩戸に隠れてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seventh section: Susanoo committed an outrage and Amaterasu hid behind Ama no Iwato (The cave of the sun god).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventh section: Susanoo committed an outrage and Amaterasu hid behind Ama no Iwato (The cave of the sun god).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventh section: Susanoo committed an outrage and Amaterasu hid behind Ama no Iwato (The cave of the sun god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>神々がいろいろな工夫の末アマテラスを引き出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gods finally pull out Amaterasu after various trials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gods finally pull out Amaterasu after various trials.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gods finally pull out Amaterasu after various trials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>スサノオは罪を償った上で放たれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Susanoo was exiled after he expiated his guilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Susanoo was exiled after he expiated his guilt.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Susanoo was exiled after he expiated his guilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>（岩戸隠れ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Iwato-gakure (the hiding of Amaterasu Omikami, the sun goddess, in the heavenly rock cave))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Iwato-gakure (the hiding of Amaterasu Omikami, the sun goddess, in the heavenly rock cave))</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Iwato-gakure (the hiding of Amaterasu Omikami, the sun goddess, in the heavenly rock cave))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="220">
<j>第八段、スサノオが古代出雲に降り、アシナヅチ・テナヅチに会う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eighth section: Susanoo went down to the ancient Izumo region and met Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth section: Susanoo went down to the ancient Izumo region and met Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth section: Susanoo went down to the ancient Izumo region and met Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>スサノオがクシイナダヒメを救うため八岐大蛇を殺し、出てきた草薙剣（くさなぎのつるぎ）をアマテラスに献上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Susanoo killed Yamatanoorochi (eight-forked-snake) in order to escape kushiinadahime (Princess Kushinada), and presented Kusanagi no tsurugi (a sacred sword) to Amaterasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Susanoo killed Yamatanoorochi (eight-forked-snake) in order to escape kushiinadahime (Princess Kushinada), and presented Kusanagi no tsurugi (a sacred sword) to Amaterasu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Susanoo killed Yamatanoorochi (eight-forked-snake) in order to escape kushiinadahime (Princess Kushinada), and presented Kusanagi no tsurugi (a sacred sword) to Amaterasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>姫と結婚し、大国主を産み、スサノオは根の国に行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Susanoo got married with the princess, who gave a birth to Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region), and he went to Nenokuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Susanoo got married with the princess, who gave birth to Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region), and he went to Nenokuni.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Susanoo got married with the princess, who gave birth to Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region), and he went to Nenokuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="223">
<j>卷第二</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 2</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="224">
<j>神代下（かみのよのしものまき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiyo no Shimo no maki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyo no Shimo no maki</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyo no Shimo no maki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="225">
<j>第九段、葦原中国の平定、オオナムチ父子の国譲り、ニニギの降臨、サルタヒコの導き、ホオリらの誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 9th section: the subjugation of Ashihara no nakatsukuni (another word for the country or the location of Japan), Kuniyuzuri (transfer of the land) by Onamuchi and son, the descent to earth of Ninigi, the leading by Sarutahiko (an earthly deity) and the birth of Hoori and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 9th section: the subjugation of Ashihara no nakatsukuni (another word for the country or the location of Japan), Kuniyuzuri (transfer of the land) by Onamuchi and son, the descent to earth of Ninigi, the leading by Sarutahiko (an earthly deity) and the birth of Hoori and others.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 9th section: The subjugation of Ashihara no nakatsukuni (another word for the country or the location of Japan), Kuniyuzuri (transfer of the land) by Onamuchi and son, the descent to earth of Ninigi, the leading by Sarutahiko (an earthly deity) and the birth of Hoori and others.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>（葦原中国平定・天孫降臨）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The subjugation of Ashihara no nakatsukuni and tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The subjugation of Ashihara no nakatsukuni and tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess))</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The subjugation of Ashihara no nakatsukuni and tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="227">
<j>第十段、山幸彦と海幸彦の話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tenth section: the story of Yamasachihiko and Umisachihiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tenth section: the story of Yamasachihiko and Umisachihiko</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenth section: The story of Yamasachihiko and Umisachihiko</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="228">
<j>第十一段、神日本盤余彦尊（かむやまといはれびこのみこと）誕生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 11th section: the birth of Kamuyamato iharebiko no Mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 11th section: the birth of Kamuyamato iharebiko no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 11th section: The birth of Kamuyamato iharebiko no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="229">
<j>※卷第三より以降の漢風諡号は、『日本書紀』成立時にはなく、その後の人が付け加えたものと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*The Chinese-style posthumous names after volume 3 were not seen at the time of the establishment of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; so that they are guessed to be added by another person later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*The Chinese-style posthumous names after volume 3 were not seen at the time of the establishment of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; so that they are guessed to be added by another person later.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*The Chinese-style posthumous names after volume 3 were not seen at the time of the establishment of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; so that they are guessed to be added by another person later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="230">
<j>卷第三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 3</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 3</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 3</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="231">
<j>神日本磐余彦天皇（かむやまといはれびこのすめらみこと）神武天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamuyamato iharebiko no Mikoto, the Emperor Jinmu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamuyamato iharebiko no Mikoto, the Emperor Jinmu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamuyamato iharebiko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Jinmu</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="232">
<j>卷第四</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 4</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 4</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 4</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="233">
<j>神淳名川耳天皇（かむぬなかはみみのすめらみこと）綏靖天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamununakahamimi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Suizei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamununakahamimi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Suizei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamununakahamimi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Suizei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="234">
<j>磯城津彦玉手看天皇（しきつひこたまてみのすめらみこと）安寧天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikitsuhikotamatemi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Annei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikitsuhikotamatemi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Annei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikitsuhikotamatemi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Annei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="235">
<j>大日本彦紹友天皇（おほやまとひこすきとものすめらみこと）懿徳天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyamatohikosukitomo no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Itoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyamatohikosukitomo no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Itoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyamatohikosukitomo no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Itoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="236">
<j>観松彦香殖稲天皇（みまつひこすきとものすめらみこと）孝昭天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimatsuhikokaeshine no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kosho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimatsuhikokaeshine no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kosho</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimatsuhikosukitomo no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kosho</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="237">
<j>日本足彦国押人天皇（やまとたらしひこくにおしひとのすめらみこと）孝安天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatotarashihikokunioshihito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Koan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatotarashihikokunioshihito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Koan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatotarashihikokunioshihito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Koan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="238">
<j>大日本根子彦太瓊天皇（おほやまとねこひこふとにのすめらみこと）孝霊天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyamatonekohikofutoni no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Korei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyamatonekohikofutoni no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Korei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyamatonekohikofutoni no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Korei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="239">
<j>大日本根子彦国牽天皇（おほやまとねこひこくにくるのすめらみこと）孝元天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyamatonekohikokunikuru no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kogen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyamatonekohikokunikuru no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kogen</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyamatonekohikokunikuru no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kogen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="240">
<j>稚日本根子彦大日日天皇（わかやまとねこひこおほひひのすめらみこと）開化天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakayamatonekohikoobibi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kaika</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakayamatonekohikoobibi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kaika</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakayamatonekohikoobibi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kaika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="241">
<j>卷第五</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 5</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 5</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 5</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="242">
<j>御間城入彦五十塑殖天皇（みまきいりびこいにゑのすめらみこと）崇神天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimaki iribikoinie no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Sujin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimaki iribikoinie no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Sujin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimaki iribikoinie no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Sujin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="243">
<j>卷第六</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 6</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 6</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 6</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="244">
<j>活目入彦五十狭茅天皇（いくめいりびこいさちのすめらみこと）垂仁天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikumeiribikoisachi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Suinin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikumeiribikoisachi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Suinin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikumeiribikoisachi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Suinin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="245">
<j>卷第七</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 7</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 7</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 7</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="246">
<j>大足彦忍代別天皇（おほたらしひこおしろわけのすめらみこと）景行天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otarashihiko oshirowake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Keiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otarashihiko oshirowake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Keiko</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otarashihiko oshirowake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Keiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="247">
<j>稚足彦天皇（わかたらしひこのすめらみこと）成務天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakatarashihiko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Seimu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakatarashihiko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Seimu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakatarashihiko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Seimu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="248">
<j>卷第八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 8</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 8</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 8</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="249">
<j>足仲彦天皇（たらしなかつひこのすめらみこと）仲哀天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tarashinakatsuhiko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Chuai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tarashinakatsuhiko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Chuai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tarashinakatsuhiko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Chuai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="250">
<j>卷第九</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 9</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 9</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 9</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="251">
<j>気長足姫尊（おきながたらしひめのみこと）神功皇后</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okinagatarashihime no Mikoto, the Empress Jingu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okinagatarashihime no Mikoto, the Empress Jingu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okinagatarashihime no Mikoto, the Empress Jingu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="252">
<j>卷第十</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 10</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 10</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 10</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="253">
<j>誉田天皇（ほむだのすめらみこと）応神天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homuda no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ojin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homuda no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ojin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homuda no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ojin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="254">
<j>卷第十一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 11</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 11</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 11</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="255">
<j>大鷦鷯天皇（おほさざきのすめらみこと）仁徳天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osazaki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Nintoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osazaki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Nintoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osazaki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Nintoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="256">
<j>卷第十二</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 12</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 12</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 12</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="257">
<j>去来穂別天皇（いざほわけのすめらみこと）履中天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izahowake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Richu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izahowake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Richu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izahowake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Richu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="258">
<j>瑞歯別天皇（みつはわけのすめらみこと）反正天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuhawake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Hanzei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuhawake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Hanzei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuhawake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Hanzei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="259">
<j>卷第十三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 13</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 13</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 13</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="260">
<j>雄朝津間稚子宿禰天皇（をあさづまわくごのすくねのすめらみこと）允恭天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oasazumawakugo no sukune no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ingyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oasazumawakugo no sukune no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ingyo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oasazumawakugo no sukune no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ingyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="261">
<j>穴穂天皇（あなほのすめらみこと）安康天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anaho no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Anko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anaho no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Anko</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anaho no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Anko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="262">
<j>卷第十四</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 14</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 14</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 14</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="263">
<j>大泊瀬幼武天皇（おほはつせのわかたけるのすめらみこと）雄略天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohatsuse no wakatakeru no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Yuryaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohatsuse no wakatakeru no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Yuryaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohatsuse no wakatakeru no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Yuryaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="264">
<j>第第十五</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 15</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 15</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 15</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="265">
<j>白髪武広国押稚日本根子（しらかのたけひろくにおしわかやまとねこのすめらみこと）清寧天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiraka no takehirokunioshiwakayamatoneko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Seinei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiraka no takehirokunioshiwakayamatoneko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Seinei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiraka no takehirokunioshiwakayamatoneko no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Seinei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="266">
<j>弘計天皇（をけのすめらみこと）顕宗天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oke no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kenzo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oke no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kenzo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oke no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kenzo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="267">
<j>億計天皇（おけのすめらの天皇）仁賢天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oke no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ninken</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oke no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ninken</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oke no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ninken</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="268">
<j>卷第十六</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 16</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 16</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 16</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="269">
<j>小泊瀬稚鷦鷯天皇（おはつせのわかさざきのすめらみこと）武烈天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohatsuse no wakasazaki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Buretsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohatsuse no wakasazaki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Buretsu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohatsuse no wakasazaki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Buretsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="270">
<j>卷第十七</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 17</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 17</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 17</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="271">
<j>男大述天皇（おほどのすめらみこと）継体天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohodo no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Keitai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohodo no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Keitai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohodo no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Keitai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="272">
<j>卷第十八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 18</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 18</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 18</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="273">
<j>広国押武金日天皇（ひろくにおしたけかなひのすめらみこと）安閑天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirokunioshitakekanahi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ankan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirokunioshitakekanahi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ankan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirokunioshitakekanahi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Ankan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="274">
<j>武小広国押盾天皇（たけをひろくにおしたてのすめらみこと）宣化天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeohirokunioshitate no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Senka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeohirokunioshitate no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Senka</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeohirokunioshitate no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Senka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="275">
<j>卷第十九</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 19</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 19</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 19</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="276">
<j>天国排開広庭天皇（あめくにおしはらきひろにはのすめらみこと）欽明天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amekunioshiharakihironiha no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kinmei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amekunioshiharakihironiha no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kinmei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amekunioshiharakihironiha no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kinmei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="277">
<j>卷第二十</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 20</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 20</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 20</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="278">
<j>淳中倉太珠敷天皇（ぬなかくらのふとたましきのすめらのみこと）敏達天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nunakakuranofutomashiki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Bidatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nunakakuranofutomashiki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Bidatsu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nunakakuranofutotamashiki no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Bidatsu</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="279">
<j>卷第二十一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 21</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 21</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 21</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="280">
<j>橘豊日天皇（たちばなのとよひのすめらみこと）用明天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tachibana no toyohi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Yomei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tachibana no toyohi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Yomei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tachibana no toyohi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Yomei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="281">
<j>泊瀬部天皇（はつせべのすめらみこと）崇峻天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatsusebe no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Sushun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatsusebe no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Sushun</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatsusebe no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Sushun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="282">
<j>卷第二十二</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 22</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 22</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 22</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="70">
<sen id="283">
<j>豊御食炊屋姫天皇（とよみけかしきやひめのすめらみこと）推古天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyomikekashikiyahime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Suiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyomikekashikiyahime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Suiko</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyomikekashikiyahime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Suiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="71">
<sen id="284">
<j>卷第二十三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 23</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 23</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 23</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="72">
<sen id="285">
<j>長足日広額天皇（おきながたらしひひぬかのすめらみこと）舒明天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okinagatarashihihinuka no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Jomei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okinagatarashihihinuka no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Jomei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okinagatarashihihinuka no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Jomei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="73">
<sen id="286">
<j>卷第二十四</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 24</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 24</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 24</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="74">
<sen id="287">
<j>天豊財重日足姫天皇（あめとよたからいかしひたらしひめのすめらのみこと）皇極天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Kogyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Kogyoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Kogyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="75">
<sen id="288">
<j>卷第二十五</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 25</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 25</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 25</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="76">
<sen id="289">
<j>天万豊日天皇（あめよろづとよひのすめらみこと）孝徳天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ameyorozutoyohi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kotoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ameyorozutoyohi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kotoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ameyorozutoyohi no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Kotoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="77">
<sen id="290">
<j>卷第二十六</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 26</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 26</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 26</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="78">
<sen id="291">
<j>天豊財重日足姫天皇（あめとよたからいかしひたらしひめのすめらみこと）皇極天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Kogyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Kogyoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Kogyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="79">
<sen id="292">
<j>卷第二十七</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 27</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 27</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 27</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="80">
<sen id="293">
<j>天命開別天皇（あめみことひらかすわけのすめらみこと）天智天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amemikotohirakasuwake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor tenchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amemikotohirakasuwake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor tenchi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amemikotohirakasuwake no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Tenchi</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="81">
<sen id="294">
<j>卷第二十八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 28</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 28</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 28</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="82">
<sen id="295">
<j>天淳中原瀛真人天皇（あまのぬなはらおきのまひとのすめらみことのかみのまき）天武天皇 上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amanonunaharaoki no mahito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Tenmu, the first volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amanonunaharaoki no mahito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Tenmu, the first volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amanonunaharaoki no mahito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Tenmu, the first volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="83">
<sen id="296">
<j>卷第二十九</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 29</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 29</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 29</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="84">
<sen id="297">
<j>天淳中原瀛真人天皇（あまのぬなはらおきのまひとのすめらみことのしものまき）天武天皇 下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amanonunaharaoki no mahito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Tenmu, the second volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amanonunaharaoki no mahito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Tenmu, the second volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amanonunaharaoki no mahito no Sumeramikoto, the Emperor Tenmu, the second volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="85">
<sen id="298">
<j>卷第三十</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 30</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 30</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 30</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="86">
<sen id="299">
<j>高天原広野姫天皇（たかまのはらひろのひめのすめらみこと）持統天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamanoharahiro no hime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Jito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamanoharahiro no hime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Jito</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamanoharahiro no hime no Sumeramikoto, the Empress Jito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>現存本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing books</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing books</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing books</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="300">
<j>現存する最古のものは平安極初期のもの（田中本第10巻ならびにその僚巻に相当する巻1断簡）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing oldest book was written in the beginning of the Heian period (the tenth volume of Tanaka book (the TANAKA original copy) and dankan (fragmentary leaves of a book) of the one volume which corresponds to the same copy)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest existing book was written in the beginning of the Heian period (the tenth volume of the Tanaka book (the TANAKA original copy) and dankan (fragmentary leaves of a book) of the one volume which corresponds to the same copy).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest existing book was written in the beginning of the Heian period (the tenth volume of the Tanaka book (the TANAKA original copy) and dankan (fragmentary leaves of a book) of the one volume which corresponds to the same copy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="301">
<j>写本は古本系統と卜部家系統の本に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manuscripts are classified into the Old book group and the Urabe family group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manuscripts are classified into the Old book group and the Urabe family group.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manuscripts are classified into the Old book group and the Urabe family group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>（この他に「伊勢系」を分けて考える説もある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Addition to this, &apos;the Ise group&apos; can be separated in another theory)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In addition to this, &apos;the Ise group&apos; can be another group according to another theory)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In addition to this, &apos;the Ise group&apos; can be another group according to another theory)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="303">
<j>神代巻（巻第一・第二）の一書が小書双行になっているものが古本系統である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those in which Jindaikan (the volumes of divine age (Volume 1 and 2)) is written in the style of kogaki sogyo (small letters and double lines) are in the Old book group.</e>
<cmt>「一書」の解釈不明です。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those in which Jindaikan (the volumes of divine age (Volume 1 and 2)) is written in the style of kogaki sogyo (small letters and double lines) are in the Old book group.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those in which Jindaikan (the volumes of divine age (Volume 1 and 2)) is written in the style of kogaki sogyo (small letters and double lines) are in the Old book group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="304">
<j>大書一段下げになっているものが卜部家系統である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those written in the style of Taisho and one indentation are in the Urabe family group.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those written in the style of Taisho and one indentation are in the Urabe family group.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those written in the style of Taisho and one indentation are in the Urabe family group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>原本では古本系統諸本と同じく小書双行であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the original book was written in the style of kogaki sogyo as same as various books of the Old book group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the original book was written in the style of kogaki sogyo, same as various books of the Old book group.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the original book was written in the style of kogaki sogyo, same as various books of the Old book group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="306">
<j>以下に国宝や重要文化財に指定されているものをいくつかあげる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some books which are designated to a national treasure or an important cultural property are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some books which are designated as a national treasure or an important cultural property are as follows.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some books which are designated as a national treasure or an important cultural property are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="307">
<j>古本系統</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Old book group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Old book group</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Old book group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>佐佐木本 9世紀写 第1巻断簡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sasaki book (the Sasaki original copy) copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sasaki book (the Sasaki original copy) copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sasaki book (the Sasaki original copy) copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="308">
<j>四天王寺本・猪熊本・田中本の僚巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same copy of Shitenno-ji book (the original copy of Shitenno-ji Temple), Inokuma book (the Inokuma original copy) and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same copy of the Shitenno-ji book (the original copy of Shitenno-ji Temple), Inokuma book (the Inokuma original copy), and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same copy of the Shitenno-ji book (the original copy of Shitenno-ji Temple), Inokuma book (the Inokuma original copy), and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>紙背には空海の漢詩を集めた『遍照発揮性霊集（へんじょうほっきしょうりょうしゅう）』（真済編）が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other side of the paper, &quot;Henjo Hokki Shoryoshu&quot; (Kukai&apos;s Treatise on Poetry and Prose) (edited by Shinzei) is written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other side of the paper, &quot;Henjo Hokki Shoryoshu&quot; (Kukai&apos;s Treatise on Poetry and Prose) (edited by Shinzei) is written.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other side of the paper, &quot;Henjo Hokki Shoryoshu&quot; (Kukai&apos;s Treatise on Poetry and Prose) (edited by Shinzei) is written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>訓点なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="311">
<j>個人蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held as private collection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held in a private collection.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held in a private collection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>四天王寺本 9世紀写 第1巻断簡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original copy of Shitenno-ji Temple copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original copy of Shitenno-ji Temple copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original copy of Shitenno-ji Temple copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="312">
<j>- 佐佐木本・猪熊本・田中本の僚巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same copy of Sasaki book, Inokuma book and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same copy of the Sasaki book, Inokuma book, and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same copy of the Sasaki book, Inokuma book, and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>紙背文書については佐佐木本と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as the Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as the Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="314">
<j>訓点なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>四天王寺蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held at the Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held at the Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held at the Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>猪熊本 9世紀写 第1巻断簡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Inokuma book copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Inokuma book copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Inokuma book copied in the 9th century, the dankan of the first volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="316">
<j>- 佐佐木本・四天王寺本・田中本の僚巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same copy of Sasaki book, Shitenno-ji book and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same copy of the Sasaki book, Shitenno-ji book, and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same copy of the Sasaki book, Shitenno-ji book, and Tanaka book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="317">
<j>紙背文書については佐佐木本と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as the Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as the Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="318">
<j>訓点なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no kunten (guiding marks for rendering Chinese into Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="319">
<j>個人蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held as private collection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held in a private collection.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held in a private collection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>田中本 9世紀写 第10巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tanaka book copied in the 9th century, the tenth volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tanaka book copied in the 9th century, the tenth volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tanaka book copied in the 9th century, the tenth volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="320">
<j>- 佐佐木本・四天王寺本・猪熊本の僚巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same copy of Sasaki book, Shitenno-ji book and Inokuma book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same copy of the Sasaki book, Shitenno-ji book, and Inokuma book.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same copy of the Sasaki book, Shitenno-ji book, and Inokuma book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="321">
<j>紙背文書については佐佐木本と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as the Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the other side of the paper, it is the same as the Sasaki book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="322">
<j>訓点なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no kunten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="323">
<j>奈良国立博物館蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held at Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held at Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held at Nara National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>岩崎本 10～11世紀写 第22,24巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Iwasaki book (the Iwasaki original copy) copied in the 10-11th century, the 22 and 24 volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Iwasaki book (the Iwasaki original copy) copied in the 10-11th century, the 22nd and 24th volumes</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Iwasaki book (the Iwasaki original copy) copied in the 10 to 11th century, the 22nd and 24th volumes</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを to に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="324">
<j>- 訓点付きのものとしては最古。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the oldest among those with kunten</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the oldest among those with kunten.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the oldest among those with kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="325">
<j>本文の声点は六声体系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoten (marks to add Kanji to show Shisei) of the text is expressed in the six-tone style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoten (marks to add Kanji to show Shisei) of the text is expressed in the six-tone style.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten (marks to add Kanji to show Shisei) of the text is expressed in the six-tone style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="326">
<j>図書寮本と比較すると、本文・訓点ともに相違は大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to Zushoryo version, there are big differences both in the main text and kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to the Zushoryo version, there are big differences both in the main text and kunten.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to the Zushoryo version, there are big differences both in the main text and kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="327">
<j>京都国立博物館蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held at Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held at Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held at Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>前田本 11世紀写 第11,14,17,20巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maeda book (the Maeda original copy) copied in the 11th century, the 11, 14, 17, 20th volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maeda book (the Maeda original copy) copied in the 11th century, the 11th, 14th, 17th, and 20th volumes</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maeda book (the Maeda original copy) copied in the 11th century, the 11th, 14th, 17th, and 20th volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="328">
<j>- 訓点は図書寮本と同系統であるが、多少古態を存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunten is in the same style of Zushoryo version, but includes old version to some extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunten is in the same style as the Zushoryo version, but includes the old version to some extent.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunten is in the same style as the Zushoryo version, but includes the old version to some extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="329">
<j>声点は四声体系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="330">
<j>前田育徳会蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held by Maeda Ikutokukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held by Maeda Ikutokukai.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held by Maeda Ikutokukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>図書寮本（書陵部本） 12世紀写 第10,12-17,21-24巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zushoryo version (Book stock of Shoryo department) copied in the 12th century, the 10, 12-17, 21-24th volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zushoryo version (Book stock of Shoryo department) copied in the 12th century, the 10th, 12-17th, and 21-24th volumes</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zushoryo version (Book stock of Shoryo department) copied in the 12th century, the 10th, 12-17th, and 21-24th volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="331">
<j>- 訓点あり（第10巻を除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten (except volume 10).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten (except volume 10).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten (except volume 10).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="332">
<j>第14巻と第17巻は前田本と、第22～24巻は北野本と、それぞれ同系統。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 14th and 17th volumes are in the same style of Maeda book, and the 22nd and 24th volumes are in the same style of Kitano book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 14th and 17th volumes are in the same style as the Maeda book, and the 22nd and 24th volumes are in the same style as the Kitano book.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 14th and 17th volumes are in the same style as the Maeda book, and the 22nd and 24th volumes are in the same style as the Kitano book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="333">
<j>声点は四声体系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="334">
<j>宮内庁書陵部蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held by Book stock of Shoryo department, Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held in book stock by the Shoryo department, Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held in book stock by the Shoryo department, Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>北野本 第1類…第22-27巻（平安末期写）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kitano book: Group One includes the 22-27th volumes (copied in the end of the Heian period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kitano book: Group One includes the 22-27th volumes (copied in the end of the Heian period)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kitano book: Group One includes the 22 to 27th volumes (copied in the end of the Heian period)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを to に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="335">
<j>- 訓点あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="336">
<j>鎌倉末～南北朝期に神祇伯であった白川伯王家・資継王の所蔵本が、室町中期に吉田家系の卜部兼永の所有となったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was held by Suketsuguo (資継王) of the Shirakawahakuo family who had been Jingi haku (a chief official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism) from the end of the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts at first, and later held by Kanenaga URABE of the Yoshida family in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>資継王の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was held by Suketsuguo (資継王) of the Shirakawahakuo family who had been Jingi haku (a chief official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism) from the end of the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts at first, and later held by Kanenaga URABE of the Yoshida family in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was held by Suketsuguo (資継王) of the Shirakawahakuo family who had been Jingi haku (a chief official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism) from the end of the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts at first, and later held by Kanenaga URABE of the Yoshida family in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="337">
<j>北野天満宮蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held by Kitano Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held by Kitano Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held by Kitano Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>鴨脚本（嘉禎本） 1236年写 第2巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Icho book (the original copy of the Icho family) (the Katei book (the Katei original copy)) copied in 1236, the second volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Icho book (the original copy of the Icho family) (the Katei book (the Katei original copy)) copied in 1236, the second volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Icho book (the original copy of the Icho family) (the Katei book (the Katei original copy)) copied in 1236, the second volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="338">
<j>- 訓点あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="339">
<j>京都・賀茂御祖神社の社家・鴨脚（いちょう）氏旧蔵本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a collection of books once possessed by Icho family who was the shake (family of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) of the Kamomioya-jinja Shrine in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a collection of books once possessed by the Icho family who was the shake (family of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) of the Kamomioya-jinja Shrine in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a collection of books once possessed by the Icho family who was the shake (family of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) of the Kamomioya-jinja Shrine in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="340">
<j>本文・訓点とも大江家系か。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The text and kunten are guessed to be in the Oe family style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The text and kunten are guessed to be in the Oe family style.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The text and kunten are guessed to be in the Oe family style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="341">
<j>國學院大學蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held by the Kokugakuin University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held by the Kokugakuin University.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held by the Kokugakuin University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="342">
<j>卜部家本系統</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Urabe family group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Urabe family group</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Urabe family group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>卜部兼方本（弘安本） 1286年写 第1,2巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original copy of Kanekata URABE (the Koan book) copied in 1286, the first and second volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original copy of Kanekata URABE (the Koan book) copied in 1286, the first and second volumes</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original copy of Kanekata URABE (the Koan book) copied in 1286, the first and second volumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="343">
<j>- 訓点あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="344">
<j>平野家系の卜部兼方の書写。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was copied by Kanekata URABE who was the member of the Hirano family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was copied by Kanekata URABE who was a member of the Hirano family.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was copied by Kanekata URABE who was a member of the Hirano family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="345">
<j>大江氏点との比較を丹念に記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He patiently described on the comparison with ten (点) of the Oe family.</e>
<cmt>「点」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He patiently described the differences with ten (点) of the Oe family.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He patiently described the differences with ten (点) of the Oe family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="346">
<j>声点は四声体系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="347">
<j>京都国立博物館蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held at Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held at Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held at Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>卜部兼夏本（乾元本） 1303年写 第1,2巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original copy of Kanenatsu (兼夏) URABE (the Kengen book) copied in 1303, the first and second volumes</e>
<cmt>「兼夏」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original copy of Kanenatsu (兼夏) URABE (the Kengen book) copied in 1303, the first and second volumes</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original copy of Kanenatsu URABE (the Kengen book) copied in 1303, the first and second volumes</e>
<cmt>(兼夏)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="348">
<j>- 訓点あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="349">
<j>吉田家系の卜部兼夏の書写。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was copied by Kanekata URABE who was the member of the Yoshida family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was copied by Kanekata URABE who was a member of the Yoshida family.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was copied by Kanekata URABE who was a member of the Yoshida family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="350">
<j>『弘仁私記』（書紀古訓と書紀講筵にて後述）その他の私記を多数引用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He cited many private records such as &quot;Koninshiki&quot; (which is mentioned below in the section of the old interpretation and the lecture of Shoki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He cited many private records such as &quot;Koninshiki&quot; (which is mentioned below in the section of the old interpretation and the lecture of Shoki).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He cited many private records such as &quot;Koninshiki&quot; (which is mentioned below in the section of the old interpretation and the lecture of Shoki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="351">
<j>声点は四声体系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoten is expressed in the four-tone style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="352">
<j>天理大学附属天理図書館蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held at The Tenri library attached to the Tenri University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held at the Tenri library attached to Tenri University.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held at the Tenri library attached to Tenri University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>熱田本 1375～7年写 第1～10,12～15巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Atsuta&apos;s book (the original copy of Atsuta-jingu Shrine) copied from 1375 to 1377, the 1-10 and 12-15 volumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsuta&apos;s book (the original copy of the Atsuta-jingu Shrine) copied from 1375 to 1377, the 1-10th and 12-15th volumes</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsuta&apos;s book (the original copy of the Atsuta-jingu Shrine) copied from 1375 to 1377, the 1 to 10th and 12 to 15th volumes</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを to に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="353">
<j>- 訓点あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="354">
<j>熱田神宮蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held by the Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held by the Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held by the Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>図書寮本（書陵部本） 1346年写 第2巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zushoryo version (Book stock of Shoryo department) copied in 1346, the second volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zushoryo version (Book stock of Shoryo department) copied in 1346, the second volume</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zushoryo version (Book stock of Shoryo department) copied in 1346, the second volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="355">
<j>- 訓点あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="356">
<j>北畠親房旧蔵本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a collection of books once possessed by Chikafusa KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a collection of books once possessed by Chikafusa KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a collection of books once possessed by Chikafusa KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="357">
<j>宮内庁書陵部蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held by Book stock of Shoryo department, Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held in the book stock of the Shoryo department, Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held in the book stock of the Shoryo department, Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>北野本 第2類…第28-30巻（平安末～鎌倉初期写）、第3類…第1,4,5,7-10,12,13,15,17-21巻（南北朝写）、第4類…第3,6,11巻（室町後期写）、第5類…第16巻（幕末写）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kitano book: Group 2 includes the 28-30th volumes (copied in the end of the Heian period to the beginning of the Kamakura period), the Group 3 includes the 1, 4, 5, 7-10, 12, 13, 15, 17-21st volumes (copied in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts), the Group 4 includes the 3, 6, 11th volumes (copied in the latter part of the Muromachi period) and the Group 5 includes the 16th volumes (copied in the end of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kitano book: Group 2 includes the 28-30th volumes (copied in the end of the Heian period to the beginning of the Kamakura period), Group 3 includes the 1st, 4th, 5th, 7-10th, 12th, 13th, 15th, 17-21st volumes (copied in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts), Group 4 includes the 3rd, 6th, and 11th volumes (copied in the latter part of the Muromachi period) and Group 5 includes the 16th volumes (copied in the end of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kitano book: Group 2 includes the 28 to 30th volumes (copied in the end of the Heian period to the beginning of the Kamakura period), Group 3 includes the 1st, 4th, 5th, 7 to 10th, 12th, 13th, 15th, 17 to 21st volumes (copied in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts), Group 4 includes the 3rd, 6th, and 11th volumes (copied in the latter part of the Muromachi period) and Group 5 includes the 16th volumes (copied in the end of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを to に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="358">
<j>- 訓点あり（第1巻を除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are kunten (except the first volume).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are kunten (except the first volume).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are kunten (except the first volume).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="359">
<j>第2・3類は第1類同様白川伯王家・資継王の旧蔵本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Group 2 and 3 are collection of books once possessed by Suketsuguo of the Shirakawahakuo family as well as the Group 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Group 2 and 3 are a collection of books once possessed by Suketsuguo of the Shirakawahakuo family as well as Group 1.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Group 2 and 3 are a collection of books once possessed by Suketsuguo of the Shirakawahakuo family as well as Group 1.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="360">
<j>資継王が加点しているため、本文とは異なり訓点は伯家点系である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Suketsuguo added kunten, which is in the style of Hakke unlike the main text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suketsuguo added kunten, which is in the style of Hakke unlike the main text.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suketsuguo added kunten, which is in the style of Hakke unlike the main text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="361">
<j>北野天満宮蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held by Kitano Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held by Kitano Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held by Kitano Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="362">
<j>卜部兼右本 1540年写 第3～30巻 - 1525年に吉田家前当主の卜部兼満が家に火を放って出奔した際に卜部家伝来の本も焼失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original copy of Kanemigi URABE copied in 1540, the 3-30 volumes: when Kanemitsu URABE, the former head of the Yoshida family, set the house on fire and run away in 1525, hereditary books of the Urabe family were also burnt down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original copy that Kanemigi URABE copied in 1540, the 3-30th volumes: when Kanemitsu URABE, the former head of the Yoshida family, set the house on fire and ran away in 1525, hereditary books of the Urabe family were also burnt down.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original copy that Kanemigi URABE copied in 1540, the 3 to 30th volumes: when Kanemitsu URABE, the former head of the Yoshida family, set the house on fire and ran away in 1525, hereditary books of the Urabe family were also burnt down.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを to に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="363">
<j>このため、若くしてその後を継いだ兼右が、以前に卜部家本を書写していた三条西実隆の本を書写させてもらい、更に一条家の本（一条兼良写、卜部兼煕証）で校合して証本としたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Kanamigi, who succeeded it at a young age, copied the transcript which was copied by Sanetaka SANJONISHI from the original copy of the Urabe family before, and made shohon (a verified text) after collation with the original copy of the Ichijo family (copied by Kaneyoshi ICHIJO and checked by Kanehiro URABE).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Kanamigi, who succeeded it at a young age, copied the transcript which was copied by Sanetaka SANJONISHI from the original copy of the Urabe family before, and made shohon (a verified text) after collation with the original copy of the Ichijo family (copied by Kaneyoshi ICHIJO and checked by Kanehiro URABE).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Kanamigi, who succeeded it at a young age, copied the transcript which was copied by Sanetaka SANJONISHI from the original copy of the Urabe family before, and made shohon (a verified text) after collation with the original copy of the Ichijo family (copied by Kaneyoshi ICHIJO and checked by Kanehiro URABE).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="364">
<j>当初は全巻揃っていたが、神代巻2巻は再度失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, there were full volumes, but the two volumes of jindai (the age of the gods) were lost again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, there were full volumes, but the two volumes of jindai (the age of the gods) were lost again.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, there were full volumes, but the two volumes of jindai (the age of the gods) were lost again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="365">
<j>人代巻28巻を完備したものとしては最古に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the oldest copies which has full 28 volumes of jindai (the age of emperors) (人代).</e>
<cmt>「人代」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the oldest copies which has the full 28 volumes of jindai (the age of emperors) (人代).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the oldest copies which has the full 28 volumes of jindai (the age of emperors) (人代).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>書紀講筵と書紀古訓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecture on Shoki and the old interpretation of Shoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecture on Shoki and the old interpretation of Shoki</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecture on Shoki and the old interpretation of Shoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="366">
<j>『日本書紀』は歌謡部分を除き、原則として純粋漢文で記されているため、そのままでは日本人にとっては至極読みづらいものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was written in genuine Chinese writing style in principle except songs and ballads, it was very difficult for Japanese people to read.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was written in genuine a Chinese writing style in principle except songs and ballads, it was very difficult for Japanese people to read.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; was written in genuine a Chinese writing style in principle except songs and ballads, it was very difficult for Japanese people to read.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="367">
<j>そこで、完成の翌年である養老5年（721年）には早くも、『日本書紀』を自然な日本語で読むべく、宮中において時の博士が貴族たちの前で講義するという機会が公的に設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in 721, which was the following year of completion, there was an official opportunity for masters at the time to have a lecture in front of nobles at the Imperial Palace in order to read &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; by natural Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, in 721, which was the following year after completion, there was an official opportunity for masters at the time to have a lecture in front of nobles at the Imperial Palace in order to read &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; in natural Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in 721, which was the following year after completion, there was an official opportunity for masters at the time to have a lecture in front of nobles at the Imperial Palace in order to read &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; in natural Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="368">
<j>これを書紀講筵（こうえん）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called Shoki-koen (lecture of Shoki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called Shoki-koen (lecture of Shoki).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called Shoki-koen (lecture of Shoki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="369">
<j>開講から終講までに数年を要するほどの長期講座であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a long course which took several years from the beginning to the last lecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a long course which took several years from the beginning to the last lecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a long course which took several years from the beginning to the last lecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="370">
<j>承平年間に行なわれた講筵などは、天慶の動乱のために一時中断したとは言え、終講までに実に7年を要している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, a lecture in the Johei era took seven years, although it was interrupted because of the Tengyo War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, a lecture in the Johei era took seven years, although it was interrupted because of the Tengyo War.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, a lecture in the Johei era took seven years, although it was interrupted because of the Tengyo War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="371">
<j>代々の講筵の記録は聴講者の手によって開催された年次を冠する私記（年次私記）の形でまとめられるとともに、『日本書紀』の古写本の訓点（書紀古訓）として取り入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The records of successive lectures were collated in the form of private records which wrote the year of the lecture on the title by participants (annual private records) and were also used as kunten of old manuscript of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the old interpretation of Shoki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The records of successive lectures were collated in the form of private records which wrote the year of the lecture on the title by participants (annual private records) and were also used as kunten for old manuscripts of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the old interpretation of Shoki).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The records of successive lectures were collated in the form of private records which wrote the year of the lecture on the title by participants (annual private records) and were also used as kunten for old manuscripts of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the old interpretation of Shoki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="372">
<j>以下に過去の書紀講筵（年次は開講の時期）の概要を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The summary of the past Shoki-koen (each year shows the year of lecture) is as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The summary of the past Shoki-koen (each year shows the year of lecture) is as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The summary of the past Shoki-koen (each year shows the year of lecture) is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="373">
<j>養老五年（721年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 721</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 721</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 721</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="374">
<j>博士は太安万侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecturer was O no Yasumaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecturer was O no Yasumaro.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecturer was O no Yasumaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="375">
<j>私記は現存しないが、現存『弘仁私記』および一部の書紀古写本に「養老説」として引用の形で見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The private records do not exist now, but are cited as &apos;the Yoro theory&apos; in the existing &quot;Koninshiki&quot; and some old manuscripts of Shoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The private records do not exist now, but are cited as &apos;the Yoro theory&apos; in the existing &quot;Koninshiki&quot; and some old manuscripts of Shoki.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The private records do not exist now, but are cited as &apos;the Yoro theory&apos; in the existing &quot;Koninshiki&quot; and some old manuscripts of Shoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="376">
<j>弘仁四年（813年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 813</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 813</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 813</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="377">
<j>博士は多人長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecturer was O no Hitonaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecturer was O no Hitonaga.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecturer was O no Hitonaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="378">
<j>唯一、成書の形で私記が現存する（いわゆる私記甲本）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only this private record exists in the full form (what you call &quot;A&quot; version of private records).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only this private record exists in full form (what you call an &quot;A&quot; version of private records).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only this private record exists in full form (what you call an &quot;A&quot; version of private records).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="379">
<j>が、書紀古写本（乾元本神代紀）に「弘仁説」として引用されている『弘仁私記』（和訓が万葉仮名で表記され上代特殊仮名遣も正確）と比べると、現在の伝本（和訓の大半が片仮名表記）は書写の過程ではなはだしく劣化したものであり、原型をとどめていないと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, compared to &quot;Koninshiki&quot; (the Japanese reading of a Chinese character is written by Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves), and ancient special Kana usage is also accurate) which was cited as &apos;the Konin theory&apos; in an old manuscript of Shoki (Jindaiki (Records of period of gods) of the Kengen book), the existing denpon (existent books of transcription and published books) (most of the Japanese reading of a Chinese character are written by katakana (syllable based writing system of the Japanese language)) was greatly deteriorated during the process of transcript, so that it is regarded to be different from the original form.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, compared to &quot;Koninshiki&quot; (the Japanese reading of a Chinese character is written by Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves), and ancient special Kana usage is also accurate) which was cited as &apos;the Konin theory&apos; in an old manuscript of Shoki (Jindaiki (Records of period of gods) of the Kengen book), the existing denpon (existent books of transcription and published books) (most of the Japanese readings of Chinese characters are written in katakana (syllable based writing system of the Japanese language)) was greatly deteriorated during the process of transcript, so that it is regarded to be different from the original form.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, compared to &quot;Koninshiki&quot; (the Japanese reading of a Chinese character is written by Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves), and ancient special Kana usage is also accurate) which was cited as &apos;the Konin theory&apos; in an old manuscript of Shoki (Jindaiki (Records of period of gods) of the Kengen book), the existing denpon (existent books of transcription and published books) (most of the Japanese readings of Chinese characters are written in katakana (syllable based writing system of the Japanese language)) was greatly deteriorated during the process of transcript, so that it is regarded to be different from the original form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="380">
<j>承和六年（839年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 839</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 839</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 839</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="381">
<j>博士は菅野高平（滋野貞主とも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecturer was SUGANO no Takahira (菅野高平) (or SHIGENO no Sadanushi).</e>
<cmt>「菅野高平」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecturer was SUGANO no Takahira (菅野高平) (or SHIGENO no Sadanushi).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecturer was SUGANO no Takahira (or SHIGENO no Sadanushi).</e>
<cmt>(菅野高平)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="382">
<j>私記は現存しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The private record does not exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A private record does not exist.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A private record does not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="383">
<j>元慶二年（878年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 878</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 878</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 878</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="384">
<j>博士は善淵愛成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecturer was YOSHIBUCHI no Chikanari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecturer was YOSHIBUCHI no Chikanari.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecturer was YOSHIBUCHI no Chikanari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="385">
<j>私記は現存しないが、卜部兼方の『釈日本紀』に「私記」として引用されているのはこれではないかと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The private record does not exist, but it is said that &apos;the private record&apos; cited in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; of Kanekata URABE refers to this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The private record does not exist, but it is said that &apos;the private record&apos; cited in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; of Kanekata URABE refers to this.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The private record does not exist, but it is said that &apos;the private record&apos; cited in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; of Kanekata URABE refers to this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="386">
<j>私記作者は矢田部名実か。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the writer of the private record was YATABE no Nazane.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="387">
<j>延喜四年（904年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 904</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 904</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 904</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="388">
<j>博士は藤原春海。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecturer was FUJIWARA no Harumi (藤原春海).</e>
<cmt>「藤原春海」の定訳、読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecturer was FUJIWARA no Harumi (藤原春海).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecturer was FUJIWARA no Harumi.</e>
<cmt>(藤原春海)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="389">
<j>私記作者は矢田部公望。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The writer of the private record was YATABE no Kinmochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The writer of the private record was YATABE no Kinmochi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The writer of the private record was YATABE no Kinmochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="390">
<j>私記は現存しないが、『和名類聚抄』に「日本紀私記」として、また卜部兼方の『釈日本紀』に「公望私記」として、それぞれ引用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The private record does not exist, but it is cited as &apos;a private record of Nihongi&apos; in &quot;Wamyoruiju-sho&quot; (Kango-Japanese Dictionary) and as &apos;a private record of Kinmochi&apos; in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; of Kanekata URABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A private record does not exist, but it is cited as &apos;a private record of Nihongi&apos; in &quot;Wamyoruiju-sho&quot; (Kango-Japanese Dictionary) and as &apos;a private record of Kinmochi&apos; in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; of Kanekata URABE.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A private record does not exist, but it is cited as &apos;a private record of Nihongi&apos; in &quot;Wamyoruiju-sho&quot; (Kango-Japanese Dictionary) and as &apos;a private record of Kinmochi&apos; in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; of Kanekata URABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="391">
<j>承平六年（936年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 936</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 936</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 936</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="392">
<j>博士は矢田部公望。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecturer was YATABE no Kinmochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecturer was YATABE no Kinmochi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecturer was YATABE no Kinmochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="393">
<j>現在断片として伝わっている私記丁本がその私記であると推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is guessed that the &quot;D&quot; version private record which remains in a fragmentary fashion corresponds this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is guessed that the &quot;D&quot; version private record which remains in a fragmentary fashion corresponds this.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is guessed that the &quot;D&quot; version private record which remains in a fragmentary fashion corresponds this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="394">
<j>康保二年（965年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 965</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 965</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 965</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="395">
<j>博士は橘仲遠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lecturer was TACHIBANA no Nakato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lecturer was TACHIBANA no Nakato.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lecturer was TACHIBANA no Nakato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="396">
<j>私記は現存しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The private record does not exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A private record does not exist.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A private record does not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="397">
<j>なお、書紀古写本には単に「私記説」という形で引用されているものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are many old manuscripts which are cited simply in the form of &apos;a theory based on a private record.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are many old manuscripts which are cited simply in the form of &apos;a theory based on a private record.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are many old manuscripts which are cited simply in the form of &apos;a theory based on a private record.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="398">
<j>これらは上記年次私記のいずれかに由来するものと思われるが、残念ながら特定はできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that these originated from any of the above annual private record, but unfortunately, it can not be specified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that these originated from any of the above annual private records, but unfortunately, it can not be specified.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that these originated from any of the above annual private records, but unfortunately, it can not be specified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="399">
<j>その他にも、書紀古写本に見られる声点付きの傍訓は何らかの由緒ある説に基づくものと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to this, it seems that the bokun (kana (the Japanese syllabary)) with Shoten in old manuscripts of Shoki was based on any historic theory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to this, it seems that the bokun (kana (Japanese syllabary)) with shoten in old manuscripts of Shoki were based on any historic theory.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to this, it seems that the bokun (kana (Japanese syllabary)) with shoten in old manuscripts of Shoki were based on any historic theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="400">
<j>このため、上記私記の末裔である可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it can be the legacy of above private record.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it can be the legacy of the above private records.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it can be the legacy of the above private records.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="401">
<j>ちなみに、現在成書の形で存在する『日本紀私記』には、上述した甲本・丁本の他に、僚巻と見られる乙本（神代紀に相当）と丙本（人代紀に相当）の二種類が存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are two kinds of &quot;Nihongi Shiki&quot; (Private Notes on the Chronicles of Japan) which exist in full form now, that is, &quot;B&quot; version (corresponding to the volumes of the age of the gods) and &quot;C&quot; version (corresponding to the volumes of the age of emperors) which seem to be the same copies of &quot;A&quot; version and &quot;D&quot; version.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are two kinds of &quot;Nihongi Shiki&quot; (Private Notes on the Chronicles of Japan) which exist in full form now, that is, &quot;B&quot; version (corresponding to the volumes of the age of the gods) and &quot;C&quot; version (corresponding to the volumes of the age of emperors) which seem to be the same copies of the &quot;A&quot; version and &quot;D&quot; version.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are two kinds of &quot;Nihongi Shiki&quot; (Private Notes on the Chronicles of Japan) which exist in full form now, that is, &quot;B&quot; version (corresponding to the volumes of the age of the gods) and &quot;C&quot; version (corresponding to the volumes of the age of emperors) which seem to be the same copies of the &quot;A&quot; version and &quot;D&quot; version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="402">
<j>が、こちらはある未知の書紀古写本から傍訓のみを抜き出し、適宜片仮名を万葉仮名に書き換えてそれらしく装ったもの（時期は院政～鎌倉期か）と推定されており、いわゆる年次私記の直接の末裔ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is guessed that these are the abstracts of only bokun from an unknown old manuscript of Shoki which pretended to be a record by transferring katakana to Manyo-gana (it is guessed to be done from the insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor) to the Kamakura period), so that they are not direct legacies of so-called annual private records.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is guessed that these are the abstracts of only bokun from an unknown old manuscript of Shoki which pretended to be a record by transferring katakana to Manyo-gana (it is guessed to be done from the insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor) to the Kamakura period), so that they are not direct legacies of the so-called annual private records.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is guessed that these are the abstracts of only bokun from an unknown old manuscript of Shoki which pretended to be a record by transferring katakana to Manyo-gana (it is guessed to be done from the insei period (during the period of the government by the Retired Emperor to the Kamakura period), so that they are not direct legacies of the so-called annual private records.</e>
<cmt>)削除用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>竟宴和歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoen waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables made at a reception)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoen waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables made at a reception)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoen waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables made at a reception)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="403">
<j>元慶の講筵以降、終講の際にはそれを記念する宴会（竟宴）が行なわれるようになり、参加者によって『日本書紀』にちなむ和歌が詠まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the lecture of Nihonshoki in the Gangyo era, a reception which celebrated the end of the lecture became to be held and participants made waka which related to &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a lecture of Nihonshoki in the Gangyo era, a reception which celebrated the end of the lecture was held and participants made waka which related to &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a lecture of Nihonshoki in the Gangyo era, a reception which celebrated the end of the lecture was held and participants made waka which related to &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="404">
<j>それらを集めたものが『日本紀竟宴和歌（にほんぎきょうえんわか）』（天慶6年（943年）成立）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihongi kyoen waka&quot; was established by collecting those waka (established in 943).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihongi kyoen waka&quot; was established by collecting those waka (established in 943).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihongi kyoen waka&quot; was established by collecting those waka (established in 943).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="405">
<j>現存本は元慶・延喜・承平の各講筵の竟宴和歌より成る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing book consists of the kyoen waka of each lecture in Gangyo, Engi and Johei era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing book consists of the kyoen waka of each lecture in the Gangyo, Engi, and Johei era.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing book consists of the kyoen waka of each lecture in the Gangyo, Engi, and Johei era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="406">
<j>歌題として選ばれるのが神々や古代の聖王、伝説的な英雄たちということもあって、和歌の内容がどうしても類型的なものになりがちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contents of waka tended to be stereotyped partly because gods, ancient sacred kings and legendary heroes were often chosen as the themes of waka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contents of the waka tended to be stereotyped partly because gods, ancient sacred kings, and legendary heroes were often chosen as the themes of waka.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The contents of the waka tended to be stereotyped partly because gods, ancient sacred kings, and legendary heroes were often chosen as the themes of waka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="407">
<j>このため、文学的には特に見るべきものはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, it has no specific character in literary terms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, it has no specific character in literary terms.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, it has no specific character in literary terms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="408">
<j>が、藤原時平や藤原忠平といった当代の最上級の貴族の歌を集めているという点ですこぶるユニークな歌集となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is a very unique collection of poetry because it included the waka of nobles in the highest class at that time such as FUJIWARA no Tokihira and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is a very unique collection of poetry because it included the waka of nobles in the highest class at that time such as FUJIWARA no Tokihira and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is a very unique collection of poetry because it included the waka of nobles in the highest class at that time such as FUJIWARA no Tokihira and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 月下薄氷(id:47743), Green3558(id:59508), Nnh(id:474), Nekomiminarikin(id:199247), したたみ(id:102772), Hannah(id:15935), Eskimbot(id:29676), Shikire(id:1623), Динамо Москва(id:25756), Tribot(id:186681), Naigai(id:288953), Greenland4(id:114494), Gombe(id:27), Inforiver(id:65781), 茶－β(id:28615), ПФК ЦСКА София(id:81859), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), A-Taul(id:41790), Redattore(id:30931), 俊(id:14924), TY(id:1386), ごんた(id:62449), Shouichi(id:78888), Shimoxx(id:9332), Anarchy(id:6229), 新幹線(id:57409), Yas(id:739), FlaBot(id:30804), Kzhr(id:131), Shishin(id:22312), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Bigkoro(id:26478), Bletilla(id:38919), Stanislaus(id:1806), Nallimbot(id:230812), 曲学の徒(id:83449), Hokuto7(id:18100), MDR-SK(id:192066), Thijs!bot(id:69644), TakuyaMurata(id:156), Nakadati(id:26815), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ヤマト(id:8425), R28Bot(id:177951), 水平芳(id:203583), トホホ川(id:50502), NDR(id:5500), ばろむわん(id:262), Amat(id:87527), Freetrashbox(id:162354), CCmikan(id:108404), MIsogi(id:20599), A perfect fool(id:895), Urania(id:7213), Charenji(id:7908), 黄金もち(id:102311), Megaphone(id:10945), Qazzx(id:8772), Kiev(id:13022), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Johncapistrano(id:969), 氷鷺(id:73707), 暗黒な方(id:44101), 玄史生(id:43670), SRIA(id:56609), Kinori(id:443), Nevylax(id:38464), Unyounyo(id:38), Rei-bot(id:94097), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), Yosemite(id:5808), Inori(id:90350), Aduma(id:32899), Brisit(id:312124), デーモン博士(id:99293), Baru(id:22802), Izayohi(id:13095), Lonicera(id:20638), KEI(id:82484), 掘っ立て(id:102774), Auf(id:633), Race(id:131322), 水野白楓(id:22811), Web.dweller(id:153933), 松平定治(id:146386), Samacat(id:133386), Koiyo(id:45061), 伊勢山(id:188062), Murasagi(id:79122), VolkovBot(id:105371), Miya(id:1881), Shifumi(id:15485), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), 四方木(id:131870), YOSHI438(id:174755), Ponsaku(id:31417), Safkan(id:423), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 編集仁王(id:208160), Louperibot(id:128971), 羊鶴(id:7557), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>