<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>行遍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyohen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyohen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyohen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>行遍（ぎょうへん、生没年未詳）は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけて活躍した熊野速玉大社の社僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyohen (dates of birth and death unknown) was shaso (shrine priest) of Kumano-hayatama-taisha Shrine who did very splendid work from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyohen (dates of birth and death unknown) was shaso (shrine priest) of Kumano-hayatama-taisha Shrine who did very splendid work from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyohen (year of birth and death unknown) was shaso (shrine priest) of Kumano-hayatama-taisha Shrine who did very splendid work from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『新古今和歌集』の歌人としても有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also well known as a poet whose poems were collected in &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also well known as a poet whose poems were collected in &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also well known as a poet whose poems were collected in &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>19代熊野別当行範の六男で、母は源為義女・鳥居禅尼（「たつたはらの女房」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the sixth son of Yukinori, the nineteenth Kumano betto (title of an official who administered the shrines at Kumano), and his mother was Torii Zenni, a daughter of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi (&apos;Tatsutahara no nyobo&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth son of Yukinori, the nineteenth Kumano betto (title of an official who administered the shrines at Kumano), and his mother was Torii Zenni, the daughter of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi (&apos;Tatsutahara no nyobo&apos;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth son of Yukinori, the nineteenth Kumano betto (title of an official who administered the shrines at Kumano), and his mother was Torii Zenni, the daughter of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi (&apos;Tatsutahara no nyobo&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉幕府の初代将軍・源頼朝は母方の従兄弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Shogun of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his maternal cousin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Shogun of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his maternal cousin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Shogun of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his maternal cousin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生年について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the year of birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About the year of birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About the year of birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>生年は未詳であるが、1146年生まれの3兄行快（同母次兄，後の22代熊野別当）、1148年生まれの4兄範命（同母3兄、後の23代熊野別当）との関係から、1150年前後に比定される見解が出されている（阪本敏行『熊野三山と熊野別当』（清文堂出版、2005年）より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is still unknown when he was born, but it is considered that he was born around 1150 from the fact that his third elder brother Gyokai (second elder brother by the same mother, later known as the twenty-second Kumano betto) was born in 1146, and his fourth elder brother Hanmyo (third elder brother by the same mother, later known as the twenty-third Kumano betto). (according to &quot;Three Mountains in Kumano and Kumano betto&quot; by Toshiyuki SAKAMOTO, published by Seibundo Publishing Co., Ltd, 2005)</e>
<cmt>範命→Hanmyo[正しい読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is still unknown, but it is considered that he was born around 1150 from the fact that his third elder brother Gyokai (second elder brother by the same mother, later known as the twenty-second Kumano betto) was born in 1146, and his fourth elder brother Hanmyo (third elder brother by the same mother, later known as the twenty-third Kumano betto). (according to &quot;Three Mountains in Kumano and Kumano betto&quot; by Toshiyuki SAKAMOTO, published by Seibundo Publishing Co., Ltd, 2005)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is still unknown, but it is considered that he was born around 1150 from the fact that his third elder brother Gyokai (second elder brother by the same mother, later known as the twenty-second Kumano betto) was born in 1146, and his fourth elder brother Hanmyo (third elder brother by the same mother, later known as the twenty-third Kumano betto). (according to &quot;Three Mountains in Kumano and Kumano betto&quot; by Toshiyuki SAKAMOTO, published by Seibundo Publishing Co., Ltd, 2005)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歌人として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a poet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a poet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a poet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>国文学界には、『新古今和歌集』の「法橋行遍」を、熊野出身で熊野速玉大社の社僧・御師を家業とする行遍とする説と、鎌倉時代中期に活躍した東寺四長者の1人である大僧正行遍（1181年 - 1264年）とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among classical Japanese scholars, there are two theories about &apos;Hokkyo Gyohen&apos; in &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;: one is that the Gyohen was onshi (a low-ranking Shinto priest), who was from Kumano and a shaso of Kumano-hayatama-taisha Shrine, while the other is that it was daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order), Gyohen (1181-1264), one of the four chief priests of To-ji temple, who did remarkable work during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処東寺四長者→four chief priests of To-ji temple[定訳不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among classical Japanese scholars, there are two theories about &apos;Hokkyo Gyohen&apos; in &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;: one is that the Gyohen was onshi (a low-ranking Shinto priest), who was from Kumano and a shaso of Kumano-hayatama-taisha Shrine, while the other is that it was daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order), Gyohen (1181-1264), one of the four chief priests of To-ji temple, who did remarkable work during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among classical Japanese scholars, there are two theories about &apos;Hokkyo Gyohen&apos; in &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;: one is that the Gyohen was onshi (a low-ranking Shinto priest), who was from Kumano and a shaso of Kumano-hayatama-taisha Shrine, while the other is that it was daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order), Gyohen (1181-1264), one of the four chief priests of To-ji Temple, who did remarkable work during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、前者を支持する説には多くの証拠資料があるのに対し、後者を支持する説には『尊卑分脈』醍醐源氏系図の任尊子行遍への注以外（「新古作者」と記載）にこれといって証拠となる資料がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are many corroboration materials to prove the former theory, while there is none to support the latter except a note on Ninsonshi Gyohen in the genealogy of Daigo-Genji (Minamoto clan) collected in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処任尊子行遍→Ninsonshi Gyohen[正しい読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are many corroborated materials to support the former theory, while there are none to support the latter except a note on Ninsonshi Gyohen about the genealogy of Daigo-Genji (Minamoto clan) collected in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are many corroborated materials to support the former theory, while there are none to support the latter except a note on Ninsonshi Gyohen about the genealogy of Daigo-Genji (Minamoto clan) collected in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>『新古今和歌集』に収められた歌は、下記の4首である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four poems were collected in &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four poems were collected in the &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four poems were collected in the &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>みし人はよにもなぎさのもしほ草かきおくたびに袖ぞしほるる（詞書付き）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people with whom I was on close terms died one after another, and every time when I wrote sotoba (a narrow wooden plank), my sleeve got wet with my tears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people with whom I was on close terms died one after another, and every time when I wrote sotoba (a narrow wooden plank), my sleeve got wet with my tears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people with whom I was on close terms died one after another, and every time when I wrote sotoba (a narrow wooden plank), my sleeve got wet with my tears. (with Kotobagaki (foreword))</e>
<cmt>(with Kotobagaki (foreword))補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>名残をばにはのあさぢにとどめおきてたれゆゑ君がすみうかれけん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Who made you go out of here lightheartedly, leaving the traces of old days in cogon-grasses in the garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Who made you go out of here so lightheartedly, leaving the traces of the old days in cogon-grass in the garden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Who made you go out of here so lightheartedly, leaving the traces of the old days in cogon-grass in the garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>あやしくぞかへさは月のくもりにし昔がたりによやふけにけむ（詞書付き）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strangely, the moon disappeared behind a cloud on my way home. I wonder if I stayed too long out of fondness for the good old days and it was far into the night, or our past stories made me cry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strangely, the moon disappeared behind a cloud on my way home. I wonder if I stayed too long out of fondness for the good old days and it was far into the night, or our past stories made me cry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strangely, the moon disappeared behind a cloud on my way home. I wonder if I stayed too long out of fondness for the good old days and it was far into the night, or our past stories made me cry. (with Kotobagaki)</e>
<cmt>(with Kotobagaki)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>たのみありていま行末を待つ人や過ぐる月日をなげかざるらむ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I wonder if the people who are hopeful about the next world and waiting for the future would not lament the time going by.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I wonder if people who are hopeful about the next world and waiting for the future would not lament the time going by.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I wonder if people who are hopeful about the next world and waiting for the future would not lament the time going by.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>3.の詞書によると、行遍は若年の頃、熊野新宮の社僧・御師としてその家業に従いつつ、熊野で修行する西行から歌道を学んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the foreword to the third poem, when Gyohen was young, he studied the art of composing tanka poetry under Saigyo, leading an ascetic life at Kumano and following the custom of shaso or onshi of Kumano Shingu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the foreword to the third poem, when Gyohen was young, he studied the art of composing tanka poetry under Saigyo, leading an ascetic life at Kumano and following the custom of shaso or onshi of Kumano Shingu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the foreword to the third poem, when Gyohen was young, he studied the art of composing tanka poetry under Saigyo who was leading an ascetic life at Kumano following the custom of shaso or onshi of Kumano Shingu.</e>
<cmt>原文に合うように、内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その時期は1160年代後半から1170年代前半にかけての時期と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is conjectured that he did it between the latter half of the 1160s and the first half of the 1170s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is conjectured that he did it between the latter half of the 1160s and the first half of the 1170s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is conjectured that he did it between the latter half of the 1160s and the first half of the 1170s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>元久元年（1204年）、熊野行遍法橋は、『新古今和歌集』の撰者の1人である藤原定家を訪ね、西行（1118年 - 1190年）のことなどを懐かしく語り合った（『明月記』元久元年6月15日条）結果、『新古今和歌集』に「法橋行遍」という名前で上記の4首が入撰された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1204, Kumano Gyohen Hokkyo visited FUJIWARA no Teika, one of the selectors of &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu,&quot; having a talk with him about Saigyo (1118-1190) and others with nostalgia (&quot;Meigetsuki,&quot; July 20, 1204), as a result, four of his poems were selected under the name of &apos;Hokkyo Gyohen&apos; for &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1204, Kumano Gyohen Hokkyo visited FUJIWARA no Teika, one of the selectors of &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu,&quot; having a talk with him about Saigyo (1118-1190) and others with nostalgia (&quot;Meigetsuki,&quot; July 20, 1204), as a result, four of his poems were selected under the name of &apos;Hokkyo Gyohen&apos; for &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1204, Kumano Gyohen Hokkyo visited FUJIWARA no Teika, one of the selectors of &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu,&quot; having a talk with him about Saigyo (1118-1190) and others with nostalgia (&quot;Meigetsuki,&quot; July 20, 1204), as a result, four of his poems were selected under the name of &apos;Hokkyo Gyohen&apos; for &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>元久2年（1205年）、実兄の23代熊野別当範命の推挙により、法眼となる（『明月記』元久元年元日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1205, he became hogen (the second highest rank for Buddhist priests) by recommendation of his older brother by blood, the 23rd Kumano Betto Hanmyo. (&quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) February 10, 1204)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1205, he became hogen (the second highest rank for a Buddhist priests) on the recommendation of his older brother by blood, the 23rd Kumano Betto Hanmyo. (&quot;Meigetsuki&quot; - Chronicles of the Bright Moon) February 10, 1204)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1205, he became hogen (the second highest rank for a Buddhist priests) on the recommendation of his older brother, the 23rd Kumano Betto Hanmyo. (&quot;Meigetsuki&quot; - Chronicles of the Bright Moon) February 10, 1204)</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>死亡時期は、鎌倉時代初期の1210年頃に比定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of his death is considered the early Kamakura period, about 1210.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year of his death is considered to be the early Kamakura period, about 1210.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year of his death is considered to be the early Kamakura period, about 1210.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>享年60前後か。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age at death, around 60.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age at death, around 60.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of around 48.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>僧侶としての極位は法眼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The highest rank as a priest was hogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The highest rank as a priest was hogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The highest rank as a priest was hogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dr jimmy(id:111486), Ks8823(id:130146), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Ikedat76(id:34218), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>