<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古史古伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshi Koden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshi Koden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi Koden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>古史古伝（こしこでん）とは、日本の古代史で主要資料とされている「記紀（『古事記』と『日本書紀』）」とは著しく異なる内容歴史を伝える文献のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshi koden means literatures that record contents and history which are remarkably different from those in kiki (&quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)) which are treated as main materials or ancient history of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshi koden means literatures that record contents and history which are remarkably different from those in kiki (&quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan)), which are treated as main materials on the ancient history of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi koden are historical documents with content that is significantly different from the kiki (&quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan)), which are considered as the major historical documents in the field of ancient Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>種類が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many types.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また「超古代文書」とも「偽史」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also called &quot;chokodai monjo&quot; (super-ancient documents&quot; or &quot;gishi (apocryphal history).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called &quot;chokodai monjo&quot; (super-ancient documents&quot; or &quot;gishi (apocryphal history).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called &apos;chokodai monjo&apos; (super-ancient documents) or &apos;gishi&apos; (pseudo-histories).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>古代史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>写本自体が私有され非公開である、などの理由で史料批判がなされる予定がなく、史料として使えないものも多い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It includes many documents which cannot be used as a historical material because criticism on them as historical materials is not expected due to reasons such as manuscript itself is privately owned and not opened to public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It includes many documents that can&apos;t be used as historical materials because criticism of them as historical materials isn&apos;t expected due to reasons such as the manuscript itself is privately owned and not open to the public.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It includes many documents that cannot be used as historical material because academic consideration as historical material is not possible because the manuscript is privately owned and not open to the public.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>超古代文明について言及されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Super-ancient civilization is mentioned in them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Super-ancient civilization is mentioned in them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Super-ancient civilization is mentioned in them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>漢字伝来以前に日本にあったと言われている神代文字で綴られている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are written in the ancient Japanese characters which are said to have existed in Japan before introduction of kanji (Chinese character).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are written in the ancient Japanese characters, which are said to have existed in Japan before the introduction of kanji (Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are written in the ancient Japanese characters, which are said to have existed in Japan before the introduction of kanji (Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近代以降の用語が使用されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words in and after the modern times were used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words in and after the modern times were used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words originating from the modern times are used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>等々の理由で古代からの伝来である可能性は極めて低く、古代史研究における歴史学的な価値は非常に低いと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of such reasons, the possibility that they were handed down from the ancient times is quite small and it is considered that their historical value for studying ancient history is very low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the foregoing reasons, the possibility that they were handed down from ancient times is quite small and it is considered that they have very low historical value for the study of ancient history.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above reasons, the possibility that they were handed down from ancient times is quite small and it has very low historical value in regard to the study of ancient history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、古史古伝は種類が多く、それらの諸点についての度合いは各書ごとに様々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are many different types of koshi koden, and the degree of correspondence with those points differ for each document.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are many different types of koshi koden, and the degree of correspondence with those points differs for each document.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are many different types of koshi koden, and the degree to which the above points are true widely differs depending on the document.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>現在では、近代における日本人の国家観・民族観への受容等のあらわれとして、写本作成を行う者の思想に対する研究が始まったところである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, study has just been commenced on thought of those who prepared manuscripts as expression of acceptance to view of the state and view of the race of Japanese people in the modern times.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味が不明確ですが、訳文のように解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, a study is now under way in consideration of those who prepared the manuscripts as an expression of acceptance in viewing the state and perception of the Japanese race in modern times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, studies on the ideology of those who prepared the manuscripts as as an expression of acceptance of the concept of a Japanese state/race in modern times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>名称由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>第2次世界大戦前には「神代史」「太古史」など言われ、戦後（1970年代頃まで）には吾郷清彦が「超古代文書」と呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Second World War, they were called &quot;jindaishi (history of mythological age)&quot; or &quot;taikoshi (history of ancient times)&quot; and, after the War (until 1970&apos;s), Kiyohiho AGO called them &quot;chokodai monjo&quot; (super-ancient documents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to World War II, they were called &quot;jindaishi (history of mythological age)&quot; or &quot;taikoshi (history of ancient times)&quot; and, after the war (until the 1970s) Kiyohiho AGO called them &quot;chokodai monjo&quot; (super-ancient documents).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to World War II, they were called &apos;jindaishi (history of mythological age)&apos; or &apos;taikoshi (history of ancient times)&apos; and, after the war (until the 1970s) Kiyohiho AGO called them &apos;chokodai monjo (super-ancient documents).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また同じ頃、武田崇元（武内裕）は「偽書」「偽史」「偽典」などといっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the same time, Sugen TAKEDA (HiroshinTAKEUCHI) called them &quot;gisho (apocryphal document)&quot;, &quot;gishi (apocryphal history)&quot; or &quot;giten (apocryphal book).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置「武内裕」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At around the same time, Sugen TAKEDA (Hiroshin TAKEUCHI) called them &quot;gisho (apocryphal document),&quot; &quot;gishi (apocryphal history)&quot; or &quot;giten (apocryphal book).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At around the same time, Sugen TAKEDA (Yu TAKEUCHI) called them &apos;gisho (pseudo-document),&apos; &apos;gishi (pseudo-history)&apos; or &apos;giten (pseudo- book).&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「偽書」「偽典」は用語として別に確立したものがあり紛らわしいので、やがて「偽史」という言い方に統一されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as &quot;gisho&quot; and &quot;giten&quot; had already been established as words to show other matters and, therefore, they were confusing, it was gradually unified to the expression &quot;gishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as &quot;gisho&quot; and &quot;giten&quot; had already been established as words to show other matters and were therefore confusing, it was gradually unified to the expression &quot;gishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &apos;gishi&apos; gradually became the word to be used for such documents sinceit would be confusing to use &apos;gisho&apos; and &apos;giten&apos; because they had already been established as words to indicate other matters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>「古史古伝」という言い方は、吾郷清彦が著書『古事記以前の書』（大陸書房、1972年）で最初に提唱したもので、この段階では「古典四書」「古伝三書」「古史三書」とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;koshi koden&quot;was proposed by Kiyohiko AGO in his book &quot;Kojiki izen no sho&quot; (documents before Kojiki)(published by Tairiku Shobo, 1972) and, in this stage, it was said &quot;koten sisho (four classics)&quot;, &quot;koden sansho (three legends)&quot;, and &quot;koshi sansho (three ancient historical documents).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置「大陸書房」の英語名は確認できないため、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;koshi koden&quot; was proposed by Kiyohiko AGO in his book &quot;Kojiki izen no sho&quot; (documents before Kojiki) (published by Tairiku Shobo, 1972) and, at this stage reference was made to &quot;koten sisho (four classics),&quot; &quot;koden sansho (three legends)&quot; and &quot;koshi sansho (three ancient historical documents).</e>
<cmt>sp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;koshi koden&apos; was proposed by Kiyohiko AGO in his book &quot;Kojiki izen no sho (documents before Kojiki)&quot; (published by Tairiku Shobo, 1972) and, at this stage reference was made to &apos;koten sisho (four classics),&apos; &apos;koden sansho (three legends)&apos; and &apos;koshi sansho (three ancient historical documents).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>著書『日本超古代秘史資料』（新人物往来社、1976年）では、「古典四書」「古伝四書」「古史四書」「異録四書」に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his book &quot;Nihon Chokodaihishi Siryo&quot; (Materials for super-ancient history of Japan) (published by Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha Co., Ltd., in 1976), it was expanded to &quot;koten sisho (four classics)&quot;, &quot;koden shisho (four legends)&quot;, &quot;koshi shisho (four ancient historical documents) and &quot;iroku sisho (four miscellaneous records).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his book &quot;Nihon Chokodaihishi Siryo&quot; (Materials for Super-Ancient History of Japan) (published in 1976 by Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha Co., Ltd.), it was expanded to &quot;koten sisho (four classics),&quot; &quot;koden shisho (four legends),&quot; &quot;koshi shisho (four ancient historical documents) and &quot;iroku sisho (four miscellaneous records).&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his book &quot;Nihon Chokodaihishi Siryo (Reference on Super-Ancient History of Japan)&quot; (published in 1976 by Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha Co., Ltd.), it was expanded to &apos;koten sisho (four classics),&apos; &apos;koden shisho (four legends),&apos; &apos;koshi shisho (four ancient historical documents)&apos; and &apos;iroku sisho (four miscellaneous records).&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>初期の頃の吾郷清彦は「超古代文書」という言い方を好み、「古史古伝」とは言わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early stage, Kiyohiko AGO liked the expression &quot;chokodai monjo&quot; and did not say &quot;koshi koden.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, Kiyohiko AGO liked the expression &quot;chokodai monjo&quot; but didn&apos;t say &quot;koshi koden.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, Kiyohiko AGO preferred the expression &apos;chokodai monjo&apos; but did not use &apos;koshi koden.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>あくまで分類上の用語として「古伝四書」とか「古史四書」といっていたにすぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only as words for classification, &quot;kosho shisho&quot; or &quot;koshi shisho&quot; were used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only as terms for classification, either &quot;kosho shisho&quot; or &quot;koshi shisho&quot; was used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He only used &apos;kosho shisho&apos; or &apos;koshi shisho&apos; as terms for classificationﾙ</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1980年代以降、佐治芳彦がこれをくっつけて「古史古伝」と言い出したのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1980&apos;s and on, Yoshihiko SAJI combined them and said &quot;koshi koden,&quot; and this was the origin of the word.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the 1980s onward, Yoshihiko SAJI combined them and said &quot;koshi koden,&quot; so this was the origin of the word.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">he origin of the word From the 1980s onward, Yoshihiko SAJI combined them and said &apos;koshi koden,</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>下記の分類は前述の『日本超古代秘史資料』を基本としているが、その後、他の文献写本が発見されるに従って吾郷清彦自身によって徐々に改訂が繰り返され増殖していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following classification is based on the above -mentioned &quot;Nihon Chokodaihishi Siryo,&quot; but later, as manuscripts of other literatures were found, Kiyohiko AGO himself repeated revision and the number was increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following classification is based on the above-mentioned &quot;Nihon Chokodaihishi Siryo,&quot; but later, as manuscripts of other literature were found, Kiyohiko AGO himself repeatedly conducted revisions and the number was increased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following classification is based on the above-mentioned &quot;Nihon Chokodaihishi Siryo,&quot; but later, as copies of other documents were found, Kiyohiko AGO himself repeatedly revised the classification as it grew.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その分として若干の補足を加えてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Certain supplements were added to cover such literatures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Certain supplements were added to cover such literature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some additions were added to cover such literature.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>吾郷清彦による分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification by Kiyohiko AGO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Kiyohiko AGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by Kiyohiko AGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>古典四書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koten shisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koten shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koten shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>『古事記』『日本書紀』『先代旧事本紀』（旧事紀）が古典三書、『古語拾遺』を加えて古典四書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojiki&quot;, &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot; (ancient Japanese history) are koten sansho and koten sansho added with &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (history of the Inbe clan) is koten shisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojiki,&quot; &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot; (ancient Japanese history) are koten sansho, and koten sansho added with &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (history of the Inbe clan) is koten shisho.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kojiki,&quot; &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot; (ancient Japanese history) are koten sansho, and koten sansho added with &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (history of the Inbe clan) is koten shisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この「古典四書」（または古典三書）という分類は、異端としての超古代文書に対して正統な神典としての比較対象のための便宜的な分類である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification of this &quot;koten shisho&quot; (or, koten sansho) is a classification for convenience sake in order to compare them as legitimate Shinto scriptures with chokodai monjo as heretical.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classification of this &quot;koten shisho&quot; (or koten sansho) is a classification for the sake of convenience in order to compare them as legitimate Shinto scriptures with chokodai monjo as heretical.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classification of &apos;koten shisho&apos; (or koten sansho) is a classification for the sake of convenience in order to compare heretical chokodai monjo with legitimate Shinto scriptures</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「古典四書」はいわゆる超古代文書（古史古伝）ではなく、通常の「神典」から代表的・基本的な四書を出したもので、実質は「神典」の言い替えにすぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koten shisho&quot; is not so-called super-ancient documents (koshi koden) and four representative and basic literatures were picked up from usual &quot;Shinto scriptures&quot;, and, therefore, it is just another expression of &quot;Shinto scripture.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Koten shisho&quot; are not so-called super-ancient documents (koshi koden) but instead four representative and basic literature were picked from the usual &quot;Shinto scriptures,&quot; and therefore it is just another expression of &quot;Shinto scripture.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koten shisho&apos; are not the so-called super-ancient documents (koshi koden) but instead four representative and basic literature were picked from the usual &apos;Shinto scriptures,&apos; and therefore it is just another term for &apos;Shinto scriptures.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>（神典の範囲をどう定めるかは古来諸説があるが『万葉集』『風土記』『新撰姓氏録』などを含むことが多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(There have been various views with respect to the scope of Shinto scriptures, it usually includes Manyoshu (literally, collection of ten thousand leaves), &quot;fudoki&quot; (description of regional climate, culture, etc.), &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (literally, newly compiled register of clan names and titles of nobility), etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(There have been various views with respect to the scope of Shinto scriptures, which usually include Manyoshu (literally, collection of 10,000 leaves), &quot;fudoki&quot; (description of regional climate, culture, etc.), &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (literally, newly compiled register of clan names and titles of nobility), etc.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There have been various theories with respect to the scope of Shinto scriptures, but it usually includes &quot;Manyoshu (literally, collection of 10,000 leaves),&quot; &quot;Fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.),&quot; &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku (literally, newly compiled register of clan names and titles of nobility)&quot; and so on.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし『先代旧事本紀』については若干の説明が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to &quot;Sendai Kujihongi &quot;, certain explanation is necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to &quot;Sendai Kujihongi,&quot; a certain explanation is necessary.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some explanation is required regarding the &quot;Sendai Kujihongi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>『先代旧事本紀』は江戸時代以来、偽書であるとの評価が一般的であり、当然、吾郷清彦も最初からそれを認識していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to &quot;Sendai Kujihongi &quot;, since the Edo period, it was generally judged as a gisho (apocryphal book) and, needless to say, Kiyohiko AGO also knew it from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to &quot;Sendai Kujihongi,&quot; since the Edo period it was generally judged as a gisho (apocryphal book) and, needless to say, Kiyohiko AGO knew it from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The&quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot; has generally been judged as a gisho (psuedo-document) since the Edo period and Kiyohiko AGO was aware of this from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかしまた同時に、通説と同様に、その価値を全面否定はせず、記紀に次ぐ重要な「神典」とみなされてきた事実には変わりない、と（記紀ほどではないが）評価もしていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, however, he did not totally deny its value and he appreciated it as there was no change in the fact that it had been deemed as the most important &quot;Shinto scripture&quot; next to kiki (although not comparable to kiki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he didn&apos;t fully deny its value but appreciated it, since there was no change in the fact that it had been deemed the most important &quot;Shinto scripture&quot; next to kiki (although it wasn&apos;t considered comparable to kiki).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he did not fully deny its value but appreciated it, since it had been deemed as the most important &apos;Shinto scripture&apos; after to the Kiki (although notcomparable to the Kiki).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この本来の旧事紀（十巻本）とは別に異本（『先代旧事本紀大成経』（72巻本）・『白河本旧事紀』（30巻本）・『大成経鷦鷯伝』（31巻本））もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than this original Kujiki (ten volume set), there are alternative versions (&quot;Sendai Kujihongi Taiseikyo&quot; (seventy-to volume set). &quot;Shirakawa Hon Kujiki&quot; (thirty volume set) and &quot;Taiseikyo Sasakiden&quot; (thirty-one volume set)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than this original Kujiki (ten-volume set), there are alternative versions (&quot;Sendai Kujihongi Taiseikyo&quot; (72-volume set), &quot;Shirakawa Hon Kujiki&quot; (30-volume set) and &quot;Taiseikyo Sasakiden&quot; (31-volume set)).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than this original Kujiki (ten-volume set), there are alternative versions (&quot;Sendai Kujihongi Taiseikyo&quot; (72-volume set), &quot;Shirakawa Hon Kujiki&quot; (30-volume set) and &quot;Taiseikyo Sasakiden&quot; (31-volume set)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>こちらは論者によっては古史古伝の一種とされることもありがちなのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are argued rather often to be a kind of koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Often it is asserted that they represent a kind of koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Often it is asserted that they represent a kind of koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、超古代文書（＝古史古伝）は「偽書」の一種ではあっても、「偽書」のすべてが古史古伝かというとそれも疑問である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although chokodai monjo (= koshi koden) is a kind of &quot;gisho,&quot;all of &quot;gisho&quot; should not be taken as koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although chokodai monjo (= koshi koden) is a kind of &quot;gisho,&quot; not all &quot;gisho&quot; should be taken as koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although chokodai monjo (= koshi koden) is a kind of &apos;gisho,&apos; not all &apos;gisho&apos; should be taken as koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>吾郷清彦はその著作の中で『旧事紀』の異本を紹介しながらもこれらを古史古伝とはしていないのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyohiko AGO introduced alternative books of &quot;Kujiki&quot; in his literary works, but he did not judged them as koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyohiko AGO introduced alternative books of &quot;Kujiki&quot; in his literary works, but he did not consider them to be koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyohiko AGO introduced alternative books of &quot;Kujiki&quot; in his literary works, but he did not consider them to be koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>同様に『天書』（「天書紀」ともいう）・『日本国総風土記』・『前々太平記』の三書を異端古代史書として加える説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, there is a view to add three books, &quot;Tensho&quot; (also called &quot;Tenshoki&quot;) (a chronological history of Japan), &quot;Nihonkoku sofudoki&quot; and Zen-zen Taiheiki (a military story) as heretical ancient history books</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, there is a view that adds three books--&quot;Tensho&quot; (also called &quot;Tenshoki&quot;) (a chronological history of Japan), &quot;Nihonkoku sofudoki&quot; and Zen-zen Taiheiki (a military story)--as heretical ancient history books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, there is a view that adds three books--&quot;Tensho (also called &apos;Tenshoki&apos;)&quot; (a chronological history of Japan), &quot;Nihonkoku sofudoki&quot; and &quot;Zen-zen Taiheiki (a military story)&quot;--as heretical ancient history books.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に原文の『』に合わせ&quot;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>このうち『天書』は古史古伝の類とはいえず、他の二書も超古代文書というほどの内容をもっているわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, &quot;Tensho&quot; is not a koshi koden, and other two also do not contain anything to make them chokodai monjo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, &quot;Tensho&quot; isn&apos;t a koshi koden, and the other two contain nothing that would make them chokodai monjo.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, &quot;Tensho&quot; isn&apos;t a koshi koden, and the other two contain nothing that would make them chokodai monjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これらは古典四書の周辺的な類書であり古史古伝に準ずる異端古代史書とはいえても、超古代文書だとか古史古伝そのものに入れるのは相当な無理がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are similar books in the periphery of koten shisho and, although we may call them heretical ancient historic book similar to koshi koden, but it is unreasonable to include them in chokodai monjo or koshi koden itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are similar books in the periphery of koten shisho and, although we may call them heretical ancient historic book similar to koshi koden, it is unreasonable to include them in chokodai monjo or koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are similar books in the periphery of koten shisho and, although we may call them heretical ancient historic book similar to koshi koden, it is unreasonable to include them in chokodai monjo or koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>（また『新撰姓氏録』を超古代史書として解釈する説もある。これは解釈が超古代史なのであって本文そのものが超古代史なわけではない）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>「解釈が超古代史」は、「解釈の対象が超古代史」等の表現の誤りと思われますが、原文に忠実に訳しました。(したがって、意味不明の文になりました。)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Also, there is a view in which &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; is interpreted as a chokodai shisho (super-ancient historic book. However, the interpretation is super-ancient history but the text itself is not super-ancient history.)</e>
<cmt>Translatedspelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Also, there is a view in which &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; is interpreted as a chokodai shisho (super-ancient historic book). However, the interpretation may be considered super-ancient history but the text itself is not super-ancient history.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。is may be→may be</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>古伝四書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koden shisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koden shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koden shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>『上紀』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Uetsufumi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Uetsufumi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Uetsufumi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>『秀真伝』（※漢字ではなくカナ書きするのが吾郷の流儀）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hotsumatsutae&quot; (AGO&apos;s way is not to write in Chinese character, but in kana.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hotsumatsutae&quot; (AGO&apos;s way is not to write in Chinese characters but to use kana instead).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotsumatsutae (Ago uses kana instead of kanji characters)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>『三笠紀』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mikasafumi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mikasafumi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mikasafumi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>『カタカムナ文献』（いわゆる「カタカムナ」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Katakamuna literature&quot; (so-called &quot;Katakamuna&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Katakamuna literature&quot; (so-called &quot;Katakamuna&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Katakamuna literature&quot; (so-called &apos;Katakamuna&apos;)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>「カタカムナ」を除いて「古伝三書」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excluding &quot;Katakamuna,&quot; they are callsed &quot;Koden Sansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exception of &quot;Katakamuna,&quot; they are called &quot;Koden Sansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of &apos;Katakamuna,&apos; they are called &apos;Koden Sansho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この「古伝四書」は全文が神代文字で書かれているという外見上の体裁による分類であって、内容に基づく分類ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;koden shisho&quot; is a classification from their appearance that whole sentences are written in the ancient Japanese characters not by their contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;koden shisho&quot; is a classification from their appearance in which whole sentences are written in the ancient Japanese characters, not strictly in accordance with their contents.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;koden shisho&apos; is a classification based not strictly in accordance with their contents, but on their appearance in which whole sentences are written in the ancient Japanese characters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>また『フトマニ』という書がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is a document called &quot;Futomani.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there is a document called &quot;Futomani.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is a document called &quot;Futomani.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>『ホツマツタヱ』『ミカサフミ』とともにこの三書は世界観を同じくする同一体系内の一連の書であり「ホツマ系文書」ということができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three documents, &quot;Futomani,&quot; &quot;Hotsumatsutae&quot;and &quot;Mikasafumi&quot; are a series of documents belonging to a same system of the same view of the world and, therefore, we can call them &quot;hotsuma-kei monjo (hotsuma system documents)&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three documents--&quot;Futomani,&quot; &quot;Hotsumatsutae&quot; and &quot;Mikasafumi&quot;--are a series of documents belonging to the same system having the same view of the world, and therefore we can call them &quot;hotsuma-kei monjo (hotsuma system documents).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three documents--&quot;Futomani,&quot; &quot;Hotsumatsutae&quot; and &quot;Mikasafumi&quot;--are a series of documents belonging to the same system having the same view of the world, and therefore we can call them &apos;hotsuma-kei monjo (hotsuma system documents).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>信奉者からは「ヲシデ文献」と一括してよばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Believers call them collectively &quot;Woshide literatures.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Believers refer to them collectively as &quot;Woshide literature.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Believers refer to them collectively as &apos;Woshide literature.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>この『フトマニ』は普通名詞の太占（ふとまに）と紛らわしいので吾郷清彦は『カンヲシデモトウラツタヱ』（神璽基兆伝）と名付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because this &quot;Futomani&quot; was confusing with a common noun &quot;futomani,&quot; Kiyohiko AGO named it &quot;Kanwoshide motoura tsutae.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because this &quot;Futomani&quot; was easily confused with the common noun &quot;futomani,&quot; Kiyohiko AGO called it &quot;Kanwoshide motoura tsutae.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because this &quot;Futomani&quot; was easily confused with the common noun &quot;futomani,&quot; Kiyohiko AGO called it &quot;Kanwoshide motoura tsutae.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>またカタカムナに関係する『神名比備軌』（かむなひびき）や『間之統示』（まのすべし）という漢字文献も「カタカムナ系の文献」として一括できるが、これらカタカムナを含むカタカムナ系の諸文献は「歴史書」ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literatures in Chinese characters &quot;Kamuna hibiki&quot; and &quot;Ma no subeshi&quot; which relate to Katakamuna can be calassified in one group &quot;Katakamuna system literatures, but those literatures of the katakamuna system including katakamuna are not &quot;history book.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literature in Chinese characters &quot;Kamuna hibiki&quot; and &quot;Ma no subeshi,&quot; which relate to Katakamuna, can be classified in one group &quot;Katakamuna system literature, but such literature of the katakamuna system including katakamuna doesn&apos;t constitute &quot;history books.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literature in kanji characters, &quot;Kamuna hibiki&quot; and &quot;Ma no subeshi,&quot; which relate to Katakamuna, can be classified in one group &apos;Katakamuna system literature, but katakamuna system documents including katakamuna are not considered as &apos;history books.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>「超古代文書＝古史古伝」は、このように歴史書以外をも含む幅広い概念である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chokodai monjo = koshi kode&quot; is a wide concept that includes literatures other than history book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chokodai monjo = koshi kode&quot; is a broad concept that includes literature other than history books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokodai monjo = koshi kode&apos; is a broad concept that includes documents other than history books.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>古史四書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshi shisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshi shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>『九鬼文書』（いわゆる「九鬼文書』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kuki monjo (Kuki documents)&quot; (So-called &quot;Kuki monjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kuki monjo (Kuki documents)&quot; (so-called &quot;Kuki monjo)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kuki monjo (Kuki documents)&quot; (so-called &apos;Kuki monjo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に)削除ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>『天津鞴韜秘文』（あまつたたらのひふみ）は九鬼文書群の一部である）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Amatsu tatara no hifumi&quot; is a part of Kuki monjo group.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Amatsu tatara no hifumi&quot; is part of the Kuki monjo group.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Amatsu tatara no hifumi&quot; is part of the Kuki monjo group.)</e>
<cmt>(削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>『竹内文書』（いわゆる「竹内文献」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Takeuchi monjo (Takeuchi documents)&quot; (So-called &quot;Takeuchi bunken (Takeuchi literatures)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Takeuchi monjo (Takeuchi documents)&quot; (so-called &quot;Takeuchi bunken (Takeuchi literature)&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Takeuchi monjo (Takeuchi documents)&quot; (so-called &apos;Takeuchi bunken (Takeuchi literature).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>「天津教文書」「磯原文書」ともいう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called &quot;Amatsukyo monjo (Amatsukyo documents)&quot; or &quot;Isohara monjo (Isohara documents))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also called &quot;Amatsukyo monjo (Amatsukyo documents)&quot; or &quot;Isohara monjo (Isohara documents))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called &apos;Amatsukyo monjo (Amatsukyo documents)&apos; or &apos;Isohara monjo (Isohara documents).&apos;)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にピリオド&apos;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>『宮下文書』（いわゆる「富士谷文書」（ふじやもんじょ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Miyashita monjo (Miyashita documents)&quot;(So-called &quot;Fujiya monjo (Fujiya documents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Miyashita monjo (Miyashita documents)&quot; (so-called &quot;Fujiya monjo (Fujiya documents).&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Miyashita monjo (Miyashita documents)&quot; (so-called &apos;Fujiya monjo (Fujiya documents).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>「宮下文書」「富士宮下古文献」ともいう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called &quot;Miyashita monjo (Miyashita documents)&quot; or &quot;Fuji Miyashita komonjo (Fuji Miyashita old documents).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called &quot;Miyashita monjo (Miyashita documents)&quot; or &quot;Fuji Miyashita komonjo (Fuji Miyashita old documents).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called &apos;Miyashita monjo (Miyashita documents)&apos; or &apos;Fuji Miyashita komonjo (Fuji Miyashita old documents)&apos;.)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="54">
<j>『物部文書』（いわゆる「物部文書」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mononobe monjo (Mononobe documents)&quot; (So-called &quot;Mononobe monjo&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mononobe monjo (Mononobe documents)&quot; (so-called &quot;Mononobe monjo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mononobe monjo (Mononobe documents)&quot; (so-called &apos;Mononobe monjo&apos;)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>『物部秘史』を除いて「古史三書」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excluding &quot;Mononobe hishi (Mononobe secret history), they are also called &quot;koshi sansho (three ancient history documents.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excluding &quot;Mononobe hishi (Mononobe secret history), they are also called &quot;koshi sansho (three ancient history documents).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called the &apos;koshi sansho (three ancient history documents)&apos; excluding &quot;Mononobe hishi (Mononobe secret history).&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>「古史四書」は神代文字をも伝えてはいるものの、本文は漢字のみまたは漢字仮名まじり文で書かれたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koshi shisho&quot;conveyed ancient Japanese characters, but its text is written in only Chinese characters or kana mixed with Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Koshi shisho&quot; conveyed ancient Japanese characters, but its text is written only in Chinese characters or kana mixed with Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi shisho&apos; includes ancient Japanese characters, but its text is written only in kanji characters or kana mixed with kanji characters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>やはり内容による分類ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is not classification by contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is not classified according to its contents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is not classified according to its contents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>上記の四つのタイトル（九鬼神伝精史・竹内太古史・富士高天原朝史・物部秘史）は、吾郷清彦が独自に名付けたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Above-mentioned four titles (Kuki Shinden Seishi, Takeuchi Taikoshi, Fuji Takamagahara Chosi and Mononobe Hishi) were named by Kiyohiko AGO independently.</e>
<cmt>書名は正しい読みが確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above-mentioned four titles (Kuki Shinden Seishi, Takeuchi Taikoshi, Fuji Takamagahara Chosi and Mononobe Hishi) were named independently by Kiyohiko AGO.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above-mentioned four titles (Kuki Shinden Seishi, Takeuchi Taikoshi, Fuji Takamagahara Chosi and Mononobe Hishi) were named independently by Kiyohiko AGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="59">
<j>異録四書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iroku shisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iroku shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iroku shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>『東日流外三郡誌』（つがるそとさんぐんし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsugaru Sotosangun Shi&quot;(</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsugaru Sotosangun Shi&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tsugaru Sotosangun Shi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>「和田家文書」ともいう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, called &quot;Wadake Bunsho&quot; (Wada family documents)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Wadake Bunsho&quot; (Wada family documents).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is also called &apos;Wadake Bunsho&apos; (Wada family documents).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に(補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="62">
<j>『但馬故事記』（たじまこじき。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tajima Kojiki&quot;(</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tajima Kojiki&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tajima Kojiki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>「但馬故事記」とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, called &quot;Tajimakojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, called &quot;Tajimakojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Also, called &apos;Tajimakojiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>(補足原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>但馬故事記は本来は但馬国司文書の中の代表的な書物の名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Tajima Kojiki is a name of representative book among Tajima Kokushi monjo (documents of the provincial governor of Tajima)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Tajima Kojiki was the name of a representative book among the Tajima Kokushi monjo (documents of the provincial governor of Tajima).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Tajima Kojiki was the name of an important book among the Tajima Kokushi monjo (documents of the provincial governor of Tajima).)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="65">
<j>『忍日伝天孫記』（おしひのつたえてんそんき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Oshihinotsutae Tensonki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Oshihinotsutae Tensonki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Oshihinotsutae Tensonki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>『神道原典』（しんとうげんてん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shinto Genten&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shinto Genten&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shinto Genten&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>『神道原典』を除いて「異録三書」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excluding &quot;Shinto Genten,&quot; they are called &quot;Iroku sansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excluding &quot;Shinto Genten,&quot; they are called &quot;Iroku sansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are called &apos;Iroku sansho&apos; excluding &quot;Shinto Genten.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="68">
<j>このうち、『忍日伝天孫記』と『神道原典』は古文書・古文献ではなく、前者は自動書記、後者は霊界往来による霊感の書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, &quot;Oshihinotsutae Tensonki&quot; and &quot;Shinto Genten&quot; are not komonjo (old document) or kobunken (old literature), but the former is automatic writing and the latter is the book of inspiration by visit to the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, &quot;Oshihinotsutae Tensonki&quot; and &quot;Shinto Genten&quot; aren&apos;t komonjo (old documents) or kobunken (old literature), but the former is automatic writing and the latter is the book of inspiration by visit to the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, &quot;Oshihinotsutae Tensonki&quot; and &quot;Shinto Genten&quot; are not komonjo (old documents) or kobunken (old literature), but the former is a document written through automatism and the latter is a book of inspired by a visit to the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>このように吾郷清彦の「古史古伝」（超古代文書）という概念は「古代から伝わった書物」という意味だけでなく、「自動書記などの霊感によって超古代の情報をもたらす現代の書」まで含む幅広い概念である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen above, Kiyohiko AGO&apos;s concept of &quot;koshi koden&quot; (chokodai bunsho) is a wide one that includes not only &quot;books handed down from the ancient times&quot;, but also &quot;books of modern times that bring information form of super-ancient times through inspiration such as automatic writing.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen above, Kiyohiko AGO&apos;s concept of &quot;koshi koden&quot; (chokodai bunsho) is a broad one that includes not only &quot;books handed down from ancient times,&quot; but also &quot;books of modern times that bring information from super-ancient times through inspiration such as automatic writing.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen above, Kiyohiko AGO&apos;s concept of &apos;koshi koden (chokodai bunsho)&apos; is a broad one that includes not only &apos;books handed down from ancient times,&apos; but also &apos;books of modern times that brings information from super-ancient times through inspiration such as automatism.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>吾郷清彦による分類の発展</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expansion of classification by Kiyohiko AGO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expansion of classifications by Kiyohiko AGO</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expansion of classifications by Kiyohiko AGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>東亜四書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toa shisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toa shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toa shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>『契丹古伝』（『神頌叙伝』ともいう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kittan Koden&quot; (also called &quot;Shinin Joden&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kittan Koden&quot; (also called &quot;Shinin Joden&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kittan Koden&quot; (also called &quot;Shinin Joden&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>『桓檀古記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kandan Koki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kandan Koki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kandan Koki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>『香山宝巻』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kozan Hokan&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kozan Hokan&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kozan Hokan&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>『宝巻変文類』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>吾郷は「新しき世界へ」誌（日本CI協会刊）に寄稿した際「東亜四書」という項目を追加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When AGO contributed to &quot;Atarasikisekaie (literally, to new world) (published by Nippon CI Association), he added an item &quot;Toa Shisho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When AGO contributed to &quot;Atarashikisekaie (literally, to new world) (published by Nippon CI Association), he added an item &quot;Toa Shisho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Atarashikisekaie</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When AGO contributed to &apos;Atarashikisekaie (literally, to new world)&apos; (published by Nippon CI Association), he added an item &apos;Toa Shisho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="75">
<j>構想段階では『香山宝巻』『宝巻変文類』がなく『竹書紀年』『穆天子伝』だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the stage of idea, &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot; were not included and there was on &quot;Chikusho Kinen&quot; and &quot;Bokutenshiden.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the conceptual stage, &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot; weren&apos;t included, but &quot;Chikusho Kinen&quot; and &quot;Bokutenshiden&quot; were.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chikusho Kinen&quot; and &quot;Bokutenshiden&quot; were included but &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot; were not included the initial conceptual stage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>この両書を古史古伝だというのは無理があり、後の著作では『竹書紀年』『穆天子伝』をはずし『香山宝巻』『宝巻変文類』を入れた形で発表されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it is unreasonable to include both books in koshi koden, and his writings of the alter stage is published removing &quot;Chikusho Kinen&quot; and &quot;Bokutenshiden&quot; and adding &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it&apos;s unreasonable to include both books in koshi koden, and his writings of the latter stage are published by removing &quot;Chikusho Kinen&quot; and &quot;Bokutenshiden&quot; and adding &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it is unreasonable to consider &quot;Chikusho Kinen&quot; and &quot;Bokutenshiden&quot; as koshi koden, his later works removed these two books and added &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>しかし『香山宝巻』『宝巻変文類』は世間的には有名ではなかったが専門家の世界ではもとから知られたものであり、超古代史文書に入れるのは異論もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot; were not famous in the world, but they have been known in the world of specialists and, therefore, there is opposing view to included them in chokodaishi bunsho (super-ancient history documents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot; weren&apos;t famous in the world, but they have been known in the world of specialists; thus there is an opposing view that they should be included among the chokodaishi bunsho (super-ancient history documents).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;Kozan Hokan&quot; and &quot;Hokan Henbunrui&quot; were not known to the general public, but were known to specialists and some oppose considering them as chokodaishi bunsho (super-ancient history documents).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>ほかに東アジアに関連するものとして『山海経』『封神演義』をあげる論者もいるが、『山海経』は古来有名な古典であり、一方『封神演義』は小説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some mention &quot;Sankaikyo&quot; and &quot;Fujin Engi&quot; as East Asia related ones, but &quot;Sankaikyo&quot; is a famous classic since old time and, on the other hand, &quot;Fujin Engi&quot; is a novel.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some mention &quot;Sankaikyo&quot; and &quot;Fujin Engi&quot; as being related to East Asia, but &quot;Sankaikyo&quot; is a famous classic since old times and &quot;Fujin Engi,&quot; by contrast, is a novel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some mention &quot;Sankaikyo&quot; and &quot;Fujin Engi&quot; as being related to East Asia, but &quot;Sankaikyo&quot;has been a famous classic for a long time and &quot;Fujin Engi&quot; is a novel.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>いくら内容が面白いからといってもこの両書を古史古伝というのは無理がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if contents are interesting, it is unreasonable to say those two books are koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if the contents are interesting, it&apos;s unreasonable to say those two books are koshi koden.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unreasonable to consider these two books are koshi koden even if the content is interesting.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>それよりも『契丹古伝』や『桓檀古記』とならぶべき超古代文書といえば『南淵書』があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If we say chokodai monjo comparable to &quot;Kittan Koden&quot; and &quot;Kandan Koki,&quot; we can mention &quot;Nanensho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If we say chokodai monjo comparable to &quot;Kittan Koden&quot; and &quot;Kandan Koki,&quot; we can also mention &quot;Nanensho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nanensho&quot; would be a chokodai monjo comparable to &quot;Kittan Koden&quot; and &quot;Kandan Koki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>また『桓檀古記』は『癸園史話』や『檀奇古史』などの同系の書物とともに「檀君系文献群」として一括してよぶことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We can call &quot;Kandan Koki&quot; collectively with books in similar system such as &quot;Kien Shiwa&quot; and &quot;Danki Koshi&quot; as &quot;Dankun system literature group.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We can refer to &quot;Kandan Koki&quot; collectively with books in a similar system, such as &quot;Kien Shiwa&quot; and &quot;Danki Koshi&quot; as being of the &quot;Dankun system literature group.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We can collectively refer to &quot;Kandan Koki&quot;, together with similar books such as &quot;Kien Shiwa&quot; and &quot;Danki Koshi&quot;, as being of the &apos;Dankun system literature group.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>欧米の古史古伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshi koden in Europe and U.S.A.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshi koden in Europe and the U.S.A.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi koden in Europe and the U.S.A.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>『ウラ・リンダの書』（『ウラ・リンダ年代記』ともいう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Oera Linda Book&quot; (also, called &quot;Oera-Linda Chronicle&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Oera Linda Book&quot; (also called &quot;Oera-Linda Chronicle&quot;)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Oera Linda Book&quot; (also called &quot;Oera-Linda Chronicle&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>『OAHSPE』（オアフスペ、オアースプ等いろいろに読まれる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OAHSPE (pronounced in various ways such as oafuspe and oah-supu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OAHSPE (pronounced in various ways, such as oafuspe and oah-supu)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;OAHSPE&quot; (pronounced in various ways, such as oafuspe and oah-supu)</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合わせ&quot;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>『モルモン経』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Book of Mormon&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Book of Mormon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Book of Mormon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>『アカーシャ年代記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Akasha Chronicle&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Akasha Chronicle&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Akasha Chronicle&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>『OAHSPE』『モルモン経』『アカーシャ年代記』は古代から伝来した書物ではなく神の啓示とか、霊感や自動書記などになるものだが、それは古史古伝の定義上問題ないことは上述の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;OAHSPE&quot;, &quot;The Book of Mormon&quot; and &quot;Akasha Chronicle&quot; are not books handed down from the ancient time and correspond to revelation of god, inspiration or automatic writing and there is no problem in definition of koshi koden was described above..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;OAHSPE,&quot; &quot;The Book of Mormon&quot; and &quot;Akasha Chronicle&quot; aren&apos;t books handed down since ancient times but instead correspond to the revelation of God, inspiration or automatic writing; neither is there a problem in defining them as koshi koden, as described above.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OAHSPE, &quot;The Book of Mormon&quot; and &quot;Akasha Chronicle&quot; are not books handed down since ancient times but documents the revelation of God, inspiration or automatism but there is no problem in defining them as koshi koden as described above.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>他に『ネクロノミコン』『トートの書』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there are &quot;Necronomicon&quot; and &quot;THOTH.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there are &quot;Necronomicon&quot; and &quot;THOTH.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there are &quot;Necronomicon&quot; and &quot;THOTH.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>この両書は架空の書物だが、実在と信じる人もいるのでその場合は超古代文書の一種となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although those two books are fictional books, but there are some who believe they exist and in such case they become a kind of chokodai monjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the two works are fictional, there are some who believe they exist and in such case they become a kind of chokodai monjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the two works are fictional, there are some who believe they exist and in such case they become a kind of chokodai monjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>『阿蘇幣立神社文書』（『高天原動乱の秘録』ともいう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Aso Heiritsu Jinja Monjo&quot; (document so the Aso Heiritsu Jinja Shrine) (also called &quot;Takamagahara Doran no Hiroku&quot; (Secret record of disturbance in Takamagahara)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Aso Heiritsu Jinja Monjo&quot; (documents of the Aso Heiritsu Jinja Shrine) (also called &quot;Takamagahara Doran no Hiroku&quot; (Secret Record of the Disturbance in Takamagahara)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Aso Heiritsu Jinja Monjo&quot; (documents of Aso Heiritsu-jinja Shrine) (also called &quot;Takamagahara Doran no Hiroku&quot; (Secret Record of the Disturbance in Takamagahara),</e>
<cmt>Aso Heiritsu Jinja Shrine→Aso Heiritsu-jinja Shrine,補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>『美杜神字録』（「美しの杜物語」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot; (also, called &quot;Utsukushi no Mori Monogatari&quot; (story of beautiful woods))</e>
<cmt>書名の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot; (also, called &quot;Utsukushi no Mori Monogatari&quot; (Story of Beautiful Woods))</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Book by Naozumi OCHIAI (deciphered) is called &quot;Bisha Shinji Kai.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>落合直澄による著作（解読文）は『美杜神字解』という）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Writing by Naozumi OCHIAI (deciphered sentence) is called &quot;Bisha Shinji Kai&quot;)</e>
<cmt>書名の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Writing by Naozumi OCHIAI (deciphered sentence) is called &quot;Bisha Shinji Kai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Writing by Naozumi OCHIAI (deciphered sentence) is called &quot;Bisha Shinji Kai.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>『上代天皇紀』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jodai Tennoki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jodai Tennoki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jodai Tennoki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>「春日文書」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kasuga Bunsho&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kasuga Bunsho&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga Bunsho&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>『美杜神字録』は神代文字で書かれており定義からいえば「古伝四書」の方に入れてもよさそうではあるが、吾郷清彦はその件については特にふれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot; is written in ancient Japanese characters and, according to the definition, it could be included in &quot;Koden shisho&quot;, but Kiyohiko AGO did not mention it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot; is written in ancient Japanese characters and, according to the definition, it could be included in &quot;Koden shisho,&quot; but Kiyohiko AGO didn&apos;t mention it.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot; is written in ancient Japanese characters and, according to the definition, it could be included in &apos;Koden shisho,&apos; but Kiyohiko AGO didn&apos;t mention it.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>『美杜神字録』のように地方色豊かなものとしては他にも『甲斐古蹟考』がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As one similar to &quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot; which is rich in local taste, there is &quot;Kai Kosekiko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As one similar to &quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot; which is rich in local flavor, there is &quot;Kai Kosekiko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than &quot;Bisha Shinjiroku&quot;, the &quot;Kai Kosekiko&quot;is rich in regional flavor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>原田実はさらに『真清探當證』（ますみたんとうしょう）・『伊未自由来記』（いみじ・ゆらいき）・『肯搆泉達録』（かんかんせんだつろく）の三書をあげている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Minoru HARADA mentioned three books, &quot;Masumi Tantosho&quot;, &quot;Imiji Yuraiki&quot; and &quot;Kankansen Datsuroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Minoru HARADA mentioned three books: &quot;Masumi Tantosho,&quot; &quot;Imiji Yuraiki&quot; and &quot;Kankansen Datsuroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Minoru HARADA mentioned three books: &quot;Masumi Tantosho,&quot; &quot;Imiji Yuraiki&quot; and &quot;Kankansen Datsuroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="98">
<j>「春日文書」は言霊（ことだま）関係の文献であり歴史書ではないが、古史古伝には歴史書以外も含みうるのは、上述のカタカムナの場合と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kasuga Bunsho&quot; is a literature related to kotodama (spirit of language) and not a history book, but it is same as above-mentioned Katakamuna that koshi koden may contain books other than history book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kasuga Bunsho&quot; is literature related to kotodama (spirit of language) so it isn&apos;t a history book, but in a way similar to the above-mentioned Katakamuna, koshi koden may contain books other than history books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga Bunsho&apos; is a document related to kotodama (spirit of language) so it is not a history book, but as with the above-mentioned Katakamuna, koshi koden may contain books other than history books.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="99">
<j>これらの他にも「大伴文書」「安倍文書」「斎部文書」「清原文書」「久米文書」などがあるともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than those, it is said that there are &quot;Otomo Bunsho,&quot; &quot;Abe Bunsho,&quot; &quot;Inbe Bunsho,&quot; &quot;Kiyohara Bunsho&quot; and &quot;Kume Bunsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than those, it is said that there are &quot;Otomo Bunsho,&quot; &quot;Abe Bunsho,&quot; &quot;Inbe Bunsho,&quot; &quot;Kiyohara Bunsho&quot; and &quot;Kume Bunsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than those, it is said that there are &apos;Otomo Bunsho,&apos; &apos;Abe Bunsho,&apos; &apos;Inbe Bunsho,&apos; &apos;Kiyohara Bunsho&apos; and &apos;Kume Bunsho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>この五書は噂の域をでず詳細不明であり、実在しない可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those five documents are just rumored but their details are not known, and the possibility that they do not exist is high.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those five documents are only rumored, but their details aren&apos;t known it is very possible that they don&apos;t actually exist.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is very possible that these five documents do not actually exist since there are only rumors and details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Straysheep(id:42448), Fujikko(id:62756), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), 三竹修二郎(id:88082), Himazin(id:22034), うまやど(id:93760), Red Snake(id:45806), Charon(id:9162), Askr(id:202037), Murasagi(id:79122), 代言人(id:33675), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Oga(id:116), Point136(id:211299), Safkan(id:423), Corwin(id:973), Nopira(id:29335), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>