<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>とはずがたり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Towazugatari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towazugatari (&apos;The Confessions of Lady Nijo&apos;)</e>
<cmt>Added the English translation in parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towazugatari (The Confessions of Lady Nijo)</e>
<cmt>削除</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>とはずがたり（とわずがたり）とは、鎌倉時代の中後期に後深草院二条（ごふかくさいんのにじょう）が綴ったとみられる日記および紀行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Confessions of Lady Nijo (Towazugatari) is the diary and travel book thought to have been written by Nijo GOFUKAKUSA-IN (Lady Nijo) in the middle or late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>タイトルはより文字通りの訳として&quot;The unrequested tale&quot;&quot;A tale nobody asked for&quot;がありますが、より一般的なこちらを採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towazugatari&apos; is the diary and travel book thought to have been written by Nijo GOFUKAKUSA-IN (Lady Nijo) in the middle or late Kamakura period (1185-1333)</e>
<cmt>Removed the English translation since I already included it above. Added dates of Kamakura period as it helps give it historical context.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towazugatari is the diary and travel book thought to have been written by Nijo GOFUKAKUSA-IN (Lady Nijo) in the middle or late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>削除 (1185-1333)削除ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>誰に問われるでもなく自分の人生を語るという自伝形式で、後深草天皇に仕えた女房二条の14歳（1271年）から49歳（1306年）ごろまでの境遇を書いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Telling her story though asked by no one, it is written in an autobiographical style, recounting the life of Lady Nijo, Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s lady-in-waiting, from the age of 14 (1271) to around 49 (1306); it records her relationships with the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa and other lovers, ceremonies at court, and the travels she made after becoming a nun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although no one requested it (&apos;Towazugatari&apos; literally means &quot;a tale nobody asked for&quot;), Lady Nijo wrote her autobiographical tale as she served as Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s lady-in-waiting from the age of 14 (1271) to around 49 (1306). It records her relationships with the Cloistered (retired) Emperor Gofukakusa and other lovers, ceremonies at court, and her travels after becoming a nun.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Telling her story though asked by no one&quot; = &quot;Although no one requested it&quot;. Added literal translation of Towazugatari to make it a little clearer. I thought with &quot;autobiographical tale&quot;, &quot;recounting the life&quot; became redundant so I cut it. Changed &quot;the travels she made&quot; to &quot;her travels&quot; to be more succinct. I also added the meaning of &quot;cloistered&quot; as I don&apos;t think many native speakers will be aware of the term.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although no one requested it (&apos;Towazugatari&apos; literally means &quot;a tale nobody asked for&quot;), Lady Nijo wrote her autobiographical tale as she served as Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s lady-in-waiting from the age of 14 (1271) to around 49 (1306).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後深草院や恋人との関係、宮中行事、尼となってから出かけた旅の記録などが綴られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It records her relationships with the Gofukakusa-in and other lovers, ceremonies at court, and her travels after becoming a nun.</e>
<cmt>Cloistered (retired) Emperor削除 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>二条の告白という形だが、ある程度の物語的虚構性も含まれると見る研究者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in the form of a confession by Lady Nijo, but some scholars think that it also includes elements of narrative fiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in the form of a confession by Lady Nijo, but some scholars think that it also includes elements of narrative fiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in the form of a confession by Lady Nijo, but some scholars think that it also includes elements of narrative fiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>5巻5冊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has five books, five volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is comprised of five books in five volumes.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;has&quot; to &quot;comprised of&quot;as this sounds more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is comprised of five books in five volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1313年ごろまでに成立した模様。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems to have been written by approximately 1313.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems to have been completed by approximately 1313.</e>
<cmt>I changed &quot;written by&quot; to &quot;completed by&quot; to make it read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems to have been completed by approximately 1313.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>この日記は宮内庁書陵部所蔵の桂宮蔵書に含まれていた桂宮本（後代―江戸時代前期の写本）のみ現存。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only existing version of this diary is the Katsura no Miya text (a manuscript written in 後代 - the early Edo period)included in the Katsura no Miya collection owned by the Imperial Household Archives.</e>
<cmt>原文「後代」いつかの時代の後期かと思われるが、意味不明なため訳出できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only existing version of this diary is the Katsura no Miya text (a manuscript written in 後代 - the early Edo period)included in the Katsura no Miya collection owned by the Imperial Household Archives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only existing version of this diary is the Katsura no Miya text (a manuscript written in 後代 - the early Edo period)included in the Katsura no Miya collection owned by the Imperial Household Archives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1940年（昭和15年）山岸徳平により紹介されるまでは、その存在を知る人も少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until found in 1940 by Tokuhei YAMAGISHI, its existence had been known to very few people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until found in 1940 by Tokuhei YAMAGISHI, its existence had been known to very few people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until found in 1940 by Tokuhei YAMAGISHI, its existence had been known to very few people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>書陵部（当時は図書寮）で『とはずがたり』を見出した山岸徳平は『蜻蛉日記』にも対等すると直感したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokuhei YAMAGISHI, when he discovered &quot;The Confessions of Lady Nijo&quot; in the Imperial Household Archive (at that time the Bureau of Drawings and Books) felt by intuition that it was equal to even &quot;The Gossamer Years&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tokuhei YAMAGISHI discovered &apos;Towazugatari&apos; in the Imperial Household Archive (at that time known as the Bureau of Drawings and Books), he felt intuitively that it was equal to even &quot;The Gossamer Years&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Changed the word order to start the sentence with &quot;when&quot; and changed &quot;by intuition&quot; to &quot;intuitively&quot; so it reads more naturally. Used the Japanese title of the book to keep it consistent with how it is written elsewhere in the translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tokuhei YAMAGISHI discovered &quot;Towazugatari&quot; in the Imperial Household Archive (at that time known as the Bureau of Drawings and Books), he felt intuitively that it was equal to even &quot;Kagero Nikki&quot; (The Gossamer Years).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kagero Nikki&quot; 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼により「国語と国文学」9月号で「とはずがたり覚書」という形で紹介された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The work was introduced by his article &apos;Notes on Towazugatari&apos;, in the September issue of &apos;Kokugo to Kokubungaku&apos; (Japanese Language and Literature).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The work was introduced in his article &apos;Notes on Towazugatari&apos;, in the September issue of &apos;Kokugo to Kokubungaku&apos; (Japanese Language and Literature).</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;by&quot; to &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The work was introduced in his article &apos;Notes on Towazugatari,&apos; in the September issue of &apos;Kokugo to Kokubungaku&apos; (Japanese Language and Literature).</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一般への公開は1950年（昭和25年）の桂宮本叢書第15巻が初。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its first publication was in the 15th volume of the Katsura no Miya series of texts in 1950.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its first publication was in the 15th volume of the Katsura no Miya series of texts in 1950.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its first publication was in the 15th volume of the Katsura no Miya series of texts in 1950.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお鎌倉時代後期にさかのぼるとみられる古写本一種類の断簡が数点知られるが、本文は書陵部本と差異が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are several fragments of an old manuscript regarded as going back to the late Kamakura period, the text is strikingly different from the Imperial Household Archive version.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although several fragments of an old manuscript exist that are believed to date from the late Kamakura period, the text is strikingly different from the Imperial Household Archive version.</e>
<cmt>Omitted &quot;there are&quot; in favour of &quot;exist&quot; and changed &quot;regarded as going back to&quot; to &quot;believed to date from&quot; to make the sentence read a little smoother and more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although several fragments of an old manuscript exist that are believed to date from the late Kamakura period, the text is strikingly different from the Imperial Household Archive version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>主な登場人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main Characters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main Characters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main characters</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>「二条」：久我雅忠の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lady Nijo&apos;: the daughter of Masatada KOGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lady Nijo&apos;: the daughter of Masatada KOGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lady Nijo&apos;: the daughter of Masatada KOGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「あかこ」と呼ばれ童名とする説と、吾が子（あがこ）とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was called &apos;Akako&apos;, regarded as her childhood name by one theory, taken to mean &quot;my child&quot; (a ga ko) by another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was either called &apos;Akako&apos;, (thought to be her childhood name) according to one theory, or &apos;Agako&apos; (&quot;my child&quot;) according to another.</e>
<cmt>Changed the order of the sentence to make the issue of her names a bit less confusing. Changed &quot;regarded as&quot; to &quot;thought to be&quot;,added &quot;either&quot; and changed &quot;by&quot; to &quot;according to&quot; to make the sentence read a bit more naturally. Removed &quot;taken to mean&quot; as I thought it was redundant.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was either called &apos;Akako,&apos; (thought to be her childhood name) according to one theory, or &apos;Agako&apos; (&quot;my child&quot;) according to another.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>「後深草天皇」：太上天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;: the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;: the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;: the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>二条の主人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijo&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijo&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijo&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>「亀山天皇」：後深草院の弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama&apos;: the brother of Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kameyama&apos;: the brother of Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kameyama&apos;: the brother of Gofukakusa-in.</e>
<cmt>Cloistered Emperor削除in補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>「雪の曙」：西園寺実兼と見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Snow Dawn&apos;: taken to be Sanekane SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Snow Dawn&apos;: thought to be Sanekane SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Thought&quot; seems a little clearer than &quot;taken&quot; in this context</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Snow Dawn&apos;: thought to be Sanekane SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>「有明の月」：阿闍梨。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dawn Moon&apos;: an ajari (holy teacher)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dawn Moon&apos;: an ajari (holy teacher)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dawn Moon&apos;: an ajari (holy teacher)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>性助法親王と見られるが、法助法親王説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taken to be the Cloistered Prince Shojo, though another theory regards him as the Cloistered Prince Hojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thought to be the Cloistered Prince Shojo, though another theory believes him to be the Cloistered Prince Hojo.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;taken&quot; to &quot;thought&quot; as above. Changed &quot;regarded as&quot; to &quot;believed him to be&quot; to sound a bit more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thought to be the Cloistered Imperial Prince Shojo, although another theory believes him to be the Cloistered Imperial Prince Hojo.</e>
<cmt>Imperial補足&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>「近衛大殿」：鷹司兼平と見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Guards Minister&apos;: taken to be Kanehira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minister of the Imperial Guard&apos;: thought to be Kanehira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Imperial Guards Minister&quot; to &quot;Minister of the Imperial Guard&quot;to read more naturally. Changed &quot;taken&quot; as above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minister of the Imperial Guard&apos;: thought to be Kanehira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>第1巻：二条は2歳の時に母を亡くし4歳からは後深草院のもとで育てられ、14歳にして他に想い人「雪の曙」がいるにも関わらず、後深草院の寵を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first volume: Lady Nijo loses her mother at the age of 2, is taken under the wing of the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa at 4, and receives Gofukakusa&apos;s favor at the age of 14, despite having &apos;Snow Dawn&apos;, a man she feels deeply about.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first volume: Lady Nijo loses her mother at the age of 2, is taken under the wing of the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa at 4, and accepts his affections at the age of 14, despite the presence of &apos;Snow Dawn&apos;, a man she feels deeply about.</e>
<cmt>Cut the second &quot;Gofukakusa&quot; as it is redundant. Changed &quot;favor&quot; to &quot;affections&quot; for the translation of 「寵」 to make the meaning a bit clearer (although I think &quot;concubine&quot; may be more accurate, I wasn&apos;t sure if that was an appropriate translation of 「寵」). Changed &quot;having&quot; to &quot;the presence of&quot; so it reads more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first volume: Lady Nijo loses her mother at the age of 2, is taken under the wing of the Gofukakusa-in at 4, and accepts his affections at the age of 14, despite the presence of &apos;Snow Dawn,&apos; a man she feels deeply about.</e>
<cmt>Cloistered Emperor削除in補足コンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>院の子を懐妊、程なく父が死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She becomes pregnant with the child of the Cloistered Emperor, and soon after her father dies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She becomes pregnant with the child of the Cloistered Emperor, and soon after her father dies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She becomes pregnant with the child of the Cloistered Emperor, and soon after her father dies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>皇子を産む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gives birth to the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gives birth to the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gives birth to the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>後ろ楯を亡くしたまま、女房として院に仕え続けるが、雪の曙との関係も続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although she keeps serving the Cloistered Emperor as a lady-in-waiting with her support now gone, her relationship with Snow Dawn also continues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite losing her support she continues to serve the Cloistered Emperor as a lady-in-waiting, while also continuing her relationship with &apos;Snow Dawn&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Who did she lose the support of? It would be nice to include that for clarification. Changed &quot;although&quot; to &quot;despite&quot; so it sounds more natural. Changed &quot;support&quot; to &quot;patronage&quot; in keeping with what I wrote above. Changed &quot;her relationship with Snow Dawn also continues&quot; to &quot;while also continuing her relationship with Snow Dawn&quot; as this reads more naturally to me.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite losing her support she continues to serve the Cloistered Emperor as a lady-in-waiting, while also continuing her relationship with &apos;Snow Dawn.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>雪の曙の女児を産むが、他所へやる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gives birth to Snow Dawn&apos;s daughter, but gives her away to someone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gives birth to Snow Dawn&apos;s daughter, but gives her away.</e>
<cmt>Cut &quot;to someone&quot; as I felt it was redundant.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gives birth to Snow Dawn&apos;s daughter, but gives her away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>ほぼ同じ頃、皇子夭逝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s son dies prematurely at almost the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s son dies prematurely at about the same time.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;almost&quot; to &quot;about&quot; so it reads more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s son dies prematurely at about the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>第2巻：粥杖騒動と贖い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second volume: the commotion over the rice-gruel stick and the atonement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second volume: the commotion over the rice-gruel stick and atonement.</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;the&quot; before atonement. Unsure about 粥杖騒動- &quot;rice gruel stick&quot; is confusing but I can&apos;t come up with a better translation for 粥杖.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second volume: the commotion over the rice-gruel stick and atonement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>「有明の月」に迫られて契る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She begins a relationship with &apos;Dawn Moon&apos; at his urging.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She begins a relationship with &apos;Dawn Moon&apos; on his insistence.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;at his urging&quot; to &quot;on his insistence&quot; which I think sounds more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She begins a relationship with &apos;Dawn Moon&apos; on his insistence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>女楽で祖父の兵部卿四条隆親と衝突。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At onnagaku (women&apos;s music), she clashes with her grandfather Takachika SHIJO, Minister of War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At onnagaku (a musical performace by women peformed for the Imperial court), she clashes with her grandfather Takachika SHIJO, Minister of War.</e>
<cmt>Added an explanation for 女楽</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At onnagaku (a musical performance by women performed for the Imperial court), she clashes with her grandfather Takachika SHIJO, Minister of War.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>「近衛大殿」と心ならずも契る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She unwillingly begins a relationship with the &apos;Imperial Guards Minister&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She unwillingly begins a relationship with the Minister of the Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Imperial Guards Minister&quot; in keeping with what I wrote above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She unwillingly begins a relationship with the Minister of the Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>第3巻：有明の月の男児を産むが他所へやる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third volume: she gives birth to Dawn Moon&apos;s son, but gives him away to someone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third volume: she gives birth to &apos;Dawn Moon&apos;s&apos; son, but gives him away.</e>
<cmt>Cut &quot;to someone&quot; as above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third volume: she gives birth to Dawn Moon&apos;s son, but gives him away.</e>
<cmt>削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>有明死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dawn Moon&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dawn Moon&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dawn Moon&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>有明の男児を再び産むが、今回は自らも世話をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gives birth to another son by Dawn Moon, but this time looks after him herself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gives birth to another son by &apos;Dawn Moon&apos;, but this time she looks after him herself.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;she&quot; to make it read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gives birth to another son by Dawn Moon, but this time she looks after him herself.</e>
<cmt>削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>御所を退出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She leaves the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She leaves the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She leaves the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>第4巻：尼となったのちの日々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth volume: the days after becoming a nun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth volume: the days after becoming a nun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth volume: the days after becoming a nun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>熱田神宮から、鎌倉、善光寺、浅草へ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She travels to Atsuta-jingu shrine, then to Kamakura, Zenko-ji Temple, and Asakusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Atsuta-jingu shrine, she travels to Kamakura, Zenko-ji Temple, and Asakusa.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order to read a little smoother and be closer to the original Japanese.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Atsuta-jingu Shrine, she travels to Kamakura, Zenko-ji Temple, and Asakusa.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>八幡宮で後深草法皇に再会。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She meets the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa again at Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She meets the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa again at Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She meets the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa again at Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>伊勢へ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She travels to Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She travels to Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She travels to Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="40">
<j>第5巻：厳島へ、後深草院死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifth volume: She travels to Itsukushima, Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa dies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth volume: She travels to Itsukushima, and the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa dies.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;and the&quot; to separate the clauses.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth volume: She travels to Itsukushima, and the Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa dies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>跋文。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The epilogue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The epilogue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The epilogue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>『源氏物語』の影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>若紫：後深草院は想いを寄せていた自身の乳母であった、大納言典侍（だいなごんのすけ）の娘である二条を引き取るが、これは多分に『源氏物語』の若紫を連想させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Young Murasaki: where Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa takes and raises Nijo, the daughter of his nursemaid Dainagon-no-suke for whom he had feelings, it is strongly reminiscent of Young Murasaki in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Young Murasaki: The passage where Cloistered Emperor Gofukakusa takes and raises Lady Nijo, the daughter of his beloved nursemaid Dainagon-no-suke, is strongly reminiscent of Young Murasaki in &apos;The Tale of Genji&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the passage&quot; before &quot;where&quot; so we are made immdiately aware that we are referring to a section of the book. Changed &quot;for whom he had feelings&quot; to &quot;beloved&quot; to make it a bit less clumsy. Added &quot;Lady&quot; before &quot;Nijo&quot; for the sake of continuity. Removed &quot;it&quot; so it reads more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Young Murasaki: The passage where Gofukakusa-in takes and raises Lady Nijo, the daughter of his beloved wet nurse Dainagon-no-suke, is strongly reminiscent of Young Murasaki in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Cloistered Emperor削除ピリオド位置&quot;nursemaid&quot;→&quot;wet nurse&quot;に変更しました。&apos;The Tale of Genji.&apos;→&quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>女楽：若菜・下巻にある女楽を模して行うことになったが、紫の上に東の御方、女三宮に祖父隆親の娘があてられ、二条は一番身分の低い明石の御方として琵琶を弾くこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onnagaku: when onnagaku is held following the example of the second volume of Wakana (New Herbs), the lady of the east wing is like Murasaki-no-ue (Lady Murasaki), the daughter of Nijo&apos;s grandfather Takachika like the Third Princess, and Nijo herself playing the Biwa lute like Akashi-no-okata (Lady Akashi), the most humble of the three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onnagaku: An onnagaku is held imitating the one held in the second volume of Wakana (&apos;New Herbs&apos;, a book from &apos;The Tale of Genji&apos;), in which the lady of the east wing represents Murasaki-no-ue (Lady Murasaki), the daughter of Nijo&apos;s grandfather, Takachika, represents Onnasan-no-miya (the Third Princess), and Lady Nijo herself, playing the Biwa lute, represents Akashi-no-okata (Lady Akashi), the most humble of the three.</e>
<cmt>After some Googling, I added that Wakana was from &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; for clarity. Changed &quot;followed&quot; to &quot;imitating&quot; to be less confusing. Added &quot;in which&quot; to make it read a little more naturally. Changed &quot;is like&quot; to &quot;represents&quot; to make it less confusing.. Added commas to punctuate the sentences to make them easier to read. Added the romanji reading of 女三宮 for consistancy. Added &quot;Lady&quot; to &quot;Nijo&quot; as above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onnagaku: An onnagaku is held imitating the one held in the second volume of Wakana (&apos;New Herbs,&apos; a book from &apos;The Tale of Genji&apos;), in which the lady of the east wing represents Murasaki-no-ue (Lady Murasaki), the daughter of Nijo&apos;s grandfather, Takachika, represents Onnasan-no-miya (the Third Princess), and Lady Nijo herself, playing the Biwa lute, represents Akashi-no-okata (Lady Akashi), the most humble of the three.</e>
<cmt>コンマ位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>『増鏡』との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Connections with &quot;The Clear Mirror&quot; (Masukagami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Connections with Masukagami (&apos;The Clear Mirror&apos;)</e>
<cmt>Put the English translation in parenthesis to keep it consistent with how it is written elsewhere in the translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Connections with &quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror)</e>
<cmt>Masukagami (&apos;The Clear Mirror&apos;)→&quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror)に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>『増鏡』（南北朝時代_(日本)成立）には『とはずがたり』の文章が数段に渡って用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Clear Mirror&quot; (written in the Northern and Southern Courts period (Japan)) uses several paragraphs from &quot;The Confessions of Lady Nijo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masukagami&apos; (written in the Northern and Southern Courts period of Japan) uses several paragraphs from &apos;Towazugatari&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Used original Japanese titles for consistency reasons as above. Replaced &quot;(Japan)&quot; with &quot;of Japan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Masukagami&quot; (written in the Northern and Southern Court period of Japan) uses several paragraphs from &quot;Towazugatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>→&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また、『とはずがたり』発見以前には後深草天皇の女性関係に関する記録が乏しく、『増鏡』における同天皇の女性関係の記述を創作あるいは弟の亀山天皇のものとの誤認説を唱える学者もいたが、この書の発見以後『増鏡』の記述に根拠がある事が確認された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, because there were very few records of Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s romances before &quot;The Confessions of Lady Nijo&quot; was found, some scholars used to think that the descriptions of his romances in &quot;The Clear Mirror&quot; were fictional or had been confused with those of his brother Emperor Kameyama, but after the discovery of &apos;The Confessions of Nijo&apos;, it was confirmed that there was a basis for the descriptions in &quot;The Clear Mirror&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, because there were very few records of Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s romances before &apos;Towazugatari&apos; was found, some scholars used to think that the descriptions of his romances in &apos;Masukagami&apos; were fictional or had been confused with those of his brother Emperor Kameyama, but after the discovery of &apos;Towazugatari&apos;, it was confirmed that there was a basis for the descriptions in &apos;Masukagami&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Used original Japanese titles for consistency reasons as above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, because there were very few records of Emperor Gofukakusa&apos;s romances before &quot;Towazugatari&quot; was found, some scholars used to think that the descriptions of his romances in &quot;Masukagami&quot; were fictional or had been confused with those of his brother Emperor Kameyama, but after the discovery of &quot;Towazugatari,&quot; it was confirmed that there was a basis for the descriptions in &quot;Masukagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>コンマとピリオド位置移動&apos;→&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Yelm(id:33836), Mooko(id:36162), Ceridwen(id:36889), Miya(id:1881), 水野白楓(id:22811), JF-Sydney Library(id:82008), MIO(id:31681), YOSHI438(id:174755), Yuming(id:17854), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>