<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤裏葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji no uraba (Wisteria Leaves)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji no uraba (Wisteria Leaves)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji no uraba (Wisteria Leaves)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤裏葉（ふじのうらば）は、『源氏物語』五十四帖の巻名のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji no uraba is one of the 54 chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji no uraba is one of the 54 chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji no uraba is one of the 54 chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第33帖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the 33rd chapter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the 33rd chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the 33rd chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>巻名は頭中将が詠んだ和歌「春日さす藤の裏葉のうらとけて君し思はば我も頼まむ」に因む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The title of this chapter was derived from the waka poetry which Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) composed: &quot;New leaves of wisteria in the sunlight of spring; if you open your heart to me, I will place my trust in you.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title of this chapter was derived from the waka poem that Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) composed: &quot;New leaves of wisteria in the sunlight of spring; if you open your heart to me, I will place my trust in you.&quot;</e>
<cmt>poetry-&gt;poemwhich-&gt;that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of this chapter was derived from the waka poem that To no Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) composed: &quot;New leaves of wisteria in the sunlight of spring; if you open your heart to me, I will place my trust in you.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました→To no Chujo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>光源氏39歳の話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikaru Genji, age 39.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikaru Genji, age 39.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikaru Genji, age 39.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>四月、内大臣は自邸で藤の花の宴を開き、その場でかねての仲であった娘の雲居の雁と夕霧の結婚を認める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, Minister of the Palace held a flower festival at his residence, and approved a marriage between his daughter, Kumoi no Kari, and Yugiri, who had been in love with each other for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, the Minister of the Palace held a flower festival at his residence, and approved a marriage between his daughter, Kumoi no Kari, and Yugiri, who had been in love with each other for a long time.</e>
<cmt>added article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, the Minister of the Palace held a flower festival at his residence, and approved a marriage between his daughter, Kumoi no Kari, and Yugiri, who had been in love with each other for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>仲睦まじい夫婦の誕生に、光源氏も内大臣もこの結婚を喜んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Hikaru Genji and Minister of the Palace were pleased with the happy newlyweds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Hikaru Genji and the Minister of the Palace were pleased with the happy newlyweds.</e>
<cmt>added article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Hikaru Genji and the Minister of the Palace were pleased with the happy newlyweds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>一方、光源氏の娘明石の姫君は宮中入りが決まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, it was decided that Hikaru Genji&apos;s daughter, young lady Akashi would enter the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, it was decided that Hikaru Genji&apos;s daughter, young lady Akashi, would enter the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, it was decided that Hikaru Genji&apos;s daughter, young lady Akashi, would enter the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>養母紫の上は実母明石の御方に配慮し、後見役を譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki no ue, an adoptive mother, considered Lady Akashi, the birth mother, and gave the role of guardian to her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki no ue gave up the role of guardian to Lady Akashi, the birth mother.</e>
<cmt>reworded to sound more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki no ue gave up the role of guardian to Lady Akashi, the birth mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>姫が入内し、入れ違いになった二人の母は初めて対面する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When their daughters entered the Imperial court as a bride, the two mothers passed each other, which was their first meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two mothers first met when their daughter entered the Imperial court as a bride, and they changed positions with each other.</e>
<cmt>I think that “daughter” should be singular here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two mothers first met when their daughter entered the Imperial Court as a bride, and they changed positions with each other.</e>
<cmt>Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>互いに相手の美点を見いだして認め合った二人はこれまでのわだかまりも氷解し、心を通わせるのだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They found out their virtues and approved of each other, so the ill feeling between the two has been dispelled and they understood each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They saw each other&apos;s virtues and approved of each other, so there was no ill feeling and they reached an understanding.</e>
<cmt>reworded to sound more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They saw each other&apos;s virtues and approved of each other, so there was no ill feeling and they reached an understanding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>秋になり、四十の賀を控えて光源氏は准太上天皇の待遇を受け、内大臣が太政大臣に昇任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In autumn, Hikaru Genji, having his 40th birthday ceremony imminent, came to be treated as Jun Daijo tenno (quasi ex-emperor) and Minister of the Palace got promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In autumn, Hikaru Genji, approaching his 40th birthday celebration, came to be treated as Jun Daijo tenno (quasi ex-emperor) and the Minister of the Palace got promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>“imminent” seemed a bit stiff an expression for an upcoming birthday</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In autumn, Hikaru Genji, approaching his 40th birthday celebration, came to be treated as Jun Daijo tenno (quasi ex-emperor) and the Minister of the Palace got promoted to Daijo daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>Daijo daijin、ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>十一月、紅葉の六条院へ冷泉帝と朱雀帝が揃って行幸し、華やかな宴が催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, Emperor Reizei and Emperor Suzaku went to the Rokujo-in Palace together, where a splendid banquet was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, Emperor Reizei and Emperor Suzaku went to the Rokujo-in Palace together, where a splendid banquet was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, Emperor Reizei and Emperor Suzaku went to the Rokujo-in Palace together, where a splendid banquet was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>かくて、少年の日の高麗人の予言は実現を見、光源氏は栄華の絶頂に立ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And thus, the prophecy which Hikaru Genji was told when he was a boy by a person from Goryeo, came true, and he was in the height of his prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And thus, the prophecy that Hikaru Genji was told by someone from Goryeo when he was a boy came true, and he was in the height of his prosperity.</e>
<cmt>changed order of phrases to improve flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And thus, the prophecy that Hikaru Genji was told by someone from Goryeo when he was a boy came true, and he was in the height of his prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), Masyu(id:31065), 亘(id:74738), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>