<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺実定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesada TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesada TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesada TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 実定（とくだいじ さねさだ、保延5年（1139年） - 建久2年12月16日 (旧暦)（1192年2月1日））は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけての公家・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesada TOKUDAIJI (born 1139, died February 1, 1192 according to the modern calendar) was a court noble and poet who lived in the closing days of the Heian period and into the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesada TOKUDAIJI (born 1139, died February 1, 1192 according to the modern calendar) was a court noble and poet who lived in the closing days of the Heian period and into the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesada TOKUDAIJI (1139 - February 1, 1192) was a court noble and poet who lived in the closing days of the Heian period and into the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>日付の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は徳大寺公能（きんよし）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kin&apos;yoshi TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kin&apos;yoshi TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原俊忠の娘豪子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Goshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Goshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Goshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原俊成の甥、藤原定家の従兄弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the nephew of FUJIWARA no Toshinari (Shunzei), and the cousin of FUJIWARA no Teika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the nephew of FUJIWARA no Toshinari (Shunzei), and the cousin of FUJIWARA no Teika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the nephew of FUJIWARA no Toshinari (Shunzei), and the cousin of FUJIWARA no Teika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major events in his life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major events in his life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>天養元年（1144年）に叙爵してから順調に昇進を重ねて、保元元年（1156年）11月に従三位に叙任して公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his first court rank was conferred upon him in 1144 (Tenyo 1), he received a steady stream of promotions, until in the eleventh month of 1156 (Hogen 1), he was invested with the Junior Third Rank and began to be counted a high-ranking court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his first court rank was conferred upon him in 1144 (Tenyo 1), he received a steady stream of promotions, until in the eleventh month of 1156 (Hogen 1), he was invested with the Junior Third Rank and began to be counted a high-ranking court noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his first court rank was conferred upon him in 1144, he received a steady stream of promotions, until in the eleventh month of 1156, he was invested with the Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and began to be counted a high-ranking court noble.</e>
<cmt>元号削除Jusanmi補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）には権大納言へ昇り、翌年、これを辞して正二位に叙任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1164 (Chokan 2), he reached the rank of Gon-Dainagon (Surrogate Major Counselor), and the following year resigned when he ascended to Second Rank, Senior Grade at court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1164 (Chokan 2), he reached the rank of Gon-Dainagon (Surrogate Major Counselor), and the following year resigned when he ascended to Second Rank, Senior Grade at court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1164, he reached the rank of Gon-Dainagon (Surrogate Major Counselor), and the following year resigned when he ascended to Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>元号削除Second Rank, Senior Grade at court→Shonii (Senior Second Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『著聞集』によれば、同官で越階された藤原実長を越え返すためであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Chomonju&quot; (Collected Anecdotes (Ancient and Modern)) this was in order to surpass FUJIWARA no Sanenaga, who in turn had risen beyond him in rank while working in the same department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Chomonju (Collected Anecdotes (Ancient and Modern)) this was in order to surpass FUJIWARA no Sanenaga, who in turn had risen beyond him in rank while working in the same department.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Chomonju&quot; (Collected Anecdotes (Ancient and Modern)) this was in order to surpass FUJIWARA no Sanenaga, who in turn had risen beyond him in rank while working in the same department.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>治承元年（1177年）3月、大納言に還任し、12月には左近衛大将を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the third month of 1177 (Jisho 1), he was named a Dainagon (Major Counselor), and then in the twelfth month was also made Sakonoe Daisho, or Commander of the Left Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the third month of 1177 (Jisho 1), he was named a Dainagon (Major Counselor), and then in the twelfth month was also made Sakonoe Daisho, or Commander of the Left Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the third month of 1177, he was named a Dainagon (chief councilor of state), and then in the twelfth month was also made Sakonoe Daisho, or Commander of the Left Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt>元号削除&quot;(Major Counselor)&quot;→&quot;(chief councilor of state)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この人事に関して『平家物語』は実定が平清盛の同情を乞うために厳島神社に参詣したためと語っているが、実際に実定が厳島を参詣したのは2年後の治承3年（1179年）3月である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning these assignments, the &quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heike) claims that Sanesada went on a pilgrimage to Itsukushima (Miyajima) shrine at this point in order to elicit the sympathy of TAIRA no Kiyomori, but in actuality, he did not set off on his pilgrimage then but two years later, in the third month of 1179 (Jisho 3).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning these assignments, the Heike monogatari (Tale of the Heike) claims that Sanesada went on a pilgrimage to Itsukushima (Miyajima) shrine at this point in order to elicit the sympathy of TAIRA no Kiyomori, but in actuality, he did not set off on his pilgrimage then but two years later, in the third month of 1179 (Jisho 3).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning these assignments, the &quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heike) claims that Sanesada went on a pilgrimage to Itsukushima (Miyajima) Shrine at this point in order to elicit the sympathy of TAIRA no Kiyomori, but in actuality, he did not set off on his pilgrimage then but two years later, in the third month of 1179.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足スペルを修正元号削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寿永二年（1183年）内大臣となるが、同年11月におこった源義仲の法住寺合戦によるクーデターの際に法皇派公卿として解官される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Naidaijin (Grand Minister of the Center) in 1183 (Juei 2), but as a court noble loyal to the Imperial faction, he was dismissed from his position during the coup d&apos;etat launched by means of the battle at Hojuji temple instigated in the eleventh month of 1183 by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Naidaijin (Grand Minister of the Center) in 1183 (Juei 2), but as a court noble loyal to the Imperial faction, he was dismissed from his position during the coup d&apos;etat launched by means of the battle at Hojuji temple instigated in the eleventh month of 1183 by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Naidaijin (Grand Minister of the Center) in 1183, but as a court noble loyal to the Imperial faction, he was dismissed from his position during the coup d&apos;etat launched by means of the battle at Hoju-ji Temple instigated in the eleventh month of 1183 by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>元号削除寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし翌年1月には義仲が敗死したことで復官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But with Yoshinaka&apos;s defeat and death in the first month of the following year, Sanesada was restored to his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But with Yoshinaka&apos;s defeat and death in the first month of the following year, Sanesada was restored to his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But with Yoshinaka&apos;s defeat and death in the first month of the following year, Sanesada was restored to his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後の源義経と後白河法皇による源頼朝追討院宣には慎重な姿勢を示したので、義経亡命後、源頼朝の推挙で議奏公卿十人の一人に押され、文治2年（1186年）10月には右大臣、文治5年（1189年）7月に左大臣となり、世に後徳大寺左大臣と称されて、九条兼実の片腕として朝幕関係の取り次ぎに活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he showed prudence and caution in how he responded to the Imperial decree to hunt down and destroy MINAMOTO no Yoritomo requested by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and issued by the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa, so that even after Yoshitsune fled the capital, upon Yoritomo&apos;s recommendation he was pressed into service as one member of his ten-man council of nobles; in the tenth month of 1186 (Bunji 2) he was made Udaijin (Grand Minister of the Right), and then in the seventh month of 1189 (Bunji 5) he ascended to Sadaijin (Grand Minister of the Left), thereafter becoming popularly known as &quot;Tokudaiji Sadaijin,&quot; and working as Kanezane KUJO&apos;s right-hand man to facilitate relations between the court and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he showed prudence and caution in how he responded to the Imperial decree to hunt down and destroy MINAMOTO no Yoritomo requested by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and issued by the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa, so that even after Yoshitsune fled the capital, upon Yoritomo&apos;s recommendation he was pressed into service as one member of his ten-man council of nobles; in the tenth month of 1186 (Bunji 2) he was made Udaijin (Grand Minister of the Right), and then in the seventh month of 1189 (Bunji 5) he ascended to Sadaijin (Grand Minister of the Left), thereafter becoming popularly known as &quot;Tokudaiji Sadaijin,&quot; and working as Kanezane KUJO&apos;s right-hand man to facilitate relations between the court and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he showed prudence and caution in how he responded to the Imperial decree to hunt down and destroy MINAMOTO no Yoritomo requested by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and issued by the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, so that even after Yoshitsune fled the capital, upon Yoritomo&apos;s recommendation he was pressed into service as one member of his ten-man council of nobles; in the tenth month of 1186 he was made Udaijin (Minister of the Right), and then in the seventh month of 1189 he ascended to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left), thereafter becoming popularly known as &quot;Tokudaiji Sadaijin,&quot; and working as Kanezane KUJO&apos;s right-hand man to facilitate relations between the court and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>天皇表記元号削除&quot;Grand Minister of the Right&quot;→&quot;Minister of the Right&quot;に変更しました。&quot;Grand Minister of the Left&quot;→&quot;Minister of the Left&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>建久2年（1191年）6月20日、病のため官を辞して出家、法名は如円。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 20th day of the sixth month of 1191 (Kenkyu 2), he resigned his position due to illness and took the tonsure, receiving the priestly name &quot;Nyoen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 20th day of the sixth month of 1191 (Kenkyu 2), he resigned his position due to illness and took the tonsure, receiving the priestly name &quot;Nyoen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 20th day of the sixth month of 1191, he resigned his position due to illness and took the tonsure, receiving the priestly name Nyoen.</e>
<cmt>元号削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同年閏12月16日に薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died that same year, on the sixteenth day of the intercalary twelfth month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died that same year, on the sixteenth day of the intercalary twelfth month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died that same year, on the sixteenth day of the intercalary twelfth month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>享年53。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was fifty-three years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was fifty-three years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was fifty-three years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>その死について『吾妻鏡』は「幕下（源頼朝）殊に溜息し給う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Azuma kagami (Mirror of the East) describes the reaction to news of his death: &quot;Yoritomo in particular heaved a great sigh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Azuma kagami (Mirror of the East) describes the reaction to news of his death: &quot;Yoritomo in particular heaved a great sigh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Azuma kagami&quot; (Mirror of the East) describes the reaction to news of his death: &apos;Yoritomo in particular heaved a great sigh.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>関東由緒あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was of the Kanto lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was of the Kanto lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was of the Kanto lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>日来重んぜらるる所也」と書いてあり源頼朝の信頼ぶりがうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was always held in high esteem,&quot; revealing just how much confidence Yoritomo had held in Sanesada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was always held in high esteem,&quot; revealing just how much confidence Yoritomo had held in Sanesada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was always held in high esteem,&apos; revealing just how much confidence MINAMOTO no Yoritomo had held in Sanesada.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;MINAMOTO no補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また文才があり『庭槐抄』（『槐林記』ともいう）という治承・寿永年間（1177年 - 1185年）の行幸に関する記録を抄出した日記を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also possessed considerable literary talents, as evidenced by excerpts of entries describing Imperial state visits from 1177-1185 (covering the Jisho and Juei eras) in the diary he left behind, the &quot;Teikaisho&quot; (also known as the Kairinki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also possessed considerable literary talents, as evidenced by excerpts of entries describing Imperial state visits from 1177-1185 (covering the Jisho and Juei eras) in the diary he left behind, the Teikaisho (also known as the Kairinki).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also possessed considerable literary talents, as evidenced by excerpts of entries describing Imperial state visits from 1177-1185 in the diary he left behind, the &quot;Teikaisho&quot; (also known as the &quot;Kairinki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>元号削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>他にも『掌函補抄』10巻の著述が存在したらしいが、現存していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, he apparently wrote another book, the ten-volume &quot;Shogaku hosho,&quot; but it is no longer extant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he apparently wrote another book, the ten-volume Shogaku hosho, but it is no longer extant.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he apparently wrote another book, the ten-volume &quot;Shogaku hosho,&quot; but it is no longer extant.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『著聞集』129に「風月の才人にすぐれ」と語るように、漢詩をも能くしたが、特に和歌の才能に優れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In section 129 of the Chomonju (Collected Anecdotes (Ancient and Modern)), he is described as being &quot;A man of talent who excelled at [describing] the beauty of nature,&quot; and indeed, although he was skilled at writing Chinese poetry, he truly excelled at waka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In section 129 of the Chomonju (Collected Anecdotes (Ancient and Modern)), he is described as being &quot;A man of talent who excelled at [describing] the beauty of nature,&quot; and indeed, although he was skilled at writing Chinese poetry, he truly excelled at waka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In section 129 of the &quot;Chomonju&quot; (Collected Anecdotes (Ancient and Modern)), he is described as being &apos;A man of talent who excelled at [describing] the beauty of nature,&apos; and indeed, although he was skilled at writing Chinese poetry, he truly excelled at waka.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>嘉応2年（1170年）10月9日の『住吉社歌合』、治承2年の『右大臣藤原兼実家百首』など、多くの歌合・歌会に参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in many poetry contests and poetry gatherings, including the &quot;Poetry Contest at Sumiyoshi Shrine&quot; held on the ninth day of the tenth month of 1170 (Kao 2) and the &quot;100 verses by the family of the Udaijin (Minister of the Right) FUJIWARA no Kanezane.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in many poetry contests and poetry gatherings, including the &quot;Poetry Contest at Sumiyoshi Shrine&quot; held on the ninth day of the tenth month of 1170 (Kao 2) and the &quot;100 verses by the family of the Udaijin (Minister of the Right) FUJIWARA no Kanezane.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in many poetry contests and poetry gatherings, including the &quot;Poetry Contest at Sumiyoshi Shrine&quot; held on the ninth day of the tenth month of 1170 and the &quot;100 verses by the family of the Udaijin (Minister of the Right) FUJIWARA no Kanezane&quot; in 1178.</e>
<cmt>元号削除年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>実定の家集を『林下集』といい、『千載和歌集』『新古今和歌集』以下の勅撰集にも73首が入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesada&apos;s personal poetry anthology is called &quot;Ringashu&quot; (&quot;[Poems] Collected under the Wood&quot;), and 73 poems of his were selected to be included in the &quot;Senzai wakashu&quot; (Collected Waka of a Thousand Years), the &quot;Shin kokin wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Waka), and the Imperially commissioned waka anthology described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesada&apos;s personal poetry anthology is called Ringashu ([Poems] Collected under the Wood), and 73 poems of his were selected to be included in the Senzai wakashu (Collected Waka of a Thousand Years), the Shin kokin wakashu (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Waka), and the Imperially commissioned waka anthology described below.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesada&apos;s personal poetry anthology is called &quot;Ringashu&quot; ([Poems] Collected under the Wood), and 73 poems of his were selected to be included in the &quot;Senzai wakashu&quot; (Collected Waka of a Thousand Years), the &quot;Shin kokin wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Waka), and the Imperially commissioned waka anthology described below.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>百人一首</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hyakunin Isshu (One Poem each from 100 Poets)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hyakunin Isshu (One Poem each from 100 Poets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hyakunin Isshu (One Poem each from 100 Poets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>ほととぎす　鳴きつる方を　ながむれば　ただ有明の　月ぞ残れる（「千載和歌集」夏161）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As I gaze upon the cuckoo, who continues his plaintive cry, only the moon remains to light the dawn (the 161st verse in the summer section of &quot;Senzai wakashu&quot; (Collected Waka of 1000 Years)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As I gaze upon the cuckoo, who continues his plaintive cry, only the moon remains to light the dawn (the 161st verse in the summer section of Senzai wakashu (Collected Waka of 1000 Years)).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As I gaze upon the cuckoo, who continues his plaintive cry, only the moon remains to light the dawn (the 161st verse in the summer section of &apos;Senzai wakashu&apos; (Collected Waka of 1000 Years)).</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 朝綺波音(id:133609), 伏儀(id:142093), 代言人(id:33675), 小者(id:172526), Hannah(id:15935), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>