<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>江談抄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godansho (The Oe Conversations)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godansho (The Oe Conversations)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godansho (The Oe Conversations)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>江談抄（ごうだんしょう）は、院政期の説話集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godansho, written as 江談抄 in Japanese, is a collection of narratives of the period of the government by retired emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godansho, written as 江談抄 in Japanese, is a collection of narratives from the period of cloistered emperors.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Godansho,&quot; written as 江談抄 in Japanese, is a collection of narratives from the Insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Godansho にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。用語集の表記を参考に、the period of cloistered emperors をInsei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor) に修正しました（※）。※ 用語集では insei と小文字になっていましたが、他の年号 (Heian, Kamakura, Muromachi 等）が大文字で始まっていますので、Insei も大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「江談」二字の偏を取って「水言抄」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Suigensho,&apos; written as &apos;水言抄&apos; in Japanese, derived from the left-hand parts of the Chinese characters &apos;江談,&apos; as the left-hand part of 江 and the left-hand part of 談 respectively stand for &quot;水&quot; (pronounced as sui) and &quot;言&quot; (pronounced as gen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Suigensho,&quot; written as 水言抄 in Japanese, which is derived from the radicals of the two kanjis &quot;江談,&quot; i.e. the left-hand part of 江 and the left-hand part of 談, which respectively represent &quot;水&quot; (pronounced as &quot;sui&quot;) and &quot;言&quot; (pronounced as &quot;gen&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Suigensho,&apos; written as 水言抄 in Japanese, which is derived from the radicals of the two kanjis &apos;江談,&apos; i.e. the left-hand part of 江 and the left-hand part of 談, which respectively represent &quot;水&quot; (pronounced as &quot;sui&quot;) and &quot;言&quot; (pronounced as &quot;gen&quot;).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Suigensho,&quot; &quot;江談,&quot;の ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテーションに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>漢詩文・公事・音楽など多方面にわたる談話の記録である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a record of informal talks covering a wide range of topics including Chinese classical literature and poetry, public affairs, and music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a record of informal talks covering a wide range of topics including Chinese classical literature and poetry, public affairs, and music.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a record of informal talks covering a wide range of topics including Chinese classical literature and poetry, public affairs, music and so on.</e>
<cmt>「など」訳漏れのためpublic affairs, and music をpublic affairs, music and so on. に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>帥中納言大江匡房（1041－1111）の談話を、進士蔵人藤原実兼 (蔵人)（黒衣の宰相といわれた信西の父）が筆記したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A shinshi (person who has passed the examination for entrance to the civil service) named FUJIWARA no Sanekane, who worked as a kuroudo (chamberlain) and was the father of a &quot;kokui no saisho&quot; (Buddhist priest who has great political influence) named Shinzei, took notes from talks of his teacher the Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) OE no Masafusa (1041 - 1111).</e>
<cmt>原文に”進士蔵人藤原実兼 (蔵人)”とございますが、リンク先の用語と混ざっているようです。ウェブを確認し、”進士蔵人藤原実兼 ”と訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are based on notes taken by FUJIWARA no Sanekane, a shinshi (person who has passed the examination for entrance to the civil service) and a kuroudo (chamberlain) (and the father of a &quot;kokui no saisho&quot; (a Buddhist monk who has great political influence) named Shinzei), during talks with his teacher, the Chunagon (Vice-Councilor) OE no Masafusa (1041 - 1111).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are based on notes taken by FUJIWARA no Sanekane, a shinshi (person who has passed the examination for entrance to the civil service) and a kurodo (chamberlain) (and the father of a kokui no saisho (Buddhist priest who has great political influence) named Shinzei), during talks with his teacher, the Sochi no Chunagon (vice-councilor of state and director of Dazaifu, local government office in Kyushu region) OE no Masafusa (1041 - 1111).</e>
<cmt>帥中納言の「帥」訳漏れのため、the Chunagon (Vice-Councilor) をSochi no Chunagon (vice-councilor of state and director of Dazaifu, local government office in Kyushu region) に修正しました（※）。※　「帥」とは大宰府の長官のことです。http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%B8%A5「そちのちゅうなごん」の読みについては以下のサイトを参照しました。http://katohjuk-web.hp.infoseek.co.jp/aduma09-04b.htmkuroudo を kurodo に修正しました。a &quot;kokui no saisho&quot; (a Buddhist monk をa kokui no saisho (Buddhist priest に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>長治から嘉承にかけて（1104－1108年）成立したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that this book appeared between the Choji era and the Kasho era (between 1104 and 1108).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book is believed to have appeared between the Choji era and the Kasho era (between 1104 and 1108).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book is believed to have appeared between the Choji era and the Kasho era (between 1104 and 1108).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現存本は、雑纂形態の「古本系」と、類聚形態の「類聚本系」に大別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing books are roughly classified into the &apos;old book group&apos; which adopts a miscellaneous collection style in which articles are just put together in one book, or the &apos;similarity-based classified book group&apos; which adopts a systematic style in which articles are arranged according to categories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Existing books are generally classified as the &quot;old book&quot; type or as the &quot;similar book&quot; type.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Existing books are generally classified as the &apos;old book&apos; type or as the &apos;similar book&apos; type.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテーションに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>談話形式を取り、連関性を欠く古本系に対し、中世に改編・加筆されたと思われる類聚本の方では内容に沿って六部に分けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The books in the old book group take on a conversation style and lack a correlation between stories, while the books in the similarity-based classified book group, which are thought to have been added some modifications and improvement in the middle ages, have six sections divided by themes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The books of the &quot;old book&quot; type take on a conversational style and lack correlation between stories, while the books of the &quot;similar book&quot; type, which are thought to have included some additions and improvements during the Middle Ages, are divided into six sections which are based on themes.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The books of the old book type take on a conversational style and lack correlation between stories, while the books of the similar book type, which are thought to have included some additions and improvements during the Middle Ages, are divided into six sections which are based on themes.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>匡房は後三条天皇・白河天皇・堀河天皇三帝の侍読を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masafusa was an imperial tutor and he served three emperors: Emperor Gosanjo, Emperor Shirakawa, and Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masafusa was an Imperial tutor and served three emperors: Emperor Gosanjo, Emperor Shirakawa, and Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masafusa was an Imperial tutor and served three emperors: Emperor Gosanjo, Emperor Shirakawa, and Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>詩文に秀で、また有職故実にも通じた名高き才子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a very talented person who was outstanding at literature as well as yusoku-kojitsu (the study of the traditional protocol of the Imperial Court, courtiers, and leading warrior houses).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a very talented person and was well-known for his mastery of poetry as well as yusoku-kojitsu (the study of the traditional protocol of the Imperial Court, courtiers, and leading warrior houses).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a very talented person and was well-known for his mastery of poetry as well as Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette).</e>
<cmt>用語集の表記に従い、yusoku-kojitsu (the study of the traditional protocol of the Imperial Court, courtiers, and leading warrior houses) をYusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼の博学を反映してか、『江談抄』はあまりに雑多な内容を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reflecting his enormous amount of knowledge, &quot;Godansho&quot; covers a very wide range of topics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As if to reflect his erudition, &quot;Godansho&quot; covers an extremely wide range of topics.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As if to reflect his erudition, &quot;Godansho&quot; covers an extremely wide range of topics.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのうち、朝儀公事に関する故事や詩文にまつわる逸話が大半を占める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most topics are about historical events of the Imperial ceremonies and public affairs or about stories around the literature.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most topics cover historical events of the Imperial ceremonies and public affairs or anecdotes on literature.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most topics cover historical events of the Imperial ceremonies and public affairs or anecdotes on literature.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>貴族社会の世相を伝える説話も多く、後者は後世の説話文学へ影響を及ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Godansho includes many stories about the trend of the aristocracy as well, and such stories had great influence on later narrative literature.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godansho includes many stories about the trend of the aristocracy as well, and such stories appears to have had great influence on later narrative literature.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godansho includes many stories about the trend of the aristocracy as well, and such stories appears to have had great influence on later narrative literature.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>新日本古典文学大系（岩波書店）所収。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godansho is available in the Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (New Japanese Classis Literature Systematic Edition, published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godansho is included in the Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (New Japanese Classic Literature Systematic Edition, published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godansho is included in the Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (New Japanese Classic Literature Systematic Edition, published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yume149(id:17504), SK(id:64397), Andee(id:20421), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>