<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>タギシミミの反逆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rebellion of Tagishimimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rebellion of Tagishimimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rebellion of Tagishimimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>タギシミミの反逆（タギシミミのはんぎゃく）は、神武天皇が亡くなった後、皇位に就こうと策略した手研耳命をカムヌナカワミミ（後の綏靖天皇）らが討ったという日本神話の説話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rebellion of Tagishimimi is a tale of Japanese myth that after Emperor Jinmu passed away, Tagishimimi devised a ploy to be an emperor but was defeated by Kamununakawamimi (later Emperor Suizei) and his army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rebellion of Tagishimimi is a tale of Japanese mythology that after Emperor Jinmu passed away, Tagishimimi devised a ploy to become the emperor but was defeated by Kamununakawamimi (later, Emperor Suizei) and his army.</e>
<cmt>vocab/ myth-mythologyarticle/vocab be-become an-thecomma between later and Emperor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rebellion of Tagishimimi is a tale of Japanese mythology that after Emperor Jinmu passed away, Tagishimimi devised a ploy to become the emperor but was defeated by Kamununakawamimi (later, Emperor Suizei) and his army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story Outline</e>
<cmt>capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>天皇（神武天皇）にはヒメタタライスケヨリヒメ（ヒメタタライスズヒメ）との間の子、神八井耳命、日子八井命、カムヌナカワミミ（神沼河耳命）の他に、日向にいたころに吾平津媛との間に手研耳命（多芸志美美命）、キスミミ（岐須美美命）の二柱の子をもうけていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to three children (deities) he had with Himetataraisukeyori hime (Himetataraisuzuhime), Kamuyaimimi no mikoto, Hikoyai no mikoto, and Kamununakawamimi no mikoto, the emperor (Emperor Jinmu) also had two children (deities) with Ahiratsu-hime while he was in Himuka (Hyuga): Tagishimimi no mikoto and Kisumimi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記にすると同じ場合は括弧内を省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to three children he had with Himetataraisukeyorihime (Himetataraisuzuhime), Kamuyaimimi no Mikoto, Hikoyai no Mikoto, and Kamununakawamimi no Mikoto, the emperor (Emperor Jinmu) also had two children with Ahiratsuhime while he was in Himuka (Hyuga), Tagishimimi no Mikoto and Kisumimi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>took out (deities)took out the space between Himetataraisukeyori and himetook out the hyphen between Ahiratsu and hime</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to three children he had with Himetataraisukeyorihime (Himetataraisuzuhime), Kamuyaimimi no Mikoto, Hikoyai no Mikoto, and Kamununakawamimi no Mikoto, the emperor (Emperor Jinmu) also had two children with Ahiratsuhime while he was in Himuka (Hyuga), Tagishimimi no Mikoto and Kisumimi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天皇が亡くなった後、タギシミミはヒメタタライスケヨリヒメを妻にし、その3人の御子を殺そうと計画していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the emperor passed away, Tagishimimi had a ploy to marry Himetataraisukeyori hime and kill her three children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the emperor passed away, Tagishimimi had a ploy to marry Himetataraisukeyorihime and kill her three children.</e>
<cmt>took out the space between Himetataraisukeyori and hime</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the emperor passed away, Tagishimimi had a ploy to marry Himetataraisukeyorihime and kill her three children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それを知ったイスケヨリヒメは3人の御子にそれを知らせようと、「狭井河から雲が立ち登って、畝傍山では大風が吹く前触れとして、木の葉がざわめいている」という内容の歌を詠んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On knowing his ploy, Isukeyorihime made a poem depicting that clouds were rising from the Saikawa River and leaves on the trees were rustling in Mount Unebi to tell that it was a sign of a storm, to warn her three children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon knowing his ploy, Isukeyorihime made a poem depicting clouds rising from the Sai-gawa River and leaves on the trees rustling on Mount Unebi to tell that it was a sign of a storm, to warn her three children.</e>
<cmt>狭井河 pronunciation reference (not validated eoungh)/ http://www.geocities.jp/masuga68jp/kahi-50.htmlhyphenwording changed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon knowing his ploy, Isukeyorihime made a poem depicting clouds rising from the Sai-gawa River and leaves on the trees rustling on Mount Unebi to tell that it was a sign of a storm, to warn her three children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その歌の意味を解した御子たちはすぐにタギシミミを殺すことにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her children understood the meaning of the poem and decided to kill Tagishimimi immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her children understood the meaning of the poem and decided to kill Tagishimimi immediately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her children understood the meaning of the poem and decided to kill Tagishimimi immediately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>カムヌナカワミミは、兄のカムヤイミミに武器を渡してタギシミミを殺すように言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamununakawamimi gave a weapon to his elder brother Kamuyaimimi and told him to kill Tagishimimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamununakawamimi gave a weapon to his older brother Kamuyaimimi and told him to kill Tagishimimi.</e>
<cmt>vocab/ elder-older (following the provided word list, 用語統一)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamununakawamimi gave a weapon to his older brother Kamuyaimimi and told him to kill Tagishimimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、カムヤイミミは手足がわなないて殺すことができなかったので、カムヌナカワミミが兄の持っている武器を取ってとどめを刺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamuyaimimi failed, however, because his hands and legs were trembling, so Kamununakawamimi took the weapon from his elder brother and gave a finishing blow to Tagishimimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamuyaimimi failed, however, because his hands and legs were trembling, so Kamununakawamimi took the weapon from his older brother and gave the finishing blow to Tagishimimi.</e>
<cmt>articlevocab/ elder-older (following the provided word list, 用語統一)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamuyaimimi failed, however, because his hands and legs were trembling, so Kamununakawamimi took the weapon from his older brother and gave the finishing blow to Tagishimimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そこで、それを賛えてカムヌナカワミミはタケヌナカワミミ（建沼河耳命）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To praise his bravery, Kamununakawamimi is also called Takenunakawamimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To praise his bravery, Kamununakawamimi is also called Takenunakawamimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To praise his bravery, Kamununakawamimi is also called Takenunakawamimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>カムヤイミミはこの失態を恥じ、弟のカムヌナカワミミに皇位を譲り、自らは神官となって仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashamed of his failure, Kamuyaimimi gave up the Imperial Throne to his younger brother Kamununakawamimi and served as a Shinto priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashamed of his failure, Kamuyaimimi gave up the Imperial throne to his younger brother Kamununakawamimi and served as a Shinto priest.</e>
<cmt>capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashamed of his failure, Kamuyaimimi gave up the Imperial throne to his younger brother Kamununakawamimi and served as a Shinto priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explanation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>神武天皇の御子のうち、末子であるカムヌナカワミミが皇位を継いだのは、古代日本において末子相続の風習があったことを示すものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that the youngest son Kamununakawamimi among Emperor Jinmu&apos;s children succeeded the Imperial throne indicates that there was a custom of postremogeniture in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that among Emperor Jinmu&apos;s children, the youngest son Kamununakawamimi succeeded the Imperial throne indicates that there was a custom of postremogeniture in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that among Emperor Jinmu&apos;s children, the youngest son Kamununakawamimi succeeded the Imperial throne indicates that there was a custom of postremogeniture in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>父の神武天皇（カムヤマトイワレビコ）も、ウガヤフキアエズの4人の御子の末子であり、ウガヤフキエアズの父のホオリもまた末子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The father Emperor Jinmu (Kamuyamatoiwarebiko) was also the youngest among four children of Ugayafukiaezu, whose father Hoori was also the youngest child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamununakawamimi&apos;s father, Emperor Jinmu (Kamuyamatoiwarebiko), was also the youngest among four children of Ugayafukiaezu, whose father Hori was also the youngest child.</e>
<cmt>the father-Kamununakawamimi&apos;s fatherHoori-Hori</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamununakawamimi&apos;s father, Emperor Jinmu (Kamuyamatoiwarebiko), was also the youngest among four children of Ugayafukiaezu, whose father Hori was also the youngest child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>あらすじでは省略したが、皇位を継がなかったカムヤイミミとヒコヤイは、多くの氏族の祖とであると記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was omitted in Story outline described above, Kamuyaimimi and Hikoyai who didn&apos;t succeed the Imperial throne were described as the founder of many clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was omitted in the story outline described above, Kamuyaimimi and Hikoyai, who didn&apos;t succeed the Imperial throne, were described as the founder of many clans.</e>
<cmt>extra spacearticles, comma, capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was omitted in the story outline described above, Kamuyaimimi and Hikoyai, who didn&apos;t succeed the Imperial throne, were described as the founder of many clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは、それらの氏族が祖先の出自を神武天皇に結び付け、大和王権と関係が深いことを示そうとしていたためとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This description indicates that those clans intended to connect their ancestry to Emperor Jinmu to show their deep relationship with the Yamato Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This description indicates that those clans intended to connect their ancestry to Emperor Jinmu to show their deep relationship with the Yamato Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This description indicates that those clans intended to connect their ancestry to Emperor Jinmu to show their deep relationship with the Yamato Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 梛(id:208034), Shimoxx(id:9332), Nnh(id:474), 代言人(id:33675), 上(id:14148), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>