<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>漢文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese classical literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese classical literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese classical literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>漢文学（かんぶんがく）とは、漢文（古典中国語）で書いた作品の総称と、それに対する研究の学問のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese classical literature is a general term for the works written in Chinese (classical Chinese) and a study of these classics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese classical literature is a general term for the works written in Chinese (classical Chinese) and the study of these classics.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese classical literature is a general term for the works written in Chinese (classical Chinese) and the study of these classics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>本来は日本人など中国人（漢族）以外の人々が漢文で書いた作品及びそれに関する学問を指していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally it designated the works written in Chinese by the people other than Chinese (the Han people) such as Japanese, and a study concerning these works.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally the term referred to works written in Chinese by people other than the Chinese (the Han people), such as Japanese people, and the studies concerning these works.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally the term referred to works written in Chinese by people other than the Chinese (the Han people), such as Japanese people, and the studies concerning these works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、辛亥革命以後の白話運動や簡体字の導入などによって、漢文と現代中国語の文体に差異が生じるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the vernacular language movement in China and introduction of the simplified form of a Chinese character, the difference between classical and modern Chinese came to arise.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the vernacular language movement in China and the introduction of simplified Chinese characters, a distinction between classical and modern Chinese arose.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the vernacular language movement in China after the Xinhai Revolution and the introduction of simplified Chinese characters, a distinction between classical and modern Chinese arose.</e>
<cmt>「辛亥革命以後」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そのため、辛亥革命以前に中国人（漢族）によって漢文で書かれた作品についても、現代中国語で書かれた（現代）中国文学と区別する意味で「漢文学」と呼称する場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the works written in classical Chinese by Chinese people (the Han people) before Xinhai Revolution are sometimes called &apos;Chinese classical literature&apos; to distinguish them from the (contemporary) Chinese literature written in modern Chinese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the works written in classical Chinese by Chinese people (the Han people) before the Xinhai Revolution are sometimes called &apos;Chinese classical literature&apos; to distinguish them from the (contemporary) Chinese literature written in modern Chinese.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the works written in classical Chinese by Chinese people (the Han people) before the Xinhai Revolution are sometimes called &apos;Chinese classical literature&apos; to distinguish them from the (contemporary) Chinese literature written in modern Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>本項目においては本来の意味である前者の意味を中心に解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this section, the former Chinese classical literature in the original meaning will be mainly explained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this section, the explanation will focus mainly on the former Chinese classical literature by the original definition.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this section, the explanation will focus mainly on the former Chinese classical literature by the original definition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後者については中国文学の項目を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See the section of Chinese literature for the further information about the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See the section of Chinese literature for further information about the latter.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See the section of Chinese literature for further information about the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本における漢文学（日本漢文学）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classical Chinese literature in Japan (Japanese Chinese classical literature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classical Chinese literature in Japan (Japanese Chinese classical literature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classical Chinese literature in Japan (Japanese Chinese classical literature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>総説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>もともと日本には文字がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, there is no literature in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, there was no literature in Japan.</e>
<cmt>The original Japanese is in the past tense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, there were no characters in Japan.</e>
<cmt>was no literature→were no characters</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（いわゆる神代文字なるものが後世の仮託であることは定説化されている）ので、中国より漢字を受け入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is an established theory that what is called the ancient Japanese character is a pretense made by posterity), therefore Chinese characters were introduced from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is an established theory that what are called ancient Japanese characters are a pretense made by posterity), therefore Chinese characters were introduced from China.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is an established theory that what are called ancient Japanese characters are a pretense made by posterity), therefore Chinese characters were introduced from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのとき、最初は中国語を習得することが最初の課題であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the first task was to learn Chinese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the first task was to learn Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the first task was to learn Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>朝廷の正史として編纂された『日本書紀』が、正統的な漢文で書かれたことも、そうした流れに日本社会があったことの例証である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), which was compiled as an authenticated history of Imperial court, was written in orthodox Chinese, which illustrated that the Japanese society was in the current as such.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), which was compiled as an authentic history of the Imperial court, was written in orthodox Chinese, which illustrates that Japanese society was in the process of adopting written Chinese.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), which was compiled as an authentic history of the Imperial court, was written in orthodox Chinese, which illustrates that Japanese society was in the process of adopting written Chinese.</e>
<cmt>文頭の &quot;&quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>散文のみならず、詩作も試みられ、『懐風藻』には、7世紀からの作品が収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only prose but also poetry was tried to make, and &quot;Kaifusou&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry) contained the works which had been written since the seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only prose but also poetry was attempted to be written, and &quot;Kaifusou&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry) contained works which had been written since the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only prose but also poetry was attempted to be written, and &quot;Kaifuso&quot; (Fond Recollections of Poetry) contained works which had been written since the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>Kaifusou→Kaifuso</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後も、漢詩漢文は日本社会で作られ続けたが、広まりと高まりを見せたのは、9世紀の菅原道真の時期、15世紀の禅宗寺院を中心にした〈五山文学〉の時期、18世紀の儒学が武士たちに広まった菅茶山たちの時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Chinese poetry and prose were made in Japan, and it reached the peak in the following three periods: in the 9th century, when SUGAWARA no Michizane was alive, the 15th century when &lt;Gozan Bungaku&gt; (Literally, Five Mountain Literature) flourished mainly in Zen temples, and the 18th century when Confucianism became widely known to samurai, or the period of Chazan KAN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, Chinese poetry and prose were made in Japan, and this trend reached its peak during the following three periods: In the 9th century, when SUGAWARA no Michizane was alive, the 15th century when &lt;Gozan Bungaku&gt; (Literally, Five Mountain Literature) flourished mainly in Zen temples, and the 18th century when Confucianism became widely known to samurai, also know as the period of Chazan KAN.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, Chinese poetry and prose were made in Japan, and this trend reached its peak during the following three periods: In the ninth century, when SUGAWARA no Michizane was alive, the 15th century when &lt;Gozan Bungaku&gt; (Literally, Five Mountain Literature) flourished mainly in Zen temples, and the 18th century when Confucianism became widely known to samurai, also known as the period of Chazan KAN.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更know→known</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>明治維新のころも、西洋の文物を輸入するときに、翻訳語として漢文に源流をもつ語彙が多く採用されたこともあって、漢詩が流行した時期もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the time of Meiji Restoration, when the western books were imported, many vocabularies which had Chinese origin were adopted as they were translated, so there was a time when Chinese poetry became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the time of the Meiji Restoration, when many western books were imported, many vocabularies which had Chinese origin were adopted as they were translated, so there was a time when Chinese poetry became popular.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the time of the Meiji Restoration, when many western books were imported, many vocabularies which had Chinese origin were adopted as they were translated, so there was a time when Chinese poetry became popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この時期に活躍した漢詩人として、森槐南が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative poet who wrote in Chinese around this time is Kainan MORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An example of a famous poet who wrote in Chinese around this time is Kainan MORI.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An example of a famous poet who wrote in Chinese around this time is Kainan MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、大正後期以降になると急速に衰え、漢詩漢文の製作は、一部の趣味人の手わざとなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the late Taisho period, it declined rapidly, and composition of Chinese poetry and prose was done by only a limited number of people with refined taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the late Taisho period, this practice declined rapidly, and composition of Chinese poetry and prose was done by only a limited number of people with refined taste.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the late Taisho period, this practice declined rapidly, and composition of Chinese poetry and prose was done by only a limited number of people with refined taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>1960年代になって、ドイツ文学者の富士川英郎や小説家の中村真一郎たちが、江戸時代の漢詩文の再評価をはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 1960&apos;s, Hideo FUJIKAWA, a scholar of German literature, Shinichiro NAKAMURA, a novelist, and so on began to revalue the Chinese poetry and prose in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1960&apos;s, Hideo FUJIKAWA, a scholar of German literature, Shinichiro NAKAMURA, a novelist, and others began to reevaluate the Chinese poetry and prose from the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1960&apos;s, Hideo FUJIKAWA, a scholar of German literature, Shinichiro NAKAMURA, a novelist, and others began to reevaluate the Chinese poetry and prose from the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この頃から、日本の漢文学の伝統が見直されるようになり、1980年代から刊行された岩波書店の『日本古典文学大系』のシリーズには、続編の明治篇も含めて、多くの漢文学に属する作品が収録されるようになり、研究も進んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this time, the tradition of Chinese literature in Japan has been revaluated, and a series of &quot;Japanese Classic Literature Systematic Edition&quot; published since the 1980&apos;s by Iwanami Shoten, Publishers came to contain many works belonging to the genre of Chinese literature, including a sequel, the volume of the Meiji period, and the study is advanced, too.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this time, the tradition of Chinese literature in Japan has been reevaluated and the research has continued to advance; a series of books titled &quot;Compendium of Japanese Classic Literature&quot; has been published since the 1980&apos;s by Iwanami Shoten, and publishers came to include many works belonging to the genre of Chinese literature, including a second volume on the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this time, the tradition of Chinese literature in Japan has been reevaluated and the research has continued to advance; a series of books titled &quot;Compendium of Japanese Classic Literature&quot; has been published since the 1980&apos;s by Iwanami Shoten, which came to include many works belonging to the genre of Chinese literature, including a second volume on the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>and publishers→which （不特定多数の出版社ではなく、岩波書店を指していると思います。）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ねこぱんだ(id:35119), Yes0song(id:40398), Straysheep(id:42448), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>