<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紫式部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki Shikibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紫式部（むらさきしきぶ、生没年不明）は、平安時代中期の女性作家、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu (dates of birth and death unknown) was a female author and poet in the middle of the Heian era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki Shikibu (dates of birth and death unknown) was a female author and poet in the middle of the Heian era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu (dates of birth and death unknown) was a female author and poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>era →period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源氏物語の作者として有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is well known as the author of The Tale of Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is well known as the author of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is well known as the author of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中古三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is one of the Chuko Sanjurokkasen (thirty-six poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane).</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E4%B8%AD%E5%8F%A4%E4%B8%89%E5%8D%81%E5%85%AD%E6%AD%8C%E4%BB%99&amp;stype=1&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is one of the Chuko Sanjurokkasen (36 poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane).</e>
<cmt>numbering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is one of the Chuko Sanjurokkasen (medieval 36 Immortal Poets).</e>
<cmt>&quot;36 poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane&quot; -&gt; &quot;medieval 36 Immortal Poets&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『小倉百人一首』にも「めぐりあひて 見しやそれとも わかぬまに　雲がくれにし 夜半の月かな」で入選。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her poem, &apos;I met a friend after so long, who went back in a hurry before recognizing his face.Like the moon goes behind a cloud at a blow.&apos; was selected for &quot;Ogura Hyakunin isshu (One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets).&quot;</e>
<cmt>http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~sg2h-ymst/yamatouta/sennin/musikibu.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her poem, &quot;I met a friend after so long, who went back in a hurry before recognizing his face.Like the moon goes behind a cloud at a blow&quot; was selected for &quot;Ogura Hyakunin isshu (One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her poem, &apos;I met a friend after so long, who went back in a hurry before I recognized his face; like the moon goes behind a cloud at a blow&apos; was selected for &quot;Ogura Hyakunin isshu (One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets).&quot;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原氏の出で、女房名は「藤式部」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was from the FUJIWARA Clan, and her name as a court lady was &apos;Fuji Shikibu (Murasaki Shikibu).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was from the FUJIWARA clan, and her name as a court lady was &apos;Fuji Shikibu (Murasaki Shikibu).&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was from the Fujiwara clan, and her name as a court lady was &apos;Fuji Shikibu (Murasaki Shikibu).&apos;</e>
<cmt>clan名小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「紫」の称は『源氏物語』の作中人物「紫の上」に、「式部」は父が式部大丞だったことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She acquired the sobriquet of &apos;Murasaki&apos; from the name of the heroine &apos;Murasaki no Ue&apos; of &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; and &apos;Shikibu&apos; refers to her father&apos;s position Shikibutaijo (Aide of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>「式部大丞」の訳語はMeredith McKinney翻訳&quot;The Pillow Book&quot;（以下、&quot;PB&quot;）のAppendix5 (Cort Ranks, Titles and Bureaucracy)より</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She acquired the sobriquet of &quot;Murasaki&quot; from the name of the heroine &quot;Murasaki no Ue&quot; of &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; and &quot;Shikibu&quot; refers to her father&apos;s position Shikibutaijo (Aide of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She acquired the sobriquet of &apos;Murasaki&apos; from the name of the heroine &apos;Murasaki no Ue&apos; of &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; and &apos;Shikibu&apos; refers to her father&apos;s position as Shikibutaijo (Aide of Ceremonials).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>プロフィール</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>紫式部の本名は不明であるが、「御堂関白記」の寛弘4年正月29日の条において掌侍になったとされる記事のある「藤原香子」（かおりこ/たかこ/こうし）との説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s real name is unknown, but there is a supposition that she was the Kaoriko/Takako/Koshi FUJIWARA who became Shoji (rank) on January 29 1007, which was described in &apos;Mido Kampakuki (Michinaga FUJIWARA&apos;s diary).&apos;</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E5%BE%A1%E5%A0%82%E9%96%A2%E7%99%BD%E8%A8%98&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s real name is unknown, but there is a supposition that she was the Kaoriko/Takako/Koshi FUJIWARA, who became Shoji (rank) on January 29 1007, which was described in &quot;Mido Kampakuki (Michinaga FUJIWARA&apos;s diary).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s real name is unknown, but it is assumed that she was the &apos;FUJIWARA no Kaoriko/Takako/Koshi,&apos; who became shoji (ranked) on January 29, 1007, which was described in &apos;Mido Kanpakuki (FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s diary).&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正FUJIWARA no Kaoriko/Takako/Koshiとしました（他の人物名と合わせ）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>但し、この説は仮定を重ねている部分も多く、推論の過程に誤りが含まれているといった批判もあり、仮定の域を出るものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However this view is mostly based on the other suppositions, which is said to contain some mistakes in the process of making inferences, therefore it is still a matter of conjecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However this view is generally based on the other assumptions, which are said to contain errors in the process of making inferences, so it remains a matter of conjecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However this view is generally based on the other assumptions, which are said to contain errors in the process of making inferences, so it remains a matter of conjecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>また生没年も伝わっていないが、資料・作品等から寛弘5年（1008年）に30歳位と推測されるので、逆算して天延元年（979年）頃生？ - 長和五年（1016年）頃没？と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, her dates of birth and death are unknown, but it is conjectured that she was about 30 in 1008 from historical materials and her works; by counting backwards from the age, she would be born around 979 and die around 1016.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, her dates of birth and death are unknown, but it is suggested that she was about 30 years old in 1008, based on historical materials and her works; by counting backwards from that age, she would have been born around 979 and died around 1016.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, her dates of birth and death are unknown, but it is suggested that she was about 30 years old in 1008, based on historical materials and her works; by counting backwards from that age, she would have been born around 979 and died around 1016.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>貴族ではめずらしいイワシ好きであったという説話があるが、もとは「猿源氏草紙」で和泉式部の話であり、後世の作話と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradition has it that she liked sardines, which was unusual for aristocracy, but this episode is based on a story of Izumi Shikibu in &apos;Sarugenji no soshi (The Sarugenji Book),&apos; so it seems to have been made up by somebody in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tradition has it that she liked sardines, which was unusual for aristocracy, but this episode is based on a story of Izumi Shikibu in &quot;Sarugenji no soshi (The Sarugenji Book),&quot; so it seems to have been made up by someone in later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tradition has it that she liked sardines, which was unusual for aristocracy, but this episode is based on a story of Izumi Shikibu in &apos;Sarugenji no soshi (The Sarugenji Book),&apos; so it seems to have been made up by someone at a later date.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>越後国守藤原為時の娘で、母は摂津国守藤原為信女であるが、紫式部の幼少期に母を亡くしたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tametoki, governor of Echigo Province, and her mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tamenobu from Settsu Province, but she lost her mother when she was little.</e>
<cmt>http://spysee.jp/藤原為時http://www.tulips.tsukuba.ac.jp/jart/sakuhin/indexAu_Ha.html「女」は文脈からは「daughter」の可能性が高いと思われます。（藤原為信女の読みは確認できませんでした）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tametoki, governor of Echigo Province, and her mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tamenobu from Settsu Province, but she lost her mother when she was little.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tametoki, governor of Echigo Province, and her mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tamenobu from Settsu Province, but she lost her mother when she was little.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同母の兄弟に藤原惟規がいるほか、姉の存在も知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobunori was her brother by a different father, and she also seemed to have an older sister.</e>
<cmt>http://www.geocities.jp/youchan_morita/keisai6.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nobunori was her brother by a different father, and apparently she also had an older sister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobunori was her brother by a different father, and apparently she also had an older sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>三条右大臣藤原定方、堤中納言藤原兼輔はともに父方の曽祖父で、一族には文辞を以って聞こえた人が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadakata, Sanjo Udaijin (minister of the right), and FUJIWARA no Kanesuke, Tsutsumi Chunagon (middle counsellor), were her paternal great grandfathers, and she had many relatives who had been known as good writers.</e>
<cmt>http://spysee.jp/藤原定方http://spysee.jp/藤原兼輔中納言の訳語は&quot;PB&quot; Appendix5より</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sadakata, Sanjo Udaijin (minister of the right), and FUJIWARA no Kanesuke, Tsutsumi Chunagon (middle counsellor), were her paternal great grandfathers, and she had many relatives who had been known as good writers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadakata, Sanjo Udaijin (Sanjo minister of the right), and FUJIWARA no Kanesuke, Tsutsumi Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), were her paternal great grandfathers, and she had many relatives who were known as talented writers.</e>
<cmt>Sanjo minister としました。&quot;middle councilor&quot;→&quot;vice-councilor of state&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>幼少の頃より、当時の女性に求められる以上の才能で漢文を読みこなしたなど、才女としての逸話が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many anecdotes that since she was a child, she had a talent for reading Chinese classics more than that required for women in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many anecdotes stating that since she was a child she had more talent for reading Chinese classics than a woman would have needed in those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many anecdotes stating that, since her childhood, she had had more talent for reading Chinese classics than women were required to have in those days.</e>
<cmt>Just substituting &quot;than was required to &quot; would make the sentence grammatically incorrect so I have had to tweak the sentence to make it work.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>五十四帖にわたる大作『源氏物語』、宮仕え中の日記『紫式部日記』を著したというのが通説、家集『紫式部集』が伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally considered that she wrote both &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; consisting of 54 chapters and &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Diary,&quot; which was about her days of serving at the imperial court, and &quot;Collection of Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s work&quot; is also said to be her work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally considered that she wrote both &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; which consists of 54 chapters, and &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Diary,&quot; which was about her days in service to the Imperial Court, as well as &quot;Collection of Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s Works.&quot;</e>
<cmt>cap</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally considered that she wrote both &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; which consists of 54 chapters, and &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Diary,&quot; which was about her days in service to the Imperial Court, as well as &quot;Collection of Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s Works.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>父・藤原為時は30代に東宮の読書役を始めとして、東宮が花山天皇になると蔵人、式部大丞と出世したが、花山天皇が出家すると失職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father FUJIWARA no Tametoki got a reading job in Togu (Crown Prince&apos;s Palace) in his thirties, and when the crown prince became Kazan emperor, he was promoted to Kurodo (Chamberlain), and then to Shikibutaijo, but when the emperor became a priest, he lost his job.</e>
<cmt>読書役の定訳不明蔵人の訳語は&quot;PB&quot; Appendix5より</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father, FUJIWARA no Tametoki, obtained employment as a reader in Togu (the palace of the Crown Prince) while in his thirties, and when the Crown Prince became Emperor Kazan he was promoted to the post of kurodo (Chamberlain) and then to Shikibutaijo; however, when the Emperor became a priest, he lost his job.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father, FUJIWARA no Tametoki, obtained employment as a reader in Togu (the palace of the Crown Prince) while in his thirties, and when the Crown Prince became Emperor Kazan he was promoted to the post of kurodo (Chamberlain) and then to Shikibutaijo; however, when the Emperor became a priest, he lost his job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>10年後、一条天皇に詩を奉じた結果、越前国の受領となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten years later, in consequence of dedicating a poem to Ichijo emperor, he became a governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten years later, as a consequence of dedicating a poem to Emperor Ichijo, he became a governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten years later, as a consequence of dedicating a poem to Emperor Ichijo, he became a governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>紫式部は娘時代の約2年を父の任国で過ごす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu lived in the place of her father&apos;s assignment for 2 years when she was a girl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki Shikibu, during her childhood, spent two years in the place of her father&apos;s assignment.</e>
<cmt>numbering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu, during her childhood, spent two years in the place of her father&apos;s assignment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>長徳四年（998年）頃、親子ほども年の差がある山城国守藤原宣孝と結婚し、長保元年（999年）に一女・藤原賢子（かたいこ・けんし）（大弐三位）を儲けたが、この結婚生活は長く続かず、まもなく宣孝と死別した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 998, She married a Governor of Yamashiro Province FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was old enough to be her father, and in 999 she bore him a daughter FUJIWARA no Kataiko/Kenshi, but this marriage life didn&apos;t last long because Nobutaka died soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In about 998, she married a governor of Yamashiro Province FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was old enough to be her father; in 999 she bore him a daughter, FUJIWARA no Kataiko/Kenshi, but this marriage life didn&apos;t last long because Nobutaka died soon afterward.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In about 998, she married a governor of Yamashiro Province FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was old enough to be her father; in 999 she bore him a daughter, FUJIWARA no Kataiko/Kenshi, but this marriage life didn&apos;t last long because Nobutaka died soon afterward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>寛弘二年（1005年）12月29日 (旧暦)より、一条天皇の中宮・藤原彰子（藤原道長の長女、のち院号宣下して上東門院）に女房兼家庭教師役として仕え、少なくとも同八年頃まで奉仕し続けたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since December 29 (according to lunar calendar) in 1005, she started to serve the Empress of Ichijo Emperor, FUJIWARA no Shoshi/Akiko (the oldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and later given the name of ex-emperor, Jotomonin) as a court lady-cum-tutor, and she had served the Empress at least until 1011.</e>
<cmt>http://spysee.jp/藤原彰子</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 29 (according to the lunar calendar) of 1005, she began serving the Empress of Emperor Ichijo FUJIWARA no Shoshi/Akiko (the oldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and later given the name of the ex-emperor Jotomonin) as a court lady-cum-tutor, and she served the Empress at least until 1011.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 29 (according to the lunar calendar) of 1005, she began serving the Empress of Emperor Ichijo FUJIWARA no Shoshi/Akiko (the oldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and later given the name of the Retired Emperor Jotomonin) as a court lady-cum-tutor, and she served the Empress at least until 1011.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor Jotomoninとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>『詞花和歌集』に収められた伊勢大輔の「いにしへの奈良の都の八重桜けふ九重ににほひぬるかな」という和歌は、宮廷に献上された八重桜を受け取り、中宮に奉る際に詠まれたものだが、『伊勢大輔集』によればこの役目は当初紫式部の役目だったものを式部が新参の大輔に譲ったものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a poem created by ISE no osuke, &apos;Sometime ago, double-flowered cherry trees bloomed in colorful Nara Capital.Today they bloom in the Kuju Castle in this Kyo Capital like before,&apos; which was collected in &quot;Shika Wakashu (collection of poetry),&quot; and the poem was written for dedicating the empress along with Yaezakura (double cherry blossoms) presented to the imperial court, but according to &quot;ISE no Osuke shu (private collection),&quot; it had been supposed to be a duty of Murasaki Shikibu, but she devolved the duty on a newcomer Osuke.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?p=%E4%BC%8A%E5%8B%A2%E5%A4%A7%E8%BC%94&amp;enc=UTF-8&amp;stype=1&amp;dtype=0http://members.at.infoseek.co.jp/jsjtm/hyaku61.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a poem created by ISE no osuke, &quot;Sometime ago, double-flowered cherry trees bloomed in colorful Nara Capital; today they bloom in the Kuju Castle in this Kyo Capital like before,&quot; which was collected in &quot;Shika Wakashu (Collection of Poetry)&quot;; the poem was written for dedicating the Empress along with Yaezakura (double cherry blossoms) presented to the Imperial Court, but according to &quot;ISE no Osuke shu (Private Collection),&quot; it had been supposed to be a duty of Murasaki Shikibu, but she devolved the duty on a newcomer, Osuke.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a poem created by ISE no Taifu, &apos;Some time ago, double-flowered cherry trees bloomed in the colorful capital of Nara; today they bloom in Kuju Castle in this capital of Kyo, as they did before,&apos; which was collected in &quot;Shika Wakashu (Collection of Poetry)&quot;; the poem was written in dedication to the Empress along with yaezakura (double cherry blossoms) presented to the Imperial Court; however, according to &quot;ISE no Taifu shu (Private Collection)&quot; it was supposed to be a duty of Murasaki Shikibu, but she delegated the duty to a newcomer, Taifu.</e>
<cmt>taifuとしました。括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>藤原実資の日記『小右記』長和2年5月25日 (旧暦)条で「『越後守為時女』として皇太后彰子と実資の取り次ぎ役を務めた」との記述が紫式部で残された最後のものとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last description about Murasaki Shikibu appears in &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, dated May 25 (lunar calendar) 1014, saying that as &apos;a daughter of Tametoki who was a Governor of Echigo Province,&apos; she conveyed a message from Shoshi ex-emperor&apos;s wife to Sanesuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>http://spysee.jp/藤原実資『越後守為時女』は為時の妻ではなく、娘のこと</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last description about Murasaki Shikibu appears in &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, dated May 25 (lunar calendar) 1014, saying that as &quot;a daughter of Tametoki, who was a governor of Echigo Province,&quot; she conveyed a message from the wife of ex-Emperor Shoshi to Sanesuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last description about Murasaki Shikibu appears in &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, dated May 25 (lunar calendar) 1014, saying that &apos;as &quot;a daughter of Tametoki, who was a governor of Echigo Province,&quot; she conveyed a message from the wife of the Retired Empress Shoshi to Sanesuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>皇太后彰子 →　Retired Empress Shoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>よって三条天皇の長和年間（1012年-1016年）に没したとするのが通説だが、異見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is widely believed that she died between 1012 and 1016, a reign of Sanjo Emperor, but some people disagree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is widely believed that she died between 1012 and 1016, in the reign of Emperor Sanjo, but some people disagree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is widely believed that she died between 1012 and 1016, in the reign of Emperor Sanjo, but some people disagree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、伝・紫式部墓が京都市北区 (京都市)紫野西御所田町（堀川北大路下ル西側）に残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there remained Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s grave at Murasaki no Nishigoshoden-cho (Horikawa Kitaoji Kudaru, West side), Kita-ku, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/101/?start=300</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there remained Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s grave at Murasaki no Nishigoshoden-cho (Horikawa Kitaoji Kudaru, West side), Kita-ku, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, tradition has it that Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s grave can be found at Murasaki no Nishigoshoden-cho (Horikawa Kitaoji Kudaru, West side), Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>I would have no idea what &quot;loral grave&quot; was supposed to mean without looking at the Japanese.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>現在、日本銀行D銀行券 2000円札の裏には小さな肖像画と、『源氏物語絵巻』の一部分が使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, Bank of Japan&apos;s D note of 2000 yen has a portrait of Murasaki Shikibu and a part of &quot;Emaki (picture scroll) of The Tale of Genji&quot; on its back side.</e>
<cmt>http://www.boj.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, Bank of Japan&apos;s D-note of 2000 yen has a portrait of Murasaki Shikibu and a part of &quot;Emaki (picture scroll) of The Tale of Genji&quot; on its back side.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the Bank of Japan&apos;s D-note of 2,000 yen has a portrait of Murasaki Shikibu and a part of &quot;The Tale of Genji Emaki (picture scroll)&quot; on its back side.</e>
<cmt>The Tale of Genji Emaki としました（統一）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>国際連合教育科学文化機関（国際連合教育科学文化機関＝UNESCO）偉人暦に日本人として唯一人名を連ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name appeared in the great historical figures calendar of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (=UNESCO), and she was the only one Japanese enrolled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name appeared in the great historical figures calendar of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (=UNESCO), and she was the only Japanese to be thus enrolled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name appeared in the great historical figures calendar of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (=UNESCO), and she was the only Japanese to be thus enrolled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>紫式部日記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu Diary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki Shikibu Diary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu Diary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>人物評</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comment about people around her</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comment about people around her</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comment about people around her</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>同時期の有名だった女房たちの人物評が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can read some comments about her contemporary famous court ladies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You can read some comments about her contemporary famous court ladies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can read some comments about her contemporary famous court ladies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>中でも最も有名なのが枕草子作者の清少納言に対する、（以下、意訳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Above all, a comment about Sei Shonagon, an author of The Pillow Book, is the most famous (the following is a free translation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Above all, a comment about Sei Shonagon, author of &quot;The Pillow Book,&quot; is the most famous (the following is a free translation).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Above all, a comment about Sei Shonagon, the author of The Pillow Book, is the most famous (the following is a free translation):</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>「得意げに真名（漢字）を書き散らしているが、よく見ると間違いも多いし大した事はない」（「清少納言こそ したり顔にいみじうはべりける人 さばかりさかしだち 真名書き散らしてはべるほども よく見れば まだいと足らぬこと多かり」『紫日記』黒川本）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sei Shonagon is a jerk who acts proudly. Chinese characters, she blots in a wise, have full of mistakes.&apos;(&quot;Murasaki Diary&quot; Kurokawabon (type of manuscript))</e>
<cmt>「黒川本」&quot;Murasaki Shikibu Her diary and Poetic Memoirs&quot;by Richard Browringより</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sei Shonagon is a jerk who acts proudly. Chinese characters, she blots in a wise, have full of mistakes.&apos;(&quot;Murasaki Diary&quot; Kurokawabon (type of manuscript))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sei Shonagon is a jerk who acts proudly. Chinese characters, she blots in a wise, have full of mistakes.&apos;(&quot;Murasaki Diary&quot; Kurokawabon (type of manuscript))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>「こんな人の行く末にいいことがあるだろうか（いや、ない）」（「そのあだになりぬる人の果て いかでかはよくはべらむ」『紫日記』黒川本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Will life of a person with such insincerity be better in the future?&apos; (from &quot;Murasaki Diary&quot; Kurokawabon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Will the life of a person with such insincerity be better in the future?&quot; (from &quot;Murasaki Diary&quot; Kurokawabon)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Will the life of a person with such insincerity be better in the future?&quot; (from &quot;Murasaki Diary&quot; Kurokawabon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>などの、殆ど陰口ともいえる辛辣な批評である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These comets are quite severe and can be said almost backbiting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These comets are quite severe and can be said to be almost backbiting.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These comments are quite severe and can be said to be almost backbiting.</e>
<cmt>comets → comments</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これらの表記は近年に至るまで様々な憶測や、ある種野次馬的な興味（紫式部が清少納言の才能に嫉妬していたのだ、など）を持って語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These descriptions have been brought into conversation with various conjectures and curiosity (Murasaki Shikibu was jealous of the talent of Sei Shonagon, etc.) up until recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These descriptions have been brought into conversation with various conjectures and curiosity (Murasaki Shikibu was jealous of the talent of Sei Shonagon, etc.) up until recently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These descriptions have been brought into conversation with various conjectures and curiosity (Murasaki Shikibu was jealous of the talent of Sei Shonagon, etc.) up until recently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>もっとも、本人同士は年齢や宮仕えの年代も10年近く異なるため、実際に面識は無かったものと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these two people were separated in age and served the imperial court in different times, so they seem not to have known each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these two people were distant in age and served the Imperial Court in different times, so they seem not to have known each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these two people were distant in age and served the Imperial Court in different times (nearly a decade), so they seem not to have known each other.</e>
<cmt>「10年近く」を括弧で補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>同輩であった女流歌人の和泉式部（「素行は良くないが、歌は素晴らしい」など）や赤染衛門には好感を見せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She wrote some positive comments about her contemporary female poets, Izumi Shikibu and Akazome-emon (&apos;her behavior is not good, but poems are excellent.&apos; etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She wrote some positive comments about her contemporary female poets, Izumi Shikibu and Akazome-emon (&quot;her behavior is not good, but poems are excellent,&quot; etc.).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She wrote some positive comments about her contemporary female poets, Izumi Shikibu (&apos;her behavior is not good, but her poems are excellent,&apos; etc.), and Akazome-emon.</e>
<cmt>一部移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>日本紀の御局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsubone (court lady) of Nihongi (Six National Histories)</e>
<cmt>日本紀の訳語は「ルミナス和英辞典」（研究社）より。[以下、「ル和」と表記]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsubone (court lady) of Nihongi (Six National Histories)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsubone (court lady) of Nihongi (Six National Histories)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>『源氏物語』を女房に読ませて聞いた一条天皇が作者を褒めて、きっと日本紀（日本紀は『続日本紀』によれば『日本書紀』のことであるので『日本書紀』をさすという説がある）をよく読みこんでいる人に違いないと言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijo Emperor had a court lady read aloud &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; and praised the author saying that she must have read eagerly Nihongi. (According to &quot;Shoku Nihongi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan),&quot; Nihongi refers to &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; so some people claim that &quot;Nihongi&quot; in this context means &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Ichijo had a court lady read aloud &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; and praised the author, saying that she must have read eagerly Nihongi (according to &quot;Shoku Nihongi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan),&quot; Nihongi refers to &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; so some people claim that &quot;Nihongi&quot; in this context means &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Ichijo had a court lady read aloud &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; at which he praised the author, saying she must have been an eager reader of Nihongi (according to &quot;Shoku-Nihongi (Continuation of Chronicles of Japan),&quot; whereby Nihongi refers to &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot;; thus some people claim that &quot;Nihongi&quot; in this context means &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Shoku-Nihongiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このことから、「日本紀の御局」とあだ名されたとの逸話があるが、これには女性が漢文を読むことへの揶揄があり、本人には苦痛だったようであるとする説が通説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Murasaki Shikibu was given a nickname of &apos;Nihongi no Otsubone,&apos; but it is widely thought that Emperor&apos;s words brought her into ridicule that woman shouldn&apos;t read Chinese classics, and she was distressed by the words.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Murasaki Shikibu was given the nickname &quot;Nihongi no Otsubone,&quot; but it is widely thought that Emperor&apos;s words brought her into ridicule that woman shouldn&apos;t read Chinese classics, and she was distressed by the words.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Murasaki Shikibu was given the nickname &apos;Nihongi no Otsubone,&apos; but it is widely thought that the Emperor&apos;s words brought her into ridicule because it was felt that a woman shouldn&apos;t read Chinese classics, and she was distressed by the words.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>道長妾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga&apos;s mistress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga&apos;s mistress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga&apos;s mistress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>紫日記及び紫日記に一部記述が共通の『栄花物語』には又、夜半に道長が彼女の局をたずねて来る一節がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki Diary and &quot;Eiga monogatari (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes),&quot; which has some descriptions common to Murasaki Diary, says that Michinaga visited her chamber at night.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki Diary and &quot;Eiga monogatari (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes),&quot; the latter of which has some descriptions common to the Murasaki Diary, states that Michinaga visited her chamber at night.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki Diary and &quot;Eiga monogatari (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes),&quot; the latter of which has some descriptions common to the Murasaki Diary, states that Michinaga visited her chamber at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>鎌倉時代の公家系譜の集大成である『尊卑分脈』（『新編纂図本朝尊卑分脉系譜雑類要集』）になると、「上東門院女房　歌人　紫式部是也　源氏物語作者　或本雅正女云々　為時妹也云々　御堂関白道長妾」と紫式部の項にはっきり道長妾との註記が付くようになるが、彼女と道長の関係は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, &quot;Japanese Various Families&apos; Trees&quot; (&quot;New Compilation of Japanese Various Families&apos; Trees Analogy&quot;) says that &apos;A court lady of Jotomonin, poet, Murasaki Shikibu, an author of The Tale of Genji, or Masatada&apos;s granddaughter, Tametoki&apos;s daughter, mistress of Michinaga, the chief adviser to the Emperor,&apos; which shows clearly that she was a mistress of Michinaga, but true relationship between them is unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, &quot;Japanese Various Families&apos; Trees&quot; (&quot;New Compilation of Japanese Various Families&apos; Trees Analogy&quot;) says that &quot;a court lady of Jotomonin, poet, Murasaki Shikibu, an author of The Tale of Genji, or Masatada&apos;s granddaughter, Tametoki&apos;s daughter, mistress of Michinaga, the chief adviser to the Emperor,&quot; which shows clearly that she was a mistress of Michinaga, but true relationship between them is unknown.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, &quot;Various Japanese Family Trees&quot; (&quot;New Compilation of Various Japanese Family Trees Analogy&quot;) says that &apos;a court lady of Jotomonin, a poet, Murasaki Shikibu, an author of The Tale of Genji, or Masatada&apos;s granddaughter, Tametoki&apos;s daughter, mistress of Michinaga, the chief adviser to the Emperor,&apos; which clearly shows that she was a mistress of Michinaga, but the true relationship between them is unknown.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>主な作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>紫式部日記絵詞 （国宝） 藤田美術館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu Diary Ekotoba (explanation on a picture scroll) (National treasure) Fujita Museum of Art</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.okayama.okayama.jp/museum/fujita/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki Shikibu Diary Ekotoba (explanation on a picture scroll) (National treasure) Fujita Museum of Art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki Shikibu Diary Ekotoba (explanation on a picture scroll) (National treasure) Fujita Museum of Art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>紫式部学会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Academy of Murasaki Shikibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Academy of Murasaki Shikibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Academy of Murasaki Shikibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>紫式部学会とは、1932年（昭和7年）6月4日に、東京帝国大学文学部国文学科主任教授であった藤村作（会長）、東京帝国大学文学部国文学科教授であった久松潜一（副会長）、東京帝国大学文学部国文学研究室副手であった池田亀鑑（理事長）らによって源氏物語に代表される古典文学の啓蒙を目的として設立された学会である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose of Academy of Murasaki Shikibu is to promote classical literature represented by The Tale of Genji, and the academy was established on June 4 1932 by Tsukuru FUJIMURA (president), who was a head of Department of Japanese literature, Faculty of Letters at Tokyo Imperial University, and Senichi HISAMATSU (vice president), a professor of Japanese literature at Tokyo Imperial University, and Kikan IKEDA (chairperson), a junior assistant of the Japanese literature study room in Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E8%97%A4%E6%9D%91%E4%BD%9C&amp;stype=4&amp;dtype=0http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E4%B9%85%E6%9D%BE%E6%BD%9C%E4%B8%80&amp;stype=4&amp;dtype=0http://spysee.jp/池田亀鑑</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of the Academy of Murasaki Shikibu is to promote classical literature represented by &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; and the academy was established on June 4, 1932 by Tsukuru FUJIMURA (president), who was a head of the Department of Japanese literature, Faculty of Letters at Tokyo Imperial University, Senichi HISAMATSU (vice-president), a professor of Japanese literature at Tokyo Imperial University, and Kikan IKEDA (chairperson), a junior assistant of the Japanese literature study room of Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of the Academy of Murasaki Shikibu is to promote classical literature as represented by &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;; the academy was established on June 4, 1932 by Tsukuru FUJIMURA (president), who was the head of the Department of Japanese Literature, Faculty of Letters at Tokyo Imperial University; Senichi HISAMATSU (vice-president), a professor of Japanese literature at Tokyo Imperial University; and Kikan IKEDA (chairperson), a junior assistant of the Japanese literature study room at Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>1964年（昭和39年）1月より事務局が神奈川県横浜市鶴見区 (横浜市)にある鶴見大学文学部日本文学科研究室に置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since January 1964, the office has been set in Japanese literature department lab, School of Literature, Tsurumi University, which is located in Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>http://www.tsurumi-u.ac.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since January 1964, the office has been set in Japanese Literature Department lab, School of Literature, Tsurumi University, which is located in Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since January 1964, the office has been set in Japanese Literature Department lab, School of Literature, Tsurumi University, which is located in Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>現在の会長は秋山虔がつとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present president is Ken AKIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>http://spysee.jp/秋山虔</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current president is Ken AKIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current president is Ken AKIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>講演会を実施したり源氏物語を題材にした演劇の上演を後援したりしているほか以下の出版物を刊行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The academy holds lecture meetings, supports a play based on The Tale of Genji, and publishes the following periodicals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The academy holds lecture meetings, supports a play based on &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; and publishes the following periodicals:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The academy holds lecture meetings, supports a play based on &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; and publishes the following periodicals:</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>機関誌『むらさき』戦前（1934年（昭和9年）8月～1944年（昭和19年）6月）は月刊、戦後版（1962年（昭和37年）～）は年刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bulletin &quot;Murasaki&quot; was published every month before WWII (August, 1934 - June, 1944), and has been published annually after the war (since 1962).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bulletin &quot;Murasaki&quot; was published every month before World War II (August 1934 - June 1944), and has been published annually after the war era (since 1962).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bulletin &quot;Murasaki&quot; was published every month before World War II (August 1934 - June 1944), and has been published annually after the war era (since 1962).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>論文集『研究と資料　古代文学論叢』1969年（昭和44年）6月～年刊　武蔵野書院より刊行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collection of academic papers &quot;Studies and Data Traditional Literature Article&quot; has been published by Musashinoshoin annually since June, 1969.</e>
<cmt>http://www.musashinoshoin.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection of academic papers &quot;Studies and Data Traditional Literature Article&quot; has been published by Musashinoshoin annually since June 1969.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection of academic papers &quot;Studies and Data Traditional Literature Article&quot; has been published by Musashinoshoin annually since June 1969.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Topgun2(id:127294), Eskimbot(id:29676), Ideal(id:236), Lupinoid(id:68), Mishika(id:276), PipepBot(id:146181), ＋－(id:17104), 代言人(id:33675), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), BotMultichill(id:132395), Point136(id:211299), 豊臣浩勝(id:96439), Kzhr(id:131), Edith(id:10112), Toki-ho(id:10691), Romanm(id:963), MIO(id:31681), Escarbot(id:59151), Shimotsuke(id:19741), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Futy(id:195), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Jennifer(id:6990), AuBot(id:179501), 伏儀(id:142093), Suisui(id:69), Jade0416(id:104181), 唐変木(id:17050), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), JAnDbot(id:66507), 翠碧晶(id:68524), Reggaeman(id:6214), HenryLi(id:32447), Rai koku(id:1661), Mintleaf(id:2216), Qazzx(id:8772), Aa akogareno waga akita(id:27813), Kurz(id:1601), Masyu(id:31065), Yang g(id:3065), さららゆら(id:12274), A6M4(id:14155), Ganman(id:96316), 玄史生(id:43670), Goki(id:7107), Rei-bot(id:94097), こぶまき(id:38278), 竹麦魚(id:11012), A ITO(id:101750), ５１６(id:45205), Love(id:266), LERK(id:4460), Izayohi(id:13095), CALCULATOR(id:107643), 柿浜三歩(id:94283), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Tokumiki0(id:12043), Setu(id:88), Sokuraku(id:175042), Kyube(id:9866), 663highland(id:18755), Yume149(id:17504), Baffclan(id:499), Falcosapiens(id:221), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), Ytk m(id:112588), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>