<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新続古今和歌集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin Shoku Kokin Wakashu (NEW Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry Continued)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin Shoku Kokin Wakashu (NEW Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry Continued)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Shoku Kokin Wakashu (NEW Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry Continued)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『新続古今和歌集』（しんしょくこきんわかしゅう）は、室町時代の勅撰集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Shoku Kokin Wakashu&quot; is an anthology compiled by imperial command in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin Shoku Kokin Wakashu is an anthology compiled by imperial command in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Shoku Kokin Wakashu&quot; is an anthology compiled by imperial command in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>二十一代集の最後にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the last book of Nijuichidaishu (the twenty-one collections of waka compiled by imperial command).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the last book of Nijuichidaishu (the twenty-one collections of waka compiled by imperial command).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the last book of Nijuichidaishu (the twenty-one collections of waka compiled by imperial command).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>室町幕府第6代征夷大将軍足利義教の執奏により、後花園天皇の勅宣を以って中納言飛鳥井雅世（初名雅清）が撰進、和歌所開闔として堯孝が編纂に助力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) suggested to the Emperor Gohanazono to compile a new anthology, Emperor ordered Chunagon (Middle Councillor) Masayo ASUKAI (first named Masakiyo) to select poems, and Gyoko helped him with compilation as Deputy Chief of the office to compile imperial poetic anthology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) suggested to the Emperor Gohanazono to compile a new anthology, the Emperor ordered Chunagon (Middle Councillor) Masayo ASUKAI (first named Masakiyo) to select poems, and Gyoko helped him as Deputy Chief of the office to compile the imperial poetic anthology.</e>
<cmt>Cut &quot;with compilation&quot;. &quot;The Emperor&quot;. &quot;The imperial poetic anthology&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) suggested to the Emperor Gohanazono to compile a new anthology, the Emperor ordered Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) Masayo ASUKAI (first named Masakiyo) to select poems, and Gyoko helped him as Deputy Chief of the office to compile the imperial poetic anthology.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Middle Councillor&quot;→&quot;vice-councilor of state&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>永享五年（1433）八月二十五日下命、同十年（1438）八月二十三日四季部奏覧、翌十一年六月二十七日成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 25, 1433, the order was issued; on August 23, 1438, the four seasons&apos; part was submitted to the Emperor for inspection; on June 27 of the following year the anthology was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 25, 1433, the order was issued; on August 23, 1438, the four seasons&apos; part was submitted to the Emperor for inspection; on June 27 of the following year the anthology was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 17, 1433, the order was issued; on September 21, 1438, the four seasons&apos; part was submitted to the Emperor for inspection; on August 15 of the following year the anthology was completed.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に変更しました。。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>真・仮名序は共に一条兼良の筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manajo and Kanajo (the Chinese preface and the kana (the Japanese syllabaries) preface) were written by Kanera ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manajo and Kanajo (the Chinese preface and the kana (the Japanese syllabaries) preface) were written by Kanera ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manajo and Kanajo (the Chinese preface and the kana (the Japanese syllabaries) preface) were written by Kanera ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>撰進のために応製百首（永享百首）が召され、宝治（後嵯峨天皇）・弘安（亀山天皇）・嘉元（後宇多天皇）・文保（同）・貞和（尊円法親王）度の百首歌も選考資料となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to present poems to the Emperor, Oseihyakushu (100 poems on set themes, also known as Eikyo hyakushu) were composed, and some Hundred-Poem collections were also used for the anthology such as Hoji (hosted by Emperor Gosaga), Koan (hosted by Emperor Kameyama), Kagen (hosted by Emperor Gouda), Bunpo (hosted by Emperor Gouda), and Jowa (hosted by Imperial Prince priest Sonen).</e>
<cmt>宝治（後嵯峨天皇）は、後嵯峨天皇が主催した題詠の歌会のようです。その他、弘安、嘉元･･･なども同じです。参考URL（http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~sg2h-ymst/yamatouta/sennin/gosaga.html）（http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~SG2H-YMST/yamatouta/sennin/gouda.html）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to present poems to the Emperor, Oseihyakushu (100 poems on set themes, also known as Eikyo hyakushu) were composed, and some Hundred-Poem collections were also used for the anthology such as Hoji (hosted by Emperor Gosaga), Koan (hosted by Emperor Kameyama), Kagen (hosted by Emperor Gouda), Bunpo (hosted by Emperor Gouda), and Jowa (hosted by Imperial Prince priest Sonen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to present poems to the Emperor, Oseihyakushu (100 poems on set themes, also known as Eikyo hyakushu) were composed, and some Hundred-Poem collections were also used for the anthology such as Hoji (hosted by Emperor Gosaga), Koan (hosted by Emperor Kameyama), Kagen (hosted by Emperor Gouda), Bunpo (hosted by Emperor Gouda), and Jowa (hosted by Cloistered Imperial Prince priest Sonen).</e>
<cmt>Cloistered補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>下命時の後花園院は十五歳の若年ながら詩歌管弦の造詣深く、御製も多く伝わる好文の賢主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Gohanazono In ordered to compile the anthology, he was only 15, but had a profound knowledge of poetry and music, being known as a wise Emperor who made many poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Gohanazono In ordered to compile the anthology, he was only 15, but had a profound knowledge of poetry and music, being known as a wise Emperor who made many poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Gohanazono in ordered to compile the anthology, he was only 15, but had a profound knowledge of poetry and music, being known as a wise Emperor who made many poems.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>飛鳥井雅世は新古今和歌集選者の一人飛鳥井雅経の六世孫であり、庇護を受けた足利義教の推輓で選者の栄誉に浴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masayo ASUKAI was a great-great-great-great-great grandson of Masatsune ASUKAI, who was one of the compilers of Shin Kokin Waka Shu (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), and he had the honor to be chosen as compiler thanks to Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, who was his supporter.</e>
<cmt>六世孫→昆孫のことだと思いますが、ご確認ください。great-great-great-great-grandchildという訳語もあり、「great」の数がいくつ必要か不明です。参考URL（http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=great-great-great-great-great-great-grandchild）新編英和活用大辞典（研究社）では、「a great-great-great grandson of…： …の 4 代目の孫」となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masayo ASUKAI was a great-great-great-great-great grandson of Masatsune ASUKAI, who was one of the compilers of Shin Kokin Waka Shu (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), and he had the honor to be chosen as compiler thanks to Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, who was his supporter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masayo ASUKAI was a sixth generation descendant of Masatsune ASUKAI, who was one of the compilers of Shin Kokin Waka Shu (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), and he had the honor to be chosen as compiler thanks to Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, who was his supporter.</e>
<cmt>「六世孫」を&quot;sixth generation descendant&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>序文を執筆した一条兼良はいうまでもなく室町時代随一の文化人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Needles to day, Kanera ICHIJO was the greatest person of culture who lived in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Needless to say, Kanera ICHIJO was the greatest person of culture who lived in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Corrected spelling of &quot;needless to say&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Needless to say, Kanera ICHIJO was the greatest person of culture who lived in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>二十巻勅撰集の伝統的な構成を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Imperial anthology has a traditional structure of 20-volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Imperial anthology has a traditional structure of 20-volumes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Volumes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Imperial anthology has a traditional structure of 20-volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>名義を継いだ続古今和歌集の部立から、神祇と賀歌を入れ替え、千載和歌集に倣い神祇を末に置いた他に相違はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is no doubt that the anthology was compiled following the categorization used in Shoku Kokin Wakashu, though replacing poems on gods with ones on celebrating longevity, and putting the poems on gods at the end of the book modeled after Senzai Wakashu (Collection of Japanese Poems of a Thousand Years).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no doubt that the anthology was compiled following the categorization used in Shoku Kokin Wakashu, though replacing poems on gods with ones on celebrating longevity, and putting the poems on gods at the end of the book modeled after Senzai Wakashu (Collection of Japanese Poems of a Thousand Years).</e>
<cmt>&quot;It&quot;-&quot;there&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no doubt that the anthology was compiled following the categorization used in Shoku Kokin Wakashu, although replacing poems on gods with ones on celebrating longevity, and putting the poems on gods at the end of the book modeled after Senzai Wakashu (Collection of Japanese Poems of a Thousand Years).</e>
<cmt>though -&gt; &quot;although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>歌数は2140首強。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 2140 or more poems were collected in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 2140 or more poems were collected in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 2140 or more poems were collected in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幽玄・枯淡を基調とする二条派の歌風を踏襲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It follows a poetry style of the Nijo group which depended on ideas of yugen (a subtle and profound beauty) and kotan (simple and refined).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It follows the poetry style of the Nijo group which depended on ideas of yugen (a subtle and profound beauty) and kotan (simple and refined).</e>
<cmt>&quot;A&quot;-&quot;the&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It follows the poetry style of the Nijo group which depended on ideas of yugen (a subtle and profound beauty) and kotan (simple and refined).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>頓阿（19首）・二条為定（14首）・慶運（13首）に代表される二条派の重視に対し、京極派・冷泉派の入集は皆無に近く、選者とその庇護者の態度が知れよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nijo group&apos;s poems represented by Tona (19 poems), Tamesada NIJO (14 poems), and Keiun (13 poems) were considered important, while almost no poem of the Kyogoku group and Reizei group was collected, which makes the selectors and patron&apos;s intention revealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nijo group&apos;s poems represented by Tona (19 poems), Tamesada NIJO (14 poems), and Keiun (13 poems) were considered important, while almost no poems of the Kyogoku group and Reizei group were collected, revealing the selectors and patron&apos;s intentions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Poems…were&quot;. &quot;Which makes&quot;-&quot;revealing&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nijo group&apos;s poems represented by Tona (19 poems), Tamesada NIJO (14 poems), and Keiun (13 poems) were considered important, while almost no poems of the Kyogoku group and Reizei group were collected, revealing the selectors and patron&apos;s intentions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、女流の入選は極めて少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, a tiny number of poems written by the female poets were selected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, only a tiny number of poems written the female poets were selected.</e>
<cmt>Cut &quot;the&quot; and added &quot;only&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, only a tiny number of poems written the female poets were selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>選歌範囲は広く、新古今以後に重心を置きながら各時代より入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the poems were mainly selected from the ones composed after Shin Kokin, they range widely over every era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the poems were mainly selected from the ones composed after Shin Kokin, they range widely over every era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the poems were mainly selected from the ones composed after Shin Kokin, they range widely over every era.</e>
<cmt>Though -&gt; &quot;Although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>なかでも新古今時代を尊重し、九条良経・藤原俊成・藤原定家・藤原家隆および後鳥羽天皇・順徳天皇両院が入集数の上位を占める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compilers respected the period of Shin Kokin, and especially poems by Yoshitsune KUJO, FUJIWARA no Shunzei, FUJIWARA no Teika, Emperor Gotoba, and Emperor Juntoku which were selected more than others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compilers respected the period of Shin Kokin, and especially poems by Yoshitsune KUJO, FUJIWARA no Shunzei, FUJIWARA no Teika, Emperor Gotoba, and Emperor Juntoku which were selected more than others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compilers respected the period of Shin Kokin, and especially poems by Yoshitsune KUJO, FUJIWARA no Shunzei, FUJIWARA no Teika, FUJIWARA no Ietaka, Emperor Gotoba, and Emperor Juntoku which were selected more than others.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA no Ietaka補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当代からは、後小松天皇（26首）が入集数第三位、新続古今の発意者足利義教（18首）、そして下命者後花園院（12首）が重んじられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the contemporary poets, poems by Emperor Gokomatsu takes third place (26 poems), and a proposer of compiling Sin Shoku Kokin Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (18 poems) and a commander Gohanazono In (12 poems) were taken seriously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the contemporary poets, poems by Emperor Gokomatsu takes third place (26 poems), and the man who proposed the compilation of Sin Shoku Kokin Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (18 poems) and commander Gohanazono In (12 poems) were taken seriously.</e>
<cmt>&quot;A proposer of compiling&quot;-&quot;the man who proposed&quot;. Cut &quot;a&quot; from &quot;commander&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the contemporary poets, poems by Emperor Gokomatsu takes third place (26 poems), and the man who proposed the compilation of Sin Shoku Kokin Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (18 poems) and commander Gohanazono in (12 poems) were taken seriously.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義教以外にも武家方の歌が頗る多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many poems composed by those who were from the samurai families except Yoshinori were chosen too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many poems composed by those who were from the samurai families except Yoshinori were chosen too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many poems composed by those who were from the samurai families except Yoshinori were chosen too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>巻頭歌人にして最多入集は選者雅世の父飛鳥井雅縁（29首）であり、雅世（18首）自身、雅経（18首）・飛鳥井雅有（14首）ら選者の先祖の優遇が目立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The selector Masayo&apos;s father, Masayori ASUKAI&apos;s poems were selected most (29 poems) and one of his poems was put at the beginning of the book; besides it is obvious that the poems by the selector&apos;s ancestors were treated favorably: Masayo&apos;s own poems (18 poems), Masatsune&apos;s (18 poems), and Masaari ASUKAI&apos;s (14 poems) were selected a lot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The selector Masayo&apos;s father, Masayori ASUKAI&apos;s poems were selected most (29 poems) and one of his poems was put at the beginning of the book; besides it is obvious that the poems by the selector&apos;s ancestors were treated favorably: Masayo&apos;s own poems (18 poems), Masatsune&apos;s (18 poems), and Masaari ASUKAI&apos;s (14 poems) were frequently selected.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Selected a lot&quot;-&quot;frequently selected&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The selector Masayo&apos;s father, Masayori ASUKAI&apos;s poems were selected most (29 poems) and one of his poems was put at the beginning of the book; besides it is obvious that the poems by the selector&apos;s ancestors were treated favorably: Masayo&apos;s own poems (18 poems), Masatsune&apos;s (18 poems), and Masaari ASUKAI&apos;s (14 poems) were frequently selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>後花園は再度の勅撰集計画も練っていたが、応仁の乱によって中断し、以後勅撰集は編まれなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gohanazono was planning to make another Imperial anthology, but it was interrupted by the Onin War, and no anthology was compiled after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gohanazono was planning to make another Imperial anthology, but it was interrupted by the Onin War, and no anthology was compiled after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gohanazono was planning to make another Imperial anthology, but it was interrupted by the Onin War, and no anthology was compiled after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yume149(id:17504), Yas(id:739), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>