<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>布都御魂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futsu no mitama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futsunomitama</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futsunomitama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>布都御魂（ふつのみたま）は、記紀神話に現れる霊剣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futsu no mitama is a divine sword described in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futsunomitama is a divine sword described in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and mythology.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futsunomitama is a divine sword described in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>韴霊剣、布都御魂剣（ふつみたまのつるぎ）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Futsunomitama no Tsurugi (sword).</e>
<cmt>韴霊剣、布都御魂剣はいずれも同じ読みなので英文ではひとつにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Futsunomitama no Tsurugi (sword) or Futsumitama no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>韴霊剣、布都御魂剣はいずれも同じ読みなので英文ではひとつにしました→different pronunciation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Futsunomitama no Tsurugi (sword) or Futsumitama no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>佐士布都神（さじふつのかみ）、甕布都神（みかふつのかみ）とも言い、「ふつ」は物を断ち切る音を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Sajifutsu no kami or Mikafutsu no kami, and a word &quot;futsu&quot; in these names indicates a sound of cutting something off with a sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Sajifutsu no Kami or Mikafutsu no Kami, and the word &quot;futsu&quot; in these names indicates the sound of cutting something off with a sword.</e>
<cmt>capital for name/article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Sajifutsu no Kami or Mikafutsu no Kami, and the word &quot;futsu&quot; in these names indicates the sound of cutting something off with a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>建御雷神（たけみかずちのかみ）はこれを用い、葦原中国（あしはらのなかつくに）を平定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takemikazuchi-no-kami used this sword to pacify Ashihara no Nakatsukuni (the Central Land of Reed Plains).</e>
<cmt>原文では「タケミカヅチ」とカタカナでしたがWebでは漢字でしたので修正しました。また、「葦原中国平定した。」とありましたが単に「平定した。」でしたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takemikazuchi no Kami (The god Takemikazuchi) used this sword to pacify Ashihara no Nakatsukuni (the Central Land of Reed Plains).</e>
<cmt>capital and spacing instead of hyphensadded the explanation of Takemikazuchi no Kami</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takemikazuchi no Kami (The god Takemikazuchi) used this sword to pacify Ashihara no Nakatsukuni (the Central Land of Reed Plains).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>神武東征の折り、ナガスネヒコ誅伐に失敗し、熊野山中で危機に陥った時、高倉下が神武天皇の下に持参した劔がふつみたまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Jinmu tosei (Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu), when the emperor failed to kill Nagasunehiko and beleaguered in the Mount Kumano, Takakuraji presented the Futsumitama sword to the emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Jinmu tosei (Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu), when the emperor failed to kill Nagasunehiko and was beleaguered in the Mount Kumano, Takakuraji presented the Futsumitama sword to the Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>articlecapital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the Jinmu tosei (Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu), when the emperor failed to kill Nagasunehiko and was beleaguered in the Mount Kumano, Takakuraji presented the Futsumitama sword to the Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その剣の霊力は軍勢を毒気から覚醒させ、活力を得てのちの戦争に勝利し、大和国の征服に大いに役立ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spiritual power of the sword awakened the army from the poisonous air and revived them to win the war, so the sword was very useful in the conquest of the Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spiritual power of the sword awakened the army from the poisonous air and revived them to win the war, so it is said that the sword was very useful in the conquest of the Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>added words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spiritual power of the sword awakened the army from the poisonous air and revived them to win the war, so it is said that the sword was very useful in the conquest of the Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>荒ぶる神を退けるちからを持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sword has a power to defeat Araburu Kami (Malignant gods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sword has the power to defeat Araburu Kami (malignant gods).</e>
<cmt>article/ lower case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sword has the power to defeat Araburu Kami (malignant gods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>神武の治世にあっては、物部氏の祖と言われる宇摩志麻治命（うましまじのみこと）が宮中で祭った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Jinmu, Futsu no mitama was enshrined in the Imperial court by Umashimaji no mikoto who was said to be the founder of the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of Emperor Jinmu, Futsunomitama was enshrined in the Imperial court by Umashimaji no Mikoto who is said to be the founder of the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>spacing/ capital/ grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Jinmu, Futsunomitama was enshrined in the Imperial court by Umashimaji no Mikoto who is said to be the founder of the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>崇神天皇の代に至り、同じく物部氏の伊香色雄命（いかがしこおのみこと）の手によって石上神宮に移され、御神体となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Sujin, Ikagashiko o no mikoto of the Mononobe clan transferred the sword to the Isonokami Shrine where it was worshipped as goshintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the reign of Emperor Sujin, Ikagashiko no Mikoto of the Mononobe clan transferred the sword to the Isonokami-jingu Shrine where it was worshipped as a goshintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt>the name rule for temples and shrinescapital/ article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Sujin, Ikagashiko no Mikoto of the Mononobe clan transferred the sword to the Isonokami-jingu Shrine where it was worshipped as a goshintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同社の祭神である布都御魂大神（ふつのみたまのおおかみ）は、布都御魂の霊とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enshrined deity of the Isonokami Shrine is Futsu no mitama no Okami that is said to be a divine spirit of Futsu no mitama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enshrined deity of the Isonokami-jingu Shrine is Futsunomitama no Okami which is said to be a divine spirit of Futsunomitama.</e>
<cmt>the name rule for temples and shrinescapital/vocabulary/ spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enshrined deity of the Isonokami-jingu Shrine is Futsunomitama no Okami which is said to be a divine spirit of Futsunomitama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>布都御魂はやがて拝殿の裏手の禁足地に埋められるが、明治7年（1874年）に当時の大宮司の菅政友によって発掘され、本殿に奉安され、神体として祭られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futsu no mitama was later buried in the Kinsokuchi (tabooed land) at the back of the haiden (a hall of worship) of the shrine, but in 1874 it was excavated by Masatomo KAN, the chief priest of the shrine at the time, and enshrined in the Honden (main shrine building) and it is still worshipped today as goshintai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futsunomitama was later buried in the kinsokuchi (tabooed land) at the back of the haiden (a hall of worship) of the shrine, but in 1874 it was excavated by Masatomo KAN, the chief priest of the shrine at the time, and enshrined in the honden (main shrine building) and it is still worshipped today as goshintai.</e>
<cmt>lower case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futsunomitama was later buried in the kinsokuchi (tabooed land) at the back of the haiden (a hall of worship) of the shrine, but in 1874 it was excavated by Masatomo KAN, the chief priest of the shrine at the time, and enshrined in the honden (main shrine building) and it is still worshipped today as goshintai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>菅政友によって発掘された物は、形状は内反り（通常の日本刀とは逆に刃の方に湾曲）の片刃の鉄刀。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The object excavated by Masatomo KAN was a single-edged iron sword that was curved to the opposite side to the ordinary Japanese swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The object excavated by Masatomo KAN was a single-edged iron sword that was curved to the opposite side to the ordinary Japanese swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The object excavated by Masatomo KAN was a single-edged iron sword that was curved to the opposite side to the ordinary Japanese swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>柄頭に環頭が付いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had a ring pommel at the handle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had a ring pommel at the handle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had a ring pommel at the handle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>全長は記録によって微妙に異なるが、85cm位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length of the sword is about 85 centimeters, although it slightly varies from record to record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The length of the sword is about 85 centimeters, although it varies slightly from record to record.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The length of the sword is about 85 centimeters, although it varies slightly from record to record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>一方、鹿島神宮にも布都御魂剣または韴霊剣（ふつのみたまのつるぎ）と称する巨大な直刀が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kashima-jingu Shrine also has a huge straight sword named Futsunomitama no Tsurugi (sword).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kashima-jingu Shrine also has a huge straight sword named Futsumitama no Tsurugi (sword) or Futsunomitama no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>addded words for 布都御魂剣または</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kashima-jingu Shrine also has a huge straight sword named Futsumitama no Tsurugi (sword) or Futsunomitama no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>由来は不明であるが、奈良時代末期から平安時代初期の制作とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its origin is unknown, but it is estimated to be made in the days between the end of Nara Period and the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its origin is unknown, but it is estimated to have been made in the days between the end of Nara Period and the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its origin is unknown, but it is estimated to have been made in the days between the end of Nara Period and the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>国宝に指定されており、鹿島神宮の宝物館にて展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is designated as the National Treasure and exhibited in the treasure hall of the Kashima-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is designated as a national treasure and exhibited in the treasure hall of the Kashima-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>article/ lower case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is designated as a national treasure and exhibited in the treasure hall of the Kashima-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>→鹿島神宮国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kashima-jingu Shrine National Treasure</e>
<cmt>web表記では「→詳細」となっているので翻訳対象外ではないでしょうか。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kashima-jingu Shrine National Treasure</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashima-jingu Shrine National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>登場する作品および扱い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary works in which Futsu no mitama appears</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary works in which Futsunomitama appears</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary works in which Futsunomitama appears</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>赤石路代『永遠かもしれない』で登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futsu no mitama appears in Michiyo AKAISHI&apos;s manga comic &quot;Towa kamo shirenai (may be eternal).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futsunomitama appears in Michiyo AKAISHI&apos;s manga comic &quot;Towa kamo shirenai&quot; (May Be Eternal).</e>
<cmt>spacing/ punctuation rules/ capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futsunomitama appears in Michiyo AKAISHI&apos;s manga comic &quot;Towa kamo shirenai&quot; (May Be Eternal).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>巫女守である日嗣が鹿島神宮に収められていたのを手にし、結界を作るために神宮内にある石鳥居を斬った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsugi, a guardian of miko (a shrine maiden), took Futsu no mitama that was enshrined in the Kashima-jingu Shrine and cut the stone Torii (shrine gate) to create kekkai (barrier).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsugi, a guardian of miko (a shrine maiden), took the Futsunomitama that was enshrined in the Kashima-jingu Shrine and cut the stone torii (shrine gate) to create kekkai (barrier).</e>
<cmt>spacing/ lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsugi, a guardian of miko (a shrine maiden), took the Futsunomitama that was enshrined in the Kashima-jingu Shrine and cut the stone torii (shrine gate) to create kekkai (barrier).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>後に富士山での噴火を沈めるために溶岩を断ち斬った際に大破してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when Hitsugi used the sword to cut lava to put out an eruption of the Mount Fuji, the sword was destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when Hitsugi used the sword to cut lava to stop an eruption of Mount Fuji, the sword was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary/article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when Hitsugi used the sword to cut lava to stop an eruption of Mount Fuji, the sword was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Plume(id:28701), SKD(id:16685), Suguri F(id:11127), Wiki0825(id:34646), Nnh(id:474), 新芽(id:50924), K-Phil(id:53114), ひろたん(id:28163), Himazin(id:22034), Greenland4(id:114494), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>