<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京極為兼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamekane KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamekane KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamekane KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>京極 為兼（きょうごく ためかね、建長6年（1254年） - 元徳4年/元弘2年3月21日 (旧暦)（1332年4月16日））は、鎌倉時代後期の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamekane KYOGOKU (born 1254, died April 16, 1332 according to the modern calendar) was a late Kamakura-period waka poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamekane KYOGOKU (born 1254, died April 16, 1332 according to the modern calendar) was a late Kamakura-period waka poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamekane KYOGOKU (1254 - April 16, 1332) was a late Kamakura-period waka poet.</e>
<cmt>日付の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は藤原為家の3男で京極家の祖京極為教。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Tamenori KYOGOKU, third son of FUJIWARA no Tameie and founder of the KYOGOKU family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Tamenori KYOGOKU, third son of FUJIWARA no Tameie and founder of the KYOGOKU family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Tamenori KYOGOKU, third son of FUJIWARA no Tameie and founder of the KYOGOKU family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は三善雅衡の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Gako MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Gako MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Gako MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>冷泉為兼・入江為兼とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also sometimes known as Tamekane REIZEI or Tamekane IRIE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also sometimes known as Tamekane REIZEI or Tamekane IRIE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also sometimes known as Tamekane REIZEI or Tamekane IRIE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>若い頃に祖父藤原為家に和歌を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was a boy, he learned about waka poetry from his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Tameie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was a boy, he learned about waka poetry from his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Tameie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was a boy, he learned about waka poetry from his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Tameie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1280年（弘安3年）東宮煕仁親王（後の伏見天皇）に出仕し、東宮及びその側近らに和歌を指導して京極派と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1280 (Koan 3), Tamekane began serving crown prince Hirohito (who later became Emperor Fushimi), and the style of waka poetry in which he instructed the crown prince and his close associates came to be known as the Kyogoku school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1280 (Koan 3), Tamekane began serving crown prince Hirohito (who later became Emperor Fushimi), and the style of waka poetry in which he instructed the crown prince and his close associates came to be known as the Kyogoku school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1280, Tamekane began serving Imperial Prince Hirohito (who later became Emperor Fushimi), and the style of waka poetry in which he instructed the Imperial Prince and his close associates came to be known as the Kyogoku school.</e>
<cmt>元号削除親王の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>伏見天皇が践践した後は政治家としても活躍したが、持明院統側公家として皇統の迭立に関与したことから、1298年（永仁6年）佐渡国に配流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once Emperor Fushimi ascended to the throne Tamekane also became active as a politician, but was banished to Sado province in 1298 (Einin 6) for his participation in the attempt, as an aristocratic supporter of the Jimyoin lineage, to manipulate the Imperial succession in favor of the Jimyoin line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once Emperor Fushimi ascended to the throne Tamekane also became active as a politician, but was banished to Sado province in 1298 (Einin 6) for his participation in the attempt, as an aristocratic supporter of the Jimyoin lineage, to manipulate the Imperial succession in favor of the Jimyoin line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once Emperor Fushimi ascended to the throne Tamekane also became active as a politician, but was banished to Sado Province in 1298 for his participation in the attempt, as an aristocratic supporter of the Jimyoin lineage, to manipulate the Imperial succession in favor of the Jimyoin line.</e>
<cmt>元号削除スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1303年（嘉元元年）に帰京が許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1303 (Kagen 1) he received permission to return to the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1303 (Kagen 1) he received permission to return to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1303 he received permission to return to the capital.</e>
<cmt>元号削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>勅撰和歌集の撰者をめぐって二条為世と論争するが、院宣を得て1312年（正和元年）「玉葉和歌集」を撰集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fell into conflict with Tameyo NIJO over who would be chosen as a compiler of the latest Imperial waka anthology, but received an imperial decree appointing him such, and in 1312 (Showa 1) he set about compiling the Gyokuyo wakashu (The Jeweled Leaves Collection).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fell into conflict with Tameyo NIJO over who would be chosen as a compiler of the latest Imperial waka anthology, but received an imperial decree appointing him such, and in 1312 (Showa 1) he set about compiling the Gyokuyo wakashu (The Jeweled Leaves Collection).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fell into conflict with Tameyo NIJO over who would be chosen as a compiler of the latest Imperial waka anthology, but received an imperial decree appointing him such, and in 1312 he set about compiling the &apos;Gyokuyo wakashu&apos; (The Jeweled Leaves Collection).</e>
<cmt>元号削除&apos;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌1313年（正和2年）伏見上皇とともに出家し、法号を蓮覚のちに静覚と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, in 1313 (Showa 2), he took the tonsure together with Retired Emperor Fushimi, and took the monk-name &quot;Renkaku,&quot; and later &quot;Shokaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, in 1313 (Showa 2), he took the tonsure together with Retired Emperor Fushimi, and took the monk-name &quot;Renkaku,&quot; and later &quot;Shokaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, in 1313, he took the tonsure together with Retired Emperor Fushimi, and took the monk-name &quot;Renkaku,&quot; and later &quot;Shokaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>元号削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1315年（正和4年）再び鎌倉幕府の六波羅探題に捕らえられ、翌1316年（正和5年）土佐国に配流となり、帰京を許されないまま河内国で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1315 (Showa 4), he was once again arrested by the Tandai (Governor-General) of Rokuhara, and in 1316 was exiled to Tosa province; this time, he never received permission to return to the capital, and ended his life in Kawachi province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1315 (Showa 4), he was once again arrested by the Tandai (Governor-General) of Rokuhara, and in 1316 was exiled to Tosa province; this time, he never received permission to return to the capital, and ended his life in Kawachi province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1315, he was once again arrested by the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), and in 1316 was exiled to Tosa Province; this time, he never received permission to return to the capital, and ended his life in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>元号削除Tandai (Governor-General) of Rokuhara→Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto)スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>2度の流刑の背景には「徳政」の推進を通じて朝廷の権威を取り戻そうとしていた伏見天皇と鎌倉幕府の対立が激化して、為兼が天皇の身代わりとして処分されたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The background for why he was twice punished with exile lies in his promoting of the idea of &quot;benevolent rule,&quot; in which he and Emperor Fushimi sought to restore true power to the imperial court and fell into an intensifying conflict with the Kamakura shogunate; one explanation has it that Tamekane served as scapegoat for the Emperor, being punished in his stead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background for why he was twice punished with exile lies in his promoting of the idea of &quot;benevolent rule,&quot; in which he and Emperor Fushimi sought to restore true power to the imperial court and fell into an intensifying conflict with the Kamakura shogunate; one explanation has it that Tamekane served as scapegoat for the Emperor, being punished in his stead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background for why he was twice punished with exile lies in his promoting of the idea of &apos;benevolent rule,&apos; in which he and Emperor Fushimi sought to restore true power to the imperial court and fell into an intensifying conflict with the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun); one explanation has it that Tamekane served as scapegoat for the Emperor, being punished in his stead.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>家風は実感を尊び、繊細で感覚的な表現による歌を詠み、沈滞していた鎌倉時代末期の歌壇に新風を吹き込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the poetic style of his family the evoking of true emotions was very highly prized, leading him to compose waka that expressed a delicate yet sensuous quality; this new style breathed life into the stagnated waka circles of late Kamakura-period Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the poetic style of his family the evoking of true emotions was very highly prized, leading him to compose waka that expressed a delicate yet sensuous quality; this new style breathed life into the stagnated waka circles of late Kamakura-period Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the poetic style of his family the evoking of true emotions was very highly prized, leading him to compose waka that expressed a delicate yet sensuous quality; this new style breathed life into the stagnated waka circles of late Kamakura-period Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「玉葉和歌集」「風雅和歌集」に和歌が入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His waka were included in the &quot;Gyokuyo wakashu&quot; (Collected Jeweled Leaves (of waka)) and the &quot;Fuga wakashu&quot; (Collected Elegant Waka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His waka were included in the Gyokuyo wakashu (Collected Jeweled Leaves (of waka)) and the Fuga wakashu (Collected Elegant Waka).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His waka were included in the &apos;Gyokuyo wakashu&apos; (Collected Jeweled Leaves (of waka)) and the &apos;Fuga wakashu&apos; (Collected Elegant Waka).</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>