<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竹河</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takekawa (Bamboo River)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takekawa (Bamboo River)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takekawa (Bamboo River)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>竹河（たけかわ）は、『源氏物語』五十四帖の巻名のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takekawa is a chapter title of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) which has fifty four chapters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takekawa is a chapter title of Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji) which has fifty four chapters.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takekawa is a chapter title of &quot;Genji Monogatari &quot;(The Tale of Genji) which has fifty four chapters.</e>
<cmt>書名の引用符を元に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第44帖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the forty-fourth chapter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the forty-fourth chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the forty-fourth chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>髭黒太政大臣亡き後の北の方玉鬘 (源氏物語)の奮闘記を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It describes the struggle of Kita no kata (the woman living in the north of the house; wife) Tamakazura after the death of Higekuro Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It describes the struggle of Kita no kata (the woman living in the north of the house) Tamakazura after the death of Higekuro Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>Wasn&apos;t sure what &quot;wife&quot; meant here so I cut it.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It describes a struggle of Tamakazura, Kita no kata (the woman living in the north of the house; wife) of Higekuro Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), after his death.</e>
<cmt>（源氏物語）はリンク先の言葉のため、訳出しませんでした。FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plot summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Story line&quot;-&quot;plot summary&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plot summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>薫14歳から23歳までの話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a story of Kaoru&apos;s life between the ages of fourteen and twenty three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the story of Kaoru&apos;s life between the ages of fourteen and twenty three.</e>
<cmt>&quot;A&quot;-&quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the story of Kaoru&apos;s life between the ages of fourteen and twenty three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>髭黒太政大臣亡き後、玉鬘は遺された三男二女を抱え、零落した家を復興させんと躍起になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Higekuro Daijo-daijin passed away, Tamakazura was out to revive the reduced family raising her three sons and two daughters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Higekuro Daijo-daijin passed away, Tamakazura was out to restore her ruined family by raising her three sons and two daughters.</e>
<cmt>I thought &quot;Revive&quot;-&quot;restore&quot; and &quot;Reduced&quot;-&quot;ruined&quot; would read better here. Also added &quot;by&quot; before &quot;raising&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Higekuro Daijo-daijin passed away, Tamakazura was left with her three sons and two daughters, and tried to restore her ruined family.</e>
<cmt>（源氏物語）はリンク先の言葉のため、訳出しませんでした。FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>姫君二人（大君、中の君）には、今上帝 (源氏物語)や冷泉帝から声がかかるが、帝には義妹の明石の姫君が、冷泉院には異母姉の弘徽殿女御がいるため、玉鬘は判断に迷っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two himegimi (daughter of a person of high rank), Oigimi (oldest sister) and Naka no Kimi were asked to marry by Kinjo no Mikado and Emperor Reizei, but Mikado and Emperor Reizei were already married to young lady Akashi, her sister-in-law and Kokiden no nyogo (Empress Kokiden), her half sister, respectively, thus Tamakazura hesitated what to do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two himegimi (daughter of a person of high rank), Oigimi (oldest sister) and Naka no Kimi were asked to marry Kinjo no Mikado and Emperor Reizei, but Mikado and Emperor Reizei were already married to young lady Akashi, her sister-in-law and Kokiden no nyogo (Empress Kokiden), her half sister, respectively, thus Tamakazura hesitated about what to do.</e>
<cmt>Not entirely sure about the meaning of this sentence, but I assumed the &quot;by&quot; after &quot;marry&quot; should be deleted.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinjo no Mikado and Emperor Reizei asked Tamakazura to let them marry her two daughters, Oigimi (oldest sister) and Naka no Kimi, but Mikado had already been married to young lady Akashi, her sister-in-law, and Emperor Reizei had Kokiden no nyogo (Empress Kokiden), her older sister by a different mother, so she did not know what to do.</e>
<cmt>（源氏物語）はリンク先の言葉のため、訳出しませんでした。FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、薫や蔵人少将（夕霧 (源氏物語)の五男）も大君に思いを寄せる求婚者の一人だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Kaoru and Kurodo no Shosho (Chamberlain Lieutenant) who was Yugiri (Evening Mist)&apos;s fifth son were Oigimi&apos;s suitors.</e>
<cmt>蔵人少将の訳語は下記サイトを参考にしました。http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=M76Xesfoy3sC&amp;pg=PA1161&amp;lpg=PA1161&amp;dq=%E2%80%9DKurodo+no+Shosho%E2%80%9D&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Yi724BsUFM&amp;sig=h6nJFlWUcP9zlo7KsB3W-wilChA&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=t6isStTIAo6YkQW60OCVBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1#v=onepage&amp;q=%E2%80%9DKurodo%20no%20Shosho%E2%80%9D&amp;f=false</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru and Kurodo no Shosho (Chamberlain Lieutenant) who was Yugiri (Evening Mist)&apos;s fifth son were also Oigimi&apos;s suitors.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;also&quot; to after &quot;were&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru and Kurodo no Shosho (Chamberlain Lieutenant) who was Yugiri (Evening Mist)&apos;s fifth son were also Oigimi&apos;s suitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>薫15歳の正月下旬、玉鬘邸に若者たちが集まって催馬楽の「竹河」を謡い興じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late January when Kaoru was fifteen, young people gathered at Tamakazura&apos;s residence to sing &quot;Takekawa&quot; of Saibara (genre of Heian-period Japanese court music (primarily consisting of gagaku-styled folk melodies)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In late January when Kaoru was fifteen, young people gathered at Tamakazura&apos;s residence to sing &quot;Takekawa&quot; in the Saibara style (a genre of Heian-period Japanese court music (primarily consisting of gagaku-styled folk melodies)).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;in the Saibara style&quot; to make it a bit clearer.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In late January when Kaoru was fifteen, young people gathered at Tamakazura&apos;s residence to sing &quot;Takekawa&quot; in the Saibara style (a genre of Heian-period Japanese court music (primarily consisting of gagaku-styled folk melodies)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その席で玉鬘は薫が弾く和琴の音色が亡父頭中将や亡兄柏木に似ていることに気付く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Tamakazura realized that the sound of wagon (Japanese harp) which Kaoru was playing was similar to that of her deceased father, Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) and her deceased older brother, Kashiwagi (The Oak Tree).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Tamakazura realized that the sound of wagon (Japanese harp) which Kaoru was playing was similar to that of her deceased father, Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) and her deceased older brother, Kashiwagi (The Oak Tree).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Tamakazura realized that the sound of wagon (Japanese harp) which Kaoru was playing was similar to that by her deceased father, Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain), and her deceased older brother, Kashiwagi (The Oak Tree).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>3月のサクラの盛りの夕暮れ時、二人の姫君は御簾をあげ、桜の木を賭け碁を打っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At dusk of March, when the cherry blossoms were in full bloom, two himegimi opened the bamboo blind and played a game of Go for a cherry blossom tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At dusk in March, when the cherry blossoms were in full bloom, two himegimi opened the bamboo blind and played a game of Go with a cherry blossom tree for stakes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Of&quot;-&quot;in&quot;. Added &quot;for stakes&quot; to make it a bit clearer.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At dusk in March, when the cherry blossoms were in full bloom, two himegimi opened the bamboo blind and played a game of Go for the cherry blossom tree.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>蔵人少将はその姿を垣間見て、ますます大君への思いを募らせるのだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurodo no Shosho saw that and increasingly heighten feelings for Oigimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurodo no Shosho saw this and felt his feelings for Oigimi deepen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;That&quot;-&quot;this&quot;. I thought &quot;and felt his feelings for Oigimi deepen&quot; would read more naturally here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurodo no Shosho saw this and felt his feelings for Oigimi deepen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>玉鬘は、大君を冷泉院のもとへ参らせることを決意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamakazura decided to make Oigimi get marry to Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamakazura decided to make Oigimi marry Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;get&quot; and &quot;to&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamakazura decided to make Oigimi marry Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これを知った少将は落胆のあまり母雲居の雁に訴える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">when Shosho found the fact, he was so disappointed and appealed to his mother, Kumoi no Kari and she sent a letter of protest to Tamakazura, then Tamakazura puzzled over that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shosho discovered this, he was so disappointed he appealed to his mother, Kumoi no Kari and she sent a letter of protest to Tamakazura, who was unsure what to do.</e>
<cmt>&quot;when&quot;-&quot;When&quot;. &quot;Found the fact&quot;-&quot;discovered this&quot;. &quot;And&quot;-&quot;he&quot;. &quot;then Tamakazura puzzled over that&quot;-&quot;who was unsure what to do&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shosho knew this, he was so disappointed that he appealed to his mother, Kumoi no Kari,</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>雲居雁は玉鬘に抗議の文を送り、玉鬘は頭を悩ませる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumoi no Kari sent a letter of protest to Tamakazura, so she was unsure what to do.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>4月に参院した大君は冷泉院に深く寵愛される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oigimi entered the imperial palace and deeply favored by Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oigimi entered the imperial palace and Emperor Reizei felt great affection towards her.</e>
<cmt>&quot;deeply favored by Emperor Reizei&quot;-&quot;Emperor Reizei felt great affection towards her&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oigimi entered the imperial palace in April and Emperor Reizei felt great affection towards her.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>一方所望が叶わなかった今上帝の機嫌は悪く、息子たちは玉鬘を責める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Kinjo no Mikado was in a bad mood because his wish was not granted, thus her sons blamed Tamakazura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Kinjo no Mikado was in a bad mood because his wish was not granted, and her sons blamed Tamakazura for this.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Thus her sons&quot;-&quot;and her sons…for this&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Kinjo no Mikado was in a bad mood because his wish was not accepted, so her sons blamed Tamakazura.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>翌年4月、大君は女宮を出産。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of the following year, Oigimi gave birth to an onna miya (Japanese imperial princess).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of the following year, Oigimi gave birth to an onna miya (Japanese imperial princess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of the following year, Oigimi gave birth to an onna miya (Japanese imperial princess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>玉鬘は自分の内侍司の役を中の君に譲り、今上帝のもとへ入内させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamakazura transferred her position as Naishi no tsukasa (female palace attendants) to Naka no Kimi and made her get married to Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamakazura transferred her position as Naishi no tsukasa (female palace attendants) to Naka no Kimi and made her marry Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Get married to&quot;-&quot;marry&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamakazura handed over her position of Naishi no tsukasa (female palace attendant) to Naka no Kimi, marrying her to Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>その後も冷泉院の寵愛は冷めやらず、数年後、大君は男御子を出産する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after that, Emperor Reizei&apos;s favor didn&apos;t fade and Oigimi gave birth to an imperial prince a few years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that, Emperor Reizei&apos;s affection didn&apos;t fade and Oigimi gave birth to an imperial prince a few years later.</e>
<cmt>Changed to &quot;affection&quot; to match translation above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that, Emperor Reizei&apos;s affection didn&apos;t fade and Oigimi gave birth to an imperial prince a few years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>冷泉院は大喜びだがかえって周囲の者たちから嫉妬を買い、気苦労から大君は里下がりすることが多くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Reizei was greatly pleased, but Oigimi was envied by other people and she often went home due to the worry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Reizei was greatly pleased, but Oigimi was envied by other people and she often went home due to the worry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Reizei was greatly pleased, but Oigimi came to go back home frequently due to mental exhaustion because those around her were jealous.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>一方、中の君は今上帝のもとで気楽に過ごしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Naka no Kimi lived in comfort with Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Naka no Kimi lived in comfort with Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Naka no Kimi lived in comfort with Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>それから数年の月日が流れ、薫は中納言に、蔵人少将も宰相中将に、それぞれ順調に昇進していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A few years have passed since then, Kaoru and Kurodo no Shosho were steadily promoted to Chunagon (middle counsellor) and Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain), respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A few years later, Kaoru and Kurodo no Shosho were steadily promoted to Chunagon (middle counsellor) and Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain), respectively.</e>
<cmt>&quot;A few years passed&quot;-&quot;a few years later&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A few years later, Kaoru and Kurodo no Shosho were steadily promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) and Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain) respectively.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。middle counsellor→vice-councilor of stateに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>玉鬘は大君の不幸や自分の息子たちの出世の遅さと比べるにつけ、思うに任せぬ世を悔しく思い後悔の念は耐えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamakazura compared Oigimi&apos;s unhappiness and her sons&apos; slow promotion to theirs and was frustrated with the perverse world and always smitten by remorse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamakazura compared Oigimi&apos;s unhappiness and her sons&apos; slow promotion to theirs and was frustrated with the perverse world and constantly smitten by remorse.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Always&quot;-&quot;constantly&quot; to read a bit smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every time when Tamakazura thought of unhappiness of Oigimi and compared Kaoru and Kurodo no Shosho with her sons whose promotions were slow, she was bitterly disappointed by this frustrating world and could not help feeling regret.</e>
<cmt>原文「自分の息子たちの出世の遅さと比べるにつけ」には比べる対象がかかれていませんが、文脈から「薫」と「蔵人少将」を補って訳しました。FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="25">
<j>後記説・別作者説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Written later&apos; theory and &apos;Different author&apos; theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Written later&apos; and &apos;Different author&apos; theories.</e>
<cmt>Cut first &quot;theory&quot; to avoid repetition. &quot;Theory&quot;-&quot;theories&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory about the additional chapter/ Theory about the authorship</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この巻では、薫が中納言に昇進するとともに、紅梅 (源氏物語)が大納言から右大臣に、夕霧 (源氏物語)が右大臣から左大臣にそれぞれ昇進している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this chapter, while Kaoru was promoted to Chunagon, Kobai (the rose plum) was promoted from Dainagon (Major Counselor) to Udaijin (minister of the right) and Yugiri was from Udaijin to Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this chapter, while Kaoru was promoted to Chunagon, Kobai (the rose plum) was promoted from Dainagon (Major Counselor) to Udaijin (minister of the right) and Yugiri was from Udaijin to Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this chapter, Kaoru was promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), and Kobai (the rose plum) and Yugiri were also promoted from Dainagon (chief councilor of state) to Udaijin (minister of the right), and from Udaijin to Sadaijin (minister of the left) respectively.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Chunagon→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)に変更Major Counselor→chief councilor of stateに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>にもかかわらず、これに続く巻では昇進以前の官名のままで呼ばれているといった官名の記述に矛盾がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, in the following chapter, there are some discrepancies in the description of officiary titles like their officiary titles are still previous ones, also, this is the only chapter in which the narrator shows its position in fifty four chapters, for these several reasons, some people proposed &apos;Written later&apos; theory and &apos;Different author&apos; theory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, in the following chapter, there are some discrepancies in the description of officiary titles, such as their officiary titles being kept as their previous ones, also, this is the only chapter in which the narrator shows its position in fifty four chapters, and for these few reasons, some people proposed the &apos;Written later&apos; and &apos;Different author&apos; theories.</e>
<cmt>Added comma after &quot;titles&quot;. &quot;Like&quot;-&quot;such as&quot; and &quot;still&quot;- &quot;being kept as&quot; to make it a bit easier to read. &quot;Several&quot;-&quot;few&quot;. Added &quot;and&quot; to &quot;for these&quot;. Cut &quot;theory&quot; after &quot;written later&quot; as above. &quot;Theory&quot;-&quot;theories&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, in the following chapters, there are inconsistent descriptions of official titles, for example, some characters are called by their old titles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、54帖中唯一作中での語り手がその立場を明らかにしていることなど、いくつかの理由から後記説や別作者説が唱えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, of the 54 chapters, this is the only chapter in which the narrator shows its position; for these reasons, some people claimed that the chapter was written in later years or by a different author.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>但し、このような現象は構想上の問題として説明できるとして後記説や別作者説を否定する見解も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are some opinions denying &apos;Written later&apos; theory and &apos;Different author&apos; theory, saying that these phenomena can be explained as structural issues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are some opinions denying the &apos;Written later&apos; and &apos;Different author&apos; theories, saying that these phenomena can be explained as being structural issues.</e>
<cmt>Cut first &quot;theory&quot; as above. &quot;Theory&quot;-&quot;theories&quot;. Added &quot;being&quot; to read a bit smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some people deny these theories about the additional chapter and the different author, stating that these problems can be explained as a matter of structure.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), Y-take(id:132371), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>