<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>作り物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukuri Monogatari (fanciful tale)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukuri Monogatari (fanciful tale)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukuri Monogatari (fanciful tale)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>作り物語（つくりものがたり）は、王朝物語のうち架空の人物を主人公として展開される小説的な作品を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Ocho Monogatari (tales of Heian and Kamakura period), Tsukuri monogatari refers to the fictitious works in which a story unfolds with a fictitious person as a main character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Ocho Monogatari (tales from the Heian and Kamakura periods), Tsukuri monogatari refers to the fictitious works in which a story unfolds with a fictitious person as the main character.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Ocho Monogatari (tales from the Heian and Kamakura periods), Tsukuri monogatari refers to the fictitious works in which a story unfolds with a fictitious person as the main character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>『竹取物語』『はこやのとじ』『からもり』などを嚆矢として、『源氏物語』によって頂点を迎え、これにつづく一群源氏亜流物語、さらに中世期物語にいたるまで、王朝物語の主流を成し、もっとも多くの作品数を誇る分野である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Taketori Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter), &quot;Hakoya no toji,&quot; and &quot;Karamori,&quot; were the first instances in this genre, and &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; brought it to the peak, forming the main stream of the Ocho monogatari that ranges from the successive series of inferior imitations of The Tale of Genji to the Medieval tales, and this genre is proud of the most number of works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The genre started with &quot;Taketori Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter), while &quot;Hakoya no toji,&quot; &quot;Karamori,&quot; and &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; brought it to its peak, these formed the main stream Ocho monogatari that ranged from a successive series of inferior imitations of The Tale of Genji to the Medieval tales, this genre is also proud to have the most number of works of any genre.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ocho monogatari genre started with &quot;Taketori Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter), &quot;Hakoya no toji&quot; and &quot;Karamori,&quot; but it reached its peak with &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji); these works, which formed the mainstream of this genre, were followed by works ranging from a succession of inferior imitations of The Tale of Genji to the Medieval tales, and this genre boasts the highest number of works of any genre.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが「竹取物語」で始まりと変更されていますが、始まりは三つの物語なので変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Carkuni(id:79281), さららゆら(id:12274), Enthousiasme(id:42600), 頭痛(id:201680), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>