<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紫の上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki no ue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki no ue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki no ue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紫の上（むらさきのうえ）は、紫式部の古典『源氏物語』のヒロイン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasaki no ue is a heroine in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; a classic written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasaki no ue is a heroine in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; a classic written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasaki no ue is a heroine in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; a classic written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>架空の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is a fictitious character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is a fictitious character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is a fictitious character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>始め紫の君、後に光源氏の妻となって紫の上と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the tale, she is called Murasaki no kimi at first, but after she has become Hikaru Genji&apos;s wife, she is called Murasaki no ue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially she is called Murasaki no kimi, but once she becomes Hikaru Genji&apos;s wife she is called Murasaki no ue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially she is called Murasaki no kimi, but once she becomes Hikaru Genji&apos;s wife she is called Murasaki no ue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なお「若紫」は第5帖の題名であり作中には出てこず、他には『紫式部日記』に「左衞門のかみあなかしこ此のわたりにわかむらさきやさふらふとうかゝいたまふ」（藤原公任が酔って式部のいるあたりを「私の若紫おいでですか？」といいたまう）とあるのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the name of Wakamurasaki was used for the title of the fifth chapter, the name does not appear in the chapter and only &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Diary&quot; contains the name: &apos;When FUJIWARA no Kinto got drunk, turning up around the place where Shikibu was supposed to be, and asked, &apos;Is there my Wakamurasaki?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the name of Wakamurasaki is used in the title of the fifth chapter, the name doesn&apos;t appear in the chapter but only &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Diary&quot; contains the name: &apos;When FUJIWARA no Kinto got drunk, turning up around the place where Shikibu was supposed to be, and asked, &apos;Is there my Wakamurasaki?&apos;&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the name of Wakamurasaki is used in the title of the fifth chapter, the name doesn&apos;t appear in the chapter but only appears in &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Diary&quot;, &apos;When FUJIWARA no Kinto got drunk, turning up around the place where Shikibu was supposed to be, and asked, &apos;Is my Wakamurasaki there?&apos;&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>俗には紫の上の幼少期をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commonly Wakamurasaki refers to Murasaki no ue in her infancy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commonly, Wakamurasaki refers to Murasaki no ue in her infancy.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commonly, Wakamurasaki refers to Murasaki no ue in her infancy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「紫」の名は古今和歌集の雑歌「紫のひともとゆゑに武蔵野の草はみながらあはれとぞみる」に因む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of &apos;Murasaki&apos; came from the miscellaneous poem collected in Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry): &apos;Because of this one gromwell, I feel affection for everything on Musashi plain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Murasaki&apos; came from the miscellaneous poem collected in Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry): &apos;Because of this one gromwell, I feel affection for everything on Musashi Plain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Murasaki&apos; came from a poem on miscellaneous matters in the Kokin Wakashu (imperial anthology of old and new Japanese Poetry): &apos;Because of this one gromwell plant, I feel affection for everything on Musashi Plain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>光源氏の「永遠の女性」である藤壺の縁者（紫のゆかり）であることを婉曲に表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It implies that she is a relative of Fujitsubo (Murasaki no yukari), Hikaru Genji&apos;s &apos;eternal woman.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It implies that she is a relative of Fujitsubo (Murasaki no yukari), Hikaru Genji&apos;s &apos;eternal woman.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It implies that she is a relative of Fujitsubo (Murasaki no yukari), Hikaru Genji&apos;s &apos;eternal woman.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また「上」の呼称が示すように、源氏の正妻格として源氏にも周囲にも扱われるが、正式な結婚披露をした北の方ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, &apos;ue&apos; suggests that she is Genji&apos;s legal wife, being treated as such by Genji and other people, but she has never made an announcement of marriage officially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, &apos;ue&apos; suggests that she is Genji&apos;s legal wife, being treated as such by Genji and other people, but she has never made an official announcement of marriage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, &apos;ue&apos; suggests that she is Genji&apos;s legal wife, being treated as such by Genji and other people, but there was never an official announcement of marriage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>父は兵部卿宮（後に式部卿宮、桐壺帝の先帝の皇子）、母は按察使大納言の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father is Hyobukyo no Miya (later called Shikibukyo no Miya, and a son of the Emperor Kiritsubo&apos;s preceding Emperor), and her mother is a daughter of Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) no Dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father is Hyobukyo no Miya (later called Shikibukyo no Miya, and a son of the Emperor Kiritsubo&apos;s predecessor), and her mother is a daughter of Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) no Dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father is Hyobukyo no Miya (later called Shikibukyo no Miya, and a son of the Emperor Kiritsubo&apos;s predecessor), and her mother is a daughter of Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) no Dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>藤壺の姪にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is a niece of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is a niece of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is a niece of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「若紫」の帖に初めて登場し、以後「御法」まで登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First she appears in the chapter of &apos;Wakamurasaki,&quot; and then enters the story until the chapter of &apos;Minori&apos; (The Rites).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She appears in the chapter of &apos;Wakamurasaki,&quot; and remains a part of the story until the chapter of &apos;Minori&apos; (The Rites).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She appears in the chapter of &apos;Wakamurasaki,&apos; and remains a part of the story until the chapter of &apos;Minori&apos; (The Rites).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>正妻による圧力のために父兵部卿宮の訪問は間遠で、生まれてすぐ母は亡くなり、その後は祖母の北山の尼君に育てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father Hyobukyo no Miya does not often visit her under pressure from his legal wife, while her mother died soon after she was born, so she has been brought up by her grandmother, Kitayama no Amagimi (nun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father Hyobukyo no Miya rarely visits her (due to pressure from his legal wife), and her mother died soon after she was born, so she has been brought up by her grandmother, Kitayama no Amagimi (a nun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father Hyobukyo no Miya rarely visited her (due to pressure from his legal wife), and her mother died soon after she was born, so she was brought up by her grandmother, Kitayama no Amagimi (a nun).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大伯父僧都によると母親が亡くなって10余年たち、北山に病気療養に来ていた光源氏に垣間見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to her great-uncle, Sozu, ten years have passes since her mother died, and she was found by Hikaru Genji, who visited Kitayama for receiving medical treatment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to her great-uncle, Sozu, ten years have passed since her mother&apos;s death, and she was found by Hikaru Genji, who visited Kitayama to receive medical treatment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to her great-uncle, Sozu, ten years had passed since her mother&apos;s death before she was found by Hikaru Genji, who had visited Kitayama to receive medical treatment</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このとき源氏は、幼いながらもその藤壺と生き写しの容姿に一目で惹かれ、さらに藤壺の姪であることを知り執着をもつようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Genji falls in love with her at first sight --although she is still young but looks exactly like Fujitsubo--, and after he gets to know that she is a niece of Fujitsubo, he comes to be attached to her more and more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji falls in love with her at first sight, as she&apos;s still young but looks exactly like Fujitsubo, and once he learns that she&apos;s a niece of Fujitsubo he becomes increasingly attached to her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji falls in love with her at first sight because she looks exactly like Fujitsubo even though she is young, and once he learns that she was a niece of Fujitsubo, he becomes increasingly attached to her.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>祖母の死後、父に引き取られるはずであった若紫を略取した源氏は、自邸の二条院において、周囲には彼女の素性を隠しながら理想の女性に育てる（「若紫」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of her grandmother, she is supposed to be taken in by her father, but Genji takes her to his residence Nijoin, bringing up her to become his ideal woman there without telling anybody who she is (&apos;Wakamurasaki&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of her grandmother, she is supposed to be taken in by her father, but Genji takes her to his residence Nijoin and brings her up to become his ideal woman without telling anyone who she is (&apos;Wakamurasaki&apos;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of her grandmother, she is supposed to be taken in by her father, but Genji takes her to his residence Nijoin and brings her up to become his ideal woman without telling anyone who she is (&apos;Wakamurasaki&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>光源氏の最初の正妻である葵の上の没後に、源氏と初床となり以後公に正妻同様に扱われる（「葵_(源氏物語)」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genji has first sexual relationship with her after his first legal wife Aoi no ue passed away, and since then she is treated like his legal wife. (&apos;Aoi&apos; (hollyhock))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji has first sexual relationship with her after his first legal wife Aoi no ue passes away, and since then she is treated as his legal wife (&apos;Aoi&apos; (hollyhock)).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji has their first sexual relationship with her after his first legal wife Aoi no ue passes away, and after that she is treated as his legal wife (&apos;Aoi&apos; (hollyhock)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>以後は光源氏の須磨退隠時期を除き、常に光源氏の傍らにあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She has always stayed with Hikaru Genji since then except the time when he was driven away to Suma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She remains with Hikaru Genji, except during the time when he is driven away to Suma.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She remains with Hikaru Genji, except during the time when he is driven away to Suma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>紫の上が妻として扱われるようになって初めて、父兵部卿宮にも、行方不明であった娘が源氏のもとにいることが知らされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Murasaki no ue comes to be treated as his wife, her father, Hyobukyo no Miya, is let to know for the first time that his missing daughter has stayed with Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Murasaki no ue comes to be treated as his wife, her father, Hyobukyo no Miya, is told for the first time that his missing daughter has stayed with Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father, Hyobukyo no Miya, is finally told after Murasaki no ue is treated as Genji&apos;s wife that his missing daughter had been under the care of Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>兵部卿宮は始めこれを歓迎したが、源氏が須磨に隠棲したときには右大臣の権勢を恐れて紫の上を支援しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first Hyobukyo no Miya gives a welcome to Genji, but when he lives in seclusion at Suma, Hyobukyo no Miya does not support Murasaki no ue for fear of the power of Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first Hyobukyo no Miya gives a welcome to Genji, but when he lives in seclusion at Suma, Hyobukyo no Miya doesn&apos;t support Murasaki no ue for fear of the power of Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first Hyobukyo no Miya gives welcomes Genji, but when he lives in seclusion at Suma, Hyobukyo no Miya does not support Murasaki no ue because he feared the power of the Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このため源氏は帰京後は兵部卿宮を冷遇する事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Genji comes to treat Hyobukyo no Miya coldly after he returns to the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Genji treats Hyobukyo no Miya coldly after he returns to the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Genji treats Hyobukyo no Miya coldly after he returns to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>紫の上には子供がなかったため、源氏は明石の御方が生んだ女の子（のちの明石の姫君）を紫の上の養女とし、将来の后候補として育てさせた（「薄雲」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Murasaki no ue does not have any child, Genji adopts a baby daughter of Akashi no Onkata for Murasaki no ue, having her bring up the baby to be the future Empress (&apos;Usugumo&apos; (Wisps of Cloud)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Murasaki no ue is childless, Genji adopts a baby daughter of Akashi no Onkata for Murasaki no ue, and has her raise the child to be the future Empress (&apos;Usugumo&apos; (Wisps of Cloud)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Murasaki no ue is childless, Genji adopts a baby daughter of Akashi no Onkata for Murasaki no ue, and has her raise the child to be the future Empress (&apos;Usugumo&apos; (Wisps of Cloud)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また明石中宮の入内後には、中宮の産んだ女一宮と三の宮（匂宮）を養育しており、特に愛した匂宮には遺言で二条院を遺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Akashi Empress enters the Imperial Palace, she grows Onna Ichi no Miya and San no Miya (Nioumiya), children of the Empress, and she loves especially Nioumiya and leaves Nijoin to him by will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once Empress Akashi enters the Imperial Palace, she raises Onna Ichi no Miya and San no Miya (Nioumiya), children of the Empress; she particularly loves Nioumiya and leaves Nijoin to him in her will.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once Empress Akashi enters the Imperial Palace, she raises Onna Ichi no Miya and San no Miya (Nioumiya) who were children of the Empress and she particularly loves Nioumiya, leaving Nijoin to him in her will.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>光源氏に誰よりも愛された最愛の妻である一方、源氏の子を産んだ明石の御方にはたびたび嫉妬し、また朝顔 (源氏物語)と源氏の結婚の噂が立った時には動揺もした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is loved by Hikaru Genji most and has been his beloved wife all the time, but she is often jealous of Akashi no Onkata, who bears Genji a child, and when a rumor that Asagao and Genji are going to get married is going around, she is upset.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is loved by Hikaru Genji most, as she has been his beloved wife all along, but she is often jealous of Akashi no Onkata, who bears Genji a child; and when a rumor that Asagao and Genji are going to get married begins to circulate, she is upset.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was loved by Hikaru Genji the most as his beloved wife all along, but she was often jealous of Akashi no Onkata, who bore Genji a child, and was upset when a rumor circulated that Asagao and Genji were getting married.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、六条院の春の町に移って以降は名実ともに源氏の正夫人として「春の上」「北の方」等と呼ばれ、容貌も心ばせも完璧な女性と謳われて本人もそれを誇りに思っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after she moves to the spring section of the Rokujoin Palace, she is considered Genji&apos;s legal wife both nominally and virtually, being called &apos;Haru no ue&apos; or &apos;Kita no kata,&apos; and she is praised for her beauty and kindheartedness, of which she is also proud.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after she moves to the spring section of Rokujoin Palace, she is considered Genji&apos;s legal wife both nominally and virtually, being called &apos;Haru no ue&apos; or &apos;Kita no kata,&apos; and she is praised for her beauty and kind-heartedness, of which she is proud.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after she moves to the spring section of Rokujoin Palace, she is considered Genji&apos;s legal wife both in name and actuality, being called &apos;Haru no ue&apos; or &apos;Kita no kata,&apos; and she is praised for her beauty and kind-heartedness, of which she is proud.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし実子を持たず確かな後見ある正妻でもなかったため、朱雀帝の女三宮の降嫁が決まった時には衝撃を受け、自分の身の不安定さに改めて気付かされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because she does not have her own child and a powerful guardian, she is so shocked when she knows that Emperor Suzaku&apos;s daughter, Onna San no Miya, is going to get married to Genji, and realizes how vulnerable she is.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because she has no children of her own but is a powerful guardian, she is shocked when she learns that Emperor Suzaku&apos;s daughter, Onna San no Miya, is going to get married to Genji, and she realizes how vulnerable she is.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because she has no children of her own and no powerful guardian, she is shocked when she learns that Emperor Suzaku&apos;s daughter, Onna San no Miya, is going to get married to Genji, and she realizes how vulnerable she is.</e>
<cmt>原文に合うように修正but is→and no</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし紫の上の悩みに気づかぬ源氏と次第にすれ違いを重ね、その心労から37歳の厄年に重病にかかる（「若菜 (源氏物語)」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Genji does not notice the concern of Murasaki no ue, and discrepancy in their feelings for each other gets bigger and bigger, then the anxious makes her fall seriously ill at the age of 37, a critical age for woman (&apos;Wakana&apos; (new herbs)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Genji doesn&apos;t notice the concern of Murasaki no ue; the difference in their feelings for each other gets bigger and bigger, whereupon the anxiety makes her fall seriously ill at the age of 37, a critical age for a woman (&apos;Wakana&apos; (new herbs)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Genji doesn&apos;t notice the concern of Murasaki no ue and the difference in their feelings for each other gets bigger and bigger, and at the age of 37 which is considered a critical age for a woman, she falls seriously ill because of anxiety (&apos;Wakana&apos; (new herbs)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後療養のために二条院に移り、時折出家したい心境をもらすこともあったが、最後までそれを許されぬまま、光源氏に先立って病没した（「御法」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later she moves to the Nijoin residence for receiving medical treatment, and sometimes mentions that she wants to become a nun, but she dies of disease before Hikaru Genji without being allowed to be in priesthood (&apos;Minori&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later she moves to the Nijoin residence in order to receive medical treatment, and sometimes mentions that she wants to become a nun, but she dies of illness before Hikaru Genji without being allowed to enter the clergy (&apos;Minori&apos;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later she moves to the Nijoin residence in order to receive medical treatment, and sometimes mentions that she wants to become a nun, but she dies before Hikaru Genji of an illness without being allowed to become a nun (&apos;Minori&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>彼女の完璧さを頼りに安堵しきっていた源氏は、悲嘆の中で改めて彼女が隠してきた苦悩と孤独を痛感し、その後の一年あまり紫の上を偲び続けた（「幻 (源氏物語)」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genji, who has depended on her and felt at ease completely with her, realizes her secret agony and loneliness, and is thinking of her for more than a year (&apos;Maboroshi&apos; (The Wizard)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji, who has depended on her and always felt at ease completely with her, realizes the secret agony and loneliness she felt, and as a result he mourns her death for more than a year (&apos;Maboroshi&apos; (The Wizard)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji, who had depended upon her to be perfect, realizes the secret agony and loneliness she felt, and as a result he mourns her death for more than a year (&apos;Maboroshi&apos; (The Wizard)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), Izayohi(id:13095), さららゆら(id:12274), 松茸(id:27535), ブリキの太鼓叩き(id:3586), Ideal(id:236), いたる(id:58536), MIO(id:31681), Point136(id:211299), Maxima m(id:28947), Aphaia(id:3132), Ws227(id:208643), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>