<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>禁秘抄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>禁秘抄（きんぴしょう）は、第84代順徳天皇自身の手による有職故実の解説書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpisho is a book written by the 84th Emperor Juntoku on the history and origin of imperial court ceremonies whereby serving an instruction manual for the rules and etiquette concerning such ceremonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpisho is a book written by the 84th Emperor Juntoku on the history and origin of imperial court ceremonies, whereby serving as an instruction manual for the rules and etiquette concerning such ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>added comma, fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpisho is a book written by the 84th Emperor Juntoku on the history and origin of imperial court ceremonies, whereby serving as an instruction manual for the rules and etiquette concerning such ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現存するのは、上下二巻の体裁をとっているが本来三部構成であることから三巻であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing copy consists of 2 volumes but, since it was initially organized in 3 parts, it is considered that the original copy came in 3 volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing copy consists of two volumes, but since it was initially organized in three parts, the original copy is considered to have had three volumes.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar; typed out numerals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing copy consists of two volumes, but since it was initially organized in three parts, the original copy is considered to have had three volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>成立は1221年（承久3年)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpisho was completed in 1221.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpisho was completed in 1221.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpisho was completed in 1221.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>作者順徳天皇（生年1197年~1242年没）は、後鳥羽天皇の第三皇子として生れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author Emperor Juntoku (1197 – 1242) was born the third prince of Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author, Emperor Juntoku (1197 - 1242), was born the third prince of Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>added commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author, Emperor Juntoku (1197 - 1242), was born the third prince of Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>年少より学問を好み、和歌にも秀で、「八雲御抄」他、歌集・歌学集を編纂している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From a young age, Emperor Juntoku enjoyed learning and excelled in waka compiling various anthologies and research documents on waka such as Yakumomisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From a young age, Emperor Juntoku enjoyed learning about and excelled in compiling various waka anthologies and research documents on waka, such as Yakumomisho.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From a young age Emperor Juntoku enjoyed learning; he also excelled in waka poetry and compiled various waka anthologies and research documents on waka, such as &apos;Yakumomisho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「禁秘抄」は朝廷における儀式作法の根源・由来・を究め古来よりの慣習を後の世代に残さんとしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinpisho made an in-depth study of the root and origin of manners and etiquette of ceremonies performed at the Imperial Court with an intent to pass the ancient custom down to the succeeding generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinpisho was an in-depth study of the root and origin of manners and etiquette of ceremonies performed at the Imperial Court, with an intent to pass the ancient customs down to succeeding generations.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpisho was an in-depth study of the root and origin of manners and etiquette of ceremonies performed at the Imperial Court, with an intent to pass the ancient customs down to succeeding generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>本書完成直後に承久の乱を起こしている事でもわかるように、天皇政治復興の情熱がこめられ、次代の皇子に帝王の道を伝えようとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As evidenced by the outbreak of the Jokyu War immediately after the completion of this book, there was an impassioned wish for restoration of the Imperial government and the intent to pass the way of monarch down to princes of the next generation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As revealed by the outbreak of the Jokyu War immediately after the completion of the book, there was a profound yearning for the restoration of the Imperial government and to pass the way of the sovereign down to the princes of the next generation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;evidenced&quot; is a little awkward, so I changed it to &quot;revealed&quot;; fixed sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As revealed by the outbreak of the Jokyu War immediately after the completion of the book, there was a profound yearning for the restoration of the Imperial government and to pass the way of the sovereign down to the princes of the next generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 伏儀(id:142093), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>