<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宗長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Socho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Socho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Socho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>宗長（そうちょう、1448年（文安5年） - 1532年4月11日（天文 (元号)元年3月6日 (旧暦)））は、室町時代後期の連歌師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Socho (1448 - April 11, 1532 (March 6, Tenbun 1st (Old calendar))was a renga (linked-verse) poet of the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Socho (1448 - April 11, 1532 (March 6, Tenbun 1 (old calendar))was a renga (linked-verse) poet of the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Tenbun 1&quot; pulled more hits than &quot;1st&quot; so I changed it.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Socho (1448 - April 11, 1532) was a renga (linked-verse) poet of the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>（March 6, Tenbun 1 (old calendar)削除スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>号は柴屋軒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His literary name was Saiokuken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pen name was Saiokuken.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;pen name&quot; is perhaps more accurate than &quot;literary name&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pen name was Saiokuken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>駿河国島田（現在の静岡県島田市）の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Shimada, Suruga province (present-day Shimada city, Shizuoka prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Shimada, Suruga province (present-day Shimada city, Shizuoka prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Shimada, Suruga Province (present-day Shimada City, Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鍛冶職五条義助の子として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the son of a blacksmith, Yoshisuke GOJO.</e>
<cmt>史実によると父は刀鍛冶（a swordsmith)だったですが、原文には刀鍛冶とはないため、ひとまず「blacksmith」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the son of a blacksmith, Yoshisuke GOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the son of a blacksmith, Yoshisuke GOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>寛正6年（1465年）に出家して、後に今川義忠に仕えたが、義忠が戦死すると駿河を去り上洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a Buddhist monk in 1465 and later served Yoshitada IMAGAWA, but after Yoshitada&apos;s death in battle, he left Suruga and went to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a Buddhist monk in 1465 and later served Yoshitada IMAGAWA, but after Yoshitada&apos;s death in battle, he left Suruga and went to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a Buddhist monk in 1465 and later served Yoshitada IMAGAWA, but after Yoshitada&apos;s death in battle, he left Suruga and went to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>宗祇に師事して連歌を学び、水無瀬三吟（長享2年（1488年））、湯山三吟（延徳3年（1491年））などの席に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied renga under Sogi, and was present at Three Poets at Minase (Minase Sangin Hyakuin)(in 1488), Three Poets at Yuyama (Yuyama Sangin Hyakuin) (in 1491), and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied renga under Sogi, and participated in Minase Sangin Hyakuin (One Hundred Stanzas by Three Poets at Minase) in 1488, Yuyama Sangin Hyakuin (One Hundred Stanzas by Three Poets at Yuyama) in 1491, amongst others.</e>
<cmt>I changed &quot;was present at&quot; to &quot;participated in&quot; here as I think that is a bit more accurate. With the help of Google I decided to use the translation for Minase Sangin Hyakuin from Meiji Gakuin University ref: http://www.meijigakuin.ac.jp/~pmjs/rom/trans_mn.html. Finally, changed &quot;and&quot; to &quot;amongst&quot; to read a bit smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied renga under Sogi, and participated in Minase Sangin Hyakuin (One Hundred Stanzas by Three Poets at Minase) in 1488, Yuyama Sangin Hyakuin (One Hundred Stanzas by Three Poets at Yuyama) in 1491, amongst others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>大徳寺の一休宗純に参禅、大徳寺真珠庵の傍らに住み、宗純没後は神奈備に近い山城国薪村（現在の京都府京田辺市）の酬恩庵に住んで宗純の菩提を弔った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He practiced Zen Buddhism under Sojun IKKYU of Daitoku-ji Temple, living by Shinjuan in Daitoku-ji Temple, and after Sojun passed away, he lived near kannabi, in Shuonan in Takigi village, Yamashiro province (present-day Kyotanabe city, Kyoto prefecture) and prayed for the repose of Sojun&apos;s soul.</e>
<cmt>原文中の「神奈備」、現地の地図を調べてみたところ「甘南備（かんなび）山」と「神奈備神社」が「薪」の地名が残っている場所にあり、どちらかではないかと思われますが不明です。(引用出典では森となっています）本文中ではひとまずkannabiとだけ訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He practiced Zen Buddhism under Sojun IKKYU of Daitoku-ji Temple, living by Shinjuan in Daitoku-ji Temple, and after Sojun passed away, he lived near a kannabi (a place serving as a residence to a god), in Shuonan in Takigi village, Yamashiro province (present-day Kyotanabe city, Kyoto prefecture) and prayed for the repose of Sojun&apos;s soul.</e>
<cmt>Added brief explanation for &quot;kannabi&quot; ref: http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/modules/xwords/entry.php?entryID=254</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He practiced Zen Buddhism under Sojun IKKYU of Daitoku-ji Temple, living by Shinjuan in Daitoku-ji Temple, and after Sojun passed away, he lived near a kannabi (a place serving as a residence to a god), in Shuonan in Takigi village, Yamashiro Province (present-day Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture) and prayed for the repose of Sojun&apos;s soul.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明応5年（1496年）駿河に戻って今川氏親に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1496, he went back to Suruga, and served Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1496, he went back to Suruga, and served Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1496, he went back to Suruga, and served Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>文亀2年（1502年）、宗祇が箱根湯本で倒れたとの報を聞き、その最期を看取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1502, hearing the news of Sogi&apos;s fall at Hakone Yumoto, he went to care for him on his deathbed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1502, hearing the news of Sogi&apos;s fall at Hakone Yumoto, he went to care for him on his deathbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1502, hearing the news of Sogi&apos;s fall at Hakone Yumoto, he went to care for him on his deathbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宗祇没後は連歌界の指導者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sogi&apos;s death, he became the leader of the renga world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Sogi&apos;s death, he became the leader of the renga world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Sogi&apos;s death, he became the leader of the renga world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、有力な武将や公家との交際も広く、三条西実隆や細川高国、大内義興、上杉房能とも交流を持ち、今川氏の外交顧問であったとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he had many influential warlords and court nobles as his associates, getting to know Sanetaka SANJONISHI, Takakuni HOSOKAWA, Yoshioki OUCHI and Fusayoshi UESUGI, and is said to have been a diplomatic adviser to the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he had many influential warlords and court nobles as his associates, such as Sanetaka SANJONISHI, Takakuni HOSOKAWA, Yoshioki OUCHI and Fusayoshi UESUGI, and is said to have been a diplomatic adviser to the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>I felt &quot;getting to know&quot; was a bit redundant here since we already know they were his &quot;associates&quot; so I replaced it with &quot;such as&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he had many influential warlords and court nobles as his associates, such as Sanetaka SANJONISHI, Takakuni HOSOKAWA, Yoshioki OUCHI and Fusayoshi UESUGI, and is said to have been a diplomatic adviser to the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>晩年は、斎藤安元の援助により遠江国宇津山のふもと泉谷に柴屋軒（現在の柴屋寺）を結び、京との間を往還して大徳寺の山門造営にも関与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, he built the Saiokuken (present-day Saioku-ji Temple)at Izumigaya at the foot of Utsunoyama in Totomi province with the help of Yasumoto SAITO, travelling between there and Kyoto, and was also involved in building the gate of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, he built the Saiokuken (present-day Saioku-ji Temple)at Izumigaya at the foot of Utsunoyama in Totomi province with the help of Yasumoto SAITO, travelling between there and Kyoto, and was also involved in building the gate of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, he built the Saiokuken (present-day Saioku-ji Temple)at Izumigaya at the foot of Mt. Utsuno in Totomi Province with the help of Yasumoto SAITO, travelling between there and Kyoto, and was also involved in building the gate of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正山の表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>「急がば回れ」を唱えた人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one who advised &apos;The greater your hurry, the slower you should go.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one who advised &quot;More haste, less speed.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Translated 「急がば回れ」 to a more familiar &quot;more haste, less speed&quot;. As it&apos;s a quote, put it in inverted commas.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one who advised &quot;More haste, less speed.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>代表作として、句集「那智篭（なちごもり）」、日記「宗長手記」、「宗長日記」があり、ほかに「東路の津登（あづまじのつと）」、「宇津山記」、「宗祇終焉記」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works are the collection of renga stanzas &apos;Secluded at Nachi&apos; (Nachigomori), the diaries &apos;The Journal of Socho&apos; (Socho shuki) and &apos;The Diary of Socho&apos; (Socho nikki), also &apos;Souvenir of the Eastland&apos; (Azumaji no tsuto), &apos;Record of Utsunoyama&apos; (Utsunoyama no ki), and &apos; A Record of Sogi&apos;s Passing&apos; (Sogi shuen ki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works are the collection of renga stanzas Nachigomori (Secluded at Nachi); the diaries Socho shuki (The Journal of Socho) and Socho nikki (The Diary of Socho), as well as Azumaji no tsuto (Souvenir of the Eastland), Utsunoyama no ki (Record of Utsunoyama), and Sogi shuen ki (A Record of Sogi&apos;s Passing).</e>
<cmt>Added semi colons where appropriate. Changed &quot;also&quot; to &quot;as well as&quot; to make it read a bit more smoothly. Placed English translation in parenthesis instead of Japanese for continuity with the rest of the translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works are the collection of renga stanzas &apos;Nachigomori&apos; (Secluded at Nachi); the diaries &apos;Socho shuki&apos; (The Journal of Socho) and &apos;Socho nikki&apos; (The Diary of Socho), as well as &apos;Azumaji no tsuto&apos; (Souvenir of the Eastland), &apos;Utsunoyama no ki&apos; (Record of Utsunoyama), and &apos;Sogi shuen ki&apos; (A Record of Sogi&apos;s Passing).</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Izayohi(id:13095), Rusk(id:9895), 与左衛門(id:159462), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>