<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文屋康秀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUNYA no Yasuhide</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUNYA no Yasuhide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUNYA no Yasuhide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>文屋 康秀（ふんや の やすひで、生年不詳 - 仁和元年（885年）？）は、平安時代前期の歌人で、六歌仙・三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUNYA no Yasuhide (year of birth unknown - 885?) was kajin (waka poet) in the early Heian period and one of Rokkasen (six best Waka poets) and the Thirty-six Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUNYA no Yasuhide (year of birth unknown - 885?) was a waka poet in the early Heian period and one of Rokkasen (six best Waka poets) and the 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>arabic numerals, articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUNYA no Yasuhide (year of birth unknown - c. 885) was a waka poet in the early Heian period and one of Rokkasen (six best waka poets) and the 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>?→c.,Waka→waka に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>文屋宗于の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child of FUNYA no Muneyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a child of FUNYA no Muneyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a child of FUNYA no Muneyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に文屋朝康がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child was FUNYA no Asayasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His child was FUNYA no Asayasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUNYA no Asayasu was his child.</e>
<cmt>オーダーを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官人としては縫殿助（正六位下相当）任官したことが伝わる程度で卑官に終始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be appointed to Nuidono no suke (Assistant Director in the Bureau of the Wardrobe and Court Ladies)(equivalent to Shorokuinoge (Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade)) as a government official, but he stayed as a government man in a low rank.</e>
<cmt>下記用語については、ウェブの用語を使用して訳出しました。縫殿寮→縫殿助</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be appointed to Nuidono no suke (Assistant Director in the Bureau of the Wardrobe and Court Ladies)(equivalent to Shorokuinoge, or Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) as a government official, but he remained a government worker in a low rank.</e>
<cmt>removed nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be appointed to Nuidono no suke (Assistant Director in the Bureau of the Wardrobe and Court Ladies [equivalent to Shorokuinoge, or Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade]) as a government official, but he remained a government worker in a low rank.</e>
<cmt>カッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>「古今和歌集」仮名序では、「詞はたくみにて、そのさま身におはず、いはば商人のよき衣着たらんがごとし」と評される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kokin Wakashu Kanajo (Preface of Kokinwakashu written in kana by KI no Tsurayuki), he was described as &apos;his poems are excellent, but his appearance is not good enough as if a merchant wearing good cloth.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kokin Wakashu Kanajo (Preface of Kokinwakashu written in kana by KI no Tsurayuki), it was written that &apos;his poems are excellent, but his appearance is not good enough, as a merchant wearing good cloth.&apos;</e>
<cmt>deleted “if”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; Kanajo (Preface of Kokinwakashu written in kana by KI no Tsurayuki), it was written that &quot;his poems are excellent, but his appearance is not good enough, as a merchant wearing good cloth.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーツを挿入、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「古今集」に5首、「後撰和歌集」に1首入集する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five of his poems were selected in &apos;Kokinshu&apos; (abbreviation of &quot;Collection of Ancient and Modern&quot;) and one poem in &apos;Gosen Wakashu&apos; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five of his poems were selected for &apos;Kokinshu&apos; (abbreviation of &quot;Collection of Ancient and Modern&quot;) and one poem for &apos;Gosen Wakashu&apos; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five of his poems were selected for &quot;Kokinshu&quot; (Collection of Ancient and Modern) and one poem for &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、「古今集」の2首は子の朝康の作ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, two of his poems in &apos;Kokinshu&apos; were said to be composed by Asayasu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, two of his poems in &apos;Kokinshu&apos; were said to be composed by Asayasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, two of his poems in &quot;Kokinshu&quot; were said to be composed by his son, Asayasu.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。”子の”部分を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>小野小町と親密だったとされ、三河国に赴任する際に小野小町を誘ったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be close to ONO no Komachi and asked her out when he left for his assignment in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be close to ONO no Komachi and asked her out when he left for his assignment in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be close to ONO no Komachi and asked her for a company when he left for his assignment in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>out→for a company と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>代表作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative works</e>
<cmt>deleted “his”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>吹くからに秋の草木のしをるれば むべ山風を嵐といふらむ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the wind blows, autumn leaves of trees and grasses are withered away. That is why people call the mountain wind storm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the wind blows, autumn leaves of trees and grasses are withered away. That is why people call the mountain wind storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the wind blows, autumn leaves of trees and grasses are withered away. That is why people call the mountain wind storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>春の日の光にあたる我なれど 頭の雪となるぞわびしき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I have myself expose to spring sunlight, but it is lonesome to have my head become snowy (gray hair).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I have myself exposed to spring sunlight, but it is lonesome to have my head become snowy.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think the explanation about gray hair is necessary in the context of a poem</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I have myself exposed to spring sunlight, but it is lonesome to have my head become snowy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), さららゆら(id:12274), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), 代言人(id:33675), Point136(id:211299), NDR(id:5500), Snap55(id:89773), Escarbot(id:59151), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>