<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日高見国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitakami no kuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitakami no kuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitakami no kuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日高見国（ひたかみのくに）は、『日本書紀』に登場する、現在の東北地方（岩手県内の北上川流域）にあった蝦夷の国（地方勢力圏）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitakami no kuni is described in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) as a province of Emishi (local influence area) in the present-day Tohoku region (the Kitakami-gawa River basin in Iwate Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitakami no kuni is a province ruled by Emishi (a group of people) as a local sphere of influence, which was located in the present-day Tohoku region (the Kitakami-gawa River basin in Iwate Prefecture) and described in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>vocab/ a province of Emishi-Emishi Provincevocab/local influence area-local sphere of influenceorderwording change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitakami no kuni is a province ruled by Emishi (a group of people) as a local sphere of influence, which was located in the present-day Tohoku region (the Kitakami-gawa River basin in Iwate Prefecture) and described in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>景行天皇27年、武内宿禰が東国を巡視し、「東に日高見国がある。蝦夷が住んでおり、土地は肥沃で広大である。征服すべきである」と報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In A.D. 97, TAKENOUCHI no Sukune made a tour of inspection in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) and reported, &quot;There is Hitakami no kuni in the east where Emishi lives in the vast and fertile land, so we should conquer there.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In A.D. 97, TAKENOUCHI no Sukune made a tour of inspection in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) and reported, &quot;There is Hitakami no kuni in the east where Emishi live and it is a vast and fertile land, so we should conquer there.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording change/ article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In A.D. 97, TAKENOUCHI no Sukune made a tour of inspection in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) and reported, &quot;There is Hitakami no kuni in the east where Emishi live and it is a vast and fertile land, so we should conquer there.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ヤマトタケルが派遣され、平定されたとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described that Yamatotakeru was dispatched and pacified the region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described that Yamatotakeru was dispatched and pacified the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described that Yamatotakeru was dispatched and pacified the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>北上川流域に比定されており、北上川という名前は「ヒタカミ」に由来するとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The province is identified in the Kitakami-gawa River basin, and the name of river Kitakami is said to come from &quot;Hitakami.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the province was around the Kitakami-gawa River basin, and the name of the river is said to come from &quot;Hitakami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>order/ wording change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the province was around the Kitakami-gawa River basin, and the name of the river is said to come from &quot;Hitakami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>祝詞の一つである「大祓詞」の中では「大倭日高見国（おほやまとひたかみのくに）」が日本の別名として登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In one of norito (Shinto ritual prayer) &quot;Oharae no kotoba,&quot; Oyamato-Hitakami-no-kuni appears as another name of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In one norito (Shinto ritual prayer) &quot;Oharae no kotoba,&quot; Ohoyamatohitakami no kuni appears as another name of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammartook out space and hyphen (to consolidate the style)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In one norito (Shinto ritual prayer) &quot;Oharae no kotoba,&quot; Ohoyamatohitakami no kuni appears as another name of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これについては神話学者の松村武雄が、「日高見」は「日の上」のことであり、天孫降臨のあった日向国から見て東にある大和国のことを「日の上の国（日の昇る国）」と呼んだものだとする説を唱えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A mythologist Takeo MATSUMURA argued that &quot;Hitakami&quot; means above the Sun, and Yamato Province was called the province above the Sun (province of rising Sun) because it was in the east from Hyuga Province where the grandson of the sun goddess descended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A mythologist, Takeo MATSUMURA, argued that &quot;Hitakami&quot; means above the sun, and Yamato Province was called the province above the sun (province of the rising sun) because it was to the east from Hyuga Province where the grandson of the sun goddess descended.</e>
<cmt>comma/ capitals/ preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A mythologist, Takeo MATSUMURA, argued that &quot;Hitakami&quot; means above the sun, and Yamato Province was called the province above the sun (province of the rising sun) because it was to the east from Hyuga Province where the grandson of the sun goddess descended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その説によれば、神武東征によって大和国に移ったことによって「日高見国」が大和国よりも東の地方を指すようになり、最後には北上川流域を指すようになったということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this theory, Jimmu tosei (Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu) moved the capital to Yamato Province and &quot;Hitakami no kuni&quot; referred to the region to the east of Yamato Province, so it came to refer to the Kitakami-gawa River basin at the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this theory, the Jimmu tosei (eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu) moved the capital to Yamato Province and &quot;Hitakami no kuni&quot; started to be referred to as the region to the east of Yamato Province, so it finally came to be referred to as the Kitakami-gawa River basin.</e>
<cmt>capitalswording change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this theory, the Jimmu tosei (eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu) moved the capital to Yamato Province and &quot;Hitakami no kuni&quot; started to be referred to as the region to the east of Yamato Province, so it finally came to be referred to as the Kitakami-gawa River basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>旧国名の常陸国（ひたち）は、ひたかみのくにへの道（ひたかみみち）の転訛といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former name of the province Hitachi is said to be corrupted from &quot;Hitakami no kuni eon mochi&quot; or &quot;Hitakamimichi&quot; (the road to Hitakami).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former name of the province, Hitachi no kuni, is said to be corrupted from &quot;Hitakami no kuni eno michi&quot; or &quot;Hitakamimichi&quot; (the road to Hitakami).</e>
<cmt>japanese spelling/ comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former name of the province, Hitachi no kuni, is said to be corrupted from &quot;Hitakami no kuni eno michi&quot; or &quot;Hitakamimichi&quot; (the road to Hitakami).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), Ｍ．Ｇ(id:27945), Nnh(id:474), Mochi(id:9489), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Chobot(id:20846), ねこぱんだ(id:35119), Aphaia(id:3132), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>