<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>相聞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Somon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Somon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Somon (Love Poetry)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>相聞（そうもん）とは、雑歌・挽歌とともに『万葉集』の三大部立を構成する要素の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Somon is one of the three main poetic categories to constitute the old collection of poetry &quot;Manyoshu&quot; together with Zoka and Banka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Somon is one of the three main poetic categories to constitute the old collection of poetry &quot;Manyoshu&quot; together with Zoka and Banka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Somon is one of the three main poetic categories to constitute the old collection of poetry &quot;Manyoshu&quot; together with Zoka (Miscellaneous Poem) and Banka (Laments).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>互いに安否を問うて消息を通じ合うという意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means keeping in touch with each other by exchanging the words to ask after safety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means keeping in touch with each other by exchanging the words to ask after safety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means keeping in touch with each other by exchanging the words to ask after safety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>元は漢籍の書翰などで家族・友人など広い範囲の人々を対象とした私情を交わす書翰や歌に対して用いられてきたが、『万葉集』では転じて男女間の恋愛を詠った作品をまとめて呼称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originally meant poems and personal notes and letters of the Chinese classics addressed to wide variety of people including family members and friends to exchange personal feelings, but in &quot;Manyoshu&quot;, poetry about love between men and women was categorized as Somon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originally meant poems and personal notes and letters of the Chinese classics addressed to a wide variety of people including family members and friends to exchange personal feelings, but in &quot;Manyoshu&quot;, poetry about love between men and women was categorized as Somon.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originally meant poems and personal notes and letters of the Chinese classics addressed to a wide variety of people including family members and friends to exchange personal feelings, but in &quot;Manyoshu&quot;, poetry about love between men and women was categorized as Somon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『古今和歌集』以後の勅撰和歌集における「恋歌」の部門に相当すると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Somon in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; is considered as correspondent with the category of love poems in imperial anthology of poetry &quot;Kokinwakashu&quot; and subsequent ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Somon in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; is considered equivalent to the category of love poems in imperial anthologies of poetry &quot;Kokinwakashu&quot; and subsequent ones.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Somon is considered equivalent to the category of &apos;love poems&apos; in imperial anthologies of poetry &quot;Kokinwakashu&quot; and subsequent ones.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>