<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>狭衣物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo Monogatari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo Monogatari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo Monogatari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>狭衣物語（さごろもものがたり）は平安時代、王朝末期の作り物語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo Monogatari is a fiction made at the end of the dynastic period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo Monogatari is a work of fiction created at the end of the dynastic period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Sagoromo) is a story written at the end of the dynastic era of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Sagoromo Mongatari→Sagoromo Monogatari</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>四巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>作者を大弐三位とする説もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a view that the author was Daini no Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was once thought that the author was Daini no Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was once thought that the author was Daini no Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現在では六条斎院宣旨（禖子内親王家宣旨）源頼国女を作者とする説が圧倒的に有力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the view that the author is Rokujosaiin no senji (Baishi Naishinnoke senji), a daughter of MIANAMOTO no Yorikuni, is overwhelmingly dominant.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置Wikipediaの原文に、不要な要素が加えられて意味不明の文になっているため、Ｗｉｋipediaの原文に従って訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the predominant view is that the author was Rokujosaiin no senji (Baishi Naishinnoke senji), a daughter of MIANAMOTO no Yorikuni.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now the overwhelmingly predominant view that the author was Rokujosaiin no senji (Baishi Naishinnoke senji), a daughter of MIANAMOTO no Yorikuni.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>成立時期は後冷泉天皇朝の康平頃とも、後三条天皇・白河天皇朝の延久・承保頃ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time of formation is said to be Kohei era (1058 - 1064) in the era of the Emperor Goreizei or Enkyu era (1069 - 1073) to Shoho era (1074 - 1076) in the era of the Emperor Gosanjo and the Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The time of formation is said to be Kohei period (1058 - 1064) during the era of the Emperor Goreizei or Enkyu era (1069 - 1073) to the Shoho era (1074 - 1076) in the era of the emperors Gosanjo and Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been written between the Kohei era (1058 - 1064) during the reign of the Emperor Goreizei and the Enkyu era (1069 - 1073) or Joho era (1074 - 1076) during the reigns of Emperor Gosanjo and Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Goreizeiに修正しました。Gosanjoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『無名草子』では「狭衣こそ、源氏に次ぎてはようおぼえ侍れ」（群書類従本）と賞賛されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is praised in Mumyozoshi (critique of tales) as &quot;Sagoromo is very good next to Genji&quot; (Gunsho Ruiju version)..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is praised in Mumyozoshi (critique of tales) as &quot;Sagoromo is very good next to Genji&quot; (Gunsho Ruiju version).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mumyo Zoshi&quot; (Story Without a Name) praises the work by stating that &apos;Sagoromo Monogatari is second only to Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji).&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。Sagoromo Mongatari→Sagoromo Monogatari</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>『源氏物語』宇治十帖の薫に酷似する主人公・狭衣の恋愛遍歴を描き、主題・構成には『源氏物語』の顕著な影響が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It describes love life of the hero, Sagoromo, who closely resembled Kaoru in Uji jujo (The Ten Quires of Uji) of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) and remarkable influence of Genji Monogatari is seen in the subject and structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It describes the love life of the hero, Sagoromo, who closely resembles Kaoru in Uji jujo (The Ten Quires of Uji) of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji), and the significant influence of Genji Monogatari is seen in the subject and structure.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; depicts the love affairs of a hero who closely resembles Kaoru from the &apos;Uji Jujo&apos; (The Ten Quires of Uji) section of &quot;Genji Monogatari,&quot; and the significant influence of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; can be seen in its themes and structure.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Sagoromo Mongatari→Sagoromo Monogatari</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、「いずれの御時にか」で始まる『源氏物語』と違い、「少年の春は惜しめども留まらぬものなりければ、弥生の二十日余になりぬ」（有朋堂文庫）と始まる書き出しは、白居易の漢詩や『古今和歌集』の名歌を踏まえ、従妹源氏の宮への遂げられぬ恋に起因する狭衣の煩悶を描き、現実を意識したものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different from Genji Monogatari that begins with &quot;In certain era,&quot; the first line that begins with &quot;The time of youth does not stop, it is already around March 20&quot; (Yuhodo Bunko) is based on a Chinese poem by Juyi BAI and a waka in Kokinwakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and describes Sagoromo&apos;s mental conflict caused by unachievable love to his younger female cousin, Genji no miya, and it is conscious of the reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike Genji Monogatari, which begins with &quot;In a certain era,&quot; the first line begins with &quot;The time of youth does not stop, it is already around March 20&quot;; (Yuhodo Bunko) is based on a Chinese poem by Juyi BAI and a waka in Kokinwakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and describes Sagoromo&apos;s mental conflict caused by the unrequited love for his younger female cousin, Genji no miya, and it is conscious of the reality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, unlike &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; which begins &apos;in a certain era,&apos; &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; begins with &apos;The springtime of youth does not stop, for it is already around the 20th day of the third month&apos; (Yuhodo Bunko), which is based on a Chinese poem and a famous poem from &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and depicts Sagoromo&apos;s anguish caused by his unrequited love for his younger female cousin Genji no Miya while being true to reality.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Sagoromo Mongatari→Sagoromo Monogatari</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>飛鳥井姫君の物語や狭衣の即位など、宿命観や幻想的描写が目立ち、主人公の優柔不断さや物語全体を覆う憂愁な雰囲気も『源氏』とだいぶ相違するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fatalism and fantastic descriptions are significant as seen in the story of Asukai Himegimi (young lady of the Asukai family) and enthronement of Sagoromo, and hero&apos;s irresolution and melancholic atmosphere covering the whole story are also different from &quot;Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fatalism and fantastic descriptions are significant, as seen in the story of Asukai Himegimi (a young lady of the Asukai family) and the enthronement of Sagoromo; moreover, the hero&apos;s irresolution and the melancholic atmosphere covering the whole story are different from &quot;Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fatalism and fantastic depictions stand out as can be seen in the story of Asukai no Onnagimi and Sagoromo&apos;s enthronement, while the hero&apos;s indecisiveness and the melancholic atmosphere that envelops the entire narrative are very different from &quot;Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>異本が多く、室町時代に奈良絵本『狭衣』としても改作された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many alternative versions and, in the Muromachi Period, it was adapted as a naraehon (short stories accompanied by illustration) &quot;Sagoromo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many alternate versions, and in the Muromachi period it was adapted as a naraehon (short stories accompanied by illustration) called &quot;Sagoromo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many variations of the story and it was adapted into a nara-ehon (a type of illustrated woodblock-printed book or handscroll popular from the Muromachi through mid-Edo periods) called &quot;Sagoromo&quot; during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。There many variations→There are many variations</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、14世紀に制作された伝土佐光顕筆『狭衣物語絵巻』も残欠6段が現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is six sections of incomplete remain of &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari Emaki (illustrated Sagoromo Monogatari)&quot;, which is told to have been painted by Mitsuaki TOSA in Fourteenth Century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remain six incomplete sections of &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari Emaki&quot; (illustrated Sagoromo Monogatari), which is said to have been painted by Mitsuaki TOSA in the fourteenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remain six incomplete sections of the &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari Emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscroll of the Tale of Sagoromo) which are thought to have been painted by Mitsuaki TOSA in the 14th century.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。The remain→There remainthought →which are thought</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The storyline</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The storyline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>第一巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 1</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 1</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume One</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>帝（嵯峨帝）の弟・堀川関白の一人息子である狭衣は、兄妹同様に育てられた従妹源氏の宮に密かに恋焦がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo, who is the only son of Horikawa Kanpaku, who is the younger brother of the emperor (Emperor Saga) secretly loves his younger female cousin, Genji no Maya, with whom he was brought up same as elder brother and younger sister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo, who is the only son of Emperor Saga&apos;s younger brother Horikawa Kanpaku, secretly loves his younger female cousin, Genji no Maya, with whom he has been brought up in the manner of an elder brother and younger sister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo, who is the only son of Emperor Saga&apos;s younger brother Chancellor (kanpaku) Horikawa, is secretly deeply in love with his younger female cousin, Genji no Miya, with whom he was raised like a brother.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>源氏の宮が東宮妃に望まれていると知って焦った狭衣は、ある時源氏の宮に想いを告白するが拒絶される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo knew that Genji no miya is asked for Imperial Crown Princess and he panicked and told his love to Genji no miya but she refused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo knows that Genji no miya is asked to be the Imperial Crown Princess; he panics and admits his love to Genji no miya, but she refuses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing of the hope that Genji no Miya would become Imperial Crown Princess, Sagoromo panics and declares his feelings for her but she rejects him.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同じ頃狭衣は帝の愛娘・女二宮と婚約した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same period, Sagoromo engaged with Onna ninomiya, who is the Emperor&apos;s beloved daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same period, Sagoromo becomes engaged to Onna ninomiya, the Emperor&apos;s beloved daughter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is around this time that Sagoromo becomes engaged to Onna Ninomiya, the emperor&apos;s beloved daughter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。It around this time→It is around this time</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>源氏の宮に拒まれて傷心を抱える狭衣は、偶然出会った飛鳥井女君と契って心を癒される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo, who had a broken heart by refusal by Genji no miya made love with Asukai onnagimi [飛鳥井女君 正しい読み不明], with whom he happened to meet, and had his heart healed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo, whose heart is broken by the refusal of Genji no miya, makes love to Asukai onnagimi [飛鳥井女君 正しい読み不明], whom he happens to meet, and his heart is healed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo is heartbroken after being rejected by Genji no Miya but his heart is healed after a chance sexual encounter with Asukai no Onnagimi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし狭衣は身分低い飛鳥井女君を侮って名前すら明かさなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sagoromo took Asukai onnagimi, whose status was low, lightly and did not even tell his name to her.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sagoromo takes lightly the Asukai onnagimi, whose status is low, and doesn&apos;t even tell her his name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sagoromo thinks little of Asukai no Onnagimi whose social status is low, and does not even reveal his name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。who&apos;s social status is low→whose social status is low</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>狭衣の愛を信じられない飛鳥井女君は、狭衣の子を妊娠したまま乳母にだまされて筑紫へ連れ去られ、その途中で入水自殺を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asukai onnagimi, who cannot believe love of Sagoromo, got pregnant with Sagoromo&apos;s baby and got cheated by the foster mother and took away to Tsukushi and tried suicide on midway by throwing herself into water.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asukai onnagimi, who cannot believe the love of Sagoromo, becomes pregnant with Sagoromo&apos;s baby but is cheated by the foster mother and taken away to Tsukushi; along the way, she tries to commit suicide by throwing herself into the water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asukai no Onnagimi is unable to have faith in the love of Sagoromo and, while pregnant with his child, is cheated by her wet nurse and taken away to Tsukushi but attempts to commit suicide on the way by drowning herself.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>第二巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume Two</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>飛鳥井女君の失踪に衝撃を受けた狭衣は、頑なに女二宮との結婚を拒絶していたが、ある時彼女を見初めて寝室に押し入り強引に契る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo, who was shocked by disappearance of Asukai onnagimi, refused marriage with Onna ninomiya, but one day he fell in love with her and pushed in the bedroom and forcibly made love with her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo, who is shocked by the disappearance of Asukai onnagimi, refuses marriage to Onna ninomiya; however, he eventually falls in love with her, whereupon he pushes her into the bedroom and makes love to her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo is shocked by the disappearance of Asukai Onnagimi and obstinately refuses to marry Onna Ninomiya but falls in love with her at first sight, breaks into her bedroom and forces himself upon her.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その結果女二宮は妊娠、母大宮により事実は隠し通される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Onna ninomiya got pregnant, and her mother arrange to conceal the fact.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Onna ninomiya becomes pregnant, and her mother arranges to conceal the fact.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onna Ninomiya becomes pregnant as a result and her mother Omiya arranges to hide the fact of her daughter&apos;s condition.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>狭衣の優柔不断で不誠実な態度に絶望した女二宮は、狭衣の男児・若宮（表向きは大宮の産んだ嵯峨帝の第二皇子とされた）を出産した後出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onna ninomiya who got disappointed with Sagoromo&apos;s irresolute and insincere attitude, gave birth to Sagoromo&apos;s son, Wakamiya (outwardly, he was made as the second Imperial Prince of the Emperor Saga born by Omiya) and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onna ninomiya, who is disappointed by Sagoromo&apos;s irresolute and insincere attitude, gives birth to Sagoromo&apos;s son, Wakamiya (outwardly he is made the second Imperial Prince of the Emperor Saga, born by Omiya) and ultimately becomes a priestess.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onna Ninomiya, driven to despair by Sagoromo&apos;s indecisive and dishonest attitude, becomes a nun after giving birth to Sagoromo&apos;s son, Wakamiya (announced as the second son of Emperor Saga and Omiya).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一方、嵯峨帝が譲位して東宮が即位するが（後一条帝）、新帝への入内を予定されていた源氏の宮は神託により斎院になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Emperor Saga abdicated the throne and the Crown Prince ascended the throne (Emperor Goichijo), but Genji no miya, who was expected to enter into the court as the consort of the new emperor, became a Sai-in (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Kamo-jinja Shrines) in accordance with an oracle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Emperor Saga abdicates the throne and the Crown Prince ascends the throne (Emperor Goichijo), but Genji no miya, who has been expected to enter into the court as the consort of the new emperor, becomes a Sai-in (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Kamo-jinja shrines) in accordance with an oracle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Saga abdicates the throne and the Crown Prince is crowned (Emperor Goichijo) but Genji no Miya, who was expected to become the consort of the new emperor is appointed a Sai-in (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Kamo-jinja Shrines) by an oracle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Crown Prince大文字にしました。Goichijoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>世の中が嫌になった狭衣は粉河寺に参詣したが、その途上で飛鳥井女君の消息と彼女の生んだ自分の娘（飛鳥井姫君）の存在を知った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo, who got sick and tired of the world, paid a visit to the Kokawa-dera Temple and, on his way, he knew Asukai onnagimi&apos;s whereabouts and existence of his daughter born by her (Asukai himegimi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo, who has grown sick and tired of the world, pays a visit to the Kokawa-dera Temple and, on his way, he learns of Asukai onnagimi&apos;s whereabouts and the existence of his daughter born by her (Asukai himegimi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo grows sick and tired of the world, and on his way to Kokawa-dera Temple receives news of Asukai Onnagimi and the existence of his daughter (Asukai Himegimi) to whom she gave birth.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>第三巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 3</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 3</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume Three</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>狭衣は飛鳥井女君の忘れ形見の姫君に会いたい一心で、姫君を引き取った一品宮の屋敷に忍び込んで騒がれたため、心ならずも一回り年上の一品宮と結婚する羽目になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the sole desire to see the girl who was left behind by Asukai onnagimi&apos;s death, Sagoromo stole in the residence of mansion of Ippon no Miya, who took the girl, and was shouted an alarm, and, therefore, he got obliged to marry Ippon no Miya, who is older than Sagoromo for twelve years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the sole desire to see the girl who was left behind by Asukai onnagimi&apos;s death, Sagoromo steals into the residence in the mansion of Ippon no Miya, who has taken the girl; but shouts of alarm go up, and Sagoromo is obliged to marry Ippon no Miya, who is 12 years his senior.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the sole desire to meet his daughter, Himegimi, born to the dead Asukai Onnagimi, he sneaks into the residence of Ippon no Miya who took in Himegimi but the ensuing chaos results in a situation in which he is obliged to marry Ippon no Miya who is 12 years his senior.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>狭衣の真意を知った一品宮も頑なな態度を貫いて打ち解けず、結婚生活は最初から冷え切っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ippon no Miya, who noticed Sagoromo&apos;s real intention, maintained her heart of stone and did not throw away all reserve and, therefore, their marriage life was cold one from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ippon no Miya, who notices Sagoromo&apos;s real intention, maintains her heart of stone and does not throw away her reserve; thus their marriage life is cold from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ippon no Miya discovers Sagoromo&apos;s real intention but maintains her obstinate resolve, resulting in a marriage that is cold from the outset.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>第四巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 4</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 4</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume Four</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>心底から俗世が嫌になった狭衣は出家を決意するが、賀茂明神の神託と両親によって出家を阻止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagoromo, who got fed up with this world from the bottom of his heart, made his mind to become a priest, but he was prevented by an oracle of the Kamo Myojin Shrine and his parents from becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo, who is weary of the world from the bottom of his heart, makes up his mind to become a priest, but his parents and an oracle of the Kamo Myojin Shrine prevent him from doing so.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo grows weary of the world from the bottom of his heart and resolves to enter the priesthood but his parents and an oracle of Kamo Myojin Shrine prevent him from doing so.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その後狭衣は源氏の宮に瓜二つの美しい式部卿宮の姫君と結ばれ、心を癒された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Sagoromo was united with Shikibukyo no Miya no Himegimi (daughter of the Highness of Ceremonial), who was beautiful and exactly alike Genji no miya and his spirit was healed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagoromo is then united with Shikibukyo no Miya no Himegimi (daughter of the Highness of Ceremonial), who is beautiful and exactly alike Genji no miya, and his spirit is healed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo later becomes involved with Shikibukyo no Miya no Himegimi, who is beautiful and exactly like Genji no Miya, and his heart is healed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>やがて神託によって狭衣は帝位につき、彼の実の息子・若宮の皇位継承が約束される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Sagoromo enthroned by an oracle and his real son, Wakamiya&apos;s enthronement was promised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Sagoromo is enthroned by an oracle and the eventual enthronement of his real son, Wakamiya, is promised.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagoromo is eventually declared emperor by an oracle, and it is promised that his real son, Wakamiya, will succeed the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>式部卿宮の姫君（藤壺女御）は皇子をもうけて中宮に立ち、娘の飛鳥井姫君も一品内親王になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikibukyo no Miya no Himegimi (Fujitsubo Nyogo (consort)) gave birth to an Imperial Prince and became chugu (consort of higher rank than nyogo) and his daughter Asukai no himegimi became an ippon naishinno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikibukyo no Miya no Himegimi (Fujitsubo Nyogo (consort)) gives birth to an Imperial Prince and became chugu (consort of higher rank than nyogo) and his daughter Asukai no himegimi becomes an ippon naishinno.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikibukyo no Miya no Himegimi (Fujitsubo Nyogo (consort)) gives birth to an Imperial Prince and becomes chugu (the second consort of an emperor), while his daughter Asukai Himegimi becomes Ippon Naishinno (Imperial Princess Ippon).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし栄光の極みにあっても、狭衣の心は源氏の宮や女二宮を想って憂愁に閉ざされたままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if he is in the peak of glory, his heart remained closed because of melancholy thinking of Genji no miya and Onna ninomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even at the peak of glory, his heart remains closed because of melancholy; he is lost in thoughts of Genji no miya and Onna ninomiya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even at the peak of his glory, Sagoromo&apos;s heart remains trapped in the melancholy of thoughts of Genji no Miya and Onna Ninomiya.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 頭痛(id:201680), 水野白楓(id:22811), Yume149(id:17504), こぶまき(id:38278), YOSHI438(id:174755), Kouko0515(id:100370), 捕澤(id:23785), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>