<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蛍 (源氏物語)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotaru (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotaru (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotaru (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蛍（ほたる）は、『源氏物語』五十四帖の巻名のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotaru (The Fireflies) is one of the 54 chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotaru (The Fireflies) is one of the 54 chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotaru (The Fireflies) is one of the 54 chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第25帖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the 25th chapter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the 25th chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the 25th chapter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>光源氏36歳の5月の話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikaru Genji, age 36, in May.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chapter concerns the month of May when Hikaru Genji was 36.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chapter concerns the month of May when Hikaru Genji was 36.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>五月雨の頃、蛍兵部卿宮から玉鬘 (源氏物語)に文が届き、源氏はそれに返事を書かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the time when an early summer rain was falling, a letter arrived to Tamakazura from Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya, so Genji had her write a reply</e>
<cmt>（源氏物語）はリンク先の語のため、省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the time of the early summer rains, a letter arrived for Tamakazura from Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya, so Genji had her write a reply</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - I don&apos;t know if it needs some explanation of the relationships between the people</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the time of the early summer rains, a letter arrived for Tamakazura from Hotaru Hyobukyonomiya, so Genji had her write a reply.</e>
<cmt>Hyobukyonomiya 煮訂正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>喜び勇んで六条院にやってきた兵部卿宮の前で、源氏は几帳の内にホタルを放ち、その光で玉鬘の姿を浮かび上がらせて見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In front of Hyobukyo no Miya, who came to the Rokujo-in Palace with great glee, Genji released fireflies inside of the screen, lighting faintly Tamakazura with the glow and showing her figure to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji released fireflies behind the screen separating Hyobukyo no Miya, who had arrived at the Rokujo-in Palace in high spirits, and Tamakazura, softly illuminating her silhouette.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji released fireflies behind the screen separating Hyobukyonomiya, who had arrived at the Rokujo-in Palace in high spirits, and Tamakazura, softly illuminating her silhouette.</e>
<cmt>Hyobukyonomiya 煮訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>予想以上の美しさに心を奪われた兵部卿宮は想いを和歌で訴えるが、玉鬘はつれなくあしらうだけだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyobukyo no Miya was deeply attracted to her beauty, which was more than he had expected, so sent a waka poem to express his love to her, but she just gave him a flat refusal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyobukyo no Miya was deeply attracted to her beauty, which was greater than he had expected, so he sent a waka poem to express his love to her, but she just ignored him.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyobukyonomiya was deeply attracted to her beauty, which was greater than he had expected, so he sent a waka poem to express his love to her, but she just ignored him.</e>
<cmt>Hyobukyonomiya 煮訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（この逸話から、兵部卿宮は蛍宮、蛍兵部卿宮等と呼ばれる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Due to this episode, Hyobukyo no Miya came to be called Hotaru no Miya or Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Due to this episode, Hyobukyo no Miya came to be called Hotaru no Miya or Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Due to this episode, Hyobukyonomiya came to be called Hotaru no miya or Hotaru Hyobukyonomiya).</e>
<cmt>Hyobukyonomiya 煮訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>5月5日の端午、玉鬘の下には数多くのくす玉が贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the festival on the fifth day of the fifth month (of the lunar calendar), many decorative paper balls were sent to Tamakazura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a festival on the fifth day of the fifth month, many decorative paper balls were sent to Tamakazura.</e>
<cmt>ArticleDeleted &quot;(of the lunar calendar)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At a festival on the fifth day of the fifth month, many decorative paper balls were sent to Tamakazura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>源氏は夏の町で騎射と宴を催し、その晩は花散里のところに泊まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genji shot arrows from horseback at a town in summer and held a banquet, and then he stayed over night at Hanachirusato&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji held horseback archery events and banquets at the Natsu no Machi section of the palace and spent the night at Hanachirusato&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - I believe &quot;夏の町&quot; was the part of the 六條院 where 花散里 lived</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji held horseback archery events and banquets at the Natsu no Machi section of the palace and spent the night at Hanachirusato&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>やがて長雨の季節に入り、物語に熱中する玉鬘に源氏は物語評論を聞かせ、相も変わらず言い寄って玉鬘を困らせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, a season of a long spell of rainy weather came, and Genji told a critique of a tale to Tamakazura, who was absorbed in reading tales, and bothered her, trying to get close to her as usual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, the rainy season arrived, and Genji spent time giving critiques of the tales that Tamakazura was absorbed in, and bothering her with his unending wooing.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, the rainy season arrived, and Genji spent time giving critiques of the tales that Tamakazura was absorbed in, and bothering her with his unending wooing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その頃玉鬘の実父頭中将も、夢占でかつて夕顔 (源氏物語)との間にもうけた娘が他人の養女になっているだろうと告げられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, Tamakazura&apos;s real father, Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) was also told by a dream diviner that a daughter between him and Yugao became someone else&apos;s adoptive daughter.</e>
<cmt>（源氏物語）はリンク先の語のため、省略しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, Tamakazura&apos;s real father, To no Chujo, was told by a dream diviner that his daughter by Yugao had been adopted by someone else.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationRevised for clarity - although 頭中将 is a title, I don&apos;t think it needs a translation as it&apos;s used as a name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Tamakazura&apos;s real father, To no Chujo, was told by a dream diviner that his daughter by Yugao had been adopted by someone else.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>まさか源氏の下にいるとは知らずにその行方を捜していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He never imagined that she lived with Genji, and was looking for her.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Never imagining that she lived with Genji, he set out to look for her.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - not an exact translation but reads better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Never imagining that she lived with Genji, he set out to look for her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>