<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竹取物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taketori Monogatari (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taketori Monogatari (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taketori Monogatari (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>竹取物語（たけとりものがたり）は、日本最古の一覧とされる物語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Taketori Monogatari is the oldest tale in Japan.</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアを参照して、原文の意味の通らない箇所を修正いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Taketori Monogatari is the oldest tale in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Taketori Monogatari is the oldest tale in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>竹取物語は通称であり、竹取翁の物語ともかぐや姫の物語とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it is commonly known as Taketori Monogatari, it was also called Taketori no Okina no Monogatari (The Tale of the Old Bamboo Cutter) or Kaguyahime no Monogatari (The Tale of Princess Kaguya).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it is commonly known as Taketori Monogatari, it was also called Taketori no Okina no Monogatari (The Tale of the Old Bamboo Cutter) or Kaguyahime no Monogatari (The Tale of Princess Kaguya).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is commonly known as Taketori Monogatari, it was also called Taketori no Okina no Monogatari (The Tale of the Old Bamboo Cutter) or Kaguyahime no Monogatari (The Tale of Princess Kaguya).</e>
<cmt>Though -&gt; &quot;Although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>成立年、作者ともに不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both the year of creation and the author are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the year of completion and the author are unknown.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Creation&quot;-&quot;completion&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the year of completion and the author are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>仮名によって書かれた最初期の物語の一つでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is also known as one of the tales written in kana (the Japanese Syllabaries) in the early period in a history of literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is also known as one of the earliest tales written in kana (the Japanese Syllabaries) in the history of Japanese literature.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;earliest&quot; to &quot;tales&quot;. Cut &quot;early period&quot; and added &quot;in the history of Japanese literature&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is also known as one of the earliest tales written in kana (the Japanese Syllabaries) in the history of Japanese literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>光り輝く竹の中から出てきて竹取の翁の夫婦に育てられたかぐや姫の物語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a tale about Princess Kaguya who comes from the inside of a shining bamboo and is brought up by a bamboo cutter and his wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the tale of Princess Kaguya who comes from the inside of a shining bamboo shoot and is brought up by a bamboo cutter and his wife.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The tale of&quot;. Added &quot;shoot&quot; to &quot;bamboo&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the tale of Princess Kaguya who comes from the inside of a shining bamboo shoot and is brought up by a bamboo cutter and his wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『万葉集』巻十六の第三七九一歌には、「竹取の翁」が天女を詠んだという長歌があり、この物語との関連が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 3791st poem collected in the 16th volume of &quot;Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)&quot; is a choka (long poem) in which &apos;the bamboo cutter&apos; composes a poem about a heavenly maiden, which suggests that it might be related to the tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 3791st poem collected in the 16th volume of Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) is a choka (long poem) in which &apos;the bamboo cutter&apos; composes a poem about a heavenly maiden, which suggests that it might be related to the tale.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 3791st poem collected in the 16th volume of Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) is a choka (long poem) in which &apos;the bamboo cutter&apos; composes a poem about a heavenly maiden, which suggests that it might be related to the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Creation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completion</e>
<cmt>Changed to match translation above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Completion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>成立年は明らかにされていないが、原本は当然現存せず、最古の写本は天正年間（安土桃山時代）のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of creation is not revealed, and of course the original manuscript is not extant; the oldest manuscript was made during the Tensho era (Azuchi-Momoyama period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year of completion is unknown, and of course the original manuscript is not extant; the oldest manuscript was made during the Tensho era (Azuchi-Momoyama period).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Creation&quot;-&quot;completion&quot;. &quot;Not revealed&quot;-&quot;unknown&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year of completion is unknown, and of course the original manuscript is not extant; the oldest manuscript was made during the Tensho era (Azuchi-Momoyama period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、10世紀の『大和物語』、『うつほ物語』や11世紀の『栄花物語』、『狭衣物語』などに『竹取物語』への言及が見られ、また『源氏物語』「絵合」巻に「物語の出で来はじめの祖なる竹取の翁」とあることから、遅くとも10世紀半ばまでに成立したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;Yamato Monogatari (Tales of Yamato)&quot; and &quot;Utsuho Monogatari (The Tale of the Cavern)&quot; completed in the tenth century, and &quot;Eiga Monogatari (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes)&quot; and &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari (The Tale of Sagoromo)&quot; in the eleventh century refer to &quot;Taketori Monogatari,&quot; and moreover a chapter of &apos;A Picture Contest&apos; in &quot;Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji)&quot; says, &apos;Taketori no Okina, a founder of the tale,&apos; which suggests that the tale was completed at least by the mid-tenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yamato Monogatari (Tales of Yamato) and Utsuho Monogatari (The Tale of the Cavern) completed in the tenth century, and Eiga Monogatari (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) and Sagoromo Monogatari (The Tale of Sagoromo) in the eleventh century refer to Taketori Monogatari, and moreover a chapter of &apos;A Picture Contest&apos; in Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji) says, &apos;Taketori no Okina, a founder of the tale,&apos; which suggests that the tale was completed at least by the mid-tenth century.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Yamato) and &quot;Utsuho Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Cavern) completed in the tenth century, and &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) and &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Sagoromo) in the eleventh century refer to &quot;Taketori Monogatari,&quot; and moreover a chapter of &apos;A Picture Contest&apos; in &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) says, &apos;Taketori no Okina, a founder of the tale,&apos; which suggests that the tale was completed at least by the mid-tenth century.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>通説は、平安時代前期の貞観 (日本)年間 - 延喜年間、特に890年代後半に書かれたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally considered that the tale was written between the Jogan era, the first half of the Heian period, and the Engi era, especially the latter half of the 890s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally considered that the tale was written between the Jogan era, the first half of the Heian period, and the Engi era, especially the latter half of the 890s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally considered that the tale was written between the Jogan era, the first half of the Heian period, and the Engi era, especially the latter half of the 890s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>元々、口承説話として伝えられたものが『後漢書』や『白氏文集』など漢籍の影響を受けて一旦は漢文の形で完成されたが、後に平仮名で書き改められたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the influence of the Chinese books like &quot;History of the Later han Dynasty&quot; and &quot;Bai-Shi Wen Ji,&quot; the original tale, which had been passed on by word of mouth, was once written down in Chinese, and then it seems to have be rewritten in kana later.</e>
<cmt>『白氏文集』の定訳はネットで見る限り&quot;Bai-Shi Wen Ji&quot;の方が多いため、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the influence of the Chinese books like History of the Later han Dynasty and Bai-Shi Wen Ji, the original tale, which had been passed on by word of mouth, was once written down in Chinese, and then it seems to have be rewritten in kana later.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the influence of the Chinese books like &quot;History of the Later han Dynasty&quot; and &quot;Bai-Shi Wen Ji,&quot; the original tale, which had been passed on by word of mouth, was once written down in Chinese, and then it seems to have been rewritten in kana later.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足be→been</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>作者についても不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author is also unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author is also unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author is also unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>作者像として、当時の識字率から庶民は考えられず上流階級に属しており、貴族の情報が入手できる平安京近隣に居住していたと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the literacy rate in those days, a common man would not be a possible author, therefore it is conjectured that the author would have been somebody who belonged to the upper class and lived near the Heiankyo (the Heian Palace), easily accessing information of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the literacy rate in those days, a common man could not be a possible author, therefore it is conjectured that the author would have been somebody who belonged to the upper class and lived near the Heiankyo (the Heian Palace), easily accessing information of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Would&quot;-&quot;could&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the literacy rate in those days, a common man could not be a possible author, therefore it is conjectured that the author would have been somebody who belonged to the upper class and lived near the Heiankyo (the Heian Palace), easily accessing information of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、物語内容に反体制な要素が認められることから当時権力を握っていた藤原氏の係累ではなく、漢学・仏教・民間伝承に精通し、仮名文字を操ることができ、貴重だった紙の入手も可能な人物で性別は男性だったのではないかと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is something antiestablishment in the tale, so the author couldn&apos;t have been a descendant of the Fujiwara clan who held power in those days, therefore it is considered that the tale would have been written by a male writer who was familiar with the study of the Chinese classics, Buddhism, folklore, and able to write kana letters and get some paper, which was precious.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there is something antiestablishment in the tale, so the author couldn&apos;t have been a descendant of the Fujiwara clan who held power in those days, therefore it is considered that the tale would have been written by a male writer who was familiar with the study of the Chinese classics, Buddhism, folklore, and able to write kana letters on paper, which was precious.</e>
<cmt>&quot;And get some&quot;-&quot;on&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is something antiestablishment in the tale, so the author couldn&apos;t have been a descendant of the Fujiwara clan who held power in those days, therefore it is considered that the tale would have been written by a male writer who was familiar with the study of the Chinese classics, Buddhism, folklore, and able to write kana letters on paper, which was precious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>以上をふまえ、源順、源融、遍昭、紀貫之、紀長谷雄などの作者説が唱えられているが、いずれも決め手に欠けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on these things mentioned above, the author would have been MINAMOTO no Shitagou, MINAMOTO no Toru, Henjo, KI no Tsrurayuki, or KI no Haseo, but there is no decisive factor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on these things mentioned above, the author could have been MINAMOTO no Shitagou, MINAMOTO no Toru, Henjo, KI no Tsrurayuki, or KI no Haseo, but it is impossible to say for sure.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Would&quot;-&quot;could&quot;. &quot;No decisive factor&quot;-&quot;impossible to say for sure&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on these things mentioned above, the author could have been MINAMOTO no Shitago, MINAMOTO no Toru, Henjo, KI no Tsurayuki, or KI no Haseo, but it is impossible to say for sure.</e>
<cmt>人名のスペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>竹を切って来ていろいろな製品を作って暮らしていた竹取の翁（おきな）とその妻の嫗（おうな）がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are Taketori no Okina (an old man) and his wife Ona (an old woman), and the Okina makes a living by creating various things with bamboo he cuts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characters are Taketori no Okina (an old man) and his wife Ona (an old woman), and the Okina makes a living by creating various things with the bamboo he cuts.</e>
<cmt>&quot;There is&quot;-&quot;the characters are&quot;. &quot;The bamboo&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characters are Taketori no Okina (an old man) and his wife Ona (an old woman), and the Okina makes a living by creating various things with the bamboo he cuts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ある日、竹取の翁が竹林に出かけていくと、根元が光り輝いている竹があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, when Taketori no Okina goes to a bamboo thicket, he sees a bamboo whose base is shining.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, when Taketori no Okina goes to a bamboo thicket, he sees a bamboo whose base is shining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, when Taketori no Okina goes to a bamboo thicket, he sees a bamboo whose base is shining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>なんだろうと思って切ってみると、中から三寸ほどの可愛らしい女の子が出てきたので、自分たちの子供として育てることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wondering what it is, he cuts the bamboo and finds a lovely girl about three inches tall in there, so he decides to bring her up as their child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wondering what it is, he cuts the bamboo and finds a lovely girl about three inches tall in there, so he decides to bring her up as their child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wondering what it is, he cuts the bamboo and finds a lovely girl about three inches tall in there, so he decides to bring her up as their child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その日から竹の中に金を見つける日が続き、竹取の翁の夫婦は豊かになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then he finds gold in bamboos every day, and the couple become rich.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he finds gold in bamboos every day, and the couple become rich.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Since then&quot;-&quot;after that&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he finds gold in bamboos every day, and the couple become rich.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>翁が見つけた子供はどんどん大きくなり、三ヶ月ほどで年頃の娘になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The child whom the Okina has found grows bigger and bigger, and arrives at the age of marriage in three months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The child whom the Okina has found grows bigger and bigger, and reaches adolescence in three months.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and arrives at the age of marriage&quot;-&quot;and reaches adolescence&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The child whom the Okina has found grows bigger and bigger, and reaches adolescence in three months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この世のものとは思えないほど美しくなった娘に、人を呼んで名前をつけることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She becomes an incredibly beautiful lady, and someone is called to give her a name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She becomes an incredibly beautiful lady, and someone is called to give her a name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She becomes an incredibly beautiful lady, and someone is called to give her a name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>呼ばれてきた人は、「なよ竹のかぐや姫」と名づけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person names her &apos;Nayotake (pliable bamboo) no Kaguyahime.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person names her &apos;Nayotake (pliable bamboo) no Kaguyahime.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person names her &apos;Nayotake (pliable bamboo) no Kaguyahime.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この時、男女を問わず人を集め、三日にわたって様々な遊びをした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, many people, both men and women, are gathered to play for three days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, many people, both men and women, gather to celebrate for three days.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Are gathered&quot;-&quot;gather&quot;. &quot;Play&quot;-&quot;celebrate&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, many people, both men and women, gather to celebrate for three days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>世間の男たちは、高貴な人も下層の人も皆なんとかしてかぐや姫と結婚したいと思った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both noble and vulgar men all try to marry Princess Kaguya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both noble and vulgar men all try to marry Princess Kaguya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both noble and vulgar men all try to marry Princess Kaguya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その姿を覗き見ようと竹取の翁の家の周りをうろつく公達は後を絶たず、彼らは竹取の翁の家の周りで過ごしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many young court nobles who try to take a peek at her constantly come and surround the residence of Taketori no Okina, spending their time around it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many young court nobles who try to take a peek at her constantly come and surround the residence of Taketori no Okina, spending their time around it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many young court nobles who try to take a peek at her constantly come and surround the residence of Taketori no Okina, spending their time around it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そのうちに熱意のないものは来なくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, those who are not so enthusiastic stop visiting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, those who are not so enthusiastic stop visiting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, those who are not so enthusiastic stop visiting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>最後に残ったのは好色といわれる5人の公達で、彼らはあきらめず夜昼となく通ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five young court nobles who are said to be lecherous are left, and they keep visiting his house day and night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five young court nobles who are said to be lecherous remain, and they keep visiting his house day and night.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Are left&quot;-&quot;remain&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five young court nobles who are said to be lecherous remain, and they keep visiting his house day and night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>5人の公達は、石作皇子、車持皇子、右大臣阿倍御主人、大納言大伴御行、中納言石上麻呂といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These five young court nobles are as follows: Prince Ishizukuri, Prince Kurumamochi, Minister of the Right Abe no Miushi, Major Councillor OTOMO no Miyuki, and Middle Councillor ISONOKAMI no Maro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These five young court nobles are as follows: Prince Ishizukuri, Prince Kurumamochi, Minister of the Right Abe no Miushi, Major Councillor OTOMO no Miyuki, and Middle Councillor ISONOKAMI no Maro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These five young court nobles are as follows: Prince Ishizukuri, Prince Kurumamochi, Minister of the Right Abe no Miushi, Dainagon (chief councilor of state) OTOMO no Miyuki, and Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) ISONOKAMI no Maro.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Major Councillor&quot;→&quot;Dainagon (chief councilor of state)&quot;に変更しました。&quot;Middle Councillor&quot;→&quot;Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>彼らがあきらめそうにないのを見て、翁がかぐや姫に「女は男と結婚するものだ。お前も彼らの中から選びなさい」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Okina, who realizes that these men wouldn&apos;t give up, tells Princess Kaguya that &apos;women should marry men. You should choose one from them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Okina, who realizes that these men won&apos;t give up, tells Princess Kaguya that &apos;women should marry men. You should choose one from them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Wouldn&apos;t&quot;-&quot;won&apos;t&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okina, who realizes that these men won&apos;t give up, tells Princess Kaguya that &apos;women should marry men. You should choose one from them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>かぐや姫は「『私の言うものを持ってくることができた人と結婚したいと思います』と彼らに伝えてください」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Princess Kaguya says, &apos;Please tell them that I would like to marry the man who will bring something I want.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Princess Kaguya says, &apos;Please tell them that I would like to marry the man who will bring me something I want.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Bring me&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Princess Kaguya says, &apos;Please tell them that I would like to marry the man who will bring me something I want.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>夜になると、例の五人が集まって来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When night comes, the five men gather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When night comes, the five men gather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When night comes, the five men gather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>翁は五人の公達を集め、かぐや姫の意思を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Okina tells them what Princess Kaguya wants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Okina tells them what Princess Kaguya wants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okina tells them what Princess Kaguya wants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>その意思とは石作皇子には仏の御石の鉢、車持皇子には蓬莱の玉の枝、右大臣阿倍御主人には火鼠の裘、大納言大伴御行には龍の首の珠、中納言石上麻呂には燕の子安貝を持ってこさせるというものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She asks Prince Ishizukuri to bring the stone begging bowl used by Buddha; Prince Kurumamochi, a branch of a tree with jeweled fruit from Penglai, the legendary Isle of the Immortals; Minister of the Right ABE no Miushi, a robe made of the fire-rat; Major Councillor OTOMO no Miyuki, a gemstone from a dragon&apos;s head; Middle Councillor ISONOKAMI no Maro, one of the easy-birth shells supposedly possessed by swallows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She asks Prince Ishizukuri to bring the stone begging bowl used by Buddha; Prince Kurumamochi, a branch of a tree with jeweled fruit from Penglai, the legendary Isle of the Immortals; Minister of the Right ABE no Miushi, a robe made of the fire-rat; Major Councillor OTOMO no Miyuki, a gemstone from a dragon&apos;s head; Middle Councillor ISONOKAMI no Maro, one of the easy-birth shells supposedly possessed by swallows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She asks Prince Ishizukuri to bring the stone begging bowl used by Buddha; Prince Kurumamochi, a branch of a tree with jeweled fruit from Penglai, the legendary Isle of the Immortals; Minister of the Right ABE no Miushi, a robe made of the fire-rat; Dainagon (chief councilor of state) OTOMO no Miyuki, a gemstone from a dragon&apos;s head; Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) ISONOKAMI no Maro, one of the easy-birth shells supposedly possessed by swallows.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Major Councillor&quot;→&quot;Dainagon (chief councilor of state)&quot;に変更しました。&quot;Middle Councillor&quot;→&quot;Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>どれも話にしか聞かない珍しい宝ばかりで、手に入れるのは困難だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of them are legendary rare treasures and difficult to get.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of them are legendary rare treasures and difficult to get.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of them are legendary rare treasures and difficult to get.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>石作は只の鉢を持っていってばれ、車持は偽物をわざわざ作ったが職人がやってきてばれ、阿倍はそれは燃えない物とされていたのに燃えて別物、大伴は嵐に遭って諦め、石上は大炊寮の大八洲という名の大釜が据えてある小屋の屋根に上って取ろうとして腰を打ち、断命。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishizukuri takes a mere bowl to be found out that it is a fake; Kurumamochi has a craftsman make an imitation, which is also revealed because the craftsman shows up; What Abe has brought is supposed not to burn, but actually it does; Otomo gives up bringing the treasure because of the storm; Isonokami dies because he tries to take the shell climbing up the roof of a shed on which a big pot called Oyashima of the Oiryo (a part of the Imperial Household) is set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishizukuri takes an ordinary bowl which is revealed to be a fake; Kurumamochi has a craftsman make an imitation, which is also revealed because the craftsman shows up; What Abe has brought is supposed not to burn, but actually it does; Otomo gives up bringing the treasure because of the storm; Isonokami dies because he tries to take the shell climbing up the roof of a shed on which a big pot called Oyashima of the Oiryo (a part of the Imperial Household) is set.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Mere&quot;-&quot;ordinary&quot;. &quot;found out that it is a fake&quot;-&quot;revealed to be a fake&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishizukuri takes an ordinary bowl which is revealed to be a fake; Kurumamochi has a craftsman make an imitation, which is also revealed because the craftsman shows up; What Abe has brought is supposed not to burn, but actually it does; Otomo gives up bringing the treasure because of the storm; Isonokami dies because he tries to take the shell climbing up the roof of a shed on which a big pot called Oyashima of the Oiryo (a part of the Imperial Household) is set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>結局誰一人として成功しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, nobody succeeds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, nobody succeeds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, nobody succeeds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>そんな様が天皇に伝わり、御門が会いたがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikado (the Emperor) hears about what is going on, and he wants to see her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikado (the Emperor) hears about what is going on, and he wants to see her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikado (the Emperor) hears about what is going on, and he wants to see her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>翁が取り持ったが、彼女は拒否し、一度は姿を見られたものの、姿を消して見せたりして結局御門も諦めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Okina tries to arrange the meeting, but she refuses it, and she makes the Mikado give up her too, disappearing from his sight, though she has been seen by him once.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味が不鮮明なためウィキペディアを参照したところ、この部分は次のようになっていました。「喜ぶ翁の取りなしにも関わらず彼女はあくまで拒否を貫くが、不意をついて訪ねてきた帝に姿を見られてしまう。しかし、一瞬のうちに姿を消して地上の人間でない所を見せ、結局帝をも諦めさせた。」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Okina tries to arrange the meeting, but she refuses it, and she makes the Mikado give up on her too, disappearing from his sight, though she has only been seen by him once.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Give up on her&quot;. &quot;Only been seen by him once&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okina tries to arrange the meeting, but she refuses it, and she makes the Mikado give up on her too, disappearing from his sight, although she has only been seen by him once.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Though&quot; -&gt; &quot;Although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、彼と和歌の交換はするようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she comes to exchange waka poems with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she comes to exchange waka poems with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she comes to exchange waka poems with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>御門と和歌を遣り取りするようになって三年の月日が経った頃、かぐや姫は月を見て物思いに耽るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three years have passed since she started to exchange poems with the Mikado, and Princess Kaguya comes to be lost in deep thought whenever she looks at the moon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three years have passed since she started to exchange poems with the Mikado, and Princess Kaguya comes to be lost in deep thought whenever she looks at the moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three years have passed since she started to exchange poems with the Mikado, and Princess Kaguya comes to be lost in deep thought whenever she looks at the moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>八月の満月が近づくにつれ、かぐや姫は激しく泣くようになり、翁が問うと「自分はこの国の人ではなく月の都の人であり、十五日に帰らねばならぬ」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a full moon of August comes near, she is often crying bitterly, so the Okina asks her why and she replies, &apos;I&apos;m not from this planet but from the moon, and have to return to it on 15th.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a full moon of August comes near, she is often crying bitterly, so the Okina asks her why and she replies, &apos;I&apos;m not from this planet but from the moon, and have to return to it on 15th.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a full moon of August comes near, she is often crying bitterly, so the Okina asks her why and she replies, &apos;I&apos;m not from this planet but from the moon, and have to return to it on 15th.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>それを御門が知り、勇ましい軍勢も送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mikado knows it and sends brave troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mikado discovers this and sends brave troops.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Knows it&quot;-&quot;discovers this&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mikado discovers this and sends brave troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>そして当日、子の刻頃、空から人が降りてきたが、軍勢も翁も嫗も抵抗できないまま、かぐや姫は月へ帰っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the day, around midnight, somebody comes from the sky, but the troops, the Okina and Ona can&apos;t resist, and Princess Kaguya goes back to the moon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the day, around midnight, somebody comes from the sky, but the troops, the Okina and Ona can&apos;t resist, and Princess Kaguya goes back to the moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the day, around midnight, somebody comes from the sky, but the troops, the Okina and Ona can&apos;t resist, and Princess Kaguya goes back to the moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>別れの時、かぐや姫は御門に不死の薬と天の羽衣、文を贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Princess Kaguya leaves, she presents the Mikado the elixir of life and a feathered robe worn by heavenly beings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Princess Kaguya leaves, she presents the Mikado the elixir of life and a feathered robe worn by heavenly beings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Princess Kaguya leaves, she presents the Mikado the elixir of life, a feathered robe worn by heavenly beings and a letter.</e>
<cmt>and a letter補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>しかし御門はそれを駿河国の日本一の一覧高い山で焼くように命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Mikado orders to burn them at the highest mountain in Japan, which is in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味が通らないのでウィキペディアを参照したところ、次のようになっていました。「それを駿河国の日本で一番高い山で焼くように命じた。」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Mikado orders to burn them at the highest mountain in Japan, which is in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Mikado orders to burn them at the highest mountain in Japan, which is in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>それからその山は「不死の山」（後の富士山）と呼ばれ、また、その山からは常に煙が上がるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then the mountain is called &apos;Fushi no yama (literally, a mountain of immortal)&apos; (later called Mt. Fuji), and smoke comes to rise from the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then the mountain is called &apos;Fushi no yama (literally, a mountain of immortal)&apos; (later called Mt. Fuji), and smoke comes to rise from the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then the mountain is called &apos;Fushi no yama&apos; (literally, a mountain of immortal) (later called Mt. Fuji), and smoke comes to rise from the mountain.</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>物語としての性格</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A characteristic of the tale</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of the tale</e>
<cmt>Cut &quot;the&quot;. &quot;Characteristics&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of the tale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>この作品には、かぐや姫が竹の中から生まれたという竹中生誕説話（異常出生説話）、かぐやが3ヶ月で大きくなったという急成長説話、かぐや姫の神異によって竹取の翁が富み栄えたという致富長者説話、複数の求婚者へ難題を課していずれも失敗する求婚難題説話、帝の求婚を拒否する帝求婚説話、かぐや姫が月へ戻るという昇天説話（羽衣説話）、最後に富士山の地名由来を説き明かす地名起源説話など、非常に多様な要素が含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This work contains very different elements of story: a story of Princess Kaguya&apos;s being born from a bamboo (a story of extraordinary birth); a story of sudden growth as Kaguya&apos;s becoming grown-up in three months; a story of becoming a rich man as Taketori no Okina&apos;s flourishing due to miracles created by Princess Kaguya; a story of suitors and difficult tasks as her giving difficult tasks to the suitors to fail in solving them; a story of Emperor&apos;s marriage proposal as her refusing Emperor&apos;s courtship; a story of rising to heaven (a story of a robe of feathers) as Princess Kaguya&apos;s returning to the moon; a story of an origin of the name of the place as the name of Mt. Fuji being revealed at the end of the tale.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処竹中生誕説話（異常出生説話）→the birth in the bamboo story (extraordinary birth story)神異→supernatral acts致富長者説話→making a man rich story求婚難題説話→giving difficult conditions for marriage story帝求婚説話→Emperor&apos;s propose story昇天説話（羽衣説話）→apotheosis story (the feather robe story)地名起源説話→the origin of the name of the place story</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This work contains very different elements of story: a story of Princess Kaguya&apos;s being born from a bamboo (a story of extraordinary birth); a story of sudden growth as Kaguya&apos;s becoming grown-up in three months; a story of becoming a rich man as Taketori no Okina&apos;s flourishing due to miracles created by Princess Kaguya; a story of suitors and difficult tasks as her giving difficult tasks to the suitors to fail in solving them; a story of Emperor&apos;s marriage proposal as her refusing Emperor&apos;s courtship; a story of rising to heaven (a story of a robe of feathers) as Princess Kaguya&apos;s returning to the moon; a story of an origin of the name of the place as the name of Mt. Fuji being revealed at the end of the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This work contains very different elements of story: a story of Princess Kaguya&apos;s being born from a bamboo (a story of extraordinary birth); a story of sudden growth as Kaguya&apos;s becoming grown-up in three months; a story of becoming a rich man as Taketori no Okina&apos;s flourishing due to miracles created by Princess Kaguya; a story of suitors and difficult tasks as her giving difficult tasks to the suitors to fail in solving them; a story of Emperor&apos;s marriage proposal as her refusing Emperor&apos;s courtship; a story of rising to heaven (a story of a robe of feathers) as Princess Kaguya&apos;s returning to the moon; a story of an origin of the name of the place as the name of Mt. Fuji being revealed at the end of the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>にも関わらず、高い完成度を有していることから物語、または古代小説の最初期作品として評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of including so many different elements of story, the tale has reached a high degree of perfection, being valued as the tale or the ancient novel in the early period of a history of literature.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of including so many different elements of story, the tale has reached a high degree of perfection, being valued as the tale or the ancient novel in the early period of a history of literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of including so many different elements of story, the tale has reached a high degree of perfection, being valued as the tale or the ancient novel in the early period of a history of literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>多くの要素を含んでいるため、他作品との類似性ないし他作品からの影響が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of so many different elements, the resemblance to or influence of the other works has been pointed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of so many different elements, the resemblance to or influence of the other works has been pointed out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of so many different elements, the resemblance to or influence of the other works has been pointed out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>竹取物語は、異界から来た主人公が貧しい人を富ませた後に再び異界へ去っていくという構造から成り立っており、構造的には羽衣伝説と同一である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taketori Monogatari has basically the same structure as Robe of Feathers Legend, in which a main character from the supernatural world makes a poor man flourish and returns where she comes from.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taketori Monogatari has basically the same structure as Robe of Feathers Legend, in which a main character from the supernatural world makes a poor man flourish and returns where she comes from.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taketori Monogatari has basically the same structure as Robe of Feathers Legend, in which a main character from the supernatural world makes a poor man flourish and returns where she comes from.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>このほか、中国の典籍（『後漢書』『白氏文集』など）との類似点も多数指摘されており、これらの影響を受けていると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the resemblance to the Chinese classical books (&quot;History of the Later Han Dynasty,&quot; &quot;Bai-Shi Wen Ji,&quot; and so on) has been pointed out by many people, so the tale seems to have been affected by these books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the resemblance to the Chinese classical books (History of the Later Han Dynasty, Bai-Shi Wen Ji, and so on) has been pointed out by many people, so the tale seems to have been affected by these books.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the resemblance to the Chinese classical books (&quot;History of the Later Han Dynasty,&quot; &quot;Bai-Shi Wen Ji,&quot; and so on) has been pointed out by many people, so the tale seems to have been affected by these books.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="51">
<j>平安時代後期の『今昔物語集』にも竹取物語と同様の説話（巻31｢竹取の翁、女児を見つけて養う語」）が採集されているが、求婚者への難題は3題のみであり、月へ帰る夜も十五夜でなく、富士山の地名由来譚も登場しない、『竹取物語』より簡略された内容である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu (Tales of Times Now Past)&quot; completed in the late Heian period also includes a similar story to Taketori Monogatari (volume 31, &apos;A story of Taketori no Okina who found a baby girl and brought her up&apos;), but in this version the plot is more simplified: only three difficult tasks are given to the suitors; Princess Kaguya doesn&apos;t return to the moon on the 15th night; a history of the name of Mt. Fuji is not introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konjaku Monogatari Shu (Tales of Times Now Past) completed in the late Heian period also includes a similar story to Taketori Monogatari (volume 31, &apos;A story of Taketori no Okina who found a baby girl and brought her up&apos;), but in this version the plot is more simplified: only three difficult tasks are given to the suitors; Princess Kaguya doesn&apos;t return to the moon on the 15th night; a history of the name of Mt. Fuji is not introduced.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) completed in the late Heian period also includes a similar story to Taketori Monogatari (volume 31, &apos;A story of Taketori no Okina who found a baby girl and brought her up&apos;), but in this version the plot is more simplified: only three difficult tasks are given to the suitors; Princess Kaguya doesn&apos;t return to the moon on the 15th night; a history of the name of Mt. Fuji is not introduced.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>漢籍などを参照したと考えられ、完成した内容を持つ『竹取物語』とは異なり、今昔所収の説話は口頭伝承されてきた「竹取の翁の物語」の古態を伝えているのではないかと想定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tale collected in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; seems to have been referred to the Chinese books, being different from the consummate work of &quot;Taketori Monogatari,&quot; and has been assumed that it told an old form of &apos;The Tale of Taketori no Okina,&apos; which had been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>口頭伝承→oral tradition, folklore→oral transmissionですが、「口承伝承される」という単位で言葉をとらえて訳しましたので、名詞としての訳語は削除させて頂きました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tale collected in Konjaku Monogatari seems to have been referred to the Chinese books, being different from the consummate work of Taketori Monogatari, and has been assumed that it told an old form of The Tale of Taketori no Okina, which had been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tale collected in Konjaku Monogatari seems to have been referred to the Chinese books, being different from the consummate work of &quot;Taketori Monogatari,&quot; and has been assumed that it told an old form of &apos;The Tale of Taketori no Okina,&apos; which had been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>&quot;と&apos;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>竹取物語に似た外国の民間伝承としては、例えば中国四川省のガパ蔵族羌族自治州に伝わる「斑竹姑娘」（田海燕『金玉鳳凰』1961年（中国）に収載）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an example of a foreign folklore similar to Taketori Monogatari; &apos;Banzhu Guniang&apos; (collected in &quot;Jinyu Fenghuang&quot; written and edited by Tian Haiyan in 1961), which has been handed down in Ngawa Tibetan-Qiang Autonomous Region in Sichuan Province, China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an example of a foreign folklore similar to Taketori Monogatari; Banzhu Guniang (collected in Jinyu Fenghuang written and edited by Tian Haiyan in 1961), which has been handed down in Ngawa Tibetan-Qiang Autonomous Region in Sichuan Province, China.</e>
<cmt>Cut quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an example of a foreign folklore similar to Taketori Monogatari; &apos;Banzhu Guniang&apos; (collected in &quot;Jinyu Fenghuang&quot; written and edited by Tian Haiyan in 1961), which has been handed down in Ngawa Tibetan-Qiang Autonomous Region in Sichuan Province, China.</e>
<cmt>&quot;と&apos;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>その内容は、竹の中から生まれた少女が、領主の息子たちから求婚を受けたが難題をつけて退け、かねてより想いを寄せていた男性と結ばれるという話だが、中でも求婚の部分は宝物の数、内容、男性側のやりとりや結末などが非常に酷似している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story is that a girl being born from a bamboo comes to be asked to marry by sons of a feudal lord, but she refuses them giving difficult tasks, and she is wedded to a man whom she has loved for a long time in the end; especially the number of treasure in the scene of courtship, the treasures themselves, conversation with the men, and the ending are quite similar to Taketori Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story is that a girl being born from a bamboo shoot comes to be asked to marry by sons of a feudal lord, but she refuses them giving difficult tasks, and she is wedded to a man whom she has loved for a long time in the end; especially the number of treasures in the scene of courtship, the treasures themselves, conversation with the men, and the ending are quite similar to Taketori Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;shoot&quot; to &quot;bamboo&quot;. &quot;Treasures&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story is that a girl being born from a bamboo shoot comes to be asked to marry by sons of a feudal lord, but she refuses them giving difficult tasks, and she is wedded to a man whom she has loved for a long time in the end; especially the number of treasures in the scene of courtship, the treasures themselves, conversation with the men, and the ending are quite similar to Taketori Monogatari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>登場人物と時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characters and time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characters and time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characters and time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>かぐや姫・老夫婦・御門などは架空の人物だが、実在の人物が登場していることも本作品の特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Princess Kaguya, the old couple, and Mikado are fictional characters, while there are several characters borrowed from reality, which is one of the characteristics of this tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princess Kaguya, the old couple, and Mikado are fictional characters, while there are several characters borrowed from reality, which is one of the characteristics of this tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Princess Kaguya, the old couple, and Mikado are fictional characters, while there are several characters borrowed from reality, which is one of the characteristics of this tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>5人の公達のうち、阿倍御主人、大伴御行、石上麻呂は実在の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of five young court nobles, ABE no Miushi, OTOMO no Miyuki, and ISONOKAMI no Maro were real people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of five young court nobles, ABE no Miushi, OTOMO no Miyuki, and ISONOKAMI no Maro were real people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of five young court nobles, ABE no Miushi, OTOMO no Miyuki, and ISONOKAMI no Maro were real people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また、車持皇子のモデルは藤原不比等、石作皇子のモデルは多治比嶋だっただろうと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is conjectured that Prince Kurumamochi was modeled after FUJIWARA no Fuhito, and Prince Ishizukuri&apos;s model was TAJIHI no Shima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is conjectured that Prince Kurumamochi was modeled after FUJIWARA no Fuhito, and Prince Ishizukuri&apos;s model was TAJIHI no Shima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is conjectured that Prince Kurumamochi was modeled after FUJIWARA no Fuhito, and Prince Ishizukuri&apos;s model was TAJIHI no Shima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>この5人はいずれも壬申の乱の功臣で天武天皇・持統天皇に仕えた人物であることから、奈良時代初期が物語の舞台に設定されたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These five men were all meritorious vassals at the Jinshin War serving Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito, which suggests that the tale takes place in the early Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These five men were all meritorious vassals at the Jinshin War serving Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito, which suggests that the tale takes place in the early Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These five men were all meritorious vassals at the Jinshin War serving Emperor Tenmu and Empress Jito, which suggests that the tale takes place in the early Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>主人公のかぐや姫も、垂仁天皇妃である迦具夜比売（かぐやひめ、大筒木垂根王の女）との関係や、赫夜姫という漢字が「とよひめ」と読めることからから豊受大神との関係について論じられるなど、様々な説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the main character Princess Kaguya, people made various suppositions; for example, a relationship with Emperor Suinin&apos;s consort Kaguyahime (a daughter of Otsuki no Miko (King Otsuki Tarine)), and a relationship with Toyouke Taijin (Grand Divine Toyouke) was discussed because the name of Kaguyahime written in Chinese characters (赫夜姫) can also be read as &apos;Toyohime.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the main character Princess Kaguya, people made various suppositions; for example, a relationship with Emperor Suinin&apos;s consort Kaguyahime (a daughter of Otsuki no Miko (King Otsuki Tarine)), and a relationship with Toyouke Taijin (Grand Divine Toyouke) was discussed because the name of Kaguyahime written in Chinese characters (赫夜姫) can also be read as &apos;Toyohime.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the main character Princess Kaguya, people made various suppositions; for example, a relationship with Emperor Suinin&apos;s consort Kaguyahime (a daughter of Otsuki no Miko (King Otsuki Tarine)), and a relationship with Toyouke Taijin (Grand Divine Toyouke) was discussed because the name of Kaguyahime written in Chinese characters (赫夜姫) can also be read as &apos;Toyohime.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>由来の地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A place in connection with the tale</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Places in connection with the tale</e>
<cmt>&quot;A place&quot;-&quot;places&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Places in connection with the tale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>竹取の翁は、物語の中でかつては「さぬきの造（みやつこ）」と呼ばれていたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taketori no Okina was once called &apos;Sanuki no Miyatsuko&apos; in the tale.</e>
<cmt>「さぬきの造（みやつこ）」→&quot;Chie of Sanuki&quot;とterms欄にありましたが(ChieはChiefのこと？）、「造」はスーパー大辞林に、「古代の姓の一。渡来系技術者集団の統率者をはじめとする伴造（とものみやつこ）系の氏族に与えられた。そのうちの有力氏族の多くは天武朝に連（むらじ）に改姓された。」とあるので、単なる名前としてローマ字表記にとどめました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taketori no Okina was once called &apos;Sanuki no Miyatsuko&apos; in the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taketori no Okina was once called &apos;Sanuki no Miyatsuko&apos; in the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>ここから、物語においては大和国広瀬郡散吉（さぬき）郷（現奈良県北葛城郡広陵町）に竹取の翁が居住していた、とするのが通説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, it is commonly considered that Taketori no Okina lived in Sanuki Village, Hirose District, Yamato Province (the present Koryo-Cho, Kita katsuragi District, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, it is commonly considered that Taketori no Okina lived in Sanuki Village, Hirose District, Yamato Province (the present Koryo-Cho, Kita katsuragi District, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, it is commonly considered that Taketori no Okina lived in Sanuki Village, Hirose District, Yamato Province (the present Koryo-cho, Kita katsuragi-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>ほかにも日本各地に竹取物語由来の地と名乗る地域があり、竹取物語（かぐや姫）をテーマにしたまちづくりを行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than this, there are some areas which people consider to be a place in connection with Taketori Monogatari, designing a town using a theme of Taketori Monogatari (Princess Kaguya).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than this, there are some areas which people consider to be a place in connection with Taketori Monogatari, designing a town using a theme of Taketori Monogatari (Princess Kaguya).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than this, there are some areas which people consider to be a place in connection with Taketori Monogatari, designing a town using a theme of Taketori Monogatari (Princess Kaguya).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また以下の7市町では「かぐや姫サミット」という地域間交流が定期的に開催されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the following seven cities and towns, &apos;Princess Kaguya Summit &apos; is regularly held for promoting local interaction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the following seven cities and towns, &apos;Princess Kaguya Summit &apos; is regularly held for promoting local interaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the following seven cities and towns, &apos;Princess Kaguya Summit &apos; is regularly held for promoting local interaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>静岡県富士市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>奈良県広陵町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koryo-cho, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>訳補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>京都府向日市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muko City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muko City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muko City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>香川県長尾町 (香川県)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagao-cho, Kagawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagao-cho, Kagawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagao-cho, Kagawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>岡山県真備町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mabi-cho, Okayama Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mabi-cho, Okayama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mabi-cho, Okayama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>広島県竹原市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takehara City, Hiroshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takehara City, Hiroshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takehara City, Hiroshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>鹿児島県宮之城町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyanojo-cho, Kagaoshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyanojo-cho, Kagaoshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyanojo-cho, Kagoshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shinsk330(id:41138), Nnh(id:474), わかみん(id:16858), 経済準学士(id:22656), Kstigarbha(id:13376), D.h(id:79056), 海那(id:69795), Sutou(id:32), Tarosan(id:330), Spyle135(id:48034), Mytho88(id:57385), 高木あゆみ(id:6492), Masyu(id:31065), Textex(id:27452), Fxcxt(id:21803), Tsk(id:1153), さららゆら(id:12274), ハエ叩きと虱潰し(id:135640), Mocchy(id:146197), Tenmams(id:72762), SRIA(id:56609), 影武者(id:87561), Staka(id:74758), Takeshick(id:35943), Arria Belli(id:133170), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), Avxz(id:123412), 竹麦魚(id:11012), びーろんぐ(id:131462), Kzhr(id:131), 捕澤(id:23785), RiotVan(id:84545), Izayohi(id:13095), なおぞー(id:80442), 恵比須(id:25433), Angelus(id:42142), 松茸(id:27535), 円口類(id:186088), 逃亡者(id:14864), Hagaren(id:161278), Kaznov17(id:68122), 榎(id:91458), 暫し佇み(id:65239), Wind of tukishiro(id:10247), Shota(id:10854), Kamitani(id:30757), Miketukunibito(id:9680), Lanceraaaa(id:148554), クロサキ(id:169477), FeZn(id:444), Miya(id:1881), R28Bot(id:177951), Little tree(id:43251), レイザン(id:143588), Chatama(id:16156), ZARK(id:98404), Suisui(id:69), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>