<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>保暦間記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horyakukanki (A History Book of the 14 century in Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horyakukanki (A History Book of the 14 century in Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horyakukanki (A History Book of the 14 century in Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『保暦間記』（ほうりゃくかんき）は日本の中世、南北朝時代 (日本)に成立した歴史書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Horyakukanki &quot; is a history book which was completed during the Japanese middle ages, the Northern and Southern Dynasties period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Horyakukanki&quot; is a history book which was completed during the Japanese middle ages, the Northern and Southern Dynasties period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Horyakukanki&quot;内にあったスペースを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Horyakukanki&quot; is a history book which was completed during the Japanese middle ages, the Northern and Southern Dynasties period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉時代後半から南北朝時代前期を研究する上での基本史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a fundamental historical material to study the ages from the latter half of the Kamakura period to the first half of the Northern and Southern Dynasties period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a fundamental historical material to study the ages from the late Kamakura period to the early Northern and Southern Dynasties period.</e>
<cmt>the latter half of the Kamakura period →the late Kamakura period　the first half of the→the early 用語に則して変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a fundamental historical material to study the ages from the late Kamakura period to the early Northern and Southern Court period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>成立は14世紀半ば、延文元年（1356年）以前。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in the mid-14th century, or before 1356.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in the mid-14th century, before 1356.</e>
<cmt>orを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in the mid-14th century, before 1356.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>作者は不明であるが、南北朝時代の足利方の武士と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author is unknown, but it is conjectured that the book was written by a warrior who was in Ashikaga side during the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author is unknown, but it is conjectured that the book was written by a warrior who was in Ashikaga side during the Northern and Southern Dynasties period.</e>
<cmt>the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.→the Northern and Southern Dynasties period　上で使用されている文章と単語を一致させるため、変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author is unknown, but it is conjectured that the book was written by a warrior who was in Ashikaga side during the Northern and Southern Court period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『群書類従』第26輯雑部所収。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was collected in the miscellaneous part of the 26th volume of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; (Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was collected in the miscellaneous part of the 26th volume of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; (Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was collected in the miscellaneous part of the 26th volume of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; (Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱に始まり、暦応2年（1339年）後醍醐天皇崩御までを記述し、これが書名の由来となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book covers the incidents from the Hogen Disturbance in 1156 to the demise of Emperor Godaigo in 1339, which became the origin of the title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book covers the incidents from the Hogen Disturbance in 1156 to the demise of Emperor Godaigo in 1339, which became the origin of the title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book covers the incidents from the Hogen Disturbance in 1156 to the demise of Emperor Godaigo in 1339, which became the origin of the title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『吾妻鏡』の記載が終了する文永3年（1266年）以降の鎌倉時代に起こった事件の概要を研究するうえで貴重な史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an important historical material to study an outline of the incidents occurring during the Kamakura period, especially after 1266, when the description of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) ended.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an important historical material to study an outline of the incidents occurred during the Kamakura period, especially after 1266, when the description of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) ended.</e>
<cmt>occurring→occurredに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an important historical material to study an outline of the incidents occurred during the Kamakura period, especially after 1266, when the description of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「和田合戦」、「承久の乱」、「宝治合戦」、「二月騒動」、「霜月騒動」など、現在使用されている鎌倉時代の事件名称の多くは本書の記述に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names of incidents which took place during the Kamakura period such as &apos;Battle of Wada,&apos; &apos;Jokyu War,&apos; &apos;Battle of Hoji,&apos; &apos;February Riot,&apos; &apos;Shimotsuki Incident,&apos; etc. are used widely today, and most of them came from the descriptions in this book.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names of incidents which occurred during the Kamakura period such as &apos;Battle of Wada,&apos; &apos;Jokyu War,&apos; &apos;Battle of Hoji,&apos; &apos;February Riot,&apos; &apos;Shimotsuki Incident,&apos; etc. are used widely today, and most of them are derived from the descriptions in this book.</e>
<cmt>took place→occurred に変更come from→are derived from に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of incidents which occurred during the Kamakura period such as &apos;Battle of Wada,&apos; &apos;Jokyu War,&apos; &apos;Battle of Hoji,&apos; &apos;February Riot,&apos; &apos;Shimotsuki Incident,&apos; etc. are used widely today, and most of them are derived from the descriptions in this book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>源頼朝の死について、建久10年（1199年）に、相模川橋供養の帰路、八的ヶ原（現在の辻堂および茅ヶ崎の広域名）で源義経らの亡霊を、稲村ヶ崎海上に安徳天皇の亡霊を見て、鎌倉で気を失い病に倒れたと記しているが、実際の死因については諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various opinions about the actual reason of the death of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, but according to this book, it was because he saw a ghost of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune at Yamatogahara (the present Tsujido and wide area of Chigasaki) on his way back from Buddhist ceremony for bridging Sagami-gawa River, and also saw a ghost of Emperor Antoku in the sea of Inamuragasaki, then he fainted and was struck down by a illness at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various opinions about the actual reason of the death of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, however, according to this book, it was because he saw a ghost of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune at Yamatogahara (the present Tsujido and wide area of Chigasaki) on his way back from Buddhist ceremony for bridging Sagami-gawa River, and also saw a ghost of Emperor Antoku on the sea of Inamuragasaki, then he fainted and was struck down by a illness at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>butは口語的なのでhoweverに変更in the sea→on the seaに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various opinions about the actual reason of the death of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, however, according to this book, it was because he saw a ghost of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune at Yamatogahara (the present Tsujido and wide area of Chigasaki) on his way back from Buddhist ceremony for bridging Sagami-gawa River, and also saw a ghost of Emperor Antoku on the sea of Inamuragasaki, then he fainted and was struck down by a illness at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Web.dweller(id:153933), Ktmchi(id:113301), 月下薄氷(id:47743), 星組背番号10(id:19983), Naigai(id:288953), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>