<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>兵部卿宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyobukyo no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyobukyo no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyobukyo no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>兵部卿宮（ひょうぶきょうのみや）は、物語に登場する、本名のわからない架空の皇子の便宜上の名称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyobukyo no Miya is a name for convenience to call a fictitious Imperial prince whose real name is unknown in a tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyobukyo no Miya is a name for a fictitious Imperial prince, for convenience, whose real name is unknown in the tale.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyobukyo no Miya is a name for a fictitious Imperial prince, for convenience, whose real name is unknown in the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>代表的な例として、『源氏物語』に登場する親王が3人いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative examples are three Imperial Princes appearing in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example there are three Imperial Princes appearing in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example there are three Imperial Princes appearing in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>先帝の皇子、藤壺の兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An Imperial prince of the late Emperor, an older brother of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first being an Imperial prince of the late Emperor, and an older brother of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first being an Imperial Prince of the late Emperor, and an older brother of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt>prince→Prince</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>紫の上の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The father of Murasaki no ue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the father of Murasaki no ue.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the father of Murasaki no ue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後述。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This will be discussed in detail below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This will be discussed in detail below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This will be discussed in detail below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>桐壺帝の皇子、光源氏の異母弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince of Emperor Kiritsubo, Hikaru Genji&apos;s younger paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second is the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kiritsubo, Hikaru Genji&apos;s younger paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second is the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kiritsubo, Hikaru Genji&apos;s younger paternal half-brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>蛍兵部卿宮を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>今上帝の第三皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third prince of Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt>（源氏物語）はリンク先の語のため、訳出しませんでした。以下、同様です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lastly, there is the third prince of Kinjo no Mikado.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lastly, there is the third prince of Emperor Kinjo.</e>
<cmt>Kinjo no mikado→Emperor Kinjo原文の（源氏物語）も削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>匂宮を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>兵部卿宮（ひょうぶきょうのみや）は、紫式部が著した小説『源氏物語』に登場する架空の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyobukyo no Miya is a fictitious character who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; which was written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyobukyo no Miya is a fictitious character who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; which was written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyobukyo no Miya is a fictitious character who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; which was written by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（後に朝顔の父・桃園式部卿宮死去をうけて式部卿宮となる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(After the death of Prince Momozono, the father of Asagao, he came to be known as Shikibukyo no Miya)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(After the death of Prince Momozono, the father of Asagao, he came to be known as Shikibukyo no Miya)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(After the death of Prince Momozono, the father of Asagao, he became Shikibukyo no Miya)</e>
<cmt>原文の（源氏物語）も削除came to be known as→became</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>先帝の皇子であり、藤壺の兄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of the former Emperor, and also an older brother of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of the former Emperor, and also an older brother of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of the former Emperor, and also an older brother of Fujitsubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>高貴な出自の北の方との間に二人の娘があり、恐らく同腹と思われる息子も四人いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had two daughters by his lawful wife, who was from a noble family, and seems to have had four sons by the same mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had two daughters by his lawful wife, who was from a noble family, and seems to have had four sons by the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had two daughters by his lawful wife, who was from a noble family, and seems to have had four sons by the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この他、側室（按察大納言の娘）との間に一女（のちの紫の上）をもうけたが、北の方がこれを憎んだため、側室が亡くなった後も滅多に訪れなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to them, he had a daughter (later known as Murasaki no ue) by his concubine (the daughter of Azechi no Dainagon), but his lawful wife hated it, so he rarely visited her even after the concubine died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to them, he had a daughter (later known as Murasaki no ue) by his concubine (the daughter of Azechi no Dainagon), but his lawful wife hated her, so he rarely visited her even after the concubine died.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to them, he had a daughter (later known as Murasaki no ue) by his concubine (the daughter of Azechi no Dainagon), but his lawful wife hated her, so he rarely visited her even after the concubine died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そのため娘を光源氏に略奪され、後に妻となったことを知らされてから音信を復活する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore after his daughter was taken by Hikaru Genji and then later he was let to know that she became his wife, he began to contact her again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during Genji&apos;s dark days, he even deserted Murasaki no ue, though he was Genji&apos;s biological father, and it earned Genji&apos;s displeasure, so he was treated coolly after Genji&apos;s return.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during Genji&apos;s dark days, he even deserted Murasaki no ue, though he was Genji&apos;s biological father, and it earned Genji&apos;s displeasure, so he was treated coolly after Genji&apos;s return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし源氏の失意時代には権力者を憚って、実父でありながら紫の上をも見捨てて源氏の不興を買い、源氏の復帰後は逆に冷たくあしらわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during Genji&apos;s dark days, he even deserted Murasaki no ue, though he was Genji&apos;s biological father, and it earned Genji&apos;s displeasure, so he was treated coolly after Genji&apos;s return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during Genji&apos;s dark days, by deserting Murasaki no ue, despite being her biological father, Hyobukyo no miya earned Genji&apos;s displeasure, and so was treated coolly after Genji&apos;s return.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand how &quot;Genji&apos;s biological father&quot; is related to this sentence. I believe the original Japanese is referring to Murasaki no ue&apos;s biological father, who abandoned her.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during Genji&apos;s dark days, by deserting Murasaki no ue, despite being her biological father, Hyobukyo no miya earned Genji&apos;s displeasure, and so was treated coolly after Genji&apos;s return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>藤壺中宮の兄、冷泉帝の外戚として、源氏や太政大臣（頭中将）に次ぐ声望があるとされ、世間からも重く扱われた（「若菜下」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was treated seriously as the older brother of Empress Fujitsubo and a maternal relative of Emperor Reizei, considered that he had a reputation after Genji and Dajodaijin (Grand minister of state) (Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was treated seriously as the older brother of Empress Fujitsubo and a maternal relative of Emperor Reizei, and considered to have a reputation second to Genji and Dajodaijin (Grand minister of the state) (Tono Chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain)).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was treated seriously as the older brother of Empress Fujitsubo and a maternal relative of Emperor Reizei, and considered to have a reputation second to Genji and Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) (Tono Chujo [the first secretary&apos;s captain]).</e>
<cmt>太政大臣の定訳括弧内の括弧を[]に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし北の方腹の次女（王女御）は冷泉帝の後宮に入内したものの、源氏の協力を得られなかったこともあって立后できずに終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the second daughter (O nyogo) of the lawful wife entered kokyu (Empress&apos;s residence), she could not get Genji&apos;s support and ended without becoming the Empress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the second daughter (O nyogo) of his lawful wife entered kokyu (Empress&apos;s residence), she could not attain Genji&apos;s support and her life ended without her becoming the Empress.</e>
<cmt>Unclear in what capacity she &quot;ended&quot;. I assume it refers to the end of her life.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the second daughter (O nyogo) of his lawful wife entered kokyu (Empress&apos;s residence), she could not attain Genji&apos;s support and her life ended without her becoming the Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また同腹の長女（髭黒の北の方）も、夫を源氏の養女である玉鬘に奪われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest daughter (lawful wife of Higekuro) by the same mother also had her husband taken away by Tamakazura, an adopted daughter of Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His oldest daughter (the lawful wife of Higekuro) by the same mother also had her husband taken away by Tamakazura, an adopted daughter of Genji.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His oldest daughter (the lawful wife of Higekuro) by the same mother also had her husband taken away by Tamakazura, an adopted daughter of Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらに長女と共に引き取った孫の真木柱も、のち蛍兵部卿宮と結婚したもののうまくいかないなど、家庭は不幸であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he took in his grandchild, Makibashira, together with his eldest daughter, and later she got married to Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya, but they did not get along, so the family was unhappy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he took in his grandchild, Makibashira, together with his eldest daughter, who later married Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya, unfortunately, they did not get along and so the family was unhappy.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he took in his grandchild, Makibashira, together with his eldest daughter, who later married Hotaru Hyobukyo no Miya; unfortunately, they did not get along and so the family was unhappy.</e>
<cmt>unfortunately の前のMiyaの後ろに;を付けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 夏の雪雲(id:188722), 松茸(id:27535), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>