<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>猪苗代兼載</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kensai INAWASHIRO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kensai INAWASHIRO</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kensai INAWASHIRO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>猪苗代 兼載（いなわしろ けんさい、享徳元年（1452年） - 永正7年6月6日 (旧暦)（1510年7月11日））は、戦国時代 (日本)の連歌師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kensai INAWASHIRO (1452 - July 11, 1510) was a renga poet (linked-verse poet) in the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kensai INAWASHIRO (1452 - July 11, 1510) was a renga poet (linked-verse poet) in the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kensai INAWASHIRO (1452 - July 21, 1510) was a renga poet (linked-verse poet) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>戦国時代　の表現を修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>初め興俊・宗春と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He initially called himself Koshun/Soshun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He initially called himself Koshun/Soshun.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He initially called himself Koshun/Soshun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>別号は相園坊・耕閑軒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His another names were Soenbo and Kokanken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His other names were Soenbo and Kokanken.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His other names were Soenbo and Kokanken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法橋に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was conferred Hokyo (the third highest rank of Buddhist monk).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was conferred Hokyo (the third highest rank of Buddhist monk).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred Hokyo (the third highest rank of Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>monk→ priest としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>陸奥国（後の岩代国）会津の猪苗代城主の家に生れたが、早い時期に出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born to the family of the lord of Inawashiro castle in Mutsu Province (later became Iwashiro Province) Aizu and became a monk in his childhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born to the family of the lord of Inawashiro castle in Mutsu Province (later became Iwashiro Province) Aizu and became a monk in his childhood.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born to the family of the lord of Inawashiro-jo Castle in Mutsu Province (later became Iwashiro Province) in Aizu and became a priest in his childhood.</e>
<cmt>monk→ priest としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>19歳のとき「河越千句」に参加し心敬の教えを受け、飯尾宗祇とも交流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was 19 years old, he participated in &quot;Kawagoe senku&quot; (event of renga held at Kawagoe castle), learn from Shinkei and became acquainted with Sogi IIo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was 19 years old, he participated in &quot;Kawagoe senku&quot; (event of renga held at Kawagoe castle), learned from Shinkei and became acquainted with Sogi IIo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was 19 years old, he participated in &apos;Kawagoe senku&apos; (event of renga held at Kawagoe-jo Castle), learned from Shinkei and became acquainted with Sogi IO.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>連歌界での活躍は目覚しく、38歳で北野連歌会所奉行及び師匠となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His activities in the renga society was remarkable and he became the manager cum instructor of Kitano Renga-kaisho (place of a gathering of renga poets) at the age of 38.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His activities in the renga society was remarkable and he became the manager and instructor of Kitano Renga-kaisho (place of a gathering of renga poets) at the age of 38.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His activities in the renga society was remarkable and he became the manager and instructor of Kitano Renga-kaisho (place of a gathering of renga poets) at the age of 38.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>周防国山口の大内政弘の後援を得て、飯尾宗祇の「新撰菟玖波集」の編纂にも参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the support of Masahiro Ouchi of Suo Province Yamaguchi, he also participated in the compilation work of &quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu&quot; (New Collection of Renga Poems of Tsukuba) led by Sogi IIo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the support of Masahiro Ouchi of Suo Province, Yamaguchi, he also participated in the compilation work of &quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu&quot; (New Collection of Renga Poems of Tsukuba) led by Sogi IIo.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the support of Masahiro Ouchi of Suo Province, Yamaguchi, he also participated in the compilation work of &apos;Shinsen Tsukubashu&apos; (New Collection of Renga Poems of Tsukuba) led by Sogi IO.</e>
<cmt>Soi IO としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>50歳のとき関東に下り、各地を巡り、下総国古河で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Kanto region when he was 50, visited various places and died in Koga of Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to the Kanto region when he was 50, visited various places, and died in Koga of Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to the Kanto region when he was 50, visited various places, and died in Koga of Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt>Shimosa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、和歌を二条派の尭恵に学んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, he learned waka poem from Gyoe of Nijo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, he learned waka poem from the Gyoe of Nijo school.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, he learned waka poem from Gyoe of Nijo school.</e>
<cmt>the を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>飯尾宗祇とともに連歌の最盛期を作り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with Sogi IIO, he built up the golden age of renga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with Sogi IIO, he built up the golden age of renga.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with Sogi IO, he built up the golden age of renga.</e>
<cmt>Soi IO としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>句集に「園塵」、連歌論書に「心敬僧都庭訓」「梅薫抄」「兼載雑談」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Enjin&quot; was his personal collection of renga, and &quot;Shinkei sozu teikun&quot;, &quot;Baikunsho&quot; and &quot;Kensaizotan&quot; were his thorey book of renga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Enjin&quot; was his personal collection of renga and &quot;Shinkei sozu teikun,&quot; &quot;Baikunsho,&quot; and &quot;Kensaizotan&quot; were his theory books on renga.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Flow, Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He compiled &apos;Enjin&apos; which is his personal collection of renga, and &apos;Shinkei sozu teikun,&apos; &apos;Baikunsho,&apos; and &apos;Kensaizotan&apos; which were his theory books on renga.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Desumo(id:90943), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 電田蒸(id:249216), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>