<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山部赤人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YAMABE no Akahito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YAMABE no Akahito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YAMABE no Akahito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山部 赤人（やまべ の あかひと、生没年不詳）は、奈良時代の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YAMABE no AKAHITO (dates of birth and death unknown) was a poet who lived during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YAMABE no AKAHITO (dates of birth and death unknown) was a poet who lived during the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YAMABE no AKAHITO (dates of birth and death unknown) was a poet who lived during the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the Sanjurokkasen (Thirty-six poets chosen by FUJIWARA no Kinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the Sanjurokkasen (thirty-six poets chosen by FUJIWARA no Kinto).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the Sanjurokkasen (thirty-six poets chosen by FUJIWARA no Kinto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>姓は宿禰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was Sukune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kabane (hereditary title) was Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>山部足島の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A son of YAMABE no Ashijima.</e>
<cmt>山部足島の正しい読み方不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of YAMABE no Ashijima.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of YAMABE no Ashijima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>官職は上総国国司。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His government post was Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His government post was Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His government post was Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後世、山邊（辺）赤人と表記されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years, his name was sometimes written like this: 山邊(辺)赤人.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記が問題になっているため、訳文中にも漢字を使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, his name was sometimes written as 山邊(辺)赤人.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, his name was sometimes written as 山邊(辺)赤人.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>『古今和歌集』の仮名序において、柿本人麻呂とともに歌聖と呼ばれ称えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kanajo (a preface written in kana) for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), he was praised as Kasei (a great poet) together with KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the kanajo (a preface written in kana) for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), he was feted as a kasei (great poet) together with KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the kanajo (a preface written in kana) for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), he was feted as a kasei (great poet) together with KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この人麻呂との対は、『万葉集』の大伴家持の漢文に、「山柿の門」（山部の「山」と柿本の「柿」）とあるのを初見とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two great people were first mentioned in the writing written by OTOMO no Yakamochi in Chinese, which was collected in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves): &apos;A school of 山柿&apos; (&apos;山&apos; means Yamabe, and &apos;柿&apos; means Kakinomoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two great people were first mentioned in a work by OTOMO no Yakamochi, written in Chinese, which was collected in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) as &apos;A school of 山柿&apos; (&apos;山&apos; means Yamabe, and &apos;柿&apos; means Kakinomoto).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two great people were first mentioned in a work by OTOMO no Yakamochi, written in Chinese, which was collected in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) as &apos;A school of 山柿&apos; (&apos;山&apos; means Yamabe, and &apos;柿&apos; means Kakinomoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>その経歴は定かではないが、『続日本紀』などの史書に名前が見えないことから、下級官人であったと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His detailed career was not known, but it is conjectured that he would have been a lower-ranking government official because his name was not mentioned in history books such as &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details of his life are unknown, but it is thought that he was a lower-ranking government official as his name does not appear in history books such as &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details of his life are unknown, but it is thought that he was a lower-ranking government official as his name does not appear in history books such as &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>神亀・天平の両時代にのみ作品が残され、行幸などにしたがっての天皇讃歌の多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote poems only in the Jinki and Tenpyo eras, and composed many poems in praise of the Emperor when he followed an Imperial visit.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poems remain from only the Jinki and Tenpyo eras, and he composed many poems in praise of the Emperor during imperial visits.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poems remain from only the Jinki and Tenpyo eras, and he composed many poems in praise of the Emperor during imperial visits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのことから、聖武天皇時代の宮廷歌人だったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why it is assumed that he was a court poet who lived during the reign of Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason it is assumed that he was a court poet who lived during the reign of Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason it is assumed that he was a court poet who lived during the reign of Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>作られた和歌から諸国を旅したとも推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from his waka poems, he seems to have traveled various provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from his waka poems, he seems to have traveled to various provinces.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from his waka poems, he seems to have traveled to various provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同時代の歌人には憶良や大伴旅人がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His contemporary poets were Okura and OTOMO no Tabito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okura and OTOMO no Tabito were his contemporaries.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okura and OTOMO no Tabito were his contemporaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『万葉集』には長歌13首、短歌37首が掲載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">13 choka (long poem) and 37 tanka (short poem of 31 syllables) composed by him were collected in &quot;Manyoshu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Manyoshu&quot; contains 13 of his choka (long poems) and 37 tanka (short poems of 31 syllables).</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Manyoshu&quot; contains 13 of his choka (long poems) and 37 tanka (short poems of 31 syllables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>自然の美しさや清さを詠んだ叙景歌に定評がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a reputation for descriptive poetry dealing with the beauty cleanliness of nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a reputation for descriptive poetry dealing with the beauty and cleanliness of nature.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a reputation for descriptive poetry dealing with the beauty and cleanliness of nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>平安時代中期（『拾遺和歌集』頃とされる）には名声の高まりに合わせて、私家集の『赤人集』（三十六人集のひとつ）も編まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the mid-Heian period (around the time when &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) was compiled), his private poetry collection, &quot;Akahito shu,&quot; (one of the Sanjurokunin shu (Collected Poems of Thirty-six Poets)) was made as his reputation grew.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the middle of the Heian Period, around the time when &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) was compiled, his private poetry collection, &quot;Akahito shu&quot;, (one of the Sanjurokunin shu, or Collected Poems of Thirty-six Poets) was written as his reputation grew.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the middle of the Heian Period, around the time when &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) was compiled, his private poetry collection, &quot;Akahito shu,&quot; (one of the Sanjurokunin shu, or Collected Poems of Thirty-six Poets) was written as his reputation grew.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは万葉集の巻11の歌などを集めたもので、『人麻呂集』や『家持集』とおなじく万葉の赤人の作はほとんど含んでいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a collection which contained some poems in the 11th volume of Manyoshu, but as well as &quot;Hitomaroshu&quot; (the collection of KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro) and &quot;Yakamochishu&quot; (the Collected Works of OTOMO no Yakamochi), it hardly included works by Akahito of the Manyo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a collection which contained some poems from the 11th volume of Manyoshu, but as with &quot;Hitomaroshu&quot; (the collection of KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro) and &quot;Yakamochishu&quot; (the Collected Works of OTOMO no Yakamochi), it hardly included any works by Akahito of the Manyo period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a collection which contained some poems from the 11th volume of Manyoshu, but as with &quot;Hitomaroshu&quot; (the collection of KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro) and &quot;Yakamochishu&quot; (the Collected Works of OTOMO no Yakamochi), it hardly included any works by Akahito of the Manyo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>『後撰和歌集』まではあまり採られることのなかった人麻呂ら万葉歌人の作が、『拾遺集』になって急増するので、関連が考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poems by Manyo poets such as Hitomaro had not been selected until &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry), but in the period of &quot;Shuishu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) their poems came to be included suddenly, so it is considered that there was a relevance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poems by Manyo poets such as Hitomaro were not included until &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry), but in the period of &quot;Shuishu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) the number of poems suddenly increased, and this is considered relevant.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poems by Manyo poets such as Hitomaro were not included until &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry), but in the period of &quot;Shuishu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) the number of poems suddenly increased, and this is considered relevant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>赤人の作として、もっともよく知られているのは百人一首におさめられた、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The best known poem by Akahito seems to be the one collected in Hyakunin Isshu (one hundred waka poems by one hundred poets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The best known poem by Akahito seems to be that which appears in the Hyakunin Isshu (a collection of one hundred waka poems by one hundred poets).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The best known poem by Akahito seems to be that which appears in the Hyakunin Isshu (a collection of one hundred waka poems by one hundred poets).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>田子の浦にうち出でてみれば白妙の富士の高嶺に雪は降りつつ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tago no ura ni uchi idete mireba shirotae no fuji no takane ni fuki ha furi tsutsu (When I am walking along the Tago coast, I can see the snow falling on the lofty peak of Mt. Fuji).</e>
<cmt>詩の内容は下の万葉歌と同じですが、言葉遣いが異なるため、ローマ字表記も載せました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tago no ura ni uchi idete mireba shirotae no fuji no takane ni fuki ha furi tsutsu (When I am walking along the Tago coast, I can see the snow falling on the lofty peak of Mt. Fuji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tago no ura ni uchi idete mireba shirotae no fuji no takane ni yuki ha furi tsutsu (When I am walking along the Tago coast, I can see the snow falling on the lofty peak of Mt. Fuji).</e>
<cmt>fuki→yuki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>であると思われるが、これは万葉歌を改作したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is a revised version of the Manyo poem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is a revised version of a Manyo poem.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is a revised version of a Manyo poem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>万葉集には、田子の浦ゆうち出でてみれば真白にそ富士の高嶺に雪は降りける、とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Manyoshu, the poem was Tago no ura yu uchi idete mireba mashiro ni so fuji no takane ni yuki ha furi keru.</e>
<cmt>３つに分かれていたのを統合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Manyoshu, the poem was &apos;Tago no ura yu uchi idete mireba mashiro ni so fuji no takane ni yuki ha furi keru&apos; which is similar in meaning.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Manyoshu, the poem was &apos;Tago no ura yu uchi idete mireba mashiro ni so fuji no takane ni yuki ha furi keru&apos; which is similar in meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), さららゆら(id:12274), 翠碧晶(id:68524), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Pitan(id:171), TY(id:1386), Loveless(id:129239), Zerozeros(id:189962), Point136(id:211299), Rai koku(id:1661), 味っ子(id:17086), Avxz(id:123412), Aphaia(id:3132), Snap55(id:89773), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>