<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>和泉式部日記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumi Shikibu Nikki (Diary of Izumi Shikibu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumi Shikibu Nikki (Diary of Izumi Shikibu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumi Shikibu Nikki (Diary of Izumi Shikibu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>和泉式部日記（いずみしきぶにっき）は和泉式部によって記された日記であり、女流日記文学の代表的作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Izumi Shikibu Nikki is a diary written by Izumi Shikibu, and this is a notable example of women&apos;s diary literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Izumi Shikibu Nikki is a diary written by Izumi Shikibu, and is a notable example of women&apos;s literature in diaries.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Izumi Shikibu Nikki&quot; is a diary written by Izumi Shikibu, and is a notable example of women&apos;s literature in diaries.</e>
<cmt>The Izumi Shikibu Nikki にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>中古三十六歌仙の一人、小倉百人一首にもその歌が収められている、平安時代を代表する歌人である和泉式部にふさわしく、日記のなかに和歌の贈答の場面が頻出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumi Shikibu, whose poem is included in the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets, is one of the Medieval Thirty Six Immortal Poets (the thirty-six major poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane in the middle of the Heian period), and her diary includes many poet exchange scenes, reflecting her talent as one of the greatest poets of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumi Shikibu, whose poem is included in the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets, is one of the Medieval Thirty Six Immortal Poets (the thirty-six major poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane in the middle of the Heian period), and her diary includes many correspondence of waka (Japanese poems), reflecting her talent as one of the greatest poets of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumi Shikibu, whose poem is included in the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets, is one of the Medieval Thirty Six Immortal Poets (the thirty-six major poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane in the middle of the Heian period), and her diary includes many correspondence of waka (traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables), reflecting her talent as one of the greatest poets of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語集の表記に従い、(Japanese poems) を(traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この作品を大きく特徴付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That gives this work very unique characteristics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the unique characteristics of her literary work.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The many correspondence of waka is one of the unique characteristics of this work.</e>
<cmt>This is one of the unique characteristics of her literary work をThe many correspondence of waka is one of the unique characteristics of this work.に修正しました（※）。※trans2 の訳では「この作品」という主語が「彼女の作品」に変わっていますが、前述の特徴は「和泉式部日記」の特徴であって、「彼女の作品」の特徴ではありません。前述の文章が長いことから、主部を再度補足した上で上記のとおり修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>作者は和泉式部の本人自筆の作品とされることもあるものの、かつては『和泉式部物語』とも呼ばれたこともあり、また主人公であり筆者であるはずの和泉式部本人を「女」という三人称的呼称で扱っていることから別に作者がいるのではないか、との意見もある(この説に従うなら和泉式部の恋愛に仮託した日記風歌物語、ということになる)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people believe this work was written by Izumi Shikibu herself, but some other people think another writer made this work because this work was once called &quot;Izumi Shikibu Monogatari&quot; (the Story of Izumi Shikibu), and Izumi Shikibu, who is regarded as the author and the heroine of the story, is treated as a third person and referred to as &apos;she&apos; in the diary (according to this opinion, this work is a diary-style fiction under the guise of her romance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although most believe this work to be written by Izumi Shikibu herself, there are others who think a different author may have created this work due to the fact that this work was once called &quot;Izumi Shikibu Monogatari&quot; (the Story of Izumi Shikibu), and that Izumi Shikibu is treated as a third person and referred to as the &quot;lady&quot; when it is herself that is the main character and she herself is the author (according to this argument, this work is a diary-style fiction under the guise of her romantic episodes).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although most believe this work to be written by Izumi Shikibu herself, there are others who think a different author may have created this work due to the fact that this work was once called &quot;Izumi Shikibu Monogatari&quot; (the Story of Izumi Shikibu), and that Izumi Shikibu is treated as a third person and referred to as the &apos;lady&apos; when it is herself that is the main character and she herself is the author (according to this argument, this work is a diary-style fiction under the guise of her romantic episodes).</e>
<cmt>&quot;lady&quot; を &apos;lady&apos; に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>一巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This work consists of one volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This work consists of one volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This work consists of one volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>敦道親王が亡くなった後の、喪に服している一年の間（寛弘5年、1008年）に書かれたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this work was written in 1008, during the one-year mourning period for Imperial Prince Atsumichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that this work was written in 1008, during the one-year mourning period for Imperial Prince Atsumichi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that this work was written in 1008, during the one-year mourning period for Imperial Prince Atsumichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>内容構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長保5年（1003年）4月〜寛弘元年（1004年）1月までの数ヶ月間の出来事をつづる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story is about happenings during several months between May 1003 and January 1004.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story takes place during the several months between May 1003 and January 1004.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story takes place during the several months between May 1003 and January 1004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>恋人冷泉天皇第三皇子弾正宮為尊親王が前年長保4年に薨じ、また為尊親王との恋のため父親にも勘当され、さらに夫橘道貞との関係も冷めたものとなって嘆きつつ追憶の日々を過ごしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumi Shikibu was spending sad days just being immersed in reminiscences as she had been disowned by her father and treated coldly by her husband TACHIBANA no Michisada due to the romance with her lover Imperial Prince Tametaka of Danjo (the third prince of Emperor Reizei), who had passed away in 1002.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処宮号がついた場合の皇族の英語表記については、宮内庁ウェブサイトの方式に従いました。参考：http://www.kunaicho.go.jp/e-about/activity/activity.html　など</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a time when Izumi Shikibu was grieving over the death of her lover, Imperial Prince Tametaka of Danjo (the Third Prince of Emperor Reizei), who had passed away in 1002, the disownment by her father, and the cold relationship between her husband TACHIBANA no Michisada.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a time when Izumi Shikibu was grieving over the death of her lover, Imperial Prince Tametaka of Danjo (the Third Prince of Emperor Reizei), who had passed away in 1002, the disownment by her father, and the cold relationship between her husband TACHIBANA no Michisada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>和泉式部のもとに、為尊親王の弟冷泉天皇第四皇子帥宮敦道親王の消息の便りが届く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day Izumi Shikibu heard about Imperial Prince Atsumichi of Sochi, who was a younger brother of Imperial Prince Tametaka and the fourth prince of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, Izumi Shikibu learns about Imperial Prince Atsumichi of Sochi, who was a younger brother of Imperial Prince Tametaka and the Fourth Prince of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, Izumi Shikibu hears from Imperial Prince Atsumichi of Sochi, who was a younger brother of Imperial Prince Tametaka and the Fourth Prince of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>learns about を hears from に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後帥宮と和歌や手紙などを取り交わし、また数度の訪問を受けるうちにお互いを深く愛する関係となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, she began to exchange poems and letters with Prince Sochi, and they fell in love after he visited her several times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She begins to correspond with Prince Sochi through waka and letters, and meets him during his occasional visits, and before long, they fall deep in love with each other.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She begins to correspond with Prince Sochi through waka and letters, and meets him during his occasional visits, and before long, they fall deep in love with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>最終的に和泉式部は帥宮邸に迎えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumi Shikibu was finally allowed to move to the Sochi residence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Izumi Shikibu is welcomed into the Sochi residence.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Izumi Shikibu is welcomed into the Sochi residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この間の和歌の取り交わしと、この恋愛に関する和泉式部のありのままの心情描写が本作品の大きな特色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This work features the exchanges of poems and the description of Izumi Shikibu&apos;s honest feelings about this love.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristic features of this work are the exchanges of waka and the expression of Izumi Shikibu&apos;s honest feelings toward her lover.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristic features of this work are the exchanges of waka and the expression of Izumi Shikibu&apos;s honest feelings toward her lover.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 べにましこ(id:261367), Janus01(id:69663), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nlkl(id:88201), Kiev(id:13022), 捕澤(id:23785), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>