<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>堤中納言物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari (The Riverside Counselor&apos;s Tales)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari (The Riverside Counselor&apos;s Tales)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari</e>
<cmt>説明が続くので、削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>堤中納言物語（つつみちゅうなごんものがたり）は、日本の平安時代後期以降に成立した短編物語集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari (The Riverside Counselor&apos;s Tales) is a collection of short stories edited in late Heian period or later in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari (The Riverside Counselor&apos;s Tales) is a collection of short stories edited in the late Heian period or later in Japan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari (The Riverside Counselor&apos;s Tales) is a collection of short stories edited in the late Heian period or later in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>編者は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The editor is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The editor is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The editor is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>10編の短編物語および１編の断片からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of ten pieces of short stories, and one incomplete fragment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of ten short story pieces, and one incomplete fragment.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of ten short story pieces, and one incomplete fragment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>成立年代や筆者はそれぞれ異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each piece was written by different author at various times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pieces were written by different authors at various times.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pieces were written by different authors at various times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>遅いものは13世紀以後の作品と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latest piece was most likely written in 13th century or later.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latest piece was most likely written in the 13th century or later.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latest piece was most likely written in the 13th century or later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>10編中の1編『逢坂越えぬ権中納言』以外の著者・詳細な成立年代は不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except &quot;Osaka Koenu Gon Chunagon&quot;, authors of all ten pieces and exactly when they were written are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for &quot;Osaka Koenu Gon Chunagon,&quot; the authors of all ten pieces and exactly when they were written are unknown.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for &quot;Osaka Koenu Gon Chunagon,&quot; the authors of all ten pieces and exactly when they were written are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし、文永八年(1271年)成立の『風葉和歌集』に同編および「花桜折る少将（中将）」「はいずみ」「ほどほどの懸想」「貝合はせ」から歌が入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;Fuyo Wakashu&quot; (collection of Japanese poems based on fictional stories), edited in 1271, contains the poetries from the same, &quot;Hanazakura Oru Shosho (Chusho)&quot;, &quot;Haizumi&quot;, &quot;Hodohodo no Keso&quot; and &quot;Kaiawase.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Fuyo Wakashu&quot; (collection of Japanese poems based on fictional stories), edited in 1271, contains poetry from the same, &quot;Hanazakura Oru Shosho (Chusho)&quot;, &quot;Haizumi&quot;, &quot;Hodohodo no Keso,&quot; and &quot;Kaiawase.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;Fuyo Wakashu&quot; (collection of Japanese poems based on fictional stories), edited in 1271, contains poetry from the same, &apos;Hanazakura Oru Shosho (Chusho),&apos; &apos;Haizumi,&apos; &apos;Hodohodo no Keso,&apos; and &apos;Kaiawase.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このため、これらの物語が文永八年以前の成立であることは確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the stories were certainly written before 1271.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the stories were certainly written before 1271.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the stories were certainly written before 1271.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、10編の物語のなかのいずれにも「堤中納言」という人物は登場していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">None of ten stories has a character called Tsutsumi Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">None of the ten stories has a character called Tsutsumi Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">None of the ten stories has a character called Tsutsumi Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この表題が何に由来するものなのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How and why it was titled is unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How and why it was so titled is unknown.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;so&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How and why it was so titled is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>複数の物語をばらけないように包んでおいたため「つつみの物語」と称され、それがいつの間にか実在の堤中納言（藤原兼輔）に関連づけられて考えられた結果「つつみ」中納言物語となったのではないか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, it was called &quot;Tsutsumi no Monogatari&quot; because various stories (monogatari) were wrapped (tsutsumi) so that the stories might not come apart; then it was related to a real person, Tsutsumi Chunagon (FUJIWARA no Kanesuke) and became &quot;Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari&quot; in the end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, it was called &quot;Tsutsumi no Monogatari&quot; because various stories (monogatari) were wrapped (tsutsumi) so that the stories might not come apart; then it was related to a real person, Tsutsumi Chunagon (FUJIWARA no Kanesuke) and in the end became &quot;Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, it was called &apos;Tsutsumi no Monogatari&apos; because various stories (monogatari) were wrapped (tsutsumi) so that the stories might not come apart; then it was related to a real person, Tsutsumi Chunagon (FUJIWARA no Kanesuke) and in the end became &apos;Tsutsumi Chunagon Monogatari.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>など様々な説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are diverse theories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are various other theories.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are various other theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>以下の10編、及び未完の断片からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of the following ten stories and an incomplete fragment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of the following ten stories and an incomplete fragment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of the following ten stories and an incomplete fragment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>作品の配列順・題名等については、伝本により異同がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The orders and titles of the stories may differ depending on the manuscript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The order and titles of the stories may differ depending on the manuscript.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The order and titles of the stories may differ depending on the manuscript.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、現存する伝本は全て江戸期の写本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, all existing manuscripts were written in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, all existing manuscripts were written in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, all existing manuscripts were written in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「逢坂越えぬ権中納言」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Koenu Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Koenu Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Koenu Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>唯一筆者と成立年代が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the only story whose author and written year are identified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the only story whose author and year of writing are identified.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the only story whose author and year of writing are identified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天喜３年(1055年)成立、筆者は小式部（小式部内侍とは別人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written in 1055 by Koshikibu (Koshikibu no Naishi is different person).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was written in 1055 by Koshikibu (Koshikibu no Naishi is a different person).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written in 1055 by Koshikibu (Koshikibu no Naishi is a different person).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「六条斎院物語合」のために新作された作品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story was originally written for the &quot;Rokujosaiin Monogatari awase&quot; (Collection of unusual stories with Japanese poems).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story was originally written for the &quot;Rokujosaiin Monogatari awase&quot; (Collection of unusual stories with Japanese poems).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story was originally written for the &apos;Rokujosaiin Monogatari awase&apos; (Collection of unusual stories with Japanese poems).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>いわゆる「薫型」の貴公子の恋を描いたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It depicts so-called &quot;Kaoru style (indecisive style like Kaoru, a character of The Tale of Genji)&quot; love of a young noble.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It depicts the so-called &quot;Kaoru style&quot; (indecisive style like that of Kaoru, a character of The Tale of Genji) love of a young noble.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It depicts the so-called &apos;Kaoru style&apos; (indecisive style like that of Kaoru, a character of The Tale of Genji) love of a young noble.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>あらすじ：諸事にわたって完璧な貴公子である中納言が、恋する女宮の側まで参上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: the Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) who is a perfect young noble in every way visits an imperial princess whom he falls for.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: the Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), who is a perfect young noble in every way, visits an imperial princess whom he falls for.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: the Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), who is a perfect young noble in every way, visits an imperial princess whom he falls for.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、遠慮のためについに契ることは出来ずに終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he hesitates to sleep with her after all.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the end he hesitates to sleep with her.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the end he hesitates to sleep with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>「花桜折る少将（中将）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanazakura Oru Shosho (Chusho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanazakura Oru Shosho (Chusho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanazakura oru shosho (Chusho)</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>主人公の官位が伝本によって「少将」「中将」「大将」と異なり、題名もそれに従って異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on the manuscript, official rank of the main character may be shosho (major general), chusho (lieutenant general) or taisho (general), and the title differs accordingly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the manuscript, the official rank of the main character may be shosho (major general), chusho (lieutenant general), or taisho (general), and the title differs accordingly.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the manuscript, the official rank of the main character may be shosho (major general), chusho (lieutenant general), or taisho (general), and the title differs accordingly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>あらすじ：主人公の少将は美しい姫君に恋をし、彼女が入内する前に盗み出そうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: The main character, Shosho falls for a beautiful princess and tries to snatch her before she does Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: The main character, Shosho, falls for a beautiful princess and tries to snatch her before she enters the court as an Imperial Consort bride.</e>
<cmt>entry</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: The main character, Shosho, falls for a beautiful princess and tries to snatch her before she enters the court as an Imperial Consort bride.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、誤って姫の祖母を連れてきてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he accidentally takes princess&apos;s grandmother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he accidentally takes the princess&apos;s grandmother.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he accidentally takes the princess&apos;s grandmother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>「虫愛づる姫君」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mushi Mezuru Himegimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mushi Mezuru Himegimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mushi mezuru himegimi</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>一説には「蜂飼大臣」と称された太政大臣藤原宗輔とその娘がモデルであるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, the story is based on Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Munesuke called &quot;Hachikai no Otodo&quot; (Beekeeper Minister of State) and his daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, the story is based on Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Munesuke, called &quot;Hachikai no Otodo&quot; (Beekeeper Minister of State), and his daughter.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, the story is based on Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Munesuke, called &apos;Hachikai no Otodo&apos; (Beekeeper Minister of State), and his daughter.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>アニメーション作家宮崎駿の｢風の谷のナウシカ」のナウシカはこの姫君から着想を得ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nausicaa of animation cartoonist Hayao MIYAZAKI&apos;s &quot;Nausicaa of the Valley of Wind&quot; was inspired by the princess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nausicaa of animation cartoonist Hayao MIYAZAKI&apos;s &quot;Nausicaa of the Valley of Wind&quot; was inspired by the princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nausicaa of animation cartoonist Hayao MIYAZAKI&apos;s &quot;Nausicaa of the Valley of Wind&quot; was inspired by the princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>あらすじ：按察使大納言の姫は美しく気高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: the princess of Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) chief councillor of state is beautiful and noble.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: the princess of Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) chief councillor of state is beautiful and noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: The princess of Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) chief councillor of state is beautiful and noble.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし、裳着(元服に相当)を済ませたにも拘らず化粧せず、お歯黒を付けず、引眉せず、平仮名を書かず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even after her Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony for girls), she does not make up, paint eyebrows, paint her teeth black, or write hiragana (Japanese syllabary characters).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even after her Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony for girls), she does not wear make up, paint her eyebrows, paint her teeth black, or write hiragana (Japanese syllabary characters).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even after her Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony for girls), she does not wear make up, paint her eyebrows, paint her teeth black, or write hiragana (Japanese syllabary characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>可憐なものを愛さず毛虫を愛する風変わりな姫君だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is a strange princess who does not love pretty things but loves hairy caterpillars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is a strange princess who does not love pretty things but loves hairy caterpillars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is a strange princess who does not love pretty things but loves hairy caterpillars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その様子を屋敷に入り込んだ風流男が覗き、歌を読みかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tasteful man who has entered the residence looks into the situation and reads poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tasteful man who has entered the residence looks into the situation and reads poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tasteful man who has entered the residence looks into the situation and reads poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>「このついで」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kono Tsuide</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kono Tsuide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kono tsuide</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>あらすじ：中宮（または女御）の無聊と徒然を慰めようと薫き物を試みたことをきっかけに、中宮の弟である宰相の中将と、中納言の君・少将の君といった女房らが今まで見聞きしたしみじみとする話を語り合う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: when incense is burned to beguile the tedium and boredom of the Empress (or court lady), Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain) who is a younger brother of the Empress and nyobo (court ladies), Chinagon no kimi and Shosho no kimi, talk together about touching episodes they have heard before.</e>
<cmt>参考：堤中納言物語 - 大学受験予備校フロンティアセミナーhttp://onda.frontierseminar.com/kodai/13.doc</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: when incense is burned to beguile the tedium and boredom of the Empress (or court lady), Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain), who is a younger brother of the Empress, and nyobo (court ladies) Chinagon no kimi and Shosho no kimi, talk together about touching episodes they have heard before.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: When incense is burned to beguile the tedium and boredom of the Empress (or court lady), Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain), who is a younger brother of the Empress, and nyobo (court ladies) Chunagon no kimi and Shosho no kimi, talk together about touching episodes they have heard before.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>「よしなしごと」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinashigoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinashigoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinashigoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>書簡風の短編。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a short story in letter style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a short story in letter style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a short story in letter style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ある手紙の内容を筆者が引用した、という体裁を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written as the author cited the content of a letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written as if the author cited the content of a letter.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;if&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written as if the author cited the content of a letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>あらすじ：ある僧が他人から品物を借りるために書いた長い手紙は、驚き呆れるようなものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: a Buddhist priest wrote a long letter to borrow goods; the contents of his letter are astonishing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: a Buddhist priest wrote a long letter to borrow goods; the contents of his letter are astonishing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: A Buddhist priest wrote a long letter to borrow goods; the contents of his letter are astonishing.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>「はなだの女ご（花々の女ご）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanada no Nyogo (Hanabana no Nyogo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanada no Nyogo (Hanabana no Nyogo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanada no nyogo (Hanabana no nyogo)</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>題名に関しては諸説あり、大別して</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various views on the title; they may be broadly classified as followings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various views on the title; they may be broadly classified as follows.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various views on the title; They may be broadly classified as follows.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>前半部を「はなだ」とするか、「はなばな」とするか</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether the first word is supposed to be &quot;Hanada&quot; or &quot;Hanabana.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether the first word is supposed to be &quot;Hanada&quot; or &quot;Hanabana.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether the first word is supposed to be &apos;Hanada&apos; or &apos;Hanabana.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「はなだ」を取る場合、それは「花田」か「縹」か</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it is &quot;Hanada&quot;, it means &quot;Hanada (flower field)&quot; or &quot;Hanada (light blue).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it is &quot;Hanada&quot;, it means &quot;Hanada (flower field)&quot; or &quot;Hanada (light blue).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it is &apos;Hanada&apos;, it means &apos;Hanada&apos; (flower field) or &apos;Hanada&apos; (light blue).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>「女ご」を「女御（にょうご）」とするか「女子（をんな子）」とするか</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether &quot;Nyogo&quot; should be considered as &quot;court lady&quot; or &quot;girl.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether &quot;Nyogo&quot; should be considered &quot;court lady&quot; or &quot;girl.&quot;</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether &apos;Nyogo&apos; should be considered &apos;court lady&apos; or &apos;girl.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>で意見が分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opinion is divided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opinion is divided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opinion is divided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>あらすじ：ある屋敷につどった姉妹達が、それぞれ仕えている女主人のうわさ話をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: The sisters gather at one residence and talk about each of the landladies whom they serve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: Sisters gather at one residence and talk about the landladies whom they serve.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: Sisters gather at one residence and talk about the landladies whom they serve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>姉妹達の大半と関係がある風流男が、そのさまをこっそりと覗き見る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tasteful man who has a connection with most of them looks into secretly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tasteful man who has a connection with most of them looks in secretly.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tasteful man who has a connection with most of them looks in secretly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>「はいずみ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haizumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haizumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haizumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>『古本説話集』第十九段「平中事」、狂言「墨塗」などに見られるモチーフ「墨塗説話」系の短編。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a short story of &quot;Suminuri (putting black ink) tale&quot; style seen in &quot;Heichugoto,&quot; the 19th section of &quot;Kohon Setsuwashu (Collection of Old Tales),&quot; Kyogen (farce played during a Noh cycle) &quot;Suminuri&quot;, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a short story of &quot;Suminuri (putting black ink) tale&quot; style seen in &quot;Heichugoto,&quot; the 19th section of &quot;Kohon Setsuwashu (Collection of Old Tales),&quot; Kyogen (farce performed during a Noh cycle) &quot;Suminuri.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a short story of &apos;Suminuri (putting black ink) tale&apos; style seen in &apos;Heichugoto,&apos; the 19th section of &quot;Kohon Setsuwashu&quot; (Collection of Old Tales), Kyogen (farce performed during a Noh cycle) &apos;Suminuri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この段では、話の前半は『伊勢物語』二十三段などに見られる二人妻物語を基調とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first part of the story is inspired by tales of two wives seen in the 23rd story of &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise) etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first part of the story is inspired by tales of two wives seen in the 23rd story of &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise).</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;etc.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first part of the story is inspired by tales of two wives seen in the 23rd story of &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>後半はいわゆる平中墨塗譚を基調とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last part is inspired by so-called &quot;Suminuri Tale&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last part is inspired by so-called &quot;Suminuri Tale&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last part is inspired by so-called &quot;Suminuri Tale.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>あらすじ：新旧二人の妻を持った男が新しい妻を家に迎えようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: a married man is going to receive a new wife to the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: a married man is going to receive a new wife to the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: A married man is going to receive a new wife to the family.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかし、もとの妻の哀しむ様子を見て思いなおす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he starts to reconsider when he sees that the first wife is grieving.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he starts to reconsider when he sees that the first wife is grieving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he starts to reconsider when he sees that the first wife is grieving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ある日新しい妻の所へ行くと、慌てた妻ははいずみ（眉墨）を白粉と間違えて顔に塗ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, when he visits his new wife&apos;s place, she mistakenly applies eyebrow powder on her face in a hurry instead of face powder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, when he visits his new wife&apos;s place, she is in a hurry and mistakenly applies eyebrow powder on her face instead of face powder.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, when he visits his new wife&apos;s place, she is in a hurry and mistakenly applies eyebrow powder on her face instead of face powder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>男はそれに幻滅し、もとの妻のもとへ戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The man is disappointed with her look and returns to his first wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The man is disappointed with her look and returns to his first wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The man is disappointed with her look and returns to his first wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>「ほどほどの懸想」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hodohodo no Keso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hodohodo no Keso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hodohodo no keso</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>あらすじ：女童と小舎人童の恋から、侍と女房、頭中将と宮の姫、という主従3組の恋が進んでゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: love story of three couples in various social classes: a girl and a Kodoneri Warawa (Juvenile who served Court nobles and samurai families), a samurai and a nyobo (court lady) and a head lieutenant general and an imperial princess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: love story of three couples in various social classes: a girl and a Kodoneri Warawa (Juvenile who served Court nobles and samurai families), and a samurai and a nyobo (court lady) and a head lieutenant general and an imperial princess.</e>
<cmt>added &apos;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: Love story of three couples in various social classes: a girl and a Kodoneri Warawa (Juvenile who served Court nobles and samurai families), and a samurai and a nyobo (court lady) and a head lieutenant general and an imperial princess.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>「貝合はせ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaiawase</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaiawase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaiawase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>この物語における貝合は、珍しく美しい貝を集めて競い合う本来の貝合であり、現在知られているいわゆる貝覆いではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this story, kaiawase is the original kaiawase game, collecting and vying rare and beautiful shells; it is not the so-called Kaioi (pairing shells) known today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this story, kaiawase is the original kaiawase game, collecting and competing with rare and beautiful shells; it is not the so-called Kaioi (pairing shells) known today.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this story, kaiawase is the original kaiawase game, collecting and competing with rare and beautiful shells; it is not the so-called Kaioi (pairing shells) known today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>あらすじ：蔵人少将は、偶然ある姫君とその腹違いの姉が貝合をすることを知る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: Kurodo no Shosho (major general) finds out by chance that a princess and her half sister play kaiawase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: Kurodo no Shosho (major general) finds out by chance that a princess and her half sister play kaiawase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: Kurodo no Shosho (major general) finds out by chance that a princess and her half sister play kaiawase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>母の居ない姫君の境遇に同情した少将は、こっそりと素晴らしい貝を用立てて、味方してやる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sympathized with the princess, who lost her mother, and takes her side by secretly bringing wonderful shells.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sympathizes with the princess, who had lost her mother, and takes her side by secretly bringing wonderful shells.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sympathizes with the princess, who had lost her mother, and takes her side by secretly bringing wonderful shells.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>「思はぬ方にとまりする少将」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omowanu Kata ni Tomari suru Shosho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omowanu Kata ni Tomari suru Shosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omowanu kata ni tomari suru shosho</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>あらすじ：姉妹の姫君にそれぞれ通って相婿となっている二人の少将がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line: two major generals are brother in law, married to sisters respectively, and are commuting husbands.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story line: two major generals are brothers in law, married to sisters, and are commuting husbands.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story line: Two major generals are brothers in law, married to sisters, and are commuting husbands.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>ふとした取り違えで、妻ではない方の姫君とそれぞれ契ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By unexpected mistakes, they sleep with the other wives.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By unexpected mistakes, they sleep with each other&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By unexpected mistakes, they sleep with each other&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>未完断片</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incomplete Fragment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incomplete Fragment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incomplete fragment</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>「冬ごもる……」という書き出しで始まる、数行程度の断片。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a fragment of several lines starting with &quot;Fuyugomoru&quot; (Immersed winter).</e>
<cmt>冬ごもる:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a fragment of several lines starting with &quot;Fuyugomoru&quot; (Immersed winter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a fragment of several lines starting with &apos;Fuyugomoru&apos; (Immersed winter).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>物語の冒頭部分と見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be the beginning of a story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may be the beginning of a story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be the beginning of a story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>しかしこれがただの断片の混入なのか、意図的に置かれたものなのか、あるいは写本時の書きさしなのかについては不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, whether it is just a placed fragment, inserted intentionally or added at transcription is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, whether it is just a placed fragment, inserted intentionally or added at transcription, is unknown.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, whether it is just a placed fragment, inserted intentionally or added at transcription, is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 頭痛(id:201680), Mikomaid(id:56139), 水野白楓(id:22811), Newtype(id:185412), E091559(id:162832), 捕澤(id:23785), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>