<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>玉葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyokuyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyokuyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyokuyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『玉葉』（ぎょくよう）は、関白・太政大臣九条兼実の日記。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; is a diary of Kanezane KUJO, who was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; is a diary of Kanezane KUJO, who was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; is a diary of Kanezane KUJO, who was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名玉葉、月輪兼実公記とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Gyokukai&quot; or &quot;Tsukinowa Kanezaneko Ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Gyokukai&quot; or &quot;Tsukinowa Kanezaneko Ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Gyokukai&quot; or &quot;Tsukinowa Kanezaneko Ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>朝廷から武家政治への激動期に際して関白の職にあった兼実の公私にわたる記録である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a record of public and private matters by Kanezane who was in the position of Kanpaku in the era of great transition from the Imperial Court to samurai government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a record of public and private matters by Kanezane, who was in the position of Kanpaku in the era of great transition from the Imperial Court to samurai government.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a record of public and private matters by Kanezane, who was in the position of Kanpaku in the era of great transition from the Imperial Court to samurai government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>Overview→Summary</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>記述は1164年（長寛2年）から1200年（正治2年）に及んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descriptions cover a period from 1164 to 1200.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descriptions cover a period from 1164 to 1200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descriptions cover a period from 1164 to 1200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>公家の日記は、宮中行事のしきたりなどを後に伝える目的があり、儀式の次第が詳細に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diaries of court nobles had a purpose to pass down traditional practices of court functions, etc. to future generations and, therefore, procedures of ceremonies are described in details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diaries of court nobles had a purpose to pass down traditional practices of court functions, etc. to future generations and, therefore, procedures of ceremonies are described in detail.</e>
<cmt>singular detail</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diaries of court nobles had a purpose to pass down traditional practices of court functions, etc. to future generations and, therefore, procedures of ceremonies are described in detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、当時の治承・寿永の乱についても多く記されており、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期の変動期についての基礎史料になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it contains a large number of descriptions on Jisho-Juei War in that period and it became a basic historical material.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it contains many descriptions of the Jisho-Juei War in that period, and it became a basic historical material.</e>
<cmt>a large number-&gt;many</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it contains many descriptions of the Jisho-Juei War in that period, and it became a basic historical material of the era, from the end of Heian period to the beginning of Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>”平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期の変動期”という部分を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同時代の史料としては『吾妻鏡』もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a historical material of the same era, there is &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other historical sources of the same era include &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rephrased for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other historical sources of the same era include &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これは鎌倉幕府の北条氏の立場で編纂された正史に近いものであるから、朝廷側の人間の日記として記述された『玉葉』と相補的に用いられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was edited from the standpoint of the Hojo clan of the Kamakura bakufu and it close to an official history, it is used with &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; which was described as a diary of a person on the Royal Court side, to complement with each other.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was edited from the standpoint of the Hojo clan of the Kamakura bakufu and is close to an official history, it is used along with and to complement &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; which was described as a diary of a person on the Royal Court side.</e>
<cmt>edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was edited from the standpoint of the Hojo clan of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and is close to an official history, it is used along with and to complement &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; which was described as a diary of a person on the Royal Court side.</e>
<cmt>the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) と挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>兼実の孫である九条道家没後、元本は一条家に、写本が九条家に伝来された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Michiie KUJO, who was a grandson of Kanezane, the original was passed down in the Ichijo family and a transcript in Kujo familty.ne&lt; the</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Michiie KUJO, who was a grandson of Kanezane, the original was passed down in the Ichijo family.</e>
<cmt>looks like the translator started editing but got distracted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Michiie KUJO, who was a grandson of Kanezane, the original was passed down in the Ichijo family, the manuscript copy was passed down in the Kujo family.</e>
<cmt>”写本が九条家に”という部分を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、二条家では『玉葉』という名称を用いずに『玉海』と呼称を用いたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reportedly, the name &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; had not been used by Nijo family, but &quot;Gyokukai&quot; had been used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reportedly, although the name &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; was not used by the Nijo family, &quot;Gyokukai&quot; was used.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reportedly, although the name &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; was not used by the Nijo family, &quot;Gyokukai&quot; was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Spirituelle(id:654), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 玄史生(id:43670), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Suetsugu1980(id:24831), Ktmchi(id:113301), Co.kyoto(id:79296), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>