<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>秋好中宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akikonomu Chugu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akikonomu Chugu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akikonomu Chugu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>秋好中宮（あきこのむちゅうぐう）は、紫式部の物語『源氏物語』に登場する架空の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akikonomu Chugu is a fictional character who appears in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s novel &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akikonomu Chugu is a fictional character who appears in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s novel &quot;Genji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akikonomu Chugu is a fictional character who appears in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s novel &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>作中では前斎宮であることから斎宮女御（さいぐうのにょうご）、また凝花舎を局としたことから梅壺女御（うめつぼのにょうご）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, as she is a former saigu (), she was called saigu no nyogo), or umetsubo no tsubone as she used Gyokasha as tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the story, as she is a former saigu (), she was called saigu no nyogo), or umetsubo no tsubone as she used Gyokasha as tsubone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the story, she is called saigu no nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor))because she was a former saigu (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Ise-jingu Shrine) or umetsubo no tsubone because she used Gyokasha (one of the shichiden gosha (literally, seven palaces and five houses) which was also called Umetsubo) as her living quarters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>六条御息所と前坊（ぜんぼう。桐壺帝の弟。桐壺帝の第一皇子（後の朱雀帝）が東宮に擁立する前の東宮。ただし作中には登場せず）との間の一人娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is an only daughter between Rokujo no Miyasudokoro and Zenbo (a younger brother of the Emperor Kiritsubo; the crown prince before the first imperial prince of the Emperor Kiritsubo (later, the Emperor Suzaku) was helped to the crown prince; he does not appear in the story).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is the only daughter between Rokujo no Miyasudokoro and Zenbo (the younger brother of the Emperor Kiritsubo; the crown prince before the first imperial prince of Emperor Kiritsubo (later, Emperor Suzaku), was helped to be the crown prince; he does not appear in the story).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is the only daughter of Rokujo no Miyasudokoro and Zenbo (the younger brother of Emperor Kiritsubo; crown prince before the first imperial prince of Emperor Kiritsubo (later, Emperor Suzaku), was crown prince; he does not appear in the story).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>光源氏の従妹にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is a younger cousin sister of Hikaru Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is the younger cousin and sister of Hikaru Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is a cousin of Hikaru Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父の前坊が亡くなった後、母と共に内裏を去り、六条の邸宅にて育った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her father, Zenbo, died, she left the court with her mother and was brought up in the mansion in Rokujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her father, Zenbo, died, she left the court with her mother and was brought up in a mansion in Rokujo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her father, Zenbo, died, she left the court with her mother and was brought up in a mansion in Rokujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>12歳の頃桐壺帝が朱雀帝に譲位、これに伴い新たな伊勢の斎宮に選ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When she was around twelve years old, the Emperor Kiritsubo abdicated the throne to the Emperor Suzaku and, in line with this, she was chosen to new saigu of the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When she was around twelve years old, Emperor Kiritsubo abdicated the throne to the Emperor Suzaku and, in line with this, she was chosen to be the new saigu of the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When she was around twelve years old, Emperor Kiritsubo abdicated the throne to the Emperor Suzaku and she was chosen to be the new saigu of the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この時、光源氏との恋愛関係が破綻していた母御息所も伊勢に同行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, her mother, Miyasudokoro, whose love with Hikaru Genji had broken, went to Ise together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, her mother, Miyasudokoro, whose love affair with Hikaru Genji had broken off, went to Ise together.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother, Miyasudokoro, whose love affair with Hikaru Genji had ended,, went to Ise together.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>伊勢へ旅立つための宮中での儀式で斎宮と対面した朱雀帝は、斎宮のあまりの美しさに一目惚れしその後も忘れられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Suzaku met the saigu in the ceremony in court for departing to Ise and fell in love at first sight because of her beauty and could not forget her after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Suzaku met the saigu in the ceremony in court for departing to Ise and fell in love at first sight because of her beauty and could not forget her after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Suzaku met the saigu at the court ceremony fpr departing to Ise and fell in love at first sight because of her beauty and could not forget her after that.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後に朱雀帝は位を降りてから斎宮を妃にと望むが、母御息所の反対に遭い、その死後も源氏の意向により実現しなかった（「葵 (源氏物語)」「賢木」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Emperor Suzaku wanted to marry the saigu after his abdication, but her mother, Miyasudokoro opposed and, even after her death, it cannot be realized because of Genji&apos;s intention (&quot;Aoi (Genji Monogatari)&quot;, &quot;Sakaki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Emperor Suzaku wanted to marry the saigu after his abdication, but her mother, Miyasudokoro opposed and, even after her death, it couldn&apos;t be realized because of Genji&apos;s intention (&quot;Aoi (Genji Monogatari),&quot; &quot;Sakaki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Emperor Suzaku wanted to marry the saigu after his abdication, but her mother, Miyasudokoro opposed this and, even after her death, Genji prevented this from happening (&apos;Aoi (Genji Monogatari),&apos; &apos;Sakaki&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>21～2歳の頃朱雀帝が退位したことで斎宮は任期を終え、退下し母と京に戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Emperor Suzaku abdicated when she was 21 to 22 years old, the saigu completed hr term her term and left Ise and returned to Kyoto together with her mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Emperor Suzaku abdicated when she was 21 to 22 years old, the saigu completed her term, left Ise, and returned to Kyoto together with her mother.</e>
<cmt>redundant, grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was 21 to 22 years old when Emperor Suzaku abdicated and with the completion of her term, the saigu left Ise, and returned to Kyoto together with her mother.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その頃母御息所はすでに病床についており、源氏に斎宮の後見を言い置いて亡くなった（「澪標」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, her mother, Miyasudokoro, was ill in bed, and died after requesting Genji to guard Saigu (&quot;Miotsukushi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, her mother, Miyasudokoro, was ill in bed, and died after requesting that Genji guard Saigu (&quot;Miotsukushi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother, Miyasudokoro, was ill in bed at that time and died after requesting that Genji become guardian of the Saigu (&apos;Miotsukushi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>復権した源氏は内大臣に昇進、斎宮を養女に迎えて後宮政治に乗り出し、実の子である11歳の冷泉帝の元へ女御として入内させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rehabilitated Genji was promoted to naidaijin (minister for interior) and adopted the saigu and took part in politics in harem and let her enter into court as nyogo (emperor&apos;s consort) to the Emperor Reizei, who was eleven years old and his real chile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rehabilitated Genji was promoted to naidaijin (minister of the interior), adopted the saigu and took part in politics in harem and let her enter into court as nyogo (emperor&apos;s consort) to the Emperor Reizei, who was eleven years old and was his real child.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji was back in power and promoted to naidaijin (minister of the interior), adopted the saigu and took part in politics via the Emperor&apos;s inner court and supported her entry into court as nyogo (emperor&apos;s consort) to the eleven-year-old Emperor Reizei, who was his biological son.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その一方で女御への興味も強く持っていたが（「絵合」）、女御は母の恋人であった源氏が近寄る事を厭い、源氏自身も亡き御息所の遺言で強く諌められていたため、未練を抱きつつもあくまで後見役に徹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he had strong interest in nyogo (&quot;Eawase&quot;), but since nyogo did not like Genji, who was her mother&apos;s lover, come close to her and Genji himself was strongly constrained by late Miysasudokoro&apos;s will, he played a role of the guarding while attaching to her to some extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he had a strong interest in nyogo (&quot;Eawase&quot;), but since nyogo did not like Genji, who was her mother&apos;s lover, to come close to her and Genji himself was strongly constrained by late Miysasudokoro&apos;s will, he played the role of guardian while being attached to her to some extent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Genji was strong;y interested in the nyogo (&apos;Eawase&apos;), but since the nyogo did not want Genji, who was her mother&apos;s lover, to come close to her and Genji himself was strongly constrained by the late Miyasudokoro&apos;s will, he played the role of guardian while being attached to her to some extent.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また女御は源氏の妻紫の上とも親交を持ち、同じ邸内に住むようになってからは親しい友人のような関係を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, nyogo had close friendship with Genji&apos;s wife, Murasaki no Ue and, after they began to live in a same mansion, continued to have relationship of close friends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, nyogo had close friendship with Genji&apos;s wife, Murasaki no Ue and, after they began to live in a same mansion, continued to have relationship of close friends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the nyogo had a close friendship with Genji&apos;s wife, Murasaki no Ue and after they began to live in a same mansion, continued to have a close friendship.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>彼女の呼称「秋好中宮」は後世の読者につけられたもので、源氏が彼女に言い寄る口実に「あなたは春と秋のどちらがお好きか」と尋ねた際（「薄雲」）、「母御息所の亡くなった秋に惹かれる」と答えた事に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here name &quot;Akikonomu Chugu&quot; was give by the readers of later age and was derived from the edisode that, when Genji asked her &quot;Which do you like spring or autumn?&quot; to make advance to her (&quot;Usugumo&quot;), she answered &quot;I am attracted autumn in which my mother, Miyasudokoro, passed away.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here name &quot;Akikonomu Chugu&quot; was give by the readers of a later age and was derived from the episode when Genji asked her &quot;Which do you like spring or autumn?&quot; to make advance to her (&quot;Usugumo&quot;), she answered &quot;I am attracted autumn in which my mother, Miyasudokoro, passed away.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name &apos;Akikonomu Chugu&apos; was given by readers of later ages and was derived from the episode when Genji asked her &apos;Which do you like spring or autumn?&apos; when making advances to her (&apos;Usugumo&apos;), and she answered &apos;I am attracted to autumn because my mother, Miyasudokoro, passed away.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また源氏はこれに案を得て、四つの町からなる広大な邸宅（六条院）を造営し、秋好のために亡き御息所の邸跡の西南の町に秋の風物を配して彼女の里邸（里下がり時の邸）に用意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting an idea from this, Genji constructed a large mansion consisting of four towns (Rokujoin) and prepared a village residence (residence used when she returns to her family) for Akikonomu by arranging autumnal natural features in the town located in the southwest which was the location of the residence of late Miyasudokoro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Getting an idea from this, Genji constructed a large mansion consisting of four towns (Rokujoin) and prepared a village residence (residence used when she returned to her family) for Akikonomu by arranging natural autumnal features in town located to the southwest which was the location of the residence of late Miyasudokoro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji got an idea from this and constructed a large mansion consisting of four sections(Rokujoin) and prepared a home residence (residence used when she returned to her family) for Akikonomu by arranging natural autumnal features in the southwest section, which was previously the location of the residence of late Miyasudokoro.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>一方春を好む紫の上は隣の東南の春の町に住まい、紫の上と秋好は六条院の春の主と秋の主として、春秋の優劣を競う風流な挑み合いを繰り広げた（「少女 (源氏物語)」「胡蝶 (源氏物語)」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Murasaki no Ue who liked spring lived in the spring town and Murasaki no Ue and Akikonomu as the master of the spring and the master of autunm of Rokujoin respectively, conducted elegant competition between the spring and the autumn (&quot;Otome (Genji Monogatari), &quot;Kocho (Genji Monogatari)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Murasaki no Ue, who liked spring, lived in the spring town and Murasaki no Ue and Akikonomu as the master of the spring and the master of autunm of Rokujoin respectively, conducted elegant competitions between the spring and the autumn (&quot;Otome - Genji Monogatari), &quot;Kocho - Genji Monogatari).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Murasaki no Ue, who liked spring, lived in the spring section and Murasaki no Ue and Akikonomu as the master of the spring and autumn of Rokujoin, respectively, conducted an elegant competition betweenspring and autumn (&apos;Otome&apos; (Genji Monogatari), &apos;Kocho&apos; (Genji Monogatari).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>源氏の強い後押しもあり中宮に立后（「少女」）、以後の源氏のさらなる栄華へ大きく貢献する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Partly because of strong backup by Genji, she was elected to chugu (emperor&apos;s second consort)(&quot;Otome&quot;) and greatly contributed to Genji&apos;s futehr prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Partly because of strong backup by Genji, she was elected to chugu (emperor&apos;s second consort) (&quot;Otome&quot;) and greatly contributed to Genji&apos;s futher prosperity.</e>
<cmt>spelling, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Partly because of strong support Genji, she was elected to chugu (emperor&apos;s second consort) (&apos;Otome&apos;) and greatly contributed to Genji&apos;s further prosperity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>源氏の一人娘明石の姫君の裳着では腰結役を務め（「梅枝」）、源氏の四十の賀にも養女として盛大な祝いをした（「若菜 (源氏物語)」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In mogi (coming-of-age ceremony for girls) of Genji&apos;s only daughter, Akashi no Himegimi, she served as koshimusubiyaku (a role to tie an obi (belt)) (Umegae&apos;), and, for the ceremony of forty years old for Genji, she arranged splended celebration (&quot;Wakana (Genji Monogatari)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In mogi (the coming-of-age ceremony for girls) for Genji&apos;s only daughter, Akashi no Himegimi, she served as koshimusubiyaku (the role of tying an obi or belt) (Umegae&apos;), and, for the forty year ceremony or Genji, she arranged a splended celebration (&quot;Wakana - Genji Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She served as koshimusubiyaku (person with role of tying an obi or belt) (&apos;Umegae&apos;) in the mogi (the coming-of-age ceremony for girls) for Genji&apos;s only daughter, Akashi no Himegimi and she arranged a splendid celebration (&apos;Wakana&apos; (Genji Monogatari) for Genji&apos;s fortieth birthday ceremony.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>母代りの後見役として入内した夫冷泉帝は9歳年下で、また子もなかったが、絵画という共通の趣味により寵愛を得て、冷泉帝の退位後も良好な夫婦関係であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her husband, the Emperor Reizei, for whom she entered court as a guardian instead of his mother was younger than her by nine years and they had no child between them, but she was loved by him through their common hobby of painting and they kept good relationship as a married couple even after abdiction of the Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her husband, Emperor Reizei, for whom she entered court as his guardian instead of mother, was younger than her by nine years and they had no child between them, but she was loved by him through their common hobby of painting and they kept a good relationship as a married couple even after the abdiction of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her husband, Emperor Reizei, for whom she entered court as his guardian instead of mother, was younger than her by nine years and they had no child between them, but she was loved by him through their common hobby of painting and they kept a good relationship as a married couple even after the addiction of Emperor Reizei.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>源氏の死後はその遺児薫を冷泉院と共に寵遇、息子代わりの後見として頼みにしていた（「匂宮」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Genji&apos;s death, she loved his son left behing him, Kaoru, together with the Retired Emperor Reizei and relied on him as a guardian instead of son (&apos;Nioumiya&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Genji&apos;s death, she loved his son left behind by him, Kaoru, together with the Retired Emperor Reizei and relied on him as a guardian instead of son (&apos;Nioumiya&apos;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She loved Genji&apos;s son, Kaoru, together with the Retired Emperor Reizei and since she did not have any sons herself, relied on him as a guardian (&apos;Nioumiya&apos;) after Genji&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Maxima m(id:28947), Masyu(id:31065), Izayohi(id:13095), Christina(id:18965), いたる(id:58536), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>