<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>別本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>別本（べっぽん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>同じ正本に基づくが、内容に相違がある本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a book based on the same original book, but has differences in the contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a book based on the same original book, but has differences in the contents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to a book based on the same original book, but has differences in the contents.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>異本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ihon (alternative version)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ihon (alternative version)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called &quot;Ihon&quot; (alternative version).</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>写本参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See manuscript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See manuscript.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See the section on &quot;manuscript.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>源氏物語の写本のうち、青表紙本、河内本のいずれにも属さないもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the manuscripts of The Tale of Genji, it does not belong to either Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or Kawachi-bon manuscript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the manuscripts of The Tale of Genji, it does not belong to either Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or the Kawachi-bon manuscript.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to a manuscript which, among those of The Tale of Genji, does not belong to either Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or the Kawachi-bon manuscript.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>本項で説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will be explained in this category.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It will be explained in this category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be explained in this category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>別本（べっぽん）とは、源氏物語の写本のうち、青表紙本、河内本のいずれにも属さないものをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppon is the manuscript of The Tale of Genji which does not belong to either Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or Kawachi-bon manuscript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppon is the manuscript of The Tale of Genji which does not belong to either the Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or the Kawachi-bon manuscript.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppon is the manuscript of The Tale of Genji which does not belong to either the Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or the Kawachi-bon manuscript among those of The Tale of Genji.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>またそのような写本によって伝えられる本文を指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also refers to the text of such manuscript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also refers to the text of such manuscript.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also refers to the text of such manuscript.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「別本」の呼称は池田亀鑑により1942年（昭和17年）に出版された源氏物語の校本である「校異源氏物語」において初めて用いられたもので、後に「源氏物語大成」などにも採用されて広く普及することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of &apos;Beppon&apos; was first used in &apos;Koi Genji monogatari,&apos; a variorum of The Tale of Genji, published by Kikan IKEDA in 1942, and later it also came to be widely used in &apos;Genji monogatari taisei&apos; (Comprehensive Study of The Tale of Genji), and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of &apos;Beppon&apos; was first used in &apos;Koi Genji monogatari,&apos; a variorum of The Tale of Genji, published by Kikan IKEDA in 1942, and later it also came to be widely used in &apos;Genji monogatari taisei&apos; - Comprehensive Study of The Tale of Genji), and so on.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name, &apos;Beppon,&apos; was first used in &apos;Koi Genji monogatari,&apos; a variorum of The Tale of Genji, published by Kikan IKEDA in 1942, and later it also came to be widely used in &apos;Genji monogatari taisei&apos; (Comprehensive Study of The Tale of Genji), and so on.</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そもそも「別本」とは青表紙本でもなく河内本でもないと認められる諸写本を、その性格・系統などを考慮に入れず一様に「別本」という一つの呼称で扱おうとするあくまで便宜的な用語であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, &apos;Beppon&apos; was just an expedient name for a group of manuscripts which were not recognized as Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or Kawachi-bon manuscript, and it was treated under the name of &apos;Beppon&apos; without considering the nature or line of the manuscripts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, &apos;Beppon&apos; was just an expedient name for a group of manuscripts not recognized as an Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or an Kawachi-bon manuscript, and it was treated under the name of &apos;Beppon&apos; without considering the nature or line of the manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, &apos;Beppon&apos; was just an expedient name for a group of manuscripts not recognized as an Aobyoshi-bon manuscript or an Kawachi-bon manuscript, and it was treated under the name of &apos;Beppon&apos; without considering the nature or line of the manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>青表紙本や河内本のように特定の祖本から分かれた何らかの共通の性格を持った一群の写本が存在するわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are not necessarily a group of manuscripts which had common distinctions and branched from the particular original manuscript such as Aobyoshi-bon manuscript and Kawachi-bon manuscript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were not necessarily a group of manuscripts which had common distinctions and that branched from the particular original manuscript such as Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were not necessarily a group of manuscripts which had common distinctions and that branched from the particular original manuscript such as Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この術語を提唱した池田亀鑑によれば、「青表紙本や河内本が「青表紙本系統」や「河内本系統」と呼ばれたりするのと同様に別本を「別本系統」と呼ぶのは誤りであり、別本という呼称やその性格は源氏物語の本文の研究が進んで青表紙本や河内本の性格が明らかになった後で改めて検討され、分類・整理されるべきものである」としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kikan IKEDA, an advocator of this term, &apos;it is wrong to call Beppon &apos;Beppon line&apos; just like calling Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon &apos;Aobyoshi-bon line&apos; and &apos;Kawachibon-line&apos; respectively, and the name and characteristics of Beppon should be restudied, classified, and organized after the text study of The Tale of Genji is advanced and distinction of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon are revealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kikan IKEDA, an advocator of this term, &apos;it is wrong to call Beppon &apos;Beppon line&apos; just like calling Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon &apos;Aobyoshi-bon line&apos; and &apos;Kawachibon-line&apos; respectively, and the name and characteristics of Beppon should be restudied, classified, and organized after the text study of The Tale of Genji is advanced and the distinction of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon are revealed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kikan IKEDA, an advocator of this term, &apos;it is wrong to call Beppon &apos;Beppon line&apos; just like calling Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon &apos;Aobyoshi-bon line&apos; and &apos;Kawachibon-line&apos; respectively, and the name and characteristics of Beppon should be restudied, classified, and organized after the text study of The Tale of Genji is advanced and the distinction of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon are revealed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文末のシングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Varieties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Varieties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Varieties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>池田亀鑑は別本の中には次のようなものが含まれるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kikan IKEDA considered that the following manuscripts were classified into Beppon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kikan IKEDA considered that the following manuscripts were classified into Beppon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kikan IKEDA considered that the following manuscripts were classified into Beppon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>古伝本系の別本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppon of old tradition line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppon of old tradition line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppon of old tradition line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>混成本文系の別本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppon of mixed texts line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppon of mixed texts line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppon of mixed texts line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>注釈的本文系の別本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beppon of annotative text line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beppon of annotative text line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beppon of annotative text line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>実際には青表紙本であるという確証もなく河内本であるという確証も無いというだけでどのような性格を持った写本なのか不明な「別本」も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, there are not a few &apos;Beppon&apos; whose characteristics are unclear and which simply do not have evidences to prove that they belong to Aobyoshi-bon or Kawachi-bon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, there are many &apos;Beppon&apos; with characteristics that are unclear and which simply do not have any evidence to prove that they belong to Aobyoshi-bon or Kawachi-bon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, there are many &apos;Beppon&apos; with characteristics that are unclear and which simply do not have any evidence to prove that they belong to Aobyoshi-bon or Kawachi-bon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>古伝本系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old tradition line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old tradition line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old tradition line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>古伝本系別本とは青表紙本や河内本が成立する以前の本文を伝えていると考えられている写本をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old tradition line Beppon are manuscripts which seem to contain the text before Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon were completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old tradition line Beppon are manuscripts which seem to contain the text before Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon were completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old tradition line Beppon are manuscripts which seem to contain the text before Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon were completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>甲南女子大学所蔵の伝藤原為家筆本が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The manuscript, owned by Konan Women&apos;s University, is said to have been written by FUJIWARA no Tameie is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manuscript, owned by Konan Women&apos;s University, said to have been written by FUJIWARA no Tameie is famous.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manuscript, owned by Konan Women&apos;s University, said to have been written by FUJIWARA no Tameie is famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、古伝本系別本であるかどうかは書写年代によって決まるものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether the manuscript belongs to the old tradition line or not does not necessarily depend on the year of the transcription.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether the manuscript belongs to the old traditional line or not does not necessarily depend upon the year of transcription.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether the manuscript belongs to the old traditional line or not does not necessarily depend upon the year of transcription.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>確かに青表紙本や河内本が成立する以前に存在した写本は、すでに失われたと考えられる紫式部の自筆本等を含め、全てこの古伝本系別本ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is certain that all the manuscripts which appeared before completion of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon, including the manuscripts in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s own handwriting which have been considered already lost, belong to this old traditional line of Beppon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is certain that all the manuscripts that appeared before completion of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon, including the manuscripts in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s own handwriting which have been considered already lost, belong to this old traditional line of Beppon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is certain that all the manuscripts that appeared before completion of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon, including the manuscripts in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s own handwriting which have been considered already lost, belong to this old traditional line of Beppon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、写本の性格は書写の元になった写本の性格によって決まるため、河内本や青表紙本の成立以後、例えば江戸時代に作られた写本であっても元になる写本が古伝本系別本であれば出来上がった写本も古伝本系別本でありうる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, distinction of manuscripts depends on the original manuscript from which they were transcribed, so the manuscripts which were made after the completion of Kawachi-bon and Aobyoshi-bon, or the one which was made even during the Edo period, could belong to the old traditional line manuscripts if they were based on the old traditional version.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, distinction of manuscripts depends upon the original manuscript from which they were transcribed, so the manuscripts made after the completion of Kawachi-bon and Aobyoshi-bon, or those made even during the Edo period, could belong to the old traditional line manuscripts if they were based upon the old traditional version.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, distinction of manuscripts depends upon the original manuscript from which they were transcribed, so the manuscripts made after the completion of Kawachi-bon and Aobyoshi-bon, or those made even during the Edo period, could belong to the old traditional line manuscripts if they were based upon the old traditional version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>混成本文系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mixed texts line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mixed texts line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mixed texts line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>混成本文系の別本とは、青表紙本や河内本が成立して以後に成立した複数の系統の本文が混じった本文を有する伝本のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mixed texts line of Beppon refers to existing manuscripts which contain the text of several groups of manuscript completed after Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mixed texts line of Beppon refers to existing manuscripts which contain the text of several groups of manuscripts completed after Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mixed texts line of Beppon refers to existing manuscripts which contain the text of several groups of manuscripts completed after Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>混成本文系別本に分類される別本については、以下のようなさまざまな形での混成が考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Beppon which belong to the mixed texts line, there are the following various types of mixture:Mixture of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bonMixture of Aobyoshi-bon and old traditional manuscript Mixture of Kawachi-bon and old traditional manuscript</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Beppon which belong to the mixed texts line, there are the following various types of mixture:Mixture of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bonMixture of Aobyoshi-bon and old traditional manuscript Mixture of Kawachi-bon and old traditional manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Beppon which belong to the mixed texts line, there are the following various types of mixture.</e>
<cmt>本文を分け、それそれ英文を充てました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>青表紙本と河内本との混成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mixture of Aobyoshi-bon and Kawachi-bon</e>
<cmt>本文を分け、それそれ英文を充てました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>青表紙本と古伝本との混成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mixture of Aobyoshi-bon and old traditional manuscript</e>
<cmt>本文を分け、それそれ英文を充てました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>河内本と古伝本との混成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mixture of Kawachi-bon and old traditional manuscript</e>
<cmt>本文を分け、それそれ英文を充てました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>また混成の原因には元々あった本文に異なる系統の本文を校合することによる混成の発生と一部分が欠けた写本に残った部分の本文と異なる系統の本文を持つ写本によって補ったことによって発生した混成とが存在すると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two reasons for mixture of the text; one is that when the manuscript was collated, the different group of text was added to the original text, while the other is that the manuscript whose text was partly missing was supplemented by the different group of text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two reasons for the mixture of the text; one is that when the manuscript was collated, the different group of text was added to the original text, while the other is that the manuscript where the text was partly missing was supplemented by a different group of text.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two reasons for the mixture of the text; one is that when the manuscript was collated, the different group of text was added to the original text, while the other is that the manuscript where the text was partly missing was supplemented by a different group of text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>注釈的本文系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annotative texts line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annotative texts line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annotative texts line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>注釈的本文系の別本とは、絵詞・古註釈・古系図等に引用されて残存する註釈的意図によつて取扱はれた本文をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annotative texts line of Beppon refers to the existing annotations which were originally explanations on picture scrolls, old annotations, old genealogies, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annotative texts line of Beppon refers to the existing annotations which were originally explanations on picture scrolls, old annotations, old genealogies, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annotative texts line of Beppon refers to the existing annotations which were originally explanations on picture scrolls, old annotations, old genealogies, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これらの中に含まれる本文は、通常の写本の中にある本文と比べて何らかの意図により改変されている可能性があると考えられることから通常の写本の中にある本文とは別の扱いをする必要があると考えられており、そのためにこれらをまとめて一つのグループとして取り扱っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with the regular texts of the manuscript, it could be considered that some of them were changed on purpose, so some people claim that these texts should be treated in a different way from the regular ones, therefore these are treated together as one group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with the regular texts of the manuscript, it could be considered that some were changed on purpose, so some people claim that these texts should be treated in a different way from the regular ones, therefore these are treated together as one group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with the regular texts of the manuscript, it could be considered that some were changed on purpose, so some people claim that these texts should be treated in a different way from the regular ones, therefore these are treated together as one group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="36">
<j>二分類説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theories of two groups</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theories of two groups</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theories of two groups</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>阿部秋生により唱えられたもので、「もし青表紙本が藤原定家の目の前にあったある写本（当然これは古伝本系の別本の一つである）の中の一つを忠実に写し取ったものであるならば、青表紙本とは実は古伝本系別本の一つであるということになる。」という考え方をもとに、青表紙本を別本に含めて考えることにより、源氏物語の本文を河内本と別本の二系統に分類する考え方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a theory advocated by Akio ABE that Aobyoshi-bon could be included in the Beppon group, so the texts of The Tale of Genji are divided into two groups, Kawachi-bon and Beppon lines, which was based on the idea that &apos;if Aobyoshi-bon had been a manuscript faithfully transcribed from the manuscript (one of the Beppon of the old traditional line in those days) which had been right in front of FUJIWARA no Teika, the Aobyoshi-bon, in fact, would be one of the Beppon of the old traditional line.&apos;</e>
<cmt>2つに分かれていたセルを統合</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a theory advocated by Akio ABE that Aobyoshi-bon could be included in the Beppon group, so the texts of The Tale of Genji are divided into two groups, Kawachi-bon and Beppon lines, which was based on the idea that &apos;if Aobyoshi-bon had been a manuscript faithfully transcribed from the manuscript (one of the Beppon of the old traditional line in those days) which had been right in front of FUJIWARA no Teika, the Aobyoshi-bon, in fact, would be one of the Beppon of the old traditional line.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a theory advocated by Akio ABE that Aobyoshi-bon could be included in the Beppon group, so the texts of The Tale of Genji are divided into two groups, Kawachi-bon and Beppon lines, which was based on the idea that &apos;if Aobyoshi-bon had been a manuscript faithfully transcribed from the manuscript (one of the Beppon of the old traditional line in those days) which had been right in front of FUJIWARA no Teika, the Aobyoshi-bon, in fact, would be one of the Beppon of the old traditional line.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="38">
<j>主な写本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major manuscripts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major manuscripts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major manuscripts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この中には一揃いの写本がある巻では青表紙本であり、別のある巻では河内本であり、またある巻では別本であるということもしばしば起きる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the following set of manuscripts often contain the volumes which belong to the different group of manuscript, for example, one volume belongs to Aobyoshi-bon, but another volume is Kawachi-bon, or Beppon.</e>
<cmt>少し言葉を補って訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the following set of manuscripts often contain the volumes which belong to a different group of manuscripts, for example, one volume belongs to Aobyoshi-bon, but another volume is Kawachi-bon, or Beppon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the following set of manuscripts often contain the volumes which belong to a different group of manuscripts, for example, one volume belongs to Aobyoshi-bon, but another volume is Kawachi-bon, or Beppon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="40">
<j>陽明文庫本 『源氏物語別本集成』の底本として採用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomei bunko bon (literally, the Yomei Archives manuscript), which was adopted as the original book of &quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomei bunko bon (literally, the Yomei Archives manuscript), adopted as the original book of &quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomei bunko bon (literally, the Yomei Archives manuscript), adopted as the original book of &quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="41">
<j>国冬本 天理大学図書館蔵・伝津守国冬筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunifuyu-hon manuscript owned by Tenri University Library, attributed to Kunifuyu TSUMORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunifuyu-hon manuscript owned by Tenri University Library, attributed to Kunifuyu TSUMORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunifuyu-hon manuscript owned by Tenri University Library, attributed to Kunifuyu TSUMORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>阿里莫本 阿里莫神社旧蔵・天理図書館蔵・高坂松陰筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arima-bon manuscript previously owned by Arimaka-jinja Shrine, now owned by Tenri Library</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arima-bon manuscript previously owned by Arimaka-jinja Shrine, now owned by Tenri Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arima-bon manuscript previously owned by Arimaka-jinja Shrine, now owned by Tenri Library, attributed to Shoin KOSAKA</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>麦生本 天理図書館蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munyu-bon manuscript owned by Tenri University Library</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munyu-bon manuscript owned by Tenri University Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munyu-bon manuscript owned by Tenri Library</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて、Tenri Library としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>穂久迩文庫本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honokuni Bunko-bon manuscript</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honokuni Bunko-bon manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honokuni Bunko-bon manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>桃園文庫本 東海大学桃園文庫蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toen Bunko-bon manuscript owned by Tokai University Toen Bunko Library</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toen Bunko-bon manuscript owned by Tokai University Toen Bunko Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toen Bunko-bon manuscript owned by Tokai University Toen Bunko Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>東京大学本 東京大学附属図書館蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo University manuscript owned by Tokyo University Affiliated Library</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo University manuscript owned by Tokyo University Affiliated Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo University manuscript owned by Tokyo University Affiliated Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>鶴見大学本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsurumi University manuscript</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsurumi University manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsurumi University manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>中京大学本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chukyo University manuscript</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chukyo University manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chukyo University manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>日本大学本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon University manuscript</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon University manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon University manuscript</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>飯島本 飯島春敬旧蔵本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ijima-bon manuscript previously owned by Shunkei IIJIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ijima-bon manuscript previously owned by Shunkei IIJIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iijima-bon manuscript previously owned by Shunkei IIJIMA</e>
<cmt>Iijima としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="51">
<j>校本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Variorum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Variorum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variorum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>校異を収録した本として、次のようなものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Books which collected differences among the texts are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Books which collected differences among the texts are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Books which collected differences among the texts are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="53">
<j>『源氏物語大成 校異篇』池田亀鑑編（中央公論社、1953年〜）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genji monogatari taisei Koi hen&quot; edited by Kikan IKEDA (Chuo Koronsha, since 1953)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genji monogatari taisei Koi hen&quot; edited by Kikan IKEDA (Chuo Koronsha, since 1953)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genji monogatari taisei Koi hen&quot; edited by Kikan IKEDA (Chuo Koronsha, since 1953)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>『源氏物語別本集成』（全15巻）伊井春樹他源氏物語別本集成刊行会（おうふう、1989年3月～2002年10月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus&quot; (15 volumes in total) Haruki II et al. Publishing The Tale of Genji Betsubon Corpus Committee (Ofu, March 1989-October 2002)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus&quot; (15 volumes in total) Haruki II et al. Publishing The Tale of Genji Betsubon Corpus Committee (Ofu, March 1989-October 2002)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus&quot; (15 volumes in total) Haruki II et al. Committee for Publishing The Tale of Genji Betsubon Corpus (Ofu, March 1989 - October 2002)</e>
<cmt>刊行会→Committee for としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>『源氏物語別本集成　続』（全15巻の予定）伊井春樹他源氏物語別本集成刊行会（おうふう、2005年～）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus 2&quot; (scheduled to be 15 volumes in total) Haruki II et al. Publishing The Tale of Genji Betsubon Corpus Committee (Ofu, since 2005)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus 2&quot; (scheduled to be 15 volumes in total) Haruki II et al. Publishing The Tale of Genji Betsubon Corpus Committee (Ofu, since 2005)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genji Betsubon, Another Tale of Genji corpus 2&quot; (scheduled to be 15 volumes in total) Haruki II et al. Committee for Publishing The Tale of Genji Betsubon Corpus (Ofu, since 2005)</e>
<cmt>刊行会→Committee for としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>