<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>拾遺和歌集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shui wakashu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shui wakashu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shui wakashu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『拾遺和歌集』（しゅういわかしゅう）は、古今和歌集・後撰和歌集に次ぐ第三番目の勅撰和歌集で、いわゆる「三代集」の最後にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shui wakashu&quot; is the third imperial anthology of Japanese poetry after Kokin wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese poems) and Gosen wakashu (Later Collection of Japanese poems), and is the last one of the so called &quot;Sandai shu&quot; (The Collections of Three Eras).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shui wakashu&quot; is the third imperial anthology of Japanese poetry after Kokin wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese poems) and Gosen wakashu (Later Collection of Japanese poems), and is the last one of the so called &quot;Sandai shu&quot; (The Collections of Three Eras).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shui wakashu&quot; is the third imperial anthology of Japanese poetry after Kokin wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese poems) and Gosen wakashu (Later Collection of Japanese poems), and is the last one of the so called &apos;Sandai shu&apos; (The Collections of Three Eras).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一条天皇の代、寛弘三年（1006）頃の成立か。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have been compiled around 1006, during the reign of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have been compiled around 1006, during the reign of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been compiled around 1006, during the reign of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古来、花山天皇の親撰もしくは院が藤原長能・源道済に撰進させたといわれてきたが、確証はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said since ancient times that Emperor Kazan selected the poems himself, or he ordered FUJIWARA no Nagato (or Nagayoshi) and MINAMOTO no Michinari to select them, but there is no positive proof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said since ancient times that Emperor Kazan selected the poems himself, or he ordered FUJIWARA no Nagato (or Nagayoshi) and MINAMOTO no Michinari to select them, but there is no positive proof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said since ancient times that Emperor Kazan selected the poems himself, or he ordered FUJIWARA no Nagato (or Nagayoshi) and MINAMOTO no Michinari to select them, but there is no positive proof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>先行する二つの勅撰集と違い、和歌所が置かれなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the previous two imperial collections, &quot;wakadokoro&quot; (an office for selecting poems) was not set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the previous two imperial collections, &quot;wakadokoro&quot; (an office for selecting poems) was not set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the previous two imperial collections, wakadokoro (an office for selecting poems) was not set up.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原公任の撰という『拾遺抄』との命名の相似性を考え、それをベースに編まれたと思われる（両者の先後関係については、古来論争が続いて来たが、近代になって拾遺抄から拾遺集へとの説が固着した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought to have been compiled based on &quot;Shui sho&quot; selected by FUJIWARA no Kinto considering the similarity with the name (the issue of which one was the former was controversial for a long time, but in modern days the theory that &quot;Shui sho&quot; was the former has been established).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to have been compiled based on &quot;Shui sho&quot; selected by FUJIWARA no Kinto, considering the similarity with the name (the issue of which one was the earlier was controversial for a long time, but in modern days the theory that &quot;Shui sho&quot; was the earlier has been established).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought to have been compiled based on &quot;Shui sho&quot; selected by FUJIWARA no Kinto, considering the similarity with the name (the issue of which one was the earlier was controversial for a long time, but in modern days the theory that &quot;Shui sho&quot; was the earlier has been established).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>春、夏、秋、冬、賀、別、物名、雑（上・下）、神楽歌、恋（五巻）、雑春、雑秋、雑賀、雑恋、哀傷の二十巻、約1350首からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of approximately 1350 poems: twenty volumes organized under headings of spring, summer, autumn, winter, congratulations, parting, acrostics, miscellaneous (One, Two), &quot;Kagura uta&quot; (poems, the theme of which is sacred Shinto dancing), love (five volumes), miscellaneous spring, miscellaneous autumn, miscellaneous congratulations, miscellaneous love, and laments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of approximately 1350 poems: twenty volumes organized under headings of spring, summer, autumn, winter, congratulations, parting, acrostics, miscellaneous (One, Two), &quot;Kagura uta&quot; (poems, the theme of which is sacred Shinto dancing), love (five volumes), miscellaneous spring, miscellaneous autumn, miscellaneous congratulations, miscellaneous love, and laments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of approximately 1350 poems: twenty volumes organized under headings of spring, summer, autumn, winter, congratulations, parting, acrostics, miscellaneous (One, Two), Kagura uta (poems, the theme of which is sacred Shinto dancing), love (five volumes), miscellaneous spring, miscellaneous autumn, miscellaneous congratulations, miscellaneous love, and laments.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>雑春・雑恋といった部類を持つ構成はかなり独創的なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The composition including headings of miscellaneous spring and miscellaneous love is quite original.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The composition inclusion of headings of miscellaneous spring and miscellaneous love is quite original.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The composition inclusion of headings of miscellaneous spring and miscellaneous love is quite original.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>「拾遺」の名義は前代の勅撰集に漏れた秀歌を拾い集める意で、その名の通り、この集では紀貫之（107首）をはじめとする古今歌人が引き続き多数入集する一方、柿本人麻呂（104首）ら万葉集歌人が再評価され、大中臣能宣（59首）・清原元輔（48首）・平兼盛（39首）ら後撰集時代の歌人の作が新たに補われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Shui&quot; means to glean excellent poems that were not selected in the previous imperial collections, and by definition, while many poets from Kokin wakashu including KI no Tsurayuki (107) were selected again, poets from Manyo shu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) such as KAKINOMOTO Hitomaro (104) were re-evaluated, and poems by ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu (59), KIYOHARA no Motosuke (48) and TAIRA no Kanemori (39) from Gosen wakashu era were added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Shui&quot; means to glean excellent poems that had not been selected in the previous imperial collections, and by definition, while many poets from Kokin wakashu including KI no Tsurayuki (107) were selected again, poets from Manyo shu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) such as KAKINOMOTO Hitomaro (104) were re-evaluated, and poems by ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu (59), KIYOHARA no Motosuke (48) and TAIRA no Kanemori (39) from Gosen wakashu era were added.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Shui&apos; means to glean excellent poems that had not been selected in the previous imperial collections, and by definition, while many poets from Kokin wakashu including KI no Tsurayuki (107) were selected again, poets from Manyo shu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) such as KAKINOMOTO Hitomaro (104) were re-evaluated, and poems by ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu (59), KIYOHARA no Motosuke (48) and TAIRA no Kanemori (39) from Gosen wakashu era were added.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、徽子女王・藤原道綱母・藤原公任などの当代歌人も登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, contemporary poets such as Kishi Joo (high ranking lady in the court), FUJIWARA no Michitsuna&apos;s Mother, and FUJIWARA no Kinto were included.</e>
<cmt>女王という語の意味がはっきりわかりませんでしたが、斎宮女御とも呼ばれることから、女御の意味を()内に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, contemporary poets such as Kishi Joo (high ranking lady in the court), FUJIWARA no Michitsuna&apos;s Mother, and FUJIWARA no Kinto were included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, contemporary poets such as Kishi Joo (high ranking lady in the court), FUJIWARA no Michitsuna&apos;s Mother, and FUJIWARA no Kinto were included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>物名部において、卑官の藤原輔相が37首も採られているのも興味深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is interesting that as many as 37poems by FUJIWARA no Sukemi, who is in a lower ranking post, were selected in the acrostics section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is interesting that as many as 37poems by FUJIWARA no Sukemi, who was in a lower ranking post, were selected in the acrostics section.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is interesting that as many as 37 poems by FUJIWARA no Sukemi, who was in a lower ranking post, were selected in the acrostics section.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>『拾遺集』は総じて平明優美な歌風で、賀歌・屏風歌・歌合など晴れの歌が多いが、殊に恋歌はすぐれ、小倉百人一首に8首も採られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shui shu&quot; (abridged form of Shui wakashu) in general has a plain and graceful style, and includes many poems for a formal occasion such as &quot;ga no uta&quot; (poems for congratulations), &quot;byobu uta&quot; (poems matching with a painting on the byobu, folding screen), and poems for &quot;uta awase&quot; (poetry competition), and especially includes excellent ones of love, eight of which were selected for &quot;Ogura Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (the Ogura One Hundred Poets, One Poem Each).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shui shu&quot; (abridged form of Shui wakashu) in general has a plain and graceful style, and includes many poems for formal occasions such as &quot;ga no uta&quot; (poems for congratulations), &quot;byobu uta&quot; (poems matching with a painting on the byobu, folding screen), and poems for &quot;uta awase&quot; (poetry competition), and especially includes excellent ones of love, eight of which were selected for &quot;Ogura Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (the Ogura One Hundred Poets, One Poem Each).</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shui shu (abridged form of Shui wakashu) in general has a plain and graceful style, and includes many poems for formal occasions such as ga no uta (poems for congratulations), byobu uta (poems matching with a painting on the byobu, folding screen), and poems for uta awase (poetry competition), and especially includes excellent ones of love, eight of which were selected for Ogura Hyakunin Isshu (the Ogura One Hundred Poets, One Poem Each).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), SK(id:64397), さららゆら(id:12274), Yume149(id:17504), Jennifer(id:6990), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), Kiev(id:13022), Yuming(id:17854), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>