<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>薫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>薫（かおる）は、紫式部の物語『源氏物語』に登場する架空の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru is a fictional character who appears in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s novel &quot;Genji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru is a fictional character who appears in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s novel &quot;Genji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru is a fictional character who appears in Murasaki Shikibu&apos;s novel &quot;Genji Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>いわゆる第三部「宇治十帖」の中心人物の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is one of leading figures for Part III, so-called &quot;Uji Jujo (Ten Quires of Uji).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is one of leading figures in Part III, so-called &quot;Uji Jujo (Ten Quires of Uji).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is one of leading figures in Part III, so-called &apos;Uji Jujo&apos; (Ten Quires of Uji).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>薫の君（かおるのきみ）、薫大将（かおるだいしょう、かおるのたいしょう）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also called Kaoru no Kimi, Kaoru Daisho (or, Kaoru no Taisho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also called Kaoru no Kimi, Kaoru Daisho (or, Kaoru no Taisho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also called Kaoru no Kimi, Kaoru Daisho (or, Kaoru no Taisho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「薫」は本名ではなく、生まれつき身体にえもいわれぬ芳香を帯びていたことに因む通称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kaoru&quot; is not his real name, but a nickname based on the fact that he has an indefinable sweet scent by nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kaoru&quot; is not his real name, but a nickname based on the fact that he has an indefinable sweet scent by nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru&apos; was not his real name, but a nickname based on the fact that he had an indefinable sweet scent by nature.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>表向きは光源氏の次男だが、実は柏木 (源氏物語)の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he is ostensibly the second son of Hikaru Genji, he is a child of Kashiwagi (Genji Monogatari).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he is ostensibly the second son of Hikaru Genji, he is a child of Kashiwagi (Genji Monogatari).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was ostensibly the second son of Hikaru Genji, he was actually the child of Kashiwagi (Genji Monogatari).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は源氏の正妻女三宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is Onna Sannomiya, who was Genji&apos;s legitimate wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother is Onna Sannomiya, who was Genji&apos;s legitimate wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Genji&apos;s legitimate wife, Onna Sannomiya.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>源氏48歳の春に誕生（「柏木」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in the spring when Genji was forty-eight years old (&quot;Kashiwagi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in the spring when Genji was forty-eight years old (&quot;Kashiwagi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji was forty-eight years old when he was born in spring (&apos;Kashiwagi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>産養が盛大に行われるが、その一方彼の誕生は決して喜ばれたものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although ubuyashinai (party to celebrate birth of a baby) was carried out in grand style, his birth was not pleased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although ubuyashinai (party to celebrate the birth of a baby) was carried out in a grand style, his birth did not please.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although ubuyashinai (party to celebrate the birth of a baby) was carried out as a grand event, his birth was not particularly welcomed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>出産後母女三宮は突然出家、父源氏も過去の因果が忘れられず、表向きは可愛がるもうちとけられずにいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After childbirth, his mother, Onna Sannomiya suddenly became a priest and his father, Genji, also could not forget past karma and although he outwardly treat the baby kindly but he could not behave unreserved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After childbirth, his mother, Onna Sannomiya suddenly became a priest and his father, Genji, also could not forget past karma and although he outwardly treated the baby kindly, he could not behave unreserved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After childbirth, Onna Sannomiya, his mother, suddenly became a nun and his father, Genji, also could not forget past karma and although he outwardly treated the baby kindly, he could not do so without reservation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>六条院で育ち、源氏没後は、子のなかった冷泉帝（表向きは桐壺帝の第十皇子、実は源氏の子）と秋好中宮に実子同然にかわいがられ育つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was brought up in Rokujoin and, after Genji&apos;s death, he was brought up by the Emperor Reizei (ostensibly, tenth Imperial Prince of the Emperor Kiritsubo, but in reality, a Genji&apos;s child) and Akikonomu Chugu,, who did not have any child between them, and treated favorably same as their real child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was brought up in Rokujoin and, after Genji&apos;s death, he was brought up by Emperor Reizei (ostensibly, tenth Imperial Prince of the Emperor Kiritsubo, but in reality, Genji&apos;s child) and Akikonomu Chugu,, who did not have any children between them, and treated him favorably, the same as if he were their own real child.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was brought up iat Rokujoin and, after Genji&apos;s death, he was brought up by Emperor Reizei (tenth Imperial Prince of the Emperor Kiritsubo, but in reality, Genji&apos;s child) and Akikonomu Chugu, who did not have any children and they treated him favorably as if he were their own real child.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>14歳で元服、二月に中将、秋に右近中将、19歳で宰相中将と順調に昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of fourteen, he celebrated his coming of age and he was promoted smoothly, in February, appointed to Chujo (Middle Captain) and in the autumn Ukon chujo and at the age of nineteen, &quot;Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain).&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of fourteen, he celebrated his coming of age and he was promoted smoothly, in February, appointed to Chujo (Middle Captain) and in the autumn Ukon chujo and at the age of nineteen, &quot;Saisho no Chujo (Consultant Captain).&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of fourteen, he celebrated his coming of age and was steadily promoted in February as Chujo (Middle Captain) and in the autumn, Ukon chujo and at the age of nineteen, &apos;Saisho no Chujo&apos; (Consultant Captain).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>幼馴染の匂宮と並び、「光る君」と呼ばれた光源氏の栄華を継ぐ者として、世間では「匂う兵部卿、薫る中将」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a successor of prosperity of Hikaru Genji, who was called &quot;Hikaru Gimi (literally, shining boy)&quot;, he was called, together with Nioumiya, who was his childhood friend, &quot;Niou Hyobukyo (Minister of Hyobusho (Ministry of Military), Kaoru Chujo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a successor of prosperity of Hikaru Genji, who was called &quot;Hikaru Gimi (literally, shining boy),&quot; he was called, together with Nioumiya, who was his childhood friend, &quot;Niou Hyobukyo (Minister of Hyobusho (Ministry of the Military), Kaoru Chujo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a successor to the prosperity of Hikaru Genji, who was called &apos;Hikaru Gimi&apos; (literally, shining boy), he was called together with his childhood friend, Nioumiya, &apos;Niou Hyobukyo (Minister of Hyobusho (Ministry of the Military), Kaoru Chujo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>（「匂宮」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Nioumiya&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Nioumiya&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Nioumiya&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>高貴の出自で、恵まれた環境で育ったが、幼いころから自己の出生に疑念を感じ、悶々とした日々を過ごしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he had a noble root and he wa brought up in blessed environment, he had a doubt since his childhoo about his birth and passed disconted days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he had noble roots and he was brought up in a blessed environment, he had a doubts since childhood about his birth and passed discontented days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he had noble roots and he was brought up in a blessed environment, he had doubts since childhood about his birth and spent discontented days.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>仏教に帰依しだすのもこの頃からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around this time, he began to believe Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, he began to believe Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He began to believe Buddhism around this time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ある時宇治市に俗聖（出家せず俗のまま戒律を守り仏道修行する人）がいるという噂を聞き、宇治八の宮（桐壺帝の皇子、光源氏の異母弟）邸を訪れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, he heard a rumor that there was a zokuhijiri (person who is engaged in Buddhist training without becoming a priest) in Uji City, he visited a mansion of Uji Hachinomiya (Imperial Prince of the Emperor Kiritsubo, Hikaru Genji&apos;s younger brother from different mother).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, he heard a rumor that there was a zokuhijiri (person who is engaged in Buddhist training without becoming a priest) in Uji City, he visited a mansion of Uji Hachinomiya (Imperial Prince of the Emperor Kiritsubo, Hikaru Genji&apos;s younger brother from a different mother).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, he heard a rumor that there was a zokuhijiri (person who is engaged in Buddhist training without becoming a priest) in Uji City and visited the mansion of Uji Hachinomiya (Imperial Prince of the Emperor Kiritsubo, Hikaru Genji&apos;s younger brother from a different mother).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>ここから始まるのがいわゆる「宇治十帖」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uji Jujo (Ten Quires of Uji) start on this point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uji Jujo (Ten Quires of Uji) started at this point.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji Jujo&apos; (Ten Stories of Uji) starts from this point.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>律儀で細かな心遣いに長けたまめ人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a faithful person with kind consideration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a faithful person with kind and considerate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was faithful, kind and considerate person.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一方で、優柔不断で特に女性関係には消極的だが、身分低い女房などが相手の時は積極的に事を運ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he was irresolute and passive in relations with women, but he quickly carried out things if the partner is a low-level court lady.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he was irresolute and passive in relations with women, but quickly carried things out if his partner was a low-level court lady.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he had indecisiveness and especially passive in relationships with women, but carried things out quickly if his partner was a lower level court lady.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>偶然垣間見た宇治の大君（おおいぎみ、八の宮の長女）に思いを寄せるが、受け入れられぬまま死に別れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fell in love with Oigimi (first daughter of Hachinomiya) in Uji, whom he caught a glimpse of her by change but she died before his love is accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fell in love with Oigimi (the first daughter of Hachinomiya) in Uji, whom he caught a glimpse of her by chance, but she died before his love was accepted.</e>
<cmt>spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fell in love with Oigimi (first daughter of Hachinomiya) in Uji when he caught a glimpse of her by chance, but she died before his love was accepted.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その傷心から一時は宇治の中の君（八の宮の次女で大君の同母妹、匂宮の妻）に迫り、さらにその後大君に生き写しの田舎育ちの娘浮舟 (源氏物語)（大君と中の君の異母妹）を形代にし、宇治の邸に囲わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of grief from this, he once approached Nakanokimi (second daughter of Hachinomiya and younger sister from same mother of Oigimi; wife of Nioumiya) in Uji and, later, took Ukifune (Genji Monogatari)(younger sister from different mother of Oigiki and Nakanokimi) who was exactly like Oigimi and brought up in the country side as a representation as and kept her in the mansion in Uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this grief, he once approached Nakanokimi (the second daughter of Hachinomiya and younger sister fromthe same mother of Oigimi; wife of Nioumiya) in Uji and, later, took Ukifune (Genji Monogatari)(younger sister from a different mother of Oigiki and Nakanokimi) who was exactly like Oigimi and was brought up in the country side and kept her in a mansion in Uji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of his grief, he once approached Nakanokimi (second daughter of Hachinomiya and younger sister from the same mother of Oigimi; wife of Nioumiya) in Uji and, later, took Ukifune (Genji Monogatari) (younger sister from a different mother of Oigimi and Nakanokimi) who looked exactly like Oigimi and was brought up in the countryside, as katashiro (representation of a sacred object) and kept her in a mansion in Uji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし浮舟は薫とその存在を知って現れた匂宮の二人の間で心が揺れ動き、淀川に入水してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ukifune was in two minds between Kaoru and Nioumiya, who knew her existence and appeared before her and threw herself into the Yodogawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ukifune was of two minds between Kaoru and Nioumiya, who knew her existence and appeared before her and she threw herself into the Yodogawa River.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ukifune was of two minds between Kaoru and Nioumiya, who appeared before her when he knew of her existence and she threw herself into the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>（「橋姫 (源氏物語)」～「浮舟」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Hashihime (Genji Monogatari)&quot; through &quot;Ukifune&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Hashihime (Genji Monogatari)&quot; through &quot;Ukifune&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Hashihime&apos; (Genji Monogatari) through to &apos;Ukifune&apos;)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>一方、今上帝 (源氏物語)の女二宮が降嫁し北の方となり、栄華はこの上なきものとなる（権大納言兼右大将に昇進したのもこのころ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Onna Ninomiya of the current emperor (Genji Monogatari) marries him and became his legitimate wife and his prosperity became incomparable (also, he was promoted to Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) and also Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) around this time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Onna Ninomiya of the current emperor (Genji Monogatari) married him and became his legitimate wife and his prosperity became incomparable) also, he was promoted to Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) and also Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) around this time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, he married Onna Ninomiya of the current emperor (Genji Monogatari) who became his legitimate wife and his prosperity reached its height (he was also promoted to Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) and Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) around this time).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし妻とあまり接することはなく、浮舟亡き後は今上帝の女一宮（母は明石中宮）を思って悶々と過ごしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he did not contact his wife so often and, after Ukifune&apos;s death, he passed discontented days thinking about Onna Ichinomiya of the current emperor (mother was Akashi Chugu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he did not contact his wife so often and, after Ukifune&apos;s death, he passed his days discontented, thinking about Onna Ichinomiya of the current emperor (her mother was Akashi Chugu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he did not frequently interact with his wife and after Ukifune&apos;s death, he passed his days discontented, thinking about Onna Ichinomiya, daughter of the current emperor (her mother was Akashi Chugu).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ある時氷を弄んでいる女一宮の美しい姿を垣間見た時は、それと同じ装いを女二宮にさせて気の慰みにしようとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he caught a glimpse of beautiful figure of Onna Ichinomiya, who was playing with ice, he tried to have a joy by making Onna Ninomiya wear same costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he caught a glimpse of the beautiful figure of Onna Ichinomiya, who was playing with ice, he tried to have some fun by making Onna Ninomiya wear the same costume.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he caught a glimpse of the beautiful figure of Onna Ichinomiya, who was playing with ice, he tried to have some fun by making Onna Ninomiya wear the same costume.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>（「宿木」「蜻蛉 (源氏物語)」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Yadorigi&quot;, &quot;Kagero (Mayfly) (Genji Monogatari&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Yadorigi,&quot; &quot;Kagero (Mayfly) (Genji Monogatari&quot;)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Yadorigi,&apos; &apos;Kagero&apos; (Mayfly) (Genji Monogatari))</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>浮舟の葬儀から一周忌を過ぎたある日、明石中宮を通じて浮舟生存の情報を知った薫は、浮舟の異父弟小君に文を持たせ小野の山里へ向かわせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day after the first anniversary of the funeral for Ukifune, he came to know through Akashi no Chugu that Ukifune was alive, he sent Kogimi, who was Ukifune&apos;s younger brother from different father to a village f Ono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day after the first anniversary of the funeral for Ukifune, he came to know through Akashi no Chugu that Ukifune was alive, he sent Kogimi, who was Ukifune&apos;s younger brother from a different father to the village of Ono.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day after the first anniversary of the funeral for Ukifune, Kaoru came to know through Akashi no Chugu that Ukifune was still alive and sent Kogimi, Ukifune&apos;s younger brother from a different father, to the village of Ono.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし尼となり俗世に未練のない浮舟に「所違へにもあらむ（人違いでしょう）」と突っぱねられ、屈辱を味わった薫は「人の隠し据ゑたるにやあらん（どうせ誰か男がいて囲われているんだろう）」と自分を慰めるのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was rejected by Ukifune, who had become a priestess and had no attachment to the secular society, by telling &quot;It must be a mistake,&quot; and humiliated Kaoru consoled himself as &quot;There must be a certain man who is keeping her.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was rejected by Ukifune, who had become a priestess and had no attachment to secular society, by saying &quot;It must be a mistake,&quot; and the humiliated Kaoru consoled himself as &quot;There must be some man who is keeping her.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was rejected by Ukifune, who had become a nun and had no attachment to secular society, saying &apos;You must have the wrong person,&apos; and the humiliated Kaoru consoled himself by thinking &apos;There must be some man who is keeping her.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>（「手習」「夢浮橋」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Tenarai&quot;, &quot;Yume no Ukihashi&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Tenarai,&quot; &quot;Yume no Ukihashi&quot;)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Tenarai,&apos; &apos;Yume no Ukihashi&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>この優柔不断の塊のような鬱屈した主人公像は、『狭衣物語』や『堤中納言物語』などその後の王朝女流文学に多大なる影響を与え、数多くの薫型主人公を生み出すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The image of the main character which looks like an incarnation of irresolution gave great influence to the later dynastic style literature by women writers such as &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari (The Tale of Sagoromo) and Tsutsumi-Chunagon Monogatari (Collection of ten short stories after the late Heian period) and created many Kaoru-like main character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of the main character that looks like an incarnation of an irresolution gave great influence to the later dynastic style literature by women writers such as &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Sagoromo) and &quot;Tsutsumi-Chunagon Monogatari&quot; (Collection of ten short stories after the late Heian period) and created many Kaoru-like main characters.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of the main character full of irresolution greatly influenced later dynastic-style literature by female authors such as &quot;Sagoromo Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Sagoromo) and &quot;Tsutsumi-Chunagon Monogatari&quot; (Collection of ten short stories after the late Heian period) and created many Kaoru-type main characters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>薫が本当に柏木の子であるかどうかについては、光源氏や夕霧 (源氏物語)が幼い薫を見て目元が似ていると感じており（「柏木」「横笛」）、また冷泉帝ら光源氏の血筋は絵画（「絵合」）、柏木ら頭中将の血筋は音楽に秀でているといった描写が常々なされているのに対し、薫は柏木が得意とした琴や、横笛を演奏して頭中将の血筋に近いとされている（「竹河」「宿木」）ことから、間違いないようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the question whether or not Kaoru was really a son of Kashiwagi, it seems to be true that Hikaru Genji and Yugiri (Genji Monogatari) felt that eyes were similar when they saw Kaoru as a small boy (&quot;Kashiwagi,&quot; &quot;Yokobue&quot;) and it was repeatedly described that, while Genji&apos;s line including the Emperor Reizei were good at painting (&quot;Eawase&quot;), the To no Chujo&apos;s line including Kashiwagi were good at musing, and Kaoru played a koto and flute for which Kashiwagi was good and said to be close to the line of To no Chujo (&quot;Takekawa&quot;, &quot;Yadorigi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the question whether or not Kaoru was really the son of Kashiwagi, it seems to be true that Hikaru Genji and Yugiri (Genji Monogatari) felt that their eyes were similar when they saw Kaoru as a small boy (&quot;Kashiwagi,&quot; &quot;Yokobue&quot;) and it was repeatedly described that, while Genji&apos;s line, including Emperor Reizei, were good at painting (&quot;Eawase&quot;), the To no Chujo&apos;s line including Kashiwagi were good at musing, and Kaoru played the koto and flute for which Kashiwagi was good and said to be close to the line of To no Chujo (&quot;Takekawa,&quot; &quot;Yadorigi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the question whether or not Kaoru was really the son of Kashiwagi, it seems to be true that Hikaru Genji and Yugiri (Genji Monogatari) felt that his eyes were similar when they saw Kaoru as a small boy (&apos;Kashiwagi,&apos; &apos;Yokobue&apos;) and it was repeatedly described that, while Genji&apos;s lineage including Emperor Reizei were good at painting (&apos;Eawase&apos;), the To no Chujo&apos;s lineage including Kashiwagi were good at music, and Kaoru played the koto and flute, which Kashiwagi was also good at this shows him to be close to the lineage of To no Chujo (&apos;Takekawa,&apos; &apos;Yadorigi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお薫の出生の秘密を知るのは本人以外では光源氏、実父柏木、母女三宮、小侍従（女三宮の女房）、弁（八の宮の女房、小侍従の従姉妹）の5人で、この他夕霧も薄々事情を察している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than Kaoru himself, Hikaru Genji, Kashiwagi who was the real father, Onna Sannomiya who was his mother, Kojiju (Onna Sannomiya&apos;s waiting maid), and Ben (court lady for Hachinomiya, cousin of Kojiju), and Yugiri also knew the situations to some extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than Kaoru himself, Hikaru Genji, Kashiwagi who was the real father, Onna Sannomiya who was his mother, Kojiju (Onna Sannomiya&apos;s waiting maid), and Ben (court lady for Hachinomiya, cousin of Kojiju), and Yugiri also knew the situations to some extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than Kaoru himself, five people, Hikaru Genji, Kashiwagi who was the real father, Onna Sannomiya who was his mother, Kojiju (Onna Sannomiya&apos;s waiting maid), and Ben (court lady for Hachinomiya, cousin of Kojiju) knew the secret of Kaoru&apos;s birth, and Yugiri also knew the situation to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), Dump(id:26383), 二八(id:10408), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>