<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浮舟 (源氏物語)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune (A Boat upon the Waters) (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune (A Boat upon the Waters) (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune (The Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浮舟（うきふね）は、『源氏物語』五十四帖の巻名の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune is one of the title of fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune is the title of one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune is one of the fifty-four chapters of &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第51帖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the chapter 51.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is chapter 51.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the 51st chapter.</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第三部の一部「宇治十帖」の第7帖にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It coincides with chapter 7 of &quot;Uji Jujo&quot; (ten chapters of Uji), a part of Part 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It coincides with chapter 7 of &quot;Uji Jujo&quot; (ten chapters of Uji), Part 3.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the seventh chapter of &apos;Uji jujo&apos; (The Ten Quires of Uji), a part of the tale&apos;s third section.</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>巻名は、薫の庇護を受けていた女が匂宮に連れ出されて淀川対岸の隠れ家へ向かう途中に詠んだ和歌に因む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This chapter title derived from the waka poem shown below that was composed by a woman under Kaoru&apos;s patronage when she was on her way, after being taken out by Nioumiya, to a hideaway located on the other side of the Yodo River.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This chapter title derived from the waka poem shown below that was composed by a woman under Kaoru&apos;s patronage when she was on her way, after being taken out by Nioumiya, to a hideaway located on the other side of the Yodo River.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of this chapter was derived from the waka poetry composed by a woman under Kaoru&apos;s patronage when she was on her way, after being taken out by Nioumiya, to a hideaway located on the other side of the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と一部表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「橘の小島の色はかはらじをこのうき舟ぞゆくへ知られぬ」（橘の茂る小島の色のようにあなたの心は変わらないかも知れないけれど、水に浮く小舟のような私の身は不安定でどこへ漂ってゆくかも知れません）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tachibana no kojima no iro ha kawaraji o, kono ukifune zo yukue shirarenu&quot; (While I believe your heart will not change like the color of island with tachibana (mandarin orange tree) thickly grown, I am not sure where I am going to since I am in the unstable position like Ukifune.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tachibana no kojima no iro ha kawaraji o, kono ukifune zo yukue shirarenu&quot; (While I believe your heart will not change like the color of islands with tachibana (mandarin orange tree) thickly grown, I am not sure where I am going to since I am in an unstable position like Ukifune.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tachibana no kojima no iro ha kawaraji o, kono ukifune zo yukue shirarenu&quot; (While I believe your heart will not change like the color of islands with tachibana (mandarin orange tree) thickly grown, I am not sure where I am going to since I am in an unstable position like Ukifune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>『源氏物語』に登場する架空の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune is the name of fictitious person appeared in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune is the name of a fictitious person who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune is the name of a fictitious person who appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>第三部「宇治十帖」の中心人物の一人で、その呼称は巻名の由来ともなった上記の和歌による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is one of the main characters appeared in the Part 3 &quot;Uji Jujo&quot; and her name derived from the above-mentioned waka poem, which was also the origin of the chapter title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is one of the main characters who appears in Part 3, &quot;Uji Jujo&quot; and her name is derived from the above-mentioned waka poem, which was also the origin of the chapter title.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is one of the main characters who appears in &apos;Uji jujo,&apos; a part of the tale&apos;s third section, and her name is derived from the above-mentioned waka poem, which was also the origin of the chapter title.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>詳細は下記。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Detailes are shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details are shown below.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details are shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>帖のあらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline of the chapter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline of the chapter</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>薫27歳の春の話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tale in the spring when Kaoru was 27 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tale tells of the spring when Kaoru was 27 years old.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tale tells of the spring when Kaoru was 27 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>薫は浮舟を宇治市の山荘に放置したまま、訪れるのも間遠であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru left Ukifune unattended at a villa located in Uji City and seldom visited her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru left Ukifune unattended at a villa located in Uji City and seldom visited her.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru left Ukifune unattended at a villa located in Uji City and seldom visited her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一方、匂宮は二条院で見かけた女のことが忘れられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Nioumiya, who once saw a woman at Nijo-in, couldn&apos;t forget this woman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Nioumiya, who once saw her at Nijo-in, couldn&apos;t forget her.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Nioumiya, who once saw her at Nijo-in, couldn&apos;t forget her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>正月、中の君のもとに届いた文を見て女の居所を知った匂宮は、薫の邸の事情に通じている家臣に探らせ、女が薫の囲い人として宇治に住んでいることを知る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he came to know the whereabouts of a woman on the New Year Day seeing a letter delivered to Naka no kimi, Nioumiya made his vassal who was well informed about the internal situations of Kaoru&apos;s residence probe and finally came to know that a woman resided in Uji as Kaoru&apos;s mistress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he came to know the whereabouts of the woman on New Years Day after seeing a letter delivered to Naka no kimi, Nioumiya made his vassal who was well informed about the internal situations of Kaoru&apos;s residence probe and finally came to know that the woman who resided in Uji was Kaoru&apos;s mistress.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he came to know the whereabouts of the woman on New Years Day after seeing a letter delivered to Naka no kimi, Nioumiya made his vassal who was well informed about the internal situations of Kaoru&apos;s residence probe and finally came to know that the woman lives in Uji as Kaoru&apos;s mistress.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>匂宮はある夜、ひそかに宇治を訪れ、薫を装って寝所に忍び入り、浮舟と強引に契りを結んでしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One night, Nioumiya furtively visited Uji, stole into her bedroom pretending Kaoru and coerced Ukifune to sleep together with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One night, Nioumiya furtively visited Uji, stole into her bedroom pretending to be Kaoru and coerced Ukifune to sleep together with him.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One night, Nioumiya furtively visited Uji, stole into her bedroom pretending to be Kaoru and coerced Ukifune to sleep together with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>人違いに気づくも時すでに遅く、浮舟は重大な過失におののく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ukifune realized mistaken identity, it was too late and she shuddered at her serious mistake.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ukifune realized it was someone else, it was too late and she shuddered at her serious mistake.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ukifune realized it was someone else, it was too late and she shuddered at her serious mistake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、心は次第に情熱的な匂宮に惹かれていくのだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she was gradually attracted to passionate Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she gradually became attracted to Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she gradually became attracted to Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>二月、ようやく宇治を訪れた薫は、浮舟の思い悩むさまを女として成長したものと誤解して喜び、京へ迎える約束をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When visiting Uji in February, Kaoru misunderstood Ukifune&apos;s worrying looks as the growth of woman and promised her that he would invite her to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When visiting Uji in February, Kaoru misunderstood Ukifune&apos;s worrying looks as the growth of woman and promised her that he would invite her to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When visiting Uji in February, Kaoru misunderstood Ukifune&apos;s worrying looks as the growth of woman and promised her that he would invite her to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>宮中の詩宴の夜、浮舟を思って古歌を口ずさむ薫の様子に焦りを覚えた匂宮は、雪を冒して再び宇治に赴き、浮舟を淀川対岸の隠れ家へ連れ出し、そこで二日間を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nioumiya, who became impatient when he saw Kaoru was humming an old waka poem with Ukifune in his mind at the night of court poetry feat, revisited Uji despite of snowfall, abducted Ukifune to a hideaway located on the other side of the Yodo River and spent there for two days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nioumiya, who became impatient when he saw Kaoru was humming an old waka poem with Ukifune in his mind at the night of the court poetry reading, revisited Uji despite it snowing, abducted Ukifune to a hideaway located on the other side of the Yodo River and spent two days there.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nioumiya, who became impatient when he saw Kaoru was humming an old waka poem with Ukifune in his mind at the night of the court poetry reading, revisited Uji despite it snowing, abducted Ukifune to a hideaway located on the other side of the Yodo-gawa River and spent two days there.</e>
<cmt>Yodo-gawa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>薫は浮舟を京に迎える準備を進めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru was proceeding the preparations for receiving Ukifune to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru proceeded with preparations for receiving Ukifune in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru proceeded with preparations for receiving Ukifune in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>匂宮はその前に浮舟を引き取ろうと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nioumiya told Ukifune that he would receive her before that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nioumiya told Ukifune that he would receive her before that.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nioumiya told Ukifune that he would receive her before that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>何も知らずに上京の準備を手伝う母中将の君に苦悩を打ち明けることもできず、浮舟は宇治川の流れを耳にしながら物思う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune couldn&apos;t consult her mother Chujo no kimi, who knew nothing and was helping with the preparations for going to Kyoto, and worried while listening to the sound of the Uji River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune couldn&apos;t consult her mother Chujo no kimi, who knew nothing and was helping with the preparations for going to Kyoto, and worried while listening to the sound of the Uji River.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune couldn&apos;t consult her mother Chujo no kimi, who knew nothing and was helping with the preparations for going to Kyoto, and worried while listening to the sound of the Uji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Uji-gawa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ある日、宇治で薫と匂宮両者の使者が鉢合わせしたことからこの秘密は薫に知られ、宇治の邸は薫によって警戒体制が敷かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, this secret came to be known by Kaoru when the messengers of Kaoru and Nioumiya came across in Uji and since then, Uji residence was put on security alert by Kaoru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, Kaoru found out about this secret when the messengers of Kaoru and Nioumiya came across each other in Uji and since then, the Uji residence was put on security alert by Kaoru.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, Kaoru found out about this secret when the messengers of Kaoru and Nioumiya came across each other in Uji and since then, the Uji residence was put on security alert by Kaoru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>薫に恨みの歌を送られ、匂宮との板ばさみになって進退窮まった浮舟はついに死を決意をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune, who received the letter of grudge from Kaoru and was driven into a corner while being caught between Kaoru and Nioumiya, finally resolved to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune, who received a letter of grudge from Kaoru and was driven into a corner while being caught between Kaoru and Nioumiya, finally resolved to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune, who received a letter of grudge from Kaoru and was driven into a corner while being caught between Kaoru and Nioumiya, finally resolved to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>死を間近に、薫や匂宮、母や中の君を恋しく思いながら、浮舟は匂宮と母にのみ最後の文を書きしたためた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately before her death, Ukifune wrote letters only to Nioumiya and her mother though she loved Kaoru, Nioumiya, her mother and Naka no kimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately before her death, Ukifune wrote letters only to Nioumiya and her mother though she loved Kaoru, Nioumiya, her mother, and Naka no kimi.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately before her death, Ukifune wrote letters only to Nioumiya and her mother though she loved Kaoru, Nioumiya, her mother, and Naka no kimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>人物としての浮舟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune as a person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune as a person</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune as a person</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>光源氏の弟である宇治八の宮の三女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the third daughter of Uji Hachi no Miya, a younger brother of Hikaru Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the third daughter of Uji Hachi no Miya, a younger brother of Hikaru Genji.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the third daughter of Uji Hachi no Miya, a younger brother of Hikaru Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>宇治の大君、中の君の異母妹で、特に大君によく似る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a younger sister with the same mother of Uji no O no kimi and Naka no kimi and closely resembled O no kimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a younger sister with the same mother of Uji no O no kimi and Naka no kimi and closely resembled O no kimi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a younger paternal half-sister of Uji no Oikimi and Naka no kimi and closely resembled O no kimi.</e>
<cmt>異母妹　の表現を変更しました。大君→Oikimi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>母はかつて八の宮に仕えていた女房・中将の君（八の宮の北の方の姪）で、このため父八の宮から娘と認知されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As her mother was nyobo (a court lady) Chujo no kimi (a niece of the wife of Hachi no Miya), she was not acknowledged by her father Hachi no Miya as his real daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As her mother was nyobo (a court lady) Chujo no kimi (a niece of the wife of Hachi no Miya), she was not acknowledged by her father Hachi no Miya as his real daughter.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As her mother was nyobo (a court lady) Chujo no kimi (a niece of the wife of Hachi no Miya), she was not acknowledged by her father Hachi no Miya as his real daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>「宇治十帖」後半の「宿木」から「夢浮橋」の6帖にかけて登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She appears in the last six chapters of &quot;Uji Jujo&quot;, from &quot;Yadorigi&quot; to &quot;Yume no Ukihashi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She appears in the last six chapters of &quot;Uji Jujo,&quot; from &quot;Yadorigi&quot; to &quot;Yume no Ukihashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She appears in the last six chapters of &apos;Uji Jujo,&apos; from &apos;Yadorigi&apos; to &apos;Yume no Ukihashi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>本文中では「姫」「娘」「女」などとさまざまな呼ばれ方をされており、一定した呼び方はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the text, she was referred to as &quot;hime&quot; (princess), &quot;musume&quot; (daughter) or &quot;onna&quot; (wife) and has no fixed name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the text, she was referred to as &quot;hime&quot; (princess), &quot;musume&quot; (daughter) or &quot;onna&quot; (wife) and has no fixed name.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the text, she was referred to as &apos;hime&apos; (princess), &apos;musume&apos; (daughter) or &apos;onna&apos; (wife) and has no fixed name.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>「浮舟」という呼称は彼女が詠んだ和歌に因むもので、古注釈などで初めて現れる名前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of &quot;Ukifune&quot; derived from waka poem composed by her and firstly appeared in commentaries of the ancients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of &quot;Ukifune&quot; was derived from the waka poem composed by her and first appeared in commentaries of the ancients.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of &apos;Ukifune&apos; was derived from the waka poem composed by her and first appeared in commentaries of the ancients.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>『源氏物語古系図』『無名草子』『河海抄』などでは「手習の君（てならいのきみ）」とも注釈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was called &quot;Tenarai no kimi&quot; in &quot;Genjimonogatari Kokeizu&quot;, &quot;Mumyozoshi&quot; and &quot;Kakai sho&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was called &quot;Tenarai no kimi&quot; in &quot;Genjimonogatari Kokeizu,&quot; &quot;Mumyozoshi,&quot; and &quot;Kakai sho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was called &apos;Tenarai no kimi&apos; in &quot;Genji monogatari kokeizu&quot; (old genealogies on the Tale of Genji), &quot;Mumyo Zoshi&quot; (Story Without a Name) and &quot;Kakai-sho&quot; Commentary.</e>
<cmt>書籍の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>「東屋の君（あずまやのきみ）」と呼ばれていることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was sometimes called &quot;Azumaya no kimi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was sometimes called &quot;Azumaya no kimi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was sometimes called &apos;Azumaya no kimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>母中将の君の再婚に従い東国へ下り、受領階級の常陸国介の継娘として育つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She went to the eastern region of Japan in the wake of her mother&apos;s remarriage and grew up as a stepdaughter of Hitachi no kuni no suke (the lord of Hitachi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She went to the eastern region of Japan in the wake of her mother&apos;s remarriage and grew up as a stepdaughter of Hitachi no kuni no suke (the lord of Hitachi Province).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She went to the eastern region of Japan in the wake of her mother&apos;s remarriage and grew up as a stepdaughter of Hitachi no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Hitachi Province) whose rank was zuryo.</e>
<cmt>常陸国介　補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>常陸介からは疎んじられるが、中将の君は数多い子の中でも美しく高貴な血筋の浮舟を大切にし、良縁を願って大切にかしずき育てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though she was given the cold shoulder by Hitachi no suke, Chujo no kimi brought up Ukifune with great care hoping her good match since Ukifune was particularly pretty among Chujo no kimi&apos;s many children and came from a line of noble family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though she was given the cold shoulder by Hitachi no suke, Chujo no kimi brought up Ukifune with great care hoping her good match since Ukifune was particularly pretty among Chujo no kimi&apos;s many children and came from a line of noble family.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although she was given the cold shoulder by Hitachi no suke, Chujo no kimi brought up Ukifune with great care hoping her good match since Ukifune was particularly pretty among Chujo no kimi&apos;s many children and came from a line of noble family.</e>
<cmt>Although としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>20歳を過ぎたころに中流貴族の左近少将との縁談が出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When she was over 20, she received an offer of marriage from middle-ranking nobility Sakon no shosho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When she was over 20, she received an offer of marriage from middle-ranking nobility Sakon no shosho.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When she was over 20, she received an offer of marriage from middle-ranking nobility Sakon no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>左近少将 補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、少将にとっては裕福な常陸介と近づくための政略結婚であり、浮舟が常陸介の継娘と知った少将は実娘の異母妹に乗り換えてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as shosho&apos;s real purpose was the marriage of convenience in order to get closer to rich Hitachi no suke, he exchanged Ukifune for her sister with the same mother, a real daughter of Hitachi no suke, when he came to know that Ukifune was a stepdaughter of Hitachi no suke.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as shosho&apos;s real purpose was a marriage of convenience in order to get closer to rich Hitachi no suke, he exchanged Ukifune for her sister with the same mother, a real daughter of Hitachi no suke, when he came to know that Ukifune was a stepdaughter of Hitachi no suke.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as shosho&apos;s real purpose was a marriage of convenience in order to get closer to rich Hitachi no suke, he exchanged Ukifune for her sister with the same mother, a real daughter of Hitachi no suke, when he came to know that Ukifune was a stepdaughter of Hitachi no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>破談で家に身の置き場のなくなった浮舟は、今は匂宮の北の方となった異母姉の中の君に預けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the marriage proposal was withdrawn, Ukifune couldn&apos;t stay at home any more and she was put in custody of her elder sister with the same mother Naka no kimi, who was then the wife of Nioumia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the marriage proposal was withdrawn, Ukifune couldn&apos;t stay at home any more and she was put in custody of her elder sister with the same mother Naka no kimi, who was then the wife of Nioumia.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the marriage proposal was withdrawn, Ukifune couldn&apos;t stay at home any more and she was put in custody of her elder paternal half-sister Naka no kimi, who was then the wife of Nioumiya.</e>
<cmt>異母姉　の表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その後、中の君の勧めにより今も亡き大君の面影を追う薫の愛人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, at Naka no kimi&apos;s suggestion, she became the mistress of Kaoru, who was still recalling the image of deceased O no kimi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, at Naka no kimi&apos;s suggestion, she became the mistress of Kaoru, who was still recalling the image of deceased O no kimi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, at Naka no kimi&apos;s suggestion, she became the mistress of Kaoru, who was still recalling the image of deceased Oikimi.</e>
<cmt>大君→Oikimi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>浮舟は薫の手で宇治に囲われるが、彼の留守に忍んできた匂宮とも関係を持ってしまい、対極的な二人の貴人に愛される板ばさみに苦しむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune was given the residence in Uji by Kaoru, but she had a relationship also with Nioumiya when he stole into her residence in Kaoru&apos;s absence and was torn between two noble men who were in strong contrast each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune was given a residence in Uji by Kaoru, but she had a relationship also with Nioumiya when he stole into her residence in Kaoru&apos;s absence and was torn between two noble men who were in strong contrast each other.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune was given a residence in Uji by Kaoru, but she had a relationship also with Nioumiya when he stole into her residence in Kaoru&apos;s absence and was torn between two noble men who were in strong contrast each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>やがて事が露見し、追い詰められた浮舟は自ら死を決意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The secret was revealed before long and Ukifune, who was driven into a corner, made up her mind to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The secret was revealed before long and Ukifune, who was driven into a corner, made up her mind to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The secret was revealed before long and Ukifune, who was driven into a corner, made up her mind to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>しかし果たせず、山で行き倒れている所を横川の僧都に救われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she failed in committing suicide and was rescued by Yokawa no sozu (the Prelate of Yokawa) when she fell down in a mountain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she failed in committing suicide and was rescued by Yokawa no sozu (the Prelate of Yokawa) when she fell down in a mountain.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she failed in committing suicide and was rescued by Yokawa no sozu (the Prelate of Yokawa) when she fell down in a mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>その後僧都の手により出家を果たし、薫に消息を捉まれ自らの元に戻るよう勧められても、終始拒み続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, she entered the Buddhist priesthood under the guidance of Yokokawa no sozu and even after her whereabouts was located by Kaoru, she constantly refused to return to his mistress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, she entered the Buddhist priesthood under the guidance of Yokokawa no sozu and even after her whereabouts were located by Kaoru, she constantly refused to return to be his mistress.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, she entered the Buddhist priesthood under the guidance of Yokokawa no sozu and even after her whereabouts were located by Kaoru, she constantly refused to return to be his mistress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="44">
<j>浮舟に話しかける時、薫も匂宮も引歌をしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When taking to Ukifune, neither Kaory nor Nioumiya did hikiuta (poem quotation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When taking to Ukifune, neither Kaoru nor Nioumiya did hikiuta (poem quotation).</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When taking to Ukifune, neither Kaoru nor Nioumiya did hikiuta (poem quotation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>これは東育ちの受領の子で音楽の嗜みもない浮舟が、二人から宮廷的な教養と趣味を身につけていない田舎者として見下され軽んじられていたことの傍証であるとの見方がある（ただし浮舟自身が詠んだ和歌は多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people assert that this is a collateral evidence proving the fact that Ukifune, who was brought up in the eastern region of Japan as a daughter of zuryo (the head of provincial governors) and didn&apos;t acquire the knowledge of music, was played down by them as a country-bred woman with no courtly culture and hobbies (however, there were a lot of waka poems composed by her).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people assert that this is collateral evidence proving the fact that Ukifune, who was brought up in the eastern region of Japan as a daughter of zuryo (the head of provincial governors) and didn&apos;t acquire the knowledge of music, was played down by them as a country-bred woman with no courtly culture and hobbies (however, there were a lot of waka poems composed by her).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people assert that this is collateral evidence proving the fact that Ukifune, who was brought up in the eastern region of Japan as a daughter of zuryo (provincial governor) and didn&apos;t acquire the knowledge of music, was played down by them as a country-bred woman with no courtly culture and hobbies (however, there were a lot of waka poems composed by her).</e>
<cmt>受領　補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>亡き姉大君の身代わりの「人形（ひとがた）」にしばしば例えられ、性格的にもイメージとしても「流される」女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was often compared with &quot;hitogata&quot; (a doll) that substitutes her deceased sister O no kimi and judging from her personality as well as image, she was a woman who tend to be &quot;influenced&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was often compared with &quot;hitogata&quot; (a doll) that substitutes her deceased sister O no kimi and judging from her personality as well as image, she was a woman who tend to be &quot;influenced.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was often compared with &apos;hitogata&apos; (a doll) that substitutes her deceased sister Oikimi and judging from her personality as well as image, she was a woman who tend to be &apos;influenced.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。大君→Oikimi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>自殺の決意を彼女の自我の芽生えと評価する向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people appreciate her resolution of committing suicide as the awakning of self-awareness,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people appreciate her resolution of committing suicide as the awakening of self-awareness.</e>
<cmt>Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people appreciate her resolution of committing suicide as the awakening of self-awareness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかしいざ自殺の実行の段階に至ると、どうしても思い切る事が出来ず、「鬼が私を喰い殺してくれれば」と嘆き悲しんでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When actually committing suicide, however, she cuoldn&apos;t dare to do so and deplored saying &quot;I wish to be eaten by an ogre&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When actually committing suicide, however, she didn&apos;t dare to do so and deplored saying &quot;I wish to be eaten by an ogre.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When actually committing suicide, however, she didn&apos;t dare to do so and deplored saying &apos;I wish to be eaten by an ogre.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>浮舟はこの幻を匂宮と勘違いしたが、実際は後に横川の僧都に祓われる法師の悪霊であった（「手習」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukifune misunderstood this phantom as Nioumiya, but actually it was the evil spirit of monk which was later exorcized by Yokawa no sozu. (&quot;Tenarai&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukifune misunderstood this phantom as Nioumiya, but actually it was the evil spirit of a monk which was later exorcized by Yokawa no sozu (&quot;Tenarai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukifune misunderstood this phantom as Nioumiya, but actually it was the evil spirit of a monk which was later exorcized by Yokawa no sozu (&apos;Tenarai&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="50">
<j>なお「あさきゆめみし」ではこの幻は光源氏の霊として描かれており、後には身の処遇に迷う浮舟に仏門の道を指し示す導き手としても登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, this phantom is depicted as the spirit of Hikaru Genji in &quot;Asaki Yume mishi&quot; (Japanese contemporary comic based on the Tale of Genji) and it also appears as a guide who instructed Ukifune, who was wondering what to do with herself, to enter the Buddhist priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, this phantom is depicted as the spirit of Hikaru Genji in &quot;Asaki Yume mishi&quot; (Japanese contemporary comic based on the Tale of Genji) and it also appears as a guide who instructed Ukifune, who was wondering what to do with herself, to enter the Buddhist priesthood.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, this phantom is depicted as the spirit of Hikaru Genji in &apos;Asaki Yume mishi&apos; (Japanese contemporary comic based on the Tale of Genji) and it also appears as a guide who instructed Ukifune, who was wondering what to do with herself, to enter the Buddhist priesthood.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), まむし(id:40389), Miya(id:1881), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Sayosayo(id:109202), Point136(id:211299), Tamifull(id:124292), Usagi8(id:240568), Sharksnow622(id:253903), 詠狸庵(id:41048), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>