<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>馬内侍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uma no naishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uma no naishi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uma no naishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>馬内侍（うまのないし、生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期の女流歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uma no naishi (date of birth and death unknown) was a Woman poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Woman poet [Weblio 英和和英辞典]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uma no naishi (date of birth and death unknown) was a female poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uma no naishi (year of birth and death unknown) was a female poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>生没年不詳　の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源時明の娘であるが、実父は時明の兄源致明（むねあきら）と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was MINAMOTO no Tokiaki, but her biological father is thought to have been MINAMOTO no Muneaki, Tokiaki&apos;s elder brother.</e>
<cmt>源時明の読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was MINAMOTO no Tokiaki, but her biological father is thought to have been MINAMOTO no Muneaki, Tokiaki&apos;s elder brother.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was MINAMOTO no Tokiaki, but her biological father is thought to have been MINAMOTO no Muneakira, Tokiaki&apos;s elder brother.</e>
<cmt>Muneakira としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中古三十六歌仙・女房三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is regarded as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets and one of the medieval 36 Immortal Women Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is regarded as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets and one of the medieval 36 Immortal Women Poets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is regarded as one of the Chuko sanjurokkasen (medieval 36 Immortal Poets) and one of the Nyobo sanjurokkasen (36 Immortal Lady Poets).</e>
<cmt>女房三十六歌仙　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>斎宮女御徽子女王（村上天皇女御）、円融天皇中宮媓子、斎院選子内親王、東三条院藤原詮子（円融天皇女御）、一条天皇皇后藤原定子に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She served under Empress Saigunyogo Kishi (the Emperor Murakami Nyogo), the Emperor Enyu chugu Koshi, Imperial Princess Saiin Senshi, Higashisanjoin FUJIWARA no Senshi (the Emperor Enyu Nyogo) and the Emperor Ichijo Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She served under Empress Saigunyogo Kishi (the Emperor Murakami Nyogo), the Emperor Enyu chugu Koshi, Imperial Princess Saiin Senshi, Higashisanjoin FUJIWARA no Senshi (the Emperor Enyu Nyogo), and the Emperor Ichijo Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She served under Empress Saigunyogo Kishi (consort of Emperor Murakami), the Emperor Enyu Chugu Koshi (Empress of Emperor Enyu), Imperial Princess Saiin Senshi, Higashisanjoin FUJIWARA no Senshi (the Emperor Enyu Nyogo), and the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi.</e>
<cmt>円融天皇中宮媓子→Emperor Enyu Chugu Koshi (Empress of Emperor Enyu)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原朝光・藤原伊尹・藤原道隆・藤原道兼など権門の公家と恋愛関係があり、華やかな宮廷生活を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had romantic relationships with Court nobles from Kenmon (powerful family lineage) including FUJIWARA no Asateru, FUJIWARA no Koretada, FUJIWARA no Michitaka and FUJIWARA no Michikane, and she enjoyed a brilliant court life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had romantic relationships with Court nobles from Kenmon (powerful family lineage) including FUJIWARA no Asateru, FUJIWARA no Koretada, FUJIWARA no Michitaka and FUJIWARA no Michikane, and she enjoyed a brilliant court life.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had romantic relationships with court nobles from Kenmon (powerful family lineage) including FUJIWARA no Asateru, FUJIWARA no Koretada, FUJIWARA no Michitaka and FUJIWARA no Michikane, and she enjoyed a brilliant court life.</e>
<cmt>court nobles としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>「拾遺和歌集」以下の勅撰和歌集に入集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of poems collected by Imperial command) when and after &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (the third imperial anthology) was compiled.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみShui wakashu (a kind of anthology of poems collected by Imperial command)とする初出の場合のみChokusen wakashu (anthology of poem collected by Imperial command)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of poems collected by Imperial command) when and after &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (the third imperial anthology) was compiled.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her waka poems were selected for chokusen wakashu (anthologies of poems collected by Imperial command) when and after &apos;Shui Wakashu&apos; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) was compiled.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家集に「馬内侍集」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Kashu (collection of her own works) is &quot;Uma no naishi shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみKashu (collection of one&apos;s own works)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Kashu (collection of her own works) is &quot;Uma no naishi shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She privately compiled &apos;Uma no naishi shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>他の記事と表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), 代言人(id:33675), Escarbot(id:59151), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>