<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊勢集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise shu (Collection of Ise)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise shu (Collection of Ise)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise shu (Collection of Ise)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊勢集（いせしゅう）は平安時代の歌人伊勢 (歌人)の私家集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise shu is a personal collection of poems by Ise (a poet), who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise shu is a personal collection of poems by Ise (a poet), who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise shu is a personal collection of poems by Ise (a poet), who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>宇多天皇の中宮藤原温子に仕えた女房、伊勢の家集である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a collection of poetry by Ise, who served FUJIWARA no Onshi, the second consort of the Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a collection of poetry by Ise, who served FUJIWARA no Onshi, the second consort of Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a collection of poetry by Ise, who served FUJIWARA no Onshi, the second consort of Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伊勢は、『古今和歌集』の撰者時代の代表的歌人であり、同集には女性として最多の二十二首が入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise was a representative poet in the time when &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) was compiled, and twenty-two poems by her were collected in it, which is the most among the poems by female poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise was a representative poet in the time when &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) was compiled, and twenty-two poems written by her were collected in it, which is the most among poems written by female poets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise was a representative poet in the time when &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) was compiled, and twenty-two poems written by her were collected in it, which is the most among poems written by female poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また三十六歌仙、『百人一首』の入選者の一人でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was also one of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets, and one of her poems was selected for &quot;Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (one hundred waka poems by one hundred poets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was also one of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets, and one of her poems was selected for &quot;Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (one hundred waka poems by one hundred poets).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was also one of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets, and one of her poems was selected for &quot;Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (one hundred waka poems by one hundred poets).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>伊勢集の諸本は三系統ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are three different lineages of the manuscript of Ise shu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are three different lines of the manuscript of Ise shu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are three different lines of the manuscript of Ise shu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>最も古態を残すのは西本願寺本であり、他の二系統は歌仙家集本および群書類従本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest is the one owned by Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and other two are Kasen Kashu lineage (Poetry Collection of Kasen (superior poets)) and Gunsho Ruiju version.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest is the one owned by Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and other two are Kasen Kashu lineage (Poetry Collection of Kasen - superior poets) and Gunsho Ruiju version.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest is the one owned by Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and other two are Kasen Kashu lineage (Poetry Collection of Kasen - superior poets) and Gunsho Ruiju version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>冒頭部分は自伝性が強い物語風の記述となっており、のちの『和泉式部日記』などに代表される女流日記文学に先駆けた内容となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opening lines of the collection is a narrative description with strong autobiographical elements, and it was a pioneer of the female diary literature represented by &quot;Izumi Shikibu Diary,&quot; which was written in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opening lines of the collection is a narrative description with strong autobiographical elements, and it was a pioneer of the female diary literature represented by the &quot;Izumi Shikibu Diary,&quot; written in later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opening lines of the collection is a narrative description with strong autobiographical elements, and it was a pioneer of the female diary literature represented by the &quot;Izumi Shikibu Diary,&quot; written in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>本歌集収録の歌は、『新古今和歌集』や『小倉百人一首』にも採用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poems collected in this collection were also selected for &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry)) and &quot;Ogura Hyakunin isshu&quot; (the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Tanka-poems by One Hundred Poets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poems in this collection were also selected for &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and &quot;Ogura Hyakunin isshu&quot; (the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Tanka-poems by One Hundred Poets).</e>
<cmt>redundancy, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poems in this collection were also selected for &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and &quot;Ogura Hyakunin isshu&quot; (the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Tanka-poems by One Hundred Poets).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 かぼ(id:79147), Mobnoboka(id:35218), 青心(id:173433), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>