<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大江匡衡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OE no Masahira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OE no Masahira</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Masahira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大江 匡衡（おおえ の まさひら、天暦6年（952年）- 寛弘9年7月16日 (旧暦)（1012年8月6日））は、平安時代中期の儒者・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OE no Masahira (952 to August 12, 1012) was a Confucian and Poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Confucian [英辞郎 on the web]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OE no Masahira (952 to August 12, 1012) was a Confucian and poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Masahira (952 - August 12, 1012) was a Confucian and poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>to をハイフンにして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中納言大江維時の孫で、京職大江重光の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather was Chunagon (a vice-councilor of state) OE no Koretoki, and his father was Kyoshiki (an officer of capital government institution) OE no Shigemitsu.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみChunagon (vice-councilor of state)とする初出の場合のみKyoshiki (officer of capital government institution)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather was Chunagon (a vice-councilor of the state) OE no Koretoki, and his father was Kyoshiki (an officer of the capital government institution) OE no Shigemitsu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather was Chunagon (a vice-councilor of the state) OE no Koretoki, and his father was Kyoshiki (an officer of the capital government institution) OE no Shigemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正四位・式部省。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) at Shikibusho (Personnel and educational ministry).</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみShoshii (Senior Fourth Rank)とする初出の場合のみShikibusho (Personel and educational ministry)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) at Shikibusho (Personnel and educational ministry).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court rank was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) at Shikibusho (Personnel and educational ministry).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中古三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is regarded as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is regarded as one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is regarded as one of the Chuko sanjurokkasen (medieval 36 Immortal Poets).</e>
<cmt>中古三十六歌仙　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>村上天皇期である天暦6年に出生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 952 during the Emperor Murakami&apos;s era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 952 during the Emperor Murakami&apos;s era.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 952 during the Emperor Murakami&apos;s era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大江氏（江家）は大江音人を祖とし菅原氏（菅家）と並ぶ学問の家柄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oe clan (also known as the Go family), whose founder was OE no Otondo, was a family lineage of academics, along with the Sugawara clan (also known as the Kan family).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The OE clan (also known as the Go family), whose founder was OE no Otondo, was a family lineage of academics, along with the Sugawara clan (also known as the Kan family).</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The OE clan (also known as the Go family), whose founder was OE no Otondo, was a family lineage of academics, along with the Sugawara clan (also known as the Kan family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>大江氏は菅原道真の失脚後に飛躍し、「聖代」とされている村上朝には匡衡の祖父にあたる維時や一族の朝綱らが儒家の中心的存在となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oe clan made a leap forward after SUGAWARA no Michizane&apos;s downfall, and the clan including Koretoki and Asatsuna became a pillar of Confucianists in &quot;Seidai&quot; (great imperial prince&apos;s time), the Emperor Murakami&apos;s era.</e>
<cmt>SUGAWARA no Michimasa, Doshinとも読むようです初出の場合のみSeidai (great imperial prince&apos;s time)とする。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The OE clan made a leap forward after SUGAWARA no Michizane&apos;s downfall, and the clan including Koretoki and Asatsuna became a pillar of Confucianists in &quot;Seidai&quot; (great imperial prince&apos;s time), the Emperor Murakami&apos;s era.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The OE clan made a leap forward after SUGAWARA no Michizane&apos;s downfall, and the clan including Koretoki and Asatsuna became a pillar of Confucianists in &apos;Seidai&apos; (great imperial prince&apos;s time), the Emperor Murakami&apos;s era.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>父の重光は対策に及第している文人官僚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Shigemitsu was Bunjinkanryo (a high-educated bureaucrat) who Kyudai (passed) Taisaku (test for recruitment of government clerks).</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみTaisaku (test for recruitment of government clerks)とする初出の場合のみKyudai (pass a test)とする初出の場合のみBunjinkanryo (high-educated and passed bureaucrat)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Shigemitsu was Bunjinkanryo (a highly educated bureaucrat) who passed Taisaku (test for recruitment of government clerks).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Shigemitsu was Bunjinkanryo (a highly educated bureaucrat) who passed Taisaku (test for recruitment of government clerks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>匡衡は晩年に自信の半生を回顧した長編の述懐詩を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masahira, later in his life, wrote long Jukkai shi (a retrospective poem), an account of his past half.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみJukkai shi (retrospective poem)とする「自信」を「自身」として訳しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masahira, later in his life, wrote long Jukkai shi (a retrospective poem), an account of his past.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masahira, later in his life, wrote long Jukkai shi (a retrospective poem), an account of his past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これには幼少期から青年期の様子も記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This includes his childhood and adolescence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This includes his childhood and adolescence.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This includes his childhood and adolescence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>述懐詩によれば匡衡は7歳で読書をはじめ、9歳で詠作を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Jukkai shi, he started reading at the age of 7 and composed waka poems at the age of 9.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Jukkai shi, he started reading at the age of 7 and composed waka poems at the age of 9.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Jukkai shi, he started reading at the age of seven and composed waka poems at the age of nine.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>康保（966年）、13歳で元服し、祖父の維時から教戒を受けたという（維時は実際には応和3年（963年）に死去『公卿補任』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in 966, he engaged in Genbuku (coming-of-age ritual) and received a cautionary lesson from his grandfather Koretoki at the age of 13 (in fact, Koretoki died in 963, according to &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (list of upper officers)).</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみGenbuku (coming-of-age ritual)とするGenpukとも読むようですcautionary lesson [英辞郎 on the web]初出の場合のみKugyobunin (list of upper officers)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in 966, he engaged in Genbuku (coming-of-age ritual) and received a cautionary lesson from his grandfather Koretoki at the age of 13 (in fact, Koretoki died in 963, according to &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (list of upper officers)).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in 966, he engaged in Genpuku (coming-of-age ritual) and received a cautionary lesson from his grandfather Koretoki at the age of 13 (in fact, Koretoki died in 963, according to &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (list of upper officers)).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、元服に際して改めた「匡衡」の名は漢代の文人である匡衡に由来すると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In passing, the name &quot;Masahira&quot; which was given to him at Genbuku is thought to derive from the name of a Chinese literatus at the age of the Han dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In passing, the name &quot;Masahira&quot; which was given to him at Genbuku is thought to derive from the name of a Chinese literary at the age of the Han dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In passing, the name &apos;Masahira&apos; (匡衡) which was given to him at Genpuku is thought to derive from the name of a Chinese literary, KYO Ko (匡衡), at the age of the Han dynasty.</e>
<cmt>中国の文人の匡衡も追加しました（KYO Koとして、漢字を追加しました）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>康保3年（966年）、15歳で大学寮に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 966, he was admitted to Daigakuryo (training institution for bureaucrats under the personnel and educational ministry) at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみDaigakuryo (training institution for bureaucrat under the personel and educational ministry)とする。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 966, he was admitted to Daigakuryo (training institution for bureaucrats under the personnel and educational ministry) at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 966, he was admitted to Daigakuryo (training institution for bureaucrats under the personnel and educational ministry) at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>翌康保4年には寮試に合格して擬文章生となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, he got through Ryoshi (test which students of Daigakuryo can take) and became Gimonjosho (a student who passed Ryoshi).</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみRyoshi (test which students of Daigakuryo can take)とする初出の場合のみGimonjosho (student passed Ryoshi)とする。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, he got through Ryoshi (test which students of Daigakuryo can take) and became Gimonjosho (a student who passed Ryoshi).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, he got through Ryoshi (test which students of Daigakuryo can take) and became Gimonjosho (a student who passed Ryoshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>匡衡は紀伝道を学び、天延元年に少試に合格して文章生となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After learning Kidendo (subject of history (Chinese history)), he passed the Shoshi test and became Monjosho (a student of poem and history) in 974.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみKidendo (subject of history (Chinese history))とする初出の場合のみMonjosho (a student of poem and history)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After learning Kidendo (subject of history (Chinese history)), he passed the Shoshi test and became Monjosho (a student of poem and history) in 974.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After learning Kidendo (subject of history (Chinese history)), he passed the Shoshi test and became Monjosho (a student of poem and history) in 974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>なお、この時期に父の大江重光が死去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, his father Shigemitsu died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, his father Shigemitsu died.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, his father Shigemitsu died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天元2年（979年）に対策を行い及第する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 979, Masahira took Taisaku and Kyudai it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 979, Masahira took Taisaku and passed it.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 979, Masahira took Taisaku and passed it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（策門作者は問頭博士菅原文時。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Montohakase (questioner) SUGAWARA no Fumitoki drew up Policy questions.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみMontohakase (questioner)とする。「策門」は「策問」として訳しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Montohakase (questioner) SUGAWARA no Fumitoki drew up Policy questions.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Montohakase (questioner) SUGAWARA no Fumitoki drew up Policy questions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>策問（問題）と匡衡の回答は『本朝文粋』に収録されている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Policy questions and Masahira&apos;s answers were included in &quot;Honchomonzui&quot; (anthology of waka poems and prose written in classical Chinese).)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Policy questions and Masahira&apos;s answers were included in &quot;Honchomonzui&quot; (anthology of waka poems and prose written in classical Chinese).)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Policy questions and Masahira&apos;s answers were included in &quot;Honchomonzui&quot; (anthology of waka poems and prose written in classical Chinese).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>匡衡は赤染時用の娘で歌人として知られる赤染衛門を妻としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took to wife Tokimochi AKAZOME&apos;s daughter AKAZOME emon who is known as a Poet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married Tokimochi AKAZOME&apos;s daughter, AKAZOME emon, who is known as a Poet.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married Tokimochi AKAZOME&apos;s daughter, AKAZOME emon, who is known as a Poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>長子挙周の出生時期から天元年間の婚姻であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their marriage lasted from the birth of their first child Takachika to the end of the Tengen era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their marriage lasted from the birth of their first child, Takachika, to the end of the Tengen era.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their marriage lasted from the birth of their first child, Takachika, to the end of the Tengen era (978 - 983).</e>
<cmt>天元年間の年を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>東宮学士や文章博士を経て、正四位下式部省に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masahira became Togugakushi (an educator of the Princess) and Monjohakase (a teacher of poem and history) before getting promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) at Shikibusho.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみTogugakushi (educator of the Princess)とする初出の場合のみMonjohakase (teacher of poem and history)とする初出の場合のみShoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masahira became Togugakushi (an educator of the Princess) and Monjohakase (a teacher of poem and history) before getting promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) at Shikibusho.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masahira became Togugakushi (an educator of the Crown Prince) and Monjohakase (a teacher of poem and history) before getting promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) at Shikibusho.</e>
<cmt>東宮博士　の補足を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>匡衡は一条天皇期に文人として活躍し、藤原道長・藤原行成・藤原公任などと交流があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active as a man of literature in the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s era and interacted with FUJIWARA no Michinaga, FUJIWARA no Yukinari, FUJIWARA no Kinto and others.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA no Goseiとも読むようです。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active as a man of literature in the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s era and interacted with FUJIWARA no Michinaga, FUJIWARA no Yukinari, FUJIWARA no Kinto, and others.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active as a man of literature in the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s era and interacted with FUJIWARA no Michinaga, FUJIWARA no Yukinari, FUJIWARA no Kinto, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>時折彼らの表や願文、奏上などの文章を代作し、名儒と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On behalf of them, he sometimes wrote compositions on front pages of Kaishi writing sheets, ganmon (prayers), reports to the Emperor and so on, and he was called Meiju (Great confucian).</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみMeiju (Great confucian)とする。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On their behalf, he sometimes wrote compositions on the front pages of Kaishi writing sheets, ganmon (prayers), reports to the Emperor, and so on, and he was called Meiju (Great confucian).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On their behalf, he sometimes wrote hyo (documents to be submitted to the emperor), ganmon (prayers), reports to the Emperor, and so on, and he was called Meiju (Great Confucian).</e>
<cmt>表→hyo (documents to be submitted to the emperor)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また地方官としても善政の誉れ高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also acclaimed as chihokan (a local official) for his good government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also acclaimed as chihokan (a local official) for his good government.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also acclaimed as chihokan (a local official) for his good government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>尾張国の国司としての在任中は学校院を設立し、地域の教育の向上に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He, as Kokushi (an officer in charge of regional administration) of Owari no kuni, established Gakkoin (training insutition for officers) to improve the regional education.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみKokushi (officer in charge of regional administration)とするKuni no tukasaとも読むようです初出の場合のみGakkoin (training insutition for officer)とする。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He, as Kokushi (an officer in charge of regional administration) of Owari no kuni, established Gakkoin (training institution for officers) to improve the regional education.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He, as Kokushi (an officer in charge of regional administration) of Owari Province, established Gakkoin (training institution for officers) to improve the regional education.</e>
<cmt>Owari Province としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>公卿としての地位を望んだが果たせずに終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wanted to become a Noble, but did not go through with it.</e>
<cmt>Noble [英辞郎 on the web]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wanted to become a Noble, but did not go through with it.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wanted to become a Noble, but did not go through with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>漢詩文に『江吏部集』、私家集に『匡衡朝臣集』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He compiled a collection of Chinese poems &quot;Gorihoshu&quot; and Shikashu (a collection of his own works) &quot;Masahira ason shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみShikashu (collection of one&apos;s own works)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He compiled a collection of Chinese poems &quot;Gorihoshu&quot; and Shikashu (a collection of his own works) &quot;Masahira ason shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He compiled a collection of Chinese poems &quot;Gorihoshu&quot; and Shikashu (a collection of his own works) &quot;Masahira ason shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>『後拾遺和歌集』以下の勅撰和歌集に12首採録。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His 12 waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of poems collected by Imperial command) when and after &quot;Goshui wakashu&quot; (the fourth imperial anthology) was compiled.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合のみGoshui wakashu (a kind of anthology of poems collected by Imperial command)とする初出の場合のみChokusen wakashu (anthology of poems collected by Imperial command)とする</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">12 of his waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of poems collected by Imperial command) starting when &quot;Goshui wakashu&quot; (the fourth imperial anthology) was compiled and onwards.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">12 of his waka poems were selected for chokusen wakashu (anthologies of poems collected by Imperial command) starting when &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry) was compiled and onwards.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), VolkovBot(id:105371), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 湖沼亭(id:126910), Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), Snap55(id:89773), Junger(id:10282), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>