<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>抄物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomono (books of commentary on Chinese literary works created from the mid-Muromachi period to the early Edo period)</e>
<cmt>説明補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>抄物（しょうもの）は、室町時代中期から江戸時代初期にかけて製作された、ある漢文作品に対する解説・註釈をむねとする書物の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomono is a general term for commentary books on Chinese literary works created from the mid-Muromachi period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomono is a general term for books of commentary on Chinese literary works created from the mid-Muromachi period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomono is a general term for books of commentary on Chinese literary works created from the mid-Muromachi period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>先行する諸註釈を参照にしながら、わかりやすくまとめられた講義の筆録もしくは講義体の形式を借りた註釈書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a written record of lecture or a commentary written in the form of a lecture, which was organized to be understood easily, referring to the various preceding commentaries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a written record of lectures or commentary written in the form of a lecture, organized to be understood easily while referring to various preceding commentaries.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a written record of lectures or commentary written in the form of a lecture, organized to be understood easily while referring to various preceding commentaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>口頭語的な要素を生かしつつ仮名書きであらわされることが多いため、註釈の内容のほかに中世後期の国語学的資料としての高い価値をも持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making the best of colloquial element, it was written in kana (the Japanese syllabary), therefore it is of great value not only as a commentary but also as a material for Japanese study in the latter half of the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making the most of colloquial elements, they were written in kana (the Japanese syllabary), and are therefore of great value not only as commentary but also as a reference for studying the Japanese of the latter half of the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making the most of colloquial elements, they were written in kana (the Japanese syllabary), and are therefore of great value not only as commentary but also as a reference for studying the Japanese of the latter half of the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>抄物は、講義のために講師の製作する手控え形式のものと、講義の参加者がその内容を筆録した聞書形式のもの、さらに先行抄物を集大成した形式のものに大別することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomono can be classified into three groups: notes for a lecture created by a speaker; a verbatim record which was written down by the attendant of the lecture; compiled book of the preceding shomono.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomono can be classified into three groups: Notes for a lecture created by a speaker, a verbatim record which was written down by and attendant of a lecture, and book compilations of the preceding shomono.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomono can be classified into three groups: Notes for a lecture created by a speaker, a verbatim record which was written down by an attendant of a lecture, and book compilations of the preceding shomono.</e>
<cmt>and →an</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>実際には聞書であっても直接の筆録ではなく講師の手控えを引き写したものであったり、手控えであっても先行する抄物を参照しつつ作り上げられたものであったり、その内容は幅広い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, some verbatim record were not written records but copies of speaker&apos;s notes, or some notes were made referring to the preceding shomono, so the contents range widely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, some records were not, in fact, &quot;verbatim&quot; but rather copies of a speaker&apos;s notes, also some notes refer to the preceding shomono, so their contents range widely.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, some records were not, in fact, &quot;verbatim&quot; but rather copies of a speaker&apos;s notes, also some notes refer to the preceding shomono, so their contents range widely.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>概して言えば、初期の抄物は純粋な手控え・聞書の形式が多く、後期になるほど右に述べたような複雑な成立ちによるものや集大成形式のものが多くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a whole, most of the earliest shomono took the form of notes or a verbatim record, and as time passed to the latter stage, more and more complicated form mentioned above or the form of compiled books appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a whole, most of the earliest shomono took the form of notes or verbatim records, as time passed, though, more and more complicated forms, as mentioned above, as well compiled books appeared.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a whole, most of the earliest shomono took the form of notes or verbatim records, as time passed, though, more and more complicated forms, as mentioned above, as well compiled books appeared.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、註釈・解説としての性質上、先行の抄物の内容をそのまま踏襲することはしばしば見られ、この点において一般の文学作品などとは性質が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the properties of commentary or explanation often made it follow the contents of the preceding shomono; in this sense, it has a different character from general literary works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, due to the nature of commentary and explanation, it was common to see shomono which emulated the contents of previous compositions, in this way shomono differs from general literary works.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, due to the nature of commentary and explanation, it was common to see shomono which emulated the contents of previous compositions, in this way shomono differs from general literary works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>文体は漢文によるものもあるが、多くは和文、それも当時の口語の様相をそのままにとどめたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some were written in Chinese, but most of them were written in Japanese; there are many shohon which retain colloquial speech in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some were written in Chinese, but most of them were written in Japanese; there are many shohon which retain the colloquial language of those days.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some were written in Chinese, but most of them were written in Japanese; there are many shomono which retain the colloquial language of those days.</e>
<cmt>shohon→shomono</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また「～ゾ」と、係助詞ゾを文末終止に用いた独特の文体が用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, a unique style of writing was adopted such as &apos;--zo,&apos; as a binding particle used at the end of a sentence.</e>
<cmt>「～ゾ」の訳は、&apos;---zo&apos;とローマ字表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, unique styles of writing were adopted such as using &apos;--zo,&apos; as a binding particle at the end of a sentence.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, unique styles of writing were adopted such as using &apos;--zo,&apos; as a binding particle at the end of a sentence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これらの特色は後期の、実際には講義とはかかわりを持たなかった抄物においても踏襲されるなど、抄物というジャンルを特色づけるものとして扱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are treated as distinctions of a genre of shomono, being followed by the latter works which had, in fact, nothing to do with a lecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are treated as a distinct genre of shomono, and are followed by later works which have, in fact, nothing to do with lectures.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are treated as a distinct genre of shomono, and are followed by later works which have, in fact, nothing to do with lectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>和文の場合には片仮名書きが一般的で、こうした抄物を特に「仮名書抄物」と称することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it was written in Japanese, the shomono written in the katakana syllabary was common, which is sometimes called &apos;kanagaki shomono&apos; (shomono written in kana).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When shomono were written in Japanese, use of the katakana syllabary was common, these are sometimes called &apos;kanagaki shomono&apos; (shomono written in kana).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When shomono were written in Japanese, use of the katakana syllabary was common; these are sometimes called &apos;kanagaki shomono&apos; (shomono written in kana).</e>
<cmt>,→;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>講義・註釈の対象となった作品は、漢籍と内典および一部の国書が中心である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The works which were annotated or a speaker lectured were mostly Chinese classics, Buddhist literature, and a part of national literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The works which were annotated or presented by a lecturer were mostly Chinese classics, Buddhist literature, and a part of national literature.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The works which were annotated or presented by a lecturer were mostly Chinese classics, Buddhist literature, and a part of national literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>漢籍は経書では四書、『詩経』、『易経』などに多く抄物がつくられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Chinese classics of Confucianism, the Four Confucian Classics, &quot;The Shih Ching&quot; (The Book of Songs), &quot;I-Ching&quot; (The Book of Changes), and so on were mainly annotated to make shomono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Chinese classics of Confucianism, the Four Confucian Classics, &quot;The Shih Ching&quot; (The Book of Songs), &quot;I-Ching&quot; (The Book of Changes), and so on were annotated to make shomono.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Chinese classics of Confucianism, the Four Confucian Classics, &quot;The Shih Ching&quot; (The Book of Songs), &quot;I-Ching&quot; (The Book of Changes), and so on were annotated to make shomono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>製作者の大半は明経道博士家にかかわりを持つ人々であり、特に清原宣賢がこの分野において果たした役割は大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the writers had something to do with the family of Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics) expert, and especially Nobukata KIYOHARA played an important role in this genre.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the writers were connected with the family of Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics) experts, and Nobukata KIYOHARA played an especially important role in this genre.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the writers were connected with the family of Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics) experts, and Nobukata KIYOHARA played an especially important role in this genre.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>註の内容としては、初期にはもっぱら旧註によるものが主で、後期にいたって新註の成果が加えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annotations made in the early years were mainly based on old annotations, but in the latter period, the result of new annotations came to be added.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annotations made in the early years were mainly based on older annotations, but as time progressed the results of newer annotations came to be added.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annotations made in the early years were mainly based on older annotations, but as time progressed the results of newer annotations came to be added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、その場合にも旧註と新註が併記されているところに特色があり、概していえば旧註の勢力のほうがつよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even in that case, shomono made in the later years was characterized by containing both old and new annotations, and as a rule, old annotations were dominant.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even in this case, shomono made in the later years were characterized by containing both old and new annotations, and as a rule, the influence of the older annotations was dominant.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even in this case, shomono made in the later years were characterized by containing both old and new annotations, and as a rule, the influence of the older annotations was dominant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>史書においては『史記』および『漢書』の列伝を中心とする部分に多くの抄物が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the genre of history books, many shomono were left mainly in a part of a series of biographies in &quot;Shih-chi&quot; (the Historical Records) and &quot;Han Shu&quot; (The History of the Han).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the category of history books, many shomono were left mainly as part of a series of biographies in &quot;Shih-chi&quot; (the Historical Records) and &quot;Han Shu&quot; (The History of the Han).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the category of history books, many shomono were left mainly as part of a series of biographies in &quot;Shih-chi&quot; (the Historical Records) and &quot;Han Shu&quot; (The History of the Han).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>初期には紀伝道博士家の手になるものがあるが、しだいに五山僧がこの分野の抄物を担うようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early period, some of shomono were made by the family of Kidendo (the study of the histories) expert, but gradually priests of the Five Zen Monasteries took this genre of shomono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, some shomono were made by the family of Kidendo (the study of the histories) experts, but gradually priests of the Five Zen Monasteries took responsibility for the shomono.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, some shomono were made by the family of Kidendo (the study of the histories) experts, but gradually priests of the Five Zen Monasteries took responsibility for the shomono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『漢書列伝竺桃抄』は現存する抄物のうちでも最古のものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kanjo retsuden jikutosho&quot; is the oldest of the extant shomono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kanjo retsuden jikutosho&quot; is the oldest shomono in existence today.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Extant&quot; isn&apos;t incorrect, but it seems unnecessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjo retsuden jikutosho is the oldest shomono in existence today.</e>
<cmt>文頭の &quot;&quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>子書（子部、四部分類を参照）では『荘子』などの抄物が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the genre of The Hundred Schools of Thought (see also a group of the Hundred Schools of Thought in the four groups of Chinese classics), shomono such as &quot;Chuang-tzu&quot; and so on was left.</e>
<cmt>子書、子部、四部分類の定訳は未詳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among &quot;The Hundred Schools of Thought&quot; (see also the Hundred Schools of Thought in the four groups of Chinese classics), shomono such as &quot;Chuang-tzu&quot; and so on were left.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among &quot;The Hundred Schools of Thought&quot; (see also the Hundred Schools of Thought in the four groups of Chinese classics), shomono such as &quot;Chuang-tzu&quot; and so on were left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>集書（集部）では『古文真宝』、『三体詩』、『長恨歌』、蘇軾・黄庭堅など北宋詩などに盛んに抄物が行われ、現存する量も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the genre of literary works, poetry of Northern Sung such as &quot;Kobun Shinpo,&quot; &quot;Santaishi,&quot; &quot;The Song of Everlasting Sorrow,&quot; Su Shi (Chinese poet), and Huang Tingjian (Chinese calligrapher, painter, and poet) were vigorously annotated, and many of them are extant.</e>
<cmt>集部は「文学作品」ジャンルです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among literary works, such as the poetry of Northern Sung &quot;Kobun Shinpo,&quot; &quot;Santaishi,&quot; &quot;The Song of Everlasting Sorrow,&quot; Su Shi (Chinese poet), and Huang Tingjian (Chinese calligrapher, painter, and poet) were enthusiastically annotated, and many of them still exist today.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among literary works, such as the poetry of Northern Sung &quot;Kobun Shinpo,&quot; &quot;Santaishi,&quot; &quot;The Song of Everlasting Sorrow,&quot; Su Shi (Chinese poet), and Huang Tingjian (Chinese calligrapher, painter, and poet) were enthusiastically annotated, and many of them still exist today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また五山僧を中心とする日本詩人や中国詩人の詞華集が独自にあまれ、これに対する抄物が作られることもあった（『中華若木抄』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anthologies of Japanese and Chinese poet centering on Five Zen Monastries were independently edited, and annotations on these anthologies were sometimes made (&quot;Selected Chinese Saplings Poems&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anthologies of Japanese and Chinese poetry centering on the Five Zen Monasteries were independently edited, and annotations on these anthologies were sometimes made (&quot;Selected Chinese Saplings Poems&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anthologies of Japanese and Chinese poetry centering on priests of the Five Zen Monasteries were independently edited, and annotations on these anthologies were sometimes made (&quot;Selected Chinese Saplings Poems&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>monastery は修道院なので priests of を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>子書においても、抄物の大きな担手は五山僧であり、江戸後期の漢文註釈と比較すると、『文章軌範』ではなく『古文真宝』、『唐詩選』ではなく『三体詩』、南宋詩よりも北宋詩など、その内容に独自の傾向が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary works were mainly annotated by the Five Zen Monastries, and compared with the annotation on the Chinese classics made in the late Edo period, they seem to have their own tendency; for example, shomono annotated &quot;Kobun Shinpo&quot; instead of &quot;A standard of Composition,&quot; &quot;Santaishi&quot; instead of &quot;Selected Poems of the Tang Dynasty,&quot; and Northern Sung poetry instead of Southern Sung poetry.</e>
<cmt>『文章軌範』→定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary works were mainly annotated by the Five Zen Monasteries, and compared with the annotation of Chinese classics made in the late Edo period, they seem to have their own tendencies; for example, shomono annotated &quot;Kobun Shinpo&quot; instead of &quot;A standard of Composition,&quot; &quot;Santaishi&quot; instead of &quot;Selected Poems of the Tang Dynasty,&quot; and Northern Sung poetry instead of Southern Sung poetry.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary works were mainly annotated by priests of the Five Zen Monasteries, and compared with the annotation of Chinese classics made in the late Edo period, they seem to have their own tendencies; for example, shomono annotated &quot;Kobun Shinpo&quot; instead of &quot;A standard of Composition,&quot; &quot;Santaishi&quot; instead of &quot;Selected Poems of the Tang Dynasty,&quot; and Northern Sung poetry instead of Southern Sung poetry.</e>
<cmt>monastery は修道院なので priests of を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>内典は主に五山僧によって抄物がつくられたために、原典はほとんどすべてが禅籍である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly Five Zen Monastries made shomono on Buddhist literature, so most of the original texts were books about Zen Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Five Zen Monasteries made shomono mainly regarding Buddhist literature, so most of the original texts were books about Zen Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Priests of the Five Zen Monasteries made shomono mainly regarding Buddhist literature, so most of the original texts were books about Zen Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>monastery は修道院なので priests of を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>国書は日本書紀の抄物がさかんに作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the genre of National literature, a lot of shomono on Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan) were made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the genre of National literature, a lot of shomono on Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan) were made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the genre of National literature, a lot of shomono on Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan) were made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは清原宣賢、吉田兼倶らの手になるもので、中世神道と深いかかわりを持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are produced by Nobukata KIYOHARA and Kanetomo YOSHIDA, and deeply involved in Shintoism in the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were produced by Nobukata KIYOHARA and Kanetomo YOSHIDA, and were deeply involved with Shintoism in the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were produced by Nobukata KIYOHARA and Kanetomo YOSHIDA, and were deeply involved with Shintoism in the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Touryuuuan(id:89696), Ajax(id:11202), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>