<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>在原元方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ARIWARA no Motokata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ARIWARA no Motokata</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ARIWARA no Motokata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>在原 元方（ありわら の もとかた、生没年不詳）は、平安時代の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ARIWARA no Motokata (date of birth and death unknown) was kajin (a waka poet) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ARIWARA no Motokata (date of birth and death unknown) was kajin (a waka poet) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ARIWARA no Motokata (year of birth and death unknown) was a waka poet in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>生没年不詳　の表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は中古三十六歌仙の一人在原棟梁で、六歌仙・三十六歌仙の一人在原業平は祖父にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets ARIWARA no Muneyana, and his grandfather was ARIWARA no Narihira who was one of Rokkasen (six best waka poets) and one of the 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets ARIWARA no Muneyana, and his grandfather was ARIWARA no Narihira who was one of Rokkasen (six best waka poets) and one of the 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was one of the Chuko sanjurokkasen (medieval 36 Immortal Poets) ARIWARA no Muneyana, and his grandfather was ARIWARA no Narihira who was one of Rokkasen (six best waka poets) and one of the Sanjurokkasen (36 Immortal Poets).</e>
<cmt>中古三十六歌仙、三十六歌仙　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>元方は、平城天皇の孫である在原業平の孫（平城天皇の玄孫）にあたるが、官位などの経歴については不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his grandfather was a grandchild of the Emperor Heizei (he was a great-great-grandchild of the Emperor Heizei), Motokata&apos;s official court rank or career is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his grandfather was a grandchild of the Emperor Heizei (he was a great-great-grandchild of the Emperor Heizei), Motokata&apos;s official court rank or career is unknown.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his grandfather was a grandchild of the Emperor Heizei (he was a great-great-grandchild of the Emperor Heizei), Motokata&apos;s official court rank or career is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>勅撰和歌集では『古今和歌集』に14首、『後撰和歌集』に8首、『拾遺和歌集』に2首が入集し、以後『新古今和歌集』以下の勅撰和歌集に9首が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command): fourteen poems for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), eight poems for &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (the later selected collection of Japanese poetry), two poems for &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems), nine poems for &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and Chokusen wakashu that follow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His waka poems were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command): fourteen poems for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), eight poems for &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (the later selected collection of Japanese poetry), two poems for &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems), nine poems for &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and Chokusen wakashu that follow.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His waka poems were selected in the folllowing chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command): fourteen poems for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), eight poems for &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry), two poems for &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) and nine poems for &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) and other chokusen Wakashu that follow.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>元方は「古今和歌集」の巻頭の歌を詠んだ人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He composed Kantoka (a prefatory poem or an opening poem) of &quot;Kokin Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He composed Kantoka (a prefatory poem or an opening poem) for &quot;Kokin Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He composed Kantoka (a prefatory poem or an opening poem) for &apos;Kokin Wakashu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>家集に「元方集」があるが、断片的なものが伝わるだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He privately compiled &quot;Motokata shu,&quot; but it has been transmitted only in fragments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He privately compiled &quot;Motokata shu,&quot; but it has been transmitted only in fragments.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He privately compiled &apos;Motokata shu,&apos; but it has been transmitted only in fragments.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>代表歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative Poem</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative Poem</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative poem</e>
<cmt>poem を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>あふことのなぎさにし寄る浪なればうらみてのみぞ立ちかへりける（古今・恋三・626）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waves lapping against the shore are just looking at the shore and going back into the sea; With Kakekotoba (one of waka&apos;s oratories), it also means that I cannot see you at night, just reproaching you and going home (Kokin Wakashu, Love vol.3, 626).</e>
<cmt>参考：http://www.k5.dion.ne.jp/~totoya/b_class/waka_05.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waves lapping against the shore are just looking at the shore and going back into the sea; with Kakekotoba (one of waka&apos;s oratories), it also means that I cannot see you at night, just reproaching you and going home (Kokin Wakashu, Love vol.3, 626).</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waves lapping against the shore are just looking at the shore and going back into the sea; with Kakekotoba (one of waka&apos;s oratories), it also means that I cannot see you at night, just reproaching you and going home (Kokin Wakashu, Love vol.3, 626).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), Point136(id:211299), 名古屋市16(id:74281), ArthurBot(id:265089), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 代言人(id:33675), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>