<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>飛鳥井雅庸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsune ASUKAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsune ASUKAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsune ASUKAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>飛鳥井 雅庸（あすかい まさつね、永禄12年10月20日(旧暦) （1569年11月28日） - 元和(日本)元年12月22日 (旧暦)（1616年2月9日））は、戦国時代(日本)の戦国期から江戸時代前期にかけての公家・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsune ASUKAI (born November 28, 1569, died February 9, 1616 according to the modern calendar) was a court noble and waka poet who lived through the turmoil of the warring states in the Sengoku period and into the beginning of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsune ASUKAI (born November 28, 1569, died February 9, 1616 according to the modern calendar) was a court noble and waka poet who lived through the turmoil of the warring states in the Sengoku period and into the beginning of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsune ASUKAI (November 28, 1569 - February 9, 1616) was a court noble and waka poet who lived through the turmoil of the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) and into the beginning of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>日付の表記を修正戦国時代表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は飛鳥井雅敦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father&apos;s name was Masaatsu ASUKAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father&apos;s name was Masaatsu ASUKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father&apos;s name was Masaatsu ASUKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初名は雅継、雅枝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsune was also initially known as Masatsugu and Masae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsune was also initially known as Masatsugu and Masae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsune was also initially known as Masatsugu and Masae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>1613年（慶長18年）従二位に至り、1615年（元和元年）権大納言に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1613 (Keicho 18), he reached the junior second rank at court, and in 1615 (Genwa 1) he was appointed to the position of Gonno Dainagon (Assistant Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1613 (Keicho 18), he reached the junior second rank at court, and in 1615 (Genwa 1) he was appointed to the position of Gonno Dainagon (Assistant Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1613 (Keicho 18), he reached the Junii (Junior Second Rank), and in 1615 he was appointed to the position of Gonno Dainagon (Assistant Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>junior second rank at court修正元号削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>昭高院准后道澄から古今伝授を、また藤木成定から入木道（じゅぼくどう＝書道）伝授を受け、後水尾上皇・徳川秀忠・細川忠興・島津家久に蹴鞠を指導するなど諸芸に秀でていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was initiated into kokin denju (the art of interpreting the kokinshu) by the Shoko-in Dogo JUNGO, and initiated into the art of calligraphy by Narisada FUJIKI, and was exceptionally accomplished instructing such luminaries as Retired Emperor Go-Mizuo, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, and Iehisa SHIMAZU in the game of kemari (an ancient kick-ball game similar to soccer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was initiated into kokin denju (the art of interpreting the kokinshu) by the Shoko-in Dogo JUNGO, and initiated into the art of calligraphy by Narisada FUJIKI, and was exceptionally accomplished instructing such luminaries as Retired Emperor Go-Mizuo, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, and Iehisa SHIMAZU in the game of kemari (an ancient kick-ball game similar to soccer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was initiated into kokin denju (the art of interpreting the kokinshu) by the Shoko-in Dogo JUNGO, and initiated into the art of calligraphy by Narisada FUJIKI, and was exceptionally accomplished instructing such luminaries as Retired Emperor Gomizuo, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, and Iehisa SHIMAZU in the game of kemari (an ancient kick-ball game similar to soccer).</e>
<cmt>天皇の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>日記に「雅継卿記」、歌集に「入道大納言雅庸卿百首」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left a diary, called &quot;Masatsugu kyo ki&quot; (the Diary of Lord Masatsugu (Masatsune)), and a waka anthology, &quot;Nyudo dainagon masatsugu kyo hyakushu&quot; (One Hundred Verses by the Priest Lord Masatsune, the Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left a diary, called Masatsugu kyo ki (the Diary of Lord Masatsugu (Masatsune)), and a waka anthology, Nyudo dainagon masatsugu kyo hyakushu (One Hundred Verses by the Priest Lord Masatsune, the Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left a diary, called &apos;Masatsugu kyo ki&apos; (the Diary of Lord Masatsugu (Masatsune)), and a waka anthology, &apos;Nyudo dainagon masatsugu kyo hyakushu&apos; (One Hundred Verses by the Priest Lord Masatsune, the chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>補足&quot;Major Counselor&quot;→&quot;chief councilor of state&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yonoemon(id:55450), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 代言人(id:33675), 在処(id:195599), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>