<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>続日本後紀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Chronicle of Japan Continued</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoku Nihon Koki (Later Chronicle of Japan, Continued)</e>
<cmt>Added Japanese title and moved English to parentheis. Added comma after &quot;Japan&quot;. This reads more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoku Nihon Koki (Later Chronicle of Japan, Continued)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>続日本後紀（しょくにほんこうき）は、日本の平安時代の869年に成立された歴史書で、六国史の第四にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Later Chronicle of Japan Continued (Shoku Nihon Koki) is a history compiled in 869 during the Heian era in Japan, and the fourth of the Six National Histories (Rikkokushi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoku Nihon Koki is a history compiled in 869 during the Heian era in Japan, and is the fourth of the Six National Histories (Rikkokushi).</e>
<cmt>Cut English translation as it is already included above. Changed to &quot;and is the fourth&quot; to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoku Nihon Koki is a history compiled in 869 during the Heian period in Japan, and is the fourth of the Six National Histories (Rikkokushi).</e>
<cmt>era→period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仁明天皇の代、天長10年（833年）から嘉祥3年（850年）までの18年間を扱う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It covers the 18 years of the reign of Emperor Ninmyo, from 833 to 850.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It covers the 18 years of the reign of Emperor Ninmyo, from 833 to 850.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It covers the 18 years of the reign of Emperor Ninmyo, from 833 to 850.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>文徳天皇の勅命により斉衡2年（855年）編纂が開始され、貞観11年（869年）に完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilation was begun in 855 by the Imperial order of Emperor Montoku, and completed in 869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compilation was begun in 855 on the Imperial order of Emperor Montoku, and completed in 869.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;On&quot; feels a bit more natural than &quot;by&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compilation was begun in 855 on the Imperial order of Emperor Montoku, and completed in 869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天皇の動静の記録を詳述し天皇親政から摂関政治へうつる時代の根本史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the main historical sources for the period of the shift from direct rule by the emperor to the regency, and describes the emperor&apos;s deeds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the main historical sources for the period of the shift from direct rule by the emperor to the regency, and describes the emperor&apos;s deeds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the main historical sources for the period of the shift from direct rule by the emperor to the regency, and describes the emperor&apos;s deeds.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>編年体全二十巻からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of 20 volumes in annalistic style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of 20 volumes in annalistic style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of 20 volumes in annalistic style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>編纂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compilation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compilation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compilation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>本書の編纂は文徳天皇の斉衡2年（855年）、藤原良房、伴善男、春澄善縄、安野豊道により始められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilation of this book was begun in 855 by FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, TOMO no Yoshio, HARUZUMI no Yoshitada and Toyomichi YASUNO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compilation of this book was begun in 855 by FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, TOMO no Yoshio, HARUZUMI no Yoshitada and Toyomichi YASUNO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compilation of this book was begun in 855 by FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, TOMO no Yoshio, HARUZUMI no Yoshitada and Toyomichi YASUNO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、良房の弟・藤原良相が加わるが完成前に逝去、善男は応天門の変で流罪、豊道の下総介赴任などがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshifusa&apos;s brother FUJIWARA no Yoshimi later joined but passed away before the work was completed, Yoshio was exiled due to the Otenmon incident, and Toyomichi was appointed as the Vice-governor of Shimosa.</e>
<cmt>「下総介」直接の出典はありませんが、源氏物語の「伊予介」 &quot;vice-governor of Iyo&quot;に倣いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshifusa&apos;s brother FUJIWARA no Yoshimi later joined the compilation effort but passed away before the work was completed, Yoshio was exiled due to the Otenmon incident (an event centering around the destruction of the main gate of the Imperial Palace in Kyoto), and Toyomichi was appointed as the Vice-governor of Shimosa.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;compilation effort&quot; after &quot;Yoshimi&quot; as I thought it would help to clarify it. Added explanation of Otenmon incident. Also, Google gives a lot more hits for Otenmon Conspiracy over incident, so people may be more aware of it as that, but I decided to leave it to what the original translator translated it as.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshifusa&apos;s brother FUJIWARA no Yoshimi later joined the compilation effort but passed away before the work was completed, Yoshio was exiled due to the Otenmon incident (an event centering around the destruction of the main gate of the Imperial Palace in Kyoto), and Toyomichi was appointed as the Vice-governor of Shimosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>だが、編纂者の追加が行われなかっために最終的には藤原良房と春澄善縄の２名のみが編纂者として残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because no other compilers were supplemented, only FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and HARUZUMI no Yoshitada remained as a compiler in the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because no one else was provided to help, only FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and HARUZUMI no Yoshitada remained as compilers in the end.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &quot;compiler&quot; to prevent the repetition of the word. Changed &quot;supplemented&quot; to &quot;provided&quot; as this sounds a bit more natural. Changed &quot;as a compiler&quot; to &quot;as compilers&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because no one else was provided to help, only FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and HARUZUMI no Yoshitada remained as compilers in the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このため、編纂方針については良房の、記述については善縄の意向が強く反映されたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that in editorial policy, Yoshifusa&apos;s views were strongly reflected and in description, Yoshitada&apos;s views were strongly reflected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that their views are strongly reflected in the text, Yoshifusa&apos;s in editorial policy, and Yoshitada&apos;s in description.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to remove the second redundant &quot;strongly reflected&quot;. Added &quot;in the text&quot; to make it read a little smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that their views are strongly reflected in the text, Yoshifusa&apos;s in editorial policy, and Yoshitada&apos;s in description.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>六国史中、初めて天皇一代を対象にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the first work among the Six National Histories (Rikkokushi) that covered only one emperor&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the first work among the Rikkokushi to cover only one emperor&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;that covered&quot; to &quot;to cover&quot; to read more naturally. Cut the English title as it is provided elsewhere.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the first work among the Rikkokushi to cover only one emperor&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>承和の変もこの書に記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jowa Incident is also described in this book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jowa Incident is also described in this book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jowa Incident is also described in this book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>本書の「続日本後紀」という書名は、「日本後紀」に続くという意味であるが、「続日本紀」は九代、「日本後紀」は四代と複数の天皇の治世を対象としているのに対し本書は、仁明天皇一代の歴史である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The title of this book &apos;Later Chronicle of Japan Continued &apos; means a continuation of &apos;Later Chronicle of Japan&apos; (Nihon Koki)&apos;, but in contrast to &apos;Chronicle of Japan Continued&apos; (Shoku Nihongi) covering the reigns of nine emperors, and &apos;Later Chronicle of Japan&apos; (Nihon Koki) covering four, this book is a history of only one, Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt>「複数の天皇の治世を対象としているのに対し」前に4、9と具体的に複数の数字が出ており、もう一度「複数」を訳出すると返ってくどいため、「複数」のみ削りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Shoku&apos; in the title of this fourth book Shoku Nihon Koki means &apos;continued&apos;, so it can be seen as a direct continuation of the third book Nihon Koki (Later Chronicle of Japan), but in contrast to that third book, which covers the reigns of four emperors, and the second book Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan, Continued) which covers the reign of nine, this fourth book covers only one, Emperor Ninmyo</e>
<cmt>To avoid confusion around all these books with similar titles I numbered them. I also changed the order around to remove the second redundant &apos;Later Chronicle of Japan&apos; which just added to the confusion. Also added a quick explanation of &apos;shoku&apos; which I thought might help provide a clearer explanation. Used Japanese titles and removed quotation marks as before.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Shoku&apos; in the title of this fourth book Shoku Nihon Koki means &apos;continued,&apos; so it can be seen as a direct continuation of the third book Nihon Koki (Later Chronicle of Japan), but in contrast to that third book, which covers the reigns of four emperors, and the second book Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan, Continued) which covers the reign of nine, this fourth book covers only one, Emperor Ninmyo</e>
<cmt>コンマ移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>本書の対象とした仁明朝は、嵯峨・淳和両朝の後を受けた太平の世であり、「承和の変」以外大きな事件は無かったために、宮中行事などは詳しいが、政治関係の記事は少ないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the reign of Emperor Ninmyo, whom this book focused on, was in a time of peace after the reigns of Emperor Saga and Emperor Junna, and no big incident occurred except &apos;the Jowa Incident&apos;, it is said to have more detailed descriptions of court ceremonies, etc., but less material related to politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the reign of Emperor Ninmyo was in a time of peace after the reigns of Emperor Saga and Emperor Junna, and as nothing big occurred except the Jowa Incident, this book is said to have more detailed descriptions of court ceremonies, etc., but less material related to politics.</e>
<cmt>I didn&apos;t think it was neccesary to repeat that this book focusses on Ninmyo as that is written elsewhere so I cut it. Replaced &quot;no big incident occurred&quot; with &quot;as nothing big occurred&quot; to avoid repetition of the word &quot;incident&quot;. Removed quotation marks from &quot;Jowa Incident&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the reign of Emperor Ninmyo was in a time of peace after the reigns of Emperor Saga and Emperor Junna, and as nothing big occurred except the Jowa Incident, this book is said to have more detailed descriptions of court ceremonies, etc., but less material related to politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一説には「承和の変」における皇太子恒貞親王の廃止と新皇太子道康親王（文徳天皇）擁立の正当性を主張するために書かれたとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, it was written to emphasize the legitimacy of Prince Tsunesada&apos;s demotion from Crown Prince and the raising of Prince Michiyasu(Emperor Montoku) as the new Crown Prince in &apos;the Jowa Incident&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, it was written to emphasize the legitimacy of what happened in the Jowa Incident, where the title of Crown Prince was taken from Prince Tsunesada and given to Prince Michiyasu(Emperor Montoku).</e>
<cmt>Rewrote the sentence to be a little clearer for a native English reader and more succinct.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, it was written to emphasize the legitimacy of Prince Tsunesada&apos;s demotion from Crown Prince and the raising of Prince Michiyasu(Emperor Montoku) as the new Crown Prince in &apos;the Jowa Incident&apos;.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天皇の挙動を重視し実録的性格を国史に反映させた点で後の、日本三代実録等に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It greatly affected later works such as Veritable Records of Three Reigns of Japan (Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku), etc., on the point of emphasizing the emperor&apos;s actions and reflected the veritable record style of the National Histories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the points of emphasizing the emperor&apos;s actions and reflecting the authentic style of the National Histories, it greatly influenced later works such as Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (Veritable Records of Three Reigns of Japan).</e>
<cmt>Reordered the sentence to make it read a little better. Changed &quot;affected&quot; to &quot;influenced&quot; to be more accurate. Changed &quot;veritable record style&quot; to &quot;authentic style&quot; to read more naturally. Used Japanese title as above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the points of emphasizing the emperor&apos;s actions and reflecting the authentic style of the National Histories, it greatly influenced later works such as Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (Veritable Records of Three Reigns of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>平安時代後期には抄本が流布していたとされ、最古の写本である保延年間のものは、類聚国史から本文を補っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that abridged manuscripts were circulating in the late Heian period, and the oldest of these from the Hoen era was supplemented by using the text of the Classified National History (Ruiju Kokushi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that abridged manuscripts were circulating in the late Heian period, and that the oldest of these (from the Hoen era) was supplemented by using text from Ruiju Kokushi (Classified National History).</e>
<cmt>Put &quot;from the Hoen era&quot; in parentheses to make the sentence read a little smoother. Added &quot;that&quot; to &quot;the oldest of these&quot;. Removed &quot;the&quot; and replaced &quot;of&quot; with &quot;from&quot;. Used original Japanese title as above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that abridged manuscripts were circulating in the late Heian period, and that the oldest of these (from the Hoen era) was supplemented by using text from Ruiju Kokushi (Classified National History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、三条西家の六国史書写の段階でも、善本が入手できず、また、旁書などを本文に反映させた際、誤脱、錯簡などが生じ、現行の刊本もその影響を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as the complete text was not available even when the Six National Histories were copied by the Sanjonishi family, and with commentaries and other writings sometimes being incorporated into the text, there were several errors, omissions, and pages out of order due to errors in binding, etc., also reflected in the surviving printed editions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as the complete text was not available when the Six National Histories were transcribed by the Sanjonishi family, and commentaries and other writings were sometimes incorporated into the text which had pages out of order due to binding errors, many mistakes and omissions were made that are still present in the current printed editions.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &quot;also&quot; with &quot;furthermore&quot; as it seems more appropriate in this context. Removed &quot;even&quot; as I wasn&apos;t sure of its purpose. &quot;Transcribed&quot; is probably more accurate than &quot;copied&quot; here so I changed it. Replaced &quot;there were&quot; with &quot;along with&quot; to make the sentence read a bit smoother. Changed &quot;also reflected in the surviving printed editions&quot; to &quot;still present in the current printed editions&quot; as I think this reads more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as the complete text was not available when the Six National Histories were transcribed by the Sanjonishi family, and commentaries and other writings were sometimes incorporated into the text which had pages out of order due to binding errors, many mistakes and omissions were made that are still present in the current printed editions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lonicera(id:20638), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), BAKU(id:55205), 玄史生(id:43670), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nighthawks(id:36125), Ktoetx(id:104437), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>