<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古本説話集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kohon Setsuwashu (Collection of Old Tales)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kohon Setsuwashu (Collection of Old Tales)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kohon Setsuwashu (Collection of Old Tales)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>古本説話集（こほんせつわしゅう）は、平安時代末期か、遅くとも鎌倉時代初期には成立したと見られる説話集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kohon Setsuwashu is a narrative collection which is thought to have appeared during the last years of the Heian period, or in the early Kamakura period at latest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kohon Setsuwashu is a narrative collection and is believed to have appeared during the end of the Heian period, or at the latest, during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Kohon Setsuwashu&quot; is a narrative collection and is believed to have appeared during the end of the Heian period, or at the latest, during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>The Kohon Setsuwashu にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>具体的な成立時期は大治 (日本)年間（1126年－1131年）など諸説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opinion is divided on its specific appearance period, and some people believe it appeared in the Daiji era (from 1126 to 1131).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are others who believe that it had appeared in the Daiji era (1126 - 1131).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are others who believe that it had appeared in the Daiji (Japan) era (1126 - 1131).</e>
<cmt>大治（日本）年間 (Japan) を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>長く埋もれていたのを昭和18年（1943年）発見され、「古本説話集」と暫定的に命名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book had been in obscurity for a long time until it was discovered in 1943, and it was temporarily named &apos;Kohon Setsuwashu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book had been in obscurity for a long time until it was discovered in 1943, when it was temporarily named &apos;Kohon Setsuwashu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book had been in obscurity for a long time until it was discovered in 1943, when it was temporarily named &apos;Kohon Setsuwashu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>表紙が脱落し内題・外題が無く、編者・原書名ともに未詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The discovered book did not have its cover, the cover title, and the title on the first page of the book, so neither the name of the compiler nor the original title is still unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book was discovered without its cover or its title page, so neither the name of the compiler nor the original title is known.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book was discovered without its cover or its title page, so neither the name of the compiler nor the original title is known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>重要文化財梅沢本一冊が天下の孤本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Umezawa-bon (which literally means &quot;Umezawa book,&quot; representing a book held by the Umezawa family), which is designated as an important cultural property, is the only existing book.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Umezawa-bon (representing a book held by the Umezawa Family), which is designated as an important cultural property, is the only existing copy.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Umezawa-bon (representing a book held by the Umezawa Family), which is designated as an important cultural property, is the only existing copy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>前半は世俗説話46話、後半は仏法説話24話を収録。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first half of the book consists of 46 narratives about common customs, and the latter half consists of 24 Buddhist narratives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first part of the book consists of 46 narratives about common culture, and the latter part consists of 24 Buddhist narratives.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first part of the book consists of 46 narratives about common culture, and the latter part consists of 24 Buddhist narratives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>世俗説話には、紀貫之・凡河内躬恒・藤原公任などの才子に加え、和泉式部・赤染衛門・伊勢大輔・選子内親王ら王朝を代表する才媛が登場し、和歌を中心とする宮廷社会の風雅な逸事を集める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The common custom stories refer to notable talented women at the Imperial Court such as Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon, ISE no Taifu, and Imperial Princess Senshi as well as talented men such as KI no Tsurayuki, OSHIKOCHI no Mitsune, and FUJIWARA no Kinto, and elegant anecdotes of the Imperial Court are collected centering on Japanese poems in the first half part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characters of the stories of the first part include noteworthy and talented women of the Imperial Court such as Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon, ISE no Taifu, and Imperial Princess Senshi, as well as talented men such as KI no Tsurayuki, OSHIKOCHI no Mitsune, and FUJIWARA no Kinto, and many elegant anecdotes based on waka (Japanese poems) are used in the narratives.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characters of the stories of the first part include noteworthy and talented women of the Imperial Court such as Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon, ISE no Taifu, and Imperial Princess Senshi, as well as talented men such as KI no Tsurayuki, OSHIKOCHI no Mitsune, and FUJIWARA no Kinto, and many elegant anecdotes based on waka (Japanese poems) are used in the narratives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一方、仏法説話には観音・天王などの霊験譚や、寺院の縁起譚、往生譚、怪異譚などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Buddhist narratives include tales of miraculous efficacy of the Buddhist goddess of mercy and the god of Deva, tales of the history of Buddhist temples, tales about an easy and peaceful death, and tales of the supernatural.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Buddhist narratives include miraculous tales of devas and gods such as Kannon (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy), historical tales of Buddhist temples, tales about passing to the next life, and tales of the supernatural.</e>
<cmt>rewording;the actual name of Kannon should be used here;it is unclear what Tenno is referring to;(as a side note, devas are not gods, so &quot;god of Deva&quot; is not appropriate)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Buddhist narratives include miraculous tales of devas and gods such as Kannon (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy), historical tales of Buddhist temples, tales about passing to the next life, and tales of the supernatural.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『今昔物語集』『宇治拾遺物語』『世継物語』と共通する説話を多く有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many narratives in this book are also seen in the &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past), the &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (Collection of Tales from Uji), or the &quot;Yotsugi Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Generations).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many narratives in this book are also seen in the &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (Tales of the Past and Present), the &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (Tales from Uji Collection), or the &quot;Yotsugi Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Generations).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many narratives in this book are also seen in &quot;The Konjaku Monogatarishu&quot; (Tales of the Past and Present), &quot;The Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (Tales from Uji Collection), or &quot;The Yotsugi Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Generations).</e>
<cmt>Monogatari Shu をMonogatarishu に修正しました。統一リスト（レビュー結果：2009/06/30）を参考に、書名の定冠詞を大文字にしてクォーテーション内に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>新日本古典文学大系（岩波書店）に、『宇治拾遺物語』と合わせて収録。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The full text is available in the Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (New Japanese Classis Literature Systematic Edition, published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers) along with the &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The full text is available in both the Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (New Japanese Classic Literature Systematic Edition, published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers) and the &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>misspelling;rewording;if all of the narratives appear in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot;, then what is the point mentioning &quot;Uji&quot; in the previous sentence?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The full text is available in both the Shin Nihon Koten Bungaku Taikei (New Japanese Classic Literature Systematic Edition, published by Iwanami Shoten Publishers) and &quot;The Uji Shui Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（レビュー結果：2009/06/30）を参考にthe &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; を &quot;The Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、講談社学術文庫からは全訳が刊行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a complete modern translation is available in Kodansha Gakujutsu Bunko (The Academic Library, Kodansha Ltd.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a complete modern translation is available from Kodansha Gakujutsu Bunko (The Academic Library, Kodansha Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a complete modern translation is available from Kodansha Gakujutsu Bunko (The Academic Library, Kodansha Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yume149(id:17504), Oddmake(id:29591), Point136(id:211299), ECLIPSE(id:39342), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>