<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竹内文書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeuchi Monjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeuchi Monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeuchi Monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>竹内文書（たけうちもんじょ/たけのうちもんじょ。磯原文書、天津教文書ともいう）とは、神代文字で記された文書と、それを武烈天皇の勅命により武内宿禰（たけのうちのすくね）の孫の平群真鳥（へぐりのまとり）が漢字と片仮名交じり文に訳したとする写本群と、文字の刻んだ石、鉄剣など、一連の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeuchi monjo (or Takenouchi monjo; also called Isohara monjo or Amatsukyo monjo) is a collective name of a group of documents written in ancient Japanese characters and their translation in the form of a group of manuscripts written in mixture of Chinese characters and katakana prepared by HEGURI no Matori, who was a grandson of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune.and stones, iron sword, etc. inscribed with characters.</e>
<cmt>石や鉄剣を書物というのは無理があると思いますが、原文の通りに訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeuchi monjo (or Takenouchi monjo; also called Isohara monjo or Amatsukyo monjo) is the name for a number of documents written in ancient Japanese characters and their translations in the form of manuscripts written in a mixture of Chinese characters and katakana prepared by HEGURI no Matori, the grandson of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, and also including stones, iron swords, etc. inscribed with the characters.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeuchi monjo (or Takenouchi monjo; also called Isohara monjo or Amatsukyo monjo) is the name for a number of documents written in ancient Japanese characters and include their translations in the form of manuscripts written in a mixture of kanji characters and katakana prepared by HEGURI no Matori, the grandson of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, under the order of Emperor Buretsu and also inscriptions on stones, iron swords, etc.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>いわゆる古史古伝の書物であり、写本自体が焼失もしくは非公開であるため、「偽書」「偽史」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are so-called koshi koden books and, because manuscripts themselves were lost by fire or not open to the public, they are deemed as &quot;gisho (apocryphal documents)&quot; or &quot;gishi (apocryphal history).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are the so-called koshi koden books and, because the original manuscripts themselves were lost in a fire or were not open to the public, they are deemed as &quot;gisho (apocryphal documents)&quot; or &quot;gishi (apocryphal history).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are the so-called koshi koden books and, because the original manuscripts themselves were lost in a fire or were not open to the public, they are deemed as &apos;gisho&apos; (apocryphal documents) or &apos;gishi&apos; (apocryphal history).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>竹内文書は、新宗教団体である天津教の教典にも、位置づけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeuchi monjo is also ranked as the scriptures of Amatsukyo, which is an organization of new religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeuchi monjo are also ranked as scriptures of Amatsukyo, a new organized religion.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeuchi monjo are also considered as the scriptures of Amatsukyo, a new organized religion.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>書物だけではなく、下記に述べる神宝の類まで包括して「竹内文献」ということが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Takeuchi bunken (Takeuchi literature)&quot; is often used to cover not only books, but also shinpo (sacred treasure) as described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Takeuchi bunken (Takeuchi literature)&quot; is often used to cover not only books, but also shinpo (sacred treasure) as described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeuchi bunken&apos; (Takeuchi literature) is often used to cover not only books, but also shinpo (sacred treasure) as described below.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>平群真鳥の子孫であるとされる竹内家に、養子に入ったと自称する竹内巨麿（たけうちきよまろ/たけのうちきよまろ）が、昭和3年（1928年）3月29日に文書の存在を公開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKEUCHI Kiyomaro (or TAKENOUCHI Kiyomaro), who profess himself as an adopted child of the Takeuchi family which is said to be a descendant of HEGURI no Matori, opened to the public the existence of monjo (documents) on March 29, 1928.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKEUCHI Kiyomaro (or TAKENOUCHI Kiyomaro), who professed himself to be an adopted child of the Takeuchi family which is said to be a descendant of HEGURI no Matori, opened to the public the existence of monjo (documents) on March 29, 1928.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAKEUCHI Kiyomaro (or TAKENOUCHI Kiyomaro), who professed himself to be an adopted child of the Takeuchi family which is said to be a descendant of HEGURI no Matori, announced the existence of monjo (documents) to the public on March 29, 1928.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>写本の多くは焼失し失われているが、南朝 (日本)系の古文献を再編したとされる写本もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of manuscripts were lost by fire or other causes, but there are manuscripts which are said to be reorganized from old literatures of the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of manuscripts were lost in fire or from other causes, but there are manuscripts in existence which are said to be reorganized from the old literature of the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of manuscripts were lost in fire or from other causes, but there are manuscripts in existence which are said to be edited from old documents of the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>竹内文書では神武天皇からはじまる現在の皇朝を「神倭朝（かむやまとちょう）」と呼び、これ以前に「上古25代」（または「皇統25代」）とそれに続く「ウガヤフキアエズ王朝（あえずちょう）73代」（73代目は神武天皇のことである）があり、さらにそれ以前に「天神7代」があったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Takeuchi monjo, the present reigning line starting from the Emperor Jinmu is called &quot;Kamuyamato-cho&quot; and it is said that, before it, there were &quot;joko (ancient times) twenty-five eras&quot; (or, &quot;koto (imperial line) twenty-five eras) followed by &quot;seventy-three eras of Ugaya Fukiaezu Dynasty&quot; (the seventy-third emperor was the Emperor Jinmu) and even before them there were &quot;Tenjin seven eras.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Takeuchi monjo, the present reigning line starting from Emperor Jinmu is called &quot;Kamuyamato-cho&quot; and it is said that, before that, there were &quot;joko (ancient times) twenty-five eras&quot; (or, &quot;koto - imperial line - twenty-five eras) followed by &quot;seventy-three eras of the Ugaya Fukiaezu Dynasty&quot; (the seventy-third emperor was Emperor Jinmu) and even before these there were &quot;seven Tenjin eras.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Takeuchi monjo, the present reigning line starting from Emperor Jinmu is called &apos;Kamuyamato-cho&apos; and it is said that, before that, there were &apos;joko (ancient times) twenty-five eras&apos; (or, &apos;koto - imperial line - twenty-five eras&apos;) followed by &apos;seventy-three eras of the Ugaya Fukiaezu Dynasty&apos; (the seventy-third emperor was Emperor Jinmu) and even before these there were &apos;seven Tenjin eras.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>ちなみに上古21代天皇は、「伊邪那岐身光天津日嗣天日天皇」といい、イザナギ（『古事記』では伊邪那岐命、『日本書紀』では、伊弉諾神）にあたるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the twenty-first emperor of the joko dynasty is called &quot;Izanagi mihikari amatsu hitsugi amehino sumiramikoto&quot;and, according to their insistence, corresponds to Izanagi (Izanagi no mikoto, in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (literally,records of ancient matters) and Izanagi no kami in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twenty-first emperor of the joko dynasty is called &quot;Izanagi mihikari amatsu hitsugi amehino sumiramikoto&quot;and, according to their insistence, corresponds to Izanagi (Izanagi no mikoto, in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (literally,records of ancient matters) and Izanagi no kami in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twenty-first emperor of the Joko dynasty is called &apos;Izanagi mihikari amatsu hitsugi amehino sumiramikoto&apos; and corresponds to Izanagi (Izanagi no mikoto, in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (literally, records of ancient matters) and Izanagi no kami in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その2子のうち1子が「月向津彦月弓命亦ノ名須佐之男命」すなわちツクヨミ（『古事記』では月読命、『日本書紀』では月弓尊）であり、スサノオ（『日本書紀』では素盞嗚尊・素戔嗚尊、『古事記』では建速須佐之男命・須佐乃袁尊）の別名とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his two children was 月向津彦月弓命 [読み不明] or, another name, Susanoo no mikoto, namely Tsukuyomi (&quot;Tsukuyomi no mikoto in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and Tsukuyuno no mikoto in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;) and it is said to be another name of Susanoo (Susanoo no mikoto, written as 素盞嗚尊 or 素戔嗚尊 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and 建速須佐之男命 or 須佐乃袁尊 in &quot;Kojiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his two children was 月向津彦月弓命 [読み不明] or, another name, Susanoo no mikoto, namely Tsukuyomi (&quot;Tsukuyomi no mikoto in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and Tsukuyuno no mikoto in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;) and it is said to be another name of Susanoo (Susanoo no mikoto, written as 素盞嗚尊 or 素戔嗚尊 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and 建速須佐之男命 or 須佐乃袁尊 in &quot;Kojiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his two children was 月向津彦月弓命 otherwise known as Susanoo no mikoto, in other words, Tsukuyomi (Tsukuyomi no mikoto in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and Tsukuyumi no mikoto in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;) and it is said to be another name of Susanoo (Susanoo no mikoto, written as 素盞嗚尊 or 素戔嗚尊 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and 建速須佐之男命 or 須佐乃袁尊 in &quot;Kojiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>その他次のような記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are following descriptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are the following descriptions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are the following descriptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>ビッグバンさえ起こっていない紀元前3175億年に上古初代天皇が存在し、上古2代天皇の在位が320億年に達している（もっとも上古天皇では天皇の名前は世襲であり、1代数十人だとしているが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first emperor of joko existed in 317.5 billion years before Christ when even Big Bang had not occurred and the reign of the second emperor of joko covers 32 billion years (although it is said that the name of emperor of joko was succeeded and there were several tens of emperors existed for one era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first emperor of joko existed 317.5 billion years before Christ even before the Big Bang occurred and the reign of the second emperor of joko covers 32 billion years (although it is said that the name of the emperor of joko was succeeded and there were several tens of emperors existed for one era).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first emperor of Joko existed 317.5 billion years before Christ, even before the Big Bang occurred and the reign of the second emperor of Joko covers thirty-two billion years (although it is said that the name of the emperor of Joko was passed on to his successor and there were about fifty emperors per generation).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>「イスキリス・クリスマス（イエス・キリストとされる）の遺言」という「イスキリス・クリスマス。福の神。八戸太郎天空神。五色人へ遣わし文」で始まる文書がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a document called &quot;Will of Isukirisu Kurisumasu (said to be Jesus Christ) that begins with &quot;Isukirisu Kurisumasu. A God of Wealth. Hachinohe Taro Tenkujin. Letter given to five-color people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>四つの文を一つにし、三つに分割し直しました。「イスキリス・クリスマス」の綴りは、不明です。「八戸太郎天空神」の読み方は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a document called the &quot;Will of Isukirisu Kurisumasu (said to be Jesus Christ) that begins with &quot;Isukirisu Kurisumasu. The God of Wealth. Hachinohe Taro Tenkujin. Letter given to five-color people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a document called the &apos;Will of Isukirisu Kurisumasu&apos; (said to be Jesus Christ) that begins with &apos;Isukirisu Kurisumasu. God of good fortune. Hachinohe Taro Tenkujin (heavenly person, Taro HACHINOHE). Letter given to five-color people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それによると十字架上で死なずに渡来（ゴルゴダの丘で処刑されたのは、弟のイスキリと記する）、1935年（昭和10年）8月初に竹内巨麿が青森県の戸来村（現在の新郷村）で発見した十来塚（竹内巨麿が村長に書くようにいった）が「イスキリス・クリスマス」の墓であるすなわちキリストの墓とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to it, he did not die on the cross and came to Japan (it is recorded that the person who was killed on the hill of Golgotha was his younger brother. Isukiri.), and Juraizuka [十来塚 正しい読み不明] (Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI told the village chief to write it.) which Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI found in Herai Village (present Shingo Village) in Aomori Prefecture at the beginning of August 1935 is the grave of &quot;Isukirisu Kurisumasu&quot; namely the grave of Jesus Christ.</e>
<cmt>四つの文を一つにし、三つに分割し直しました。「イスキリ」の綴りは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this document, he did not die on the cross but came to Japan (it is recorded that the person who was killed on the hill of Golgotha was his younger brother. Isukiri.), and Juraizuka [十来塚 正しい読み不明] (Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI told the village chief to write it.) which Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI found in Herai Village (present Shingo Village) in Aomori Prefecture at the beginning of August 1935 is the grave of &quot;Isukirisu Kurisumasu&quot; namely the grave of Jesus Christ.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this document, he did not die on the cross but came to Japan (it is recorded that the person who was killed on the hill of Golgotha was his younger brother, Isukiri), and Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI found Juraizuka (十来塚) (Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI told the village chief to write it), the grave of &apos;Isukirisu Kurisumasu&apos;, namely the grave of Jesus Christin Herai Village (present Shingo-mura) in Aomori Prefecture at the beginning of August 1935.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、モーセの十戒は実は表十戒、裏十戒であり、真十戒を天津教の神宝として天津教が所有し、天皇が、来日したモーセに授け、モーセの墓が石川県の宝達志水町に存在しているとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it says that Moses&apos; Ten Commandments are in fact Omote jikkai (front ten commandments) and Ura jikkai (back ten commandments) and true ten commandments was possessed by Amatsukyo and the emperor gave it to Moses when he came to Japan, and Moses&apos; grave exists in Hodatsushimizu Town in Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>四つの文を一つにし、三つに分割し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it says that Moses&apos; Ten Commandments are in fact Omote jikkai (front ten commandments) and Ura jikkai (back ten commandments) and the true ten commandments were possessed by Amatsukyo and the emperor gave it to Moses when he came to Japan, and Moses&apos; grave exists in Hodatsushimizu Town in Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it says that Moses&apos; Ten Commandments are in fact Omote jikkai (front ten commandments) and Ura jikkai (back ten commandments) and the true ten commandments were held by Amatsukyo as sacred treasures and the emperor gave them to Moses when he came to Japan, and Moses&apos; grave exists in Hodatsushimizu-cho in Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>釈迦をはじめ世界の大宗教教祖はすべて来日し、天皇に仕えたことになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to it, founders of all major religions including Shakyamuni came to Japan, and served the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, founders of all major religions including Shakyamuni came to Japan, and served the emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, founders of all major religions including Shakyamuni came to Japan, and served the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>世界には五色人（いついろひと。黄人（きびと、日本人を含むアジア人）、赤人（あかびと、ネイティブアメリカンやユダヤ人等に少し見られる）、青人（あおびと、肌が青白い。現在は純血種ほとんどなし）、黒人（くろびと、インドの原住民族やアフリカ人等）、白人（しろびと、白い肌やプラチナ、ブロンドを髪をしたヨーロッパ人））が存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There existed itsuirohito (five-color people) (kibito (yellow people, Asian including Japanese), akabito (red people, some native Americans and Jews); aobito (blue people, pale skin, very few pure-blooded at present), kurobito (black people, natives in India and Africans, etc.) and shirobito (white people, Europeans with white skin and platinum blonde hair) in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There existed itsuirohito (five-color people) (kibito (yellow people, Asian including Japanese), akabito (red people, some native Americans and Jews); aobito (blue people, pale skin, very few pure-blooded at present), kurobito (black people, natives in India and Africans, etc.) and shirobito (white people, Europeans with white skin and platinum blonde hair) in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There existed itsuirohito (five-color people) (kibito (yellow people, Asian including Japanese), akabito (red people, some native Americans and Jews); aobito (blue people, pale skin, very few pure-blooded at present), kurobito (black people, natives in India and Africans, etc.) and shirobito (white people, Europeans with white skin and platinum blonde hair) in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>皇祖皇太神宮が全世界の中心である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koso Kotai Jingu Shrine is the center of the whole world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koso Kotai Jingu Shrine is the center of the whole world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koso Kotai Jingu Shrine is the center of the whole world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>注：現在茨城県に存在する神宮は、遷宮したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note: The shrine which exists in Ibaraki Prefecture was moved from other place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note: The shrine which exists in Ibaraki Prefecture was moved from another place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note: The shrine which exists in Ibaraki Prefecture was moved from another place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>3000年以上前の上古2代天皇の時代に16人の弟妹たちが全世界に散らばり、彼らの名前は今も地名として残っているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the era of the second emperor of joko more than three thousand years before, sixteen younger brothers and sisters scattered all over world and their names still remain as names of place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the era of the second emperor of joko more than three thousand years before, sixteen younger brothers and sisters scattered all over world and their names still remain as names of the place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the era of the second emperor of joko more than three thousand years ago, sixteen younger brothers and sisters scattered all over world and their names still remain as place names</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その中には「ヨハネスブルグ」「ボストン」「ニューヨーク」といった名前が見られるが、これらの都市が建設されたのはかなり新しい時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Johannesburg&quot;, &quot;Boston&quot; and &quot;New York&quot; are included in such names, those cities were built in rather recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;Johannesburg,&quot; &quot;Boston,&quot; and &quot;New York&quot; are included in such names, those cities were built rather recently.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &apos;Johannesburg,&apos; &apos;Boston,&apos; and &apos;New York&apos; are included as such names, these cities were built rather recently.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>約3000年前の不合朝64代の時代に皇子31名と皇女43名が巡幸し、長である万国巡知彦尊が知勇大力で外敵を制圧したのが「桃太郎」の起源だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the origin of &quot;Momotaro&quot; is that, approximately three thousand years ago in the era of the sixty-fourth emperor of Aezucho (Aezu dynasty) thirty-one princes and forty-three princesses made imperial tours and 万国巡知彦尊 [読み不明], who was the head of them, was remarkable for both wisdom and courage and had matchless physical strength.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the origin of &quot;Momotaro&quot; is that, approximately three thousand years ago in the era of the sixty-fourth emperor of Aezucho (Aezu dynasty) thirty-one princes and forty-three princesses made imperial tours and 万国巡知彦尊 [読み不明], who was their leader, was remarkable for both wisdom and courage and had matchless physical strength.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the origin of &apos;Momotaro&apos; (the Peach Boy) is that, approximately three thousand years ago in the era of the sixty-fourth emperor of Aezucho (Aezu dynasty) thirty-one princes and forty-three princesses made imperial tours and 万国巡知彦尊, who was a leader with wisdom, courage and matchless physical strength, battled and won over external enemies.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>不合朝69代神足別豊鋤天皇の代にミヨイ、タミアラが陥没した（なおこのミヨイ、タミアラの文字は1940年10月の『天国棟梁天皇御系図宝の巻き前巻・後巻』児玉天民著が初出である）とムー大陸（1938年6月号の『神日本』の「陥没大陸ムー国」が日本での初期紹介）やアトランティス大陸を思わせる記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a description that, in the era of the sixty-ninth emperor of Aezu dynasty, the Emperor Kantaru waketoyosuki, Miyoi and Tamiara collapsed (Those characters, Miyoi and Tamiara&quot; were first seen in &quot;天国棟梁天皇御系図宝の巻き前巻・後巻&quot; [正しい読み、意味とも確認できていません。] by Tenmin KODAMA in October 1940), which description remind us of the Continent of Mu (&quot;Kanbotsu tairiku Mu koku&quot; (Collapsed Continent of Mu) in &quot;Kami Nihon,&quot; June edition in 1938 was the early introduction to Japan) or Continent of Atlantis.</e>
<cmt>『神日本』の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description that explains, in the era of the sixty-ninth emperor of the Aezu dynasty, the Emperor Kantaru waketoyosuki, Miyoi and Tamiara collapsed (Those characters, Miyoi and Tamiara&quot; were first seen in &quot;天国棟梁天皇御系図宝の巻き前巻・後巻&quot; [正しい読み、意味とも確認できていません。] by Tenmin KODAMA in October 1940), in which the description reminds us of the Continent of Mu (&quot;Kanbotsu tairiku Mu koku&quot; (Collapsed Continent of Mu) in &quot;Kami Nihon,&quot; June edition in 1938 was the early introduction to Japan) or Continent of Atlantis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description that explains Miyoi and Tamiara collapsed (the characters for Miyoi and Tamiara are first seen in the books &quot;天国棟梁天皇御系図宝の巻き前巻・後巻&quot; by Tenmin KODAMA in October 1940) in the era of the sixty-ninth emperor of the Aezu dynasty, the Emperor Kantaru waketoyosuki, which reminiscent of the Continent of Mu first introduced into Japan in &apos;Kanbotsu tairiku Mu koku&apos; (Collapsed Continent of Mu) in &quot;Kami Nihon,&quot; June 1938 edition) or the Continent of Atlantis.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>※このページの記述には宗教団体「天津教」の教理が含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Descriptions on this page contains the religious principles of the religious organization &quot;Amatsukyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Descriptions on this page contain the religious principles of the religious organization &quot;Amatsukyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Descriptions on this page contain the religious principles of the religious organization &apos;Amatsukyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そのため、本来の竹内文書の内容と相違する文も含まれていることに注意して欲しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, please note that certain sentences with different contents from that of original Takeuchi monjo are contained.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, please note that there are certain sentences containing differing content from the original Takeuchi monjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, please note that there are certain sentences containing differing content from the original Takeuchi monjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>元々の竹内文書は、同宗教団体と直接関係はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Takeuchi monjo has no direct relationship with the religious organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Takeuchi monjo had no direct relationship with the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Takeuchi monjo had no direct relationship with the religious organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>竹内巨麿について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>竹内巨麿（明治8年(1875年)? - 昭和40年(1965年)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI (circa 1875 - 1965)</e>
<cmt>生年没年を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>明治43年（1910年）秋、皇祖皇太神宮を復興。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In autumn 1910, he restored Kosokotai Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In autumn 1910, he restored Kosokotai Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In autumn 1910, he restored Kosokotai Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>天津教の開祖となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the founder of Amatsukyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the founder of Amatsukyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the founder of Amatsukyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>『明治奇人今義経鞍馬修行実歴譚』長峰波山 大正元年(1912年) 八幡書店 ISBN 4893502328 (1987/01)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Meiji kijin imayoshitsune Kurama shugyo jitsurekitan&quot; by Hazan NAGAMINE, 1912, Hachiman Shoten ISBN 4893502328 (1987/01)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Meiji kijin imayoshitsune Kurama shugyo jitsurekitan&quot; by Hazan NAGAMINE, 1912, Hachiman Shoten ISBN 4893502328 (1987/01)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Meiji kijin imayoshitsune Kurama shugyo jitsurekitan&quot; by Hazan NAGAMINE, 1912, Hachiman Shoten ISBN 4893502328 (1987/01)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>竹内巨麿の口述書であるが、これにはまだ、竹内文書も平群真鳥についても述べられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a transcription by Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, but neither Takeuchi monjo nor HEGURI no Matori was mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a transcription by Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, but neither Takeuchi monjo nor HEGURI no Matori were mentioned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a transcription by Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, but neither Takeuchi monjo nor HEGURI no Matori were mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大正10年頃、『長慶天皇御真筆』、『後醍醐天皇御真筆』、『日蓮上人御真筆』などを所有していると公開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1921, he announced that he possessed &quot;Own handwriting of the Emperor Chokei,&quot; &quot;Own handwriting of the Emperor Godaigo,&quot; &quot;Own handwriting of Nichiren Shonin&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1921, he announced that he possessed &quot;the handwriting of the Emperor Chokei,&quot; &quot;the handwriting of the Emperor Godaigo,&quot; &quot;the handwriting of Nichiren Shonin&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1921, he announced that he possessed &quot;the handwriting of the Emperor Chokei,&quot; &quot;the handwriting of the Emperor Godaigo,&quot; &quot;the handwriting of Nichiren Shonin&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>昭和4年（1929年）8月14日、戸籍の名を巨麿に改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 14, 1929, he changed his name in the family register to Kiyomaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 14, 1929, he changed his name in the family register to Kiyomaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 14, 1929, he changed his name in the family register to Kiyomaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>昭和11～12年（1936～37年）頃（諸伝あり）、不敬罪で起訴される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1936 to 1937 (there are various views), he was indicted for lese majesty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1936 to 1937 (there are various views), he was indicted for lese majesty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1936 or 1937 (there are several theories), he was indicted for defamation of royalty.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>文献批判</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Criticism on literatures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Criticism of the literature</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Criticism of the literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>山崎鐵丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsumaru YAMAZAKI</e>
<cmt>「山崎鐵丸」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsumaru YAMAZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsumaru YAMAZAKI (山崎鐵丸)</e>
<cmt>読み方が確認できないため、漢字名を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>山崎鐵丸は、川浦操の竹内文書紹介論文「長慶天皇の山陵に就いて」（昭和2年4月5日『國學院雑誌』33巻4号）をみた後「竹内家の記録に就いて」（昭和2年8月『國學院雑誌』33巻8号）において文献批判を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After reading an article by Misao KAWAURA &quot;Regarding mausoleum of the Emperor Chokei &quot; introducing Takeuchi monjo (&quot;Kokugakuin Zasshi&quot; Vol. 33 No. 4, April 5, 1927), Tetsumaru YAMAZAKI criticized about literatures in &quot;Regarding records of the Takeuchi family&quot; (&quot;Kokugakuin Zasshi&quot; Vol. No. 8, August 1927).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After reading an article by Misao KAWAURA &quot;Regarding the mausoleum of the Emperor Chokei &quot; introducing Takeuchi monjo (&quot;Kokugakuin Zasshi&quot; Vol. 33 No. 4, April 5, 1927), Tetsumaru YAMAZAKI criticized the literature &quot;Regarding records of the Takeuchi family&quot; (&quot;Kokugakuin Zasshi&quot; Vol. No. 8, August 1927).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After reading an article by Misao KAWAURA, &apos;Regarding the mausoleum of the Emperor Chokei&apos; (&quot;Kokugakuin Zasshi&quot; (The Journal of Kokugakuin University) Vol. 33 No. 4, April 5, 1927) that introduced Takeuchi monjo, Tetsumaru YAMAZAKI criticized the work in his article &apos;Regarding records of the Takeuchi family&apos; (&quot;Kokugakuin Zasshi&quot; Vol. 33 No. 8, August 1927).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>狩野亨吉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokichi KANO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokichi KANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokichi KANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>狩野亨吉は昭和3年5月に、天津教信者2名から7枚の写真の鑑定依頼を受けたが断った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1928, Kokichi KANO was asked for expert opinion on seven photographs by two believers of Amatsukyo, but he refused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1928, Kokichi KANO was asked for an expert opinion of seven photographs by two believers of Amatsukyo, but he refused.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1928, Kokichi KANO was asked for an expert opinion of seven photographs by two believers of Amatsukyo, but he refused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>昭和10年(1935年)『日本医事新報』から鑑定を依頼され、7枚中5枚を鑑定し、偽造と回答した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1935, he was asked by Japan Medical Journal for expert opinion, and he checked five out of seven and replied that they were apocryphal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1935, he was asked by the Japan Medical Journal for an expert opinion, and he checked five out of seven and replied that they were apocryphal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1935, he was asked by the &quot;Japan Medical Journal&quot; for an expert opinion, and he checked five out of seven and replied that they were fakes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>翌、昭和11年（1936年）6月、岩波書店の『思想』誌上に発表した「天津教古文書の批判」により偽書と証明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next year, in June 1936, he proved by &quot;Criticism on ancient documents of Amatsukyo&quot; published in &quot;Shiso&quot; of Iwanami Shoten, that they were apocryphal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, in June 1936, he proved in &quot;Criticism on ancient documents of Amatsukyo&quot; published by &quot;Shiso&quot; of Iwanami Shoten, that they were apocryphal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, in June 1936, he proved in &apos;Criticism on ancient documents of Amatsukyo&apos; published by &quot;Shiso&quot; of Iwanami Shoten, that they were apocryphal.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>なお、鑑定したのは以下の5文書の写真である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He checked photographs of the following five documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He checked the photographs of the following five documents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He checked the photographs of the following five documents.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>『長慶太神宮御由来』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chokei daijingu goyurai&quot; (History of Chokei Daijingu Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chokei daijingu goyurai&quot; (History of the Chokei Daijingu Shrine)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chokei daijingu goyurai&quot; (History of the Chokei Daijingu Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>『長慶天皇御真筆』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chokei Tenno Goshinpitsu&quot; (Own handwriting of the Emperor Chokei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chokei Tenno Goshinpitsu&quot; (the handwriting of Emperor Chokei</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chokei Tenno Goshinpitsu&quot; (the handwriting of Emperor Chokei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>『後醍醐天皇御真筆』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Godaigo Tenno Goshinpitsu&quot; (Own handwriting of the Emperor Godaigo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Godaigo Tenno Goshinpitsu&quot; (the handwriting of Emperor Godaigo)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Godaigo Tenno Goshinpitsu&quot; (the handwriting of Emperor Godaigo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>『大日本天皇同太古上々代御皇統譜神代文字之巻 大臣紀氏竹内平群真鳥宿禰書字真筆』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;大日本天皇同太古上々代御皇統譜神代文字之巻 大臣紀氏竹内平群真鳥宿禰書字真筆&quot; [正確な読みが確認できませんでした。]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;大日本天皇同太古上々代御皇統譜神代文字之巻 大臣紀氏竹内平群真鳥宿禰書字真筆&quot; [正確な読みが確認できませんでした。]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roll of the names of Japanese Emperors from ancient times in ancient Japanese characters written by Daijin Kishi Takuchi Heguri Mato Sukune</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>『大日本国太古代上々代神代文字之巻』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;大日本国太古代上々代神代文字之巻&quot; [正確な読みが確認できませんでした。]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;大日本国太古代上々代神代文字之巻&quot; [正確な読みが確認できませんでした。]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roll of ancient Japanese characters from ancient times</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>なお狩野亨吉は、昭和17年に検察側証人として言語学者の橋本進吉とともに出廷証言する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1942, Kokichi KANO appeared in court and testified as a witness for the prosecution, together with Shinkichi HASHIMOTO, who was a linguist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1942, Kokichi KANO appeared in court and testified as a witness for the prosecution, together with Shinkichi HASHIMOTO, who was a linguist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1942, Kokichi KANO appeared in court and testified as a witness for the prosecution, together with Shinkichi HASHIMOTO, who was a linguist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>熊沢天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumazawa Tenno (Emperor Kumazawa)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumazawa Tenno (Emperor Kumazawa)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumazawa Tenno (Emperor Kumazawa)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>吉野朝廷の熊沢天皇と名乗った熊沢寛道は、明治39年ごろ南朝方の寺院から盗まれた宝が古物商を経て天津教が買いとったと推測し、返還を要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiromichi KUMAZAWA, who announced himself as the Emperor Kumazawa of the Yoshino Court, surmised that treasures stolen from temples on the Southern Court side around 1906 were bought by Amatsukyo through a secondhand dealer and required return of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiromichi KUMAZAWA, who announced himself as Emperor Kumazawa of the Yoshino Court, surmised that treasures stolen from temples on the Southern Court side around 1906 were bought by Amatsukyo through a secondhand dealer and required their return.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromichi KUMAZAWA, who proclaimed himself as Emperor Kumazawa of the Yoshino Court, surmised that treasures stolen from temples of the Southern Court around 1906 were bought by Amatsukyo through a secondhand dealer and demanded their return.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>天津教弾圧事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>第一次天津教弾圧事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>昭和5年（1930年）12月7日～19日、「東京日日新聞」に批判記事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From December 7 through 19, 1930, articles of criticism appeared in &quot;Tokyo Nichinichi Shimbun.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From December 7 through 19, 1930, articles of criticism appeared in the &quot;Tokyo Nichinichi Shimbun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From December 7 through 19, 1930, articles of criticism appeared in the &apos;Tokyo Nichinichi Shimbun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>警視庁が詐欺罪容疑で竹内巨磨、前田常蔵、高畠康寿を取り調べする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keishi-cho (Tokyo Metropolitan Police Department) questioned Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, Tsunezo MAEDA and Yasuhisa TAKABATAKE on suspicion of fraud.</e>
<cmt>「前田常蔵、高畠康寿」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keishi-cho (Tokyo Metropolitan Police Department) questioned Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, Tsunezo MAEDA and Yasuhisa TAKABATAKE on suspicion of fraud.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keishi-cho (Tokyo Metropolitan Police Department) questioned Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, Tsunezo MAEDA (前田常蔵) and Yasuhisa TAKABATAKE (高畠康寿) on suspicion of fraud.</e>
<cmt>読み方が不明なため、漢字を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>不起訴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nonprosecution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nonprosecution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No one was prosecuted.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>昭和7年（1932年）内務省特高警察が竹内巨磨を拘引、不敬の言動により同年6月、神宝拝観禁止、神社の鳥居を撤去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1932, the Special Higher Police of the Ministry of Home Affairs arrested Kiyomaro, and, in June in the same year, showing sacred treasures was prohibited and the torii of the shrine was removed due to insulting and disrespectful speech and behavior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1932, the Special Higher Police of the Ministry of Home Affairs arrested Kiyomaro, and, in June of the same year, showing of the sacred treasures was prohibited and the torii of the shrine was removed due to insulting, disrespectful speech and behavior.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1932, the Special Higher Police of the Ministry of Home Affairs arrested Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, and showing of the sacred treasures was prohibited and the torii (shrine gate) of the shrine was removed due to insulting, disrespectful speech and behavior in June 1932.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>第二次天津教弾圧事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second oppression of Amatsukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>昭和10年（1935年）12月28日神宝が秦真次（皇道派の実質リーダーの真崎甚三郎の腹心でもあった）の手により東京市・靖国神社の遊就館の松田常太館長にたくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 28, 1935, the sacred treasures were deposited to Tsuneta MATSUDA, who was chief of Yushukan of the Yasukuni Jinja Shrine in Tokyo by Shinji HATA (who was also a confidant of Jinzaburo MAAKI who was virtual leader of Kodo-ha (Imperial Way&apos; faction)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 28, 1935, the sacred treasures were given to Tsuneta MATSUDA, who was chief of Yushukan of the Yasukuni Jinja Shrine in Tokyo by Shinji HATA (who was also a confidant of Jinzaburo MAAKI who was the virtual leader of Kodo-ha - Imperial Way&apos; faction).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 28, 1935, the sacred treasures were given to Tsuneta MATSUDA, who was chief of Yushukan of the Yasukuni Jinja Shrine in Tokyo by Shinji HATA (who was also a close confidant of Jinzaburo MAZAKI, the actual leader of Kodo-ha - Imperial Way&apos; faction).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>昭和11年(1936年)2月13日朝、茨城県多賀郡磯原町にて竹内巨麿（昭和12年7月7日まで水戸警察で拘留）と磯原館という旅館の吉田兼吉が不敬罪、文書偽造行使罪、詐欺罪容疑で逮捕された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the morning on February 13, 1936, in Isohara Town, Taga County, Ibaraki Prefecture, Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI (put under arrest in Mito Police until July 7, 1937) and Kanekichi YOSHIDA of Isoharakan hotel were arrested on suspicion of lese majesty, forgery of documents and uttering forged documents and fraud.</e>
<cmt>「吉田兼吉」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the morning of February 13, 1936, in Isohara Town, Taga County, Ibaraki Prefecture, Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI (placed under arrest by Mito Police until July 7, 1937) and Kanekichi YOSHIDA of Isoharakan hotel were arrested on suspicion of lese majesty, forgery of documents and uttering forged documents and fraud.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the morning of February 13, 1936, in Isohara-cho, Taga-gun, Ibaraki Prefecture, Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI (under custody of the Mito Police until July 7, 1937) and Kanekichi YOSHIDA of Isoharakan hotel were arrested on suspicion of defamation of royalty, forgery and use of forged documents and fraud.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>同年、4月17日検察書類送致、同月30日、竹内巨麿、神宝を水戸地方裁判所に移す旨の受託書を書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 17 in the same year, prosecutor&apos;s paper was sent and on April 30, Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI wrote a jutakusho (depositing documents) to transfer the sacred treasures to Mito District Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 17 of the same year, the prosecutor&apos;s paper was sent and on April 30, Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI wrote a jutakusho (depositing documents) to transfer the sacred treasures to the Mito District Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 17 of the same year, the prosecution papers were processed and on April 30, Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI wrote a jutakusho (consignment documents) to transfer the sacred treasures to the Mito District Court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>昭和12年(1937年）12月11日、逮捕者15名中竹内巨麿のみが不敬罪で起訴される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 11, 1937, only Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, out of 15 arrested persons, was prosecuted for lese majesty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 11, 1937, only Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI, out of 15 people arrested, was prosecuted for lese majesty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 11, 1937, only Kiyomaro TAKEUCHI out of fifteen people arrested, was prosecuted for defamation of royalty.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>昭和17年（1942年）3月16日一審不敬罪有罪判決。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 16, 1942, the first trial decided guilty for lese majesty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 16, 1942, the first trial decision was guilty for lese majesty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 16, 1942, the first trial decision was guilty for defamation of royalty.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>上告。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>上告代理人弁護士は田多井四郎治、宮本正美、特別弁護人鵜澤總明（後の極東国際軍事裁判の日本弁護団長）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attorneys for appeal were Shiroji TATAI and Masami MIYAMOTO, and the special counsel was Fusaaki UZAWA (later, chief of defense team of Japan in Tokyo Tribunal of War Criminals.</e>
<cmt>「田多井四郎治、宮本正美」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attorneys for the appeal were Shiroji TATAI and Masami MIYAMOTO, and the special counsel was Fusaaki UZAWA (later, chief of the defense team of Japan in Tokyo Tribunal of War Criminals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attorneys for the appeal were Shiroji TATAI and Masami MIYAMOTO, and the special counsel was Fusaaki UZAWA (later, chief of the defense team for Japan during the Tokyo Tribunal of War Criminals).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>昭和19年12月12日、大審院（現最高裁判所）無罪判決、結審。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 12, Daishinin (present Japanese Supreme Court) found not guilty and the trial was concluded..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 12, Daishinin (present Japanese Supreme Court) found he was not guilty and the trial was concluded..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 12, 1944, the Daishinin (present Japanese Supreme Court) found him not guilty and the trial was concluded.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>解散指定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designation for dissolution</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designation for dissolution</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designated to be dissolved</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>昭和25年（1950年）1月連合国軍最高司令官総司令部（GHQ/SCAP）から天津教は解散指定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1950, the General Headquarters of the Allied Forces/Supreme Commander for the Allied Power (GHQ/SCAP) designated Amatsukyo as a n organization to dissolve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1950, the General Headquarters of the Allied Forces/Supreme Commander for the Allied Power (GHQ/SCAP) designated Amatsukyo as an organization to be dissolved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1950, the General Headquarters of the Allied Forces/Supreme Commander for the Allied Power (GHQ/SCAP) designated Amatsukyo as an organization to be dissolved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>焼失と疑惑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Destruction by fire and suspicion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Destruction by fire and suspicion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Destruction by fire and suspicion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>この裁判にあたり、皇祖皇太神宮から「神宮神祠不敬被告事件上告趣意書」が、神宝を含む竹内文書約4,000点と史跡の現地調査の報告書などとともに、提出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this trial, Koso Kotai Jingu Shrine submitted the &quot;Statement of grounds of the final criminal appeal for Jingu Shinshi lese majesty case&quot; with approximately 4,000 pieces of Takeuchi monjo including sacred treasures and reports on field surveys of historic sites.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this trial, Koso Kotai Jingu Shrine submitted the &quot;Statement on grounds of the final criminal appeal for Jingu Shinshi lese majesty case&quot; along with approximately 4,000 pieces of Takeuchi monjo including sacred treasures and reports on field surveys of historic sites.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this trial, Koso Kotai Jingu Shrine submitted the &apos;Statement on grounds of the final criminal appeal for Jingu Shinshi defamation case&apos;, along with approximately 4,000 pieces of Takeuchi monjo, including sacred treasures and reports on field surveys of historic sites.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>無罪判決となるも、提出物は裁判が終了してもすぐに返還がかなわず、それら原本は太平洋戦争中の空襲により『吉備津彦命兵法之巻』などを焼失したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a decision of &quot;not guilty&quot; was obtained, submitted materials were not returned immediately even after the trial was concluded and, reportedly, original of &quot;吉備津彦命兵法之巻&quot; [正しい読みが確認できておりません。] etc. were destructed by fire due to air raids during the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a decision of &quot;not guilty&quot; was obtained, the submitted materials were not returned immediately even after the trial was concluded and, reportedly, the original of &quot;吉備津彦命兵法之巻&quot; [正しい読みが確認できておりません。] etc. were destroyed by fire because of air raids during the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a decision of &quot;not guilty&quot; was obtained, the submitted materials were not returned immediately after the conclusion of the trial and the original documents such as &quot;吉備津彦命兵法之巻&quot; were were reportedly destroyed by firebecause of air raids during the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>戦後、巨麿の子、竹内義宮がその写本を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the War, TAKEUCHI Gikyu [義宮 読みが確認できておりません], a son of Kiyomaro, shoed its transcript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the War, TAKEUCHI Gikyu [義宮 読みが確認できておりません], a son of Kiyomaro, showed the transcript.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the War, Gikyu TAKEUCHI (竹内義宮), a son of Kiyomaro, has held a transcript.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>一説には、竹内文書は焼失しておらず、『NARA（アメリカ国立公文書記録管理局）』または『国立公文書館（旧内閣文庫）』に保管されているのではないかとも言われているが、真偽は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One version of the story is that Takeuchi monjo has not been destructed by fire and it was kept in &quot;United States National Archives and Records Administration (NARA)&quot; or &quot;National Archives of Japan (former, Naikaku Bunko (literally, Cabinet Archives)&quot;, but this remains to be confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One version of the story is that Takeuchi monjo had not been destroyed by fire and it was kept in the &quot;United States National Archives and Records Administration (NARA)&quot; or &quot;National Archives of Japan (former, Naikaku Bunko (literally, Cabinet Archives)&quot;, but this remains to be confirmed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One version of the story is that Takeuchi monjo had not been destroyed by fire and it was kept in the &quot;United States National Archives and Records Administration (NARA)&quot; or &quot;National Archives of Japan (former, Naikaku Bunko (literally, Cabinet Archives)&quot;, but this remains to be confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>『旧約聖書』などの古代文献に出てくる人物や乗り物らしきものと、竹内文書に出てくる人物や乗り物らしきものとが何らかの関連性があるかのような記述がされることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, it is described that a person or vehicle in ancient literatures such as &quot;Old Testament&quot; have certain relation with a person or vehicle in Takeuchi monjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, it is described that a person or a vehicle in ancient literature such as the &quot;Old Testament&quot; have certain relationships with a person or a vehicle in Takeuchi monjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some descriptions as if a person or a vehicle in ancient literature such as the &quot;Old Testament&quot; has a certain relationship with a person or a vehicle in Takeuchi monjo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Pentagon999(id:278678), Izayohi(id:13095), ことりさん(id:53563), Nnh(id:474), グラン(id:16915), Nighthawks(id:36125), Tom-spring(id:42457), Bokeboketus(id:285141), Qazzx(id:8772), Tribot(id:186681), Jazzy(id:3202), 沢田(id:40580), はるひ(id:59079), Arpeggio(id:9385), Yukichi99(id:29402), Murasagi(id:79122), 神子原光(id:68491), Otanagano(id:104988), Re-GZ(id:173906), Oga(id:116), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Slot28(id:79910), Point136(id:211299), 辻斬(id:119418), Fievarsty(id:201483), Carender(id:86517), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>