<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>与謝野晶子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiko YOSANO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiko YOSANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiko YOSANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>与謝野 晶子（よさの あきこ、正字体：與謝野晶子、明治11年（1878年）12月7日 - 昭和17年（1942年）5月29日）は明治時代から昭和時代にかけて活躍した歌人、作家、思想家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiko YOSANO (与謝野 晶子 or 與謝野晶子 in orthographic style; December 7, 1878 - May 29, 1942) is a kajin (waka poet), novelist, and thinker who were active in Meiji Period through Showa Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiko YOSANO (与謝野 晶子 or 與謝野晶子 in orthographic style; December 7, 1878 - May 29, 1942) is a kajin (waka poet), novelist, and thinker active during the Meiji through Showa Periods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiko YOSANO (与謝野 晶子 or 與謝野晶子 in orthographic style; December 7, 1878 - May 29, 1942) is a kajin (waka poet), novelist, and thinker active during the Meiji through Showa Periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大阪府堺市（現在の堺区）出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born in Sakai City (present-day Sakai Ward), Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born in Sakai City (present-day Sakai Ward), Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born in Sakai City (present-day Sakai Ward), Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>旧姓は鳳（ほう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her maiden name was Ho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her maiden name was Ho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her maiden name was Ho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>戸籍は「志よう」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the family register, her name was Shiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the family register, her name was Shiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the family register, her name was &apos;Shiyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ペンネームの「晶子」の「晶」はこの「しよう」から取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanji character &quot;晶&quot; in her pen name &quot;晶子&quot; came from her real name Shiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanji character &quot;晶&quot; in her pen name &quot;晶子&quot; came from her real name Shiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanji character &apos;晶&apos; in her pen name &apos;晶子&apos; came from her real name &apos;Shiyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。原文「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>夫は与謝野鉄幹（与謝野寛）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her husband was Tekkan YOSANO (Hiroshi YOSANO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her husband was Tekkan YOSANO (Hiroshi YOSANO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her husband was Tekkan YOSANO (Hiroshi YOSANO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>鳳志ようは、大阪府堺市甲斐町（現在の堺区甲斐町）で老舗和菓子屋「駿河屋」を営む、父・鳳宗七、母・津祢の三女として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiyo Ho was born as the third daughter of Soshichi HO (father) and Tune (mother) who run a long-established Japanese confectionery shop &quot;Surugaya&quot; in Kaino-cho, Sakai City (present-day Kaino-cho, Sakai Ward), Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiyo Ho was born as the third daughter of Soshichi HO (father) and Tune (mother) who ran a long-established Japanese confectionery shop &quot;Surugaya&quot; in Kaino-cho, Sakai City (present-day Kaino-cho, Sakai Ward), Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiyo Ho was born as the third daughter of Soshichi HO (father) and Tsune (mother) who ran a long-established Japanese confectionery shop &apos;Surugaya&apos; in Kaino-cho, Sakai City (present-day Kaino-cho, Sakai Ward), Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>TuneをTsuneに変更しました。&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>実の兄にはのちに電気工学者となる鳳秀太郎がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of her real brother was Hidetaro HO who later became an electrical engineer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of her real brothers was Hidetaro HO who later became an electrical engineer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of her real brothers was Hidetaro HO who later became an electrical engineer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>9歳で漢学塾に入り、琴・三味線も習った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiyo entered a school of Sinology (the study of the Chinese classics) at the age of nine and also learned koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) and shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiyo entered a school of Sinology (the study of the Chinese classics) at the age of nine and also learned koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) and shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiyo entered a school of Sinology (the study of the Chinese classics) at the age of nine and also learned koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) and shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>堺女学校（現・大阪府立泉陽高等学校）に入学すると『源氏物語』などを読み始め古典に親しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After she entered Sakai Girl&apos;s School (present-day Osaka Prefectural Senyo Senior High School), she devoured Japanese classics such as &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After entering Sakai Girl&apos;s School (present-day Osaka Prefectural Senyo Senior High School), she devoured the Japanese classics such as &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After entering Sakai Girl&apos;s School (present-day Osaka Prefectural Senyo Senior High School), she devoured the Japanese classics such as &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また兄の影響を受け、「十二、三のころから、『柵草紙』（後には『めざまし草』）『文学界』や尾崎紅葉、幸田露伴、樋口一葉などの小説を読むのが一番の楽しみ」（『明星』明治39年5月）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, she said, under her elder brother&apos;s influence, &quot;by the time I was twelve or thirteen, my greatest pleasure was reading literary magazines &quot;Shigaramisoshi&quot; (and later its successor &quot;Mezamashigusa&quot;) and &quot;Bungakukai&quot; as well as novels by Koyo OZAKI, Rohan KODA, and Ichiyo HIGUCHI&quot; (&quot;Myojo&quot; May 1906).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, she said, under her elder brother&apos;s influence, &quot;by the time I was twelve or thirteen, my greatest pleasure was reading literary magazines &quot;Shigaramisoshi&quot; (and later its successor &quot;Mezamashigusa&quot;) and &quot;Bungakukai&quot; as well as novels by Koyo OZAKI, Rohan KODA, and Ichiyo HIGUCHI&quot; (&quot;Myojo&quot; May 1906).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, she said, under her elder brother&apos;s influence, &apos;by the time I was twelve or thirteen, my greatest pleasure was reading literary magazines &quot;Shigaramisoshi&quot; (and later its successor &quot;Mezamashigusa&quot;) and &quot;Bungakukai&quot; as well as novels by Koyo OZAKI, Rohan KODA, and Ichiyo HIGUCHI&apos; (&quot;Myojo&quot; May 1906).</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>20歳ごろより店番をしつつ和歌を投稿するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the age of twenty she started contributing her poems to magazines while she helped her family business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the age of twenty she started contributing her poems to magazines while she helped her family business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the age of twenty she started contributing her poems to magazines while she helped her family business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>浪華青年文学会に参加の後、明治33年（1900年）、浜寺公園の旅館で行なわれた歌会で歌人・与謝野鉄幹と親しくなり、鉄幹が創立した新詩社の機関誌『明星』に短歌を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After participated in the Kansai Young Men&apos;s Literary Society, in 1900, she became acquainted with a waka poet Tekkan YOSANO at a poetry reading held at a Japanese-style hotel in Hamaderakoen and contributed her poem to &quot;Myojo,&quot; in-house magazine of Shinshisha (New Poetry Society) founded by Tekkan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After participated in the Kansai Young Men&apos;s Literary Society, in 1900, she became acquainted with a waka poet Tekkan YOSANO at a poetry reading held at a Japanese-style hotel in Hamaderakoen and contributed her poem to &quot;Myojo,&quot; an in-house magazine of Shinshisha (New Poetry Society) founded by Tekkan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After participated in the Kansai Young Men&apos;s Literary Society, in 1900, she became acquainted with a waka poet Tekkan YOSANO at a poetry reading held at a Japanese-style hotel in Hamaderakoen and contributed her poem to &quot;Myojo,&quot; an in-house magazine of Shinshisha (New Poetry Society) founded by Tekkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>翌年家を出て東京に移り、女性の官能をおおらかに謳う処女歌集『みだれ髪』を刊行し浪漫派の歌人としてのスタイルを確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year she left her home and moved to Tokyo, and published her first poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) that expressed female sensuality in open fashion with which she established her style as a romantic poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year she left her home and moved to Tokyo, and published her first poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) that expressed female sensuality in open fashion with which she established her style as a romantic poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year she left her home and moved to Tokyo, and published her first poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) that expressed female sensuality in open fashion with which she established her style as a romantic poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>のちに鉄幹と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later she married Tekkan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later she married Tekkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later she married Tekkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>明治37年（1904年）9月、『君死にたまふことなかれ』を『明星』に発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1904, she published a poem &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) in &quot;Myojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1904, she published a poem &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) in &quot;Myojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1904, she published a poem &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) in &quot;Myojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明治44年（1911年）には史上初の女性文芸誌『青鞜』創刊号に「山の動く日きたる」で始まる詩を寄稿した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911, she contributed a poem that started with &quot;Yama no ugoku hi kitaru&quot; (The day comes when a mountain moves) to the first issue of &quot;Seito&quot;, the first female literary magazine in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911, she contributed a poem that started with &quot;Yama no ugoku hi kitaru&quot; (The day comes when a mountain moves) to the first issue of &quot;Seito,&quot; the first female literary magazine in Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911, she contributed a poem that started with &apos;Yama no ugoku hi kitaru&apos; (The day comes when a mountain moves) to the first issue of &quot;Seito,&quot; the first female literary magazine in Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>明治45年（1912年）、晶子は鉄幹の後を追ってフランスのパリに行くことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1912, Akiko followed Tekkan to move to Paris, France.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1912, Akiko followed Tekkan and moved to Paris, France.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1912, Akiko followed Tekkan and moved to Paris, France.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>洋行費の工面は、森鴎外幅の広い文芸活動と交際が手助けをし、また『新訳源氏物語』の序文を書いた鴎外がその校正を代わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai MORI helped her to raise money for going abroad with his wide range of literary works and large circle of contacts, and he also proofread &quot;Shinyaku Genji Monogatari (New Translation of The Tale of Genji)&quot; on behalf of Akiko to which he wrote the preface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai MORI helped her to raise money for going abroad with his wide range of literary works and large circle of contacts, and he also proofread &quot;Shinyaku Genji Monogatari (New Translation of The Tale of Genji)&quot; on behalf of Akiko to which he wrote the preface.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai MORI helped her to raise money for going abroad with his wide range of literary works and large circle of contacts, and he also proofread &quot;Shinyaku Genji Monogatari (New Translation of The Tale of Genji)&quot; on behalf of Akiko to which he wrote the preface.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>同年5月5日、読売新聞が「新しい女」の連載を開始し、第一回に晶子のパリ行きを取り上げ、翌6日には晶子の出発の様子を報じた（平塚らいてうなど総勢500余名が見送った）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 5, 1912, the Yomiuri Shimbun started a series of articles entitled &quot;Atarashii Onna (New Women)&quot; with an article on Akiko&apos;s voyage to Paris, and on the following day the newspaper reported her departure (some 500 people including Raicho HIRATSUKA saw her off).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 5, 1912, the Yomiuri Shimbun started a series of articles entitled &quot;Atarashii Onna (New Women)&quot; with an article on Akiko&apos;s voyage to Paris, and on the following day the newspaper reported her departure (some 500 people including Raicho HIRATSUKA saw her off).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 5, 1912, the Yomiuri Shimbun started a series of articles entitled &apos;Atarashii Onna&apos; (New Women) with an article on Akiko&apos;s voyage to Paris, and on the following day the newspaper reported her departure (some 500 people including Raicho HIRATSUKA saw her off).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更し、()を&apos; &apos;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>翌6月の『中央公論』では、晶子の特集が組まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following June issue of the Chuo koron magazine run the feature story on Akiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following June issue of the Chuo koron magazine ran a feature story on Akiko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following June issue of the &quot;Chuo koron&quot; magazine ran a feature story on Akiko.</e>
<cmt>原文『』の部分を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>5月19日、シベリア鉄道経由でパリに到着した晶子は、9月21日にフランスのマルセイユ港から帰国の途につくまでの4ケ月間、イギリス、ベルギー、ドイツ、オーストリア、オランダなどを訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 19, Akiko arrived in Paris via Trans-Siberian Railway; during four months up to her leaving to Japan from Marseille, France on September 21, she visited England, Belgium, Germany, Austria, and the Netherland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 19, Akiko arrived in Paris via the Trans-Siberian Railway; during four months up to her leaving to Japan from Marseille, France on September 21, she visited England, Belgium, Germany, Austria, and the Netherlands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 19, Akiko arrived in Paris via the Trans-Siberian Railway; during four months up to her leaving to Japan from Marseille, France on September 21, she visited England, Belgium, Germany, Austria, and the Netherlands and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また帰国してから2年後、鉄幹との共著『巴里より』で、「（上略）要求すべき正当な第一の権利は教育の自由である。」と、女性教育の必要性などを説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two years after returning to Japan, she wrote a book with Tekkan called &quot;Pari yori (From Paris)&quot; in which she argued the necessity of education for women, stating &quot;(snip) the first legitimate right to claim is the freedom of education.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two years after returning to Japan, she wrote a book with Tekkan called &quot;Pari yori (From Paris)&quot; in which she argued the necessity of education for women, stating &quot;(snip) the first legitimate right to claim is the freedom of education.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two years after returning to Japan, she wrote a book with Tekkan called &quot;Pari yori&quot; (From Paris) in which she argued the necessity of education for women, stating &apos;(snip) the first legitimate right to claim is the freedom of education.&apos;</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動させました。原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>子だくさんだったが、鉄幹の詩の売れ行きは悪くなる一方で、彼が大学教授の職につくまで夫の収入がまったくあてにならず孤軍奮闘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiko and Tekkan had many children but sales of Tekkan&apos;s poetry kept falling, so she worked very hard as a sole bread-winner until her husband gained a position as a college professor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiko and Tekkan had many children, but sales of Tekkan&apos;s poetry kept falling, so she worked very hard as the sole bread-winner until her husband gained a position as a college professor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiko and Tekkan had many children, but sales of Tekkan&apos;s poetry kept falling, so she worked very hard as the sole bread-winner until her husband gained a position as a college professor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>来る仕事はすべて引き受けなければ家計が成り立たず、歌集の原稿料を前払いしてもらっていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had to take every offer to make ends meet and even asked advanced payment for her poetry anthologies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had to take every offer to make ends meet and even asked advanced payment for her poetry anthologies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had to take every offer to make ends meet and even asked advanced payment for her poetry anthologies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>多忙なやりくりの間も、即興短歌の会を女たちとともに開いたりし、残した歌は5万首にも及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While she was busy working and managing the household, she held improvised tanka poem meetings with women and made about 50,000 poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While she was busy working and managing the household, she held improvised tanka poem meetings with women and wrote about 50,000 poems.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While she was busy working and managing the household, she held improvised tanka poem meetings with women and wrote about 50,000 poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『源氏物語』の現代語訳『新新源氏』、詩作、評論活動とエネルギッシュな人生を送り、女性解放思想家としても巨大な足跡を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her energetic works include a contemporary translation of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; called &quot;Shin Shin Genji,&quot; poetry, and critiques, and she also left a vast mark as a pioneering feminist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her energetic works include a contemporary translation of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; called &quot;Shin Shin Genji,&quot; poetry, and critiques, and she also left a vast mark as a pioneering feminist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her energetic works include a contemporary translation of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; called &quot;Shin Shin Genji,&quot; poetry, and critiques, and she also left a vast mark as a pioneering feminist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>墓は多磨霊園にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is in the Tama Cemetery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is located in the Tama Cemetery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is located in the Tama Cemetery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>業績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>作家・歌人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As novelist and poet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As novelist and poet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As novelist and poet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>情熱的な作品が多いと評される歌集『みだれ髪』明治34年（1901年）や日露戦争の時に歌った『君死にたまふことなかれ』が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her famous works include the poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) in 1901 which is remarked that it includes many passionate poems and &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) that was made during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her famous works include the poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) in 1901 that includes many passionate poems and &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) made during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her famous works include the poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) in 1901 that includes many passionate poems and &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) made during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>『源氏物語』の現代語訳でも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is also known for her translation of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) in modern language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is also known for her translation of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) in modern language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is also known for her translation of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) in modern language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>歌集『みだれ髪』では、女性が自我や性愛を表現するなど考えられなかった時代に女性の官能をおおらかに詠い、浪漫派歌人としてのスタイルを確立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) she expressed female sensuality in open fashion at the time when it was outrageous that a woman expressed her ego and sexuality, and she established her style as a romantic poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) she expressed female sensuality in open fashion at the time when it was outrageous that a woman expressed their ego and sexuality, and she established her style as a romantic poet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the poetry anthology &quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled hair) she expressed female sensuality in open fashion at the time when it was outrageous that a woman expressed their ego and sexuality, and she established her style as a romantic poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>伝統的歌壇から反発を受けたが、世間の耳目を集めて熱狂的支持を受け、歌壇に多大な影響を及ぼすこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional poetry circles were offended by her poems, but the world was startled and enthusiastically supported her, so her poems had a significant impact on the circles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional poetry circles were offended by her poems, but the world was startled and enthusiastically supported her, so her poems had a significant impact on the circles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional poetry circles were offended by her poems, but the world was startled and enthusiastically supported her, so her poems had a significant impact on the circles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>所収の短歌にちなみ「やは肌の晶子」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was called &quot;Yawahada no Akiko&quot; after a poem in the anthology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was called &quot;Yawahada no Akiko&quot; after a poem in the anthology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was called &apos;Yawahada no Akiko&apos; after a poem in the anthology.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>明治37年（1904年）9月、半年前に召集され旅順攻囲戦に加わっていた弟を嘆いて『君死にたまふことなかれ』を『明星』に発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1904, she made a poem &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) in Myojo on lamenting her younger brother who was recruited half a year ago and sent to the Siege of Port Arthur.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1904, she wrote the poem &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) in Myojo on lamenting her younger brother who was recruited half a year ago and sent to the Siege of Port Arthur.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1904, she wrote the poem &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; (Thou Shalt Not Die) in Myojo on lamenting her younger brother who was recruited half a year ago and sent to the Siege of Port Arthur.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その三連目で「すめらみことは戦いに　おおみずからは出でまさね（天皇は戦争に自ら出かけられない）」と唱い、晶子と親交の深い歌人であったが国粋主義者であった文芸批評家の大町桂月はこれに対して｢家が大事也、妻が大事也、国は亡びてもよし、商人は戦ふべき義務なしといふは、余りに大胆すぐる言葉」と批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the third verse of the poem she wrote that the Emperor was not allowed to join the war himself; a literary critique Keigetsu OMACHI who was a close friend of Akiko but at the same time nationalist criticized her by stating &quot;it was too audacious to say that what matters to you is your family and wife, that it doesn&apos;t matter if your country was destroyed, and that merchants are not bound to fight in the war.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the third verse of the poem she wrote that the Emperor was not allowed to join the war himself; a literary critique Keigetsu OMACHI who was a close friend of Akiko, but at the same time a nationalist, criticized her by stating &quot;it was too audacious to say that what matters to you is your family and wife, that it doesn&apos;t matter if your country is destroyed, and that merchants are not bound to fight in the war.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the third verse of the poem she wrote that the Emperor was not allowed to join the war himself; a literary critique Keigetsu OMACHI who was a close friend of Akiko, but at the same time a nationalist, criticized her by stating &apos;it was too audacious to say that what matters to you is your family and wife, that it doesn&apos;t matter if your country is destroyed, and that merchants are not bound to fight in the war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>晶子は『明星』11月号に『ひらきぶみ』を発表、「桂月様たいさう危険なる思想と仰せられ候へど、当節のやうに死ねよ死ねよと申し候こと、またなにごとにも忠君愛国の文字や、畏おほき教育御勅語などを引きて論ずることの流行は、この方かへつて危険と申すものに候はずや｣と国粋主義を非難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiko published &quot;Hirakibumi&quot; on November issue of &quot;Myojo&quot; to criticize the extreme patriotism by stating &quot;Dear Mr. Keigetsu, you said that I had very dangerous ideas but don&apos;t you think that it is far dangerous to tell young men to die for the country, and to cite loyalty, patriotism and the Imperial Ordinance on Education in any discussions, do you?&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiko published &quot;Hirakibumi&quot; in the November issue of &quot;Myojo&quot; to criticize extreme patriotism by stating &quot;Dear Mr. Keigetsu, you said that I had very dangerous ideas, but don&apos;t you think that it is far more dangerous to tell young men to die for the country, and to cite loyalty, patriotism and the Imperial Ordinance on Education in any discussions, don&apos;t you?&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiko published &quot;Hirakibumi&quot; in the November issue of &quot;Myojo&quot; to criticize extreme patriotism by stating &apos;Dear Mr. Keigetsu, you said that I had very dangerous ideas, but don&apos;t you think that it is far more dangerous to tell young men to die for the country, and to cite loyalty, patriotism and the Imperial Ordinance on Education in any discussions, don&apos;t you?&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>さらに「歌はまことの心を歌うもの」と桂月の批判を一蹴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stating that waka poetry should express true feelings of people, she scoffed at Keigetsu&apos;s criticism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stating that waka poetry should express the true feelings of people, she scoffed at Keigetsu&apos;s criticism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stating that &apos;waka poetry should express the true feelings of people,&apos; she scoffed at Keigetsu&apos;s criticism.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>(日露戦争当時は満州事変後の昭和の戦争の時期ほど言論弾圧が厳しかったわけではなく、白鳥省吾、木下尚江、中里介山、大塚楠緒子らにも戦争を嘆く詩を垣間見ることができる。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(During the Russo-Japanese War, the suppression of free speech was not so fierce as that in war time in the Showa Period, and many other poets made poems to deplore the war, including Seigo SHIROTORI, Naoe KINOSHITA, Kaizan NAKAZATO, and Kusuoko OTSUKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(During the Russo-Japanese War, the suppression of free speech was not so fierce as that during war time in the Showa Period, and many other poets wrote poems deploring the war, including Seigo SHIROTORI, Naoe KINOSHITA, Kaizan NAKAZATO, and Kusuoko OTSUKA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(During the Russo-Japanese War, the suppression of free speech was not so fierce as that during war time in the Showa Period, and many other poets wrote poems deploring the war, including Seigo SHIROTORI, Naoe KINOSHITA, Kaizan NAKAZATO, and Kusuoko OTSUKA.)</e>
<cmt>)を閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>大町桂月は『太陽』誌上で論文『詩歌の骨髄』を掲載し「皇室中心主義の眼を以て、晶子の詩を検すれば、乱臣なり賊子なり、国家の刑罰を加ふべき罪人なりと絶叫せざるを得ざるものなり」と激しく非難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the magazine &quot;Taiyo,&quot; Keigetsu OMACHI published a thesis &quot;Shiika no kotsuzui&quot; (Bone marrow of poetry) to fiercely criticize Akiko, stating &quot;If you scrutinize Akiko&apos;s poetry from a perspective of imperial centrism, you can&apos;t help but screaming that she is a traitor, betrayer, and offender who should be punished by the state.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the magazine &quot;Taiyo,&quot; Keigetsu OMACHI published a thesis &quot;Shiika no kotsuzui&quot; (Bone marrow of poetry) to fiercely criticize Akiko, stating &quot;If you scrutinize Akiko&apos;s poetry from a perspective of imperial centrism, you can&apos;t help but scream that she is a traitor, betrayer, and offender who should be punished by the state.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the magazine &quot;Taiyo,&quot; Keigetsu OMACHI published a thesis &quot;Shiika no kotsuzui&quot; (Bone marrow of poetry) to fiercely criticize Akiko, stating &apos;If you scrutinize Akiko&apos;s poetry from a perspective of imperial centrism, you can&apos;t help but scream that she is a traitor, betrayer, and offender who should be punished by the state.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>夫・与謝野鉄幹と平出修の直談判により、桂月は「詩歌も状況によっては国家社会に服すべし」とする立場は変えなかったものの、晶子に対する「乱臣賊子云々」の語は取り下げ、論争は収束する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By negotiating with Akiko&apos;s husband Tekkan YOSANO and Shu HIRAIDE in person, Keigetsu, while he never changed his position that poetry should obey the nation and society in particular situation, agreed to withdraw his criticism against Akiko calling her a traitor, betrayer, etc., and thus the dispute was settled.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By negotiating with Akiko&apos;s husband Tekkan YOSANO and Shu HIRAIDE in person, Keigetsu, while he never changed his position that poetry should obey the nation and society in a particular situation, agreed to withdraw his criticism against Akiko calling her a traitor, betrayer, etc., and thus the dispute was settled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By negotiating with Akiko&apos;s husband Tekkan YOSANO and Shu HIRAIDE in person, Keigetsu, while he never changed his position that poetry should obey the nation and society in a particular situation, agreed to withdraw his criticism against Akiko calling her &apos;a traitor, betrayer, etc.,&apos; and thus the dispute was settled.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この後、大正14年（1911年）6月11日、桂月は57歳で病没するが『横浜貿易新報』に晶子は追憶をよせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Keigetsu died of illness at the age of 57 on June 11, 1911, Akiko contributed a memoir to the newspaper &quot;Kanagawa Boeki Shimpo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「神奈川新聞」はWeb表記は『横浜貿易新報』で当時の紙名もこちらなので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Keigetsu died of illness at the age of 57 on June 11, 1911, Akiko contributed a memoir to the newspaper &quot;Kanagawa Boeki Shimpo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Keigetsu died of illness at the age of 57 on June 11, 1911, Akiko contributed a memoir to the newspaper &quot;Kanagawa Boeki Shimpo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="42">
<j>この騒動のため晶子は「嫌戦の歌人」という印象が強いが、明治43年（1910年）に発生した第六潜水艇の沈没事故の際には、「海底の　水の明りにしたためし　永き別れの　ますら男の文」等約十篇の歌を詠み、第一次世界大戦の折は『戦争』という詩のなかで、「いまは戦ふ時である　戦嫌ひのわたしさへ　今日此頃は気が昂る」と極めて励戦的な戦争賛美の歌を作っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this dispute left her image of anti-war poet, when the Submarine No.6 sunk in 1910, she made about ten poems including &quot;At the bottom of the sea; writing under the light of water; for farewell; the letters from Japanese men&quot;; and during the World War I, she wrote a poem entitled &quot;War&quot; that encourages and praises the war: &quot;This is the time to fight; even I who usually detest wars; feel excited these days.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this dispute left her image as an anti-war poet, when Submarine No.6 sunk in 1910, she wrote about ten poems including &quot;At the bottom of the sea; writing under the light of water; for farewell; the letters from Japanese men;&quot; and during World War I, she wrote a poem entitled &quot;War&quot; that encourages and praises the war: &quot;This is the time to fight; even I, who usually detests war; feel excited these days.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this dispute left her image as an anti-war poet, when Submarine No.6 sunk in 1910, she wrote about ten poems including &apos;At the bottom of the sea; writing under the light of water; for farewell; the letters from Japanese men;&apos; and during World War I, she wrote a poem entitled &quot;War&quot; that encourages and praises the war: &apos;This is the time to fight; even I, who usually detests war; feel excited these days.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>満州事変勃発以降は、戦時体制・翼賛体制が強化されたことを勘案しても、満州国成立を容認・擁護し、昭和17年（1942年）に発表した『白櫻集』で、以前の歌「君死にたまうことなかれ」とは正反対に、戦争を美化し、鼓舞する歌を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Manchurian Incident broke out, by taking into consideration that the wartime regime and Yokusan Taisei (Support system of Taisei Yokusan-kai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association)) were strengthened, she approved and supported the establishment of Manchukuo and in &quot;Hakuo-shu&quot; that she published in 1942, she made poems that glorified and encouraged the war, in completely opposition to her pervious work &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Manchurian Incident broke out, by taking into consideration that the wartime regime and Yokusan Taisei (Support system of Taisei Yokusan-kai - Imperial Rule Assistance Association) were strengthened, she approved and supported the establishment of Manchukuo and in &quot;Hakuo-shu&quot; that she published in 1942, she wrote poems that glorified and encouraged the war, completely opposite of her pervious work &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Manchurian Incident broke out, by taking into consideration that the wartime regime and Yokusan Taisei (Support system of Taisei Yokusan-kai - Imperial Rule Assistance Association) were strengthened, she approved and supported the establishment of Manchukuo and in &quot;Hakuo-shu&quot; that she published in 1942, she wrote poems that glorified and encouraged the war, completely opposite of her pervious work &apos;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>例えば、「強きかな　天を恐れず　地に恥ぢぬ　戦をすなる　ますらたけをは」や、海軍大尉として出征する四男に対して詠んだ『君死にたまうことなかれ』とは正反対の意味となる「水軍の　大尉となりて　わが四郎　み軍にゆく　たけく戦へ」など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such poems include &quot;How strong, without fear of the heaven, act worthy of themselves, in the battle, our brave men&quot; or the one dedicated to her fourth son who went to the war as an naval captain, which had a completely opposite meaning to &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot;: &quot;As a naval captain, my son Shiro will join the Imperial force; Fight bravely.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such poems include &quot;How strong, without fear of the heaven, they act worthy of themselves, in battle, our brave men&quot; or the one dedicated to her fourth son who went to the war as an naval captain, which had the completely opposite meaning to &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare:&quot; &quot;As a naval captain, my son Shiro will join the Imperial force; Fight bravely.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such poems include &apos;How strong, without fear of the heaven, they act worthy of themselves, in battle, our brave men&apos; or the one dedicated to her fourth son who went to the war as an naval captain, which had the completely opposite meaning to &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare:&quot; &apos;As a naval captain, my son Shiro will join the Imperial force; Fight bravely.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>このようなことから、反戦としての立場に一貫性がなかった、あるいは時勢により心情を変化させた転向であると評する者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on these facts, some comment that her conduct as anti-war protestant lacks consistency or she converted depending on the tendency of the times by changing her sentiment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based upon these facts, some comments about her conduct as being anti-war lacks consistency or she converted depending upon the tendency of the times by changing her sentiment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based upon these facts, some comments about her conduct as being anti-war lacks consistency or she converted depending upon the tendency of the times by changing her sentiment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>日露戦争当時に「幸徳秋水の反戦論は大嫌いだ」と公言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Russo-Japanese War, she made public that she hated the anti-war theory of Shusui KOTOKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Russo-Japanese War, she made public that she hated the anti-war theory of Shusui KOTOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Russo-Japanese War, she made public that she hated the anti-war theory of Shusui KOTOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ただし、大逆事件では秋水ら死刑になった十二人に「産屋なる　わが枕辺に　白く立つ　大逆囚の　十二の棺」という歌を明治44年（1911年）3月7日に『東京日日新聞』に発表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be noted, however, that she published the following poem dedicated to twelve people including Shusui who were sentenced to death in the case of high treason on March 7, 1911 on Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper: &quot;Ubuyanaru; by my pillow; standing in white; prisoners for high treason; their twelve coffins&quot;</e>
<cmt>「産屋なる」の英訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted, however, that she published the following poem dedicated to twelve people including Shusui sentenced to death in a case of high treason on March 7, 1911 on Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper: &quot;Ubuyanaru; by my pillow; standing in white; prisoners for high treason; their twelve coffins.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted, however, that she published the following poem dedicated to twelve people including Shusui sentenced to death in a case of high treason on March 7, 1911 on &quot;Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper&quot;: &apos;Ubuyanaru; by my pillow; standing in white; prisoners for high treason; their twelve coffins.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文『』の部分に&quot; &quot;を、「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>刑死者の一人大石誠之助は『明星』の同人で関わりも深く、また女性でただ一人死刑となった菅野スガは未決在監中に平出修弁護士に晶子の歌集の差し入れを頼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among those executed, Seinosuke OISHI was a member of &quot;Myojo&quot; whom Akiko knew well; and Suga KANNO was the only female and she asked her attorney Shu HIRAIDE to send her Akiko&apos;s poetry anthology while she was in detention before verdict.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those executed, Seinosuke OISHI was a member of &quot;Myojo&quot; whom Akiko knew well; and Suga KANNO was the only female and she asked her attorney Shu HIRAIDE to send her Akiko&apos;s poetry anthology while she was in detention before the verdict.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those executed, Seinosuke OISHI was a member of &quot;Myojo&quot; whom Akiko knew well; and Suga KANNO was the only female and she asked her attorney Shu HIRAIDE to send her Akiko&apos;s poetry anthology while she was in detention before the verdict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>晶子は直接差し入れなかったことを悔恨して小林天眠への手紙に残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiko remorsed for not bringing the book to Suga in person and wrote her regret in the letter to Tenmin KOBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiko was full of remorse for not giving the book to Suga in person and wrote her regrets in a letter to Tenmin KOBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiko was full of remorse for not giving the book to Suga in person and wrote her regrets in a letter to Tenmin KOBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>明治44年に『青鞜』発刊に参加、『そぞろごと』で賛辞を贈って巻頭を飾り、「新しい女の一人」として名を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911, Akiko participated in the launch of the monthly magazine &quot;Seito&quot; that opened with her poem &quot;Sozorogoto&quot; that praised the magazine, and she was listed as &quot;one of new women.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911, Akiko participated in the launch of the monthly magazine &quot;Seito&quot; that opened with her poem &quot;Sozorogoto&quot; that praised the magazine, and she was listed as &quot;one of the new women.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911, Akiko participated in the launch of the monthly magazine &quot;Seito&quot; that opened with her poem &quot;Sozorogoto&quot; that praised the magazine, and she was listed as &apos;one of the new women.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>同年、文部省と内務省 (日本)が文芸作品の顕彰と称し、諮問機関・文芸委員会を作ったことに対し、晶子は「小松原英太郎　平田東助といふ　大臣は　文学をしらず　あはれなるかな」と皮肉に満ちて批判的な歌を作っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, the Ministry of Education and the Ministry of Home Affairs established a consultative body called the Literature Committee in the name of honoring literary works, but on this event Akiko made a critical poem filled with irony &quot;Eitaro KOMATSUBARA and Tosuke HIRATA; these ministers know nothing about literature; poor things.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, the Ministry of Education and the Ministry of Home Affairs established a consultative body called the Literature Committee in the name of honoring literary works, but on this event Akiko wrote a critical poem filled with irony &quot;Eitaro KOMATSUBARA and Tosuke HIRATA; these ministers know nothing about literature; poor things.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, the Ministry of Education and the Ministry of Home Affairs established a consultative body called the Literature Committee in the name of honoring literary works, but on this event Akiko wrote a critical poem filled with irony &apos;Eitaro KOMATSUBARA and Tosuke HIRATA; these ministers know nothing about literature; poor things.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>文芸委員会に対しては、夏目漱石も「最も不愉快な方法で行政上に都合のいい作品のみを奨励するのが見えすいている」と言っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding this literature committee, Soseki NATSUME was also critical by commenting &quot;it is too obvious that their intention is to promote nothing but such works that are convenient for the administration in the most disgusting way.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding this literature committee, Soseki NATSUME was also critical by commenting &quot;it is too obvious that their intention is to promote nothing, but such works that are convenient for the administration in the most disgusting way.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding this literature committee, Soseki NATSUME was also critical by commenting &apos;it is too obvious that their intention is to promote nothing, but such works that are convenient for the administration in the most disgusting way.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="53">
<j>大正4年（1915年）に読売新聞に『駄獣の群』という国会や議員に対する不信を詠う長詩を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1915, Akiko published on the Yomiuri Shimbun a long poem entitled &quot;Daju no mure&quot; (a group of dumb beasts) that depicted her distrust of the congress and politicians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1915, Akiko published in the Yomiuri Shimbun a long poem entitled &quot;Daju no mure&quot; (a group of dumb beasts) that depicted her distrust of the congress and politicians.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1915, Akiko published in the Yomiuri Shimbun a long poem entitled &quot;Daju no mure&quot; (a group of dumb beasts) that depicted her distrust of the congress and politicians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、晶子は婦人参政権を唱え、『婦選の歌』を作っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She also advocated female suffrage and made a song &quot;Fusen no uta&quot; (song for female suffrage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She also advocated female suffrage and wrote a song &quot;Fusen no uta&quot; (song for female suffrage).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She also advocated female suffrage and wrote a song &quot;Fusen no uta&quot; (song for female suffrage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この歌は山田耕筰作曲で第一回全日本婦選大会において披露された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This song, composed by Kosaku YAMADA, was presented at the first national conference for female suffrage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This song, composed by Kosaku YAMADA, was presented at the first national conference for female suffrage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This song, composed by Kosaku YAMADA, was presented at the first national conference for female suffrage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="56">
<j>晶子が34歳のとき『新訳源氏物語』を四冊本として出したが、拠り所とした北村季吟の『湖月抄』には誤りが多く、外遊の資金調達のために急ぎ、また、校訂に当たった森鴎外は『源氏物語』の専門家でないなど欠陥が多いものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Akiko was 34, &quot;New Translation of The Tale of Genji&quot; was published as a four-volume work, but it was filled with flaws because its source Kigin KITAMURA&apos;s &quot;Kogetsu-sho Commentary&quot; contained many errors, the process of publication was hasty in order to earn the money for traveling abroad, and Ogai MORI who was in charge of proofreading was not an expert of The Tale of Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Akiko was thirty-four, &quot;the New Translation of The Tale of Genji&quot; was published as a four-volume work, but was filled with flaws because its source Kigin KITAMURA&apos;s &quot;Kogetsu-sho Commentary&quot; contained many errors, the process of publication was hasty in order to earn money for traveling abroad, and Ogai MORI who was in charge of proofreading was not an expert on The Tale of Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Akiko was thirty-four, &quot;the New Translation of The Tale of Genji&quot; was published as a four-volume work, but was filled with flaws because its source Kigin KITAMURA&apos;s &quot;Kogetsu-sho Commentary&quot; contained many errors, the process of publication was hasty in order to earn money for traveling abroad, and Ogai MORI who was in charge of proofreading was not an expert on &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>The Tale of Genji.に&quot; &quot;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>そのため、一からやり直し、源氏五十四帖のうち最後の『宇治十帖』を残すまで書き上げたが、関東大震災のために文化学院にあった原稿が灰になってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Akiko started all over from scratch and finished up to the one before the last Uji Jujo (last ten chapters) of 54 chapters of The Tale of Genji, but the Great Kanto Earthquake burnt all the manuscript kept in Bunka Gakuin into ashes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Akiko started all over from scratch and finished up to the one before the last Uji Jujo (last ten chapters) of fifty-four chapters of The Tale of Genji, but the Great Kanto Earthquake burnt all the manuscripts kept in Bunka Gakuin into ashes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Akiko started all over from scratch and finished up to the one before the last &quot;Uji Jujo&quot; (last ten chapters) of fifty-four chapters of The Tale of Genji, but the Great Kanto Earthquake burnt all the manuscripts kept in Bunka Gakuin into ashes.</e>
<cmt>原文『　』の部分に&quot; &quot;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>またも一からやり直し、さらに十七年かけて六巻本『新新訳源氏物語』を完成させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once again she started over and it took 17 years for her to complete the six-volume &quot;New-New Translation of the Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once again she started over and it took seventeen years for her to complete the six-volume &quot;New-New Translation of the Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once again she started over and it took seventeen years for her to complete the six-volume set &quot;New-New Translation of the Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>volumeの後にsetを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>昭和13年（1938年）10月より刊行し、翌年9月に完結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The publication started in October 1938 and completed in September of the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The publication started in October 1938 and was completed in September of the following year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The publication started in October 1938 and was completed in September of the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>評論家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As critic</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As critic</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As critic</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>晶子は日露戦争後から新聞や雑誌に警世の文を書くようになり、評論活動をはじめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Russo-Japanese War Akiko started her activity as a critic by contributing articles to newspapers and magazines to rebuke the society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Russo-Japanese War Akiko started her activity as a critic by contributing articles to newspapers and magazines to rebuke society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Russo-Japanese War, Akiko started her activity as a critic by contributing articles to newspapers and magazines to rebuke society.</e>
<cmt>Warの後に,を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>評論は、女性の自立論と政治評論に分類できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her reviews can be classified into two categories: female self-independence and politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her reviews can be classified into two categories: female self-independence, and politics.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her reviews can be classified into two categories: female self-independence, and politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>教育問題なども評論している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She also made comments on education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She also made comments on education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She also made comments on education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>女性の自立論は、女性が自分で自己鍛錬・自己修養し、人格陶冶することを説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of female self-independence, she argued that a woman should be self-discipline and self-cultivated to develop her own personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of female self-independence, she argued that a woman should be self-disciplined and self-cultivated to develop her own personality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of female self-independence, she argued that a woman should be self-disciplined and self-cultivated to develop her own personality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>英米思想的な個人主義である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So she was an advocate of westernized individualism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So she was an advocate of westernized individualism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So she was an advocate of westernized individualism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>反良妻賢母主義を危険思想だと見る文部省は取り締まり強化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the Ministry of Education was strengthening the censorship of ideas because the Ministry regarded any ideas as dangerous if they argued that an ideal woman was not a dutiful wife and devoted mother.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the Ministry of Education was strengthening the censorship of ideas because the Ministry regarded any ideas as dangerous if they argued that an ideal woman was not a dutiful wife and devoted mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the Ministry of Education was strengthening the censorship of ideas because the Ministry regarded any ideas as dangerous if they argued that an ideal woman was not a dutiful wife and devoted mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>これに対し、妊娠・出産を国庫に補助させようとする平塚らいてうの唱える母性中心主義は、形を変えた新たな良妻賢母にすぎないと論評し、平塚らいてう、山田わからを相手に母性保護論争を挑んで「婦人は男子にも国家にも寄りかかるべきではない」と主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Raicho HIRATSUKA supported maternity-centrism and demanded that the National Treasury should cover all the costs of pregnancy and delivery; Akiko criticized, however, that maternity-centrism was merely an alternative approach of supporting a concept of dutiful wife and devoted mother, and argued against Hiratsuka and Waka YAMADA about maternal care stating &quot;women should not depend on men or the nation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Raicho HIRATSUKA supported maternity-centrism and demanded that the National Treasury should cover all the costs of pregnancy and delivery; Akiko criticized, however, that maternity-centrism was merely an alternative approach of supporting the concept of a dutiful wife and devoted mother, and argued against Hiratsuka and Waka YAMADA about maternal care stating &quot;women should not depend on men or the nation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Raicho HIRATSUKA supported maternity-centrism and demanded that the National Treasury should cover all the costs of pregnancy and delivery; Akiko criticized, however, that maternity-centrism was merely an alternative approach of supporting the concept of a dutiful wife and devoted mother, and argued against Hiratsuka and Waka YAMADA about maternal care stating &apos;women should not depend on men or the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>ここで論壇に登場した女性解放思想家山川菊栄は、保護（平塚）か経済的自立（与謝野）かの対立に、婦人運動の歴史的文脈を明らかにし、差別のない社会でしか婦人の解放はありえないと社会主義の立場で整理した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here a women&apos;s liberation activist Kikue YAMAKAWA participated in this dispute of protection (Hiratsuka) versus financial independence (Yosano) by clarifying the historical context of feminist movement and arguing logically from a socialist viewpoint that women&apos;s liberation could be achieved only in the society without discrimination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here a women&apos;s liberation activist Kikue YAMAKAWA participated in this dispute of protection (Hiratsuka) versus financial independence (Yosano) by clarifying the historical context of feminist movement and arguing logically from a socialist viewpoint that women&apos;s liberation could be achieved only in a society without discrimination.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here a women&apos;s liberation activist Kikue YAMAKAWA participated in this dispute of protection (Hiratsuka) versus financial independence (Yosano) by clarifying the historical context of feminist movement and arguing logically from a socialist viewpoint that women&apos;s liberation could be achieved only in a society without discrimination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>文部省の意向とは全く違う次元で論争は終始した（現代でも問題になっているアグネス論争も類似した論争である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This dispute was far from the intention of the Ministry of Education from beginning to end (a similar dispute occurred even in our time that was known as &quot;Agnes Dispute&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This dispute was far from the intention of the Ministry of Education from beginning to end (a similar dispute occurred even in our time that was known as the &quot;Agnes Dispute&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This dispute was far from the intention of the Ministry of Education from beginning to end (a similar dispute occurred even in our time that was known as the &quot;Agnes Dispute&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="69">
<j>政治評論については反共産主義、反ソ連の立場から論陣を張った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a political critic, she commented from a perspective of anti-communism and anti-USSR.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a political critic, she commented from the perspective of anti-communism and anti-USSR.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a political critic, she commented from the perspective of anti-communism and anti-USSR.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>その論文の数は、20本を越える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She wrote over 20 articles on this subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She wrote over twenty articles on this subject.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She wrote over twenty articles on this subject.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>『君死にたまふことなかれ』を前面に出して一概に反戦・反天皇の人物であったわけではなく、当時『労農主義』として紹介されていたマルクス・レーニン主義も批判していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite of her &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; fame, she was not an unconditional anti-war and anti-Emperor activist; she also criticized Marxism-Leninism that was introduced as Labor-Peasant-ism at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite her &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; fame, she was not an unconditional anti-war and anti-Emperor activist; she also criticized Marxism-Leninism that was introduced as Labor-Peasantism at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite her &quot;Kimi Shinitamou koto nakare&quot; fame, she was not an unconditional anti-war and anti-Emperor activist; she also criticized Marxism-Leninism that was introduced as &quot;Labor-Peasantism&quot; at that time.</e>
<cmt>Labor-Peasantismに&quot; &quot;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="72">
<j>シベリア出兵を日本の領土的野心を猜疑され日露戦争の外債による国民生活の疲弊を再び起こす、と反対している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was against Siberian Intervention by stating that such act would arouse suspicions that Japan had territorial ambitions, resulting in impoverishment of people&apos;s lives again as it was caused by foreign loans in the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was against the Siberian Intervention by stating that such an act would arouse suspicions that Japan had territorial ambitions, resulting in impoverishment of people&apos;s lives again caused by foreign loans in the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was against the Siberian Intervention by stating that such an act would arouse suspicions that Japan had territorial ambitions, resulting in impoverishment of people&apos;s lives again caused by foreign loans in the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また、米騒動に関して『太陽』誌上に「食料騒動について」という文を書き、その中で当時の寺内正毅内閣の退陣を要求している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She also contributed an article &quot;On Food Riot&quot; to the magazine &quot;Taiyo&quot; regarding the rice riot and demanded resignation of the Masatake TERAUCHI&apos;s Cabinet at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She also contributed an article &quot;On Food Riots&quot; to the magazine &quot;Taiyo&quot; regarding rice riot and demanded the resignation of Masatake TERAUCHI&apos;s Cabinet at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She also contributed an article &apos;On Food Riots&apos; to the magazine &quot;Taiyo&quot; regarding rice riot and demanded the resignation of Masatake TERAUCHI&apos;s Cabinet at that time.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="74">
<j>晶子は『中央公論』大正8年（1919年）5月号に「教育の国民化を望む」（単行本『激動の中を行く』にした時『教育の民主主義化を要求す』と改題）という文を書いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiko contributed an article to May issue of the Chuo koron in 1919 entitled &quot;Expecting the national education&quot; (the title was altered to &quot;Demanding for the democratization of education&quot; when it was included in a book &quot;Gekido no naka o yuku&quot; (Going through Turbulent Times)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiko contributed an article to the May issue of the Chuo koron in 1919 entitled &quot;Expecting national education&quot; (the title was altered to &quot;Demanding for the democratization of education&quot; when it was included in a book &quot;Gekido no naka o yuku&quot; (Going through Turbulent Times)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiko contributed an article to the May issue of the Chuo koron in May 1919 entitled &apos;Expecting national education&apos; (the title was altered to &quot;Demanding for the democratization of education&quot; when it was included in a book &quot;Gekido no naka o yuku&quot; (Going through Turbulent Times)).</e>
<cmt>1919の前にMayを挿入しました。原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>各府県市町村に民選の教育委員を設けることを提案している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She suggested to establish the board of education by popular vote in each municipality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She suggested establishing a board of education by popular vote in each municipality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She suggested establishing a board of education by popular vote in each municipality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>今の教育は「文部省の専制的裁断に屈従した教育」であるから、それを「各自治体におけるそれらの教育委員の自由裁量に一任」し、それによって「教育が国民自身のものとなる」と主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She argued that the education of the time was &quot;the education submissive to the Ministry of Education&apos;s despotic decisions&quot; but it should be &quot;left to a discretionary power of the board of education of each municipality&quot; in order to realize &quot;the education for the people.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She argued that education of the times was &quot;an education submissive to the Ministry of Education&apos;s despotic decisions&quot; but it should be &quot;left to a discretionary power of the board of education of each municipality&quot; in order to realize &quot;education for the people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She argued that education of the times was &apos;an education submissive to the Ministry of Education&apos;s despotic decisions&apos; but it should be &apos;left to a discretionary power of the board of education of each municipality&apos; in order to realize &apos;education for the people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>他にも、ヨーロッパの老婦人が若い婦人とさまざまの社会奉仕に努力する姿を見て、日本にも成人教育や社会教育の場を作るよう提言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, based on her experience to meet elder women in Europe who were devoting to various social volunteer activities with younger women, she proposed to offer adult and social educational opportunities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, based on her experience to meet elder women in Europe who were devoted to various social volunteer activities with younger women, she proposed to offer adult and social educational opportunities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, based on her experience to meet elder women in Europe who were devoted to various social volunteer activities with younger women, she proposed to offer adult and social educational opportunities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="78">
<j>羽仁もと子による自由学園の開校と前後して文化学院の創立に尽力、文部省の規定に逆らい、男女共学で開校。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the time that Motoko HANI established the Jiyu Gakuen, Akiko devoted to found the Bunka Gakuin (Institute of Culture), a coeducational school against the specification by the Ministry of Education,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the time that Motoko HANI established Jiyu Gakuen, Akiko devoted her time to found the Bunka Gakuin (Institute of Culture), a coeducational school against the specifications by the Ministry of Education,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the time that Motoko HANI established Jiyu Gakuen, Akiko devoted her time to found the Bunka Gakuin (Institute of Culture), a coeducational school against the specifications by the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>文末の,を.に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>のち文化学院女学部長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She later became the school&apos;s director of the department of women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She later became the school&apos;s director for the department of women.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She later became the school&apos;s director for the department of women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>著作・文献</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>自著</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Books written by Akiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Books written by Akiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Books written by Akiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>『定本 与謝野晶子全集』全20巻（講談社、1979年 - 1981年刊）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Teihon Yosano Akiko Zenshu&quot; (Complete collection of Akiko Yosano) 20 volumes (Kodansha, published in 1979 - 1981)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Teihon Yosano Akiko Zenshu&quot; (Complete collection of Akiko Yosano) twenty volumes (Kodansha, published in 1979 - 1981)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Teihon Yosano Akiko Zenshu&quot; (Complete collection of Akiko Yosano) twenty volumes (Kodansha, published in 1979 - 1981)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>『みだれ髪』（新潮文庫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled Hair) (Shincho Bunko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled Hair) (Shincho Bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Midaregami&quot; (Tangled Hair) (Shincho Bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>『みだれ髪 附みだれ髪拾遺』（角川文庫クラシックス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Midaregami with Midaregami shui&quot; (Tangled Hair with additional collection) (Kadokawa Bunko Classics)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Midaregami with Midaregami shui&quot; (Tangled Hair with additional collection) (Kadokawa Bunko Classics)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Midaregami with Midaregami shui&quot; (Tangled Hair with additional collection) (Kadokawa Bunko Classics)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>『全訳源氏物語』上・中・下（角川文庫クラシックス）・大活字版『ザ・源氏物語』全文対訳（第三書館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zenyaku Genji Monogatari&quot; (Complete translation of The Tale of Genji&quot; three volumes (Kadokawa Bunko Classics); Large-print edition &quot;The Genji Monogatari&quot; with complete text and translation (Daisan Shokan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zenyaku Genji Monogatari&quot; (Complete translation of the The Tale of Genji&quot; three volumes (Kadokawa Bunko Classics); Large-print edition &quot;The Genji Monogatari&quot; with complete text and translation (Daisan Shokan)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Zenyaku Genji Monogatari&quot; (Complete translation of the &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; three volumes (Kadokawa Bunko Classics); Large-print edition &quot;The Genji Monogatari&quot; with complete text and translation (Daisan Shokan)</e>
<cmt>The Tale of GenjiのTheの前に&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>『梗概源氏物語』（武蔵野書院）鶴見大学文学部、池田利夫 編</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kogai Genji Monogatari&quot; (Outline of The Tale of Genji) (Musashinoshoin) Faculty of Letters, Tsurumi University, edited by Toshio Ikeda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kogai Genji Monogatari&quot; (Outline of The Tale of Genji) (Musashinoshoin) Faculty of Letters, Tsurumi University, edited by Toshio Ikeda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kogai Genji Monogatari&quot; (Outline of The Tale of Genji) (Musashinoshoin) Faculty of Letters, Tsurumi University, edited by Toshio Ikeda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>『蜻蛉日記』（平凡社ライブラリー）与謝野晶子 訳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kagero Nikki&quot; (The Gossamer Years) (Heibonsha library) translated by Akiko Yosano</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kagero Nikki&quot; (The Gossamer Years) (Heibonsha library) translated by Akiko Yosano</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kagero Nikki&quot; (The Gossamer Years) (Heibonsha library) translated by Akiko Yosano</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>『与謝野晶子歌集』（岩波文庫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Poetry anthology of Akiko Yosano&quot; (Iwanami bunko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Poetry anthology of Akiko Yosano&quot; (Iwanami bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Poetry anthology of Akiko Yosano&quot; (Iwanami bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>『与謝野晶子評論集』（岩波文庫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Collection of Commentary by Akiko Yosano&quot; (Iwanami bunko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Collection of Commentaries by Akiko Yosano&quot; (Iwanami bunko)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Collection of Commentaries by Akiko Yosano&quot; (Iwanami bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>『愛、理性及び勇気』（講談社文芸文庫 現代日本のエッセイ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ai, Risei oyobi yuki&quot; (Love, Reason and Courage) (Kodansha Bungei Bunko, Contemporary Japanese Essays)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ai, Risei oyobi yuki&quot; (Love, Reason, and Courage) (Kodansha Bungei Bunko, Contemporary Japanese Essays)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ai, Risei oyobi yuki&quot; (Love, Reason, and Courage) (Kodansha Bungei Bunko, Contemporary Japanese Essays)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>『女人創造 叢書 女性論』（大空社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nyonin Sozo (Creation of Women) The Series of Feminism&quot; (Ozorasha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nyonin Sozo (Creation of Women) The Series on Feminism&quot; (Ozorasha)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nyonin Sozo (Creation of Women) The Series on Feminism&quot; (Ozorasha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>『与謝野寛晶子書簡集成』（八木書店）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Collection of Letters by Hiroshi and Akiko Yosano&quot; (Yagishoten)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Collection of Letters by Hiroshi and Akiko Yosano&quot; (Yagishoten)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Collection of Letters by Hiroshi and Akiko Yosano&quot; (Yagishoten)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>『私の生ひ立ち』（女性文庫／学陽書房）竹久夢二 挿絵／（刊行社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Watashi no oitachi&quot; (My biography) (Josei bunko/Gakuyo Shobo) illustrated by Yumeji TAKEHISA (Kankosha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Watashi no oitachi&quot; (My biography) (Josei bunko/Gakuyo Shobo) illustrated by Yumeji TAKEHISA (Kankosha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Watashi no oitachi&quot; (My biography) (Josei bunko/Gakuyo Shobo) illustrated by Yumeji TAKEHISA (Kankosha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>『童話 環の一年間』（和泉書院）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Dowa Tamaki no ichinenkan&quot; (Nursery story: A year of Tamaki&quot; (Izumi-shoin publishing)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Dowa Tamaki no ichinenkan&quot; (Nursery story: A year of Tamaki&quot; (Izumi-shoin publishing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Dowa Tamaki no ichinenkan&quot; (Nursery story: A year of Tamaki&quot; (Izumi-shoin publishing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>児童・子ども向け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Children&apos;s book</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Children&apos;s book</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Children&apos;s book</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>『きんぎょのおつかい』（架空社）高部晴市、与謝野晶子 著</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kingyo no otsukai&quot; (The Gold Fish Couriers) (Kakusha) by Seiichi TAKABE, Akiko Yosano</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kingyo no otsukai&quot; (The Gold Fish Couriers) (Kakusha) by Seiichi TAKABE, Akiko Yosano</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kingyo no otsukai&quot; (The Gold Fish Couriers) (Kakusha) by Seiichi TAKABE, Akiko Yosano</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>『与謝野晶子 女性の自由を歌った情熱の歌人』（学習まんが人物館／小学館）入江春行、あべさより 著</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Akiko Yosano: A poet of passion for freedom of women&quot; (Gakushu Manga Jinbutsukan/Shogakukan) by Haruyuki IRIE, Sayori ABE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Akiko Yosano: A poet of passion for the freedom of women&quot; (Gakushu Manga Jinbutsukan/Shogakukan) by Haruyuki IRIE, Sayori ABE</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Akiko Yosano: A poet of passion for the freedom of women&quot; (Gakushu Manga Jinbutsukan/Shogakukan) by Haruyuki IRIE, Sayori ABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>与謝野という姓は、京都府北部の与謝野町に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family name YOSANO was derived from the name of town Yosano-cho in north Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name YOSANO was derived from the name of town Yosano-cho in north Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name YOSANO was derived from the name of town Yosano-cho in north Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="96">
<j>華の乱（1988年、東映京都製作所、深作欣二監督）は与謝野晶子の生涯を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hana no ran&quot; (A Chaos of Flowers) (1988, Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, directed by Kinji FUKASAKU) is a film on the life of Akiko Yosano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hana no ran&quot; (A Chaos of Flowers) (1988, Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, directed by Kinji FUKASAKU) is a film on the life of Akiko Yosano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hana no ran&quot; (A Chaos of Flowers) (1988, Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, directed by Kinji FUKASAKU) is a film on the life of Akiko Yosano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>吉永小百合が晶子を演じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sayuri YOSHINAGA played the role of Akiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sayuri YOSHINAGA played the role of Akiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sayuri YOSHINAGA played the role of Akiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="98">
<j>1998年5月に生誕120周年を記念して堺市の南海本線堺駅西口に銅像が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1998, a bronze statue of Akiko was built in the commemoration of her 120th anniversary at the west gate of Sakai Station, Nankai Main Line, in Saki City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1998, a bronze statue of Akiko was built in the commemoration of her 120th anniversary at the west gate of Sakai Station, Nankai Main Line, in Saki City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1998, a bronze statue of Akiko was built in the commemoration of her 120th anniversary at the west gate of Sakai Station, Nankai Main Line, in Saki City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="99">
<j>通産相や金融経済財政担当相、自民党政調会長などを務めた衆議院議員・与謝野馨（2007年安倍改造内閣時の内閣官房長官）は晶子の孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru YOSANO, a member of the House of Representatives and former the Minister of International Trade and Industry, Minister of State for Economicand Fiscal Policy and Financial Services, and Chairman of Policy Research Council of Liberal Democratic Party (and the Chief Cabinet Secretary of the Abe Administration in 2007) is Akiko&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru YOSANO, a member of the House of Representatives and former the Minister of International Trade and Industry, Minister of State for Economicand Fiscal Policy and Financial Services, and Chairman of Policy Research Council of Liberal Democratic Party (and the Chief Cabinet Secretary of the Abe Administration in 2007) is Akiko&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru YOSANO, a member of the House of Representatives and the former Minister of International Trade and Industry, the Minister of State for Economicand Fiscal Policy and Financial Services, and the Chairman of Policy Research Council of Liberal Democratic Party (and the Chief Cabinet Secretary of the Abe Administration in 2007) is Akiko&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt>Minister of International Trade and Industryの前のtheをformerの前に移動しました。Minister of State、Chairman of Policyの前にtheを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>馨が幼い頃に晶子が死去したが、初めて衆議院議員選挙に立候補して落選し、浪人生活を送っているときに、祖母の詩集『みだれ髪』を復刻させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaoru was at an early age when Akiko died, but after he run unsuccessfully for his first election of members of the House of Representatives, he published the reprint of his grandmother&apos;s collection of poetry &quot;Midaregami&quot; while he was preparing for the next election.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaoru was an early age when Akiko died, but after he ran unsuccessfully for his first election as a member of the House of Representatives, he published the reprint of his grandmother&apos;s collection of poetry &quot;Midaregami&quot; while he was preparing for the next election.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaoru was an early age when Akiko died, but after he ran unsuccessfully for his first election as a member of the House of Representatives, he published the reprint of his grandmother&apos;s collection of poetry &quot;Midaregami&quot; while he was preparing for the next election.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="101">
<j>与謝野晶子の作品をモチーフに、2006年8月、京都八幡市で開催された「全国高校総合文化祭演劇部門」において、第二次大戦の時代の波に翻弄される漫才師姉弟を描いた「君死にたまふことなかれ」が上演されたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on Akiko&apos;s works, in the Drama Division of the National High School Arts Festival held in Yawata City, Kyoto in August 2006, a play entitled &quot;Kimi Shinitamou Koto Nakare&quot; was performed that depicted a sister and her younger brother who were stand-up comedians at the mercy of the time during the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on Akiko&apos;s works, in the Drama Division of the National High School Arts Festival held in Yawata City, Kyoto in August 2006, a play entitled &quot;Kimi Shinitamou Koto Nakare&quot; was performed that depicted a sister and her younger brother who were stand-up comedians at the mercy of the time during World War II.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on Akiko&apos;s works, in the &apos;Drama Division of the National High School Arts Festival&apos; held in Yawata City, Kyoto in August 2006, a play entitled &apos;Kimi Shinitamou Koto Nakare&apos; was performed that depicted a sister and her younger brother who were stand-up comedians at the mercy of the time during World War II.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), 月下薄氷(id:47743), 経済準学士(id:22656), Georva(id:15984), Yuichiokubo(id:88759), シェスカ(id:103078), 0太郎(id:7375), Electric goat(id:2935), Greenland4(id:114494), Chiba007(id:106206), Christopher Patrick Johnson(id:51765), 78(id:10935), Yukichi99(id:29402), Opponent(id:720), FOXi(id:153687), Michey.M(id:906), 名無し(id:7386), 清水友一(id:277503), TY(id:1386), Kanoe(id:17203), Point136(id:211299), 5816K(id:102574), Yas(id:739), PuzzIeBacheIor(id:18744), M-sho-gun(id:88956), XXx(id:75211), Pacifist(id:63219), Deepimpact(id:129352), Carbuncle(id:346), Complex01(id:10454), Xqbot(id:273540), Alecs.bot(id:194707), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Saigo Takamori(id:123997), Afghanistanbananastan(id:164462), Hetareguma(id:102862), 小太刀(id:18154), Deewell(id:22093), ゆいしあす(id:79629), エラリー(id:670), Pgdk(id:81209), ワイバーン(id:23593), 鈴虫(id:193720), さららゆら(id:12274), 野良人(id:58574), Loveless(id:129239), Izayohi(id:13095), PANYNJ(id:38638), Hamlet(id:50119), User(id:20390), Aphaia(id:3132), CaCO3(id:111669), Yhiroyuki(id:84500), Lucas0123(id:130266), Clarin(id:60278), Hiroshi007(id:287410), Sarumann(id:56190), VolkovBot(id:105371), 上田隼人(id:23104), Kropsoq(id:10072), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 663highland(id:18755), ISSHIE(id:63943), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Falcosapiens(id:221), SieBot(id:126695), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>