<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徽子女王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Queen Kishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Queen Kishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Queen Kishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徽子女王（きし（よしこ）じょおう、延長 (元号)7年（929年） - 寛和元年（985年））は平安時代中期の皇族、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Queen Kishi (also known as Yoshiko) was a poet and member of the Imperial family who lived in the middle of the Heian period, from 929 (Encho 7) to 985 (Kanna 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Queen Kishi (also known as Yoshiko) was a poet and member of the Imperial family who lived in the middle of the Heian period, from 929 (Encho 7) to 985 (Kanna 1).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Queen Kishi (also known as Yoshiko) was a poet and member of the Imperial Family who lived in the middle of the Heian period, from 929 to 985.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>醍醐天皇皇孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a descendant of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a descendant of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a descendant of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>式部卿宮重明親王の第一王女、母は藤原忠平の次女藤原寛子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the firstborn daughter of Shigeaki Shikibu-kyonomiya, the Imperial prince; her mother was FUJIWARA no Hiroko (also known as Kanshi), second daughter of FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the firstborn daughter of Shigeaki Shikibu-kyonomiya, the Imperial prince; her mother was FUJIWARA no Hiroko (also known as Kanshi), second daughter of FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the firstborn daughter of Shigeaki Shikibu-kyonomiya, the Imperial Prince; her mother was FUJIWARA no Hiroko (also known as Kanshi), second daughter of FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>朱雀天皇朝斎宮、のち村上天皇女御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She served as one of the Sainomiya (Imperial princesses at Ise shrine) for the court of Emperor Suzaku, and afterwards was a lady-in-waiting for Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She served as one of the Sainomiya (Imperial princesses at Ise shrine) for the court of Emperor Suzaku, and afterwards was a lady-in-waiting for Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She served as one of the Sainomiya (Imperial Princesses at Ise Shrine) for the court of Emperor Suzaku, and afterwards was a lady-in-waiting for Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>別名斎宮女御、または承香殿女御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, she is also known as &quot;Lady Sainomiya,&quot; and as &quot;the lady of Shokoden palace.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, she is also known as Lady Sainomiya, and as the Lady of Shokoden Palace.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks and capitalised title.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, she is also known as Lady Sainomiya, and as the Lady of Shokoden Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>三十六歌仙および女房三十六歌仙の一。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is counted as one of the Thirty-Six Poet Immortals as well as one of the Thirty-Six Lady Poet Immortals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is counted as one of the Thirty-Six Poet Immortals as well as one of the Thirty-Six Lady Poet Immortals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is counted as one of the 36 Immortal Poets as well as one of the 36 Lady Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>Thirty-Six Poet Immortals→ 36 Immortal Poets</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>統一&quot;Brief personal history&quot;→&quot;Brief Personal History&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>承平 (日本)6年（936年）、時の斎宮斉子内親王（醍醐天皇皇女）の急逝により、8歳で伊勢斎宮に選ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 936 (Johei 6), the current high priestess of Ise shrine, Princess Saishi (daughter of Emperor Daigo), suddenly died, prompting Kishi to be chosen as the next high priestess of Ise, at the age of eight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 936 (Johei 6), the current high priestess of Ise shrine, Princess Saishi (daughter of Emperor Daigo), suddenly died, prompting Kishi to be chosen as the next high priestess of Ise, at the age of eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 936, the current high priestess of Ise Shrine, Imperial Princess Saishi (daughter of Emperor Daigo), suddenly died, prompting Kishi to be chosen as the next high priestess of Ise, at the age of eight.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除スペルを修正&quot;Princess Saishi&quot;→&quot;Imperial Princess Saishi&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天慶元年（938年）、10歳で伊勢へ下向。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 938 (Tengyo 1), at the age of ten, she went down to Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 938 (Tengyo 1), at the age of ten, she went down to Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 938, at the age of ten, she went down to Ise.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この時の発遣の儀（出発前の儀式）は朱雀天皇が物忌中のため、外祖父の摂政忠平が執り行い、また群行には長奉送使（斎宮を伊勢まで送り届ける勅使）として伯父の中納言藤原師輔が同行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the time came for the hakken no gi (the pre-departure ceremony), Emperor Suzaku was still working to avoid a taboo, so his maternal grandfather, the Regent Tadahira, performed his duties for him, and for the pilgrimage to Ise, the Choho-soshi (Imperial envoy who was responsible for seing each high priestess safely arrive at Ise) for Kishi&apos;s journey was her uncle, the Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who traveled on the pilgrimage with her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the time came for the hakken no gi (the pre-departure ceremony), Emperor Suzaku was still working to avoid a taboo, so his maternal grandfather, the Regent Tadahira, performed his duties for him, and for the pilgrimage to Ise, the Choho-soshi (Imperial envoy who was responsible for seing each high priestess safely arrive at Ise) for Kishi&apos;s journey was her uncle, the Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who traveled on the pilgrimage with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the time came for the hakken no gi (the pre-departure ceremony), Emperor Suzaku was still working to avoid a taboo, so his maternal grandfather, the Regent Tadahira, performed his duties for him, and for the pilgrimage to Ise, the Choho-soshi (Imperial envoy who was responsible for seeing each high priestess safely arrive at Ise) for Kishi&apos;s journey was her uncle, the Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who traveled on the pilgrimage with her.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正&quot;Middle Counselor&quot;→&quot;vice-councilor of state&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同8年（945年）、母の死により17歳で退下、帰京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 945 (Tengyo 8), at the age of seventeen, she resigned from her post because of her mother&apos;s death, and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 945 (Tengyo 8), at the age of seventeen, she resigned from her post because of her mother&apos;s death, and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 945, at the age of seventeen, she resigned from her post because of her mother&apos;s death, and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>天暦2年（948年）、叔父村上天皇に請われて20歳で入内し、同3年（949年）女御の宣旨を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 948 (Tenryaku 2), at the age of twenty, she entered the Court at the request of her uncle Emperor Murakami, and received her official appointment as Court Lady in 949.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 948 (Tenryaku 2), at the age of twenty, she entered the Court at the request of her uncle Emperor Murakami, and received her official appointment as Court Lady in 949.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 948, at the age of twenty, she entered the Court at the request of her uncle Emperor Murakami, and received her official appointment as Court Lady in 949.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>局を承香殿としたことから承香殿女御、また父重明親王の肩書から式部卿の女御などと称されたが、前斎宮であった故の「斎宮女御」の通称が最もよく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because she was assigned as lady-in-waiting to the Shokaden Palace and because her father Prince Shigeaki&apos;s Court title was &quot;Lord Shikibukyo,&quot; she was called &quot;Lady Shokaden&quot; and &quot;Lady Shikibukyo,&quot; but her most widely known popular name was &quot;the Lady of Ise&quot; due to her earlier role as high priestess of Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because she was assigned as lady-in-waiting to the Shokaden Palace and because her father Prince Shigeaki&apos;s Court title was Lord Shikibukyo, she was called Lady Shokaden and Lady Shikibukyo, but her most widely known popular name was the Lady of Ise due to her earlier role as high priestess of Ise.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because she was assigned as lady-in-waiting to the Shokaden Palace and because her father Imperial Prince Shigeaki&apos;s Court title was Lord Shikibukyo, she was called Lady Shokaden and Lady Shikibukyo, but her most widely known popular name was the Lady of Ise due to her earlier role as high priestess of Ise.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Prince&quot;→&quot;Imperial Prince&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>子女は規子内親王（村上天皇第四皇女、天暦3年-寛和2年）と皇子一人（早世）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had two children, a daughter called Princess Kishi (the fourth imperial daughter of Emperor Murakami, who lived from Tenryaku 3 to Kanna 2) and one son (who died young).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had two children, a daughter called Princess Kishi (the fourth imperial daughter of Emperor Murakami, who lived from Tenryaku 3 to Kanna 2) and one son (who died young).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had two children, a daughter called Imperial Princess Kishi (the fourth imperial daughter of Emperor Murakami, who lived from 949 to 986) and one son (who died young)).</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に）補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>中宮藤原安子、宣耀殿女御藤原芳子など美女才女の多い後宮にあって徽子女王の父譲りの和歌と琴の天分は名高く、ことに古琴の名手であったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She lived in the inner palace surrounded by many beautiful and talented women including Empress FUJIWARA no Anshi and Sen&apos;yoden no Nyogo FUJIWARA no Hoshi (or Yoshiko), yet Queen Kishi&apos;s exceptional talents in waka poetry and in playing the koto, which she had inherited from her father, were especially famous, and she was known as an expert at the kokin (a musical instrument, like the koto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She lived in the inner palace surrounded by many beautiful and talented women including Empress FUJIWARA no Anshi and Sen&apos;yoden no Nyogo FUJIWARA no Hoshi (or Yoshiko), yet Queen Kishi&apos;s exceptional talents in waka poetry and in playing the koto, which she had inherited from her father, were especially famous, and she was known as an expert at the kokin (a musical instrument, like the koto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She lived in the inner palace surrounded by many beautiful and talented women including Empress FUJIWARA no Anshi and Senyoden no Nyogo FUJIWARA no Hoshi (or Yoshiko), yet Queen Kishi&apos;s exceptional talents in waka poetry and in playing the koto, which she had inherited from her father, were especially famous, and she was known as an expert at the kokin (a musical instrument, like the koto).</e>
<cmt>人名表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>詠歌にも琴にまつわる秀歌が多く、また『大鏡』171段にも天皇と徽子女王の琴をめぐる逸話が語られており、『夜鶴庭訓抄』は斎宮女御が右手を琴を引く手として大切にし、普段は左の手を使ったと伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She also wrote a large number of excellent waka as songs for the koto, and section 171 of the &quot;Okagami&quot; tells an anecdote about the Emperor and Queen Kishi playing the koto together; the &quot;Yakakutei kinsho&quot; reports that priestesses of Ise and court ladies valued playing the koto so highly that they reserved their right hands only for that, and used their left hands only in daily life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She also wrote a large number of excellent waka as songs for the koto, and section 171 of the Okagami tells an anecdote about the Emperor and Queen Kishi playing the koto together; the Yakakutei kinsho reports that priestesses of Ise and court ladies valued playing the koto so highly that they reserved their right hands only for that, and used their left hands only in daily life.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She also wrote a large number of excellent waka as songs for the koto, and section 171 of the &quot;Okagami&quot; tells an anecdote about the Emperor and Queen Kishi playing the koto together; the &quot;Yakakutei kinsho&quot; reports that priestesses of Ise and court ladies valued playing the koto so highly that they reserved their right hands only for that, and used their left hands only in daily life.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その他、天暦10年（956年）に「斎宮女御徽子女王歌合」を、天徳 (日本)3年（959年）に「斎宮女御徽子女王前栽合」を主催するなど、文雅豊かな御世に華を添えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, having come into full bloom during a generation that was exceptionally elegant and refined, she organized several cultured activities, including the &quot;Poetry Contest of Queen Kishi, High Priestess of Ise and Court Lady&quot; held in 956 (Tenryaku 10) and the &quot;Senzai (gardening) contest of Queen Kishi, High Priestess of Ise and Court Lady&quot; in 959 (Tentoku 3).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, having come into full bloom during a generation that was exceptionally elegant and refined, she organized several cultured activities, including the Poetry Contest of Queen Kishi, High Priestess of Ise and Court Lady held in 956 (Tenryaku 10) and the Senzai (gardening) contest of Queen Kishi, High Priestess of Ise and Court Lady in 959 (Tentoku 3).</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, having come into full bloom during a generation that was exceptionally elegant and refined, she organized several cultured activities, including the Poetry Contest of Queen Kishi, High Priestess of Ise and Court Lady held in 956 and the Senzai (gardening) contest of Queen Kishi, High Priestess of Ise and Court Lady in 959.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>康保4年（967年）に村上天皇が崩御、その後は一人娘規子内親王と共に里第で暮らす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 967 (Koho 4), Emperor Murakami passed away, and thereafter she lived together with her only daughter, Princess Kishi, in a palace outside the Imperial enclosure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 967 (Koho 4), Emperor Murakami passed away, and thereafter she lived together with her only daughter, Princess Kishi, in a palace outside the Imperial enclosure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 967, Emperor Murakami passed away, and thereafter she lived together with her only daughter, Imperial Princess Kishi, in a palace outside the Imperial enclosure.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除&quot;Princess&quot;→&quot;Imperial Princess&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天延3年（975年）、規子内親王が27歳で円融天皇の斎宮に選ばれると、翌貞元_(日本)元年（976年）の初斎院入りに徽子女王も同行、同年冬の野宮歌合では有名な「松風入夜琴」の歌を詠む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 975 (Ten&apos;en 3), at 27 years old, Princess Kishi was the imperial princess chosen to serve as high priestess of Ise for Emperor En&apos;yu, so the following year (Jogen 1, or 976), Queen Kishi traveled with her daughter for the ceremonial first entry of the new high priestess; it was in the winter of that same year that Queen Kishi composed her famous &quot;Shofu nyu yakin&quot; (into the night of koto music comes the wind of the pines) poem, during the poetry contest held at the temporary shrine of Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 975 (Ten&apos;en 3), at 27 years old, Princess Kishi was the imperial princess chosen to serve as high priestess of Ise for Emperor En&apos;yu, so the following year (Jogen 1, or 976), Queen Kishi traveled with her daughter for the ceremonial first entry of the new high priestess; it was in the winter of that same year that Queen Kishi composed her famous Shofu nyu yakin (Into the Night of Koto Music Comes the Wind of the Pines) poem, during the poetry contest held at the temporary shrine of Ise.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks. Capitalised title.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 975, at 27 years old, Imperial Princess Kishi was the imperial princess chosen to serve as high priestess of Ise for Emperor Enyu, so the following year in 976, Queen Kishi traveled with her daughter for the ceremonial first entry of the new high priestess; it was in the winter of that same year that Queen Kishi composed her famous Shofu nyu yakin (Into the Night of Koto Music Comes the Wind of the Pines) poem, during the poetry contest held at the temporary shrine of Ise.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除人名表記&quot;Princess&quot;→&quot;Imperial Princess&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そして同2年（977年）、円融天皇の制止を振り切って斎宮と共に伊勢へ下向し、前例のないこととして人々を驚かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, in 977 (Jogen 2), Queen Kishi shook off Emperor En&apos;yu&apos;s attempts to thwart her and processed down to Ise together with her daughter; this was completely without precedent, and as such left everyone shocked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And then, in 977 (Jogen 2), Queen Kishi shook off Emperor En&apos;yu&apos;s attempts to thwart her and processed down to Ise together with her daughter; this was completely without precedent, and as such left everyone shocked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And then, in 977, Queen Kishi shook off Emperor Enyu&apos;s attempts to thwart her and processed down to Ise together with her daughter; this was completely without precedent, and as such left everyone shocked.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除人名表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>（この時の逸話は後に『源氏物語』で六条御息所・秋好中宮親子のモデルになったと言われる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is thought this historical episode later served as the inspiration for the scene in the Tale of Genji where Lady Rokujo accompanies her daughter Empress Akikonomu to Ise.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is thought this historical episode later served as the inspiration for the scene in the Tale of Genji where Lady Rokujo accompanies her daughter Empress Akikonomu to Ise.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is thought this historical episode later served as the inspiration for the scene in the &quot;Tale of Genji&quot; where Lady Rokujo accompanies her daughter Empress Akikonomu to Ise.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>永観2年（984年）、円融天皇の譲位で斎宮規子内親王は退下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 984 (Enkan 2), Emperor En&apos;yu abdicated the throne, which prompted Princess Kishi to resign her position as high priestess of Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 984 (Enkan 2), Emperor En&apos;yu abdicated the throne, which prompted Princess Kishi to resign her position as high priestess of Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 984, Emperor Enyu abdicated the throne, which prompted Imperial Princess Kishi to resign her position as high priestess of Ise.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除人名表記&quot;Princess&quot;→&quot;Imperial Princess&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>翌寛和元年（985年）母娘共に帰京するが、この頃既に徽子女王は病身であったらしく、同年卒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year (985, or Kanna 1) mother and daughter returned to the capital together, but Queen Kishi seems already to have been suffering from an illness at this point, and she died one year later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year (985, or Kanna 1) mother and daughter returned to the capital together, but Queen Kishi seems already to have been suffering from an illness at this point, and she died one year later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year mother and daughter returned to the capital together, but Queen Kishi seems already to have been suffering from an illness at this point, and she died one year later.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>従四位上、享年57。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of her death, at age 57, she had reached the upper level of the Junior Fourth Rank at court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of her death, at age 57, she had reached the upper level of the Junior Fourth Rank at court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of her death, at age 57, she had reached the Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>upper level of the Junior Fourth Rank at court修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>「斎宮女御」の通称で知られる徽子女王は、前斎宮としては平城天皇妃朝原内親王以来の皇妃であり、また母娘二代の斎宮となったのも酒人内親王・朝原内親王以来であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Queen Kishi, known by her popular name &quot;Saigu nyogo&quot; (&quot;the high priestess and court lady&quot;), became empress starting after Princess Asahara, Empress to Emperor Heizei, and was part of the first mother-daughter, two-generation monopoly of the position of high priestess at Ise since Princess Sakahito and her daughter Princess Asahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Queen Kishi, known by her popular name Saigu nyogo (the High Priestess and Court Lady), became empress starting after Princess Asahara, Empress to Emperor Heizei, and was part of the first mother-daughter, two-generation monopoly of the position of high priestess at Ise since Princess Sakahito and her daughter Princess Asahara.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks. Capitalised title.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Queen Kishi, known by her popular name Saigu nyogo (the High Priestess and Court Lady), became empress starting after Imperial Princess Asahara, Empress to Emperor Heizei, and was part of the first mother-daughter, two-generation monopoly of the position of high priestess at Ise since Imperial Princess Sakahito and her daughter Imperial Princess Asahara.</e>
<cmt>Imperial補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし当時の後宮は中宮安子を始めとして摂家出身の妃が多く、そんな中で徽子女王は最も高貴な出自故に有力な後見を欠き、また頼りになる兄弟や皇子にも恵まれなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the inner palace in those days was filled with consorts from the family of regents and advisors (a different branch of the Fujiwara clan), and Empress Anshi first among them; although she was the one of the highest birth among all these women, Queen Kishi gradually lost her influential supporters, and was not blessed with brothers or imperial princes (i.e., sons) on whom she could rely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the inner palace in those days was filled with consorts from the family of regents and advisors (a different branch of the Fujiwara clan), and Empress Anshi first among them; although she was the one of the highest birth among all these women, Queen Kishi gradually lost her influential supporters, and was not blessed with brothers or imperial princes (i.e., sons) on whom she could rely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the inner palace in those days was filled with consorts from the family of regents and advisors (a different branch of the Fujiwara clan), and Empress Anshi first among them; although she was the one of the highest birth among all these women, Queen Kishi gradually lost her influential supporters, and was not blessed with brothers or imperial princes (i.e., sons) on whom she could rely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>特に外祖父忠平と父重明の死後は自身の病、また前斎宮という特異な身の上もあってか、なかなか参内せず里にこもりがちであったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not clear whether it was the deaths of her maternal grandfather Tadahira and her father Shigeaki in particular, or her own illness, or because of her unique position as a former high priestess of Ise, but whatever the cause, it appears she had a tendency to shut herself up in rural seclusion and hardly ever made her way to Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clear whether it was the deaths of her maternal grandfather Tadahira and her father Shigeaki in particular, or her own illness, or because of her unique position as a former high priestess of Ise, but whatever the cause, it appears she had a tendency to shut herself up in rural seclusion and hardly ever made her way to Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clear whether it was the deaths of her maternal grandfather Tadahira and her father Shigeaki in particular, or her own illness, or because of her unique position as a former high priestess of Ise, but whatever the cause, it appears she had a tendency to shut herself up in rural seclusion and hardly ever made her way to Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>後に父の未亡人藤原登子（中宮安子の妹）が村上天皇に召されるという事件が起こったことも、徽子女王が後宮に落ち着かなかった一因であったろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And later, when her father&apos;s widow FUJIWARA no Nariko (the younger sister of Empress Anshi) was summoned to court by Emperor Murakami, may have contributed to Kishi&apos;s unease at the inner palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And later, her father&apos;s widow FUJIWARA no Nariko (the younger sister of Empress Anshi) was summoned to court by Emperor Murakami may have contributed to Kishi&apos;s unease at the inner palace.</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;when&quot; and comma after &quot;Murakami&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And later, her father&apos;s widow FUJIWARA no Nariko (the younger sister of Empress Anshi) was summoned to court by Emperor Murakami may have contributed to Kishi&apos;s unease at the inner palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>一方で『栄花物語』は村上天皇が女御を「大層高貴で優雅な人」と恋しく思い、度々便りを使わしたと記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Eiga monogatari records Emperor Murakami as yearning for Kishi, &quot;a person of such nobility, such refinement,&quot; and frequently sending for her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Eiga monogatari records Emperor Murakami as yearning for Kishi, &quot;a person of such nobility, such refinement,&quot; and frequently sending for her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the &quot;Eiga monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) records Emperor Murakami as yearning for Kishi, &apos;a person of such nobility, such refinement,&apos; and frequently sending for her.</e>
<cmt>(A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) 補足&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>事実『村上御集』等に残る天皇と妃たちの相聞歌の中でも、入内前の求愛の歌を始め徽子女王と交わした詠歌は群を抜いて多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, among the poems romantically exchanged between the Emperor and his ladies that are recorded in &quot;Emperor Murakami&apos;s Imperial Poetry Anthology&quot; and other collections, the poems sent to and by Queen Kishi, especially the courting poems before she entered the court, stand out from the rest, and are quite numerous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, among the poems romantically exchanged between the Emperor and his ladies that are recorded in Emperor Murakami&apos;s Imperial Poetry Anthology and other collections, the poems sent to and by Queen Kishi, especially the courting poems before she entered the court, stand out from the rest, and are quite numerous.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, among the poems romantically exchanged between the Emperor and his ladies that are recorded in &quot;Emperor Murakami&apos;s Imperial Poetry Anthology&quot; and other collections, the poems sent to and by Queen Kishi, especially the courting poems before she entered the court, stand out from the rest, and are quite numerous.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのやりとりの睦まじさを見ても、徽子女王に対する天皇の寵愛が決して浅いものではなかったことが想像される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the level of harmony shown in these exchanges, it is easy to surmise that the affection Emperor Murakami felt towards Queen Kishi was anything but slight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the level of harmony shown in these exchanges, it is easy to surmise that the affection Emperor Murakami felt towards Queen Kishi was anything but slight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the level of harmony shown in these exchanges, it is easy to surmise that the affection Emperor Murakami felt towards Queen Kishi was anything but slight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>村上天皇の崩御後は源順、大中臣能宣、平兼盛ら著名な歌人たちが徽子女王・規子内親王母娘の元に出入りして度々歌合せなどを催し、村上朝の歌壇を引き継ぐ風雅のサロンとして評判を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Murakami&apos;s death several celebrated poets, including MINAMOTO no Shitago, ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, and TAIRA no Kanemori, frequently came to visit Queen Kishi and her daughter Princess Kishi at their home, where they organized poetry contests and other activities; she gathered together a popular and elegant literary salon, taking over leadership of the poetry circles of Emperor Murakami&apos;s court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Murakami&apos;s death several celebrated poets, including MINAMOTO no Shitago, ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, and TAIRA no Kanemori, frequently came to visit Queen Kishi and her daughter Princess Kishi at their home, where they organized poetry contests and other activities; she gathered together a popular and elegant literary salon, taking over leadership of the poetry circles of Emperor Murakami&apos;s court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Murakami&apos;s death several celebrated poets, including MINAMOTO no Shitago, ONAKATOMI no Yoshinobu, and TAIRA no Kanemori, frequently came to visit Queen Kishi and her daughter Imperial Princess Kishi at their home, where they organized poetry contests and other activities; she gathered together a popular and elegant literary salon, taking over leadership of the poetry circles of Emperor Murakami&apos;s court.</e>
<cmt>Imperial補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また一方で一品宮資子内親王や後の大斎院選子内親王（共に村上天皇皇女、母は中宮安子）、円融天皇中宮藤原こう子等との交流も親しく、規子内親王と共に伊勢へ下向した後も折に触れてこまやかな便りを交わしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Queen Kishi was close and affectionate with many ladies, including Princess Ippon-nomiya Shishi and Princess Daisai-in Senshi (both daughters of Emperor Murakami and Empress Anshi) as well as FUJIWARA no Koshi, Empress to Emperor En&apos;yu, and occasionally exchanged quite delicate letters with them even after traveling together with her daughter Princess Kishi to Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Queen Kishi was close and affectionate with many ladies, including Princess Ippon-nomiya Shishi and Princess Daisai-in Senshi (both daughters of Emperor Murakami and Empress Anshi) as well as FUJIWARA no Koshi, Empress to Emperor En&apos;yu, and occasionally exchanged quite delicate letters with them even after traveling together with her daughter Princess Kishi to Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Queen Kishi was close and affectionate with many ladies, including Imperial Princess Ippon-nomiya Shishi and Imperial Princess Daisai-in Senshi (both daughters of Emperor Murakami and Empress Anshi) as well as FUJIWARA no Koshi, Empress to Emperor Enyu, and occasionally exchanged quite delicate letters with them even after traveling together with her daughter Imperial Princess Kishi to Ise.</e>
<cmt>Imperial補足人名表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>現在残る徽子女王の詠歌の多くは没後編纂された私家集『斎宮女御集』によるものであり、たおやかで優婉な調べは「いとあてになまめかしう」あったという斎宮女御その人の高雅な人柄を窺わせて趣深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of Queen Kishi&apos;s extant poems are known today because they were included in her (posthumous) personal waka anthology, the &quot;Saigu nyogoshu,&quot; and in her graceful, elegant melodies, called &quot;ito ate ni namamekashu&quot; (&quot;very noble and bewitching&quot;), one can catch glimpses of the true refinement of Queen Kishi&apos;s character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of Queen Kishi&apos;s extant poems are known today because they were included in her (posthumous) personal waka anthology, the Saigu nyogoshu, and in her graceful, elegant melodies, called Ito ate ni namamekashu (Very Noble and Bewitching), one can catch glimpses of the true refinement of Queen Kishi&apos;s character.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks. Capitalised title.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of Queen Kishi&apos;s extant poems are known today because they were included in her (posthumous) personal waka anthology, the &quot;Saigu nyogoshu,&quot; and in her graceful, elegant melodies, called Ito ate ni namamekashu (Very Noble and Bewitching), one can catch glimpses of the true refinement of Queen Kishi&apos;s character.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>初出の『拾遺和歌集』を始めとする勅撰集にも数多く入集しており、歴代の中でも質量共に際立っている点において、後の斎院式子内親王と並ぶ双璧として名高い斎王歌人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of her poems were included in the imperial waka anthologies, notably the first appearance of the &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (Collection of Poetic Gleanings), making her stand out from the crowd of poets even of successive generations, and is one of the pair of matchless jewels, Saio kajin (poet-priestesses), along with Princess Sai-in Shishi, who came after her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of her poems were included in the imperial waka anthologies, notably the first appearance of the Shui wakashu (Collection of Poetic Gleanings), making her stand out from the crowd of poets even of successive generations, and is one of the pair of matchless jewels, Saio kajin (poet-priestesses), along with Princess Sai-in Shishi, who came after her.</e>
<cmt>Removed quotation marks.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of her poems were included in the imperial waka anthologies, notably the first appearance of the &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (Collection of Poetic Gleanings), making her stand out both in quality and quantity from the crowd of poets even of successive generations, and is one of the pair of matchless jewels, Saio kajin (poet-priestesses), along with Imperial Princess Sai-in Shishi, who came after her.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足both in quality and quantity 補足&quot;Princess&quot;→&quot;Imperial Princess&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>代表歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of her best representative poems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of her best representative poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of her best representative poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>琴の音に峰の松風かよふらしいづれのをよりしらべそめけむ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sound of the koto seems to seems to mingle with the wind through the pines on the ridge; which does the melody come from, I wonder?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound of the koto seems to seems to mingle with the wind through the pines on the ridge; which does the melody come from, I wonder?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound of the koto seems to seems to mingle with the wind through the pines on the ridge; which does the melody come from, I wonder?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>世にふればまたも越えけり鈴鹿山むかしの今になるにやあるらむ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having turned my back on the world and even climbed over Mt. Suzuka, I expect it shall be as it was once long ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having turned my back on the world and even climbed over Mt. Suzuka, I expect it shall be as it was once long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having turned my back on the world and even climbed over Mt. Suzuka, I expect it shall be as it was once long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歌仙絵の斎宮女御</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The portrait of Saigu nyogo (Queen Kishi) as part of the series of portraits of Poet Immortals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The portrait of Saigu nyogo (Queen Kishi) as part of the series of portraits of Poet Immortals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The portrait of Saigu nyogo (Queen Kishi) as part of the series of portraits of Immortal Poets</e>
<cmt>Poet Immortals修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>三十六歌仙の中でも五人しかいない女性の一人で、しかも唯一の皇族歌人である斎宮女御は、後の歌仙絵の中でも際立った存在感を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of only five women counted among the Thirty-Six Poet Immortals, and moreover the only member of the Imperial family so selected, Queen Kishi&apos;s portrait occupies a prominent place even among portraits of the subsequent Poet Immortals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of only five women counted among the Thirty-Six Poet Immortals, and moreover the only member of the Imperial family so selected, Queen Kishi&apos;s portrait occupies a prominent place even among portraits of the subsequent Poet Immortals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of only five women counted among the 36 Immortal Poets, and moreover the only member of the Imperial family so selected, Queen Kishi&apos;s portrait occupies a prominent place even among portraits of the subsequent Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>Thirty-Six Poet Immortals→ 36 Immortal Poets</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>絵柄は数種の構図が知られており、高貴な身分を示す繧繝縁の畳に伏し美麗な几帳の陰に姿を隠したものが最も一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the various styles of portrait composition known, it was most common to show people of noble birth seated on tatami mats with dyed rims, their figures hidden behind beautiful screens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the various styles of portrait composition known, it was most common to show people of noble birth seated on tatami mats with dyed rims, their figures hidden behind beautiful screens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the various styles of portrait composition known, it was most common to show people of noble birth seated on tatami mats with dyed rims, their figures hidden behind beautiful screens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>現存最古の作品として名高い佐竹本三十六歌仙絵巻でも、束帯や華麗な十二単の正装に居住まいを正す歌仙が大半を占める中で、一人くつろいだ袿姿で慎ましく顔を伏せた斎宮女御は、いかにも深窓の姫君らしい気品漂う姿が華やかな色彩で美しく描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in Satake&apos;s famous volume, the handscroll showing the portraits of the Thirty-Six Poet Immortals, which is the oldest surviving work depicting them, among the vast majority of the figures shown seated in sokutai (ceremonial court robes) and sumptuous twelve-layered kimonos, one, Queen Kishi, is shown in a more relaxed posture, in uchiki-sugata (informal dress), modestly hiding her face from view; she is painted beautifully, with vivid colors, and her appearance reflects a truly regal quality, secluded there deep in her inner rooms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in Satake&apos;s famous volume, the handscroll showing the portraits of the Thirty-Six Poet Immortals, which is the oldest surviving work depicting them, among the vast majority of the figures shown seated in sokutai (ceremonial court robes) and sumptuous twelve-layered kimonos, one, Queen Kishi, is shown in a more relaxed posture, in uchiki-sugata (informal dress), modestly hiding her face from view; she is painted beautifully, with vivid colors, and her appearance reflects a truly regal quality, secluded there deep in her inner rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in Satake&apos;s famous volume, the handscroll showing the portraits of the 36 Immortal Poets, which is the oldest surviving work depicting them, among the vast majority of the figures shown seated in sokutai (ceremonial court robes) and sumptuous twelve-layered kimonos, one, Queen Kishi, is shown in a more relaxed posture, in uchiki-sugata (informal dress), modestly hiding her face from view; she is painted beautifully, with vivid colors, and her appearance reflects a truly regal quality, secluded there deep in her inner rooms.</e>
<cmt>Thirty-Six Poet Immortals→ 36 Immortal Poets</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>なお、大正8年（1919年）にその佐竹本が切断・売却された際には、六歌仙の一でもある小野小町をも上回って斎宮女御に三十六歌仙中最高の価格が付けられたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And indeed, in 1919 (the eighth year of the Taisho era) when the Satake volume was cut up into its individual portraits and sold, the price for the portrait of Queen Kishi surpassed that for all the other poet immortals, even ONO no Komachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And indeed, in 1919 (the eighth year of the Taisho era) when the Satake volume was cut up into its individual portraits and sold, the price for the portrait of Queen Kishi surpassed that for all the other poet immortals, even ONO no Komachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And indeed, in 1919 when the Satake volume was cut up into its individual portraits and sold, the price for the portrait of Queen Kishi surpassed that for all the other Immortal Poets, even ONO no Komachi.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Yukichi99(id:29402), Masyu(id:31065), Yonoemon(id:55450), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), VoidAimai(id:212464), YOSHI438(id:174755), Yas(id:739), 伏儀(id:142093), Emk(id:78926), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>