<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>歌学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagaku (study of waka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagaku (study of waka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagaku (study of waka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>歌学（かがく）は、和歌の本質・作法、古歌の解釈、故実、歴史など和歌に関する総てを研究する学問。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagaku is a study that researches everything related to waka such as essence and manners of waka, interpretation of old waka, ancient practices and history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagaku is a study that researches everything related to waka, such as its essence and mannerisms, the interpretation of old waka, ancient practices and history.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagaku is a study that researches everything related to waka, such as its essence and mannerisms, the interpretation of old waka, ancient practices and history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通常、和歌の本質論は歌論と称し、それ以外の和歌に関する諸知識を求める学問を歌学と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, discussion on the essence of waka is called karon (treatise on waka poetry) and the study for various knowledge concerning waka other than karon is called kagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, a discussion of the essence of waka is called a karon (treatise on waka poetry) and the study of various knowledge concerning waka other than in a karon is called kagaku.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, a discussion of the essence of waka is called a karon (treatise on waka poetry) and the study of various knowledge concerning waka other than karon is called kagaku.</e>
<cmt>in a を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>歌学の起源は8世紀にさかのぼるが当時は中国の詩論を模したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of kagaku goes back to eighth century, but at that time, it was imitation of the poetics in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of kagaku goes back to the eighth century, but at that time it was an imitation of the poetics of China.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of kagaku goes back to the eighth century, but at that time it was an imitation of the poetics of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>平安時代中期に成立した古今和歌集仮名序で日本的歌論が展開されるようになってから歌学は盛んとなり、歌論と並んで「万葉集」の研究も始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Japanese karon was explicated in Kanajo (Japanese preface) of Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) which was formed in the middle of the Heian Period, kagaku was actively pursued and, in line with karon and study on Manyoshu&quot; (anthology of Japanese poems) was commenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Japanese karon was explicated in Kanajo (Japanese preface) of Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), which was formed in the middle of the Heian period, kagaku was actively pursued and, in keeping with karon the study of Manyoshu&quot; (anthology of Japanese poems) was commenced.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning with the kanajo (a preface written in Japanese script) to the Kokin wakashu (Collection of Japanese Poetry from Ancient and Modern Times), which was written in the mid-Heian period, Japanese karon began to expand as a field, and kagaku began to flourish; in keeping with karon, research into the Manyoshu (an eighth-century anthology of Japanese poems) began.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代前期か中期にかけて和歌の本質を論じた歌論書が数多く作られたが、中でも藤原俊成・藤原定家の幽玄・有心の歌論は後世の歌学の基礎となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many books on karon that discussed the essence of waka were made in the beginning and middle of the Kamakura Period, karon of Yugen (the subtle and profound)/Ushin by FUJIWARA no Toshinari and FUJIWARA no Sadaie later became the basis for kagaku of later generation.</e>
<cmt>「有心」の後には説明をつけるべきと思いますが、辞典、事典の説明を抄訳してもこの本文より長くなると思われますので省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many books on karon that discussed the essence of waka were produced in the beginning and middle of the Kamakura period, including the karon of Yugen (the subtle and profound) (Ushin), by FUJIWARA no Toshinari and FUJIWARA no Sadaie later became the basis for the kagaku of succeeding generations.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the early to the mid-Kamakura period, many karon books discussing the true essence of waka were written, among which were FUJIWARA no Toshinari and FUJIWARA no Sadaie&apos;s &quot;Yugen&quot; and &quot;Ushin,&quot; which later became the foundational texts for kagaku in later generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>鎌倉時代末期には歌学の家が成立し、京極家と二条家・冷泉家が対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the end of the Kamakura Period, families of kagaku were established and the Kyogoku family and the Nijo family/Reizei family were opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the end of the Kamakura period, families of kagaku were established, whereby the Kyogoku family and Nijo family (Reizei family) were opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the end of the Kamakura period, families of kagaku were established, whereby the Kyogoku family and Nijo family (Reizei family) were opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>室町時代に入り、古今伝授などの風が生じ歌学の固定化・形式化が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Muromachi Period started, customs like Kokin denju (the secret transmissions of the &quot;Kokinshu,&quot; Anthology of Old and New Japanese Poems) were commenced and stabilization and formalization of kagaku progressed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the start of the Muromachi period, customs like Kokin denju (the secret transmission of the &quot;Kokinshu,&quot; Anthology of Old and New Japanese Poems) were commenced and the stabilization and formalization of kagaku progressed.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the Muromachi period began, customs like Kokin denju (the secret transmission of a certain interpretation of the Kokin wakashu) arose, and more progress was made towards the stabilization and formalization of kagaku as a discipline.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この時代の歌論はその枠を超えて一つの芸術論、思想体系とも言うべきものになっており能の大成者世阿弥も「能楽師に必要な学問は歌学のみである」と述べるなど他の芸能にも大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karon in this period had already surpassed its frame and become essays on art or a system of ideology, and it gave deep influence to other arts as Zeami, who brought Noh to its completion, commented, &quot;Only study necessary for Noh player is Kagaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karon in this period had already exceeded its original framework and thus comprised essays on art or a system of ideology; thus it had a deep influence on other arts. Zeami, who brought Noh to its completion, commented, &quot;The only study necessary for a Noh player is Kagaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Two sentences</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karon in this period had already moved beyond its original narrow focus on poetry and began to include essays on art in general or essays that outlined an entire ideological system, and thereby came to have a deep influence on other art forms; Zeami, who perfected the art of Noh, commented that &quot;Kagaku is the only type of learning a Noh actor really needs.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代中期には、戸田茂睡・下河辺長流・契沖などにより中世歌学に対する批判が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of the Edo Period, Mosui TODA, Choryu SHIMOKOUBE, Keichu and others criticized chusei kagaku (Mediaeval Poetics)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Edo period, Mosui TODA, Choryu SHIMOKOUBE, Keichu and others criticized chusei kagaku (medieval poetics).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Edo period, Mosui TODA, Choryu SHIMOKOBE, Keichu and others criticized chusei kagaku (medieval poetics).</e>
<cmt>SHIMOKOBE　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>賀茂真淵・田安宗武などの万葉集を模範とするグループ、荷田在満・本居宣長などの新古今和歌集を模範とするグループ、小沢蘆庵・香川景樹などの古今和歌集を模範とするグループの三代潮流がうまれ、万葉集・古今和歌集・新古今和歌集の研究が盛んに行われ、これが明治時代初期まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three main streams, a group of Mabuchi KAMO, Munetake TAYASU, etc. that took Manyoshu as example, a group of KADA no Arimaro, Norinaga MOTOORI, etc. which took Shinkokinwakashu as an example and a group of Roan OZAWA, Kageki KAGAWA, etc. were formed, study on Manyoshu, Kokinwakashu and Shinkokinwakashu was actively carried on and this continued until the beginning of the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置「三代潮流」は「三大潮流」の誤りと考えられますが、「三代潮流」のまま訳すことはできませんので、「三大潮流」に訂正して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three main streams--a group comprising Mabuchi KAMO, Munetake TAYASU, etc., which took Manyoshu as an example; a group comprising KADA no Arimaro, Norinaga MOTOORI, etc., which took Shinkokinwakashu as an example; and a group comprising Roan OZAWA, Kageki KAGAWA, etc.--were formed; the study of Manyoshu, Kokinwakashu and Shinkokinwakashu was actively carried on, and this continued until the beginning of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three main schools of thought arose--the group made up of KAMO no Mabuchi, Munetake TAYASU, and others, which took the Manyoshu as its model; the group that included KADA no Arimaro and Norinaga MOTOORI, which took the Shin kokin wakashu as its model; and the group whose adherents included Roan OZAWA and Kageki KAGAWA, which took the Kokin wakashu as its model--these groups vigorously studied the Manyoshu, the Kokin wakashu and the Shin kokin wakashu, a state of affairs that continued until the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治時代中期になると、正岡子規の写生主義がでて歌論を風靡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of the Meiji Era, shaseishugi [定訳不明]　by Shiki MASAOKA came out and swept through karon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Meiji period, &quot;Shaseishugi [定訳不明],&quot; by Shiki MASAOKA, came out and swept through karon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid-Meiji period, Shiki MATSUOKA&apos;s theory of Shaseishugi (realism) first came out, and it shook the world of karon to its foundations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明治以降の歌学は、歌論よりも古歌・古歌集の研究に重点がおかれ、万葉集・古今和歌集の研究や和歌史・歌論史及び古歌集の書誌学的研究などが目覚しい発展を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In kagaku in and after the Meiji Era, focus was placed on study of old waka and old collections of waka rather tan karon and study on Manyoshu, Kokinwakashu, and study on the history of waka and the history of karon and bibliographic study of old collections of waka were remarkably developed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In kagaku in and after the Meiji period, focus was placed on the study of old waka and old collections of waka rather than karon and the study on Manyoshu and Kokinwakashu; thus the study of the history of waka and the history of karon and bibliographic study of old collections of waka were developed to a remarkable extent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kagaku of the Meiji period and thereafter was focused on studying ancient waka and old waka anthologies rather than on karon itself; as a result, remarkable progress has been made in research on the Manyoshu and the Kokin wakashu, in study of the history of waka and of karon, and in the bibliographic study of old waka anthologies.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>主な歌学書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ｍａｉｎ kagakusho (a book on the study of waka poems)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ｍａｉｎ kagakusho (a book on the study of waka poems)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main kagakusho (a book on the study of waka poems)</e>
<cmt>2バイト文字修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>歌経標式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakyo Hyoshiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakyo Hyoshiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakyo Hyoshiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>古今和歌集仮名序</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokinwakashu Kanajo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokinwakashu Kanajo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokin Wakashu Kanajo</e>
<cmt>Kokin Wakashu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>古来風体抄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korai Futeisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korai Futeisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korai Futeisho (a treatise on poetry-writing and the history of waka, written by FUJIWARA no Toshinari)</e>
<cmt>古来風体抄→Korai Futeisho (a treatise on poetry-writing and the history of waka, written by FUJIWARA no Toshinari) と補足しました。　[参考：http://books.google.com/books?id=5aEUI5roS6EC&amp;pg=PR42&amp;lpg=PR42&amp;dq=korai+futaisho&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=CrPqiqmSss&amp;sig=x2JroQbgxbwuzTdCE31IPkD5x9Q&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=yZDNStfuONCIkQWh6dnxAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1#v=onepage&amp;q=korai%20futaisho&amp;f=false]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sat666(id:127263), Ai yuto(id:97523), Nighthawks(id:36125), 愛国の歌人(id:173428), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>