<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>日本文学（にほんぶんがく）とは、日本語で書かれた文学作品、もしくはそれらの作品や作家を研究する学問のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon bungaku (Japanese literature) refers either to literary works written in Japanese or to the academic field that studies such works and their authors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon bungaku (Japanese literature) refers either to literary works written in Japanese or to the academic field that studies such works and their authors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon bungaku (Japanese literature) refers either to literary works written in Japanese or to the academic field that studies such works and their authors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>國文学ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called kokubungaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as kokubungaku.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as kokubungaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本文学の定義を何に求めるかについては諸説あり、言語、発表された地域、文学の形式など多くの要素が考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories about how to define Japanese literature, and many factors are considered, such as language, the area of publication, and literary form.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about how to define Japanese literature, and many factors are considered, such as language, the area of publication, and literary form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about how to define Japanese literature, and many factors are considered, such as language, the area of publication, and literary form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>（近年は外国籍作家が日本語作品を書く例など国籍や居住地と言語とが一致しない場合もあることを考慮し、日本語文学という呼称が使われることもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Recently some people are calling it nihongo bungaku (literally, literature written in Japanese) considering that in some cases the author&apos;s nationality or place of residence does not correspond to language, such as with foreign writers who write works in Japanese.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Recently some people are calling this literature nihongo bungaku (literally, literature written in Japanese) due to the fact that in some cases the author&apos;s nationality or place of residence does not correspond to the language used, such as with foreign writers who write works in Japanese.)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Recently some people are calling this literature nihongo bungaku (literally, literature written in Japanese) due to the fact that in some cases the author&apos;s nationality or place of residence does not correspond to the language used, such as with foreign writers who write works in Japanese.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>時代区分による分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Categorization by historical period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Categorization by historical period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Categorization by historical period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史学のように政権の移動に注目することが必ずしもふさわしいとは考えられないが、目安にされることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although paying attention to changes in political power is not always considered to be as suitable as it is for history, it is often used as a standard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although paying attention to changes in political power is not always considered to be as suitable as it is for history, it is often used as a reference point.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although paying attention to changes in political power is not always considered to be as suitable as it is for history, it is often used as a reference point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、上代・中古・中世・近世・近現代という区分けには研究者によって異論もあり、中古を設定しない場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are some scholars who dissent from the categories of Jodai (until the Nara period), Chuko (in and around the Heian period), medieval, early modern, modern, and present, and in some cases Chuko is not used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are some scholars who differ on opinions about the categories of Jodai (until the Nara period), Chuko (in and around the Heian period), medieval, early modern, modern, and present, and in some cases Chuko is not used at all.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are some scholars who differ on opinions about the categories of Jodai (until the Nara period), Chuko (in and around the Heian period), medieval, early modern, modern, and present, and in some cases Chuko is not used at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近代と現代の区分についても諸説あり定まっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also various theories about the division between modern and present, and the border has not been fixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also various theories about the division between modern and present, and the border has yet to be settled on.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also various theories about the division between modern and present, and the border has yet to be settled on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>丸谷才一は勅撰集により日本文学史の歴史区分を行うことを提示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saiichi MARUYA advocated dividing the history of Japanese literature into historically-periodized categories using chokusenshu (anthologies of Japanese waka poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saiichi MARUYA advocated dividing the history of Japanese literature into categories based on historical periods using the chokusenshu (anthologies of Japanese waka poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiichi MARUYA advocated dividing the history of Japanese literature into categories based on historical periods using the chokusenshu (anthologies of Japanese waka poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本史時代区分表も参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See also a chart of the periodization of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See also the chart on the periodization of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See also the chart on the periodization of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>古典文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classical Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classical Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classical Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>上代文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodai Literature (Early literature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodai Literature (Early literature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodai Literature (Early literature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>およそ奈良時代まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This refers to literary works written approximately by the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>原文だけを読むと「期間」を意味しているようにとれますが、ここは「上代に書かれた文学」についての説明、と解釈して訳出しました。（以下中古、中世、近世、近現代文学の冒頭についても同様）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This refers to literary works written approximately up until the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This refers to literary works written approximately up until the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中国大陸から朝鮮半島を経由して漢字が輸入され、漢文と、自分たちの話し言葉に漢字を当てはめた万葉仮名が使われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese characters were imported from the Chinese continent by way of the Korean peninsula, and people started to use Chinese prose and Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves), which fitted Chinese characters to their own spoken language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese characters were imported from the Chinese continent by way of the Korean peninsula, and people started to use Chinese prose and Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves), which fitted Chinese characters to their own spoken language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese characters were imported from the Chinese continent by way of the Korean peninsula, and people started to use Chinese prose and Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves), which fitted Chinese characters to their own spoken language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『古事記』（７１２年）『日本書紀』（７２０年）のような史書や、『万葉集』のような歌集が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History books such as the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters, 712) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan, 720) and collections of poems such as the &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) were produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History books such as the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters, written 712 C.E.) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan, written 720 C.E.) and collections of poems such as the &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) were produced.</e>
<cmt>Added C.E. to make it clearer that those numbers are years.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History books such as the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters, written 712 C.E.) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan, written 720 C.E.) and collections of poems such as the &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) were produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>中古文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literature in Chuko (the times around the Heian period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literature from the Chuko period (the times around the Heian period)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literature from the Chuko period (the times around the Heian period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>およそ平安時代にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to literary works written roughly in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This refers to literary works written roughly during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This refers to literary works written roughly during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>漢詩・漢文が引き続き栄えるとともに、初の勅撰和歌集である古今和歌集が編纂され、和歌が漢詩と対等の位置を占めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Chinese prose and poetry continued to thrive, the first of the Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of waka poetry compiled by Imperial command), the Kokin wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems), was compiled and waka poems achieved a status equal to that of Chinese poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Chinese prose and poetry continued to thrive, the first of the Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of waka poetry compiled by Imperial command), the Kokin wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems), was compiled and waka poems achieved a status equal to that of Chinese poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Chinese prose and poetry continued to thrive, the first of the Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of waka poetry compiled by Imperial command), the Kokin wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems), was compiled and waka poems achieved a status equal to that of Chinese poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>当時の公式文書は漢文であったが、平仮名の中古日本語による表現が盛んにはじまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the official documents in those days were written in Chinese prose, expressing something in Early Middle Japanese, using hiragana, started to become popular.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the official documents during this period continued to be written in Chinese prose, expressing things in Early Middle Japanese, using hiragana, started to become popular.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the official documents during this period continued to be written in Chinese prose, expressing things in Early Middle Japanese, using hiragana, started to become popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>紀貫之の『土佐日記』が書かれたのに続き、清少納言の随筆『枕草子』、紫式部の『源氏物語』など古典文学の代表作と言える作品が著された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works that can be said to be representative of Japanese classical literature were written, starting with the &quot;Tosa Nikki&quot; (The Tosa Diary) written by KI no Tsurayuki, then the miscellany &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book) by Sei Shonagon and &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, works that can be said to be representative of Japanese classical literature were written, starting with the &quot;Tosa Nikki&quot; (The Tosa Diary) written by KI no Tsurayuki, then the miscellaneous compositions of &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book) by Sei Shonagon, as well as &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, works that can be said to be representative of Japanese classical literature were written, starting with the &quot;Tosa Nikki&quot; (The Tosa Diary) written by KI no Tsurayuki, then the miscellaneous compositions of &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book) by Sei Shonagon, as well as &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>中世文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medieval Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medieval Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medieval Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>およそ鎌倉時代から安土桃山時代まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to literary works written approximately from the Kamakura to the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This refers to literary works written from approximately the Kamakura to the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This refers to literary works written from approximately the Kamakura to the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>藤原定家らによって華麗な技巧に特徴がある『新古今和歌集』が編まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Shin Chokusen wakashu&quot; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry), which is characterized by elaborately decorated techniques, was compiled by FUJIWARA no Sadaie and other poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Shin Chokusen wakashu&quot; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry), which is characterized by the elaborate techniques used, was compiled by FUJIWARA no Sadaie and other poets.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Shin Kokin wakashu&quot; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry), which is characterized by the elaborate techniques used, was compiled by FUJIWARA no Sadaie and other poets.</e>
<cmt>Chokusen→Kokin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、現代日本語の直系の祖先と言える和漢混淆文によって多くの作品が書かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, a lot of works were written using a style that mixed Japanese and Chinese words, which can be said to be the direct ancestor of the modern Japanese language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, many works were written using a style that mixed Japanese and Chinese words, which can be said to be the direct predecessor of the modern Japanese language.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, many works were written using a style that mixed Japanese and Chinese words, which can be said to be the direct predecessor of the modern Japanese language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>鴨長明の『方丈記』、吉田兼好の『徒然草』などがこれにあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are such works as the &quot;Hojoki&quot; (An Account of My Hut) by KAMO no Chomei and the &quot;Tsurezure gusa&quot; (Essays in Idleness) by Kenko YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are such works as the &quot;Hojoki&quot; (An Account of My Hut) by KAMO no Chomei and the &quot;Tsurezure gusa&quot; (Essays in Idleness) by Kenko YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are such works as the &quot;Hojoki&quot; (An Account of My Hut) by KAMO no Chomei and the &quot;Tsurezure gusa&quot; (Essays in Idleness) by Kenko YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>作者不詳のものとして『平家物語』が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also works of unknown authorship such as the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also works of unknown authorship such as the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also works of unknown authorship such as the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、能の発達が見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the above, Noh drama also developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the above, Noh drama also developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the above, Noh drama also developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>近世文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early Modern Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early Modern Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early Modern Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>およそ江戸時代の文学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roughly the literature of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This refers to the literature written approximately during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This refers to the literature written approximately during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>お伽草子の流れを汲み、仮名草子や井原西鶴らの浮世草子がうまれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being descended from the otogi zoshi, kana zoshi (novels written for women and children using kana rather than Chinese characters to make them easily understandable) and ukiyozoshi (literally, &quot;books of the floating world&quot;) were produced by Saikaku IHARA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In succession to the otogi zoshi, kana zoshi (novels written for women and children using kana rather than Chinese characters to make them easily understandable) and ukiyozoshi (literally, &quot;books of the floating world&quot;) were produced by Saikaku IHARA and others.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In succession to the otogi zoshi, kana zoshi (novels written for women and children using kana rather than Chinese characters to make them easily understandable) and ukiyozoshi (literally, &quot;books of the floating world&quot;) were produced by Saikaku IHARA and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、歌舞伎や浄瑠璃が興り人気を博した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, kabuki and joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) flourished and became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, kabuki and joruri (dramatic narrative sung with a samisen accompaniment) flourished and became popular.</e>
<cmt>reword. It could also be spelled &quot;shamisen&quot;, though, samisen isn&apos;t incorrect.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, kabuki and joruri (dramatic narrative sung with a shamisen accompaniment) flourished and became popular.</e>
<cmt>samisen→shamisen</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>俳諧が盛んになり、松尾芭蕉、小林一茶といった人々が活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) also became popular and people such as Basho MATSUO and Issa KOBAYASHI played the leading parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) also became popular and people such as Basho MATSUO and Issa KOBAYASHI played leading roles.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) also became popular and people such as Basho MATSUO and Issa KOBAYASHI played leading roles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>近現代文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern and Present Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern and Present Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern and Present Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>明治時代以降。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The literature in the Meiji period and afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The literature of the Meiji period and afterwards.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The literature of the Meiji period and afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>開国とともに西欧の文明が流入し文明開化が起こると、日本文学も大きな影響を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the opening up of the country, the influx of Western civilization gave rise to the civilization and progress movement, and Japanese literature was also affected dramatically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the opening of Japan to the world, the influx of Western civilization gave rise to a movement to Westernize Japan, and Japanese literature was also affected dramatically.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the opening of Japan to the world, the influx of Western civilization gave rise to a movement to Westernize Japan, and Japanese literature was also affected dramatically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>西欧近代小説の理念が輸入され、坪内逍遥の『小説神髄』、二葉亭四迷の『小説総論』『浮雲 (二葉亭四迷)』などによって実質的に近代の日本文学が出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea of the modern Western novel was imported into Japan and modern Japanese literature essentially began with works such as Shoyo TSUBOUCHI&apos;s &quot;Shosetsu shinzui&quot; (The essence of the novel), and FUTABATEI Shimei&apos;s &quot;Shosetsu soron&quot; (General theory of the novel) and &quot;Ukigumo&quot; (the drifting cloud).</e>
<cmt>原文中『浮雲 (二葉亭四迷)』の人名部分が重複するため、訳出では削りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea of the modern Western novel was imported into Japan and modern Japanese literature essentially began with works such as Shoyo TSUBOUCHI&apos;s &quot;Shosetsu shinzui&quot; (The essence of the novel), FUTABATEI Shimei&apos;s &quot;Shosetsu soron&quot; (General theory of the novel) and &quot;Ukigumo&quot; (the drifting cloud).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea of the modern Western novel was imported into Japan and modern Japanese literature essentially began with works such as Shoyo TSUBOUCHI&apos;s &quot;Shosetsu shinzui&quot; (The essence of the novel), FUTABATEI Shimei&apos;s &quot;Shosetsu soron&quot; (General theory of the novel) and &quot;Ukigumo&quot; (the drifting cloud).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>いわゆる「文学」という概念は、この頃に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concept of so-called &apos;literature&apos; was born then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concept of so-called &apos;literature&apos; was born during this period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concept of so-called &apos;literature&apos; was born during this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、近代文学と現代文学の境界は非常にあいまいで諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The boundary between modern literature and present literature is quite vague, and there are various theories about it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The boundary between modern literature and present day literature is quite vague, and there are various theories about it.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boundary between modern literature and present day literature is quite vague, and there are various theories about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>日本文学の形式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forms of Japanese literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The forms of Japanese literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The forms of Japanese literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>散文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prose</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prose</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prose</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>物語 - 古物語 - 作り物語 - 歌物語 - 擬古物語 - 軍記物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tales: furu monogatari (old stories, especially tales before the Tale of Genji), tsukuri monogatari (fictional tales), uta-monogatari (poem-tales), giko monogatari (archaistic fiction, referring especially to fictional writing during the Kamakura and Muromachi periods in imitation of the Heian tales) and gunki monogatari (martial tales)</e>
<cmt>原文「-」でつないでいる部分は、時系列順につないであるものについては&quot;from…,…, …to…&quot;等の形にし、そうでないものについてはカンマでつなぎました。（以下同じ）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tales: Furu monogatari (old stories, especially tales before the Tale of Genji), tsukuri monogatari (fictional tales), uta-monogatari (poem-tales), giko monogatari (archaistic fiction, referring especially to fictional writing during the Kamakura and Muromachi periods in imitation of the Heian tales) and gunki monogatari (martial tales)</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tales: Furu monogatari (old stories, especially tales before the Tale of Genji), tsukuri monogatari (fictional tales), uta-monogatari (poem-tales), giko monogatari (archaistic fiction, referring especially to fictional writing during the Kamakura and Muromachi periods in imitation of the Heian tales) and gunki monogatari (martial tales)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>説話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narratives</e>
<cmt>&quot;Anecdotes&quot; are usually humorous while the forms mentioned aren&apos;t necessarily.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narratives</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>小説 - 私小説 - 戯作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Novels: the &quot;I&quot; novels and gesaku (literary works of a playful, mocking, joking, silly or frivolous nature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Novels: Novels narrated in the first person and gesaku (literary works of a playful, mocking, joking, silly or frivolous nature)</e>
<cmt>I believe this is a clearer translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Novels: Novels narrated in the first person and gesaku (literary works of a playful, mocking, joking, silly or frivolous nature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>戯曲 - 能 - 歌舞伎 - 文楽（人形浄瑠璃）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drama: Noh plays, kabuki and bunraku (ningyo joruri, dramas using puppets with joruri recitation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drama: Noh plays, kabuki and bunraku (ningyo joruri, dramas using puppets with joruri recitation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drama: Noh plays, kabuki and bunraku (ningyo joruri, dramas using puppets with joruri recitation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>随筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miscellanies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Essays</e>
<cmt>随筆＝essayにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>日記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diaries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diaries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diaries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>紀行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Travel literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Travel literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Travel literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>伝記・自伝 - 往生伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biographies and autobiographies: ojoden (biographies of people who attained rebirth in the Pure Land)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biographies and autobiographies: Ojoden (biographies of people who attained rebirth in the Pure Land)</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biographies and autobiographies: Ojoden (biographies of people who attained rebirth in the Pure Land)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>文芸評論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary criticism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary criticism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary criticism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>日本漢文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese prose written by Japanese people</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese prose written by Japanese people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese prose written by Japanese people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>韻文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Verse</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Verse</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Verse</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>詩 - 自由詩 - 定型詩 - 散文詩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poetry: free verse, fixed verse and poems in prose</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poetry: Free verse, fixed verse and poems in prose</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poetry: Free verse, fixed verse and poems in prose</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>和歌 - 短歌 - 長歌 - 旋頭歌 - 仏足石歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka poetry: tanka (literally, &quot;short poems&quot;), choka (literally, &quot;long poems&quot;), sedoka (head-repeating poems) and bussokusekika (the Buddha&apos;s Footprint Poems at the Yakushiji-temple in Nara)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka poetry: Tanka (literally, &quot;short poems&quot;), choka (literally, &quot;long poems&quot;), sedoka (poems where the first line is repeated) and bussokusekika (the Buddha&apos;s Footprint Poems at the Yakushiji-temple in Nara)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka poetry: Tanka (literally, &quot;short poems&quot;), choka (literally, &quot;long poems&quot;), sedoka (poems where the first line is repeated) and bussokusekika (the Buddha&apos;s Footprint Poems at the Yakushiji-temple in Nara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>連歌 - 俳諧連歌 - 狂歌 - 俳諧（連句）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renga (linked verse): haikai renga (the origin of haiku), kyoka (comic or satirical tanka) and haikai (today also called renku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renga (linked verse): Haikai renga (the origin of haiku), kyoka (comic or satirical tanka) and haikai (today also called renku)</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renga (linked verse): Haikai renga (the origin of haiku), kyoka (comic or satirical tanka) and haikai (today also called renku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>俳句 - 定型 - 自由律</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haiku: a fixed form and free-verse haiku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiku: A fixed form and free-verse haiku</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haiku: A fixed form and free-verse haiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>川柳 - 狂句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senryu (satirical haiku): kyoku (a kind of humorous haikai without haikai conventions)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senryu (satirical haiku): Kyoku (a kind of humorous haikai without the usual haikai conventions)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senryu (satirical haiku): Kyoku (a kind of humorous haikai without the usual haikai conventions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>短歌（近代短歌）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanka poetry (the modern tanka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanka poetry (the modern tanka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanka poetry (the modern tanka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>歌謡 - 記紀歌謡 - 今様 - 小唄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Songs and ballads: the Kiki kayo (ballads found in the Kojiki and Nihon shoki), imayo (literary &quot;in the modern style&quot;, songs that were popular in the late Heian period) and kouta (ballads sung to samisen accompaniment)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Songs and ballads: The Kiki kayo (ballads found in the Kojiki and Nihon shoki), imayo (literally &quot;in the modern style&quot;, songs that were popular in the late Heian period) and kouta (ballads sung to a samisen accompaniment)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Songs and ballads: The Kiki kayo (ballads found in the Kojiki and Nihon shoki), imayo (literally &quot;in the modern style&quot;, songs that were popular in the late Heian period) and kouta (ballads sung to a shamisen accompaniment)</e>
<cmt>samisen→shamisen</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>漢詩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese poetry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese poetry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese poetry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>日本文学に隣接する文学活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary Activities in Contiguous to Japanese Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary Activities related to Japanese Literature</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary Activities related to Japanese Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>近隣では古代から中国文学の大きな影響を受け続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese literature has been greatly influenced by Chinese literature, its close neighbor, since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese literature has been greatly influenced by Chinese literature, its close neighbor, since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese literature has been greatly influenced by Chinese literature, its close neighbor, since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>アイヌ文学や琉球文学の活動と隣接する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is contiguous to activities in Ainu literature and Ryukyu literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has connections with activities in Ainu literature and Ryukyu literature.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has connections with activities in Ainu literature and Ryukyu literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>明治時代の日本への中国人・韓国人留学生の中から文学の担い手が生まれたことにより、日本文学は近代文学としての中国文学・朝鮮文学の成立に深く関わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese literature has deep connections with the establishment of Chinese and Korean literatures as modern literature because some of the founders of these literatures came from among Chinese and Korean students who had studied in Japan in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese literature has deep connections with the establishment of modern literature in China and Korea due to some of the founders of modern literature in those countries having come from among Chinese and Korean students who had studied in Japan during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese literature has deep connections with the establishment of modern literature in China and Korea due to some of the founders of modern literature in those countries having come from among Chinese and Korean students who had studied in Japan during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>日本文学の研究</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Studies in Japanese literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Studies in Japanese literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Studies in Japanese literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>特に古典では書誌学的な研究も多く行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the study of classical literature, studies related to bibliography are also often carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the study of classical literature, bibliographic studies are also often carried out.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the study of classical literature, bibliographic studies are also often carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>近代以降、著名な文学者によっていくつかの文学論争が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the modern period, there have been several arguments about literature among prominent literary scholars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the modern period, there has been some dispute about literature among prominent literary scholars.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the modern period, there has been some dispute about literature among prominent literary scholars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>やがて外国の研究者の注目も集めるようになり、古典から現代文学まで幅広く研究対象になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It eventually came to attract the attention of foreign scholars, and Japanese literature, from classical literature to the modern, was widely made an object of study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It eventually came to attract the attention of foreign scholars, and Japanese literature, from classical literature to the modern, was widely made an object of study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It eventually came to attract the attention of foreign scholars, and Japanese literature, from classical literature to the modern, was widely made an object of study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>20世紀後半には文学理論の影響で研究の手法は非常に幅広いものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late twentieth century, styles and techniques for study became quite wide due to the influence of literary theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late twentieth century, styles and techniques for studying literature varied significantly due to the influence of literary theory.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late twentieth century, styles and techniques for studying literature varied significantly due to the influence of literary theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="62">
<j>評論家一覧、比較文学、翻訳文学も参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See also the list of critics, comparative literature and literature in translation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See also the list of critics, comparative literature and literature in translation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See also the list of critics, comparative literature and literature in translation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>文学賞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary Awards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary Awards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary Awards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>近代以降多くの文学賞が創設され、作家の発掘と育成に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the modern period, numerous literary awards have been established and have contributed to the discovery and development of potential writers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the modern period, numerous organizations for literary awards have been established and have contributed to the discovery and development of potential writers.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the modern period, numerous organizations for literary awards have been established and have contributed to the discovery and development of potential writers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Worris(id:65), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Endy Leo(id:314338), Suguri F(id:11127), Yukawaguchi(id:247744), Sashisu(id:27243), Eskimbot(id:29676), Lupinoid(id:68), Mintleaf(id:2216), Esperanto(id:138866), さららゆら(id:12274), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), Gig(id:2773), Kinori(id:443), Rei-bot(id:94097), Tofu and moon(id:105903), TY(id:1386), Yas(id:739), Piasu9(id:134995), FlaBot(id:30804), Toki-ho(id:10691), Samai(id:117), Daisuke.IW(id:1206), Izayohi(id:13095), Setu(id:88), Aphaia(id:3132), 青山コロハ(id:118527), 亀井健吾(id:83873), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), 榎(id:91458), Escarbot(id:59151), Kiku b(id:14507), ArnoLagrange(id:1002), Amaki bo(id:13580), Mays(id:87), ニューワーカー(id:16977), Amanatto(id:93), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Chlewbot(id:33904), せいうち(id:1180), Earthian(id:105), Yoshitaka Mieda(id:26), Alexbot(id:157199), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), NDR(id:5500), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Trek011(id:7105), Suisui(id:69), HIJ(id:114), Yoira(id:99), SieBot(id:126695), Sabulyn(id:28132), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>