<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>建武式目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Kenmu Code</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenmu shikimoku (the Kenmu Code)</e>
<cmt>Used Japanese title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenmu shikimoku (the Kenmu Code)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>建武式目（けんむしきもく、建武式目条々）とは室町幕府の施政方針を示した政綱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenmu shikimoku (or Kenmu shikimoku jojo) is a political statement showing the governing philosophy of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenmu shikimoku (or Kenmu shikimoku jojo) is a political statement showing the governing philosophy of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenmu shikimoku (or Kenmu shikimoku jojo) is a political statement showing the governing philosophy of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御成敗式目と合わせて貞建の式条と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This code and the Joei code together are called the Joken codes.</e>
<cmt>御成敗式目・・・&quot;goseibai shikimoku&quot;という表記もないではないが、歴史学の文献では明らかにthe joei codeの方がよく使われていたため、こちらを採用した。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This code and the Joei Code together are called the Joken Codes.</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &quot;code&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This code and the Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai) together are called the Joken Codes.</e>
<cmt>Joei Code→Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai) 他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉幕府滅亡後に開始された後醍醐天皇の建武の新政から離反した足利尊氏は、南北朝時代 (日本)の1336年に湊川の戦いで新田義貞・楠木正成らを破り京都へ入り、施政方針を定めた建武式目を制定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Northern and Southern Courts (Nanbokucho) period (Japan) in 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had turned against the Kenmu Restoration started by Emperor Go-Daigo after the fall of the Kamakura Shogunate, defeated Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI in the battle of Minatogawa, entered Kyoto, and established his administrative policies in the Kenmu Code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Nanbokucho (Northern and Southern Courts) period of Japan in 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had turned against the Kenmu Restoration started by Emperor Go-Daigo after the fall of the Kamakura Shogunate, defeated Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI in the battle of Minatogawa, entered Kyoto, and established his administrative policies in the Kenmu Code.</e>
<cmt>Took &quot;Japan&quot; out of parenthesis and replaced it with &quot;of Japan&quot;. Used Japanese and put English in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Northern and Southern Court period of Japan in 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had turned against the Kenmu Restoration started by Emperor Godaigo after the fall of the Kamakura bakufu, defeated Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI in the battle of Minatogawa, entered Kyoto, and established his administrative policies in the Kenmu Code.</e>
<cmt>Nanbokucho ()削除人名のスペルを修正Shogunate→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>尊氏は後醍醐から三種の神器を接収して光明天皇を即位させ、2年後の1338年に征夷大将軍に任命されて正式に武家政権を成立させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji seized the Three Imperial Regalia from Go-Daigo, had Emperor Komyo accede to the throne, and 2 years later in 1338, he was appointed as seii taishogun (barbarian subduing generalissimo) and formally established a warrior government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji seized the Three Imperial Regalia from Go-Daigo, had Emperor Komyo accede to the throne, and 2 years later in 1338, he was appointed as seii taishogun (barbarian subduing generalissimo) and formally established a warrior government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji seized the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family from Godaigo, had Emperor Komyo accede to the throne, and 2 years later in 1338, he was appointed as seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and formally established a warrior government.</e>
<cmt>人名のスペルを修正Three Imperial Regalia→Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family(barbarian subduing generalissimo)→(literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>鎌倉幕府の奉行人である二階堂道昭（是円）・二階堂恵兄弟、藤原藤範、玄恵ら8人の答申の形で制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took the form of reports from 8 officials of the Kamakura Shogunate: the brothers Nikaido Dosho (Zeen) and Nikaido Shine, FUJIWARA no Fujinori, Gene and others.</e>
<cmt>「二階堂恵」は二階堂真恵　Nikaido Shineの誤りでした。また、現在の研究では二階堂道昭（是円）の姓は中原とのことでした。藤原藤範・・・同時代に「日野藤範」（ひのふじより）という人が似たような文脈で出てきますが、同一人物かどうかの確認がとれませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took the form of reports from 8 officials of the Kamakura Shogunate: the brothers Nikaido Dosho (Zeen) and Nikaido Shine, FUJIWARA no Fujinori, Gene and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took the form of reports from 8 officials of the Kamakura bakufu: the brothers Dosho (Zeen) and Shine NIKAIDO, FUJIWARA no Fujinori, Gene and others.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufu人名</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>武家の基本法である御成敗式目に対して建武式目は武家政権の施政方針を示すもので、拘束力がある法令ではないとも、御成敗式目の改廃を伴う法令ではない（御成敗式目を基本法とした）とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with the Joei code, which was the fundamental law for warriors, the Kenmu Code showed the governing philosophy of the warrior government, though it is said that it was neither legally binding nor a revision of the Joei code (it regarded the Joei code as the fundamental law).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with the Joei Code, which was the fundamental law for warriors, the Kenmu Code showed the governing philosophy of the warrior government, though it is said that it was neither legally binding nor a revision of the Joei Code (which it regarded as the fundamental law).</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &quot;code&quot;. Cut repetition of &quot;Joei Code&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with the Goseibai-shikimoku, which was the fundamental law for warriors, the Kenmu Code showed the governing philosophy of the warrior government, although it is said that it was neither legally binding nor a revision of the Goseibai-shikimoku (which it regarded as the fundamental law).</e>
<cmt>Joei Code→Goseibai-shikimoku&quot;though&quot;→&quot;alghough&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>尊氏は政務を弟の足利直義に任せており、式目の制定には直義の意思があったとも指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has also been pointed out that as Takauji let his brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA handle political affairs, it was Tadayoshi&apos;s determination behind the establishment of this code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also been pointed out that as Takauji let his brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA handle political affairs, it was Tadayoshi&apos;s determination that lay behind the establishment of this code.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;that lay&quot; before &quot;behind&quot; to make the sentence read a bit smoother.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also been pointed out that as Takauji let his brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA handle political affairs, it was Tadayoshi&apos;s determination that lay behind the establishment of this code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、太子信仰の風習から、聖徳太子の制定した憲法十七条に影響されたとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also thought to have been influenced by the Seventeen Article Constitution, given the Shotoku Taishi cult at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is also thought to have been influenced by the Seventeen Article Constitution that was established by Prince Shotoku from the traditions of the cult of Taishi.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &quot;given the Shotoku Taishi cult at the time.&quot; as it seemed confusing.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also thought to have been influenced by the Seventeen Article Constitution that was established by Prince Shotoku from the traditions of the cult of Taishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉幕府の「御成敗式目」と並び戦国大名の分国法にも影響する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the Joei code of the Kamakura shogunate, it also had influence on the provincial codes established by sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the Joei Code of the Kamakura shogunate, it also had influence on the provincial codes established by sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &quot;code&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the Goseibai-shikimoku of the Kamakura bakufu, it also had influence on the provincial codes established by daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufuJoei Code→Goseibai-shikimokusengoku daimyo→daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>構成は2項17条で、第1項で鎌倉幕府の得宗家専制以前の北条義時・北条泰時の施政を理想とし、足利幕府（室町幕府）が正統な後継者である事を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is composed of 2 sections and 17 articles, the first section of which held as ideal the administration of Yoshitoki HOJO and Yasutoki HOJO before the tokuso autocracy period of the Kamakura Shogunate, and showed how the Ashikaga Shogunate(the Muromachi Shogunate) was their legitimate successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is composed of 2 sections and 17 articles, the first section of which held as ideal the administration of Yoshitoki HOJO and Yasutoki HOJO before the tokuso autocracy period of the Kamakura Shogunate, and showed how the Ashikaga Shogunate(the Muromachi Shogunate) was their legitimate successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is composed of 2 sections and 17 articles, the first section of which held as ideal the administration of Yoshitoki HOJO and Yasutoki HOJO before the tokuso autocracy period of the Kamakura bakufu, and showed how the Ashikaga Shogunate(the Muromachi bakufu) was their legitimate successor.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>第2項では17条の条文において具体的方針を提示し、地方行政官である守護職は戦功よりも能力を重んじて任命することや、徳政令に関わる法令が多くを占める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the second section, the text of the 17 articles laid out the concrete policies of this code, and there were many laws stating that military governors (shugo), as local administrators, should be appointed for their ability rather than for their war records, and also many laws relating to debt-abrogation decrees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the second section, the text of the 17 articles laid out the concrete policies of this code, and there were many laws stating that shugo (military governors), as local administrators, should be appointed for their ability rather than for their war records, as well as many laws relating to debt-abrogation decrees.</e>
<cmt>Replacing &quot;and also&quot; with &quot;as well as&quot; makes the sentence read a bit more naturally for me. Used Japanese &quot;shugo&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the second section, the text of the 17 articles laid out the concrete policies of this code, and there were many laws stating that shugo (military governors), as local administrators, should be appointed for their ability rather than for their war records, as well as many laws relating to debt-abrogation decrees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、南北朝時代の社会的風潮であった「ばさら」を禁止している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also banned &apos;basara&apos; (extravagance), a social phenomenon of the Northern and Southern Court period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also banned &apos;basara&apos; (extravagance), a social phenomenon of the Northern and Southern Court period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also banned &apos;basara&apos; (extravagance), a social phenomenon of the Northern and Southern Court period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>本法以降に出された追加の法令は「建武以来追加」と呼ばれるが、これは建武式目の追加という意味ではなく、建武年間以降に出された御成敗式目の追加という意味だとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the additional laws made after this code are called &apos;Kenmu supplementary legislation&apos;, it is said that the name does not refer to supplements of the Kenmu Code, but rather to supplements of the Joei code that were made after the Kenmu period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the additional laws made after this code are called &apos;Kenmu supplementary legislation&apos;, it is said that the name does not refer to supplements of the Kenmu Code, but rather to supplements of the Joei Code that were made after the Kenmu period.</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &quot;code&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the additional laws made after this code are called &apos;Kenmu supplementary legislation,&apos; it is said that the name does not refer to supplements of the Kenmu Code, but rather to supplements of the Goseibai-shikimoku that were made after the Kenmu period.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置を修正Joei Code→Goseibai-shikimoku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 竹麦魚(id:11012), PPP(id:22924), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 甚平(id:167443), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>