<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>笠郎女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KASA no Iratsume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KASA no Iratsume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KASA no Iratsume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>笠郎女（かさのいらつめ）は奈良時代中期の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KASA no Iratsume (Lady Kasa) was a poet of the mid-Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KASA no Iratsume (Lady Kasa) was a poet of the mid-Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KASA no Iratsume (Lady Kasa) was a poet of the mid-Nara period.</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>生没年未詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of her birth and death are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year of her birth and death are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Year of birth and death unknown.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一説には笠金村の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that considers her to be the daughter of KASA no Kanemura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that considers her to be the daughter of KASA no Kanemura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that considers her to be the daughter of KASA no Kanemura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大伴家持とかかわりのあった十余人の女性のひとりで、同時代では大伴坂上郎女とならび称されるすぐれた女性歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was one of among more than ten lovers of OTOMO no Yakamochi, and was an poetess as excellent as her contemporary, OTOMO no Sakanoue no Iratsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was one of among more than ten lovers of OTOMO no Yakamochi, and was a poetess as excellent as her contemporary, OTOMO no Sakanoue no Iratsume.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was one of among more than 10 lovers of OTOMO no Yakamochi, and was a poetess as excellent as her contemporary, OTOMO no Sakanoue no Iratsume.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『万葉集』巻三、巻四、巻八に計29首の歌が収載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-nine of her poems appear in volumes three, four and eight of the &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twenty-nine of her poems appear in volumes three, four and eight of the &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">29 of her poems appear in volumes three, four and eight of the &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>内訳は、譬喩歌3首、相聞歌24首、春および秋の相聞各1首。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In detail, three of them were metaphorical poems, twenty-four were love poems, and there was one love poem each for spring and autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In detail, three of them were metaphorical poems, twenty-four were love poems, and there was one love poem each for spring and autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In detail, 3 of them were metaphorical poems, 24 were love poems, and there was 1 love poem each for spring and autumn.</e>
<cmt>そろえてアラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>いずれも家持に贈った歌である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were all addressed to Yakamochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were all addressed to Yakamochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were all addressed to Yakamochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>作品の周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>森鴎外らが訳詩集『於母影』（1889年）を出すにあたって、396番歌を題名の典拠としたことはよく知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is widely known that when Ogai MORI and others published the &quot;Omokage&quot; (1889), an anthology of poems in translation, they used the 396th poem of the Manyoshu as the source for its title.</e>
<cmt>原文「396番歌」は、文脈より「万葉集」での順番である（裏付け調査済み）ため、訳文では「万葉集の●番の歌」としました(以下同じ）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is widely known that when Ogai MORI and others published the &quot;Omokage&quot; (1889), an anthology of poems in translation, they used the 396th poem of the Manyoshu as the source for its title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is widely known that when Ogai MORI and others published the &quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges, 1889), an anthology of poems in translation, they used the 396th poem of the Manyoshu as the source for its title.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、594番歌を本歌取りしたものに、庭に生ふる ゆふかげ草の した露や 暮を待つ間の 涙なるらむ（藤原道経、新古今和歌集巻第十三、恋三、1190）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is an adaptation of the 594th poem of the Manyoshu: the dewdrops, under the grass in the garden which is seen in the light of the setting sun, are like the tears shed while waiting for evenings. (composed by FUJIWARA no Michitsune, Shinkokin Wakashu (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) volume 13, Love (3), 1190)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is an adaptation of the 594th poem of the Manyoshu: the dewdrops, under the grass in the garden which is seen in the light of the setting sun, are like the tears shed while waiting for evenings. (composed by FUJIWARA no Michitsune, Shinkokin Wakashu - New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry – volume 13, Love, 1190)</e>
<cmt>parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is an adaptation of the 594th poem of the Manyoshu: The dewdrops, under the grass in the garden which is seen in the light of the setting sun, are like the tears shed while waiting for evenings (composed by FUJIWARA no Michitsune, No. 1190, Love Third, Volume 13 of Shinkokin Wakashu [New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry]).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>608番歌を本歌取りしたものに、行く水に 数書くよりも はかなきは 思はぬ人を 思ふなりけり （よみ人知らず、古今和歌集恋一、522）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another poem which consciously imitated the 608th poem of the Manyoshu: love for the person who doesn&apos;t care for me is more in vain than writing numbers on flowing water. (Author unknown, Kokin wakashu (Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems), Love (1), 522)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another poem which consciously imitated the 608th poem of the Manyoshu: love for the person who doesn&apos;t care for me is more in vain than writing numbers on flowing water. (Author unknown, Kokin wakashu - Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems - Love, 522)</e>
<cmt>parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another poem which consciously imitated the 608th poem of the Manyoshu: Love for the person who doesn&apos;t care for me is more in vain than writing numbers on flowing water (Anonymous, No. 522, Love First, Kokin Wakashu [A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry]).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>