<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>福知山線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt>他と統一し、theを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>福知山線（ふくちやません）は、兵庫県尼崎市の尼崎駅 (JR西日本)から京都府福知山市の福知山駅に至る西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）の鉄道路線（幹線）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Line is a railway (trunk line) of West Japan Railway Company that connects Amagasaki Station in Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture, with Fukuchiyama Station in Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line is a railway (trunk line) of the West Japan Railway Company that connects Amagasaki Station in Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture, with Fukuchiyama Station in Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line is a (trunk) railway line operated by the West Japan Railway Company that connects Amagasaki Station in Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture, and Fukuchiyama Station in Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>レビュー結果の翻訳に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>東海道本線の大阪～尼崎間を含む大阪～篠山口間にJR宝塚線（ジェイアールたからづかせん）の愛称がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The line between Osaka Station and Sasayamaguchi Station on Tokaido Main Line, including the line between Osaka Station and Amagasaki Station, is fondly referred to as &quot;JR Takarazuka Line.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The line between Osaka Station and Sasayamaguchi Station on the Tokaido Main Line, including the section between Osaka Station and Amagasaki Station, is fondly referred to as the &quot;JR Takarazuka Line.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line that runs between Osaka Station and Sasayamaguchi Station on the Tokaido Main Line, which includes the line between Osaka Station and Amagasaki Station, is fondly referred to as the JR Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt>レビュー結果の翻訳に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>阪急電鉄にも阪急宝塚本線があるため、混同を避けるために愛称に「JR」と付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Hankyu Corporation owns the Hankyu Takarazuka Line, &quot;JR&quot; is added to the nickname so as to avoid confusion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Hankyu Corporation owns the Hankyu Takarazuka Line, &quot;JR&quot; is added to the nickname in order to avoid confusion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prefix &quot;JR&quot; is added to &quot;Takarazuka Line&quot; to prevent confusion as the Hankyu Corporation operates a line called the Hankyu Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt>レビュー結果の翻訳に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また尼崎～谷川間が大都市近郊区間に含まれ、JR宝塚線の区間はアーバンネットワークの路線の一つとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the line between Amagasaki Station and Tanikawa Station is included in the urban neighborhood, the block on the JR Takarazuka Line is one of the Urban Network lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the line between Amagasaki Station and Tanikawa Station is included within the urban neighborhood, the block on the JR Takarazuka Line is one of the Urban Network lines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the line between Amagasaki Station and Tanikawa Station runs through an urban neighborhood, the JR Takarazuka Line portion of the Fukuchiyama Line is one of JR West&apos;s Urban Network lines.</e>
<cmt>レビュー結果の翻訳に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>塚口・尼崎間で東海道本線に合流し大阪駅に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line merges into the Tokaido Main Line at a point between Tsukaguchi Station and Amagasaki Station, and reaches Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line merges into the Tokaido Main Line at a point between Tsukaguchi Station and Amagasaki Station, and then reaches Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line merges into the Tokaido Main Line at a point between Tsukaguchi Station and Amagasaki Station, and then reaches Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>JR宝塚線としての日本の鉄道ラインカラー一覧は黄色（■）であり、選定理由は「これからの新しい開発エリアを示すイキイキとしたイメージ」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The line&apos;s own color of JR Takarazuka Line is yellow, which is said to be chosen as &apos;a vivid image representing new developable areas for the future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>（■）の表記に関して、実際のサイト上では■が黄色になっておりますが、翻訳には関係ないので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color of the JR Takarazuka Line is yellow, which is said to have been chosen as &apos;a vivid image representing new developable areas for the future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color of the JR Takarazuka Line is yellow, which is said to have been chosen as &apos;a vivid image representing new developable areas for the future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>大阪と北近畿を結ぶ路線であると同時に、兵庫県東部の各都市から大阪への通勤・通学路線となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line is not only a line that connects Osaka with northern Kinki but is a commuter line for office workers and students who commute from each city in eastern Hyogo to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>この「大阪」は、「府」とも「市」とも判断できない表記なので、「Osaka」と致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line isn&apos;t simply a line that connects Osaka with northern Kinki but is also a commuter line for office workers and students who commute from the cities of eastern Hyogo to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line isn&apos;t simply a line that connects Osaka with northern Kinki but is also a commuter line for office workers and students who commute from the cities of eastern Hyogo to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、大阪と山陰地方を結ぶルートの一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also one of the lines connecting Osaka and the Sanin region.</e>
<cmt>この「大阪」は、「府」とも「市」とも判断できない表記なので、「Osaka」と致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also one of the lines connecting Osaka and the Sanin region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also one of the lines connecting Osaka and the Sanin region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>尼崎～篠山口間のJR宝塚線各駅ではJスルー・ICOCA、及び東日本旅客鉄道（JR東日本）のSuica、東海旅客鉄道（JR東海）のTOICA、またスルッとKANSAIのPiTaPaが使用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">J-Through Card and ICOCA, Suica issued by East Japan Railway Company, TOICA issued by Central Japan Railway Company, and PiTaPa issued by Surutto KANSAI Association are available at each station on the JR Takarazuka Line between Amagasaki and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>スルッとKANSAI→KANSAI THRU PASS[http://www.surutto.com/conts/ticket/3dayeng/index.html]を使用するようにとの指示ですが、「KANSAI THRU PASS」は「スルッとKANSAI 協議会」が発行するパスの総称で、この場合の「スルッとKANSAIのPiTaPa」とは、「スルッとKANSAI 協議会が発行するPiTaPa」という意味ですので、「Surutto KANSAI Association」を採用いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">J-Through Card and ICOCA, Suica, issued by the East Japan Railway Company, TOICA issued by the Central Japan Railway Company, and Itapúa issued by the Surutto KANSAI Association are available at each station on the JR Takarazuka Line between Amagasaki and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">J-Through Card and ICOCA, Suica, issued by the East Japan Railway Company, TOICA issued by the Central Japan Railway Company, and PiTaPa issued by the Surutto KANSAI Association can be used at each station on the JR Takarazuka Line between Amagasaki and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>文字化け単語をPiTaPaに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>路線データ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway data</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway data</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway data</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>管轄（事業種別）：西日本旅客鉄道（鉄道事業者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jurisdiction (industrial classification): West Japan Railway Company (railway company)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jurisdiction (industrial classification): West Japan Railway Company (railway company)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jurisdiction (industrial classification): West Japan Railway Company (railway company)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>路線距離（営業キロ）：106.5km</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway distance (operation kilometers): 106.5km</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway distance (operation kilometers): 106.5km</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway distance (operation kilometers): 106.5 km</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>軌間：1067mm</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Track gauge: 1067mm</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Track gauge: 1067mm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Track gauge: 1067 mm</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>駅数：30駅（起終点駅含む。JR宝塚線としては23駅）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number of stations: 30 stations (including the starting station and the final station, 23 stations on JR Takarazuka Line alone)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Number of stations: Thirty (including the starting station and the final station, 23 stations on the JR Takarazuka Line alone)</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Number of stations: Thirty (including the stations of origin and terminus; 23 stations on the JR Takarazuka Line alone)</e>
<cmt>起終点→stations of origin and terminusとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>複線区間：尼崎～篠山口間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Double-tracked section: between Amagasaki Station and Sasayamaguchi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Double-track section: Between Amagasaki Station and Sasayamaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Double-track section: Between Amagasaki Station and Sasayamaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>電化区間：全線電化（直流1500V）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Electrified section: the whole line (DC1500V)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Electrified section: Entire line (DC1500V)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Electrified section: Entire line (DC1500V)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>閉塞 (鉄道)：自動閉塞式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Block (railway) system: automatic block system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Block (railway) system: Automatic block system</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Block (railway) system: Automatic block system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>保安装置：尼崎～新三田間自動列車停止装置P形（パターン形）（自動列車停止装置拠点P）/ATS-SW併設、新三田～福知山間自動列車停止装置改良形ATS（Sx形）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Control and protection system: Automatic Train Stop system (ATS) P-type (Pattern-type) (=ATS-P) and ATS-SW between Amagasaki Station and Shinsanda Station, improved ATS (ATS-Sx) between Shinsanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Control and protection system: Automatic Train Stop system (ATS) P-type (pattern-type) (=ATS-P) and ATS-SW between Amagasaki Station and Shinsanda Station, improved ATS (ATS-Sx) between Shinsanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Control and protection system: Automatic Train Stop system (ATS) P-type (pattern-type) (=ATS-P) and ATS-SW between Amagasaki Station and Shin-Sanda Station, improved ATS (ATS-Sx) between Shin-Sanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>最高速度：110km/h</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maximum speed: 110km/h</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maximum speed: 110km/h</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maximum speed: 110 km/h</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>運転指令所：</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Train control center:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train control centers:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train control centers:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>尼崎～新三田：新大阪総合指令所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Amagasaki Station and Shinsanda Station: Shin-Osaka Sogo Control Center</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Amagasaki Station and Shinsanda Station: Shin-Osaka Sogo Control Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Amagasaki Station and Shin-Sanda Station: Shin-Osaka General Control Center</e>
<cmt>総合指令所→general control center としました（仮訳）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="21">
<j>新三田～福知山：福知山運輸指令所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Shinsanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station: Fukuchiyama Unyu Control Center</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Shinsanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station: Fukuchiyama Unyu Control Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Shin-Sanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station: Fukuchiyama Transport Control Center</e>
<cmt>運輸指令所→Transport Control Center　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="22">
<j>※尼崎～新三田間は西日本旅客鉄道大阪支社の直轄、新三田～福知山間は両端の駅を除き同・西日本旅客鉄道福知山支社篠山口鉄道部の管轄である（福知山駅は福知山支社直轄）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* The section between Amagasaki Station and Shinsanda Station is under the direct control of West Japan Railway Company, Osaka Branch Office while that between Shinsanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station, except stations at both ends of this interval, is under the control of West Japan Railway Company, Fukuchiyama Branch Office, Sasayamaguchi Railways Department (Fukuchiyama Station is under the direct control of the Fukuchiyama Branch Office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* The section between Amagasaki Station and Shin-Sanda Station is under the direct control of the West Japan Railway Company&apos;s Osaka Branch Office, while that between Shin-Sanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station (except for the stations at both ends of this interval) is under the control of West Japan Railway Company&apos;s Fukuchiyama Branch Office, Sasayamaguchi Railways Department (Fukuchiyama Station is under the direct control of the Fukuchiyama Branch Office).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* The section between Amagasaki Station and Shin-Sanda Station is under the direct control of the West Japan Railway Company&apos;s Osaka Branch Office, while that between Shin-Sanda Station and Fukuchiyama Station (except for the stations at both ends of this interval) is under the control of West Japan Railway Company&apos;s Fukuchiyama Branch Office, Sasayamaguchi Railways Department (Fukuchiyama Station is under the direct control of the Fukuchiyama Branch Office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿線風景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Landscape along the railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Landscape along the railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Landscape along the railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>1986年まで客車普通列車が走っていたり、生瀬～道場付近では武庫川の渓流の眺めを楽しめたりするなど、のどかなローカル路線の体であったが、同年の宝塚～新三田間の複線電化を機にそれらは姿を消し、沿線住宅開発の進展とJR東西線の開業などにより新型電車が行き交う通勤路線となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to 1986, the Fukuchiyama Line was a tranquil local line where passenger local trains were running and scenery of a Muko-gawa River stream was enjoyed near Namaze and Dojo; however, these scenes disappeared as the line between Takarazuka Station and Shinsanda Station was double-tracked and electrified in 1986, and it was transformed into a commuter line on which new type of trains run with the promotion of housing development along the line and the establishment of the JR Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to 1986, the Fukuchiyama Line was a tranquil local line where passenger local trains ran and the scenery of a Muko-gawa River stream was enjoyed near Namaze and Dojo; however, these scenes disappeared as the line between Takarazuka Station and Shin-Sanda Station was double-tracked and electrified in 1986, and it was transformed into a commuter line on which new types of trains run, housing development is promoted along the line and the JR Tozai Line has been established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to 1986, the Fukuchiyama Line was a tranquil local line where passenger local trains ran and the scenery of a Muko-gawa River stream was enjoyed near Namaze and Dojo; however, these scenes disappeared as the line between Takarazuka Station and Shin-Sanda Station was double-tracked and electrified in 1986, and it was transformed into a commuter line on which new types of trains run, housing development is promoted along the line and the JR Tozai Line has been established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>宝塚以北の武庫川渓流沿いの旧線は廃線となったが（一部は遊歩道となっている）、それでもこの線は川との関係が深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the old railway to the north of Takarazuka along Muko-gawa River was discontinued (a part of the line is now used as a walking trail), the Fukuchiyama Line and Muko-gawa River still have close ties with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the old railway to the north of Takarazuka along the Muko-gawa River was discontinued (a part of the line is now used as a walking trail), the Fukuchiyama Line and Muko-gawa River still have close mutual ties.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the old railway to the north of Takarazuka along the Muko-gawa River was discontinued (a part of the line is now used as a walking trail), the Fukuchiyama Line and Muko-gawa River still have close mutual ties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>宝塚駅から古市駅までは武庫川と何度も交差しながら遡り、篠山口駅から谷川駅は加古川支流の篠山川の渓流沿いに下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The railway lies upward along and crosses Muko-gawa River at many locations between Takarazuka Station and Furuichi Station, and stretches downward along Sasayama-gawa River which is a stream of Kako-gawa River between Sasayamaguchi Station and Tanigawa Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railway lies upward along and crosses THE Muko-gawa River at many points between Takarazuka Station and Furuichi Station, and it stretches downward along the Sasayama-gawa River, which is a stream of Kako-gawa River between Sasayamaguchi Station and Tanigawa Station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The railway lies upward along and crosses the Muko-gawa River at many points between Takarazuka Station and Furuichi Station, and it stretches downward along the Sasayama-gawa River, which is a stream of Kako-gawa River between Sasayamaguchi Station and Tanikawa Station.</e>
<cmt>THE →the　としました。Tanikawa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>福知山線の最大の特徴はトンネル無しに分水界を越えること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The greatest characteristic of the Fukuchiyama Line is that it crosses the watershed with no tunnels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The greatest characteristic of the Fukuchiyama Line is that it crosses the watershed with no tunnels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The greatest characteristic of the Fukuchiyama Line is that it crosses the watershed with no tunnels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>石生駅周辺は太平洋と日本海を分ける分水嶺の高度が本州で最も低い所（この辺りでは分水田圃）であり、田圃の中を走っているうちにいつの間にか日本海へ注ぐ由良川沿いの福知山駅に到着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area around Iso Station has the lowest point of watershed in Honshu (rice fields around this area are watershed rice fields) and the railway reaches Fukuchiyama Station on Yura-gawa River that flows into the Sea of Japan, without even noticing while a train is running in the scenery of rice fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area around Iso Station has the lowest point of watershed in Honshu (the fields around this area are watershed rice fields) and the railway reaches Fukuchiyama Station on the Yura-gawa River, which flows into the Sea of Japan, seemingly oblivious to the fact that a train is running amid the scenery of rice fields.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area around Iso Station has the lowest point of watershed in Honshu which devides Pacific Ocean and the Sea of Japan (the fields around this area are watershed rice fields) and the railway reaches Fukuchiyama Station on the Yura-gawa River, which flows into the Sea of Japan, seemingly oblivious to the fact that a train is running amid the scenery of rice fields.</e>
<cmt>太平洋と日本海を分ける　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>福知山駅の手前では、再建された福知山城天守閣が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tower of Fukuchiyama-jo Castle, which has been reconstructed, can be seen from a train window before Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tower of Fukuchiyama-jo Castle, which has been reconstructed, can be seen from a train window before reaching Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tower of Fukuchiyama-jo Castle, which has been reconstructed, can be seen from a train window before reaching Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>川西池田駅から西宮名塩駅間、三田駅から丹波大山駅間、柏原駅から福知山駅間は国道176号とほぼ並行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sections between Kawanishiikeda Station and Nishinomiyanajio Station, between Sanda Station and Tamba-Oyama Station, and between Kaibara Station and Fukuchiyama Station are running nearly in parallel with the National Highway 176.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sections between Kawanishiikeda Station and Nishinomiyanajio Station, between Sanda Station and Tamba-Oyama Station, and between Kaibara Station and Fukuchiyama Station run nearly parallel to National Highway 176.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sections between Kawanishiikeda Station and Nishinomiyanajio Station, between Sanda Station and Tamba-Oyama Station, and between Kaibara Station and Fukuchiyama Station run nearly parallel to National Route 176.</e>
<cmt>National Hightway→ National Routeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>運行形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of Operations</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of Operations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>福知山線は尼崎駅が起点だが、すべての列車が尼崎駅を介して大阪駅（一部はさらにその先のJR京都線）に、もしくはJR東西線を経由し片町線に乗り入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The starting point of the Fukuchiyama Line is Amagasaki Station, but all trains get to Osaka Station (some of them even go up to the JR Kyoto Line beyond Osaka Station) via Amagasaki Station or go into the Katamachi Line through the JR Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The starting point of the Fukuchiyama Line is Amagasaki Station, but all trains reach Osaka Station (some of them even go up to the JR Kyoto Line beyond Osaka Station) via Amagasaki Station or go into the Katamachi Line via the JR Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Fukuchiyama Line starts at Amagasaki Station, all trains reach Osaka Station (some of them even go up to the JR Kyoto Line beyond Osaka Station) via Amagasaki Station or go into the Katamachi Line via the JR Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>起点だが→ Although Fukuchiyama Line starts at Amagasaki Station としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>福知山駅からは特急列車が山陰本線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道に直通している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Limited Express trains directly run into the track of Kitakinki Tango Railway on the Sanin Main Line from Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some limited express trains run directly into the track of Kitakinki Tango Railway on the Sanin Main Line from Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some limited express trains run directly into the track of Sanin Main Line or Kitakinki Tango Railway from Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>山陰本線または北近畿タンゴ鉄道　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>優等列車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higher category trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higher-Category Trains</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higher-category trains</e>
<cmt>小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>北近畿ビッグXネットワークの一角（「X」の左斜め下の部分が福知山線）としての機能があり、以下の列車が福知山線全線を通して運転され、さらに北近畿タンゴ鉄道・宮津駅方面、山陰本線・豊岡駅 (兵庫県)・城崎温泉駅（下り）方面まで運転されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The higher category trains function as a part of the North Kinki Big X Network (the left oblique downward part of X represents the Fukuchiyama Line) and the following trains run not only throughout the Fukuchiyama Line but for Miyazu Station on the Kitakinki Tango Railway and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture) or Kinosakionsen Station (down line) on the Sanin Main.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The higher category trains function as part of the North Kinki Big X Network (the left oblique downward part of &quot;X&quot; represents the Fukuchiyama Line), and the following trains run not only throughout the Fukuchiyama Line but also for Miyazu Station on the Kitakinki Tango Railway and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture) or Kinosakionsen Station (down line) on the Sanin Main Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line functions as part of the North Kinki Big X Network (the left oblique downward part of &quot;X&quot; represents the Fukuchiyama Line), and the following higher category trains run not only throughout the Fukuchiyama Line but also for Miyazu Station on the Kitakinki Tango Railway and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture) or Kinosakionsen Station (outbound line) on the Sanin Main Line.</e>
<cmt>下り→outbound としました。北近畿ビッグXネットワークを担うのは優等列車ではなく福知山線と解釈し、左記のように文頭を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>2004年10月16日に急行「だいせん (列車)」が廃止されてからは、夜行列車の運転は無くなり、昼行列車のみの運転となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Express train &quot;Daisen&quot; was discontinued on October 16, 2004, no night trains have been running and only day trains have been running.</e>
<cmt>「だいせん (列車)」の「列車」の部分は、特に訳に反映いたしませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Express train &quot;Daisen&quot; was discontinued on October 16, 2004, no night trains have run so only day trains have been operated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the express train &apos;Daisen&apos; was discontinued on October 16, 2004, no night trains have run so only day trains have been operated.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Express → express と小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>エル特急「北近畿 (列車)」（新大阪－福知山・豊岡・城崎温泉：10.5往復）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">L Express train &quot;Kitakinki&quot; (Between Shin-Osaka and Fukuchiyama, Toyooka, Kinosakionsen: 10.5 round trips)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The limited express train &quot;Kitakinki&quot; (Between Shin-Osaka and Fukuchiyama, Toyooka, Kinosakionsen: 10.5 round trips)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The L-limited Express &apos;Kita-Kinki (train)&apos; (between Shin-Osaka and Fukuchiyama, Toyooka, Kinosakionsen: 10.5 round trips)</e>
<cmt>→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>特急「文殊 (列車)」（新大阪－天橋立：1往復）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited Express train &quot;Monju&quot; (Between Shin-Osaka and Amanohashidate: 1round trip)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The limited express train &quot;Monju&quot; (between Shin-Osaka and Amanohashidate: one round trip)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Limited Express &apos;Monju&apos; (between Shin-Osaka and Amanohashidate: one round trip)</e>
<cmt>→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>特急「タンゴエクスプローラー」（新大阪－宮津・豊岡：2往復）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited Express &quot;Tango Explorer&quot; (Between Shin-Osaka and Miyazu, Toyooka: 2 round trips)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The limited express &quot;Tango Explorer&quot; (between Shin-Osaka and Miyazu, Toyooka: two round trips)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Limited Express &apos;Tango Explorer&apos; (between Shin-Osaka and Miyazu, Toyooka: two round trips)</e>
<cmt>→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>普通列車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>全線直通運転を行う普通列車（快速列車を含む）は、朝と夕方以降に限定されており、昼間時間帯は尼崎～篠山口間、篠山口～福知山間で運行系統が分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local trains (including Rapid trains) that run the whole line without a transfer are available only in the early hours of the morning or in the evening, and the routes which those trains that run during midday hours take are separated depending on where the train run on the line between Amagasaki and Sasayamaguchi or between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">local trains (including rapid trains) that run the entire line without a transfer are available only in the early hours of the morning or in the evening, and the routes those trains that run during the midday hours are separated according to where the train runs on the line between Amagasaki and Sasayamaguchi or between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local trains (including rapid trains) that run the entire line without a transfer are available only in the early hours of the morning or in the evening, and the routes for those trains that run during the midday hours are separated according to where the train runs on the line between Amagasaki and Sasayamaguchi or between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>routes for those trains としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>快速列車は大阪またはJR東西線方面から篠山口・福知山方面まで運転されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid trains run from Osaka or the direction of the JR Tozai Line to the direction of Sasayamaguchi or Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid trains run from Osaka or the direction of the JR Tozai Line in the direction of Sasayamaguchi or Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid trains run from Osaka or the direction of the JR Tozai Line to the direction of Sasayamaguchi or Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>in →　to　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>昼間時の大阪～篠山口間には「快速（大阪発着）、丹波路快速」が運転されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During midday hours, some Rapid trains (starting from and terminating at Osaka Station) and Tambaji Rapid Services are available on the section between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the midday hours, some rapid trains (starting from and terminating at Osaka Station) and Tambaji rapid services are available on the section between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the midday hours, rapid trains (starting from and terminating at Osaka Station) called &apos;Tambaji Rapid Service&apos; are available on the section between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>大阪発着の快速が「丹波路快速」と呼ばれているようですので、ここも「「丹波路快速」という名前の大阪発着の快速」　という表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>昼間時には、各駅停車がJR神戸・京都線直通、「快速」がJR東西線方面直通の快速列車、および「丹波路快速」が大阪発着の快速列車として区別されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trains available during midday hours are distinguished as follows: Local trains are trains that run directly to the JR Kobe Line and JR Kyoto Line, &quot;Rapid&quot; represents a Rapid train that directly runs to the direction of the JR Tozai Line, and &quot;Tambaji Rapid Service&quot; represents a Rapid train that starts from and terminates at Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trains available during the midday hours are distinguished as follows: local trains run directly to the JR Kobe Line and JR Kyoto Line, &quot;rapid&quot; represents a rapid train that directly runs in the direction of the JR Tozai Line, and &quot;Tambaji Rapid Service&quot; represents a rapid train that starts from and terminates at Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trains available during the midday hours are distinguished as follows: local trains run directly to the JR Kobe Line and JR Kyoto Line, &apos;rapid&apos; represents a rapid train that directly runs in the direction of the JR Tozai Line, and &apos;Tambaji Rapid Service&apos; represents a rapid train that starts from and terminates at Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>JR東西線直通の快速列車と大阪発着の快速列車とでは性格が違ってくるためここでは分けて述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid trains that directly runs to the direction of the JR Tozai Line and those that start from and terminate at Osaka Station will hereinafter be explained separately because of their different characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid trains that run directly toward the JR Tozai Line and those that start from and terminate at Osaka Station will hereinafter be explained separately due to their different characteristics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid trains that run directly toward the JR Tozai Line and those that start from and terminate at Osaka Station will hereinafter be explained separately due to their different characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>快速（JR東西線直通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid (directly to the JR Tozai Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid (directly to the JR Tozai Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid (directly to the JR Tozai Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>JR東西線・片町線と直通する快速列車は終日ほぼ15分間隔で運転される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid trains that go directly to the JR Tozai Line or the Katamachi Line are operated with approximately 15-minute intervals all day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid trains that go directly to the JR Tozai Line or the Katamachi Line are operated with approximately 15-minute intervals all day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid trains that go directly to the JR Tozai Line or the Katamachi Line are operated with approximately 15-minute intervals all day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>昼間時間帯は宝塚駅までの運転、ラッシュ時には新三田（一部列車は篠山口）までの運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those trains are in service up to Takarazuka Station during the daytime and up to Shinsanda Station (some of them are up to Sasayamaguchi Station) during the rush hour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those trains are in service up to Takarazuka Station during the daytime and up to Shinsanda Station (some of them are up to Sasayamaguchi Station) during the rush hour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those trains are in service up to Takarazuka Station during the daytime and up to Shin-Sanda Station (some of them are up to Sasayamaguchi Station) during the rush hour.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>全列車がJR西日本207系電車電車で運転され篠山口まで7両編成で運転される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All cars of the Rapid trains use JR (West) Commuter Trains Series 207 and each train has 7 cars up to Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All cars of the rapid trains use JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207, and each train has seven cars up to Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All cars of the rapid trains use JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207, and each train has seven cars up to Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>尼崎駅ではJR神戸線の快速列車と相互接続を行う（時間帯によっては新快速・普通列車とも接続をする場合もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Amagasaki Station, the Rapid train makes a mutual connection with another Rapid train that runs on the JR Kobe Line (Some Rapid trains may make a mutual connection with a Special Rapid or Local train depending on the time zone).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Amagasaki Station, the rapid train makes a mutual connection with another rapid train that runs on the JR Kobe Line (some rapid trains may make a mutual connection with a special rapid or a local train, depending on the time zone).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Amagasaki Station, the rapid train makes a mutual connection with another rapid train that runs on the JR Kobe Line (some rapid trains may make a mutual connection with a special rapid or a local train, depending on the time zone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>早朝・深夜にはJR東西線・学研都市線で区間快速（一部は普通）に種別が変わる列車がある（この場合下りは京橋で、上りは尼崎で、列車番号が変わる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some Rapid trains whose type changes to Regional Rapid (or Local) on the JR Tozai Line and the Gakkentoshi Line early in the morning and late at night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some rapid trains whose type changes to regional rapid (or local) on the JR Tozai Line and the Gakkentoshi Line early in the morning and late at night.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some rapid trains whose type changes to regional rapid (or local) on the JR Tozai Line and the Gakkentoshi Line early in the morning and late at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>この列車は駅の時刻表では区間快速として案内される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type of train is referred to as a Regional Rapid train on the timetable at a station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This type of train is referred to as a regional rapid train on the timetable at a station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This type of train is referred to as a regional rapid train on the timetable at a station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>快速（大阪発着）、丹波路快速</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid (starting from and terminating at Osaka Station), Tambaji Rapid Service</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid (starting from and terminating at Osaka Station), Tambaji Rapid Service</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid trains (starting from and terminating at Osaka Station) called Tambaji Rapid Service</e>
<cmt>大阪発着の快速が「丹波路快速」と呼ばれているようですので、ここも「「丹波路快速」という名前の大阪発着の快速」　という表現にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>大阪発着の快速列車の本数は区間・時間帯によって異なり、ラッシュ時には本数が増える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Rapid trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station varies from section to section and time zone to time zone, and it increases in the rush hour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of rapid trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station varies from section to section and from time zone to time zone, but it increases during the rush hour.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of rapid trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station varies from section to section and from time zone to time zone, but it increases during the rush hour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>なお特急列車が設定されるサイクルには大阪始発の快速の設定はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station are not set in cycles in which Limited Express trains are supposed to be set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station aren&apos;t set in cycles in which limited express trains are supposed to be set.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station aren&apos;t set in cycles in which limited express trains are supposed to be set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>「丹波路快速」は昼間時にJR西日本221系電車電車によって大阪～篠山口間で運転される快速列車の愛称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tambaji Rapid Service&quot; is a nickname for Rapid trains that use the JR (West) Suburban Trains Series 221 and are operated between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi during the daytime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tambaji Rapid Service&quot; is a nickname for rapid trains that use the JR (West) Suburban Train Series 221 and are operated between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi during the daytime.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tambaji Rapid Service&apos; is a nickname for rapid trains that use the JR (West) Suburban Train Series 221 and are operated between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi during the daytime.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>快速に221系電車が増投入された2000年3月のダイヤ改正で登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The service first started when the timetable was revised in March 2000 as Series 221 trains were added to the Rapid services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The service first started when the timetable was revised in March 2000, as Series 221 trains were added to the rapid services.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The service first started when the timetable was revised in March 2000, as Series 221 trains were added to the rapid services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>昼間からラッシュ時を除く夕方までの閑散時に毎時2本運転される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two services are available every hour in the off-hour from the daytime through the evening except the rush hour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two services are available every hour in the off-hours from the daytime through the evening, except for the rush-hour period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two services are available every hour in the off-hours from the daytime through the evening, except for the rush-hour period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>停車駅は他の快速と同一である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rapid train stops at the same stations at which other Rapid trains stop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rapid train stops at the same stations at which other rapid trains stop.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rapid train stops at the same stations at which other rapid trains stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>丹波路快速の多くは4両編成であるが一部6両以上で運転されるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the trains operated in the Tambaji Rapid Service have four cars; however, there are some trains that have 6 or more cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the trains operated as part of the Tambaji Rapid Service have four cars; however, some trains have six or more cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the trains operated as part of the Tambaji Rapid Service have four cars; however, some trains have six or more cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>昼間の毎時1本は篠山口で福知山行きに相互接続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the two services in each hour makes a mutual connection at Sasayamaguchi Station with a train that goes to Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the two services in each hour makes a mutual connection at Sasayamaguchi Station with a train that goes to Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the two services in each hour makes a mutual connection at Sasayamaguchi Station with a train that goes to Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>「丹波路快速」運行時間帯の他の「快速」は全て東西線直通となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any Rapid trains other than trains in the &quot;Tambaji Rapid Service&quot; are direct trains to the JR Tozai Line during the operational hour of the Tambaji Rapid Service.</e>
<cmt>ここでいう「東西線」とは「JR東西線」のことと判断しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any rapid train other than a train in the Tambaji Rapid Service is a direct train to the JR Tozai Line during the operating hours of the Tambaji Rapid Service.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any rapid train other than Tambaji Rapid Service is a direct train to the JR Tozai Line during the operating hours of the Tambaji Rapid Service.</e>
<cmt>a train in the を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>朝・夕方以降の快速列車は運転区間を問わずすべて「快速」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any Rapid trains operated in the early morning and the evening are categorized as &quot;Rapid&quot; regardless of the operation section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any rapid train that&apos;s operated in the early morning and the evening is categorized as &quot;rapid,&quot; regardless of the operation section.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any rapid train that&apos;s operated in the early morning and the evening is categorized as &apos;rapid,&apos; regardless of the operation section.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>大阪発着の「快速」にも221系電車が中心的に使われるが、ラッシュ時には国鉄113系電車電車とJR西日本207系電車電車も使われ、篠山口以北に乗り入れる普通・快速には113系と221系が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Train Series 221 is also mainly used for Rapid trains that start from and terminate at Osaka Station; however, the JNR/JR Suburban Trains Series 113 and the JR (West) Commuter Trains Series 207 are often used during the rush hour, and the Train Series 113 and 221 are used for both Local and Rapid trains that go above Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Train Series 221 is also mainly used for rapid trains that start from and terminate at Osaka Station; however, the JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 113 and the JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207 are often used during the rush hour, while the Train Series 113 and Series 221 are used for both local and rapid trains that go above Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Train Series 221 is also mainly used for rapid trains that start from and terminate at Osaka Station; however, the JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 113 and the JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207 are often used during the rush hour, while the Train Series 113 and Series 221 are used for both local and rapid trains that go above Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>2005年までは快速列車に国鉄117系電車電車も使われていたが、ATS-Pが搭載されていないために当線から撤退し、下関地区や嵯峨野線、湖西線へ転出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to 2005, the JNR/JR Suburban Trains Series 117 was used for the Rapid trains, but those trains were withdrawn from the Fukuchiyama Line because they were not equipped with an ATS-P system and then moved to the Shimonoseki Region, the Sagano Line and the Kosei Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to 2005, the JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 117 was used for the rapid trains, but those trains were withdrawn from the Fukuchiyama Line because they weren&apos;t equipped with an ATS-P system and were then moved to the Shimonoseki Region, the Sagano Line and the Kosei Line.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to 2005, the JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 117 was used for the rapid trains, but those trains were withdrawn from the Fukuchiyama Line because they weren&apos;t equipped with an ATS-P system and were then moved to the Shimonoseki Region, the Sagano Line and the Kosei Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>なお篠山口以北はホーム有効長が6両のため、8両編成で運転される場合は篠山口で増解結して以北は4両編成となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the effective length of platforms of the stations above Sasayamaguchi Station is for up to 6 cars, four cars are disconnected from a Rapid train that is operated with 8 cars at Sasayamaguchi Station and the rest of the four cars are operated after Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the effective length of platforms of the stations above Sasayamaguchi Station is for up to six cars, four cars are disconnected from a rapid train that&apos;s operated with eight cars at Sasayamaguchi Station, and the rest of the four cars are operated after Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the effective length of platforms of the stations above Sasayamaguchi Station is for up to six cars, four cars are disconnected from a rapid train that&apos;s operated with eight cars at Sasayamaguchi Station, and the rest of the four cars are operated after Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>福知山発着の快速列車は途中駅で特急列車に追い抜かれることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the Rapid trains that start from and terminate at Fukuchiyama Station may allow some Limited Express trains to pass at way stations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the rapid trains that start from and terminate at Fukuchiyama Station may allow some limited express trains to pass at way stations.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the rapid trains that start from and terminate at Fukuchiyama Station may allow some limited express trains to pass at way stations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="62">
<j>快速列車は日本国有鉄道時代は1日に数本程度運転されるだけであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Japan National Railways (JNR) was privatized as the JR Group, only a few Rapid trains had been operated a day.</e>
<cmt>「日本国有鉄道がJRグループに民営化される前は」というニュアンスで訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Japan National Railways (JNR) was privatized as the JR Group, only a few rapid trains had been operated each day.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Japan National Railways (JNR) was privatized as the JR Group, only a few rapid trains had been operated each day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>国鉄末期の1983年頃のダイヤでは、大阪～篠山口間に尼崎・伊丹・宝塚・武田尾・三田・広野・相野・古市を停車駅とする快速列車が1日2往復のみ設定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the timetable of 1983 in the last years of JNR, only two round-trip Rapid trains which stopped at Amagasaki, Itami, Takarazuka, Takedao, Sanda, Hirono, Aino and Furuichi were operated a day between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the timetable of 1983 in the last years of JNR, only two round-trip rapid trains that stopped at Amagasaki, Itami, Takarazuka, Takedao, Sanda, Hirono, Aino and Furuichi were operated each day between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the timetable of 1983 in the last years of JNR, only two round-trip rapid trains that stopped at Amagasaki, Itami, Takarazuka, Takedao, Sanda, Hirono, Aino and Furuichi were operated each day between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>快速列車が多数運転されるようになったのは1989年3月からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not so many Rapid trains were operated until March 1989.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fewer rapid trains were operated prior to March 1989.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fewer rapid trains were operated prior to March 1989.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>1997年3月から広野・藍本・草野・古市・南矢代駅を通過する列車も夕方以降の下りに設定されていたが、2003年12月のダイヤ改正で廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1997, some Rapid trains that passed Hirono Station, Aimoto Station, Kusano Station, Furuichi Station and Minami-Yashiro Station without stopping were introduced for the downline in the evening, but they were discontinued when the timetable was revised on December 2003.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1997, some rapid trains that passed Hirono Station, Aimoto Station, Kusano Station, Furuichi Station and Minami-Yashiro Station without stopping were introduced for the downline in the evening, but they were discontinued in December 2003, when the timetable was revised.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1997, some rapid trains that passed Hirono Station, Aimoto Station, Kusano Station, Furuichi Station and Minami-Yashiro Station without stopping were introduced for the outbound line in the evening, but they were discontinued in December 2003, when the timetable was revised.</e>
<cmt>下り→outbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この快速列車には207系電車が使用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Trains Series 207 was used for these Rapid trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Train Series 207 was used for these rapid trains.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Train Series 207 was used for these rapid trains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>なお、臨時列車では新三田以北にも通過駅のある列車がしばしば設定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some trains which also pass some stations above Shinsanda without stopping are often operated as a special train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some trains that also pass some stations above Shinsanda without stopping are often operated as special trains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some trains that also pass some stations above Shin-Sanda without stopping are often operated as special trains.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>普通列車（各駅停車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local train (stopping at every station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">local train (stopping at all stations)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">local train (stopping at all stations)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>JR京都線と直通し京都・高槻～大阪～新三田間に運転される列車が中心である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Majority of the Local trains are directly connected to the JR Kyoto Line and operated in the section between Kyoto/Takatsuki and Shinsanda via Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the local trains are directly connected to the JR Kyoto Line and operated in the section between Kyoto/Takatsuki and Shinsanda via Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the local trains are directly connected to the JR Kyoto Line and operated in the section between Kyoto/Takatsuki and Shin-Sanda via Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>早朝・朝ラッシュ時、深夜などには大阪～福知山間の列車やJR東西線直通列車（新三田～北新地～四条畷・松井山手・京田辺・木津間）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early morning, during the morning rush hour, and late at night, some Local trains that connect Osaka and Fukuchiyama and are operated directly to and from the JR Tozai Line (Shinsanda - Kitashinchi - Shijonawate/Matsuiyamate/Kyotanabe/Kizu) are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early morning, during the morning rush hour and late at night, some local trains that connect Osaka and Fukuchiyama and are operated directly to and from the JR Tozai Line (Shinsanda - Kitashinchi - Shijonawate/Matsuiyamate/Kyotanabe/Kizu) are available.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early morning, during the morning rush hour and late at night, some local trains that connect Osaka and Fukuchiyama and are operated directly to and from the JR Tozai Line (Shin-Sanda - Kitashinchi - Shijonawate/Matsuiyamate/Kyotanabe/Kizu) are available.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>平日朝ラッシュ時には野洲発、草津発及び草津行きの普通列車も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also some Local trains that start from Yasu Station or Kusatsu Station and go to Kusatsu Station during the morning rush hour on weekdays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, some local trains start from Yasu Station or Kusatsu Station and go to Kusatsu Station during the weekday morning rush hour.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there are some local trains that start from Yasu Station or Kusatsu Station, and also those that go to Kusatsu Station during the morning rush hour on weekdays.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>新三田以南の各駅停車は207系、321系電車7両編成で運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local trains operated below Shinsanda are 7-car trains of Trains Series 207 or 321.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local trains operated below Shinsanda are seven-car trains of either Series 207 or Series 321.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local trains operated below Shin-Sanda are seven-car trains of either Series 207 or Series 321.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>大阪駅でJR京都線・JR神戸線の新快速に、尼崎でJR東西線～JR神戸線直通の普通列車（松井山手～西明石）と相互接続をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local train makes a mutual connection with a Special train that is operated on the JR Kyoto or Kobe Line at Osaka Station and with another Local train (Matsuiyamate - Nishiakashi) that directly goes to the JR Kobe Line through the JR Tozai Line at Amagasaki Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local train makes a mutual connection with a special train that&apos;s operated on the JR Kyoto or Kobe Line at Osaka Station, and with another local train (Matsuiyamate - Nishiakashi) that directly goes to the JR Kobe Line via the JR Tozai Line at Amagasaki Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local train makes a mutual connection with a special rapid that&apos;s operated on the JR Kyoto or Kobe Line at Osaka Station, and with another local train (Matsuiyamate - Nishi-Akashi) that directly goes to the JR Kobe Line via the JR Tozai Line at Amagasaki Station.</e>
<cmt>新快速→special rapidとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また、川西池田駅ではJR東西線直通・大阪発着の快速列車（または特急の通過待ち）と緩急接続を行う（朝ラッシュ時には塚口駅で快速の通過待ちする列車もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, at Kawanishiikeda Station, the Local train makes a &quot;Kankyu Setsuzoku&quot; (slower- and faster-train connection) with a Rapid train (or a Local train that waits for a Limited Express train to pass) that starts from and terminates at Osaka Station and is operated directly to and from the JR Tozai Line (There are some Local trains that wait for a Rapid train to pass at Tsukaguchi Station in the morning rush hour).</e>
<cmt>「（または特急の通過待ち）」の通過待ちをする列車は、「普通列車」であると解釈して訳出してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, at Kawanishiikeda Station the local train makes a &quot;Kankyu Setsuzoku&quot; (slower and faster train connection) with a rapid train (or a local train that waits for a limited express train to pass) that starts from and terminates at Osaka Station and is operated directly to and from the JR Tozai Line (some local trains wait for a rapid train to pass at Tsukaguchi Station in the morning rush hour).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, at Kawanishiikeda Station the local train makes a connection with a rapid train that starts from and terminates at Osaka Station and is operated directly to and from the JR Tozai Line (or it waits for a limited express train to pass) (some local trains wait for a rapid train to pass at Tsukaguchi Station in the morning rush hour).</e>
<cmt>緩急接続を削除し、「普通列車が快速列車に接続する」という表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>新三田～篠山口間に関しては早朝・深夜を除き各駅停車の運転がなく、この区間で各駅に停車する丹波路快速や快速が各駅停車の役割を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the section between Shinsanda and Sasayamaguchi, no services of Local train are available except early in the morning and late at night, so trains of the Tambaji Rapid Service and Rapid trains that stop at every station in this section work as a Local train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the section between Shinsanda and Sasayamaguchi, no local train services are available except early in the morning and late at night, so trains of the Tambaji Rapid Service and rapid trains that stop at every station in this section work as local trains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the section between Shin-Sanda and Sasayamaguchi, no local train services are available except early in the morning and late at night, so trains of the Tambaji Rapid Service and rapid trains that stop at every station in this section work as local trains.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>なお、尼崎～宝塚間は基本的に普通列車よりも快速列車の方が本数が多く、普通停車駅と快速停車駅の乗降客の二極化が起こっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, more Rapid trains are operated than Local trains between Amagasaki and Takarazuka, thereby resulting in polarization in incoming and outgoing passengers patterns between the stops for Local trains and Rapid trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, more rapid trains are operated than local trains between Amagasaki and Takarazuka, thereby resulting in the polarization of incoming and outgoing passenger patterns between the stops for local trains and rapid trains.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, more rapid trains are operated than local trains between Amagasaki and Takarazuka, thereby resulting in the polarization of incoming and outgoing passenger patterns between the stops for local trains and rapid trains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>また、大阪～篠山口間の快速と接続して篠山口～福知山間の列車が運転されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also some Local trains that are operated between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama after connected with a Rapid train which runs between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, some local trains that are operated between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama after being connected with a rapid train that runs between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, some local trains that are operated between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama after being connected with a rapid train that runs between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>篠山口～福知山間では主に昼間は113系が2両でワンマン運転を行っていて、毎時1本程度運行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly in the daytime, a 2-car Local train of Trains Series 113 runs about every hour without a conductor on board in the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainly in the daytime, a two-car local train of Series 113 runs approximately every hour without a conductor on board in the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainly in the daytime, a two-car local train of Series 113 runs approximately every hour without a conductor on board in the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>福知山で列車番号が変わるものの、日中に山陰本線の城崎温泉駅から篠山口まで直通運転を行っている列車が1本ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a train whose train number changes at Fukuchiyama Station, yet it is operated from Kinosakionsen Station on the Sanin Main Line directly to Sasayamaguchi Station during the daytime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a train whose number changes at Fukuchiyama Station, but it&apos;s operated from Kinosakionsen Station on the Sanin Main Line directly to Sasayamaguchi Station during the daytime.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a train whose number changes at Fukuchiyama Station, but it&apos;s operated from Kinosakionsen Station on the Sanin Main Line directly to Sasayamaguchi Station during the daytime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>なお、篠山口～福知山間の列車のうち朝の下り2本と夜の上り1本については大阪方面から（へ）の列車とは接続しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Local trains operated between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, two down trains operated early in the morning and a up train operated at night are not connected with trains from or to the direction of Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the local trains that operate between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, two down trains operated early in the morning and an up train operated at night aren&apos;t connected with trains from or to the direction of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the local trains that operate between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, two outbound trains operated early in the morning and an inbound train operated at night aren&apos;t connected with trains from or to the direction of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>下り→outbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>JR京都線と直通する列車は塚本駅に停車するが、早朝などに見られる大阪駅始終着列車は塚本駅を通過する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although trains that go directly to the JR Kyoto Line stop at Tsukamoto Station, trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station and can be found early in the morning pass Tsukamoto Station without stopping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although trains that go directly to the JR Kyoto Line stop at Tsukamoto Station, trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station and can be found early in the morning pass Tsukamoto Station without stopping.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although trains that go directly to the JR Kyoto Line stop at Tsukamoto Station, trains that start from or terminate at Osaka Station and can be found early in the morning pass Tsukamoto Station without stopping.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>大阪発着の普通列車は113系、207系、221系、321系電車が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Trains Series 113, 207, 221 and 321 are used for Local trains that start from and terminate at Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Series 113, 207, 221 and 321 trains serve as local trains that start from and terminate at Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Series 113, 207, 221 and 321 trains serve as local trains that start from and terminate at Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>221系の普通列車はラッシュ時に数本存在するのみで、ワンマン運転時を除いても113系の普通列車のほうが圧倒的に多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, only a few Local trains of Trains Series 221 are operated during the rush hour, while Local trains with Trains Series 113 are overwhelmingly present even except trains without a conductor on board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, only a few local trains of Series 221 are operated during the rush hour, while local trains with Train Series 113 are overwhelmingly present except for trains without conductors on board.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, only a few local trains of Series 221 are operated during the rush hour, while local trains with Train Series 113 are overwhelmingly present except for trains without conductors on board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>過去には早朝・深夜のみ新大阪駅始終着の普通列車も存在していた（こちらも塚本駅は通過）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There used to be some Local trains that started from and terminated at Shin-Osaka Station only early in the morning and late at night (These Local trains also passed Tsukamoto Station without stopping).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There used to be some local trains that started from and terminated at Shin-Osaka Station only early in the morning and late at night (these local trains also passed Tsukamoto Station without stopping).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There used to be some local trains that started from and terminated at Shin-Osaka Station only early in the morning and late at night (these local trains also passed Tsukamoto Station without stopping).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="84">
<j>2008年3月15日のダイヤ改正より平日朝ラッシュのピーク時（8時台）の下り列車は特急および篠山口行きの普通列車を除き全てJR東西線からの直通列車となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the timetable was revised on March 15, 2008, all of the down trains except Limited Express trains and Local trains bound for Sasayamaguchi have been operated directly from the JR Tozai Line at a peak period in the rush hour in the weekday morning (between 8:00 a.m. and 9:00 a.m.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequent upon the timetable revision of March 15, 2008, all of the down trains (except for limited express trains and local trains bound for Sasayamaguchi) have been operated directly from the JR Tozai Line at a peak period in the rush hour in the weekday morning (between 8:00 a.m. and 9:00 a.m.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequent upon the timetable revision of March 15, 2008, all of the outbound trains (except for limited express trains and local trains bound for Sasayamaguchi) have been operated directly from the JR Tozai Line at a peak period in the rush hour in the weekday morning (between 8:00 a.m. and 9:00 a.m.).</e>
<cmt>下り→outbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>このために尼崎駅折り返しの普通列車との接続を取るケースが増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the number of cases where those trains make a connection with a Local train shuttled at Amagasaki Station is increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the number of cases where those trains connect with a local train shuttled at Amagasaki Station has increased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the number of cases where those trains connect with a local train that shuttled at Amagasaki Station has increased.</e>
<cmt>local train that shuttled としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>使用車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>現在の使用車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling stock currently used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolling stock currently used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling stock currently used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>JR宝塚線（大阪～尼崎～篠山口）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Takarazuka Line (Osaka - Amagasaki - Sasayamaguchi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Takarazuka Line (Osaka - Amagasaki - Sasayamaguchi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Takarazuka Line (Osaka - Amagasaki - Sasayamaguchi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>JR西日本207系電車（快速・普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR (West) Commuter Trains Series 207 (Rapid train and Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207 (rapid train and local train)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207 (rapid train and local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="87">
<j>JR西日本321系電車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR (West) Commuter Trains Series 321 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR (West) Commuter Train Series 321 (local train)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR (West) Commuter Train Series 321 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="88">
<j>JR西日本221系電車（丹波路快速・快速・普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR (West) Suburban Trains Series 221 (Tambaji Rapid Service, Rapid train and Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR (West) Suburban Train Series 221 (Tambaji Rapid Service, rapid train and local train)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR (West) Suburban Train Series 221 (Tambaji Rapid Service, rapid train and local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="89">
<j>国鉄113系電車（快速・普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Suburban Trains Series 113 (Rapid train and Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 113 (rapid train and local train)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 113 (rapid train and local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>篠山口～福知山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasayamaguchi - Fukuchiyama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasayamaguchi - Fukuchiyama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasayamaguchi - Fukuchiyama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>221系 - 朝夕の快速・普通列車で乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trains Series 221 - Used for Rapid and Local trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train Series 221 - Used for rapid and local trains</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train Series 221: Used for rapid and local trains in the morning and evening.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。「朝夕」　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>113系 - 大阪からは朝夕に乗り入れ、区間運転は終日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trains Series 113 - Used for morning and evening trains from Osaka and available for operations limited to a certain section all day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train Series 113 - Used for morning and evening trains from Osaka and available for operations limited to a certain section throughout the day.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train Series 113: Used for morning and evening trains from Osaka and available for operations limited to a certain section throughout the day.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>区間運転では専用の3800番台が運用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Train numbers in the 3800s are exclusively used for operations limited to a certain section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train numbers in the 3800s are exclusively used for operations limited to a certain section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train numbers in the 3800s are exclusively used for operations limited to a certain section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>特急列車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited Express train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Limited Express Trains</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limited express trains</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>国鉄183系電車（特急「北近畿」「文殊」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Limited Express Series 183 (Limited Express &quot;Kitakinki&quot; and &quot;Monju&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Limited Express Series 183 (limited express &quot;Kitakinki&quot; and &quot;Monju&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Limited Express Series 183 (Limited Express &apos;Kitakinki&apos; and &apos;Monju&apos;)</e>
<cmt>&quot; →&apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>国鉄キハ65形気動車（臨時特急カニカニ北近畿・臨時特急カニカニエクスプレス） - 以前は特急エーデル北近畿・丹後・鳥取、急行だいせんでの運用があったが、これらが廃止されたため、定期運用はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Diesel Cars Type Kiha 65 (special limited express &quot;Kani Kani Kitakinki&quot; and &quot;Kani Kani Express&quot;) - Used to be used for Limited Express &quot;Edel-kitakinki&quot;, &quot;Edel-Tango&quot;, &quot;Edel-Tottori&quot; and Express &quot;Daisen,&quot; but no longer operated periodically as these trains were discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Diesel Car Type Kiha 65 (special limited express &quot;Kani Kani Kitakinki&quot; and &quot;Kani Kani Express&quot;) used to be used for the limited express &quot;Edel-kitakinki,&quot; &quot;Edel-Tango,&quot; &quot;Edel-Tottori&quot; and express &quot;Daisen&quot; but is no longer operated periodically, as these trains have been discontinued.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Diesel Car Type Kiha 65 (Special Limited Express Kani Kani Kitakinki and Kani Kani Express) used to be used for the Limited Express Edel-Kitakinki, Edel-Tango, Edel-Tottori and Express Daisen but is no longer operated periodically, as these trains have been discontinued.</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR001形気動車（特急タンゴエクスプローラー）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KTR Limited Express (Diesel Cars) Series KTR001 (Limited Express &quot;Tango Explorer&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR001 (limited express &quot;Tango Explorer&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR001 (Limited Express Tango Explorer)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="96">
<j>国鉄485系電車（特急北近畿）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NR/JR Limited Express Series 485 (Limited Express &quot;Kitakinki&quot;)</e>
<cmt>「国鉄485系電車」は定訳が見つかりませんでした。既出の「国鉄183系電車」＝「NR/JR Limited Express Series 183」を参考に訳出致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NR/JR Limited Express Series 485 (limited express &quot;Kitakinki&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NR/JR Limited Express Series 485 (Limited Express Kitakinki)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>過去の使用車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling stock used in past years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolling stock used in past years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling stock used in past years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>国鉄201系電車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Commuter Trains Series 201 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 201 (local train)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 201 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="98">
<j>国鉄205系電車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Commuter Trains Series 205 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 205 (local train)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 205 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="99">
<j>国鉄117系電車（快速・普通列車） - 2001年までは奈良線と共通運用だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Suburban Trains Series 117 (Rapid train and Local train) - Collectively used with the JR Nara Line up to 2001.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 117 (rapid train and local train) were collectively used with the JR Nara Line up to 2001.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 117 (rapid and local trains): Collectively used with the JR Nara Line up to 2001.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="100">
<j>国鉄103系電車（普通列車）- 1981年4月～2003年8月。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Commuter Trains Series 103 (Local train) - Operated between April 1981 and August 2003.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 103 (local train) - Operated between April 1981 and August 2003.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 103 (local train): Operated between April 1981 and August 2003.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>また、JR福知山線脱線事故の車両となった207系の車体塗装の塗り替えによる運用離脱が相次いだため、路線の運転再開後に一時的ではあるが応援運用にも入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This series was also temporarily used after the resumption of operation instead of the Trains Series 207 which was used as the train of the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident was Trains Series 207 because many trains of Trains Series 207 needed to leave the scene of their work to be repainted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This series was also temporarily used after the resumption of operations instead of the Train Series 207, which was the train involved in the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident, because many trains of that series needed to leave the scene of their work in order to be repainted.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This series was also temporarily used after the resumption of operations instead of the Train Series 207, which was the train involved in the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident, because many trains of that series needed to leave the scene of their work in order to be repainted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="102">
<j>北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR8000形気動車（特急タンゴディスカバリー）- 1996年から1999年まで新大阪発着列車が「タンゴディスカバリー」を名乗っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KTR Limited Express (Diesel Cars) Series KTR8000 (Limited Express &quot;Tango Discovery&quot;) - &quot;Tango Discovery&quot; was a name given to the trains that started from and terminated at Shin-Osaka Station from 1996 to 1999.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR8000 (limited express &quot;Tango Discovery&quot;) - &quot;Tango Discovery&quot; was a name given to the trains that started from and terminated at Shin-Osaka Station from 1996 to 1999.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR8000 (Limited Express Tango Discovery): &apos;Tango Discovery&apos; was a name given to the trains that started from and terminated at Shin-Osaka Station from 1996 to 1999.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>また、2005年6月19日～2007年3月17日の間、北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR001形気動車の代替でタンゴエクスプローラーに使用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name was also given to the Limited Express &quot;Tango Explorer&quot; which was replaced with KTR Limited Express (Diesel Cars) Series KTR001 between June 19, 2005 and March 17, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name was also given to the limited express &quot;Tango Explorer,&quot; which was replaced by the KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR001 between June 19, 2005 and March 17, 2007.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The series was also used for the Limited Express Tango Explorer in place of the KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR001 between June 19, 2005 and March 17, 2007.</e>
<cmt>「北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR8000形気動車」が「北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR001形気動車」の代替で使われていた、という表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="104">
<j>国鉄キハ58系気動車（特急エーデル北近畿・丹後・鳥取、急行だいせん、急行丹後、普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Diesel Cars Series Kiha 58 (Limited Express &quot;Edel-kitakinki&quot;, &quot;Edel-Tango&quot;, &quot;Edel-Tottori&quot;, Express &quot;Daisen&quot;, Express &quot;Tango&quot;, Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Diesel Cars Series Kiha 58 (limited express &quot;Edel-kitakinki,&quot; &quot;Edel-Tango,&quot; &quot;Edel-Tottori,&quot; express &quot;Daisen,&quot; Express &quot;Tango,&quot; local train)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Diesel Cars Series Kiha 58 (Limited Express Edel-Kitakinki, Edel-Tango, Edel-Tottori, Express Daisen, Express Tango, local train)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; &quot;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="105">
<j>国鉄キハ40系気動車 (2代)（快速・普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Diesel Cars Series Kiha 40 (second generation) (Rapid train and Local train)</e>
<cmt>「2代」の意味が明確に理解できませんでした。「2代目の」というニュアンスで訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Diesel Cars Series Kiha 40 (second generation) (rapid and local trains)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Diesel Cars Series Kiha 40 (second generation) (rapid and local trains)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="106">
<j>国鉄キハ80系気動車（特急まつかぜ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Limited Express (Diesel Cars) Series Kiha 80 (Limited Express &quot;(Super) Matsukaze&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Limited Express (diesel car) Series Kiha 80 (limited express &quot;(Super) Matsukaze&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Limited Express (diesel car) Series Kiha 80 (Limited Express (Super) Matsukaze)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="107">
<j>国鉄キハ181系気動車（特急まつかぜ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Limited Express (Diesel Cars) Series Kiha 181 (Limited Express &quot;(Super) Matsukaze&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Limited Express (diesel car) Series Kiha 181 (limited express &quot;(Super) Matsukaze&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Limited Express (diesel car) Series Kiha 181 (Limited Express (Super) Matsukaze)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="108">
<j>国鉄12系客車（急行だいせん・普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 12 (Express &quot;Daisen&quot;, Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 12 (express &quot;Daisen,&quot; local train)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 12 (Express Daisen, local train)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="109">
<j>国鉄14系客車（急行だいせん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 14 (Express &quot;Daisen&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 14 (express &quot;Daisen&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 14 (Express Daisen)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="110">
<j>国鉄20系客車（急行だいせん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 20 (Express &quot;Daisen&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 20 (express &quot;Daisen&quot;)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 20 (Express Daisen)</e>
<cmt>limited express →Limited Express としました。&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="111">
<j>国鉄オハ35系客車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series Oha 35 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series Oha 35 (local train)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series Oha 35 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="112">
<j>国鉄スハ43系客車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series Suha 43 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series Suha 43 (local train)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series Suha 43 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="113">
<j>国鉄60系客車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 60 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 60 (local train)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 60 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="114">
<j>国鉄10系客車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 10 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 10 (local train)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 10 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="115">
<j>国鉄50系客車（普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 50 (Local train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 50 (local train)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR/JR Passenger Car Series 50 (local train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utilization of the Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utilization of the Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utilization of the Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="116">
<j>福知山線は大阪と北近畿を福知山駅経由で「南北」に結ぶ鉄道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Line is a railway that connects Osaka with northern Kinki through Fukuchiyama Station north and south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama Line is a railway that connects Osaka with northern Kinki through Fukuchiyama Station north and south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Line is a railway that connects Osaka with northern Kinki through Fukuchiyama Station north and south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="117">
<j>従来、福知山線は単線の地方ローカル線として運行されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line used to be operated as a single-track local line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line used to be operated as a single-track local line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line used to be operated as a single-track local line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="118">
<j>乗車人員が少ない駅が多かったが、1986年11月1日の宝塚以北電化、宝塚～新三田間複線化を機に、篠山口駅以南では沿線の開発が急ピッチで進められ、その上並行する阪急電鉄阪急宝塚本線・阪急伊丹線から大幅に乗客がシフトしたこともあって乗客数は急増。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There used to be many stations used by a small number of passengers; however, the number of passengers increased enormously not only because the development along the line below Sasayamaguchi Station moved ahead at a fast pace as the line above Takarazuka was electrified and the line between Takarazuka and Shinsanda was doubly tracked on November 1, 1986, but also because many passengers switched from the Hankyu Takarazuka Line of Hankyu Railway and the Hankyu Itami Line, which lie in parallel with the Fukuchiyama Line, to the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There used to be many stations used by small numbers of passengers, but the numbers of passengers increased enormously, not only because the development along the line below Sasayamaguchi Station moved ahead at a fast pace as the line above Takarazuka was electrified and the line between Takarazuka and Shinsanda was double-tracked on November 1, 1986, but also because many passengers switched from the Hankyu Takarazuka Line of the Hankyu Railway and the Hankyu Itami Line (which lie in parallel with the Fukuchiyama Line) to the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There used to be many stations used by small numbers of passengers, but the numbers of passengers increased enormously, not only because the development along the line below Sasayamaguchi Station moved ahead at a fast pace as the line above Takarazuka was electrified and the line between Takarazuka and Shin-Sanda was double-tracked on November 1, 1986, but also because many passengers switched from the Hankyu Takarazuka Line of the Hankyu Railway and the Hankyu Itami Line (which lie in parallel with the Fukuchiyama Line) to the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>JR発足時は、1日の運転本数が100本足らずだった福知山線は、1997年のJR東西線開業以降は1日360本を超える過密ダイヤ（近隣の同じ複線路線である阪和線や大和路線に比べれば本数はまだ少ないが、これがJR福知山線脱線事故の一因になったともいわれる）へと変化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line, which used to have less than 100 trains operated a day at the time of the inauguration of JR, started changing to a line with a tight railroad schedule (, which is still less tight than the schedule of the Hanwa Line and the Yamatoji Line, but it is said that this tight schedule contributed to the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident) having over 360 trains a day after the inauguration of JR Tozai Line in 1997.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line, which had fewer than 100 trains operated a day at the time of the inauguration of JR, started changing to a line with a tight railroad schedule (which is still less tight than the schedule of the Hanwa Line or the Yamatoji Line, but it is said that this tight schedule contributed to the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident) had over 360 trains a day after the inauguration of the JR Tozai Line in 1997.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line, which had fewer than 100 trains operated a day at the time of the inauguration of JR, started changing to a line with a tight railroad schedule and had over 360 trains a day after the inauguration of the JR Tozai Line in 1997 (which is still less tight than the schedule of the Hanwa Line or the Yamatoji Line that are double-tracked in the same way as the Fukuchiyama Line, but it is said that this tight schedule contributed to the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident).</e>
<cmt>括弧を文末に移動しました。複線路線　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>篠山口駅以南の複線化による増発で大阪駅へのアクセスが飛躍的に向上し、JR東西線の開業で大阪市内や大阪東部、奈良方面とのアクセスも充実した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the double tracked line below Sasayamaguchi Station, the number of trains has increased and the access to Osaka Station has improved dramatically, and at the same time, the inauguration of JR Tozai Line has provided good accessibility to Osaka City, eastern Osaka, and the direction of Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the double-tracked line below Sasayamaguchi Station, the number of trains has increased and access to Osaka Station has improved dramatically; moreover, the inauguration of the JR Tozai Line has provided good accessibility to Osaka City, eastern Osaka and the direction of Nara.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the double-tracked line below Sasayamaguchi Station, the number of trains has increased and access to Osaka Station has improved dramatically; moreover, the inauguration of the JR Tozai Line has provided good accessibility to Osaka City, eastern Osaka and the direction of Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>福知山線で最も利用者の多い駅は宝塚駅で、2004年度現在 での1日の乗車客数約3万人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The busiest railway station in the Fukuchiyama Line is Takarazuka Station which is used, as of 2004, by about 30,000 people a day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The busiest railway station on the Fukuchiyama Line is Takarazuka Station, which was used by approximately 30,000 people a day in 2004.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The busiest railway station on the Fukuchiyama Line is Takarazuka Station, which was used by approximately 30,000 people a day in 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>その他の乗車客数1万人以上の主要駅は、順に伊丹駅 (JR西日本)が約2万1千人、川西池田駅が約2万人、三田駅 (兵庫県)が約1万6千人、新三田駅が約1万4千人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other major stations used by more than 10,000 people a day include, in descending order, Itami Station (West Japan Railway Company) used by about 21,000 people, Kawanishiikeda Station used by about 20,000 people, Sanda Station (Hyogo Prefecture) used by about 16,000 people, and Shinsanda Station used by about 14,000 people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other major stations used by more than 10,000 people a day include, in descending order, Itami Station (West Japan Railway Company), used by about 21,000 people; Kawanishiikeda Station, used by about 20,000 people; Sanda Station (Hyogo Prefecture), used by about 16,000 people; and Shinsanda Station, used by about 14,000 people.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other major stations used by more than 10,000 people a day include, in descending order, Itami Station (West Japan Railway Company), used by about 21,000 people; Kawanishiikeda Station, used by about 20,000 people; Sanda Station (Hyogo Prefecture), used by about 16,000 people; and Shin-Sanda Station, used by about 14,000 people.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>アーバンネットワーク内でも新三田以北では利用者数が少なくなり、7駅合計で約1万人に留まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of users of the stations above Shinsanda, even in the Urban Network, is much less than users of those major stations - the total amount of users of the 7 stations remains about 10,000 people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of users of the stations above Shinsanda, even in the Urban Network, is much lower than users of those major stations: the total amount of users of the seven stations remains at approximately 10,000.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of users of the stations above Shin-Sanda, even in the Urban Network, is much lower than users of those major stations: the total amount of users of the seven stations remains at approximately 10,000.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="124">
<j>大阪～篠山口間と篠山口～福知山間では乗客数に大きな差があるため、一部の全線直通運転の快速列車は篠山口駅で増解結が行われ、大阪～篠山口間では8両、篠山口～福知山間では4両で運転される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there is a significant difference in the amount of users between the two sections, between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi and between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, 4 cars are added to or disconnected from the Rapid trains that run all the way through these sections at Sasayamaguchi station, so 8-car Rapid trains are operated between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi while 4-car Rapid trains are operated between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there is a significant difference in the amount of users between the two sections, between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi and between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, four cars are added to or disconnected from the rapid trains that run all the way through these sections at Sasayamaguchi station, so eight-car rapid trains are operated between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi while four-car rapid trains are operated between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there is a significant difference in the amount of users between the two sections, between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi and between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, four cars are added to or disconnected from the rapid trains that run all the way through these sections at Sasayamaguchi station, so eight-car rapid trains are operated between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi while four-car rapid trains are operated between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>また特急列車は4両編成で運行されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Limited Express trains may have four cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, limited express trains may have four cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, limited express trains may have four cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>上りは朝ラッシュ時に下りは夕方から夜にかけてのラッシュ時に篠山口～大阪間を走行する列車が篠山口駅で増解結を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some cars are added to trains that run between Sasayamaguchi and Osaka during the morning rush hour for the up train and during the evening rush hour for the down train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some cars are added to trains that run between Sasayamaguchi and Osaka during the morning rush hour for the up train and during the evening rush hour for the down train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some cars are added to trains that run between Sasayamaguchi and Osaka during the morning rush hour for the inbound train and during the evening rush hour for the outbound train.</e>
<cmt>上り、下りをinbound, outbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>その他の全線直通列車は始発駅から終点に到着するまで一貫して4両編成か6両編成で運行される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other trains that run all the way through the line have either four cars or six cars consistently from the starting station to the terminal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other trains that run all the way through the line consistently have either four cars or six cars from the starting station to the terminal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other trains that run all the way through the line consistently have either four cars or six cars from the starting station to the terminal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="128">
<j>ワンマン列車や特急列車が中心で電車の本数は特急列車と普通列車が1時間に1本ずつ（ラッシュ時は普通列車が1時間に2～3本）しかなく、乗降客の少ない駅が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The majority of the trains are trains without a conductor on board and Limited Express trains, and not only the number of trains operated an hour is only one Limited Express train and one Local train (a few Local trains are available per hour during the rush hour) but there are many stations used by a small number of users.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The majority of the trains are those without conductors on board and limited express trains, and not only the number of trains operated an hour is only one limited express and one local train (a few local trains are available per hour during the rush hour) but there are many stations used by small numbers of passengers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The majority of the trains are those without conductors on board and limited express trains, and not only the number of trains operated an hour is only one limited express and one local train (a few local trains are available per hour during the rush hour) but there are many stations used by small numbers of passengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="129">
<j>また、尼崎～宝塚間も含めて国鉄時代に大阪電車特定区間に含まれなかったため大阪近辺のJR線にしては運賃が高くなっているのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line features expensive fare for a JR line around Osaka because the line, including the section between Amagasaki and Takarazuka, was not included in the Osaka Train Specific Section in the JNR years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line features expensive fare for a JR line around Osaka because the line, including the section between Amagasaki and Takarazuka, wasn&apos;t included in the Osaka Train Specific Section in the JNR years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line features expensive fare for a JR line around Osaka because the line, including the section between Amagasaki and Takarazuka, wasn&apos;t included in the Osaka Train Specific Section in the JNR years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>国有化以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pre-nationalization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pre-nationalization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pre-nationalization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>福知山線の発祥は、川辺馬車鉄道が開業させた尼ヶ崎（のちの尼崎港）～伊丹間の馬車鉄道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Line was originally started as a horse tramway that was established by Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo and was connecting Amagasaki (later Amagasaki-ko) and Itami.</e>
<cmt>「Amagasaki-ko」は駅名ですので、このような表記と致しました。（「Port of Amagasaki」とはしませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukuchiyama Line was originally established as a horse tramway by Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo and connected Amagasaki (later Amagasaki-ko) and Itami.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukuchiyama Line was originally established as a horse tramway by Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo and connected Amagasaki (later Amagasaki-ko) and Itami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>のちに摂津鉄道と改称して馬車鉄道を蒸気動力の軽便鉄道に改築し尼ヶ崎～池田（現在の川西池田）間を開業させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo later changed its name to Settsu Railway, reconstructed the horse tramway into a light railway using a steam power, and started their services between Amagasaki and Ikeda (current Kawanishiikeda).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo later had a name change to Settsu Railway; the horse tramway was reconstructed into a light railway using steam power, and services started between Amagasaki and Ikeda (currently Kawanishiikeda).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo later had a name change to Settsu Railway; the horse tramway was reconstructed into a light railway using steam power, and services started between Amagasaki and Ikeda (currently Kawanishiikeda).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>当時の池田駅は呉服橋西詰付近にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Ikeda Station was located near Kurehabashi-Nishizume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Ikeda Station was located near Kurehabashi-Nishizume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Ikeda Station was located near Kurehabashi-Nishizume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>摂津鉄道は、大阪市から舞鶴市までの鉄道を計画していた阪鶴鉄道に合併され、改軌した上で宝塚駅まで開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Settsu Railway merged with Hankaku Railway, which was planning to build a railway from Osaka City to Maizuru City then, and corrected its track gauge to expand their services up to Takarazuka Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Settsu Railway merged with the Hankaku Railway, which was planning to build a railway from Osaka City to Maizuru City, and corrected its track gauge to extend the services to Takarazuka Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Settsu Railway merged with the Hankaku Railway, which was planning to build a railway from Osaka City to Maizuru City, and corrected its track gauge to extend the services to Takarazuka Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>以後順次延伸されて、1899年には福知山南口駅（堀内田町付近）まで開通した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, their services were gradually expanded and opened to traffic up to Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station (near Horiuchida-cho) in 1899.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, their services were gradually expanded and opened to traffic up to Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station (near Horiuchida-cho) in 1899.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, their services were gradually expanded and opened to traffic up to Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station (near Horiuchida-cho) in 1899.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="135">
<j>1904年、軍部からの要請で対ロシア戦略の軍用鉄道として舞鶴鎮守府までの開通を急がされた福知山～綾部～新舞鶴（現在の東舞鶴駅）間が官設で開通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1904, the section between Fukuchiyama and Shinmaizuru (current Higashi-Maizuru Station) by way of Ayabe, which was rushed to open to traffic up to the Maizuru army base by the military as a military railway for the strategy against Russia, was opened to traffic under the control of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1904, the section between Fukuchiyama and Shinmaizuru (currently Higashi-Maizuru Station) by way of Ayabe--which was rushed by the military in order to open to traffic up to the Maizuru army base as a military railway for the strategy against Russia--was opened to traffic under the control of the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1904, the section between Fukuchiyama and Shin-Maizuru (currently Higashi-Maizuru Station) by way of Ayabe--which was rushed by the military in order to open to traffic up to the Maizuru army base as a military railway for the strategy against Russia--was opened to traffic under the control of the government.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Maizuru としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>阪鶴鉄道も現在の福知山駅（天田）まで延伸し、福知山～新舞鶴間の貸与を受けて、大阪～舞鶴間を結ぶ鉄道が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankaku Railway also expanded their services up to current Fukuchiyama Station (Amata) and completed the railway line between Osaka and Maizuru by lending the section between Fukuchiyama and Shinmaizuru.</e>
<cmt>「福知山～新舞鶴間の貸与を受けて」という部分は、「政府からの貸与を受けて」という意味だと思いますが、定かではないので、訳文には「政府から」というニュアンスは反映いたしませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankaku Railway also expanded its services up to the present-day Fukuchiyama Station (Amata), and completed the railway line between Osaka and Maizuru by lending the section between Fukuchiyama and Shinmaizuru.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankaku Railway also expanded its services up to the present-day Fukuchiyama Station (Amata), and completed the railway line between Osaka and Maizuru by lending the section between Fukuchiyama and Shin-Maizuru.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Maizuru としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>国鉄時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan National Railways (JNR) era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan National Railways (JNR) era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan National Railways (JNR) era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="137">
<j>阪鶴鉄道は1907年に国有化され、官設区間とあわせて阪鶴線と呼ばれていたが、山陰本線の京都～出雲今市（現在の出雲市）間が1912年に開通したのを機に、神崎（現在の尼崎）～福知山間、塚口～尼ヶ崎間が福知山線となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankaku Railway was nationalized in 1907 and its railway line, including the part under the control of the government, was called Hankaku Line; however, as the section on the Sanin Main Line between Kyoto and Izumoimaichi (current Izumo City) was opened to traffic in 1912, the sections between Kanzaki (current Amagasaki) and Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki became Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankaku Railway was nationalized in 1907 and its railway line, including the portion under government control, was called the Hankaku Line; however, as the section on the Sanin Main Line between Kyoto and Izumoimaichi (currently Izumo City) was opened to traffic in 1912, the sections between Kanzaki (currently Amagasaki) and Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki became known as the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankaku Railway was nationalized in 1907 and its railway line, including the portion under government control, was called the Hankaku Line; however, as the section on the Sanin Main Line between Kyoto and Izumoimaichi (currently Izumo City) was opened to traffic in 1912, the sections between Kanzaki (currently Amagasaki) and Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki became known as the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="138">
<j>大阪と山陰方面を結ぶ亜幹線とされたが、線路改良や電化などの近代化は大幅に遅れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the railway line was designated as a semi main line that connects Osaka and the direction of Sanin, the modernization such as track improvement and electrification was delayed significantly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the railway line was designated as a semi-main line connecting Osaka and the direction of Sanin, the modernization (such as track improvement and electrification) was significantly delayed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the railway line was designated as a semi-main line connecting Osaka and the direction of Sanin, the modernization (such as track improvement and electrification) was significantly delayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>さらに国鉄C54形蒸気機関車や国鉄DD54形ディーゼル機関車が配属され、特急「まつかぜ (列車)」が福知山線経由で1961年から設定されていたが、1972年に新設された特急「はまかぜ (列車)」に至っては時間短縮を理由に姫路経由となるなど亜幹線として機能しているとは言い難い状況であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, although not only JNR Steam Locomotive C54 class and JNR Diesel Locomotive Type DD54 had been assigned but Limited Express &quot;Matsukaze&quot; had been operated since 1961, given that Limited Express &quot;Hamakaze&quot; that had been newly started in 1972 was changed to a train with a stopover in Himeji for reasons related to reduction in operating hours, it was far from functioned as a semi main line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, although not only JNR Steam Locomotive C54 class and JNR Diesel Locomotive Type DD54 had been assigned but also the limited express &quot;Matsukaze&quot; had been operated since 1961, given that the limited express &quot;Hamakaze,&quot; which had been newly started in 1972, was changed to a train with a stopover in Himeji for reasons related to the reduction in operating hours, it was far from functioning as a semi-main line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, although not only JNR Steam Locomotive C54 class and JNR Diesel Locomotive Type DD54 had been assigned but also the Limited Express &apos;Matsukaze (train)&apos; had been operated since 1961, given that the Limited Express &apos;Hamakaze (train),&apos; which had been newly started in 1972, was changed to a train with a stopover in Himeji for reasons related to the reduction in operating hours, it was far from functioning as a semi-main line.</e>
<cmt>Limited Express としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>加えて、普通列車は永らく国鉄DD51形ディーゼル機関車牽引による旧型客車が使用され続けるなど、車両面での近代化は大きく遅れていた（ただ車両については1980年代前半に生瀬～武田尾間を走行中の普通列車から身を乗り出していた小学生が誤って転落死したこともあり、大阪発着の客車列車に関しては、1985年3月のダイヤ改正で自動扉がついた国鉄12系客車客車に置き換えられて近代化している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the modernization of rail cars was also delayed significantly as seen in long-time use of outmoded passenger cars pulled by JNR Diesel Locomotive Type DD51 for the Local trains (However, with an accident in which an elementary school student who was leaning out of the window accidentally tumbled off the moving train operated between Namaze and Takedao and died in the early 1980s, passenger cars that started from and terminated at Osaka Station were replaced with JNR Passenger Car Series 12 having automatic doors when the timetable was revised in March 1985).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the modernization of rail cars was also delayed significantly, as seen in the long-time use of outmoded passenger cars pulled by JNR Diesel Locomotive Type DD51 for the local trains (however, with a fatal accident in the early 1980s, in which an elementary school student who was leaning out of the window accidentally tumbled off the moving train between Namaze and Takedao, passenger cars that started from and terminated at Osaka Station were replaced with the JNR Passenger Car Series 12, equipped with automatic doors, when the timetable was revised in March 1985).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the modernization of rail cars was also delayed significantly, as seen in the long-time use of outmoded passenger cars pulled by JNR Diesel Locomotive Type DD51 for the local trains (however, with a fatal accident in the early 1980s, in which an elementary school student who was leaning out of the window accidentally tumbled off the moving train between Namaze and Takedao, passenger cars that started from and terminated at Osaka Station were replaced with the JNR Passenger Car Series 12, equipped with automatic doors, when the timetable was revised in March 1985).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="141">
<j>設備面では、1970年代後半から近代化が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the maintenance front, the modernization started to progress in the late 1970s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The modernization of maintenance started to progress in the late 1970s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The modernization of maintenance started to progress in the late 1970s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>1979～1980年にかけて塚口～宝塚間が順次複線化され、翌1981年に尼崎～宝塚間の電化が完了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1979 and 1980, the section between Tsukaguchi and Takarazuka was doubly tracked in sequence and in 1981, the section between Amagasaki and Takarazuka was completely electrified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1979 and 1980, the section between Tsukaguchi and Takarazuka was double-tracked in sequence, and in 1981 the section between Amagasaki and Takarazuka was completely electrified.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1979 and 1980, the section between Tsukaguchi and Takarazuka was double-tracked in sequence, and in 1981 the section between Amagasaki and Takarazuka was completely electrified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>また、1980年代前半まで腕木式信号機が現存したが列車集中制御装置化により姿を消した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some mechanical semaphore signals were seen up to the early 1980&apos;s but disappeared because of the adoption of the Centralized Train Control system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some mechanical semaphore signals were seen up to the early 1980s but disappeared because of the adoption of the Centralized Train Control system.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some mechanical semaphore signals were seen up to the early 1980s but disappeared because of the adoption of the Centralized Train Control system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>だが、近代化後も利用客はほとんど伸びず、宝塚まで電化と同時に国鉄103系電車6両編成による普通電車が大阪～宝塚間で運転を開始したものの、後に4両編成に減車されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, despite the consequence of the modernization, the number of users increased very little and the Local train, which had been operated with 6 cars of JNR/JR Commuter Trains Series 103 between Osaka and Takarazuka since the line up to Takarazuka was electrified, accordingly began to be operated with 4 cars later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, despite such modernization the number of users increased very little and the local train, which had been operated with six cars of the JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 103 between Osaka and Takarazuka since the line up to Takarazuka was electrified, subsequently shifted to four-car operation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, despite such modernization the number of users increased very little and the local train, which had been operated with six cars of the JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 103 between Osaka and Takarazuka since the line up to Takarazuka was electrified, subsequently shifted to four-car operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>当時の普通電車は毎時1本しかなく、さらに宝塚以北は気動車か客車での運転だったので、三田から大阪へ向かう客も宝塚で阪急宝塚本線に乗り換えされるなどしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the Local train was available only once every hour and only diesel-powered passenger cars were available above Takarazuka at that time, passengers who wanted to go from Sanda to Osaka often needed to change trains at Takarazuka Station to the Hankyu Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt>「気動車か客車での運転だったので」という意味が明確に理解できませんでした。「気動車」は「ディーゼルエンジンを動力源とする鉄道車両」（[http://d.hatena.ne.jp/keyword/%B5%A4%C6%B0%BC%D6]参考）、つまり動力の話が主なのに対し、「客車」とは動力ではなく、「乗客を運ぶ車両」という意味で、「AかB」という比べ方の出来ない2つのものではないかと考えました。したがって「気動車の（牽引による）客車での運転だったので」という解釈で訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the local train was available only once every hour and only diesel-powered passenger cars were available above Takarazuka at that time, passengers who wanted to go from Sanda to Osaka often needed to change trains at Takarazuka Station and move to the Hankyu Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the local train was available only once every hour and only diesel-powered passenger cars were available above Takarazuka at that time, passengers who wanted to go from Sanda to Osaka often needed to change trains at Takarazuka Station and move to the Hankyu Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>また当時は神戸電鉄経由（当時は北神急行電鉄北神線が開業していなかったので鈴蘭台・新開地経由）での所要時間とは大きく差がなかったが、本数は福知山線の方が相当少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, although the time needed to get to Osaka using the Fukuchiyama Line was about the same as that of the line using Kobe Electric Railway (through Suzurandai and Shinkaichi because Hokushinkyuko Railway Hokushin Line was not opened yet then), the number of trains available per hour on the Fukuchiyama Line was much less.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, although the time needed to get to Osaka using the Fukuchiyama Line was approximately the same as that of the line using the Kobe Electric Railway (through Suzurandai and Shinkaichi because Hokushinkyuko Railway Hokushin Line was not yet open), far fewer trains were available per hour on the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, although the time needed to get to Osaka using the Fukuchiyama Line was approximately the same as that of the line using the Kobe Electric Railway (through Suzurandai and Shinkaichi because Hokushinkyuko Railway Hokushin Line was not yet open), far fewer trains were available per hour on the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="147">
<j>福知山線にとって劇的な変化が起こるのは、1986年に宝塚～新三田間の複線化、福知山までの全線電化（電化は山陰本線城崎温泉駅まで）が完成してからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A drastic change for the Fukuchiyama Line came in 1986, when the section between Takarazuka and Shinsanda was doubly tracked and all of the sections up to Fukuchiyama was electrified (The electrification was extended to Kinosakionsen Station of the Sanin Main Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A drastic change for the Fukuchiyama Line came in 1986, when the section between Takarazuka and Shinsanda was double-tracked and all the sections up to Fukuchiyama were electrified (the electrification was extended to Kinosakionsen Station on the Sanin Main Line).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A drastic change for the Fukuchiyama Line came in 1986, when the section between Takarazuka and Shin-Sanda was double-tracked and all the sections up to Fukuchiyama were electrified (the electrification was extended to Kinosakionsen Station on the Sanin Main Line).</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>全線電化の少し前に、武庫川の渓谷沿いに走っていたため複線化が困難であった生瀬～道場間について、トンネルの連続する複線の新線を新規に建設して切り替えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shortly before all of the sections were electrified, the section between Namaze and Dojo, where it was difficult to doubly track because the railway lay along the gorge of Muko-gawa River, was newly constructed as a double track railway having successive tunnels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shortly before all the sections were electrified, the section between Namaze and Dojo, which was difficult to double-track because the railway lay along the Muko-gawa River gorge, was newly constructed as a double-track railway having successive tunnels.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly before all the sections were electrified, the section between Namaze and Dojo, which was difficult to double-track because the railway lay along the Muko-gawa River gorge, was newly constructed as a double-track railway having successive tunnels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>全線電化以降、電車特急「北近畿」の運転開始に加え、普通電車は国鉄113系電車2両編成を主体として日中毎時3本（1本が大阪～福知山、2本が大阪～新三田）に増発されたが、2両編成は短過ぎて多くの列車で満員となり遅延が続発、特に22時台以降から最終電車にかけては時に積み残しが出るなど苦情が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the electrification, the operation of Limited Express train &quot;Kitakinki&quot; started and the number of Local trains available every hour during the day increased to three mainly with 2 cars of JNR/JR Suburban Trains Series 113 (one for operation between Osaka and Fukuchiyama and two for operation between Osaka and Shinsanda); however, 2 cars were not sufficient and thus many of the Local trains were packed with too many passengers and accordingly delayed in succession, thereby resulting in many complaints about, for example, bumped passengers especially for the trains after 22:00 to the last train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the electrification, the operation of the limited express train &quot;Kitakinki&quot; started and the number of local trains available every hour during the day increased to three, mainly with two cars of the JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 113 (one for operation between Osaka and Fukuchiyama and two for operation between Osaka and Shinsanda); however, it wasn&apos;t sufficient to have two cars so many of the local trains were packed with too many passengers and experienced successive delays, thereby resulting in many complaints about, for example, bumped passengers, especially for the trains after 22:00 to the last train.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the electrification, the operation of the Limited Express &apos;Kitakinki&apos; started and the number of local trains available every hour during the day increased to three, mainly with two cars of the JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 113 (one for operation between Osaka and Fukuchiyama and two for operation between Osaka and Shin-Sanda); however, it wasn&apos;t sufficient to have two cars so many of the local trains were packed with too many passengers and experienced successive delays, thereby resulting in many complaints about, for example, bumped passengers, especially for the trains after 22:00 to the last train.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="150">
<j>反面、福知山線最初の開業区間でもあった塚口～尼崎港間の通称尼崎港線が、旅客営業を1981年に廃止した後、1984年に完全に廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, the service for passengers was stopped in 1981 and then the line was completely abandoned in 1984 on the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko, known as Amagasaki-ko Line, which was first opened to traffic on the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, the service for passengers was stopped in 1981 and then the line was completely abandoned in 1984 on the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko, known as Amagasaki-ko Line, which was first opened to traffic on the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, the service for passengers was stopped in 1981 and then the line was completely abandoned in 1984 on the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko, known as Amagasaki-ko Line, which was first opened to traffic on the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>同線は1898年に東海道本線の尼崎駅への連絡線を設けて大阪方面との直通運転を始めてからは、塚口～尼崎港間の盲腸線となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amagasaki-ko Line had been a Mocho (cecum) line between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko since the direct operation to the direction of Osaka was started by constructing a connecting line to Amagasaki Station on the Tokaido Main Line in 1898.</e>
<cmt>「盲腸線」に関して定訳が見つからなかったため、日本語独特の表現だと考え、定義または意味を括弧などに入れて訳文上で記した方が良いかとも考えましたが、原文と等価ではなくなるため、行いませんでした。（起点・終点のどちらかが他の鉄道路線と接続しておらず、あたかも盲腸のように見える路線(又は路線の一部)のこと。「盲腸」と言う言葉には「役に立たないのになぜか残っている」といった意味合いも込められている。そのため、「短い」「列車の運行本数が少ない(又は乗客が少ない)」ことを「盲腸線」の条件とする人もいる。）[http://d.hatena.ne.jp/keyword/%CC%D5%C4%B2%C0%FE]参考</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amagasaki-ko Line had been a Mocho (cecum) line between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko since the direct operation in the direction of Osaka was started in 1898 by constructing a connecting line to Amagasaki Station on the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amagasaki-ko Line had been a Mocho (cecum) line between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko since the direct operation in the direction of Osaka was started in 1898 by constructing a connecting line to Amagasaki Station on the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>晩年の旅客列車の本数は1日2往復であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In its later years, the Amagasaki-ko Line had only two round-trip services a day for passengers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its later years, the Amagasaki-ko Line had only two round-trip services a day for passengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its later years, the Amagasaki-ko Line had only two round-trip services a day for passengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>国鉄民営化以後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Post privatization of JNR</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the privatization of JNR</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the privatization of JNR</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="153">
<j>その後は車両増結で対処したが、当時人口が急増していた西宮市北部地区や三田市の住民から快速列車の設定を希望する声が相次いだため、民営化後の1989年より快速が登場（快速の区間は現在と同じく、大阪～三田間のみ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although some cars were added, many people living in the northern area in Nishinomiya City and Sanda City in which rapid increase in population was seen then requested to provide Rapid trains, and some Rapid trains came on the scene after the privatization of JNR in 1989 (The section for the Rapid train was only between Osaka and Sanda, which is the same as today).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some cars were added, many people living in the northern area in Nishinomiya City and Sanda City, in which a rapid increase in population was seen, asked that rapid trains be provided, and some rapid trains came on the scene after the privatization of JNR in 1989 (the section for the rapid train was only between Osaka and Sanda, which is the same as today).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although some cars were added, many people living in the northern area in Nishinomiya City and Sanda City, in which a rapid increase in population was seen, asked that rapid trains be provided, and some rapid trains came on the scene after the privatization of JNR in 1989 (the section for the rapid train was only between Osaka and Sanda, which is the same as today).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>この時点で日中は特急0～1本、快速2本、普通4本の現在とほぼ変わらぬ姿となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this stage, no or one Limited Express train, two Rapid trains and four Local trains became available an hour, which is almost the same as today.</e>
<cmt>ここでの本数は「毎時」という意味だと思うのですが、訳文には反映した方が良いと考え、反映いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this stage, no or only one limited express train, two rapid trains and four local trains became available on an hourly basis, which is almost the same as today.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this stage, no or only one limited express train, two rapid trains and four local trains became available on an hourly basis, which is almost the same as today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="155">
<j>1997年には、篠山口駅までの複線化が完成し、JR東西線・片町線（学研都市線）との直通運転が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1997, the double track railway was completed up to Sasayamaguchi Station and the direct operation with the JR Tozai Line and the Katamachi Line (Gakkentoshi Line) started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1997, the double-track railway was completed up to Sasayamaguchi Station and direct operation with the JR Tozai Line and the Katamachi Line (Gakkentoshi Line) started.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1997, the double-track railway was completed up to Sasayamaguchi Station and direct operation with the JR Tozai Line and the Katamachi Line (Gakkentoshi Line) started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="156">
<j>2005年、塚口～尼崎間を走行中の快速列車が脱線し、多くの死傷者を出すJR福知山線脱線事故が発生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2005, the derailment accident of a Rapid train running between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki, known as JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident, occurred and caused many deaths and casualties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2005, the derailment accident of a rapid train running between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki, known as the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident, occurred and caused many deaths and injuries.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2005, the derailment accident of a rapid train running between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki, known as the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident, occurred and caused many deaths and injuries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>この事故は、JR西日本の経営体質や社員の管理にまで言及されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This accident raised serious questions about the management practices of West Japan Railway Company as well as its employee management.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This accident raised serious questions about the management practices of West Japan Railway Company as well as its employee management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This accident raised serious questions about the management practices of West Japan Railway Company as well as its employee management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="158">
<j>1891年（明治24年）9月 - 川辺馬車鉄道 尼ヶ崎～伊丹間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September, 1891: Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo was opened to traffic between Amagasaki and Itami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September, 1891: Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo was opened to traffic between Amagasaki and Itami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September, 1891: Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo was opened to traffic between Amagasaki and Itami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>馬車鉄道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horse tramway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horse tramway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horse tramway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="160">
<j>1892年（明治25年）6月 - 川辺馬車鉄道が摂津鉄道に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June, 1892: Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo changed its name to Settsu Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June, 1892: Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo changed its name to Settsu Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June, 1892: Kawabe [Kawanobe] Basha Tetsudo changed its name to Settsu Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="161">
<j>1893年（明治26年）12月12日 - 尼ヶ崎～池田間（8マイル35チェーン (単位)≒13.58km）を軌間762mmの軽便鉄道に改築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 12, 1893: The track gauge was set to 762mm for light railway in the section between Amagasaki and Ikeda (8 miles and 35 chains (unit) ≒ 13.58km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 12, 1893: The track gauge was set to 762mm for light railway in the section between Amagasaki and Ikeda (8 miles and 35 chains (unit) ≒ 13.58km).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 12, 1893: The track gauge was set to 762mm for light railway in the section between Amagasaki and Ikeda (8 miles and 35 chains (unit) ≒ 13.58km).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>尼ヶ崎駅（後の尼崎港駅）、（貨）長洲駅、伊丹駅、池田駅（現在の川西池田駅）開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amagasaki Station (later Amagasaki-ko Station), (freight train) Nagasu Station, Itami Station and Ikeda Station (current Kawanishiikeda Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>（貨）は「貨物（列車）」を表すと判断いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagasaki Station (later Amagasaki-ko Station), (freight train) Nagasu Station, Itami Station and Ikeda Station (currently Kawanishiikeda Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagasaki Station (later Amagasaki-ko Station), (freight train) Nagasu Station, Itami Station and Ikeda Station (currently Kawanishiikeda Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="163">
<j>馬車鉄道時代は東海道線と平面交差していたが、改築後は貨車を除いて横断を禁止され、南北に構内を分断された長洲駅を旅客は徒歩連絡、貨車は人力で横断させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was crossing at grade with the Tokaido Line in the horse tramway era, after the track gauge was corrected, crossing became prohibited except freight trains, and thus passengers had to walk and freight trains had to be moved by humans to cross Nagasu Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was a crossing at grade with the Tokaido Line in the horse tramway era, after the track gauge was corrected crossing became prohibited except for freight trains, so passengers had to walk and freight trains had to be moved by humans to cross Nagasu Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was a crossing at grade with the Tokaido Line in the horse tramway era, after the track gauge was corrected crossing became prohibited except for freight trains, so passengers had to walk and freight trains had to be moved by humans to cross Nagasu Station whose station yard was divided north and south..</e>
<cmt>南北に　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="164">
<j>1894年（明治27年）3月6日 - 大物駅、塚口駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 6, 1894: Daimotsu Station and Tsukaguchi Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 6, 1894: Daimotsu Station and Tsukaguchi Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6, 1894: Daimotsu Station and Tsukaguchi Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="165">
<j>1897年（明治30年）2月16日 - 摂津鉄道が阪鶴鉄道に合併。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 16, 1897: Settsu Railway was merged into Hankaku Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 16, 1897: Settsu Railway was merged into Hankaku Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 16, 1897: Settsu Railway was merged into Hankaku Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="166">
<j>12月27日 - 池田～宝塚間（4M50C≒7.44km）が軌間1067mmで延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 27: The section between Ikeda and Takarazuka (4M50C≒7.44km) was extended to begin operating with 1067-mm track gauge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 27: The section between Ikeda and Takarazuka (4M50C≒7.44 km) was extended to begin operating with a track gauge of 1067 mm.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 27: The section between Ikeda and Takarazuka (4M50C≒7.44 km) was extended to begin operating with a track gauge of 1067 mm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>中山駅（後の中山寺駅）、宝塚駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakayama Station (Nakayamadera Station) and Takarazuka Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakayama Station (Nakayamadera Station) and Takarazuka Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakayama Station (Nakayamadera Station) and Takarazuka Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>池田駅移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikeda Station was redeployed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikeda Station was redeployed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikeda Station was redeployed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="169">
<j>12月28日 - 尼ヶ崎～池田間の軌間を1067mmに改軌・改キロ、同区間で43C≒0.87km短縮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 28: The track gauge between Amagasaki and Ikeda was corrected to 1067mm and the operating kilometer was also shortened by 43C≒0.87km.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 28: The track gauge between Amagasaki and Ikeda was corrected to 1067mm and the operating kilometer was also shortened by 43C≒0.87km.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 28: The track gauge between Amagasaki and Ikeda was corrected to 1067mm and the operating kilometer was also shortened by 43C≒0.87km.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="170">
<j>1898年（明治31年）6月8日 - 宝塚～有馬口間（1M11C≒1.83km）、神崎～塚口間（1M38C≒2.37km）延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 8, 1898: The sections between Takarazuka and Arimaguchi (1M11C≒1.83km) and between Kanzaki and Tsukaguchi (1M38C≒2.37km) were extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 8, 1898: The sections between Takarazuka and Arimaguchi (1M11C≒1.83km) and between Kanzaki and Tsukaguchi (1M38C≒2.37km) were extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 8, 1898: The sections between Takarazuka and Arimaguchi (1M11C≒1.83km) and between Kanzaki and Tsukaguchi (1M38C≒2.37km) were extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>有馬口駅（後の生瀬駅）開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arimaguchi Station (Namaze Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arimaguchi Station (Namaze Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arimaguchi Station (Namaze Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>東海道本線神崎駅（現在の尼崎駅）に乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The line was extended to Kanzaki Station (current Amagasaki Station) on the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The line was extended to Kanzaki Station (current Amagasaki Station) on the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line was extended to Kanzaki Station (current Amagasaki Station) on the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>長洲～塚口間（1M19C≒1.99km）廃止、尼ヶ崎～長洲間は孤立区間となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section between Nagasu and Tsukaguchi (1M19C≒1.99km) was discontinued and the section between Amagasaki and Nagasu became an isolated section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section between Nagasu and Tsukaguchi (1M19C≒1.99 km) was discontinued, and the section between Amagasaki and Nagasu became an isolated section.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section between Nagasu and Tsukaguchi (1M19C≒1.99 km) was discontinued, and the section between Amagasaki and Nagasu became an isolated section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="174">
<j>1899年（明治32年）1月25日 - 有馬口～三田間（9M68C≒15.85km）が延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 25, 1899: The section between Arimaguchi and Sanda (9M68C≒15.85km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 25, 1899: The section between Arimaguchi and Sanda (9M68C≒15.85km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 25, 1899: The section between Arimaguchi and Sanda (9M68C≒15.85km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>武田尾駅、道場駅、三田駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takedao Station, Dojo Station and Sanda Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takedao Station, Dojo Station and Sanda Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takedao Station, Dojo Station and Sanda Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="176">
<j>3月25日 - 三田～篠山間（15M29C≒24.72km）が延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 25: The section between Sanda and Sasayama (15M29C≒24.72km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 25: The section between Sanda and Sasayama (15M29C≒24.72km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 25: The section between Sanda and Sasayama (15M29C≒24.72km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>有馬口駅を生瀬駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arimaguchi Station changed its name to Namaze Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arimaguchi Station was renamed as Namaze Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arimaguchi Station was renamed as Namaze Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>広野駅、相野駅、藍本駅、古市駅、篠山駅（現在の篠山口駅）開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirono Station, Aino Station, Aimoto Station, Furuichi Station and Sasayama Station (current Sasayamaguchi Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirono Station, Aino Station, Aimoto Station, Furuichi Station and Sasayama Station (currently Sasayamaguchi Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirono Station, Aino Station, Aimoto Station, Furuichi Station and Sasayama Station (currently Sasayamaguchi Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="179">
<j>4月10日 - 改キロ、全線で2C≒0.04km延長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 10: The operating kilometer was extended by 2C≒0.04km wholly within the line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 10: The operating kilometer was extended by 2C≒0.04km fully within the line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 10: The operating kilometer was extended by 2C≒0.04km fully within the line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="180">
<j>5月25日 - 篠山～柏原間（13M34C≒21.61km）が延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 25: The section between Sasayama and Kaibara (13M34C≒21.61km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 25: The section between Sasayama and Kaibara (13M34C≒21.61km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 25: The section between Sasayama and Kaibara (13M34C≒21.61km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>大山駅（後の丹波大山駅）、下滝駅、谷川駅、柏原駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyama Station (Tamba-Oyama Station), Shimotaki Station, Tanikawa Station and Kaibara Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyama Station (Tamba-Oyama Station), Shimotaki Station, Tanikawa Station and Kaibara Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyama Station (Tamba-Oyama Station), Shimotaki Station, Tanikawa Station and Kaibara Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="182">
<j>7月15日 - 柏原～福知山南口間（15M68C≒25.51km）が延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 15: The section between Kaibara and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi (15M68C≒25.51km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 15: The section between Kaibara and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi (15M68C≒25.51km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 15: The section between Kaibara and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi (15M68C≒25.51km) was extended to begin operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>石生駅、黒井駅、市島駅、竹田駅（後の丹波竹田駅）、福知山南口駅（後の福知駅）開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iso Station, Kuroi Station, Ichijima Station, Takeda Station (Tamba-Takeda Station) and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station (Fukuchi Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iso Station, Kuroi Station, Ichijima Station, Takeda Station (Tamba-Takeda Station) and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station (Fukuchi Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iso Station, Kuroi Station, Ichijima Station, Takeda Station (Tamba-Takeda Station) and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station (Fukuchi Station) began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="184">
<j>1900年（明治33年）度 - 尼ヶ崎～長洲間（1M58C≒2.78km）休止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900: The section between Amagasaki and Nagasu (1M58C≒2.78km) was adjourned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1900: The section between Amagasaki and Nagasu (1M58C≒2.78km) was adjourned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1900: The section between Amagasaki and Nagasu (1M58C≒2.78km) was adjourned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="185">
<j>1902年（明治35年）11月12日 - マイル・チェーン表記からマイル表記に簡略化（神崎～福知山南口間 66M55C→66.7M）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 12, 1902: The description (unit) of operating distance was simplified from Mile-Chain to Mile (the section between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi: 66M55C -&gt; 66.7M).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 12, 1902: The description (unit) of operating distance was simplified from &quot;mile-chain&quot; to &quot;mile&quot; (the section between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi: 66M55C -&gt; 66.7M).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 12, 1902: The description (unit) of operating distance was simplified from &quot;mile-chain&quot; to &quot;mile&quot; (the section between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi: 66M55C -&gt; 66.7M).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="186">
<j>1903年（明治36年）4月30日 - 池田～中山間に花畑臨時駅が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 30, 1903: Hanabatake provisional train station began operating between Ikeda and Nakayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 30, 1903: The Hanabatake provisional train station began operating between Ikeda and Nakayama.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 30, 1903: The Hanabatake provisional train station began operating between Ikeda and Nakayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="187">
<j>8月1日 - 花畑仮停車場廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1: Hanabatake provisional train station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>「花畑仮停車場」とは、上記の「花畑臨時駅」と同じものであると判断いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1: The Hanabatake provisional train station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1: The Hanabatake provisional train station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="188">
<j>11月1日 - 福知山南口駅を福知駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 1: Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station changed its name to Fukuchi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 1: Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station was renamed as Fukuchi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 1: Fukuchiyama-Minamiguchi Station was renamed as Fukuchi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="189">
<j>1904年（明治37年）11月3日 - 福知～福知山間（0.7M≒1.13km）が延伸開業し、官設鉄道福知山駅に乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 3, 1904: The section between Fukuchi and Fukuchiyama (0.7M≒1.13km) was extended to begin operating and connected to Fukuchiyama Station of Japanese Imperial Government Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 3, 1904: The section between Fukuchi and Fukuchiyama (0.7M≒1.13km) was extended to begin operating and connected to Fukuchiyama Station of the Japanese Imperial Government Railway.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 3, 1904: The section between Fukuchi and Fukuchiyama (0.7M≒1.13km) was extended to begin operating and connected to Fukuchiyama Station of the Japanese Imperial Government Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>同日開業した官設鉄道 福知山～綾部～新舞鶴（現在の東舞鶴駅）間を阪鶴鉄道が借り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankaku Railway had the section of Japanese Imperial Government Railway which began its operation on the same day between Fukuchiyama and Maizuru (Higashi-Maizuru) via Ayabe on loan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankaku Railway had the section of the Japanese Imperial Government Railway, which began its operation on the same day between Fukuchiyama and Maizuru (Higashi-Maizuru) via Ayabe, on a loaned basis.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankaku Railway had the section of the Japanese Imperial Government Railway, which began its operation on the same day between Fukuchiyama and Shin-Maizuru (Higashi-Maizuru) via Ayabe, on a loaned basis.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Maizuru としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="191">
<j>1905年（明治38年）7月13日 - 貨物支線 塚口～長洲間（1.2M≒1.93km）が再開業、長洲～尼ヶ崎間（1.7M≒2.76km）が再開、東海道線と立体交差化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 13, 1905: The freight feeder line between Tsukaguchi and Nagasu (1.2M≒1.93km) and the section between Nagasu and Amagasaki (1.7M≒2.76km) were restarted and crossed with the Tokaido Line with an overpass or underpass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 13, 1905: The freight feeder line between Tsukaguchi and Nagasu (1.2M≒1.93km) and the section between Nagasu and Amagasaki (1.7M≒2.76km) were restarted and crossed the Tokaido Line by means of overpasses and underpasses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 13, 1905: The freight feeder line between Tsukaguchi and Nagasu (1.2M≒1.93km) and the section between Nagasu and Amagasaki (1.7M≒2.76km) were restarted and crossed the Tokaido Line by means of overpasses and underpasses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>尼ヶ崎駅再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amagasaki Station restarted its operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagasaki Station restarted its operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagasaki Station restarted its operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>大物駅、（貨）長洲駅廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimotsu Station and (freight train) Nagasu Station were discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimotsu Station and (freight train) Nagasu Station were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimotsu Station and (freight train) Nagasu Station were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="194">
<j>1907年（明治40年）8月1日 - 阪鶴鉄道が国有化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1, 1907: Hankaku Railway was nationalized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1, 1907: Hankaku Railway was nationalized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1907: Hankaku Railway was nationalized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="195">
<j>11月1日 - 神崎～福知山間改キロ、0.4M≒0.64km短縮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 1: The operating kilometer between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama was shortened by 0.4M≒0.64km.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 1: The operating distance (kilometer) between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama was shortened by 0.4M≒0.64km.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 1: The operating distance (kilometer) between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama was shortened by 0.4M≒0.64km.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="196">
<j>1909年（明治42年）10月1日 - 福知駅廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1909: Fukuchi Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1909: Fukuchi Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1909: Fukuchi Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="197">
<j>10月12日 - 線路名称制定、神崎～福知山～新舞鶴（現在の東舞鶴）間、塚口～尼ヶ崎間などを阪鶴線とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 12: Some sections including sections between Kanzaki and Shinmaizuru (Higashi-Maizuru) via Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki were determined as Hankaku Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 12: Some sections, including those between Kanzaki and Shinmaizuru (Higashi-Maizuru) via Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki, were designated as being of the Hankaku Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 12: Some sections, including those between Kanzaki and Shin-Maizuru (Higashi-Maizuru) via Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki, were designated as being of the Hankaku Line.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Maizuru としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="198">
<j>1911年（明治44年）9月6日 - 塚口～尼ヶ崎間の旅客営業再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 6, 1911: Services for passengers in the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki were restarted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 6, 1911: Services for passengers in the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki were restarted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 6, 1911: Services for passengers in the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki were restarted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>神崎乗降場開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanzaki Platform began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanzaki platform began operating.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanzaki platform began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="200">
<j>11月1日 - 竹田駅を丹波竹田駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 1: Takeda Station changed its name to Tamba-Takeda Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 1: Takeda Station was renamed as Tamba-Takeda Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 1: Takeda Station was renamed as Tamba-Takeda Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="201">
<j>1912年（明治45年）3月1日 - 神崎～福知山間、塚口～尼ヶ崎間が阪鶴線から分離され、福知山線となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 1, 1912: The sections between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki were separated from the Hankaku Line and determined as Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 1, 1912: The sections between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki were separated from the Hankaku Line and designated as being of the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1, 1912: The sections between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama and between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki were separated from the Hankaku Line and designated as being of the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="202">
<j>4月16日 - 支線に金楽寺駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 16: Kinrakuji Station began operating on the feeder line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 16: Kinrakuji Station began operating on the feeder line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 16: Kinrakuji Station began operating on the feeder line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="203">
<j>1913年（大正2年）9月1日 - 惣川駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 1, 1913: Sogawa Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 1, 1913: Sogawa Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1, 1913: Sogawa Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="204">
<j>1915年（大正4年）9月11日 - 中山駅を中山寺駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 11, 1915: Nakayama Station changed its name to Nakayamadera Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 11, 1915: Nakayama Station was renamed as Nakayamadera Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 11, 1915: Nakayama Station was renamed as Nakayamadera Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="205">
<j>1917年（大正6年）5月1日 - 大山駅を丹波大山駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 1, 1917: Oyama Station changed its name to Tamba-Oyama Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 1, 1917: Oyama Station was renamed as Tamba-Oyama Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 1, 1917: Oyama Station was renamed as Tamba-Oyama Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="206">
<j>1918年（大正7年）5月15日 - 伊丹～池田間に猪名川仮信号所を開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 15, 1918: Inagawa temporary signal station was installed between Itami and Ikeda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 15, 1918: The Inagawa temporary signal station was installed between Itami and Ikeda.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 15, 1918: The Inagawa temporary signal station was installed between Itami and Ikeda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="207">
<j>9月13日 - 猪名川仮信号所廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 13: The Inagawa temporary signal station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 13: The Inagawa temporary signal station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 13: The Inagawa temporary signal station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="208">
<j>1926年（大正15年）3月15日 - 惣川駅の旅客営業廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 15, 1926: Services for passengers at Sogawa Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 15, 1926: Services for passengers at Sogawa Station were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 15, 1926: Services for passengers at Sogawa Station were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="209">
<j>1930年（昭和5年）4月1日 - マイル表示からメートル表示に変更（神崎～福知山間 67.0M→108.3km、塚口～尼ヶ崎間 2.9M→4.6km）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1930: The description (unit) of operating distance was changed from Mile to Meter (the section between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama: 67M -&gt; 108.3Km, between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki: 2.9M -&gt; 4.6Km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1930: The description (unit) of operating distance was changed from &quot;mile&quot; to &quot;meters&quot; (the section between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama: 67M -&gt; 108.3km, between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki: 2.9M -&gt; 4.6km).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1930: The description (unit) of operating distance was changed from &quot;mile&quot; to &quot;meters&quot; (the section between Kanzaki and Fukuchiyama: 67M -&gt; 108.3km, between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki: 2.9M -&gt; 4.6km).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="210">
<j>1934年（昭和9年）5月15日 - 神崎～塚口間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 15, 1934: The section between Kanzaki and Tsukaguchi was doubly tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 15, 1934: The section between Kanzaki and Tsukaguchi was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 15, 1934: The section between Kanzaki and Tsukaguchi was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="211">
<j>1944年（昭和19年）3月1日 - 篠山駅を篠山口駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March1, 1944: Sasayama Station changed its name to Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March1, 1944: Sasayama Station was renamed as Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March1, 1944: Sasayama Station was renamed as Sasayamaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="212">
<j>4月1日 - 北伊丹駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1: Kita-Itami Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1: Kita-Itami Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1: Kita-Itami Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="213">
<j>1949年（昭和24年）1月1日 - 神崎駅を尼崎駅に、尼ヶ崎駅を尼崎港駅に、神崎乗降場を尼崎乗降場に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 1, 1949: Kanzaki Station, Amagasaki Station and Kanzaki Platform changed their names to Amagasaki Station, Amagasaki-ko Station and Amagasaki Platform, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 1, 1949: Kanzaki Station, Amagasaki Station and Kanzaki Platform changed their names to Amagasaki Station, Amagasaki-ko Station and Amagasaki Platform, respectively.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 1, 1949: Kanzaki Station, Amagasaki Station and Kanzaki Platform changed their names to Amagasaki Station, Amagasaki-ko Station and Amagasaki Platform, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="214">
<j>1951年（昭和26年）8月1日 - 池田駅を川西池田駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1, 1951: Ikeda Station changed its name to Kawanishiikeda Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1, 1951: Ikeda Station was renamed as Kawanishiikeda Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1951: Ikeda Station was renamed as Kawanishiikeda Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="215">
<j>1955年（昭和30年）10月24日 - 南矢代駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 24, 1955: Minami-Yashiro Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 24, 1955: Minami-Yashiro Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 24, 1955: Minami-Yashiro Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="216">
<j>1956年（昭和31年）11月19日 - 尼崎～塚口間が電化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 19, 1956: The section between Amagasaki and Tsukaguchi was electrified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 19, 1956: The section between Amagasaki and Tsukaguchi was electrified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 19, 1956: The section between Amagasaki and Tsukaguchi was electrified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="217">
<j>1958年（昭和33年）3月27日 - 草野駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 27, 1958: Kusano Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 27, 1958: Kusano Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 27, 1958: Kusano Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="218">
<j>1961年（昭和36年）10月1日 - 特急「北近畿 (列車)」運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1961: Express train &quot;Kitakinki&quot; service began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1961: The &quot;Kitakinki&quot; express train service began.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1961: The Limited Express &apos;Kitakinki&apos; began operating.</e>
<cmt>Limited Express としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="219">
<j>1969年（昭和44年）4月30日 - 尼崎乗降場を書類上尼崎駅に併合し、尼崎臨時乗降場とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 30, 1969: Amagasaki Platform was merged into Amagasaki Station on paper and named Amagasaki temporary platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 30, 1969: Amagasaki Platform was merged into Amagasaki Station on paper and designated as the Amagasaki temporary platform.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 30, 1969: Amagasaki Platform was merged into Amagasaki Station on paper and designated as the Amagasaki temporary platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="220">
<j>1979年（昭和54年）7月1日 - （貨）惣川駅廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 1, 1979: (Freight train) Sogawa Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 1, 1979: (Freight train) Sogawa Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 1, 1979: (Freight train) Sogawa Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="221">
<j>9月27日 - 塚口～北伊丹間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 27: The section between Tsukaguchi and Kita-Itami was doubly tracked..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 27: The section between Tsukaguchi and Kita-Itami was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 27: The section between Tsukaguchi and Kita-Itami was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="222">
<j>1980年（昭和55年）9月3日 - 川西池田駅が北伊丹方に0.2km移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 3, 1980: Kawanishiikeda Station was moved 0.2Km to the direction of Kita-Itami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 3, 1980: Kawanishiikeda Station was moved 0.2km toward the direction of Kita-Itami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 3, 1980: Kawanishiikeda Station was moved 0.2 km toward the direction of Kita-Itami.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="223">
<j>12月5日 - 北伊丹～中山寺間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 5: The section between Kita-Itami and Nakayamadera was doubly tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 5: The section between Kita-Itami and Nakayamadera was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 5: The section between Kita-Itami and Nakayamadera was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="224">
<j>12月11日 - 中山寺～宝塚間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 11: The section between Nakayamadera and Takarazuka was doubly tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 11: The section between Nakayamadera and Takarazuka was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 11: The section between Nakayamadera and Takarazuka was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="225">
<j>1981年（昭和56年）4月1日 - 塚口～宝塚間が電化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1981: The section between Tsukaguchi and Takarazuka was electrified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1981: The section between Tsukaguchi and Takarazuka was electrified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1981: The section between Tsukaguchi and Takarazuka was electrified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>猪名寺駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inadera Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inadera Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inadera Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>塚口～尼崎港間の旅客営業廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services for passengers in the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko were discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services for passengers in the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services for passengers in the section between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>金楽寺駅、尼崎臨時乗降場廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinrakuji Station and Amagasaki temporary platform were discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinrakuji Station and the Amagasaki temporary platform were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinrakuji Station and the Amagasaki temporary platform were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="229">
<j>1982年（昭和57年）2月27日 - 篠山口～福知山間CTC化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 27, 1982: The CTC system was adopted in the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 27, 1982: The CTC system was adopted in the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 27, 1982: The CTC system was adopted in the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="230">
<j>1984年（昭和59年）2月1日 - 貨物支線（尼崎港線）塚口～尼崎港間 (4.6km) が廃止（貨）尼崎港駅廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 1, 1984: The freight feeder line () between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko (4.6Km) was discontinued and (freight train) Amagasaki-ko Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 1, 1984: The freight feeder line () between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko (4.6km) was discontinued, and (freight train) Amagasaki-ko Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 1, 1984: The freight feeder line (Amagasaki-ko Line) between Tsukaguchi and Amagasaki-ko (4.6 km) was discontinued, and (freight train) Amagasaki-ko Station was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>尼崎港線　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="231">
<j>3月10日 - 広野～篠山口間CTC化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 10: The CTC system was adopted in the section between Hirono and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 10: The CTC system was adopted in the section between Hirono and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 10: The CTC system was adopted in the section between Hirono and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="232">
<j>1986年（昭和61年）8月1日 - 宝塚～三田間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1, 1986: The section between Takarazuka and Sanda was doubly tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1, 1986: The section between Takarazuka and Sanda was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1986: The section between Takarazuka and Sanda was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>生瀬～道場間を新線に切り替え、1.8km短縮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section between Namaze and Dojo was switched to a new line and shortened by 1.8Km.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section between Namaze and Dojo was switched to a new line and shortened by 1.8Km.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section between Namaze and Dojo was switched to a new line and shortened by 1.8 Km.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="234">
<j>10月15日 - 三田～新三田間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 15: The section between Sanda and Shinsanda was doubly tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 15: The section between Sanda and Shinsanda was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 15: The section between Sanda and Shin-Sanda was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>尼崎～広野間CTC化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The CTC system was adopted in the section between Amagasaki and Hirono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The CTC system was adopted in the section between Amagasaki and Hirono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The CTC system was adopted in the section between Amagasaki and Hirono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="236">
<j>11月1日 - 宝塚～福知山間が電化し、全線電化完了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 1: The section between Takarazuka and Fukuchiyama was electrified and the entire line, accordingly, was completely electrified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 1: The section between Takarazuka and Fukuchiyama was electrified, and consequently the entire line was electrified.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 1: The section between Takarazuka and Fukuchiyama was electrified, and consequently the entire line was electrified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>西宮名塩駅、新三田駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishinomiyanajio Station and Sanda Station began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishinomiyanajio Station and Sanda Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishinomiyanajio Station and Shin-Sanda Station began operating.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>全線の貨物営業廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The freight car services were discontinued throughout the line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Freight car services were discontinued throughout the line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Freight car services were discontinued throughout the line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>エル特急「北近畿 (列車)」運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The operation of L Express train &quot;Kitakinki&quot; began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The operation of the &quot;Kitakinki&quot; limited express train began.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The operation of the L-Limited Express &apos;Kitakinki&apos; began.</e>
<cmt>L-Limited Express としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>特急「まつかぜ」廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Limited Express train &quot;Matsukaze&quot; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Matsukaze&quot; limited express train was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The operation of Limited Express &apos;Matsukaze&apos; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>Limited Express としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="241">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日 - 国鉄分割民営化により西日本旅客鉄道が承継。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1987: West Japan Railway Company succeeded the line upon the privatization of the Japanese National Railways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1987: West Japan Railway Company succeeded the line upon the privatization of Japanese National Railways.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1987: West Japan Railway Company succeeded the line upon the privatization of Japanese National Railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="242">
<j>1988年（昭和63年）3月13日 - 大阪～篠山口間の愛称としてJR宝塚線を使用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 13, 1988: The line between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi began to be fondly referred to as &quot;JR Takarazuka Line.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 13, 1988: The line between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi began to be referred to fondly as the &quot;JR Takarazuka Line.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 13, 1988: The line between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi began to be referred to fondly as the &quot;JR Takarazuka Line.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>大阪～篠山口間に「ほくせつライナー」運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The operation of &quot;Hokusetsu Liner&quot; began between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Hokusetsu Liner&quot; began operating between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Hokusetsu Liner&apos; began operating between Osaka and Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="244">
<j>JR宝塚線については当初は新三田までであったが、発表直後に多紀郡（現篠山市）が反発し、篠山口までとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;JR Takarazuka Line&quot; was first used for the line up to Shinsanda; however, people in Taki-gun (Sasayama City) complained about it and the section was extended up to Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;JR Takarazuka Line&quot; was first used for the line up to Shinsanda; however, people in Taki-gun (Sasayama City) complained about it and the section was extended to Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;JR Takarazuka Line&quot; was first used for the line up to Shin-Sanda; however, people in Taki-gun (Sasayama City) complained about it and the section was extended to Sasayamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="245">
<j>1993年（平成5年）3月18日 - JR西日本207系電車投入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 18, 1993: JR (West) Commuter Trains Series 207 was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 18, 1993: The JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207 was introduced.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 18, 1993: The JR (West) Commuter Train Series 207 was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="246">
<j>1996年（平成8年）12月1日 - 広野～古市間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1, 1996: The section between Hirono and Furuichi was doubly tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1, 1996: The section between Hirono and Furuichi was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1, 1996: The section between Hirono and Furuichi was double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="247">
<j>1997年（平成9年）3月8日 - 新三田～広野間、古市～篠山口間が複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 8, 1997: The sections between Shinsanda and Hirono and between Furuichi and Sasayamaguchi were doubly tracked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 8, 1997: The sections between Shinsanda and Hirono and between Furuichi and Sasayamaguchi were double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 8, 1997: The sections between Shin-Sanda and Hirono and between Furuichi and Sasayamaguchi were double-tracked.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>JR東西線を経て片町線と直通運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The operation that connected the line with the Katamachi Line through the Tozai Line began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The operation that connected the line with the Katamachi Line through the Tozai Line began.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The operation that connected the line with the Katamachi Line through the JR Tozai Line began.</e>
<cmt>JR 追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="249">
<j>9月1日 - 普通列車がJR京都線と直通運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 1: The Local train services began directly to the JR Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 1: The local train services began running directly to the JR Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1: The local train services began running directly to the JR Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>それに伴い国鉄201系電車・国鉄205系電車運用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, JNR/JR Commuter Trains Series 201 and 205 began to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 201 and 205 came into use.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 201 and 205 came into use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="251">
<j>2000年（平成12年）3月11日 - 「丹波路快速」運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 11, 2000: The Tambaji Rapid Service began operating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 11, 2000: The Tambaji Rapid Service began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 11, 2000: The Tambaji Rapid Service began operating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="252">
<j>12月2日 - 篠山口～福知山間の一部列車でワンマン運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 2: The operation without a conductor on board began for some trains that ran between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 2: The operation without a conductor on board began for some trains that ran between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 2: The operation without a conductor on board began for some trains that ran between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="253">
<j>2002年（平成14年）10月5日 - 「ほくせつライナー」廃止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 5, 2002: &quot;Hokusetsu Liner&quot; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 5, 2002: The &quot;Hokusetsu Liner&quot; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 5, 2002: The &apos;Hokusetsu Liner&apos; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="254">
<j>2003年（平成15年）8月 - 国鉄103系電車運行終了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 2003: JNR/JR Commuter Trains Series 103 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 2003: The JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 103 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 2003: The JNR/JR Commuter Train Series 103 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="70">
<sen id="255">
<j>2003年（平成15年）12月1日 - 快速の停車駅に中山寺駅追加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1, 2003: Nakayamadera Station was added to the stations at which Rapid trains stopped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1, 2003: Nakayamadera Station was added to the stations at which rapid trains stopped.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1, 2003: Nakayamadera Station was added to the stations at which rapid trains stopped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="71">
<sen id="256">
<j>2004年（平成16年）10月16日 - 急行「だいせん (列車)」廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 16, 2004: The Express train &quot;Daisen&quot; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 16, 2004: The &quot;Daisen&quot; express train was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 16, 2004: The Express &apos;Daisen&apos; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>Express としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>夜行列車が消滅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The night train services disappeared completely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Night-train services disappeared completely.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Night-train services disappeared completely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="72">
<sen id="258">
<j>2005年（平成17年）4月25日 - 尼崎～塚口間でJR福知山線脱線事故。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 25, 2005: The JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident occurred between Amagasaki and Tsukaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 25, 2005: The JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident occurred between Amagasaki and Tsukaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 25, 2005: The JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident occurred between Amagasaki and Tsukaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="259">
<j>死者107名、負傷者555名の大惨事に。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The accident was a catastrophe in which 107 people were killed and 555 people were injured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The accident was a catastrophe in which 107 people were killed and 555 people were injured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The accident was a catastrophe in which 107 people were killed and 555 people were injured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>これにより尼崎～宝塚間が不通となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the line was interrupted for quite a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the line was interrupted for quite a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the line between Amagasaki and Tsukaguchi was interrupted for quite a while.</e>
<cmt>尼崎～塚口を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>詳細はJR福知山線脱線事故を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more information, refer to JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more information, refer to the article on the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For more information, refer to the article on the JR Fukuchiyama Line Train Derailment Accident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="73">
<sen id="262">
<j>6月19日 - 尼崎～宝塚間運転再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 19: The operation between Amagasaki and Takarazuka was resumed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 19: The operation between Amagasaki and Takarazuka was resumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 19: The operation between Amagasaki and Takarazuka was resumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>尼崎～新三田間ATS-P使用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ATS-P system was introduced in the section between Amagasaki and Shinsanda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ATS-P system was introduced in the section between Amagasaki and Shinsanda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ATS-P system was introduced in the section between Amagasaki and Shin-Sanda.</e>
<cmt>Shin-Sanda としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR001形気動車、国鉄117系電車運行終了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KTR Limited Express (Diesel Cars) Series KTR001 and JNR/JR Suburban Trains Series 117 were discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR001 and JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 117 were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The KTR Limited Express (diesel car) Series KTR001 and JNR/JR Suburban Train Series 117 were discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="74">
<sen id="265">
<j>11月26日 - 福知山駅付近高架化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 26: The line near Fukuchiyama Station was elevated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 26: The line near Fukuchiyama Station was elevated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 26: The line near Fukuchiyama Station was elevated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="75">
<sen id="266">
<j>12月1日 - JR西日本321系電車運行開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1: JR (West) Commuter Trains Series 321 began to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1: The JR (West) Commuter Train Series 321 came into use.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1: The JR (West) Commuter Train Series 321 came into use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="76">
<sen id="267">
<j>2006年（平成18年）2月 - 205系電車運行終了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 2006: The Trains Series 205 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 2006: The Train Series 205 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 2006: The Train Series 205 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>全編成阪和線に転属。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The series was transferred to the Hanwa Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The series was transferred to the Hanwa Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The series was transferred to the Hanwa Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="77">
<sen id="269">
<j>2007年（平成19年）3月 - 201系電車運行終了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 2007: The Trains Series 201 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 2007: The Train Series 201 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 2007: The Train Series 201 was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>KTR001形気動車がATS-P車上装置を設置の上で運行再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ATS-P system was installed in the train of KTR Diesel Cars Series 001 and its operation was resumed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ATS-P system was installed in the train of KTR Diesel Cars Series 001, and its operation was resumed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ATS-P system was installed in the train of KTR Diesel Cars Series 001, and its operation was resumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>将来の福知山線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Line in the future</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Future of the Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The future of the Fukuchiyama Line</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>伊丹駅と空港のアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access from Itami Station to the airport</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access from Itami Station to the airport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access from Itami Station to the airport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="271">
<j>現在、大阪国際空港（伊丹空港）には大阪高速鉄道が乗り入れているが、JRの路線は乗り入れていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Osaka Monorail Co., Ltd. currently has direct connection with Osaka International Airport (Itami Airport), no JR lines have been extended to the airport.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Osaka Monorail Co., Ltd., currently has a direct connection with Osaka International Airport (Itami Airport), no JR line has been extended to the airport.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Osaka Monorail Co., Ltd., currently has a direct connection with Osaka International Airport (Itami Airport), no JR line has been extended to the airport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>そこで伊丹空港に近いJR伊丹駅から伊丹空港までの空港アクセス路線を建設する「JR福知山線分岐線構想」と言われる構想がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an idea called &quot;JR Fukuchiyama Line Branch Track Plan&quot; in which an airport access railway from JR Itami Station, which is close to the Itami Airport, to the Itami Airport shall be constructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a concept called the &quot;JR Fukuchiyama Line Branch Track Plan,&quot; in which an airport access railway from JR Itami Station to the nearby Itami Airport would be constructed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a concept called the &apos;JR Fukuchiyama Line Branch Track Plan,&apos; in which an airport access railway from JR Itami Station to the nearby Itami Airport would be constructed.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>1990年代に入り一部筋から構想が持ち上がったが、猪名川を渡ったり滑走路を地下線で横断する必要があり大回りで建設費もかさむことから実現性の薄い構想といえる（建設主体や資金の手当てなどの現実的な案はない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This idea was proposed by a part of officials; however, it can be said that the possibility is very low because users would have to cross the runway which is crossing Ina-gawa River with a subway train and the line would have to make a big detour, and thus a large amount of construction cost would be required (no realistic proposal about, for example, the construction body and financing has been made).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This idea was proposed by a group of officials, but it can be said that the possibility is very low because users would have to cross the runway (which in turn crosses over the Ina-gawa River) via a subway train and the line would have to make a big detour, and thus a huge construction expense would be required (while no realistic proposal about, for example, the construction force and financing has been made).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This idea was proposed by a group of officials in the early 1990&apos;s, but it can be said that the possibility is very low because users would have to cross the runway (which in turn crosses over the Ina-gawa River) via a subway train and the line would have to make a big detour, and thus a huge construction expense would be required (while no realistic proposal about, for example, the construction force and financing has been made).</e>
<cmt>1990代に入り　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>しかも莫大な建設費の償還が必要な大阪モノレールを窮地に追い込むことからこの構想に異を唱える意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there are some people who express disagreement with this idea because it could drive Osaka Monorail Co., Ltd., which need the reimbursement of the huge construction cost, into a corner if this plan turns to reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, some have expressed disagreement with this idea because it could drive Osaka Monorail Co., Ltd., into a corner and it would need to have the construction cost reimbursed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, some have expressed disagreement with this idea because it could drive Osaka Monorail Co., Ltd., into a corner, which still needs to have its huge construction cost reimbursed.</e>
<cmt>文末に一部翻訳者さんの訳を組み込み、原文の意味に近くしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>現在は阪急が蛍池駅に快速急行（急行）を停車させ大阪モノレールとの連携を強化し、都心への所要時間を短縮したことにより本構想は代替されたともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Hankyu Railway provides Rapid Express (Express) trains that connects to Osaka Monorail at Hotarugaike Station to enhance the access, the time required to get to the city center has been reduced, and thus it may be said that &quot;JR Fukuchiyama Line Branch Track Plan&quot; has been replaced by this route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Hankyu Railway provides Rapid Express (express) trains that connect to Osaka Monorail at Hotarugaike Station for the sake of improved access, the time required to reach the city center has been reduced, and thus it can be said that &quot;JR Fukuchiyama Line Branch Track Plan&quot; has been replaced by this route.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Hankyu Railway provides Rapid Express (express) trains that connect to Osaka Monorail at Hotarugaike Station for the sake of improved access, the time required to reach the city center has been reduced, and thus it can be said that &quot;JR Fukuchiyama Line Branch Track Plan&quot; has been replaced by this route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>新駅設置計画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New station projects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New station projects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New station projects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="276">
<j>中山寺～宝塚間への新駅建設案が計画されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A new station construction project on the section between Nakayamadera and Takarazuka has been planned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A new station construction project on the section between Nakayamadera and Takarazuka has been planned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A new station construction project on the section between Nakayamadera and Takarazuka has been planned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>利用者の増加に役立つと見込まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is expected to increase users of the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is expected to increase the number of users of the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is expected to increase the number of users of the Fukuchiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>篠山口駅以北の複線化と現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prevalence and current situation of the double-track section above Sasayamaguchi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prevalence and current situation of the double-track section above Sasayamaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prevalence and current situation of the double-track section above Sasayamaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="278">
<j>丹波市は、篠山口～福知山間の単線区間を複線化をJR西日本に要望している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamba City has requested West Japan Railway Company to doubly track the single-track section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamba City has asked West Japan Railway Company to double-track the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, which is currently single-tracked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamba City has asked West Japan Railway Company to double-track the section between Sasayamaguchi and Fukuchiyama, which is currently single-tracked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="279">
<j>また丹波市は団体利用への運賃補助を行い、兵庫県も特急列車の料金補助を行う社会実験を実施している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamba City has been helping parties of users with their fare and Hyogo Prefecture has been implementing a pilot program in which fare for Limited Express trains is subsidized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamba City has been helping users with their fares, and Hyogo Prefecture has implemented a pilot program in which fares for limited express trains were subsidized.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamba City has been helping users who are party travelers with their group rates, and Hyogo Prefecture has implemented a pilot program in which fares for limited express trains were subsidized.</e>
<cmt>Tanba としました。団体料金の補助をしている、と解釈し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>そして兵庫県は「乗って 近づく 複線化」、などと呼びかけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyogo Prefecture has been declaring a slogan saying &quot;Let&apos;s promote double tracking by the use of the Fukuchiyama Line&quot; to the residents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyogo Prefecture has promoted the slogan, &quot;Let&apos;s encourage double-tracking through the use of the Fukuchiyama Line&quot; among residents.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyogo Prefecture has promoted the slogan, &apos;Let&apos;s encourage double-tracking through the use of the Fukuchiyama Line&apos; among residents.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>だが、2003年度の1日の乗車人員はこの区間の丹波大山駅から丹波竹田駅までの8駅を合わせても約3,600人であり、その多くが高校生であり、また篠山口駅以北では減少傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the ridership on this section between Tamba-Oyama Station and Tamba-Takeda Station per day in 2003, even as figures of all 8 stations on this section were added up, accounted for about 3,600 people, most of which were high school students, and furthermore, the ridership above Sasayamaguchi Station has been showing a downward trend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the ridership on this section between Tamba-Oyama Station and Tamba-Takeda Station per day in 2003, even as the figures for all eight stations on the section were added up, accounted for about 3,600 people, most of whom were high-school students; and furthermore, the ridership above Sasayamaguchi Station has shown a downward trend.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the ridership on this section between Tamba-Oyama Station and Tamba-Takeda Station per day in the fiscal 2003, even as the figures for all eight stations on the section were added up, accounted for about 3,600 people, most of whom were high-school students; and furthermore, the ridership above Sasayamaguchi Station has shown a downward trend.</e>
<cmt>2003年度　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>また、尼崎駅～篠山口駅間の駅間距離が平均約2.9km（快速停車駅のみでも平均約4.1km）であるのに対し、篠山口駅～福知山駅間の駅間距離は平均約5.3kmであり、福知山線沿線に自宅を構えていても自宅から駅まで距離がある世帯が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, while the average distance between stations on the section between Amagasaki Station and Sasayamaguchi Station is about 2.9Km (the average distance between stations for Rapid trains is about 4.1Km), the figure shows about 5.3Km on the section between Sasayamaguchi Station and Fukuchiyama Station, where quite a few people live along the Fukuchiyama Line yet far from a station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, while the average distance between stations on the section between Amagasaki Station and Sasayamaguchi Station is approximately 2.9km (the average distance between stations for rapid trains is about 4.1km), the figure indicates approximately 5.3km on the section between Sasayamaguchi Station and Fukuchiyama Station, where quite a few people live along the Fukuchiyama Line but are still far from a station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, while the average distance between stations on the section between Amagasaki Station and Sasayamaguchi Station is approximately 2.9 km (the average distance between stations for rapid trains is about 4.1 km), the figure indicates approximately 5.3 km on the section between Sasayamaguchi Station and Fukuchiyama Station, where quite a few people live along the Fukuchiyama Line but are still far from a station.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>その上、快速列車（丹波路快速を含む）は三田駅以北の72.8km（福知山線全営業キロの約68%）が各駅停車で利便性・速達性に乏しく、特別急行列車を利用するにしても特急料金が発生して交通費が高額になってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Rapid trains including trains of Tambaji Rapid Service stop every station on the 72.8-Km section above Sanda Station, which accounts for about 68% of the total operation kilometers of the Fukuchiyama Line, thereby resulting in poor convenience and promptness as well as expensive fare to take a Limited Express train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the rapid trains (including those of Tambaji Rapid Service) stop every station on the 72.8-km section above Sanda Station, which accounts for approximately 68% of the total operation kilometers of the Fukuchiyama Line, thereby resulting in poor convenience and promptness as well as the high fare of taking a limited express train.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the rapid trains (including those of Tambaji Rapid Service) stop every station on the 72.8-km section above Sanda Station, which accounts for approximately 68% of the total operation kilometers of the Fukuchiyama Line, thereby resulting in poor convenience and promptness as well as the high fare of taking a limited express train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>このため、電車よりも車でアクセスする人が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, many people living in this section use their own cars as a means of transportation instead of using a train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, many people living in this section use their cars as a means of transportation instead of taking a train.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, many people living in this section use their cars as a means of transportation instead of taking a train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="285">
<j>山間部ということもあり、複線化は困難な状態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given the fact that the railway lies in the mountains, the situation will be difficult to doubly track this section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the fact that the railway lies in the mountains, it will be difficult to double-track this section.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the fact that the railway lies in the mountains, it will be difficult to double-track this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="286">
<j>なお、篠山口駅から柏原駅までの間は谷川駅を経由するため遠回りをしており、さらに途中の川代渓谷は急曲線続きで速度が上がらず、たびたび崖崩れが発生し防災上も問題があることから、過去に何度か谷川駅を通らない鐘ヶ坂176号線沿いに鐘ヶ坂を越えるルートへの移設が検討されてきたが、現在の利用状況では新線の建設は困難と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People have often examined the idea of moving the section to the route where the train gets over Kanegasaka pass along National Highway 176 without stopping at Tanikawa Station because of the following three reasons; operating trains through Tanikawa Station in this section means an indirect path to run the train between Sasayamaguchi Station and Kaibara Station, the train cannot pick up speed due to many sharp curves along Kawashiro gorge, and this section has difficulties from the point of view of disaster prevention such as a landslide; accordingly, it seems very difficult to build a new route, given how this section has been used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People have often examined the idea of moving the section to a route whereby the train crosses Kanegasaka pass along National Highway 176 without stopping at Tanikawa Station because of the following three reasons: operation through Tanikawa Station in this section means an indirect path to run the train between Sasayamaguchi Station and Kaibara Station, the train can&apos;t pick up speed due to many sharp curves along Kawashiro Gorge, and this section has difficulties from the perspective of disaster prevention such as in the case of a landslide; accordingly, it seems very difficult to build a new route, given the manner in which this section has been used.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People have often examined the idea of moving the section to a route whereby the train crosses Kanegasaka pass along National Route 176 without stopping at Tanikawa Station because of the following three reasons: operation through Tanikawa Station in this section means an indirect path to run the train between Sasayamaguchi Station and Kaibara Station, the train can&apos;t pick up speed due to many sharp curves along Kawashiro Gorge, and this section has difficulties from the perspective of disaster prevention such as in the case of a landslide; accordingly, it seems very difficult to build a new route, given the manner in which this section has been used.</e>
<cmt>国道→national route としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="287">
<j>旧西紀町経由では丹波大山駅または下滝駅から谷川駅までが廃線になると見られることから、谷川駅に「現行ルートでの複線化」を求める横断幕があるのはこういった背景がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why a banner calling for &quot;doubly tracking without changing the route&quot; can be seen at Tanikawa Station is probably because the section between Tamba-Oyama Station or Shimotaki Station and Tanikawa Station will be dead track if the railway is moved to a route through old Nishiki-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason that a banner calling for &quot;double-tracking without changing the route&quot; can be seen at Tanikawa Station is probably because the section between Tamba-Oyama Station or Shimotaki Station and Tanikawa Station will be dead track if the railway is moved to a route through old Nishiki-cho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason that a banner calling for &apos;double-tracking without changing the route&apos; can be seen at Tanikawa Station is probably because the section between Tamba-Oyama Station or Shimotaki Station and Tanikawa Station will be dead track if the railway is moved to a route through old Nishiki-cho.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>駅一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of Stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of Stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of stations</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>営業中の区間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sections in business</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sections in Business</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sections in business</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>廃止区間（尼崎港線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discontinued sections (Amagasaki-ko Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discontinued sections (Amagasaki-ko Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discontinued sections (Amagasaki-ko Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="288">
<j>※1981年の旅客営業廃止直前のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* The section just before services for passengers were discontinued in 1981.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* The section just before services for passengers were discontinued in 1981.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* The section just before services for passengers were discontinued in 1981.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="289">
<j>尼崎港線の尼崎駅は東海道本線の駅とは約300m離れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amagasaki Station of the Amagasaki-ko Line was about 300m away from Amagasaki Station of the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>「東海道本線の尼崎駅とは、、」という解釈で訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagasaki Station of the Amagasaki-ko Line was approximately 300 m away from Amagasaki Station of the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagasaki Station of the Amagasaki-ko Line was approximately 300 m away from Amagasaki Station of the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>なお、塚口～尼崎間の実キロは約1.9kmだが、本線の同区間にあわせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The actual distance between Tsukaguchi Station and Amagasaki Station was about 1.9km; however, this distance was set up in accordance with that for the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The actual distance between Tsukaguchi Station and Amagasaki Station was about 1.9 km, but this distance was set up in accordance with that for the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The actual distance between Tsukaguchi Station and Amagasaki Station was about 1.9 km, but this distance was set up in accordance with that for the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>廃駅・廃止信号場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discontinued stations and signal stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discontinued stations and signal stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discontinued stations and signal stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="291">
<j>廃止区間（尼崎港線）にある駅を除く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except stations on the discontinued section (Amagasaki-ko Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This excludes stations on the discontinued section (Amagasaki-ko Line).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This excludes stations on the discontinued section (Amagasaki-ko Line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="292">
<j>本線（括弧内は尼崎駅起点の営業キロ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main line (the figure in parenthesis represents the operation kilometer from Amagasaki Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main line (the figure in parentheses represents the operation kilometer from Amagasaki Station)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main line (the figure in parentheses represents the operation kilometer from Amagasaki Station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="293">
<j>猪名川信号場 - 1918年廃止・伊丹～北伊丹間（約7.3km）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ina-gawa signal station: Discontinued in 1918, between Itami and Kita-Itami (about 7.3Km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ina-gawa signal station: Discontinued in 1918 between Itami and Kita-Itami (about 7.3km)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inagawa signal station: Discontinued in 1918 between Itami and Kita-Itami (about 7.3 km)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="294">
<j>花畑臨時駅 - 1903年廃止・川西池田～中山寺間（約13.4km）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanabatake provisional train station: Discontinued in 1903, between Kawanishiikeda and Nakayamadera (about 13.4Km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanabatake provisional train station: Discontinued in 1903 between Kawanishiikeda and Nakayamadera (about 13.4km)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanabatake provisional train station: Discontinued in 1903 between Kawanishiikeda and Nakayamadera (about 13.4 km)</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="295">
<j>惣川駅 - 1979年廃止・宝塚～生瀬間 (18.5km)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sogawa Station: Discontinued in 1979, between Takarazuka and Namaze (about 18.5Km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sogawa Station: Discontinued in 1979 between Takarazuka and Namaze (about 18.5km)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sogawa Station: Discontinued in 1979 between Takarazuka and Namaze (about 18.5 km)</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="296">
<j>福知駅 - 1909年廃止・丹波竹田～福知山間（約100.6km）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchi Station: Discontinued in 1909, between Tamba-Takeda and Fukuchiyama (about 100.6Km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchi Station: Discontinued in 1909 between Tamba-Takeda and Fukuchiyama (about 100.6km)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchi Station: Discontinued in 1909 between Tamba-Takeda and Fukuchiyama (about 100.6 km)</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="297">
<j>尼崎港線（括弧内は塚口駅起点の営業キロ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amagasaki-ko Line (the figure in parenthesis represents the operation kilometer from Tsukaguchi Station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagasaki-ko Line (the figure in parentheses represents the operation kilometer from Tsukaguchi Station)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagasaki-ko Line (the figure in parentheses represents the operation kilometer from Tsukaguchi Station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="298">
<j>長洲駅 - 1905年廃止・塚口～金楽寺間（約1.9km）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasu Station: Discontinued in 1905, between Tsukaguchi and Kinrakuji (about 1.9Km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasu Station: Discontinued in 1905 between Tsukaguchi and Kinrakuji (about 1.9km)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasu Station: Discontinued in 1905 between Tsukaguchi and Kinrakuji (about 1.9 km)</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="299">
<j>大物駅 - 1905年廃止・金楽寺～尼崎港間（約3.7km）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimotsu Station: Discontinued in 1905, between Kinrakuji and Amagasaki-ko (about 3.7Km).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimotsu Station: Discontinued in 1905 between Kinrakuji and Amagasaki-ko (about 3.7km)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimotsu Station: Discontinued in 1905 between Kinrakuji and Amagasaki-ko (about 3.7 km)</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>過去の接続路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Connected railways in the past</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Connected railways in the past</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Connected railways in the past</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="300">
<j>名称などは廃止時点のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The information including names is adopted at the time of the discontinuation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The information including names is current as of the time of discontinuation.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The information including names is current as of the time of discontinuation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="301">
<j>川西池田駅：能勢電鉄妙見線（能勢電鉄国鉄前線）（川西国鉄前駅）- 1981年12月20日廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawanishiikeda Station on the Myoken Line owned by Nose Electric Railway Co.,Ltd. (Nose Electric Railway before JNR) (Kawanishi-Kokutetsumae Station): Discontinued on December 20, 1981.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawanishiikeda Station on the Myoken Line, owned by Nose Electric Railway Co., Ltd. (Nose Electric Railway before JNR) (Kawanishi-Kokutetsumae Station): Discontinued on December 20, 1981</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawanishiikeda Station on the Myoken Line, owned by Nose Electric Railway Co., Ltd. (Nose Electric Railway before JNR) (Kawanishi-Kokutetsumae Station): Discontinued on December 20, 1981</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="302">
<j>三田駅：国有鉄道有馬線 - 1943年7月1日休止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanda Station on the JNR Arima Line: Suspended on July 1, 1943.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanda Station on the JNR Arima Line: Suspended on July 1, 1943.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanda Station on the JNR Arima Line: Suspended on July 1, 1943.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="303">
<j>篠山口駅：</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasayamaguchi Station:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasayamaguchi Station:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasayamaguchi Station:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="304">
<j>国鉄篠山線 - 1972年3月1日廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JNR Sasayama Line: Discontinued on March 1, 1972.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JNR Sasayama Line: Discontinued on March 1, 1972.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JNR Sasayama Line: Discontinued on March 1, 1972.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="305">
<j>篠山鉄道（篠山駅） - 1944年3月21日廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasayama Railway (Sasayama Station): Discontinued on March 21, 1944.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasayama Railway (Sasayama Station): Discontinued on March 21, 1944.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasayama Railway (Sasayama Station): Discontinued on March 21, 1944.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="306">
<j>福知山駅：北丹鉄道 - 1971年3月2日休止、1974年2月28日廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Station of the Hokutan Railway: Suspended on March 2, 1971 and discontinued on February 28, 1974.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama Station of the Hokutan Railway: Suspended on March 2, 1971 and discontinued on February 28, 1974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Station of the Hokutan Railway: Suspended on March 2, 1971 and discontinued on February 28, 1974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kakiemon(id:137948), Tosiaki(id:51926), Famsis(id:19853), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), 北大(id:110491), Yossy-(id:44838), Fucchy(id:13475), Tagaru(id:30411), Mop(id:12061), JONL(id:37424), Sen-K(id:17895), 継之助(id:39352), 湘新特快(id:17263), 5816K(id:102574), Yas(id:739), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Alive(id:88260), Kuha(id:7282), 韓国と音楽を愛する男(id:59246), 黄金雲(id:19508), Bergmann(id:85282), Utsuda(id:605), 素館(id:20524), Rusk(id:9895), はま(id:93561), Yasu2006(id:93004), 東トウ(id:21350), Kouchiumi(id:19253), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Kyoutanabe124(id:175304), Oosakasi(id:198604), Mutumi06(id:82739), 三菱善次郎(id:21924), CC(id:4162), Tokacyan(id:24008), Tabasuko0123(id:121792), Zell(id:23939), Bakkai(id:7233), FREEZA(id:68069), 暇・カキコ(id:65563), Sunen(id:10700), Ｈｏｚ(id:63526), Kone(id:377), Hirotaro(id:1437), Kenken3919(id:14848), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), ＳＴＫ(id:29099), Tam0031(id:165560), MASA(id:2399), Makiharashouten(id:1021), びぜん海月(id:71707), Sat.K(id:3751), Mover(id:7146), Kaiba21(id:108650), 鈴原みさきち(id:168059), お掃除大好き(id:99320), 220.(id:7930), Shinkansen(id:13703), Krisgrotius(id:92154), Myochu(id:17622), Miya(id:1881), Rislimric(id:54531), Unamu(id:14627), 本屋(id:125948), 663highland(id:18755), Chikara1983(id:59556), 210.(id:9838), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>