<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>嵐電天神川駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>嵐電天神川駅（らんでんてんじんがわえき）は、京都府京都市右京区太秦下刑部町にある京福電気鉄道京福電気鉄道嵐山本線の鉄道駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Uzumasa-shimokeibu-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station is a stop on the Arashiyama Main Line, which is operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station, located in Uzumasa-shimokeibu-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Arashiyama Main Line, which is operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station, located in Uzumasa-shimokeibu-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Arashiyama Main Line, which is operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>駅ナンバリングはA6。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station number is A6.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station number is A6.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station number is A6.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>開業の経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of opening the station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the station&apos;s opening</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the station&apos;s opening</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>2008年1月16日に開業した京都市営地下鉄京都市営地下鉄東西線の二条駅〜太秦天神川駅間延伸開業に伴い、蚕ノ社駅〜山ノ内駅 (京都府)間に同線太秦天神川駅との乗り換えのための駅として設置されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station was to built as a station for transferring to Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station, between Kaikonoyashiro Station and Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture), along with the extension of the Tozai Line, Kyoto City Subway Line, the section between Nijo Station and Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station, which was opened on January 16, 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station was built as a station for transfers to Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station between Kaikonoyashiro Station and Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture), along with the extension of the Tozai Line, Kyoto City Subway Line, and the section between Nijo Station and Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station, which was opened on January 16, 2008.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station was built as a station for transfers to Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station between Kaikonoyashiro Station and Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture), along with the extension of the Tozai Line of the Kyoto Municipal Subway between Nijo Station and Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station, which was opened on January 16, 2008.</e>
<cmt>city→ municipal　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同線の延伸から2か月余り遅れての開業となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station was opened two months after the extension of the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station was opened two months after the extension of the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station was opened two months after the extension of the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>開業までの2か月ほどの期間は、隣の蚕ノ社駅が乗り換え駅としての役割を担っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the opening of the station, a period of two months, the neighboring Kaikonoyashiro Station served as a transfer station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the station&apos;s opening, for a period of two months the neighboring Kaikonoyashiro Station served as a transfer point.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the station&apos;s opening, for a period of two months the neighboring Kaikonoyashiro Station served as a transfer point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>設置費用の6億4300万円のうちの6億1600万円は京都市が負担し、2007年11月中に着工した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Out of the construction costs of 643 million yen, Kyoto Prefecture funded 616 million yen, and the construction began in November 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The total construction cost was 643 million yen, of which Kyoto Prefecture funded 616 million yen, and the construction began in November 2007.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The total construction cost was 643 million yen, of which Kyoto Prefecture funded 616 million yen, and the construction began in November 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>京福電鉄にとって、既設路線の中間駅新設は、1956年開業の鹿王院駅に次いで、52年ぶりで2駅目である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station was a second station (next to Rokuoin Station opened in 1956) in 52 years for the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. to newly build an intermediate station on the existing line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station marked the second time (after Rokuoin Station, which opened in 1956) in 52 years that the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., built a new, intermediate station on the existing line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station marked the second time (after Rokuoin Station, which opened in 1956) in 52 years that the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., built a new, intermediate station on the existing line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお臨時駅の中間駅としては、現えちぜん鉄道のえちぜん鉄道三国芦原線仁愛グランド前駅が、京福電鉄時代の1992年に開業した例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, a temporary intermediate station that was built by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. in 1992 is Jinai Ground-mae Station on the Mikuni-awara Line, currently operated by the Echizen Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, a temporary intermediate station built in 1992 by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., is Jinai Ground-mae Station on the Mikuni-awara Line, currently operated by the Echizen Railway.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, a temporary intermediate station built in 1992 by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., is Jinai Ground-mae Station on the Mikuni-awara Line, currently operated by the Echizen Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>京阪京津線が同日から京都市役所前駅から同駅に乗り入れ区間を延伸したため、同線・京阪石山坂本線沿線から当駅を介して乗り換えが可能になり、嵐山・嵯峨野へのアクセスが便利になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section which the Keihan Keishin Line enters was extended from Kyoto Shiyakusho-mae Station to Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station on the same date, which allowed passengers to transfer at Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station from the Keihan Keishin Line and the Keihan Ishiyama-sakamoto Main Line, thereby improving access to Arashiyama and Sagano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section that the Keihan Keishin Line enters was extended from Kyoto Shiyakusho-mae Station to Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station on the same date, allowing passengers to transfer at Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station from the Keihan Keishin Line and Keihan Ishiyama-sakamoto Main Line, thereby improving access to Arashiyama and Sagano.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section that the Keihan Keishin Line enters was extended from Kyoto Shiyakusho-mae Station to Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station on the same date, allowing passengers to transfer at Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station from the Keihan Keishin Line and Keihan Ishiyama-sakamoto Main Line, thereby improving access to Arashiyama and Sagano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s layout</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>相対式ホーム（停留場）2面2線を持つ地上駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station is an aboveground station with two separate platforms serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station is an aboveground station with two separate platforms serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station is an aboveground station with two separate platforms serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>併用軌道区間であるが、安全地帯 (交通)ではなくプラットホームが設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station is in a tramway section situated on the road, there are provided platforms, not a safety zone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station is in a tramway section situated on the road, platforms are provided instead of a safety zone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station is in a tramway section situated on the road, platforms are provided instead of a safety zone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ホーム全体を覆う上屋が設置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A roof covers the entire platforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A roof covers the platforms in their entirety.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A roof covers the platforms in their entirety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、地下鉄駅の出口から嵐電天神川駅までの通路にも屋根が設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, a roof covers the passage that connects the exit of the subway station and Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, a roof covers the passage that connects the exit of the subway station and Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, a roof covers the passage that connects the exit of the subway station and Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>通常は駅員無配置駅となるが、多客期の週末を中心に駅員が配置される予定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Staff is not usually stationed at Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station, but staff is going to be stationed mainly on weekends in tourist seasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Staff aren&apos;t usually stationed at Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station, but staff will be stationed mainly on weekends during the tourist seasons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Staff aren&apos;t usually stationed at Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station, but staff will be stationed mainly on weekends during the tourist seasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>計画当初は、三条通東側歩道に隣接するように設置される予定だったが、現在のように三条通北行き南行き車線の中央に設置されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When planned, the station was going to be built adjacent to the sidewalk to the east of the Sanjo-dori Street; now the station stands in the center of the Sanjo-dori Street, on the north and south ways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station, at the planning phase, was going to be built adjacent to the sidewalk east of Sanjo-dori Street; now the station stands in the center of Sanjo-dori Street, on the north and south ways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station, at the planning phase, was going to be built adjacent to the sidewalk east of Sanjo-dori Street; now the station stands in the center of Sanjo-dori Street, on the north and south ways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>太秦天神川駅（京都市営地下鉄東西線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station (Tozai Line, Kyoto City Subway Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station (Tozai Line, Kyoto City Subway Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station (Tozai Line, Kyoto Municipal Subway)</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Municipal Subway　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>SANSA右京（右京区総合庁舎・京都市交通局）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SANSA Ukyo (Government Office of Ukyo Ward and Kyoto City Transportation Bureau)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SANSA Ukyo (Government Office of Ukyo Ward and the Kyoto City Transportation Bureau)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SANSA Ukyo (Government Office of Ukyo Ward and the Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau)</e>
<cmt>京都市交通局→Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>2008年3月28日 - 開業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station was opened on March 28, 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station opened on March 28, 2008.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 28, 2008: The station opened.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表現に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>京福電気鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>嵐山本線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arashiyama Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arashiyama Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arashiyama Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>山ノ内駅 (京都府) A5 - 嵐電天神川駅 A6 - 蚕ノ社駅 A7</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) A5 - Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station A6 - Kaikonoyashiro Station A7</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) A5 - Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station A6 - Kaikonoyashiro Station A7</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (A5) - Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station (A6) - Kaikonoyashiro Station (A7)</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせ、駅番号に括弧を付けました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>となりの蚕ノ社駅との駅間距離は、約250m、営業キロは0.2kmである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distance to the neighboring Kaikonoyashiro Station is about 250 m and the working kilometer is 0.2 km.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distance to the neighboring Kaikonoyashiro Station is approximately 250 m, and the working distance is 0.2 km.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distance to the neighboring Kaikonoyashiro Station is approximately 250 m, and the working distance is 0.2 km.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 マリンライン2(id:147814), Root253(id:196221), ぱむ(id:24323), Bergmann(id:85282), K-583(id:23250), Rislimric(id:54531), Tp2415(id:84801), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), 210.(id:9838), Atsasebo(id:95407), Pangelino(id:174296), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>