<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>河原町駅 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>河原町駅（かわらまちえき）は、京都府京都市下京区四条通河原町西入ル真町52にある、阪急電鉄阪急京都本線の終着駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawaramachi Station is located in 52 Shin-cho, Kawaramachi-Nishi-iru, Shijo-dori, Simogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture. It is the last station in the Hankyu Kyoto Main Line of Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawaramachi Station is the last station on the Hankyu Railway Hankyu Kyoto Main Line, and is located at 52 Shin-cho, Kawaramachi-Nishi-iru, Shijo-dori, Simogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻した。「located in」→「located at」、「in the」→「on the」、「Hankyo Kyoto Main Line of Hankyu Railway」→「Hankyu Railway Hankyu Kyoto Main Line」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawaramachi Station is the last station on the Hankyu Railway Hankyu Kyoto Main Line, and is located at 52 Shin-cho, Kawaramachi-Nishi-iru, Shijo-dori, Simogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>Outline→Summary</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>かつては京都の同社のターミナル駅であることを強調するため、「京都河原町駅」と呼んでいたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, to emphasize that it was a terminal station of the same company in Kyoto, it was once called &quot;Kyoto Kawaramachi Station&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was formerly called &apos;Kyoto Kawaramachi Station&apos;, in order to emphasize that it was a terminal station of the same company in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、「once」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was formerly called &apos;Kyoto Kawaramachi Station,&apos; in order to emphasize that it was a terminal station of the same company in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>カンマを&apos;の中に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一時期は単に「河原町」呼称となっていたが、現在は肉声放送・駅自動放送ともに「京都河原町」（英語表記は 「Kawaramachi （Kyoto）」）の呼称に戻された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it was named &quot;Kawaramachi&quot; for a certain period of time, the voice broadcasting and the automatic station broadcasting now both returned to the name &quot;Kyoto Kawaramachi&quot; (The English transcription is &quot;Kawaramachi (Kyoto)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it was called &quot;Kawaramachi&quot; for a while, the name has changed back to &quot;Kyoto Kawaramachi&quot; (&quot;Kawaramachi (Kyoto)&quot; when noted in English) in both live announcements and automatic station broadcasting.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻した。「certain period of」削除、「English transcription」→「noted in English」、「voice broadcasting」→「live announcements」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it was called &apos;Kawaramachi&apos; for a while, the name has changed back to &apos;Kyoto Kawaramachi&apos; (&apos;Kawaramachi (Kyoto)&apos; when noted in English) in both live announcements and automatic station broadcasting.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>烏丸駅までは地下道でつながっており、徒歩10分ほどでたどり着ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It connects in the underpass as far as Karasuma Station in 10 minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is connected to Karasuma Station by an underpass, which can be traveled in 10 minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is connected to Karasuma Station by an underpass, which can be traveled in 10 minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただしそれは「地下街」ではなくあくまで「地下道」であって、そこに駅売店・案内所などを除くと店舗などはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is not the usual the &quot;underground shopping center&quot; at all. It is simply an &quot;Underpass&quot; with no store etc. except perhaps for the station stall and the information office, etc..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is simply an &apos;underpass&apos;, and not the usual &apos;underground shopping center: except for the station kiosk, the information office and other essentials, there are no shops.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻した。「station stall」→「station kiosk」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is simply an &apos;underpass,&apos; and not the usual &apos;underground shopping center&apos;: except for the station kiosk, the information office and other essentials, there are no shops.</e>
<cmt>カンマを&apos;の中にshopping centerの後に&apos;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>当駅から接続する鉄道路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway route connected from this station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway routes connected to at this station</e>
<cmt>「s」挿入、「connected from」→「connected to at」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway routes connected to at this station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>京阪電気鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>会社名というよりは路線名なのでCo., Ltd.削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>京阪本線（四条駅 (京阪)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Main Line (Shijo Station (Keihan))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Main Line (Shijo Station (Keihan))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Main Line (Shijo Station (Keihan))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>乗り換えは一度地上に出て、四条大橋を渡る必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For transfer, it is necessary to go out to the ground level once, and cross the Shijyo-Ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To transfer, it is necessary to go up to ground level and cross the Shijyo-Ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>「For transfer」→「To transfer」、「go up to」→「go out to」、「level once, and」→「level and」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To transfer, it is necessary to go up to ground level and cross the Shijo-Ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>Shijyo-Ohashi→Shijo-Ohashi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>相互の乗り換えアナウンスはないが、当駅、京阪四条駅ともに、連絡通路に相手方の駅の発車時刻表を掲出して便宜を図っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though there is no mutual announcement for each other&apos;s transfer, this station, with Keihan Shijo Station, is considering of posting our each other&apos;s train timetables along the connecting passage for our passengers&apos; convenience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though neither line makes transfer announcements, both this station and Keihan Shijo Station are considering posting the other&apos;s train timetables along the connecting passage for their passengers&apos; convenience.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though neither line makes transfer announcements, both this station and Keihan Shijo Station are considering posting the other&apos;s train timetables along the connecting passage for their passengers&apos; convenience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>四条通の直下にあり、プラットホーム形状と配置1面3線の地下駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right under of the Shijo-dori Street, it is an underground station with 3 lines running along one side of the platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is underground, located directly beneath Shijo-dori Street, with single-level side platforms and 3 tracks.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。「right under of the」→「located directly beneath」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is underground, located directly beneath Shijo-dori Street, with single-level side platforms and 3 tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>四条河原町交差点南東角の阪急百貨店、及び同北東角のコトクロス阪急河原町、両方にビル外面に「阪急河原町駅」と表記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an underground station right under the Shijo-dori Street with a platform of 1 level and 3 tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Kawaramachi Station&apos; is written on the exteriors of both the Hankyu Department Store, on the southeast corner of the Shijo-Kawaramachi intersection, and the Kotocross Hankyu Kawaramachi building, on the northeast corner of the same intersection.</e>
<cmt>再翻訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Kawaramachi Station&apos; is written on the exteriors of both the Hankyu Department Store, on the southeast corner of the Shijo-Kawaramachi intersection, and the Kotocross Hankyu Kawaramachi building, on the northeast corner of the same intersection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>改札口は東改札・中央改札の2か所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 2 ticket gates; East Gate and Central Gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are 2 ticket gates: the east gate and the central gate.</e>
<cmt>「;」→「:」、「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are 2 ticket gates: the east gate and the central gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>2号線ホームに直結する西改札は2007年3月17日に閉鎖された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The west ticket gate connected directly with the second line platform was closed on March 17, 2007.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The west ticket gate, which connected directly to the Track 2 platform, was closed on March 17, 2007.</e>
<cmt>「gate connected」→「gate which connected」、「directly with」→「directly to」、コンマ挿入 「second line」→「Track 2」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The west ticket gate, which connected directly to Platform 2, was closed on March 17, 2007.</e>
<cmt>「2号線ホーム」の表記を「No.番線」の表記に統一変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（同日のダイヤ改正後、2号線ホームは1日1本しか使用しなくなったためとみられる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The low usage rate of the second line platform is thought to be the reason; only one train daily on the same day after the train schedule revision.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(This is thought to be because of the Track 2 platform&apos;s low usage rate; after the train schedule revision on March 17, 2007, the platform was used by only one train per day.)</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(This is thought to be because of Platform 2&apos;s low usage rate; after the train schedule revision on March 17, 2007, the platform was used by only one train per day.)</e>
<cmt>「2号線ホーム」の表記を「No.番線」の表記に統一変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>便所はプラットホーム東端にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lavatory is on the east end of the platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The restrooms are at the east end of the platform.</e>
<cmt>「lavatory」→「restrooms」、「are at」→「is on」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The restrooms are at the east end of the platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>1号線はかつて京阪本線の淀屋橋駅同様に同一線路を2つのホームとして使用していた時代があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, there was a time when the first line, like Yodoyabashi Station of Keihan Main Line, was being used with 2 platforms serving the same railway track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Track 1 was once served by two platforms, as at Yodoyabashi Station on the Keihan Main Line.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。「first line」→「Track 1」「was being used with」→「was served by」、「like」→「as at」、「of」→「on the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 1 was once served by two platforms, as at Yodoyabashi Station on the Keihan Main Line.</e>
<cmt>「1号線」の表記を「No.番線」の表記に統一変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>長編成化に伴い、この扱いは廃止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the longer catenation of carriages, this design is abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As trains grew longer, this method of use was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As trains grew longer, this method of use was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、通常は1・3号線のみを使用し、2号線は殆ど使用しておらず、1日1本のみ使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, only the first and the third lines were usually used. The second line was hardly used; only one train per day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, only Tracks 1 and 3 were used on a regular basis; Track 2 was used by only one train per day.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻した。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, only Platform 1 and 3 are used on a regular basis; Platform 2 is used by only one train per day.</e>
<cmt>現在の話なので、were→are, was→is「No.号線」の表記を「No.番線」の表記に統一変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（錆取り列車のためと思われる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is thought that it was for holding carriages for rust removal.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is thought to have been used to hold cars for rust removal.)</e>
<cmt>「that it was for holding」→「to have been used to hold」、「carriages」→「cars」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is thought to have been used to hold cars for rust removal.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>どのホームからどの種別という決まりはないが、昼間の時間帯は1号線より特別急行列車、3号線より準急列車が発車している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there is no regulations for which type of trains is to depart from which platform, in daytime, Limited Express trains start from the first line and semi-express trains start from the third line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While there are no set rules regarding which type of train departs from which platform, during the daytime hours, Limited Express trains depart from Track 1 and semi-express trains depart from Track 3.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While there are no set rules regarding which type of train departs from which platform, during the daytime hours, Limited Express trains depart from Platform 1 and semi-express trains depart from Platform 3.</e>
<cmt>「No.号線」の表記を「No.番線」の表記に統一変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、快速急行などの列車はすべて1号線発着となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, trains such as the Rapid Express etc. all use the first line for arrival and departure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Track 1 is used for the arrival and departure of Rapid Expresses and all other such trains.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Track 1 is used for the arrival and departure of Rapid Expresses and all other such trains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">state of usage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usage status</e>
<cmt>「state of usage」→「usage status」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usage status</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>繁華街である四条河原町へ向かう人も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also a lot of people heading toward Shijo-Kawaramachi, a bustling street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many people who head towards bustling Shijo-Kawaramachi.</e>
<cmt>「also a lot of people heading」→「many people who head」、「Shijo-Kawaramachi, a bustling street」→「bustling Shijo-Kawaramachi」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many people who head towards bustling Shijo-Kawaramachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>平成15年度の1日あたりの乗車人員は約38,164人（京都府統計書より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fiscal year 2003, the number of passengers getting on each day was about 38,164. (From Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Book)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Fiscal Year 2003, approximately 38,164 passengers boarded each day (Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Book).</e>
<cmt>「the」削除、「from」削除、再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Fiscal Year 2003, approximately 38,164 passengers boarded each day (Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Book).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vicinity of station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station vicinity</e>
<cmt>「Vicinity of station」→「Station vicinity」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station vicinity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>駅周辺およびバスのりばについては四条河原町を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the vicinity of the station and the bus terminals, please refer to Shijo-Kawaramachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please see Shijo-Kawaramachi for information regarding bus terminals and the station vicinity.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please see Shijo-Kawaramachi for information regarding bus terminals and the station vicinity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）6月17日 京都本線大宮駅 (京都府)～河原町間延伸により開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 17, 1963, trains started running between Omiya Station of Kyoto Main Line (Kyoto Prefecture) and Kawaramachi because of the extension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, 1963, because of a route extension, trains began running between the Kyoto Main Line&apos;s Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Kawaramachi.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 17, 1963: Because of a route extension, trains began running between the Kyoto Main Line&apos;s Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Kawaramachi.</e>
<cmt>日付の On を外し、表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>1982年（昭和57年）8月20日 2号線ホーム延伸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 20, 1982, the second line platform was extended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 20, 1982, the Track 2 platform was extended.</e>
<cmt>「second line」→「Track 2」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 20, 1982: Platform 2 was extended.</e>
<cmt>日付の On を外し、表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>駅名について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the station name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station name</e>
<cmt>「About the」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>地元の住民は、当駅付近一帯を呼称する時にはあくまでも四条通と河原町通の交差点名である「四条河原町」と呼ぶことが多く、ここを指す地名として「河原町」や「（阪急）河原町駅前」と呼ぶことはほとんどない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local citizens, when referring to the region near this station, often call it &quot;Shijo-Kawaramachi &quot;, which is the name of the intersection between Shijo-dori Street and Kawaramachi-dori Street. Almost never do people call here &quot;Kawaramachi&quot; or &quot;front of (Hankyu) Kawaramachi Station&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Locals usually refer to the area near the station as &apos;Shijo-Kawaramachi&apos;, which is the name of the Shijo-dori Street and Kawaramachi-dori Street intersection; they almost never call it &apos;Kawaramachi&apos; or &apos;(Hankyu) Kawaramachi Station-front area&apos;.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻した。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Locals usually refer to the area near the station as &apos;Shijo-Kawaramachi,&apos; which is the name of the Shijo-dori Street and Kawaramachi-dori Street intersection; they almost never call it &apos;Kawaramachi&apos; or &apos;(Hankyu) Kawaramachi Station-front area.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマとピリオドを&apos;の中に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ただし、京都市民でも中心部の住民以外は「河原町」あるいは「四条」と呼ぶことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kyoto citizens except the residents in the central region often call here &quot;Kawaramachi&quot; or &quot;Shijo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, except for residents of this central region, even Kyoto citizens often call the area &apos;Kawaramachi&apos; or &apos;Shijo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, except for residents of this central region, even Kyoto citizens often call the area &apos;Kawaramachi&apos; or &apos;Shijo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを&apos;の中に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>京都市民の感覚としては、「河原町」はあくまでも京都市内の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Kyoto citizens, &quot;Kawaramachi&quot; is simply like a street inside Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To residents of Kyoto, &quot;Kawaramachi&quot; is simply a street in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>「like」削除、「inside」→「in」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To residents of Kyoto, &apos;Kawaramachi&apos; is simply a street in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その一方で最近では、観光ガイドブックやグルメガイドなどで「河原町エリア」などといった用法で、この付近一帯を指す名称として「河原町」が用いられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, recently, tourist guidebooks or gourmet guidebooks etc. often refer to here as &quot;Kawaramachi area&quot; or &quot;Kawaramachi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, recent tourist guidebooks or gourmet guides often refer to this area as &apos;Kawaramachi area&apos; or &apos;Kawaramachi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「recently」→「recent」、「refer to here」→「refer to this area」、コンマ削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, recent tourist guidebooks or gourmet guides often refer to this area as &apos;Kawaramachi area&apos; or &apos;Kawaramachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを&apos;の中に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>これは四条烏丸や四条大宮でもほぼ同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is almost the same as the places like Shijo-Karasuma and Shijo-Omiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation is similar to that of Shijo-Karasuma and Shijo-Omiya.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation is similar to that of Shijo-Karasuma and Shijo-Omiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これらの場所では、バス停の名称も「○○駅（前）」とはなっておらず、前記の各交差点名がバス停の名称となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these places, the name of a bus stop does not become &quot;front of OOstation&quot; either. Instead, the above-mentioned intersection names become the names of the bus stops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these places, the bus stops are named after the intersection names, and not &apos;______ Station-front&apos;.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these places, the bus stops are named after the intersection names, and not &apos;______ Station-front.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを&apos;の中に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>一方、京都駅前や二条駅前は「○○駅（前）」がバス停の名称であり、地元の住民も「京都駅（前）」などと呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the bus stop in front of Kyoto Station front or Nijo Station is call &quot;front of OO station &quot;. For example, local citizens also call it &quot;front of Kyoto Station&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, bus stops in front of Kyoto Station or Nijo Station are called &quot;______ Station-front&quot;, even by locals.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, bus stops in front of Kyoto Station or Nijo Station are called &apos;______ Station-front,&apos; even by locals.</e>
<cmt>カンマを&apos;の中に原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>なお、当駅の駅名に「四条」が冠されていないのは、市内において阪急京都線が四条通の直下を走っているためと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why the station&apos;s name is not prefixed with &quot;Shijo&quot; is that, it may get confused with the Hankyu Kyoto Line which is running right under of Shijo-dori Street in the city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s name is not prefixed with &apos;Shijo&apos; because it might then be easily confused with the Hankyu Kyoto Line, which runs through the city directly beneath Shijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station&apos;s name is not prefixed with &apos;Shijo&apos; because it might then be easily confused with the Hankyu Kyoto Line, which runs through the city directly beneath Shijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>（烏丸御池駅を除き地下鉄烏丸線に「烏丸」が冠されていないのと同様である）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Except for Karakorum-Oike Station, subway stations along Karasuma Line are not prefixed with &quot;Karasuma&quot; by similar reason.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Except for Karasuma-Oike Station, subway stations along the Karasuma Line are not prefixed with &apos;Karasuma&apos; for similar reasons.)</e>
<cmt>「Karakorum-Oike」→「Karasuma-Oike」、「by」→「for」、「s」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Except for Karasuma-Oike Station, subway stations along the Karasuma Line are not prefixed with &apos;Karasuma&apos; for similar reasons.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The neighboring station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>「the」削除、「s」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>阪急電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>■京都本線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Main Line</e>
<cmt>■を削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>■通勤特急・■特急・■快速急行・■準急・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">commuting special express・ special express・ fast express・ semi-express・ local</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">special commuter express・ special express・ fast express・ semi-express・ local</e>
<cmt>「commuting special express」→「special commuter express」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">special commuter express/special express/fast express/semi-express/local</e>
<cmt>・を/に変更しました。■を削除しました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>烏丸駅 - 河原町駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasuma Station - Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma Station - Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma Station - Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), 城山(id:104901), Hirofumitouhei(id:104137), Ideal(id:236), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Wikipedianet(id:9608), KARS(id:43022), Tigers boy(id:15761), Fanvio(id:116155), 準急三条(id:25072), Kinori(id:443), Loveless(id:129239), 鍛高譚(id:154933), Kone(id:377), Hirotaro(id:1437), Yas(id:739), 捕澤(id:23785), Mizumono(id:606), Kumoha590(id:47430), Gargoyle(id:49233), J o(id:26533), Carbuncle(id:346), Etopirica(id:32491), MASA(id:2399), Ikaxer(id:61759), Utsuda(id:605), Shinkansen(id:13703), Bukang-liwayway(id:89706), Miyuki h(id:84952), Rusk(id:9895), Matsukaze(id:51778), Ktr(id:30468), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Kouchiumi(id:19253), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Mochi(id:9489), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Alma mater(id:45042), オナガドリ(id:15179), Takatetu(id:3231), Ariesmarine(id:70919), Learnpoint(id:186718), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>