<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大久保駅 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okubo Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okubo Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okubo Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大久保駅（おおくぼえき）は、京都府宇治市広野町西裏81番地の2にある、近畿日本鉄道近鉄京都線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located at 81-2 Nishiura Hirono-cho Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture, Okubo Station is a stop on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line of the Kintetsu Railways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okubo Station, located at 81-2 Nishiura Hirono-cho Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line of Kintetsu Railways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okubo Station, located at 81-2 Nishiura, Hirono-cho, Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line of Kintetsu Railways.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>島式2面4線のプラットホームを持つ、待避設備を備えた高架駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okubo station is an elevated rail station, with two island type platforms (one platform serving two tracks), equipped with safety measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okubo Station is an elevated rail facility with two island-type platforms (one platform serving two tracks), and equipped with safety measures.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okubo Station is an elevated station with two island-type platforms serving four tracks, and is equipped with passing facilities.</e>
<cmt>「退避施設」の箇所など訳し直しました。This is closer is meaning to the Japanese, I think.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ホーム有効長は6両。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The useful length of the platform is for six cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The platform has a length sufficient to accommodate six cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The platform has a length sufficient to accommodate six cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>改札口は1ヶ所のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is only one location of the ticket gates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ticket gates are found in only one location.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ticket gates are found in only one location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>なお自動改札機は東芝製が設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The automatic ticket gates manufactured by Toshiba are set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The automatic ticket gates were manufactured by Toshiba.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The automatic ticket gates were manufactured by Toshiba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>赤い自動改札機（EG-2000）は出場時2枚一括処理、PiTaPa・ICOCAに対応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The red automatic ticket gate (EG-2000) can treat two tickets collectively when exiting, and accepts PiTaPa/ICOCA cards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The red automatic ticket gate (EG-2000) can treat two tickets collectively when exiting, and it accepts PiTaPa/ICOCA cards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The red automatic ticket gate (EG-2000) can treat two tickets collectively when exiting, and it accepts PiTaPa/ICOCA cards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>京都府宇治市、城陽市内にある近畿日本鉄道京都線の6つの駅（小倉駅・伊勢田駅・大久保駅・久津川駅・寺田駅・富野荘駅）のうち、唯一急行の停車する駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the only station at which express trains stop among 6 stations (Ogura Station, Iseda Station, Kutsukawa Station, Terada Station, Tonosho Station and Okubo Station) on Kintetsu Kyoto Line in Uji City and Joyo City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of six stations (Ogura Station, Iseda Station, Kutsukawa Station, Terada Station, Tonosho Station and Okubo Station), this is the only one at which express trains stop on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line in Uji City and Joyo City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of six stations (Ogura Station, Iseda Station, Kutsukawa Station, Terada Station, Tonosho Station and Okubo Station), this is the only one at which express trains stop on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line in Uji City and Joyo City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また乗降客数は6駅中最も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the biggest number of the passengers among 6 stations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has the largest number of the passengers among the six stations.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has the largest number of the passengers among the six stations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>絵に描いた様な、都市型の高架2面4線駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a modern style elevated rail station with two platforms and four tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a modern-style, elevated rail station with two platforms and four tracks.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a modern-style, elevated rail station with two platforms and four tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>特急券・定期券とも購入可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited express tickets and season tickets can be available at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Limited express tickets and season tickets can be obtained at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limited express tickets and commuter passes can be purchased at this station.</e>
<cmt>定期券→commuter pass としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>バリアフリー対策も比較的早期に実施され、コンコース・ホーム間の移動のエスカレーターと、コンコースから上下線のホームへ向かうエレベーターが設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Barrier-free facilities, such as the escalator between concourse and platform, and the elevators which connect concourse and each platform, were installed relatively early.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Barrier-free facilities, such as the escalator between the concourse and the platform, and the elevators that connect the concourse with each platform, were installed relatively early.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Barrier-free facilities, such as the escalator between the concourse and the platform, and the elevators that connect the concourse with each platform, were installed relatively early.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>地上時代はホームの両端を踏切に挟まれており、5両編成までしか停車できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the station was on the ground, five-cars train was the limit of the train length because there were railroad-crossings at both ends of platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the station was at ground level, it was limited to serving five-car trains because there were railroad crossings at both ends of the platform.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the station was at ground level, it was limited to serving five-car trains because there were railroad crossings at both ends of the platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>高架化によってこの制約はなくなり、6両編成が停車できるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the station was elevated, six-cars trains could stop at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the station was elevated, six-cars trains could stop at the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the station was elevated, six-cars trains could stop at the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>高架下には、飲食や食料品など、乗客の利便を考慮した店舗施設が軒を連ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the elevated rail tracks: There are restaurants, grocery stores for passengers&apos; convenience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the elevated rail tracks: There are restaurants and grocery stores for the convenience of passengers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the elevated rail tracks, there are restaurants and grocery stores for the convenience of passengers.</e>
<cmt>There→there</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="17">
<j>市営駐輪場があり、自転車および原動機付自転車（一種・二種）を停めることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bicycles and motorized bicycles (1st, 2nd class) can be stopped at the municipal bicycle parking area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bicycles and motorized bicycles (first and second class) can be kept in the municipal bicycle parking area.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bicycles and motorized bicycles (categories one and two) can be left in the municipal bicycle parking area.</e>
<cmt>免許の種類を、一種・二種→categories one and two としました。The English is fine but I can&apos;t be sure whether &quot;categories&quot; is the appropriate word. I have changed &quot;kept&quot; to &quot;left&quot; as &quot;keep&quot; sounds a bit permanent to me.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>一時利用・月極契約ともに可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both temporary use and monthly contract use are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temporary usage and monthly contracts are available.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temporary usage and monthly contracts are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="19">
<j>月極駐車場もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a month-to-month parking area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also an area for month-to-month parking.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also an area for month-to-month parking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="20">
<j>駅の西側はバスターミナルとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bus terminal is in the west side of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bus terminal is located at the west side of the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bus terminal is located at the west side of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>宇治市内・城陽市・久御山町・京都市伏見区等に向かう京阪宇治バス等の乗り場が設けられている（後述のバスの欄参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some bus stops such as Keihan Uji Bus for inside Uji City, Joyo City, Kumiyama-cho and for Fushimi Ward Kyoto City. (Refer to the &quot;Bus&quot; section below.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some bus stops such as Keihan Uji Bus for points within Uji City, Joyo City, Kumiyama-cho and for Fushimi Ward in Kyoto City (see the &quot;Bus&quot; section below).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some bus stops such as Keihan Uji Bus for points within Uji City, Joyo City, Kumiyama-cho and for Fushimi Ward in Kyoto City (see the &quot;Bus&quot; section below).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="22">
<j>駅の東側はタクシーのりば、おりばと、市営有料駐車場（42台・時間制）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a taxi stand and municipal pay parking lot (capacity: 42 vehicles, charge by time) in the east side of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a taxi stand and municipal paid parking lot (capacity: 42 vehicles, charged by time) at the east side of the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a taxi stand and municipal paid parking lot (capacity: forty-two vehicles, charged by time) at the east side of the station.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="23">
<j>大久保駅を中心として、伊勢田駅方面は下り勾配、久津川駅方面も下り勾配となっており、発車後は下り勾配を用いて加速でき、両駅から大久保駅に向けて停車する際は上り勾配による減速が得られ、エネルギーを効率よく活かすことができるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lines toward both Iseda Station and Kutsukawa Station are downward-slopes. Therefore, trains run effectively by accelerating on down slope and slowing down on upward slope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lines toward both Iseda Station and Kutsukawa Station slope downward, so trains run efficiently by accelerating on the downslope and slowing down on the upward slope.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lines toward both Iseda Station and Kutsukawa Station slope downward, so trains run efficiently by accelerating on the downward slope after leaving Okubo station and slowing down on the upward slope when coming to a stop at Okubo Station having come from either of the two stations.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="24">
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utilization situation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conditions of usage</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger use</e>
<cmt>表現を他のl記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>2005年11月8日の調査結果によると、1日の利用客は28,635人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number of usage is 28,635 people according to the survey on November 8, 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a survey conducted on November 8, 2005, 28,635 people used the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a survey conducted on November 8, 2005, 28,635 people used the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="26">
<j>この数字は近鉄の全調査対象駅（323駅、但し調査当時の数）中、24位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This station ranks 24th among whole Kintetsu stations surveyed (323 stations at that time.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This station ranks twenty-fourth among all the Kintetsu stations surveyed (323 stations at that time).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This station ranks twenty-fourth among all the Kintetsu stations surveyed (323 stations at that time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="27">
<j>京都線の駅（26駅、大和西大寺駅含む）の中では、5位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5th among stations on Kintetsu Kyoto Line (26 stations including Yamato-Saidaiji Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It ranked fifth among the stations on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line (26 stations. including Yamato-Saidaiji Station).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It ranked fifth among the stations on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line (twenty-six stations. including Yamato-Saidaiji Station).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="28">
<j>京都府内の近鉄の駅（23駅）の中では、3位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3rd among Kintetsu stations in Kyoto Prefecture (23 stations)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was third among the Kintetsu stations in Kyoto Prefecture (23 stations).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was third among the Kintetsu stations in Kyoto Prefecture (twenty-three stations).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="29">
<j>近鉄ホームページより</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the website of Kintetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the website of Kintetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the website of Kintetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="30">
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>近鉄京都線は京都盆地をほぼ一直線に縦断するが、その盆地の中央付近で東側の山地より張り出す丘陵地帯の頂上付近に大久保駅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kintetsu Kyoto Line runs straight through the Kyoto Basin and Okubo Station is located at the top of the steep range of hills which hang from the east side of mountains in the middle of the basin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kintetsu Kyoto Line runs straight through the Kyoto Basin, and Okubo Station is located at the top of a steep range of hills that flank the east side of the mountains in the middle of the basin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kintetsu Kyoto Line runs straight through the Kyoto Basin, and Okubo Station is located at the top of a steep range of hills that flank the east side of the mountains in the middle of the basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>本駅付近が連続立体交差になっているせいもあるが上下どちらの列車に乗車してもわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the line near the station is grade separated crossing, you can see that the station is on the top of the hills from inbound and outbound trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the line near the station is a grade-separated crossing, from the inbound and outbound trains one can see that the station is located atop the hills.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the line near the station is a grade-separated crossing, from the inbound and outbound trains one can see that the station is located atop the hills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="33">
<j>開業当時は京都府久世郡大久保村と広野村のちょうど間に駅が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the station was opened, it was set right between Okubo-mura and Hirono-mura in Kuse-gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the station was opened, it was set right between Okubo-mura and Hirono-mura in Kuse-gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the station was opened, it was set right between Okubo-mura and Hirono-mura in Kuse-gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="34">
<j>現在はその間は市街化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, the area between two stations is urban area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, however, the area between two stations is urban.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, however, the area between two stations is urban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="35">
<j>旧久世郡の中心部付近、宇治市の南西部に位置し、城陽市、久世郡久御山町も徒歩圏で、又西日本旅客鉄道奈良線と新田駅 (京都府)付近でX（エックス字）型に接し、バスターミナルから各方面へバス路線が張り巡らせられ、また駅のすぐそばにはレンタカーの店舗も数店あり、一体は山城地区（人口約60万人）の交通結節点、経済の中心地として今後の整備と発展が期待される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is located in the center of former Kuse-gun, south-west of Uji City. Joyo City and Kumiyama-cho Kuse-gun can be accessible on foot. The Kintetsu Nara Line runs along with the JR Nara Line of West Japan Railway Company and runs close to the JR Nara Line near Shinden Station as like X-line shape. Various bus routes are operated from the bus terminal and there are a few rent-car agencies next to the station. This area is expected to be developed in the future as a traffic and economic key area in Yamashiro Region (population : about 600,000).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is located in the center of the former Kuse-gun, southwest of Uji City, while Joyo City and Kumiyama-cho Kuse-gun are accessible on foot; the Kintetsu Nara Line runs along with the JR Nara Line of West Japan Railway Company and runs close to the JR Nara Line near Shinden Station in an &quot;X&quot; configuration. Various bus routes are operated from the bus terminal, and there are a few car rental agencies next to the station. This area is expected to develop in the future as a key traffic and economic area in Yamashiro region (population: approximately 600,000).</e>
<cmt>separate sentences</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is located in the center of the former Kuse-gun, southwest of Uji City, while Joyo City and Kumiyama-cho Kuse-gun are accessible on foot; the Kintetsu Nara Line runs along with the JR Nara Line of West Japan Railway Company and runs close to the JR Nara Line near Shinden Station in an &quot;X&quot; configuration; various bus routes are operated from the bus terminal, and there are a few car rental agencies next to the station; this area is expected to develop in the future as a key traffic and economic area in Yamashiro region (population: approximately 600,000).</e>
<cmt>文章を一つにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="36">
<j>陸上自衛隊大久保駐屯地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Camp Okubo of Japan Ground Self-Defense Force (JGSDF)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Camp Okubo, of the Japan Ground Self-Defence Force (JGSDF)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Camp Okubo, of the Japan Ground Self-Defense Force (JGSDF)</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>日産車体京都工場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Plant of Nissan shatai Co., Ltd</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Plant of Nissan Shatai Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Plant of Nissan Shatai Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>宇治税務署</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uji Tax Office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uji Tax Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji Tax Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>日産学園京都自動車専門学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nissan Technical School Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nissan Technical School Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nissan Technical School Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>京都府立城南高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Jyonan Senior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Jyonan Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Jonan Senior High School</e>
<cmt>&quot;Jyonan&quot;→&quot;Jonan&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>立命館宇治中学校・高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsumeikan Uji Junior &amp; Senior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsumeikan Uji Junior &amp; Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsumeikan Uji Junior &amp; Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>宇治市立大久保小学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okubo Elementary School, Uji City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okubo Elementary School, Uji City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okubo Elementary School, Uji City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>近鉄ケーブルネットワーク(KCN)京都支店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Branch of Kintetsu Cable Network (KCN)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Branch of Kintetsu Cable Network (KCN)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Branch of Kintetsu Cable Network (KCN)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>サティ (チェーンストア)大久保店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SATY (chain store) Okubo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SATY (chain store), Okubo</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SATY (chain store), Okubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>イズミヤ大久保店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumiya (chain store) Okubo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumiya (chain store), Okubo</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumiya (chain store), Okubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>京都府道15号宇治淀線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto prefectural road No.15, Uji Yodo Route</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 15, Uji Yodo Route</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji Yodo Line of Kyoto Prefectural Route 15</e>
<cmt>道路表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>銀行、生命保険、損害保険等の金融機関多数</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">there are many financial offices such as banks, life insurance companies and nonlife insurance companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many financial offices such as banks, life-insurance companies and non-life insurance companies.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many financial offices such as banks, life-insurance companies and non-life insurance companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="48">
<j>バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>当駅から各地に向かう多数の路線バスが発着している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many bus routes from this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many bus routes from this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many bus routes from this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>一部に京阪シティバスがあるが大半の路線は京阪宇治バスである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them are Keihan Uji Bus, some are Keihan City Bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them are part of Keihan Uji Bus, but some are part of Keihan City Bus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them are part of Keihan Uji Bus, but some are part of Keihan City Bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="51">
<j>1番のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus station #1</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus station No. 1</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stop No. 1</e>
<cmt>bus stop としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>58A 宮ノ谷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">58A bound for Miyanotani</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 58A, bound for Miyanotani</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 58A : bound for Miyanotani</e>
<cmt>カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>54A 独立行政法人国立療養所南京都病院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">54A bound for NHO (=National Hospital Organization) Minami-Kyoto Hospital of independent administrative institution</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 54A, bound for NHO (=National Hospital Organization) Minami-Kyoto Hospital of the Independent Administrative Institution</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 54A : bound for NHO (=National Hospital Organization) Minami-Kyoto Hospital of the Independent Administrative Institution</e>
<cmt>カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>2番のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus station #2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus station No. 2</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stop No. 2</e>
<cmt>bus stop としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>21・21A 日産車体→淀駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">21・21A bound for Nissan Shatai to Yodo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nos. 21・21A, bound for Nissan Shatai to Yodo Station</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nos. 21, 21A : bound for Nissan Shatai to Yodo Station</e>
<cmt>カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>22A・22C・4・6 日産車体→久御山団地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">22A・22C・4・6 bound for Nissan Shatai to Kumiyama-danchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nos. 22A・22C・4・6, bound for Nissan Shatai to Kumiyama-danchi</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nos. 22A, 22C, 4, 6 : bound for Nissan Shatai to Kumiyama Danchi (residential complex)</e>
<cmt>カンマからコロンに変更しました。Residential complex と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>新宿・渋谷行夜行高速バス（東京ミッドナイトエクスプレス宇治号）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Midnight Highway bus bound for Shinjuku ・Shibuya (Tokyo Midnight Express Uji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Midnight Highway&quot; bus, bound for Shinjuku ・Shibuya (Tokyo Midnight Express Uji)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Midnight Highway&quot; bus, bound for Shinjuku and Shibuya (Tokyo Midnight Express Uji)</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>3番のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus station #3</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus station No. 3</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stop No. 3</e>
<cmt>bus stop としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>35 緑ヶ原・小倉→宇治車庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">35 bound for Midorigahara・Ogura to Uji-shako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 35, bound for Midorigahara・Ogura to Uji-shako</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 35 : bound for Midorigahara, Ogura to Uji-shako Depot</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>35B 小倉・宇治→京都府立菟道高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">35B bound for Ogura・Uji to Kyoto Prefectural Todo Senior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 35B, bound for Ogura・Uji to Kyoto Prefectural Todo Senior High School</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 35B : bound for Ogura, Uji to Kyoto Prefectural Todo Senior High School</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>23・23A・25・26B 久御山団地→ジャスコ久御山店前・中書島駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">23・23A・25・26B bound for Kumiyama Danchi to Jusco Kumiyama, Chushojima Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nos. 23・23A・25・26B, bound for Kumiyama Danchi to Jusco Kumiyama, Chushojima Station</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nos. 23, 23A, 25, 26B : bound for Kumiyama Danchi to JUSCO Kumiyama, Chushojima Station</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。JUSCOとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>25 ジャスコ久御山店前→京阪中書島</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">25 bound for Jusco Kumiyama to Keihan Chushojima</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 25, bound for Jusco Kumiyama to Keihan Chushojima</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 25 : bound for JUSCO Kumiyama to Keihan Chushojima</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。JUSCOとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>26 栄町→久御山団地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">26 bound for Sakaemachi to Kumiyama Danchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 26, bound for Sakaemachi to Kumiyama Danchi</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 26 : bound for Sakaemachi to Kumiyama Danchi</e>
<cmt>カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>26C 栄町→久御山中央公園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">26C bound for Sakaemachi to Kumiyama Chuo Park</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 26C, bound for Sakaemachi to Kumiyama Chuo Park</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 26C : bound for Sakaemachi to Kumiyama Chuo Park</e>
<cmt>カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>310 堀池・小倉→宇治文化センター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">310 bound for Horiike･Ogura to Uji-bunka-center</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 310, bound for Horiike･Ogura to Uji-bunka-center</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 310 : bound for Horiike, Ogura to Uji-bunka-center (Uji city culture center)</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>27C 城南荘→宇治車庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">27C bound for Jonanso to Uji shako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 27C, bound for Jonanso to Uji shako</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 27C : bound for Jonanso to Uji-shako Depot</e>
<cmt>カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>4番のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus station #4</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus station No. 4</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stop No. 4</e>
<cmt>bus stop としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>240・240A 立命館宇治高校・植物公園→宇治駅 (京阪)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">240・240A bound for Ritsumeikan Uji High School・Botanical Park to Uji Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nos. 240・240A, bound for Ritsumeikan Uji High School・Botanical Park to Uji Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nos. 240, 240A : bound for Ritsumeikan Uji High School, Botanical Park to Uji Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>250・250A 立命館宇治高校・植物公園→西日本旅客鉄道黄檗駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">250・250A bound for Ritsumeikan Uji High School・Botanical Park to JR West Obaku Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nos. 250・250A, bound for Ritsumeikan Uji High School・Botanical Park to JR West Obaku Station</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nos. 250, 250A : bound for Ritsumeikan Uji High School, Botanical Park to JR West Obaku Station</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>5番のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus station #5</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus station No. 5</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stop No. 5</e>
<cmt>bus stop としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>21・22A・22C・23・23A・27 宇治駅 (京阪)・宇治車庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">21・22A・22C・23・23A・27 Uji Station (Keihan)・Uji Shako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nos. 21・22A・22C・23・23A・27, Uji Station (Keihan)・Uji Shako</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nos. 21, 22A, 22C, 23, 23A, 27 : Uji Station (Keihan), Uji-shako Depot</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>6 城南荘・太陽が丘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">6 Jonanso･Taiyogaoka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No. 6, Jonanso･Taiyogaoka</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No. 6 : Jonanso, Taiyogaoka</e>
<cmt>・→and に変更しました。カンマからコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="73">
<j>他の鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other railroad</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other railroads</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other railroads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>新田駅 (京都府)（西日本旅客鉄道奈良線）…東に徒歩5分ほど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinden Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (JR West Nara Line) five minutes walk to the east</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinden Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (JR West Nara Line) is a five-minute walk to the east.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinden Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (JR West Nara Line) is a five-minute walk to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="75">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）11月3日 奈良電気鉄道桃山御陵前～西大寺（現・大和西大寺駅）間開通時に開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station opened on November 3, 1928 as a station of Nara Electric Railway when the line between Momoyamagoryomae Station and Saidaiji Station (now, Yamato-Saidaiji Station) was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station opened on November 3, 1928 as a station of Nara Electric Railway when the line between Momoyamagoryomae Station and Saidaiji Station (the present-day Yamato-Saidaiji Station) was opened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 3, 1928: The station opened as a station of Nara Electric Railway when the line between Momoyamagoryomae Station and Saidaiji Station (the present-day Yamato-Saidaiji Station) was opened.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>相対式2面2線の地上駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is on the ground, has two separate platforms and two tracks which run in opposite directions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is on the ground, has two separate platforms and two tracks that run in opposite directions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station was on the ground, had two separate platforms and two tracks that ran in opposite directions.</e>
<cmt>時制を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="78">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）10月1日 会社合併により近畿日本鉄道の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station became one of the stations of the Kintetsu Railways due to the amalgamation on October 1, 1963.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station became one of the stations of Kintetsu Railways due to the amalgamation that occurred on October 1, 1963.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1963: The station became one of the stations of Kintetsu Railways due to the amalgamation.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="79">
<j>従来の位置から北へ約200mの場所に仮駅舎が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temporary station-house was set up at 200 m north from the previous place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temporary station-house was set up 200 meters north of the regular location.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temporary station-house was set up 200 meters north of the regular location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>その後1987年（昭和62年）12月14日 高架化工事完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railroad elevating work was completed on December 14, 1987.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railroad elevation work was completed on December 14, 1987.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 14, 1987: Subsequently the railroad elevation work was completed.</e>
<cmt>subsequentlyを追加しました。年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>同時に仮駅舎付近に上下線共待避線付きの高架駅に改築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the station was also rebuilt as an elevated station equipped with safety measures near the temporary station-house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concurrently with that process, the station was rebuilt as an elevated station equipped with safety measures near the temporary station house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While this work was underway, the station was rebuilt as an elevated station equipped with passing loops near the temporary station house.</e>
<cmt>「退避線」をpassing loops としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="82">
<j>2007年（平成19年）4月1日 PiTaPa使用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 2007, PiTaPa card was made available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 2007, the PiTaPa card became available.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 1, 2007: The PiTaPa card became available.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="83">
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>近畿日本鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>京都線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>■急行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Express</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Express</e>
<cmt>■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>桃山御陵前駅 - 大久保駅 - 新田辺駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momoyamagoryomae Station - Okubo Station - Shin-Tanabe Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momoyamagoryomae Station - Okubo Station - Shin-Tanabe Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momoyamagoryomae Station - Okubo Station - Shin-Tanabe Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>■準急・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Semi-express・■Local</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Semi-express・■Local</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Semi-express/Local</e>
<cmt>・は/にしました。■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>伊勢田駅 - 大久保駅 - 久津川駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iseda Station - Okubo Station - Kutsukawa Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iseda Station - Okubo Station - Kutsukawa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iseda Station - Okubo Station - Kutsukawa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hideyuki(id:9577), Bakkai(id:7233), 城山(id:104901), Pixan(id:24280), Nnh(id:474), FREEZA(id:68069), Makiharashouten(id:1021), Felicemente(id:43126), Yellow Submarine(id:107099), Wikipedianet(id:9608), お掃除大好き(id:99320), Ikaxer(id:61759), Shinkansen(id:13703), Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), Bandalgom(id:31841), Kouchiumi(id:19253), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Unamu(id:14627), Wepco(id:74148), Twilight2640(id:134273), Loveless(id:129239), Kone(id:377), Hirotaro(id:1437), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Mipu(id:5360), 210.(id:9838), Riden(id:27573), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Hirohisat(id:128431), LERK(id:4460), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>