<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東山三条駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama-sanjo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama-sanjo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama-sanjo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東山三条駅（ひがしやまさんじょうえき）は、かつて京都市東山区三条大和大路下ル古川町にあった京阪電気鉄道京阪京津線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama-sanjo Station was a stop on the Keihan Keishin Line operated by the Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd., which was located in Furukawa-cho, Sanjoyamato-oji Kudaru, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama-sanjo Station, located in Furukawa-cho, Sanjoyamato-oji Kudaru, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, was a stop on the Keihan Keishin Line operated by the Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama-sanjo Station, located in Furukawa-cho, Sanjoyamato-oji Kudaru, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, was a stop on the Keihan Keishin Line operated by the Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1997年の京都市営地下鉄東西線開業に伴い京津線三条駅 (京都府)～御陵駅間が廃止されたことで廃駅となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station was abandoned when the section between Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Misasagi Station on the Keishin Line was abandoned due to the opening of the Tozai Line, Kyoto City Subway Line in 1997.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station was abandoned when the section between Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Misasagi Station on the Keishin Line ceased operations due to the opening of the Tozai Line, Kyoto City Subway Line, in 1997.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station was abandoned when the section between Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Misasagi Station on the Keishin Line ceased operations due to the opening of the Tozai Line, Kyoto Municipal Subway Line, in 1997.</e>
<cmt>city →municipal　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>三条通（旧国道1号）上に設けられた電停タイプの駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama-sanjo Station was a stop provided on the Sanjo-dori Street (old National Route No. 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama-sanjo Station was a stop provided on Sanjo-dori Street (the old National Route No. 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama-sanjo Station was a stop provided on Sanjo-dori Street (the old National Route 1).</e>
<cmt>No.を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ステップを備えた車両しか停車できない関係から、普通列車のみの停車駅で、急行（1981年廃止）・準急は通過していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only local trains would stop at Higashiyama-sanjo Station as the station was adapted only to the cars having steps; Express trains (discontinued in 1981) and local express trains passed the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only local trains would stop at Higashiyama-sanjo Station, because the facility was adapted only to cars having steps; express trains (discontinued in 1981) and local express trains would bypass the station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only local trains would stop at Higashiyama-sanjo Station, because the facility was adapted only to cars having steps; express trains (discontinued in 1981) and sub-express trains would bypass the station.</e>
<cmt>準急→sub-expressとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>南北に走る東大路通の東側に対向式のホームがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opposing platforms were located to the east of the Higashioji-dori Street which runs in the south-north direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opposing platforms were located to the east of Higashioji-dori Street, which runs in the south-north direction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opposing platforms were located to the east of Higashioji-dori Street, which runs in the south-north direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>1978年9月までは東山通を走る京都市電東山線と平面交差しており、市電の東山三条駅との乗換駅でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until September 1978, the Keishin Line would cross at grade with the Higashiyama Line of the Kyoto City Tram, which would run on the Higashiyama-dori Street, and Higashiyama-sanjo Station served as a transfer station to Higashiyama-sanjo Station of the Kyoto City Tram.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until September 1978, the Keishin Line would cross at grade with the Higashiyama Line of the Kyoto City Tram, which would run on Higashiyama-dori Street, and Higashiyama-sanjo Station served as a transfer station to Higashiyama-sanjo Station of the Kyoto City Tram.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until September 1978, the Keishin Line would cross at grade with the Higashiyama Line of the Kyoto City Trams, which would run on Higashiyama-dori Street, and Higashiyama-sanjo Station served as a transfer station to Higashiyama-sanjo Station of the Kyoto City Trams.</e>
<cmt>Tramsと複数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この東山線との間には、第二次世界大戦中に連絡線が設けられ、戦中戦後には市電側から屎尿輸送の貨物電車が京津線に乗り入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the World War II, a connecting line was provided between the Keishin Line and the Higashiyama Line, where freight trains for night-soil transportation entered the Keishin Line from the line of the Kyoto City Tram during and after the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During World War II, a connecting line was provided between the Keishin Line and the Higashiyama Line, where freight trains for night-soil transportation entered the Keishin Line from the line of the Kyoto City Tram during and after the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During World War II, a connecting line was provided between the Keishin Line and the Higashiyama Line, where freight trains for night-soil transportation entered the Keishin Line from the line of the Kyoto City Trams during and after the war.</e>
<cmt>Tramsと複数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後この連絡線は撤去されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This connecting line was removed later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This connecting line was later removed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This connecting line was later removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>1912年（大正元年）8月15日 - 京津電気軌道開業時に古川町駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 15, 1912 the station was opened as Furukawacho Station when the Keishin Electric Tramway was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, 1912, the facility opened as Furukawacho Station when the Keishin Electric Tramway was opened.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 15, 1912: The facility opened as Furukawacho Station when the Keishin Electric Tramway was opened.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表現に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>1950年（昭和25年）1月7日 - 上り線乗り場に安全地帯を設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 7, 1950 a platform were provided for an inbound track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7, 1950, a platform was provided for an inbound track.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 7, 1950: A safety zone was provided on the inbound platform.</e>
<cmt>safety zone としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>1950年（昭和25年）11月25日 - 駅名を東山三条と改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 25, 1950 the station was renamed Higashiyama-sanjo Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 25, 1950, the station was renamed as Higashiyama-sanjo Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 25, 1950: The station was renamed as Higashiyama-sanjo Station.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表現に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>1997年（平成9年）10月12日 - 廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 12, 1997 the station was abandoned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 12, 1997, the station was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 12, 1997: The station was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表現に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>京阪電気鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>京津線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keishin Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keishin Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keishin Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>三条駅 (京都府) - 東山三条駅 - （平安神宮前駅 - 岡崎道駅） - 蹴上駅 (京阪)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Higashiyama-sanjo Station - (Heianjingu-mae Station - Okazaki-michi Station) - Keage Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Higashiyama-sanjo Station - (Heianjingu-mae Station - Okazaki-michi Station) - Keage Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Higashiyama-sanjo Station - (Heianjingu-mae Station - Okazaki-michi Station) - Keage Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>接続路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Connecting rail lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Connecting rail lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Connecting rail lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>京都市電東山線 - 1912年（大正元年）12月25日の開業時から「東山三条」を名乗っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Tram, Higashiyama Line - The station had been called &apos;Higashiyama-sanjo&apos; since it was opened on December 25, 1912.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Tram, Higashiyama Line: The station had been called &apos;Higashiyama-sanjo&apos; since its opening on December 25, 1912.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Trams, Higashiyama Line: The station had been called &apos;Higashiyama-sanjo&apos; since its opening on December 25, 1912.</e>
<cmt>Tramsと複数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 七之輔(id:55793), Useful(id:80591), Sunen(id:10700), ぱむ(id:24323), Unamu(id:14627), Kone(id:377), 春野秋葉(id:36725), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Goncyan(id:92158), オナガドリ(id:15179), Mkoba(id:9856), Shinkansen(id:13703), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>