<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京福電気鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京福電気鉄道株式会社（けいふくでんきてつどう）とは、京都市内で軌道事業（路面電車）とケーブルカー及び索道を運営している会社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. is a company that operates a tramway business (electric tramway), cable cars, and cableways in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. is a company that operates a tramway business (electric tramway), cable cars and cableways in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. is a company that operates a tramway business (electric tramway), cable cars and cableways in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大阪証券取引所に上場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. lists on the Osaka Securities Exchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., is listed on the Osaka Securities Exchange.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., is listed on the Osaka Securities Exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>以前は福井県内でも鉄道事業を行っていたが、2003年をもってえちぜん鉄道に譲渡し撤退したため、京都での軌道事業と福井での小規模な不動産業を残すのみとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. once operated a railway business in Fukui Prefecture, but after the railway business was transferred to the Echizen Railway in 2003: the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. only operates a tramway business in Kyoto Prefecture, as well as a small real estate business in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., once operated a railway business in Fukui Prefecture, but since the 2003 transfer of the railway business to the Echizen Railway the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., has only operated a tramway business in Kyoto Prefecture, as well as a small real-estate business in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., once operated a railway business in Fukui Prefecture, but since the 2003 transfer of the railway business to the Echizen Railway the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., has only operated a tramway business in Kyoto Prefecture, as well as a small real-estate business in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>以後、同社唯一の軌道事業として残る京福電気鉄道嵐山本線・京福電気鉄道北野線は、嵐電（らんでん）と呼ばれ親しまれており、2007年3月からそれが公式愛称となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the Arashiyama Main Line and Kitano Line remain as a tramway business operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., which are fondly called &apos;Randen,&apos; an official nickname given after March 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the Arashiyama Main Line and Kitano Line have remained as a tramway business operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., which are fondly called &apos;Randen,&apos; an official nickname used since March 2007.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the Arashiyama Main Line and Kitano Line have remained as a tramway business operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., which are fondly called &apos;Randen,&apos; an official nickname used since March 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>京福の社名は、鉄道事業を行っていた京都と福井の頭文字を採ったものだが、京都と福井を結ぶ鉄道計画があったわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company name Keifuku (京福) was named after Kyoto (Kei:京) Prefecture and Fukui (Fuku:福) Prefecture, where the company once operated the railway business; nevertheless, there was no plan to build a railway connecting Kyoto Prefecture and Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company name Keifuku (京福) was named after Kyoto (Kei: 京) Prefecture and Fukui (Fuku: 福) Prefecture, where the company once operated the railway business; however, there was no plan to build a railway connecting Kyoto and Fukui prefectures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company name Keifuku (京福) was named after Kyoto (Kei: 京) Prefecture and Fukui (Fuku: 福) Prefecture, where the company once operated the railway business; however, there was no plan to build a railway connecting Kyoto and Fukui prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>京都は祇園を始め夜間の電力需要が多く、福井は逆に織物工場が稼動する昼間の電力需要が多いため、互いの電力を融通するために前身の京都電燈が建設した「京福送電線」が語源となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company name, Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., was originated from the &apos;Keifuku Power Line&apos; which was provided by the Kyoto Dento (the former Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.) to mutually transmit power between Kyoto Prefecture and Fukui Prefecture; as Kyoto (e.g., Gion) had a large power demand during the night, whereas Fukui had a large power demand during the day for operating textile facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company name, Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., originated from the &apos;Keifuku Power Line&apos; which was provided by the Kyoto Dento (the former Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.) to mutually transmit power between the prefectures of Kyoto and Fukui, since Kyoto (e.g., Gion) had a large power demand during the night but Fukui had a large power demand during the day for the operation of textile facilities.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company name, Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., originated from the &apos;Keifuku Power Line&apos; which was provided by the Kyoto Dento, an electric power company (the former Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.), to mutually transmit power between the prefectures of Kyoto and Fukui, since Kyoto (e.g., Gion) had a large power demand during the night but Fukui had a large power demand during the day for the operation of textile facilities.</e>
<cmt>京都電燈の補足に、an electric power company としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>大正期には競合する京阪電気鉄道と激しく争ったが、のちに資本を受け入れ、2007年3月31日現在は京阪電気鉄道が42.89%の株式を保有し京阪グループに入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company actively competed with the Keihan Electric Railway during the Taisho era, but later accepted the capital; the Keihan Electric Railway, belonging to the Keihan Group, owns 42.89% of the shares as of March 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company actively competed with the Keihan Electric Railway during the Taisho era, but later it accepted the capital; the Keihan Electric Railway, belonging to the Keihan Group, owns 42.89% of the shares as of March 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company actively competed with the Keihan Electric Railway during the Taisho period, but later it accepted the capital; the Keihan Electric Railway, belonging to the Keihan Group, owns 42.89% of the shares as of March 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt>era→ period　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大株主として財務省 (日本)が8.33%の株式を保有しているが、これは以前の個人大株主の死去により、相続税の物納として同社株式が納められたことによるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ministry of Finance (Japan) also owns 8.33% of the shares as a major shareholder, which resulted from the payment of inheritance tax in kind by an individual shareholder after he was dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Finance (Japan) also owns 8.33% of the shares as a major shareholder, consequent upon the payment of inheritance tax in kind following the death of an individual shareholder.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Finance (Japan) also owns 8.33% of the shares as a major shareholder, consequent upon the payment of inheritance tax in kind following the death of an individual shareholder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このため会社組織上は第三セクターに分類されるが、経営参加を目的とした所有でないため、通常は企業とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the company falls into the category of joint public-private venture; however, as the company is owned by the Ministry of Finance not for the purpose of participation in management, it is usually regarded as a private company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the company is categorized as a joint public-private venture; however, as the company is owned by the Ministry of Finance (but not for the purpose of participation in management), it&apos;s usually referred to as a private company.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus the company is categorized as a joint public-private venture; however, as the company is owned by the Ministry of Finance (but not for the purpose of participation in management), it&apos;s usually referred to as a private company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>福井県では三国競艇場の施設を保有している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company owns Mikuni Kyotei, a boat race stadium, in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company owns Mikuni Kyotei, a boat-racing stadium, in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company owns Mikuni Kyotei, a boat-racing stadium, in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>配電統制令により、京都電燈が配電事業を関西配電（関西電力の前身）・北陸配電（北陸電力の前身）へ、発送電事業を日本発送電へ譲渡し解散するのに伴い、同社の京都（嵐山線・北野線・叡山線）と福井（越前電気鉄道線）での鉄軌道事業を引き継ぐため1942年に設立され、同年中に傍系の鞍馬電気鉄道・三国芦原電鉄が合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. was established in 1942 to succeed the railway and tramway business that was operated by the Kyoto Dento in Kyoto Prefecture (Arashiyama, Kitano, and Eizan Lines) and Fukui Prefecture (Echizen Electric Railway Line), with the dissolution of the Kyoto Dento to transfer the power distribution business to the Kansai-haiden Power Distribution (関西配電) (a predecessor of the Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc.) and the Hokuriku-haiden Power Distribution (北陸配電) (a predecessor of the Hokuriku Electric Power Company), and the electric generation and transmission business to the Japan Electric Generation and Transmission Company (日本発送電) under the power distribution control law (配電統制令); in the same year, the collateral companies, the Kurama Electric Railway and the Mikuni Awara Electric Railway (三国芦原電鉄) were merged into the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., was established in 1942 to succeed the railway and tramway business that was operated by the Kyoto Dento in Kyoto Prefecture (Arashiyama, Kitano and Eizan lines) and Fukui Prefecture (Echizen Electric Railway Line), with the dissolution of the Kyoto Dento to transfer the power-distribution business to the Kansai-haiden Power Distribution (関西配電) (a predecessor of the Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc.) and the Hokuriku-haiden Power Distribution (北陸配電) (a predecessor of the Hokuriku Electric Power Company), and the electric generation and transmission business to the Japan Electric Generation and Transmission Company (日本発送電) under the power distribution control law (配電統制令); in the same year, the collateral companies, the Kurama Electric Railway and the Mikuni Awara Electric Railway (三国芦原電鉄), were merged into the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., was established in 1942 to succeed the railway and tramway business that was operated by the Kyoto Dento in Kyoto Prefecture (Arashiyama, Kitano and Eizan lines) and Fukui Prefecture (Echizen Electric Railway Line), with the dissolution of the Kyoto Dento to transfer the power-distribution business to the Kansai-haiden Power Distribution (関西配電) (a predecessor of the Kansai Electric Power Co., Inc.) and the Hokuriku-haiden Power Distribution (北陸配電) (a predecessor of the Hokuriku Electric Power Company), and the electric generation and transmission business to the Japan Electric Generation and Transmission Company (日本発送電) under the power distribution control law (配電統制令); in the same year, the collateral companies, the Kurama Electric Railway and the Mikuni Awara Electric Railway (三国芦原電鉄), were merged into the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>1944年には永平寺鉄道・丸岡鉄道も合併し、1950年頃には京都と福井で合わせて120.9kmもの路線網を擁することになったが、モータリゼーションの進展に伴い1960年代から1980年代にかけて、不採算路線・区間の廃止や、叡山本線・鞍馬線を叡山電鉄として分社化するなどの合理化を進めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1944 the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. merged the Eihei-ji Railway and the Maruoka Railway (丸岡鉄道) as well, thereby owing the railway of as along as 120.9 km in Kyoto and Fukui Prefectures by around 1950; however, with the development of motorization, the company streamlined the businesses from 1960s to 1980s by the abandonment of unprofitable lines and sections or by spinning off the Eizan Main Line and the Kurama Line into the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1944, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. merged the Eihei-ji Railway and the Maruoka Railway (丸岡鉄道) as well, thereby taking ownership of as much as 120.0 km of railway in Kyoto and Fukui prefectures by around 1950; however, with the development of motorization the company streamlined the businesses from the 1960s to the &apos;80s with the abandonment of unprofitable lines and sections or by spinning off the Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line into the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1944, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. merged the Eiheiji Railway and the Maruoka Railway (丸岡鉄道) as well, thereby taking ownership of as much as 120.0 km of railway in Kyoto and Fukui prefectures by around 1950; however, with the development of motorization the company streamlined the businesses from the 1960s to the &apos;80s with the abandonment of unprofitable lines and sections or by spinning off the Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line into the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line).</e>
<cmt>Eiheiji Railway としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>2000年12月と2001年6月、福井の越前本線で僅か半年間に2度の電車同士の正面列車衝突事故（京福電気鉄道越前本線列車衝突事故を参照）を起こし、国土交通省から福井地区各線の列車運行停止を命ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 2000 and June 2001, within a period of only six months, the Keifuku Electric Railroad caused two frontal impact accidents of trains on the Echizen Main Line in Fukui Prefecture (refer to the section of train crashes on the Echizen Main Line of the Keifuku Electric Railroad) and was ordered to hold up the train operation on the lines in Fukui area by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 2000 and June 2001, within a period of only six months, the Keifuku Electric Railroad suffered two frontal impact accidents of trains on the Echizen Main Line in Fukui Prefecture (refer to the section concerning train crashes on the Echizen Main Line of the Keifuku Electric Railroad) and was therefore ordered by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism to hold up the train operation on the lines in the Fukui area.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 2000 and June 2001, within a period of only six months, the Keifuku Electric Railroad suffered two frontal impact accidents of trains on the Echizen Main Line in Fukui Prefecture (refer to the section concerning train crashes on the Echizen Main Line of the Keifuku Electric Railroad) and was therefore ordered by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism to hold up the train operation on the lines in the Fukui area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>京福電気鉄道は事業継続が困難になったとして、2003年に福井地区の鉄道事業（越前本線・三国芦原線）をえちぜん鉄道へ譲渡し撤退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to difficulty in continuing the business, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. transferred its railway business (the Echizen Main Line and the Mikuni-awara Line) operated in Fukui area to the Echizen Railway in 2003, thereby withdrawing from the railway business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the difficulty of continuing the business, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., transferred its railway business (the Echizen Main Line and Mikuni-awara Line) operated in the Fukui area to the Echizen Railway in 2003, thus withdrawing from the railway business.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the difficulty of continuing the business, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., transferred its railway business (the Echizen Main Line and Mikuni-awara Line) operated in the Fukui area to the Echizen Railway in 2003, thus withdrawing from the railway business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>越前本線からの撤退で京福は経営不安が表面化したため、2002年に保有する叡山電鉄の株式を全て京阪電鉄に売却している（親会社京阪による救済策とされる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the weak operation of the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. was brought to light by the withdrawal from the Echizen Main Line, all the shares of the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line) were sold to the Keihan Electric Railway in 2002 (this is supposedly the remedy by the parent company, the Keihan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the weak operations of the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., were brought to light by the withdrawal from the Echizen Main Line, all the shares of the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line) were sold to the Keihan Electric Railway in 2002 (which was supposedly a remedy taken by the parent company, the Keihan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the weak operations of the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., were brought to light by the withdrawal from the Echizen Main Line, all the shares of the Eizan Electric Railway were sold to the Keihan Electric Railway in 2002 (which was supposedly a remedy taken by the parent company, the Keihan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt>叡山電鉄→Eizan Electric Railway　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これにより、叡山電鉄は京阪電鉄の完全子会社となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line) became a wholly-owned subsidiary of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line) became a wholly owned subsidiary of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the Eizan Electric Railway became a wholly owned subsidiary of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>叡山電鉄→Eizan Electric Railway　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>なお、京福においては、過去にも1964年1月には当時の鞍馬線で正面衝突炎上事故を起こし、わずかその7ヶ月後の同年8月には、越前本線発坂付近で下り旅客列車が貨物列車に追突する事故を起こしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. caused the train frontal impact accident on the Kurama Line at the time in January 1964; and in August 1964, only after 7 months from the accident, it caused another train crash: the passenger train hit the freight train near Hossaka on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., suffered a train frontal impact accident on the Kurama Line during that period, in January 1964; and in August 1964, only seven months after the accident, it suffered another train crash in which a passenger train hit a freight train near Hossaka on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., suffered a train frontal impact accident in the past on the Kurama Line in January 1964; and in August 1964, only seven months after the accident, it suffered another train crash in which a passenger train hit a freight train near Hossaka on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt>in the past を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>またバス部門においても、1985年10月に2階建て観光バスが、中央自動車道においてガードレールを突き破り県道に転落する事故を起こし、乗客3名死亡、57名が重傷、運転していた乗務員は、その場で自殺するという痛ましい事故を起こしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the bus department caused a deadly accident in October 1985: the two-story sightseeing bus broke through the guardrail of the Chuo Jidosha-do Expressway to tumble onto the prefectural road, killing 3 passengers and injuring 57 passengers; the driver killed himself at the scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the bus division suffered a deadly accident in October 1985, in which a two-level sightseeing bus broke through the guardrail of the Chuo Jidosha-do Expressway and tumbled onto the prefectural road, killing three passengers and injuring 57 more; the driver killed himself at the scene.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the bus division suffered a deadly accident in October 1985, in which a two-level sightseeing bus broke through the guardrail of the Chuo Jidosha-do Expressway and tumbled onto the prefectural road, killing three passengers and injuring 57 more; the driver killed himself at the scene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>京福の事業はいずれも小規模でスケールメリットを享受できないことから収益性が低く、歴史的に経営基盤が脆弱になりがちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. operates small businesses, all of which are less profitable because they cannot take advantage of scale, and thus historically its operating foundations tend to be fragile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., operates small businesses, all of which are less profitable because they can&apos;t take advantage of scale; therefore, its operating foundations have historically been fragile.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., operates small businesses, all of which are less profitable because they can&apos;t take advantage of scale; therefore, its operating foundations have historically been fragile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このため、十分に安全投資ができず安全管理がおろそかになったのではないか、との指摘がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, some point out that sufficient investments for safety and safety management might not have caused the accidents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, some point out that sufficient investments for safety and safety management might have prevented the accidents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, some point out that sufficient investments for safety and safety management might have prevented the accidents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>1942年（昭和17年）3月2日 京福電気鉄道株式会社設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 2, 1942 the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 2, 1942, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., was established.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 2, 1942: The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., was established.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>京都電燈の鉄軌道事業を継承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. succeeded the railway and tramway business of the Kyoto Dento.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., succeeded the railway and tramway business of Kyoto Dento.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., succeeded the railway and tramway business of Kyoto Dento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>1942年（昭和17年）8月1日 鞍馬電気鉄道・三国芦原電鉄を合併。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, 1942 the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. merged the Kurama Electric Railway and the Mikuni Awara Electric Railway (三国芦原電鉄).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1942, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., merged the Kurama Electric Railway and the Mikuni Awara Electric Railway (三国芦原電鉄).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1942: The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., merged the Kurama Electric Railway and the Mikuni Awara Electric Railway (三国芦原電鉄).</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鞍馬線、三国芦原線とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kurama Line and the Mikuni-awara Line were opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurama and Mikuni-awara lines were opened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kurama and Mikuni-awara lines were opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>1944年（昭和19年）12月1日 永平寺鉄道・丸岡鉄道を合併。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 1, 1944 the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. merged the Eihei-ji Railway and the Maruoka Railway (丸岡鉄道).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 1, 1944, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., merged the Eihei-ji Railway and the Maruoka Railway (丸岡鉄道).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1, 1944: The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., merged the Eiheiji Railway and the Maruoka Railway.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>永平寺線、丸岡線とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eihei-ji Line and the Maruoka Line were opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eihei-ji and Maruoka lines were opened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eiheiji and Maruoka lines were opened.</e>
<cmt>Eiheiji としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）8月1日 福井県乗合自動車を合併し、福井地区のバス事業を直営化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, 1963 the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. merged the Fukui Prefecture Share-ride Cars to directly manage the bus business operated in Fukui area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1963, the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., merged the Fukui Prefecture Share-Ride Cars in order to directly manage the bus business operated in the Fukui area.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1963: The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., merged the Fukui Prefecture Share-Ride Cars in order to directly manage the bus business operated in the Fukui area.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>1968年（昭和43年）7月11日 丸岡線を廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 11, 1968 the Maruoka Line was abandoned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 11, 1968, the Maruoka Line was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 11, 1968: The Maruoka Line was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>1978年（昭和53年）10月19日 叡山本線・鞍馬線の集電装置トロリーポール集電を集電装置パンタグラフ集電化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 19, 1978 trolley poles (power collector) of the Eizan Main Line and the Kurama Line were replaced with pantographs (power collector).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 19, 1978, trolley poles (power collectors) of the Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line were replaced with pantographs.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 19, 1978: Trolley poles (power collectors) of the Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line were replaced with pantographs.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>トロリーバスを除く通常の鉄軌道路線では、日本国内最後のトロリーポール集電であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the last trolley poles in Japan on the typical tramway except for the trolley bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were the last trolley poles in Japan on a typical tramway, except for trolley buses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were the last trolley poles in Japan on a typical tramway, except for trolley buses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>1985年（昭和60年）7月6日 叡山電鉄株式会社を全額出資の子会社として設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 6, 1985 the Eizan Electric Railway Co., Ltd. was established as a fully-owned subsidiary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 6, 1985, the Eizan Electric Railway Co., Ltd., was established as a wholly owned subsidiary.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 6, 1985: The Eizan Electric Railway Co., Ltd., was established as a wholly owned subsidiary.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>1986年（昭和61年）4月1日 叡山本線・鞍馬線を叡山電鉄に分離譲渡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 1986 the Eizan Main Line and the Kurama Line were transferred to the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 1986, the Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line were transferred to the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1986: The Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line were transferred to the Eizan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>叡山電鉄→Eizan Electric Railway　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>2000年（平成12年）4月1日 福井地区で行っていた直営バス事業を子会社の丸岡バスに譲渡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 2000 the bus business directly operated in Fukui area was transferred to the subsidiary, Maruoka Bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 2000, the bus business directly operated in the Fukui area was transferred to the subsidiary, Maruoka Bus.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 2000: The bus business directly operated in the Fukui area was transferred to the subsidiary, Maruoka Bus.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>丸岡バスは京福バスに改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maruoka Bus renamed Keifuku Bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maruoka Bus was renamed as Keifuku Bus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maruoka Bus was renamed as Keifuku Bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>2000年（平成12年）12月17日 越前本線志比堺～東古市（現在の永平寺口）間で正面衝突事故。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 17, 2000 a frontal impact accident happened between Shizakai and Higashi-furuichi (the current Eihei-ji-guchi) on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 17, 2000, a frontal-impact accident occurred between Shizakai and Higashi-furuichi (the current Eihei-ji-guchi) on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17, 2000: A frontal-impact accident occurred between Shiizakai and Higashi-furuichi (the current Eiheiji-guchi) on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>運転士が死亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The driver was killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The driver was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The driver was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="37">
<j>2001年（平成13年）6月24日 越前本線保田～発坂間で正面衝突事故。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 24, 2001 a frontal impact accident happened between Hota and Hossaka on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 24, 2001, a frontal-impact accident occurred between Hota and Hossaka on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 24, 2001: A frontal-impact accident occurred between Hota and Hossaka on the Echizen Main Line.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>福井地区各線の列車運行停止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Train operations on the lines in Fukui area were halted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train operations on the lines in the Fukui area were halted.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train operations on the lines in the Fukui area were halted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="39">
<j>2002年（平成14年）10月21日 永平寺線を廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 21, 2002 the Eihei-ji Line was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 21, 2002, the Eihei-ji Line was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 21, 2002: The Eiheiji Line was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>2003年（平成15年）2月1日 福井地区の鉄道事業をえちぜん鉄道へ譲渡（形式的には一旦全線廃止）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 1, 2003 the railway business in the Fukui area was transferred to the Echizen Railway (formally all the lines were once discontinued).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 1, 2003, the railway business in the Fukui area was transferred to the Echizen Railway (all the lines had previously been discontinued).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 1, 2003: The railway business in the Fukui area was transferred to the Echizen Railway (all the lines had previously been discontinued).</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="41">
<j>2007年（平成19年）3月19日 嵐山本線・北野線で駅ナンバリング制度を開始、7駅の駅名を変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 19, 2007 the station numbering began on the Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line; seven stations were renamed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 19, 2007, the station numbering began on the Arashiyama Main Line and Kitano Line; seven stations were renamed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 19, 2007: The station numbering began on the Arashiyama Main Line and Kitano Line; seven stations were renamed.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>日本の鉄道ラインカラー一覧を正式に導入（なお、駅番号とラインカラーはそれ以前から北野線の一部の駅で試用されていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The list of railway line colors in Japan was officially introduced (the station number and the line color were previously used at some stations on the Kitano Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The list of railway line colors in Japan was officially introduced (station numbers and line colors had previously been used at some stations on the Kitano Line).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The list of railway line colors in Japan was officially introduced (station numbers and line colors had previously been used at some stations on the Kitano Line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="43">
<j>2008年（平成20年）4月1日 四条大宮・嵐山・帷子ノ辻・北野白梅町の各駅で発車メロディ導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 2008 Shijo-Omiya, Arashiyama, Katabiranotsuji, and Kitan-Hakubaicho Stations adopted melodies for the departure of train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 2008, Shijo-Omiya, Arashiyama, Katabiranotsuji, and Kitan-Hakubaicho stations adopted melodies for the departures of trains.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 2008: Shijo-Omiya, Arashiyama, Katabiranotsuji, and Kitano-Hakubaicho stations adopted melodies for the departures of trains.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>現有路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Existing lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Existing lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Existing lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>京福電気鉄道嵐山本線 A</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Arashiyama Main Line A</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Arashiyama Main Line A</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Arashiyama Main Line A</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>京福電気鉄道北野線 B</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Arashiyama Main Line B</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Arashiyama Main Line B</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Arashiyama Main Line B</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>京福電気鉄道鋼索線（叡山ケーブル）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad Cable Car Line (Eizan Cable Railway)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad Cable Car Line (Eizan Cable Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Cable Car Line (Eizan Cable Railway)</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>叡山ロープウェイ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eizan Ropeway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eizan Ropeway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eizan Ropeway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="48">
<j>線名のあとのローマ字は駅番号の線別ローマ字記号とラインカラー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The alphabet following the line name expresses the line and the line color.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alphabet following the line name expresses the line and the line color.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alphabet following the line name expresses the line and the line color.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>京福電鉄の公式サイトなどでは、嵐山本線と北野線とを併せて、嵐山線と称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the official website of the Keifuku Electric Railroad, the Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line are collectively called the Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the official website of the Keifuku Electric Railroad, the Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line are collectively called the Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the official website of the Keifuku Electric Railroad, the Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line are collectively called the Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>譲渡・廃止路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transferred or abandoned lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transferred or abandoned lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transferred or abandoned lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>叡山本線（現：叡山電鉄叡山本線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eizan Main Line (the current Eizan Main Line operated by the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eizan Main Line (currently the Eizan Main Line operated by the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line))</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eizan Main Line (currently the Eizan Main Line operated by the Eizan Electric Railway)</e>
<cmt>叡山電鉄→Eizan Electric Railway　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>鞍馬線（現：叡山電鉄鞍馬線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurama Line (the current Kurama Line operated by the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurama Line (currently the Kurama Line operated by the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line))</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurama Line (currently the Kurama Line operated by the Eizan Electric Railway)</e>
<cmt>叡山電鉄→Eizan Electric Railway　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>越前本線（現：えちぜん鉄道勝山永平寺線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Echizen Main Line (the current Katsuyama-eiheiji Line operated by the Echizen Railway)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Echizen Main Line (currently the Katsuyama-eiheiji Line operated by the Echizen Railway)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Echizen Main Line (currently the Katsuyama-eiheiji Line operated by the Echizen Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>三国芦原線（現：えちぜん鉄道三国芦原線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikuni-awara Line (the current Mikuni-awara Line operated by the Echizen Railway)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikuni-awara Line (currently the Mikuni-awara Line operated by the Echizen Railway)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikuni-awara Line (currently the Mikuni-awara Line operated by the Echizen Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="54">
<j>京福電気鉄道永平寺線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Eihei-ji Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Eihei-ji Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Eiheiji Line</e>
<cmt>Eiheiji としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="55">
<j>京福電気鉄道丸岡線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Maruoka Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Maruoka Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keifuku Electric Railroad, Maruoka Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling stock</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolling stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>京福電気鉄道では車体デザインは大きく変更しながらも、全車が同一性能を持つという車両設計の元、1990年代後半になるまで京福電気鉄道モボ101形電車の主要機器類を踏襲した自動加速制御の吊り掛け駆動方式車を導入してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd. has developed cars with various designs of the body, all of the cars having identical performance; until the late 1990s, nose suspended drive cars of automatic acceleration control had been introduced, which followed the main equipment of the MOBO Type 101.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., has developed cars with various body designs, but all such cars are identical in performance; in the late 1990s, nose suspended drive cars with automatic acceleration control were introduced, following the main equipment of MOBO Type 101.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., has developed cars with various body designs, but all such cars are identical in performance; in the late 1990s, nose suspended drive cars with automatic acceleration control were introduced, following the main equipment of Keifuku Electric Railroad MOBO Type 101.</e>
<cmt>Keifuku Electric Railroad MOBO Type 101　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これは鉄道事業者としては異例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is unusual for the railway business operator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is unusual for a railway business operator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is unusual for a railway business operator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>だが、最新の京福電気鉄道モボ2001形電車でWN平行カルダン駆動方式や可変電圧可変周波数制御を採用するなど、最新技術を多数採用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the latest MOBO Type 2001 adopts WN parallel cardan jointed drive and Variable Voltage Variable Frequency Control, which are the latest technologies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the latest MOBO Type 2001 adopts WN parallel cardan jointed drive and &quot;Variable Voltage Variable Frequency Control,&quot; which are the latest technologies.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the latest Keifuku Electric Railroad MOBO Type 2001 adopts WN parallel cardan jointed drive and &quot;Variable Voltage Variable Frequency Control,&quot; which are the latest technologies.</e>
<cmt>Keifuku Electric Railroad MOBO Type 2001としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>叡山本線・鞍馬線の車両は叡山電鉄、旧福井鉄道部の車両はえちぜん鉄道を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the cars employed on the Eizan Main Line and the Kurama Line, refer to the section of the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line); as to the cars employed by the old Fukui Railway Department, refer to the section of the Echizen Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the cars employed on the Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line, refer to the section on the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Railway Line); regarding the cars employed by the old Fukui Railway Department, refer to the section on the Echizen Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the cars employed on the Eizan Main Line and Kurama Line, refer to the section on the Eizan Electric Railway; regarding the cars employed by the old Fukui Railway Department, refer to the section on the Echizen Railway.</e>
<cmt>叡山電鉄→Eizan Electric Railway　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fares</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fares</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>嵐山本線、北野線を通じて、大人200円、子供100円の全線均一運賃である（2002年7月1日改定）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line adopt a flat fare through out the lines: adult: 200 yen, child: 100 yen (revised on July 1, 2002).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Arashiyama Main Line and Kitano Line employ a flat fare throughout their lines: adults are 200 yen each, and children are 100 yen each (revised on July 1, 2002).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Arashiyama Main Line and Kitano Line employ a flat fare throughout their lines: adults are 200 yen each, and children are 100 yen each (revised on July 1, 2002).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>かつては180円、210円、230円の区間制運賃であったが、スルッとKANSAI加盟に際し、下車時のみのカード処理で済ませられるよう、2002年7月1日から均一運賃となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These lines used to adopt distance-based fares (180 yen, 210 yen, and 230 yen); however, along with the participation in the KANSAI THRU PASS, these lines adopted a flat fare system on July 1, 2002 so that the processing of a card is performed only one time when passengers leave the train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These lines formerly had distance-based fares (180 yen, 210 yen and 230 yen), but along with the participation in the KANSAI THRU PASS they adopted a flat-fare system on July 1, 2002, so that the processing of a card is performed only once, as the passenger leaves the train.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These lines formerly had distance-based fares (180 yen, 210 yen and 230 yen), but along with the participation in the KANSAI THRU PASS they adopted a flat-fare system on July 1, 2002, so that the processing of a card is performed only once, as the passenger leaves the train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>これに伴い、不要となった各車両の乗車整理券発行機は撤去された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, ticket issuing machines installed on the cars became unused, thereby being removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, ticket issuing machines installed on the cars became unused and were consequently removed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, ticket issuing machines installed on the cars became unused and were consequently removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>なお、定期運賃は現在も距離制である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the distance-based system is still employed for the commuter pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the distance-based system is still employed for the commuter pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the distance-based system is still employed for the commuter pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>乗車時の改札はなく、下車時に有人駅（四条大宮、帷子ノ辻、嵐山、北野白梅町）では改札口で、無人駅では運転士に、運賃を支払うか定期券を提示する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no ticket gate for passengers getting on the train; instead, when getting off the train, passengers are required to pay fares at the ticket gate at manned stations (Shijo-Omiya, Katabiranotsuji, Arashiyama, Kitano-Hakubaicho Stations) or show the driver their commuter pass at unmanned stations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no ticket gate for passengers who will board the train; instead, when leaving the train passengers are required to pay fares at the ticket gates of manned stations (Shijo-Omiya, Katabiranotsuji, Arashiyama, Kitano-Hakubaicho Stations) or show the driver their commuter pass at unmanned stations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no ticket gate for passengers who will board the train; instead, when leaving the train passengers are required to pay fares at the ticket gates of manned stations (Shijo-Omiya, Katabiranotsuji, Arashiyama, Kitano-Hakubaicho Stations) or pay the fare to the driver or show the driver their commuter pass at unmanned stations.</e>
<cmt>運賃を払う　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>現金での支払いのほか、有人駅ではあらかじめ乗車券や回数券を購入することもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Passengers can pay by cash or buy tickets or commutation tickets in advance at manned stations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers can pay with cash or buy either regular tickets or commutation tickets in advance at manned stations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers can pay with cash or buy either regular tickets or commutation tickets in advance at manned stations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>スルッとKANSAI対応カードは、無人駅で降車の場合、運賃箱に取り付けられた路線バスに設置されているものと同様の処理機に通す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For KANSAI THRU PASS cards, passengers swipe the card through a reader when getting off the train at unmanned stations, which is the same as that installed in a collection box on the route bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the KANSAI THRU PASS card, the passenger swipes the card through a reader when getting off the train at an unmanned station, which is the same as that installed in a collection box on a route bus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the KANSAI THRU PASS card, the passenger swipes the card through a reader when getting off the train at an unmanned station, which is the same as that installed in a collection box on a route bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>有人駅では、改札口に設置されている処理機にカードを通す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At manned station, passengers swipe a card through a reader installed at the ticket gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a manned station, the passenger swipes the card through a reader installed at the ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At a manned station, the passenger swipes the card through a reader installed at the ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>上記の4つの有人駅や嵐電嵯峨駅前の商店・一部のホテルでは、500円（小児250円）で全線が1日乗り放題になる「嵐電1日フリーきっぷ」を発売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aforementioned four manned stations, the stores in front of Randensaga Station, or some hotels sell &apos;Randen 1 day Thru ticket,&apos; a daily unlimited ride card available at all stations, at 500 yen (child: 250 yen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aforementioned four manned stations, the stores in front of Randensaga Station and certain hotels sell &apos;Randen 1-Day Thru Ticket,&apos; a daily unlimited ride card available at all stations, at 500 yen (250 yen per child).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aforementioned four manned stations, the stores in front of Randen-Saga Station and certain hotels sell &apos;Randen One-day open tickets for Arashiyama,&apos; a daily unlimited ride card available at all stations, at 500 yen (250 yen per child).</e>
<cmt>乗り放題切符を、Randen One-day open tickets for Arashiyama　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>1日に3回以上乗車すれば割安になるほか、付属のクーポンで沿線社寺や観光施設で拝観料・入場料の割り引きを受けたり、粗品の進呈を受けたりすることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ticket is comparatively cheap if passengers ride on the train more than two times per day; in addition, the accompanying coupon offers a discount for an entrance fee at a shrine, temple, or sightseeing facility, as well as a little gift.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ticket is relatively inexpensive if passengers ride on the train more than two times per day; additionally, the accompanying coupon offers a discount for an entrance fee at a shrine, temple or sightseeing facility, as well as a little gift.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ticket is relatively inexpensive if passengers ride on the train more than two times per day; additionally, the accompanying coupon offers a discount for an entrance fee at a shrine, temple or sightseeing facility, as well as a little gift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>予め購入して後日利用する場合のために、通用日はスクラッチ方式により利用者が決めることもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To use the ticket after the purchase in advance, users can decide the date of use to mark the ticket by scratching it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To use the ticket after the purchase in advance, users can decide the date of use and mark the ticket by scratching it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To use the ticket after the purchase in advance, users can decide the date of use and mark the ticket by scratching it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="71">
<j>2008年からは、地下鉄側の太秦天神川駅延伸、京福側の嵐電天神川駅開業を受けて、同年3月28日から「京都嵐山・びわ湖大津1dayチケット」、「京都地下鉄・嵐電1dayチケット」が発売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, with the extension of the subway line to Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station and the opening of Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., &apos;Kyoto Subway and Randen 1 day ticket&apos; and &apos;Kyoto-Ranzan and Biwako-Otsu 1 day ticket&apos; began to be sold on March 28, 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, with the extension of the subway line to Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station and the opening of Ranzan-Tenjingawa Station by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., &apos;Kyoto Subway and Randen 1-Day Ticket&apos; and &apos;Kyoto-Ranzan and Biwako-Otsu 1-Day Ticket&apos; became available for purchase on March 28, 2008.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, with the extension of the subway line to Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station and the opening of Randen-Tenjingawa Station by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., &apos;Kyoto Subway and Randen One-day Ticket&apos; and &apos;Kyoto-Ranzan and Biwako-Otsu One-day Ticket&apos; became available for purchase on March 28, 2008.</e>
<cmt>one-day としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>関連商品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related products</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related products</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related products</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>2003年に、大手ゲームメーカータイトーの列車運転ゲーム『電車でGO!』に、京福電鉄として登場している（路線は、嵐山本線、北野線）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2003, the big playmaker Taito Corporation adopted the Keifuku Electric Railroad in Densha-de-go! (電車でGO!), a train operation game (the Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line have been adopted).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2003, the big toymaker Taito Corporation adopted the Keifuku Electric Railroad in Densha-de-go! (電車でGO!), a train operation game (the Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line have been adopted).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2003, the big toymaker Taito Corporation adopted the Keifuku Electric Railroad in Densha-de-go! (電車でGO!), a train operation game (the Arashiyama Main Line and the Kitano Line have been adopted).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>ハセガワよりモボ101形「嵐電」のNゲージ鉄道模型が発売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The N gauge mode train, MOBO Type 101 &quot;Randen,&quot; is sold by the Hasegawa Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The N gauge mode train, MOBO Type 101 &quot;Randen,&quot; is sold by the Hasegawa Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The N gauge model train, MOBO Type 101 &apos;Randen,&apos; is sold by the Hasegawa Corporation.</e>
<cmt>model train に変更しました。&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 東京特許許可局(id:7229), Nnh(id:474), 二八(id:10408), Heavy Frisker(id:160741), UE-PON2600(id:18149), Co.kyoto(id:79296), Mkb(id:11233), Roga246(id:53246), Xiaoyeze(id:41563), Grazie(id:12785), 準急三条(id:25072), Sunen(id:10700), Goki(id:7107), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), LERK(id:4460), Ritsuka(id:6464), Takobou(id:10633), MASA(id:2399), Bergmann(id:85282), Carpio(id:109342), Complex01(id:10454), Taisyo(id:6896), YAMADA(id:70254), Utsuda(id:605), Shinkansen(id:13703), Rusk(id:9895), Bueller 007(id:30970), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Tp2415(id:84801), Y3006(id:155535), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Trashwriter(id:79181), 210.(id:9838), SVS(id:18615), テラ太郎(id:175887), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>