<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>嵯峨野観光鉄道嵯峨野観光線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagano Sight-Seeing Tram of Sagano Scenic Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagano Scenic Railway&apos;s Sagano Sightseeing Tram</e>
<cmt>再構成して、「of」削除。「Sightseeing」はハイフンで分ける言葉ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagano Scenic Railway&apos;s Sagano Sightseeing Tram</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>嵯峨野観光線（さがのかんこうせん）は、京都府京都市右京区のトロッコ嵯峨駅から京都府亀岡市のトロッコ亀岡駅までを結ぶ嵯峨野観光鉄道の鉄道路線である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagano Sight-Seeing Tram runs along the Sagano Scenic Railway from Torokko Saga Station (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture) to Torokko Kameoka Station (Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sagano Sightseeing Tram runs along the Sagano Scenic Railway between Torokko Saga Station (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture) and Torokko Kameoka Station (Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「The」削除、「from」→「between」、「to」→「and」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sagano Sightseeing Tram runs along the Sagano Scenic Railway between Saga Torokko Station (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture) and Kameoka Torokko Station (Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Torokko Saga Station→Saga Torokko StationTorokko Kameoka Station→Kameoka Torokko Stationhttp://www.sagano-kanko.co.jp/eng/index.htm</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>Outline→Summary</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>鉄道の電化・複線化のため、1989年にルートが変更された山陰本線の嵯峨嵐山～馬堀間の旧線を活用して、1991年からトロッコ列車が運行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the electrification of railroads and double-tracking, the route between Saga Arashiyama and Umahori of San&apos;in Main Line was changed in1989. The old line was revived with the Torokko Tram running since 1991.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the electrification and double-tracking of railroads, the route between Saga Arashiyama and Umahori on the San&apos;in Main Line was retired in 1989, then revived for the Torokko Tram in 1991.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the electrification and double-tracking of railroads, the route between Saga Arashiyama and Umahori on the Sanin Main Line was retired in 1989, then revived for the Torokko Tram in 1991.</e>
<cmt>San&apos;in→Sanin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本初の純粋な観光専用鉄道とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is Japan&apos;s first railway exclusively used only for sightseeing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the first railway in Japan to be used exclusively for sightseeing.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the first railway in Japan to be used exclusively for sightseeing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>当初は、それほど乗客が無いか、あっても物珍しさのある開業当初だけで、早晩今日のローカル線のような状況になると思われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, it was doubted if there would be any passenger. It was thought that if it does have some curious passengers only at first of the opening, it would become just an ordinary local line of today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first it was thought that there would be only a few passengers, or that, even if some people rode out of curiosity at first, it would in time become just another local line.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first it was thought that there would be only a few passengers, or that, even if some people rode out of curiosity at first, it would in time become just another local line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>風光明媚な山陰本線旧線を走るということや、嵐山・嵯峨野といった有名観光地がそばにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it runs along the beautiful old line of San&apos;in Main Line, with famous sightseeing spots nearby such as Arashiyama and Sagano.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the tram runs along the beautiful old San&apos;in Main Line, and is near Arashiyama and Sagano, both famous sightseeing spots.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the tram runs along the beautiful old Sanin Main Line, and is near Arashiyama and Sagano, both famous sightseeing spots.</e>
<cmt>San&apos;in→Sanin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>保津川下りと周遊できることや、さらに観光客を魅せる沿線作り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourists can enjoy a Boat Ride down the Hozugawa River or other pleasure trips. In addition, these are various charm points along the railway-track.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers can enjoy excursions down the Hozugawa River, and there are various tourist attractions along the track.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers can enjoy excursions down the Hozugawa River, and there are various tourist attractions along the track.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ユニークな乗務員の放送や案内などといった嵯峨野観光鉄道従業員の努力もあり、いつの間にか嵐山の観光といえばトロッコ列車といわれるほど、メジャーなものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to the efforts of Sagano Scenic Railway&apos;s staffs, such as the trainman&apos;s unique broadcasting and explanations, the Torokko Tram has become the image of sightseeing in Arashiyama before one is aware of it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the efforts of Sagano Scenic Railway personnel, such as the unique announcements and explanations made by the train crew, the Torokko Tram became the symbol of Arashiyama sightseeing in no time at all.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the efforts of Sagano Scenic Railway personnel, such as the unique announcements and explanations made by the train crew, the Torokko Tram became the symbol of Arashiyama sightseeing in no time at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>近年は外国人団体客の利用も目立つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, the use by foreigner group tourists also became prominent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, its use by groups of foreign tourists has also become striking.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。「foreigner group tourists」→「groups of foreign tourists」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, its use by groups of foreign tourists has also become striking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>保津峡に沿った風光明媚な区間を走る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It runs in the beautiful regions along Hozukyo Gorge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It runs through the beautiful area along Hozukyo Gorge.</e>
<cmt>「in the」→「through the」、「regions」→「area」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It runs through the beautiful area along Hozukyo Gorge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>車窓からは秋には紅葉、春には嵯峨野観光鉄道社員が植えたサクラが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the carriage&apos;s windows, autumns are highlighted by red maples and springs are highlighted by blossomed cherry trees planted by employees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In autumn, red maples are visible through the tram windows, while in spring one can see blossoming cherry trees which were planted by Sagano Sightseeing Tram personnel.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In autumn, red maples are visible through the tram windows, while in spring one can see blossoming cherry trees which were planted by Sagano Sightseeing Tram personnel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>亀岡への往路に嵯峨野観光鉄道のトロッコ列車、復路に保津峡保津川下りの船と組み合わせて乗る観光客も見られ、そのため春・秋の観光シーズンでも亀岡から嵯峨方向の列車の方が比較的予約しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also tourists who take the combination of using Sagano Scenic Railway&apos;s Torokko Tram on their way to Kameoka and the boat ride down Hozugawa River on their return. Therefore, even during the sightseeing seasons of autumn or spring, it is relatively easier to reserve the tram running from Kameoka in the direction of Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some tourists take the Sagano Scenic Railway Torokko Tram to Kameoka and return down the Hozugawa River by boat; for this reason, even in the spring and autumn peak seasons, it is relatively easier to reserve tram seats in the Kameoka-Saga direction.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some tourists take the Sagano Scenic Railway Torokko Tram to Kameoka and return down the Hozugawa River by boat; for this reason, even in the spring and autumn peak seasons, it is relatively easier to reserve tram seats in the Kameoka-Saga direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>路線データ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route data</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route data</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route data</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>管轄（事業種別）：嵯峨野観光鉄道（鉄道事業者第二種鉄道事業）・西日本旅客鉄道（鉄道事業者第一種鉄道事業）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jurisdiction (Business Type): Sagano Scenic Railway (Railway Business Type II Railway Business)/West Japan Railway (Railway Business Type I Railway Business)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jurisdiction (business type): Sagano Scenic Railway (railway business Type II Railway Business)/West Japan Railway (railway business Type I Railway Business)</e>
<cmt>固有名詞ではない名詞の先頭を小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jurisdiction (business type): Sagano Scenic Railway (railway business Type II Railway Business), West Japan Railway (railway business Type I Railway Business)</e>
<cmt>･→,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>路線距離（営業キロ）：7.3km</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route distance (working kilometers): 7.3km</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Line distance (working kilometers): 7.3 km</e>
<cmt>単位の前にスペース挿入Route→Line 北野線の修正に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>軌間：1067mm</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Track gauge:1067mm</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Track gauge:1067mm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Track gauge:1067 mm</e>
<cmt>単位の前にスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>駅数：4駅（起終点駅含む）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number of stations: 4 stations (including the origin station and the destination station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Number of stations: 4 stations (including the station of origin and the destination station)</e>
<cmt>「origin station」→「station of origin」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Number of stations: 4 (including the station of origin and the destination station)</e>
<cmt>&quot;4 stations&quot;→&quot;4&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>複線区間：なし（全線単線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The double-track regions: no (the whole line is single tracked.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Double-tracked sections: none (the whole line is single-tracked.)</e>
<cmt>「The」削除、「no」→「none」、「single tracked」→「single-tracked」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Double-tracked sections: none (the entire line is single-tracked.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;the whole line&quot;→&quot;the entire line&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>電化区間：なし（全線非電化）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The electrification region: no (the whole line is not electrified yet)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Electrified sections: none (no part of the line has been electrified yet)</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Electrified sections: none (no part of the line has been electrified yet)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>閉塞 (鉄道)：スタフ閉塞式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Block (railway): Staff block system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Block (railway): Staff block system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Block (railway): Staff block system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>嵯峨野観光線の線路は現在もJR西日本の所有であり（戸籍上もJR西日本の路線としては全区間が山陰本線）、嵯峨野観光鉄道がこれを利用して鉄道事業法上の第二種鉄道事業者として列車を運行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagano Sight-Seeing Tram Line is now still owned by JR West. (Even on the register, it is a route of JR West with all sections belong to San&apos;in Main Lines) Sagano Scenic Railway runs the tram as a Type II Railway Business under the Law for Railway Business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sagano Sightseeing Tram Line is still owned by JR West (it is even registered as a route of JR West, with all sections belonging to San&apos;in Main Lines), but the tram is run by Sagano Scenic Railway as a Type II Railway Business under the Law for Railway Businesses.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sagano Sightseeing Tram Line is still owned by JR West (it is even registered as a route of JR West, with all sections belonging to Sanin Main Lines), but the tram is run by Sagano Scenic Railway as a Type II Railway Business under the Law for Railway Businesses.</e>
<cmt>San&apos;in→Sanin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>トロッコ嵯峨～トロッコ嵐山間に山陰本線との一部共用区間があり、トロッコ亀岡発の列車は山陰本線の下り線を逆走する形で運転する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Torokko Saga and Torokko Arashiyama, there is a portion of common region with San-in Main Line, where the tram departing from Torokko Kameoka runs away from Kyoto in a direction opposite to the normal trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a section between Torokko Saga and Torokko Arashiyama which is shared with the San&apos;in Main Line, where the tram leaving from Kameoka runs on the San&apos;in Main Line away from Kyoto, but in the opposite direction to the one taken by normal trains.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a section between Saga Torokko Station and Arashiyama Torokko Station which is shared with the Sanin Main Line, where the tram leaving from Kameoka runs on the Sanin Main Line away from Kyoto, but in the opposite direction to the one taken by normal trains.</e>
<cmt>San&apos;in→SaninTorokko Saga→Saga Torokko StationTorokko Arashiyama→ Arashiyama Torokko Station英語の駅名表記を統一するため、語順を入れ替えStationを補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ちなみに、嵯峨野観光鉄道自体もJR西日本の完全子会社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, Sagano Scenic Railway is a wholly owned subsidiary of JR West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Parenthetically, Sagano Scenic Railway is a wholly-owned subsidiary of JR West.</e>
<cmt>「By the way」→「Parenthetically」、「wholly owned」→「wholly-owned」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Parenthetically, Sagano Scenic Railway is a wholly-owned subsidiary of JR West.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>運行形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operation system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operating pattern</e>
<cmt>「Operation system」→「Operating pattern」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Operating pattern</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>全てトロッコ嵯峨～トロッコ亀岡間の折り返し運転である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The entire route between Torokko Saga and Torokko Kameoka is run by only one tram moving to and fro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entire route between Torokko Saga and Torokko Kameoka is run by a single tram going back and forth.</e>
<cmt>「only one」→「a single」、「moving to and fro」→「going back and forth」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entire route between Saga Torokko Station and Kameoka Torokko Station is run by a single tram going back and forth.</e>
<cmt>Torokko Saga→Saga Torokko StationTorokko Kameoka→Kameoka Torokko Station英語の駅名表記を統一するため、語順を入れ替えStationを補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>水曜日（休日・行楽期除く）並びに冬期（12月30日～2月末日）は運休する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Wednesday (except for holidays and excursion periods) or during winter (December 30 to end of February), there is no running of tram.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tram does not run on Wednesdays (except for holidays and excursion periods), or during the winter (from December 30 until the end of February).</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tram does not run on Wednesdays (except for holidays and excursion periods), or during the winter (from December 30 until the end of February).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>車両関係は営業線内に保守設備を持たず予備のない1編成のみのため、冬期運休期間内に親会社のJR西日本の車両基地へ保守や検査に出されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The carriage management unit does not have the maintenance equipment along the business line and there is only one tram with no substitute. Therefore, during the resting period in winter, it is likely sent to the rail yard of the parent company JR West for maintenance and inspection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there is only one tram, and as the carriage management unit does not have maintenance facilities along the business line, the tram is sometimes sent to parent company JR West&apos;s rail yard for maintenance and inspection during the winter off-season.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there is only one tram, and as the carriage management unit does not have maintenance facilities along the business line, the tram is sometimes sent to parent company JR West&apos;s rail yard for maintenance and inspection during the winter off-season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>運賃は均一制で大人600円、小人300円である（2008年4月現在）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fare is a flat system of 600 yen for adult and 300 yen for child (as of April, 2008).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A flat-fare system is used, with adults costing 600 yen and children costing 300 yen (as of April, 2008).</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A flat-fare system is used, with adults costing 600 yen and children costing 300 yen (as of April, 2008).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>全席指定で、前売り券一般発売は1か月前よりJR西日本の主な駅のみどりの窓口などで実施される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All seats are reserved with the advance ticketing for the public available for purchasing one month before at a Midori window at the main stations of JR West etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All seats may be reserved beforehand; tickets are available to the general public for purchase one month in advance at the Green (or &apos;Midori&apos;) Window at any major JR West station.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All seats may be reserved beforehand; tickets are available to the general public for purchase one month in advance at the Green (or &apos;Midori&apos;) Window at any major JR West station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>（団体発売は別枠で受付）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Group purchasing is available at special request.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Group purchasing is available by special request.)</e>
<cmt>「at」→「by」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Group purchasing is available by special request.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、トロッコ嵯峨・トロッコ嵐山・トロッコ亀岡での当日発売もあって、先着順で発売されるが、紅葉シーズンなどの繁忙期はすぐに売り切れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the tickets for Torokko Saga, Torokko Arashiyama, and Torokko Kameoka may be purchased on the day. Though the tickets are sold on a first-come-first-served basis, they may be sold out soon during a busy time such as the autumn tint season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tickets for Torokko Saga, Torokko Arashiyama and Torokko Kameoka may be purchased on the day; these tickets are sold on a first come, first served basis, but may sell out fast during peak seasons such as autumn, when the leaves change color.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tickets for Saga Torokko Station, Arashiyama Torokko Station and Kameoka Torokko Station may be purchased on the day; these tickets are sold on a first come, first served basis, but may sell out fast during peak seasons such as autumn, when the leaves change color.</e>
<cmt>Torokko Saga→Saga Torokko StationTorokko Arashiyama→ Arashiyama Torokko StationTorokko Kameoka→Kameoka Torokko Station英語の駅名表記を統一するため、語順を入れ替えStationを補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>この路線は周遊券「京阪神ゾーン」のフリー区間に含まれており、ゾーン券提示で乗車することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this route is included in the free region of the excursion ticket &quot;Keihanshin Zone&quot;, one can ride on the tram by presenting the zone ticket.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This route is included in the free region covered by the &apos;Keihanshin Zone&apos; excursion ticket, so one can ride the tram by presenting the zone ticket.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This route is included in the free region covered by the &apos;Keihanshin Zone&apos; excursion ticket, so one can ride the tram by presenting the zone ticket.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Carriage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cars</e>
<cmt>「Carriage」→「Cars」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>車両は国鉄トキ25000形貨車の改造車5両編成 (SK300-1+SK100-1+SK100-11+SK100-2+SK200-1) で、トロッコ嵯峨寄りに国鉄DE10形ディーゼル機関車 (DE10 1104) を連結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Torokko Saga tram comprises five remodeled carriages of Japanese National Railways Toki 25000 type (SK300-1+SK100-1+SK100-11+SK100-2+SK200-1) connected to a Japanese National Railways DE10 type diesel locomotives (DE10 1104).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Torokko Saga tram is composed of five remodeled Japanese National Railways Toki 25000-type cars (SK300-1, SK100-1, SK100-11, SK100-2, SK200-1) connected to a Japanese National Railways DE10-type diesel locomotive (DE10 1104).</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。「comprises」→「is composed of」、「s」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tram is composed of five remodeled Japanese National Railways Toki 25000-type cars (SK300-1, SK100-1, SK100-11, SK100-2, SK200-1) connected to a Japanese National Railways DE10-type diesel locomotive (DE10 1104) on the Saga Torokko Station side.</e>
<cmt>Torokko Saga削除「トロッコ嵯峨寄りに」（トロッコ嵯峨駅に向かっている側にという意味です。）を訳出しました。on the Saga　Torokko Station side補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>機関車次位のSK300形は、「ザ・リッチ」と称する側板や床まで素通しとした「特別車」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The locomotive SK300 type next to the diesel locomotive is a &quot;Special Carriage&quot; called &quot;The Rich&quot; with the shrouds and the floor transparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SK300-type next to the diesel locomotive is a &apos;special car&apos; called &apos;The Rich&apos;, whose shrouds and floor are transparent.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SK300-type next to the diesel locomotive is a &apos;special car&apos; called &apos;The Rich,&apos; whose shrouds and floor are transparent.</e>
<cmt>カンマを&apos;内に移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この車両は雨天時には客を乗せられないため、指定券は前売りされず当日販売のみとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this tram does not take passengers at rain, reservation tickets are not sold in advance. Tickets are sold only on the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this car does not take passengers in rainy weather, tickets are sold only on the day and cannot be reserved in advance.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this car does not take passengers in rainy weather, tickets are sold only on the day and cannot be reserved in advance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>トロッコ亀岡寄りのSK200形には機関車を遠隔制御する運転台を装備する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SK200 type of Torokko Kameoka is equipped with an operating center which remotely controls the locomotive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torokko Kameoka SK200-type is equipped with an operating center which remotely controls the locomotive.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SK200-type on the Kameoka Torokko Station side is equipped with an operating center which remotely controls the locomotive.</e>
<cmt>「トロッコ亀岡寄りの」（トロッコ亀岡駅に向かっている側にという意味です。）を訳出しました。on the Kameoka Torokko Station side補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1号車（「ザ・リッチ」）以外の車両では、窓にガラスがはまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In carriages other than the first carriage (&quot;The Rich&quot;), the windows are fitted with glass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The windows of all cars other than the first one (&apos;The Rich&apos;) are fitted with glass.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The windows of all cars other than the first one (&apos;The Rich&apos;) are fitted with glass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>なお、この「ザ・リッチ」を紹介するチラシはかなりユニークな内容となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The handbill that introduces &quot;The rich&quot; has considerably unique contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The content of the handbill which introduces &apos;The Rich&apos; is considerably unique.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The content of the handbill which introduces &apos;The Rich&apos; is considerably unique.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>1899年（明治32年）8月15日 京都鉄道が嵯峨（現在の嵯峨嵐山）～園部間を開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 15, 1899, Kyoto Railway started the running between Saga (present Saga Arashiyama) and Sonobe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, 1899, Kyoto Railway began service between Saga (present Saga Arashiyama) and Sonobe.</e>
<cmt>「started the running」→「began service」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 15, 1899: Kyoto Railway began service between Saga (present Saga Arashiyama) and Sonobe.</e>
<cmt>日付から On を外し、表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>1907年（明治40年）8月1日 国有化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, 1907, the railway became owned by the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1907, the railway became nationalized.</e>
<cmt>「owned by the nation」→ 「nationalized」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1907: The railway became nationalized.</e>
<cmt>日付から On を外し、表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日 国鉄分割民営化により西日本旅客鉄道に承継。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 1987, with the dissolution of Japan National Railway into privatization, the ownership was succeeded by West Japan Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Japanese National Railway was split up and privatized on April 1, 1987, ownership was transferred to West Japan Railway.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1987: When the Japanese National Railway was split up and privatized, ownership was transferred to West Japan Railway.</e>
<cmt>日付から On を外し、表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>1989年（平成元年）3月5日 山陰本線の嵯峨～馬堀間を複線の新線に切り替え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 5, 1989, the portion of San&apos;in Main Line between Saga and Umahori was switched to a new double-tracked route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 5, 1989, the portion of the San&apos;in Main Line between Saga and Umahori was switched to a new double-tracked route.</e>
<cmt>「the]挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 5, 1989: The portion of the Sanin Main Line between Saga and Umahori was switched to a new double-tracked route.</e>
<cmt>San&apos;in→Sanin日付から On を外し、表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>旧線の列車運行廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Train running was abolished in the old line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train service on the old line was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train service on the old line was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>1991年（平成3年）4月27日 山陰本線旧線を嵯峨野観光鉄道嵯峨野観光線としてトロッコ嵯峨～トロッコ亀岡間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 27, 1991, this old route of San&apos;in Main Line between Torokko Saga and Torokko Kameoka was put into operation as Sagano Sight-Seeing Tram by Sagano Scenic Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 27, 1991, the old San&apos;in Main Line route was brought back by the Sagano Scenic Railway as the Sagano Sightseeing Tram, and service between Torokko Saga and Torokko Kameoka began.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 27, 1991: The old Sanin Main Line route was brought back by the Sagano Scenic Railway as the Sagano Sightseeing Tram, and service between Saga Torokko Station and Kameoka Torokko Station began.</e>
<cmt>Torokko Saga→Saga Torokko StationTorokko Kameoka→Kameoka Torokko Station日付から On を外し、表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>トロッコ列車を運行開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torokko Tram started running.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Torokko Tram began running.</e>
<cmt>「started」→「began」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Torokko Tram began running.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>駅一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>トロッコ嵯峨駅 - トロッコ嵐山駅 - トロッコ保津峡駅 - トロッコ亀岡駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torokko Saga-Torokko Arashiyama Station-Torokko Hozukyo Station-Torokko Kameoka Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga Torokko Station – Arashiyama Torokko Station – Hozukyo Torokko Station – Kameoka Torokko Station</e>
<cmt>駅の名前を対訳で書かれてる順番に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga Torokko Station – Arashiyama Torokko Station – Hozukyo Torokko Station – Kameoka Torokko Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>接続路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Connecting route</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Connecting routes</e>
<cmt>「ｓ」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Connecting routes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>トロッコ嵯峨駅：山陰本線（嵯峨野線）（嵯峨嵐山駅）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga Torokko Station: San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) (Saga Arashiyama Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga Torokko Station: San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) (Saga Arashiyama Station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga Torokko Station: Sanin Main Line (Sagano Line) (Saga Arashiyama Station)</e>
<cmt>San&apos;in→Sanin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>トロッコ保津峡駅：山陰本線（嵯峨野線）（保津峡駅）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torokko Hozukyo Station: San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line)(Hozukyo Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torokko Hozukyo Station: San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line)(Hozukyo Station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozukyo Torokko Station: Sanin Main Line (Sagano Line) (Hozukyo Station)</e>
<cmt>Torokko Hozukyo Station→Hozukyo Torokko StationSan&apos;in→Saninスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>トロッコ亀岡駅：山陰本線（嵯峨野線）（馬堀駅）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torokko Kameoka Station: San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line)(Umahori Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torokko Kameoka Station: San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line)(Umahori Station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameoka Torokko Station: Sanin Main Line (Sagano Line) (Umahori Station)</e>
<cmt>Torokko Kameoka Station→Kameoka Torokko StationSan&apos;in→Saninスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>「s」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>運転シミュレーションゲーム「電車でGO!」（初代）では山陰本線の上り普通列車が運転できるが、この旧線を運転することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the driving simulation game &quot;GO by Tram&quot; (first generation), one can drive a local train in San&apos;in Main Line toward Kyoto. It is a drive in this old route though.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the driving simulation game &apos;GO by Tram&apos; (first generation), one can drive a local train towards Kyoto on the San&apos;in Main Line, and the route used is this old one.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the driving simulation game &apos;GO by Tram&apos; (first generation), one can drive a local train towards Kyoto on the Sanin Main Line, and the route used is this old one.</e>
<cmt>San&apos;in→Sanin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>発売から少したって、トロッコ嵯峨駅にその初代の筐体が置かれたが、インカムなどが良くなかったのか、あまり期間を経たずに撤去されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a short while after the sale, a show box containing the equipment of the first generation carriage was put at Torokko Saga Station. However, perhaps the income was not so good that the box was removed after a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A short while after the game went on sale, a show box containing its first-generation housing was put at the Saga Torokko Station; however, possibly because it didn&apos;t bring in much money, the box was removed before long.</e>
<cmt>再構成して、一文に戻しました。文がちょっと不明です。「筐体」だけではなく、ゲーム自体ではありませんでしょうか。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A short while after the game went on sale, a show box containing its first-generation housing was put at the Saga Torokko Station; however, possibly because it didn&apos;t bring in much money, the box was removed before long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Blackhouse(id:65078), Sakura tsutsuji(id:13201), 味村(id:128437), Bergmann(id:85282), Kaidai(id:15804), ZZZ(id:9462), Maxima m(id:28947), Mover(id:7146), Blackboard(id:53314), Utsuda(id:605), Rusk(id:9895), Sunen(id:10700), Miya(id:1881), Tawashi2006(id:95112), Kone(id:377), まったけ(id:130042), Muyo(id:14948), CC(id:4162), 210.(id:9838), Ogeshi(id:80487), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>