<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二ノ瀬駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninose Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninose Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninose Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二ノ瀬駅（にのせえき）は、京都府京都市左京区にある、叡山電鉄叡山電鉄鞍馬線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in the Sakyo Ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, the Ninose Station is a stop on the Kurama Line, the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninose Station, located in the Sakyo Ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kurama Line, the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninose Station, located in the Sakyo ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kurama Line of the Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt>既出記事と表現を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>単線区間のほぼ中間に位置し、日中はすべての列車がこの駅で列車交換する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the station is located almost in the middle of a single track section, the station serves as a pass-by track for all trains during the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the station is located almost in the middle of a single-track section, the station serves as a bypass track for all trains during the day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the station is located almost in the middle of a single-track section, the station serves as a bypass track for all trains during the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>プラットホーム2面2線の無人駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An unmanned station with two platforms serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an unmanned station with two platforms serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an unmanned station with two platforms serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>出町柳駅行きホームにはログハウス状の待合室がありワンマンカーの乗車口にあたるため、上屋は設置されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since a log cabin-style waiting room is installed on the Demachiyanagi Station-bound platform, which a train door of a one-man-operated train meets, a roof is not installed on the platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because a log cabin-style waiting room is installed on the Demachiyanagi Station-bound platform, which a train door of a one-man-operated train meets, the platform has no roof.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because a log cabin-style waiting room is installed on the Demachiyanagi Station-bound platform, which a train door of a one-man-operated train meets, the platform has no roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鞍馬駅行きホームには短い上屋を備えたベンチがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A bench with a short roof is installed on the Kurama Station-bound platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bench with a short roof is installed on the Kurama Station-bound platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bench with a short roof is installed on the Kurama Station-bound platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>主要な出入り口はホームの鞍馬駅側にあり、駅構内踏切（第4種）によって両ホームは結ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A main entrance is located on the Kurama Station side of the platform and two platforms are connected by a level crossing (Class 4) in the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A main entrance is located on the Kurama Station side of the platform, and two platforms are connected by a level crossing (Class 4) in the station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A main entrance is located on the Kurama Station side of the platform, and two platforms are connected by a level crossing (Class 4) in the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>駅から二ノ瀬集落へは階段で下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ninose Village can be reached by going down the stairs from the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninose Village can be reached by taking the stairs down from the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninose Village can be reached by taking the stairs down from the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>出町柳駅行きホームの出町柳側にホームを下ったところにトイレがあり、このトイレ前からも階段で集落に下ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lavatory is installed below the platform on the Demachiyanagi side of the Demachiyanagi Station-bound platform, from where the village can also be reached by going down the stairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lavatory is located below the platform on the Demachiyanagi side of the Demachiyanagi Station-bound platform, from which the village can also be reached by taking the stairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lavatory is located below the platform on the Demachiyanagi side of the Demachiyanagi Station-bound platform, from which the village can also be reached by taking the stairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>叡山電鉄で最も山深い雰囲気の駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is the hilliest among the stations of the Eizan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is in the hilliest situation among the stations of the Eizan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is in the hilliest situation among the stations of the Eizan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>立地上、車椅子等での利用は不可の状態。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is not accessible to a person in wheelchairs due to its layout.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given its layout, the station isn&apos;t accessible to persons in wheelchairs.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given its layout, the station isn&apos;t accessible to persons in wheelchairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>京都府道38号京都広河原美山線（鞍馬街道）とは集落を挟んだ反対側の山の斜面にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is located on the mountainside which is the other side of the Kyoto-hirogawara-miyamasen Kyoto Fudo 38 Go (Kyoto Prefecture Road 38) (Kurama-kaido) over the village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is located on the mountainside, and beyond the village on the other side is the Kyoto-hirogawara-miyamasen Kyoto Fudo 38 Go (Kyoto Prefecture Road 38) (Kurama-kaido).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is located on the mountainside, and beyond the village on the other side is the Kyoto-hirogawara-miyama Line of the Kyoto Prefectural Route 38 (Kurama-kaido).</e>
<cmt>Kyoto-hirogawara-miyama Line of the Kyoto Prefectural Route 38としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>駅や周囲に商店、自動販売機の類はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no stores or vending machines in or around the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no stores or vending machines in or around the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no stores or vending machines in or around the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>最近、衛星放送受信アンテナが目立ち、近代化された住宅も建ち始めているが、それでもなお駅から見る山間の集落そのものがすばらしい風景であると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently some modern houses with satellite antennas have been built, but still the view of the mountain village itself as seen from the station is beautiful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently some modern houses with satellite antennas have been built, but still the view of the mountain village, as seen from the station, is beautiful.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently some modern houses with satellite antennas have been built, but still the view of the mountain village, as seen from the station, is beautiful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>東海自然歩道　夜泣峠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokai-shizen-hodo (nature trail), Yonaki-toge (mountain pass)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokai-shizen-hodo (nature trail), Yonaki-toge (mountain pass)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokai-shizen-hodo (nature trail), Yonaki-toge (mountain pass)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>二ノ瀬ユリ登山道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninose-yuri Trail</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninose-yuri Trail</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninose-yuri Trail</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>称名院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomyo-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomyo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomyo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>富士神社・守谷神社（貴船口側、登山道への踏切横。2つの神社が共通の社を持つ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji-jinja Shrine and Moritani-jinja Shrine (On the Kibuneguchi side, beside the level crossing to the trail. The two shrines have a common shrine.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fuji-jinja and Moritani-jinja shrines are on the Kibuneguchi side, beside the level crossing to the trail. The two shrines have a common shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji-jinja Shrine and Moritani-jinja Shrine are on the Kibuneguchi side, beside the level crossing to the trail (the two shrines have a common shrine).</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しなおしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>龍田神社（非公開であるが、庭園の一部は市原側の鉄橋付近で車内から見ることができる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatsuta-jinja Shrine (The shrine is not open to the public, but part of its garden can be seen from the car near a rail bridge on the Ichihara side.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatsuta-jinja Shrine is not open to the public, but part of its garden can be seen from the car near a rail bridge on the Ichihara side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatsuta-jinja Shrine isn&apos;t open to the public, but part of its garden can be seen from the car near a rail bridge on the Ichihara side.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しなおしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>市原～二ノ瀬間の叡山電鉄鞍馬線もみじのトンネル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momiji no Tonneru (tunnel) on the Kurama Line, the Eizan Electric Railway between Ichihara and Ninose</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momiji no Tonneru (tunnel) is located on the Kurama Line, the Eizan Electric Railway between Ichihara and Ninose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momiji no Tonneru (Tunnel of maple leaves) is located on the Kurama Line of the Eizan Electric Railway between Ichihara and Ninose.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しなおしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>「貴船もみじ灯篭」（11月に開催）の際は、駅構内の紅葉がライトアップされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the &apos;Kibune Momiji-toro&apos; (held in November), autumn leaves in the station are illuminated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the &apos;Kibune Momiji-toro&apos; (held in November), the autumn leaves in the station are illuminated.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the &apos;Kibune Momiji-toro&apos; (held in November), the autumn leaves in the station are illuminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>1929年（昭和4年）10月20日 鞍馬電気鉄道の駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station opened on October 20, 1929, as a station owned by the Kurama Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station opened on October 20, 1929 under the ownership of the Kurama Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 20, 1929: The station opened under the ownership of the Kurama Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>1942年（昭和17年）8月1日 会社合併により京福電気鉄道の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, 1942, the station came to be owned by the Keifuku Electric Railroad as a result of amalgamation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1942 the station came under the ownership of the Keifuku Electric Railroad as a result of the amalgamation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1942: The station came under the ownership of the Keifuku Electric Railroad as a result of the amalgamation.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>1986年（昭和61年）4月1日 会社再編により叡山電鉄の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 1986, the station came to be owned by the Eizan Electric Railway as a result of reorganization of companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 1986 the station came under the ownership of the Eizan Electric Railway due to the reorganization of companies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1986: The station came under the ownership of the Eizan Electric Railway due to the reorganization of companies.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>叡山電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eizan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eizan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eizan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鞍馬線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurama Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurama Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurama Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>市原駅 - 二ノ瀬駅 - 貴船口駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichihara Station - Ninose Station - Kibuneguchi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichihara Station - Ninose Station - Kibuneguchi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichihara Station - Ninose Station - Kibuneguchi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hideyuki(id:9577), Bakkai(id:7233), Bergmann(id:85282), Nkensei(id:26989), Y3006(id:155535), Hidama(id:73276), Kansai explorer(id:48975), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), KARS(id:43022), Aryarya(id:35365), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>