<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>烏丸御池駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasuma Oike Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma Oike Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma Oike Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>烏丸御池駅（からすまおいけえき）は、京都府京都市中京区にある、京都市営地下鉄の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto, Kyto Prefecture, Karasuma Oike Station is a stop on a Kyoto City Subway line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma Oike Station, located in Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kyoto City Subway line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma Oike Station, located in Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kyoto Municipal Subway line.</e>
<cmt>city→ municipal　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>利用可能な鉄道路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway lines available</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway lines available</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lines</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>京都市営地下鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>京都市営地下鉄烏丸線（駅番号：K08）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasuma Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway (the station number: K08)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma Line of the Kyoto Municipal Subway (station number K08)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma Line of the Kyoto Municipal Subway (station number K08)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>京都市営地下鉄東西線（駅番号：T13）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tozai Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway (the station number: T13)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tozai Line of the Kyoto Municipal Subway (station number T13)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tozai Line of the Kyoto Municipal Subway (station number T13)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>地下に烏丸線が走る烏丸通と、同じく地下に東西線が走る御池通の交差点に位置する両路線の乗換駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located at the crossing of Karasuma-dori Street, under which Karasuma Line runs, and Oike-dori Street, under which Tozai Line runs, this station enables passengers on trains on each of the lines to change their trains to those on the other line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located at the crossing of Karasuma-dori Street, under which the Karasuma Line runs, and Oike-dori Street, under which the Tozai Line runs, this station enables passengers on either line to switch to the train on the other line.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located at the crossing of Karasuma-dori Street, under which the Karasuma Line runs, and Oike-dori Street, under which the Tozai Line runs, this station enables passengers on either line to switch to the train on the other line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>プラットホームは、改札階の下にある烏丸線ホームが同線で唯一の相対式2面2線（開業時から東西線との乗り換え駅となる事を見越しての設計であった）、そのさらに下層にある東西線ホームが島式1面2線となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Karasuma Line placed in the level immediately under the gate-installed level, two separate platforms with two tracks served between them, the structure of which type is used only here on Karasuma Line, are provided (designed considering enabling passengers to change train lines here), and for Tozai Line placed in the level immediately under the Karasum Line level, an island platform serving two tracks is provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Karasuma Line, placed at the level immediately under the gate-installed level, two separate platforms with two tracks served between them, the structure of this type being used only here on the Karasuma Line, are provided (having been designed to allow passengers to change train lines here), while an island platform serving two tracks is provided for the Tozai Line placed at the level immediately under the Karasuma Line level.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Karasuma Line, placed at the level immediately under the gate-installed level, two separate platforms with two tracks served between them, the structure of this type being used only here on the Karasuma Line, are provided (having been designed to allow passengers to change trains with Tozai Line here), while an island platform serving two tracks is provided for the Tozai Line placed at the level immediately under the Karasuma Line level.</e>
<cmt>東西線との乗り換え　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>エレベーターは日立製でコンコース内に2台あり、1台は烏丸線竹田方面ホームと東西線ホームに、1台は烏丸線国際会館方面と東西線ホーム間を昇降する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two elevetors from Hitachi are installed: one operating between the platform for the direction of Takeda Staion on Karasuma Line and the platform for Tozai Line, and the other between the platform for the direction of Kokusaikaikan Staion on Karasuma Line and the platform for Tozai Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two elevators from Hitachi are installed: one operating between the platform for the direction of Takeda Station on the Karasuma Line and the platform for Tozai Line; and the other between the platform for the direction of Kokusaikaikan Station on the Karasuma Line and the platform for the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two elevators from Hitachi are installed: one operating between the platform for the direction of Takeda Station on the Karasuma Line and the platform for the Tozai Line; and the other between the platform for the direction of Kokusaikaikan Station on the Karasuma Line and the platform for the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>Tozai Line→the Tozai Lineに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このエレベーターはストレッチャーに対応するため20名乗りとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supporting use of a stretcher, these elevators are for 20 passemgers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These elevators accommodate 20 passengers and support the use of a stretcher.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These elevators accommodate 20 passengers and support the use of a stretcher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また東西線ホームはプラットホーム安全対策を装備している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the platform of Tozai Line, saftey measures are provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the platform of the Tozai Line, safety measures are provided.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the platform of the Tozai Line, safety measures are provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>東西線のステーションカラーは朱色。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station color of Tozai Line is vermillion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station color of the Tozai Line is vermillion.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station color of the Tozai Line is vermillion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>駅の北側に有人改札口があり売店（サービスセンター）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the northern side of the station, a manned ticket gate and a shop (service center) are placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A manned ticket gate and a shop (service center) are located on the north side of the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A manned ticket gate and a shop (service center) are located on the north side of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>有人改札口を入ったところ（改札階から見ると中2階的な空間にあたる）には『御池駅ギャラリー』があり地域の情報や美術工芸品が掲示・展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering from the manned ticket gate, you will find &quot;Oike Station Gallery&quot; (in a mezzanine-like space when viewed from the gate-placed level), where local information and art/craft works are displayed or exhibited</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering from the manned ticket gate, you will find &quot;Oike Station Gallery&quot; (in a mezzanine-like space when viewed from the gate-placed level), where local information and art/craft works are displayed.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering from the manned ticket gate, you will find &quot;Oike Station Gallery&quot; (in a mezzanine-like space when viewed from the gate-placed level), where local information and art/craft works are displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>駅の北側には烏丸御池交差点（烏丸通と御池通）があり閑静なオフィス街を形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the Karasuma Oike crossing on the northern side of this station, the area around it constitutes a quiet business district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the Karasuma Oike crossing on the north side of this station, the area around it constitutes a quiet business district.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the Karasuma Oike crossing (Karasuma-dori Street and Oike-dori Street) on the north side of this station, the area around it constitutes a quiet business district.</e>
<cmt>烏丸通と御池通　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>新風館（旧京都中央電話局）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIN-PUH-KAN (Shimpukan) (former Kyoto Central Telephone Office)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIN-PUH-KAN (Shimpukan) (formerly the Kyoto Central Telephone Office)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHIN-PUH-KAN (Shinpukan) (formerly the Kyoto Central Telephone Office)</e>
<cmt>Shinpukan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>中京郵便局（旧京都郵便電信局：国の重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakagyo Post Office (former Kyoto Post &amp; Telegraph office: national important cultural property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakagyo Post Office (formerly the Kyoto Post &amp; Telegraph office, a national important cultural property)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakagyo Post Office (formerly the Kyoto Post &amp; Telegraph office, a national important cultural property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>京都文化博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Museum of Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Museum of Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Museum of Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>別館（旧日本銀行京都支店：国の重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The annex (former Bank of Japan Kyoto Branch: national important cultural property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The annex (formerly the Bank of Japan Kyoto Branch, a national important cultural property)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The annex (formerly the Bank of Japan Kyoto Branch, a national important cultural property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>ニチコン本社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The headquaters of Nichicon Corporation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headquaters of Nichicon Corporation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headquarters of Nichicon Corporation</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>京都国際マンガミュージアム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto International Manga Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto International Manga Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto International Manga Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>京都市女性活動センター（ウィングス京都）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wings Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wings Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wings Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>京都市中京青少年活動センター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto-shi [Kyoto City] Nakagyo Youth Action Center</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-shi [Kyoto City] Nakagyo Youth Action Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-shi [Kyoto City] Nakagyo Youth Action Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>ハローワーク烏丸御池</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hellow Work (public employment security office) Karasuma Oike</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hello Work (public employment security office) Karasuma Oike</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hello Work (public employment security office) Karasuma Oike</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="23">
<j>京都労働局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Labour Bureau</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Labour Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Labour Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>西日本電信電話京都支店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto branch of Nippon Telegraph and Telephone West Corporation (NTT West)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto branch of Nippon Telegraph and Telephone West Corporation (NTT West)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto branch of Nippon Telegraph and Telephone West Corporation (NTT West)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="25">
<j>六角堂(頂法寺)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokkaku-do (Choho-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokkaku-do (Choho-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokkaku-do (Choho-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>1981年5月29日 - 烏丸線北大路～京都間の開通とともに御池駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 29, 1981 - Corresponding to the start of operation of the portion between Kitaoji Station and Kyoto of Karasuma Line, this station started its operation as the Oike station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 29, 1981 - Corresponding to the operational start of the portion between Kitaoji Station and Kyoto on the Karasuma Line, this station started its operation as Oike Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 29, 1981: Corresponding to the operational start of the portion between Kitaoji Station and Kyoto Station on the Karasuma Line, this station started its operation as Oike Station.</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Station としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>1997年5月22日 - 東西線開業に備え、烏丸御池駅と改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 22, 1997 - Its name was changed to Karasuma Oike preparing for the start of operation of Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 22, 1997 - Its name was changed to Karasuma Oike in preparation for the start of operations of the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 22, 1997: Its name was changed to Karasuma Oike in preparation for the start of operations of the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>1997年10月12日 - 東西線醍醐～二条間開業、乗換駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 12, 1997 - The portion between Daigo Station and Nijo Station of Tozai Line started its operation, and this station became the one where the train lines to be used can be changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 12, 1997 - The portion between Daigo Station and Nijo Station on the Tozai Line started its operation, and this station became the one at which the train lines to be used could be changed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 12, 1997: The portion between Daigo Station and Nijo Station on the Tozai Line started its operation, and this station became the one at which the train lines to be used could be changed.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>2007年4月1日 - PiTaPa使用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 2007 - PiTaPa became usable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 2007 - PiTaPa came into use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 2007: PiTaPa came into use.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>2008年1月16日 - 京阪京津線直通、乗り入れ開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 16, 2008 - Use of this station by trains of Keihan Keishin Line started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 16, 2008 - Trains of the Keihan Keishin Line started using this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 16, 2008: Trains of the Keihan Keishin Line started using this station.</e>
<cmt>- → :　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>東西線開業前は、単なる通過駅でありビジネス街としての発展度も低かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Tozai Line started its operation, not many passengers got off trains at this station and the area around it was not well developed as a business district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Tozai Line commenced operations, not many passengers got off trains at this station; consequently, the area around it wasn&apos;t well developed as a business district.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Tozai Line commenced operations, not many passengers got off trains at this station; consequently, the area around it wasn&apos;t well developed as a business district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>東西線開業後は、京都市内唯一の地下鉄の交差する交通至便の場所として駅周辺が発展し始めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tozai Line started its operation, this station, becoming only one subway station in Kyoto City where two subway lines crossed, was able to provide quite convenirent transportation means, promoting development of the area around the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the Tozai Line started operating, this station, becoming the only subway station in Kyoto City where two subway lines crossed, was able to provide very convenient transportation means, thus promoting the development of the area around the station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the Tozai Line started operating, this station, becoming the only subway station in Kyoto City where two subway lines crossed, was able to provide very convenient transportation means, thus promoting the development of the area around the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>第2回近畿の駅百選選定駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station was selected in the second event for a selection of 100 prominent stations in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station was among those chosen in the second selection of 100 prominent stations in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station was among those chosen in the second selection of 100 prominent stations in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>京都市営地下鉄烏丸線は烏丸通に交差する通り名のみを駅名に名づけてきた（例、五条駅、丸太町駅など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Karasuma Line of Kyoto City Subwway, where a station was placed at the crossing of a street and the Karasuma street, only the street name has been given as the station name as well (such as Gojo Station and Marutamachi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Karasuma Line of the Kyoto City Subway, where a station was placed at the crossing of a street and the Karasuma street, only the street name and station name are given (such as Gojo Station and Marutamachi).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the Karasuma Line of the Kyoto Municipal Subway, where a station was placed at the crossing of a street and the Karasuma-dori Street, only the street name was given as the station name (such as Gojo Station and Marutamachi Station).</e>
<cmt>烏丸通に交差する通り名のみを駅名に名づけた　の箇所を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この駅も烏丸線開業当初は「御池」駅であったが、東西線開通を控えて交差点名と同じ「烏丸御池」に改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of this station was initially &quot;Oike&quot;Station when Karasuma Line started its operation, but was changed to &quot;Karasuma Oike,&quot; the name of the crossing, preparing the opening of Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of this station was initially &quot;Oike&quot; Station when the Karasuma Line commenced operations, but it was changed to &quot;Karasuma Oike,&quot; the name of the crossing, in preparation for the opening of the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of this station was initially &apos;Oike&apos; Station when the Karasuma Line commenced operations, but it was changed to &apos;Karasuma Oike,&apos; the name of the crossing, in preparation for the opening of the Tozai Line.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>京都市営地下鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>city→ municipal　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>■烏丸線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt>記号削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>丸太町駅_(京都市営地下鉄)(K07) - 烏丸御池駅(K08) - 四条駅_(京都市営地下鉄)(K09)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marutamachi Station (Kyoto City Subway) (K07) - Karasuma Oike Station (K08) - Shijo Station (Kyoto City Subway) ((k09)</e>
<cmt>”四条駅_”の”_”は無視して訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marutamachi Station (Kyoto City Subway) (K07) - Karasuma Oike Station (K08) - Shijo Station (Kyoto City Subway) ((k09)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marutamachi Station (Kyoto Municipal Subway) (K07) - Karasuma Oike Station (K08) - Shijo Station (Kyoto Municipal Subway) (K09)</e>
<cmt>city→ municipal　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>■東西線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ Tozai Line</e>
<cmt>Tozai Line</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ Tozai Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tozai Line</e>
<cmt>記号削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="40">
<j>京都市役所前駅(T12) - 烏丸御池駅(T13) - 二条城前駅(T14)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Shiyakusho-mae Station (T12) - Karasuma Oike Station (T13) - Nijojo-mae Station (T14)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Shiyakusho-mae Station (T12) - Karasuma Oike Station (T13) - Nijojo-mae Station (T14)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Shiyakusho-mae Station (T12) - Karasuma Oike Station (T13) - Nijojo-mae Station (T14)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tau(id:629), Shain2006(id:66860), Irc(id:67862), ゴンボ(id:22207), 城山(id:104901), Bellcricket(id:37640), Wikipedianet(id:9608), Tigers boy(id:15761), 絵描きのやす(id:70642), Mari(id:1553), Sunen(id:10700), 絵描き教室(id:150968), LAMS(id:131528), Goki(id:7107), Har-Poon-SSM(id:72987), Hirotaro(id:1437), Alljal(id:46858), Kyoww(id:126965), STB-1(id:8775), 癒し絵作家 絵描きのやす(id:135203), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Sushiya(id:110938), TRIBESMAN(id:4735), 七之輔(id:55793), Lonicera(id:20638), Hideyuki(id:9577), Etopirica(id:32491), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), 松茸(id:27535), こうやま(id:74302), 絵が伝える感動(id:172537), Felicemente(id:43126), S-PAI(id:4705), Memeja(id:110500), Utsuda(id:605), 素館(id:20524), Rusk(id:9895), Ktr(id:30468), ハイゼン(id:21182), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Kyoto-u(id:96969), Hidama(id:73276), I-Yassie(id:143230), 210.(id:9838), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>