<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>タンゴディスカバリー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited Express Tango Discovery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Limited Express Tango Discovery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limited Express Tango Discovery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>タンゴディスカバリーとは、北近畿タンゴ鉄道が運行する特別急行列車で、同列車に運用される北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR8000形気動車の愛称でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tango Discovery&quot; is a type of Limited Express train operated by Kitakinki Tango Railway, and is the nickname of Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR Type 8000 diesel multiple unit used for the this train service.</e>
<cmt>北近畿タンゴ鉄道→Kitakinki Tango Railway [http://ktr-tetsudo.jp]、北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR8000形→定訳不明 [Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR Type 8000]、気動車→diesel multiple uni　[英辞郎on the WEB]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Tango Discovery&quot; is a type of limited express train operated by Kitakinki Tango Railway, and it&apos;s the nickname for the Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR Type 8000 diesel multiple unit used for this train service.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Tango Discovery&quot; is a type of limited express train operated by Kitakinki Tango Railway, and it&apos;s the nickname for the Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR Type 8000 diesel multiple unit used for this train service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この愛称は、日本語で「丹後国発見」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This nickname means &quot;Discovery of Tango Province&quot; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>「丹後国発見」→定訳不明 [Discovery of Tango Province]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nickname means &quot;Discovery of Tango Province&quot; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nickname means &apos;Discovery of Tango Province&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>北近畿ビッグXネットワークを形成する列車の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a part of the trains that form the Kita (north) Kinki Big X Network.</e>
<cmt>北近畿ビッグXネットワーク→定訳不明 [Kita (north) Kinki Big X Network ]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s among the trains that form the Kita (north) Kinki Big X Network.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s among the trains that form the Kita (north) Kinki Big X Network.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>現行の運転系統</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current operation system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current system of operation</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current system of operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>運転系統としては、京都駅から西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）山陰本線経由で、舞鶴線の東舞鶴駅および北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮福線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮津線経由で豊岡駅 (兵庫県)に直通運転する系統と、天橋立駅で特急「はしだて (列車)」又は「文殊 (列車)」に接続し、宮津線内で完結する系統の2種がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two operation routes starting from Kyoto via the West Japan Railway (JR West) San&apos;in Line; one is the route to reach directly to Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture) through Higashi-Maizuru Station on the Maizuru Line, and through the Kitakinki Tango Railway Miyafuku Line and Kitakinki Tango Railway Miyazu Line; the other is the route in which the train terminates on the Miyazu Line after making a connection with Limited Express &quot;Hashidate (train)&quot; or &quot;Monju (train).&quot;</e>
<cmt>「近畿タンゴ鉄道宮福線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮津線経由」の場合の「・」は&quot;and&quot;の意味と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two operation routes starting from Kyoto via the West Japan Railway (JR West) San&apos;in Line: the route that goes directly to Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture) through Higashi-Maizuru Station on the Maizuru Line, and through the Kitakinki Tango Railway Miyafuku Line and Kitakinki Tango Railway Miyazu Line; and the route in which the train terminates on the Miyazu Line after making a connection with the limited express &quot;Hashidate&quot; train or &quot;Monju&quot; (train).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two operation routes starting from Kyoto via the West Japan Railway Company (JR West) Sanin Main Line: the route that goes directly to Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture) through Higashi-Maizuru Station on the Maizuru Line, and through the Kitakinki Tango Railway Miyafuku Line and Kitakinki Tango Railway Miyazu Line; and the route in which the train terminates on the Miyazu Line after making a connection with the limited express trains &apos;Hashidate (train)&apos; or &apos;Monju (train).&apos;</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを削除し、Sanin としました。&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>いずれも、専用のKTR8000形気動車を使用する特急列車に付与されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of them are operated with the Express Train using its dedicated KTR Type 8000 diesel multiple unit.</e>
<cmt>「に付与されている。」→「が運用されている」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of them are operated with the express train using its dedicated KTR Type 8000 diesel multiple unit.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both of them are operated with the express train using its dedicated KTR Type 8000 diesel multiple unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>京都直通系統については、2往復が運転されているが、うち1号・2号・4号は、京都～豊岡駅 (兵庫県)間の列車と京都～東舞鶴駅間の列車が綾部駅で分割併合する多層建て列車となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The direct route to Kyoto provide 2 round service with a train set of layered structure, and Tango Discovery 1, 2, and 4 are decoupled and coupled at Ayabe Station in case that that are running between Kyoto Station and Toyooka (Hyogo Prefecture) and between Higashi-Maizuru Station.</e>
<cmt>分割併合する→decoupled and coupled [鉄道技術用語辞典online参照, online, http:www.yougo.rtri.or.jp/dic/]、多層建て列車→rain set of layered structre[鉄道技術用語辞典online参照,, http:www.yougo.rtri.or.jp/dic/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The direct route to Kyoto provides two round-trip services with a train set of layered structure, and Tango Discovery 1, 2, and 4 are decoupled and coupled at Ayabe Station when running between Kyoto Station and Toyooka (Hyogo Prefecture) and between Kyoto Station and Higashi-Maizuru Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar. ASSUMING between Kyoto and Higashi-Maizuru</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The direct route to Kyoto provides two round-trip services with a train set of layered structure, and Tango Discovery nos. 1, 2, and 4 are decoupled and coupled at Ayabe Station when running between Kyoto Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture) and between Kyoto Station and Higashi-Maizuru Station.</e>
<cmt>Station を追加しました。Discovery nos. x,x and x としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、1号は久美浜から豊岡まで、2号は豊岡から久美浜まで快速列車として運転される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Discovery 1 is operated as a Rapid train from Kumihama Station to Toyooka Station, and Tango Discovery 2 from Toyooka Station to Mihama Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Discovery 1 is operated as a rapid train from Kumihama Station to Toyooka Station, and Tango Discovery 2 operates as a rapid train from Toyooka Station to Mihama Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Discovery No. 1 is operated as a rapid train from Kumihama Station to Toyooka Station, and Tango Discovery No. 2 operates as a rapid train from Toyooka Station to Kumihama Station.</e>
<cmt>Discovery No. x としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>3号は京都～福知山・東舞鶴間のみの運転で北近畿タンゴ鉄道線内に乗り入れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Discovery 3 is operated only between Kyoto Station and Fukuchiyama Station/Higashi-Maizuru Station, and does not run on the lines of Kitakinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Discovery 3 is operated only between Kyoto Station and Fukuchiyama Station/Higashi-Maizuru Station; it doesn&apos;t run on the lines of Kitakinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Discovery No. 3 is operated only between Kyoto Station and Fukuchiyama Station/Higashi-Maizuru Station; it doesn&apos;t run on the lines of Kitakinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt>Discovery No. x としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>豊岡発着便は宮津駅で、東舞鶴発着便は綾部駅で進行方向が変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trains starting from and terminating at Toyooka Station change their traveling direction at Miyazu Station, and those starting from and terminating at Higashi-Maizuru Station at Ayabe Station.</e>
<cmt>進行方向→定訳不明 [traveling directionとしました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trains starting from and terminating at Toyooka Station change their direction of travel at Miyazu Station, and those starting from and terminating at Higashi-Maizuru Station change at Ayabe Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trains arriving at and departing from Toyooka Station change their direction of travel at Miyazu Station, and those arriving at and departing from Higashi-Maizuru Station change at Ayabe Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot;starting from and terminating at&quot; -&gt; &quot;arriving at and departing from&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>列車番号は、東舞鶴発着が号数+3000D、北近畿タンゴ鉄道線内では号数+3010Dである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the numbering of train units, the trains starting from and terminating at Higashi-Maizuru Station are identified with the ordinal train number + 3000D, and those operated within the Kitakinki Tango lines are identified with the train number + 3010D</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the numbering of train units, the trains starting from and terminating at Higashi-Maizuru Station are identified with the ordinal train number + 3000D, and those operated within the Kitakinki Tango lines are identified with the train number + 3010D</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the numbering of train units, the trains arriving at and departing from Higashi-Maizuru Station are identified with the ordinal train number + 3000D, and those operated within the Kitakinki Tango lines are identified with the train number + 3010D</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>京都～綾部・福知山間は、電車特急である「きのさき」「たんば」「まいづる」に比すると所要時間の面で劣る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To run between Kyoto Station and Ayabe Station/Fukuchiyama Station, this train requires much time compared with the electric multiple-unit limited express trains such as &quot;Kinosaki,&quot; &quot;Tanba,&quot; and &quot;Maizuru.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To run between Kyoto Station and Ayabe Station/Fukuchiyama Station, this train requires considerable time compared with electric multiple-unit limited express trains such as &quot;Kinosaki,&quot; &quot;Tanba&quot; and &quot;Maizuru.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To run between Kyoto Station and Ayabe Station/Fukuchiyama Station, this train requires considerable time compared with electric multiple-unit limited express trains such as &apos;Kinosaki,&apos; &apos;Tanba&apos; and &apos;Maizuru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。&quot;Tamba&quot; -&gt; &quot;Tanba&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>北近畿タンゴ鉄道線内での運行概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operational outline on the Kitakinki Tango Railway lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operational outline on the Kitakinki Tango Railway lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Operational outline on the Kitakinki Tango Railway lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>北近畿タンゴ鉄道線内完結系統については、天橋立～豊岡間に2往復が設定されており、号数は60・70番台が付与されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of the route that terminates within the Kitakinki Tango Railway lines, 2 round services are provided between Amanohashidate Station and Toyooka Station, and these trains are given a certain number in the 60s or 70s as their train number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the route that terminates within the Kitakinki Tango Railway lines, two round-trip services are provided between Amanohashidate Station and Toyooka Station, and these trains are given certain numbers in the 60s or 70s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the route that terminates within the Kitakinki Tango Railway lines, two round-trip services are provided between Amanohashidate Station and Toyooka Station, and these trains are given certain numbers in the 60s or 70s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>列車番号は、号数Dである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The train number of these trains are composed by the ordinal number (&quot;go-su&quot;) and the letter &quot;D&quot;.</e>
<cmt>号数→定訳不明 [ordinal number (&quot;go-su&quot;) としました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The numbers of these trains comprise the ordinal number (&quot;go-su&quot;) and the letter &quot;D.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The numbers of these trains comprise the ordinal number (&quot;go-su&quot;) and the letter &quot;D.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>京都直通の系統運行開始以前は、2編成で運用され、ほとんどの「はしだて」・「文殊」と連絡をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until this direct route to Kyoto was set up, the operation was carried out with the trains made up of 2 cars, and most of them made a connection with &quot;Hashidate&quot; or &quot;Monju.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until this direct route to Kyoto was set up, the operation was carried out with trains made up of two cars, and most of them connected with &quot;Hashidate&quot; or &quot;Monju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until this direct route to Kyoto was set up, the operation was carried out with trains made up of two cars, and most of them connected with &apos;Hashidate&apos; or &apos;Monju.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、綾部で京都方面の特急と連絡の上、綾部～天橋立・久美浜間（綾部～西舞鶴間快速）を運行し、非電化だった舞鶴線の特急連絡を担う系統もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was another route to secure a connection with a Limited Express train on the then unelectrified Maizuru Line, and the trains were operated between Ayabe Station and Amanohashidate Station/Kumihama Station (between Ayabe and Nishi-Maizuru, the trains are operated as Rapid) by making a connection at Ayabe Station with a Limited Express train proceeding to the Kyoto area.</e>
<cmt>非電化→unelectrified [プログレッシブ英和中辞典辞典参照]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was another route to secure a connection with a limited express train on the Maizuru Line (which wasn&apos;t electrified), and the trains were operated between Ayabe Station and Amanohashidate Station/Kumihama Station (between Ayabe and Nishi-Maizuru they&apos;re operated as rapid trains) by making a connection at Ayabe Station with a limited express train proceeding to the Kyoto area.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was another route to secure a connection with a limited express train on the Maizuru Line (which wasn&apos;t electrified), and the trains were operated between Ayabe Station and Amanohashidate Station/Kumihama Station (between Ayabe and Nishi-Maizuru they&apos;re operated as rapid trains) by making a connection at Ayabe Station with a limited express train proceeding to the Kyoto area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>現在は、1編成のみで運用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the operation is undertaken with only one-train set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the operation is undertaken with only one train set.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the operation is undertaken with only one train set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>2往復とも、西舞鶴～天橋立間において、列車番号を変更の上、普通列車（64・72号は、土曜・休日のみ「タンゴ悠遊号」として運転）として運転する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In both of 2 round services, between Nishi-Maihara Station and Amanohashidate Station, the train changes its train number and is operated as a Local train (Tango Discovery 64 and 72 are operated only on Sundays and holidays as Limited Express &quot;Tango-yuyu&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In each of two round-trip services between Nishi-Maihara Station and Amanohashidate Station, the train changes its train number and is operated as a local train (Tango Discovery 64 and 72 are operated only on Sundays and holidays as the limited express &quot;Tango-yuyu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In each of two round-trip services between Nishi-Maizuru Station and Amanohashidate Station, the train changes its train number and is operated as a local train (Tango Discovery nos. 64 and 72 are operated only on Saturdays and holidays as the limited express &apos;Tango-yuyu&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Nishi-Maizuru としました。Sunday →Saturday としました。&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>それぞれの連絡特急列車は、以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Followings are connecting Limited Express trains available:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are the available connecting limited express trains:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are the available connecting limited express trains:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>63号･･･天橋立にて「はしだて_(列車)」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Discovery 63…Limited Express &quot;Hashidate (train)&quot; at Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Discovery 63…The limited express &quot;Hashidate (train)&quot; at Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Discovery No. 63: The Limited Express &apos;Hashidate (train)&apos; at Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>67号･･･天橋立にて「はしだて7号」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Discovery 67…Limited Express &quot;Hashidate 7&quot; at Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Discovery 67…The limited express &quot;Hashidate 7&quot; at Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Discovery No. 67: The Limited Express &apos;Hashidate No. 7&apos; at Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>64号･･･※連絡する特急はなし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Discovery 64…※ no connection with a Limited Express train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Discovery 64…※ no connection with a limited express train</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Discovery No. 64: * no connection with a limited express train</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>72号･･･天橋立にて「文殊_(列車)」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Discovery 72…Limited Express &quot;Monju (train)&quot; at Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Discovery 72…The limited express &quot;Monju (train)&quot; at Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Discovery No. 72: The Limited Express &apos;Monju (train)&apos; at Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="25">
<j>使用車両・編成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling stock used and train sets</e>
<cmt>編成　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR8000形気動車を使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The train uses Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR 8000 Type diesel multiple unit.</e>
<cmt>北近畿タンゴ鉄道KTR8000形気動車→定訳不明 [Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR 8000 Type diesel multiple unitとしました。ただし、気動車 [英辞郎 on the WEB]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The train uses the Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR 8000 Type diesel multiple unit.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The train uses the Kitakinki Tango Railway KTR Type 8000 diesel multiple unit.</e>
<cmt>Type 8000として統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>全車両普通車_(鉄道車両)として運用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All train sets are operated as ordinary cars (railway vehicle).</e>
<cmt>普通車→ordinary car 「http://www.jreast.co.jp/e/ticket/types.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All train sets are operated as ordinary cars (railway vehicles).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All train sets are operated as ordinary cars (railway vehicles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="28">
<j>記号凡例 自＝自由席、指＝座席指定席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend symbol: 自＝Non-reserved seat, 指＝Reserved seat</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend symbols: 自＝Non-reserved seat, 指＝Reserved seat</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend symbols: 自＝Non-reserved seat, 指＝Reserved seat</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="29">
<j>1・2号車は豊岡・福知山←→京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cars No.1 and No.2 are operated between Toyooka Station/Fukuchiyama Station and Kyoto Station (Toyooka/Fukuchiyama←→Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Car nos. 1 and 2 are operated between Toyooka Station/Fukuchiyama Station and Kyoto Station (Toyooka/Fukuchiyama←→Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Car nos. 1 and 2 are operated between Toyooka Station/Fukuchiyama Station and Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>括弧を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>5・6号車は東舞鶴←→京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cars No.5 and No.6 are operated between Higashi-Maizuru Station and Kyoto Station (Higashi-Maizuru←→Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Car nos. 5 and 6 are operated between Higashi-Maizuru Station and Kyoto Station (Higashi-Maizuru←→Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Car nos. 5 and 6 are operated between Higashi-Maizuru Station and Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>括弧を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>綾部～東舞鶴間、宮津～豊岡は逆向き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Ayabe Station and Higashi-Maizuru Station, and between Miyazu Station and Toyooka Station, the moving direction is inverted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Ayabe Station and Higashi-Maizuru Station, and between Miyazu Station and Toyooka Station, the direction of movement is inverted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Ayabe Station and Higashi-Maizuru Station, and between Miyazu Station and Toyooka Station, the direction of movement is inverted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>繁忙期には2号車と5号車の間に3・4号車が増結される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During busy seasons, between the car No.2 and No.5, two cars, No.3 and 4, are coupled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During busy seasons, between car nos. 2 and 5, two cars--nos. 3 and 4--are coupled.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During busy seasons, between car nos. 2 and 5, two cars--nos. 3 and 4--are coupled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="33">
<j>1～4号を除く列車は1・2号車のみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for Tango Discovery 1-go to 4-go, the trains are made up of only two cars, the 1st and 2nd cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for Tango Discovery 1-go to 4-go, the trains are made up of only two cars: the first and second cars.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for Tango Discovery nos. 1, 2, 3 and 4, the trains are made up of only two cars: the first and second cars.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="34">
<j>運行区間・停車駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operation section and stops</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operation section and stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Operation section and stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>運行区間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operation section</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operating section</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Operating section</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>京都駅〜豊岡駅 (兵庫県)／東舞鶴駅間下り1本・上り2本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Kyoto Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture)/Higashi-Maizuru Station: 1 down train and 2 up trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Kyoto Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture)/Higashi-Maizuru Station: One down train and two up trains</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Kyoto Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture)/Higashi-Maizuru Station: One outbound train and two inbound trains</e>
<cmt>上り、下り→inbound, outboundとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>京都駅〜福知山駅／東舞鶴駅間下り1本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Kyoto Station and Fukuchiyama Station/Higashi-Maizuru Station: 1 down train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Kyoto Station and Fukuchiyama Station/Higashi-Maizuru Station: One down train</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Kyoto Station and Fukuchiyama Station/Higashi-Maizuru Station: One outbound train</e>
<cmt>上り、下り→inbound, outboundとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>天橋立駅〜豊岡駅 (兵庫県)間2往復</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Amanohashidate Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture): 2 round services</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Amanohashidate Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture): Two round-trip services</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Amanohashidate Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture): Two round-trip services</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="39">
<j>停車駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stops</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>京都駅 - 二条駅 -　亀岡駅 -　園部駅 -　綾部駅 - 福知山駅 - 大江駅 (京都府) - 宮津駅 - 天橋立駅 - 野田川駅 - 丹後大宮駅 - 峰山駅 - 網野駅 - 木津温泉駅 - （丹後神野駅） - 久美浜駅 - 豊岡駅 (兵庫県)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station -　Kameoka Station -　Sonobe Station -　Ayabe Station - Fukuchiyama Station - Oe Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station - Nodagawa Station - Tango-Omiya Station - Mineyama Station - Amino Station - Kizu-onsen Station - （Tango-Kanno Station） - Kumihama Station - Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station -　Kameoka Station -　Sonobe Station -　Ayabe Station - Fukuchiyama Station - Oe Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station - Nodagawa Station - Tango-Omiya Station - Mineyama Station - Amino Station - Kizu-onsen Station - （Tango-Kanno Station） - Kumihama Station - Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station -　Kameoka Station -　Sonobe Station -　Ayabe Station - Fukuchiyama Station - Oe Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station - Nodagawa Station - Tango-Omiya Station - Mineyama Station - Amino Station - Kizu-onsen Station - （Tango-Kanno Station） - Kumihama Station - Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="41">
<j>（）内の駅は天橋立駅発着の一部列車が停車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stations in the parenthesis are the stops of some of the trains starting from and terminating at Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stations shown in parentheses are the stops of some of the trains starting from and terminating at Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stations shown in parentheses are the stops of some of the trains arriving at and departing from Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot;starting from and terminating at&quot; -&gt; &quot;arriving at and departing from&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="42">
<j>東舞鶴駅発着編成は綾部駅以降以下の停車駅に停車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The train sets that start and terminate at Higashi-Maizuru Station make a stop at Ayabe Station and the subsequent stations as follows</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The train sets that start and terminate at Higashi-Maizuru Station make stops at Ayabe Station and the subsequent stations as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The train sets that arrive at and depart from Higashi-Maizuru Station make stops at Ayabe Station and the subsequent stations as follows:</e>
<cmt>&quot;start and terminate at&quot; -&gt; &quot;arrive at and depart from&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="43">
<j>綾部駅　-　西舞鶴駅 - 東舞鶴駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - Higashi-Maizuru Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - Higashi-Maizuru Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - Higashi-Maizuru Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="44">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporate History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corporate History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="45">
<j>1996年3月16日、新大阪駅～久美浜駅間を福知山線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮福線・宮津線経由で運行する列車を運行開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 16, 1996: The train service started between Shin-Osaka Station and Kumihama Station via the Fukuchiyama Line, and the Miyafuku Line and the Miyazu Line of Kinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 16, 1996: The train service started between Shin-Osaka Station and Kumihama Station via the Fukuchiyama Line, and between the Miyafuku Line and the Miyazu Line of the Kinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 16, 1996: The train service started between Shin-Osaka Station and Kumihama Station via the Fukuchiyama Line, the Miyafuku Line and the Miyazu Line of the Kinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt>and between を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>新大阪駅～福知山駅間はエル特急「北近畿 (列車)」と連結して運行開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Shin-Osaka Station and Fukuchiyama Station, the train coupled with L-limited Express &quot;Kita-Kinki (train)&quot; began the operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Shin-Osaka Station and Fukuchiyama Station, the operation started with the train coupled with the L-limited express &quot;Kita-Kinki (train).&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Shin-Osaka Station and Fukuchiyama Station, the operation started with the train coupled with the L-Limited Express &apos;Kita-Kinki (train).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、綾部駅～豊岡駅 (兵庫県)間を京都駅より運行される列車に接続する特別急行列車として運行開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Ayabe Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture), the train began the operation as a Special Express train, which makes a connection with the train operated from Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Ayabe Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture), the train began the operation as a special express train, which makes a connection with the train that&apos;s operated from Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Ayabe Station and Toyooka Station (Hyogo Prefecture), the train began the operation as a special express train, which makes a connection with the train that&apos;s operated from Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この列車は、綾部駅～西舞鶴駅間のJR西日本管内は快速列車扱い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This train is categorized as Rapid in the section between Ayabe Station and Nishi-Maizuru Station, which is controlled by JR West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This train is categorized as &quot;rapid&quot; in the section between Ayabe Station and Nishi-Maizuru Station, which is controlled by JR West.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This train is categorized as &quot;rapid&quot; in the section between Ayabe Station and Nishi-Maizuru Station, which is controlled by JR West.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="49">
<j>1999年10月2日、舞鶴線電化に伴い運転系統を「タンゴエクスプローラー」と振替え、「京都駅 - 二条駅 -　亀岡駅 -　園部駅 -　綾部駅 - 西舞鶴駅 - （丹後神崎駅） - （丹後由良駅） - 宮津駅 - 天橋立駅 - 野田川駅 - 丹後大宮駅 - 峰山駅 - 網野駅 - 木津温泉駅 - （丹後神野駅） - 久美浜駅 - 豊岡駅 - 城崎温泉駅」に変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 2, 1999: Following the electrification of the Maizuru Line, the operation route was changed by transferring to Limited Express &quot;Tango Explorer&quot; with the following stops: Kyoto Station - Nijo Station -　Kameoka Station -　Sonobe Station -　Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - （Tamgo-Kanzaki Station） - （Tango Yura Station） - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station - Nodagawa Station - Tango-Omiya Station - Mineyama Station - Amino Station - Kizu-onsen Station- （Tango-Kanno Station） - Kumihama Station - Toyooka Station - Kinosakionsen Station.</e>
<cmt>「タンゴエクスプローラー」と振替え→transferring it (Tango Discovery) to Limited Express [下線部の意味がよくわかりませんでした。「タンゴディスカバリーに替わって・・・」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 2, 1999: Following the electrification of the Maizuru Line, the operation route was changed by transferring to the limited express &quot;Tango Explorer&quot; with the following stops: Kyoto Station - Nijo Station -　Kameoka Station -　Sonobe Station -　Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - （Tamgo-Kanzaki Station） - （Tango Yura Station） - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station - Nodagawa Station - Tango-Omiya Station - Mineyama Station - Amino Station - Kizu-onsen Station- （Tango-Kanno Station） - Kumihama Station - Toyooka Station - Kinosakionsen Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 2, 1999: Following the electrification of the Maizuru Line, the operation route was changed by transferring to the Limited Express &apos;Tango Explorer&apos; with the following stops: Kyoto Station - Nijo Station -　Kameoka Station -　Sonobe Station -　Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - （Tango-Kanzaki Station） - （Tango Yura Station） - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station - Nodagawa Station - Tango-Omiya Station - Mineyama Station - Amino Station - Kizu-onsen Station- （Tango-Kanno Station） - Kumihama Station - Toyooka Station - Kinosakionsen Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="50">
<j>2005年6月19日、JR福知山線脱線事故の影響で運休していた福知山線運転再開に伴うダイヤ改正による編成変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 19, 2005: the train set was changed by the timetable revision made following the restarted operation of the Fukuchiyama Line, which had been suspended because of the JR Fukuchiyama Line derailment accident.</e>
<cmt>JR福知山線脱線事故→定訳不明 [JR Fukuchiyama Line derailment accidentとしました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 19, 2005: The train set was changed by the timetable revision made following the restarted operation of the Fukuchiyama Line, which had been suspended due to the JR Fukuchiyama Line derailment accident.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 19, 2005: The train set was changed by the timetable revision made following the restarted operation of the Fukuchiyama Line, which had been suspended due to the JR Fukuchiyama Line derailment accident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>JR線乗り入れ列車は、多客期はJR線内は183系で運転されていたが現在はATS-P型のつけられていない車両での運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trains that were running on the JR lines were operated with Series 183 while they were on the JR Line during busy seasons, however nowadays the cars used in the section are not equipped with ATS-P type system.</e>
<cmt>183系→定訳不明： [JNR Series 183としました]、ATS-P型→ 速度パターン方式[ATS-P type systemとしました, http://www.geocities.co.jp/Technopolis-Mars/8897/FIG/320p/atsp_why.html参照]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trains that were running on the JR lines were operated with Series 183 while they were on the JR Line during busy seasons, but nowadays the cars used in the section aren&apos;t equipped with the ATS-P type system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trains that were running on the JR lines were operated with Series 183 while they were on the JR Line during busy seasons, but nowadays the cars used in the section aren&apos;t equipped with the ATS-P type system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>但しKTR線内のみの列車はKTR001形気動車「タンゴエクスプローラー」の編成での運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in case that they are operated exclusively on the KRT lines, the operation is undertaken with KRT001 type diesel multiple unit Limited Express known &quot;Limited Express Tango Explorer.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「タンゴエクスプローラー」→ &quot;Limited Express Tango Explorer&quot; [http://ktr-tetsudo.jp/information/H21miyaduekimiyahuku.pdf]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the event they&apos;re operated exclusively on the KRT lines, the operation is undertaken with the KRT001 type diesel multiple unit limited express known as &quot;Limited Express Tango Explorer.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the event they&apos;re operated exclusively on the KTR lines, the operation is undertaken with the KTR Type 001 diesel multiple unit limited express known as &apos;Tango Explorer.&apos;</e>
<cmt>KRT →KTR　としました。Type 001としました。&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="53">
<j>2005年夏、KTR8000系1編成が故障のため、京都～西舞鶴間を国鉄183系電車により約20日間代走。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In summer 2005: A train set made up of one KTR　8000 Series car was broken down and the service between Kyoto Station and Nishi-Maizuru Station was substituted by JNR Series 183 for about 20 days.</e>
<cmt>KTR8000系1編成→定訳不明 [a train set made up of one KTR　8000 Series car、編成→train set[鉄道技術用語辞典 online] を参照しました]、国鉄183系→定訳不明 [JNR Series 183としました。　なお、この行以外（4, 11, 41行）ではKTR8000形（KTR　8000 Type）とあります、同じものでしょうか]]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In summer 2005: A train set made up of one KTR 8000 Series car was broken down and the service between Kyoto Station and Nishi-Maizuru Station was substituted by JNR Series 183 for a period of approximately 20 days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In summer 2005: A train set made up of one KTR 8000 Series car was broken down and the service between Kyoto Station and Nishi-Maizuru Station was substituted by JNR Series 183 for a period of approximately 20 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="54">
<j>2007年3月18日、全面禁煙化を実施。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 18. 2007: All trains became no-smoking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 18, 2007: All trains became non-smoking.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 18, 2007: All trains became non-smoking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="55">
<j>2008年3月15日、福知山経由となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 15, 2008: The trains began operating through Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 15, 2008: The trains began operating through Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 15, 2008: The trains began operating through Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>快速として運行していた1・64号の豊岡駅～城崎温泉駅間廃止（経路変更後は1号が福知山駅で「北近畿7号」と対面接続できるようになったための措置だと思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Discovery 1 and 64, which had been operated between Toyooka Station and Kinosakionsen Station, became discontinued (this measure was probably taken because after the route had changed, Tango Discovery 1 became able to make a cross-platform connection (connection that allows cross-platform transfer) with Limited Express &quot;Kitakinki 7&quot; at Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>対面接続→cross-platform connection[http://www.railroad.net/forums/viewtopic.php?f=46&amp;t=59336&amp;p=656206, http://www.aatob.org.uk/Bike_Rail.htmlなど参照: (connection that allows cross-platform transfer) を加えてあります。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Discovery 1 and 64, which had been operated between Toyooka Station and Kinosakionsen Station, were discontinued (this measure was probably taken because, after the route had changed, Tango Discovery 1 became able to make a cross-platform connection (a connection allowing cross-platform transfer) with the limited express &quot;Kitakinki 7&quot; at Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Discovery nos. 1 and 64, which had been operated between Toyooka Station and Kinosakionsen Station as a rapid train, were discontinued (this measure was probably taken because, after the route had changed, Tango Discovery No. 1 became able to make a cross-platform connection (a connection allowing cross-platform transfer) with the Limited Express &apos;Kitakinki No. 7&apos; at Fukuchiyama Station.</e>
<cmt>Discovery No. x としました。快速として　を追加しました。&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 のねをつほ(id:105913), L,t,d,express(id:173068), 味村(id:128437), Cprobot(id:97843), Sat.K(id:3751), Goncyan(id:92158), DDatKYOTO(id:122010), Nakadachi(id:111078), Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), Yasu2006(id:93004), 継之助(id:39352), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), 化学屋さん(id:18131), Kyoutanabe124(id:175304), Kone(id:377), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Chikara1983(id:59556), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), 210.(id:9838), Sea of Japan(id:3230), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>