<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>はしだて (列車)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashidate (a train)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashidate (a train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashidate (a train)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>はしだてとは、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）が京都駅～天橋立駅間を山陰本線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮福線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮津線経由で運行する特別急行列車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashidate is the name of a limited express train that West Japan Railway Company (JR West) operates between Kyot Station and Amanohashidate Station via San&apos;in Main Line, Miyafuku Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation and Miyazu Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation.</e>
<cmt>北近畿タンゴ鉄道北近畿タンゴ鉄道：　”北近畿タンゴ鉄道”がだぶっていると考え、一方を削除したとして、訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashidate is the name of a limited express train that the West Japan Railway Company (JR West) operates between Kyoto Station and Amanohashidate Station via the San&apos;in Main Line, the Miyafuku Line of the Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation and the Miyazu Line of the Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashidate is the name of a limited express train that the West Japan Railway Company (JR West) operates between Kyoto Station and Amanohashidate Station via the Sanin Main Line, the Miyafuku Line of the Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation and the Miyazu Line of the Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを削除して、Sanin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>北近畿ビッグXネットワークを形成する列車の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This train is one of those used in the north kinki big X network.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This train is one of those used in the North Kinki Big X Network.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This train is one of those used in the North Kinki Big X Network.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>名称は景勝地の天橋立から採られたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is named after the Amanohashidate scenic area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is named after the Amanohashidate scenic area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is named after the Amanohashidate scenic area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>イメージカラーは赤色。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its image color is red.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its color theme is red.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its color theme is red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>走行路線の一つである北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮福線沿線に聳え立つ大江山の鬼伝説から取って、その中の「赤鬼」にちなんでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was namded after the &quot;red orge&quot; in an ogre-related legend remaining around Oe-yama Mountain Range towering along Miyafuku Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation, on which this train also runs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was named after the &quot;red orge&quot; in an ogre-related legend surrounding the Oe-yama mountain range, which towers over the Miyafuku Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation, on which this train also runs.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was named after the &apos;red ogre&apos; in an ogre-related legend surrounding the Oe-yama mountain range, which towers over the Miyafuku Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation, on which this train also runs.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>尚、本項では舞鶴線・小浜線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮津線の優等列車の沿革についても記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this item, the history of higher-class trains on the Maizuru Line, Obama Line and Miyazu Line of the Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation is also desribed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this item, the history of higher-class trains on the Maizuru Line, Obama Line and Miyazu Line of the Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation is also described.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this section, the history of higher-class trains on the Maizuru Line, Obama Line and Miyazu Line of the Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation is also described.</e>
<cmt>&quot;this item&quot;→&quot;this section&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>運行概況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General situations of the operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General operating conditions</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General operating conditions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>使用車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The train cars used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train cars used</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train cars used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>国鉄183系電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NR/JR Limited Express Series 183</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NR/JR Limited Express Series 183</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NR/JR Limited Express Series 183</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>編成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>■枠＝グリーン車　白枠＝普通車 (鉄道車両)　自＝自由席　指＝座席指定席　×＝禁煙席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">frame = a first-class car, white frame = an ordinary-calss car, 自=nonreserved seats, 指=reserved seats, X= Smoking is prohibited when using the seats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frame = a first-class car, white frame = an ordinary-class car, 自=non-reserved seats, 指=reserved seats, X= Smoking is prohibited when using the seats.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frame = a first-class car, white frame = an ordinary-class car, 自=non-reserved seats, 指=reserved seats, X= Smoking is prohibited when using the seats.</e>
<cmt>記号削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>この編成ははしだて3・7・1・2・6号の編成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This organization is for Hashidate 3, 7, 1, 2 and 6.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This organizational system is for Hashidate 3, 7, 1, 2 and 6.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This organizational system is for Hashidate 3, 7, 1, 2 and 6.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1・2・6号は「はしだて＋はしだて」の編成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The organization of Hashidate 1, 2 and 6 is &quot;Hashidate + &quot;Hashidate.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The organization of Hashidate 1, 2 and 6 is &quot;Hashidate + &quot;Hashidate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The organization of Hashidate 1, 2 and 6 is &apos;Hashidate&apos; + &apos;Hashidate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>3・7号「はしだて＋まいづる」の編成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The organization of Hashidate 3 and 7 is &quot;Hashidate + &quot;Maizuru.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The organization of Hashidate 3 and 7 is &quot;Hashidate + &quot;Maizuru.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The organization of Hashidate 3 and 7 is &apos;Hashidate&apos; + &apos;Maizuru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>はしだて2号6号車は自由席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seats of the sixth care of Hashidate 2 are nonreserved ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seats of the sixth car of Hashidate 2 are non-reserved ones.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seats of the sixth car of Hashidate 2 are non-reserved ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>この編成ははしだて5・4・8号の編成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This organization is for Hashidate 5, 4 and 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This organizational system is for Hashidate 5, 4 and 8.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This organizational system is for Hashidate 5, 4 and 8.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>停車駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stations where this train stops</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stations at which this train stops</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stations at which this train stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>はしだて</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashidate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashidate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashidate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>京都駅 － 二条駅 － 亀岡駅 － 園部駅 －（日吉駅 (京都府)）－（和知駅）－ 綾部駅 － 福知山駅 － 大江駅 (京都府) － 宮津駅 － 天橋立駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station - Kameoka Station - Sonobe Station - (Hiyoshi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)) - (Goma Station) - Ayabe Station - Fukuchiyama Station - Oe Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station - Kameoka Station - Sonobe Station - (Hiyoshi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)) - (Goma Station) - Ayabe Station - Fukuchiyama Station - Oe Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station - Kameoka Station - Sonobe Station - (Hiyoshi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)) - (Goma Station) - Ayabe Station - Fukuchiyama Station - Oe Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Miyazu Station - Amanohashidate Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>まいづる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>京都駅 － 二条駅 － 亀岡駅 － 園部駅 － 綾部駅 － 西舞鶴駅 － 東舞鶴駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station - Kameoka Station - Sonobe Station - Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - Higashi-Maizuru Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station - Kameoka Station - Sonobe Station - Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - Higashi-Maizuru Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station - Kameoka Station - Sonobe Station - Ayabe Station - Nishi-Maizuru Station - Higashi-Maizuru Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>舞鶴線・小浜線・宮津線優等列車沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of higher-class trains on Maizuru Line, Obama Line and Miyazu Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of higher-class trains on the Maizuru, Obama and Miyazu lines</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of higher-class trains on the Maizuru, Obama and Miyazu lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="23">
<j>「はしだて」は、1965年より1968年まで大阪駅～天橋立駅間を福知山線・山陰本線・宮津線経由で運行する準急列車の名称として使用されたのが初出とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the name of &quot;Hashidate&quot; was first used for a semi-express train operated in 1965 to 1968 between Osaka Station and Amanohashidate Station via Fukuchiyama Line, San&apos;in Main Line and Miyazu Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the name &quot;Hashidate&quot; was first used for a semi-express train operated in the period of 1965 to 1968 between Osaka Station and Amanohashidate Station via the Fukuchiyama Line, San&apos;in Main Line and Miyazu Line.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the name &apos;Hashidate&apos; was first used for a semi-express train operated in the period of 1965 to 1968 between Osaka Station and Amanohashidate Station via the Fukuchiyama Line, Sanin Main Line and Miyazu Line.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを削除して、Sanin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1966年からは急行列車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashidate became an express train in 1996.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashidate became an express train in 1996.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashidate became an express train in 1966.</e>
<cmt>1966 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1968年、「きのさき (列車)」に吸収される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The express train merged into the &quot;Kinosaki&quot; train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The express train merged into the &quot;Kinosaki&quot; train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The express train merged into the &apos;Kinosaki&apos; train in 1968.</e>
<cmt>1968年を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ちなみに現行ダイヤで運行される列車として近いものは特急「文殊 (列車)」・「タンゴディスカバリー」が相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Monju&quot; and &quot;Tango Discovery&quot;limited express trains in the present train schedule are operated in the ways similar to the one in which this train was operated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Monju&quot; and &quot;Tango Discovery&quot; limited express trains in the present train schedule are operated in ways similar to the one in which this train was operated.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Monju (train)&apos; and &apos;Tango Discovery&apos; limited express trains in the present train schedule are operated in ways similar to the one in which this train was operated.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="27">
<j>1982年から1992年までは福井駅 (福井県)～天橋立駅間を小浜線・宮津線経由で運行する急行列車「はしだて」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In between 1982 and 1992, &quot;Hashidate&quot; was an express train operated between Fukui Staion (Fukui Prefecture) and Amanohashidate via Obama Line and Miyazu Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period from 1982 to 1992, &quot;Hashidate&quot; was an express train operated between Fukui Station (Fukui Prefecture) and Amanohashidate via the Obama and Miyazu lines.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period from 1982 to 1992, &apos;Hashidate&apos; was an express train operated between Fukui Station (Fukui Prefecture) and Amanohashidate Station via the Obama and Miyazu lines.</e>
<cmt>Station を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="28">
<j>なお、同区間には「わかさ」が運行されており、また同区間を運行していた急行列車であった「大社」についてもここで記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Wakasa&quot; was also operated between the two stations above; A description is also made for Taisha, an express train operated between the two stations as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Wakasa&quot; was also operated between those two stations; a description is also made for Taisha, an express train that was operated between the two stations as well.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakasa&apos; was also operated between those two stations; a description is also made for &apos;Taisha,&apos; an express train that was operated between the two stations as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>1961年3月1日：西舞鶴駅～金沢駅間を走る準急列車として「わかさ」誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 1, 1961: &quot;Wakasa&quot; was introduced as a sem-express train running between Nishimaizuru Station and Kanazawa Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 1, 1961: &quot;Wakasa&quot; was introduced as a semi-express train running between Nishimaizuru Station and Kanazawa Station.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1, 1961: &apos;Wakasa&apos; was introduced as a semi-express train running between Nishi-Maizuru Station and Kanazawa Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　, Nishi-Maizuru としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="30">
<j>1963年4月20日：「わかさ」、1往復増発し東舞鶴駅・西舞鶴駅～福井駅間の運転となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 20, 1963: One up-train service and one down-train service were added to the operation of &quot;Wakasa, becoming operated between Fukui Station and both stations of Higashimaizuru and Nishimaizuru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 20, 1963: One up-train service and one down-train service were added to the operation of &quot;Wakasa,&quot; being operated between Fukui Station and the Higashimaizuru and Nishimaizuru stations.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 20, 1963: One inbound train service and one outbound train service were added to the operation of &apos;Wakasa,&apos; being operated between Fukui Station and the Higashi-Maizuru and Nishi-Maizuru stations.</e>
<cmt>上り、下りをinbound, outbound としました。Nishi-Maizuru., Higashi-Maizuru としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="31">
<j>1964年10月1日：「わかさ」1往復廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1964: One up-train service and one down-train service of &quot;Wakasa&quot; was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1964: One up-train service and one down-train service of &quot;Wakasa&quot; were abolished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1964: One inbound train service and one outbound train service of &apos;Wakasa&apos; were abolished.</e>
<cmt>上り、下りをinbound, outbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>但し12月1日の金沢駅～出雲市駅間の急行「あさしお」運転開始まで臨時列車として運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the &quot;Wakasa&quot; special train was operated until operation of the &quot;Asashio&quot; express train started on December 1 between Kanazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the &quot;Wakasa&quot; special train was operated until the &quot;Asashio&quot; express train came into use on December 1 between Kanazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the &apos;Wakasa&apos; special train was operated until the &apos;Asashio&apos; express train came into use on December 1 between Kanazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="33">
<j>1966年3月5日：「わかさ」急行に格上げ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 5, 1966: The status of &quot;Wakasa was raised to an express train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 5, 1966: The status of &quot;Wakasa&quot; was raised to an express train.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 5, 1966: The status of &apos;Wakasa&apos; was raised to an express train.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="34">
<j>同年10月1日：名古屋駅～敦賀駅～出雲市駅間を運行する急行「大社」運行開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1966: Operation of the &quot;Taisha&quot; express train started between Nagoya Station, Tsuruga Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1966: Operation of the &quot;Taisha&quot; express train started between Nagoya Station, Tsuruga Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1966: Operation of the &apos;Taisha&apos; express train started between Nagoya Station, Tsuruga Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>金沢駅～出雲市駅間の急行「あさしお」と敦賀駅～米子駅間で併結運転する多層建て列車となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This train is operated between Tsuruga Station and Yonago Station, connected with the &quot;Asashio&quot; express train running between Kanazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This train is operated between Tsuruga Station and Yonago Station, connected with the &quot;Asashio&quot; express train running between Kanazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This train is operated between Tsuruga Station and Yonago Station, connected with the &apos;Asashio&apos; express train running between Kanazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="36">
<j>1968年7月：「大社」の補完として「エメラルド」を名古屋～東舞鶴間に運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July, 1968: Operation of &quot;Emerald&quot; started to supplement that of &quot;Taisha.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July, 1968: The &quot;Emerald&quot; operation started to supplement that of &quot;Taisha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July, 1968: The &apos;Emerald&apos; operation started to supplement that of &apos;Taisha,&apos; running between Nagoya and Higashi-Maizuru.</e>
<cmt>名古屋～東舞鶴　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="37">
<j>名古屋から小浜線を経由して出雲市まで運行されていた急行「大社」は、敦賀にて金沢編成と併結する関係上、海水浴シーズンの増結が難しくその補完として運転を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the &quot;Taisha&quot; express train, which ran from Nagoya to Izumo City via Obama Line, was connected at Tsuruga to a train organized at Kanazawa, it was difficult in the sea-bathing season to increase the number of its train cars, and therefore, &quot;Emerald&quot; was introduced for supplementing its operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the &quot;Taisha&quot; express train, which ran from Nagoya to Izumo City via the Obama Line, was connected at Tsuruga to a train organized at Kanazawa, it was difficult in the sea-bathing season to increase the number of its train cars, and therefore &quot;Emerald&quot; was introduced as a means to supplement its operation.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the &apos;Taisha&apos; express train, which ran from Nagoya to Izumo City via the Obama Line, was connected at Tsuruga to a train organized at Kanazawa, it was difficult in the sea-bathing season to increase the number of its train cars, and therefore &apos;Emerald&apos; was introduced as a means to supplement its operation.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後、「大社」は廃止されるが、「エメラルド」はその後も海水浴シーズンに運行を継続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the operation of &quot;Taisha&quot; was abolished later, &quot;Emerald&quot; continued its operation during the sea-bathing season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the operation of &quot;Taisha&quot; was later abolished, &quot;Emerald&quot; continued to operate during the sea-bathing season.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the operation of &apos;Taisha&apos; was later abolished, &apos;Emerald&apos; continued to operate during the sea-bathing season.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>同列車は1995年まで夏期に運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot; Emerald&quot; was operated in the summer season until 1995.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot; Emerald&quot; was operated in the summer season until 1995.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emerald&apos; was operated in the summer season until 1995.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="40">
<j>1968年10月1日：急行「あさしお」を「大社」と名称変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oct 1, 1968: The name of the &quot;Asashio&quot; express train was changed to &quot;Taisha.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oct 1, 1968: The name of the &quot;Asashio&quot; express train was changed to &quot;Taisha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1968: The name of the &apos;Asashio&apos; express train was changed to &apos;Taisha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>「大社」は名古屋駅・金沢駅～出雲市駅間の列車となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stations served by &quot;Taisha&quot; became Nagoya Station and some of those between Knazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stations served by &quot;Taisha&quot; became Nagoya Station and some of those between Knazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stations served by &apos;Taisha&apos; became Nagoya Station and some of those between Kanazawa Station and Izumoshi Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。Kanazawa に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="42">
<j>1970年10月1日：「わかさ」1往復増発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1970: One up-train service and one down-train service were added to the operation of &quot;Wakasa.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1970: One up-train service and one down-train service were added to the operation of &quot;Wakasa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1970: One inbound train service and one outbound train service of &apos;Wakasa&apos; were added to the operation of &apos;Wakasa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。上り、下りをinbound, outbound としました。「わかさ」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="43">
<j>1972年3月15日：「わかさ」舞鶴線・山陰本線への乗り入れ開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 15, 1972: Operation of &quot;Wakasa&quot; on Maizuru Line and San&apos;in Main Line started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 15, 1972: The operation of &quot;Wakasa&quot; on the Maizuru Line and San&apos;in Main Line started.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 15, 1972: The operation of &apos;Wakasa&apos; on the Maizuru Line and Sanin Main Line started.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを削除して、Sanin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>1往復のみ京都駅発着に。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only one &quot;Wakasa&quot; train started at and returned to Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only one &quot;Wakasa&quot; train started at and returned to Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only one &apos;Wakasa&apos; train started at and returned to Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>まいづる (列車)も参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also refer to &quot;Maizuru (a train).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also refer to &quot;Maizuru (a train).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also refer to &apos;Maizuru (train).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="46">
<j>1978年10月2日：「大社」金沢駅発着編成の運行区間を福井駅～天橋立駅間とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 2, 1978: It became that the &quot;Taisha&quot; trains organized for starting at and returning to Kanazawa Station were operated between Fukui Station and Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 2, 1978: The &quot;Taisha&quot; trains organized for starting at and returning to Kanazawa Station began operating between Fukui Station and Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 2, 1978: The &apos;Taisha&apos; trains organized for starting at and returning to Kanazawa Station began operating between Fukui Station and Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="47">
<j>1982年7月1日：「大社」名古屋駅発着編成の運行区間を名古屋駅～天橋立駅間とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 1, 1982: It became that the &quot;Taisha&quot; trains organized for starting at and returning to Nagoya station were operated between Nagoya Station and Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 1, 1982: The &quot;Taisha&quot; trains organized for starting at and returning to Nagoya station began operating between Nagoya Station and Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 1, 1982: The &apos;Taisha&apos; trains organized for starting at and returning to Nagoya station began operating between Nagoya Station and Amanohashidate Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="48">
<j>1982年11月15日：「大社」名古屋駅発着編成を廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 15, 1982: The operation of the &quot;Taisha&quot; trains organized for starting at and returning to Nagoya stationwas abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 15, 1982: The operation of the &quot;Taisha&quot; trains organized for starting at and returning to Nagoya station was abolished.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 15, 1982: The operation of the &apos;Taisha&apos; trains organized for starting at and returning to Nagoya station was abolished.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>「はしだて」に名称変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The train name was changed to &quot;Hashidate.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The train name was changed to &quot;Hashidate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The train name was changed to &apos;Hashidate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="50">
<j>1986年11月1日：日本国有鉄道民営化を前に「わかさ」福井駅発着の1往復削減。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 1, 1986: Prior to the privitalization of Japan National Railways (JNR), one up-train service and one down-train service was reduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 1, 1986: Prior to the privatization of Japan National Railways (JNR), one up-train service and one down-train service were abolished.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 1, 1986: Prior to the privatization of Japan National Railways (JNR), one inbound train service and one outbound train service of &apos;Wakasa&apos; starting at and returning to Fukui Station were abolished.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。上り、下りをinbound, outbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="51">
<j>1992年3月13日：「はしだて」廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 13, 1992: The operation of &quot;Hashidate&quot; was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 13, 1992: The operation of &quot;Hashidate&quot; was abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 13, 1992: The operation of &apos;Hashidate&apos; was abolished.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="52">
<j>1996年3月16日：「わかさ」東舞鶴駅～敦賀駅間の運転となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 16, 1996: It became that &quot;Wakasa&quot; was operated between Higashimaizuru Station and Tsuruga Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 16, 1996: &quot;Wakasa&quot; began operating between Higashimaizuru Station and Tsuruga Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 16, 1996: &apos;Wakasa&apos; began operating between Higashi-Maizuru Station and Tsuruga Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="53">
<j>1999年10月2日：「わかさ」廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 2, 1999: The operation of &quot;Wakasa&quot; was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 2, 1999: The operation of &quot;Wakasa&quot; was abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 2, 1999: The operation of &apos;Wakasa&apos; was abolished.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="54">
<j>1996年、山陰本線園部駅～福知山駅及び北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮福線福知山駅～宮津駅・北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮津線宮津駅～天橋立駅間の電化により、電車特急を運行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1996, the operation of trains between Sonobe Station and Fukuchiyama Station on Sain&apos;in Main Line, between Fukuchiyama Station and Miyazu Station on Miyafuku Line fof Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation and between Miyazu Station and Amanohashidate on Miyazu Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation were electrified, andcorrespondingly, operation of electric limited express trains started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1996, the operation of trains between Sonobe Station and Fukuchiyama Station on the Sain&apos;in Main Line, between Fukuchiyama Station and Miyazu Station on the Miyafuku Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation and between Miyazu Station and Amanohashidate on the Miyazu Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation were electrified, and therefore the operation of electric limited express trains started.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1996, the operation of trains between Sonobe Station and Fukuchiyama Station on the Sanin Main Line, between Fukuchiyama Station and Miyazu Station on the Miyafuku Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation and between Miyazu Station and Amanohashidate Station on the Miyazu Line of Kitakinki Tango Railway Corporation were electrified, and therefore the operation of electric limited express trains started.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを削除して、Sanin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>京都駅発着の列車にこの名称を充てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name was given to trains that starting at and returning to Kytoo Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name was given to trains that started at and returned to Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name was given to trains that started at and returned to Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="56">
<j>2007年3月18日：全面禁煙化を実施。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 18, 2007: Since then, smoking has been prohibited entirely on the train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since March 18, 2007, smoking has been prohibited throughout the train.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 18, 2007: Smoking was prohibited throughout the train.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 北大(id:110491), L,t,d,express(id:173068), 味村(id:128437), 相模原の人(id:124032), 兵士兎(id:162694), 月夜野ほたる(id:7183), Lupinoid(id:68), Sat.K(id:3751), Mover(id:7146), Mkb(id:11233), Goncyan(id:92158), Zzzz(id:16596), Fjord(id:15599), Nakadachi(id:111078), Bandalgom(id:31841), Zlan(id:11942), Yasu2006(id:93004), ぱむ(id:24323), 継之助(id:39352), 化学屋さん(id:18131), Twilight2640(id:134273), Kone(id:377), HK3817(id:21293), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>