<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>保津峡駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hozukyo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hozukyo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozukyo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>保津峡駅（ほづきょうえき）は、京都府京都市西京区と亀岡市保津町にまたがる、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）山陰本線（嵯峨野線）の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located over the boundary of Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture and Hozu-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture, Hozukyo Station is a stop on San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) of West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hozukyo Station, located over the boundary of Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture and Hozu-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozukyo Station, located over the boundary of Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture and Hozu-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Sanin Main Line (Sagano Line) of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを削除し、Sanin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧保津峡駅の所在地は京都市西京区であったが、現在の駅はホーム中央部の直下を市境界の保津川が流れているため、ホームの一部と駅舎が亀岡市側にあり、所在地表記は亀岡市保津町になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Hozukyo Station was located in Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, but part of the platform of the present station and its station house are situated on the Kameoka City side, because Hozu-gawa River, constituting a boundary between the ward and the city, flows just under the central part of the platform, and therefore, its location is listed as Hozu-cho, Kameoka City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Hozukyo Station was located in Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, but part of the platform of the present station and its station house are situated on the Kameoka City side because the Hozu-gawa River, which constitutes a boundary between the ward and the city, flows just under the central part of the platform, and therefore its location is listed as Hozu-cho, Kameoka City.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Hozukyo Station was located in Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, but part of the platform of the present station and its station house are situated on the Kameoka City side because the Hozu-gawa River, which constitutes a boundary between the ward and the city, flows just under the central part of the platform, and therefore its location is listed as Hozu-cho, Kameoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>駅名電略は「オサホツ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The telegraphic address for the station name is &quot;Osahotsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The telegraphic address for the station name is &quot;Osahotsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The telegraphic address for the station name is &apos;Osahotsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、駅開設および移転の経緯から、長距離運賃の特定都区市内発着による特例運賃計算の対象であり、営業上は利用実態のとおり「京都市内の駅」に含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from the history that the station was opened and moved, the special train fare calculation method, which applies to long-distance travels on trains starting at and/or arriving at specific city areas, also applies to this station, and therefore, it can be said that in the viewpoint of business, this station is included in the &quot;stations in Kyoto City.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, given the history of the station, in which it was opened and later moved, the special train-fare calculation method, which applies to long-distance travels on trains starting at and/or arriving at specific city areas, also applies to this station, and therefore it can be said that from the business perspective this station is included among the &quot;stations in Kyoto City.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, given the history of the station, in which it was opened and later moved, the special train-fare calculation method, which applies to long-distance travels on trains arriving at and/or departing from specific city areas, also applies to this station, and therefore it can be said that from the business perspective this station is included among the &apos;stations in Kyoto City.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。&quot;starting at and/or arriving at&quot;→&quot;arriving at and/or departing from&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>ICOCA・Jスルー利用可能駅（相互利用可能ICカードはICOCAの項を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this station, ICOCA/J-through cards can be used (for interchangeably usable IC cards, refer to ICOCA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this station, ICOCA/J-through cards can be used (for interchangeably usable IC cards, refer to ICOCA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this station, ICOCA/J-through cards can be used (for interchangeably usable IC cards, refer to ICOCA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>但しJスルーカードについては、簡易改札機による対応のため複数枚の処理不可。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with simplified gate-passing check machines used in this station, more than one J-through card cannot be handled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the simplified gate-passing check machines used in the station can&apos;t handle more than one J-through card at a time.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the simplified gate-passing check machines used in the station can&apos;t handle more than one J-through card at a time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>相対式プラットホーム2面2線の無人駅だが、券売機（近距離区間）、簡易型自動改札機（ICOCA等ICカード対応）あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two separate platforms with two tracks served between them are provided, and although no station officer is stationed, an automatic ticket vending machine and a simplified automatic ticket gate (supporting IC cards, such as ICOCA) are provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two separate platforms (with two tracks served between them) are provided, and although no station officer is on duty an automatic ticket vending machine and a simplified automatic ticket gate (supporting IC cards such as ICOCA) are provided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two separate platforms (with two tracks served between them) are provided, and although no station officer is on duty an automatic ticket vending machine and a simplified automatic ticket gate (supporting IC cards such as ICOCA) are provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>馬堀駅寄りに地下歩道があり、反対側のホームへの移動はこの歩道を使うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An underground foot-path provided on the Umahori Station side is used when moving between the two platforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers use an underground foot path provided on the Umahori Station side when moving between the two platforms.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers use an underground passage provided on the Umahori Station side when moving between the two platforms.</e>
<cmt>地下歩道→underground passage としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>ホームからの保津川、および保津峡の遊覧船の眺めは格別。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The views of Hozu-gawa River and of pleasure boats on Hozukyo Gorge from the platforms are especially splendid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The views of the Hozu-gawa River and of pleasure boats on Hozukyo Gorge from the platforms are truly remarkable.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The views of the Hozu-gawa River and of pleasure boats on Hozukyo Gorge from the platforms are truly remarkable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（ホームの一部は橋上にあるため真下を船が通過する）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since part of the platfporms is located immediately above a bridge, such boats pass immediately under these platforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the platforms are partially located immediately above a bridge, the boats pass immediately under them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the platforms are partially located immediately above a bridge, the boats pass immediately under them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>駅舎はかなり小さく、ホームも狭い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station house is fairly small and the platforms are narrow as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station house is fairly small, and the platforms are narrow as well.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station house is fairly small, and the platforms are narrow as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、新線切り替え後も、現駅舎と駅前整備の完成以前に駅業務が旧保津峡駅で行われていた時期があり、そのため旧山陰本線を伝い新駅ホームの東端へ繋がる通路が整備されていたが、現在では閉鎖されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the new line started its operation, former Hozukyo Station was used for station operations for a period of time before the present station house and the area in front of the new station became normally usable, and for this reason, a path reaching the east ends of the platforms of the new station by walking along the former San&apos;in Main Line was provided but now this path is unusable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the new line started its operation, the former Hozukyo Station was used for a period of time before the present station house and the area in front of the new station became normally usable, and for this reason a path reaching the east ends of the platforms of the new station by walking along the former San&apos;in Main Line was provided; today, however, the path is unusable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the new line started its operation, the former Hozukyo Station was used for a period of time before the present station house and the area in front of the new station became normally usable, and for this reason a path reaching the east ends of the platforms of the new station by walking along the former Sanin Main Line was provided; today, however, the path is unusable.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを削除し、Sanin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>大晦日の終夜運転時の臨時列車は、普通列車であっても当駅を通過する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Special trains run on New Year&apos;s Eve are local ones but do not stop at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The special trains that run on New Year&apos;s Eve are local ones, but they don&apos;t stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The special trains that run on New Year&apos;s Eve are local ones, but they don&apos;t stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="15">
<j>※一見、駅構内にはどこにものりば番号が書かれていないように見えるが、実は駅掲示の時刻表で上記のように案内されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Seemingly, it appears that no track number is dispalyed anywhere, but actually, the time table displayedinn the station gives such information as described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Apparently, no track number is displayed anywhere, but actually the timetable displayed in the station gives such information as described above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apparently, no track number is displayed anywhere, but in fact the timetable displayed in the station gives such information as described above.</e>
<cmt>記号削除&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="16">
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use status</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conditions of usage</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger use</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>2006年度の1日あたりの乗車人員は約260人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of persons getting on board at this station is approx. 260 a day in the fiscal 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of persons getting on board at this station was approximately 260 a day in fiscal 2006.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of persons getting on board at this station was approximately 260 a day in fiscal year 2006.</e>
<cmt>fiscal → fiscal yearに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（京都府統計書より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(From statistics of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(From the statistics of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to the Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Report)</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="19">
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="20">
<j>駅自体が保津川渓谷の中にあり、周辺に人家はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station itself is located in Hozu-gawa River Gorge and no man lives around it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station itself is located in the Hozu-gawa River Gorge, so no one lives around it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station itself is located in the Hozu-gawa River Gorge, so no one lives around it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>北 約4kmに、近年 柚子風呂で有名な水尾集落があり、自治会バスが運行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizuo Village, recently becoming faimous for its hot citron bath, is located about 4.1-km north of this station, and the residents&apos;s association operates its own bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizuo Village, which has lately become famous for its hot citron bath, is located about 4.1 km north of this station, and the residents&apos; association operates its own bus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizuo Village, which has lately become famous for its hot citron bath, is located about four kilometers north of this station, and the residents&apos; association operates its own bus.</e>
<cmt>数字を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>（一日に４本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Four trips a day)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Four trips a day)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Four trips a day)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="23">
<j>屏風岩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Byobu-Iwa (sheer [perpendicular] cliff)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Byobu-Iwa (sheer [perpendicular] cliff)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Byobu-Iwa (sheer cliff)</e>
<cmt>sheer cliff としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ライオン岩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lion rock</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lion Rock</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lion Rock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>トロッコ保津峡駅（嵯峨野観光鉄道嵯峨野観光線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hozukyo Torokko Station (on Saga Sight-Seeing Tram Line of Sagano Scenic Railway)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hozukyo Torokko Station (on the Saga Sightseeing Tram Line of the Sagano Scenic Railway)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozukyo Torokko Station (on the Saga Sightseeing Tram Line of the Sagano Scenic Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>※両駅は距離にして約1100m離れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* The distance between two stations is approx. 1,100 m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* The distance between two stations is approximately 1,100 m.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distance between two stations is approximately 1,100 m.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>連絡交通機関はなく、道路は水尾川の谷を迂回しているため徒歩で約15分の連絡となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With no means of transportation available between the two stations, it takes about 15 minutes on foot to reach one of the two stations from the other because the road connecting them goes around a valley of Mizuo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With no means of transportation available between the two stations, it takes about 15 minutes on foot to reach one of the two stations from the other because the road connecting them goes around a valley of the Mizuo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With no means of transportation available between the two stations, it takes about 15 minutes on foot to reach one of the two stations from the other because the road connecting them goes around a valley of the Mizuo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>なお、移転当時は新駅舎が未完成であったために保守用通路（旧線･軌道上の仮通路）を介して旧駅から出入りしていた（当時の旧線は廃線で、トロッコ列車はまだ計画のみであった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the station was moved to the new site, the construction of its station house had not been competed, and therefore, for entering or exiting from the station, the former station house was actually used via a passage for maintenance (a temporay passage on the former tram track).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the station was moved to the new site, the construction of its station house had not been competed; consequently, to enter or exit the station, the former station house was actually used via a passage for maintenance (a temporary passage on the former tram track).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the station was moved to the new site, the construction of its station house had not been completed; consequently, to enter or exit the station, the former station house was in fact used via a passage for maintenance (a temporary passage on the former tram track) (at that time, the former tram track was a dead track, and the operation of the tram was still under contemplation).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました（最後の括弧の箇所）。&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、現在この通路は一般人の通行は禁止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, this passage is not usable by the general public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, this passage isn&apos;t usable by the general public.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, this passage isn&apos;t usable by the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="30">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1929年（昭和4年）8月17日 - 日本国有鉄道の松尾山信号場開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 17, 1929 - The Matsuoyama signal station was established by Japan National Railways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 17, 1929 - The Matsuoyama signal station was established by Japan National Railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 17, 1929: The Matsuoyama signal station was established by Japan National Railways.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="32">
<j>1936年（昭和11年）4月15日 - 駅に格上げし、保津峡駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 15, 1936 - With the status of the station raised, its operation started as Hozukyo Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 15, 1936 - With the status of the station thus elevated, operations commenced as Hozukyo Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 15, 1936: With the status of the station thus elevated, operations commenced as Hozukyo Station.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>旅客取扱を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operations for passengers started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passenger operations started.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger operations started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>現在のトロッコ保津峡駅付近。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around present Hozukyo Torokko Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the present-day Hozukyo Torokko Station</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the present-day Hozukyo Torokko Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="35">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日 - 国鉄分割民営化により、JR西日本の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1987 - Due to the division and privatization of JNR, it became a station of JR West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1987 - Due to the division and privatization of JNR, it became a station of JR West.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1987: Due to the division and privatization of JNR, it became a station of JR West.</e>
<cmt>表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="36">
<j>1989年（平成元年）3月5日 - 嵯峨嵐山駅～馬堀駅間が新線に切り替え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 5, 1989 - The portion between Saga-Arashiyama Station and Umahori Station was changed to a new line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 5, 1989 - The portion between Saga-Arashiyama Station and Umahori Station was changed to a new line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 5, 1989: The portion between Saga-Arashiyama Station and Umahori Station was changed to a new line.</e>
<cmt>表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>同時に現在の場所に移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same timing, the station was moved to the present site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the station was moved to the present site.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the station was moved to the present site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="38">
<j>1991年（平成3年）4月27日 - 旧駅がトロッコ保津峡駅として再開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 27, 1991 - The former station restarted its operation as Hozukyo Torokko Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 27, 1991 - The former station restarted its operation as Hozukyo Torokko Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 27, 1991: The former station restarted its operation as Hozukyo Torokko Station.</e>
<cmt>表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="39">
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan Railway Company</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West Japan Railway Company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan Railway Company (JR West)</e>
<cmt>JR West を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>■嵯峨野線（山陰本線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagano Line (San&apos;in Main Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagano Line (San&apos;in Main Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagano Line (Sanin Main Line)</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを削除し、Sanin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>■快速</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid trains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>通過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not stops at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No stops are made at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No stops are made at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local trains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>嵯峨嵐山駅 - 保津峡駅 - 馬堀駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga-Arashiyama Station - Hozukyo Station - Umahori Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga-Arashiyama Station - Hozukyo Station - Umahori Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga-Arashiyama Station - Hozukyo Station - Umahori Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Etopirica(id:32491), Bergmann(id:85282), Hikichimin Jr.(id:147077), Yuta415(id:149253), Laichuan Yinfu(id:152533), Mover(id:7146), Ikaxer(id:61759), Fjord(id:15599), 樒(id:35770), Rusk(id:9895), Sunen(id:10700), Matsukaze(id:51778), 継之助(id:39352), Hidama(id:73276), R28Bot(id:177951), Chobot(id:20846), Kone(id:377), まったけ(id:130042), Hirotaro(id:1437), Sprinkler(id:14399), Ogeshi(id:80487), Tsubame-ex(id:53988), Takatetu(id:3231), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>