<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>国際会館駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokusai Kaikan (international conference hall) Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokusai Kaikan (international conference hall) Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokusaikaikan Station</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、カッコ内の補足は削除しました。Kokusaikaikan としました（京都市交通局のサイトより）。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>国際会館駅（こくさいかいかんえき）は、京都府京都市左京区岩倉にある、京都市営地下鉄烏丸線の終着駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Iwakura, Sakyo Ward Kyoto, City Kyoto Prefecture, Kokusai Kaikan Station is a terminal on the Karasuma Line, which is operated by Kyoto City Subway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokusai Station, located in Iwakura, Sakyo Ward Kyoto, City Kyoto Prefecture, is a terminal on the Karasuma Line, which is operated by Kyoto City Subway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokusaikaikan Station, located in Iwakura, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto, City Kyoto Prefecture, is a terminal on the Karasuma Line, which is operated by Kyoto Municipal Subway.</e>
<cmt>Kokusaikaikan Station　としました。City →municipal　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>駅番号はK01。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station number is K01.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station number is K01.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station number is K01.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>国立京都国際会館での第3回気候変動枠組条約締約国会議開催を機に開業した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operation of this station started when Third Session of the Conference of the Parties was held at Kyoto International Conference Center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station became operational when the Third Session of the Conference of the Parties was held at Kyoto International Conference Center.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station became operational when the Third Session of the Conference of the Parties was held at Kyoto International Conference Center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>プラットホーム1面2線の地下駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This station is located underground, with a platform serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is located underground, with a platform serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is located underground, with a platform serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>改札口は1ヶ所のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only one entrance/exit gate place is provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only one entrance/exit gate place is provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only one ticket gate is provided.</e>
<cmt>改札→ticket gate　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>国立京都国際会館は駅の南側にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto International Conference Center is loacted on the south side of this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto International Conference Center is loacted on the south side of this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto International Conference Center is located on the south side of this station.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その周辺は宝ヶ池公園であり、グランドプリンスホテルも近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the station, Takaragaike Park is situated and Grand Prince Hotel is also located nearby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaragaike Park and Grand Prince Hotel are located nearby.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaragaike Park and Grand Prince Hotel are located nearby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>駅北側と東側は新しい住宅地である（岩倉地区は市街化調整区域のため、高層マンションなどの大規模開発は出来ず、一戸建て住宅と低層集合住宅が中心となっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New housing areas are situated on the north and east sides (because they are included in urbanization-restricted areas, construction of large-scale developments, such ashigh-risecondominiums, is prohibited and detached houses or low-rise housing complexes are mostly built there).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New housing areas are situated on the north and east sides (because they&apos;re included in urbanization-restricted areas, the construction of large-scale developments, such as high-rise condominiums, is prohibited and detached houses or low-rise housing complexes predominate there).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New housing areas are situated on the north and east sides (because they&apos;re included in urbanization-restricted areas, the construction of large-scale developments, such as high-rise condominiums, is prohibited and detached houses or low-rise housing complexes predominate there).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>駅の北、宝ヶ池通を挟んで同志社高等学校がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the north of this station, Doshisha High School is located across Takaragaike-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha High School is located north of the station, across Takaragaike-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha High School is located north of the station, across Takaragaike-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宝ヶ池通沿いには郊外型の店舗が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suburban-type stores are found along Takaragaike-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suburban-type stores are found along Takaragaike-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suburban-type stores are found along Takaragaike-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、やや距離はあるが、叡山電鉄鞍馬線岩倉駅 (京都府)も徒歩圏内である（北へ約10分程度）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located a bit distantly, Iwakura Station (located in Kyoto Prefecture) on the Kurama Line, operated by Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway), is within a walking distance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura Station (located in Kyoto Prefecture) on the Kurama Line, operated by Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway), is a bit distant but still reachable on foot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Kurama Line, operated by Eizan Electric Railway, is a bit distant but still reachable on foot (about 10-minute walk to the north).</e>
<cmt>括弧内のlocated in を削除しました。Eizan dentetsuは削除しました。翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>駅前の通りを東に行くと叡山電鉄鞍馬線八幡前駅 (京都府)がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Going to the east along the road in front of the station, you can reach Hachiman-mae Station (located in Kyoto Prefecture) on the Kurama Line, operated by Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Going to the east along the road in front of the station, one can reach Hachiman-mae Station (located in Kyoto Prefecture) on the Kurama Line, operated by Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Going to the east along the road in front of the station, one can reach Hachiman-mae Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Kurama Line, operated by Eizan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>括弧内のlocated in を削除しました。Eizan dentetsuは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>円通寺 (京都市) 西へ1.5km</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entsu-ji Temple (located in Kyoto Prefecture) is located at 1.5 km west of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entsu-ji Temple (located in Kyoto Prefecture) is located 1.5 km west of the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entsu-ji Temple (Kyoto Prefecture) is located 1.5 km west of the station.</e>
<cmt>括弧内のlocated in を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>岩倉地区のバスターミナル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus terminals in the Iwakura area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus terminals in the Iwakura area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus terminals in the Iwakura area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>駅の地上部分には開業時に整備されたタクシー乗り場・バスターミナルが存在し、住宅地となっている岩倉方面や大原 (京都)方面への京都バス各路線の始終着点ともなっている（京都市営バスから移管された路線もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the ground level above the station, a taxi terminal and a bus terminal were established when the station started its operation, providing terminal functions for buses on Kyoto Bus routes in the directions of the Iwakura and Ohara (Kyoto Prefecture) areas (there are also the routes transferred from Kyoto City Bus, and</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the ground level above the station, a taxi terminal and bus terminal were established when the station became operational, and provided terminal functions for buses on Kyoto Bus routes in the directions of Iwakura and Ohara (Kyoto Prefecture) (there are also routes transferred from Kyoto City Bus, and</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the ground level above the station, a taxi terminal and bus terminal were established when the station became operational, and provided terminal functions for buses on Kyoto Bus routes in the directions of Iwakura and Ohara (Kyoto Prefecture) (there are also routes transferred from Kyoto City Bus;</e>
<cmt>最後のand を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>現在でも駅西側にある岩倉操車場始発の市バス路線が経由する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">even at present, buses on a city bus route starting at Iwakura Soshajo (bus yard), placed on the west side of this station, stop here).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">even at present, buses on a city bus route starting at Iwakura Soshajo (bus yard), placed on the west side of this station, stop here).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">even at present, buses on a city bus route starting at Iwakura Soshajo (bus yard), placed on the west side of this station, stop here).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>観光シーズンには、都心部での渋滞や混雑を回避する為に、この駅発着の路線バスを利用する乗客も目立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sight-seeing seasons, conspicuously many persons use buses starting from or arriving at this terminal, to avoid congestion in the central area of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the tourist seasons, significant numbers of people use buses starting from or arriving at this terminal in order to avoid the congestion in central Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the tourist seasons, significant numbers of people use buses arriving at and departing from this terminal in order to avoid the congestion in central Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;starting from and terminating at&quot; -&gt; &quot;arriving at and departing from&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>1997年（平成9年）6月3日 烏丸線 国際会館-北山間の開通とともに開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 3, 1997: Operation of this station started when the Karasuma Line started its operation between Kokusai Kaikan and Kitayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 3, 1997: This station became active when the Karasuma Line started operating between Kokusai Kaikan and Kitayama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 3, 1997: This station became active when the Karasuma Line started operating between Kokusaikaikan and Kitayama.</e>
<cmt>Kokusaikaikan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>2007年（平成19年）4月1日 PiTaPa使用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 2007, PiTaPa became usable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 2007: PiTaPa became accepted</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 2007: PiTaPa became accepted</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>第3回近畿の駅百選選定駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This station was selected in the third event for a selection of 100 prominent stations in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This station was chosen in the third event to select 100 prominent stations in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This station was chosen in the third event to select 100 prominent stations in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>京都市営地下鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>City →municipal　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>■烏丸線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt>■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>国際会館駅(K01) - 松ヶ崎駅 (京都府)(K02)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokusai Kaikan Station (K01) - Matsugasaki Station (located in Kyoto Prefecture) (K02)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokusai Kaikan Station (K01) - Matsugasaki Station (located in Kyoto Prefecture) (K02)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokusaikaikan Station (K01) - Matsugasaki Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (K02)</e>
<cmt>Kokusaikaikan としました。括弧内のlocated in を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sushiya(id:110938), Gugh(id:158052), Hideyuki(id:9577), 城山(id:104901), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), Etopirica(id:32491), Memeja(id:110500), Jinenjo51(id:93469), 素館(id:20524), Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), Sunen(id:10700), Matsukaze(id:51778), Ktr(id:30468), Joh shoh(id:9812), Kouchiumi(id:19253), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Goki(id:7107), Hidama(id:73276), Hirotaro(id:1437), Tomika(id:43050), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>