<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本のタクシー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese taxis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxis in Japan</e>
<cmt>他ファイル（日本の鉄道　など）は Railways in Japan という標題になっておりますので、こちらもそのように合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本のタクシー（にっぽんのタクシー）では、日本におけるタクシーについての事情などについて記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section of &quot;Japanese taxis&quot; describes the conditions and situations of taxis in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section &quot;Japanese taxis&quot; describes the conditions and situations of taxis in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section, &quot;Taxis in Japan&quot; describes the conditions and situations of taxis in Japan.</e>
<cmt>同上です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>法的定義など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legal definition, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legal definition, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legal definition, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本においてタクシー事業は、道路運送法上の「一般乗用旅客自動車運送事業」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operators of taxi business in Japan are categorized as &quot;Common taxicab operators&quot; in the Road Transportation Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operators of taxi business in Japan are categorized as &quot;Common taxicab operators&quot; in the Road Transportation Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Operators of taxi business in Japan are categorized as &apos;Common taxicab operators&apos; in the Road Transportation Act.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>第3条第1号「一般旅客自動車運送事業（特定旅客自動車運送事業以外の旅客自動車運送事業）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number 1 of Article 3: &quot;General Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business&quot; (Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business other than Specific Vehicle Transportation Business)</e>
<cmt>「特定旅客自動車運送事業」と「旅客自動車運送事業」については、ソースが何も見つけられなかったため、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Number 1 of Article 3: &quot;General Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business&quot; (Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business other than Specific Vehicle Transportation Business)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Number 1 of Article 3: &quot;General Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business&quot; (Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business other than Specific Vehicle Transportation Business)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>（ハ）一般乗用旅客自動車運送事業（一個の契約により乗車定員10人以下の自動車を貸し切つて旅客を運送する一般旅客自動車運送事業）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(ハ) Common taxicab operators (General Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business in which a vehicle with a carrying capacity of 10 or less passengers is chartered to transport the passengers for one contract)</e>
<cmt>（ハ）はそのまま訳文にも反映いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(ハ) Common taxicab operators (General Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business in which a vehicle with a carrying capacity of 10 or less passengers is chartered to transport the passengers for one contract)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(3) Common taxicab operators (General Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business in which a vehicle with a carrying capacity of 10 or less passengers is chartered to transport the passengers for one contract)</e>
<cmt>（ハ）はイロハの順番と理解して、3 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>事業用自動車を示す緑地に白字、3ナンバー又は5ナンバーのナンバープレート (日本)がつけられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A 3- or 5-type license vehicle with a license plate which is designed white against a green background, indicating a business-purpose vehicle (in Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A 3- or 5-type license vehicle with a license plate which is designed white against a green background, indicating a business-purpose vehicle (in Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vehicle is attached with a license plate (Japan) whose number starts from either 3 or 5, which is painted in white against a green background, indicating a business-purpose vehicle.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>自家用自動車を用いて無資格で営業しているものは白タクと呼ばれ、違法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxis operated with private cars without permission, license, or qualification are called &quot;Shiro-taku (unlicensed taxi)&quot; and illegal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxis operated with private cars without permission, license, or qualification are called &quot;Shiro-taku (unlicensed taxis)&quot; and are illegal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxis operated with private cars without permission, license, or qualification are called &quot;Shiro-taku&quot; (literally, white taxi, meaning unlicensed taxis) and are illegal.</e>
<cmt>白タク　を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この呼び方はナンバープレートの色が事業用車のそれに対して白地緑文字であることに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this naming comes from the fact that license plates of these types of taxis are painted green against a white background, while those of legal taxis are different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this name comes from the fact that license plates of these types of taxis are painted green against a white background, while those of legal taxis are different.</e>
<cmt>grammr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name comes from the fact that license plates of these types of taxis are painted green against a white background, while those of legal taxis are different.</e>
<cmt>however を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>この他、タクシー業務適正化特別措置法、旅客自動車運送事業運輸規則、一般乗用旅客自動車運送事業標準運送約款などの法令の適用を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, operators of taxi business are subject to the Act on Special Measures concerning Regulation of Taxi Services, the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law, the Common Taxicab Operators Standard Transportation Clause, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, operators of taxi business are subject to the Act on Special Measures concerning Regulation of Taxi Services, the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law, the Common Taxicab Operators Standard Transportation Clause, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, operators of taxi business are subject to the Act on Special Measures concerning Regulation of Taxi Services, the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law, the Common Taxicab Operators Standard Transportation Clause, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本では1912年7月10日、東京市有楽町にタクシー自働車株式会社が設立され、8月5日から本社前でフォード・モデルTを6台使用して旅客営業を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Taxi Jidosha Kabushikigaisha was established in Yuraku-cho, Tokyo City on July 10, 1912, and its passenger transport operations started on August 5 in front of the head office using six Ford Model Ts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Taxi Jidosha Kabushikigaisha was established in Yuraku-cho, Tokyo City on July 10, 1912, and its passenger transport operations started on August 5 in front of the head office using six Ford Model Ts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Taxi Jidosha Kabushikigaisha was established in Yuraku-cho, Tokyo City on July 10, 1912, and its passenger transport operations started on August 5 in front of the head office using six Ford Model Ts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これが日本における、自動車を使用したタクシーの最初の営業であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the first taxi business using automobiles in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first taxi business using automobiles in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first taxi business using automobiles in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このタクシーはタクシーメーターを搭載して「辻待ち自動車」と呼ばれており、上野駅と新橋駅を拠点に営業していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These taxis were equipped with a taximeter and called &quot;Tsuji-machi jidosha (vehicle waiting to be hired),&quot; which are based in Ueno Station and Shimbashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These taxis were equipped with a taximeter and called &quot;Tsuji-machi jidosha (vehicle waiting to be hired),&quot; which were based in Ueno and Shimbashi Stations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These taxis were equipped with a taximeter and called &apos;Tsuji-machi jidosha&apos; (vehicle waiting to be hired), which were based in Ueno and Shimbashi Stations.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>料金は最初の1マイルが60銭、以後1マイル毎に10銭増しであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The taxi fare was 60 sen (one sen is 1/100 of one yen) for the first 1 mile, and then 10 sen was added per 1 mile after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The taxi fare was 60 sen (one sen is 1/100 of one yen) for the first 1 mile, and then 10 sen was added per mile after that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The taxi fare was 60 sen (one sen is 1/100 of one yen) for the first 1 mile, and then 10 sen was added per mile after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、1914年には東京駅が開業したことにより、同社によって東京駅でも営業が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, as Tokyo Station started in practice, the company also began their services at Tokyo Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, as Tokyo Station started in practice, the company also began servicing Tokyo Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, as Tokyo Station started in practice in 1914, the company also began servicing Tokyo Station.</e>
<cmt>1914年　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>1960年代にはモータリゼーションの発達により、「神風タクシー」が問題となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1960&apos;s, with the development of motorization, Kamikaze taxis (taxis whose drivers drove recklessly) became a social issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1960&apos;s, with the development of motorization, Kamikaze taxis (taxis whose drivers drove recklessly) became a social issue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1960&apos;s, with the development of motorization, Kamikaze taxis (taxis whose drivers drove recklessly) became a social issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>2002年2月1日に道路運送法・タクシー業務適正化臨時措置法の一部が改正施行され、事業はこれまでの免許制から許可制とし、事業者の車両数増減も届出のみで自由に可能になった（いわゆる「タクシー規制緩和」とはこれらの法改正を指す）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Part of the Road Transportation Act and the Act on Temporary Measures concerning Regulation of Taxi Services were revised to come to effect in February 2002, and accordingly, the system of the business was switched from the licensing system to the approval system, allowing operators of the business to freely conduct business only by reporting increase and decrease in vehicles (so-called &quot;relaxation of the taxi regulations&quot; means the revision of these acts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Part of the Road Transportation Act and the Act on Temporary Measures concerning the Regulation of Taxi Services were revised to come to effect in February 2002, and accordingly, the system of the business was switched from the licensing system to the approval system, allowing operators of the business to freely conduct business only by reporting increases and decreases in vehicles (so-called &quot;relaxation of the taxi regulations&quot; means the revision of these acts).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Part of the Road Transportation Act and the Act on Temporary Measures concerning the Regulation of Taxi Services were revised to come to effect on February 1, 2002, and accordingly, the system of the business was switched from the licensing system to the approval system, allowing operators of the business to freely conduct business only by reporting increases and decreases in vehicles (so-called &apos;relaxation of the taxi regulations&apos; means the revision of these acts).</e>
<cmt>2月1日　としました。&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これにより大都市では新規参入事業者が増加している反面、既存の中小事業者は地方・大都市の別を問わず、マイカーの普及や公共交通網の拡充、社会事情の変化などによる乗客の減少に加え、業務の性質そのものが収入を増やせず支出を減らせないため、構造的な業績不良に陥り、経営の苦しいところが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this relaxation of the taxi regulations, while the number of new taxi operators has been increasing in large cities, the existing small- and mid-sized operators, regardless of in large cities or in rural areas, have been in structural slump in business and suffering difficult management because of the decrease in users due to dissemination of private cars, improvement and expansion of the public transportation net, and change in social environment, as well as the nature of the business itself that cannot increase the income and decrease the spending.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this relaxation of the taxi regulations, while the number of new taxi operators has been increasing in large cities, the existing small- and mid-sized operators, regardless whether in large cities or in rural areas, have been in a business slump suffering difficult management because of the decrease in customers due to dissemination of private cars, improvement and expansion of the public transportation net, and change in the social environment, as well as the nature of the business itself that cannot increase the income and decrease the expenses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this relaxation of the taxi regulations, while the number of new taxi operators has been increasing in large cities, the existing small- and mid-sized operators, regardless whether in large cities or in rural areas, have been in a business slump suffering difficult management because of the decrease in customers due to dissemination of private cars, improvement and expansion of the public transportation net, and change in the social environment, as well as the nature of the business itself that cannot increase the income and decrease the expenses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、売り上げを上げるため労働者に過大な負担がかかるようになってきていることも問題視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the fact that heavy burdens are placed on the workers to build up sales has been seen as a problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the fact that heavy burdens are placed on the drivers to build up sales has been seen as a problem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the fact that heavy burdens are placed on the drivers to build up sales has been seen as a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>1912年（大正元年）8月15日東京市の上野駅前・新橋駅前で営業開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 15, in 1912: The first taxi operations started in front of Ueno Station and Shimbashi Station in Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 15, in 1912: The first taxi operations started in front of Ueno and Shimbashi Stations in Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 15, 1912: The first taxi operations started in front of Ueno and Shimbashi Stations in Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt>inを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>1914年（大正3年）東京駅開業とともに駅構内営業開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1914: With the start up of the operations of Tokyo Station, the taxi business started in the station yard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1914: Together with the start up of operations at Tokyo Station, the taxi business started in the station yard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1914: Together with the start up of operations at Tokyo Station, the taxi business started in the station yard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>タクシー自働車株式会社による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Taxi Jidosha Kabushikigaisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Taxi Jidosha Kabushikigaisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Taxi Jidosha Kabushikigaisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>1924年（大正13）年6月27日大阪、1926（大正15）年6月10日東京で、市内1円均一タクシー（通称円タク）が登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka, on June 27, in 1924 and in Tokyo, on June 10, in 1926: A type of taxis that were available with flat fare of 1 yen in the city (so-called &quot;En-taku&quot;) appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka, on June 27, 1924 and in Tokyo, on June 10, in 1926: A type of taxis appeared that were available with a flat fare of 1 yen in the city (so-called &quot;En-taku&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka, on June 27, 1924 and in Tokyo, on June 10, in 1926: A type of taxis appeared that were available with a flat fare of one yen in the city (so-called &apos;En-taku&apos;).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>1945年（昭和20年）迄の間、全国各地で政府勧奨による企業統合が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to around 1945: Many companies were integrated throughout the nation under the encouragement of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to around 1945: Many companies were integrated throughout the nation under the encouragement of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to around 1945: Many companies were integrated throughout the nation under the encouragement of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>（いわゆる戦時統合）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(So-called Senji-togo (wartime integration))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(So-called Senji-togo or wartime integration)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(So-called Senji-togo or wartime integration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>各地区の大手タクシー会社は概ねこの時期に成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the major taxi companies in each area were established during this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the major taxi companies in each area were established during this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the major taxi companies in each area were established during this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>東京では三度に分けて企業合同が行われた結果、大和自動車交通・日本交通 (東京都)・帝都自動車交通・国際自動車の4社に集約され、また大阪では相互タクシー・澤タクシー（現：日本交通 (大阪)）・信興タクシー（現：三菱タクシー）・大阪交通（現：国際興業大阪）・都島自動車の5社に、名古屋は名鉄交通（名タク）・東和交通・名古屋相互交通（現：第一交通産業）の3社に、横浜・川崎は東横タクシー（現：神奈川都市交通）に、神戸は神姫合同自動車（現：神姫バス）・神戸タクシー（現在の国際興業神戸）の2社にそれぞれ集約された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While, as a result of three-time corporate coalitions in Tokyo, the major companies were integrated into four companies: Daiwa Motor Transportation Co., Ltd., Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (Tokyo), Teito Jidousha Kotsu Co.,Ltd., and Kokusai Mortorcars Co., Ltd.; in Osaka, those were integrated into five companies: Sogotaxi Co., Ltd., Sawa taxi (present day Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (Osaka Prefecture)), Shinko taxi (present day Mitsubishi Taxi Group), Osaka Kotsu (present day Kokusai Kogyo Osaka), and Miyakojima Jidosha; in Nagoya, those were integrated into three companies: Meitetsu Kotsu (Mei-taku), Towa Taxi, and Nagoya Sogo Kotsu (present day Daiichi Koutsu Sangyo Co., Ltd.); in Yokohama and Kawasaki, those were integrated into Toyoko taxi (present day Kanagawa Toshikoutsu Limited); and in Kobe, those were integrated into two companies: Shinki Godo Jidosha Kabushikigaisha (present day Shinki Bus) and Kobe taxi (present day Kokusai Kougyou Kobe K.K.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While, as a result of three-time corporate coalitions in Tokyo, the major companies were integrated into four companies: Daiwa Motor Transportation Co., Ltd., Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (Tokyo), Teito Jidousha Kotsu Co., Ltd., and Kokusai Mortorcars Co., Ltd.; in Osaka, these were integrated into five companies: Sogotaxi Co., Ltd., Sawa taxi (present day Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. in Osaka Prefecture), Shinko taxi (present day Mitsubishi Taxi Group), Osaka Kotsu (present day Kokusai Kogyo Osaka), and Miyakojima Jidosha; in Nagoya, these were integrated into three companies: Meitetsu Kotsu (Mei-taku), Towa Taxi, and Nagoya Sogo Kotsu (present day Daiichi Koutsu Sangyo Co., Ltd.); in Yokohama and Kawasaki, these were integrated into Toyoko taxi (present day Kanagawa Toshikoutsu Limited); and in Kobe, these were integrated into two companies: Shinki Godo Jidosha Kabushikigaisha (present day Shinki Bus) and Kobe taxi (present day Kokusai Kougyou Kobe K.K.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While, as a result of three-time corporate coalitions in Tokyo, the major companies were integrated into four companies: Daiwa Motor Transportation Co., Ltd., Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (Tokyo), Teito Jidousha Kotsu Co., Ltd., and Kokusai Motorcars Co., Ltd.; in Osaka, these were integrated into five companies: Sogotaxi Co., Ltd., Sawa taxi (present day Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. in Osaka Prefecture), Shinko taxi (present day Mitsubishi Taxi Group), Osaka Kotsu (present day Kokusai Kogyo Osaka), and Miyakojima Jidosha; in Nagoya, these were integrated into three companies: Meitetsu Kotsu (Mei-taku), Towa Taxi, and Nagoya Sogo Kotsu (present day Daiichi Koutsu Sangyo Co., Ltd.); in Yokohama and Kawasaki, these were integrated into Toyoko taxi (present day Kanagawa Toshikoutsu Limited); and in Kobe, these were integrated into two companies: Shinki Godo Jidosha Kabushikigaisha (present day Shinki Bus) and Kobe taxi (present day Kokusai Kougyou Kobe K.K.).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>1949年戦時統合以外の新規免許取得会社が登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1949, newly licensed taxi companies other than ones appeared in Senji-togo were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1949, newly licensed taxi companies other than ones appearing in Senji-togo were established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1949: Newly licensed taxi companies other than ones appearing in Senji-togo were established.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="27">
<j>1953年10月13日札幌にて日本初のタクシー無線が運用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 13, in 1959: The operation of Japan&apos;s first radio taxis started in Sapporo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 13, in 1959: The operation of Japan&apos;s first radio taxis started in Sapporo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 13, 1953: The operation of Japan&apos;s first radio taxis started in Sapporo.</e>
<cmt>in　を削除しました。1953年　に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>1959年12月3日東京都区部で個人タクシー営業が許可され173人に初免許交付。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 3, in 1959: The operation of privately owned taxis was licensed in Tokyo&apos;s 23 wards and the first license was issued to 173 people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 3, in 1959: Operations of privately owned taxis were licensed in Tokyo&apos;s 23 wards and the first licenses was issued to 173 people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 3, 1959: Operations of privately owned taxis were licensed in Tokyo&apos;s wards and the first licenses was issued to 173 people.</e>
<cmt>in　を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1960年1月15日には大阪市、同3月1日名古屋市へと全国に免許区域拡大する等個人タクシー復活。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As more and more areas issued the license to operators of privately owned taxis, for example, in Osaka on January 15 and in Nagoya on March 1, in 1960, operations of privately owned taxis made a comeback.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As more and more areas issued licenses to operators of privately owned taxis, for example, in Osaka on January 15 and in Nagoya on March 1, in 1960, operations of privately owned taxis made a comeback.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As more and more areas issued licenses to operators of privately owned taxis, for example, in Osaka on January 15 and in Nagoya on March 1, in 1960, operations of privately owned taxis made a comeback.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>（「個人タクシーの日」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Privately Owned Taxi Day&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Privately Owned Taxi Day&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Privately Owned Taxi Day&apos;)</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="31">
<j>1969年財団法人東京タクシー近代化センター（東京都23特別区と武蔵野市、三鷹市を管理）と財団法人大阪タクシー近代化センター（大阪市、門真市、守口市、豊中市、吹田市、茨木市、高槻市、堺市、和泉市などを管理）が開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1969, Tokyo taxi modernization center (which manages the 23 special wards of Tokyo, Musashino City, and Mitaka City) and Osaka taxi modernization center (which manages Osaka City, Kadoma City, Moriguchi City, Toyonaka City, Suita City, Ibaraki City, Takatsuki City, Sakai City, Izumi City, and some other areas) were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1969, The Tokyo taxi modernization center (which manages the 23 special wards of Tokyo, Musashino City, and Mitaka City) and Osaka taxi modernization center (which manages Osaka City, Kadoma City, Moriguchi City, Toyonaka City, Suita City, Ibaraki City, Takatsuki City, Sakai City, Izumi City, and some other areas) were established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1969: The Tokyo taxi modernization center (which manages the 23 special wards of Tokyo, Musashino City, and Mitaka City) and Osaka taxi modernization center (which manages Osaka City, Kadoma City, Moriguchi City, Toyonaka City, Suita City, Ibaraki City, Takatsuki City, Sakai City, Izumi City, and some other areas) were established.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="32">
<j>2002年東京タクシー近代化センターが「東京タクシーセンター」に、大阪タクシー近代化センターが「大阪タクシーセンター」に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2002, Tokyo taxi modernization center and Osaka taxi modernization center changed their names to &quot;Tokyo taxi center&quot; and &quot;Osaka taxi center&quot; respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2002, The Tokyo taxi modernization center and the Osaka taxi modernization center changed their names to &quot;Tokyo taxi center&quot; and &quot;Osaka taxi center&quot; respectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2002: The Tokyo taxi modernization center and the Osaka taxi modernization center changed their names to &apos;Tokyo taxi center&apos; and &apos;Osaka taxi center&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。日付、コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="33">
<j>2008年東京新橋駅前にて、優良タクシー（10年間クレームなし・過去3年無事故無違反）の専用乗り場が設置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, a taxi stand exclusively for excellent taxis (which have had no complaints for past 10 years and whose drivers have had no accidents and traffic violations for past 3 years) was set up in front of Shinbashi Station in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, a taxi stand exclusively for excellent taxis (which have had no complaints for past 10 years and whose drivers have had no accidents and traffic violations for past 3 years) was set up in front of Shinbashi Station in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2008: A taxi stand exclusively for excellent taxis (which have had no complaints for past 10 years and whose drivers have had no accidents and traffic violations for past 3 years) was set up in front of Shimbashi Station in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>日付、コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="34">
<j>タクシーの形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of taxis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>介護・福祉タクシー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elder-care and welfare taxis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elder-care and welfare taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elder-care and welfare taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>タクシーの利点の一つが「旅客をドアtoドアで輸送できる」という点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the advantages of a taxi is its capability to &quot;carry the passengers from the entrance of the point of departure to the entrance of the destination.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the advantages of a taxi is its capability to &quot;carry passengers from the entrance of the point of departure to the entrance of the destination.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the advantages of a taxi is its capability to &apos;carry passengers from the entrance of the point of departure to the entrance of the destination.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>昨今この利点を活かして、身体障害者や高齢者など、移動に大きな制約を伴う人々を対象にするタクシー事業者が増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, taking advantages of this feature, the number of taxi companies which aim at people whose transportation is constrained, such as disabled people and elderly people, has been increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, taking advantages of this feature, the number of taxi companies that aim at people whose transportation is constrained, such as disabled people and elderly people, has been increasing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, taking advantages of this feature, the number of taxi companies that aim at people whose transportation is constrained, such as disabled people and elderly people, has been increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>中には、運転手にホームヘルパー、救命講習などの公的資格を取得させている事業者もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of those companies, there are some operators who make the drivers obtain the public qualification of care attendant and/or lifesaving certification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of those companies, there are some operators who make their drivers obtain public qualifications of care attendant and/or obtain lifesaving certification.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of those companies, there are some operators who make their drivers obtain public qualifications of care attendant and/or obtain lifesaving certification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>車椅子を積載できるタクシーには8ナンバーの特種用途自動車の登録となっているものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the taxis that can carry wheelchairs are registered as a special-purpose vehicle with 8-type license.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the taxis that can carry wheelchairs are registered as a special-purpose vehicles with an 8-type license.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the taxis that can carry wheelchairs are registered as a special-purpose vehicles having a license plate whose number starts from 8.</e>
<cmt>8ナンバー→vehicles having a license plate whose number starts from 8　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>本業がタクシーではない介護事業者（特に訪問介護・居宅介護事業者）が、介護サービスの利用者を病院などへ移送することを目的に、一般乗用旅客自動車運送事業（患者等輸送限定）という種別の許可を受けることも多くなってきている（「介護タクシー」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More and more nursing-care companies (especially companies of care attendants who visit users&apos; houses to take care of the users or Itaku nursing-care service companies), whose main business is not taxi operations, are now getting a license of Common taxicab operators (limited to carry only patients or the like) for the purpose of sending the users of nursing-care services to a hospital or some other places (&quot;Elder-care taxi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More and more nursing-care companies (especially companies with care attendants who visit customers&apos; houses to take care of the patients or Itaku nursing-care service companies), whose main business is not taxi operations, are now getting a license for Common taxicab operators (limited to carry only patients or the like) for the purpose of taking the users of nursing-care services to a hospital or some other places (&quot;Elder-care taxi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More and more nursing-care companies (especially companies with care attendants who visit customers&apos; houses to take care of the patients or Itaku nursing-care service companies), whose main business is not taxi operations, are now getting a license for Common taxicab operators (limited to carry only patients or the like) for the purpose of taking the users of nursing-care services to a hospital or some other places (&apos;Elder-care taxi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>このうち、介護保険や支援費制度を適用しない場合をケア輸送サービス、適用する場合（通院等乗降介助）を介護輸送サービスといい、運賃の収受方法に差がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of these types, services to which the nursing-care insurance and the Assistance Benefit Supply System are not applied are called Care transportation service, while services to which those are applied are called Nursing-care transportation service (assistance of getting in-out the taxi when going to a hospital, etc.), with a difference in fare collection system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of these types, services to which the nursing-care insurance and the Assistance Benefit Supply System are not applied are called Care transportation service, while services to which those are applied are called Nursing-care transportation service (assistance of getting in-out the taxi when going to a hospital, etc.), with a difference in the fare collection system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of these types, services to which the nursing-care insurance and the Assistance Benefit Supply System are not applied are called Care transportation service, while services to which those are applied are called Nursing-care transportation service (assistance of getting in-out the taxi when going to a hospital, etc.), with a difference in the fare collection system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>道路運送法第80条を拡大解釈し、普通二種運転免許を持たずとも陸運局の認可を受ければ旅客を有償運送できる、いわゆる「80条許可車両」（詳細は廃止代替バス80条バス参照）があるが、タクシー業界から「完全な白タクではないか」との強い異議が国土交通省に寄せられ、厚生労働省との折衝で現時点ではなんとか折り合いがつけられている状態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some companies that provide services of fare-paying conveyance of passengers without Class II driver license but with a permission of the motor vehicle official by interpreting the Article 80 of the Road Transportation Act beyond the realm of its original scope, which is so-called &quot;Article 80 authorized vehicle&quot; (see abolished substitution bus Article 80 bus); however, many ordinary taxi operators have broken the force of an objection to the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism saying that what those companies are doing is a Shiro-taku (unlicensed taxi) operation, which has somehow reached an understanding between these two types of companies through negotiations with the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some companies that provide services of fare-paying conveyance of passengers without a Class II driver license, but with the permission of the motor vehicle official by interpreting the Article 80 of the Road Transportation Act beyond the realm of its original scope, which is so-called &quot;Article 80 authorized vehicle&quot; (see abolished substitution bus Article 80 bus); however, many ordinary taxi operators have broken the force of an objection to the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism saying that what those companies are doing is a Shiro-taku (unlicensed taxi) operation, which has somehow reached an understanding between these two types of companies through negotiations with the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some companies that provide services of fare-paying conveyance of passengers without a Class II driver license, but with the permission of the motor vehicle official by interpreting the Article 80 of the Road Transportation Act beyond the realm of its original scope, which is so-called &apos;Article 80 authorized vehicle&apos; (see abolished substitution bus Article 80 bus); however, many ordinary taxi operators have broken the force of an objection to the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism saying that what those companies are doing is a Shiro-taku operation, which has somehow reached an understanding between these two types of companies through negotiations with the Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>地域防犯・防災の役割を担うタクシー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxis taking on a role of local anticrime and disaster-preventing activities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxis taking on a role of local anticrime and disaster-preventing activities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxis taking on a role of local anticrime and disaster-preventing activities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>タクシーには「24時間365日、地域内のあらゆる場所を走行し、無線により連絡手段を確保している」という特性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxis have characteristics of running around everywhere in the area 24 hours a day, 365 days a year, with a radio communication means.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxis run around everywhere in the area 24 hours a day, 365 days a year, with radio communication means.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxis run around everywhere in the area 24 hours a day, 365 days a year, with radio communication means.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この特性を活かして、非常時には警察無線とも連絡を取り合う体制を築いている地域もある（犯人が犯行後タクシーを使用して逃走した疑いがある場合は暗号による一斉手配が無線で流れる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some areas with a structure in which taxis can communicate with police radio by taking advantages of these characteristics (if a criminal may be running away in a taxi after the fact, a message of the fugitive criminal is sent in code to all taxis over the radio).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some areas where taxis can communicate with police radio by taking advantages of these characteristics (if a criminal may be running away in a taxi after the fact, a message about the fugitive criminal is sent in code to all taxis over the radio).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some areas where taxis can communicate with police radio by taking advantages of these characteristics (if a criminal may be running away in a taxi after the fact, a message about the fugitive criminal is sent in code to all taxis over the radio).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、乗務員に警備員などの資格を取得させている事業者もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are some taxi companies that make the drivers be certified as a security guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are some taxi companies that have the driver certified as a security guard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are some taxi companies that have the driver certified as a security guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>運転代行業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Replacement driver service</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Replacement driver service</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Replacement driver service</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>タクシー事業者が運転代行業を兼業する例は古くから地方で数多く存在するが、タクシー事業の多角化に加えて、2004年の法改正によりタクシー同様第二種運転免許を取得した者でなければ代行運転に従事できなくなった（法律自体は2002年に施行されたが、二種免許義務化は2年間の猶予期間が設けられていた）ため、運転代行業に参入するタクシー事業者がさらに急増している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There have been many cases where taxis companies also offer replacement driver services since long time ago in local regions; however, due to diversification of taxi business as well as the law revision in 2004, in which only persons who have Class II driver license can carry out replacement driver services as taxi operations (the law itself became effective in 2002, but mandatory operation with Class II driver license was actually started two years later), the number of taxi companies which start offering replacement driver services has been increasing more and more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have been many cases where taxi companies also offer replacement driver services since long ago in local regions; however, due to diversification of the taxi business as well as the law revision in 2004, in which only persons who have Class II driver license can carry out replacement driver services as taxi operations (the law itself became effective in 2002, but mandatory operation with Class II driver license was actually started two years later), taxi companies that have started offering replacement driver services have been increasing more and more.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have been many cases where taxi companies also offer replacement driver services since long ago in local regions; however, due to diversification of the taxi business as well as the law revision in 2004, in which only persons who have Class II driver license can carry out replacement driver services as taxi operations (the law itself became effective in 2002, but mandatory operation with Class II driver license was actually started two years later), taxi companies that have started offering replacement driver services have been increasing more and more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>詳細運転代行参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Detailed replacement driver services</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to Detailed replacement driver services</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the section on &quot;Replacement driver services.&quot;</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>荷物の運搬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Freight transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Freight transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Freight transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>人ではなく、コンピュータなどの保守用部品、データメディアなど、近距離の小物の輸送を引き受けているタクシー事業者もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some taxi companies that take on transportation of not only people but small items for a short distance, such as maintenance parts and data media for computers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some taxi companies that take on transportation of not only people but small items for a short distance, such as maintenance parts and data media for computers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some taxi companies that take on transportation of not only people but small items for a short distance, such as maintenance parts and data media for computers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>（バイク便、あるいは全国赤帽軽自動車運送協同組合連合会などと似た使い方であるが、タクシーは旅客運送事業であり、貨物運送事業を行うことは道路運送法上違法である）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(This is the similar service what motorbike messengers and the United Association of Japan Light Motor Vehicle Porter provide; however, taxis are supposed to offer services to carry passengers and carrying freight by taxi violates the Road Transportation Act.)</e>
<cmt>「全国赤帽軽自動車運送協同組合連合会」＝「United Association of Japan Light Motor Vehicle Porter」は、先に単語調査をされた方も定訳を見つけられず、日本語のまま残しえありましたので、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(This is a similar service that motorbike messengers and the United Association of Japan Light Motor Vehicle Porters provide; however, taxis are supposed to offer services to carry passengers so, carrying freight by taxi violates the Road Transportation Act.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(This is a similar service that motorbike messengers and the United Association of Japan Light Motor Vehicle Porters provide; however, taxis are supposed to offer services to carry passengers so, carrying freight by taxi violates the Road Transportation Act.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>以上のほかにも、日用品の買い物代行や、子供の幼稚園や小学校への送迎など、様々な種類のユニークな事業があり、最近では同じタクシー事業といえども地域や事業者により、多角化の方向を示しているといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the above, there are various kinds of unique services including shopping of daily necessities on behalf of the customers and driving small children to their kindergartens or elementary schools, indicating that taxi operators are diversifying their businesses in the different directions depending on the area and company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the above, there are various kinds of unique services including shopping for daily necessities on behalf of customers and driving small children to their kindergartens or elementary schools, indicating that taxi operators are diversifying their businesses into different directions depending on the area and the company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the above, there are various kinds of unique services including shopping for daily necessities on behalf of customers and driving small children to their kindergartens or elementary schools, indicating that taxi operators are diversifying their businesses into different directions depending on the area and the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>タクシーの利用方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to use taxis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to use taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to use taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>鉄道駅、空港、港、百貨店、観光地、繁華街、病院などにはタクシー乗り場が設けられており、順番に並んで乗車する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Users are supposed to stand in a queue at taxi stand which is set up at stations, airports, ports, department stores, tourism destinations, downtown areas, hospitals, and some other places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Users are supposed to stand in a queue at taxi stand which is set up at stations, airports, ports, department stores, tourism destinations, downtown areas, hospitals, and some other places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Users are supposed to stand in a queue at taxi stand which is set up at stations, airports, ports, department stores, tourism destinations, downtown areas, hospitals, and some other places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>ただしタクシー車両を選ぶのは基本的に客の自由であり、「先頭の車両にお乗りください。」と注意すると乗車拒否扱いされる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, which taxi to take is basically up to the customer and thus a customer may deny taking the taxi at the head of the taxi queue even if the customer is told to take the taxi at the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, which taxi to take is basically up to the customer and thus a customer may deny taking the taxi at the head of the taxi queue even if the customer is told to take the taxi at the head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, which taxi to take is basically up to the customer and thus a customer may deny taking the taxi at the head of the taxi queue even if the customer is told to take the taxi at the head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>なお一部では、特定の事業者に属するタクシー専用の乗り場がある場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, there are some cases where a taxi stand for a specific taxi company is set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, there are some cases where a taxi stand for a specific taxi company is set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, there are some cases where a taxi stand for a specific taxi company is set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>タクシー乗り場には、入構するタクシー事業者がその施設所有者へ施設使用料を支払いタクシーの構内権なる権利を購入している場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi companies that use a taxi stand may need to pay the usage charge to the facility owner to purchase the right to drive taxis in the facility area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi companies that use a taxi stand may need to pay a usage charge to the facility owner to purchase the right to drive taxis in the facility area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi companies that use a taxi stand may need to pay a usage charge to the facility owner to purchase the right to drive taxis in the facility area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、主要都市の市街地では、フロントガラスから見えるように「空車」のプレートをダッシュボードに掲げて走っている（流し）タクシーに対して手をあげたら停車するので乗車すればよい（なお一部テレビドラマ等で散見されるが、「タクシー！」などと叫ぶ必要はない。そもそも声を上げても運転手には聞こえない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in urban areas in major cities, a customer should just raise his/her hand to stop and take a (cruising) taxi with an &quot;empty car&quot; sing on the dashboard which can be seen from outside through the windshield (customers who want to take a cruising taxi do not have to shout &quot;taxi!&quot; as often seen in TV dramas; it is meaningless to shout because the taxi driver cannot hear it anyway).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in urban areas in major cities, a customer should just raise his/her hand to stop and take a (cruising) taxi with an &quot;vacant car&quot; sign on the dashboard which can be seen from outside through the windshield (customers who want to take a cruising taxi do not have to shout &quot;taxi!&quot; as often seen in TV dramas; it is meaningless to shout because the taxi driver cannot hear it anyway).</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in urban areas in major cities, a customer should just raise his/her hand to stop and take a (cruising) taxi with an &apos;vacant car&apos; sign on the dashboard which can be seen from outside through the windshield (customers who want to take a cruising taxi do not have to shout &apos;taxi!&apos; as often seen in TV dramas; it is meaningless to shout because the taxi driver cannot hear it anyway).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>夜間の場合はプレートが見づらいことから、プレートの代わりに車上の社名表示灯が点灯しているか否かで区別できる地域もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it is harder to see the &quot;empty car&quot; sing at night, taxis in some areas light on the company logo indicating lamp on the top of the taxi, instead of showing the &quot;empty car&quot; sing, to show the taxi is empty (available), meaning if the company logo indicating lamp is off, the taxi is occupied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it is harder to see the &quot;vacant car&quot; sign at night, taxis in some areas light up the company logo indicating lamp on the top of the taxi, instead of showing the &quot;vacant car&quot; sign, to show the taxi is available, meaning if the company logo indicating lamp is off, the taxi is occupied.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it is harder to see the sign at night, taxis in some areas light up the company logo indicating lamp on the top of the taxi, instead of showing the sign, to show the taxi is available, meaning if the company logo indicating lamp is off, the taxi is occupied.</e>
<cmt>&quot;vacant car&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>最近はほとんどの車両で電光式の「空車」「迎車」「予約車」「回送」「賃走」「割増」「支払」などの表示がされており、プレート表示は減っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, most taxis use electronic signs of &quot;empty car,&quot; &quot;Geisha (taxi which is on the way to a customer to pick him/her up),&quot; &quot;Reserved,&quot; &quot;Not in service,&quot; &quot;In service,&quot; &quot;Extra fare,&quot; &quot;Pay,&quot; and thus the number of taxis that use non-lighting (non-electronic) sings is decreasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, most taxis use electronic signs of &quot;vacant car,&quot; &quot;Geisha&quot; (taxi which is on the way to a customer to pick him/her up), &quot;Reserved,&quot; &quot;Not in service,&quot; &quot;In service,&quot; &quot;Extra fare,&quot; &quot;Pay,&quot; and thus taxis that use non-lighting (non-electronic) signs are decreasing.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, most taxis use electronic signs of &apos;vacant car,&apos; &apos;Geisha&apos; (taxi which is on the way to a customer to pick him/her up), &apos;Reserved,&apos; &apos;Not in service,&apos; &apos;In service,&apos; &apos;Extra fare,&apos; &apos;Pay,&apos; and thus taxis that use non-lighting (non-electronic) signs are decreasing.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>各家や会社などに電話をして迎えに来てもらうこともできるが、その場合は迎車料金がかかる（無料の場合もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Users can call a taxi company to come to their house or office to pick them up, but the &quot;Geisha&quot; charge is needed (there are some taxi companies which do not charge it).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Users can call a taxi company to be picked up at their house or office, but the &quot;Geisha&quot; charge is required (however, there are some taxi companies which do not charge this fee).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Users can call a taxi company to be picked up at their house or office, but the charge to be picked up is required (however, there are some taxi companies which do not charge this fee).</e>
<cmt>迎車料金→charge to be picked up としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>地方においては、流し営業を行わず、ほとんどが呼び出しまたはタクシー乗り場での乗車という地域も多い（しかし、走行しているタクシーが空車であった場合、手を上げれば乗り込めることは都市部と変わらない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many rural areas, cruising taxis are rare and most services are provided by calling for one over the telephone or taking one at a taxi stand (but if one raises his/her hand as he/she finds a taxi with an &quot;empty car&quot; sing, the taxi is supposed to stop as with cruising taxis in urban areas.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many rural areas, cruising taxis are rare and most services are provided by calling for one over the telephone or taking one at a taxi stand (but if one raises his/her hand as he/she finds a taxi with an &quot;vacant car&quot; sign, the taxi is supposed to stop like a cruising taxi does, in urban areas.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many rural areas, cruising taxis are rare and most services are provided by calling for one over the telephone or taking one at a taxi stand (but if one raises his/her hand as he/she finds a vacant taxi, the taxi is supposed to stop like a cruising taxi does, in urban areas.).</e>
<cmt>vacant taxi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>タクシーは自動で（一部タクシー会社は乗務員が後方に回り込んで開ける）後方左側のドアを開ける場合が多いので、客は自分で開ける必要はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi drivers open the left back door for customers most of the time (for some taxis, the driver goes to the back door and opens it for the customers) so the passengers do not need to open the door by themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi drivers mechanically open the left back door for customers most of the time (for some taxis, the driver goes to the back door and opens it for the customers) so the passengers do not need to open the door by themselves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi drivers mechanically open the left back door for customers most of the time (for some taxis, the driver goes to the back door and opens it for the customers) so the passengers do not need to open the door by themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>後方左側以外のドアは自動では開かないので客が開ける（ただし、タクシー乗り場によっては左回りの一方通行になっている関係で後方右側から乗り降りする場合もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other doors do not open automatically, so the customers open them when necessary (however, when taxis pick up customers at a taxi stand where they are supposed to turn in a counterclockwise direction, they often open the right back door).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other doors do not open mechanically, so the customers open them when necessary (however, when taxis pick up customers at a taxi stand where they are supposed to turn in a counterclockwise direction, they often open the right back door).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other doors do not open mechanically, so the customers open them when necessary (however, when taxis pick up customers at a taxi stand where they are supposed to turn in a counterclockwise direction, they often open the right back door).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>なお、ドアを客があける必要の無いのは日本以外にはほとんどなく、日本を旅する外国人は驚くことが多い（日本旅行向けガイドブックに紹介されていることがある。逆に日本人が外国でタクシーに乗ろうとするときは、ドアは開かないので注意）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, taxis whose door customers do not need to open can rarely seen overseas, and thus many foreign tourists visiting Japan are surprised by the automatic door (The information on automatic taxi doors is often introduced in some guide books for foreigners to Japan. In a contrasting situation, Japanese should be careful when they take a taxi in foreign countries because the door does not open automatically.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, taxis with doors that customers do not need to open themselves can rarely be seen overseas, and thus many foreign tourists visiting Japan are surprised by the automatic door (The information on automatic taxi doors is often introduced in some guide books for foreigners to Japan. In a contrasting situation, Japanese should be careful when they take a taxi in foreign countries because the door does not open automatically).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, taxis with doors that customers do not need to open themselves can rarely be seen overseas, and thus many foreign tourists visiting Japan are surprised by the automatic door (the information on automatic taxi doors is often introduced in some guide books for foreigners to Japan; in a contrasting situation, Japanese should be careful when they take a taxi in foreign countries because the door does not open automatically).</e>
<cmt>カッコ内にセミコロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="62">
<j>タクシーに乗り込んだら行き先を告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Passengers tell where they want to go to the driver after getting in a taxi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers tell the driver their destination after getting into the taxi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers tell the driver their destination after getting into the taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>走り出すときに乗務員が運賃メーターをセットする（スタートさせる）ことにより料金計算が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the taxi starts running, the taxi driver sets (starts) some meters to calculate the fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the taxi starts running, the taxi driver sets (starts) some meters to calculate the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the taxi starts running, the taxi driver sets (starts) some meters to calculate the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ただし、電話などで呼び出し迎車で進行してきた場合、既に基本料金分のメーターが作動している場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the passenger have called for the taxi over the telephone or some other means, the basic charge may be already added to the meters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the passenger have called for the taxi over the telephone or some other means, the basic charge may be already added to the meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the passenger have called for the taxi over the telephone or some other means, the basic charge may be already added to the meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>いずれの場合も、一定の走行距離か乗車時間（但し途中でタクシーを待たせて車から離れても乗車時間としてカウントされる）、もしくはその双方で運賃は算定（後述）され、同時にメーターに料金が表示される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In each case, the fare is accumulated ever time the taxi runs a certain distance or a certain time passes (even if the passenger stops and gets out the taxi on the way to the destination, the fare meter keeps counting the time), or based on the combination of the distance and the time, and the current fare is displayed on the meters (described later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In each case, the fare is accumulated ever time the taxi runs a certain distance or a certain time passes (even if the passenger stops and gets out the taxi on the way to the destination, the fare meter keeps counting the time), or based on the combination of the distance and the time, and the current fare is displayed on the meters (described later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In each case, the fare is accumulated every time the taxi runs a certain distance or a certain time passes (even if the passenger stops and gets out the taxi on the way to the destination, the fare meter keeps counting the time), or based on the combination of the distance and the time, and the current fare is displayed on the meters (described later).</e>
<cmt>ever →every　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>目的地につくと乗務員が運賃メーターを止めるので、そのときに表示された額に従って額を払う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the taxi arrives at the destination, the driver stops the fare meter, so the passenger pays the fare according to the meters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the taxi arrives at the destination, the driver stops the fare meter, so the passenger pays the fare according to the meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the taxi arrives at the destination, the driver stops the fare meter, so the passenger pays the fare according to the meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>多くの場合、基本となるメーターの他に、ユニットといわれる支払額を示すメーターがついており、これに従って運賃料金を精算する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most taxis have a meter called unit that indicates the amount of payment, other than a basic meter that calculates distance and/or time, so the passenger is supposed to pay the fare based on this meter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most taxis have a meter called unit that indicates the amount of payment, other than a basic meter that calculates distance and/or time, so the passenger is supposed to pay the fare based on this meter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most taxis have a meter called unit that indicates the amount of payment, other than a basic meter that calculates distance and/or time, so the passenger is supposed to pay the fare based on this meter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>これは、遠距離割引や迎車料金、予約料金等の、通常のメーター以外の割引や加算をした額を示すものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the basic meter, this meter shows the actual amount of payment from which discount charges such as discounts for long-distance travel are subtracted or to which extra charges such as Geisha charge and reservation charge are added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the basic meter, this meter shows the actual amount of payment from which discount charges such as discounts for long-distance travel are subtracted or to which extra charges such as a Geisha charges or a reservation charges are added.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the basic meter, this meter shows the actual amount of payment from which discount charges such as discounts for long-distance travel are subtracted or to which extra charges such as a Geisha charges or a reservation charges are added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>例外として、あらかじめ定められた定額の運賃による利用もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an exceptional case, the fare may be predetermined regardless of the distance or the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In exceptional cases, the fare may be predetermined regardless of the distance or the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In exceptional cases, the fare may be predetermined regardless of the distance or the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>この場合、メーターによる運賃の収受ではなく、あらかじめ決められた運賃を支払えばよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the passenger should just pay the predetermined amount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the passenger should just pay the predetermined amount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, the passenger should just pay the predetermined amount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>なお、有料道路を利用した場合の通行料や、観光で利用するなどの際に有料駐車場を使用したときの駐車料金は、乗客が負担するものなので、メーター額のほかに支払わねばならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the taxi uses some tollway or toll parking for a purpose of the passenger, for example, sightseeing, the passenger is supposed to pay those charges separately from the taxi fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the taxi uses some tollway or toll parking for a purpose of the passenger, for example, sightseeing, the passenger is supposed to pay those charges separately from the taxi fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the taxi uses some tollway or toll parking for a purpose of the passenger, for example, sightseeing, the passenger is supposed to pay those charges separately from the taxi fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="72">
<j>なお、信号待ちのときに乗車した場合は、多少車が前進しても、信号が青に代わって本格的に走り出すまではメーターをセットしない乗務員も多いが、そう決まっている訳ではなく、乗務員の心遣いか、トラブル防止といった意味合いによるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, when a taxi is flagged down while the taxi is stopping at a red light, many taxi drivers do not start the meter until the taxi starts running completely after the signal changes to green; however, there is no general rule for this; this simply indicates the drivers&apos; consideration to the passengers or means they want to avoid trouble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, when a taxi is flagged down while the taxi is stopping at a red light, many taxi drivers do not start the meter until the taxi starts running completely after the signal changes to green; however, there is no general rule for this; this simply indicates the drivers&apos; consideration to the passengers or means they want to avoid trouble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, when a taxi is flagged down while the taxi is stopping at a red light, many taxi drivers do not start the meter until the taxi starts running completely after the signal changes to green; however, there is no general rule for this; this simply indicates the drivers&apos; consideration to the passengers or means they want to avoid trouble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="73">
<j>また、降車で停車する直前にメーターが変わった場合、変わる前の料金で良いと言う乗務員もいるが、これもトラブル防止の意味合いが多く、また差額は乗務員の自己負担である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, when the meter changes and the fare increases immediately before the taxi stops as it arrives at the destination, many taxi drivers charge the fare the meter was showing before the fare increased; however, this also means they want to avoid trouble with the passenger and the driver is responsible for the amount of difference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, when the meter changes and the fare increases immediately before the taxi stops as it arrives at the destination, many taxi drivers charge the fare the meter was showing before the fare increased; however, this also means they want to avoid trouble with the passenger and the driver is responsible for the difference in the amount.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, when the meter changes and the fare increases immediately before the taxi stops as it arrives at the destination, many taxi drivers charge the fare the meter was showing before the fare increased; however, this also means they want to avoid trouble with the passenger and the driver is responsible for the difference in the amount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="74">
<j>但し、道路運送法第10条(運賃又は料金の割戻しの禁止)違反行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this violates Article 10 of the Road Transportation Act (prohibition of returning the fare or charge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this violates Article 10 of the Road Transportation Act (prohibition of returning the fare or charge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this violates Article 10 of the Road Transportation Act (prohibition of returning the fare or charge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="75">
<j>精算方法としては、現金の他、チケット、クーポン、クレジットカードなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cash, tickets, coupon, and credit cards are available for payment of fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cash, tickets, coupons, and credit cards can be used for payment of the fare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cash, tickets, coupons, and credit cards can be used for payment of the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>現金以外の場合は、使えるタクシー（事業者）が限られているので、よく確認して利用すべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, taxis (companies) that accept tickets, coupon, and/or credit cards are limited, so users should ask the driver whether he/she takes other than cash.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, taxis (companies) that accept tickets, coupons, and/or credit cards are limited, so users should ask the driver whether he/she accepts other than cash.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, taxis (companies) that accept tickets, coupons, and/or credit cards are limited, so users should ask the driver whether he/she accepts other than cash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>なお、特殊な利用方法として、後でタクシー会社からの請求に応じる約束で何も持たずに、あるいは名刺などをチケットの代わりとして利用される場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As special ways to pay the fare, there are some cases where the user of a taxi takes no means of payment with him/her or only with his/her business card as a ticket and makes a promise to accept the bill from the taxi company later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As special ways to pay the fare, there are some cases where the customer of a taxi takes no means of payment with him/her or only with his/her business card as a ticket and makes a promise to accept the bill from the taxi company later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As special ways to pay the fare, there are some cases where the customer of a taxi takes no means of payment with him/her or only with his/her business card as a ticket and makes a promise to accept the bill from the taxi company later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="78">
<j>降りるときもまた左後方のドアが自動で開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When passengers get out a taxi, the left back door opens automatically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When passengers gets out of the taxi, the left back door opens mechanically.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When passengers gets out of the taxi, the left back door opens mechanically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>客が降りるとドアが閉まるので客は閉める必要はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the passengers get out of the taxi, the door closes automatically, so customers need not close it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the passengers get out of the taxi, the door closes mechanically, so customers need not close it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the passengers get out of the taxi, the door closes mechanically, so customers need not close it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>ただし、これは乗務員が客の動作や周囲の状況を確認し操作するものであり、一般的な意味での自動ドアとは違う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system, however, is different from general automatic doors because the driver controls the door after checking the passengers&apos; movement and the surroundings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system, however, is different from general automatic doors because the driver controls the door after checking the passengers&apos; movement and the surroundings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system, however, is different from general automatic doors because the driver controls the door after checking the passengers&apos; movement and the surroundings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>近年では、油圧式で強く腕力を要しないものも増えてきたが、ワイヤーなどで乗務員の人力に頼るものも多く、意外な肉体作業である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, the number of hydraulic doors which do not need much human power has been increasing, but there are still quit a few taxis with a human-powered door using a wire or similar material, which means that this task of taxi drivers is a heavy physical work surprisingly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, the number of hydraulic doors, that do not need much human power, has been increasing, but there are still quit a few taxis with a human-powered doors using a wire or similar device, which means that this task for the taxi drivers is surprisingly heavy physical work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, the number of hydraulic doors, that do not need much human power, has been increasing, but there are still quit a few taxis with a human-powered doors using a wire or similar device, which means that this task for the taxi drivers is surprisingly heavy physical work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>また、降車時に客がドアを閉めると、ワイヤー式やてこを利用したレバー式の場合、乗務員側のレバーも連動して動くため、乗務員の腕がレバーに挟まれる場合もあるので、ドアの開閉は乗務員に任せるべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, if the customer shuts the automatic door as he/she gets out of a taxi, the lever system with a wire or a leverage on the driver side moves together along with the door, and the driver might get his/her arm caught by the lever accordingly, and thus operation of the automatic door should be always performed by the driver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, if the customer shuts the automatic door as he/she gets out of a taxi, the lever system with a wire or a leverage on the driver side moves together along with the door, and the driver might get his/her arm caught by the lever accordingly, and thus operation of the automatic door should be always performed by the driver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, if the customer shuts the automatic door as he/she gets out of a taxi, the lever system with a wire or a leverage on the driver side moves together along with the door, and the driver might get his/her arm caught by the lever accordingly, and thus operation of the automatic door should be always performed by the driver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>後方右側のドアは乗り逃げ防止のためチャイルドロックが掛けられていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The right back door, on the other hand, is often set the childproof door lock for the prevention of fare dodger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The right back door, on the other hand, is often set in the childproof door lock position to prevent of fare dodging.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The right back door, on the other hand, is often set in the childproof door lock position to prevent of fare dodging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>タクシーの運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>タクシーの運賃はかつて、同一地域同一運賃制度に従い、原則として同じ地域では会社を問わず同じ運賃であったが、1993年にこの制度が廃止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi fares used to be the same across all taxi companies in a area in accordance with the &quot;same fare in the same region system,&quot; but this system was abolished in 1993.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi fares used to be the same across all taxi companies in an area in accordance with the &quot;same fare in the same region system,&quot; but this system was abolished in 1993.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi fares used to be the same across all taxi companies in an area in accordance with the &quot;same fare in the same region system,&quot; but this system was abolished in 1993.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>現在では、地域ごとに定められた金額を上限とする一定の範囲内であれば、各社の裁量により運賃を自由に決めることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, each company can freely determine its own fare according to its discretion within a certain range up to a ceiling of the predetermined amount for the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, each company can freely determine its own fare according to its discretion within a certain range up to a ceiling of the predetermined amount for the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, each company can freely determine its own fare according to its discretion within a certain range up to a ceiling of the predetermined amount for the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>たとえば、2007年12月現在、東京都区部における一般的な普通車初乗り運賃は710円であるが、500円とする会社も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, as of December 2007, the common Hatsunori fare (minimum taxi fare which is the first amount of charge before charge goes up as the taxi runs a certain distance or a certain time passes) of ordinary taxis in Tokyo&apos;s 23 wards is 710 yen, but there are some companies which set their Hatsunori fares to 500 yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, as of December 2007, the common Hatsunori fare (minimum taxi fare which is the first amount of charge before charge goes up as the taxi runs a certain distance or a certain time passes) for ordinary taxis in Tokyo&apos;s 23 wards is 710 yen, but there are some companies which set their Hatsunori fares to 500 yen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, as of December 2007, the common Hatsunori fare (minimum taxi fare which is the first amount of charge before charge goes up as the taxi runs a certain distance or a certain time passes) for ordinary taxis in Tokyo&apos;s 23 wards is 710 yen, but there are some companies which set their Hatsunori fares to 500 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>また、1997年には初乗距離短縮運賃制という制度が一部の会社で導入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1997, a system called &quot;reduction of distance for Hatsunori fare system&quot; was introduced in some taxi companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1997, a system called &quot;reduction of distance for the Hatsunori fare system&quot; was introduced in some taxi companies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1997, a system called &quot;reduction of distance for the Hatsunori fare system&quot; was introduced in some taxi companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>これは、初乗り運賃を安くする代わりに初乗り運賃が適用される距離を短くするというもので、一定距離を走行すると通常の運賃と同額になるが、初乗り運賃の高さから敬遠されがちな短距離利用の促進を狙っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system is to reduce the distance for the Hatsunori fare instead of reducing the amount of Hatsunori fare, which is intended to obtain more customers who want to use a taxi for a short distance but do not want to pay a high Hatsunori fare because unless the taxi runs a certain distance, the fare will not go up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is to reduce the distance for the Hatsunori fare instead of reducing the amount of Hatsunori fare, which is intended to attract more customers who want to use a taxi for a short distance, but do not want to pay a high Hatsunori fare because unless the taxi runs a certain distance, the fare will not go up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is to reduce the distance for the Hatsunori fare instead of reducing the amount of Hatsunori fare, which is intended to attract more customers who want to use a taxi for a short distance, but do not want to pay a high Hatsunori fare because unless the taxi runs a certain distance, the fare will not go up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>日本で初乗り運賃が一番安いタクシーは、石川県七尾市の港観光タクシーで、250円である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The taxi company that offers services with the lowest Hatsunori fare in Japan, which is 250 yen, is Minato Kanko taxi in Nanao City, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The taxi company that offers services with the lowest Hatsunori fare in Japan, which is 250 yen, is Minato Kanko taxi in Nanao City, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The taxi company that offers services with the lowest Hatsunori fare in Japan, which is 250 yen, is Minato Kanko taxi in Nanao City, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="90">
<j>また、徳島県の金比羅タクシーで初乗り運賃は260円 (中型車。大型車は280円) である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konpira taxi in Tokushima Prefecture offers services with Hatsunori fare of 260 yen (for a medium-sized car, 280 yen for a full-size car)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpira taxi in Tokushima Prefecture offers services with Hatsunori fare of 260 yen (for a medium-sized car, 280 yen for a full-size car)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpira taxi in Tokushima Prefecture offers services with Hatsunori fare of 260 yen (for a medium-sized car, 280 yen for a full-size car)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>原則予約制で運営するからこそ可能な料金である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These taxi companies can achieve such low fares because they basically provide their services by advance reservation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These taxi companies can achieve such low fares because they basically provide their services by advance reservation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These taxi companies can achieve such low fares because they basically provide their services by advance reservation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>しかし、2008年8月4日、大型車を350円とする認可が降りた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the approval of setting Hatsunori fare for a full-size car to 350 yen was obtained on August 4, in 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, approval for setting the Hatsunori fare for a full-size car at 350 yen was obtained on August 4, in 2008.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, approval for setting the Hatsunori fare for a full-size car at 350 yen was obtained on August 4, in 2008.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="93">
<j>個人タクシーでは消費税法に基づく事業者免税点制度が適用されることから（売り上げが規定値以下のため）消費税の納税義務を免除されており、その分、個人タクシー「個人タクシー」と「法人タクシー」よりも運賃が安くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operators of privately owned taxis are given remission from tax payments including the consumption tax because the business operator tax exemption point system based on the Consumption Tax Act applies to them (since their sales are less than the prescribed value); therefore, the fare of privately owned taxis is set less expensive than that of corporate taxis.</e>
<cmt>「その分、個人タクシー「個人タクシー」と「法人タクシー」よりも運賃が安くなっている。」の部分は文章として意味が良く理解できませんでした。仕方なく単純に「その分、個人タクシーは法人タクシーよりも運賃が安くなっている。」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operators of privately owned taxis are often given refunds from tax payments including the consumption tax because the business operator tax exemption point system based on the Consumption Tax Act applies to them (since their sales are less than the prescribed value); therefore, the fare of privately owned taxis is set lower than that of corporate taxis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Operators of privately owned taxis are often given refunds from tax payments including the consumption tax because the business operator tax exemption point system based on the Consumption Tax Act applies to them (since their sales are less than the prescribed value); therefore, the fare of privately owned taxis is set lower than that of corporate taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>基本的な運賃料金システム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basic fare system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basic fare system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basic fare system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>通常のタクシーの運賃・料金は以下のように構成される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fare of general taxis consists of the following items.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fare of general taxis consists of the following items.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fare of general taxis consists of the following items.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>基本運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basic fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basic fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basic fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>距離制運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mileage system fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mileage system fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mileage system fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="96">
<j>初乗り運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatsunori fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatsunori fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatsunori fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="97">
<j>乗車してから一定距離までは定額の運賃となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fare is flat until the taxi runs for a certain distance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fare is flat until the taxi runs for a certain distance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fare is flat until the taxi runs for a certain distance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>これを初乗り運賃という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This fare is called Hatsunori fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fare is called a Hatsunori fare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fare is called a Hatsunori fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="99">
<j>距離制運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mileage system fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mileage system fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mileage system fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="100">
<j>一定距離を走行するごとに、一定額の運賃が加算される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A certain amount of charge is added every time the taxi runs for a certain distance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A certain amount is charged every time the taxi runs for a certain distance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A certain amount is charged every time the taxi runs for a certain distance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>2002年の規制緩和以降、加算額は事業者が自由に設定できるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the relaxation of the taxi regulations in 2002, each operator can freely determine the amount of charge to be added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the relaxation of taxi regulations in 2002, each operator can freely determine the amount of charge to be added.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the relaxation of taxi regulations in 2002, each operator can freely determine the amount of charge to be added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>また地域によっては、高速道路に限り、距離制運賃だけの加算（次項に挙げる時間制運賃を適用しない加算）へ切り替えられるようにされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some areas, the system is changing to only add the mileage system fare only when the taxi runs on an Expressway (the charge is not added in the time charge system which is described in the next section).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some areas, the system is changing to only the mileage system fare, only when the taxi runs on an Expressway (the charge is not added in the time charge system which is described in the next section).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some areas, the system is changing to only the mileage system fare, only when the taxi runs on an Expressway (the charge is not added in the time charge system which is described in the next section).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>これは途中下車ができない高速道路上で渋滞にはまってしまい、運賃が上がり過ぎないようにするため。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is to avoid the fare to be so expensive when the taxi gets stuck in a jam on an Expressway where the passenger cannot get out of the taxi on the way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is to avoid the fare becoming so expensive if the taxi gets stuck in a jam on an Expressway where the passenger cannot get out of the taxi on the way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is to avoid the fare becoming so expensive if the taxi gets stuck in a jam on an Expressway where the passenger cannot get out of the taxi on the way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="104">
<j>時間制運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Time charge fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Time charge fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Time charge fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="105">
<j>一定速度（時速10km）以下で走行していたり、停止していたりする間は、走行距離の代わりに経過時間を一定基準の計算法により距離に換算し、運賃が加算される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While a taxi is running slower than a certain speed (10 kilometers per hour) or stopping, the elapse time is calculated in a certain standard method to be converted into the distance and then the amount is added to the fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While a taxi is running slower than a certain speed (10 kilometers per hour) or stopping, the elapse time is calculated in a certain standard method to be converted into the distance and then the amount is added to the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While a taxi is running slower than a certain speed (10 kilometers per hour) or stopping, the elapse time is calculated in a certain standard method to be converted into the distance and then the amount is added to the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>このため走行経路が渋滞していると、移動距離の割に高額な運賃となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, if the pathway to the destination has a traffic jam, the fare tends to be fairly expensive for the travel distance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, if the pathway to the destination has a traffic jam, the fare tends to be fairly expensive for the travel distance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, if the pathway to the destination has a traffic jam, the fare tends to be fairly expensive for the travel distance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="107">
<j>時間制運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Time charge fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Time charge fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Time charge fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="108">
<j>乗った時間だけで決まる運賃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fare which is determined by how long the passenger has used the taxi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fare determined by how long the passenger has used the taxi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fare determined by how long the passenger has used the taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>観光地周りなどの場合によく使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system is often used for visiting tourist spots by a taxi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is often used for visiting tourist spots by a taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is often used for visiting tourist spots by a taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="110">
<j>定額制運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flat-rate fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flat-rate fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flat-rate fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="111">
<j>距離や時間にかかわらず決まっている運賃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fare which is predetermined regardless of the distance or time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fare which is predetermined regardless of the distance or time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fare which is predetermined regardless of the distance or time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>空港連絡の場合などに使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system is often used for a taxis which brings passengers to an airport.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is often used for a taxis which takes passengers to an airport.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is often used for a taxis which takes passengers to an airport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="113">
<j>貸切制運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charter system fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charter system fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charter system fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="114">
<j>時間、距離に関係なく、例えば、「乗務員の一日の売り上げで見込まれるであろう最低補償を客が“運賃”として負担することによって、乗務員と乗務員の運転する車を一日借り上げる」という方法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A system in which, for example, a user charters a taxi and its driver for a day by paying the minimum amount of compensation as a fare, which is seemingly equivalent to the daily sales of the driver, regardless of distance or time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A system in which, for example, a user charters a taxi and its driver for a day by paying the minimum amount of compensation as a fare, which is seemingly equivalent to the daily sales of the driver, regardless of distance or time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A system in which, for example, a user charters a taxi and its driver for a day by paying the minimum amount of compensation as a fare, which is seemingly equivalent to the daily sales of the driver, regardless of distance or time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>常連客を抱える個人事業者に、たまに見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system can be sometimes seen in private companies that have regular patrons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system can be sometimes seen in private companies that have regular patrons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system can be sometimes seen in private companies that have regular patrons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>割増・割引運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extra fare and discount fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extra fare and discount fares</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extra fare and discount fares</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="116">
<j>深夜割増運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higher fare for late hours</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higher fare for late hours</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higher fare for late hours</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="117">
<j>22時（一部大都市圏では23時）から翌5時まで加算される運賃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fare which applies between 22:00 (23:00 in some urban cities) and 5:00 in the next morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fare which applies between 22:00 (23:00 in some urban cities) and 5:00 the next morning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fare which applies between 22:00 (23:00 in some urban cities) and 5:00 the next morning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>通常2～3割加算される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually 20 to 30% of the regular fare is added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually 20 to 30% of the regular fare is added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually 20 to 30% of the regular fare is added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>この時間帯は、表示灯に青く「割増」と表示されることから「アオタン」とも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This time zone is also called &quot;Aotan&quot; because &quot;Warimashi (Extra fare)&quot; is displayed in blue on the indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This time zone is also called &quot;Aotan&quot; because &quot;Warimashi (Extra fare)&quot; is displayed in blue on the indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This time zone is also called &apos;Aotan&apos; (literally, blue strip of paper) because &apos;Warimashi&apos; (Extra fare) is displayed in blue on the indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。アオタン→青い短冊形　の意味であることのようですので、補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="120">
<j>冬季割増運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higher fare for winter time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higher fare for winter time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higher fare for winter time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="121">
<j>北海道や東北、北陸信越地方などで、冬季の道路状況が劣悪になることに鑑みて、特定の地域を走行するタクシーにおいて、厳冬期間に限って終日加算される運賃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the fact that road conditions become hazardous in the winter in Hokkaido, Tohoku region, Hokuriku region, and Shinetsu region, this system applies to taxis which are operated in the specific areas of these regions only during midwinter all day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the fact that road conditions become hazardous in the winter in Hokkaido, Tohoku region, Hokuriku region, and Shinetsu region, this system applies to taxis which are operated in the specific areas of these regions only during midwinter all day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the fact that road conditions become hazardous in the winter in Hokkaido, Tohoku region, Hokuriku region, and Shinetsu region, this system applies to taxis which are operated in the specific areas of these regions only during midwinter all day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>通常2割加算される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually 20% of the regular fare is added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually 20% of the regular fare is added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually 20% of the regular fare is added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="123">
<j>障害者割引</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disability discount</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disability discount</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disability discount</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="124">
<j>障害者は障害者手帳を提示することにより、地域にもよるがおおむね運賃が1割引となる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on the area, but people with disabilities are usually entitled to 10% discount by showing their identification booklet for the physically disabled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the area, but people with disabilities are usually entitled to 10% discount by showing their identification booklet for the physically disabled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the area, people with disabilities are usually entitled to 10% discount by showing their identification booklet for the physically disabled.</e>
<cmt>butを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="125">
<j>遠距離割引</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discount for long-distance travel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discount for long-distance travel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discount for long-distance travel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="126">
<j>一定距離以上を利用された場合、一定額が割り引かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a passenger uses a taxis over a certain distance, a certain amount of fare is discounted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a passenger uses a taxis over a certain distance, a certain amount of fare is discounted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a passenger uses a taxis over a certain distance, a certain amount of fare is discounted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="127">
<j>5000円以上の運賃の5割引（ゴーゴー運賃）や5000円以上3割引、9000円以上1割引など会社によって様々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various styles of discount depending on the taxi company, including 50% off of the fare (Go-Go fare) when the fare is over 5000 yen, 30% off when the fare is over 5000 yen, and 10% off when the fare is over 9000 yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various types of discounts depending on the taxi company, including 50% off of the fare (Go-Go fare) when the fare is over 5000 yen, 30% off when the fare is over 5000 yen, and 10% off when the fare is over 9000 yen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various types of discounts depending on the taxi company, including 50% off of the fare (Go-Go fare) when the fare is over 5000 yen, 30% off when the fare is over 5000 yen, and 10% off when the fare is over 9000 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>遠距離割引を採用していない法人・個人もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some corporate and private taxi companies that do not adopt any discounts for long-distance travel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some corporate and private taxi companies that do not adopt any discounts for long-distance travel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some corporate and private taxi companies that do not adopt any discounts for long-distance travel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>車種による運賃の違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Difference in fare according to types of vehicles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Difference in the fare according to types of vehicles</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Difference in the fare according to types of vehicles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="129">
<j>以上の運賃体系のほか、タクシーの車両は車種によりクラス分けがされており、クラスによって運賃が異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the fare systems described above, vehicles used as taxis are classified by car types and fares differ from class to class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the fare systems described above, vehicles used as taxis are classified by car types and fares differ from class to class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the fare systems described above, vehicles used as taxis are classified by car types and fares differ from class to class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>初乗り運賃だけでなく、運賃が加算される走行距離なども異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only Hatsunori fares but distance in which the fare is added up are also different depending on the class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only Hatsunori fares, the fare is added according to the distance, are also different depending on the class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only Hatsunori fares, but also the fare added according to the distance, are also different depending on the class.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="131">
<j>概ね以下の4種類に分類されているが、この分類は必ずしも全国共通のものというわけではなく、特に大型車と特定大型車の区別がない地域や、これらと中型車を同一とする地域は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vehicles are roughly divided into the following four types, but it does not mean that these types are common throughout the nation; in fact there are many areas in the distinction between full-size cars and specific full-size cars is not made or full-size cars and specific full-size cars are included in medium-size cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vehicles are roughly divided into the following four types, but it does not mean that these types are common throughout the nation; in fact there are many areas where the distinction between full-size cars and specific full-size cars is not made or full-size cars and specific full-size cars are included in the category of medium-size cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vehicles are roughly divided into the following four types, but it does not mean that these types are common throughout the nation; in fact there are many areas where the distinction between full-size cars and specific full-size cars is not made or full-size cars and specific full-size cars are included in the category of medium-size cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>分類方法が道路交通法と異なる事に注意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note that this classification differs from that of the Road Traffic Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that this classification differs from that of the Road Traffic Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that this classification differs from that of the Road Traffic Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="133">
<j>特定大型車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specific full-size car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specific full-size car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specific full-size car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="134">
<j>普通自動車及び小型自動車で乗車定員7名以上の車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A specific full-size car is an ordinary motor vehicle and a compact car with a riding capacity of 7 people or more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A specific full-size car is an ordinary motor vehicle and is a compact car with a riding capacity of 7 people or more.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A specific full-size car is an ordinary motor vehicle and is a compact car with a riding capacity of seven people or more.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>ワゴン車・ワンボックス車を用いるジャンボタクシーなどはこれに該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A jumbo taxi that usually uses a van or a minivan is included in this type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A jumbo taxi that usually uses a van or a minivan is included in this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A jumbo taxi that usually uses a van or a minivan is included in this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>トヨタ・アルファード、日産・エルグランド、トヨタ・エスティマ（7人乗り）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyota ALPHARD, Nissan ELGRAND, TOYOTA ESTIMA (for 7 people), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyota ALPHARD, Nissan ELGRAND, TOYOTA ESTIMA (for 7 people), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyota ALPHARD, Nissan ELGRAND, TOYOTA ESTIMA (for seven people), etc.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="137">
<j>大型車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Full-size car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Full-size car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Full-size car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="138">
<j>普通自動車（3ナンバー車）で乗車定員6名以下の車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A full-size car is an ordinary motor vehicle (3-type license vehicle) with a riding capacity of 6 people or less.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A full-size car is an ordinary motor vehicle (number 3-type license vehicle) with a riding capacity of 6 people or less.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A full-size car is an ordinary motor vehicle (with a license plate whose number starts from 3) with a riding capacity of six people or less.</e>
<cmt>3ナンバー車　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>日産・シーマ、日産・フーガ、トヨタ・センチュリー、トヨタ・セルシオ、トヨタ・クラウンマジェスタ、トヨタ・クラウン（ロイヤルシリーズ／アスリート）、トヨタ・マークX、ホンダ・レジェンドなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nissan CIMA, Nissan FUGA, TOYOTA Century, TOYOTA Celsior, TOYOTA Crown Majesta, TOYOTA Crown (Royal series/Athlete), TOYOTA MARK X, HONDA LEGEND, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nissan CIMA, Nissan FUGA, TOYOTA Century, TOYOTA Celsior, TOYOTA Crown Majesta, TOYOTA Crown (Royal series/Athlete), TOYOTA MARK X, HONDA LEGEND, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nissan CIMA, Nissan FUGA, TOYOTA Century, TOYOTA Celsior, TOYOTA Crown Majesta, TOYOTA Crown (Royal series/Athlete), TOYOTA MARK X, HONDA LEGEND, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>トヨタ・エスティマ（8人乗り）、日産・プレサージュやホンダ・オデッセイなどのミニバン（3列目シートは撤去、実質ステーションワゴンに近似している）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some minivans such as TOYOTA ESTIMA (for 8 people), Nissan PRESAGE, and HONDA ODYSSEY (the third row is removed and thus it actually looks like a station wagon) are also included in this type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some minivans such as TOYOTA ESTIMA (for 8 people), Nissan PRESAGE, and HONDA ODYSSEY (the third row is removed and thus it actually looks like a station wagon) are also included in this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some minivans such as TOYOTA ESTIMA (for eight people), Nissan PRESAGE, and HONDA ODYSSEY (the third row is removed and thus it actually looks like a station wagon) are also included in this type.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="141">
<j>中型車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medium-size car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medium-size car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medium-size car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="142">
<j>小型自動車（5ナンバー車）のうち、自動車の長さが4.6メートル以上で乗車定員が6名以下の車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A compact car (5-type license vehicle) whose length is 4.6 meters or longer and with a riding capacity of 6 people or less.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A compact car (5-type license vehicle) where the length is 4.6 meters or longer and with a riding capacity of 6 people or less.</e>
<cmt>grammr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A compact car is a vehicle (with a license plate whose number starts from 5) where the length is 4.6 meters or longer and with a riding capacity of 6 people or less.</e>
<cmt>5ナンバー車 を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>トヨタ・クラウンセダン、トヨタ・クラウンコンフォート、日産・セドリック営業車など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOYOTA Crown Sedan, TOYOTA Crown Comfort, Nissan CEDRIC commercial vehicle, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TOYOTA Crown Sedan, TOYOTA Crown Comfort, Nissan CEDRIC commercial vehicle, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TOYOTA Crown Sedan, TOYOTA Crown Comfort, Nissan CEDRIC commercial vehicle, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>2000cc以下の3ナンバー車を含む場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3-type license vehicle of 2000 cc or less displacement may be included in this class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3-type license vehicle of 2000 cc or less displacement may be included in this class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vehicles with a license plate whose number starts from 3 and is 2000 cc or less displacement may be included in this class.</e>
<cmt>3 ナンバー車 を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>かつて中型タクシーはコラムシフトを備えた前部座席がベンチシートの6人乗り（乗客は5人まで）の車種が主流であったが、現在ではクラウン(セダン、コンフォート共)に定員6名設定のモデルがなく、セドリックの一部に細々と残っているに過ぎない状況であることから、現在では中型タクシーのほとんどが5人乗り（乗客は4人まで）となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major vehicles for medium-size car taxis used to be types of cars having a column shift (a gearshift lever is on the steering column), whose front seats are bench seats, and with a riding capacity of 6 people (5 passengers); however, most medium-size taxis today are for 5 people (4 passengers) mainly because there are no CROWNs (both Sedan and Comfort) with a riding capacity of 6 people and only a few Cedrics still have the style mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major vehicles for medium-size car taxis used to be types of cars having a column shift (a gearshift lever is on the steering column), whose front seats are bench seats, and with a riding capacity of 6 people (5 passengers); however, most medium-size taxis today are for 5 people (4 passengers) mainly because there are no CROWNs (both Sedan and Comfort) with a riding capacity of 6 people and only a few Cedrics still have the style mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major vehicles for medium-size car taxis used to be types of cars having a column shift (a gearshift lever is on the steering column), whose front seats are bench seats, and with a riding capacity of six people (five passengers); however, most medium-size taxis today are for five people (four passengers) mainly because there are no CROWNs (both Sedan and Comfort) with a riding capacity of six people and only a few Cedrics still have the style mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="146">
<j>小型車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compact car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compact car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compact car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="147">
<j>小型自動車（5ナンバー車）のうち、自動車の長さが4.6メートル以下で乗車定員が5名以下の車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A compact car (5-type license vehicle) whose length is 4.6 meters or shorter and with a riding capacity of 5 people or less.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A compact car (5-type license vehicle) whose length is 4.6 meters or shorter and with a riding capacity of 5 people or less.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A compact car is a vehicle (with a license plate whose number starts from 5) whose length is 4.6 meters or shorter and with a riding capacity of five people or less.</e>
<cmt>5ナンバー車 を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>トヨタ・コンフォート、日産・クルーなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOYOTA Comfort, Nissan CREW, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TOYOTA Comfort, Nissan CREW, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TOYOTA Comfort, Nissan CREW, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>日産・キューブやトヨタ・ファンカーゴなどの小型ワゴンもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some small wagons such as Nissan cube and TOYOTA Fun Cargo are often included in this class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some small wagons such as Nissan cube and TOYOTA Fun Cargo are often included in this class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some small wagons such as Nissan cube and TOYOTA Fun Cargo are often included in this class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>かつては1980年代のマークIIなど、全長4.6メートル以上であっても1800ccクラスのエンジンを積む車種は小型車に分類されていた時代があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an era in which vehicles, such as MARK II, of 1800-cc class were classified as compact cars even though their length was 4.6 meters or longer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an era in which vehicles, such as MARK II, of the 1800-cc class were classified as compact cars even though their length was 4.6 meters or longer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an era in which vehicles, such as MARK II, of the 1800-cc class were classified as compact cars even though their length was 4.6 meters or longer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="151">
<j>乗車定員には乗務員も含まれるため、実際に乗車できる乗客の数は乗車定員より1名少ない数となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the taxi driver is included in the riding capacity, the actual number of passengers who can take a taxi is one person less than the capacity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the taxi driver is included in the riding capacity, the actual number of passengers who can take a taxi is one person less than the capacity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the taxi driver is included in the riding capacity, the actual number of passengers who can take a taxi is one person less than the capacity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="152">
<j>地域により中型車の多い地域と、小型車の多い地域、中型車と小型車が半々程度の地域がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some regions have more medium-size cars than compact cars, and vice versa, and some other regions have fifty-fifty ratio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some regions have more medium-size cars than compact cars, and vice versa, and some other regions have fifty-fifty ratio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some regions have more medium-size cars than compact cars, and vice versa, and some other regions have fifty-fifty ratio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>概ね首都圏・近畿圏・中京圏の三大都市圏は中型車が多いが、例外的に京都市や和歌山市では中型車と小型車が半々程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, the three major metropolitan areas including the national capital region, the Kinki Region, and the Chukyo-ken (Chukyo area) have more medium-size cars than compact cars; however, in an exceptional case, Kyoto City and Wakayama City have fifty-fifty split of taxis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, the three major metropolitan areas including the national capital region, the Kinki Region, and the Chukyo-ken (Chukyo area) have more medium-size cars than compact cars; however, in an exceptional case, Kyoto City and Wakayama City have a fifty-fifty split when it comes to taxis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, the three major metropolitan areas including the national capital region, the Kinki region, and the Chukyo region have more medium-size cars than compact cars; however, in an exceptional case, Kyoto City and Wakayama City have a fifty-fifty split when it comes to taxis.</e>
<cmt>chukyo-ken を削除し、chukyo region のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>また北海道・東北・北陸・四国・九州・沖縄では小型車が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hokkaido, Tohoku, Hokuriku, Shikoku, Kyushu, and Okinawa, the number of compact cars exceeds that of medium-size cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hokkaido, Tohoku, Hokuriku, Shikoku, Kyushu, and Okinawa, the number of compact cars exceed those of medium-size cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hokkaido, Tohoku, Hokuriku, Shikoku, Kyushu, and Okinawa, the number of compact cars exceed those of medium-size cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>料金など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charges and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charges and others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charges and others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="155">
<j>迎車料金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geisha charge (charge for a taxi which is on the way to a customer to pick him/her up)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geisha charge (charge for a taxi which is on the way to a customer to pick him/her up)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geisha charge (charge for a taxi which is on the way to a customer to pick him/her up)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>車を呼んだ場合にかかる料金。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A charge needed when customers call for a taxi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A charge required when customers call for a taxi</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A charge required when customers call for a taxi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>最近では無料化する会社も増えつつあるが、東京の大手タクシー会社では2007年の料金改定と共に新たに設定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of taxi companies that offer free Geisha charge has been increasing these days, but at the same time, some major taxi companies in Tokyo have newly set up the charge along with the charge revision in 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of taxi companies that offer free Geisha charge has been increasing these days, but at the same time, some major taxi companies in Tokyo have newly set up the charge together with the charge revision in 2007.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of taxi companies that offer free Geisha charge has been increasing these days, but at the same time, some major taxi companies in Tokyo have newly set up the charge together with the charge revision in 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="158">
<j>待料金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waiting charge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waiting charge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waiting charge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>利用者の都合で待機している場合にかかる料金。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A charge added on while the taxi is waiting for the user for his/her own convenience</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A charge added on while the taxi is waiting for the customer for his/her own convenience</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A charge added on while the taxi is waiting for the customer for his/her own convenience</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>迎車料金無料の場合はこちらも無料。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the Geisha charge is free, this charge is also free.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the Geisha charge is free, this charge is also free.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the Geisha charge is free, this charge is also free.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="161">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>高速道路などの有料道路を通った場合、その通行料金を請求される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a taxi uses a tollway such as an expressway, the fee is charged the user.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a taxi uses a tollway such as an expressway, the fee is charged to the passenger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a taxi uses a tollway such as an expressway, the fee is charged to the passenger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>客を降ろした後の戻りにもその有料道路を通らなければならない場合は往復の料金を請求されることもあり、拾った車がその戻りであった場合は料金を請求されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the taxi needs to use the same tollway for its return journey, the user may be asked to pay for a return trip, but if someone flags down the same taxi on its way back, he/she does not need to pay for the tollway charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the taxi needs to use the same tollway for its return journey, the user may be asked to pay for a return trip, but if someone flags down the same taxi on its way back, he/she does not need to pay for the tollway charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the taxi needs to use the same tollway for its return journey, the user may be asked to pay for a return trip, but if someone flags down the same taxi on its way back, he/she does not need to pay for the tollway charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="164">
<j>昔のタクシーはそのような設備が整っていなかったため、目的地まで運転手が料金を決めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because taxis of a few decades ago did not have the systems mentioned above, the driver used to decide the fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because taxis of a few decades ago did not have the systems mentioned above, the driver used to decide the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because taxis of a few decades ago did not have the systems mentioned above, the driver used to decide the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>支払方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to pay fares</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to pay fares</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to pay fares</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="165">
<j>現金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cash</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cash</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cash</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>最も一般的な手段。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most common means of payment of taxi fares</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most common means of payment for taxi fares</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most common means of payment for taxi fares</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>現金乗車を認めないタクシーはありえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There can be no such thing as a taxi which does not accept cash.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no such thing as a taxi that does not accept cash.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no such thing as a taxi that does not accept cash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>ただ、安全面などの関係から、次項以降の現金以外の支払方法を拡充する方向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, for safety reasons, other means of payment mentioned below, which are other than cash, have been tended to be expanded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for safety reasons, other means of payment mentioned below, other than cash, have been increasing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for safety reasons, other means of payment mentioned below, other than cash, have been increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="169">
<j>チケット（タクシーチケット）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tickets (Taxi tickets)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tickets (Taxi tickets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tickets (Taxi tickets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>近年ではチケットをICカード化している場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, some tickets are embedded with IC chips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, some tickets are embedded with IC chips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, some tickets are embedded with IC chips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="171">
<j>タクシー会社または無線グループ、お得意先顧客、クレジットカード会社が発行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tickets are issued by taxi companies or Musen (radio) groups, business friend customers, or credit-card companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tickets are issued by taxi companies or Musen (radio) groups, business friend customers, or credit-card companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tickets are issued by taxi companies or Musen (radio) groups, business friend customers, or credit-card companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>厳密にいえばチケットは金額欄を乗客が下車時に記入するもの（着服防止のため乗務員は記入できない）であるが、広義的には金額があらかじめ設定されたクーポン券や、地方自治体が発行する金額が決められた福祉チケットも含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly speaking, taxi tickets are those whose payment column is supposed to be filled in by the passenger when he/she gets out the taxi (the driver must not fill it in to prevent embezzlement); however, in the broad sense, tickets here include coupons whose value is set up in advance and welfare tickets whose value is also set up in advance and which are issued by the local government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, taxi tickets are those with payment columns that are supposed to be filled in by the passenger when he/she gets out the taxi (the driver must not fill it in to prevent embezzlement); however, in the broad sense, tickets here include coupons where the value is set up in advance and welfare tickets where the value is also set up in advance and are issued by the local government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, taxi tickets are those with payment columns that are supposed to be filled in by the passenger when he/she gets out the taxi (the driver must not fill it in to prevent embezzlement); however, in the broad sense, tickets here include coupons where the value is set up in advance and welfare tickets where the value is also set up in advance and are issued by the local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>有効期限があるものや、使用金額上限が設定されているものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expiration date and/or upper limit of use amount may be determined for some tickets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expiration date and/or upper limit of amounts may be determined for some tickets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expiration date and/or upper limit of amounts may be determined for some tickets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="174">
<j>クレジットカード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Credit cards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Credit cards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Credit cards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>カードを読み込む端末（インプリンタの場合もある）が装備された車両なら、利用制限を守っていれば使用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Credit cards are accepted by taxis with a terminal to read a credit card (or an imprinter) as long as using one within the limits of its use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Credit cards are accepted by taxis with a terminal to read a credit card (or an imprinter) as long as it is used within the limits of its use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Credit cards are accepted by taxis with a terminal to read a credit card (or an imprinter) as long as it is used within the limits of its use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>ただし、前述のチケット発行会社と異なる（どちらかしか対応していない）場合もあるので注意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note, however, that some taxis only accept either above-mentioned taxi tickets or credit cards.</e>
<cmt>この文章の意味が明確に理解できませんでした。（前述のチケット発行会社と「何が」異なるのか？）仕方なく「前述のチケットかクレジットカードのどちらか一方しか使用できない場合もあるので注意。」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note, however, that some taxis only accept either the above-mentioned taxi tickets or credit cards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note, however, that some taxis only accept either the above-mentioned taxi tickets or credit cards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="177">
<j>デビットカード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Debit cards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Debit cards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Debit cards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>金融機関の口座から直接料金を差し引いて支払う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Payment is directly subtracted from the user&apos;s account of a financial institution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Payment is directly subtracted from the user&apos;s account in a financial institution.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Payment is directly subtracted from the user&apos;s account in a financial institution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>クレジットカード端末を装備している車両の一部で使用できるが、まだ普及率は低く、時間帯によっては利用できない場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Debit cards are only available in some of the taxies with a credit card terminal, but its penetration rate is still low and they may not be accepted depending on the hours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Debit cards are only accepted in some of the taxies tht have a credit card terminal, but its penetration rate is still low and they may not be accepted depending on the hours.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Debit cards are only accepted in some of the taxies that have a credit card terminal, but its penetration rate is still low and they may not be accepted depending on the hours.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="180">
<j>会員カード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Membership cards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Membership cards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Membership cards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>タクシー会社または無線グループがお得意先顧客（上客）に対し発行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Membership cards are issued by taxi companies or Musen (radio) groups for their special customers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Membership cards are issued by taxi companies or Musen (radio) groups for their special customers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Membership cards are issued by taxi companies or Musen (radio) groups for their special customers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>クレジットカードと違い、タクシー乗車専用である他、有効期限内であれば使い放題である（タクシーチケットの変形とも言える）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike credit cards, membership cards are only available for use of taxis and unmetered within the expiration date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike credit cards, membership cards are only available for use in taxis and are unmetered within the expiration date.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike credit cards, membership cards are only available for use in taxis and are unmetered within the expiration date (they can be said to be another version of taxi tickets).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="183">
<j>電子マネー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Electronic money</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Electronic money</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Electronic money</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>各種電子マネーカードまたは「電子マネー内蔵の携帯電話（おサイフケータイ）」を専用の支払端末にかざして非接触方式かつサイン等無しで料金を支払う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An electronic money card or a cell phone with a built-in electronic money (mobile wallet) is available for taxis with a special terminal for payment by holding it over the terminal in a contactless way and without signing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An electronic money card or a cell phone with a built-in electronic money (mobile wallet) is accepted by taxis with a special terminal for payment by simply holding it over the terminal and this does not require signing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An electronic money card or a cell phone with a built-in electronic money (mobile wallet) is accepted by taxis with a special terminal for payment by simply holding it over the terminal and this does not require signing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>2007年3月現在は都内の東京無線、チェッカーキャブ無線、中央無線、ANZENグループ、および愛媛県松山地区の伊予鉄タクシーなどしか対応していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of March 2007, only several companies, including Tokyo Musen, Checker Cab Musen, Chuomusen Taxi, ANZEN Group in Tokyo, and Iyotetsu taxi in Matsuyama area, Ehime Prefecture, accept electronic money.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of March 2007, only a few companies, including Tokyo Musen, Checker Cab Musen, Chuomusen Taxi, ANZEN Group in Tokyo, and Iyotetsu taxi in Matsuyama area, Ehime Prefecture, accept electronic money.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of March 2007, only a few companies, including Tokyo Musen, Checker Cab Musen, Chuomusen Taxi, ANZEN Group in Tokyo, and Iyotetsu taxi in Matsuyama area, Ehime Prefecture, accept electronic money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>さらに一部の電子マネー（2007年3月時点ではID (クレジット決済サービス)、DCMX、Edy、ICいーカード）しか利用できず、普及にはなお時間を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, only some types of electronic money (as of March 2007, ID (credit settlement service), DCMX, Edy, and IC E-card) are available, meaning that it will take longer to familiarize the electric money system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, only some types of electronic money (as of March 2007, ID (credit settlement service), DCMX, Edy, and IC E-card) are acceptable, and this means that it will take longer for the electric money system to become familiarized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, only some types of electronic money (as of March 2007, ID (credit settlement service), DCMX, Edy, and IC E-card) are acceptable, and this means that it will take longer for the electric money system to become familiarized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>なお、2007年3月より国際自動車・日本交通ではSuicaショッピングサービスが使える（順次導入）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, in March 2007, Suica shopping service will be available for Kokusai Mortorcars Co., Ltd. and Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (the system will be adopted gradually).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, in March 2007, Suica shopping service will be available for Kokusai Mortorcars Co., Ltd. and Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (the system will be adopted gradually).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, in March 2007, Suica shopping service will be available for Kokusai Mortorcars Co., Ltd. and Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (the system will be adopted gradually).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>関西地区の一部ではPiTaPaを利用することが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a part of Kansai area, PiTaPa Cards are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a part of Kansai area, PiTaPa Cards are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a part of Kansai area, PiTaPa Cards are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>タクシー運賃改定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revision of taxi fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Revision of taxi fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Revision of taxi fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="189">
<j>営業区域内の7割以上のタクシーが値上げ申請すると国土交通省はその審議に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism begins deliberations on the application if more than 70% of taxi companies in a business district apply for a raise in fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism will begin deliberations on the application if more than 70% of the taxi companies in a business district apply for a raise in fare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism will begin deliberations on the application if more than 70% of the taxi companies in a business district apply for a raise in fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>特に東京地方では、物価安定審議会を開催し審議する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in Tokyo, a price stabilization council is held to deliberate the application.</e>
<cmt>「物価安定審議会」＝「price stabilization council」は、用語調査担当の方も調べがつかなかったようですので、仮訳です。（翻訳者も定訳を見つけられませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in Tokyo, a price stabilization council is held to deliberate the application.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in Tokyo, a price stabilization council is held to deliberate the application.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="191">
<j>東京地区運賃値上げ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raise in fare in Tokyo area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raise in fare in the Tokyo area</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raise in fare in the Tokyo area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>東京地区においては、2007年12月3日に初乗り660円から710円へ運賃改定が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tokyo area, the Hatsunori fare was revised from 660 yen to 710 yen on December 3, in 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tokyo, the Hatsunori fare was revised from 660 yen to 710 yen on December 3, in 2007.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tokyo, the Hatsunori fare was revised from 660 yen to 710 yen on December 3, in 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>マスコミ報道では「値上げ」だけが強調されたが、午後11時以降に乗車する利用では反対に僅かながら値下げとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although media reports solely emphasized raise in fare, passengers who use the taxis after 11:00 p.m. are supposed to enjoy the benefits of slight reduction in fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although media reports solely emphasized the raise in the fare, passengers who use the taxis after 11:00 p.m. are supposed to enjoy the benefits of a slight reduction in fare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although media reports solely emphasized the raise in the fare, passengers who use the taxis after 11:00 p.m. are supposed to enjoy the benefits of a slight reduction in fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>これは深夜割増の適用時間帯・割増率が「午後11時以降3割増し」から「午後10時以降2割増し」になったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the hours and rate of premium to which higher fare is adopted were changed from &quot;30% more after 11:00 p.m.&quot; to &quot;20% more after 10:00p.m.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because the hours and rate of premium to which higher fare is adopted were changed from &quot;30% more after 11:00 p.m.&quot; to &quot;20% more after 10:00p.m.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the hours and rate of premium to which higher fare is adopted were changed from &apos;30% more after 11:00 p.m.&apos; to &apos;20% more after 10:00p.m.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>空港送迎タクシー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuttle taxi to the airport</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuttle taxi to the airport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuttle taxi to the airport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="195">
<j>南関東、愛知県（名古屋市とその周辺部）、京阪神、中四国では自宅と空港の間で乗合タクシーサービスを行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Share-ride taxi services are offered between one&apos;s home and the airport in Southern Kanto region, Aichi Prefecture (Nagoya City and the surrounding area), Keihanshin, and Chu-Shikoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Share-ride taxi services are offered between one&apos;s home and the airport in Southern Kanto region, Aichi Prefecture (Nagoya City and the surrounding area), Keihanshin, and Chu-Shikoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Share-ride taxi services are offered between one&apos;s home and the airport in Southern Kanto region, Aichi Prefecture (Nagoya City and the surrounding area), Keihanshin area (Kyoto, Osaka and Kobe), and central Shikoku region.</e>
<cmt>一部地域名を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>これには二種類のものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two types of share-ride taxi services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two types of share-ride taxi services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two types of share-ride taxi services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>一つは「自宅からある場所までは普通のタクシーで行き、そこで大型のタクシーに乗り換え、他の客と一緒に空港に行く」パターンである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One type is a style in which users take an ordinary taxi from home to a certain place and transfer to a full-size taxi and go to the airport with other passengers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One way is where customers take an ordinary taxi from home to a certain place and transfer to a full-size taxi and go to the airport with other passengers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One type is where customers take an ordinary taxi from home to a certain place and transfer to a full-size taxi and go to the airport with other passengers.</e>
<cmt>way →typeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>もう一つは「大型タクシーが各利用者のもとを巡回して集客後、直接空港に向かう」パターンである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other type is a full-size taxi picks up each passenger at home and then directly heads to the airport.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other way is where a full-size taxi picks up each passenger at home and then directly heads to the airport.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other is where a full-size taxi picks up each passenger at home and then directly heads to the airport.</e>
<cmt>way を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>単独でタクシーに乗って空港に行くよりも安い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These services are cheaper than taking a taxi to the airport individually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These services are cheaper than taking a taxi to the airport individually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These services are cheaper than taking a taxi to the airport individually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>また中型車もしくは小型車にて自宅より直接（もしくは遠回りしない距離の立ち寄り先を絡めて）空港に向かうパターンもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are cases where a medium-sized taxi or compact-car taxi takes passengers from home to the airport directly (or may stop at some places on the way which is not a circuitous route).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are cases where a medium-sized taxis or compact-car taxis take passengers from home to the airport directly (or may stop at some places along the way and this is not a circular route).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are cases where a medium-sized taxis or compact-car taxis take passengers from home to the airport directly (or may stop at some places along the way which is not a circuitous route).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>たいていサービス提供地域のどこから乗っても定額である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of these services have a flat-rate fare no matter where a passenger takes the taxi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of these services have a flat-rate fare no matter where a passenger boards the taxi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of these services have a flat-rate fare no matter where a passenger boards the taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="202">
<j>空港連絡バス乗り場まで行く手間が省けることから、特に荷物の多い海外旅行客を中心に需要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These services are popular among users who go abroad with a lot of baggage because they do not need to go to the bus stop for connecting to the airport.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These services are popular among users who go abroad with a lot of baggage because they do not need to go to the bus stop to connect to the airport.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These services are popular among users who go abroad with a lot of baggage because they do not need to go to the bus stop to connect to the airport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>また、24時間運用の空港を深夜から早朝にかけて発着する場合、鉄道や路線バスなどの公共交通機関を利用できないことも、海外旅行客の利用を伸ばす要因となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, another factor that these services have been gaining more overseas tourists is because public transportations such as trains and route buses are not available when an airplane takes off from or arrives at an airport that offers around-the-clock services between midnight and early morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, another reason that these services have been gaining more overseas tourists is because public transportation such as trains and route buses are not available when an airplane takes off from or arrives at an airport that offers around-the-clock services between midnight and early morning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, another reason that these services have been gaining more overseas tourists is because public transportation such as trains and route buses are not available when an airplane takes off from or arrives at an airport that offers around-the-clock services between midnight and early morning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>中には、マイカーを空港に置きっぱなしにできない飛行機の乗務員専用（通勤のための自宅や宿泊先と空港との送迎）のタクシー会社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of taxi companies that offer these services, there are some taxi companies that offer services exclusively for flight attendants who cannot leave their cars at the airport (the taxi takes them between home or their accommodation and the airport).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of taxi companies that offer these services, there are some that offer services exclusively for flight attendants who cannot leave their cars at the airport (the taxi takes them between home or their accommodation and the airport).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of taxi companies that offer these services, there are some that offer services exclusively for flight attendants who cannot leave their cars at the airport (the taxi takes them between home or their accommodation and the airport).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>こちらは完全予約制で、一般の客は利用できない（むしろハイヤーに近い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This service is by advance reservation only and not available for ordinary customers (it rather close to a hire (a kind of taxi without fare meter and provides services by request from the customer)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This service is by advance reservation only and are not available for ordinary customers (it rather close to a hire - a kind of taxi without a fare meter tht provides services by request from a customer).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This service is by advance reservation only and are not available for ordinary customers (it is rather close to a hire - a kind of taxi without a fare meter that provides services by request from a customer).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>乗務員</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi driver</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi driver</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi driver</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="206">
<j>タクシーの乗務には第二種運転免許が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi drivers must have a Class II driver license.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi drivers must have a Class II driver license.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi drivers must have a Class II driver license.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>AT車にしか乗務しないのであればオートマチックトランスミッション限定の普通二種免許で乗務することもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If someone can drive only an automatic transmission car, he/she can take a Class II driver license limited to automatic transmission cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If someone can drive only an automatic transmission car, he/she can take a Class II driver license limited to automatic transmission cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If someone can drive only an automatic transmission car, he/she can take a Class II driver license limited to automatic transmission cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>二種免許の取得資格がある者（普通第一種運転免許を3年以上取得している者）を教習生として雇い、二種免許を取得させる事業者もあるが（都内の大手タクシー会社では、グループに自動車教習所を持っている場合が多く、ここで二種免許取得のための教習が可能）､その場合数年（おおむね1～2年）の拘束期間が発生する（この期間を終える前に退職した場合、取得費用を返還しなければならないという契約で雇用されている場合が多い。ただし、法的な拘束力はない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some taxi companies that hire people who have a right to take a Class II driver license (who took Class I driver license three years ago or before) as aspiring drivers and have them obtain a Class II driver license (many of the major taxi companies in Tokyo run a driving school as a group company, which can offer training to obtain a Class II driver license), but the people are usually tied to the company for a few years (most of the time, the aspiring drivers are supposed to agree to a contract saying &quot;if he/she quits the company before the training period is over, he/she must pay back the cost for obtaining the license.&quot; before employed, but this is legally nonbinding).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some taxi companies that hire people who have a right to take a Class II driver license (who took Class I driver license three years ago or before) as aspiring drivers and have them obtain a Class II driver license (many of the major taxi companies in Tokyo run a driving school as a group company, which can offer training to obtain a Class II driver license), but the people are usually tied to the company for a few years (most of the time, the aspiring drivers are supposed to agree to a contract saying &quot;if he/she quits the company before the training period is over, he/she must pay back the cost for obtaining the license.&quot; before they were employed, but this is not legally binding).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some taxi companies that hire people who have a right to take a Class II driver license (who took Class I driver license three years ago or before) as aspiring drivers and have them obtain a Class II driver license (many of the major taxi companies in Tokyo run a driving school as a group company, which can offer training to obtain a Class II driver license), but the people are usually tied to the company for a few years (most of the time, the aspiring drivers are supposed to agree to a contract saying &quot;if he/she quits the company before the training period is over, he/she must pay back the cost for obtaining the license.&quot; before they were employed, but this is not legally binding).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>さらに上に述べたタクシー事業の多角化に対応するため、入社後、ホームヘルパー、警備員検定、救命講習修了等の資格取得を求められる会社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, to diversify their taxi businesses, there are also some taxi companies that have the drivers obtain qualification of care attendant, lifesaving certification, or be certified as a security guard after they enter the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, to diversify their taxi businesses, there are also some taxi companies that have the drivers obtain qualifications of a care attendant, lifesaving certification, or be certified as a security guard after they enter the company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, to diversify their taxi businesses, there are also some taxi companies that have the drivers obtain qualifications of a care attendant, lifesaving certification, or be certified as a security guard after they enter the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="210">
<j>乗務員は男性が多いが、タクシー乗務員については1999年の労働基準法改正以前から女性の深夜労働（22時～5時）が認められており、女性の乗務員も少なからずいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Majority of taxi drivers are men, but because late-night work (between 22:00 and 5:00 in the next morning) by women has been permitted even before the Labor Standards Act was revised in 1999, and thus there are some female drivers in no small measure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Majority of taxi drivers are men, but because late-night work (between 22:00 and 5:00 the next morning) by women has been permitted even before the Labor Standards Act was revised in 1999, and thus there are some female drivers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Majority of taxi drivers are men, but because late-night work (between 22:00 and 5:00 the next morning) by women has been permitted even before the Labor Standards Act was revised in 1999, and thus there are some female drivers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>しかし、一般的には昼日勤をする場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, female drivers tend to work in the daytime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, female drivers tend to work in the daytime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, female drivers tend to work in the daytime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>乗務員は、一般に正社員（期限の無い雇用契約）が多く、隔日勤務の場合、月に11から13乗務行なう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most taxi drivers are employees (termless employment contract) and work from 11 to 13 times a month in, for example, an alternate-day shift.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most taxi drivers are employees (termless employment contract) and work from 11 to 13 times a month in, for example, an alternate-day shift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most taxi drivers are employees (termless employment contract) and work from 11 to 13 times a month in, for example, an alternate-day shift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>隔日勤務の場合、一回の乗務を2日分の労働と計算するので、一ヶ月に 22日から26日の勤務をすることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an alternate-day shift, because one service is counted as a two-day work, a driver is supposed to work from 22 to 26 days a month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an alternate-day shift, because one service is counted as two-day work, a driver is supposed to work from 22 to 26 days a month.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an alternate-day shift, because one service is counted as two-day work, a driver is supposed to work from 22 to 26 days a month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>昼日勤（朝から夕方まで）、夜日勤（夜から朝まで）を毎日乗務する勤務体系もあるが、この場合、一ヶ月に22回から26回の乗務をすることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some work shifts in which drivers work in the daytime (morning through evening) and night-time (evening through next morning) everyday, which is calculated as 22 - 26 services a month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some work shifts in which drivers work in the daytime (morning through evening) and night-time (evening through next morning) everyday, which is calculated as 22 - 26 services a month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some work shifts in which drivers work in the daytime (morning through evening) and night-time (evening through next morning) everyday, which is calculated as 22 - 26 services a month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>正社員は通常、このような勤務体制をとる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Permanent employees usually take this work shift.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Permanent employees usually take this work shift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Permanent employees usually take this work shift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="216">
<j>定時制といわれる乗務員は、正社員ではなく、月に8乗務しかできない（昼・夜日勤の場合、16回）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drivers called &quot;Teiji-sei (part-time system)&quot; are not employees and are allowed to work only 8 times a month (16 times if he/she works both in the daytime and night-time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drivers called &quot;Teiji-sei (part-time system)&quot; are not employees and are allowed to work only 8 times a month (16 times if he/she works both in the daytime and night-time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drivers called &quot;Teiji-sei (part-time system)&quot; are not employees and are allowed to work only 8 times a month (16 times if he/she works both in the daytime and night-time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>主に、高齢者や兼業者がこういった勤務をする場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type of drivers are mainly older persons or persons in dual employment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These types of drivers are mainly older persons or persons with dual employment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These types of drivers are mainly older persons or persons with dual employment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="218">
<j>毎月の給与は固定給と歩合給が両方存在する形が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most taxi companies have a system in which both straight salary and percentage pay exist for the monthly salary payment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most taxi companies have a system in which both straight salary and percentage pay exist for monthly salary payment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most taxi companies have a system in which both straight salary and percentage pay exist for monthly salary payment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>したがって稼働日が多いときや売上が多いときは給与も高く、少ない時は給与が安い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the more days a driver works or the more sales he/she achieves, the more salary he/she gets, and in the contrary case, the less salary he/she gets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the more days a driver works or the more sales he/she achieves, the more salary he/she gets, and in the contrary case, the less salary he/she gets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the more days a driver works or the more sales he/she achieves, the more salary he/she gets, and in the contrary case, the less salary he/she gets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>一定の運送収入に達しない場合、歩合率が下げられる場合が多い（一般的に「足切り」と呼ばれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the total sales do not reach a certain goal of the company, the rate for percentage pay is often lowered (which is generally called &quot;Ashikiri (kind of reimbursement)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the total sales do not reach a certain goal of the company, the rate for percentage pay is often lowered (which is generally called &quot;Ashikiri&quot; or a kind of reimbursement).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the total sales do not reach a certain goal of the company, the rate for percentage pay is often lowered (which is generally called &apos;Ashikiri&apos; or a kind of reimbursement).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>賞与は毎月の支払べき給与の中から一定の割合で控除し、賞与の時に渡すのが慣例であり、売上が少ない場合は支給されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonus is set off from the monthly salary at a constant rate to be given to each driver, but if the sales are not sufficient, bonus is not paid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bonus is set off from the monthly salary at a constant rate to be given to each driver, but if the sales are not sufficient, the bonus is not paid.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bonus is set off from the monthly salary at a constant rate to be given to each driver, but if the sales are not sufficient, the bonus is not paid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>歩合は運賃の50ないし60％を基本として各種条件により上下するというのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Percentage pay, on the other hand, is based on 50% - 60% of the fare and increases or decreases according to various conditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Percentage pay, on the other hand, is based on 50% - 60% of the fare and increases or decreases according to various conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Percentage pay, on the other hand, is based on 50% - 60% of the fare and increases or decreases according to various conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="223">
<j>なお、近年の規制緩和によりタクシー台数が急増し、一部地域では過当競争が発生し、乗務員の労働環境を低下させているとの見方がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that taxi drivers&apos; work environment has been becoming bad as excessive competition arises in some areas due to rapid increase in the number of taxis triggered by the relaxation of the taxi regulations of recent years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say that taxi drivers&apos; work environment has been becoming worse as excessive competition arises in some areas due to rapid increase in the number of taxis triggered by the relaxation of the taxi regulations of recent years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that taxi drivers&apos; work environment has been becoming worse as excessive competition arises in some areas due to rapid increase in the number of taxis triggered by the relaxation of the taxi regulations of recent years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>乗務員の平均年収は全労働者の平均年収を大きく下回っており、格差社会問題の一端が表れているとの新聞特集記事が掲載されたこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some newspaper has once written as a feature story that the average yearly income of taxi drivers is much lower than that of all workers in Japan, which is representing a part of the gap-widening society issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some newspapers have written feature stories about the average yearly income of taxi drivers being much lower than that of all workers in Japan, which represents a part of the gap-widening social issue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some newspapers have written feature stories about the average yearly income of taxi drivers being much lower than that of all workers in Japan, which represents a part of the gap-widening social issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>タクシー運転手の求人広告は、主にスポーツ新聞や夕刊紙、公共職業安定所（ハローワーク）で行われることが多く、新聞や一般の求人情報誌、求人ウェブサイト（リクルート社のリクナビなど）にタクシー運転手の求人広告が載ることは少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Job-placement ads of taxi drivers are mainly shown on sports papers, evening papers, and at public job stabilization offices (Helloworks) and are seldom shown on daily papers, general help-wanted magazines, and help-wanted websites (e.g. RecNavi of RECRUIT Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Job-placement ads for taxi drivers are mainly shown in sports papers, evening papers, and at public job stabilization offices (Helloworks) and are seldom shown on daily papers, general help-wanted magazines, and help-wanted websites (e.g. RecNavi of RECRUIT Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Job-placement ads for taxi drivers are mainly shown in sports papers, evening papers, and at public job stabilization offices (Helloworks) and are seldom shown on daily papers, general help-wanted magazines, and help-wanted websites (e.g. RecNavi of RECRUIT Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>大都市近郊では吊り広告など電車内の広告（特に私鉄系のタクシー会社）やラジオCMで求人を募集している会社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the suburbs of the metropolitan areas, there are some taxi companies that post available job positions on advertisements which hung in trains (this is mainly performed by taxi companies belonging to a private railway group) and commercials on the radio.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the suburbs of metropolitan areas, there are some taxi companies that post available job positions on advertisements hung in trains (this is mainly performed by taxi companies belonging to a private railway group) and commercials on the radio.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the suburbs of metropolitan areas, there are some taxi companies that post available job positions on advertisements hung in trains (this is mainly performed by taxi companies belonging to a private railway group) and commercials on the radio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>運送引受の拒絶・旅客の禁止行為</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rejection of transportation and prohibited acts of passengers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rejection of transportation and prohibited acts of passengers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rejection of transportation and prohibited acts of passengers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="227">
<j>道路運送法第13条の定めるところにより、運送事業者は次の場合を除いては、運送の引受を拒絶してはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the provision of Article 13 in the Road Transportation Act, transportation operators cannot reject offers of transportation except for the following cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the provision of Article 13 in the Road Transportation Act, transportation operators cannot reject offers of transportation except in the following cases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the provision of Article 13 in the Road Transportation Act, transportation operators cannot reject offers of transportation except in the following cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="228">
<j>(1)当該運送の申込みが認可を受けた運送約款によらないものであるとき。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(1) In case that the application of the relevant transportation does not abide by the transportation clause</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(1) In case that the applicant of the relevant transportation does not abide by the transportation clause</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(1) In case that the applicant of the relevant transportation does not abide by the transportation clause</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="229">
<j>一般乗用旅客自動車運送事業標準運送約款</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Common Taxicab Operators Standard Transportation Clause</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common Taxicab Operators Standard Transportation Clause</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common Taxicab Operators Standard Transportation Clause</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>｢運送の引受け及び継続の拒絶｣（第4条）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Rejection of offer and continuation of transportation&quot; (Article 4)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Rejection of offer and continuation of transportation&quot; (Article 4)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rejection of offer and continuation of transportation&apos; (Article 4)</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>旅客は運転者その他の係員が運送の安全確保のために行う職務上の指示に従わなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Passengers must follow the official instructions of the driver or other attendants to ensure safety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers must follow official instructions of the driver or other attendants to ensure safety.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers must follow official instructions of the driver or other attendants to ensure safety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="232">
<j>運送に関し、申込者（旅客）から特別な負担を求められたとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the driver is asked to bear a special burden regarding the transportation by the offerer (passenger)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In case that the driver is asked to bear a special burden regarding the transportation by the passenger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In case that the driver is asked to bear a special burden regarding the transportation by the passenger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>運送が法令の規定又は公の秩序若しくは善良の風俗に反するものであるとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the transportation violates the rules of the act, public policy, or good morals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event that transportation violates the rules of the act, public policy, or good morals</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event that transportation violates the rules of the act, public policy, or good morals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>天災その他やむを得ない事由による運送上の支障があるとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the driver has an adverse effect on the transportation due to circumstances beyond one&apos;s control such as a natural disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event the driver faces an adverse effect on the transportation due to circumstances beyond one&apos;s control such as a natural disaster.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event the driver faces an adverse effect on the transportation due to circumstances beyond one&apos;s control such as a natural disaster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>旅客が乗務員の旅客自動車運送事業運輸規則の規定に基づいて行う措置に従わないとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the passenger does not follow the actions based on the rules of the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event that the passenger does not follow the procedures based on the rules of the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event that the passenger does not follow the procedures based on the rules of the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>旅客が旅客自動車運送事業運輸規則の規定により持込みを禁止された物品を携帯しているとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the passenger has goods which is prohibited to carry in taxis by the rules of the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In th event the passenger has goods that are prohibited to carry in taxis according to the rules of the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event the passenger has goods that are prohibited to carry in taxis according to the rules of the Passenger Vehicle Transportation Business Law.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>旅客が行先を明瞭に告げられないほど又は人の助けなくしては歩行が困難ほど泥酔しているとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the passenger is completely drunk so that he she cannot tell the driver where to go or walk without someone&apos;s help.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event that the passenger is completely drunk and he/she cannot tell the driver where to go or walk without someone&apos;s help.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event that the passenger is completely drunk and he/she cannot tell the driver where to go or walk without someone&apos;s help.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>旅客が車内を汚染するおそれがある不潔な服装をしているとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the passenger is dressed filthily so that he/she might contaminate the car interior</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In case that the passenger is dressed filthily so that he/she might contaminate the car interior</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In case that the passenger is dressed filthily so that he/she might contaminate the car interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>旅客が付添人を伴わない重病者であるとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the passenger is a critically ill person without any escort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event that the passenger is a critically ill person without any escort.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event that the passenger is a critically ill person without any escort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>旅客が感染症の予防及び感染症の患者に対する医療に関する法律による一類感染症、二類感染症若しくは指定感染症（入院を必要とするものに限る）の患者（これらの患者とみなされた者を含む）又は新感染症の所見のある者であるとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the passenger is a patient (and person who is regarded as a patient) of Class I infection, Class II infection, or designated infection (only one that requires admission to hospital), or a patient with suspected new infection, which are classified by the laws regarding medical treatment for patients of infection prevention or infection disease</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event that the passenger is a patient (and person who is regarded as a patient) of Class I infection, Class II infection, or designated infection (only one that requires admission to hospital), or a patient with suspected new infection, classified by the laws regarding medical treatment for patients of infection prevention or infectius diseases</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event that the passenger is a patient (and person who is regarded as a patient) of Class I infection, Class II infection, or designated infection (only one that requires admission to hospital), or a patient with suspected new infection, classified by the laws regarding medical treatment for patients of infection prevention or infectious diseases</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>禁煙車両（禁煙車である旨を表示した車両をいう）内では、旅客は喫煙を禁止する</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Smoking in a non-smoking vehicle (vehicle with non-smoking sign on) is banned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Smoking in a non-smoking vehicle (vehicle with non-smoking sign on) is banned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Smoking in a non-smoking vehicle (vehicle with non-smoking sign on) is banned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>旅客が禁煙車両内で喫煙し、又は喫煙しようとしている場合、運転者は喫煙を中止するよう求めることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a passenger smokes or is about to smoke in a non-smoking vehicle, the driver has a right to ask the passenger to stop smoking.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a passenger smokes or is about to smoke in a non-smoking vehicle, the driver has a right to ask the passenger to stop smoking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a passenger smokes or is about to smoke in a non-smoking vehicle, the driver has a right to ask the passenger to stop smoking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>旅客がこの求めに応じない場合には、運送の引受または継続を拒絶できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the passenger fails to comply with the driver&apos;s demand, the driver can reject the offer or continuation of the transportation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the passenger fails to comply with the driver&apos;s demand, the driver can reject the passenger&apos;s offer or the continuation of the transportation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the passenger fails to comply with the driver&apos;s demand, the driver can reject the passenger&apos;s offer or the continuation of the transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>(2)運送に関する設備のないとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(2) In case that the taxi has no equipment regarding the transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(2) In case that the taxi has no equipment required for transportation</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(2) In case that the taxi has no equipment required for transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>(6)国土交通省令の定める正当な事由のあるとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(6) In case that the driver has a fair reason defined by the Ordinances of the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(6) In case that the driver has a fair reason defined by the Ordinances of the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(6) In case that the driver has a fair reason defined by the Ordinances of the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>(イ)火薬類その他の危険物を携帯している者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(イ) A passenger who has explosives or other dangerous objects</e>
<cmt>「(イ)」は訳文にそのまま使用致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(イ) A passenger who has explosives or other dangerous objects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(1) A passenger who has explosives or other dangerous objects</e>
<cmt>(イ）は、イロハの順番と理解し、(1) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>(カ)食事若しくは休憩のため運送の引受をすることのできない場合又は乗務の終了などのため車庫若しくは営業所に回送しようとして回送板を掲出しているとき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(カ) In case the driver cannot accept an offer of a transportation because it is time for meal or break, or the taxi is showing a &quot;Not in service&quot; sign to go back to the garage or office at the close of business.</e>
<cmt>「(カ)」は訳文にそのまま使用致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(カ) In case the driver cannot accept an offer of a transportation because it is time for a meal or break, or the taxi is showing a &quot;Not in service&quot; sign to go back to the the garage or office at the end of business hours.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(14) In case the driver cannot accept an offer of a transportation because it is time for a meal or break, or the taxi is showing a &quot;Not in service&quot; sign to go back to the garage or office at the end of business hours.</e>
<cmt>(カ) はイロハ順と理解して、14としました。The のダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>運送事業者は、発地及び着地のいずれもがそのタクシーの営業区域外に存する旅客の運送をしてはならない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation operators must not provide a transportation service to someone whose point of departure and destination are located outside of their business district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation operators must not provide transportation service to someone whose point of departure and destination are located outside of their business district.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation operators must not provide transportation service to someone whose point of departure and destination are located outside of their business district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="249">
<j>車内への持込み禁止品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Objects that cannot be carried in a taxi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Objects that cannot be carried in a taxi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Objects that cannot be carried in a taxi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>火薬類（ただし50発以内の実包及び空包であって弾帯又薬盒に挿入してあるものを除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explosives (except a cartridge and a blank ammunition having less than 50 bullets, which are inserted in a cartridge belt or a ammunition pouch)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explosives (except a cartridge and a blank ammunition having less than 50 bullets, which are inserted in a cartridge belt or a ammunition pouch)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explosives (except a cartridge and a blank ammunition having less than 50 bullets, which are inserted in a cartridge belt or a ammunition pouch)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="251">
<j>100グラムを越える玩具用煙火（花火）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fireworks for personal use, which weigh more than 100 grams</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fireworks for personal use, that weigh more than 100 grams</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fireworks for personal use, that weigh more than 100 grams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>揮発油、灯油、軽油、アルコール、二硫化炭素その他の引火性液体（喫煙用ライター及び懐炉（カイロ）に利用している物を除く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inflammable liquid such as volatile oil, kerosene, light oil, alcohol, carbon disulfide (except materials for cigarette lighters and body warmers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inflammable liquid such as volatile oil, kerosene, light oil, alcohol, carbon disulfide (except materials for cigarette lighters and body warmers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inflammable liquid such as volatile oil, kerosene, light oil, alcohol, carbon disulfide (except materials for cigarette lighters and body warmers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>100グラムを越えるフイルムその他のセルロイド類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Film and other celluloid goods which weigh more than 100 grams</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Film and other celluloid goods which weigh more than 100 grams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Film and other celluloid goods which weigh more than 100 grams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>黄燐、カーバイト、金属ナトリウムその他の発火性物質及びマグネシウム粉、過酸化水素、過酸化ソーダその他の爆発性物質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Combustible substances such as yellow phosphorus, carbide, metal sodium, and explosive substances such as magnesium powder, hydrogen peroxide, soda peroxide</e>
<cmt>「過酸化ソーダ」＝「soda peroxide」は定訳不明により、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Combustible substances such as yellow phosphorus, carbide, metal sodium, and explosive substances such as magnesium powder, hydrogen peroxide, soda peroxide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Combustible substances such as yellow phosphorus, carbide, metal sodium, and explosive substances such as magnesium powder, hydrogen peroxide, soda peroxide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>放射性物質（放射性同位元素、核燃料物質）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Radioactive materials (radioisotope, nuclear fuel material)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Radioactive materials (radioisotope, nuclear fuel material)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Radioactive materials (radioisotope, nuclear fuel material)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>苛性ソーダ、硝酸、硫酸、塩酸その他の腐食性物質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Caustic materials such as caustic soda, nitric acid, sulfuric acid, and hydrochloric acid</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Caustic materials such as caustic soda, nitric acid, sulfuric acid, and hydrochloric acid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Caustic materials such as caustic soda, nitric acid, sulfuric acid, and hydrochloric acid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>高圧ガス（ただし、消火器内に封入した炭酸ガス及び医薬用酸素器に封入した酸素ガスを除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">High-pressure gas (except carbon dioxide gas filled in a fire extinguisher and oxygen gas filled in a medical oxygen equipment)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">High-pressure gas (except carbon dioxide gas filled in a fire extinguisher and oxygen gas filled in a medical oxygen equipment)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">High-pressure gas (except carbon dioxide gas filled in a fire extinguisher and oxygen gas filled in a medical oxygen equipment)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="258">
<j>クロルピクリン、メチルクロライド、液体青酸、クロロホルム、ホルマリンその他の有毒ガスを発する恐れのある物質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Substances that may emit poisonous gas, including trichloronitromethane, chloromethane, liquid hydrocyanic acid, chloroform, and formalin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Substances that may emit poisonous gas, including trichloronitromethane, chloromethane, liquid hydrocyanic acid, chloroform, and formalin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Substances that may emit poisonous gas, including trichloronitromethane, chloromethane, liquid hydrocyanic acid, chloroform, and formalin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="259">
<j>500グラムを越える量のマッチ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matches which weigh more than 500 grams</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matches which weigh more than 500 grams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matches which weigh more than 500 grams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>電池（乾電池を除く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Batteries (except dry-cell batteries)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Batteries (except dry-cell batteries)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Batteries (except dry-cell batteries)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>死体</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dead body</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dead body</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dead body</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>動物（身体障害者補助犬、またはそれと同等の能力があると認められた犬や愛玩用の小動物を除く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Animals (except assistance dogs or other dogs with equal ability as an assistance dog, or small animals as pets)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Animals (except assistance dogs or other dogs with equal ability as an assistance dog, or small animals as pets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Animals (except assistance dogs or other dogs with equal ability as an assistance dog, or small animals as pets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="263">
<j>タクシーの「乗車拒否」問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issue of &quot;rejection of boarding&quot; of taxis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issue of &quot;rejection of boarding&quot; of taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issue of &apos;rejection of boarding&apos; of taxis</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>乗車拒否とは「駐停車中又は客を認めて一時停止もしくは徐行を行い、運送の申し込みを受けてから、正当な理由なくその引き受けを拒否する事」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rejection of boarding means that a taxi driver rejects offer of transportation without reasonable excuse despite the fact that the driver has accepted the offer of transportation while the taxi is parked or after the driver stops or slows down the taxi because he/she has found the passenger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rejection of boarding means that a taxi driver rejects offer of transportation without reasonable excuse despite the fact that the driver has accepted the offer of transportation while the taxi is parked or after the driver stops or slows down the taxi because he/she has found a passenger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rejection of boarding means that a taxi driver rejects offer of transportation without reasonable excuse despite the fact that the driver has accepted the offer of transportation while the taxi is parked or after the driver stops or slows down the taxi because he/she has found a passenger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="265">
<j>バブル期において乗車拒否が多く見受けられていたが、昨今の社会状況において、乗務員が意図的に乗車拒否をすることは少なくなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there were many rejections of boarding during the years of the asset-inflated economy, the number of cases where taxi drivers intentionally reject offers of boarding is getting less under the recent social conditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were many rejections of boarding during the years of the asset-inflated economy, the number of cases where taxi drivers intentionally rejected offers of boarding is becoming less under recent social conditions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were many rejections of boarding during the years of the asset-inflated economy, the number of cases where taxi drivers intentionally rejected offers of boarding is becoming less under recent social conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="266">
<j>また、複数車線のある道路において、第1通行帯以外を通行しているときは、たとえ客を認めて運送の申し込みを受けたとしても、安全を考慮してその引き受けを受諾してはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, when a taxi is running in the first lane on a road having multiple lanes, the taxi driver must not accept the offer of transportation for safety reasons even if the driver finds a customer and has accepted the offer of transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, when a taxi is running in the first lane on a road having multiple lanes, the taxi driver must not accept the offer of transportation for safety reasons even if the driver finds a customer and has accepted the offer of transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, when a taxi is running in a lane other than the first lane on a road having multiple lanes, the taxi driver must not accept the offer of transportation for safety reasons even if the driver finds a customer and has accepted the offer of transportation.</e>
<cmt>第一通行帯以外　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vehicles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vehicles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vehicles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="267">
<j>車両は排気量2リッター級のセダンがおもに使われるが、最近ではステーションワゴンやミニバンもみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vehicles for a taxi are mainly sedans of 2000 cc displacement, but some station wagons and minivans can be seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vehicles for a taxi are mainly sedans of 2000 cc displacement, but some station wagons and minivans can be seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vehicles for a taxi are mainly sedans of 2000 cc displacement, but some station wagons and minivans can be seen in recent years.</e>
<cmt>最近では　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>以前は1.5～2リッター級二輪駆動方式の市販車をベースに若干の設計変更を施した車両を使っていたが、現在ではそのクラスの市販車がFRからFFに切り替えられ、またタクシーとしての快適性の追求と合わせて、FR駆動のタクシー専用車が開発されるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In past days, vehicles for taxis were based on commercially available two-wheel drive cars of 1500 - 200 cc displacement with a little change in design; however, because the same commercially available cars have been switched from FR to FF in recent years, as well as because the pursuit of vehicle comfort, vehicles exclusively for FR drive taxis have been being developed in recent years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In past days, vehicles for taxis were based on commercially available two-wheel drive cars of 1500 - 200 cc displacement with a little change in design; however, because the same commercially available cars have been switched from FR to FF in recent years, as well as because the pursuit of vehicle comfort, vehicles exclusively for FR drive taxis have been being developed in recent years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In past days, vehicles for taxis were based on commercially available two-wheel drive cars of 1500 - 2000 cc displacement with a little change in design; however, because the same commercially available cars have been switched from FR to FF in recent years, as well as because the pursuit of vehicle comfort, vehicles exclusively for FR drive taxis have been being developed in recent years.</e>
<cmt>2000　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>軽自動車は介護用以外で使用されることは少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicars (light motor vehicles) are rarely used for other than nursing purposes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicars (light motor vehicles) are rarely used for other than nursing purposes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicars (light motor vehicles) are rarely used for other than nursing purposes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="270">
<j>1980年代までのタクシー車両は、燃費の関係上、AT（オートマチックトランスミッション）車よりも、MT（マニュアルトランスミッション）車が多く用いられていたが、現在では、AT車の改良により燃費も改善されMT車との格差が少なくなってきたことや、乗務員の疲労軽減等からAT車が主流になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to 1980&apos;s, manual transmission vehicles were more common than automatic transmission vehicles for taxis because of the better fuel consumption, but because automatic transmission vehicles have been being improved and there is little difference in fuel consumption between those two types and to reduce fatigue of taxi drivers, automatic transmission vehicles have been becoming mainstream for taxis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to 1980&apos;s, manual transmission vehicles were more common than automatic transmission vehicles for taxis because of the better fuel consumption, but because automatic transmission vehicles have been being improved and there is little difference in fuel consumption between these two types and to reduce fatigue of taxi drivers, automatic transmission vehicles have been becoming mainstream for taxis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to 1980&apos;s, manual transmission vehicles were more common than automatic transmission vehicles for taxis because of the better fuel consumption, but because automatic transmission vehicles have been being improved and there is little difference in fuel consumption between these two types and to reduce fatigue of taxi drivers, automatic transmission vehicles have been becoming mainstream for taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="271">
<j>後部座席に旅客を乗せて営業するためそれ相応の安全性・乗降のスムーズさが求められることから、車両が国土交通省の道路運送車両の保安基準（以下、保安基準と略）に適合していなければ運用できないことになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because passengers usually take backseats of a taxi, appropriate safety and smoothness for incoming and outgoing are required, and thus vehicles for taxis must adapt to the safety standards for road trucking vehicles (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the safety standards&quot;) set by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because passengers usually take the backseats of a taxi, appropriate safety and smoothness for entering and exiting are required, and thus vehicles for taxis must adapt to the safety standards for road trucking vehicles (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the safety standards&quot;) set by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because passengers usually take the backseats of a taxi, appropriate safety and smoothness for entering and exiting are required, and thus vehicles for taxis must adapt to the safety standards for road trucking vehicles (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the safety standards&quot;) set by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>例えば、後部座席には必ずヘッドレストが設けられており（価格の安い自家用車には設けられていない場合が多い）、他にも前後の間隔やドアーの開口部についても、基準以上の数値を満たすことが義務付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the safety standards stipulates that headrests are set up in backseats (but often not set up in inexpensive private cars) and obliges that the separation between the front seat and backseat and the opening of the door, for example, must ensure more than the standards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the safety standards stipulates that headrests are set up in backseats (but often not set up in inexpensive private cars) and obliges that the separation between the front seat and backseat and the opening of the door, for example, must ensure more than the standards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the safety standards stipulates that headrests are set up in backseats (but often not set up in inexpensive private cars) and obliges that the separation between the front seat and backseat and the opening of the door, for example, must ensure more than the standards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="273">
<j>現在、全国のタクシーのほとんどはトヨタ自動車のトヨタ・クラウンコンフォート、トヨタ・コンフォート、トヨタ・クラウンセダン、日産自動車の日産・クルー、日産・セドリックセダンのいずれかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most taxis used in Japan are any of TOYOTA Crown Comfort, TOYOTA Comfort, TOYOTA Crown Sedan, Nissan CREW, and Nissan CEDRIC Sedan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most taxis used in Japan are any models of TOYOTA Crown Comfort, TOYOTA Comfort, TOYOTA Crown Sedan, Nissan CREW, and Nissan CEDRIC Sedan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most taxis used in Japan are any models of TOYOTA Crown Comfort, TOYOTA Comfort, TOYOTA Crown Sedan, Nissan CREW, and Nissan CEDRIC Sedan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>このうちセドリック以外はタクシー専用車として開発された車種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of these vehicles except Nissan CEDRIC Sedan are designed exclusively for taxis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of these vehicles except Nissan CEDRIC Sedan are designed exclusively for taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of these vehicles except Nissan CEDRIC Sedan are designed exclusively for taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>ただ、これらの専用車は内装があまりにも安っぽいので、あえて高価なクラウンセダンやセドリックのハイグレードタクシーを選択する会社も増えてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because interior of these specialized vehicles is so cheap that more companies have began selecting TOYOTA Crown Sedan or Nissan CEDRIC Sedan, which will be high-grade taxis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the interior of these specialized vehicles is so cheap that more companies have began selecting TOYOTA Crown Sedan or Nissan CEDRIC Sedan, as high-grade taxis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the interior of these specialized vehicles is so cheap that more companies have begun selecting high-grade taxis such as TOYOTA Crown Sedan or Nissan CEDRIC Sedan, which are more expensive.</e>
<cmt>begun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="276">
<j>また最近は地球温暖化に対する意識の高まりを受けてハイブリッド車であるトヨタ・プリウスも使われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the increased interest in global warming in recent years, TOYOTA Prius, a hybrid car, is becoming popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the increased interest in global warming in recent years, the TOYOTA Prius, a hybrid car, is becoming popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the increased interest in global warming in recent years, the TOYOTA Prius, a hybrid car, is becoming popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>しかし、2代目プリウスは1500ccエンジン搭載車であるにもかかわらず、横幅が1.7mを越えた3ナンバーになってしまい中型車として扱われるため、小型車中心の地域では初代ほど登録されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, although second-generation Prius has a 1500-cc engine, it is treated as a medium-size car of 3-type license vehicle as its width is over 1.7 meter, and thus its demand is not as high as the first generation in areas where majority of the taxis are compact cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, although second-generation Prius has a 1500-cc engine, it is treated as a medium-size car of 3-type license vehicle as its width is over 1.7 meter, and thus its demand is not as high as the first generation in areas where majority of the taxis are compact cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, although second-generation Prius has a 1500-cc engine, it is treated as a medium-size car with a license plate whose number starts from 3 because its width is over 1.7 meter, and thus its demand is not as high as the first generation in areas where majority of the taxis are compact cars.</e>
<cmt>3ナンバー　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="278">
<j>また2代目プリウスは空気抵抗軽減重視ボディのため、クラウンコンフォートやクルーに比べ後席の頭上に空間の余裕が少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, because of its body design to reduce air resistance, the second-generation Prius has less space above head in the backseats compared to Crown Comfort and Nissan CREW</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, because of its body design to reduce air resistance, the second-generation Prius has less space above the head in the backseats compared to Crown Comfort and Nissan CREW</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, because of its body design to reduce air resistance, the second-generation Prius has less space above the head in the backseats compared to Crown Comfort and Nissan CREW</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="279">
<j>積雪地ではFR車は走行しにくいため、FF車の市販車をベースにしたタクシーもまれに見られる（1999年までは三菱自動車の三菱・ギャランΣにFF・LPGのタクシー専用車が設定されていた。なお、現在でも北海道や東北、中国地方でごくたまに見られる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because rear-wheel-drive vehicles have a disadvantage for running in snow-covered regions, there are a few taxis based on front-wheel-drive stock cars (up to 1999, front-wheel-drive Mitsubishi GALANT_SIGMA that uses liquefied petroleum gas (LPG) was used exclusively for a taxi, and even today, taxis using this vehicle can be seen in Hokkaido, Tohoku, and Chugoku region on rare occasions).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because rear-wheel-drive vehicles have a disadvantage running in snow-covered regions, there are a few taxis based on front-wheel-drive stock cars (up to 1999, front-wheel-drive Mitsubishi GALANT_SIGMA that uses liquefied petroleum gas (LPG) was used exclusively as a taxi, and even today, taxis using this vehicle can be seen in Hokkaido, Tohoku, and Chugoku region on rare occasions).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because rear-wheel-drive vehicles have a disadvantage running in snow-covered regions, there are a few taxis based on front-wheel-drive stock cars (up to 1999, front-wheel-drive Mitsubishi GALANT_SIGMA that uses liquefied petroleum gas (LPG) was used exclusively as a taxi, and even today, taxis using this vehicle can be seen in Hokkaido, Tohoku, and Chugoku region on rare occasions).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>4WD車は燃費が悪いため、導入している会社は積雪地でも少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of its bad fuel consumption, taxi companies that use four-wheel-drive vehicles are very rare even in snow-covered regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of bad fuel consumption, taxi companies that use four-wheel-drive vehicles are very rare, even in snow-covered regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of bad fuel consumption, taxi companies that use four-wheel-drive vehicles are very rare, even in snow-covered regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>燃料としては、税金の関係で液化石油ガスを使用する車両が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many taxis use LPG as a fuel because of its cheaper tax.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many taxis use LPG as a fuel because of its cheaper tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many taxis use LPG as a fuel because of its cheaper tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>LPG仕様がメーカーで設定されている車種は限られているので、ガソリンエンジンをLPGに改造するケースも個人タクシーや大都市圏のハイヤーで見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there are a limited number of vehicles whose manufacturers set LPG as the standard issue, there are some cases where gasoline engines are remodeled to LPG engines for privately owned taxis and hires in metropolitan areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there are a limited number of vehicles for which manufacturers set LPG as a standard, there are some cases where gasoline engines are remodeled to LPG engines for privately owned taxis and hires in metropolitan areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there are a limited number of vehicles for which manufacturers set LPG as a standard, there are some cases where gasoline engines are remodeled to LPG engines for privately owned taxis and hires in metropolitan areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="283">
<j>LPGスタンドの設置がない地域や、タクシー事業者がガソリンスタンドも経営している場合などでは、ディーゼルエンジンの車両を使用しているところもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In areas where there are not enough LPG stations or if a taxi operator also runs a gas station, there are some taxis that use a diesel engine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In areas where there are not enough LPG stations or if a taxi operator also runs a gas station, there are some taxis that use diesel engines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In areas where there are not enough LPG stations or if a taxi operator also runs a gas station, there are some taxis that use diesel engines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>24時間営業のLPGスタンドは少ないため、閉店間際は混雑しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there aren&apos;t very many 24 hr LPG stations, LPG stations become crowded shortly before closing a business for the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there aren&apos;t very many 24 hr LPG stations, LPG stations become crowded shortly before closing business for the day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there aren&apos;t very many 24 hr LPG stations, LPG stations become crowded shortly before closing business for the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="285">
<j>これを避けるべく、ガソリンエンジンやディーゼルエンジンを使用する個人タクシーも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many privately owned taxis that use a gasoline engine or a diesel engine to avoid this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many privately owned taxis that use a gasoline engine or a diesel engine to avoid this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many privately owned taxis that use a gasoline engine or a diesel engine to avoid this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="286">
<j>また、法人タクシーの多くはフェンダーミラーである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, most corporate taxis use fender mirrors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, most corporate taxis use fender mirrors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, most corporate taxis use fender mirrors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="287">
<j>理由として、視認時の視線移動が少量で済む事、ドアミラーと比較して車幅が狭くなるため、狭い路地に出入りし易いなどが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons include the driver&apos;s eye movement for visual contact is less and it is easier to drive on a narrow road because the body width is narrower than that with side mirrors on the doors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons include the driver&apos;s eye movement required for visual contact is less and it is easier to drive on a narrow road because the body width is narrower than that with side mirrors on the doors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons include the driver&apos;s eye movement required for visual contact is less and it is easier to drive on a narrow road because the body width is narrower than that with side mirrors on the doors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>またドアミラーでは左のミラーを視認する際に運転手が客の方を向いていると誤解される場合があり、それを避ける意図もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, another reason for use of fender mirrors is to avoid the passenger&apos;s misunderstanding that the driver is watching him/her when the driver gives visual contact to the side mirror on the left door.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, another reason for using fender mirrors is to avoid the passenger&apos;s misunderstanding that the driver is watching him/her when the driver gives visual contact to the side mirror on the left door.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, another reason for using fender mirrors is to avoid the passenger&apos;s misunderstanding that the driver is watching him/her when the driver gives visual contact to the side mirror on the left door.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="289">
<j>タクシーは、停止や方向転換、乗客の乗降車などでのウインカーやハザードランプの点灯を周囲に認知させる必要性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi drivers need to let people around know about stopping, change of direction, boarding and exiting of passengers, etc. by using the turn signals and hazard indicator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi drivers need to let people around them know about stopping, change of direction, boarding and exiting of passengers, etc. by using the turn signals and hazard indicator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi drivers need to let people around them know about stopping, change of direction, boarding and exiting of passengers, etc. by using the turn signals and hazard indicator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>東京や仙台など、地域によっては屋根の上、あんどん両脇への補助ウインカーの装備が標準化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some areas such as Tokyo and Sendai, installation of indicators both sides of the indicating lamp on the rooftop is standardized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some areas such as Tokyo and Sendai, installation of indicators both sides of the indicating lamp on the rooftop is standardized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some areas such as Tokyo and Sendai, installation of indicators on both sides of the indicating lamp on the rooftop is standardized.</e>
<cmt>on を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="291">
<j>ミニバンを使用する場合は保安基準で3列目シートの乗客が避難できるように、2列目のシートはキャプテンシートの車が多く使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a minivan is used as a taxi, seat in the second row is usually a &quot;captain seat (a seat for one person)&quot; so that the passenger(s) in the third row can evacuate the taxi by the safety standards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a minivan is used as a taxi, the seat in the second row is usually a &quot;captain seat (a seat for one person)&quot; so that the passenger(s) in the third row can evacuate the taxi in accordance with the safety standards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a minivan is used as a taxi, the seat in the second row is usually a &quot;captain seat (a seat for one person)&quot; so that the passenger(s) in the third row can evacuate the taxi in accordance with the safety standards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="292">
<j>2列目がベンチシートの車を使う場合、3列目シートを撤去し5人乗りとして用いる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, if a minivan whose second row is a bench seat is used as a taxi, most operators remove the seat in the third row and use it as a vehicle of carrying capacity of 5.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, if a minivan whose second row is a bench seat is used as a taxi, most operators remove the seat in the third row and use it as a vehicle with a carrying capacity of 5.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, if a minivan whose second row is a bench seat is used as a taxi, most operators remove the seat in the third row and use it as a vehicle with a carrying capacity of five.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="293">
<j>このほか、車体にタクシー会社の名前が入っているがよく見ると白ナンバーという車両がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vehicles with company names painted on their bodies but with a license plate which is designed green against a white background can be often seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vehicles with company names painted on their bodies but with a license plate which is designed green against a white background can be often seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vehicles with company names painted on their bodies but with a license plate which is designed green against a white background can be often seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>これは営業用としては引退した車両を社内教習用として使用しているものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These vehicles are used for in-company training after used for business purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These vehicles are used for in-company training after being used for business purpose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These vehicles are used for in-company training after being used for business purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>ごくまれではあるが運転代行の随伴車として使用するケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On rare occasions, these vehicles are used as an accompanying car in a replacement driver service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On rare occasions, these vehicles are used as an accompanying car in a replacement driver service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On rare occasions, these vehicles are used as an accompanying car in a replacement driver service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="296">
<j>この車両はメーターなどの装備品の基本操作の教習を目的に使用され、当然ながら本物の客を乗せることはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although these vehicles have some basic equipment for a taxi such as a fare meter, because they are used for training of basic operations of the equipment, it is prohibited to carry real passengers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although these vehicles have some basic equipment for a taxi such as a fare meter, because they are used for training for basic operations of the equipment, it is prohibited to carry real passengers in them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although these vehicles have some basic equipment for a taxi such as a fare meter, because they are used for training for basic operations of the equipment, it is prohibited to carry real passengers in them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>こちらの車両での教習の後、本物のタクシー車両で教官役の上司と本物の客を乗せて実務教習を行う（どちらかの教習を省略する会社もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After trained with these vehicles, people who are trying to become a taxi driver take a practical training with an actual taxi in which the supervisor who acts as an instructor and a real passenger are seated (there are some taxi companies that omit one of the two training sessions mentioned above).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being trained in these vehicles, people who are trying to become a taxi driver take practical training with an actual taxi in which the supervisor who acts as an instructor and a real passenger are seated (there are some taxi companies that omit one of the two training sessions mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being trained in these vehicles, people who are trying to become a taxi driver take practical training with an actual taxi in which the supervisor who acts as an instructor and a real passenger are seated (there are some taxi companies that omit one of the two training sessions mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="298">
<j>車体のカラーリングは緑（東京無線など）やオレンジといった明るい色を使うところが首都圏を中心に多いが、逆に京阪神、北関東、北陸、四国のタクシーには少なく、黒や紺の割合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While many taxi companies use bright colors such as green (Tokyo Musen) and orange for taxi body painting in the national capital region, taxi companies in Keihanshin, Kita Kanto, Hokiriku, and Shikoku tend to use black and dark blue more than bright colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While many taxi companies use bright colors such as green (Tokyo Musen) and orange for taxi body painting in the national capital region, taxi companies in Keihanshin, Kita Kanto, Hokiriku, and Shikoku tend to use black and dark blue more than bright colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While many taxi companies use bright colors such as green (Tokyo Musen) and orange for taxi body painting in the national capital region, taxi companies in Keihanshin, northern Kanto, Hokuriku and Shikoku tend to use black and dark blue more than bright colors.</e>
<cmt>北関東→northern Kanto としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="299">
<j>車内装備</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interior equipment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interior equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interior equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>車内装備</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interior equipment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interior equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interior equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="301">
<j>タクシーメーター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taximeter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taximeter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taximeter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>料金を表示するメーター。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A meter that shows the fare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A meter that shows the fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A meter that shows the fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>実空車表示器と連動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is interfaced with the actual empty car indicator.</e>
<cmt>「実空車表示器」＝「actual empty car indicator」は、用語調査担当の方も調べがつかなかったようですので、仮訳です。（翻訳者も定訳を見つけられませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is interfaced with the actual vacant car indicator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is interfaced with the actual vacant car indicator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="304">
<j>深夜料金適用時間になると自動的に深夜料金に切り替わり、適用時間が終わると通常料金に戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is automatically switched to apply the late-night charge as the valid time for late night comes and returned to apply the regular charge as the valid time for late night is over.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is automatically switched to apply the late-night charge as the applicable time for late night comes and returned to apply the regular charge as the applicable time for late night is over.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is automatically switched to apply the late-night charge as the applicable time for late night comes and returned to apply the regular charge as the applicable time for late night is over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>これに対し割引料金はメーター本体では計算できず、備え付けのボタンを押したり、外部ユニットとカードリーダー端末を設置して計算する場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reduced rates, on the other hand, cannot be calculated by the taximeter itself, and thus they are often calculated by pressing an attached button or installing an external unit and a card reader terminal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reduced rates, on the other hand, cannot be calculated by the taximeter itself, and thus they are often calculated by pressing an attached button or installing an external unit and a card reader terminal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reduced rates, on the other hand, cannot be calculated by the taximeter itself, and thus they are often calculated by pressing an attached button or installing an external unit and a card reader terminal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>個人タクシーにおいて、タクシー用車両を自家用車として使う場合は、「自家使用」と書かれたフードを表示機の上から被せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a privately owned taxi needs to be used as a private car, a hood saying &quot;private use&quot; must be put on the indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a privately owned taxi needs to be used as a private car, a hood saying &quot;private use&quot; must be put over the indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a privately owned taxi needs to be used as a private car, a hood saying &apos;private use&apos; must be put over the indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="307">
<j>メーターは計量法により1年毎の検査（正確には有効期限が1年間の検定）を受検することが義務付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taximeters are required to be inspected annually (actually it is a screening whose time of validity is one year) by the Measurement Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taximeters are required to be inspected annually (actually screening validity is one year) according to the Measurement Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taximeters are required to be inspected annually (actually screening validity is one year) according to the Measurement Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>メーター内部を調整するなどの不正が行われないよう、メーターには鉛の封印（検定証印）が施される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taximeters are set under lead seal (inspected stamp) so that no one can act wrong, for example, adjusting the inside of the meter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taximeters are set under a lead seal (inspected stamp) so that no one can manipulate the meter, for example, adjusting the inside of the meter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taximeters are set under a lead seal (inspected stamp) so that no one can manipulate the meter, for example, adjusting the inside of the meter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>領収書を発行するプリンタと連動しており、支払い操作を行うと領収書が印字される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The taximeter is interfaced with a printer to print out receipts, so a receipt is issued as the passenger pays the fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The taximeter is interfaced with a printer to print out receipts, so a receipt is issued after the passenger pays the fare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The taximeter is interfaced with a printer to print out receipts, so a receipt is issued after the passenger pays the fare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>1980年代頃までのものは、長さ20センチ程度で、先端に直径10センチ程度の「空車」文字入り円板がついたレバーを回してモードを切り替えていたが、実空車表示器と連動した電子式に切り替えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The taximeters used up to 1980&apos;s were about 20 centimeters long and having a lever of 10 centimeters in diameter with a disk saying &quot;empty car&quot; at the top, which was used to switch modes by rotating; however, they were replaced with electronic types interfaced with the actual empty car indicator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The taximeters used up to 1980&apos;s were about 20 centimeters long and having a lever of 10 centimeters in diameter with a disk saying &quot;vacant car&quot; at the top, which was used to switch modes by rotating; however, they were replaced with electronic types interfaced with the actual vacant car indicator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The taximeters used up to 1980&apos;s were about 20 centimeters long and having a lever of 10 centimeters in diameter with a disk saying &apos;vacant car&apos; at the top, which was used to switch modes by rotating; however, they were replaced with electronic types interfaced with the actual vacant car indicator.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="311">
<j>（注：「タキシー」という表現がされていた時代があった（昭和初年ぐらいまで）ため、計量法に基づく解説書の中で比較的古いものにはその経緯から「タキシーメーター」との表記がなされている場合があるが、これは読み替えて差し支えない。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Note: Because there was a time (until about the first year of Showa era) when taxi was expressed as &quot;TAKISHI&quot; instead of &quot;TAKUSHI,&quot; the contemporary expression, some relatively old practical guide books based on the Measurement Act still use the expression of taximeter as &quot;TAKISHI META,&quot; which should naturally be interpreted as &quot;TAKUSHI META,&quot; the contemporary expression.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Note: Because there was a time (until about the first year of Showa era) when taxi was expressed as &quot;TAKISHI&quot; instead of &quot;TAKUSHI,&quot; the contemporary expression, some relatively old practical guide books based on the Measurement Act still use the expression of taximeter as &quot;TAKISHI META,&quot; which should naturally be interpreted as &quot;TAKUSHI META,&quot; the contemporary expression.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Note: Because there was a time (until about the first year of Showa period, around 1926) when taxi was expressed as &apos;TAKISHI&apos; instead of &apos;TAKUSHI,&apos; the contemporary expression, some relatively old practical guide books based on the Measurement Act still use the expression of taximeter as &apos;TAKISHI META,&apos; which should naturally be interpreted as &apos;TAKUSHI META,&apos; the contemporary expression.)</e>
<cmt>昭和初年ぐらい→around 1926 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="312">
<j>実空車表示器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actual empty car indicator</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actual vacant car indicator</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actual vacant car indicator</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>スーパーサイン、ウインドウサイン、またはタリフともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as super sign, window sign, or tariff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as super sign, window sign, or tariff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as super sign, window sign, or tariff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="314">
<j>車両の状態を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It indicates the state of the taxi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It indicates the state of the taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates the state of the taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>かつては、タクシーメーターのレバーが上部にあれば空車と判断できたが、電子式に切り替えられたために登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be possible to judge a taxi empty if the level of the taximeter was positioned on the top, but this system became no longer available as an electronic taximeter was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be possible to judge if a taxi is vacant if the level of the taximeter was positioned on the top, but this system was no longer available as the electronic taximeter was introduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be possible to judge if a taxi is vacant if the lever of the taximeter was positioned on the top, but this system was no longer available as the electronic taximeter was introduced.</e>
<cmt>レバー　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="316">
<j>初めて設置された頃は「空車」と「回送」しか表示しない物しかなかったが、「回送」では分かりにくいので「迎車」や「予約車」、更に最近では「賃走」、「支払」、「無線予約」などが表示できる物の搭載が義務付けられるようになってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of the introduction of the electronic type, indication of the taximeter had only &quot;empty car&quot; and &quot;Kaiso (Not in service)&quot;; however, because &quot;Not in service&quot; was ambiguous, taxi operators are obligated to set up an indicator which has signs of &quot;Geisha&quot; and &quot;Reserved,&quot; and in recent years &quot;In service,&quot; &quot;Pay,&quot; and &quot;Reserved by radio&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of the introduction of the electronic type, indication of the taximeter had only &quot;vacant car&quot; and &quot;Kaiso (Not in service);&quot; however, because &quot;Not in service&quot; was ambiguous, taxi operators are obligated to set up an indicator which has signs of &quot;Geisha&quot; and &quot;Reserved,&quot; and in recent years &quot;In service,&quot; &quot;Pay,&quot; and &quot;Reserved by radio&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the introduction of the electronic type, indication of the taximeter had only &apos;vacant car&apos; and &apos;Kaiso (Not in service);&apos; however, because &apos;Not in service&apos; was ambiguous, taxi operators are obligated to set up an indicator which has signs of &apos;Geisha&apos; and &apos;Reserved,&apos; and in recent years &apos;In service,&apos; &apos;Pay,&apos; and &apos;Reserved by radio&apos; as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="317">
<j>以前は電照式や幕式が多かったが、最近は発光ダイオード表示タイプの物が多く、緊急時に社名表示灯と連動して「SOS」や「助けて」と表示するものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The actual empty car indicator used to be a lighting type or a Maku type (a type in which displayed items are switched by changing written cards or panels), but majority of the current indicators are LED type, which can indicate &quot;SOS&quot; or &quot;HELP&quot; in an emergency by linking with the company name indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The actual empty car indicator used to be a lighting type or a Maku type (a type in which displayed items are switched by changing written cards or panels), but majority of the current indicators are LED type, which can indicate &quot;SOS&quot; or &quot;HELP&quot; in an emergency by linking with the company name indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The actual empty car indicator used to be a lighting type or a Maku type (a type in which displayed items are switched by changing written cards or panels), but majority of the current indicators are LED type, which can indicate &apos;SOS&apos; or &apos;HELP&apos; in an emergency by linking with the company name indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="318">
<j>カードリーダー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Card reader</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Card reader</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Card reader</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="319">
<j>クレジットカードの支払いに対応する機械。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A machine used for payment by a credit card</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A machine used for payment by credit card</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A machine used for payment by credit card</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="320">
<j>後部左側窓ガラスに使用可能なカード会社のステッカーが貼られているので、客は乗る前に確認が必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stickers of available credit card companies are put on the left side of the rear window, so customers who want to pay by a credit card need to check.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stickers of available credit card companies are put on the left side of the rear window, so customers who want to pay by credit card need to check for them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stickers of available credit card companies are put on the left side of the rear window, so customers who want to pay by credit card need to check for them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="321">
<j>搭載されていない車では当然カード払いができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally, credit cards are not available for a taxi with no credit card companies&apos; stickers on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally, credit cards are not available for a taxi with no credit card companies&apos; stickers on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, credit cards are not available for a taxi with no credit card companies&apos; stickers on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="322">
<j>デビットカードが使用できるものもあり、電波が届きデータの通信が可能であれば使用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A debit card is available for some taxis only if the radio wave condition is good and data can be transmitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A debit card is available for some taxis only if the radio wave condition is good and data can be transmitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A debit card is available for some taxis only if the radio wave condition is good and data can be transmitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="323">
<j>ただし手数料は乗務員が負担する会社があるなど、問題も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are still quit a few problems in use of a debit card, for example, the driver may have to pay the commission for some card companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are still quit a few problems in using a debit card, for example, the driver may have to pay a commission to some card companies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are still quite a few problems in using a debit card; for example, the driver may have to pay a commission to some card companies.</e>
<cmt>quite としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="324">
<j>速度記録計（タコグラフ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Speed recorder (tachograph)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Speed recorder (tachograph)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Speed recorder (tachograph)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="325">
<j>法令によって速度記録計の設置が義務付けられている営業区域では、円盤状の紙に速度・時間・距離が記録されるタコグラフが装着されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a business district where the law obliges installation of a speed recorder on a taxi, a tachograph that records speed, time, and distance on a disk-shape paper is installed on taxis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a business district where the law obliges installation of a speed recorder on a taxi, a tachograph that records speed, time, and distance on a disk-shape paper is installed on taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a business district where the law obliges installation of a speed recorder on a taxi, a tachograph that records speed, time, and distance on a disk-shape paper is installed on taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="326">
<j>形状はメーターパネル（車種によってはトランク内、ボンネット内、コンソールボックス内）に埋め込まれた錠前付きの大きなアナログ時計。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It looks like a big analog clock with a pad lock and is embedded in the meter panel (or in the trunk, the inside of the hood, or the in the console box depending on the type of vehicle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It looks like a big analog clock with a pad lock and is embedded in the meter panel (or in the trunk, the inside of the hood, or the in the console box depending on the type of vehicle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It looks like a big analog clock with a pad lock and is embedded in the meter panel (or in the trunk, the inside of the hood, or in the console box depending on the type of vehicle).</e>
<cmt>the ダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="327">
<j>最近はメモリーカード方式（デジタル）のタコグラフを使う事業者もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, some taxi companies use tachographs with a memory card (digital) system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, some taxi companies use tachographs with a memory card (digital) system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, some taxi companies use tachographs with a memory card (digital) system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="328">
<j>また最近ではメーターパネル内にタコグラフ用のスペースのないハイグレード車を使用する会社が増えたことから、タクシーメーター一体型のものも増えてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, because more and more taxi companies began using high-grade vehicles which have no space for a tachograph in their meter panel in these days, tachographs that are integrated with a taximeter are becoming popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, because more and more taxi companies began using high-grade vehicles which have no space for a tachograph in their meter panel in these days, tachographs that are integrated with a taximeter are becoming popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, because more and more taxi companies began using high-grade vehicles which have no space for a tachograph in their meter panel in these days, tachographs that are integrated with a taximeter are becoming popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="329">
<j>またグローバル・ポジショニング・システム機能により、乗下車した場所をメモリーカードに記録し、乗務員がその場で業務日報を手書きする手間を省くものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there is a system in which drivers can omit their task of recording the daily labor report by recording the positions of boarding and exiting into a memory card using the global positioning system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there is a system in which drivers can omit their task of recording the daily labor report by recording the positions of boarding and exiting into a memory card using the global positioning system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there is a system in which drivers can omit their task of recording the daily labor report by recording the positions of boarding and exiting into a memory card using the global positioning system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="330">
<j>社名表示灯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Company logo indicating lamp</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Company logo indicating lamp</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Company logo indicating lamp</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="331">
<j>俗に「あんどん」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly known as &quot;Andon.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly known as &quot;Andon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly known as &apos;Andon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="332">
<j>天井灯、屋上灯、防犯灯などとも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as &quot;Tenjo-to (ceiling lamp),&quot; &quot;Okujo-to (rooftop lamp),&quot; and &quot;Bohan-to (crime-prevention lamp).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as &quot;Tenjo-to (ceiling lamp),&quot; &quot;Okujo-to (rooftop lamp),&quot; and &quot;Bohan-to (crime-prevention lamp).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as &apos;Tenjo-to (ceiling lamp),&apos; &apos;Okujo-to (rooftop lamp),&apos; and &apos;Bohan-to (crime-prevention lamp).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="333">
<j>空車時は点灯して実車時は消灯する地方、夜だけ点灯する地方など、点灯方法には地域差がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of the company logo indicating lamp varies from region to region; for example, in some areas the indicating lamp is on when the taxi is empty and it is off when it is in service, or the indicating lamp is on only at night in some other areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use of the company logo indicating lamp varies from region to region; for example, in some areas the indicating lamp is on when the taxi is vacant and it is off when it is in service, or the indicating lamp is on only at night in some other areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Use of the company logo indicating lamp varies from region to region; for example, in some areas the indicating lamp is on when the taxi is vacant and it is off when it is in service, or the indicating lamp is on only at night in some other areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="334">
<j>強盗など緊急時には、赤色に点滅させることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company logo indicating lamp can blink in red in case of emergency such as robbery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company logo indicating lamp can blink in red in case of emergency such as robbery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company logo indicating lamp can blink in red in case of emergency such as robbery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="335">
<j>最近では社名表示灯と連動して実空車表示機に「SOS」や「助けて」と表示するものもある（街中でこのような状況を見かけた場合にはすぐに警察へ通報する事が望ましい）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, some company logo indicating lamps can indicate &quot;SOS&quot; or &quot;HELP&quot; on the actual empty car indicator by linking each other (if this kind of sign is seen in town, it is advisable to report it to the police promptly).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, some company logo indicating lamps can indicate &quot;SOS&quot; or &quot;HELP&quot; on the actual empty car indicator by linking each other (if this kind of sign is seen in town, it is advisable to report it to the police promptly).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, some company logo indicating lamps can indicate &apos;SOS&apos; or &apos;HELP&apos; on the actual empty car indicator by linking each other (if this kind of sign is seen in town, it is advisable to report it to the police promptly).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="336">
<j>無線機器が連動して、防犯ONにすると自動的に車両の位置情報と救難信号が送信され、無線のマイクがつなぎっぱなしとなり、車内のやり取りが無線室に聞こえるシステムを採用している会社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some taxi companies that employs a system in which when some taxi driver belongs to any of the companies turns on the crime-prevention switch, the wireless equipment sends the taxi&apos;s current positional information and a distress signal to the wireless office, and the taxi&apos;s radio becomes always-on state so that the conversation in the taxi can be heard by people in the wireless office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some taxi companies that employ a system whereby a taxi driver belonging to any of the companies turns on the crime-prevention switch, the wireless equipment sends the taxi&apos;s current positional information and a distress signal to the wireless office, and the taxi&apos;s radio becomes always-on state so that the conversation in the taxi can be heard by people in the wireless office.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some taxi companies that employ a system whereby a taxi driver belonging to any of the companies turns on the crime-prevention switch, the wireless equipment sends the taxi&apos;s current positional information and a distress signal to the wireless office, and the taxi&apos;s radio becomes always-on state so that the conversation in the taxi can be heard by people in the wireless office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="337">
<j>最近では広告付きのものを使用する事業者も出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some taxi companies began adopting company logo indicating lamps with some ads on them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some taxi companies began adopting a company logo indicating lamps with some ads on them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some taxi companies began adopting a company logo indicating lamps with some ads on them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="338">
<j>形は蒲鉾型、ラグビーボール型、球型、星型、太鼓型などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some different shapes for company logo indicating lamps, hog-backed, rugby-ball shaped, round, star-shaped, drum-shaped, etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some different shapes for company logo indicating lamps, hog-backed, rugby-ball shaped, round, star-shaped, drum-shaped, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some different shapes for company logo indicating lamps, hog-backed, rugby-ball shaped, round, star-shaped, drum-shaped, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="339">
<j>渦巻き型（一般にデンデン型と呼ばれる）や提灯型は個人タクシー専用となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Company logo indicating lamps that are spiral-shaped (generally called &quot;den-den shape&quot;) or Japanese lantern-shaped are only available for privately owned taxis.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Company logo indicating lamps that are spiral-shaped (generally called &quot;den-den shape&quot;) or Japanese lantern-shaped are only available for privately owned taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Company logo indicating lamps that are spiral-shaped (generally called &quot;den-den shape&quot;) or Japanese lantern-shaped are only available for privately owned taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="340">
<j>オートドア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Automatic door</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Automatic door</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Automatic door</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="341">
<j>てこ式や圧縮空気などを利用して後部左ドアを運転席で操作することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A taxi driver can manipulate the left back door using a leverage or hydraulic system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A taxi driver can manipulate the left back door using a leverage or hydraulic system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A taxi driver can manipulate the left back door using a leverage or hydraulic system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="342">
<j>世界的に見てオートドアが標準になっている国は少なく、外国人客が驚くことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nations that have taxis with an automatic door are very rare in the world, and thus many foreign people visiting Japan are often surprised with the door.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nations that have taxis with an automatic door are very rare in the world, and thus many foreign people visiting Japan are often surprised by the door.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nations that have taxis with an automatic door are very rare in the world, and thus many foreign people visiting Japan are often surprised by the door.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="343">
<j>日本でも運転手が車の外側から開けるドアサービスを実施する会社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are some taxi companies that offer a door service in which the driver does to the door and opens it from outside for passengers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are some taxi companies that offer a door service in which the driver goes to the door and opens it from the outside for passengers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are some taxi companies that offer a door service in which the driver goes to the door and opens it from the outside for passengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="344">
<j>カーナビ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Automotive navigation system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Automotive navigation system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Automotive navigation system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="345">
<j>最近は事業者が設置している事も多いが、乗務員が私物を取り付けている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, many taxi operators install a car navigation system, but there are also some cases where taxi drivers install his/her own navigation equipment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, many taxi operators install a car navigation system, but there are also some cases where taxi drivers install his/her own navigation equipment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, many taxi operators install a car navigation system, but there are also some cases where taxi drivers install his/her own navigation equipment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="346">
<j>GPSで位置を捕捉されている場合は、無線配車で近い車から配車されるので便利ではあるが、完全に拘束されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the location of each taxi is captured by GPS, a taxi that is closest to the customer is sent by radio, which seems convenient yet all drivers are completely bound by the system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the location of each taxi is captured by GPS, a taxi that is closest to the customer is sent by radio, which seems convenient yet all drivers are completely bound by the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the location of each taxi is captured by GPS, a taxi that is closest to the customer is sent by radio, which seems convenient yet all drivers are completely bound by the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="347">
<j>無線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wireless system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wireless system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wireless system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="348">
<j>配車係が乗務員へ客のいる所へ案内するのに使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for the staff in the dispatch control center to send a taxi driver to a customer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used for the staff in the dispatch control center to send a taxi driver to a customer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for the staff in the dispatch control center to send a taxi driver to a customer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="349">
<j>屋根に無線用のアンテナを装備する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An antenna for the wireless system is set on the roof of taxis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An antenna for the wireless system is set on the roof of taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An antenna for the wireless system is set on the roof of taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="350">
<j>パトカーなどのアンテナは、屋根に直接、専用の物が取り付けられているが、タクシー用は、ほぼすべて後付け（マグネット、シール貼付、雨どいにネジ締め）であり、アンテナケーブルも露出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Police cars usually have an antenna designed specially exclusively on their roof, but almost all taxis have an antenna which has been mounted by the taxi company later (using magnet, adhesive, or screwed on the gutter), and thus the antenna cable is also exposed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Police cars usually have an antenna designed specially exclusively on their roof, but almost all taxis have an antenna which has been mounted by the taxi company later (using magnet, adhesive, or screwed onto the gutter), and thus the antenna cable is also exposed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Police cars usually have an antenna designed specially exclusively on their roof, but almost all taxis have an antenna which has been mounted by the taxi company later (using magnet, adhesive, or screwed onto the gutter), and thus the antenna cable is also exposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="351">
<j>周波数は400MHz帯を使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxis usually use the frequency band of 400MHz.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxis usually use the frequency band of 400MHz.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxis usually use the frequency band of 400MHz.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="352">
<j>配車係が最寄の車を調べるには、乗務員に無線ナンバーと現在地を報告してもらう、GPSで検索するなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Staff in the dispatch control center has the drivers report his/her radio number and current location or use GPS to search the closest taxi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Staff in the dispatch control center have the drivers report his/her radio number and current location or use GPS to search for the closest taxi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Staff in the dispatch control center have the drivers report his/her radio number and current location or use GPS to search for the closest taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="353">
<j>乗務員同士の会話はできるものとできないものがあり、事業者の方針によって異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While some wireless systems allow the drivers to communicate each other, some other systems do not allow it, depending on the policy of each taxi company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While some wireless systems allow the drivers to communicate with each other, some other systems do not allow it, depending on the policy of each taxi company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While some wireless systems allow the drivers to communicate with each other, some other systems do not allow it, depending on the policy of each taxi company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="354">
<j>会話できないものは、配車係（基地局）の送信周波数と乗務員（移動局）の送信周波数を変えることで実現している（一種の半複信方式）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system which do not allow the drivers talk each other realizes this by using different transmit frequencies between the dispatch control center (base station) and the drivers (mobile stations) (a kind of semi-duplex operation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system which does not allow the drivers to talk to each other realizes this by using different transmiting frequencies between the dispatch control center (base station) and the drivers (mobile stations) (a kind of semi-duplex operation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system which does not allow the drivers to talk to each other realizes this by using different transmitting frequencies between the dispatch control center (base station) and the drivers (mobile stations) (a kind of semi-duplex operation).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="355">
<j>大都市では周波数の有効利用と安定した通信のために集中基地局方式が取られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In large cities, a concentrated base station system is adopted for effective use of frequency and for stable communication.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In large cities, a concentrated base station system is adopted for effective use of the frequency and for stable communication.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In large cities, a concentrated base station system is adopted for effective use of the frequency and for stable communication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="356">
<j>この方式の場合、基地局の電波は常に送信されており、配車係がマイクの送信ボタンを離したときの「ザッ」と言う音（スケルチのテールノイズ）が聞こえないため判別可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this system, radio waves are always transmitted from the base station, and thus it is identifiable because the squelch tail noise, a noise generated when staff in the dispatch control center lets go of the sending button of the microphone, cannot be heard.</e>
<cmt>何が「判別可能」なのか明確に理解できませんでしたので、「何が」を訳語にも反映せず、そのまま訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this system, radio waves are always transmitted from the base station, and thus it is identifiable because the squelch tail noise, a noise generated when staff in the dispatch control center lets go of the sending button of the microphone, cannot be heard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this system, radio waves are always transmitted from the base station, and thus it is identifiable because the squelch tail noise, a noise generated when staff in the dispatch control center lets go of the sending button of the microphone, cannot be heard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="357">
<j>ほとんどの会社が無線営業を独自にしているが、大都市では混信を避けるため、いくつかのグループにまとまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although most taxi companies use their own wireless systems, taxi companies are divided into several groups to avoid interference in the large cities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although most taxi companies use their own wireless systems, taxi companies are divided into several groups to avoid interference in large cities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although most taxi companies use their own wireless systems, taxi companies are divided into several groups to avoid interference in large cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="358">
<j>主に大都市ではタクシーが多過ぎることや、予約せずに飛び込む客や駅待ちの客がそれほど少なくないこと、乗務員のほとんどが携帯電話を持っていることなどにより、無線のない車もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the large cities, partly because there are quit a few customers who flag down a taxi on a street without reservation or take a taxi at a station and partly because most taxi drivers have their own cell phones, there are some taxis without a wireless system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in large cities, partly because there are quit a few customers who flag down a taxi on a street without reservation or take a taxi at a station and partly because most taxi drivers have their own cell phones, there are some taxis without a wireless system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in large cities, partly because there are quite a few customers who flag down a taxi on a street without reservation or take a taxi at a station and partly because most taxi drivers have their own cell phones, there are some taxis without a wireless system.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="359">
<j>個人タクシーではアマチュア無線を装備している人もおり（“タクシー業者でハム”という人が集まって、「無線クラブ」を作ったり、クラブの名義でアマチュア無線社団局を開設したりしている場合もある。）空車中は雑談を楽しんでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some privately owned taxis which are equipped with ham radio equipment to enjoy a chitchat while the taxi is not in service (some people who are taxi driver-cum-radio ham often get together to form a &quot;ham radio club&quot; or establish an amateur radio station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some privately owned taxis equipped with ham radio equipment to enjoy a chitchat while the taxi is not in service (some people who are taxi driver-cum-radio ham often get together to form a &quot;ham radio club&quot; or establish an amateur radio station).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some privately owned taxis equipped with ham radio equipment to enjoy a chitchat while the taxi is not in service (some people who are taxi driver-cum-radio ham often get together to form a &apos;ham radio club&apos; or establish an amateur radio station).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="360">
<j>しかしながら、一部にはアマチュア無線を使って業務上のものと思われる通信（道路の混雑や、客待ちの情報など）を行なう者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are some taxi drivers who exchange business information (traffic jam information or information on customers waiting for a taxi) using ham radio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are some taxi drivers who exchange business information (traffic jam information or information on customers waiting for a taxi) using ham radio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are some taxi drivers who exchange business information (traffic jam information or information on customers waiting for a taxi) using ham radio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="361">
<j>このことは電波法（昭和25年5月2日法律第131号）第52条の「目的外使用」にあたる違法行為であり、一般のアマチュア無線家から批判されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This violates Article 52 of the Radio Act (Law No. 131 came into effect on May 2, in 1945), &quot;use for purposes other than allowed purposes&quot; and some radio hams complain about this act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This violates Article 52 of the Radio Act (Law No. 131 came into effect on May 2, in 1945), &quot;use for purposes other than allowed purposes&quot; and some radio hams complain about this act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This violates Article 52 of the Radio Act (Law No. 131 came into effect on May 2, in 1945), &apos;use for purposes other than allowed purposes&apos; and some radio hams complain about this act.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="362">
<j>また、無線の使用料を乗務員から徴収する会社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, some taxi companies charge radio fee from the drivers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, some taxi companies charge radio fee to the drivers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, some taxi companies charge radio fee to the drivers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="363">
<j>乗務員証・運転者証</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Driver ID card</e>
<cmt>調査したところ「乗務員証」も「運転者証」も同一のものであるようですので、訳語上では仮訳ですが「Driver ID card」のみと致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Driver ID card</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Driver ID card</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="364">
<j>そのタクシー会社の社員証。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An employee ID card of the taxi company</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An employee ID card of the taxi company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An employee ID card of the taxi company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="365">
<j>東京・大阪についてはタクシーセンター発行の乗務員登録証となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A driver registration card is equivalent to this card in Tokyo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A driver registration card is equivalent to this card in Tokyo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A driver registration card is equivalent to this card in Tokyo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="366">
<j>顔写真（寸法も法令で規定がある）を貼り付けて実空車表示器の室内側表示部分に、客室に見えるように提示しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The driver ID card with a photo (the photo size is actually designated by the law) must be set up on the display part on the interior side by the actual empty car indicator so that passengers can see it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The driver ID card with a photo (the photo size is actually designated by the law) must be set up on the display part on the interior side by the actual vacant car indicator so passengers can see it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The driver ID card with a photo (the photo size is actually designated by the law) must be set up on the display part on the interior on the side by the actual vacant car indicator so passengers can see it.</e>
<cmt>on the side としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="367">
<j>もし写真と運転手の顔が一致しなければ、車両強奪の犯罪行為が疑われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the face of the driver and the photo do not match, it is suspected of seizing the taxi, a criminal act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the face of the driver and the photo do not match, it is suspect as a seized taxi, a criminal act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the face of the driver and the photo do not match, it is suspect as a seized taxi, a criminal act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="368">
<j>ドライブレコーダー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drive recorder</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drive recorder</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drive recorder</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="369">
<j>最近装備する事業者が増えてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More and more taxi companies are install one there days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More and more taxi companies are install one there days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More and more taxi companies are installing one these days.</e>
<cmt>文法、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="370">
<j>ルームミラーに内蔵し、常に前方の状況を撮影してHDDに記録しているが、不要部分は自動的に消去されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A drive recorder is embedded in the rearview mirror and always films a front view and records the data in an HDD, but unnecessary scenes are automatically deleted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A drive recorder is embedded in the rearview mirror and always films a front view and records the data in an HDD, but unnecessary scenes are automatically deleted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A drive recorder is embedded in the rearview mirror and always films a front view and records the data in an HDD, but unnecessary scenes are automatically deleted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="371">
<j>予め決められた一定の条件（急ブレーキ、振動など）を感知すると、前後数秒の映像が保存される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it detects any of the predetermined conditions (sudden braking, vibration, etc.), moving images for several seconds before and after the incident are recorded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it detects any of the predetermined conditions (sudden braking, vibration, etc.), moving images for several seconds before and after the incident are recorded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it detects any of the predetermined conditions (sudden braking, vibration, etc.), moving images for several seconds before and after the incident are recorded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="372">
<j>当初は、タクシーの事故後の解決･交渉をスムーズに進めるために導入されたが、副次的な成果として、ドライバーの運転マナーの向上やタクシーが当事者ではない事件や事故の証拠、事故原因の解析による事故予防などに活用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The drive recorder was originally introduced to proceed with investigation of the causes and negotiations promptly after the taxi gets involved in an accident; however, due to its secondary effects, it is now used for improving driving manners of the drivers, presenting evidence for a crime or accident in which the taxi was not the party in charge, and preventing accidents by analyzing the cause of the accident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The drive recorder was originally introduced to proceed with investigation of the causes and negotiations promptly after a taxi becomes involved in an accident; however, due to its secondary effects, it is now used for improving driving manners of the drivers, presenting evidence for a crime or accidents in which the taxi was not the party in charge, and preventing accidents by analyzing the cause of the accident.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The drive recorder was originally introduced to proceed with investigation of the causes and negotiations promptly after a taxi becomes involved in an accident; however, due to its secondary effects, it is now used for improving driving manners of the drivers, presenting evidence for a crime or accidents in which the taxi was not the party in charge, and preventing accidents by analyzing the cause of the accident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="373">
<j>ETC車載器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In-vehicle ETC</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In-vehicle ETC</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In-vehicle ETC</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="374">
<j>都市部を中心に、最近装備する事業者が増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More and more taxi companies are install one there days, especially in the large cities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More and more taxi companies are install one there days, especially in large cities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More and more taxi companies are installing one these days, especially in large cities.</e>
<cmt>文法、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="375">
<j>深夜時間帯などに高速道路を通行した場合のETC割引制度を受けられる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Passengers who use a taxi with an ETC can often take the ETC discount system when the taxi runs on an expressway during late night hours or similar occasions.</e>
<cmt>「ETC割引制度を受けられる場合が多い。」とは「ETCを搭載したタクシー側のこと」なのか「ETCを搭載したタクシーを使う乗客のこと」なのか判断できませんでした。ここでは「乗客側のこと」として訳出しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers who use a taxi with an ETC can often take the ETC discount system when the taxi runs on an expressway during late night hours or similar occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers who use a taxi with an ETC can often take the ETC discount system when the taxi runs on an expressway during late night hours or similar occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="376">
<j>通常はタクシー会社の保有するETCカードを利用して、運賃と合わせて領収書を発行するが、利用客の保有するETCカードを利用して、通行料を支払うことができるケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally, the expressway charge is added to the taxi fare to issue a receipt using an ETC card that belongs to the taxi company; however, there are some case where the expressway charge is paid using an ETC card of the passenger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally, the expressway charge is added to the taxi fare and issues a receipt using an ETC card that belongs to the taxi company; however, there are some cases where the expressway charge is paid using an ETC card of the passenger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally, the expressway charge is added to the taxi fare and a receipt is issued using an ETC card that belongs to the taxi company; however, there are some cases where the expressway charge is paid using an ETC card of the passenger.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="377">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="378">
<j>バッテリーケーブル（仲間がバッテリーが上がったときに救援するため）、ゴムバンド（トランクルームに蓋が閉まらなくなるほどの大きな荷物を積載したときの落下防止用）救急箱、傘（雨の日の迎車のため。宣伝になるので会社名が大きく入ったオリジナル傘をそろえている会社もある）、バケツ、消火器、毛布、洗車ブラシ（会社によっては各自で持参しなければならない）などを搭載している場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some taxis that carry jumper cables (to help co-workers when his/her taxi runs out of battery), rubber bands (to prevent a large baggage from falling from the trunk), a first-aid box, an umbrella (to pick up passengers on a rainy day, there are some taxi companies that prepare its own original umbrellas with a large company logo for aiming advertising effects), a bucket, a fire extinguisher, a blanket, a car-washing brush (some taxi companies make the drivers prepare his/her own one), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some taxis that carry jumper cables (to help co-workers when his/her taxi battery runs down), rubber straps (to prevent a large baggage from falling from the trunk), a first-aid box, an umbrella (to pick up passengers on a rainy day, there are some taxi companies that prepare its own original umbrellas with a large company logo for advertising effect), a bucket, a fire extinguisher, a blanket, a car-washing brush (some taxi companies make the drivers prepare his/her own one), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some taxis that carry jumper cables (to help co-workers when his/her taxi battery runs down), rubber straps (to prevent a large baggage from falling from the trunk), a first-aid box, an umbrella (to pick up passengers on a rainy day; there are some taxi companies that prepare its own original umbrellas with a large company logo for advertising effect), a bucket, a fire extinguisher, a blanket, a car-washing brush (some taxi companies make the drivers prepare his/her own one), etc.</e>
<cmt>セミコロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="379">
<j>車両広告</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxi advertisings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxi advertising</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxi advertising</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="380">
<j>車両は不特定多数の乗客が乗降し、一日中街中を走行しているため広告媒体としても利用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because taxis are used by a large indefinite number of people and run around town all day, they are also used as advertising media.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because taxis are used by a large indefinite number of people and run around town all day, they are also used as advertising media.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because taxis are used by a large indefinite number of people and run around town all day, they are also used as advertising media.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="381">
<j>タクシー広告専門の広告代理店も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are even some advertising agencies solely for advertisings placed on taxis.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are even some advertising agencies solely for advertisings placed on taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are even some advertising agencies solely for advertisings placed on taxis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="382">
<j>車体広告</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Advertisings on vehicles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Advertisings on vehicles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Advertisings on vehicles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="383">
<j>ラッピング広告</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posters:</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="384">
<j>- 車体の両面ドア4枚に広告を印刷したフィルムを貼り付けるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thin films on which advertisings are printed are pasted on the four side doors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thin films on which advertisings are printed are pasted on the four side doors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thin films on which advertisings are printed are pasted on the four side doors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="385">
<j>後部ドアにマグネットで広告を貼り付けるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Advertisings are placed on the back door with magnet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Advertising is placed on the back door with a magnet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Advertising is placed on the back door with a magnet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="386">
<j>後部左側ドアのウィンドウにステッカーを貼り付けるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sticker on which advertisings are printed is pasted on the left back door.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sticker on which advertising is printed is pasted on the left back door.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sticker on which advertising is printed is pasted on the window of the left back door.</e>
<cmt>窓　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="387">
<j>リアウィンドウにフィルムを貼り付けるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A film on which advertisings are printed is pasted on the rear window.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Film on which advertisings are printed is pasted on the rear window.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Film on which advertisings are printed is pasted on the rear window.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="388">
<j>車内からは透視でき、外部からは広告面が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a transparent material when seen from inside, but ads are seen on it when seen from outside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a transparent material when seen from inside, but ads are seen on it when seen from outside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a transparent material when seen from inside, but ads are seen on it when seen from outside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="389">
<j>大型の社名表示灯に商品広告が施されているもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A product advertising is placed on the large-size company logo indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A product advertisment is placed on the large-size company logo indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A product advertisement is placed on the large-size company logo indicating lamp.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="390">
<j>ホイールに静止ホイールを取り付けるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Pascap with an advertising is placed on a wheel of the taxi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Pascap with an advertising is placed on a wheel of the taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Pascap with an advertising is placed on a wheel of the taxi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="391">
<j>車内広告</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Advertisings in taxis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Advertisings in taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Advertisings in taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="392">
<j>助手席背中部分にケースを取り付け、チラシ広告をおくもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Advertisings are placed in a case located on the back of the backrest of the passenger&apos;s seat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Advertisings are placed in a case located on the back of the backrest of the passenger&apos;s seat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Advertisings are placed in a case located on the back of the backrest of the passenger&apos;s seat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="393">
<j>車中への忘れ物に備えて社名とナンバー、車番（会社での車両登録番号）が明記された名刺風カードが設置されていることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some taxis have business-card type cards, on which the company name, phone number, vehicle number (vehicle identification number in the company) are described, are set in the vehicle in case passengers can contact the taxi company about lost articles.</e>
<cmt>ここでいう「ナンバー」とは、「電話番号」であると解釈して訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some taxis have business-card type cards, on which the company name, phone number, vehicle number (vehicle identification number in the company) are described, are set in the vehicle in case passengers want to contact the taxi company about lost articles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some taxis have business-card type cards, on which the company name, phone number, vehicle number (vehicle identification number in the company) are described, and they are set in the vehicle in case passengers want to contact the taxi company about lost articles.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="394">
<j>液晶ディスプレイを設置し、動画広告を流していることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There also some taxis which have a LCD to show advertisings of moving pictures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There also some taxis which have an LCD screen to show advertisings of moving pictures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also some taxis which have an LCD screen to show advertisings of moving pictures.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="395">
<j>日本のタクシーが抱える問題点</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Problems of taxis in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Problems of taxis in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Problems of taxis in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="396">
<j>交通事故の多さ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A large number of traffic accidents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A large number of traffic accidents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large number of traffic accidents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="397">
<j>一般車に比べ事故が非常に多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of traffic accidents involving taxis is much more than that of general automobiles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of traffic accidents involving taxis is much more than that of general automobiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of traffic accidents involving taxis is much more than that of general automobiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="398">
<j>1台あたりの事故件数は全自動車と比べて8倍以上と極めて高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of traffic accidents per taxi is over eight times of that of all automobiles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of traffic accidents per taxi is over eight times of those of all automobiles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of traffic accidents per taxi is over eight times of those of all automobiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="399">
<j>原因として強引な運転や、疲労運転が挙げられる（いずれも道路交通法違反）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Possible causes include aggressive driving and driving in a fatigued state (both of which violate the Road Traffic Act).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Possible causes include aggressive driving and driving in a fatigued state (both of which violate the Road Traffic Act).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Possible causes include aggressive driving and driving in a fatigued state (both of which violate the Road Traffic Act).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="400">
<j>「1台あたりの走行距離が長いから、事故が多く見えるのは見かけ上の問題だ」との主張もあるが、走行100万キロメートルあたりの事故件数ベースで比較してもタクシーの事故率が突出している（2003年の時点では走行100万kmあたりタクシーの事故件数1.704件に対して、全自動車は1.195件）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are some opinions saying &quot;it apparently looks like taxis have more traffic accidents because the driving distance per taxi is much longer than that per general car,&quot; even when the data of accidents occurring in driving distance of 1 million kilometers are compared, the number of accidents caused by taxis is still high exceptionally (as of 2003, the number of traffic accidents occurring in driving distance of 1 million kilometers and caused by taxis was 1.704, while that of all automobiles was 1.195).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are some opinions saying &quot;it apparently looks like taxis have more traffic accidents because the driving distance per taxi is much longer than that per general car,&quot; even when the data of accidents occurring in driving distance of 1 million kilometers are compared, the number of accidents caused by taxis is still high exceptionally (as of 2003, the number of traffic accidents occurring in driving distance of 1 million kilometers and caused by taxis was 1.704, while that of all automobiles was 1.195).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are some opinions saying &apos;it apparently looks like taxis have more traffic accidents because the driving distance per taxi is much longer than that per general car,&apos; even when the data of accidents occurring in driving distance of one million kilometers are compared, the number of accidents caused by taxis is still high exceptionally (as of 2003, the number of traffic accidents occurring in driving distance of one million kilometers and caused by taxis was 1.704, while that of all automobiles was 1.195).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="401">
<j>ドライバーの賃金問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issues of wages of taxi drivers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issues of wages of taxi drivers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issues of wages of taxi drivers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="402">
<j>法人タクシードライバーの賃金は累進歩合制がほとんどであり、これに対して国土交通省は変更を勧告する通達を繰り返している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of wages of corporate taxi drivers are paid in a graduated commission system; however, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism has been repeatedly issuing directives for changing this system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of wages of corporate taxi drivers are paid in a graduated commission system; however, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism has been repeatedly issuing directives for changing this system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of wages of corporate taxi drivers are paid in a graduated commission system; however, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism has been repeatedly issuing directives for changing this system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="403">
<j>累進歩合制給与とは、売上高に応じて累進的に給与が加算される能力給制給与の一種であるが、ベースとなる固定給が極めて低いのがタクシー業界の一般的特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The graduated commission system is a type of pay-for-performance wage system in which salary is progressively increased according to the sales, but the base fixed wage is very low in general characteristics of taxi companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The graduated commission system is a type of pay-for-performance wage system in which salary is progressively increased according to sales, but the base fixed wage is very low in general characteristics of taxi companies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The graduated commission system is a type of pay-for-performance wage system in which salary is progressively increased according to sales, but the base fixed wage is very low in general characteristics of taxi companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="404">
<j>これと近年の規制緩和でタクシー台数が増やされたことをあわせると、限られたパイを取り合う構図になり、満足な収入を得られるのは一部の優れたドライバーに限られ、ほとんどのドライバーは極めて少ない収入となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Combined this issue with the issue of increased number of taxis due to relaxation of the taxi regulations in recent years, there are limits to what parties involved can do and only a small number of excellent drivers can get satisfactory income, meaning that most drivers get extremely low income.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「限られたパイを取り合う構図になり、、」とは「出来ることは限られ、、」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Combining this issue with the issue of increased number of taxis due to relaxation of the taxi regulations in recent years, there are limits to what the parties involved can do and only a small number of excellent drivers can get satisfactory income, meaning that most drivers get extremely low income.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Combining this issue with the issue of increased number of taxis due to relaxation of the taxi regulations in recent years, there are limits to what the parties involved can do and only a small number of excellent drivers can get satisfactory income, meaning that most drivers get extremely low income.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="405">
<j>（矢貫隆が『カーグラフィック』誌に2006年12月号より連載している「京都・タクシードライバー日記」によると、例えば1ヶ月毎日12時間以上働いても売上高が30万円、賃金が手取り8万円というような状態が珍しくないという。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(According to &quot;Kyoto Taxi Driver Diary&quot; which has been written by Takashi YANUKI in serial form in &apos;CAR GRAPHIC&apos; magazine since December 2006, it is not a rare case in which a taxi driver achieves sales of 300,000 yen but can get wage of only 80,000 yen a month even though he/she works over 12 hours every day.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(According to &quot;Kyoto Taxi Driver Diary&quot; which has been written by Takashi YANUKI in serial form in &apos;CAR GRAPHIC&apos; magazine since December 2006, it is not a rare case in which a taxi driver achieves sales of 300,000 yen but can get a wage of only 80,000 yen a month even though he/she works over 12 hours every day.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to &apos;Kyoto Taxi Driver Diary&apos; which has been written by Takashi YANUKI in serial form in &quot;CAR GRAPHIC&quot; magazine since December 2006, it is not a rare case in which a taxi driver achieves sales of 300,000 yen but can get a wage of only 80,000 yen a month even though he/she works over 12 hours every day.)</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="406">
<j>この問題に関連して、大阪府内の法人タクシーの運転手4人が、規制緩和による過度な増車等によって収入が低下し、労働条件の悪化と交通事故の増加を招いたなどとして、増車・運賃値下げの許認可取り消しと、1人当たり約50万円の損害賠償を国に対し求める訴訟を、2005年10月に大阪地方裁判所に起こしたが、同地裁は2009年3月25日に、「規制緩和があったからといって、供給過多や極端な運転手の給与水準の低下があったとは認められない」として、訴えを棄却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related to this issue, insisting that the income has decreased, the work conditions have worsened, and the number of traffic accidents has increased due to relaxation of the taxi regulations, four taxi drivers of corporate taxi companies in Osaka Prefecture brought a lawsuit against the nation, demanding for revoking the approval and license for increase in the number do taxis and reduce in taxi drivers&apos; wages, and demanding damages of about a half million yen per person, with the Osaka District Court in October 2005; however, the Osaka District Court dismissed the lawsuit on March 25, in 2009, saying that people cannot say excess of supply and extreme decrease in drivers&apos; income were due to the relaxation of the taxi regulations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related to this issue, insisting that the income has decreased, the work conditions have worsened, and the number of traffic accidents has increased due to relaxation of the taxi regulations, four taxi drivers of corporate taxi companies in Osaka Prefecture brought a lawsuit against the nation, demanding revoking the approval and license for increase in the number of taxis and reduce in taxi drivers&apos; wages, and demanding damages of about a half million yen per person, with the Osaka District Court in October 2005; however, the Osaka District Court dismissed the lawsuit on March 25, in 2009, saying that people cannot say excess of supply and extreme decrease in drivers&apos; income were due to the relaxation of the taxi regulations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related to this issue, insisting that the income has decreased, the work conditions have worsened, and the number of traffic accidents has increased due to relaxation of the taxi regulations, four taxi drivers of corporate taxi companies in Osaka Prefecture brought a lawsuit against the nation, demanding revoking the approval and license for increase in the number of taxis and for reduce in taxi fares, and demanding damages of about a half million yen per person, with the Osaka District Court in October 2005; however, the Osaka District Court dismissed the lawsuit on March 25, 2009, saying that people cannot say excess of supply and extreme decrease in drivers&apos; income were due to the relaxation of the taxi regulations.</e>
<cmt>運賃値下げ　とありますので、driver&apos;s wages→ taxi fares としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 A301m089(id:127121), ＫＡＺＵ(id:46839), 竹富島(id:97808), Caveman(id:137032), アイザール(id:133157), Panpulha(id:42950), 大内一郎(id:64047), D.Bellwood(id:10032), Borg(id:4390), Dream100(id:41924), Fxcxt(id:21803), Yanagi774(id:15206), 橄欖岩(id:24996), まるゆ(id:4371), Kenpei(id:11349), Misola(id:36747), ECLIPSE(id:39342), Point136(id:211299), Toteknon(id:48011), YukkeBot2(id:251491), M abe(id:37612), Krs13(id:23984), Starbacks(id:1018), Tetsuo1968(id:12092), 整理人(id:105304), Bloodserver(id:33911), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Rapidservice(id:165470), MEDITATE(id:168298), Spring days(id:282539), CLUTCH(id:100194), Rusk(id:9895), Baioextra(id:164616), Kentaro Matsui(id:146351), McRash-F4(id:146046), R28Bot(id:177951), NOWOW(id:62041), Simon(id:6494), Kuha455405(id:35818), やすとし(id:63220), Ki4Utsu(id:88849), Truck(id:256194), Nsq(id:54991), 大人の事情(id:172697), You tiara(id:44563), MD242(id:11277), Sogiya(id:82968), のりお(id:99401), 田無稲子(id:63575), Iteron(id:162209), Charenji(id:7908), 凛々(id:14112), Jr223(id:102454), PALNAS,MOSCOW-TASTE(id:140939), Gnsin(id:12351), DNCAL(id:120593), Jekatsumi(id:30314), 宅銅鑼(id:246355), Sadnese(id:169079), 崎宏(id:64519), 地図帳(id:122587), デジタルチョコ(id:27299), ボンバー佐藤(id:45776), EpiXS53(id:60567), Kawai masashi(id:95892), U1p(id:48290), Ra550rbn(id:59942), Nopira(id:29335), Dojima(id:104278), Vivo(id:24436), Qurren(id:20140), Aizumikotsu(id:125412), Taka1981(id:62489), Ken-train19890106(id:74126), なんざいせん(id:154906), 神代 刹那(id:94620), 白鐘沙羅(id:86553), Taisyo(id:6896), Sat.K(id:3751), Kminowa(id:57304), JunK(id:14563), Type85(id:127824), Ypy31(id:30771), FOZ(id:44646), Carbucketty(id:253794), 通(id:45307), 南タクシー(id:93793), Otoshigo(id:80102), Fromm(id:71291), 地吹雪(id:38741), Tokorozawa22(id:111065), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Wakei(id:79080), Muyo(id:14948), 毛が生えた程度(id:44385), Comyu(id:58135), ホイップ(id:44812), Atsasebo(id:95407), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>