<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>阪急電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>http://rail.hankyu.co.jp/en/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>阪急電鉄株式会社（はんきゅうでんてつ、英語 Hankyu Corporation）は、大阪梅田駅と神戸市・宝塚市・京都市を結ぶ大手私鉄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation (Hankyu Dentetsu) is a major private railway company operating the railways that connect Osaka Umeda Station with Kobe City, Takarazuka City, and Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Corporation (Hankyu Dentetsu) is a major private railway company operating the railways that connect Osaka Umeda Station with Kobe City, Takarazuka City and Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation (Hankyu Dentetsu) is a major private railway company operating the railways that connect Osaka Umeda Station with Kobe City, Takarazuka City and Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>阪急阪神ホールディングスの子会社で、阪急阪神東宝グループに属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a subsidiary of Hankyu Hanshin Holdings, Inc., and belongs to Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>阪急阪神ホールディングス→Hankyu Hanshin Holdings, Inc. (http://holdings.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/gaiyo.html)、阪急阪神東宝グループ→Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group（http://www.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/hankyu-hanshin-toho-group/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a subsidiary of Hankyu Hanshin Holdings, Inc., and belongs to the Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a subsidiary of Hankyu Hanshin Holdings, Inc., and belongs to the Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>本社事務所は大阪府大阪市北区 (大阪市)にあるが、登記上の本店所在地は大阪府池田市栄町1番1号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The central office of the company is located in Osaka City (Kita Ward, Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture), but the location of the registered head office is 1-1, Sakae-cho, Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company&apos;s central office is located in Osaka City (Kita Ward, Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture), but the location of the registered head office is 1-1, Sakae-cho, Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company&apos;s central office is located in Osaka City (Kita Ward, Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture), but the location of the registered head office is 1-1, Sakae-machi, Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Sakae-machiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>平均利用者数195万人/日、営業キロ146.6kmに及ぶ、大手私鉄の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the major private railway companies with an average of the 1,950,000 (one million nine hundred fifty thousand) users a day and the total operation kilometer of 146.6km.</e>
<cmt>営業キロ→operation kilometer (英辞郎on the WEB)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the major private railway companies with an average of 1,950,000 (one million nine hundred fifty thousand) users a day and a total operation of 146.6km kilometers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the major private railway companies with an average of 1,950,000 (one million nine hundred fifty thousand) users a day and a total operation of 146.6 kilometers.</e>
<cmt>kmを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、女性のみで構成される劇団「宝塚歌劇団」を運営していることでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company is also known for managing the &quot;Takarazuka Revue,&quot; which is a theater company consisted of only female members.</e>
<cmt>宝塚歌劇団→Takarazuka Revue(http://kageki.hankyu.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company is also known for managing the &quot;Takarazuka Revue,&quot; a theater troupe consisting exclusively of female members.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company is also known for managing the &apos;Takarazuka Revue,&apos; a theater troupe consisting exclusively of female members.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>スルッとKANSAIでカードに印字される符号はHKである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At an automated ticket gate accepting &quot;KANSI THRU PASS&quot;, the code &quot;HK&quot; is printed on the card.</e>
<cmt>スルッとKANSAI　→KANSAI THRU PASS (http://www.surutto.com.conts/ticket/3dayeng/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At an automated ticket gate accepting &quot;KANSI THRU PASS,&quot; the code &quot;HK&quot; is printed on the card.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At an automated ticket gate accepting KANSAI THRU PASS, the code HK is printed on the card.</e>
<cmt>KANSI →KANSAI 括弧を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>1907年に設立された箕面有馬電気軌道が、1910年3月10日に現在の宝塚本線・箕面線にあたる梅田駅～宝塚駅、石橋駅 (大阪府)～箕面駅を開業したのが始まり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initiation of the company dated back to March 10, 1910, when Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline (Minoo-Arima denki kido) began operating the section between Umeda Station and Takarazuka Station as well as the section between Ishibashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) and Minoo Station, which respectively corresponds to the current Takarazuka Line and the Minoo Line.</e>
<cmt>箕面有馬電気軌道→Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline (Mino-Arima denki kido) （箕面：Mino→Minooとしました。以下同)（http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=52xS)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company&apos;s founding dates to March 10, 1910, when the Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline (Minoo-Arima denki kido) began operating the section between Umeda Station and Takarazuka Station as well as the section between Ishibashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) and Minoo Station, which respectively corresponds to the current Takarazuka Line and the Minoo Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mino-Arima Electric Tramline (Mino-Arima denki kido), which was founded in 1907, began operating the section between Umeda Station and Takarazuka Station as well as the section between Ishibashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) and Mino Station, which respectively correspond to the current Takarazuka Line and the Mino Line, on March 10, 1910,</e>
<cmt>Minoo→ Mino</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>創業者の小林一三は経営安定のため沿線開発に力を入れ、住宅地分譲、宝塚新温泉、宝塚唱歌隊（後の少女歌劇団、現在の宝塚歌劇団）などの事業を多角的に展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder, Ichizo KOBAYASHI made efforts in developing the areas along the railway line, in order to stabilize the management and introduced multiple businesses, such as, selling land in lot, developing Takarazuka New Hot Spring, and creating the Takarazuka Shokatai (Takarazuka Chorus Group), which is the later Shojo Kageki-dan (girls&apos; operetta company), and the actual Takarazuka Revue Company.</e>
<cmt>宝塚新温泉→定訳不明：Takarazuka New Hot Spring、宝塚唱歌隊→Takarazuka Shokatai (Takarazuka Chorus Group) (http://www.ndl.go.jp/scenary/kansai/e/column/takarazuka_onsen.html)、少女歌劇団→定訳不明：Shojo Kageki-dan (girls&apos; operetta company).</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder, Ichizo Kobayashi, made efforts to develop the areas along the railway line in order to stabilize the management, and introduced multiple businesses such as land sales in lots, developing the Takarazuka New Hot Spring and creating the Takarazuka Shokatai (Takarazuka Chorus Group), which later became the Shojo Kageki-dan (Girls&apos; Operetta Company), as well as the Takarazuka Revue Company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder, Ichizo KOBAYASHI, made efforts to develop the areas along the railway line in order to stabilize the management, and introduced multiple businesses such as land sales in lots, developing the Takarazuka New Hot Spring and creating the Takarazuka Shokatai (Takarazuka Chorus Group, which later became the Shojo Kageki-dan (Girls&apos; Operetta Company), the current Takarazuka Revue Company).</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。括弧の場所を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>続いて阪神間の輸送に参入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, the company went into the transportation business between Osaka and Kobe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the company went into the transportation business, operating between Osaka and Kobe.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the company went into the transportation business, operating between Osaka and Kobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1918年、社名を阪神急行電鉄に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1918, the company changed its name to Hanshin Electric Express Railway.</e>
<cmt>阪神急行電鉄→Hanshin Electric Express Railway (http://www.jtr.net/jtr08/history.html)、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918, the company changed its name to Hanshin Electric Express Railway.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918, the company changed its name to Hanshin Electric Express Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>現在まで続く略称の「阪急」はこれに由来する（後、正式社名にも採用される）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The abbreviated name of the company &quot;Hankyu&quot; derives from this name (later it was adopted as official name).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The abbreviated name of the company, &quot;Hankyu,&quot; is derived from this name (later it was adopted as the official name).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company&apos;s abbreviated name, &apos;Hankyu,&apos; is derived from this name (later it was adopted as the official name).</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>阪神間に参入したことで、以後既に阪神間で都市間連絡電車を営業していた阪神電気鉄道とは激しく争うライバル関係となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its emergence in the transportation between Osaka and Kobe triggered a severe rivalry competition with Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd., which had been already operating urban commutation trains between Osaka and Kobe.</e>
<cmt>阪神電気鉄道→Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. (http://www.hanshin.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its emergence in the field of transportation between Osaka and Kobe triggered a severe rivalry in competition with Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd., which was already operating urban commuter trains between Osaka and Kobe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its emergence in the field of transportation between Osaka and Kobe triggered a severe rivalry in competition with Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd., which was already operating urban commuter trains between Osaka and Kobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1920年に神戸本線十三～神戸（後の上筒井駅）間を開業し、1936年には神戸市内の三宮駅へ高架線で乗り入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1920, the operation between Juso Station on the Kobe Line and Kobe Station (later Kamitsutsui Station) started, and in 1936, the railway was extended to Sannomiya Station located in Kobe City, using an elevated track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1920, the operation between Juso Station on the Kobe Line and Kobe Station (later Kamitsutsui Station) started, and in 1936 the railway was extended to Sannomiya Station (located in Kobe City) using an elevated track.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1920, the operation between Juso Station on the Kobe Line and Kobe Station (later Kamitsutsui Station) started, and in 1936 the railway was extended to Sannomiya Station (located in Kobe City) using an elevated track.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、「電鉄」という語は、「電気鉄道」という語を商号に使用することに、鉄道省があくまで軌道法準拠の「電気軌道」である事を根拠として難色を示したことから、対策として小林一三が考え出した語で、以後軌道法監督下の各社が高速電気鉄道への脱皮を図る際に有効活用されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the word &quot;Dentetsu&quot; is a coined term made by Ichizo KOBAYASHI, because the then Japanese Government of Railways (JGR) opposed to the use of the word &quot;Denki Tetsudo&quot; (electric railway),&quot; as a corporate name, based on the argument that this name was considered identical with &quot;electric tramways,&quot; the term regulated by the Tramways Act, therefore, the word, &quot;Dentetsu&quot; was conveniently adopted, afterwards, by various companies regulated by the Tramways Act, when they intended to morph into rapid electric railways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the word &quot;Dentetsu&quot; is a coined term by Ichizo Kobayashi, because the then Japanese Government of Railways (JGR) was opposed to the use of the term &quot;Denki Tetsudo&quot; (electric railway)&quot; as a corporate name, based on the argument that this name was considered identical with &quot;electric tramways,&quot; the term regulated by the Tramways Act; thereafter, the word &quot;Dentetsu&quot; was conveniently adopted by various companies regulated by the Tramways Act when they intended to morph into rapid electric railways.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the word &apos;Dentetsu&apos; is a term coined by Ichizo KOBAYASHI because the then Japanese Government Railways (JGR) was opposed to the use of the term &apos;Denki Tetsudo (electric railway)&apos; as a corporate name, based on the argument that this name was considered identical with &apos;electric tramways,&apos; the term regulated by the Tramways Act; thereafter, the word &apos;Dentetsu&apos; was conveniently adopted by various companies regulated by the Tramways Act when they intended to convert into rapid electric railways.</e>
<cmt>Japanese Government Railways (JGR) としました。括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>1943年、戦時企業統合政策（陸上交通事業調整法）により京阪電気鉄道を合併、京阪神急行電鉄となる（この経緯については阪神急行電鉄京阪電気鉄道の統合と分離も参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1943, under the wartime enterprise integration policy -&quot;Rikujokotsu Jigyo Chosei-ho&quot; (land traffic business adjustment act)- the company incorporated Keihan Electric Railway and became Keihanshin Electric Express Railway (for details of the merger, please refer to &quot;Unification of Hanshin Electric Express Railway and Keihan Electric Railway&quot;).</e>
<cmt>戦時企業統合政策（陸上交通事業調整法）→定訳不明 ： wartime enterprise integration policy -&quot;Rikujokotsu Jigyo Chosei-ho&quot; (land traffic business adjustment act) - としました、京阪電気鉄道→Keihan Electric Railway (http://www.keihan.co.jp)、京阪神急行電鉄→定訳不明：Keihanshin Electric Express Railway、阪神急行電鉄→Hanshin Electric Express Railway (http://www.jtr.net/jtr08/history.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1943, under the wartime enterprise integration policy &quot;Rikujokotsu Jigyo Chosei-ho&quot; (Land Traffic Business Adjustment Act), the company incorporated Keihan Electric Railway and became Keihanshin Electric Express Railway (for details of the merger, please refer to &quot;Unification of Hanshin Electric Express Railway and Keihan Electric Railway&quot;).</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1943, under the wartime enterprise integration policy Rikujokotsu Jigyo Chosei-ho (Land Traffic Business Adjustment Act), the company incorporated Keihan Electric Railway and became Keihanshin Electric Express Railway (for details of the merger, please refer to &quot;Unification of Hanshin Electric Express Railway and Keihan Electric Railway&quot;).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、このとき「阪急」と「京阪」の略称は公式には使用されなくなり「京阪神（急行）」とされたが、世間には定着せず、大阪市電の電停名でも「阪急阪神前」（梅田）・「京阪前」（天満橋）・「京阪神急行前」（天六）などと、混合して用いられていたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">since then, the abbreviated name &quot;Hankyu&quot; and &quot;Keihan&quot; were officially disused and &quot;Keihanshin (Express)&quot; was introduced as a new abbreviation, the new name had not been fixed among the people and these names were used in a confused manner, such as &quot;Hankyu-Hanshin-mae&quot; (Umeda) for an Osaka city tram station (Umeda), &quot;Keihan-mae&quot;(Tenmabashi), or &quot;Keihanshin-kyuko-mae&quot; (Tenroku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the abbreviated name &quot;Hankyu&quot; and &quot;Keihan&quot; were officially abandoned and &quot;Keihanshin (Express)&quot; was introduced as a new abbreviation; however, the new name had not been fixed among the people and these names were used in a confused manner, such as &quot;Hankyu-Hanshin-mae&quot; (Umeda) for an Osaka city tram station (Umeda), &quot;Keihan-mae&quot;(Tenmabashi) or &quot;Keihanshin-kyuko-mae&quot; (Tenroku).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the abbreviated names &apos;Hankyu&apos; and &apos;Keihan&apos; were officially abandoned and &apos;Keihanshin (Express)&apos; was introduced as a new abbreviation; however, the new name had not been fixed among the people and these names were used in a confused manner, such as &apos;Hankyu-Hanshin-mae&apos; (Umeda) for an Osaka city tram station, &apos;Keihan-mae&apos; (Tenmabashi) or &apos;Keihanshin-kyuko-mae&apos; (Tenroku).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>戦後の1949年に京阪線・交野線・宇治線・京津線・石山坂本線が京阪電気鉄道として再分離。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, in 1949, the Keihan Line, Katano Line, Uji Line, Keishin Line, and Ishiyama-Sakamoto Line were separated to form Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>京阪電気鉄道→Keihan Electric Railway (http://www.keihan.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war (in 1949), the Keihan Line, Katano Line, Uji Line, Keishin Line and Ishiyama-Sakamoto Line were separated to form Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war (in 1949), the Keihan Line, Katano Line, Uji Line, Keishin Line and Ishiyama-Sakamoto Line were separated to form Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>かつて京阪の路線であった新京阪鉄道は阪急に残存し、京都本線・千里山線（後に千里線と改称）・十三線（後に京都本線へ編入）・嵐山線となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinkeihan Railway, which was a part of the Keihan, remained in Hankyu, forming the Kyoto Line, Senriyama Line (later Senri Line), Juso Line (later incorporated into the Kyoto Line), and the Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>京阪→京阪電気鉄道Keihan Electric Railway？原文のとおりKeihanとだけしてあります。新京阪鉄道→定訳不明：Shinkeihan Railwayとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinkeihan Railway (which was part of the Keihan) remained in Hankyu, forming the Kyoto Line, Senriyama Line (later the Senri Line), Juso Line (later incorporated into the Kyoto Line) and Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinkeihan Railway (which was part of the Keihan) remained in Hankyu, forming the Kyoto Line, Senriyama Line (later the Senri Line), Juso Line (later incorporated into the Kyoto Line) and Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この時、略称も「京阪神」から「阪急」へ戻している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the abbreviated name was also changed back to &quot;Hankyu&quot; from &quot;Keihanshin&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the abbreviated name was also changed back to &quot;Hankyu&quot; from &quot;Keihanshin&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, the abbreviated name was also changed back to &apos;Hankyu&apos; from &apos;Keihanshin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正&quot;At this time&quot; -&gt; &quot;On this occasion&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>1959年、梅田～十三間が3複線化され、京都本線のターミナルが天神橋駅（現・天神橋筋六丁目駅）から梅田駅になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1959, the section between Umeda Station and Juso Station was installed with 3 tracks in each direction, and the terminal on the Kyoto Line was changed to Umeda Station from Tenjinbashi Station (current Tenjinbashisuji-rokuchome Station).</e>
<cmt>3複線化→定訳不明：3 tracks in each directionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1959, the section between Umeda Station and Juso Station was installed with three tracks in each direction, and the terminal on the Kyoto Line was changed to Umeda Station from Tenjinbashi Station (currently Tenjinbashisuji-rokuchome Station).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1959, the section between Umeda Station and Juso Station was installed with three tracks in each direction, and the terminal on the Kyoto Line was changed to Umeda Station from Tenjinbashi Station (currently Tenjinbashisuji-rokuchome Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>1973年、阪急電鉄に社名変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1973, the company&apos;s name was changed to Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1973, the company&apos;s name was changed to Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1973, the company&apos;s name was changed to Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1992年、後にスルッとKANSAIへ発展するラガールカードによる乗車カード「ラガールカード」を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1992, a travel card, Lagare Card, was introduced, which have later developed to be KNSAI THRU PASS.</e>
<cmt>ラガールカード→Lagare Card (http://rail.hankyu.co.jp/en/toor_info04.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1992, a travel card called the Lagare Card was introduced, but subsequently it developed into the KANSAI THRU PASS.</e>
<cmt>gram, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1992, a travel card called the Lagare Card was introduced, but subsequently it developed into the KANSAI THRU PASS.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、バブル経済崩壊で茶屋町地区などの再開発事業の失敗による巨額の損失を蒙った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the bubble economy collapsed, the company suffered a huge amount of loss by the failure of redevelopment projects in Chayamachi area and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the bubble economy collapsed the company suffered a huge loss due to the failure of redevelopment projects in the Chayamachi area and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the bubble economy collapsed the company suffered a huge loss due to the failure of redevelopment projects in areas such as Chayamachi.</e>
<cmt>一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>追い討ちをかけるように、1995年1月17日の阪神・淡路大震災では、神戸本線・伊丹線・今津（北）線などが甚大な被害を受けたが、同年6月12日にほぼ全線が復旧、1998年には伊丹駅 (阪急)も再建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Kobe Line, Itami Line, and the Imazu Line, among others, were seriously damaged by the great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake occurred on January 17, 1995, but almost all lines were restored by June 12 of the same year and Itami Station (Hankyu) was reconstructed in 1998.</e>
<cmt>今津（北）線→定訳不明：Imazu （north) Lineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the Kobe Line, Itami Line and the Imazu Line, among others, were seriously damaged by the great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake that occurred on January 17, 1995, but nearly all the lines were restored by June 12 of the same year and Itami Station (Hankyu) was reconstructed in 1998.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Kobe Line, Itami Line and the Imazu-kita (north) Line, among others, were seriously damaged by the great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake that occurred on January 17, 1995, but nearly all the lines were restored by June 12 of the same year and Itami Station (Hankyu) was reconstructed in 1998.</e>
<cmt>Imazu-kita (north) Line　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>震災以降も、長引く消費不況や西日本旅客鉄道などとの激しい競合、少子化などの影響により輸送人員は減少。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, by the influence of the prolonged consumers&apos; recession, intensified competition with West Japan Railway Company (JR West), and the declining birthrate, the number of passengers has decreased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, given the influence of the prolonged consumer recession, being intensified competition with West Japan Railway Company (JR West) and the declining birthrate, the number of passengers has subsequently decreased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, given the influence of the prolonged consumer recession, being intensified competition with West Japan Railway Company (JR West) and the declining birthrate, the number of passengers has subsequently decreased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>不動産・ホテル事業の再編や、宝塚新温泉以来90年以上の歴史を持つ遊園地「宝塚ファミリーランド」の閉園、ポートアイランドにあった「神戸ポートピアランド」からの事業撤退（その後暫くは神戸市の手で運営を継続ののち、2006年閉園）など、グループ事業の再編が進められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group&apos;s businesses are now undergoing the reorganization, such as, the restructuring of real estate and hotel management, the closing of an amusement park &quot;Takarazuka Family Land,&quot; which has more than 90 years&apos; history since the opening Takarazuka New Hot Spring, and the withdrawal from the management of &quot;Kobe Portopia Land&quot; located in the Port Island (it was run by Kobe City for a while afterwards, but definitively closed in 2006).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group&apos;s businesses are now undergoing reorganization, such as the restructuring of real estate and hotel management; the closing of the &quot;Takarazuka Family Land&quot; amusement park, which has more than 90 years&apos; history since the opening Takarazuka New Hot Spring; and the withdrawal from the management of &quot;Kobe Portopia Land&quot; located in the Port Island (which was run by Kobe City for a while afterwards but was permanently closed in 2006.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group&apos;s businesses are now undergoing reorganization, such as the restructuring of real estate and hotel management; the closing of the &apos;Takarazuka Family Land&apos; amusement park, whose 90-year history goes back to the opening of Takarazuka New Hot Spring; and the withdrawal from the management of &apos;Kobe Portopia Land&apos; located in the Port Island (which was run by Kobe City for a while afterwards but was permanently closed in 2006).</e>
<cmt>opening of としました。括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その集大成として、2005年4月1日に、旧・阪急電鉄から鉄道、不動産、レジャー、流通の4事業を分割承継する新・阪急電鉄（阪急電鉄分割準備（株）から商号変更）と、ホテル経営を統括する阪急ホテルマネジメント、旅行業の阪急交通社の直営事業会社2社の合わせて3社に再編し、旧・阪急電鉄は持株会社阪急ホールディングス（現・阪急阪神ホールディングス）に移行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And to finalize the restructure, on April 1, 2005, the company was reorganized into 3 companies: i) New Hankyu Corporation (the corporate name was changed from Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (Hankyu corporation division preparation company)), which partially succeeded 4 businesses -railway, real estate, leisure, and commodity distribution- from the former Hankyu Corporation, ii) Hankyu Hotel Management, which controls the hotel business, and iii) Hankyu Travel International Co., Ltd., for tour business, amalgamating two direct subsidiaries: and the former Hankyu Railway was transferred to the holding company, Hankyu Holdings (current Hankyu Hanshin Holdings, Inc.).</e>
<cmt>阪急電鉄分割準備（株） →定訳不明：Hankyu Dentesu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (Hankyu corporation division preparation)としました。阪急ホテルマネジメント→Hanshin Hotel Management (http://hankyu-hotal.com/group/management.html) 阪急交通社→Hankyu Travel International (http://hankyu-travel.com/company/outline/about.html) 阪急ホールディングス→Hankyu Holdings (http://holdings.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/index.html)　阪急阪神ホールディングス→Hankyu Hanshin Holdings(http://holdings.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To finalize the restructuring, on April 1, 2005 the company was reorganized into three companies: i) New Hankyu Corporation (the corporate name was changed from Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (Hankyu Corporation Division Preparation Company)), which partially succeeded four businesses--railway, real estate, leisure and commodity distribution--from the former Hankyu Corporation, ii) Hankyu Hotel Management, which controls the hotel business, and iii) Hankyu Travel International Co., Ltd., for tour business, amalgamating two direct subsidiaries; moreover, the former Hankyu Railway was transferred to the company Hankyu Holdings (currently Hankyu Hanshin Holdings, Inc.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To finalize the restructuring, on April 1, 2005 the company was reorganized into three companies: i) New Hankyu Corporation (the corporate name was changed from Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (Hankyu Corporation Division Preparation Company)), which partially succeeded four businesses--railway, real estate, leisure and commodity distribution--from the former Hankyu Corporation, ii) Hankyu Hotel Management, which controls the hotel business, and iii) Hankyu Travel International Co., Ltd., for tour business, amalgamating two direct subsidiaries; moreover, the former Hankyu Railway was transferred to the company Hankyu Holdings (currently Hankyu Hanshin Holdings, Inc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>なお、2007年10月19日に創業100年を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation cerebrated the centennial anniversary on October 19, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Corporation celebrated its centennial anniversary on October 19, 2007.</e>
<cmt>spell, gram</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation celebrated its centennial anniversary on October 19, 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>1906年（明治39年）1月15日 箕面有馬電気鉄道創立発起人会設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 15, 1906: Organizing Committee of Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline was established.</e>
<cmt>箕面有馬電気鉄道創立発起人会→定訳不明：Organizing Committee of Minoo-Arima Electric Tramlineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 15, 1906: The organizing committee of Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline was established.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 15, 1906: The organizing committee of Mino-Arima Electric Tramline (Mino-Arima denki tetsudo) was established.</e>
<cmt>次の文との関係で、電気鉄道の読みを入れました。Minoo →Mino</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>1907年（明治40年）6月1日 箕面有馬電気軌道に社名変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 1, 1907: The name was changed to Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline.</e>
<cmt>箕面有馬電気軌道→ Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline　（ｈｔｔｐ://books.google.co.jp/books?id=ny52xS9)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 1, 1907: The name was changed to Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 1, 1907: The name was changed to Mino-Arima Electric Tramline (Mino-Arima denki kido).</e>
<cmt>電気軌道の読みを入れました。Minoo →Mino</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>1907年（明治40年）10月19日 箕面有馬電気軌道創立総会。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 19, 1907: The inaugural general meeting of Minoo-Arima Electric Tramway Company was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 19, 1907: The inaugural general meeting of Minoo-Arima Electric Tramway Company was held.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 19, 1907: The inaugural general meeting of Mino-Arima Electric Tramway Company was held.</e>
<cmt>Minoo →Mino</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>1909年（明治42年）9月25日 新淀川橋梁が竣工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 25, 1909: Shin-Yodogawa Bridge was completed.</e>
<cmt>新淀川橋梁→Shin-Yodogawa Bridge (用語リスト#3747）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 25, 1909: Shin-Yodogawa Bridge was completed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 25, 1909: Shin-Yodogawa Bridge was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>1910年（明治43年）3月10日 宝塚本線梅田～宝塚間、箕面線石橋～箕面間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 10, 1910: The Takarazuka line between Umeda and Takarazuka, and the Minoo Line between Ishibashi and Minoo began the operation..</e>
<cmt>宝塚本線→Takarazuka Line (Main）なし、としました。以下同じ</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 10, 1910: The Takarazuka line between Umeda and Takarazuka, as well as the Minoo Line between Ishibashi and Minoo, went into operation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 10, 1910: The Takarazuka line between Umeda and Takarazuka, as well as the Mino Line between Ishibashi and Mino, went into operation.</e>
<cmt>Minoo →Mino</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>1911年（明治44年）5月1日 宝塚新温泉（後の宝塚ファミリーランド）が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 1, 1911: Takarazuka New Hot Spring (later Takarazuka Family Land) was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 1, 1911: Takarazuka New Hot Spring (later Takarazuka Family Land) was opened.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 1, 1911: Takarazuka New Hot Spring (later Takarazuka Family Land) was opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>1913年（大正2年）7月1日 宝塚唱歌隊（現在の宝塚歌劇団）を組織。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 1, 1913: Takarazuka Chorus Group (current Takarazuka Revue Company) was organized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 1, 1913: The Takarazuka Chorus Group (current Takarazuka Revue Company) was organized.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 1, 1913: The Takarazuka Chorus Group (current Takarazuka Revue Company) was organized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>1918年（大正7年）2月4日 阪神急行電鉄に社名変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 4, 1918: The name was changed to Hanshin Kyuko Railway Company.</e>
<cmt>阪神急行電鉄→Hanshin Electric Express Railway (http://www.jtr.net/jtr08/history.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 4, 1918: The name was changed to Hanshin Kyuko Railway Company.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 4, 1918: The name was changed to Hanshin Electric Express Railway.</e>
<cmt>Hanshin Electric Express Railway としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>1920年（大正9年）7月16日 神戸本線 十三～神戸（後の上筒井）間、伊丹線が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 16, 1920: the Kobe Line between Juso and Kobe (later Kamitsutsui), and the Itami Line were opened.</e>
<cmt>Kobe Line (Main）なし、としました。以下同じ</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 16, 1920: The Kobe Line between Juso and Kobe (later Kamitsutsui) was opened, along with the Itami Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 16, 1920: The Kobe Line between Juso and Kobe (later Kamitsutsui) was opened, along with the Itami Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>1921年（大正10年）4月1日 北大阪電気鉄道（1923年に新京阪鉄道へ事業譲渡）により、十三～豊津間（現在の京都本線・千里線の一部）が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1921: Kita-Osaka Electric Railway (the business was transferred to Shinkeihan Railway in 1923) opened the section between Juso and Toyotsu (a part of the current Kyoto Line and Senri Line).</e>
<cmt>北大阪電気鉄道→、新京阪鉄道→定訳不明：Shinkeihan Railway</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1921: The Kita-Osaka Electric Railway (the business was transferred to Shinkeihan Railway in 1923) opened the section between Juso and Toyotsu (a part of the current Kyoto Line and Senri Line).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1921: The Kita-Osaka Electric Railway (the business was transferred to Shinkeihan Railway in 1923) opened the section between Juso and Toyotsu (a part of the current Kyoto Line and Senri Line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>1921年（大正10年）9月2日 西宝線宝塚～西宮北口間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 2, 1921: The Saiho Line began operating between Takarazuka and Nishinomiya-kitaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 2, 1921: The Saiho Line began operating between Takarazuka and Nishinomiya-kitaguchi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 2, 1921: The Saiho Line began operating between Takarazuka and Nishinomiya-kitaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="40">
<j>1924年（大正13年）10月1日 甲陽線が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1924: The Koyo Line was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1924: The Koyo Line was opened.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1924: The Koyo Line was opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="41">
<j>1925年（大正14年）6月1日 梅田阪急ビル（旧館）に阪急マーケットが開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 1, 1925: Hankyu Market was opened in Umeda Hankyu Building (old wing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 1, 1925: Hankyu Market was opened in the Umeda Hankyu Building (the old wing).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 1, 1925: Hankyu Market was opened in the Umeda Hankyu Building (the old wing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="42">
<j>1925年（大正14年）10月15日 新京阪鉄道（1930年に京阪電気鉄道へ合併）により天神橋～淡路間（現在の千里線の一部）が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 15, 1925: Shinkeihan Railway (incorporated into Keihan Electric Railway in 1930) opened the section between Tenjinbashi and Awaji (a part of the current Senri Line).</e>
<cmt>新京阪鉄道→定訳不明：Shinkeihan Railway、京阪電気鉄道→Keihan Electric Railway (http:://keihan.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 15, 1925: Shinkeihan Railway (incorporated into Keihan Electric Railway in 1930) opened the section between Tenjinbashi and Awaji (a part of the current Senri Line).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 15, 1925: Shinkeihan Railway (incorporated into Keihan Electric Railway in 1930) opened the section between Tenjinbashi and Awaji (a part of the current Senri Line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="43">
<j>1926年（大正15年）7月5日 梅田～十三間が高架複々線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 5, 1926: Quadruple tracks were introduced in the section between Umeda and Juso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 5, 1926: Quadruple tracks were introduced in the section between Umeda and Juso.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 5, 1926: Elevated quadruple tracks were introduced in the section between Umeda and Juso.</e>
<cmt>elevatedを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>旧線は阪急北野線となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old line became the Hankyu Kitano Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old line became the Hankyu Kitano Line.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old line became the Hankyu Kitano Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="45">
<j>1926年（大正15年）12月18日 西宝線が全通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 18, 1926: The whole section of the Saiho Line was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 18, 1926: The entire section of the Saiho Line was opened.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 18, 1926: The entire section of the Saiho Line was opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>今津線に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name was changed to the Imazu Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name was changed to the Imazu Line.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name was changed to the Imazu Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="47">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）1月16日 新京阪鉄道により淡路～高槻町（現在の高槻市）間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 16, 1928: Shinkeihan Railway opened the section between Awaji and Takatsuki-cho (current Takatsuki City).</e>
<cmt>新京阪鉄道→定訳不明：Shinkeihan Railway</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 16, 1928: The Shinkeihan Railway opened the section between Awaji and Takatsuki-cho (current Takatsuki City).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 16, 1928: The Shinkeihan Railway opened the section between Awaji and Takatsuki-cho (current Takatsuki City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="48">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）11月1日 新京阪鉄道により高槻町～西院間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 1, 1928: Shinkeihan Railway opened the section between Takatsuki-cho and Saiin.</e>
<cmt>新京阪鉄道→定訳不明：Shinkeihan Railway</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 1, 1928: The Shinkeihan Railway opened the section between Takatsuki-cho and Saiin.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 1, 1928: The Shinkeihan Railway opened the section between Takatsuki-cho and Saiin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="49">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）11月9日 新京阪鉄道により嵐山線が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 9, 1928: Shinkeihan Railway opened the Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>新京阪鉄道→定訳不明：Shinkeihan Railway</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 9, 1928: The Shinkeihan Railway opened the Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 9, 1928: The Shinkeihan Railway opened the Arashiyama Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="50">
<j>1929年（昭和4年）4月15日 梅田駅に阪急百貨店が開店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 15, 1929: Hankyu Department Store was opened at Umeda Station.</e>
<cmt>阪急百貨店→Hankyu Department Store (用語リスト#3747）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 15, 1929: The Hankyu Department Store was opened at Umeda Station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 15, 1929: The Hankyu Department Store was opened at Umeda Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="51">
<j>1931年（昭和6年）3月31日 京阪電気鉄道により新京阪線西院～京阪京都（現在の大宮）間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 31, 1931: Keihan Electric Railway began the operation of the Shin Keihan Line between Saiin and Keihan Kyoto (current Omiya Station).</e>
<cmt>京阪電気鉄道→Keihan Electric Railway (http://www.keihan.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 31, 1931: The Keihan Electric Railway began the operation of the Shin Keihan Line between Saiin and Keihan Kyoto (current Omiya Station).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 31, 1931: The Keihan Electric Railway started operating the Shinkeihan Line between Saiin and Keihan Kyoto (current Omiya Station).</e>
<cmt>Shinkeihan Lineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="52">
<j>1932年（昭和7年）8月 演劇、映画の興行を主たる目的として、東京宝塚劇場（現在の東宝）を設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August, 1932: Tokyo Takarazuka Theater (current Toho Co., Ltd.) was established to promote theatrical performance and movie pictures.</e>
<cmt>東京宝塚劇場（現在の東宝）→Tokyo Takarazuka Theater (current Toho Co., Ltd.) (http://www.toho.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August, 1932: The Tokyo Takarazuka Theater (currently Toho Co., Ltd.) was established to promote theatrical performance and motion pictures.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August, 1932: The Tokyo Takarazuka Theater (currently Toho Co., Ltd.) was established to promote theatrical performance and motion pictures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="53">
<j>1936年（昭和11年）4月1日 神戸本線西灘（現在の王子公園）～神戸（現在の三宮）間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1936: The Kobe Line between Nishinada (present Oji-koen Station) and Kobe (present Sannomiya Station) was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1936: The Kobe Line between Nishinada (presently Oji-koen Station) and Kobe (presently Sannomiya Station) was opened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1936: The Kobe Line between Nishinada (presently Oji-koen Station) and Kobe (presently Sannomiya Station) was opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>西灘～上筒井間は上筒井線となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section between Nishinada and Kamitustusi became the Kamitsutsui Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section between Nishinada and Kamitustusi became the Kamitsutsui Line.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section between Nishinada and Kamitustusi became the Kamitsutsui Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="55">
<j>1940年（昭和15年）5月20日 上筒井線を廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 20, 1940: The Kamitsutsui Line was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 20, 1940: The Kamitsutsui Line was abolished.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 20, 1940: The Kamitsutsui Line was abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="56">
<j>1943年（昭和18年）10月1日 阪神急行電鉄が京阪電気鉄道を合併、京阪神急行電鉄となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1943: Hanshin Electric Express Railway swallowed Keihan Electric Railway, and became Keihanshin Electric Express Railway.</e>
<cmt>阪神急行電鉄→Hanshin Electric Express Railway (http://www.jtr.net/jtr08/history.html)、京阪電気鉄道→Keihan Electric Railway (http://www.keihan.co.jp)、京阪神急行電鉄→定訳不明：Keihanshin Electric Express Railway</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1943: The Hanshin Electric Express Railway swallowed the Keihan Electric Railway and became the Keihanshin Electric Express Railway.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1943: The Hanshin Electric Express Railway swallowed the Keihan Electric Railway and became the Keihanshin Electric Express Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="57">
<j>1945年（昭和20年）5月1日 交野電気鉄道の事業を譲り受け、交野線とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 1, 1945: The company took over the business of Katano Electric Railway, and began the operation of the Katano Line.</e>
<cmt>交野電気鉄道→定訳不明：Katano Electric Railwayとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 1, 1945: The company took over the business of Katano Electric Railway and began operating the Katano Line.</e>
<cmt>cleaner</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 1, 1945: The company took over the business of Katano Electric Railway and began operating the Katano Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="58">
<j>1946年（昭和21年）11月20日 生産部を日興殖産株式会社（現・阪急産業株式会社）として分社化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 20, 1946: The production department was separated as Nikko Shokusan KK (current Hankyu Sangyo Co., Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>日興殖産株式会社→定訳不明：Nikko Shokusan KKとしました、阪急産業→Hankyu Sangyo (http://www.hsangyo.co.jp/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 20, 1946: The production department was separated as Nikko Shokusan KK (currently Hankyu Sangyo Co., Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 20, 1946: The production department was separated as Nikko Shokusan KK (currently Hankyu Sangyo Co., Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="59">
<j>1949年（昭和24年）1月1日 北野線を休止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 1, 1949: The operation of the Kitano Line was suspended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 1, 1949: The operation of the Kitano Line was suspended.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 1, 1949: The operation of the Kitano Line was suspended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="60">
<j>1949年（昭和24年）12月1日 京阪線・交野線・宇治線・京津線・石山坂本線を京阪電気鉄道（新）として分離。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1, 1949: The Keihan Line, Katano Line, Uji Line, Keishin Line, and Ishiyama-Sakamoto Line were split off to form (New) Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>京阪電気鉄道→Keihan Electric Railway (http://www.keihan.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1, 1949: The Keihan, Katano, Uji, Keishin and Ishiyama-Sakamoto lines were split off to form the (New) Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>cleaner, gram</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1, 1949: The Keihan, Katano, Uji, Keishin and Ishiyama-Sakamoto lines were split off to form the (New) Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>新京阪線を京都本線に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinkeihan Line changed its name to Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinkeihan Line changed its name to the Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinkeihan Line changed its name to the Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="62">
<j>1959年（昭和34年）2月18日 梅田～十三間が3複線化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 18, 1959: The section between Umeda and Juso was installed with 3 tracks in both direction.</e>
<cmt>3複線化→定訳不明： 3 tracks in both directionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 18, 1959: The section between Umeda and Juso was installed with three tracks in each of the two directions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 18, 1959: The section between Umeda and Juso was installed with three tracks in each of the two directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="63">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）6月17日 京都本線大宮～河原町間が開業し、十三～河原町間が全通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 17, 1963: The Kyoto Line began full operation between Juso and Kawaramachi, with opening of the section between Omiya and Kawaramachi,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 17, 1963: The Kyoto Line began full operation between Juso and Kawaramachi with the opening of the section between Omiya and Kawaramachi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 17, 1963: The Kyoto Line began full operation between Juso and Kawaramachi with the opening of the section between Omiya and Kawaramachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="64">
<j>1967年（昭和42年）3月1日 千里山線が千里線に改称、北千里駅まで開通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 1, 1967: The Senriyama Line changed its name to Senri Line, and extended the opeartion to Kita-Senri Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 1, 1967: The Senriyama Line changed its name to the Senri Line and extended the operation to Kita-Senri Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1, 1967: The Senriyama Line changed its name to the Senri Line and extended the operation to Kita-Senri Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>北千里駅に日本初の本格的な自動改札機設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Kita-Senri Station, the full-scale automatic ticket wicket was installed for the first time in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A full-scale automatic ticket wicket was installed for the first time in Japan at Kita-Senri Station.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A full-scale automatic ticket wicket was installed for the first time in Japan at Kita-Senri Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="66">
<j>1968年（昭和43年）4月7日 神戸本線が神戸高速鉄道・山陽電気鉄道と相互直通運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 7, 1968: Kobe Line started the mutual direct operation with Kobe Rapid Transit Railway and Sanyo Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>神戸高速鉄道→Kobe Rapid Transit Railway (http://www.kobe-kousoku.jp/index.html)、山陽電気鉄道→Sanyo Electric Railway(http://www.sanyo-railway.co.jp/index.html).</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 7, 1968: The Kobe Line started mutual direct operations with Kobe Rapid Transit Railway and Sanyo Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 7, 1968: The Kobe Line started mutual direct operations with Kobe Rapid Transit Railway and Sanyo Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="67">
<j>1969年（昭和44年）12月6日 千里線・京都本線が大阪市営地下鉄堺筋線と相互直通運転開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 6, 1969: The Senri Line and the Kyoto Line started the mutual direct operation with Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line.</e>
<cmt>大阪市営地下鉄堺筋線→定訳不明：Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line　（大阪市HP(http://www.kotsu.city.osaka.jp/foreign/english/subway/index.html) ではOsaka&apos;s Subway Sakaisuji Lineとなっていますが、京都市営地下鉄（Kyoto City Subway)に合わせ、Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Lineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 6, 1969: The Senri and Kyoto lines started mutual direct operations with Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 6, 1969: The Senri and Kyoto lines started mutual direct operations with Osaka Municipal Subway Sakaisuji Line.</e>
<cmt>city →municipal　としました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="68">
<j>1973年（昭和48年）4月1日 阪急電鉄に社名変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1973: The company changed its name to Hankyu Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1973: The company changed its name to Hankyu Corporation.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1973: The company changed its name to Hankyu Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="69">
<j>1973年（昭和48年）11月23日 梅田駅の移転拡張工事が完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 23, 1973: Umeda Station&apos;s relocation and expansion work was finished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 23, 1973: Umeda Station&apos;s relocation/expansion work was finished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 23, 1973: Umeda Station&apos;s relocation/expansion work was finished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="70">
<j>1988年（昭和63年）10月31日 オリックス・バファローズをオリエント・リース（現オリックス (企業)）に譲渡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 31, 1988: Orix Buffaloes was transferred to Orient Leasing Co., Ltd. (present Orix Corporation)</e>
<cmt>オリックス・バファローズ→Orix Buffaloes(http://www.buffaloes.co.jp)、オリエント・リース（現オリックス (企業)）→Orient Leasing Co., Ltd. (Orix Corporation) (http://www.orix.co.jp/grp/co_e/history.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 31, 1988: The Orix Buffaloes baseball team was transferred to Orient Leasing Co., Ltd. (presently Orix Corporation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 31, 1988: The Orix Buffaloes baseball team was transferred to Orient Leasing Co., Ltd. (currently ORIX Corporation).</e>
<cmt>Orix→ ORIX</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="71">
<j>1989年（平成元年）4月1日 プリペイドカード「ラガールカード」導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1989: Prepaid card, Lagare Card was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1989: The Lagare Card prepaid card was introduced.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1989: The &apos;Lagare Card&apos; prepaid card was introduced.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="72">
<j>1989年（平成元年）12月7日 分社・持株会社化の準備のための完全子会社・阪急電鉄分割準備株式会社（現阪急電鉄）の登記上の設立年月日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 7, 1989: Registered date of the foundation of &quot;Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (Hankyu Dentetsu division preparation company), &quot;a complete subsidiary set up with the purpose of preparing Hankyu&apos;s split-up and making it a holding company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 7, 1989 was the registered date of the foundation of &quot;Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (Hankyu Dentetsu division preparation company), &quot;a complete subsidiary set up in order to prepare Hankyu&apos;s split-up and make it a holding company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 7, 1989 was the registered date of the foundation of Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (Hankyu Dentetsu Division Preparation Company), a complete subsidiary set up in order to prepare for Hankyu&apos;s split-up and make it a holding company.</e>
<cmt>Division Preparation Company 前出箇所と統一して頭文字を大文字にしました。括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="73">
<j>1992年（平成4年）4月1日 ストアードフェアシステム「ラガールスルー」開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1992: Stored fare system, &quot;Lagare Thru&quot; was launched.</e>
<cmt>「ラガールスルー」→定訳不明： &quot;Lagare Thru&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1992: The &quot;Lagare Thru&quot; stored fare system was launched.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1992: The &apos;Lagare Thru&apos; stored-fare system was launched.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="74">
<j>1994年（平成6年）9月1日 日本初の不正乗車防止システム「フェアライドシステム」を導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 1, 1994: &quot;Faire-Ride System&quot; was introduced, as the first Illegal ride protection system in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 1, 1994: The &quot;Faire-Ride System&quot; was introduced as the first Illegal ride protection system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1, 1994: The &apos;Fair-Ride System&apos; was introduced as the first illegal-ride protection system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Fairとしました。括弧修正Illegal → illegal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="75">
<j>1995年（平成7年）1月17日 阪神・淡路大震災で各線に被害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 17, 1995: The Great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake caused damages to various lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 17, 1995: The Great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake caused damage to various lines.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 17, 1995: The Great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake caused damage to various lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>同年1月23日までに京都本線、宝塚本線、神戸本線の一部などで運転再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By January 23 of the same year, the Kyoto Line, Takarazuka Line and a part of the Kobe Line restarted the operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By January 23 of the same year, the Kyoto Line, Takarazuka Line and a part of the Kobe Line restarted their operations.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By January 23 of the same year, the Kyoto Line, Takarazuka Line and a part of the Kobe Line restarted their operations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="77">
<j>1995年（平成7年）2月5日 今津線が全線復旧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 5, 1995: The Imazu Line was restored completely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 5, 1995: The Imazu Line was completely restored.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 5, 1995: The Imazu Line was completely restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="78">
<j>1995年（平成7年）3月1日 甲陽線が全線復旧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 1, 1995: The Koyo Line was restored completely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 1, 1995: The Koyo Line was completely restored.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1, 1995: The Koyo Line was completely restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="79">
<j>1995年（平成7年）3月11日 伊丹線が新伊丹～伊丹（仮駅）間で運行再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 11, 1995: The Itami Line restarted the operation between Shin-Itami and Itami (with the provisional station building).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 11, 1995: The Itami Line restarted the operation between Shin-Itami and Itami (with the provisional station building).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 11, 1995: The Itami Line restarted the operation between Shin-Itami and Itami (with the provisional station building).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="80">
<j>1995年（平成7年）6月12日 神戸本線が全線復旧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 12, 1995: The Kobe Line was restored in the whole section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 12, 1995: The Kobe Line was restored in the entire section.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 12, 1995: The Kobe Line was restored in the entire section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="81">
<j>1996年（平成8年）1月1日 「ジェントルサウンドサービス」の一環として、駅・車内での案内を変更（詳細は特記事項参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 1, 1996: As a part of &quot;Gentle Sound Service,&quot; the contents of the announcement at stations and trains were changed (for details, please refer to the &quot;Special comments&quot;)</e>
<cmt>特記事項→Special commentsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 1, 1996: As a part of &quot;Gentle Sound Service,&quot; the contents of the announcement at stations and trains were changed (for details, please refer to &quot;Special Comments&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 1, 1996: As a part of &apos;Gentle Sound Service,&apos; the contents of the announcements at stations and trains were changed (for details, please refer to Special Comments).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="82">
<j>1996年（平成8年）3月20日 「ラガールスルー」を改良した関西圏の共通乗車カードシステム「スルッとKANSAI」開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 20, 1996: The common travel card &quot;KANSAI THRU PASS&quot; in Kansai District became available, which is a improved system of &quot;Lagare Thru.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「ラガールスルー」→Lagare Thru、「スルッとKANSAI」→KANSAI THRU PASS</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 20, 1996: The common travel card &quot;KANSAI THRU PASS&quot; in Kansai District became available as an improved system of &quot;Lagare Thru.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 20, 1996: The common travel card &apos;KANSAI THRU PASS&apos; in the Kansai District became available as an improved system of &apos;Lagare Thru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="83">
<j>1997年（平成9年）11月17日 宝塚本線で能勢電鉄日生中央駅まで乗り入れを行う直通特急日生エクスプレスの運転を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 17, 1997: Operation of Nissei Express began to Nose Electric Railway Nissei-chuo Station on the Takarazuka Line, using the shared track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 17, 1997: Operation of the Nissei Express began to Nose Electric Railway Nissei-chuo Station on the Takarazuka Line, using the shared track.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 17, 1997: Operation of the Nissei Express began to Nose Electric Railway Nissei-chuo Station on the Takarazuka Line, using the shared track.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="84">
<j>1998年（平成10年）2月15日 山陽電気鉄道との相互直通運転を中止、神戸本線は新開地駅までの運転に。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 15, 1998: Mutual direct operation with Sanyo Electric Railway became discontinued, and the operation of the Kobe Line has limited to Shinkaichi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 15, 1998: Mutual direct operation with the Sanyo Electric Railway was discontinued, and the operation of the Kobe Line was limited to Shinkaichi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 15, 1998: Mutual direct operation with the Sanyo Electric Railway was discontinued, and the operation of the Kobe Line was limited to Shinkaichi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="85">
<j>1998年（平成10年）10月1日 今津（南）線、甲陽線でワンマン運転を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1998: The trains began running without conductors on board on the Imazu (south) Line and the Koyo Line.</e>
<cmt>今津（南）線→定訳不明：Imazu （south) Lineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1998: The trains began running without conductors aboard the Imazu (south) and Koyo lines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1998: The trains began running without conductors aboard the Imazu (south) and Koyo lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="86">
<j>1998年（平成10年）11月21日 伊丹駅本駅が完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 21, 1998: Itami Station Building (permanent building) was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 21, 1998: The Itami Station Building (the permanent structure) was completed.</e>
<cmt>article, better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 21, 1998: The Itami Station Building (the permanent structure) was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>伊丹（仮駅）～伊丹間は単線で運転再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Itami provisional station and Itami Station, the operation was restarted with a single-track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Itami provisional station and Itami Station, the operation was restarted with a single-track.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Itami provisional station and Itami Station, the operation was restarted with a single-track.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="88">
<j>1999年（平成11年）3月6日 伊丹（仮駅）～伊丹間が複線運転再開、震災から実に4年ぶりに完全復旧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 6, 1999: With the restart of double-track operation between Itami provisional station and Itami Station, full operation has been finally recovered after 4 years since the earthquake disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 6, 1999: With the restart of double-track operation between the Itami provisional station and Itami Station, full operation was finally recovered after four years since the earthquake disaster.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6, 1999: With the restart of double-track operation between the Itami provisional station and Itami Station, full operation was finally recovered after four years since the earthquake disaster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="89">
<j>1999年（平成11年）4月1日 全路線の全車両で優先席を廃止（全車両の全座席を優先座席化）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1999: The reserved priority seats for elderly or disabled persons was abolished in all cars on all lines (All seats of all cars became designated as priority seat.)</e>
<cmt>優先席→priority seat(s)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1999: The reserved priority seats for elderly or disabled persons was abolished in all cars on all lines (all seats of all cars became designated as priority seats).</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1999: The reserved priority seats for elderly or disabled persons were abolished in all cars on all lines (all seats of all cars became designated as priority seats).</e>
<cmt>was →were</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="90">
<j>2002年（平成14年）10月1日 京都本線で女性専用車両を2ヶ月間限定で試験導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 2002: Women-only train cars were experimentally introduced during two months on the Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>京都本線Kyoto Main Line?、女性専用→英辞郎WEB、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 2002: Women-only train cars were experimentally introduced over a period of two months on the Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 2002: Women-only train cars were experimentally introduced over a period of two months on the Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>阪急6300系電車の特急・通勤特急・快速特急のみに設定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The introduction of the women-only cars was limited to the limited express, commuter limited express and rapid limited express trains of Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series 6300.</e>
<cmt>阪急6300系→Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series 6300 (http://www.uraken.net/rail/chiho/hankyu/6300.html)、特急･通勤特急･快速特急→ともに limited express, commuter limited express and rapid limited express （http://www.rokko1go.jpn.org/main/photo/english/eng_jpnkind1.htm参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The introduction of the women-only cars was limited to the limited express, commuter limited express and rapid limited express trains of the Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series 6300.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The introduction of the women-only cars was limited to the limited express, commuter limited express and rapid limited express trains of the Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series 6300.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>同年12月2日から本格導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From February 2 of the same year, they are fully introduced in all trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From February 2 of the same year they were fully introduced in all trains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From February 2 of the same year they were fully introduced in all trains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="93">
<j>2003年（平成15年）6月10日 携帯電話の電源オフを終日ルールづけた車両「携帯電話 電源オフ車両」を全列車で試験的に導入（詳細は特記事項参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 10, 2003: The car named &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car,&quot; where the passengers are requested to switch off his mobil phone, was experimentally introduced in all trains (for details, please refer to &quot;special comments&quot;)</e>
<cmt>「携帯電話電源オフ車両」→定訳不明：&quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car&quot;としました、特記事項→定訳不明：special commentsとしましたが、注釈ならnotes/remarks</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 10, 2003: The car named &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car,&quot; where the passengers are requested to switch off their mobile phones, was experimentally introduced in all trains (for details, please refer to &quot;Special Comments&quot;).</e>
<cmt>add a period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 10, 2003: The car named &apos;Mobile Phone Power Source Off Car,&apos; where the passengers are requested to switch off their mobile phones, was experimentally introduced on all trains (for details, please refer to Special Comments).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正Mobil→ Mobile</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>7月11日から本格導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This rule was introduced in all cars from July 11.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This rule was introduced in all cars from July 11.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This rule was fully introduced for all cars from July 11.</e>
<cmt>「本格」を訳出。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="95">
<j>2004年（平成16年）8月1日 非接触型ICカードPiTaPaによる乗車サービスを開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1, 2004: Boarding service with a non-contact type IC card, PiTiPa, started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1, 2004: Boarding service with a non-contact type IC card, the PiTiPa, started.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 2004: Boarding service with a non-contact type IC card, the PiTaPa, started.</e>
<cmt>PiTaPaにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>STACIAカード発行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">STACIA Card was issued</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The STACIA Card was issued</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The STACIA Card was issued.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="97">
<j>2005年（平成17年）4月1日 阪急電鉄・阪急ホテルマネジメント・阪急交通社の各社を直轄する持株会社阪急ホールディングスに移行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 2005: The company was transferred to a holding company, Hankyu Holdings, which directly controls Hankyu Corporation, Hankyu Hotel Management, and Hankyu Travel International</e>
<cmt>阪急電鉄→会社名Hankyu Corporation使用（Hankyu Railwayではなく）、阪急ホテルマネジメント→Hanshin Hotel Management (http://hankyu-hotal.com/group/management.html)、阪急ホールディングス→Hankyu Holdings (http://holdings.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 2005: The company was transferred to a holding company, Hankyu Holdings, which directly controls Hankyu Corporation, Hankyu Hotel Management and Hankyu Travel International</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 2005: The company was transferred to a holding company, Hankyu Holdings, which directly controls Hankyu Corporation, Hankyu Hotel Management and Hankyu Travel International.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>同日付けで鉄道・不動産等の事業は会社分割によって阪急電鉄分割準備（株）（休眠子会社の株式会社アクトシステムズ＝1989年12月7日設立を2004年3月29日付で社名変更）に承継させた上で同社を阪急電鉄に改称、旧阪急電鉄を阪急ホールディングスに改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same date, the company was split off and the businesses such as railway and real estate are succeeded by Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (= a defunct subsidiary called KK Act Systems, which was founded on December 7, 1989, and changed the name on March 29, 2004), and then, Bunkatsu Junbi KK changed the corporate name to Hankyu Corporation and the former Hankyu Railway to Hankyu Holdings, respectively.</e>
<cmt>阪急ホールディングス→Hankyu Holdings (http://holdings.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/index.html)、株式会社悪とシステムズ→定訳不明：KK Act Systemsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same date the company was split off and the businesses such as railway and real estate were succeeded by Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (= a now-defunct subsidiary called KK Act Systems, which was founded on December 7, 1989, and changed the name on March 29, 2004), after which the corporate name of Bunkatsu Junbi KK was changed to Hankyu Corporation and the former Hankyu Railway to Hankyu Holdings, respectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same date, the company was split off and the businesses such as railway and real estate were succeeded by Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK (= a now-defunct subsidiary called KK Act Systems, which was founded on December 7, 1989, and changed the name on March 29, 2004), after which the corporate name of Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK was changed to Hankyu Corporation and the former Hankyu Railway to Hankyu Holdings, respectively.</e>
<cmt>2回目に出てくる準備会社の表記を、Hankyu Dentetsu Bunkatsu Junbi KK　としました（Hankyu Dentetsuを追加）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="99">
<j>2006年（平成18年）1月21日 西日本旅客鉄道のICOCAで鉄道路線が利用可能になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 21, 2006: ICOCS, a transportation card of West Japan Railway became accepted on the Hankyu lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 21, 2006: ICOCS, a transportation card of West Japan Railway, became accepted on the Hankyu lines.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 21, 2006: ICOCA, a transportation card of West Japan Railway, became accepted on the Hankyu lines.</e>
<cmt>ICOCS→ ICOCA</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="100">
<j>2006年（平成18年）7月1日 PiTaPa対応カードを用いた「IC定期券サービス（PiTaPa交通料金割引）」を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 1, 2006: &quot;IC commuter ticket service (PiTaPa commutation fare discount)&quot; that permits using the compatible cards with PiTaPa started.</e>
<cmt>PiTaPa対応カード→定訳不明：compatible card with PiTaPa</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 1, 2006: &quot;IC commuter ticket service (PiTaPa commutation fare discount),&quot; which permits the use of compatible cards with PiTaPa, was launched.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 1, 2006: &apos;IC commuter ticket service (PiTaPa commutation fare discount),&apos; which permits the use of compatible cards with PiTaPa, was launched.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="101">
<j>2006年（平成18年）10月1日 親会社の阪急ホールディングスが阪神電気鉄道との経営統合に伴い阪急阪神ホールディングスに社名変更（詳細は阪急・阪神経営統合を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 2006: When Hankyu Holdings swallowed Hanshin Electric Railway, the holdings&apos; name was changed to Hankyu Hanshin Holdings Inc. (for details please see &quot;Business merger of Hankyu and Hanshin&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 2006: When Hankyu Holdings swallowed Hanshin Electric Railway, the holdings&apos; name was changed to Hankyu Hanshin Holdings Inc. (for details please see &quot;Business Merger of Hankyu and Hanshin&quot;).</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 2006: When the parent company, Hankyu Holdings, swallowed Hanshin Electric Railway, the holding company&apos;s name was changed to Hankyu Hanshin Holdings Inc. (for details please see &quot;Business Merger of Hankyu and Hanshin&quot;).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 parent company追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="102">
<j>2007年（平成19年）10月1日 HANA PLUSカードに代わり、STACIAカード発行開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 2007: STACIA card started to be issued, replacing HANA PLUS card.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 2007: Issuance of the STACIA card began, replacing the HANA PLUS card.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 2007: Issuance of the STACIA card began, replacing the HANA PLUS card.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="103">
<j>2007年（平成19年）10月19日 創立100周年を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 19, 2007: The company celebrated its 100th anniversary of foundation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 19, 2007: The company celebrated the 100th anniversary of its founding.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 19, 2007: The company celebrated the 100th anniversary of its founding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="104">
<j>2007年（平成19年）10月29日 全路線の全車両に優先席を再設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 29, 2007: the reserved priority seats were designated again in all cars on all lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 29, 2007: The reserved priority seats were designated again in all cars on all lines.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 29, 2007: The reserved priority seats were designated again in all cars on all lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>合わせて携帯電話電源オフ車両の場所を一部変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, some of the cars, where mobil phones should have been switched off, underwent a modification of the place where the rule was applied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concurrently, some of the cars, where mobile phones should have been switched off, underwent a modification of the place where the rule was applied.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concurrently, some of the cars, where mobile phones should have been switched off, underwent a modification of the place where the rule was applied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lines</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>大きく神戸線・宝塚線・京都線の3つに分けられ、それぞれに本線とそれに付随する支線を有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The railway is roughly divided into 3 lines: Kobe Line, Takarazuka Line, and Kyoto Line and, each line consist of the main line and feeder lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railway is generally divided into three lines--the Kobe, the Takarazuka and the Kyoto--each of which consists of a main line and feeder lines.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The railway is generally divided into three lines--the Kobe, the Takarazuka and the Kyoto--each of which consists of a main line and feeder lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>また、神戸線と宝塚線は、車両をほとんど共有している（詳細は車両）ことから、まとめて「神宝線」と呼称されることがある（かつて軌道法に基づく路線であったことから「軌道線」とも呼称されたことがあった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kobe Line and the Takarazuka Line share almost all the cars (for details, see &quot;Rolling stock&quot;), sometimes they are correctively called &quot;Jinpo-sen&quot; taking the first letter of the both lines （once, they were also called &quot;Kido-sen&quot; or tramway ｌine).</e>
<cmt>「神宝線」→定訳不明：&quot;Jinpo-sen&quot; taking the first letter of the both lines、軌道線→定訳不明：Kido-sen &quot;tramway line)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobe Line and the Takarazuka Line share nearly all the cars (for details, see &quot;Rolling Stock&quot;); sometimes they are correctively called &quot;Jinpo-sen,&quot; taking the first letter of the both lines (but once they were also called &quot;Kido-sen,&quot; or the tramway line).</e>
<cmt>gram, cap</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobe Line and Takarazuka Line share nearly all the cars (for details, see &quot;Rolling Stock&quot;); sometimes they are collectively called &apos;Jinpo-sen,&apos; taking the first letter of both lines (but once they were also called &apos;Kido-sen,&apos; or the tramway line).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 correctively → collectively</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>日本の鉄道ラインカラー一覧は右の路線図のほか、ホームの発車番線、普通電車の行先表示板（各支線のみ）などに使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Color-codes of Railways in Japan&quot; is used not only in the diagram shown on the right, but also for the platform numbers and the destination boards of local trains (only feeder lines).</e>
<cmt>日本の鉄道ラインカラー一覧→定訳不明：&quot;Color-codes of Railways in Japan&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Color Codes of Railways in Japan&quot; is used not only in the diagram shown on the right but also for the platform numbers and the destination boards of local trains (only feeder lines).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Color Codes of Railways in Japan is used not only in the diagram shown on the right but also for the platform numbers and the destination boards of local trains (only feeder lines).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>一般的に本線系路線は「本」を略してそれぞれ神戸線・宝塚線・京都線と呼ぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, the main lines are often called omitting the word &quot;main,&quot; such as Kobe Line, Takarazuka Line, and Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, the main lines are often referred to with the work &quot;main&quot; omitted, as in the Kobe Line, Takarazuka Line and Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, the main lines are often referred to with the word &apos;main&apos; omitted, as in the Kobe Line, Takarazuka Line and Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>This was a typo. It should have said &quot;word&quot;.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="110">
<j>■神戸線 （ラインカラー：港町神戸の海からブルー）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Kobe Line (color-coded is blue from the blue sea of the port city, Kobe)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Kobe Line (color-coded in blue from the blue sea of the port city, Kobe)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Kobe Line (color-coded in blue from the blue sea of the port city, Kobe)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>阪急神戸本線 梅田駅 - 三宮駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Kobe Main Line: Umeda Station - Sannomiya Station</e>
<cmt>神戸本線→Kobe Main Line</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Kobe Main Line: Umeda Station - Sannomiya Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Kobe Main Line: Umeda Station - Sannomiya Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>神戸高速鉄道東西線 三宮 - 西代駅 （阪急が鉄道事業者第二種鉄道事業として列車を運行、神戸高速鉄道が鉄道事業者第三種鉄道事業として線路など施設を保有。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Tozai Line: Sannomiya Station - Nishidai Station (Hankyu operates as a &quot;Railway business entity: second class railway business,&quot; while Kobe Rapid Transit Railway possesses the railways and other facilities as a &quot;Railway business entity: third class railway business.&quot;</e>
<cmt>鉄道事業者第二種鉄道事業→定訳不明：&quot;Railway business entity: second class railway business&quot;、鉄道事業者第三種鉄道事業→定訳不明：&quot;Railway business entity: third class railway business&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Tozai Line: Sannomiya Station - Nishidai Station (Hankyu operates as a &quot;railway business entity, second-class railway business,&quot; while Kobe Rapid Transit Railway possesses the railways and other facilities as a &quot;railway business entity, third-class railway business.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Tozai Line: Sannomiya Station - Nishidai Station (Hankyu operates as a railway business entity, second-class railway business, while Kobe Rapid Transit Railway possesses the railways and other facilities as a railway business entity, third-class railway business.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>但し列車の運転は三宮 - 新開地駅のみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, the trains are only operated between Sannomiya Station and Shinkaichi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the trains operate only between Sannomiya Station and Shinkaichi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the trains operate only between Sannomiya Station and Shinkaichi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="114">
<j>阪急伊丹線 塚口駅 (阪急) - 伊丹駅 (阪急)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Itami Line: Tukaguchi Station (Hankyu) - Itami Station (Hankyu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Itami Line: Tukaguchi Station (Hankyu) - Itami Station (Hankyu)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Itami Line: Tsukaguchi Station (Hankyu) - Itami Station (Hankyu)</e>
<cmt>Tukaguchi →Tsukaguchi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>阪急今津線 宝塚駅 - 今津駅 (兵庫県) （宝塚 - 西宮北口は今津北線、西宮北口 - 今津は今津南線と呼ばれる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Imazu Line: Takarazuka Station - Imazu Station (Hyogo Prefecture) (the section between Takarazuka and Nishinomiya-kitaguchi is called Imazu-kita (north) Line, and the section between Nishinomiya-kitaguchi and Imazu is called Imazu-minami (south) Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Imazu Line: Takarazuka Station - Imazu Station (Hyogo Prefecture) (the section between Takarazuka and Nishinomiya-kitaguchi is called the Imazu-kita (north) Line, and the section between Nishinomiya-kitaguchi and Imazu is called the Imazu-minami (south) Line).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Imazu Line: Takarazuka Station - Imazu Station (Hyogo Prefecture) (the section between Takarazuka and Nishinomiya-kitaguchi is called the Imazu-kita (north) Line, and the section between Nishinomiya-kitaguchi and Imazu is called the Imazu-minami (south) Line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>阪急甲陽線 夙川駅 - 甲陽園駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Koyo Line: Shukugawa Station - Koyoen Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Koyo Line: Shukugawa Station - Koyoen Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Koyo Line: Shukugawa Station - Koyoen Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>■宝塚線 （ラインカラー：箕面の紅葉からオレンジ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Takarazuka Line (Color-coded is orange from the autumn leaves in Minoo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Takarazuka Line (color-coded in orange to represent the autumn leaves in Minoo</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Takarazuka Line (color-coded in orange to represent the autumn leaves in Mino)</e>
<cmt>閉じ括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>阪急宝塚本線 梅田 - 宝塚駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Takarazuka Main Line: Umeda Station - Takarazuka Station</e>
<cmt>宝塚本線→Takarazuka Main Line</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Takarazuka Main Line: Umeda Station - Takarazuka Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Takarazuka Main Line: Umeda Station - Takarazuka Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>阪急箕面線 石橋駅 (大阪府) - 箕面駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Minoo Line: Ishibashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Minoo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Minoo Line: Ishibashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Minoo Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Mino Line: Ishibashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Mino Station</e>
<cmt>Minoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>■京都線 （ラインカラー：古都京都の木々からグリーン）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Kyoto Line (Color-coded is green from the trees of the ancient capital, Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Kyoto Line (color-coded in green for the trees of the ancient capital, Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Kyoto Line (color-coded in green for the trees of the ancient capital, Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>阪急京都本線 十三駅 - 河原町駅 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Kyoto Main Line: Juso Station - Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>京都本線→Kyoto Main Line</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Kyoto Main Line: Juso Station - Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Kyoto Main Line: Juso Station - Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>阪急千里線 天神橋筋六丁目駅 - 北千里駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Senri Line: Tenmabashisuji Rokuchome Station - Kita-Senri Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Senri Line: Tenmabashisuji Rokuchome Station - Kita-Senri Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Senri Line: Tenjinbashisuji-rokuchome Station - Kita-Senri Station</e>
<cmt>天神橋筋六丁目駅のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>阪急嵐山線 桂駅 - 嵐山駅 (阪急)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Arashiyama Line: Katsura Station - Arashiyama Station (Hankyu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Arashiyama Line: Katsura Station - Arashiyama Station (Hankyu)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Arashiyama Line: Katsura Station - Arashiyama Station (Hankyu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="124">
<j>廃線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discontinued lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discontinued lines</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discontinued lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>阪急北野線 梅田 - 北野駅 (大阪府) （1949年1月1日休止）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Kitano Line: Umeda Station - Kitano Station (Osaka Prefecture) (the operation was suspended on January 1, 1949).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Kitano Line: Umeda Station - Kitano Station (Osaka Prefecture) (the operation was suspended on January 1, 1949).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Kitano Line: Umeda Station - Kitano Station (Osaka Prefecture) (the operation was suspended on January 1, 1949).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>阪急上筒井線 王子公園駅 - 上筒井駅 （1940年5月20日廃止）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Kamitsutsui Line: Oji-koen Station - Kamitsutsui Station (the line became disused on May 20, 1940)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Kamitsutsui Line: Oji-koen Station - Kamitsutsui Station (the line was abandoned on May 20, 1940)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Kamitsutsui Line: Oji-koen Station - Kamitsutsui Station (the line was abandoned on May 20, 1940)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>他社譲渡路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lines transferred to other companies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lines transferred to other companies</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lines transferred to other companies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>京阪本線 天満橋駅 - 三条駅 (京都府) ほか</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Main Line: Tenmabashi Station - Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Main Line: Tenmabashi Station - Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture), etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Main Line: Tenmabashi Station - Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>京阪大津線 三条 - 浜大津駅 及び 石山寺駅 - 坂本駅 (滋賀県)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Otsu Line: Sanjo Station - Hamaotsu Station / Ishiyamadera Station - Sakamoto Station (Shiga Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Otsu Line: Sanjo Station - Hamaotsu Station / Ishiyamadera Station - Sakamoto Station (Shiga Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Otsu Line: Sanjo Station - Hamaotsu Station / Ishiyamadera Station - Sakamoto Station (Shiga Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>※いずれも、1949年に京阪神急行電鉄から分離発足した京阪電気鉄道へ譲渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*Both lines were transferred in 1949 from Keihanshin Electric Express Railway to Keihan Electric Railway, which was divided from Keihanshin Express Railway to form a new company.</e>
<cmt>京阪神急行電鉄→定訳不明：Keihanshin Electric Express Railwayと、阪神急行電鉄の訳Hanshin Electric Express Railway (http://www.jtr.net/jtr08/history.html)にあわせました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*Both lines were transferred in 1949 from the Keihanshin Electric Express Railway to the Keihan Electric Railway, which was divided from Keihanshin Express Railway to form a new company.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*Both lines were transferred in 1949 to the Keihan Electric Railway, which was divided from Keihanshin Electric Express Railway to form a new company.</e>
<cmt>重複と思われる箇所を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>詳しくは京阪電気鉄道路線の項を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, please refer to &quot;Lines of Keihan Electric Railway&quot;.</e>
<cmt>京阪電気鉄道→Keihan Electric Railway (http://www.keihan.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, please refer to &quot;Lines of Keihan Electric Railway.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, please refer to &quot;Lines of Keihan Electric Railway.&quot;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="132">
<j>計画線・未成線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Planned lines/ uncompleted lines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Planned lines, uncompleted lines</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Planned lines, uncompleted lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>阪急新大阪連絡線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Shin-Osaka Interurban Line</e>
<cmt>阪急新大阪連絡線→定訳不明：Hankyu Shin-Osaka Interurban Line</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Shin-Osaka Inter-urban Line</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Shin-Osaka Inter-urban Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>淡路駅 - 新大阪駅 - 十三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awaji Station - Shin-Osaka Station - Juso Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awaji Station - Shin-Osaka Station - Juso Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awaji Station - Shin-Osaka Station - Juso Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>新大阪 - 神崎川駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-Osaka Station - Kanzakigawa Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-Osaka Station - Kanzakigawa Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-Osaka Station - Kanzakigawa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>※いずれも1961年事業免許取得。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*Both route were granted the business license in 1961.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*A business license was granted for both routes in 1961.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*A business license was granted for both routes in 1961.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>ただし、新大阪 - 十三を除く区間（淡路 - 新大阪 と 新大阪 - 神崎川）は、2003年3月1日付けで事業免許廃止となった（新大阪駅構想を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the license was revoked on March 1, 2003, except for the section between Shin-Osaka Station and Juso Station (Awaji Station - Shin-Osaka Station / Shin-Osaka Station - Kanzakigawa) (please refer to &quot;Shin-Osaka Station Initiative&quot;).</e>
<cmt>新大阪駅構想→定訳不明：&quot;Shin-Osaka Station Initiative</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the license was revoked on March 1, 2003, except for the section between Shin-Osaka Station and Juso Station (Awaji Station - Shin-Osaka Station / Shin-Osaka Station - Kanzakigawa) (please refer to &quot;Shin-Osaka Station Initiative&quot;).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the license was revoked on March 1, 2003, except for the section between Shin-Osaka Station and Juso Station (Awaji Station - Shin-Osaka Station / Shin-Osaka Station - Kanzakigawa) (please refer to &quot;Shin-Osaka Station Initiative&quot;).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="138">
<j>阪急の路線にはトンネルがほとんど存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu lines have very few tunnels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hankyu lines have very few tunnels.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hankyu lines have very few tunnels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>工期と費用がかさみ、明治～大正時代の土木技術では危険が大きかったため、意図的にトンネル工事を避けたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because they were deliberately avoided, as the construction of tunnels was very costly and extremely dangerous with the civil engineering technology available in the Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because they were deliberately avoided, since the construction of tunnels was very costly and extremely dangerous with the civil engineering technology available during the Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because they were deliberately avoided, as the construction of tunnels was very costly, time consuming, and extremely dangerous with the civil engineering technology available during the Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>「工期」を訳出。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>宝塚線はトンネルを必要とするルートを避けた結果、カーブの多い路線となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takarazuka Line was constructed avoiding the routes that required tunneling, and as a result, it has many curves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takarazuka Line was constructed by avoiding routes that would have required tunneling, and as a result it has many curves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takarazuka Line was constructed by avoiding routes that would have required tunneling, and as a result it has many curves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>現在でもトンネルは第二種鉄道事業区間（神戸高速鉄道）を除くと全線で3か所しか存在せず、そのうち2か所は西院～河原町間と天六付近の地下線へ通じる入口で、出入口がある純粋なトンネルは千里線の千里トンネルただ一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even nowadays, there are only three tunnels in all lines except for the section designated as a &quot;second class railway business&quot; (Kobe Rapid Transit Railway), and moreover, two of them serve as an entrance toward a underground lane, one between Saiin and Kawaramachi and the other, near Tenroku, therefore, Senri Tunnel on the Senri Line is the only tunnel that genuinely has the beginning and end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even nowadays there are only three tunnels in all lines except for the section designated as a &quot;second-class railway business&quot; (Kobe Rapid Transit Railway), and moreover, two of them serve as an entrance toward a underground lane, one between Saiin and Kawaramachi and the other, near Tenroku; therefore, Senri Tunnel on the Senri Line is the only tunnel that actually has a beginning and an end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today there are only three tunnels in all lines except for the section designated as a second-class railway business (Kobe Rapid Transit Railway), and moreover, two of them serve as entrances toward underground lanes, one between Saiin and Kawaramachi and the other, near Tenroku; therefore, Senri Tunnel on the Senri Line is the only tunnel that in fact has a beginning and an end.</e>
<cmt>toward a →toward an 括弧修正&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>なお、直通運転を行っている能勢電鉄には数多くのトンネルがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nose Railway that offers the direct operation has many tunnels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nose Railway, which offers direct operation, has many tunnels.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nose Railway, which offers direct operation, has many tunnels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="143">
<j>阪神電気鉄道阪神西大阪線が近鉄難波駅まで開業する2009年以降は（開業後は阪神なんば線に改称）、関西では唯一大阪市中央区 (大阪市) に路線がない大手私鉄となる（但し京都線の車両自体は堺筋線を介して中央区に乗り入れているものもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 2009, when the Hanshin Nishi-Osaka Line of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd is extended to Kintetsu Namba Station (scheduled to be called Hanshin Namba Line after the inauguration), Hankyu Railway will be the only big private railway company in the Kansai District which has no line in the area of Chuo Ward, Osaka City (although, some of the trains on the Kyoto Line (Hankyu) go to Chuo Ward using the track of the Osaka City subway Sakaisuji Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 2009, when the Hanshin Nishi-Osaka Line of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. is extended to Kintetsu Namba Station (scheduled to be called the Hanshin Namba Line after its inauguration), the Hankyu Railway will be the only large private railway company in the Kansai District that has no line in the area of Chuo Ward, Osaka City (although some of the trains on the Kyoto Line (Hankyu) go to Chuo Ward by using the track of the Osaka City subway Sakaisuji Line).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 2009, when the Hanshin Nishi-Osaka Line of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. is extended to Kintetsu Nanba Station (which is scheduled to be called the Hanshin Nanba Line after its inauguration), the Hankyu Railway will be the only large private railway company in the Kansai District that has no line in the area of Chuo Ward, Osaka City (although some of the trains on the Kyoto Line (Hankyu) go to Chuo Ward by using the track of the Osaka Municipal Subway&apos;s Sakaisuji Line).</e>
<cmt>city →municipal Nanba　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>列車種別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of rolling stock</e>
<cmt>種別名称は用語リスト#3747(http://www.rokko1go.jpn.org/main/photo/english/eng_jpnkind1.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of rolling stock</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of rolling stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="144">
<j>詳しくは、各種別および各路線の記事を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, please refer to the section on each type and line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, please refer to the section on each type and line.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, please refer to the section on each type and line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="145">
<j>阪急電鉄において設定される列車種別は次の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trains operated by Hankyu Corporation are categorized as follows by types.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trains operated by Hankyu Corporation are categorized by type, as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trains operated by Hankyu Corporation are categorized by type, as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="146">
<j>特別急行列車・列車種別通勤種別・快速急行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited Express / by rolling stock type and commuter type / Rapid Express</e>
<cmt>列車種別通勤種別→定訳不明（意味も）：by rolling stock type and commuter type としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Limited Express; by rolling stock type and commuter type; rapid express</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limited Express; by rolling stock type and commuter type; rapid express</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="147">
<j>神戸線・京都線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Line / Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Line / Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Line / Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="148">
<j>日生エクスプレス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nissei Express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nissei Express</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nissei Express</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="149">
<j>宝塚線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takarazuka Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takarazuka Line</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takarazuka Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="150">
<j>急行列車・列車種別通勤種別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Express / by rolling stock type and commuter type</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Express; by rolling stock type and commuter type</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Express; by rolling stock type and commuter type</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="151">
<j>神戸線・宝塚線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Line / Takarazuka Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Line / Takarazuka Line</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Line / Takarazuka Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="152">
<j>準急列車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semi Express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Semi Express</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Semi Express</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="153">
<j>神戸線・今津線・宝塚線・京都線・千里線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Line / Imazu Line / Takatazuka Line / Senri Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Line / Imazu Line / Takatazuka Line / Senri Line</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Line / Imazu Line / Takatazuka Line / Senri Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="154">
<j>列車種別通勤種別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By rolling stock type and commuter type</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By rolling stock type and commuter type</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By rolling stock type and commuter type</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="155">
<j>宝塚線・箕面線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takarazuka Line / Minoo Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takarazuka Line / Minoo Line</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takarazuka Line / Mino Line</e>
<cmt>Minoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>列車種別の表示</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Description by rolling stock type</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Description by rolling stock type</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Description by rolling stock type</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="156">
<j>列車種別は先頭車両前面の通過標識灯や方向幕で識別できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The type of the rolling stock can be recognized by marker lights or a rollsign (destination blind) installed on the front surface of the lead vehicle.</e>
<cmt>通過標識灯→marker lights (http://www.trainweb.org/tubeprune/Maker light.htm#Marker Light)、方向幕→定訳不明：下記のHPを参照に、rollsign (destination blind)としました。(htpp://www/trainhistory.org/bsra/rollsign.html 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The type of rolling stock can be recognized by marker lights or a rollsign (destination blind) installed on the front surface of the lead vehicle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The type of rolling stock can be recognized by marker lights or a rollsign (destination blind) installed on the front surface of the lead vehicle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="157">
<j>通過標識灯の点灯パターンは以下の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The marker light patterns (Headcodes of marker lights) are as follows：</e>
<cmt>点灯パターン→headcodeｓ of marker lights（http://www.trainweb.org/tubeprune/Maker light.htm#Marker Light）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The marker light patterns (headcodes of marker lights) are as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The marker light patterns (headcodes of marker lights) are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="158">
<j>正面から見て両側が点灯 - 快速急行・通勤特急・特急日生エクスプレス・特急（団体・回送・試運転列車も含む）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seen head-on, lights on both side are lighted - Rapid Express/Commuter Limited Express/ Limited Nissei Express/ Limited Express (including group trains/ deadhead trains/ trial run trains)</e>
<cmt>団体列車→定訳不明：group tour train</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seen head-on, the lights on both sides are illuminated: Rapid Express, Commuter Limited Express, Limited Nissei Express, Limited Express (including group trains, deadhead trains and trial-run trains).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seen head-on, the lights on both sides are illuminated: Rapid Express, Commuter Limited Express, Limited Nissei Express, Limited Express (including group trains, deadhead trains and trial-run trains).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="159">
<j>正面から見て右側が点灯 - 通勤準急・準急・通勤急行・急行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seen head-on, a light on the right side is lighted - Commuter Semi Express/ Semi Express/ Commuter Express/ Express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seen head-on, a light on the right side is illuminated: Commuter Semi Express, Semi Express, Commuter Express and Express.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seen head-on, a light on the right side is illuminated: Commuter Semi Express, Semi Express, Commuter Express and Express.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="160">
<j>無点灯 - 普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marker light is unlit - Local Trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marker light is unlit: All local trains</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marker light is unlit: All local trains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="161">
<j>急行の点灯パターンは近畿日本鉄道と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pattern of marker lights (Headcode of marker lights) for the express is the same as that of Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pattern of marker lights (the headcode of marker lights) for the express is the same as that of Kintetsu Railways.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pattern of marker lights (the headcode of marker lights) for the express is the same as that of Kintetsu Railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>他社線との直通運転</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shared operation with the lines of other company</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shared operation with the lines of other companies</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shared operation with the lines of other companies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="162">
<j>大阪市交通局：京都線・千里線と大阪市営地下鉄堺筋線が相互乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau: Kyoto Line and Senri Line share the track with Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line.</e>
<cmt>大阪市交通局→Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau(http://www.kotsu.city.osaka.jp/) 大阪市営地下鉄は(http://www.kotsu.city.osaka.jp/foreign/english/subway/index.html) でもOsaka&apos;s Subway Sakaisuji Lineとなっているので、京都市営地下鉄（Kyoto City Subway)に合わせ、Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Lineとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau: Kyoto Line and Senri Line share the track with Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau: Kyoto Line and Senri Line share the track with Osaka Municipal Subway Sakaisuji Line.</e>
<cmt>city →municipal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="163">
<j>大阪市営地下鉄の車両の乗り入れは基本として高槻市、北千里までだが、試運転やイベントなどで桂まで乗り入れた実績がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the shared sections with Osaka City Subway are up to Takatsuki City or Kita Senri, some fleets have entered into Katsura Station for trial run or some events.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the sections shared with Osaka City Subway are up to Takatsuki City or Kita Senri, some fleets have entered into Katsura Station for trial runs or particular events.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the sections shared with Osaka Municipal Subway are up to Takatsuki City or Kita Senri, some fleets have entered into Katsura Station for trial runs or particular events.</e>
<cmt>city →municipal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="164">
<j>神戸高速鉄道：神戸線が神戸高速鉄道東西線に乗り入れ（新開地駅まで）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway: The Kobe Line shares the track with Kobe Rapid Transit Railway (to Shinkaichi Station).</e>
<cmt>神戸高速鉄道→Kobe Rapid Transit Railway　（ｈｔｔｐ://kobe-kousoku.jp/index.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway: The Kobe Line shares the track with Kobe Rapid Transit Railway (to Shinkaichi Station).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway: The Kobe Line shares the track with Kobe Rapid Transit Railway (to Shinkaichi Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="165">
<j>山陽電気鉄道：1998年まで神戸線が乗り入れ（神戸高速鉄道東西線を経由して山陽電鉄本線須磨浦公園駅まで、山陽車両も神戸線六甲駅まで乗り入れ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway: The Kobe Line had shared the track until 1998 (The trains of the Kobe Line reached Suma-koen Station on the Sanyo Electric Railway Main Line through the Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Tozai Line, while the trains of Sanyo Electric Railways reached Rokko Station on the Kobe Line.</e>
<cmt>山陽電気鉄道→Sanyo Electric Railway (http://www.sanyo-railway.co.jp/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanyo Electric Railway shared track with the Kobe Line until 1998 (the trains of the Kobe Line reached Suma-koen Station on the Sanyo Electric Railway Main Line through the Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Tozai Line, while the trains of Sanyo Electric Railways reached Rokko Station on the Kobe Line).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway shared track with the Kobe Line until 1998 (the trains of the Kobe Line reached Sumaura-koen Station on the Sanyo Electric Railway Main Line through the Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Tozai Line, while the trains of Sanyo Electric Railways reached Rokko Station on the Kobe Line).</e>
<cmt>Suma-koen→Sumaura-koen</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="166">
<j>山陽車両は現在でも三宮駅まで乗り入れており、折り返しの回送の際、梅田側に数百メートルながら走行しており、現在でも阪急線内を走る山陽車両は存在する（客扱いはしていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even at present, the fleets of Sanyo Electric Railway are operated to Sannomiya Station, and when the shuttle trains are deadheaded, they edge into the track (of the Kobe Line), although just a few hundred meters, toward Umeda Station, therefore it can be said that there still exist the trains of Sanyo Electric Railway running on the Hankyu Line (they don&apos;t admit passengers).</e>
<cmt>梅田側に（神戸線を）数百メートルながら走行して→わかりにくいので和文にはありませんでしたが、（）内を英文に加えましたhey edge into the track (of the　Kobe Line)….</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today the fleets of Sanyo Electric Railway operate to Sannomiya Station, and when the shuttle trains are deadheaded they edge into the track (of the Kobe Line), although just a few hundred meters, toward Umeda Station; thus it can be said that there still exist the trains of Sanyo Electric Railway running on the Hankyu Line (they don&apos;t admit passengers).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today the fleets of Sanyo Electric Railway operate to Sannomiya Station, and when the shuttle trains are deadheaded they edge into the track (of the Kobe Line), although just a few hundred meters, toward Umeda Station; thus it can be said that there still exist the trains of Sanyo Electric Railway running on the Hankyu Line (they don&apos;t admit passengers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="167">
<j>能勢電鉄：宝塚線が乗り入れ（阪急グループの一員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nose Electric Railway: Takarazuka Line use the same track (Hankyu Group member).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nose Electric Railway: the Takarazuka Line uses the same track (as a member of the Hankyu Group).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nose Electric Railway: the Takarazuka Line uses the same track (as a member of the Hankyu Group).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>現在では塗色も阪急と同じくマルーン一色になっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present the trains are painted in the same solid color, maroon, as the trains of Hankyu.</e>
<cmt>マルーン→Maroon。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present the trains are painted in the same solid maroon color as the trains of Hankyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present the trains are painted in the same solid maroon color as the trains of Hankyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="169">
<j>能勢電鉄の車両（元は阪急の車両）は車両検査やイベントの際に乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of safety inspection or some events, the fleets of Nose Electric Railway (Hankyu&apos;s cars are reused) enter the spur tracks to Hirai depot or Shojaku depot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of a safety inspection or other event, the fleets of Nose Electric Railway (Hankyu&apos;s cars are reused) enter the spur tracks to the Hirai depot or the Shojaku depot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu&apos;s train cars will be substituted for the Nose Electric fleet in the event of a safety inspection or for other events.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>平井車庫や正雀車庫まで入線している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They will enter the line via the spur tracks of the Hirai Depot or Shojaku Depot.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling Stock</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolling Stock</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling Stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="171">
<j>箕面有馬電気軌道（箕有）、および、その後身の阪神急行電鉄（阪急）によって敷設された神戸線・宝塚線（神宝線）と、北大阪電気鉄道、および、その後身の新京阪鉄道によって敷設された京都線とでは、その成り立ちが異なるため、車両規格に違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rolling stock used on the Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline and on the Kobe Line/Takarazuka Line (Jinpo-Sen) that were constructed by its successor, Hanshin Electric Express Railway (Hankyu) and the rolling stock used on the Kita-Osaka Electric Railway and the Kyoto Line, which was constructed by its successor, Shinkeihan Railway, are different in specification because of the different backgrounds.</e>
<cmt>箕面有馬電気軌道（箕有）→Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline、阪神急行電鉄（阪急）→Hanshin Electric Express Railway (Hankyu) (http://www.jtr.net/jtr08/history.html)、新京阪鉄道→定訳不明:Shinkeihan Railway</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rolling stock used on the Minoo-Arima Electric Tramline and on the Kobe Line/Takarazuka Line (Jinpo-Sen) that were constructed by its successor Hanshin Electric Express Railway (Hankyu), as well as the rolling stock used on the Kita-Osaka Electric Railway and the Kyoto Line, as constructed by its successor Shinkeihan Railway, differ in their specifications due to the different backgrounds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rolling stock used on the Mino-Arima Electric Tramline and on the Kobe Line/Takarazuka Line (Jinpo-Sen) that were constructed by its successor Hanshin Electric Express Railway (Hankyu), as well as the rolling stock used on the Kita-Osaka Electric Railway and the Kyoto Line, as constructed by its successor Shinkeihan Railway, differ in their specifications due to the different backgrounds.</e>
<cmt>Minoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="172">
<j>車両の電装品も、神宝線は東芝製、京都線は新京阪時代の名残で東洋電機製造製と分けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for electric components, trains for the Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines) uses the products by Toshiba, while the trains on the Kyoto Line are still equipped with the products by Toyo Denki Seizo, as a vestige of the Shin-Keihan Railway time.</e>
<cmt>東洋電機製造→Toyo Denki Seizo (K.K.) (和英翻訳データブック：ジャパンタイムズ編）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for electric components, trains for the Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines) use products by Toshiba, while the trains on the Kyoto Line are still equipped with products by Toyo Denki Seizo, as a vestige of the Shin-Keihan Railway era.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for electric components, trains for the Jinpo-sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines) use products by Toshiba, while the trains on the Kyoto Line are still equipped with products by Toyo Denki Seizo, as a vestige of the Shinkeihan Railway era.</e>
<cmt>Shinkeihan Railwayとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>今でもこの慣習を守り続けている（ほかに、阪急において東芝製品は神宝線の電装品のほかに全駅の駅務機器や電車のエア・コンディショナー、エレベーター、業務用パーソナルコンピュータなど幅広い分野で使用されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This custom is still maintained (in addition to the electric components used on the Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines), Toshiba products are used in various ares in Hankyu Railways, such as the office equipment of all stations, air conditioners installed in the cars, elevators, personal computers for business use).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This custom is still maintained (in addition to the electric components used on the Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines), Toshiba products are used in various areas in Hankyu Railways, such as the office equipment of all stations, the air conditioners installed in the cars, elevators and personal computers for business use).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This custom is still maintained (in addition to the electric components used on the Jinpo-sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines), and therefore Toshiba products are used in various areas in Hankyu Railways, such as the office equipment of all stations, the air conditioners installed in the cars, elevators and personal computers for business use).</e>
<cmt>Jinpo-senとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>マスター・コントローラーは、関西では珍しくワンハンドルマスコンを積極的に採用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the master controller, the company actively adopts the one handle master controller, which is not common in the Kansai District.</e>
<cmt>ワンハンドルマスコン→one handle master controller (http://www/wdic.oorg/w/RAIL/ワンハンドルマスコン）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the master controller, the company actively employs the one-handle master controller, which is not common in the Kansai District.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the master controller, the company actively employs the one-handle master controller, which is not common in the Kansai District.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="175">
<j>戦後1948年の阪急550形電車以後、すべての阪急車両は系列のナニワ工機（後のアルナ車両）が建造していた（阪急では車両を新規製造することを「建造」と表現する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series 550 was born in 1948, after the war, the Hankyu&apos;s rolling stock have been fabricated by Naniwa-Koki (later, Alna Sharyo (rolling stock) Co., Ltd.), an affiliate of the company (in Hankyu Railway, the word &quot;build&quot; is used to refer to the fabrication of a new series of rolling stock).</e>
<cmt>阪急550形→Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series (用語リスト#3747参照）、ナニワ工機（アルナ車両）→Naniwa-Koki (Alna Sharyo (rolling stock) Co. Ltd.) (http://ww.holdings.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/ir/zaimu/ar2004e.pdf参照)。 「建造」と表現する→the word &quot;build &quot;is used.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series 550 was born in 1948, after the war, the Hankyu&apos;s rolling stock have been fabricated by Naniwa-Koki (later, Alna Sharyo (rolling stock) Co., Ltd.), an affiliate of the company (in Hankyu Railway, the word &quot;build&quot; is used to refer to the fabrication of a new series of rolling stock).</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the post-war launch of the Hankyu (Electric) Railway Series 550 in 1948, Hankyu&apos;s rolling stock was manufactured by Naniwa-Koki (later, Alna Sharyo (rolling stock) Co., Ltd.), an affiliate of Hankyu (in Hankyu Railway, the word Japanese word for &apos;build&apos; is used to refer to the manufacturing of a new series of rolling stock).</e>
<cmt>, after the war, の最初の, 不要</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>しかし阪急と東武鉄道、東京都交通局、大阪市交通局などの主な納入先が経営状況の厳しさから車両新造を抑制、受注が激減したため、2002年に同社は解散。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since their clients, such as Hankyu Corporation, Tobu Railway Company, The Bureau of Transportation, Tokyo Metropolitan Government, Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau, have held down the introduction of new rolling stock because of their harsh business conditions, the orders have consequently decreased drastically and the rolling stock company was dissolved in 2002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since their clients, such as Hankyu Corporation, Tobu Railway Company, The Bureau of Transportation, Tokyo Metropolitan Government and the Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau have held down the introduction of new rolling stock due to the harsh business conditions, the orders have consequently decreased drastically and the rolling-stock company was dissolved in 2002.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since their clients, such as Hankyu Corporation, Tobu Railway Company, the Bureau of Transportation Tokyo Metropolitan Government and the Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau, have held down the introduction of new rolling stock due to the harsh business conditions, the orders have consequently decreased drastically and the rolling-stock company was dissolved in 2002.</e>
<cmt>The Bureau of Transportation Tokyo Metropolitan Governmentとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>その後の阪急車の建造メーカーに選ばれたのはそれまで関西の大手私鉄と取引がなかった（ただし、公営である京都市営地下鉄・大阪市営地下鉄とは取引があった） 日立製作所 であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Hitachi, Ltd., was selected as a provider (&quot;builder&quot;) of the Hankyu&apos;s rolling stock, although Hitachi did not have any business relation with big private railway companies in the Kansai District (nonetheless, it was dealing with the public transportation companies, Kyoto City Subway and Osaka City Subway).</e>
<cmt>日立製作所→Hitachi, Ltd.(和英翻訳データブック：ジャパンタイムズ編）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Hitachi, Ltd. was selected as a provider (&quot;builder&quot;) of Hankyu&apos;s rolling stock, although Hitachi did not have business relationships with large private railway companies in the Kansai District (nonetheless, it was dealing with the public transportation companies Kyoto City Subway and Osaka City Subway).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Hitachi, Ltd. was selected as a builder of Hankyu&apos;s rolling stock, although Hitachi did not have business relationships with large private railway companies in the Kansai District (nonetheless, it was dealing with the public transportation companies Kyoto Municipal Subway and Osaka Municipal Subway).</e>
<cmt>city →municipal</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>なお、阪急の経営事情は依然として厳しいことから、新車投入と平行して、1960年代後半～1980年代前半に製造された車両をアルナ車両やグローバルテックにて更新工事を施工し、延命使用する措置を取っている（うち1970年代前半までの車両に関しては再度の更新工事施工となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Hankyu Corporation still suffers a severe financial health, in pararel with the the investment in new trains, the cars fabricated from the late 1960s to the early 1980s are renovated at Alna Sharyo Co., Ltd.. and Hitachi, Ltd., in order to prolong their life for practical use, (among them, those fabricated in the early 1970s or before undergo the second renovation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Hankyu Corporation still suffers a severe financial health, in pararel with the the investment in new trains, the cars fabricated from the late 1960s to the early 1980s are renovated at Alna Sharyo Co., Ltd.. and Hitachi, Ltd., in order to prolong their life for practical use, (among them, those fabricated in the early 1970s or before undergo the second renovation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Hankyu Corporation still suffers from severe financial health, in parallel with the investment in new trains, the cars fabricated from the late 1960s to the early 1980s are renovated at Alna Sharyo Co., Ltd. and Globaltec Ltd., in order to prolong their life for practical use (among them, those fabricated in the early 1970s or before have undergone a second renovation).</e>
<cmt>pararel → parallel　その他ダブりのピリオド、the、括弧前のカンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="179">
<j>外装のカラーリングには、伝統的に小豆色色（阪急マルーン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For coloring the exterior, maroon is traditionally adopted (known as Hankyu Maroon,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the choice of an exterior color, maroon is traditionally adopted (being known as Hankyu Maroon).</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the choice of an exterior color, maroon is traditionally adopted (being known as Hankyu Maroon).</e>
<cmt>次の文につなぐため、最後の括弧をとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>お召し列車でも用いられる色）が採用されている（ラッピング車両に抜擢された場合を除く）ほか、内装についても木目調の化粧板や色名一覧 (こ)色のアンゴラ (ヤギ)の毛のシートを採用するなど統一されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and this color is also used for the special cars for the imperial family; except for the cars selected as ad-wrapped cars), and the interior is also finished in a uniformed manner with the panel boards of woodtone finish and the seats covered with the fabric of Angola (goat) fur dyed in the colors listed in &quot;Shikimei Ichiran (こ）&quot;(Japanese color standardized naming system: color category (こ), that is, the colors whose Japanese name starts with the Japanese letter &quot;こ（ko）&quot;).</e>
<cmt>色名一覧 (こ)色→定訳不明：　&quot;Shikimei Ichiran (こ）&quot; (Japanese color standardized naming system: colors in the category (こ), that is, the colors whose Japanese name starts with the Japanese letter &quot;こ（ko）&quot;)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This color is also used for the special cars for the Imperial Family; except for the cars selected as ad-wrapped cars), and the interior is also finished in a uniform manner with the panel boards of woodtone finish and the seats covered with the fabric of angora (goat) dyed in the colors listed in &quot;Shikimei Ichiran (こ）&quot;(Japanese color standardized naming system: color category (こ); that is, the colors whose Japanese name starts with the Japanese letter &quot;こ（ko）&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This color is also used for the special cars for the Imperial Family (with the exception of cars selected as ad-wrapped cars), and the interior is also finished in a uniform manner with panel boards in a woodtone finish and the seats covered with angora (goat) fabric dyed in colors listed in the Shikimei Ichiran (the standardized color list used in Japan) that begin with the Japanese letter &quot;こ&quot; (pronounced &quot;ko&quot;).</e>
<cmt>I have had to rewrite the final part quite a bit to make it more understandable to a native speaker of English. Please check if I have understood this correctly.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>最近の車両（更新車含む）では経年劣化も考慮して妻面やドア部の化粧板にかなり濃い色の物を使うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interior of the recent cars (included the renovated cars) tend to be finished with considerably dark-toned panels for doors and the front face panel (burgeboad), anticipating the aged deterioration.</e>
<cmt>妻面→定訳不明：妻壁bargeboard (http://www.dictionaly babylon.com/bargeboard)から、front face panel (bargebord)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interiors of recent cars (included the renovated cars) tend to be finished with considerably darker-toned panels for doors and the front face panel (burgeboard), anticipating deterioration due to age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interiors of recent cars (included the renovated cars) tend to be finished with considerably darker-toned panels for doors and the front face panel (bargeboard), anticipating deterioration due to age.</e>
<cmt>bargeboardのスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="182">
<j>なお、外部塗色については8000系導入時と9300系導入時に新色採用（メタリックオレンジやマルーンの帯化などが検討された）の案が持ち上がった事があるが、利用者や社内からも抗議や反対意見が続出したため、6000、7000系列の屋根肩部分をアイボリー色に改める以外は廃案となった（ただし現在でも、利用者や部内の中からはアイボリー帯を車体裾部分にも設ける程度であれば良いとの意見も少数ながら存在している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Series 8000 and 9300 were introduced, a new coating color was proposed (introduction of metallic orange coating or a maroon colored belt on the body was studied), but many users and staff of the company opposed and these new ideas were rejected except for changing the color of the roof edge to ivory (however, even today, a few of the users and company staff consistently insist that an ivory belt at the bottom of the car body or something similar should be admissible).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the 8000 and 9300 series were introduced, a new coating color was proposed (introduction of metallic orange coating or a maroon-colored belt on the body was studied); however, many users and company staff opposed these new ideas and they werewere rejected except for changing the color of the roof edge to ivory (however, even today a few users and company staff consistently insist that an ivory belt at the bottom of the car body or something similar should be admissible).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Series 8000 and 9300 were introduced, a new coating color was proposed (the introduction of metallic orange coating or a maroon-colored belt on the body was studied); however, many users and company staff opposed these new ideas and they were rejected except for changing the color of the roof edge to ivory for the Series 6000 and 7000 (however, even today a few users and company staff continue to insist that an ivory belt at the bottom of the car body or something similar should be admissible).</e>
<cmt>wereダブりを削除しました。一部訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="183">
<j>なお、京都線に乗り入れる大阪市営地下鉄堺筋線の車両に関しては、ステンレス鋼車体に茶系の帯を巻いた66系が走っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of the Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line, which shares the track with the Kyoto Line, the Series 66 train carries a brownish belt painted around its stainlless-steel body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line, which shares the track with the Kyoto Line, the Series 66 train carries a brownish belt painted around its stainlless-steel body.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the Osaka Municipal Subway Sakaisuji Line, which shares the track with the Kyoto Line, the Series 66 train carries a brownish belt painted around its stainless-steel body.</e>
<cmt>city →municipalstainlless→ stainless</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>以前はアルミニウム合金製車体に茶帯を巻いた60系も走っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before, the trains of Series 60, with alloyed aluminum body and a brown belt painted around it, were also running.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Previously, the trains of Series 60, with aluminum-alloy bodies and brown belts painted around them, were also running.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previously, the trains of Series 60, with aluminum-alloy bodies and brown belts painted around them, were also running.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>ともに、2000年以降阪急線内で営業運行する車両では唯一マルーン中心の塗装でない車両である（山陽電鉄車両は1998年以降三宮以東で営業していない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 2000, among the cars running on the Hankyu Lines, these two types are the only cars that are not painted in dominant maroon (since 1998, Sanyo Electric Railway have suspended the operation of cars from Sannomiya Station and to the east).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 2000, among the cars running on the Hankyu Lines, these two types are the only cars that are not painted in the dominant maroon color (since 1998 the Sanyo Electric Railway has suspended the operation of cars from Sannomiya Station and to the east).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 2000, among the cars running on the Hankyu Lines, these two types are the only cars that are not painted in the dominant maroon color (since 1998 the Sanyo Electric Railway has suspended the operation of cars from Sannomiya Station and to the east).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="186">
<j>阪急電鉄における形式の符番は次の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The followings are the numbering rules by type of Hankyu Railway:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are Hankyu Railways&apos; numbering rules by type:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are Hankyu Railways&apos; numbering rules by type:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>阪急電鉄の形式番号は1980年代に廃車された810系を最後に、以後は全車4桁になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Hankyu Railway&apos;s numbering rule, all car numbers are consisted of 4 figures since the time when Series 810 became disused in the 1980s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Hankyu Railway numbering rule, all car numbers have consisted of four figures since the abandonment of the Series 810 in the 1980s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Hankyu Railway numbering rule, all car numbers have consisted of four figures since the abandonment of the Series 810 in the 1980s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="188">
<j>付随車（T車）には、同系の動力車（M車）の車番に、50を加えた番号を付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tracked cars (T-car) are given the motor car (M-car) number of the same series plus 50.</e>
<cmt>付随車（T車）→定訳不明：Tracked car (T-car)、動力車（M車）→定訳不明：Motor car (M-car)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tracked cars (T-car) are given the motor-car (M-car) number of the same series, plus 50.</e>
<cmt>clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tracked cars (T-car) are given the motor-car (M-car) number of the same series, plus 50.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="189">
<j>中間車には、先頭車の車番に500を加えた番号を付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The middle cars are given the first car number plus 500.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The middle cars are given the first-car number, plus 500.</e>
<cmt>clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The middle cars are given the first-car number, plus 500.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="190">
<j>動力車、制御車、付随車といった形式記号は付けない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Identification code by type, such as motor car, controller car or tracked car, is not attached.</e>
<cmt>制御車→定訳不明： controller car (英辞郎on the WEB参照)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An identification code by type, such as motor car, controller car or tracked car, is not attached.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An identification code by type, such as motor car, controller car or tracked car, is not attached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="191">
<j>1.はすでに3桁時代の700系（神宝線の700系は後に800系となる）新造車から始まり、2.は3000・3300系から始められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1. started with the new vehicles of Series 700 (in case of Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines), this series was later changed to Series 800), and 2. started with Series 3000 and 3300.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1. started with the new vehicles of Series 700 (in the case of the Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines), this series was later changed to Series 800); and 2. started with Series 3000 and 3300.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1. started with the new vehicles of Series 700 (in the case of the Jinpo-sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Lines), this series was later changed to Series 800); and 2. started with Series 3000 and 3300.</e>
<cmt>Jinpo-senとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="192">
<j>C7512（この場合、7012Fに属し、梅田よりの2号車）を例に取ると以下のようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking C7512 for example (in this case, it belongs to 7012F and is the 2nd car toward Umeda Station), let&apos;s see how it woks:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking C7512 as an example (in this case it belongs to 7012F and is the second car toward Umeda Station), let&apos;s see how it woks:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking C7512 as an example (in this case it belongs to 7012F and is the second car toward Umeda Station), let&apos;s see how it woks:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="193">
<j>7 （千の位）...車両形式の系列を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">7 (thousandth place)…indicates the railway series</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;7) (in the thousandth place) indicates the railway series.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 7 (in the thousandth place) indicates the railway series.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>1から始まり、形態や性能ごとに現在9までの数字で分けられている（4は事業用車）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, each number from 1 to 9 is allocated by type and capacity (4 is for utility cars).</e>
<cmt>事業用車→定訳不明：utility carとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, each number from 1 to 9 is allocated by type and capacity (&quot;4&quot; is for utility cars).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, each number from 1 to 9 is allocated by type and capacity (4 is for utility cars).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="195">
<j>5 （百の位）...0～4先頭車、5～9中間車、0～2・5～7神宝線、3・4・8・9京都線。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5 (hundredth place)…0-4: first car, 5-9: middle car, 0-2/5-7: Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Line), 3/4/8/9: Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5 (hundredth place)…0-4: first car; 5-9: middle car; 0-2/5-7: Jinpo-Sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Line); 3/4/8/9: Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5 (hundredth place)…0-4: first car; 5-9: middle car; 0-2/5-7: Jinpo-sen (Kobe/Takarazuka Line); 3/4/8/9: Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>Jinpo-senとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>1100系～3100系までは0・5が神戸線用、1・6が宝塚線用だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Series 1100 to Series 3100 were used, 0 and 5 were for the Kobe Line, and 1 and 6 were for the Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Series 1100 to Series 3100 were used, &quot;0&quot; and &quot;5&quot; were for the Kobe Line while &quot;1&quot; and &quot;6&quot; were for the Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Series 1100 to Series 3100 were used, 0 and 5 were for the Kobe Line while 1 and 6 were for the Takarazuka Line.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>2・7は普段は使用せず、試作車や特別車両用に空けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 and 7 are not for ordinary use, and reserved for experimental cars and special cars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The numbers &quot;2&quot; and &quot;7&quot; are not for ordinary use but are instead reserved for experimental cars and special cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The numbers 2 and 7 aren&apos;t for ordinary use but are instead reserved for experimental cars and special cars.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="198">
<j>1 （十の位）...0～4電動車、5～9付随車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 (tenth place)…0-4: electric motor coach, 5-9: tracked cars</e>
<cmt>電動車→electric-moter car （英辞郎on the WEB参照)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number &quot;1&quot; (in the tenth place)…0-4: electric motor coach; 5-9: tracked cars</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number 1 (in the tenth place)…0-4: electric motor coach; 5-9: tracked cars</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>2 （一の位）...製造順位番号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 (ones place)…numbering by order of production</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number &quot;2&quot; (in the ones place)…numbering by order of production</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number 2 (in the ones place)…numbering by order of production</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>製造順に他社のような1ではなく0から付けられる（山陽電気鉄道も同じ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike other companies, the number starts in order from 0 (Sanyo Electric Railway also employs the same rule).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike other companies, the number starts in order from &quot;0&quot; (Sanyo Electric Railway also employs the same rule).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike other companies, the number starts in order from 0 (Sanyo Electric Railway also employs the same rule).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>但し、3300系までは京都線用は1から始まるようにされていた（新京阪時代の名残）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, until the time when Series 3300 became in use, the cars for the Kyoto Line were given the number starting from 1 (as a vestige of the Shinkeihan time)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, until the time when Series 3300 came into use the cars for the Kyoto Line were given their numbers starting from &quot;1&quot; (as a vestige of the Shinkeihan era).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, until the time the Series 3300 came into use the cars for the Kyoto Line were given their numbers starting from 1 (as a vestige of the Shinkeihan era).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="202">
<j>ただし、もともと先頭車だった車両で、その後の改造で運転台を撤去（中間車化）した場合でも、改番されることなく、製造当時の番号のままで使用されている（例：3000系のC3000）場合があるので、注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it should be noted that the cars which were originally fabricated as leading vehicles and underwent the remodeling by removing the driver&apos;s platform (modification to middle cars) are still used with the original production numbers without renumbering (Example: Series 3000-C3000)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it should be noted that the cars originally fabricated as leading vehicles that underwent remodeling with the removal of the driver&apos;s platform (modification to middle cars) are still used with the original production numbers without renumbering (e.g., Series 3000-C3000).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it should be noted that the cars originally fabricated as leading vehicles that underwent remodeling with the removal of the driver&apos;s platform (modification to middle cars) are still used with the original production numbers without renumbering (e.g., Series 3000-C3000).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>乗り入れ車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trains with shared sections</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trains with shared sections</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trains with shared sections</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="203">
<j>大阪市交通局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>大阪市交通局66系電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau Series 66</e>
<cmt>http://www.uraken.net/rail/chiho/osaka/66.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau Series 66</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau Series 66</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>過去の乗り入れ車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trains with shared sections in the past</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trains with shared sections in the past</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trains with shared sections in the past</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="205">
<j>山陽電気鉄道 - 現在は阪神電気鉄道と神戸高速鉄道のみに乗り入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway - At present, it only goes through to Hanshin Electric Railway, and Kobe Rapid Transit Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanyo Electric Railway - Currently, it only goes through to Hanshin Electric Railway and Kobe Rapid Transit Railway.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway - This currently only goes through to the Hanshin Electric Railway and the Kobe Rapid Transit Railway.</e>
<cmt>the を補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>また普通・S特急（土曜・休日ダイヤのみ）運用のみで阪急三宮駅に姿を現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It operates only the local trains and the S-Limited Express only available on Saturdays and holidays) that can be seen at Hankyu Sannomiya Station.</e>
<cmt>S特急→定訳不明：S-Limited Expressとしましたが、Sは三洋電機製特急電車（Sanyo Electric made Limite Express）の”S”のようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It operates only the local trains (and the S-Limited Express only available on Saturdays and holidays), which can be seen at Hankyu Sannomiya Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It operates only the local trains (and the S-Limited Express only available on Saturdays and holidays), which can be seen at Hankyu Sannomiya Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="207">
<j>山陽電気鉄道5000系電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway Series 5000</e>
<cmt>http://www.uraken.net/rail/chiho/osaka/5000.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanyo Electric Railway Series 5000</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway Series 5000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>山陽電気鉄道3000系電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway Series 3000</e>
<cmt>http://www.uraken.net/rail/chiho/osaka/3000.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanyo Electric Railway Series 3000</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanyo Electric Railway Series 3000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>大阪市交通局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>大阪市交通局60系電車（66系の増備に伴い全廃された）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau Series 66（with the enhanced deployment of Series 66, this series was completely disused).</e>
<cmt>大阪市交通局60系電車</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau Series 66（with the enhanced deployment of Series 66, this series was completely abandoned).</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau Series 60（with the enhanced deployment of Series 66, this series was completely abandoned).</e>
<cmt>66→ 60</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>系列会社の車両の特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics of cars by business group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of cars by business group</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of cars by business group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="211">
<j>阪急の系列会社である北大阪急行電鉄（北急）や神戸電鉄（神鉄）、北神急行電鉄（北神）などでは、一部車両の車内装飾が阪急車両に準じたものとなっている（北急では北大阪急行電鉄8000形電車、神鉄では神戸電鉄5000系電車、北神では北神急行電鉄7000系電車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kita-Osaka Kyuko Railway (Kitakyu), Kobe Electric Railway (Shintetsu), and Hokushinkyuko Railway (Hokushin), affiliates of Hankyu Railway, follow the interior decoration of Hankyu trains (in case of Kitakyu, Kita Osaka Electric Railway Type 8000, in Shintetsu, Kobe Electric Railway Series 5000, in Hokushin, Hokushin Electric Railway Series 7000).</e>
<cmt>北大阪急行電鉄（北急）→Kita-Osaka Kyuko Railway (Kitakyu) (http://www.kita-kyu.co.jp/index.html)、神戸電鉄（神鉄）→Kobe Electric Railway (Shintetsu) (http://www.shsintetsu.co.jp/index.html)、北神急行電鉄（北神）→Hokushinkyuko Railway (Hokushin) (http;//www.hokushinkyuko.co.jp)。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kita-Osaka Kyuko Railway (Kitakyu), Kobe Electric Railway (Shintetsu) and Hokushinkyuko Railway (Hokushin), which are affiliates of Hankyu Railway, follow the interior decoration of Hankyu trains (in tje case of Kitakyu, Kita Osaka Electric Railway Type 8000; in Shintetsu, Kobe Electric Railway Series 5000; in Hokushin, Hokushin Electric Railway Series 7000).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kita-Osaka Kyuko Railway (Kitakyu), Kobe Electric Railway (Shintetsu) and Hokushinkyuko Railway (Hokushin), which are affiliates of Hankyu Railway, follow the interior decoration theme of Hankyu trains (in the case of Kitakyu, Kita Osaka Electric Railway Type 8000; in Shintetsu, Kobe Electric Railway Series 5000; in Hokushin, Hokushin Electric Railway Series 7000).</e>
<cmt>tje →the</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>内装画像はそれぞれMediaKitakyu 8000 inside、MediaShintetsu5000を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For images of the interiors, please see the section &quot;MediaKitakyu 8000 inside and MediaShintetsu5000.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For images of the interiors, please see the section &quot;MediaKitakyu 8000 inside and MediaShintetsu 5000&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For images of the interiors, please see the sections &quot;MediaKitakyu 8000 inside&quot; and &quot;MediaShintetsu 5000&quot;).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>乗務員区所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sections and affiliation of the crew</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sections and affiliations of the crew</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sections and affiliations of the crew</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="213">
<j>梅田乗務区（京都本線、宝塚本線、神戸本線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeda operation section（Kyoto Line, Takarazuka Line, and Kobe Line)</e>
<cmt>梅田乗務区→定訳不明：Umeda operation section</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeda operation section（Kyoto, Takarazuka and Kobe lines)</e>
<cmt>simpler</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeda operation section（Kyoto, Takarazuka and Kobe lines)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>西宮北口乗務区（神戸本線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishinomiya-kitaguchi operatioon section (Kobe Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishinomiya-kitaguchi operation section (Kobe Line)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishinomiya-kitaguchi operation section (Kobe Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>桂乗務区（京都本線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsura Section; (Kyoto Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsura Section (Kyoto Line)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsura Section (Kyoto Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>淡路乗務区（千里線、京都本線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awaji operation section (Senri Line, Kyoto Line)</e>
<cmt>淡路乗務区→Awaji operation section</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awaji operation section (Senri and Kyoto lines)</e>
<cmt>simpler</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awaji operation section (Senri and Kyoto lines)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>運賃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fares</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fares</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fares</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="217">
<j>大人普通旅客運賃（小児半額・10円未満切り上げ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normal passenger fare for adults (half fare for children: less than 10 yen is rounded up).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normal passenger fare for adults (half fare for children: less than 10 yen is rounded up).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normal passenger fare for adults (half fare for children: less than 10 yen is rounded up).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>2004年12月1日現在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of December 1, 2004</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of December 1, 2004</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of December 1, 2004</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>回数券の取り扱い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coupon ticket</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coupon ticket</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coupon ticket</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="219">
<j>2007年4月1日より、180円区間、260円区間、310円区間の全ての回数乗車券については、有効期間内であれば阪神電気鉄道でも利用可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From April 1, 2007 all the coupon tickets, for the section of 180 yen, 260 yen and 310 yen, became accepted for the trains of Hanshin Electric Railway, as far as they are not expired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effective on April 1, 2007 all coupon tickets--for the section of 180 yen, 260 yen and 310 yen--became accepted for the trains of Hanshin Electric Railway, as far as they have not expired.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effective on April 1, 2007 all coupon tickets--for the section of 180 yen, 260 yen and 310 yen--became accepted for the trains of Hanshin Electric Railway, as far as they have not expired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>但しそのままでは利用できず、阪神線で利用する際は入場前に青色の券売機で阪神の乗車券に引き換える必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, to use the coupon for a Hanshin line, it can not be used directly and before entering the gate, it has to be changed to the ticket of Hanshin lines using the blue-colored ticket vending machine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, to use the coupon for a Hanshin line it cannot be used directly; before the passenger enters the gate it must be changed to the ticket of Hanshin lines using the blue-colored ticket vending machine.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, to use the coupon for a Hanshin line it cannot be used directly; before the passenger enters the gate it must be changed to the ticket of Hanshin lines using the blue-colored ticket vending machine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>乗車カード・企画乗車券</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Travel cards/designed travel cards</e>
<cmt>企画乗車券→定訳不明：designed travel cardsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Travel cards/designed travel cards</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Travel cards/designed travel cards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="221">
<j>以下の各項目を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please see the following sections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please see the following sections:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please see the following sections:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="222">
<j>STACIAカード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">STACIA Card</e>
<cmt>定訳不明：STACIA Cardとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">STACIA Card</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">STACIA Card</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>ラガールカード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lagare Card</e>
<cmt>http://rail.hankyu.co.jp/en/images/b_all_map.jpg</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lagare Card</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lagare Card</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="224">
<j>阪急阪神1dayパス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Hanshin 1day pass</e>
<cmt>阪急阪神1dayパス→定訳不明：Hankyu Hanshin 1day pass</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Hanshin one-day pass</e>
<cmt>expressed as?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Hanshin one-day pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>OSAKA海遊きっぷ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OSAKA Kaiyu Kippu (Osaka sea round-trip ticket)</e>
<cmt>OSAKA海遊きっぷ→定訳不明：OSAKA Kaiyu Kippu (Osaka sea round-trip ticket)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OSAKA Kaiyu Kippu (Osaka Sea round-trip ticket)</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OSAKA Kaiyu Kippu (Osaka Sea round-trip ticket)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>大阪周遊パス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Unlimited Pass</e>
<cmt>http://www.pia-kansai.ne.jp/osp/2008/en</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Unlimited Pass</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Unlimited Pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>高野山1dayチケット</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koya-san 1day ticket</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koya-san one-day ticket</e>
<cmt>expressed as?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koya-san one-day ticket</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>奈良・斑鳩1dayチケット</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara-Ikaruga 1day ticket</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara-Ikaruga one-day ticket</e>
<cmt>expressed as?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara-Ikaruga one-day ticket</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>特記事項</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Special descriptions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Special descriptions</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special comments</e>
<cmt>前出箇所と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>プロ野球球団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pro baseball teams</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Professional baseball teams</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Professional baseball teams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="229">
<j>阪急ホールディングス（現・阪急阪神ホールディングス）として持株会社となる前の旧・阪急電鉄は1936年から1988年までプロ野球球団、阪急ブレーブス（後にオリックス・ブルーウェーブ、現在はオリックス・バファローズ）を、西宮球場（後の阪急西宮スタジアム、2002年に閉鎖）をプロ野球地域保護権として所有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Hankyu Company, which later became Hankyu Holdings (current Hankyu Hanshin Holdings), was the parent company of a pro baseball team, Hankyu Braves (later Orix Blue Wave and current Orix Buffaloes), and owed the Nishinomiya Kyujo (later Hankyu Nishinomiya Stadium which was closed in 2002) under the right of pro baseball area protection.</e>
<cmt>阪急ブレーブス、オリックス・ブルーウェーブ、、オリックス・バファローズ→Hankyu Braves, Orix Blue Wave, Orix Buffaloes(）、西宮球場（阪急西宮スタジアム）Nishinomiya Kyujo (Hankyu Nishinomiya Studium）、プロ野球地域保護権→定訳不明：the right of pro baseball area protection.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old Hankyu Company, which later became Hankyu Holdings (current Hankyu Hanshin Holdings), was the parent company of a pro baseball team, the Hankyu Braves (later Orix Blue Wave and currently the Orix Buffaloes), and owned the Nishinomiya Kyujo (later Hankyu Nishinomiya Stadium which was closed in 2002) under the right of pro baseball area protection.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old Hankyu Corporation, which later became Hankyu Holdings (currently Hankyu Hanshin Holdings), was the parent company of a pro baseball team, the Hankyu Braves (later Orix Blue Wave and currently the Orix Buffaloes) from 1936 to 1988, and owned the Nishinomiya Kyujo (later Hankyu Nishinomiya Stadium, which was closed in 2002) under the right of pro baseball area protection.</e>
<cmt>hankyu company →corporationfrom 1936 to 1988 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>阪急電車という呼称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the name, &quot;Hankyu Densha&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About the name &quot;Hankyu Densha&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About the Hankyu Densha name</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="230">
<j>関西では私鉄に対し「○○電車」という呼称が定着しているが、「阪急電車」のみ今ではあまり看板などでは見かけなくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kanto District, the way of calling a private railway company, &quot;XX-Densha (&apos;company&apos;s name&apos;- train)&quot; is quite common, however, nowadays, &quot;Hankyu Densha&quot; is seldom used on advertisement displays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kanto District, the way of calling a private railway company, &quot;XX-Densha (&apos;company name&apos;- train)&quot; is quite common; however, nowadays &quot;Hankyu Densha&quot; is seldom used on advertisement displays.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kansai District, the way of calling a private railway company, &apos;XX-Densha (&apos;company name&apos;- train)&apos; is quite common; however, nowadays &apos;Hankyu Densha&apos; is seldom used on advertisement displays.</e>
<cmt>kanto→ kansai</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>これは1992年の創業85周年を機に、会社側が公式な通称を「阪急電鉄」と変更したため。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because in 1992, the company changed its common official name to &quot;Hankyu Dentetsu (Hankyu Railway)&quot; when it celebrated the 85th anniversary of foundation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because, in 1992, the company changed its common official name to &quot;Hankyu Dentetsu (Hankyu Railway)&quot; when it celebrated the 85th anniversary of its founding.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because, in 1992, the company changed its common official name to &apos;Hankyu Dentetsu (Hankyu Railway)&apos; when it celebrated the 85th anniversary of its founding.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>ただし乗客は今でもほとんどが「阪急電車」あるいは「阪急」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, most of the passengers continue calling it &quot;Hankyu Densha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, most of the passengers continue to call it &quot;Hankyu Densha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, most of the passengers continue to call it &apos;Hankyu Densha&apos; or &apos;Hankyu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>ホームの呼称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name of platforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names of platforms</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names of platforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="233">
<j>一般的にホームの呼び方は「○番線」だが、阪急電鉄では「○号線」という呼び方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally the name of platforms includes the number like &quot;Platform No. X,&quot; however, in Hankyu Railway, &quot;go&quot; is attached to the number like &quot;Platform X-go.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, the name of a platform includes the number like &quot;Platform No. X&quot;; however, in Hankyu Railway &quot;go&quot; is attached to the number, such as &quot;Platform X-go.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, the name of a platform includes the number like &apos;Platform X&apos;; however, in Hankyu Railway &apos;go&apos; is attached to the number, such as &apos;Platform X-go.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>これは「○番線」が社内での構内配線に対しての呼び方であるため。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because this way is commonly used in the company for indicating the cables of the station wiring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is because this method is commonly used in the company to indicate the cables of the station wiring.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is because this method is commonly used in the company to indicate the cables of the station wiring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>ただし、三宮駅駅構造では例外的に「○番ホーム」という呼び方をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nonetheless, at Sannomiya Station, the platforms are exceptionally called &quot;Platform No. X.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, at Sannomiya Station the platforms are exceptionally called &quot;Platform No. X.&quot;</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, at Sannomiya Station the platforms are exceptionally called &apos;Platform X.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="236">
<j>ホームが2本しかない駅では島式・対向式に関係なく原則として自動放送でホーム番号を言わず、「皆様、まもなく大阪梅田方面に向かう電車が到着します」のように、行き先の方面で表現する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there are only two platforms, regardless of the type of platform, island type and opposing type, instead of an automated announcement of the platform number, basically the direction the car heading for is announced as follows: &quot;Ladies and gentlemen, in a short time, the train for the direction of Osaka Umeda Station will arrive.&quot;</e>
<cmt>対向式→opposing platform (http://www.patentstorm.us/patent/5343817/claims.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there are only two platforms, regardless of the type of platform, island type and opposing type, instead of an automated announcement of the platform number, basically the direction the car is heading toward is announced, as follows: &quot;Ladies and gentlemen, in a short time the train for the direction of Osaka Umeda Station will arrive.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there are only two platforms, regardless of the type of platform (island type or opposing type), instead of an automated announcement of the platform number, basically the direction the car is heading toward is announced, as follows: &apos;Ladies and gentlemen, in a short time the train for the direction of Osaka Umeda Station will arrive.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="237">
<j>例外的にホームが3本以上ある駅でも番号を言わない場合もある（京都線の駅や、優等列車通過駅が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even at stations where there are exceptionally more than 3 platforms, the number is not always mentioned (in most cases at stations on the Kyoto Line or the stations where higher category trains pass nonstop.</e>
<cmt>優等列車→定訳不明：higher category trainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even at stations where there are exceptionally more than three platforms, the number isn&apos;t always mentioned (in most cases at stations on the Kyoto Line or the stations where higher-category trains pass nonstop,</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even at stations where there are exceptionally more than three platforms, the number isn&apos;t always mentioned (in most cases at stations on the Kyoto Line or the stations where higher-category trains pass nonstop,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>例：園田駅、茨木市駅、高槻市駅、桂駅）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ex. Sonoda Station, Ibaragi Station, Takatsuki-shi Station, Katsura Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">as in Sonoda Station, Ibaragi Station, Takatsuki-shi Station and Katsura Station).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">as in Sonoda Station, Ibaraki-shi Station, Takatsuki-shi Station and Katsura Station).</e>
<cmt>Ibaraki-shi Stationとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="239">
<j>また、仁川駅では阪神競馬場開催時の臨時列車の関係で回送車の発着があるため行き先すら付かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, at Nigawa Station, where on the days when the Hanshin Race Course opens, deadhead trains arrive and depart due to the operation of the special trains, even the destination is not mentioned in the announcement.</e>
<cmt>阪神競馬場→Hanshin Race Course (http://www.jra.go.jp/facilities/race/hanshin/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at Nigawa Station, where on the days the Hanshin Race Course opens, deadhead trains arrive and depart due to the operation of special trains, even the destination isn&apos;t mentioned in the announcement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at Nigawa Station, where on the days the Hanshin Race Course opens, deadhead trains arrive and depart due to the operation of special trains, even the destination isn&apos;t mentioned in the announcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>かつては正雀駅も配線の関係上1つのホームから両方向の列車が出るため行き先が付かなかったが、列車案内装置・放送機器の更新により2008年2月から優等列車停車駅並みの詳細放送に変更された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before, the destinations were not mentioned at Shojaku Station as well, because the two trains for the opposite direction departed from the same platform due to the wiring setup, but since February, 2008, the announcement has become as detailed as that of a station where higher category trains, thanks to the updated system for train information and announcement equipment for the passengers.</e>
<cmt>列車案内装置・放送機器→定訳不明：system for train information and announcement equipment for the passengersとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Previously, the destinations weren&apos;t mentioned at Shojaku Station either, because the two trains for the opposite direction departed from the same platform due to the wiring setup; however, since February 2008, the announcement has become as detailed as that of a station for higher-category trains, thanks to the updated system for train information and announcement equipment for the passengers.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previously, the destinations weren&apos;t mentioned at Shojaku Station either, because the two trains for the opposite direction departed from the same platform due to the wiring setup; however, since February 2008, the announcement has become as detailed as that of a station for higher-category trains, thanks to the updated system for train information and announcement equipment for the passengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="241">
<j>淡路駅には1号線が無く、2～5号線のみとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Awaji Station there is no Platform 1-go, and only from 2-go to 5-go are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Awaji Station there is no Platform 1-go, so only from 2-go to 5-go are available.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Awaji Station there is no Platform 1-go, so only from 2-go to 5-go are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>かつては1号線が存在したためで、社内業務にも乗客にも混乱となることを防ぐために、1号線廃止の際に番号を順送りしなかった経緯がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because, at one time, there existed Platform 1-go, and when its became disused, the remaining platform numbers had not been shifted forward, in order to avoid the passengers&apos; confusion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because there once existed Platform 1-go, and when it was abandoned the remaining platform numbers weren&apos;t shifted forward in order to prevent confusion among the passengers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because there once existed Platform 1-go, and when it was abandoned the remaining platform numbers weren&apos;t shifted forward in order to prevent confusion among the passengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="243">
<j>桂駅には1号線の隣に「C号線」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Katsura Station, next to Platform 1-go, there is a track called &quot;C-go.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Katsura Station, next to Platform 1-go, there is a track called &quot;C-go.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Katsura Station, next to Platform 1-go, there is a track called &apos;Platform C-go.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正Platform C-go としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>もともとは、隣接する桂車庫のC号線であったものを、ホームを設置して駅としたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, this &quot;C-go&quot; was the lane constructed in the adjacent Katsura depot, and later, a platform was added along the track to form the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, &quot;C-go&quot; was the lane constructed in the adjacent Katsura depot, and later a platform was added along the track to form the station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Platform C-go was the lane constructed in the adjacent Katsura depot, and later a platform was added along the track to complete the station.</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;削除Platform C-go としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>番号を順送りしなかった点で、1号線のない淡路駅と同じ理由である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason is the same as that of Awaji Station, which does not have Track 1-go, in the point that the platform numbers had not been adjusted forward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason is the same as that of Awaji Station, which does not have Track 1-go, regarding the point that the platform numbers have not been adjusted forward.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why the platform numbers have not been adjusted forward is the same as that of Awaji Station, which does not have Platform 1-go.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m afraid this (and the Japanese) doesn&apos;t really make much sense to me so I have just looked at the grammar really. I have had to put this back into one sentence as breaking the sentence up in such a way resulted in very unnatural English.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>駅・車内での案内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Announcement at stations and in the cars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Announcements at stations and in the cars</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Announcements at stations and in the cars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="246">
<j>天神橋筋六丁目駅に停車する列車は、「次は天神橋筋六丁目、天六です」といったアナウンスをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trains that make a stop at Tenjinbashi-rokuchome Station, give an announcement such as: &quot;Next stop is Tenjinbashi-rokuchome, Tenroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trains that stop at Tenjinbashi-rokuchome Station give announcements such as, &quot;Next stop is Tenjinbashi-rokuchome, Tenroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trains that stop at Tenjinbashisuji-rokuchome Station give announcements such as, &apos;Next stop is Tenjinbashisuji-rokuchome, Tenroku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正天神橋筋のスペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>略称を最初に言う車掌が多い中、珍しい例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an exceptional case because most of the conductors pronounce the abbreviated name of a station at first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an exceptional case because most of the conductors initially announce the station by its abbreviated name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an exceptional case because most of the conductors initially announce the station by its abbreviated name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="248">
<j>梅田、三宮、宝塚といった西日本旅客鉄道の路線に乗り換え可能な駅に着く際の乗り換え案内では旧日本国有鉄道時代から一貫してJR線への案内をしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the announcement given in a train arriving at a transfer station to a certain main line of West Japan Railway Company, such as the Umeda Station, Sannnomiya Station or Takarazuka station, no information on the transfer to JR Lines is mentioned, as has been since the time of the former Japan National Railways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the announcement given in a train arriving at a transfer station to a certain main line of the West Japan Railway Company, such as Umeda Station, Sannnomiya Station or Takarazuka Station, no information on the transfer to JR Lines is mentioned, as has been the case since the time of the former Japan National Railways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the announcement given in a train arriving at a transfer station to a certain main line of the West Japan Railway Company, such as Umeda Station, Sannnomiya Station or Takarazuka Station, no information on the transfer to JR Lines is mentioned, as has been the case since the time of the former Japan National Railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>ただし2006～2007年のダイヤ改正で路線図に関してのみ表記するようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the timetable revision in 2006/2007, the JR lines was included in the diagram.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the timetable revision in 2006/2007 the JR lines were included in the diagram.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the timetable revision in 2006/2007 the JR lines were included in the diagram.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="250">
<j>ちなみに大阪市交通局は堺筋線扇町駅をJR大阪環状線への乗り換え駅として案内しているが、阪急電車の路線図にはその旨が記載されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, while Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau indicates Ogimachi Station on the Sakaisuji Line as a transfer station to the JR Osaka Loop Line, in the diagram of Hankyu Railway it is not mentioned.</e>
<cmt>JR大阪環状線→JR Osaka Loop Line(http://www.westjr.co.jp/english/travel/kix/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, while the Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau indicates Ogimachi Station on the Sakaisuji Line as a transfer station to the JR Osaka Loop Line, in the diagram of Hankyu Railway it isn&apos;t mentioned.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, while the Osaka Municipal Transportation Bureau indicates Ogimachi Station on the Sakaisuji Line as a transfer station to the JR Osaka Loop Line, in the diagram of Hankyu Railway it isn&apos;t mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="251">
<j>駅構内の自動放送はタレントの片山光男と丸子由美が担当している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Automatic announcement in the stations is made by two entertainers, Mitsuo KATAYAMA and Yumi MARUKO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Automatic announcements in the stations are made by two entertainers: Mitsuo Katayama and Yumi Maruko.</e>
<cmt>plural, lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Automatic announcements in the stations are made by two entertainers: Mitsuo KATAYAMA and Yumi MARUKO.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>ちなみに片山は並行する福知山線の駅放送も務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KATAYAMA also makes an announcement for the Fukuchiyama Line which is running in parallel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katayama also makes an announcement for the Fukuchiyama Line, which runs in parallel.</e>
<cmt>lowercase, gram</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KATAYAMA also makes an announcement in the stations for the Fukuchiyama Line, which runs in parallel.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。駅放送を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="253">
<j>1996年1月1日、「ジェントルサウンドサービス」の一環として、駅・車内での案内を変更した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 1, 1996, as a part of the &quot;Gentle Sound Service,&quot; the announcement at stations and in the cars are changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1, 1996, as part of the &quot;Gentle Sound Service,&quot; the announcements at stations and in the cars were changed.</e>
<cmt>preposition, gram</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 1996, as part of the &apos;Gentle Sound Service,&apos; the announcements at stations and in the cars were changed.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>具体的には自社線内での車掌の手笛による発車合図を原則廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More specifically: the departing signal whistled by the conductor was principally discontinue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More specifically, the departing signal whistled by the conductor was principally discontinued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More specifically, the departing signal whistled by the conductor was principally discontinued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>優等列車の停車駅の案内を「次は○○まで止まりません」から「次は○○に止まります」に。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The announcement on the stop was changed from: &quot;Next, the train will not stop until xx&quot; to &quot;Next, the train makes a stop at XX.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The announcement on the stop was changed from &quot;Next, the train will not stop until xx&quot; to &quot;Next, the train makes a stop at XX.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The announcement on the next stop for higher-category trains was changed from &apos;Next, the train will not stop until XX&apos; to &apos;Next, the train makes a stop at XX,&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正次の文章につなげるため、カンマを追加しました。 一部訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>次駅の案内を「次は○○でございます」から「次の停車駅は○○でございます」に、また案内回数を主要駅を除き原則1回とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the announcement on the next station: from &quot;Next is XX.&quot; to &quot;Next stop is XX.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the announcement on the next station: from &quot;Next is XX&quot; to &quot;Next stop is XX.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the announcement on the next station was changed from &apos;Next is XX&apos; to &apos;Next stop is XX,&apos; and basically the announcement was to be made only once except for major stations.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 一部訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>2005年10月1日から車内での案内放送を「次の停車駅は○○でございます」から「次は○○、○○です」に変更している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since October 2006, the announcement in the cars has been changed from &quot;Next stop is XX.&quot; to &quot;Next stop is XX, XX.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since October 2006, the announcement in the cars has been changed from &quot;Next stop is XX&quot; to &quot;Next stop is XX, XX.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since October 1, 2006, the announcement in the cars has been &apos;Next is XX&apos; instead of &apos;Next stop is XX, XX.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正October 1 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>2006年10月1日からは神戸線・宝塚線で2007年3月16日からは京都線の駅ホームでの案内放送を「ただいま到着の電車は各駅停車梅田行きでございます」から「ただいま到着の電車は各駅停車大阪梅田行きです」に変更している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the stations on the Kobe Line and Takarazuka Line, the announcement has been changed since October, 2006, from: &quot;The train now arriving is a local train bound for Umeda,&quot; to &quot;The train now arriving is a local train bound for Osaka Umeda,&quot; and on the platforms of the stations on the Kyoto Line since March 16, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the stations on the Kobe and Takarazuka lines, the announcement has been changed since October, 2006, from: &quot;The train now arriving is a local train bound for Umeda&quot; to &quot;The train now arriving is a local train bound for Osaka Umeda,&quot; and on the platforms of the stations of the Kyoto Line since March 16, 2007.</e>
<cmt>Preposition, gram</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the stations on the Kobe and Takarazuka lines, the announcement has been changed since October 1, 2006, from: &apos;The train now arriving is a local train bound for Umeda&apos; to &apos;The train now arriving is a local train bound for Osaka Umeda,&apos; and on the platforms of the stations of the Kyoto Line since March 16, 2007.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正October 1 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="259">
<j>梅田・三宮・新開地・河原町の4駅については「大阪梅田」「神戸三宮」「神戸新開地」「京都河原町」のようにアナウンスする（繰り返す場合は2回目以降、大阪・神戸・京都の部分を省略する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the 4 stations, Umeda, Sannomiya, Shinkaichi, and Kawaramachi, the name is announced as &quot;Osaka Umeda,&quot; &quot;Kobe Sannomiya,&quot; &quot;Kobe Shinkaichi,&quot; and &quot;Kyoto Kawaramachi&quot; (when the name is repeated twice or more, Osaka, Kobe or Kyoto is omitted).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the four stations Umeda, Sannomiya, Shinkaichi and Kawaramachi, the names are announced as &quot;Osaka Umeda,&quot; &quot;Kobe Sannomiya,&quot; &quot;Kobe Shinkaichi&quot; and &quot;Kyoto Kawaramachi&quot; (so that when the name is repeated twice or more, Osaka, Kobe or Kyoto is omitted).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the four stations of Umeda, Sannomiya, Shinkaichi and Kawaramachi, the names are announced as &apos;Osaka Umeda,&apos; &apos;Kobe Sannomiya,&apos; &apos;Kobe Shinkaichi&apos; and &apos;Kyoto Kawaramachi&apos; (so that when the name is repeated twice or more, Osaka, Kobe or Kyoto is omitted).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="260">
<j>ただし「神戸新開地」の呼称は大阪府内（梅田駅や十三駅など）のみ実施し、兵庫県内では単に「新開地」とアナウンスされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kobe Shinkaichi&quot; is the way of calling employed only inside Osaka Prefecture (Umeda Station, Juso Station, etc.) and at the stations located in Hyogo Prefecture, the name is simply announced as &quot;Shinkaichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kobe Shinkaichi&quot; is the way of calling employed only inside Osaka Prefecture (Umeda Station, Juso Station, etc.), while at the stations located in Hyogo Prefecture the name is simply announced as &quot;Shinkaichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Kobe Shinkaichi&apos; is used only inside Osaka Prefecture (Umeda Station, Juso Station, etc.), however; at the stations located in Hyogo Prefecture, just &apos;Shinkaichi&apos; is announced.</e>
<cmt>「ただし」を訳出。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>また、神戸高速線内の上り列車では「阪急三宮」「阪急・大阪梅田」とアナウンスされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the up trains running on Kobe Rapid Transit Railway lines, the names of the destinations are announced as &quot;Hankyu Sannomiya,&quot; and &quot;Hankyu/Osaka Umeda.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the up trains running on Kobe Rapid Transit Railway lines, the names of the destinations are announced as &quot;Hankyu Sannomiya&quot; and &quot;Hankyu/Osaka Umeda.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the inbound trains running on Kobe Rapid Transit Railway lines, the names of the destinations are announced as &apos;Hankyu Sannomiya&apos; and &apos;Hankyu Osaka Umeda.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 up→ inbound</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>梅田駅での乗車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boarding at Umeda Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boarding at Umeda Station</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boarding at Umeda Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="262">
<j>乗客は着席にこだわる者が多く、梅田駅では発車間際の特急や急行のドアの前に着席目当てで次の電車を待つ乗客の列がいつもできている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many passengers who obsessively stick to a determined seat, and therefore, at Umeda Station you can always see many passengers, who although are staying in rows in front of the doors of a limited express or an express train that is just to depart, are actually waiting for the next train with the expectation of sitting on their favorite seat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many passengers who obsessively stick to a determined seat, and therefore at Umeda Station one can always see many passengers, who although they are staying in rows in front of the doors of a limited express or an express train that is just to depart, are actually waiting for the next train with the expectation of sitting in their favorite seat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many passengers who insist on being seated, and therefore at Umeda Station one can always see many passengers, who although they are staying in rows in front of the doors of a limited express or an express train that is soon to depart, are in fact waiting for the next train with the expectation of sitting.</e>
<cmt>めあての座席に座りたいわけではなく、単に座りたい、という訳にしました。&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>川西能勢口駅や宝塚駅のように他線との乗換駅では次の電車の着席目当てで乗客が猛然とダッシュする風景も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At some transfer stations to other lines like Kawanishi-Noseguchi Station and Takarazuka Station, you can see many passengers making a furious dash for the next train to secure his/her seat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At some transfer stations to other lines like Kawanishi-Noseguchi Station and Takarazuka Station, one can see many passengers making a furious dash for the next train in order to secure that favorite seat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At some transfer stations to other lines like Kawanishi-Noseguchi Station and Takarazuka Station, one can see many passengers dashing furiously for the next train in order to secure seats.</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>なお、十三～梅田間の折り返し乗車は通常では不正乗車（この区間は運賃計算に含まないため）であるが、なにわ淀川花火大会（旧・平成淀川花火大会）の際には十三駅が大変混雑するため、梅田までの折り返し乗車を特例で認めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, on ordinary days, riding on a turned back train between Juso Station and Umeda Station is considered illegal (as the return-trip of the section is not calculated in the fare), but the day in which the Naniwa Yodogawa Fireworks Display (formerly called Heisei Yodogawa Fireworks Display) is celebrated, round-trip to Umeda Station is exceptionally admitted because Juso Station becomes enormously crowded.</e>
<cmt>なにわ淀川花火大会（旧・平成淀川花火大会）→定訳不明：Naniwa Yodogawa Fireworks Display (formerly called Heisei Yodogawa Fireworks Display)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, on ordinary days it&apos;s considered illegal to ride on a turned-back train between Juso Station and Umeda Station (since the return-trip of the section is not calculated in the fare); however, the day on which the Naniwa Yodogawa Fireworks Display (formerly called Heisei Yodogawa Fireworks Display) is celebrated, the round trip to Umeda Station is exceptionally admitted because Juso Station becomes enormously crowded.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, on ordinary days it&apos;s considered illegal to ride on a turned-back train between Juso Station and Umeda Station (since the return-trip of the section is not calculated in the fare); however, the day on which the Naniwa Yodogawa Fireworks Display (formerly called Heisei Yodogawa Fireworks Display) is celebrated, the round trip to Umeda Station is exceptionally admitted because Juso Station becomes enormously crowded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>携帯電話電源オフ車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car</e>
<cmt>携帯電話電源オフ車両→定訳不明： &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="265">
<j>阪急電鉄では、携帯電話の電源オフを終日ルールづけた車両「優先席携帯電話電源オフ車両」を全列車に設定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Railway sets in all the trains a car named &quot;Priority Seat / Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car,&quot; in which mobil phones are ruled to be switched off all day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Railway places in each train a car called the &quot;Priority Seat / Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car,&quot; in which mobile phones must be switched off at all times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Railway places in each train a car called the &apos;Priority Seat / Mobile Phone Power Source Off Car,&apos; in which mobile phones must remain off at all times.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 Mobil →Mobile</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>2003年6月10日から1か月間限定で試験導入、同年7月11日から本格的に導入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This car was provisionally introduced during one month from June 10, 2003 on trial basis and since July 11 of the same year, it has been formally introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This car was provisionally introduced on a trial basis during a one-month period beginning June 10, 2003, but since July 11 of the same year it has been formally operated.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This car was provisionally introduced on a trial basis during a one-month period beginning June 10, 2003, but since July 11 of the same year it has been formally operated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>また京都線に直通する大阪市営地下鉄堺筋線や同じ阪急グループの能勢電鉄・神戸電鉄でも導入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The car is also introduced in Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line, which is connected directly with the Kyoto Line, and Nose Electric Railway and Kobe Electric Railway, both of which are members of Hankyu Group.</e>
<cmt>能勢電鉄、神戸電鉄</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The car is also introduced in the Osaka City Subway Sakaisuji Line, which connects directly with the Kyoto Line as well as the Nose and Kobe electric railways, both of which are members of the Hankyu Group.</e>
<cmt>gram, lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The car is also introduced in the Osaka Municipal Subway Sakaisuji Line, which connects directly with the Kyoto Line as well as the Nose and Kobe electric railways, both of which are members of the Hankyu Group.</e>
<cmt>city→ municipal</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>またこの「携帯電話電源オフ車両」についてのアナウンスは、車掌によって少し違うことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of announcing on the &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car,&quot; sometimes varies according to the conductors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of announcing on the &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car&quot; varies occasionally, according to the conductor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manner in which the &apos;Mobile Phone Power Source Off Car&apos; is announced varies occasionally, according to the conductor.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正Mobil →Mobile</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="269">
<j>設定車両：1車両（神戸・宝塚・京都・嵐山・伊丹・箕面・川西能勢口側の先頭車両）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The designated car: 1 car (the first car of the trains heading for Kobe, Takarazuka, Kyoto, Arashiyama, Itami, Minoo, Kawanishi Noseguchi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The designated car is car &quot;1,&quot; (the first car of a train heading for Kobe, Takarazuka, Kyoto, Arashiyama, Itami, Minoo, Kawanishi Noseguchi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The designated car is car 1, (the first car of a train heading for Kobe, Takarazuka, Kyoto, Arashiyama, Itami, Mino, Kawanishi-Noseguchi).</e>
<cmt>Mino, Kawanishi-Noseguchiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>復活した「優先座席」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revived &quot;priority seats&quot;</e>
<cmt>The reserved priority seats for elderly or disabled persons was abolished in all cars on all lines (All seats of all cars were designated as priority seat.)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Revived &quot;priority seats&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Revived &apos;priority seats&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="270">
<j>もう一つ、阪急電鉄の独自ルールとして特筆されたものが「全席優先座席」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As another unique rule of Hankyu Railway worth mentioning was the designation of &quot;all seats-priority seats &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As another unique rule of Hankyu Railway worth mentioning was the designation of &quot;all seats--priority seats.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another unique rule of Hankyu Railway worth mentioning was the designation of &apos;all seats--priority seats.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>阪急電鉄では「特定の席にこだわらず、すべての座席で譲り合いの精神を」とのことから、決まった優先座席を廃止して1999年4月から「全席優先座席」を導入していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hankyu Railway, &quot;Priority seats&quot; were abolished and &quot;All seats-priority seats&quot; had been introduced since April 1999, based on the idea that &quot;we must show a spirit of give-and-take at all seats no matter whether it is designated or not.&quot;</e>
<cmt>譲り合いの精神→a spirit of give-and-take (英辞郎on the WEB)、全席優先座席→定訳不明：”All seats-priority seats&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hankyu Railway, &quot;Priority seats&quot; were abolished and &quot;All seats--priority seats&quot; was introduced in April 1999, based on the idea that &quot;we must show a spirit of give-and-take at each seat, whether it is designated or not.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hankyu Railway, &apos;Priority seats&apos; were abolished and &apos;All seats--priority seats&apos; was introduced in April 1999, based on the idea that &apos;we must show a spirit of give-and-take at each seat, whether it is designated or not.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>阪急電鉄で「携帯電話電源オフ車両」が設定されたのは、同業他社が「優先座席付近では携帯電話の電源をオフ」というルールをこぞって導入したが、阪急には特定の優先座席がなかったためこうなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related to this rule, Hankyu Railway had to set up &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off &quot;cars, because it didn&apos;t have any designated priority seats in the cars, while all other companies introduced the rule to switch off the mobil phone only around the reserved seats.</e>
<cmt>携帯電話電源オフ車両→定訳不明： &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off Car&quot;としました。　where the passengers are requested to untaggle his mobil phone, were experimentally introduced in all trains (for the details, please refer to the special comment)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coincident with this rule, Hankyu Railway had to set up &quot;Mobil Phone Power Source Off &quot; cars because it didn&apos;t have any designated priority seats in the cars, but all other companies introduced the rule to switch off the mobil phone only around the reserved seats.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coincident with this rule, Hankyu Railway had to set up &apos;Mobile Phone Power Source Off Cars&apos; because it didn&apos;t have any designated priority seats in the cars, but all other companies introduced the rule that mobile phones should remain off only around the reserved seats.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 Mobil →Mobile</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="273">
<j>ところが、阪急電鉄側の思惑とは裏腹にこの「全席優先座席」は浸透せず、ほとんど座席の譲り合いが行われていないという現状を受け、2007年6月末の阪急阪神ホールディングスの株主総会で再設置の要望があったのを機に全席優先座席を見直すことになり、同年10月29日に「全席優先座席」は廃止され、再び「優先座席」を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, against the company&apos;s expectation, it was revealed that the &quot;All seats-priority seats&quot; rule had not been penetrated among the passengers and the give-and-take spirit of the seats was seldom practiced, therefore the company decided to review the &quot;All seats-priority seats&quot; rule, based on the request for bringing back the priority seat which was presented at the shareholders meeting at the end of June, 2007, and on October 29 of the same year, the &quot;All seats-priority seats&quot; rule was abolished and the reserved &quot;priority seats&quot; were designated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, against the company&apos;s expectation it was revealed that the &quot;all seats--priority seats&quot; rule had not been penetrated among the passengers and the give-and-take spirit of the seats was seldom practiced; therefore, the company decided to review the &quot;all seats--priority seats&quot; rule, based on the request to brink back the priority seating, as presented at the shareholders meeting at the end of June 2007; and on October 29 of the same year the &quot;all seats--priority seats&quot; rule was abolished and the reserved &quot;priority seats&quot; were designated.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, against the company&apos;s expectation it was revealed that the &apos;all seats--priority seats&apos; rule had not been accepted among the passengers and the give-and-take spirit of the seats was seldom practiced; therefore, the company decided to review the &apos;all seats--priority seats&apos; rule, based on the request to bring back the priority seating, as presented at the shareholders&apos; meeting of the Hankyu Hanshin Holdings at the end of June 2007; and on October 29 of the same year the &apos;all seats--priority seats&apos; rule was abolished and the reserved &apos;priority seats&apos; were designated.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 brink →bring阪急阪神ホールディングスを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="274">
<j>しかし、優先座席の設置箇所は基本的に各車両の「梅田を前方としたときの最後尾座席」であるのだが、運転台、もしくは運転台跡が存在する車両はそれらの逆側の座席となっており、中間に運転台およびその廃止改造を行った車両が含まれる編成（神戸線の8032Fなど）だと、優先座席が車両によって前の方にあったり後ろの方にあったりとあまり統一されていないという懸念がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, the &quot;priority seats&quot; were basically set at &quot;the seats that shall be the final in the car when heading toward Umeda Station,&quot; it is not well-unified among the cars, because, in the cars with the driver&apos;s platform or the vacant space remained after the platform was removed, the priority seats are set just on the opposite of it, and when the fleets include such a car in the middle (like 8032F on the Kobe Line), the priority seats&apos; position becomes sometimes in the anterior part and other times in the posterior part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the &quot;priority seats&quot; were basically set as &quot;the seats that shall be the final in the car when heading toward Umeda Station,&quot; it is not well unified among the cars because, in the cars with the driver&apos;s platform or the vacant space remaining after the platform was removed, the priority seats are set just on the opposite of it, and when the fleet includes such a car in the middle (like 8032F of the Kobe Line), the priority seat position is sometimes in the anterior part but other times in the posterior part.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there still is a concern that, although the &apos;priority seats&apos; are basically set as &apos;the seats that shall be the most posterior part of the car when heading toward Umeda Station,&apos; it is not well unified among the cars because, in the cars with the driver&apos;s platform or the vacant space remaining after the platform was removed, the priority seats are set just on the opposite side of it, and when the fleet includes such a car in the middle (like 8032F of the Kobe Line), the priority seat position is sometimes in the anterior part or other times in the posterior part.</e>
<cmt>文脈を考えて一部修正しました。括弧修正final →most posterior part</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>乗務員と運転業務</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crew and railway operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crew and railway operation</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crew and railway operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="275">
<j>駅構内で優等列車の通過待ちをする列車の乗務員は必ずホームに立ち通過監視を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The crew of a local train waiting for a higher category train to pass at a station, is obliged to stand on the platform to monitor the passing train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The crew of a local train waiting for a higher-category train to pass at a station is obliged to stand on the platform and monitor the passing train.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crew of a local train waiting for a higher-category train to pass at a station is obliged to stand on the platform and monitor the passing train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>そのとき運転士はブレーキハンドルを非常ブレーキ位置にセットし、さらにマスコンキー（京都線車両の5300系以前についてはリバースハンドル：主幹制御器に取り付ける前進・後進の切り替えハンドル）を所持してホームに立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the driver, in addition to setting the brake handle at the emergency position, stands on the platform taking the master controller key with him (when the train is Kyoto Line Train Series 5300 or older, the reverse handle: a switching handle bar for going forward/backward, which is attachable to the principle controller).</e>
<cmt>マスコンキー（京都線車両の5300系以前についてはリバースハンドル：主幹制御器に取り付ける前進・後進の切り替えハンドル）→この部分定訳不明：mastar controller key in hand (in case of Kyoto Line Train Series 5300 and before, the reverse handle (a schiching handle bar for foreward/backward movement, which is attached to the principle controller)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the driver, in addition to setting the brake handle at the emergency position, stands on the platform, taking the master controller key with him (when the train is Kyoto Line Train Series 5300 or older, the reverse handle: a switching handlebar for going forward/backward, which is attachable to the principle controller).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the driver, in addition to setting the brake handle at the emergency position, stands on the platform, taking the master controller key with him (when the train is Kyoto Line Train Series 5300 or older, the reverse handle: a switching handlebar for going forward/backward, which is attachable to the principle controller).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="277">
<j>乗務員交替駅発車時、警笛吹鳴を行うことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the train starts at a station where the crew change has been made, it is sometimes signaled with an alarm horn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the train starts at a station where the crew change has been made, it is sometimes signaled with an alarm horn.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the train starts at a station where the crew change has been made, it is sometimes signaled with an alarm horn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>テレビ・映画撮影</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TV and movie shooting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TV and movie shooting</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TV and movie shooting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="278">
<j>1990年代後半頃に近畿地方の鉄道事業者では初めて外部の事業者のテレビ番組、映画、ドラマの撮影を認めた（日本の鉄道事業者で最初にこの事業を開始したのは京成電鉄である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late 1990s, as the first railway company in the Kinki District, Hankyu Railway allowed third-party entities to shoot TV programs, movies and dramas in its premises (in Japan, Keisei Electric Railway was the first railway company that started TV and movie shooting business).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late 1990s, as the first railway company in the Kinki District, Hankyu Railway allowed third-party entities to shoot TV programs, movies and dramas in its premises (in Japan, Keisei Electric Railway was the first railway company that started business activity related to the shooting of TV and movies).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late 1990s, as the first railway company in the Kinki District, Hankyu Railway allowed third-party entities to shoot TV programs, movies and dramas in its premises (in Japan, Keisei Electric Railway was the first railway company that started business activity related to the shooting of TV and movies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="279">
<j>登記上の本店所在地を大阪府池田市に置いていることから、池田市を所管する豊能税務署の法人税ランクでは常にトップである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the address of the registered office of the company is in Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture, it is always at the top in corporate tax ranking at Toyono Tax Office, which has jurisdiction over Ikeda City.</e>
<cmt>豊能税務署→Toyono Tax Office (http://www.city.toyonaka.osaka.jp/top/_download_/4356/p.15.pdf),</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the address of the registered office of the company is in Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture, it is always at the top in the corporate tax ranking at Toyono Tax Office, which has jurisdiction over Ikeda City.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the address of the registered office of the company is in Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture, it is always at the top in the corporate tax ranking at Toyono Tax Office, which has jurisdiction over Ikeda City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="280">
<j>日本の鉄道事業者で初めて「学生専用出口」を1960年代中頃に甲陽線甲陽園駅を皮切りに一部の駅で開設した（制服着用が条件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company set out the &quot;exit exclusively for students&quot; in the mid 1960s at several stations, starting at Koyoen Station on the Koyo Line, which was the first attempt as a railway company in the Kinki District. (applied only for the students wearing the school uniform).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company set out the &quot;exit exclusively for students&quot; in the mid-1960s at several stations, starting at Koyoen Station on the Koyo Line, which was the first attempt as a railway company in the Kinki District (this applied only to students who wore school uniforms).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company set out the &apos;exit exclusively for students&apos; in the mid-1960s at several stations, starting at Koyoen Station on the Koyo Line, which was the first attempt as a railway company in Japan (but it applied only to students who wore school uniforms).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正　Kinki District→ Japan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="281">
<j>毎年年末年始は土曜・休日ダイヤ編成だが、宝塚線に限り正月三が日は「臨時ダイヤ」として急行と普通列車をそれぞれ10分ずつの間隔で運転する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the year-end and new year period, the timetable for Saturdays and holidays are applied, but the Takarazuka Line exceptionally operates the express and local trains every 10 minutes each in the first three days of the New Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Year End/New Year period, the timetable for Saturdays and holidays is applied, but the Takarazuka Line exceptionally operates the express and local trains every 10 minutes each in the first three days of the new year.</e>
<cmt>punct, cap</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Year End/New Year period, the timetable for Saturdays and holidays is applied, but the Takarazuka Line exceptionally operates the express and local trains every 10 minutes each in the first three days of the new year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>京都線でも昼間の特急が増発されるまでは正月三が日に限って、特急・急行を増発していた時期もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one time, the Kyoto Line also operated the limited express and express trains on an extra bases during the first three days of the New Year, until the frequency of the limited express during daytime was increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one time the Kyoto Line also operated the limited express and express trains on an extra basis during the first three days of the new year, until the frequency of the limited express during daytime was increased.</e>
<cmt>lowercase in this context</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one time the Kyoto Line also operated the limited express and express trains on an extra basis during the first three days of the new year, until the frequency of the limited express during daytime was increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="283">
<j>朝夕のラッシュ時などの押し屋（アルバイト）として学生班が設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the morning and evening rush hours, &quot;student corps&quot; is stationed as Train pushers or &quot;Oshiya&quot; (part-time job).</e>
<cmt>学生班→定訳不明：&quot;student corps&quot;としました。押し屋→Train pushers or &quot;Oshiya&quot; ((http://www.jref.com/forum/showthreas.php?t=39685)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the morning and evening rush hours, &quot;student corps&quot; are stationed as train pushers or &quot;Oshiya&quot; (a part-time job).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the morning and evening rush hours, &apos;student corps&apos; are stationed as &apos;Oshiya,&apos; the staff people who push customers into trains (a part-time job).</e>
<cmt>train pushers→ staff who pushes customers into trains　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>その名の通り、大学生と専門学校生が雇用対象である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the name suggests, those employed are university students and vocational college students.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name suggests, those employed are university students and vocational college students.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name suggests, those employed are university students and vocational college students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="285">
<j>関西私鉄で初めて駅構内に立ち食いそば・うどん店を設けたのは阪急電鉄である（阪急そば）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the private railway companies in Kansai District, it was Hankyu Railway that opened Tachigui Soba/Udon noodle stand (Hankyu Soba) inside the station for the first time.</e>
<cmt>立ち食いそば・うどん→定訳不明：Tachigui Soba/Udon noodle stand としました。(http://chibadailyphoto.blogspot.com/2008/07/tachigui-soba.html 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the private railway companies in Kansai District, it was Hankyu Railway that opened the Tachigui soba/udon noodle stands (Hankyu Soba) inside the station for the first time.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the private railway companies in Kansai District, it was Hankyu Railway that opened the Tachigui soba/udon noodle stands (Hankyu Soba) inside the station for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="286">
<j>国際文化公園都市（愛称：彩都）に土地を保有している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company owns a land in the International Culture Park (Saito).</e>
<cmt>国際文化公園年（愛称：彩都）→International Culture Partk (Saito) (http://saito.tv/e/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company owns land in the International Culture Park (Saito).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company owns land in the International Culture Park (Saito).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>鉄道模型</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway models</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway models</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway models</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="287">
<j>グリーンマックスより阪急通勤車の未塗装エコノミーキットが発売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unfinished economy model kit of Hankyu commuter trains is on sale by Greenmax Corporation.</e>
<cmt>グリーンマックス→Greenmax Corporation (http://www.greenmax.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An economical, unfinished model kit of Hankyu commuter trains is sold by Greenmax Corporation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An economical, unfinished model kit of Hankyu commuter trains is sold by Greenmax Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>パーツの組合せで2000系～8000系までの車両が製作可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using various parts in combination, trains of Series 2000 to 8000 can be made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using various parts in combination, trains of the series 2000 through 8000 can be made.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using various parts in combination, trains of the Series 2000 through 8000 can be made.</e>
<cmt>Seriesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="289">
<j>その他の形式については各形式の項目を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For other types, please refer to the sections &quot;Models by type.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For other types, please refer to the section &quot;Models by Type.&quot;</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For other types, please refer to the section &quot;Models by Type.&quot;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>関係企業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Associated companies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Associated companies</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Associated companies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="290">
<j>阪急阪神東宝グループに属する全企業の一覧は阪急阪神東宝グループを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For all the companies belonging to the Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group, please refer to the section &quot;Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group.&quot;</e>
<cmt>阪急阪神東宝グループ：Hanshin Hankyu Toho Group(http://www.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/hankyu-hanshin-toho-group/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For all the companies belonging to the Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group, please refer to the section &quot;Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For all the companies belonging to the Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group, please refer to the section &quot;Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group.&quot;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="291">
<j>阪急百貨店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Department Store</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Department Store</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Department Store</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="292">
<j>東宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toho Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.toho.co.jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toho Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toho Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>阪神電気鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanshin Electric Railway Group</e>
<cmt>http://www.hanshin.co.jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanshin Electric Railway Group</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanshin Electric Railway Group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>阪急電鉄グループ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation Group</e>
<cmt>http://www.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/english/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Corporation Group</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Corporation Group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>能勢電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noze Electric Railway Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.noseden.hankyu.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noze Electric Railway Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nose Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>Noze →Nose</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="296">
<j>北大阪急行電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kita-Osaka Kyuko Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.kita-kyu.co.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kita-Osaka Kyuko Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kita-Osaka Kyuko Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>神戸電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Electric Railway Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.shintetsu.co.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Electric Railway Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>co.,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="298">
<j>北神急行電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokushinkyuko Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.hokushinkyuko.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokushinkyuko Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokushinkyuko Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>神戸高速鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Co., Ltd</e>
<cmt>http://www.kobe-kousoku.jo/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Co., Ltd</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Rapid Transit Railway Co., Ltd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>阪急バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://bus.hankyu.co.jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="301">
<j>阪急田園バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Den&apos;en Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://bus,hankyu.co.jp/denen/denen.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Den&apos;en Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Den&apos;en Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>神鉄バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintetsu Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.shintetsu-bus.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintetsu Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintetsu Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>丹後海陸交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Kairiku Kotsu Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.tankai.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Kairiku Kotsu Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Kairiku Kotsu Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="304">
<j>阪急タクシー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Taxi Inc.</e>
<cmt>http://www.hankyu-taxi.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Taxi Inc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Taxi Inc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>阪急交通社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Travel International Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.hankyu-travel.com/company/outline/about.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Travel International Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Travel International Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>関西テレビ放送 - フジニュースネットワーク/フジネットワークの準キー局。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansai Telecasting Corporation - a sub key station of Fuji New Network and Fuji Network System.</e>
<cmt>関西テレビ放送→、フジニュースネットワーク→Fuji News Network (http://www.fnn-news.com/en/index.html)、フジネットワーク→Fuji Network System (http://www.fuji-network.com),</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansai Telecasting Corporation is a sub-key station of the Fuji New Network and Fuji Network System.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansai Telecasting Corporation is a sub-key station of the Fuji News Network and Fuji Network System.</e>
<cmt>New →News</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="307">
<j>フジサンケイグループにも近い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also has a close tie with Fuji Sankei Group.</e>
<cmt>、準キー局→定訳不明：sub key stationとしました（放送局の副調整室の場合はsub control roomと呼ばれているので）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also closely tied with the Fuji Sankei Group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also closely allied with the Fujisankei Communications Group.</e>
<cmt>Fujisankei Communications Groupとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="308">
<j>阪急コミュニケーションズ（元TBSブリタニカ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Communications Co., Ltd (former TBS-Britannica)</e>
<cmt>http://www.hankyu-com.co.jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Communications Co., Ltd. (formerly TBS-Britannica)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Communications Co., Ltd. (formerly TBS-Britannica)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>アルナ車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alna Sharyo Co., Ltd</e>
<cmt>http://holdings.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/ir/zaimu/ar2004e.pdf)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alna Sharyo Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alna Sharyo Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>ステーションファイナンス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station Finance Inc.</e>
<cmt>http://stafi.jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station Finance Inc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station Finance Inc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="311">
<j>シアター・ドラマシティ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theater Drama City</e>
<cmt>http://www.umegei.com/main.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theater Drama City</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theater Drama City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="312">
<j>アーバン・エース</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urban Ace Corporation</e>
<cmt>http://www.uace.hankyu.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urban Ace Corporation</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urban Ace Corporation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>森組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mori-Gumi Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.morigumi.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mori-Gumi Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mori-Gumi Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="314">
<j>コマ・スタジアム - 東宝グループでもある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coma Stadium Co., Ltd.- also belongs to Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>コマ・スタジアム→Koma Studium Co., Ltd.(http://www.koma-sta.co.jp)、東宝グループ→Toho Group</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coma Stadium Co., Ltd. belongs to the Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koma Stadium Co., Ltd. belongs to the Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>coma→ koma</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>東京楽天地 - 東宝グループでもある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Rakutenchi Co., Ltd. - also belongs to Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>東京楽天地→Tokyo Rakiutenchi Co., Ltd.(http://www.rakutenchi.co.jp/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Rakutenchi Co., Ltd. also belongs to the Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Rakutenchi Co., Ltd. also belongs to the Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="316">
<j>オーエス - 東宝グループでもある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OS Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>オーエス→OS Co., Ltd. (http://www.osgroup.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OS Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OS Co., Ltd. also belongs to the Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="317">
<j>下津井電鉄 - 阪急電鉄が資本参加しているが、関係は比較的希薄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotsui Dentetsu - receives Hankyu Railway&apos;s capital participation, but has a rather scarce relation.</e>
<cmt>下津井電鉄→Shimotutui Dentetsu (http://www.shimoden.co.jp/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotsui Dentetsu receives Hankyu Railway&apos;s capital participation but has a somewhat minimal relationship.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimotsui Dentetsu receives Hankyu Railway&apos;s capital participation but has a somewhat minimal relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="318">
<j>全但バス - かつて阪急電鉄の関連企業であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zentan Bus Co., Ltd. - was once an affiliate to Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>全但バス→Zentan Bus Co., Ltd (http://www.sentanbus.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zentan Bus Co., Ltd. was once an affiliate of Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zentan Bus Co., Ltd. was once an affiliate of Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="319">
<j>池田銀行 - 阪急阪神ホールディングスが大株主で、阪急電鉄の駅構内に設置している現金自動預け払い機 (PatSat) の管理銀行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bank of Ikeda, Ltd. - Hankyu Hanshin Holdings is its major shareholder, and the bank is in charge of the management of the automated teller machines (PatSat) installed at stations on the Hankyu Railway lines.</e>
<cmt>池田銀行→The Bank of Ikeda Lte. (http://www.ikedabank.co.jp/)、現金自動預け払い機（PatSat）→automated teller machine (PatSat) (英辞郎on the WEB)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bank of Ikeda, Ltd., has Hankyu Hanshin Holdings is its major shareholder; the bank is in charge of the management of the automated teller machines (PatSat) installed at stations on the Hankyu Railway lines.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bank of Ikeda, Ltd. has Hankyu Hanshin Holdings as its major shareholder; the bank is in charge of the management of the automated teller machines (PatSat) installed at stations on the Hankyu Railway lines.</e>
<cmt>Ltd.の後のカンマを削除is →as</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="320">
<j>毎日放送 - 関西テレビの開局に携わっているイメージが強いが、毎日放送の前身である新日本放送の開局にも携わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainichi Broadcasting System, Inc.- Although, many people imagine that Hankyu is the company that took part in launching Kansai Telecasting Corporation, it was also involved in opening the station of Mainichi Broadcasting System, former Kansai Telecasting Corporation.</e>
<cmt>毎日放送→Mainichi Broadcasting System (http://www.mbs.jp/)、関西テレビ→Kansai Telecasting Corporation (http://www.ktv.co.jp/e/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainichi Broadcasting System, Inc.: Although many people imagine that Hankyu is the company that took part in launching Kansai Telecasting Corporation, it was also involved in opening the station of Mainichi Broadcasting System, formerly the Kansai Telecasting Corporation.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainichi Broadcasting System, Inc.: Although many people imagine that Hankyu is the company that took part in launching Kansai Telecasting Corporation, it was also involved in opening the station of Mainichi Broadcasting System, formerly the Shinnihon Broadcasting System.</e>
<cmt>新日本放送→定訳不明　Shinnihon Broadcasting Systemとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="321">
<j>エフエム大阪 - 阪急阪神ホールディングスが株主になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FM Osaka - Hankyu Hanshin Holdings is one of their shareholders.</e>
<cmt>エフエム大阪→FM Osaka (http://fmosaka.net/index.shtml)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FM Osaka: Hankyu Hanshin Holdings is one of its shareholders.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FM Osaka: Hankyu Hanshin Holdings is one of its shareholders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="322">
<j>現在SDD（ストップ・ドランク・ドライビング）プロジェクト（飲酒運転をやめる運動）のスポンサーとして阪急阪神東宝ホールディングスとして提供。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company is sponsoring the project &quot;Stop Drunk Driving (SDD)&quot; to promote the abstinence of drunk-driving, in the name of Hankyu Hanshin Toho Holdings.</e>
<cmt>阪急阪神東宝ホールディングス→阪急阪神東宝グループ：Hanshin Hankyu Toho Group (http://www.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/hankyu-hanshin-toho-group/)では？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company sponsors the project &quot;Stop Drunk Driving (SDD)&quot; to promote abstinence from drunk-driving, doing so in the name of Hankyu Hanshin Toho Holdings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company sponsors the Stop Drunk Driving (SDD) project in order to promote abstinence from drunk-driving, doing so in the name of Hankyu Hanshin Toho Group.</e>
<cmt>阪急阪神東宝ホールディングス→阪急阪神東宝グループ：Hanshin Hankyu Toho Group (http://www.hankyu-hanshin.co.jp/hankyu-hanshin-toho-group/)に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="323">
<j>Kiss-FM KOBE - 時期は不明だが、過去に提供番組があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiss-FM KOBE - Although the period of time is unknown, there was a program sponsored by Hankyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiss-FM/Kobe: Although the period of time is unknown, there was a program sponsored by Hankyu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiss-FM/Kobe: Although the period of time is unknown, there was a program sponsored by Hankyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>提供番組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sponsored programs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sponsored programs</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sponsored programs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="324">
<j>阪急ドラマシリーズ - 関西テレビで放送されていた番組で、近畿地区では阪急百貨店・阪急不動産とともにスポンサーとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Drama Series - It was televised on Kansai Telecasting (KTV), and together with Hankyu Department Store and Hankyu Realty Co., Ltd., the company was a sponsor of the series.</e>
<cmt>阪急百貨店→Hankyu Department Store</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hankyu Drama Series&quot; was televised on Kansai Telecasting (KTV) and, together with Hankyu Department Store and Hankyu Realty Co., Ltd., the company was a sponsor of the series.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Drama Series - A TV program televised on Kansai Telecasting Corporation (KTV) and, together with Hankyu Department Store and Hankyu Realty Co., Ltd., the company was a sponsor of the series.</e>
<cmt>オリジナルの訳に戻し、Corporationを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="325">
<j>MBSナウ - かつて提供していたテレビ番組。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MBS Now - A TV program once sponsored by the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;MBS Now&quot; TV program was once sponsored by the company.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MBS Now - A TV program once sponsored by the company.</e>
<cmt>オリジナルの訳に戻しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="326">
<j>MBSタイガースナイター - 「ブレーブス・ダイナミック・アワー」では阪急百貨店とともに提供したラジオ番組。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MBS Tigers Nighter (baseball night game) - A radio program cosponsored by the company and Hankyu Department Store and rebroadcasted in &quot;Braves Dynamic Hour.&quot;</e>
<cmt>阪急百貨店→Hankyu Department Store</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;MBS Tigers Nighter,&quot; was a radio program on baseball games cosponsored by the company and Hankyu Department Store and rebroadcasted as the &quot;Braves Dynamic Hour.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MBS Tigers Nighter (baseball night game) - A radio program cosponsored by the company and Hankyu Department Store and rebroadcasted in &apos;Braves Dynamic Hour.&apos;</e>
<cmt>オリジナルの訳に戻し、括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Arufu(id:733), ひななみ(id:119899), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), Nnh(id:474), 937(id:48634), Ojigiri(id:329), Link-Fight(id:112705), NHK 200X(id:214988), Tigers boy(id:15761), Engine gory(id:33022), Roga246(id:53246), 準急三条(id:25072), 秀の介(id:490), 5816K(id:102574), Amateur(id:58459), Kyoww(id:126965), Gewagewa(id:40129), 白糸(id:47025), Mikomaid(id:56139), Ritsuka(id:6464), Hoge-(id:158), Starbacks(id:1018), Tetsuo1968(id:12092), Bergmann(id:85282), Cozy(id:132), Pepsi(id:783), Toru Imanaka(id:139079), Robinhou(id:63040), T・M(id:10670), Utsuda(id:605), Shota(id:10854), 素館(id:20524), Rusk(id:9895), Ichii-ya(id:48912), Pondehiyo0000(id:182620), NOWOW(id:62041), Kyoutanabe124(id:175304), オーシャン(id:117633), Mutumi06(id:82739), 三菱善次郎(id:21924), Cho-ji(id:45537), Mipu(id:5360), TANUKI(id:28527), SVS(id:18615), 大阪日日新聞(id:97882), Tznishio(id:41400), Kawa-kei(id:15790), Bakkai(id:7233), つつお(id:102003), Mandm(id:45549), S.S.Exp.Hashimoto(id:4001), Charenji(id:7908), 山本輝雄(id:19245), Kansai explorer(id:48975), 550(id:11994), Kumatora(id:16941), 暇・カキコ(id:65563), Mkb(id:11233), Ohura(id:5986), MBP(id:93853), Naru-W(id:17852), Sunen(id:10700), Spitzcandy(id:35201), Nevylax(id:38464), Piano92925(id:83263), Tacacazu(id:32728), Mangos(id:10010), Sasara(id:28616), Chobot(id:20846), Hirotaro(id:1437), 12425183(id:80345), RheinBlitz(id:85088), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Bitland(id:14506), Tokatsu Kokubu(id:99966), 900(id:10100), HATARA KEI(id:28915), LERK(id:4460), 捕澤(id:23785), Jkr2255(id:16760), J o(id:26533), 波岡悟史(id:101567), Rokkohstream(id:17493), なおぞー(id:80442), しるふぃ(id:11247), MASA(id:2399), Nagkeihen(id:183638), こうやま(id:74302), びぜん海月(id:71707), Tokumiki0(id:12043), Sat.K(id:3751), Mover(id:7146), NヤッホーN(id:59050), 220.(id:7930), Shinkansen(id:13703), どんどん(id:172259), Ahonosuke(id:12817), Ktr(id:30468), Fromm(id:71291), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Ksoaa(id:19437), SIK(id:19166), Unamu(id:14627), Wakei(id:79080), 663highland(id:18755), Chikara1983(id:59556), Yagipedia(id:149294), Safkan(id:423), 210.(id:9838), オナガドリ(id:15179), Mtdhryk(id:106423), ホイップ(id:44812), 一騎当千(id:56448), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>