<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>同志社前駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshishamae Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshishamae Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshishamae Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>同志社前駅（どうししゃまええき）は、京都府京田辺市三山木垣ノ内にある、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）片町線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Miyamaki Kakinouchi, Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture, Doshishamae Station is a stop on the Katamachi Line of West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshishamae Station, located in Miyamaki Kakinouchi, Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Katamachi Line of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshishamae Station, located in Miyamaki Kakinouchi, Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Katamachi Line of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>名前のとおり学校法人同志社の京田辺校地（同志社大学京田辺校地・同志社女子大学京田辺校地・同志社国際中学校・高等学校）への最寄駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As indicated by its nameitself, the station is the one nearest to the Kyotanabe Campus of The Doshisha (Doshisha University, Kyotanabe Campus, Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts, Kyotanabe Campus, and Doshisha International Junior/Senior High School).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As indicated by its name, the station is the one nearest to the Kyotanabe Campus of The Doshisha (Doshisha University, Kyotanabe Campus, Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts, Kyotanabe Campus, and Doshisha International Junior &amp; Senior High School).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As indicated by its name, the station is the one nearest to the Kyotanabe Campus of The Doshisha (Doshisha University, Kyotanabe Campus, Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts, Kyotanabe Campus, and Doshisha International Junior &amp; Senior High School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>改札から同志社大学正門・同志社国際高等学校正門までは直線であるが坂道を登って徒歩10分、同志社女子大学正門までは徒歩3分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After through the exit gate, walking on a straight uphill road takes you to the main gate of Doshisha University and that of Doshisha International Senior High School in 10 minutes and to the main gate of Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts in three minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon leaving the exit gate, a ten-minute walk on a road directly uphill takes you to the main gate of Doshisha University and that of Doshisha International Senior High School, or in three minutes to the main gate of Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts.</e>
<cmt>ALTERNATIVELY, THIS WOULD BE High School, or to the main gate of Doshish Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts three minutes beyond that point</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon leaving the exit gate, a ten-minute walk on a road directly uphill takes you to the main gate of Doshisha University and that of Doshisha International Senior High School, or in three minutes to the main gate of Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同志社田辺キャンパス（現・京田辺キャンパス）の開校に伴い開業した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This station started its operation when Doshisha&apos;s Tanabe Campus (current Kyotanabe Cumpas) opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This station started its operation when Doshisha&apos;s Tanabe Campus (THE current Kyotanabe Campus) opened.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This station started its operation when Doshisha&apos;s Tanabe Campus (the current Kyotanabe Campus) opened.</e>
<cmt>THE → the　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本国有鉄道（当時）としては初めての学校（学園）名を冠した駅となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era of Japan [Japanese] National Railways (JNR), it was the first station using a school or campus name for its name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era of Japan [Japanese] National Railways (JNR), it was the first station to incorporate the name of a school or campus into its own.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era of Japan National Railways (JNR), it was the first station to incorporate the name of a school or campus into its own.</e>
<cmt>[Japanese」を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>2面2線のプラットホーム形状と配置を持つ地上駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is located on the grand level, with two platforms and a track for eack of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is located on the ground level, with two platforms and a track for each of them.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is located on the ground level, with two platforms and a track for each of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>跨線橋はなく1番線と2番線の移動は駅構内の踏切を渡ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With no bridge across railroads provided, a crossing within its premises must be used to make a movement between platform 1 and and platform 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With no bridge across the railroads provided, a crossing within the premises must be used to make a change between Platform 1 and Platform 2.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With no bridge across the railroads provided, a crossing within the premises must be used to make a change between Platform 1 and Platform 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>ICOCA・Jスルー利用可能駅であり、ICOCAの相互利用対象であるSuica、TOICA、PiTaPa（スルッとKANSAI協議会）も利用可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this station, ICOCA/J-through cards can be used and Suica, TOICA and PiTaPa (by SURUTTO KANSAI ASSOCIATION, all of which can be used interchangeably with ICOCA, can also be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this station, ICOCA/J-through cards can be used, and Suica, TOICA and PiTaPa (by SURUTTO KANSAI ASSOCIATION) can also be used interchangeably with ICOCA.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this station, ICOCA/J-through cards can be used, and Suica, TOICA and PiTaPa (SURUTTO KANSAI ASSOCIATION), which are mutually usable with ICOCA, can also be used.</e>
<cmt>表現を他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>但しJスルーカードについては、簡易改札機による対応のため複数枚の処理は駅社員への申し出が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with simplified gate-passing check machines used in this station, an officer at the station must be informed when more than one J-through card must be handled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with simplified gate-passing check machines used in this station, an officer at the station must be informed when more than one J-through card must be handled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with simplified gate-passing check machines used in this station, an officer at the station must be informed when more than one J-through card must be handled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>改札には簡易改札機が4台設置されており、通学時間帯の改札の効率化が図られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four such simplified gate-passing check machines are installed at the entrance/exit gates to facilitate the gate-passing operation during the hours when sutudents go to or return from their schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four of these simplified gate-passing check machines are installed at the entrance/exit gates to facilitate the gate-passing operation during the hours when students go to or return from their schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four of these simplified gate-passing check machines are installed at the entrance/exit gates to facilitate the gate-passing operation during the hours when students go to or return from their schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>一部の利用者からは「狭い」「7両対応はまだか」（京橋方面からの列車は1つ手前の京田辺駅で7両編成から3両切り離して4両編成となり、同志社前止まりの列車は京田辺～同志社前の1駅間だけ4両編成となる非効率な運用となっている）などの声も出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some users of the station voice that &quot;the premises are not spacious enough&quot; and &quot;when seven-car operation is to be introduced&quot; (at present, the operation is inefficient, because three cars of a seven-car train coming from Kyobacshi Station are separated at Kyotanabe Station, the last stop before Doshishamae Station, and therefore, when the train is for Doshishamae, the train is operated with a four-car organization in the last run between Kyotanabe Station and Doshishamae Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some users of the station are of the opinion that the premises aren&apos;t spacious enough and want to know when seven-car operations will be introduced, as the current operations are inefficient because three cars of a seven-car train coming from Kyobashi Station are separated at Kyotanabe Station, the last stop before Doshishamae Station, and therefore, when the train is bound for Doshishamae, the train is operated in a four-car configuration in the last run between Kyotanabe Station and Doshishamae Station).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some users of the station are of the opinion that the premises aren&apos;t spacious enough and want to know when seven-car operations will be introduced, as the current operations are inefficient because three cars of a seven-car train coming from Kyobashi Station are separated at Kyotanabe Station, the last stop before Doshishamae Station, and therefore, when the train is bound for Doshishamae, the train is operated in a four-car configuration in the last run between Kyotanabe Station and Doshishamae Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>実際、JR福知山線脱線事故では当該列車において犠牲者が多数出た前寄り4両が同志社前行きだったため、通学に利用していた同志社大学の学生が犠牲になったことから、同志社大学は同事故の対応についてのJR西日本への申し入れ事項の一つに、被害者・遺族への補償、原因究明と安全対策の徹底に加え当駅のホーム延長を挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, in the derailing accident on JR Fukuchiyama Line, many of the casualities were in the first four cars of the train that was bound for Doshishamae Station and naturally the casulaities included many students of Doshisha University, and therefore, Doshisha University included in the requests for JR Wests the extension of the platforms of this station, inaddition to compasating the victims and the bereaved families, clarifying the causes of the accident and taking thorough measures for safety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, in the derailing accident that occurred on the JR Fukuchiyama Line, many of the causalities were in the first four cars of the train, which was bound for Doshishamae Station, and naturally the casualties included many students of Doshisha University; therefore, Doshisha University included in the requests to JR West the extension of the platforms of this station, in addition to compensation for the victims and the bereaved families, clarification of the accident&apos;s causes thorough countermeasures to ensure safety.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, in the derailing accident that occurred on the JR Fukuchiyama Line, many of the causalities were in the first four cars of the train, which was bound for Doshishamae Station, and naturally the casualties included many students of Doshisha University; therefore, Doshisha University included in the requests to JR West the extension of the platforms of this station, in addition to compensation for the victims and the bereaved families, clarification of the accident&apos;s causes thorough countermeasures to ensure safety.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Actually&quot;→&quot;In fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>上記との関連性は不明だが、JR西日本は2010年3月（2009年度末）をめどに木津駅 (京都府)から同志社前駅の各駅のホームを延伸し、奈良・木津～京田辺間でも7両編成運転を行うことを発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although relations with the description above are not clear, JR West announced that the platforms in each of the stations between Kizu Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Doshishamae would be extended to enable seven-car train operation even between Nara/Kizu and Kyotanabe targeting for March, 2010 (the end of the fiscal 2009).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the relationships in the above description aren&apos;t clear, JR West announced that the platforms in each of the stations between Kizu Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Doshishamae would be extended to enable seven-car train operation even between Nara/Kizu and Kyotanabe, with a completion target of March 2010 (the end of fiscal 2009).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the relationships in the above description aren&apos;t clear, JR West announced that the platforms in each of the stations between Kizu Station (Kyoto Prefecture) and Doshishamae Station would be extended to enable seven-car train operation even between Nara/Kizu and Kyotanabe, with a completion target of March 2010 (the end of fiscal year 2009).</e>
<cmt>Doshishamae Station としました。fiscal → fiscal yearに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、折り返し専用の2番線に関してはホーム延長せずにそのまま使用停止となる予定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of Platform 2, utilized only for the returning trains, will be stopped</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of platform 2, which is employed only for the returning trains, will be stopped.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of Platform 2, which is employed only for the returning trains, will be stopped.</e>
<cmt>platform 2→Platform 2に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>当初駅舎にはかつて寝台列車等として活躍した国鉄583系電車の廃車体が使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, retired cars of JNR/JR Limited Express (Electric Cars) Series 583, which were extensively used mainly as sleeper trains, were utilized for the station house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the retired cars of JNR/JR Limited Express (Electric Cars) Series 583, which were used mainly as sleeper trains, were employed for the station house.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the retired cars of JNR/JR Limited Express (Electric Cars) Series 583, which were used mainly as sleeper trains, were employed for the station house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、利用者が増えホームを拡幅する必要が生じたことから、京田辺市・JR西日本・同志社大学の間で建て替えが決まり、2005年に同志社大学京田辺キャンパスをイメージした外観の新駅舎が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since users of the station increased and it became necessary to expand the widths of the platforms, it has been decided among Kyotanabe City, JR West and Doshisha University to newly build the station and the new station house imagining Doshisha University, Kyotanabe Campus, was completed in 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since users of the station increased and it became necessary to expand the widths of the platforms, Kyotanabe City, JR West and Doshisha University decided to rebuild the station and station house in the image of Doshisha University&apos;s Kyotanabe Campus, which was completed in 2005.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since users of the station increased and it became necessary to expand the widths of the platforms, Kyotanabe City, JR West and Doshisha University decided to rebuild the station and station house in the image of Doshisha University&apos;s Kyotanabe Campus, which was completed in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>なお当駅はジェイアール西日本交通サービスによる業務委託駅となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The operation of this station is entrusted to JR West Kotsu Service</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The operation of this station is entrusted to JR West Kotsu Service.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The operation of this station is entrusted to JR West Kotsu Service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>快速列車と区間快速のそれぞれ一部が当駅で折り返す（上り区間快速はこの駅までの設定）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the Rapid trains and of the Regional Rapid trains return at this station (it is set so that the operation of the up Rapid trains is served up to this station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the rapid trains and regional rapid trains return to this station (it is set so that the operation of the up rapid trains provide service up to this station).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the rapid trains and regional rapid trains return to this station (it is set so that the operation of the inbound rapid trains provide service up to this station).</e>
<cmt>上り→inbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>2番のりばは木津側が行き止まりで、当駅を起終点（折り返し）とする列車の停車専用ホームとなっているが、現在は折返し列車の殆ども1番のりばを使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The track on the Kizu side of platform 2 is terminated in this station and the platform is exclusively for the trains arriving and returning from there, but at present, almost all of the returning trains also use platform 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The track on the Kizu side of platform 2 terminates in this station, and the platform is exclusively for trains arriving and returning from there; currently, however, almost all the returning trains use platform 1 as well.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The track on the Kizu side of Platform 2 terminates in this station, and the platform is exclusively for trains arriving and returning from there; currently, however, almost all the returning trains use Platform 1 as well.</e>
<cmt>表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、ダイヤが乱れた際にのみ2番乗り場は昼間にも使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only when the train operation schedule is disrupted, platform 2 is used even during day time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only when the train operation schedule is disrupted is platform 2 used, even during the daytime.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only when the train operation schedule is disrupted Platform 2 used, even during the daytime.</e>
<cmt>isを削除しました。platform 2→Platform 2に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>昼間の使用されない時間帯には鎖が使用され2番乗り場には渡れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the day time when the platform is not used, a chain is placed to prevent access to platform 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the daytime, when the platform isn&apos;t used, a chain is installed to prevent access to Platform 2.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the daytime, when the platform isn&apos;t used, a chain is installed to prevent access to Platform 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>近鉄京都線 興戸駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodo Station on Kintetsu Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodo Station on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodo Station on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>同志社大学・同志社女子大学 京田辺キャンパス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha University, Kyotanabe Campus, and Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts, Kyotanabe Campus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha University, Kyotanabe Campus, and Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts, Kyotanabe Campus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha University, Kyotanabe Campus, and Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts, Kyotanabe Campus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>同志社国際中学校・高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha International Junior/Senior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha International Junior &amp; Senior High School</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha International Junior &amp; Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>ローソン田辺同志社前店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">LAWSON&apos;s Tanabe-Doshisha-mae-ten shop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">LAWSON&apos;s Tanabe-Doshisha-mae-ten shop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">LAWSON&apos;s Tanabe-Doshisha-mae-ten shop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>京都府道22号八幡木津線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto prefectural road No.22 Yawata Kizu Route</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 22, Yawata Kizu Route</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yawata Kizu Line of the Kyoto Prefectural Route 22</e>
<cmt>道路の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use status</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conditions of usage</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger use</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>2006年度の1日あたりの乗車人員は約4,904人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of persons getting on board at this station is approx. 4,904 a day in the fiscal 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fiscal 2006, each day approximately 4,904 people boarded at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fiscal year 2006, each day approximately 4,904 people boarded at this station.</e>
<cmt>fiscal → fiscal yearに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>（京都府統計書より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(From statistics of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(From statistics of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to the Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Report)</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>学生の利用が多く、車内の空席が全て埋まることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trains are used mostly by students and all of the passenger seats of a train are sometimes occupied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trains are used mostly by students, and occasionally one will find that all the passenger seats of a train are occupied.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trains are used mostly by students, and occasionally one will find that all the passenger seats of a train are occupied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>1986年（昭和61年）4月1日 開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its operation started on April 1, 1986.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It went into operation on April 1, 1986.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1986: It went into operation.</e>
<cmt>日付表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>当初は1面1線のみの棒線駅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, it was a straight line-structured station with a single platform serving a track</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the station was structured in a straight line with a single platform serving a track.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the station was structured in a straight line with a single platform serving a track.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日 国鉄分割民営化により、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the division and privatization of JNR on April 1, 1987, it becacme a station of West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the division and privatization of JNR on April 1, 1987, it became a facility of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1987: Due to the division and privatization of JNR, it became a facility of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>日付表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>2005年（平成17年）1月29日 新駅舎供用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of the new station house started on January 29, 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new station house came into use on January 29, 2005.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 29, 2005: The new station house came into use.</e>
<cmt>日付表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>2007年（平成19年）1月26日 みどりの窓口営業開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The service of JR Ticket Office &quot;Midori-no-madoguchi&quot; started on January 26, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The services of the JR Ticket Office &quot;Midori-no-madoguchi&quot; started on January 26, 2007.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 26, 2007: The services of the JR Ticket Office &quot;Midori-no-madoguchi&quot; started.</e>
<cmt>日付表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>それまで早朝・深夜は無人であったが、終日有人駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until then, no station officer was stationed in the late night and the early morning, but now a station officer is stationed throughout the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until then, no station officer was stationed during the period of late night through early morning, but now there is always an officer on duty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until then, no station officer was stationed during the period of late night through early morning, but now there is always an officer on duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>位置情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Locations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Locations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan Railway Company</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West Japan Railway Company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan Railway Company (JR West)</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>■学研都市線（片町線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gakkentoshi Line (Katamachi Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gakkentoshi Line (Katamachi Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gakkentoshi Line (Katamachi Line)</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>■快速・■区間快速・■普通（上り区間快速は当駅までの運転）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapid trains, Regional Rapid trains, Local trains (up Regional Rapid trains are operated up to this station.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapid trains, regional rapid trains, local trains (up regional rapid trains operate up to this station)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid/Regional Rapid/Local (inbound regional rapid trains operate up to this station)</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>JR三山木駅 - 同志社前駅 - 京田辺駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Miyamaki Station - Doshishamae Station - Kyotanabe Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Miyamaki Station - Doshishamae Station - Kyotanabe Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Miyamaki Station - Doshishamae Station - Kyotanabe Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), 城山(id:104901), Nnh(id:474), Ignis(id:28979), Hikichimin Jr.(id:147077), Yuta415(id:149253), Yukke123(id:178302), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Wikipedianet(id:9608), Tigers boy(id:15761), Jazzy(id:3202), Mop(id:12061), 吉祥天子(id:102033), もんじゃ(id:180813), Bandalgom(id:31841), Chobot(id:20846), Kone(id:377), Hirotaro(id:1437), Apidr(id:155448), ぽーるべあー(id:152979), 七之輔(id:55793), Hideyuki(id:9577), Otemoto(id:64180), MASA(id:2399), Utsuda(id:605), Ikaxer(id:61759), 樒(id:35770), Rusk(id:9895), Ichii-ya(id:48912), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), R28Bot(id:177951), Kyoutanabe124(id:175304), Mipu(id:5360), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>