<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都駅（きょうとえき）は、京都府京都市下京区東塩小路町・南区 (京都市)にある、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）・東海旅客鉄道（JR東海）・近畿日本鉄道・京都市交通局の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station, located in Higashi-Shiokojicho, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a railway station served by the lines of West Japan Railway Company (JR West), Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central), Kintetsu Corporation, and the Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau.</e>
<cmt>JR西日本（http://www.westjr.co.jp)、JR東海（http://jr-central.co.jp/)、京都交通局(http://www.city.Kyoto.jp/ｋoho/html/kotsu/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station, located in Higashi-Shiokojicho, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a railway station served by the lines of West Japan Railway Company (JR West), Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central), Kintetsu Corporation and the Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station, located in Higashi-Shiokojicho, Shimogyo Ward / Minami Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a railway station served by the lines of West Japan Railway Company (JR West), Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central), Kintetsu Corporation and the Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau.</e>
<cmt>南区を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本有数の観光都市である京都市の中心を担う駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It plays a central role in Kyoto City, one of the foremost tourist cities in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It plays a central role in Kyoto City, one of the foremost tourist areas in Japan.</e>
<cmt>REDUNDANT</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It plays a central role in Kyoto City, one of the foremost tourist areas in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>当駅を営業区間に含む東海道新幹線の全列車が停車し、南東北から関東地方・中部地方・中国地方・四国・九州地方に渡る広範囲からの高速バス路線が多数発着することから、日本全国から訪れる客は多く1日平均の乗降人員が各社合計で63万人を超える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As all the trains of the Tokaido Shinkansen which pass in the section operated by the station make a stop, and a lot of express buses which are connected with various destinations ranging from the South Tohoku District to Kanto, Chubu, Chugoku-Shikoku, and Kyushu District, depart from and arrive at the station, a large number of people arrive from all over Japan, and total number of the users of the railway companies exceeds 630,000 a day on an average.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because all the trains of the Tokaido Shinkansen that pass in the section operated by the station make stops--and since many express buses which are connected with various destinations ranging from the South Tohoku District to Kanto, Chubu, Chugoku-Shikoku, and Kyushu District, depart from and arrive at the station--large numbers of people arrive from all over Japan and the total number of the users of the railway companies exceeds 630,000 a day on the average.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because all the trains of the Tokaido Shinkansen make stops at Kyoto Station--and since many express buses connected with various destinations ranging from the South Tohoku District to Kanto, Chubu, Chugoku, Shikoku, and Kyushu District, depart from and arrive at the station--large numbers of people arrive from all over Japan, and the average total number of users of the Kyoto Station exceeds 630,000 a day.</e>
<cmt>中国地方と四国地方を分けました。　Railway companiesのuserではなく、京都駅のuserと解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>JR西日本が掲げる北近畿ビッグXネットワークの4つある駅の一端を担う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is one of the four stations that form the pivotal points in the North Kinki Big X Network, a project formulated by JR West, and in addition, as it is also one of the most largest terminal stations, it is deserve to be called &quot;the Entrance to a wide range of sightseeing spots&quot;.</e>
<cmt>北近畿ビッグXネットワーク：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is one of four stations that form the pivotal points in the North Kinki Big X Network, a project formulated by JR West, and in addition, since it&apos;s also one of the largest terminal stations, it is deserve to be called &quot;the entrance to a wide range of sightseeing spots.&quot;</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This station is one of four that form the pivotal points of the North Kinki Big X Network, a project formulated by JR West.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「京都～」を訳出。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>全国でも有数のターミナル駅であり、京都の観光名所の広範囲的玄関口とも言える駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, since it&apos;s also one of the largest terminal stations, it deserves to be called the entrance to a wide range of sightseeing spots in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>JR西日本（在来線）の駅はアーバンネットワークエリアに属している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stations (on the conventional lines) of JR West belong to the Urban Network area.</e>
<cmt>アーバンネットワーク→Urban Network (JR西日本HP）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stations (on the conventional lines) of JR West belong to the Urban Network area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stations (on the conventional lines) of JR West belong to the Urban Network area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>JR西日本、近鉄、地下鉄の駅ではICOCA、PiTaPaが利用可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ICOCA and PiTaPa can be used at stations of JR West, Kintetsu, and (Kyoto City) Subway.</e>
<cmt>地下鉄→ (Kyoto City) Subway　としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ICOCA and PiTaPa can be used at stations of JR West, Kintetsu and (Kyoto City) Subway.</e>
<cmt>COMMA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ICOCA and PiTaPa can be used at stations of JR West, Kintetsu and (Kyoto Municipal) Subway.</e>
<cmt>City → Municipal</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、JR西日本ではJスルー・Suica・TOICAが、地下鉄ではスルッとKANSAI対応各種カードが、近鉄ではJスルーカード及びスルッとKANSAI対応各種カードが利用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the station, various transportation cards are accepted as follows: for JR West, J-THRU, Suica, and TOICA; for Subway, the cards compatible with KANSAI THRU PASS, for Kintetsu, J-THRU and the cards compatible with KANSAI THRU PASS.</e>
<cmt>Jスルー:定訳不明J-THRUとしました、スルッとKANSA (http://www.surutto.com/conts/ticket/3dayeng/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various transportation cards are accepted at the station: for JR West, J-THRU, Suica, and TOICA; for the subway, the cards compatible with KANSAI THRU PASS; and for Kintetsu, J-THRU and the cards compatible with KANSAI THRU PASS.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various transportation cards are accepted at the station: for JR West, J-THRU, Suica, and TOICA; for the subway, the cards compatible with KANSAI THRU PASS; and for Kintetsu, J-THRU and the cards compatible with KANSAI THRU PASS.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>JR東海（新幹線）ではこれらのカードは利用できない（但し、EX-ICサービスではEX-ICカードを在来線用のSuicaやICOCA・TOICA・PiTaPaと組み合わせて使用できる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These cards are not accepted for JR Central Shinkansen (except for EX-IC service, where EX-IC card can be used in combination with the cards for conventional lines such as Suica, ICOCA, TOICA, PiTaPa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These cards are not accepted for JR Central Shinkansen (except for EX-IC service, where the EX-IC card can be used in combination with cards for conventional lines such as Suica, ICOCA, TOICA and PiTaPa).</e>
<cmt>ARTICLE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These cards are not accepted for JR Central Shinkansen (except for EX-IC service, where the EX-IC card can be used in combination with cards for conventional lines such as Suica, ICOCA, TOICA and PiTaPa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>利用可能な鉄道路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lines</e>
<cmt>文章中の表現と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan Railway (JR West)</e>
<cmt>JR西日本HP(http://www/westjr.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West Japan Railway (JR West)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan Railway Company (JR West)</e>
<cmt>Companyを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>東海道本線（米原駅方面：琵琶湖線、大阪方面：JR京都線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido Main Line (toward Maibara Station: Biwako Line, toward Osaka : JR Kyoto Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido Main Line (toward Maibara Station: Biwako Line; toward Osaka: JR Kyoto Line)</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaido Main Line (toward Maibara Station: Biwako Line; toward Osaka: JR Kyoto Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>山陰本線（嵯峨野線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanin Main Line (Sagano Line)</e>
<cmt>sanin　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>奈良線 ※始発駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Line *starting station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Line *starting station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Line *starting station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>湖西線 ※正式には近江塩津駅 - 山科駅間だが、すべての列車が当駅に直通している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosei Line *Al though this line officially covers the section between Omi-Shiotsu Station and Yamashina Station, all trains reach directly to this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosei Line *Although this line officially covers the section between Omi-Shiotsu Station and Yamashina Station, all trains come directly to this station.</e>
<cmt>USAGE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosei Line *Although this line officially covers the section between Omi-Shiotsu Station and Yamashina Station, all trains come directly to this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>東海旅客鉄道（JR東海）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central)</e>
<cmt>JR東海HP(http://www/jr-central.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>東海道新幹線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido Shinkansen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido Shinkansen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaido Shinkansen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>近畿日本鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>近畿日本鉄道HP(http://www.kintetsu.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>近鉄京都線 ※始発駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Kyoto Line *starting station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Kyoto Line *starting station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Kyoto Line *starting station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>京都市営地下鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt>(http://www.city.kyoto.jp/koho/eng/access/subway.html/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>City → Municipal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>京都市営地下鉄烏丸線（K11）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line (K 11)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line (K 11)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway Karasuma Line (K 11)</e>
<cmt>City → Municipal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>Reference 三条京阪駅　を参照</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>JR西日本・JR東海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR West and JR Central</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR West and JR Central</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR West and JR Central</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>東海道本線（JR京都線・琵琶湖線）・湖西線用のプラットホーム形状と配置4面6線とプラットホーム形状と配置1面1線、構内西側に山陰本線（嵯峨野線）用の頭端式ホーム3面4線、南側に奈良線用の頭端式ホーム2面3線（8番のりばのみ大阪方面に延びている）、東海道新幹線用の島式ホーム2面4線を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is equipped with 4 (ordinary) platforms with 6 tracks for the Tokaido Main Line (JR Kyoto Line/Biwako Line) and one (ordinary) platform with one track for the Kosei Line, 3 bay platforms with 4 tracks for the San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) in the west side of the yard, 2 bay platform with 3 tracks for the Nara Line in the south side (except platform No. 8, which extends toward the direction to Osaka), 2 island platform with 4 tracks for the Tokaido Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt>日本文の「プラットホーム形状と配置4面6線とプラットホーム形状と配置1面1線、」の文意がよくつかめませんでした。英文では(ordinary)を補ってあります。　頭端式ホーム→ (railway) bay platform、島式ホーム island platformともに (http://railbrit.co.uk/gnsr.htm/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is equipped with four (ordinary) platforms with six tracks for the Tokaido Main Line (JR Kyoto Line/Biwako Line) and one (ordinary) platform with one track for the Kosei Line, three bay platforms with four tracks for the San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) in the west side of the yard, two bay platforms with three tracks for the Nara Line in the south side (except platform No. 8, which extends toward the direction to Osaka), and two island platform with four tracks for the Tokaido Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station has four (ordinary) platforms with six tracks for the Tokaido Main Line (JR Kyoto Line/Biwako Line) and one (ordinary) platform with one track for the Kosei Line, three bay platforms with four tracks for the Sanin Main Line (Sagano Line) in the west side of the yard, two bay platforms with three tracks for the Nara Line in the south side (except Platform 8 which extends toward the direction to Osaka), and two island platforms with four tracks for the Tokaido Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt>(ordinary)となっている括弧内に、本来のホームの形状の英訳が入るのだと思いますが、この和文では形状が記載されていないため、このままとしました。ご確認ください。two island platform →two island platforms「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>在来線各線は地上駅、新幹線は高架駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surface station is for the conventional lines and the elevated station is designed for Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surface station is for the conventional lines, while the elevated station is designed for the Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surface station is for the conventional lines, while the elevated station is designed for the Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>各ホームは西側橋上駅舎と東側改札内地下通路で結ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All platforms are connected by the station building built on the west bridge as well as by the underground walkway built inside the east side of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All platforms are connected by the station building on the west bridge as well as by the underground walkway within the east side of the station.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All platforms are connected by the station building on the west bridge as well as by the underground walkway within the east side of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>北側の烏丸中央口に面しているホームは、全長558mで交通に関する日本一の一覧鉄道長いホームとして知られているが、0番のりば（旧1番線）のホーム自体の長さは323mである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the platform facing to the Karasuma Chuo-guchi (central entrance/exit) is 558m long and known as the longest railway platform in Japan in the transportation sector, the platform No.0 (former No1) itself is 323m long.</e>
<cmt>烏丸中央口→Karasuma Chuo-guchi (central entrance/exit)、文脈で出口・入口が変わるので、以降、～口という名称は、例外を除き（たとえば新幹線口）～口→～-kuchi/-guchi (entrance/exit）としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the platform facing the Karasuma Chuo-guchi (central entrance/exit) is 558 m long and is known throughout the transportation sector as the longest railway platform in Japan, platform No. 0 (former No. 1) is 323 m long.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the platform facing the Karasuma Chuo-guchi (central entrance/exit) is 558 m long and is known throughout the transportation sector as the longest railway platform in Japan, Platform 0 (former Platform 1) is 323 m long.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>残りの部分は、西端に切り欠きホームとして設けられている30番のりば（235m）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remaining part in the west side is used for the platform No. 30 (235 m), which is made for a dead-end track.</e>
<cmt>切り欠きホーム:定訳不明　platform made for a dead-end track.としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remaining part in the west side is used for the platform No. 30 (235 m), which is made for a dead-end track.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remaining part is used for Platform 30 (235m), which is built on the western side for a dead-end track.</e>
<cmt>「西端に」は「設けられている」を修飾「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この30番のりばは関西空港駅行の特急「はるか (列車)」専用で、運転開始当初は「はるかホーム」という名称が付けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The platform No. 30 is exclusively used for Limited Express &quot;Haruka&quot; bound for Kansai Airport Station, and when the operation was started, it was called &quot;Haruka (faraway) Platform&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「はるかホーム」:定訳不明。列車名と駅構内西端という位置の意味をかけて　&quot;Haruka (faraway) Platform&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform No. 30 is exclusively used for the limited express &quot;Haruka&quot; bound for Kansai Airport Station, and when the operation was started it was called &quot;Haruka (faraway) Platform.&quot;</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 30 is used exclusively for the airport express &apos;Haruka&apos; bound for Kansai-Airport Station, and when the operation was started it was called &apos;Haruka (faraway) Platform.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1番のりばを0番のりばに改称したのは、配線上の番号とホーム番号を一致させるための措置で、現在の1番線は0番のりばと2番のりばの間にある東海道線上り通過線の番号になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the former platform No. 1 was changed to platform No.0 in order to reorganize the platform numbers in concordance with the track numbers, and therefore, the present track No.1 situated in between the platform No.0 and No.2 corresponds to the Tokaido Line up track for nonstop trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the former platform No. 1 was changed to platform No. 0 in order to reorganize the platform numbers in accordance with the track numbers, and therefore the present track No. 1 situated in between platforms No. 0 and No. 2 corresponds to the Tokaido Line up track for nonstop trains.</e>
<cmt>SIMPLER USAGE, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the formerPlatform 1 was changed to Platform 0 in order to reorganize the platform numbers in accordance with the track numbers, and therefore the present Platform 1, which is situated between Platform 0 and 2, corresponds to the Tokaido Line inbound track for nonstop trains.</e>
<cmt>up→inbound「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これに関連して、東海道線の下り通過線は現在廃止されており、当駅を通過する吹田方面行きの貨物列車は7番のりばを通過する形になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In relation to this setup, the Tokaido Line down track for nonstop trains is currently disused, and the freight trains toward Suita Station pass through the platform No7.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In relation to this setup the Tokaido Line down track for nonstop trains is currently not used, and the freight trains toward Suita Station pass through the platform No. 7.</e>
<cmt>USAGE, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In relation to this setup, the Tokaido Line outbound track for nonstop trains is currently not used; instead, the freight trains toward Suita Station pass through Platform 7.</e>
<cmt>down→outbound「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>西側にある山陰本線のりばは、以前は「山陰1-4番線」と呼ばれていたが、1994年12月にホーム番号の呼び名が整理され、「はるかホーム」を含めて30-34番のりばと呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The platforms for the San&apos;in Main Line constructed in the west side were called &quot;San&apos;in No. 1&quot; to &quot;4&quot; before, but in December, 1994, the platform names were revised and since then these platforms have been called &quot;platform No. 30&quot; to &quot;34&quot; including so called &quot;Haruka Platform&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The platforms for the San&apos;in Main Line constructed on the west side were called &quot;San&apos;in No. 1&quot; to &quot;4&quot; before, but in December 1994 the platform names were revised; subsequently, these platforms have been called &quot;platform No. 30&quot; to &quot;34,&quot; including the so-called &quot;Haruka Platform.&quot;</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The platforms for the Sanin Main Line constructed on the west side were previously called &apos;Sanin Platform 1 to 4, but in December 1994 the platform names were revised; subsequently, these platforms were designated as Platform 30 to 34, including the so-called &apos;Haruka&apos; Platform.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>30番台にしたのは、山陰本線の「さん」にかけたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These platform were designated to have numbers, thirty something (&quot;san-ju …&quot; in Japanese.), in order to phonetically mach with the name of the line, the San&apos;in Line, which begins with &quot;san&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These platform were designated to have numbers incorporating &quot;thirty&quot; (&quot;san-ju …&quot; in Japanese.), in order to phonetically match the name of the line, the San&apos;in Line, which begins with &quot;san.&quot;</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These platforms were designated to have numbers incorporating &apos;30&apos; (San-ju …in Japanese), in order to phonetically match the name of the line, the Sanin Line, which begins with &apos;san.&apos;</e>
<cmt>数字を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>34番のりばは、日本一大きい数字のホーム番号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platform No.34 has the biggest number for railway platform in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform No. 34 has the biggest number of any railway platform in Japan.</e>
<cmt>SPACE, GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 34 has the biggest number of any railway platform in Japan.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>JR線、地下鉄線、近鉄線を区別するのに、地下鉄線は「地下鉄京都駅（烏丸線京都駅）」、近鉄線は「近鉄京都駅」と呼ばれる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To distinguish the Subway Line or Kintetsu Line from the JR Line, when you take the Subway Line, the station is often called &quot;Subway Kyoto Station (Karasuma Line Kyoto Station), while when you take the Kintetsu Line, it is often called &quot;Kintetsu Kyoto Station&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To distinguish the Subway Line or Kintetsu Line from the JR Line, when you take the Subway Line the station is often called &quot;Subway Kyoto Station (Karasuma Line Kyoto Station),&quot; while when you take the Kintetsu Line it is often called &quot;Kintetsu Kyoto Station.&quot;</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To distinguish the Subway Line or the Kintetsu Line from the JR Line, when you take the Subway Line the station is often called &apos;Subway Kyoto Station (Karasuma Line Kyoto Station),&apos; but when you take the Kintetsu Line it is often called &apos;Kintetsu Kyoto Station.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、新幹線ホーム（および新幹線車内）の乗り換え案内放送では、地下鉄線はアナウンスされない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the Shinkansen platforms (and inside Shinkansen), the Subway Line is not mentioned in the announcement on the lines to transfer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on the Shinkansen platforms (and within the Shinkansen) the Subway Line is not mentioned in the transfer announcement on the lines.</e>
<cmt>PREPOSITION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on the Shinkansen platforms (and within the Shinkansen) the Subway Line is not mentioned in the transfer announcement on the lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>旧駅ビル時代は待合室が存在したが、その後長らくは、6・7番のりばにある小さな列車待ちスペース以外は、待合室は存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the former Station Building, there was a waiting lounge, however, after that for a considerable time, there had not been no such lounge except a small space made on the platform No.6 and 7.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the former Station Building there was a waiting lounge; however, for a considerable time afterward there was no such lounge except for a small space on platforms No. 6 and No. 7.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the former Station Building there was a waiting lounge; however, for a considerable time afterward there was no such lounge except for a small space on Platform 6 and 7.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>2008年3月中旬、長距離列車の発着の多い0番のりばにも待合室が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of March in 2008, a waiting lounge was constructed on the platform No.0, where many long-distance trains arrive and depart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In mid-March 2008, a waiting lounge was constructed on platform No. 0, where many long-distance trains arrive and depart.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In mid-March 2008, a waiting lounge was constructed on platform No. 0, where many long-distance trains arrive and depart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>在来線のラインカラー表記について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color-coded conventional railway lines</e>
<cmt>ラインカラー表記→定訳不明：color-coded line(s)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color-coded conventional railway lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Color-coded conventional railway lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>JR京都線・琵琶湖線・奈良線・嵯峨野線...アーバンネットワークの日本の鉄道ラインカラー一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color-corded Japanese Railways: Colors used for the JR Kyoto Line, Biwako Line, Nara Line, Sagano Line, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color-corded Japanese Railways: colors used for the JR Kyoto Line, Biwako Line, Nara Line, Sagano Line, etc.)</e>
<cmt>CAP</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Color-coded Japanese Railways: the colors used for the JR Kyoto Line, Biwako Line, Nara Line, Sagano Line, etc.</e>
<cmt>最後のかっこを削除 corded →coded</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="38">
<j>草津線・湖西線...列車の方向幕（黒幕）に使われているラインカラー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Colors used for the lines (Kusatsu Line, Kosei Line, etc.) in the rollsign (destination blind).</e>
<cmt>方向幕（黒幕）→定訳不明　rollsign (destination blind) としました。(http://www.trainhistory.org/bsra/rollsign.html参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Colors used for the lines (Kusatsu Line, Kosei Line, etc.) in the rollsign (destination blind).</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Colors used for the lines (Kusatsu Line, Kosei Line, etc.) in the rollsign (destination blind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="39">
<j>発着ホームについて</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arrival and departure platforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arrival and departure platforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arrival and departure platforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="40">
<j>在来線...0 - 10のりば・30 - 34のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conventional lines: Platform No. 0-10, 30-34</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conventional lines: Platform nos. 0-10, 30-34</e>
<cmt>PLURAL</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conventional lines: Platform 0-10, 30-34</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>新幹線...11 - 14のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinkansen: Platform No. 11-14</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinkansen: Platform nos. 11-14</e>
<cmt>PLURAL</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinkansen: Platform 11-14</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>0番のりばは、スーパーはくと・オーシャンアローなどの当駅終着列車も利用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platform No. 0 is used for those trains that terminate at this station such as &quot;Super Hakuto&quot; and &quot;Ocean Arrow&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform No. 0 is used for trains that terminate at this station, such as &quot;Super Hakuto&quot; and &quot;Ocean Arrow.&quot;</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 0 is used for trains that terminate at this station, such as the Super Hakuto and Ocean Arrow.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>6・7番のりばは琵琶湖線・湖西線・草津線・奈良線からの当駅終着列車も利用する（その多くは京都総合運転所への回送になる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platform No. 6 and 7 are also used for those trains which proceed from the Biwako Line, Kosei Line, Kusatsu Line, and Nara Line and terminate at this station (many of these trains are deadheaded to the Kyoto General Operation Station).</e>
<cmt>京都総合運転所→定訳不明　Kyoto General Operation Station</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform nos. 6 and 7 are also used for trains that proceed from the Biwako Line, Kosei Line, Kusatsu Line and Nara Line and terminate at this station (many of these trains are deadheaded to the Kyoto General Operation Station).</e>
<cmt>PLURAL</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 6 and 7 are also used for trains that proceed from the Biwako Line, Kosei Line, Kusatsu Line and Nara Line and terminate at this station (many of these trains are deadheaded to the Kyoto General Operation Station).</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>以前は現0番のりばが2番線、現2番のりばが4番線、現7番のりばが11番線と呼ばれていたが、運行管理システムの導入の際に線路呼称を変え、運転線路名とのりば名を一致させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Previously, the present platforms No. 0, No.2 and No.7 were called No. 2, No.4, and No.11, respectively, but when the operation control system was introduced, their names were changed in order to conform the platform numbers to the respective track numbers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Previously, the present platforms nos. 0, 2 and 7 were called nos. 2, 4 and 11, respectively, but when the operation control system was introduced their names were changed in order for the platform numbers to conform to the respective track numbers.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, SPACING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previously, the present Platform 0, 2 and 7 were called 2, 4 and 11, respectively, but when the operation control system was introduced their names were changed in order for the platform numbers to conform to the respective track numbers.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>4代目の新駅ビル建設に際して旧1番線をつぶし、現0番のりばのホーム拡幅に利用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the 4th generation new building was constructed, the former platform No.1 was demolished, and the existent platform No.0 was widened for the actual use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the new, fourth-generation building was constructed, the former platform No. 1 was demolished, and the existing platform No. 0 was widened for actual use.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the new, fourth-generation building was constructed, the former Platform 1 was demolished, and the existing Platform 0 was widened for actual use.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>0・30・31番のりばを1つのホームとして見た時の長さが558mであり、日本最大の長さである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the platforms No. 0, 30, and 31 can be considered as one stretch of platform, it measures 558m long and is the longest platform in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the platform nos. 0, 30 and 31 were considered as one stretch of platform, it would measure 558m long and would therefore be the longest in Japan.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Platform 0, 30 and 31 were considered as one stretch of platform, it would measure 558 meters long and would therefore be the longest in Japan.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>新幹線ホームと新幹線改札口を結ぶエレベーターは駅係員の操作が必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The elevator connecting the Shinkansen platforms and the ticket wicket for the Shinkansen is controlled by an attendant of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The elevator connecting the Shinkansen platforms and the ticket wicket for the Shinkansen is controlled by an attendant of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The elevator connecting the Shinkansen platforms and the ticket wicket for the Shinkansen is controlled by an attendant of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>出入口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engrance/Exit</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entrance/Exit</e>
<cmt>SPELLING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entrance/Exit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>在来線の出入口は、北側地上に「烏丸中央口」、北側地下1階に「地下中央口」、南北自由通路に通じる西側橋上駅舎上に「西口」、地下自由通路に通じる地下1階に「地下東口」、南東側地上に「八条東口」、山陰線ホームからアクセスできるビックカメラJR京都店二階に「西洞院口」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The entrances/exits of conventional lines are situated as follows: &quot;Karasuma Chuo-guchi (Karasuma central entrance/exit)&quot; for the north side on the ground, &quot;Chika Chuo-guchi (underground central entrance/exit)&quot; for the north side of the first floor in the basement, &quot;Nishi-guchi (west entrance/exit)&quot; for the rooftop of the Station Building built on the west bridge which connects the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway), &quot;Chika Higashi-guchi (underground east entrance/exit)&quot; for the first floor in the basement which connects the Chika Jiyu Tsuro (underground free walkway), &quot;Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Hachijo east entrance/exit)&quot; for the southeast side on the ground, and &quot;Nishinotoin-guchi (Nishinotoin entrance/exit&quot; located on the second floor of Bic Camera JR Kyoto Shop, which is also accessible from the platform of San&apos;in (Main) Line.</e>
<cmt>「烏丸中央口」「地下中央口」、「西口」「地下東口」「八条東口」「西洞院口」は、ローマ字表記の次にそれぞれの仮訳をつけました（以下の部分同様に対処）。　また、南北自由通路、地下自由通路：定訳不明: Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway)、Chika Jiyu Tsuro (underground free walkway)と日本語ローマ字表記（英語仮訳）で対応しました。家電量販店ビックカメラ→Bic Camera (http://www.consultant.en-jp.com)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entrances/exits of conventional lines are situated as follows: &quot;Karasuma Chuo-guchi (Karasuma central entrance/exit)&quot; for the north side on the ground; &quot;Chika Chuo-guchi (underground central entrance/exit)&quot; for the north side of the first floor in the basement; &quot;Nishi-guchi (west entrance/exit)&quot; for the rooftop of the Station Building built on the west bridge, which connects the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway); &quot;Chika Higashi-guchi (underground east entrance/exit)&quot; for the first floor in the basement, which connects the Chika Jiyu Tsuro (underground free walkway); &quot;Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Hachijo east entrance/exit)&quot; for the southeast side on the ground; and &quot;Nishinotoin-guchi (Nishinotoin entrance/exit)&quot; located on the second floor of Bic Camera JR Kyoto Shop, which is also accessible from the platform of the San&apos;in (Main) Line.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entrances/exits of conventional lines are situated as follows: &apos;Karasuma Chuo-guchi (Karasuma central entrance/exit)&apos; for the north side on the ground; &apos;Chika Chuo-guchi (underground central entrance/exit)&apos; for the north side of the first floor in the basement; &apos;Nishi-guchi (west entrance/exit)&apos; for the rooftop of the station building on the west bridge, which connects the Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro (north-to-south main corridor); &apos;Chika Higashi-guchi (underground east entrance/exit)&apos; for the first floor in the basement, which connects the Chika-Jiyu-Tsuro (underground corridor); &apos;Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Hachijo east entrance/exit)&apos; for the southeast side on the ground; and &apos;Nishinotoin-guchi (Nishinotoin entrance/exit)&apos; located on the second floor of Bic Camera JR Kyoto Shop, which is also accessible from the platform of the Sanin (Main) Line.</e>
<cmt>南北自由通路→&quot;Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro (north-to-south main corridor)&quot;としました（http://www.granviakyoto.com/map/より）。それに合わせ、Chika-Jiyu-Tsuro (underground corridor)　としました。括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>新幹線の出入口は、南側地上に「新幹線八条口」、南東側地上に「新幹線八条東口」、新幹線コンコース西側に「新幹線中央口」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two Shinkansen entrances, &quot;Shinkansen Hachijo Entrance) and &quot;Shinkansen Central Entrance&quot; on the west side of the Shinkansen concourse.</e>
<cmt>新幹線～口→Shinkansen Entrance　（http://www.pref.kyoto.jp/visitkyoto/en/info_required/transportation/kyoto_station/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two Shinkansen entrances--&quot;Shinkansen Hachijo Entrance) and &quot;Shinkansen Central Entrance&quot;--on the west side of the Shinkansen concourse.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinkansen entrances are located as follows: &apos;Shinkansen Hachijo-guchi (Shinkansen Hachijo Entrance)&apos; on the south side at ground level, &apos;Shinkansen Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Shinkansen Hachijo East Entrance)&apos; on the southeast side at ground level, and &apos;Shinkansen Chuo-guchi (Shinkansen Central Entrance)&apos; on the west side of the Shinkansen concourse.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>在来線と新幹線は「新幹線中央乗換口」と「新幹線東乗換口」を介して乗り換えできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conventional Lines and Shinkansen can be mutually transferred through &quot;Shinkansen Central Transfer Gate&quot; and &quot;Shinkansen West Transfer Gate.</e>
<cmt>乗換口→定訳不明 transfer gateとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conventional Lines and Shinkansen can be mutually transferred through the Shinkansen Central Transfer Gate and the Shinkansen West Transfer Gate.</e>
<cmt>QUOTES NOT NEEDED</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conventional lines and the Shinkansen can be mutually transferred through the Shinkansen Central Transfer Gate and the Shinkansen East Transfer Gate.</e>
<cmt>west →east</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="51">
<j>乗り換えは、烏丸口のバス利用者は「烏丸中央口」、八条口のバス利用者は「八条東口」「新幹線八条口」など、在来線⇔近鉄線は西口、在来線⇔地下鉄は地下東口、新幹線⇔近鉄線は新幹線中央口、新幹線⇔地下鉄は新幹線八条東口が便利。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To transfer, for the passengers proceed from Karasuma-guchi bas stop, &quot;Karasuma Chuo-guchi (Karasuma central entrance)&quot;, for those from Hachijo-guchi bas stop, &quot;Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Hachijo east entrance)&quot; or &quot;Shinkansen Hachijo-guchi (Shinkansen Hachijo entrance)&quot; is convenient, and to transfer from a conventional line to the Kintetsu Railway Line, or vice versa, &quot;Nishi-guchi (west entrance/exit)&quot;, from a conventional line to the subway line, or vice versa, &quot;Chika Higashi-guchi (underground east entrance/exit)&quot;, from Shinkansen to Kintetsu Railway Line, or vice versa &quot;Shinkansen Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Shinkansen Hachijo east entrance/exit&quot; is convenient, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To transfer, for the passengers proceeding from the Karasuma-guchi bus stop, &quot;Karasuma Chuo-guchi (Karasuma central entrance)&quot;; while for those from Hachijo-guchi bus stop, &quot;Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Hachijo east entrance)&quot; or &quot;Shinkansen Hachijo-guchi (Shinkansen Hachijo entrance)&quot; is convenient; to transfer from a conventional line to the Kintetsu Railway Line, or vice versa, &quot;Nishi-guchi (west entrance/exit)&quot;; from a conventional line to the subway line, or vice versa, &quot;Chika Higashi-guchi (underground east entrance/exit)&quot;; from Shinkansen to Kintetsu Railway Line, or vice versa, &quot;Shinkansen Hachijo Higashi-guchi (Shinkansen Hachijo east entrance/exit&quot; is convenient, respectively.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To transfer, passengers proceeding to the Karasuma-guchi bus stop take &apos;Karasuma Chuo-guchi,&apos; while for those proceeding to Hachijo-guchi bus stop, &apos;Hachijo Higashi-guchi&apos; or &apos;Shinkansen Hachijo-guchi&apos; is convenient; to transfer from a conventional line to the Kintetsu Line or vice versa, use &apos;Nishi-guchi&apos;; from a conventional line to the subway line or vice versa, use &apos;Chika Higashi-guchi&apos;; from Shinkansen to Kintetsu Line or vice versa, use &apos;Shinkansen Chuo-guchi&apos;, or from Shinkansen to the subway line or vice versa, &apos;Shinkansen Hachijo Higashi-guchi&apos; is convenient.</e>
<cmt>「烏丸口のバス乗り場へ進む」というふうに解釈し、proceed to にしました。新幹線中央口の訳抜けを追加しました。 各出口の括弧内の英訳を削除しました（既出のため）。括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>他の京都市内にある各線の駅や大都市の主要駅と比べると、烏丸中央口は駅前のターミナル（バス・タクシー）が広くゆとりがあるのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comparing with other stations on different lines in Kyoto City and the terminal stations in other big cities, &quot;Karasuma Chuo-guchi (Karasuma central entrance)&quot; is distinguished by its spacious terminal for buses and taxies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with other stations on different lines in Kyoto City and the terminal stations in other large cities, &quot;Karasuma Chuo-guchi (Karasuma central entrance)&quot; is distinguished by its spacious terminal for buses and cabs.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with other stations on different lines in Kyoto City and the terminal stations in other large cities, Karasuma Chuo-guchi is distinguished by its spacious terminal for buses and cabs.</e>
<cmt>出口の括弧内の英訳を削除しました（既出のため）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>京都駅ビル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Kyoto Station Building</e>
<cmt>定訳不明　（用語リスト3735、英辞郎 on the WEB参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Kyoto Station Building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Kyoto Station Building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>現在の駅舎は4代目に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The actual station building is the 4th generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The actual station building is now the fourth generation.</e>
<cmt>NUMBER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The actual station building is now the fourth generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>1915年、大正天皇の即位の礼に併せて古典様式の2代目駅舎が渡辺節の設計により建築されたが、1950年失火により焼失、その後1952年に鉄筋コンクリート造の近代的な3代目駅舎が竣工した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1915, in conjunction with the enthronement ceremony of Emperor Taisho, the classical-style second generation station building was constructed after Setsu WATANABE&apos;s design, but it was burned down by an accidental fire in 1950, and after that, the third generation station building with ferroconcrete structure was completed in 1952.</e>
<cmt>大正天皇の即位の礼→the enthronement ceremony of Emperor Taisho（小学館プログレッシブ、英辞郎WEB参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1915, in conjunction with the enthronement ceremony of Emperor Taisho, the classical-style second-generation station building was constructed after Setsu Watanabe&apos;s design, but it was burned down by an accidental fire in 1950; subsequently, the third-generation station building with a ferroconcrete structure was completed in 1952.</e>
<cmt>COMMA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1915, in conjunction with Emperor Taisho&apos;s enthronement ceremony, the classical-style second-generation station building was constructed after Setsu WATANABE&apos;s design, but it was burned down by an accidental fire in 1950; subsequently, the third-generation station building with a ferroconcrete structure was completed in 1952.</e>
<cmt>WATANABE</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>しかし、駅が発展すると共に増築に次ぐ増築を重ねたため、地下街を含む商店街や連絡通路などを含めると構内の構造は混迷を極め、大変不便なものになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the development of the station, the building underwent further extension repeatedly, and as a consequence, the station structure with a shopping area, including an underground shopping mall, and access-ways became extremely chaotic and terribly inconvenient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the development of the station the building underwent further extensions repeatedly, and as a consequence the station structure--with its shopping area, including an underground shopping mall and access-ways--became extremely chaotic and terribly inconvenient.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the development of the station the building underwent further extensions repeatedly, and as a consequence the station structure--with its shopping area, including an underground shopping mall and access-ways--became extremely chaotic and terribly inconvenient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>また駅舎本体にも老朽化に伴う種々の問題が生じて来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the station structure itself had caused various problems as it was getting older.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the station structure had caused various problems due to its age.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the station structure had caused various problems due to its age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>そこで、抜本的対策として駅ビルの改築が計画された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the renovation of the building was planned as a drastic measure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the renovation of the building was planned as a drastic measure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the renovation of the building was planned as a drastic measure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>これは1994年の平安京記念事業の一環でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a part of the project implemented in 1994 to commemorate the anniversary of Heian-Kyo (the ancient capital).</e>
<cmt>平安京記念事業→定訳不明：project to commemorate the anniversary of Heian-Kyo (the ancient capital)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was part of the project implemented in 1994 to commemorate the anniversary of Heian-Kyo (the ancient capital).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was part of the project implemented in 1994 to commemorate the anniversary of Heian-Kyo (the ancient capital).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>なお、ホーム南側にも駅舎があるが、これは新幹線開通時に建設されたもので近鉄・新幹線のホーム下にあり、規模は小さく、新駅ビル建設の際も南北自由通路の設置やJR線と近鉄線の改札を完全分離化した事以外は大きな変更はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">South of the platforms, there is another station building beneath the platforms of the Kintetsu Railway Line and the Shinkansen, which was constructed when the Shinkansen began the operation, but underwent a little change during the renovation as being small in size, except for the construction of the Namboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway) and the complete separation of the ticket wicket of the JR Line from that of the Kintetsu Railways Line.</e>
<cmt>南北自由通路→定訳不明：Namboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">South of the platforms there is another station building beneath the platforms of the Kintetsu Railway Line and the Shinkansen, which was constructed when the Shinkansen went into operation, but it underwent a slight change during the renovation due to its small size except for the construction of the Namboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway) and the complete separation of the ticket wicket of the JR Line from that of the Kintetsu Railway Line.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">South of the platforms there is another station building beneath the platforms of the Kintetsu Line and the Shinkansen, which was constructed when the Shinkansen went into operation; however, it underwent a slight change during the renovation due to its small size except for the construction of the Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro and the complete separation of the ticket wicket of the JR Line from that of the Kintetsu Line.</e>
<cmt>文頭にon the を追加。南北自由通路の表記変更。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この新しい駅舎になり、新しい京都市の顔となりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this newly-constructed building, the Station is becoming a new landmark of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this newly constructed building, the station is becoming a new landmark of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>DON&apos;T HYPHENATE &quot;LY&quot; WORDS</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this newly constructed building, the station is becoming a new landmark of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>また、嵯峨野線ホーム亀岡寄り側付近に『京都駅NKビル』が完成し、新しく改札口を設け、京都寄り車両に乗客が集中する嵯峨野線の混雑緩和を図っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Near the edge of the platform of the Sagano Line to the direction of Kameoka Station, JR Kyoto Station NK Building was completed, and a new ticket wicket was installed there to alleviate the congestion of the Sagano Line caused by the passengers rushing to the cars stationed at the another end of the platform to the direction of Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>J『京都駅NKビル』→定訳不明：JR Kyoto Station NK Building</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Near the edge of the platform of the Sagano Line to the direction of Kameoka Station, the JR Kyoto Station NK Building was completed and a new ticket wicket was installed there to alleviate the congestion of the Sagano Line, caused by the passengers rushing to the cars stationed at the another end of the platform to the direction of Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Near the edge of the platform of the Sagano Line to the direction of Kameoka Station, the JR Kyoto Station NK building was completed and a new ticket wicket was installed there to alleviate the congestion of the Sagano Line caused by passengers rushing to the cars stationed at another end of the platform toward the direction of Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>the another のthe削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、同ビルには家電量販店ビックカメラ京都店が出店された（西洞院口）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this building, Bic Camera, an electronics retail store, opened its Kyoto shop (&quot;Nishinotoin-guchi &quot;).</e>
<cmt>家電量販店ビックカメラ(http://www.consultant.en-jp.com)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this building, Bic Camera, an electronics retail store, opened its Kyoto shop (&quot;Nishinotoin-guchi &quot;).</e>
<cmt>CLOSED SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this building, Bic Camera, an electronics retail store, opened its Kyoto shop (Nishinotoin-guchi).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>駅ビルの建築・設計</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction and design of the station building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction and design of the station building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction and design of the station building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>京都駅ビル（JR西日本）は、日本の鉄道駅舎としては異例の建築設計競技方式で行われ、新駅ビル設計者には原広司、安藤忠雄、池原義郎、黒川紀章、ジェームズ・スターリング (建築家)、バーナード・チュミ、ペーター・ブスマンの7名の複数の建築家が指名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Kyoto Station Building (JR West) underwent an architectural design competition, unusual method for a Japanese railway stations, and 7 architects, Kouji HARA, Tadao ANDO, Yoshiro IKEHARA, Kisho KUROKAWA, James STIRLING, Bernard TSCHUMI, and Peter BUSSMANN, were appointed to compete.</e>
<cmt>建築家名前は用語リスト参照（以下の部分も同様）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Kyoto Station Building (JR West) underwent an architectural design competition (an unusual method for a Japanese railway station) and seven architects--Kouji Hara, Tadao Ando, Yoshiro Ikehara, Kisho Kurokawa, James Stirling, Bernard Tschumi and Peter Bussmann--were appointed to compete.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The JR Kyoto Station Building (JR West) underwent an architectural design competition (an unusual method for a Japanese railway station) and seven architects--Hiroshi HARA, Tadao ANDO, Yoshiro IKEHARA, Kisho KUROKAWA, James STIRLING, Bernard TSCHUMI and Peter BUSSMANN--were appointed to compete.</e>
<cmt>CAPS, Koji →Hiroshi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>設計審査の結果、先ず原広司案、安藤案、スターリング案の3案に絞り込まれ、更なる協議を経て、原広司案が最終案として採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eliminatory screening of the design narrowed the 7 proposals down to those of HARA, ANDO, and STIRLING, and after the further deliberation, the proposal of Koji HARA was adopted as the final plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eliminatory screening of the design narrowed the seven proposals down to those of Hara, Ando and Stirling, and after the further deliberation the proposal of Koji Hara was adopted as the final plan.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, CAPS</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eliminatory screening of the design narrowed the seven proposals down to those of HARA, ANDO and STIRLING, and after further deliberation the proposal of Hiroshi HARA was adopted as the final plan.</e>
<cmt>CAPS</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>京都駅周辺は高さ120mまでの建築物が建築可能となる特例措置が設けられているが、高さ制限の緩和は古都の景観を損なうものとして反対意見も根強かったため、建物の巨大さ、高さに起因する圧迫感を回避し、いかに周辺環境との調和を図るかが作品の評価のポイントとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Kyoto Station area enjoys a preferential measure that permits the construction up to 120m high, the designs were evaluated from the point of how to achieve a harmony with the surrounding environment, avoiding the oppressive feeling caused by the huge size and height of the building, because there were persistent objections arguing that a loosened restriction in height might destroy the landscape of the ancient capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Kyoto Station area enjoys a preferential measure that permits the construction to a height of 120m, the designs were evaluated from the stanbdpoint of how to achieve a harmony with the surrounding environment, avoiding the oppressive feeling caused by the huge size and height of the building, because there were persistent objections arguing that a loosened restriction in height might destroy the landscape of the ancient capital.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Kyoto Station area enjoys a preferential measure that permits construction to a height of 120 m, the designs were evaluated from the standpoint of how to achieve harmony with the surrounding environment, avoiding the oppressive feeling caused by the huge size and height of the building, because there were persistent objections arguing that an easement of the height restriction might destroy the landscape of the ancient capital.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正 (standpoint)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>採用された設計案では、最大高さを60mに抑えた上で、南北方向の道路に合わせて建物を分割して視線を通すなど、圧迫感を回避するような配慮が随所に見られるが、根本的な解決になっているとは言い難い部分もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The adopted design shows a various precautions to avoided the oppressive feeling, including the measure to securing a visual axis by dividing the building and limiting the maximum height to be less than 60m, but the design does not offer a perfect solution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The adopted design shows various precautions to avoid any oppressive feeling, including the measure to secure a visual axis by dividing the building and limiting the maximum height to less than 60m, but the design does not offer a perfect solution.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The adopted design shows various precautions to avoid any oppressive feeling, including the measure to secure a visual axis by dividing the building in accordance with roads stretching to the north and south, and by limiting the maximum height to less than 60 m, but the design does not offer a perfect solution.</e>
<cmt>「南北の道路に合わせて」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>また、ハーフミラーのガラスやアルミパネルを多用した造形が古都に相応しくないとして、建設から10年近く経った今日でも否定的な意見も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, even nowadays after nearly 10 years later since the construction, there are still many negative opinions criticizing that the form with heavy usage of half-mirror crystals and aluminum panels does not match with the ancient capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, even today, nearly ten years after the construction, there are still many negative opinions stating that the form, with its heavy use of half-mirror crystals and aluminum panels, doesn&apos;t match the ancient capital.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, even today, nearly ten years after the construction, there are still many negative opinions stating that the form, with its heavy use of half-mirror crystals and aluminum panels, doesn&apos;t match the ancient capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>完成した駅ビルは、東西の両側にホテルと伊勢丹が位置し、その間の中央部は、改札口の上にある細長いホテル客室棟をガラスの正面と大屋根で覆う広々とした吹き抜けになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The completed station building has a hotel in the east side and a department store Isetan in the west side, respectively, and the center is the spacious wellhole-style hall with a huge vaulted glass ceiling and a glass facade covering the slender guestroom ward of the hotel constructed above the ticket gates.</e>
<cmt>吹き抜け→wellwhole-style (小学館プログレッシブ和英）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The completed station building has a hotel on the east side and an Isetan department store on the west side; the center is a spacious wellhole-style hall with a huge, vaulted glass ceiling and a glass facade covering the slender guestroom wing of the hotel constructed above the ticket gates.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The completed station building has a hotel on the east side and an Isetan department store on the west side; the center is a spacious wellhole-style hall with a huge, vaulted glass ceiling and a glass facade covering the slender guestroom wing of the hotel constructed above the ticket gates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>吹き抜けから東西へは渓谷状の階段が設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wellhole-style hall outstretches two &quot;valley&quot; staircases to east and to west.</e>
<cmt>渓谷状の階段→定訳不明　渓谷橋タイプ側壁のない階段のことと思われます。&quot;Valley&quot; staircaseとしました。（http:www.oyster-web.co.uk、www.panoramio.com参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wellhole-style hall outstretches two &quot;valley&quot; staircases to the east and west.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wellhole-style hall outstretches two valley-shaped staircases to the east and west.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>伊勢丹側の大階段は10階分の高低差があり、非常時の避難経路とする事を想定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grand staircase set on the Isetan side measures 10-story high, which was installed assuming that this would serve as an escape route in an emergency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grand staircase set on the Isetan side measures ten stories high, and was installed with the assumption that it would serve as an escape route in the event of an emergency.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grand staircase set on the Isetan side measures ten stories high, and was installed with the assumption that it would serve as an escape route in the event of an emergency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>階段はコンサートや、毎年2月の「JR京都駅ビル大階段駆け上がり大会」（主催：京都放送）などイベント会場としても利用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The staircase is also used for concerts and event sites, such as &quot;JR Kyoto Station Building Grand Staircase Dashing-up Competition&quot;(sponsored by Kyoto Broadcasting System) held in February every year.</e>
<cmt>「JR京都駅ビル大階段駆け上がり大会」→定訳不明&quot;JR Kyoto Station Building Grand Staiarcase Dashing-up Competition&quot;　、京都放送→Kyoto Broadcasting System (Company Ltd.) (http:///www.kbs-kyoto.ne.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The staircase is also used for concerts and event sites, such as the &quot;JR Kyoto Station Building Grand Staircase Dashing-up Competition&quot;(sponsored by Kyoto Broadcasting System) held in February of each year.</e>
<cmt>ARTICLE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The staircase is also used for concerts and events, such as the &apos;JR Kyoto Station Building Grand Staircase Dashing-up Competition&apos;(sponsored by Kyoto Broadcasting System) held in February of each year.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="72">
<j>建築・設計</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction and design</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction and design</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction and design</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="73">
<j>建築設計：原広司 / アトリエファイ建築研究所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architectural design/Architectural Institute Atelier Fai (Ф)</e>
<cmt>アトリエファイ建築研究所→定訳不明：Architectural Institute Atelier Fai (Ф)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architectural design: Architectural Institute Atelier Fai (Ф)</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architectural design: Architectural Institute Atelier Fai (Ф)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="74">
<j>施工：京都駅ビル建設工事JV</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction: Kyoto Station Building Work Joint Venture</e>
<cmt>京都駅ビル建築工事JV→定訳不明：Kyoto Station Building Work Joint Ventureとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction: Kyoto Station Building Work Joint Venture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction: Kyoto Station Building Work Joint Venture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="75">
<j>竣工：1997年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Completion of construction: 1997</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completion of construction: 1997</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Completion of construction: 1997</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="76">
<j>用途：駅舎・複合施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uses: station and complex facility</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uses: station and complex facility</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uses: station and complex facility</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="77">
<j>構造：鉄骨造+鉄骨鉄筋コンクリート造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure: steel frame, steel-reinforced concrete (SRC) structure</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: steel-frame, steel-reinforced concrete (SRC) structure</e>
<cmt>HYPHEN</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: steel-frame, steel-reinforced concrete (SRC) structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="78">
<j>階数：地上16階、地下3階 （高さ60m）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number of stories: 16 stories above the ground and 3 stories underground (60 meters high)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Number of stories: 16 stories above ground and three stories below ground (total height, 60 meters)</e>
<cmt>NUMBERS, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Number of stories: 16 stories above ground and three stories below ground (total height, 60 meters)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="79">
<j>敷地面積：38,000平方m</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Site area: 38,000 sq.m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Site area: 38,000 sq. m.</e>
<cmt>SPACING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Site area: 38,000 sq. m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="80">
<j>建築面積：32,400平方m</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Building area: 32,400 sq.m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Building area: 32,400 sq. m.</e>
<cmt>SPACING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Building area: 32,400 sq. m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="81">
<j>延床面積：238,000平方m</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Total floor area: 238,000 sq.m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Total floor area: 238,000 sq. m.</e>
<cmt>SPACING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Total floor area: 238,000 sq. m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="82">
<j>所在地：京都府京都市下京区東塩小路高倉町8番地3</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location: 8-3, Higashishiokoji-Takakuracho, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location: 8-3, Higashishiokoji-Takakuracho, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>PERIOD</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location: 8-3, Higashi-Shiokoji Takakuracho, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>用語リスト#3735</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="83">
<j>第40回建築業協会賞受賞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Received the 40th Building Constructors Society Award</e>
<cmt>建築業協会賞→Building Constructors Society Award (http://www.bcs.or.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Received the 40th Building Constructors Society Award</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Received the 40th Building Constructors Society Award</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>近畿日本鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Corporation</e>
<cmt>http://www.kintetsu.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Corporation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Corporation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>頭端式ホーム3面3線を持つ高架駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elevated station with 3 bay platforms and 3 tracks</e>
<cmt>頭端式ホーム→ (railway) bey platform (http://railbrit.co.uk/gnsr.htm/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elevated station with three bay platforms and three tracks</e>
<cmt>NUMBERS</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elevated station with three bay platforms and three tracks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>3層構造で、1階は改札口（八条口）・駅事務室・名店街、2階がホームと改札口（中央口、この改札口は開業当初から長らく旧国鉄→現JR京都駅の内部にある形で乗換用の改札機もあったが、現京都駅ビル建設および同駅南北自由通路設置に合わせて両社の改札口は完全分離化された）、3階はJR東海の新幹線ホームとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a three-layered structure: on the 1st floor, a ticket wicket (Hachijo-guchi entrance), the station office, and Meitengai shopping arcade are placed, on the 2nd floor, the platforms and a ticket wicket (Chuo-guchi entrance) are placed (a ticket gate was located inside the JNR/JR Station for a long time with a wicket machine for transfer, but when the new station building was constructed and the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway) was made, the ticket wickets of the two companies were completely separated), on the 3rd floor, the platforms for the JR Central Shinkansen..</e>
<cmt>南北自由通路→定訳不明：Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a three-layer structure: on the first floor, a ticket wicket (Hachijo-guchi entrance), the station office and Meitengai shopping arcade are located; on the second floor the platforms and a ticket wicket (Chuo-guchi entrance) are located (a ticket gate was located inside the JNR/JR Station for a long time with a wicket machine for transfer, but when the new station building was constructed and the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway) was made, the ticket wickets of the two companies were fully separated); and the third floor has the platforms for the JR Central Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a three-layer structure: a ticket wicket (Hachijo-guchi (Hachijo entrance/exit)), the station office and Meitengai shopping arcade are located on the first floor; the platforms and a ticket wicket (Chuo-guchi (Central entrance/exit)) are located on the second floor (a ticket gate was located inside the JNR/JR Station for a long time with a ｔicket machine for transfer, but when the new station building was constructed and the Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro was made, the ticket wickets of the two companies were fully separated); and the third floor has the platforms for the JR Central Shinkansen.</e>
<cmt>entrance/exitと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>ホーム有効長は6両（駅が4代目駅舎となり南北自由通路が通行可能になった1990年代後半より以前には烏丸口に有人個別対応の券売窓口が存在していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The platform&apos;s effective length is 6 cars long (until the latter half of 90s, when the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro became available, there had been a ticket booth at Karasuma-guchi entrance/exit, at which a taller was attending to the individual passengers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The platform&apos;s effective length is six cars long (until the latter half of 1990s, when the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro became available, there had been a ticket booth at Karasuma-guchi entrance/exit, at which a teller would attend to individual passengers).</e>
<cmt>SPELLING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The platform&apos;s effective length is six cars (until the latter half of 1990s, when the Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro became available, there was a ticket booth at Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit), at which a teller would attend to individual passengers).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="87">
<j>駅リニューアルの一環として、2007年12月1日からは、1階の改札口・切符売り場は廃止され、定期券売り場、駅営業所等は2階改札口（中央口）に移転、集約された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a part of the renewal of the station, on December 1, 2007, the ticket gate and ticket booth were closed, and the commuter pass booth and the station office among others were transferred and centralized to the ticket gate (Chuo-guchi entrance) on the 2nd floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As part of the renewal of the station, on December 1, 2007 the ticket gate and ticket booth were closed, and the commuter pass booth and station office (among others) were transferred and centralized to the ticket gate (Chuo-guchi entrance) on the second floor.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As part of the station&apos;s renewal, on December 1, 2007 the ticket gate and ticket booth were closed, and the commuter pass booth and station office (among others) were transferred and centralized to the ticket gate (Chuo-guchi) on the second floor.</e>
<cmt>entrance/exitと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="88">
<j>自動改札機は奈良線系統の他駅同様東芝製が設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiba automatic ticket checkers are installed like in other stations on the Nara Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiba automatic ticket checkers are installed, just as they are in other stations on the Nara Line.</e>
<cmt>MAKE IT BETTER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiba automatic ticket checkers are installed, just as they are in other stations on the Nara Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>赤い自動改札機(EG-2000)は出場時2枚一括処理、PiTaPa・ICOCAに対応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The red-colored automatic ticket checker (EG-2000) can process two outgoing tickets at the same time and accepts PiTaPa and ICOCA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The red-colored automatic ticket checker (EG-2000) can process two outgoing tickets at the same time and accepts PiTaPa and ICOCA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The red-colored automatic ticket checker (EG-2000) can process two outgoing tickets at the same time and accepts PiTaPa and ICOCA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>1・2番線は乗降分離（線路の両側に乗車専用ホームと降車専用ホームをそれぞれ配置し、旅客流動を分離する事）型となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platform No.1 and No2 employ the divided system for incoming and outgoing passengers (at the both ends of the track, two platforms, one for incoming passengers, and the other for outgoing passengers, are placed to divide the flow of the passengers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform nos. 1 and 2 employ the divided system for incoming and outgoing passengers (at both ends of the track, two platforms--one for incoming passengers and the other for outgoing passengers--are placed to divide the flow of passengers).</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 1 and 2 employ the divided system for incoming and outgoing passengers (at both ends of the track, two platforms--one for incoming passengers and the other for outgoing passengers--are placed to divide the flow of passengers).</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>ホーム配置は南から1番線乗車ホーム、1・2番線降車ホーム、2番線乗車・3番線乗降車ホームの順である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platforms are situated in the following order from the south: incoming platform for Track No.１, outgoing platform for Track No1, and 2, incoming platform for Track No.2, incoming and outgoing platform for Track No.3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platforms are situated in the following order from the south: incoming platform for Track No. 1, outgoing platform for Track nos. 1 and 2; the incoming platform for Track No. 2; and the incoming and outgoing platform for Track No. 3.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platforms are situated in the following order from the south: incoming platform for Platform 1, outgoing platform for Platform 1 and 2; the incoming platform for Platform 2; and the incoming and outgoing platform for Platform 3.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>駅リニューアル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renovation of the station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station renovation</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station renovation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>近鉄は2005年12月22日、3番線の北側に1線増線すると発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 22, 2005, Kintetsu Corporation announced the construction of another line on the north side of the platform No.3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 22, 2005 Kintetsu Corporation announced the construction of another line on the north side of platform No. 3.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 22, 2005 Kintetsu Corporation announced the construction of another line on the north side of Platform 3.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>2007年3月1日時点での計画概要、2008年3月6日時点での京都駅ターミナル整備工事の概要と進捗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the outline of the plan as of March 1, 2007, and the outline and progress of the Kyoto Station terminal improvement work as of March 6, 2008,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the outline of the plan as of March 1, 2007, and the outline and progress of the Kyoto Station terminal improvement work as of March 6, 2008,</e>
<cmt>INCOMPLETE TEXT</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the outline of the plan as of March 1, 2007, and the outline and progress of the Kyoto Station terminal improvement work as of March 6, 2008,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>によると、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(According to)</e>
<cmt>分構造上178行文頭に加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(According to)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>4番線は片面のホームとし、2008年4月に工事に着手し、2012年春に完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The platform No. 4 is constructed with one-sided structure and the work is scheduled to started in April, 2008 and complete in spring, 2012.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform No. 4 is constructed with a one-sided structure; the work is scheduled to start in April 2008 and be completed in spring 2012.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 4 is constructed with a one-sided structure; the work is scheduled to start in April 2008 and be completed in spring 2012.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="96">
<j>近鉄名店街を増床し、2008年10月にリニューアルオープンする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Meitengai shopping arcade is extended to increase the floor area, and will be renewed and opened in October 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kintetsu Meitengai shopping arcade is extended to increase the floor area, and will be renewed and opened in October 2008.</e>
<cmt>ARTICLE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kintetsu Meitengai shopping arcade is extended to increase the floor area, and will be renewed and opened in October 2008.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="97">
<j>4番線の上空部分にホテル（地上8階、368室）を建設し、2011年秋に開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A hotel (8 stories above the ground with 368 rooms) is constructed on the space above the platform No. 4, and is scheduled to open in autumn, 2011.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A hotel (with 368 rooms in eight stories above ground) is constructed on the space above platform No. 4, and is scheduled to open in autumn 2011.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A hotel (with 368 rooms in eight stories above ground) is constructed on the space above Platform 4, and is scheduled to open in autumn 2011.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="98">
<j>1階改札口を廃止し、2階改札口を拡大する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ticket wicket on the 1st floor is closed while the ticket wicket on the 2nd floor is extended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ticket wicket on the first floor is closed, but the ticket wicket on the second floor is extended.</e>
<cmt>NUMBERS</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ticket wicket on the first floor is closed, but the ticket wicket on the second floor is extended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="99">
<j>などが予定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The constructions mentioned above are scheduled:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction work mentioned above has been scheduled.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction work mentioned above has been scheduled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>それに伴い、2007年11月30日終発をもって、1階の八条改札口・切符売り場・トイレはその役目を終えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In conjunction with the renewal, the Hachijo Ticket Wicket, and its adjacent ticket booth and lavatory located on the 1st floor were closed on November 30, 2007 with the departure of the last train of that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In conjunction with the renewal, the Hachijo Ticket Wicket, as well as its adjacent ticket booth and the first-floor lavatory, were closed on November 30, 2007 with the departure of the day&apos;s last train.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In conjunction with the renewal, the Hachijo Ticket Wicket, as well as its adjacent ticket booth and the first-floor lavatory, were closed on November 30, 2007 with the departure of the day&apos;s last train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>京都市営地下鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>city→Municipal</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>島式ホーム1面2線を持つ地下駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an underground station with one island platform and two tracks.</e>
<cmt>頭端式ホーム→ (railway) bay platform、島式ホーム island platformともに (http://railbrit.co.uk/gnsr.htm/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an underground station with one island platform and two tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an underground station with one island platform and two tracks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>改札口は北改札、中央1改札、中央2改札、南改札の4か所で、JR在来線への乗り換えは中央2改札が、JR奈良線・新幹線および近鉄線との乗り換えは南改札が便利である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 4 ticket wickets: North, Central-1, Central-2, South, and to transfer to the JR conventional lines, Central-1 and -2 wickets, and to transfer from/to the JR Nara Line, the Shinkansen and the Kintetsu Line, South gate wicket are convenient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are four ticket wickets: North, Central-1, Central-2, South and, to transfer to the JR conventional lines, Central-1 and -2 wickets; for transfers from/to the JR Nara Line, the Shinkansen and the Kintetsu Line, South gate wicket are convenient.</e>
<cmt>IMPROVED</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are four ticket wickets: North, Central-1, Central-2, South and, to transfer to the JR conventional lines, Central-1 and -2 wickets; for transfers from/to the JR Nara Line, the Shinkansen and the Kintetsu Line, South gate wicket are convenient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>駅ナンバリングはK11。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station number: K11</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station number: K11</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station number: K11</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>エレベーターは日本オーチス製。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The elevator is made by Nippon Otis Elevator Co.</e>
<cmt>和英翻訳データブック（ジャパンタイムズ編）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The elevator is made by Nippon Otis Elevator Co.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The elevator is made by Nippon Otis Elevator Co.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number of passengers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Number of passengers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Number of passengers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>JR西日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR West</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR West</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR West</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="106">
<j>2006年度の1日平均の乗車人員は179,155人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The average number of passengers a day in 2006 was 179,155 persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The average daily number of passengers in 2006 was 179,155.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The average daily number of passengers in fiscal year 2006 was 179,155.</e>
<cmt>in fiscal year 2006 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="107">
<j>これはJR西日本の駅では大阪駅に次いで第2位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ranked the 2nd among the stations of JR West after Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>PUNCT</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is ranked second among the stations of JR West, after Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is ranked second among the stations of JR West, after Osaka Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="108">
<j>JR東海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Central</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Central</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Central</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="109">
<j>2006年度の1日平均の乗車人員は30,921人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The average number of passengers a day in 2006 was 30,921persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The average daily number of passengers in 2006 was 30,921.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The average daily number of passengers in fiscal year 2006 was 30,921.</e>
<cmt>in fiscal year 2006 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>これはJR東海の駅では第7位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ranked the 7th among the stations of JR Central.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is ranked seventh among the stations of JR Central.</e>
<cmt>NUMBER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is ranked seventh among the stations of JR Central.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="111">
<j>近鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="112">
<j>2005年度の1日平均乗降人員は、108,512人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The average number of passengers a day in 2005 was 108,512 persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The average daily number of passengers in 2005 was 108,512.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The average daily number of passengers in fiscal year 2005 was 108,512.</e>
<cmt>in fiscal year 2005 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>これは近鉄の全調査対象駅（323駅）中5位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ranked the 5th among all the stations on the Kintetsu Railways surveyed (323 stations).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is ranked fifth among all the stations on the Kintetsu Railways surveyed (323 stations).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is ranked fifth among all the stations on the Kintetsu Railways surveyed (323 stations).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="114">
<j>京都市交通局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>京都交通局(http://www.city.Kyoto.jp/ｋoho/html/kotsu/)と同一と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="115">
<j>2005年度の1日平均乗降人員は、105,704人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The average number of passengers a day in 2005 was 105,704 persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The average daily number of passengers in 2005 was 105,704.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The average daily number of passengers in fiscal year 2005 was 105,704.</e>
<cmt>in fiscal year 2005 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>これは京都市営地下鉄の全駅中最多。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the highest in number of passengers among all the stations of Kyoto City Subway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the highest number of passengers among all the stations of Kyoto City Subway.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the largest number of passengers among all the stations of Kyoto Municipal Subway.</e>
<cmt>City →Municipal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>駅の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>開業は1877年（明治10年）2月6日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was inaugurated on February 6, 1877.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was inaugurated on February 6, 1877.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was inaugurated on February 6, 1877.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>当初は、新橋 - 横浜間の鉄道に続いて2番目に開業した、神戸 - 京都間鉄道の終着駅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, it was the final station of the railroad between Kobe and Kyoto, and was the second railway inaugurated after the railroad opened between Shinbashi and Yokohama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, it was the final station of the railroad between Kobe and Kyoto, and I was the second railway inaugurated after the railroad opened between Shinbashi and Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it was the final station of the railroad between Kobe and Kyoto, and it was the second railway inaugurated after the railroad opened between Shimbashi and Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>I →it Shinbashi →Shimbashi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="119">
<j>このため、路線形状の都合から当時の繁華街である四条河原町地域からは遠く離れた京都市でも南の地域、即ち七条通 - 八条通付近に京都駅は設置されたが、それ以外にも用地買収の楽な寂れた地域（四条通に沿って建設する事は用地買収面以外にも、祇園地区において八坂神社などの境内に当たる事や周辺の伝統的な家屋の立ち退きを伴う事などから、市民感情から考えても猛反発を受けた可能性が高かったと見られる）だったというのが、この土地を選択した要因になったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that owing to this favorable route setup, Kyoto Station was constructed in the southern area of Kyoto City, around Shichijo-dori Street and Hachijo-dori Street, although this area was far from the Shijo Kawaramachi area, the then prominent center, but another reason for the selection can be supposed: at that time the area was underdeveloped and it was easy to acquire the site (if it had had been constructed along the Shijo-dori Street, in addition to the difficulties in purchasing the land, the acquisition would have met a strong emotional objection of the citizens because railroading should have been carried out in the Gion District that have many temples and shrines such as Yasaka-jinja Shrine and the traditional houses in the vicinity should have been removed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that owing to this favorable route setup, Kyoto Station was constructed in the southern area of Kyoto City, around Shichijo-dori Street and Hachijo-dori Street, although this area was far from the Shijo Kawaramachi area, a prominent center of the time. However, another reason for the selection can be supposed: at that time the area was underdeveloped and it was easy to acquire the site (if it had had been constructed along the Shijo-dori Street, but in addition to the difficulties in purchasing the land, the acquisition would have met a strong emotional objection of the citizens because railroading should have been carried out in the Gion District that has many temples and shrines such as Yasaka-jinja Shrine, and the traditional houses in the vicinity should have been removed).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus it is said that, owing to this favorable route setup, Kyoto Station was constructed in the southern area of Kyoto City, around Shichijo-dori Street and Hachijo-dori Street, although this area was far from the Shijo-Kawaramachi area, a prominent center of the time. However, another reason for the selection could be that the area was underdeveloped at the time and it was easy to acquire the site (if it had been constructed along the Shijo-dori Street, the acquisition of the land would have met strong emotional opposition from the citizens in addition to the difficulties in purchasing it, because railroading should have been carried out in the Gion District, which has many temples and shrines such as Yasaka-jinja Shrine, and the traditional houses in the vicinity should have been removed).</e>
<cmt>Shijo-Kawaramachi　ハイフネーション, 語順を入れ替え、had のだぶりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="120">
<j>後に京都から大津までの鉄道も開業するが、この時のルートは東山 (京都府)にトンネルを開削するだけの技術がまだなかった事から、現在のJR奈良線を稲荷駅周辺まで南下した後、現在の名神高速道路が走っている敷地を通って、大津へと向かうものとなった（大津駅の項目も参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, a railway opened from Kyoto to Otsu, but at that time the rout proceeded toward Otsu, through the site where the Meishin Highway is actually running, after going far down to the south nera the present Inari Station on the Nara Line, because the drilling technology to cut a tunnel through the Higashi-yama Mountain (Kyoto Prefecture) was not available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, a railway opened from Kyoto to Otsu, but at that time the route proceeded toward Otsu, through the site where the Meishin Highway actually runs, after going far down to the south near the present Inari Station on the Nara Line, because the drilling technology to cut a tunnel through Mt. Higashi-yama (Kyoto Prefecture) was not available.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, a railway opened from Kyoto to Otsu, but at that time the route proceeded toward Otsu, through the site where the Meishin Expressway in fact runs, after going far down to the south near the present Inari Station on the Nara Line, because the drilling technology needed to cut a tunnel through Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) wasn&apos;t available.</e>
<cmt>名神高速の訳を修正しました。&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="121">
<j>その後山陰本線が開通し、後に近鉄京都線となる奈良電気鉄道や市内の路面電車（京都市電）の発着点にもなって、京都駅周辺は急速に発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, with the opening of the San&apos;in Main Line, the station became the departure and arrival point of the Nara Electric Railway and the city trams (Kyoto City Trams), and the areas around the station had rapidly developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, with the opening of the San&apos;in Main Line the station became the departure and arrival point of the Nara Electric Railway and the city trams (Kyoto City Trams), so the area around the station developed rapidly.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, with the opening of the Sanin Main Line the station became the departure and arrival point of the Nara Electric Railway and the city trams (Kyoto City Trams), so the area around the station developed rapidly.</e>
<cmt>Sanin　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="122">
<j>なお、1921年（大正10年）8月1日に東海道本線のルートが逢坂山トンネル・東山トンネルの開通によって馬場～京都間で変更・短縮される事になった際に、至便性を上げるため五条通の市街地近くに駅を移設する案と、新しい市街地の開発を図るため京都北部を周回するルートに変えて、二条駅が現在設けられている付近に新しい京都総合駅を設けようという案もあったが、市街地付近に線路を引き込むのは予算や用地・工事の面で困難であった事と、京都付近で線路を周回させるのはトンネル開通に伴う距離短縮効果を失わせるという事から、どちらも立ち消えになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, on August 1, 1921, when the route of the Tokaido Main Line was to be changed and shortened thanks to the opening of Osakayama Tunnel and Higashiyama Tunnel, two plans － one was transferring the station toward the urban area around the Gojo-dori Street to enhance the convenience, and the other was changing the existing route to a circuitous route and constructing a new Kyoto general station near the present Nijo Station in order to promote the development of a new urban area －were proposed to improve the utility, although later on both of the two plans had faded away, owing to the difficulty of extending the line close to the urban area as well as the inconvenience that if the line were to go around Kyoto, the distance shortened by the opening of the tunnels would be offset.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, on August 1, 1921, when the route of the Tokaido Main Line was to be changed and shortened thanks to the opening of Osakayama Tunnel and Higashiyama Tunnel, two plans--one being to transfer the station toward the urban area around the Gojo-dori Street to enhance the convenience, and the other being to change the existing route to a circuitous route and construct a new Kyoto general station near the present Nijo Station in order to promote the development of a new urban area--were proposed to improve the utility, although eventually both plans faded, owing to the difficulty of extending the line close to the urban area as well as the inconvenience that if the line were to go around Kyoto the distance shortened by the opening of the tunnels would be offset.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, on August 1, 1921, when the route of the Tokaido Main Line in the section between Baba and Kyoto was to be changed and shortened thanks to the opening of Osakayama Tunnel and Higashiyama Tunnel, two plans--one being to transfer the station toward the urban area around the Gojo-dori Street in order to enhance the convenience, and the other being to change the existing route to a circuitous route in the northern part of Kyoto and construct a new Kyoto general station near the present Nijo Station so as to promote the development of a new urban area--were proposed to improve the utility, although eventually both plans faded, owing to the difficulty of budgeting and construction extending the line close to the urban area as well as the inconvenience that if the line were to go around Kyoto the distance shortened by the opening of the tunnels would be offset.</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="123">
<j>東海道新幹線の計画当初は、京都駅を経由せずに京都府南部を短絡させて同地に新幹線の駅を設け、速達列車の「ひかり (列車)」は京都を通過させる案となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact is that the original plan of the Shinkansen, in which the rapid Shinkansen &quot;Hikari&quot; was planned to go without stopping at Kyoto station, bypassing the southern Kyoto Prefecture with a new station, met considerable opposition from the local governments and residents, which had been calmed down with the plan of creating the platform for Shinkansen within the Kyoto Station (Please see the section &quot;Railways and Politics).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact is that the original plan of the Shinkansen, in which the rapid Shinkansen &quot;Hikari&quot; was planned to run without stopping at Kyoto station and thus bypass the southern Kyoto Prefecture with a new station, met considerable opposition from the local governments and residents, which had been calmed down with the plan of creating the platform for Shinkansen within the Kyoto Station (Please see the section &quot;Railways and Politics&quot;).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original plan for the &apos;Hikari&apos; Shinkansen was for it to run without stopping at Kyoto Station, thus bypassing the southern part of Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>自治体や地元市民などの猛反発を受けた事から、京都駅に新幹線ホームを併設の上で全列車停車に落ち着いた経緯がある（鉄道と政治の項目も参照の事）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was met by considerable opposition from the local governments and residents, however, who had been appeased with a plan to create a platform for the Shinkansen within Kyoto Station (see the Railways and Politics section for further details).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>また「のぞみ (列車)」が登場した1992年3月、東京発の一番列車「のぞみ301号」は名古屋駅と京都駅を通過していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When &quot;Nozomi&quot; was introduced in March, 1992, at the outset, &quot;Nozomi 301&quot;, the first train starting from Tokyo was running without stopping at Nagoya and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When &quot;Nozomi&quot; was introduced in March, 1992, at the outset &quot;Nozomi 301,&quot; the first train starting from Tokyo, ran without stopping at Nagoya and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When &apos;Nozomi&apos; was introduced in March 1992, at the outset &apos;Nozomi 301,&apos; the first train starting from Tokyo, ran without stopping at Nagoya and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>名古屋では名古屋飛ばしとして問題となったが、京都では観光に適した時間帯の列車でもなかった事から、ほとんど問題視されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nagoya the people protested saying &quot;Nagoya has been skipped, skipped&quot;, while in Kyoto, the people were little nervous about it because it was not the train that arrived at the best time for tourism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nagoya the people protested, saying &quot;Nagoya has been skipped, skipped,&quot; while in Kyoto the people were slightly nervous because it was not the train that arrived at the best time for tourism.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nagoya the people protested, saying Nagoya had been skipped, skipped, while in Kyoto the people were slightly nervous because it wasn&apos;t the train that arrived at the best time for tourism.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>1997年11月のダイヤ改正でこの「のぞみ301号」は廃止され、以降京都を通過する新幹線は存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;Nozomi 3-go&quot; was abolished by the revision of the timetable, and since then there is no Shinkansen passing nonstop at Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;Nozomi 3-go&quot; was abolished by the revision of the timetable, and consequently there is no Shinkansen passing nonstop at Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>USAGE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;Nozomi 301&apos; was abolished through the revision of the timetable in November 1997, and consequently there is no Shinkansen passing nonstop at Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>Nozomi 301としました。　括弧修正in November 1997 を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="128">
<j>1876年（明治9年）9月5日 - 大宮通仮停車場（現在の梅小路駅付近）-向日町間の鉄道が仮開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 5, 1876: The railway provisionally opened between Omiya-dori Temporary Train Station (near the present Umekoji (Freight) Station) and Mukomachi Station.</e>
<cmt>大宮通仮停車場→定訳不明　Omiya-dor Temporary Train Station (用語リスト#3735参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 5, 1876: The railway provisionally opened between Omiya-dori Temporary Train Station (near the present Umekoji (Freight) Station) and Mukomachi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 5, 1876: The railway provisionally opened between Omiya-dori Temporary Train Station (near the present Umekoji (Freight) Station) and Mukomachi Station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="129">
<j>1877年（明治10年）2月5日 - 明治天皇を迎えて鉄道開業式を挙行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 5, 1877: The Railway Inauguration Ceremony was held with the presence of Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 5, 1877: The railway&apos;s inauguration ceremony was held with the presence of Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 5, 1877: The railway&apos;s inauguration ceremony was held with Emperor Meiji present.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="130">
<j>1877年（明治10年）2月6日 - 京都停車場（京都駅）開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 6, 1877: Kyoto Teishaba (Kyoto Station) opened.</e>
<cmt>京都停車場→定訳不明　Kyoto Teishaba (Kyoto Station)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Teishaba (Kyoto Station) opened on February 6, 1877.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 6, 1877: Kyoto Teishaba (Kyoto Station) opened.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>大宮通仮停車場を廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omiya-dori Temporary Train Station was closed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya-dori Temporary Train Station was closed.</e>
<cmt>ARTICLE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya-dori Temporary Train Station was closed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="132">
<j>1879年（明治12年）8月18日 - 京都-大谷駅 (滋賀県)間の鉄道開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 18, 1879: The railway between Kyoto Station and Oya Station (Shiga Prefecture) began the operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railway between Kyoto Station and Oya Station (Shiga Prefecture) went into operation on August 18, 1879.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 18, 1879: The railway between Kyoto Station and Otani Station (Shiga Prefecture) went into operation.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>この路線はその後大津駅（後の浜大津駅）まで延伸され、さらに後には東海道本線の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This line was further extended to Otsu Station (later Hama Otsu Station), and, afterwards, was incorporated into the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This line was further extended to Otsu Station (later Hama Otsu Station), and afterwards it was incorporated into the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>SIMPLER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This line was further extended to Otsu Station (later Hamaotsu Station), and afterwards it was incorporated into the Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>浜大津の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="134">
<j>1895年（明治28年）2月1日 - 京都電気鉄道（のち京都市電に統合）の塩小路東洞院（京都駅前付近）-伏見下油掛間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 1, 1895: Kyoto Electric Railway (later integrated into Kyoto City Trams) started the operation between Shiokoji Higashi Toin Station (around Kyoto Station) and Fushimi-Shimoaburakake Station.</e>
<cmt>京都電気鉄道→定訳不明 kyoto Electric Railway、京都市電→Kyoto City Trams (http://kyoto.trolly.net)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Electric Railway (later integrated into Kyoto City Trams) started operation between Shiokoji Higashi Toin Station (around Kyoto Station) and Fushimi-Shimoaburakake Station on February 1, 1895.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 1, 1895: Kyoto Electric Railway (later integrated into Kyoto City Trams) started operating between Shiokoji-Higashitoin Station (around Kyoto Station) and Fushimi-Shimoaburakake Station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="135">
<j>9月5日 - 奈良鉄道（現在の奈良線）が乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 5, 1895: Nara Railway (nowadays Nara Line) started using the same track.</e>
<cmt>奈良鉄道→定訳不明　Nara Railway</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 5, 1895: Nara Railway (today the Nara Line) started by using the same track.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 5, 1895: Nara Railway (today the Nara Line) started by using the same track.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="136">
<j>1897年（明治30年）4月1日 - 奈良鉄道の京都駅を七条駅として分離。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1897: Kyoto Station on the Nara Railway was separated as &quot;Shichijo Station&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station on the Nara Railway was separated as &quot;Shichijo Station&quot; on April 1, 1897.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1897: Kyoto Station on the Nara Railway was separated as Shichijo Station on.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="137">
<j>11月16日 - 京都鉄道（現在の山陰本線）が乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 16, 1897: Kyoto Railway (present San&apos;in Main Line) started running the same track.</e>
<cmt>京都鉄道（用語リスト#3735参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Railway (the present-day San&apos;in Main Line) started by running the same track on November 16, 1897.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 16, 1897: Kyoto Railway (the present-day Sanin Main Line) started by running the same track.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="138">
<j>1905年（明治38年）2月7日 - 奈良鉄道が関西鉄道に事業譲渡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 7, 1905, Nara Railway transferred the business to Kansai Railway Company</e>
<cmt>関西鉄道(http://rtri.or.jp/japanrail/History1_E.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Railway transferred the business to Kansai Railway Company on February 7, 1905.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 7, 1905: Nara Railway transferred the business to Kansei Railway Company.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="139">
<j>1907年（明治40年）8月1日 - 京都鉄道鉄道国有法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1, 1907: Kyoto Railway Nationalization Act was enacted.</e>
<cmt>国有法施行？(was enacted.)を加えておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Railway Nationalization Act was enacted on August 1, 1907.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1907: The Kyoto Railway Nationalization Act was enacted.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="140">
<j>1907年（明治40年）10月1日 - 関西鉄道国有化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1907: Kansai Railway Company was nationalized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kansai Railway Company was nationalized on October 1, 1907.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1907: The Kansei Railway Company was nationalized.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="141">
<j>1908年（明治41年）6月1日 - 旧・奈良鉄道の七条駅を京都駅に統合。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June1, 1908: Shichijo Station on the former Nara Railway was integrated into Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichijo Station, on the former Nara Railway, was integrated into Kyoto Station on June 1, 1908.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 1, 1908: Shichijo Station, on the former Nara Railway, was integrated into Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="142">
<j>1912年（明治45年）6月11日 - 京都市電烏丸線が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 11, 1912: Kyoto City Trams Karasuma Line began the operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Trams Karasuma Line went into operation on June 11, 1912.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 11, 1912: Kyoto City Trams Karasuma Line went into operation.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="143">
<j>1913年（大正2年）6月21日 - 貨物の取扱いを新設の梅小路駅に分離。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 21, 1913: Cargo started to be handled in a separate form by the newly opened Umekoji Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cargo started being handled in a separate form by the newly opened Umekoji Station on June 21, 1913.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 21, 1913: Cargo started being handled in a separate form by the newly opened Umekoji Station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="144">
<j>1914年（大正3年）8月15日 - 2代目駅舎供用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 15, 1914: Preparation of the site for the second generation station building started.</e>
<cmt>供用→意味がわかりませんでした。Site preparationとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preparation of the site for the second-generation station building started on August 15, 1914.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 15, 1914: Preparation of the site for the second-generation station building started.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>1915年10月完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October, 1915: The station building completed.</e>
<cmt>完成は駅舎のことでしょうか（Station building)としておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station building was completed in October 1915.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1915: The station building was completed.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="146">
<j>1921年（大正10年）8月1日 - 奈良線旧線（伏見-京都間）廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1, 1921: The old Nara Line (between Inari Station and Kyoto Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old Nara Line (between Inari Station and Kyoto Station) was abolished on August 1, 1921.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1921: The old Nara Line (between Inari Station and Kyoto Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>桃山-稲荷間に新線を建設し、東海道本線旧線（稲荷-京都間）を奈良線に編入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A new line was constructed between Momoyama Station and Inari Station, while the old line (between Inari Station and Kyoto Station) was incorporated into the Nara Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A new line was constructed between Momoyama Station and Inari Station, while the old line (between Inari Station and Kyoto Station) was incorporated into the Nara Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A new line was constructed between Momoyama Station and Inari Station, while the old Tokaido Main Line between Inari Station and Kyoto Station was incorporated into the Nara Line.</e>
<cmt>東海道本線を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="148">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）11月15日 - 奈良電気鉄道（現在の近鉄京都線）の京都駅が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 15, 1928: Nara Electric Railways (present Kintetsu Railway Kyoto Line) opened its Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Electric Railways (present Kintetsu Railway Kyoto Line) opened its Kyoto Station on November 15, 1928.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 15, 1928: Nara Electric Railways (the present-day Kintetsu Kyoto Line) opened its Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="149">
<j>1934年（昭和9年）1月8日 - 国鉄駅構内で呉海兵団入営臨時列車の見送り客圧死事故。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 8, 1934: In the JNR Station yard, a person who came to see off a passenger of the special train provided for the people joining the Kure Marine Corps was crashed to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 8, 1934, in the JNR Station yard, a person who had come to see off a passenger of the special train provided for the people joining the Kure Marine Corps was crushed to death.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 8, 1934: In the JNR Station yard, a person who had come to see off a passenger of the special train provided for the people joining the Kure Marine Corps was crushed to death.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="150">
<j>1950年（昭和25年）11月18日 - 国鉄駅構内の食堂配電室から出火し駅舎全焼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 18, 1950: A fire broke out from the switch board room of the dinning located within the JNR Station yard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 18, 1950 a fire broke out from the switchboard room of the dinning located within the JNR Station yard.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 18, 1950: A fire broke out from the switchboard room of the dinning located within the JNR Station yard, and the station burned down.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="151">
<j>1952年（昭和27年）5月27日 - 国鉄京都駅3代目駅舎完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 27, 1952: The third generation building of JNR Kyoto Station was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third-generation building of JNR Kyoto Station was completed on Mary 27, 1952.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 27, 1952: The third-generation JNR Kyoto Station Building was completed.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="152">
<j>1961年（昭和36年）8月1日 - 京都市電堀川線（通称：北野線、京都駅前-北野）が廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1, 1961, Kyoto City Trams Horikawa Line (known as Kitano Line, between Kyoto Ekimae Station and Kitano Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1961 the Kyoto City Trams Horikawa Line (known as Kitano Line, between Kyoto Ekimae Station and Kitano Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1961: The Kyoto City Trams Horikawa Line (known as the Kitano Line, between Kyoto-ekimae Station and Kitano Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="153">
<j>1964年（昭和39年）10月1日 - 東海道新幹線が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1964: Tokaido Shinkansen was inaugurated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokaido Shinkansen was inaugurated on October 1, 1964.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1964: The Tokaido Shinkansen was inaugurated.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="154">
<j>1977年（昭和52年）10月1日 - 京都市電烏丸線の残存区間（京都駅前-烏丸七条）が廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1977: The remaining in-service section of Kyoto City Trams Karasuma Line (between Kyoto Ekimae Station and Karasuma Shichijo Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt>残存区間→remaining in-service sectionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1977 the remaining in-service section of Kyoto City Trams Karasuma Line (between Kyoto Ekimae Station and Karasuma Shichijo Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1977: The remaining in-service section of Kyoto City Trams Karasuma Line (between Kyoto-ekimae Station and Karasuma Shichijo Station) was abolished.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="155">
<j>1978年（昭和53年）10月1日 - 京都市電全廃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1978: Kyoto City Trams was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1978, Kyoto City Trams was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1978: Kyoto City Trams was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>京都駅前から姿を消す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trams disappeared around the Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>京都駅前→ここでは、around the Kyoto Stationとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trams in the vicinity of Kyoto Station disappeared.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trams in the vicinity of Kyoto Station disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="157">
<j>1981年（昭和56年）5月29日 - 京都市営地下鉄烏丸線（京都-北大路間）と共に地下鉄京都駅開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 29, 1981: Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line (between Kyoto Station and Kitaoji Station) started the operation with the inauguration of Kyoto Station on the City Subway Karasuma Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 29, 1981 the Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line (between Kyoto Station and Kitaoji Station) started operation with the inauguration of Kyoto Station on the City Subway Karasuma Line.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 29, 1981: The Kyoto Municipal Subway Karasuma Line (between Kyoto Station and Kitaoji Station) started operating with the inauguration of Kyoto Station of the Kyoto Municipal Subway.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="158">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日 - 国鉄分割民営化に伴い、国鉄京都駅の新幹線部分を東海旅客鉄道、在来線部分を西日本旅客鉄道が継承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1987: After the division and privatization of JNR, the operation of the Shinkansen at JNR Kyoto Station was succeeded by Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central), while the operation of the conventional lines was succeeded by West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>国鉄分割民営化（http://www/jrtr.net/ jrtr 13/pdf/his_13.pdf)参照</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 1987, after the division and privatization of JNR, the operation of the Shinkansen at JNR Kyoto Station was succeeded by Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central) and the operation of the conventional lines was succeeded by West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1987: After the division and privatization of JNR, the operation of the Shinkansen at JNR Kyoto Station was succeeded by Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central) and the operation of the conventional lines was succeeded by West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="159">
<j>1988年（昭和63年）6月11日 - 京都市営地下鉄烏丸線（京都-竹田間）が延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 11, 1988: Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line extended its operation (between Kyoto Station and Takeda Station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 11, 1988 the Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line extended its operation (between Kyoto Station and Takeda Station).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 11, 1988: The Kyoto Municipal Subway Karasuma Line extended its operation (between Kyoto Station and Takeda Station).</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="160">
<j>1997年（平成9年）7月12日 - JR京都駅4代目駅舎となる新・京都駅ビル完成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 12, 1997: A new Kyoto Station Building was completed as the forth generation of JR Kyoto Station building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 12, 1997 a new Kyoto Station Building was completed as the fourth generation of the JR Kyoto Station Building.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 12, 1997: A new Kyoto Station Building was completed as the fourth generation of the JR Kyoto Station Building.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>駅部分供用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station space started to be in service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station space went into service.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station space went into service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="162">
<j>1997年（平成9年）9月11日 - 京都駅ビル全面開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 11, 1997: The entire Kyoto Station Building was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 11, 1997 the entire Kyoto Station Building was opened.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 11, 1997: The entire Kyoto Station Building was opened.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>ジェイアール京都伊勢丹開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Kyoto Isetan opened</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Kyoto Isetan was opened.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Kyoto Isetan was opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="164">
<j>1998年（平成10年）3月4日 - 新幹線改札口に自動改札機を導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 4, 1998: Automatic ticket checkers were introduced at the Shinkansen Entrance.</e>
<cmt>新幹線改札口→Shinkansen Entranceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 4, 1998: Automatic ticket checkers were introduced at the Shinkansen entrance.</e>
<cmt>CAP</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 4, 1998: Automatic ticket checkers were introduced at the Shinkansen entrance.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="165">
<j>2007年（平成19年）8月23日 - JR京都駅NKビル開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 23, 2007: JR Kyoto Station NK Building opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 23, 2007 the JR Kyoto Station NK Building opened.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 23, 2007: The JR Kyoto Station NK Building opened.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>ビックカメラJR京都駅店が入店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bic Camera JR Kyoto Station Shop opened in the building.</e>
<cmt>家電量販店ビックカメラ(http://www.consultant.en-jp.com)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bic Camera JR Kyoto Station Shop opened in the building.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bic Camera JR Kyoto Station Shop opened in the building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>および嵯峨野線ホームに店内に直結する改札口の西洞院口を開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and, Nishinotoin-guchi (Nishinotoin entrance), a ticket wicket directly connecting to the platform of the Sagano Line from the shop was settled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Nishinotoin-guchi (Nishinotoin entrance), a ticket wicket directly connecting to the platform of the Sagano Line from the shop, was established.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, USAGE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Nishinotoin-guchi, a ticket wicket directly connecting to the platform of the Sagano Line from the shop, was established.</e>
<cmt>nishinotoin-guchi　既出のため英訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="168">
<j>2008年（平成20年） - 南側に府内最大のショッピングモールができるため、南北自由通路を延伸させる予定（補正予算が組まれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Year 2008: It is scheduled to extend the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway), because the construction of a new shopping mall, which will be the biggest mall in the prefecture, is planned in the south side of the station.</e>
<cmt>南北自由通路→定訳不明　Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Year 2008: It is scheduled to extend the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (free north-south walkway) because the construction of a new shopping mall, which will be the biggest mall in the prefecture, is planned for the south side of the station.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2008: It was scheduled to extend the Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro because the construction of a new shopping mall, which will be the biggest mall in the prefecture, is planned for the south side of the station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="169">
<j>第1回近畿の駅百選に選定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station was chosen as one of the top 100 stations in the Kinki District.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station was chosen as one of the top 100 stations in the Kinki District.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station was chosen as one of the top 100 stations in the Kinki District.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="170">
<j>2008年中に南北自由通路を南または南西に八条通を跨ぐ形で延伸する計画がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is scheduled to extend the existing Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free walkway) to south or south-west over the Hachijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is scheduled to extend the existing Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (free north-south walkway) to south or southwest over Hachijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is scheduled to extend the existing Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro to south or southwest over Hachijo-dori Street within 2008.</e>
<cmt>Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro としました。within 2008 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="171">
<j>特急『くろしお (列車)』の京都駅到着時の車内チャイムは「祇園小唄」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited Express &quot;Kuroshio&quot; chime out the melody of &quot;Gion Kouta&quot; when it arrives at Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>祇園小唄（http://komuso.com/pieces/Gion_Kouta.html)）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The limited express &quot;Kuroshio&quot; chimes out the melody of &quot;Gion Kouta&quot; when it arrives at Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The limited express &quot;Kuroshio&quot; chimes out the melody of &apos;Gion Kouta&apos; when it arrives at Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="172">
<j>当駅は、地上の駅に近鉄京都線が発着し、地下の駅に近鉄から京都市営烏丸線へ直通する電車が停車するため、地上と地下に同じ事業者・同じ路線の車両が停車する珍しい駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This station is considred a unique case where the same line of the same company make a stop on the ground as well as underground, because the trains of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line depart and arrive on the ground, while the trains that go though to the Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line from the Kintetsu Line make a stop underground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This station is considered a unique case where the same line of the same company makes a stop on the ground as well as underground, because the trains of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line depart and arrive on the ground while the trains that go though to the Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line from the Kintetsu Line make the stop underground.</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This station is considered a unique case where the same line of the same company makes a stop on the ground as well as underground, because the trains of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line depart and arrive on the ground while the trains that go through to the Kyoto Municipal Subway Karasuma Line from the Kintetsu Line make their stop underground.</e>
<cmt>city →municipal</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>池袋駅でも同様の現象が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same setup is also observed at Ikebukuro Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same setup is also observed at Ikebukuro Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same setup is also observed at Ikebukuro Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>JR西日本・JR東海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR West and JR Central</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR West and JR Central</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR West and JR Central</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="174">
<j>現在の駅ビルが完成すると同時に、接近メロディがかつて西武鉄道で発車メロディとして使われていた曲（西武秩父駅では現在も使用している）に変更された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the present station building was completed, the melody of the arrival chime was changed to that used as departing chime on the Seibu Line before (this melody is still used at Seibu-chichibu Station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the present station building was completed, the melody of the arrival chime was changed to the one that had previously been used as the departing chime on the Seibu Line (this melody is still used at Seibu-chichibu Station).</e>
<cmt>TENSE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the present station building was completed, the melody of the arrival chime was changed to the one that had previously been used as the departing chime on the Seibu Line (this melody is still used at Seibu-chichibu Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>また2・3代目駅舎には存在しなかった「京都駅」の看板が取り付けられた（3代目にはJR化後に取り付けられていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the station building, the sign of the station name &quot;Kyoto Station&quot; was placed, which neither the second nor the third building had (in case of the 3rd generation building, the sing was installed on the wall after the privatization to JR).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the station building the sign of the station name &quot;Kyoto Station&quot; was placed, which neither the second nor the third building had (in case of the third-generation building the sign was installed on the wall after the privatization to JR).</e>
<cmt>SPELLING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the station building the sign of the station name &apos;Kyoto Station&apos; was placed, which neither the second nor the third building had (in case of the third-generation building, the sign was installed on the wall after the privatization to JR).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="176">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京阪本線の七条駅とも若干（1km程度）距離はあるものの、徒歩で乗り換える客もいる（一般的には奈良線利用で東福寺駅または近鉄京都線利用での近鉄丹波橋駅まで出て、京阪本線に乗り換える事が多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To transfer to Shichijo Station on the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway, though it is a little far (about 1km&apos; distance), there are passengers going on foot, (most passengers use the Nara Line to Tofukuji Station or use the Kintetsu Line to Tanbabashi Station in order to take a train of the Keihan Main Line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To transfer to Shichijo Station on the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway, though it is a bit far (a distance of about a kilometer), there are passengers going on foot (most passengers use the Nara Line to Tofukuji Station or use the Kintetsu Line to Tanbabashi Station in order to take a train of the Keihan Main Line).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To transfer to Shichijo Station on the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway, though it is a bit far (a distance of about a kilometer), passengers go on foot (most passengers use the Nara Line to Tofukuji Station or use the Kintetsu Kyoto Line to Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station in order to take a train of the Keihan Main Line).</e>
<cmt>近鉄京都線、近鉄丹波橋駅を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="177">
<j>JRの特定都区市内制度における「京都市内」の駅であり、運賃計算の中心駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the base station to calculate the fare, because it is one of the stations &quot;within Kyoto City&quot; according to the JR definition of designated city areas.</e>
<cmt>JRの特定都区市内制度における「京都市内」の駅→定訳不明：&quot;within Kyoto City&quot; according to the JR definition of designated city areas としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the base station to calculate the fare, because it&apos;s one of the stations &quot;within Kyoto City&quot; according to the JR definition of designated city areas.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the base station by which to calculate the fare, because it&apos;s one of the stations &apos;within Kyoto City&apos; according to the JR definition of designated city areas.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>近鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinkitetsu Railways</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kinkitetsu&quot; should be &quot;Kintetsu.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="178">
<j>近鉄京都線の前身は奈良電気鉄道であり、同社が京都駅への乗り入れを最初に計画した時は、地下線を採用して国鉄駅の下を通り、烏丸口の北側へ設ける予定としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nara Electric Railway (present Kintetsu Kyoto Line) pretended a direct connection with Kyoto Station, the initial plan proposed to install a subway line going beneath the JNR Station and construct a station in the north side of Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nara Electric Railway (the current Kintetsu Kyoto Line) pretended a direct connection with Kyoto Station, the initial plan proposed the installation of a subway line running beneath the JNR Station and the construction of a station on the north side of Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nara Electric Railway (the current Kintetsu Kyoto Line) presented a direct connection with Kyoto Station, the initial plan proposed the installation of a subway line running beneath JNR Station and the construction of a station on the north side of Karasuma-guchi.</e>
<cmt>pretend →presented</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>しかし、昭和天皇即位の礼が実施されるのに間に合わせる必要があった事、それに予算の問題もあって、とりあえず仮の駅として、現在地に地上でターミナル駅を建設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a terminal station was provisionally constructed on the ground of the actual site, because, in addition to the budgetary constraint, the construction had to be completed before the Enthronement Ceremony of Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a terminal station was provisionally constructed on the grounds of the actual site because, in addition to the budgetary constraint, the construction had to be completed before the Enthronement Ceremony of Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a terminal station was provisionally constructed on the grounds of the present site because, in addition to budgetary constraints, there was also a need for the construction to be completed before the Enthronement Ceremony for Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>actual site→present site</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="180">
<j>その後、仮設置の予定であった駅設備は移設される事もなく、東海道新幹線の建設に合わせて駅を高架化し、現在のように新幹線駅の真下にホームが設けられる構造となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, the station facility, which was supposed to be provisional, has not been moved, and when the construction of Tokaido Shinkansen started, the station was elevated to have a similar structure to that of the present station building, which permitted the platforms to be placed just beneath the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the station facility, which was supposed to be provisional, has not been moved; and when the construction of Tokaido Shinkansen started, the station was elevated to have a similar structure to that of the present station building, which permitted the platforms to be placed just beneath the station.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the station facility, which was supposed to be provisional, has not been moved; and when the construction of Tokaido Shinkansen started, the station was elevated in order to have a similar structure to that of the present station building, which permitted the platforms to be placed just beneath the Shinkansen station.</e>
<cmt>新幹線駅　追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="181">
<j>普通電車は西大寺行がほとんどであるが、急行と特急は列車によって行先が異なり、大まかに分けて急行は奈良行（日中は地下鉄京都駅からも利用可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the local trains are bounded for Saidaiji Station, while the express and limited express trains vary their destination according to the train, although roughly speaking, the express are bound for Nara Station (during the daytime, the line is also available from Subway Kyoto Station,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the local trains are bound for Saidaiji Station, while the express and limited express trains vary their destinations according to the train, although roughly speaking the expresses are bound for Nara Station (during the daytime the line is also available from Subway Kyoto Station),</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the local trains are bound for Saidaiji Station, while the express and limited express trains vary their destinations according to the train; however, roughly speaking the expresses are bound for Nara (during the daytime the line is also available from Subway Kyoto Station,</e>
<cmt>次の文章につながるため、末尾のとじかっこを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>ただし地下鉄の運賃も必要になる）、天理行、橿原神宮前行（西大寺まではすべて同じ停車駅）が、特急は奈良行、橿原神宮前行、賢島行がある（近鉄特急を参照の事）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">though it is required to pay the extra fare for the subway section), for Tenri, and for Kashiharajingu-mae (to Saidaiji Station, the express makes a stop at the same stations), while the limited express are bound for Nara, for Kashiharajingu-mae, and for Kashikojima (please see the section &quot;Kintetsu limited express&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">though it is required to pay the extra fare for the subway section), for Tenri, and for Kashiharajingu-mae (to Saidaiji Station, the express makes a stop at the same stations), while the limited expresses are bound for Nara, for Kashiharajingu-mae and Kashikojima (please see the section &quot;Kintetsu Limited Express&quot;).</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">though it is necessary to pay the extra fare for the subway section), for Tenri, and for Kashiharajingu-mae (to Saidaiji Station, the express stops at the same stations), while the limited expresses are bound for Nara, for Kashiharajingu-mae and Kashikojima (please see the section &quot;Kintetsu Limited Express&quot;).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="183">
<j>地下鉄対応車両近鉄3200系電車、近鉄3220系電車は、運用の関係上当駅と地下鉄京都駅（烏丸京都駅）の2か所へ乗り入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trains of Kintetsu series 3200, and 3220, which are convertible with the subway, take two different track, one to this station and the other to Subway Kyoto Station (Karasuma Kyoto Station).</e>
<cmt>近鉄3200系電車、近鉄3220系電車ともに (http://trenomania.org/TMF-)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trains of the Kintetsu series 3200, and 3220, which are convertible with the subway, take two different tracks: one to this station and the other to Subway Kyoto Station (Karasuma Kyoto Station).</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trains of the Kintetsu series 3200, and 3220, which are convertible with the subway, take two different tracks: one to this station and the other to Subway Kyoto Station (Karasuma Kyoto Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="184">
<j>今後、2010年までに4番線新設（上記参照）と1階改札口を廃止し、2階へ改札口の統合を行う予定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the year 2010, the Tack No4 (see above) and the ticket wicket on the 1st floor are scheduled to be removed and integrated to the ticket wicket of the 2nd floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the year 2010, track No. 4 (see above) and the ticket wicket on the first floor are scheduled to be removed and integrated to the ticket wicket of the second floor.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the year 2010, Platform 4 (see above) will be newly constructed, and the ticket wicket on the first floor will be removed and integrated with the ticket wicket of the second floor.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="185">
<j>PiTaPa・ICOCAのチャージは改札外の券売機、改札内の精算機・チャージ機で取り扱っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">PiTaPa and ICOCA can be charged using the ticket machines installed outside the ticket gate, while the exit fare machines and chargers can be found inside the ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>チャージ機→定訳不明：chargerとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">PiTaPa and ICOCA can be charged using the ticket machines installed outside the ticket gate, while the exit fare machines and chargers can be found inside the ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">PiTaPa and ICOCA can be charged using the ticket machines installed outside the ticket gate, as well as the exit-fare machines and chargers inside the ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>和文どおりにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="186">
<j>京都線でL/Cカーを運行する際に時間帯に関係なくロングシートになっているのは、当駅の構造に起因する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kyoto Line, because of the structure of the station. the C/L cars (cross/long changeable seat cars) are setup with long seats regardless of the hours.</e>
<cmt>L/Cカー→定訳不明： C/L car (cross/long changeable seat car)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kyoto Line, due to the structure of the station. the C/L cars (cross/long changeable seat cars) are set up with long seats regardless of the hours.</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kyoto Line, due to the structure of the station, the L/C cars (long/cross changeable seat cars) are set up with long seats regardless of the hours.</e>
<cmt>L/Cカー→定訳不明： L/C car (long/cross changeable seat car) →L/Cの順番はそのままの訳に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>3番線が乗降分離できない構造となっているため、3番線に入るとクロスシートにしても折り返しの際にシートを回転できなくなるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because, the Platform No. 3 has an structure that does not permit to divide the incoming/outgoing flow, and when the train enters in the Track No.3, even if the cross seat are set, it can not turn around to adjust to the direction of the train turning back the track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because, platform No. 3 has a structure that does not permit division of the incoming/outgoing flow, and when the train enters on track No. 3, even if the cross seats are set, it cannot turn around to adjust to the direction of the train turning back on the track.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because, Platform 3 has a structure that does not permit division of the incoming/outgoing flow, and when the train enters on Platform 3, even if the cross seats are set, it cannot turn around to adjust to the direction of the train turning back on the track.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線、のりば」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>駅弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekiben (train lunch)</e>
<cmt>駅弁明は用語リスト#3735を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekiben (train lunch)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekiben (train lunch)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="188">
<j>合名会社 萩の家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haginoya Ordinary Partnership</e>
<cmt>http://www.hiraganatimes.com/index-j.html/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haginoya Ordinary Partnership</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haginoya Ordinary Partnership</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="189">
<j>岩魚寿し/鰻のねどこ/新撰組ゆかりの幕の内/平安弁当/加茂川弁当/笹うなぎ/竹籠弁当/精進弁当/鯛めし/京扇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwana-zushi (Char sushi), Unagi-no-nedoko, Shinsen-gumi yukari no Makunouchi (Shinsen-gumi Makunouchi Bento), Heian Bento, Kamo-gawa Bento, Sasa-Unagi, Takekago Bento (lunch box in bamboo basket), Shojin Bento (vegetarian lunch box), Tai-meshi (sea-bream rice), Kyo-Ogi</e>
<cmt>駅弁名：定訳不明、新撰組ゆかりの幕の内→Shinsen-gumi yukari no Makunouchi (samurai warriors&apos; boxed lunch)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwana-zushi (Char sushi), Unagi-no-nedoko, Shinsen-gumi yukari no Makunouchi (Shinsen-gumi Makunouchi Bento), Heian Bento, Kamo-gawa Bento, Sasa-Unagi, Takekago Bento (lunch box in bamboo basket), Shojin Bento (vegetarian lunch box), Tai-meshi (sea-bream rice), Kyo-Ogi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwana-zushi (Char sushi), Unagi-no-nedoko, Shinsen-gumi yukari no Makunouchi (Shinsen-gumi Makunouchi Bento), Heian Bento, Kamo-gawa Bento, Sasa-Unagi, Takekago Bento (lunch box in bamboo basket), Shojin Bento (vegetarian lunch box), Tai-meshi (sea-bream rice), Kyo-Ogi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="190">
<j>株式会社 ジェイアール西日本フードサービスネット</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan Railway Food Service Net Company</e>
<cmt>http://www.jwfsn.com/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West Japan Railway Food Service Net Company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan Railway Food Service Net Company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="191">
<j>京風幕の内/京洛弁当/こてまり/なごみ弁当/京友禅/味彩弁当/とんかつ弁当/中華弁当/こだわりおむすび弁当/洋風弁当/特製おにぎり弁当/栗おこわ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyofu Makunouchi (Kyoto-style Makunouchi), Kyoraku Bento, Kotemari, Nagomi Bento, Kyo-Yuzen, Ajisai Bento, Tonkatsu Bento (port cutlet lunch), Chuka Bento (Chinese-style lunch), Kodawari Omusubi Bento (special riceball lunch), Yofu Bento (western-style lunch), (Tokusei Onigiri Bento (special recipe riceball lunch), Kuri Okowa (glutinous rice cooked with chestnuts)</e>
<cmt>駅弁名：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyofu Makunouchi (Kyoto-style Makunouchi), Kyoraku Bento, Kotemari, Nagomi Bento, Kyo-Yuzen, Ajisai Bento, Tonkatsu Bento (pork cutlet lunch), Chuka Bento (Chinese-style lunch), Kodawari Omusubi Bento (special riceball lunch), Yofu Bento (Western-style lunch), Tokusei Onigiri Bento (special recipe riceball lunch), Kuri Okowa (glutinous rice cooked with chestnuts)</e>
<cmt>SPELLING, CAPS</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyofu Makunouchi (Kyoto-style Makunouchi), Kyoraku Bento, Kotemari, Nagomi Bento, Kyo-Yuzen, Ajisai Bento, Tonkatsu Bento (pork cutlet lunch), Chuka Bento (Chinese-style lunch), Kodawari Omusubi Bento (special riceball lunch), Yofu Bento (Western-style lunch), Tokusei Onigiri Bento (special recipe riceball lunch), Kuri Okowa (glutinous rice cooked with chestnuts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="192">
<j>株式会社 ジェイアール東海パッセンジャーズ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR-Central Passengers Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>http://www.jr-cp.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR-Central Passengers Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR-Central Passengers Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="193">
<j>日本の味博覧/そぼろぼろぼろ大好き弁当/上方幕の内 温弁当/てまり寿司/花瓢/鯛めし/竹の子ごはんと桜めし/東山五条/大阪名物まむし丼/特選弁当『京都』/牛若丸御前/弁慶御前/上方幕の内/中華餐々/じゅうじゅう亭/とんかつ弁当/21世紀出陣弁当/五目釜めし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon-no-aji Hakuran (&quot;taste of Japan&quot; expo), Soboro-boroboro Daisuki Bento, Kamigata Makunouch On-Bento (Kyoto-Osaka style hot boxed lunch), Temari-zushi, Hanahisago, Taimeshi (sea-bream rice), Takenoko-gohan to Sakura-meshi (bamboo-shoot rice and &quot;Sakura&quot; rice), Higashiyama Gojo, Osaka meibutsu Mamushi-don (Osaka specialty grilled eel rice), Tokusen Bento &quot;Kyoto&quot; (special recipe lunch &quot;Kyoto&quot;), Ushiwakamaru Gozen lunch, Benkei Gozen lunch, Kamigata Makunouchi (Kyoto-Osaka style boxed lunch), Chuka Sansan (lunch with a variety of Chinese foods), Juju-tei, Tonkatsu Bento (pork cutlet lunch), 21-seiki Shutsujin Bento (21st century warrior lunch), Gomoku Kamameshi (assorted rice in a small pot)</e>
<cmt>弁当名：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon-no-aji Hakuran (&quot;taste of Japan&quot; expo), Soboro-boroboro Daisuki Bento, Kamigata Makunouch On-Bento (Kyoto-Osaka style hot boxed lunch), Temari-zushi, Hanahisago, Taimeshi (sea-bream rice), Takenoko-gohan to Sakura-meshi (bamboo-shoot rice and &quot;Sakura&quot; rice), Higashiyama Gojo, Osaka meibutsu Mamushi-don (Osaka specialty grilled eel rice), Tokusen Bento &quot;Kyoto&quot; (special recipe lunch &quot;Kyoto&quot;), Ushiwakamaru Gozen lunch, Benkei Gozen lunch, Kamigata Makunouchi (Kyoto-Osaka style boxed lunch), Chuka Sansan (lunch with a variety of Chinese foods), Juju-tei, Tonkatsu Bento (pork cutlet lunch), 21-seiki Shutsujin Bento (21st-century warrior lunch), Gomoku Kamameshi (assorted rice in a small pot)</e>
<cmt>HYPHEN</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-no-aji Hakuran (&quot;taste of Japan&quot; expo), Soboro-boroboro Daisuki Bento, Kamigata Makunouch On-Bento (Kyoto/Osaka-style hot boxed lunch), Temari-zushi, Hanahisago, Taimeshi (sea-bream rice), Takenoko-gohan to Sakura-meshi (bamboo-shoot rice and &quot;Sakura&quot; rice), Higashiyama Gojo, Osaka meibutsu Mamushi-don (Osaka specialty grilled-eel rice), Tokusen Bento &quot;Kyoto&quot; (special recipe lunch &quot;Kyoto&quot;), Ushiwakamaru Gozen, Benkei Gozen, Kamigata Makunouchi (Kyoto/Osaka-style boxed lunch), Chuka Sansan (lunch with a variety of Chinese foods), Juju-tei, Tonkatsu Bento (pork-cutlet lunch), 21-seiki Shutsujin Bento (21st-century &quot;kick-off&quot;lunch), Gomoku Kamameshi (assorted rice in a small pot)</e>
<cmt>一部名前を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="194">
<j>株式会社 戸川</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togawa Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togawa Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togawa Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="195">
<j>味ごのみ/わらべ/京三昧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aji-gonomi, Warabe, Kyo-zanmai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aji-gonomi, Warabe, Kyo-zanmai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aji-gonomi, Warabe, Kyo-zammai</e>
<cmt>一部名前を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>他の「京都駅」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other stations named &quot;Kyoto&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other stations named &quot;Kyoto&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other stations named &apos;Kyoto&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="196">
<j>阪急京都本線の大宮駅 (京都府)は、河原町駅 (京都府)への延伸が果たされた1963年まで「阪急京都駅」（1949年の京阪電気鉄道分離前は京阪神京都駅、開業時は京阪京都駅）を駅の名称とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Hankyu Kyoto Mail Line was called &quot;Hankyu Kyoto Station&quot;, until the line was extended to Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) in 1963 (&quot;Keihanshin Kyoto Station&quot;, until 1949 when the Keihan Electric Railway was decoupled, and &quot;Keihan Kyoto Station&quot; when the station was opened).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Hankyu Kyoto Mail Line was called the &quot;Hankyu Kyoto Station&quot; until the line was extended to Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) in 1963 (&quot;Keihanshin Kyoto Station&quot; until 1949, when the Keihan Electric Railway was decoupled, and &quot;Keihan Kyoto Station&quot; when the station was opened).</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture) on the Hankyu Kyoto Main Line was called &apos;Hankyu Kyoto Station&apos; until the line was extended to Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) in 1963 (Keihanshin Kyoto Station until 1949, when the Keihan Electric Railway was decoupled, and Keihan Kyoto Station when the station was opened).</e>
<cmt>Mail Line →Main Line 括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="197">
<j>周辺は商業地域。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is located in the commercial area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is located in the commercial area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is located in the commercial area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>烏丸口（北側）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit) (north side)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit) (north side)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit) (north side)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="198">
<j>京都駅ビル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station Building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station Building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station Building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="199">
<j>JR西日本ホテルズ京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR-West Hotels Kyoto (Hotel Granvia Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>http://hotels.westjr.co.jp/english/index.html/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR-West Hotels Kyoto (Hotel Granvia Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR-West Hotels Kyoto (Hotel Granvia Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="200">
<j>ジェイアール京都伊勢丹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Kyoto Isetan(West Japan Railway Isetan Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>http://www.wjr-isetan.co.jp/Kyoto/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Kyoto Isetan(West Japan Railway Isetan Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Kyoto Isetan(West Japan Railway Isetan Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="201">
<j>京都駅ビル専門店街The CUBE</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station Building Specialty Mall &quot;The CUBE&quot;</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station Building Specialty Mall, i.e., &quot;The CUBE&quot;</e>
<cmt>CLARITY</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station Building Specialty Mall, i.e., The CUBE</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="202">
<j>京都劇場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto-Gekijo Theater</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-gekijo.com/index.html/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-Gekijo Theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-Gekijo Theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="203">
<j>美術館「えき」Kyoto</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Museum &quot;Eki&quot; Kyoto</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Museum &quot;Eki&quot; Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Museum &apos;Eki&apos; Kyoto</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="204">
<j>KYOTO手塚治虫ワールド</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KYOTO Osamu Tezuka World</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KYOTO Osamu Tezuka World</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KYOTO Osamu Tezuka World</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="205">
<j>京都ラーメン小路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Ramen Koji (Ramen Lane)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Ramen Koji (Ramen Lane)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-Ramen-Koji (Ramen Lane)</e>
<cmt>Kyoto-Ramen-Koji に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="206">
<j>京都駅前地下街ポルタ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station Underground Mall Porta</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station Underground Mall Porta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station Underground Mall Porta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="207">
<j>京都タワー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Tower</e>
<cmt>http://kyoto-tower.co.jp/english/kyototower/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Tower</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Tower</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="208">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京都ビル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>和英翻訳データブック（ジャパンタイムズ編）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Building of the Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>京都ビルを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="209">
<j>京都府赤十字血液センター（京都駅前出張所）献血ルーム京都駅前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Red Cross Blood Center, Kyoto Building</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto.bc.jrc.or.jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Red Cross Blood Center, Kyoto Building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Red Cross Blood Center, Kyoto Building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="210">
<j>阪急ホテルマネジメント</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Hotel Management.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Hotel Management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Hotel Management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="211">
<j>真宗本廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-shu Honbyo</e>
<cmt>用語リスト# 参照</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-shu Honbyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-shu Hombyo</e>
<cmt>Shin-shu Hombyoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="212">
<j>七条警察署</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shichijo Police Station</e>
<cmt>http://travel.nytimes.com/frommers/travel/guides/asia/japan/kyoto/frm_kyoto_0080020157.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichijo Police Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichijo Police Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="213">
<j>京都中央郵便局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Central Post Office</e>
<cmt>http://www.pref.kyoto.jp/visitkyoto/en/info_required/travel_info/post_offices/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Central Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Central Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="214">
<j>キャンパスプラザ京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Campus Plaza Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Campus Plaza Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Campus Plaza Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="215">
<j>オムロン本社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omron Corp. Head Office</e>
<cmt>和英翻訳データブック（ジャパンタイムズ編）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omron Corp. Head Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omron Corp. Head Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="216">
<j>京都駅前バスターミナル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus terminal in front of Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus terminal in front of Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus terminal in front of Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="217">
<j>ハローワーク京都七条</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public job-placement office &quot;Hello Work&quot; Kyoto Shichijo</e>
<cmt>定訳不明（英辞郎WEB参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public job-placement office &quot;Hello Work&quot; Kyoto Shichijo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public job-placement office Hello Work Kyoto Shichijo</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>西洞院口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishinotoin-guchi (Nishinotoin entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishinotoin-guchi (Nishinotoin entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishinotoin-guchi</e>
<cmt>既出のため、括弧内の英訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="218">
<j>ビックカメラJR京都駅店（JR京都駅NKビル）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bic Camera JR Kyoto shop (JR Kyoto Station NK Building)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bic Camera JR Kyoto shop (JR Kyoto Station NK Building)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bic Camera JR Kyoto shop (JR Kyoto Station NK Building)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>八条口（南側）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachijo-guchi (Hachijo entrance/exit) (south side)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachijo-guchi (Hachijo entrance/exit) (south side)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachijo-guchi (south side)</e>
<cmt>既出のため、括弧内の英訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="219">
<j>アバンティ (商業ビル)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Business complex &quot;Avanty&quot;</e>
<cmt>http://www.avanti-kyoto.com/index.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Avanti&quot; business complex</e>
<cmt>SPELLING, BETTER FLOW</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Avanti business complex</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="220">
<j>ホテル京阪京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotel Keihan Kyoto</e>
<cmt>http://www.hotelkeihan-kyoto.com/us/index.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotel Keihan Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotel Keihan Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="221">
<j>都ホテルズ&amp;ampリゾーツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyako Hotels and Resorts</e>
<cmt>http://www.miyakohotels.ne.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyako Hotels and Resorts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyako Hotels and Resorts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="222">
<j>定期観光バスターミナル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Routine Sightseeing Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Routine Sightseeing Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Routine Sightseeing Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="223">
<j>高速バスターミナル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Express Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>定訳不明　（英辞郎WEB参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Express Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Express Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="224">
<j>京都市上下水道局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Waterworks Bureau</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.jp/suido/engtop.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Waterworks Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Waterworks Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="225">
<j>PHP研究所本社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">PHP Interface Kyoto Head Office</e>
<cmt>PHP研究所HP (http://www.php.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">PHP Interface Kyoto Head Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">PHP Interface Kyoto Head Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="226">
<j>東寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000042&amp;InforKindCode=1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="227">
<j>洛南高等学校・附属中学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakunan High School/ Junior High School</e>
<cmt>http://www.rakunan-h.ed.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakunan High School/Junior High School</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakunan High School/Junior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="228">
<j>京都駅八条口郵便局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station Hachijo-guchi Post Office</e>
<cmt>定訳不明（用語リスト#3735参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station Hachijo-guchi Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station Hachijo-guchi Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>路線バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rout bus</e>
<cmt>定訳不明（英辞郎WEB参照）SP</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route bus</e>
<cmt>SPELLING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>烏丸口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasuma-guchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma-guchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma-guchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="229">
<j>京都駅前停留所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Ekimae Bus Stop (bus stop in front of Kyoto Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Ekimae Bus Stop (bus stop in front of Kyoto Station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-ekimae Bus Stop (bus stop in front of Kyoto Station)</e>
<cmt>「駅前」を-ekimaeにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="230">
<j>京都市交通局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.jp/koho/eng/access/transportation.html/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="231">
<j>4・5・9・快速9・16・17・19・26・28・33・特33・42・50・73・75・78・81・特81・100・101・205・快速205・206・208・南5・臨28の各系統</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route numbers: 4・5・9・Rapid 9・16・17・19・26・28・33・Limited 33・42・50・73・75・78・81・Limited 81・100・101・205・Special Limited 205・206・208・South 5・Extra 28</e>
<cmt>意味不明。バス系統番号でしょうか。南5？：South 5としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route numbers: 4・5・9・Rapid 9・16・17・19・26・28・33・Limited 33・42・50・73・75・78・81・Limited 81・100・101・205・Special Limited 205・206・208・South 5・Extra 28</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route numbers: 4・5・9・Rapid 9・16・17・19・26・28・33・Limited 33・42・50・73・75・78・81・Limited 81・100・101・205・Special Limited 205・206・208・South 5・Extra 28</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="232">
<j>京阪バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Bus</e>
<cmt>京阪バスHP (http://www.keihanbus.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="233">
<j>比叡山方面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward Hieizan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toward Hieizan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward Mt.Hiei-zan</e>
<cmt>Toward Mt.Hiei-zanに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="234">
<j>京都バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Bus</e>
<cmt>京都バスHP (http://www.kyotobus.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="235">
<j>八瀬・大原・嵐山・大覚寺・清滝・苔寺（鈴虫寺）・北大路駅前・国際会館駅前・叡山電鉄岩倉駅 (京都府)前・岩倉村松・有栖川（嵐山営業所前）・高野車庫前（高野営業所前）方面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward: Yase, Ohara, Arashiyama, Daikaku-ji, Kiyotaki, Koke-dera (Suzumushi-dera), Kitaoji-eikimae, Kokusaikaikaneki-mae, Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway) Iwakura-ekimae (Kyoto Prefecture), Iwakura Muramatsu, Arisugawa (Arashiyama-eigyoshomae), Koya-Shakomae (Koya-eigyoshomae)</e>
<cmt>バス停名称は用語リスト＃3735を参照に、日本語名のローマ字表記とし、理解の一助となると思われる時は仮英訳名、また英語表記が決まっている場合は（）内に英語定訳名を入れました。 叡山電鉄岩倉駅前→Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway) Iwakura-ekimae （http://www/keihannet.ne.jp/eiden/odekake/odekake.php)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toward: Yase, Ohara, Arashiyama, Daikaku-ji, Kiyotaki, Koke-dera (Suzumushi-dera), Kitaoji-eikimae, Kokusaikaikaneki-mae, Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway) Iwakura-ekimae (Kyoto Prefecture), Iwakura Muramatsu, Arisugawa (Arashiyama-eigyoshomae), Koya-Shakomae (Koya-eigyoshomae)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward: Yase, Ohara, Arashiyama, Daikaku-ji, Kiyotaki, Koke-dera (Suzumushi-dera), Kitaoji-eikimae, Kokusaikaikaneki-mae, Eizan-dentetsu (Eizan Electric Railway) Iwakura-ekimae (Kyoto Prefecture), Iwakura Muramatsu, Arisugawa (Arashiyama-eigyoshomae), Takano-shakomae (Takano-eigyoshomae)</e>
<cmt>koya→ takano</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="236">
<j>京阪京都交通（京阪バスの子会社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Kyoto Kotsu (subsidiary of Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Kyoto Kotsu (subsidiary of Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Kyoto Kotsu (subsidiary of Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="237">
<j>西大路七条・桂駅東口・国道中山・桂坂中央・京都成章高校前・長峰・老の坂峠・亀岡駅前方面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward: Nishioji Nanajo, Katsura-eki Higashi-guchi, Kokudo Nakayama, Katsurazaka-chuo, Kyoto Seishokoko (Kyoto Seisho Haigh School)-mae, Nagamine, Oi-no-saka Toge, Kameoka-ekimae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toward: Nishioji Nanajo, Katsura-eki Higashi-guchi, Kokudo Nakayama, Katsurazaka-chuo, Kyoto Seishokoko (Kyoto Seisho Haigh School)-mae, Nagamine, Oi-no-saka Toge, Kameoka-ekimae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward: Nishioji Nanajo, Katsura-eki Higashi-guchi, Kokudo Nakayama, Katsurazaka-chuo, Kyoto Seishokoko (Kyoto Seisho High School)-mae, Nagamine, Oi-no-saka Toge, Kameoka-ekimae</e>
<cmt>Haigh →High</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="238">
<j>京都交通 (舞鶴)（日本交通 (大阪)の子会社（京阪京都交通（京阪バスの子会社）とは別）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Kotsu (Maizuru) (subsidiary of Nippon Kotsu in Osaka, and different from Keihan Kyoto Kotsu, a subsidiary of Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>京都交通→Kyoto Kotsu（http://www.kyotokotsu.jp/index.html）、日本交通→Nihon Kotsu（http://www.nihonkotsu.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Kotsu (Maizuru) (subsidiary of Nippon Kotsu in Osaka; different from Keihan Kyoto Kotsu, a subsidiary of Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>CLEANER</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Kotsu (Maizuru) (subsidiary of Nippon Kotsu in Osaka; different from Keihan Kyoto Kotsu, a subsidiary of Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="239">
<j>綾部大橋・西舞鶴駅前・東舞鶴駅前方面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward: Ayabe Ohashi, Nishi-Maizuru-ekimae, Higashi-Maizurueki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toward: Ayabe Ohashi, Nishi-Maizuru-ekimae, Higashi-Maizurueki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward: Ayabe Ohashi, Nishi-Maizuru-ekimae, Higashi-Maizuru-ekimae</e>
<cmt>ekimaeを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="240">
<j>丹後海陸交通（丹海バス）（本社京都府与謝郡与謝野町）・快速バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango Kairiku Kotsu (Tango Bus) (head office: Yosanocho, Yosano District, Kyoto Prefecture)/Rapid Bus</e>
<cmt>丹後海陸交通（http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kansai.htm）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango Kairiku Kotsu (Tango Bus) (head office: Yosanocho, Yosano District, Kyoto Prefecture)/Rapid Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango Kairiku Kotsu (Tango Bus) (head office: Yosanocho, Yoza-gun, Kyoto Prefecture)/Rapid Bus</e>
<cmt>読み方を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="241">
<j>KTR宮津駅前・宮津桟橋（丹海バス宮津案内所（爆シード丹海サーキットIN宮津）前・一の宮航路乗り換え停留所）・KTR天橋立駅前（天橋立ホテル（オーベルジュ天橋立（レストラン「ピュール」）前）・野田川丹海前・間人（たいざ・漁港前・京丹後市・丹後町）方面行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward: KTR (Kitakinki Tango Railway) Miyazu-ekimae, Miyazu Sanbashi, (Tankai Bus Miyazu Information Office (Baku Seed Tankai Circuit-IN-Miyazu)-mae/Ichinomiya Koronorikae-teiryujo (Ichinomiya seaway transfer bus stop), KTR Ama-no-Hashidate-ekimae (Amanohashidate Hotel &quot;Auberge Amanohashidate: Restaurant Pure&quot;-mae), Nodagawa Tankai-mae, Taiza (Gyokomae (in front of the Taiza fishing port)/Kyotango City/Tango-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toward: KTR (Kitakinki Tango Railway) Miyazu-ekimae, Miyazu Sanbashi, (Tankai Bus Miyazu Information Office (Baku Seed Tankai Circuit-IN-Miyazu)-mae/Ichinomiya Koronorikae-teiryujo (Ichinomiya seaway transfer bus stop), KTR Ama-no-Hashidate-ekimae (Amanohashidate Hotel &quot;Auberge Amanohashidate: Restaurant Pure&quot;-mae), Nodagawa Tankai-mae, Taiza (Gyokomae (in front of the Taiza fishing port)/Kyotango City/Tango-cho)</e>
<cmt>NO PERIOD NEEDED</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward: KTR (Kitakinki Tango Railway) Miyazu-ekimae, Miyazu Sambashi, (Tankai Bus Miyazu Information Office (Baku Seed Tankai Circuit-IN-Miyazu)-mae/Ichinomiya Koronorikae-teiryujo (Ichinomiya seaway transfer bus stop)), KTR Ama-no-Hashidate-ekimae (Amanohashidate Hotel (Auberge Amanohashidate: Restaurant &apos;Pure&apos;)-mae), Nodagawa Tankai-mae, Taiza (Gyokomae (in front of the Taiza fishing port)/Kyotango City/Tango-cho)</e>
<cmt>sanbashi →sambashi　括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="242">
<j>（ただし、運行回数が2回と少ないので事前に確認が必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, previous confirmation is needed as there are only two services (a day).</e>
<cmt>1日2回？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, previous confirmation is needed as there are only two services (each day).</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, previous confirmation is needed as there are only two services (each day).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>また、前日までに予約が必要（電話予約も可能））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reservation is requested by the previous day (Reservation by phone is accepted).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reservation is requested by the previous day (reservation by phone is accepted).</e>
<cmt>CAP</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reservation is requested by the previous day (reservation by phone is accepted).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="244">
<j>西日本ジェイアールバス（高雄・京北線）京都駅～栂ノ尾～周山間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR West Bus (Takao-Keihoku Line) between Kyoto Station, Toganoo and Shuzan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR West Bus (Takao-Keihoku Line) between Kyoto Station, Toganoo and Shuzan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR West Bus (Takao-Keihoku Line) between Kyoto Station, Toganoo and Shuzan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>八条口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachijo-guchi (Hachijo entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachijo-guchi (Hachijo entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachijo-guchi</e>
<cmt>既出のため、英訳削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="245">
<j>京都駅八条口と京都駅八条口アバンティ前の2つの停留所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two bus stops, one at Hachijo-guchi of Kyoto Station and the other in front of Kyoto Hachijo-guchi Avanty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two bus stops: one at Hachijo-guchi of Kyoto Station and the other in front of Kyoto Hachijo-guchi Avanty.</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two bus stops: one at Hachijo-guchi of Kyoto Station and the other in front of Kyoto Hachijo-guchi Avanti.</e>
<cmt>Avantiのスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>京都駅八条口は南北自由通路に近いところ、京都駅八条口アバンティ前は八条東口に近いところにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bus stop at Hachijo Exit of Kyoto Station is situated near the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (north-south free corredor), and the bus stop in front of Kyoto Hachijoguchi Avanty is near the Hachijo East Exit.</e>
<cmt>南北自由通路→定訳不明：Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (ｎorth-ｓouth free walkway)としました。アバンティ→Avanti（http://www.avanti-kyoto.com/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bus stop at the Hachijo exit of Kyoto Station is situated near the Nanboku Jiyu Tsuro (free north-south corridor), and the bus stop in front of Kyoto Hachijoguchi Avanty is near the Hachijo East exit.</e>
<cmt>CAPS</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bus stop at the Hachijo-guchi of Kyoto Station is situated near the Nanboku-Jiyu-Tsuro, and the bus stop in front of Kyoto Hachijo-guchi Avanti is near the Hachijo Higashi-guchi.</e>
<cmt>八条東口の表記を統一、Avantiのスペル修正、南北自由通路の表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="247">
<j>京都市交通局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>http.www.city.kyoto.jp/koho/eng/access/transport.html/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Transportation Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="248">
<j>セレモニー観光（プリンセスラインバス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremony Sightseeing (Princes Line Bus)</e>
<cmt>HP:http://www.css-c.com</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremony Sightseeing (Princes Line Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ceremony Sightseeing (Princes Line Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="249">
<j>京阪七条・京都女子中学校・高等学校前・京都女子大学前方面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward: Keihan-Shichijo,Kyoto Joshichugaku-Kotogakkomae (in front of Kyoto Giirl&apos;s Junior and Senior High School), Kyoto Joshidaigakumae (in front of Kyoto Women&apos;s University)</e>
<cmt>京都女中･高等学校（http://www.kgs.ed.jp)、京都女子大学（http://kyoto-wu.ac.jp/index-e.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toward: Keihan-Shichijo, Kyoto Joshichugaku-Kotogakkomae (in front of Kyoto Girls&apos; Junior and Senior High School), Kyoto Joshidaigakumae (in front of Kyoto Women&apos;s University)</e>
<cmt>PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward: Keihan-Shichijo, Kyoto Joshichugaku-Kotogakkomae (in front of Kyoto Girls&apos; Junior and Senior High School), Kyoto Joshidaigakumae (in front of Kyoto Women&apos;s University)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>高速バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Express bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Express bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Express bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>烏丸口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma-guchi (Karasuma entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma-guchi</e>
<cmt>既出のため、括弧内の英訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="250">
<j>ドリーム京都号（西日本ジェイアールバス・ジェイアールバス関東）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/R Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>西日本ジェイアール・バス（http://www.nishinihonjrbus.co.jp)、503行、505行、507行重複？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/R Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>JR追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="251">
<j>ドリーム京都号（西日本JRバス・JRバス関東）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="252">
<j>ドリーム京都号（西日本JRバス・JRバス関東）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dream Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="253">
<j>中央道昼特急京都号（西日本JRバス・JRバス関東）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuo Highway Daytime Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>509行、511行重複？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuo Highway Daytime Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuo Highway Daytime Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="254">
<j>中央道昼特急京都号（西日本JRバス・JRバス関東）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuo Highway Daytime Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuo Highway Daytime Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuo Highway Daytime Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Bus Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="255">
<j>ハーバーライト号（西日本JRバス・湘南神奈交バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harbor Light (Nishinihon JR Bus/Shonan Kanagawa Chuo Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>神奈交：Kanagawa Chuo Kotsu（和英翻訳データブック）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harbor Light (Nishinihon JR Bus/Shonan Kanagawa Chuo Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harbor Light-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Shonan Kanagawa Chuo Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>号を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="256">
<j>京阪神ドリームさいたま号（西日本JRバス・西武バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihanshin Dream Saitama-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Seibu Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihanshin Dream Saitama-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Seibu Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihanshin Dream Saitama-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Seibu Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="257">
<j>京阪神ドリーム静岡号（西日本JRバス・ジェイアール東海バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Dream Shizuoka-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Central Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Dream Shizuoka-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Central Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihanshin Dream Shizuoka-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Central Bus)</e>
<cmt>keihan→ keihanshin</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="258">
<j>名神ハイウェイバス（西日本JRバス・ジェイアール東海バス・名古屋観光日急・名阪近鉄バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meishin Highway Bus (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Central/Nagoyakanko-nikkyu/Meihan Kintetsu Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meishin Highway Bus (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Central/Nagoyakanko-nikkyu/Meihan Kintetsu Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meishin Highway Bus (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Central Bus/Nagoyakanko-nikkyu/Meihan Kintetsu Bus)</e>
<cmt>JR Central Bus</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="259">
<j>北陸ハイウェイバス（西日本JRバス・京阪バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokuriku Highway Bus (Nishinihon JR Bus/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokuriku Highway Bus (Nishinihon JR Bus/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokuriku Highway Bus (Nishinihon JR Bus/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="260">
<j>北陸道昼特急大阪号（西日本JRバス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokuriku Highway Daytime Express Osaka-go (Nishinihon JR Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokuriku Highway Daytime Express Osaka-go (Nishinihon JR Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokuriku Highway Daytime Express Osaka-go (Nishinihon JR Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="261">
<j>津山エクスプレス京都号（西日本JRバス・神姫バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuyama Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Shinki Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuyama Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Shinki Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuyama Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Shinki Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="262">
<j>みやこライナー（京阪京都交通・中国バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MiyakoLiner (keihan Kyoto Kotsu/Chugoku Bus)</e>
<cmt>中国バス(http://www.chugokubus.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MiyakoLiner (keihan Kyoto Kotsu/Chugoku Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyako Liner (Keihan Kyoto Kotsu/Chugoku Bus)</e>
<cmt>スペース</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="263">
<j>広島昼特急京都号・広島ドリーム京都号（中国ジェイアールバス・西日本JRバス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshima Daytime Express Kyoto-go/Hiroshima Dream Kyoto-go (Chugoku JR Bus/Nishinihon JR Bus</e>
<cmt>中国ジェイアールバス(http://www/chugoku-jrbus.co.jo)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshima Daytime Express Kyoto-go/Hiroshima Dream Kyoto-go (Chugoku JR Bus/Nishinihon JR Bus)</e>
<cmt>CLOSED PARENTHESES</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshima Daytime Express Kyoto-go/Hiroshima Dream Kyoto-go (Chugoku JR Bus/Nishinihon JR Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="264">
<j>阿波エクスプレス京都号（西日本JRバス・ジェイアール四国バス・京阪バス・徳島バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awa Express Kyoto-go(Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus/Keihan Bus/Tokushima Bus)</e>
<cmt>ジェイアール四国バス(http://www.jr-shikoku.co.jp/bus/)、徳島バス(http://www.tokubus.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awa Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus/Keihan Bus/Tokushima Bus)</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awa Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus/Keihan Bus/Tokushima Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="265">
<j>松山エクスプレス号（西日本JRバス・JR四国バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsuyama Express-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsuyama Express-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsuyama Express-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus)</e>
<cmt>かっこを閉じ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="266">
<j>高松エクスプレス京都号（西日本JRバス・JR四国バス・四国高速バス・京阪バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamatsu Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus/Shikoku Kosoku Bus/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>四国高速バス (http://www.yonkou-bus.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamatsu Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus/Shikoku Kosoku Bus/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamatsu Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus/Shikoku Kosoku Bus/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="267">
<j>高知エクスプレス号（西日本JRバス・JR四国バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kochi Express-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kochi Express-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kochi Express-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/JR Shikoku Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="268">
<j>出雲阿國号・出雲エクスプレス京都号（西日本JRバス・中国JRバス・京阪バス・一畑バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo-no-Okuni-go/Izumo Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Chugoku JR Bus/Keihan Bus/Ichibata Bus)</e>
<cmt>Ichibata Bus (用語リスト#3735参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumo-no-Okuni-go/Izumo Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Chugoku JR Bus/Keihan Bus/Ichibata Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumo-no-Okuni-go/Izumo Express Kyoto-go (Nishinihon JR Bus/Chugoku JR Bus/Keihan Bus/Ichibata Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="32">
<tit>
<j>新阪急ホテル前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-Hankyu Hotel-mae (in front of Hotel New Hankyu Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>バスターミナル固有名詞：定訳不明、日本語ローマ字表記（英語仮訳）としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-Hankyu Hotel-mae (in front of Hotel New Hankyu Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-Hankyu Hotel-mae (in front of Hotel New Hankyu Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="269">
<j>アルペン長野号（阪急バス・川中島バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alpen Nagano-go (Hankyu Bus/Kawanakajima Bus)</e>
<cmt>Kawanakajima Bus (用語リスト#3735参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alpen Nagano-go (Hankyu Bus/Kawanakajima Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alpen Nagano-go (Hankyu Bus/Kawanakajima Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="270">
<j>おけさ号（阪急バス・新潟交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okesa-go (Hankyu Bus/Niigata Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>新潟交通(http://www.niigata-kotsu.co.jp/ir/index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okesa-go (Hankyu Bus/Niigata Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okesa-go (Hankyu Bus/Niigata Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="271">
<j>大阪・京都⇔富山（阪急バス・富山地方鉄道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Osaka/Kyoto and Toyama (Hankyu Bus/Toyama Chihou Tetsudou)</e>
<cmt>富山地方鉄道 (http://www/chitetsu.co.jp/index.html/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Osaka/Kyoto and Toyama (Hankyu Bus/Toyama Chihou Tetsudou)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Osaka/Kyoto and Toyama (Hankyu Bus/Toyama Chihou Tetsudou)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="272">
<j>東京・横浜 - 京都・大阪梅田線（阪急バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Tokyo/Yokohama and Kyoto/Osaka Umeda (Hankyu Bus)</e>
<cmt>阪急バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kansai.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Tokyo/Yokohama and Kyoto/Osaka Umeda (Hankyu Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Tokyo/Yokohama and Kyoto/Osaka Umeda (Hankyu Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="33">
<tit>
<j>八条口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachijo-guchi (Hachijo entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachijo-guchi (Hachijo entrance/exit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachijo-guchi</e>
<cmt>既出のため、括弧内の英訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="273">
<j>路線によって乗り場が分散している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The location of the bus station varies according to the route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The location of the bus station varies according to the route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The location of the bus station varies according to the route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="274">
<j>アルカディア号 (高速バス)（近鉄バス・山交バス (山形県)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arcadia-go (Express bus)(Kintetsu Bus/Yamako Bus)</e>
<cmt>山交バス（用語リスト＃3735参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arcadia-go (Express bus) (Kintetsu Bus/Yamako Bus)</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arcadia-go (Express bus) (Kintetsu Bus/Yamako Bus (Yamagata Prefecture))</e>
<cmt>山形県を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="275">
<j>フォレスト号 (大阪-仙台線)（近鉄バス・宮城交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forest-go (Osaka-Sendai Line)(Kintetsu Bus/Miyagi Kotus</e>
<cmt>宮城交通 （ｈｔｔｐ://miyakou.co.jp: www.tokyotomo.com)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forest-go (Osaka-Sendai Line) (Kintetsu Bus/Miyagi Kotus)</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forest-go (Osaka-Sendai Line) (Kintetsu Bus/Miyagi Kotus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="276">
<j>ギャラクシー号（近鉄バス・福島交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Galaxy-go(Kintetsu Bus/Fukushima Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>福島交通 (http://www.fukushima-koutu.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Galaxy-go (Kintetsu Bus/Fukushima Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>SPACE</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Galaxy-go (Kintetsu Bus/Fukushima Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="277">
<j>シーガル号 (高速バス)（近鉄バス・新常磐交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seagull-go (Express bus) (Kintesu Bus/Shin-Joban Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>新常磐交通 (http://www.joko.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seagull-go (Express bus) (Kintesu Bus/Shin-Joban Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seagull-go (Express bus) (Kintesu Bus/Shin-Joban Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="278">
<j>シルクライナー（日本中央バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Silk Liner (Nippon Chuo Bus)</e>
<cmt>http://www.ncbbus.co.jp/hbus/time2.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Silk Liner (Nippon Chuo Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Silk Liner (Nippon Chuo Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="279">
<j>とちの木号（近鉄バス・関東自動車 (栃木県)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tochinoki-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kantou Jidousya)</e>
<cmt>関東自動車(http://www.atochigi.ne.jp/kanto_bus/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tochinoki-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kantou Jidousya)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tochinoki-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kantou Jidousya (Tochigi Prefecture))</e>
<cmt>山形県を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="280">
<j>よかっぺ関西号（近鉄バス・関東鉄道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokappe Kansai-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kanto Railway)</e>
<cmt>関東鉄道 (http://www.kantetsu.co.jp/bus/bus_index.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokappe Kansai-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kanto Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokappe Kansai-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kanto Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="281">
<j>ウィングライナー（近鉄バス・国際十王交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wing Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Kokusai Juo)</e>
<cmt>国際十王.(http://www.juo.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wing Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Kokusai Juo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wing Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Kokusai Juo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="282">
<j>フライングスニーカー京都・茨木号（近鉄バス・東北急行バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flying Sneaker Kyoto/Ibaraki-go (Kintetsu Bus/Tohoku Kyuko Bus)</e>
<cmt>東北急行バス(http://www.tohoku-express.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flying Sneaker Kyoto/Ibaraki-go (Kintetsu Bus/Tohoku Kyuko Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flying Sneaker Kyoto/Ibaraki-go (Kintetsu Bus/Tohoku Kyuko Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="283">
<j>東京ミッドナイトエクスプレス宇治号（京阪バス・ケイビーバス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Midnight Express Uji-go (Keihan Bus/KB Bus）</e>
<cmt>ケイビーバス（関東バス子会社）：定訳不明だがKBバスとも呼ばれるとのこと→KB Busと仮訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Midnight Express Uji-go (Keihan Bus/KB Bus）</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Midnight Express Uji-go (Keihan Bus/KB Bus）</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="284">
<j>堺・なんば・京都⇔立川（南海バス・立川バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Sakai/Nanba/Kyoto and Tachikawa (Naknai Bus/Tachikawa Bus)</e>
<cmt>南海バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kansai.htm)　立川バス ((http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/tokyo.htm)) SP</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Sakai/Nanba/Kyoto and Tachikawa (Naknai Bus/Tachikawa Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Sakai/Nanba/Kyoto and Tachikawa (Naknai Bus/Tachikawa Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="285">
<j>京都～千葉（京成バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Chiba (Keisei Bus)</e>
<cmt>京成バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/tokyo.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Kyoto and Chiba (Keisei Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Chiba (Keisei Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="286">
<j>きょうと号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto-go</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-go</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-go</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="287">
<j>京都～福岡（京阪バス・西鉄バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Fukuoka (Keihan Bus/Nishitetsu Highway Bus)</e>
<cmt>西鉄高速バス (http://www.nichitetsu.co.jp/highway/gb)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Kyoto and Fukuoka (Keihan Bus/Nishitetsu Highway Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Fukuoka (Keihan Bus/Nishitetsu Highway Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="288">
<j>大阪～銚子線（南海バス・千葉交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka - Choshi Line (Nankai Bus/Chibakotsu)</e>
<cmt>南海バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kansai.htm)、千葉交通 (http://www.chibakotsu.co.jp)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka - Choshi Line (Nankai Bus/Chibakotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka - Choshi Line (Nankai Bus/Chibakotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="289">
<j>鎌倉・藤沢 - 京都・なんば・堺線（南海バス・江ノ電バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura/Fujisawa - Kyoto/Nanba/Sakai Line (Nankai Bus/Enoden Bus</e>
<cmt>江ノ電バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kanto.htm) CLOSED PARENTHESES</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura/Fujisawa - Kyoto/Nanba/Sakai Line (Nankai Bus/Enoden Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura/Fujisawa - Kyoto/Nanba/Sakai Line (Nankai Bus/Enoden Bus)</e>
<cmt>閉じかっこを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="290">
<j>フジヤマライナー（近鉄バス・富士急山梨バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiyama Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Fujikyu Yamanashi Bus)</e>
<cmt>富士急山梨バス (http://www.yamanashibus.com)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiyama Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Fujikyu Yamanashi Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiyama Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Fujikyu Yamanashi Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="291">
<j>クリスタルライナー（近鉄バス・山梨交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crystal Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Yamanashi Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>山梨交通 (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kanto.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crystal Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Yamanashi Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crystal Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Yamanashi Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="292">
<j>千曲川ライナー（近鉄バス・千曲バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikuma Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Chikuma Bus)</e>
<cmt>千曲バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/joshinetsu.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikuma Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Chikuma Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikuma-gawa Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Chikuma Bus)</e>
<cmt>Chikuma-gawa Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Chikuma Bus)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="293">
<j>なんば・京都⇔長野・湯田中（南海バス・長電バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Nanba/Kyoto and Nagano/Yudanaka (Nankai Bus/Nagaden Bus)</e>
<cmt>南海バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kansai.htm)、長電バス (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/joshinetsu.htm)、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Nanba/Kyoto and Nagano/Yudanaka (Nankai Bus/Nagaden Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Nanba/Kyoto and Nagano/Yudanaka (Nankai Bus/Nagaden Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="294">
<j>京都⇔関西国際空港（関西空港交通・大阪空港交通・京阪バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Kansai International Airport (Kansai Airport Limousine/Osaka Airpot/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>関西空港交通、大阪空港交通とも(http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kansai.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Kyoto and Kansai International Airport (Kansai Airport Limousine/Osaka Airpot/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Kansai International Airport (Kansai Airport Limousine/Osaka Airport Transport/Keihan Bus)</e>
<cmt>transportを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="295">
<j>京都⇔大阪空港（大阪空港交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Osaka Airport (Osaka Airport Transport)</e>
<cmt>大阪空港交通　(http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kansai.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Kyoto and Osaka Airport (Osaka Airport Transport)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Osaka Airport (Osaka Airport Transport)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="296">
<j>京都エクスプレス (京都 - 岡山・倉敷線)（両備バス・下津井電鉄）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Express (Kyoto-Okayama/Kurashiki Line) (Ryobi Bus/Shimotsukui Dentetsu)</e>
<cmt>両備バス、下津久井電鉄とも (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/chushikoku.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Express (Kyoto-Okayama/Kurashiki Line) (Ryobi Bus/Shimotsukui Dentetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Express (Kyoto-Okayama/Kurashiki Line) (Ryobi Bus/Shimotsukui Dentetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="297">
<j>鳥取エクスプレス京都号（京阪シティバス・日本交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tottori Express Kyoto-go (Keihan City Bus/Nihon Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>京阪シティバス:定訳不明→Keihan City Busとしました、日本交通 (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/chushikoku.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tottori Express Kyoto-go (Keihan City Bus/Nihon Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tottori Express Kyoto-go (Keihan City Bus/Nihon Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="298">
<j>米子エクスプレス京都号（京阪バス・日本交通)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonago Express Kyoto-go (Keihan Bus/Nihon Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>日本交通 ((http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/chushikoku.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonago Express Kyoto-go (Keihan Bus/Nihon Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonago Express Kyoto-go (Keihan Bus/Nihon Kotsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="299">
<j>京都エクスプレス (京都 - 松山線)（京阪バス・伊予鉄道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Express (Kyoto-Matuyama Line) (Keihan Bus/Iyo Railway)</e>
<cmt>伊予鉄道 ((http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/chushikoku.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Express (Kyoto-Matuyama Line) (Keihan Bus/Iyo Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Express (Kyoto-Matuyama Line) (Keihan Bus/Iyo Railway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="300">
<j>京都⇔高知（京阪バス・土佐電気鉄道・高知県交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Betweem Kyoto and Kochi (Keihan Bus/Tosa Electric Railway/Kochi Bureau of Transport)</e>
<cmt>土佐電気鉄道、高知県交通ともに(http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/chushikoku.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Betweem Kyoto and Kochi (Keihan Bus/Tosa Electric Railway/Kochi Bureau of Transport)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Kyoto and Kochi (Keihan Bus/Tosa Electric Railway/Kochi Bureau of Transport)</e>
<cmt>Betweem →Between</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="301">
<j>しまんとブルーライナー（近鉄バス・高知西南交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimanto Blue Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Kochi Seinan Transport Service)</e>
<cmt>高知西南交通 (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/chushikoku.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimanto Blue Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Kochi Seinan Transport Service)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimanto Blue Liner (Kintetsu Bus/Kochi Seinan Transport Service)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="302">
<j>オランダ号（近鉄バス・長崎自動車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Holland-go (Kintetsu Bus/Nagasaki Jidosha)</e>
<cmt>長崎自動車 ((http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kyushu.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Holland-go (Kintetsu Bus/Nagasaki Jidosha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Holland-go (Kintetsu Bus/Nagasaki Jidosha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="303">
<j>サンライズ号（近鉄バス・九州産業交通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sunrise-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kyusu Sanko Bus)</e>
<cmt>九州産業交通 (http://www.tokyotomo.com/travel/kyushu.htm)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sunrise-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kyusu Sanko Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sunrise-go (Kintetsu Bus/Kyusu Sanko Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="34">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="304">
<j>※東海道新幹線の列車および西日本旅客鉄道の在来線特急・急行の停車駅は各列車記事を、近畿日本鉄道の特急の停車駅は近鉄特急の項を、それぞれ参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*For the stations where the trains on the Tokaido Shinkansen and the limited express/express trains on the JR West conventional lines make a stop, please see the sections of the respective trains, and for the stations where the limited express trains of Kintetsu Railways make a stop, please see the section of &quot;Kintetsu Railways limited express&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*For the stations where the trains on the Tokaido Shinkansen and the limited express/express trains on the JR West conventional lines make their stops, please see the sections of the respective trains; for the stations where the limited express trains of Kintetsu Railways make their stops, please see the section &quot;Kintetsu Railways Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*For the stations at which the trains on the Tokaido Shinkansen and the limited express/express trains on the JR West conventional lines make their stops, please see the sections of the respective trains; for the stations where the limited express trains of Kintetsu Railways make their stops, please see the section &quot;Kintetsu Railways Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="305">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan Railway (JR West)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West Japan Railway (JR West)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan Railway (JR West)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="306">
<j>■JR京都線・琵琶湖線（東海道本線）・湖西線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■JR Kyoto Line/Biwako Line (Tokaido Main Line)/Kosei Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■JR Kyoto Line/Biwako Line (Tokaido Main Line)/Kosei Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■JR Kyoto Line/Biwako Line (Tokaido Main Line)/Kosei Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="307">
<j>■新快速</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ Special rapid</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ Special rapid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special Rapid Service</e>
<cmt>修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="308">
<j>山科駅 - 京都駅 - 高槻駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Takatsuki Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Takatsuki Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Takatsuki Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="309">
<j>■快速（朝・夜の時間帯、琵琶湖線内は普通列車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ Rapid (it is operated as a local train on the Biwako Line during the morning and at night).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ Rapid (but operated as a local train on the Biwako Line during the morning and at night)</e>
<cmt>GRAMMAR, PUNCTUATION</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid Service (it is operated as a local train on the Biwako Line during the morning and at night).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="310">
<j>山科駅 - 京都駅 - 長岡京駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Nagaokakyo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Nagaokakyo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Nagaokakyo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="311">
<j>■普通（高槻～明石駅間快速となる列車含む）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ Local Train (including the trains operated as rapid between Takatsuki and Akashi Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ Local train (including the trains operated as rapid between Takatsuki and Akashi Station)</e>
<cmt>CAP</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■ Local train (including the trains operated as rapid between Takatsuki and Akashi Station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="312">
<j>山科駅 - 京都駅 - （貨）梅小路駅 - 西大路駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Umekoji freit station</e>
<cmt>定訳不明：用語リスト#1353参照</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Umekoji Freight Station</e>
<cmt>SPELLING</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashina Station - Kyoto Station - Umekoji Freight Station - Nishioji Station</e>
<cmt>西大路駅追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="313">
<j>■奈良線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Nara Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Nara Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Nara Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="314">
<j>■みやこ路快速・■快速・■区間快速・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Miyakoji Rapid Train ■Rapid ■Rapid in designated section ■Local Train</e>
<cmt>みやこ路（http://www.eonet.ne.jp/&quot;naramachiwalk/access-to-nara.htm/）、区間快速→定訳不明：Rapid in designated sectionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Miyakoji Rapid Train ■Rapid ■Rapid in designated section ■Local train</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyakoji Rapid Service/Rapid Service/Regional Rapid Service/Local Train</e>
<cmt>「区間快速」　JR西日本ではこのように表記しているようです。　http://detail.chiebukuro.yahoo.co.jp/qa/question_detail/q1424717544・を/に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="315">
<j>京都駅 - 東福寺駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Tofukuji Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - Tofukuji Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Tofukuji Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="316">
<j>■嵯峨野線（山陰本線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagano Line (San&apos;in Main Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagano Line (San&apos;in Main Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagano Line (Sanin Main Line)</e>
<cmt>sanin　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="317">
<j>■快速</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Rapid</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Rapid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid Service</e>
<cmt>修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="318">
<j>京都駅 - 二条駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Sanjo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - Sanjo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Nijo Station</e>
<cmt>sanjo →nijo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="319">
<j>■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Local train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Local train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Local train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="320">
<j>京都駅 - 丹波口駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Tanbaguchi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - Tanbaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Tanbaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="321">
<j>東海旅客鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Central Japan Railway</e>
<cmt>和英翻訳データブック（ジャパンタイムズ編）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Central Japan Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Central Japan Railway (JR Central)</e>
<cmt>(JR Central)追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="322">
<j>■東海道新幹線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Tokaido Shinkansen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Tokaido Shinkansen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Tokaido Shinkansen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="323">
<j>米原駅 - 京都駅 - 新大阪駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonehara Station - Kyoto Station - Shin Osaka Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonehara Station - Kyoto Station - Shin Osaka Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maibara Station - Kyoto Station - Shin-Osaka Station</e>
<cmt>Maibara, Shin-Osakaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="324">
<j>近畿日本鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinki Nippon Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>和英翻訳データブック（ジャパンタイムズ編）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinki Nippon Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Railways</e>
<cmt>Kintetsu Railwaysとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="325">
<j>京都線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="326">
<j>■急行・■準急・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Rapid ■Local Express ■Local Train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Rapid ■Local Express ■Local Train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Rapid ■Local Express ■Local Train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="327">
<j>京都駅 - 東寺駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - To-ji Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - To-ji Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - To-ji Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="328">
<j>京都市営地下鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>city →municipal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="329">
<j>■烏丸線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">■Karasuma Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="330">
<j>五条駅 (京都市営地下鉄)(K10) - 京都駅(K11) - 九条駅 (京都府)(K12)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo Station (Kyoto City Subway)(K10) - Kyoto Station (K11) - Kujo Station (Kyoto Prefecture)(K12)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo Station (Kyoto City Subway) (K10) - Kyoto Station (K11) - Kujo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (K12)</e>
<cmt>SPACES</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo Station (Kyoto Municipal Subway) (K10) - Kyoto Station (K11) - Kujo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (K12)</e>
<cmt>city →municipal</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ÉdeC(id:103767), ヒロリン(id:15886), 北大(id:110491), Nnh(id:474), Okome(id:98), 雪ダルマのお人(id:183823), あずらっきー(id:160239), Tnk3a(id:30483), Lupinoid(id:68), Tagaru(id:30411), Tigers boy(id:15761), Highexpress(id:48556), JONL(id:37424), ＋－(id:17104), 準急三条(id:25072), A-Taul(id:41790), Whiz(id:15769), Adonis(id:24011), Tsim.sha.tsui(id:36918), E-yan(id:211823), Haruno Akiha(id:107628), Ogeshi(id:80487), ちょろ(id:17218), 韓国と音楽を愛する男(id:59246), Starbacks(id:1018), Felicemente(id:43126), Laichuan Yinfu(id:152533), Seibuabina(id:37532), Goncyan(id:92158), Utsuda(id:605), 樒(id:35770), Ef3(id:84901), Special rapid(id:96013), Rusk(id:9895), Matsukaze(id:51778), Ichii-ya(id:48912), ぱむ(id:24323), Kouchiumi(id:19253), おちゃわん(id:33623), Hno3(id:56786), Mipu(id:5360), TOTOBIG(id:198418), Ishidatami(id:36698), Rsa(id:38453), のねをつほ(id:105913), Haguii(id:1313), Hirofumitouhei(id:104137), Mutimaro(id:164721), マツモムシ(id:65922), ２２３系８０００番台(id:82336), Awata(id:67957), 七待人(id:915), まさマサ(id:160436), 鍛高譚(id:154933), Loveless(id:129239), Kone(id:377), RKBM(id:10435), PYON9324(id:100709), るなあるてみす(id:168261), 坊(id:32169), Makiharashouten(id:1021), ヤンパーウィック(id:7142), Yanahan(id:2437), お掃除大好き(id:99320), タカリン(id:126497), Panorama8800(id:73666), Carkuni(id:79281), 221.20(id:81524), Takasunrise0921(id:62884), Ktr(id:30468), Miya(id:1881), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Tp2415(id:84801), Sara-minori(id:139962), Kei-NIKAIDOH(id:147418), ジャスト宣言(id:33592), Chikara1983(id:59556), K-kazumasa(id:9265), I 10vetinc1ef0rever(id:148271), 1029man(id:93235), っ(id:4481), Aky(id:116544), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 東京特許許可局(id:7229), Mimasaka(id:132846), T@ka(id:12814), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), 城山(id:104901), Maxima m(id:28947), Wikipedianet(id:9608), Gombe(id:27), Opponent(id:720), Tomomarusan(id:17060), Dr jimmy(id:111486), 継之助(id:39352), Bearhouse(id:20887), Yas(id:739), Ayers Rock(id:49390), ドゥルーズ・ガタリ(id:147849), Kuha(id:7282), Sushiya(id:110938), TRIBESMAN(id:4735), Hoge-(id:158), Hideyuki(id:9577), Bergmann(id:85282), Tomos(id:10), Kura761(id:116250), Ikaxer(id:61759), Shimotsuke(id:19741), M universal(id:156273), Kanjy(id:36859), Wakkubox(id:30396), Hbcx43(id:179769), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Alexbot(id:157199), NIKE(id:16342), Ariesmarine(id:70919), ドラムスコ(id:40234), Bakkai(id:7233), FREEZA(id:68069), Charenji(id:7908), Araisyohei(id:378), Cassiopeia sweet(id:29811), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Im224(id:57113), エアスマップIRE(id:13873), Ohura(id:5986), Shayuki(id:112052), わだらん(id:84854), Sunen(id:10700), Banzan(id:32567), Lightslateblue(id:50474), Blackbus(id:37164), Goki(id:7107), Mazbot(id:181195), Staka(id:74758), Sonic883(id:36201), TERMINAL(id:107022), Alljal(id:46858), Hirotaro(id:1437), Dane-EV(id:56855), サーフィン(id:6154), Nozomikobe(id:18269), エアスマップＩＲＥ(id:17869), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Tokatsu Kokubu(id:99966), Ha-yu(id:172989), ＳＴＫ(id:29099), SH(id:18706), Washisama(id:9333), Yanaandyuta(id:179646), Etopirica(id:32491), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), 192 168 1 1(id:46388), ウース(id:31355), Sat.K(id:3751), Mover(id:7146), J8takagi(id:20409), West(id:8787), Memeja(id:110500), Shinkansen(id:13703), Bukang-liwayway(id:89706), 文姫(id:66661), Kiyok(id:76023), Seseragi(id:150723), 金沢(id:2441), 悠卯斗(id:46277), 油谷サトシ(id:27516), Tkon(id:72030), Mochi(id:9489), Unamu(id:14627), Twilight2640(id:134273), 210.(id:9838), オナガドリ(id:15179), 一騎当千(id:56448), ラッセル車大好き(id:6149), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>