<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京田辺駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyotanabe Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyotanabe Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyotanabe Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京田辺駅（きょうたなべえき）は、京都府京田辺市田辺久戸にある、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）片町線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Tanabe Kudo Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture, Kyotanabe Station is a stop on the Katamachi Line of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyotanabe Station, located in Tanabe Kudo, Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Katamachi Line of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyotanabe Station, located in Tanabe Kudo, Kyotanabe City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Katamachi Line of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京田辺市の代表駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a major station in Kyotanabe City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a major station in Kyotanabe City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a major station in Kyotanabe City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>ICOCA・Jスルー利用可能駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ICOCA and J-through cards are available.</e>
<cmt>Jスルーカードは平成21年3月1日で利用取りやめになったので、この記載は変更した方がよいのでは？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ICOCA and J-through cards are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ICOCA and J-through cards can be used at this station.</e>
<cmt>can be used としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ICOCAの相互利用対象であるSuica、TOICA、PiTaPa（スルッとKANSAI協議会）も利用可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suica, TOICA, PiTaPa (SURUTTO KANSAI ASSOCIATION) cards, which are mutually matched with ICOCA, are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suica, TOICA, PiTaPa (SURUTTO KANSAI ASSOCIATION) cards, which are mutually matched with ICOCA, are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suica, TOICA, PiTaPa (SURUTTO KANSAI ASSOCIATION) cards, which are mutually matched with ICOCA, can also be used here.</e>
<cmt>can be used としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>木津～京田辺間は4両編成、京田辺～京橋間（JR東西線以降も同じ）は7両編成で運行されるため、列車の増解結はこの駅で行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As four-car trains run between Kizu Station and Kyotanabe Station (same as well as JR Tozai Line) and seven-car trains run between Kyotanabe and Kyobashi Station, car coupling or splitting is done at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because four-car trains run between Kizu Station and Kyotanabe Station (as well as the JR Tozai Line) and seven-car trains run between Kyotanabe and Kyobashi Station, car coupling or splitting is done at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because four-car trains run between Kizu Station and Kyotanabe Station and seven-car trains run between Kyotanabe and Kyobashi Station (as well as the JR Tozai Line), car coupling or splitting is done at this station.</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>プラットホーム形状と配置2面3線の地上駅で、2面4線化も可能な構造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located on the ground, the station has two island type platforms with three tracks, and another track can be added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located at ground level, the station has two island-type platforms with three tracks, and another track can be added.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located at ground level, the station has two island-type platforms with three tracks, and another track can be added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>橋上駅を有し、両ホームと、改札外・東西に2箇所、計4箇所にエレベーターが設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two platforms are connected by the overpass, which works as a station-house. There are four elevators; two for between each platform and the station-house, the other two are outside of the ticket gates, at east and west ends of the station-house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two platforms are connected by the overpass, which works as a station house, and there are four elevators: two for between each platform and the station house, and another two outside the ticket gates, at the east and west ends of the station house.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two platforms are connected by the overpass, which works as a station house, and there are four elevators: two for between each platform and the station house, and another two outside the ticket gates, at the east and west ends of the station house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>東口は通路を経てアルプラザ京田辺（平和堂）に通じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The east exit and the Al Plaza (Heiwado) are connected through the passage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The east exit and the Al Plaza (Heiwado) are connected by means of the passage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The east exit and the Al Plaza (Heiwado) are connected by means of the passage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>旧京田辺駅は一階建ての昔の民家のような造りで、元を辿れば明治時代からあったという話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former station was one-story building like an old residential style, it is said to be built in Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former station was a one-story building in the old residential style, and was said to have been built in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former station was a one-story building in the old residential style, and was said to have been built in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>旧駅は2面2線の対向式ホームで間に中線があり、貨物扱いも行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old station had two separate platforms and two tracks which ran in opposite directions, and there was another track for freight line between two tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old station had two separate platforms and two tracks that ran in opposite directions, and between those two tracks there was another one for freight lines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old station had two separate platforms and two tracks that ran in opposite directions, and between those two tracks there was another one for freight lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>駅舎は京橋方面側にあり、木津方面へのホームへは同志社前側にある踏切を渡ることになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station-house was on the side of platform bound for Kyobashi Station. When going to the platform bound for Kizu, the railroad crossing, which was on the direction of Doshishamae Station, was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station house was on the side of platform bound for Kyobashi Station; when going to the platform bound for Kizu, the railroad crossing, which was in the direction of Doshishamae Station, was used.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station house was on the side of platform bound for Kyobashi Station; when going to the platform bound for Kizu, the railroad crossing, which was in the direction of Doshishamae Station, was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>待合室は旧信号テコ扱い所であったため、その形跡がよく分かる駅だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The waiting room was used for the track-and-signals operation, leaving the trace of the operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The waiting room was used for the track-and-signals operation, and traces of the operation were left behind.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The waiting room was used for the track-and-signals operation, and traces of the operation were left behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、昭和47年頃から平成4年頃までの間は無人駅扱いで出札業務は行わず、運転要員だけ配置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between 1972 and 1992, this station did not have any station staff to check tickets, but only operating personnel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between 1972 and 1992, this station had no station staff to check tickets; there were only operating personnel.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between 1972 and 1992, this station had no station staff to check tickets; there were only operating personnel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>3番のりばは朝・夕ラッシュ時のみ使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The platform #3 is used only morning and evening of rush hours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platform No. 3 is used only in the morning and evening rush hours.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platform 3 is used only in the morning and evening rush hours.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>基本的に1・2番のりばのみ使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, the platform #1 and #2 are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, platform nos. 1 and 2 are used.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, Platform 1 and 2 are used.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>3線もありながら発車番線は全時間帯に渡って固定されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though there are three tracks, departure platform of each train is not fixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though there are three tracks, the departure platform for each train is not fixed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though there are three platforms, the departure platform for each train is not fixed throughout the day.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは構内に引上線がなく、切り離された増結用の車両がホーム上で待機しなければならないためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because there is no lead tracks, cars which are split have to wait to be coupled on one of three tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because there is no lead track, so cars that have split must wait in order to be coupled on one of three tracks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because there is no lead track, so cars that have split must wait in order to be coupled on one of three platforms.</e>
<cmt>three tracks → three platforms</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>昼間時の運用を例として挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the platform usage example in the daytime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is an example of daytime platform usage:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is an example of daytime platform usage:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>2番のりばに増結用車両が待機した状態で、京橋方面行きが2番のりばに入り、増結用車両をつなぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While coupling cars are waiting on the platform #2, the train bound for Kyobashi arrives on the platform #2 and connects the coupling cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While coupling cars are waiting on the platform No. 2, the train bound for Kyobashi arrives on platform No. 2 and connects the coupling cars.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While coupling cars are waiting on Platform 2, the train bound for Kyobashi arrives on Platform 2 and connects the coupling cars.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>同時に木津方面行きが1番のりばに入り、切り離した増結用車両を1番のりばに残して発車する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, another train bound for Kizu arrives on the platform #1 and departs with leaving the split cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simultaneously, another train bound for Kizu arrives at platform No. 1 and departs, leaving the split cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simultaneously, another train bound for Kizu arrives at Platform 1 and departs, leaving the split cars.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>その次の京橋方面行きは1番のりばに入り、先ほど切り離された1番のりばの増結用車両をつなぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next train bound for Kyobashi comes into the platform #1 and connects the cars which the train for Kizu split from.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next train bound for Kyobashi arrives at platform No. 1 and connects the cars from which the train for Kizu had split.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next train bound for Kyobashi arrives at Platform 1 and connects the cars from which the train for Kizu had split.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同時に木津方面行きが2番のりばに入り、切り離した増結用車両を2番のりばに残して発車する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, another train bound for Kizu arrives on the platform #2 and departs with leaving the split cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, another train bound for Kizu arrives at platform No. 2 and departs, leaving the split cars.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, another train bound for Kizu arrives at Platform 2 and departs, leaving the split cars.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>以上の流れを繰り返す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repeat the above procedures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above procedure is repeated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above procedure is repeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>という、ローテーション的な運用となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a rotation system operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a rotational system operation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a rotational system operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>木津～同志社前間のホーム延伸工事完成後は行先ごとにホームが固定される可能性があるが、今のところ不明（2番のりばが一線スルーとなっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possible that the usage of platforms will be fixed for the direction after completion of platform extension work between Kizu and Doshishamae. At the moment, the detail is not clear. (But the platform #2 will be used for passing through.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible that the platform usage will be fixed in terms of direction after the completion of the platform extension work between Kizu and Doshishamae, but as of now the details aren&apos;t clear (however, platform No. 2 will be used for passing through).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible that the platform usage will be fixed in terms of direction after the completion of the platform extension work between Kizu and Doshishamae, but as of now the details aren&apos;t clear (however, Platform 2 will be used for passing through).</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>駅東方約300mに近鉄京都線の新田辺駅があり、徒歩7分程度で到着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-Tanabe Station of Kintetsu Kyoto Line is located 300 meters east from the station, taking about 7 minutes walk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-Tanabe Station, of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line, is located 300 meters (a walk of about seven minutes) east of the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-Tanabe Station, of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line, is located 300 meters (a walk of about seven minutes) east of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>市の玄関口として両駅の周辺整備が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As both stations are gateways to the city, their surroundings have been improved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given that both stations are gateways to the city, their surroundings have been improved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given that both stations are gateways to the city, their surroundings have been improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>駅のある京田辺市は、最高級茶葉である玉露の産地で有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyotanabe City is well known for the premium refined green tea (gyokuro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyotanabe City is well known for premium refined green tea (gyokuro).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyotanabe City is well known for premium refined green tea (gyokuro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="30">
<j>駅西方には一休さんこと一休宗純ゆかりの酬恩庵（一休寺）、南方には京田辺市役所、田辺公園等の施設がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuon-an Temple (Ikkyu-ji Temple) which is related to Ikkyu Sojun (Zen Buddhist monk Ikkyu) is in the west of the station, Kyotanabe city office and Tanabe-koen Park are located in the south of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuon-an Temple (Ikkyu-ji Temple), which is associated with Ikkyu Sojun (the Zen Buddhist monk Ikkyu), is west of the station, while the Kyotanabe city office and Tanabe-koen Park are south of the station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuon-an Temple (Ikkyu-ji Temple), which is associated with Ikkyu Sojun (the Zen Buddhist monk Ikkyu), is west of the station, while the Kyotanabe City Hall and Tanabe-koen Park are south of the station.</e>
<cmt>city hall としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="31">
<j>その他の周辺施設に京田辺市立中央図書館(旧田辺町役場跡地に建設された)、京都やましろ農業協同組合、商工会館、田辺保健所など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other surrounding facilities are such as Kyotanabe City Central Library, JA Kyoto Yamashiro, Commerce and Industry House, Tanabe Public Health Center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other facilities in the area include the Kyotanabe City Central Library, JA Kyoto Yamashiro, Commerce and Industry House and the Tanabe Public Health Center.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other facilities in the area include the Kyotanabe City Central Library, JA Kyoto Yamashiro, Commerce and Industry House and the Tanabe Public Health Center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="32">
<j>駅東側に国鉄C11形蒸気機関車の動輪1対とナンバープレートが置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A pair of driving wheels and number plate of the JNR steam locomotive C11 class can be seen in the east of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A pair of driving wheels and a number plate of the JNR steam locomotive (C11 class) can be seen east of the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A pair of driving wheels and a number plate of the JNR steam locomotive (C11 class) can be seen east of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>かつてここに静態保存されていた324号機のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are from the steam locomotive #324 which had been conserved there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are from the steam locomotive No. 324, which had been conserved there.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are from the steam locomotive No. 324, which had been conserved there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="34">
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utilization situation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conditions of usage</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger use</e>
<cmt>表現を他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>2006年度の1日あたりの乗車人員は約6,063人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Number of usage is about 6,063 people a day on research in fiscal 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to research conducted in fiscal year 2006, approximately 6,063 people used the facility each day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to research conducted in fiscal year 2006, approximately 6,063 people used the facility each day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>（京都府統計書より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Statistical data of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Statistical data of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(according to the Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Report)</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="37">
<j>近鉄新田辺駅への乗り換え客の利用が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of passengers use this station to transfer to Shin-Tanabe Station of Kintetsu line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many passengers use this station to transfer to Shin-Tanabe Station of the Kintetsu Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many passengers use this station to transfer to Shin-Tanabe Station of the Kintetsu Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="38">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1898年（明治31年）4月12日 関西鉄道長尾駅 (大阪府)～新木津（廃止）間延伸時に、同社の田辺駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station opened on April 12, 1898, named Tanabe Station of Kansei Railway Company when extending the line between Nagao Station (Osaka Prefecture) and Shin-Kizu (which was abandoned).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station opened on April 12, 1898, and was called Tanabe Station of Kansei Railway Company when the line was extended between Nagao Station (Osaka Prefecture) and Shin-Kizu (which was eventually abandoned).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 12, 1898: The station opened, and was called Tanabe Station of Kansei Railway Company when the line was extended between Nagao Station (Osaka Prefecture) and Shin-Kizu (which was eventually abandoned).</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>1907年（明治40年）10月1日 鉄道国有法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansei Railway Company was nationalized on October 1, 1907.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansei Railway Company was nationalized on October 1, 1907.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1907: Kansei Railway Company was nationalized.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="41">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日 国鉄分割民営化により、JR西日本の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station became one of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West) due to the division and privatization of JNR on April 1, 1987.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station became part of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West) due to the division and privatization of JNR on April 1, 1987.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1987: The station became part of the West Japan Railway Company (JR West) due to the division and privatization of JNR.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="42">
<j>1997年（平成9年）3月8日 京田辺市制施行開始に先立ち、京田辺駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to the municipalization of Kyotanabe City, the station changed the name to Kyotanabe Station on March 8, 1997.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the municipalization of Kyotanabe City, the station&apos;s name was changed to Kyotanabe Station on March 8, 1997.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 8, 1997: Prior to the municipalization of Kyotanabe City, the station&apos;s name was changed to Kyotanabe Station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="43">
<j>2002年（平成14年）2月2日 橋上駅舎化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new station-house was built with bridge style on February 2, 2002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new station house, in the bridge style, was completed on February 2, 2002.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 2, 2002: The new station house, in the bridge style, was completed.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="44">
<j>位置情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="45">
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR West</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR West</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan Railway Company (JR West)</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>■学研都市線（片町線）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Gakkentoshi Line (Katamachi Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Gakkentoshi Line (Katamachi Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gakkentoshi Line (Katamachi Line)</e>
<cmt>■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>■快速・■区間快速・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Rapid ■Regional Rapid ■Local</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Rapid ■Regional Rapid ■Local</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapid/Regional Rapid/Local</e>
<cmt>スラッシュで区切りました。■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>同志社前駅 - 京田辺駅 - 大住駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshishamae Station - Kyotanabe Station - Osumi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshishamae Station - Kyotanabe Station - Osumi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshishamae Station - Kyotanabe Station - Osumi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Bakkai(id:7233), Hideyuki(id:9577), 城山(id:104901), Otemoto(id:64180), Ignis(id:28979), Hikichimin Jr.(id:147077), Yuta415(id:149253), 準ちゃん(id:169752), Takashi4678(id:19085), Mover(id:7146), Ikaxer(id:61759), Utsuda(id:605), Mop(id:12061), はやたま(id:118370), Mari(id:1553), Miepenpen(id:65944), Ichii-ya(id:48912), Bandalgom(id:31841), Zizz(id:46697), R28Bot(id:177951), Chobot(id:20846), Kone(id:377), Hirotaro(id:1437), Mipu(id:5360), Apidr(id:155448), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>