<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伏見桃山駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi-momoyama Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi-momoyama Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi-momoyama Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伏見桃山駅（ふしみももやまえき）は、京都府京都市伏見区両替町4丁目にある、京阪電気鉄道京阪本線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Ryogae-machi, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Fushimi-momoyama Station Station is a railway stop on the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi-momoyama Station, located in Ryogae-machi, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a railway stop on the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi-momoyama Station, located in 4-chome, Ryogae-machi, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a railway stop on the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>4丁目　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>駅概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary of the station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of the station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伏見区の中心部、大手筋に面しており、戦前は急行列車停車駅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Placed along Otesuji-dori Street at the center of Fushimi Ward, express trains stopped at this station before the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it is placed along Otesuji-dori Street at the center of Fushimi Ward, express trains stopped at this station before the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it is placed along Otesuji-dori Street at the center of Fushimi Ward, express trains stopped at this station before the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし隣の丹波橋駅が奈良電気鉄道（現・近鉄京都線）との接続駅となったことから急行停車駅の座を奪われ、さらに京阪宇治線の分岐駅が土地買収などの関係で南隣の中書島駅となったことや、駅南北を踏切に挟まれてホームの8両対応化が不可能であることから、伏見区の中心部に所在するにもかかわらず、急行や特別急行列車・K特急が通過という状態となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, sicne adjacently-locating Tambabashi Station became to be used by Nara Electric Railway (present Kintetsu Kyoto Line) as well, the express trains became to stop at Tambabashi Station instead of this station, and because of the following reasons, no express train, no limited express train nor K-limited express train stops at this station, even though it is placed at the center of Fushimi Ward: Keihan Uji Line was branched at Chushojim Station, the next stop on the south side of this station, due to land acquisition and other problems, and the platforms could not support eight-car trains because a pedestrian crossing is placed on each of the north and south sides of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the adjacently located Tambabashi Station became to be used by Nara Electric Railway (presently the Kintetsu Kyoto Line) as well, the express trains began making stops at Tambabashi Station instead of this station, no express train, limited express train or K-limited express train stops at this station even though it is placed at the center of Fushimi Ward because the Keihan Uji Line was branched at Chushojim Station, the next stop on the south side of this station, due to land acquisition and other problems, and the platforms could not support eight-car trains because pedestrian crossings are placed on the north and south sides of the station.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, although Fushimi-momoyama Station is situated at the center of Fushimi Ward, no express trains, limited express trains, or K-limited express trains stop there due to the following reasons: Tanbabashi Station, located adjacent to this station, started to be used by Nara Electric Railway (presently the Kintetsu Kyoto Line) as well, so express trains began making stops at Tanbabashi Station instead of Fushimi-momoyama Station; Chushojima Station, the next stop to the south of this station became the junction station for the Keihan Uji Line due to land acquisition and other issues; and the platforms could not support eight-car trains because pedestrian crossings are located to the north and south of the station.</e>
<cmt>全体的に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>また、駅名にちなんでホーム屋根の柱や梁を桃色（ピンク）に塗られたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, the roof, pillars and beams were painted pink after the name of this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, the roof, pillars and beams were painted pink after the name of this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, the roof, pillars and beams were painted pink after the name of this station (the Japanese kanji for &quot;momo&quot; in &quot;Fushimi-momoyama&quot; means &quot;peach&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「桃山」にちなんでピンクとなる、という意味を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>相対式2面2線のホームを持つ地平駅で、改札とコンコースは地下に設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is placed on the ground, with two separate platforms with two tracks served between them, but the entrance/exit gate and concource are placed underground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is placed on the ground, with two separate platforms with two tracks served between them, but the entrance/exit gate and concourse are placed underground.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is placed on the ground, with two separate platforms with two tracks served between them, but the ticket gate and concourse are placed underground.</e>
<cmt>改札→ticket gate としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし油掛通側からの入場はできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This station cannot be entered from the Aburakake-dori Street side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This station can&apos;t be entered from the Aburakake-dori Street side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This station can&apos;t be entered from the Aburakake-dori Street side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Platforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Platforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Platforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>この駅の南北を横切る、大手筋通と油掛通の間隔がホームの長さとなっており、ちょうど7両分ぴったりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length of the platforms, just for seven-car trains, is determined by the distance between the Otesuji-dori Street Aburakake-dori Street, each of which is placed in the north or south of the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The length of the platforms, enough to accommodate seven-car trains, is determined by the distance between the Otesuji-dori Street and Aburakake-dori Street, which are respectively located on the north and south side of the station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The length of the platforms, enough to accommodate seven-car trains, is determined by the distance between the Otesuji-dori Street and Aburakake-dori Street, which are respectively located on the north and south side of the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため、8両編成の列車が停車できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, no eight-car train can stop at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, no eight-car train can stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, no eight-car train can stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただし、出町柳行きホームは7両対応とはいえ無理に延伸したため、ホーム幅の狭い部分がある（丹波橋側で乗るように看板が設置されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the length was extended forcedly, a portion of the platform for the trains for Demachiyanagi is norrow even though it is said that the platform supports seven-car trains (an information board guiding paggenssers to get on tains on the Tambabashi side is placed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the length was necessarily extended, a portion of the platform for the trains for Demachiyanagi is narrow even though it is said that the platform supports seven-car trains (there is an information board guiding passengers to get on trains on the Tambabashi side).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the length was necessarily extended, a portion of the platform for the trains for Demachiyanagi is narrow even though it is said that the platform supports seven-car trains (there is an information board guiding passengers to get on trains on the Tanbabashi side).</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>番線表示はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No track number is displayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No track number is displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No Platform number is displayed.</e>
<cmt>番線をのりばと解釈して訳を変更。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>100mほど東方には近鉄京都線の桃山御陵前駅（こちらは急行・準急列車が停車）がある（ただし、両線の公式な連絡駅は隣の丹波橋駅となっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around 100-m east of this station, Momoyamagoryo-mae Station on Kintetsu Kyoto Line is located, (where express trains and semi-express trains stop) (however, the official station to connect the two lines is the adjacent Tanbabashi Station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approximately 100 meters east of this station there is Momoyamagoryo-mae Station on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line (where express and semi-express trains stop) (however, the official station to connect the two lines is the adjacent Tanbabashi Station).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approximately 100 meters east of this station there is Momoyamagoryo-mae Station on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line (where express and semi-express trains stop) (however, the official station to connect the two lines is the adjacent Tanbabashi Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>伏見桃山陵（明治天皇陵、桃山御陵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi-Momoyama-ryo Graveyard (graveyard for Meiji Emperor and Momoyama-ryo Graveyard)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi-Momoyama-ryo Graveyard (the graveyard for Meiji Emperor and Momoyama-ryo)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial mausoleum of Emperor Meiji (Fushimi-no-Momoyama-no-Misasagi)</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>乃木神社 (京都市)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nogi-jinja Shrine (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nogi-jinja Shrine (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nogi-jinja Shrine (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>伏見桃山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Momoyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Momoyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Momoyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>御香宮神社（名水百選）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokonomiya-jinja Shrine (the 100 most excelent natural water sources in Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokonomiya-jinja Shrine (listed as one of the 100 most excellent natural water sources in Japan)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokonomiya-jinja Shrine (listed as one of the 100 most excellent natural water sources in Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>月桂冠大倉記念館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gekkeikan Okura Sake Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gekkeikan Okura Sake Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gekkeikan Okura Sake Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>キザクラカッパカントリー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kizakura Kappa Country</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kizakura Kappa Country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kizakura Kappa Country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>伏見区役所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Ward Office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Ward Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Ward Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>京都京町郵便局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto Kyomachi post office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Kyomachi post office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Kyomachi post office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ハローワーク伏見（伏見公共職業安定所）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hello Work Fushimi (Public employment security office)</e>
<cmt>追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>国道24号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Highway 24</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Highway 24</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Route 24</e>
<cmt>国道→national route としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>伏見大手筋商店街</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fushimi-Otesuji shopping area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fushimi-Otesuji shopping area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fushimi-Otesuji shopping area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>桃山駅（約600m東方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momoyama Station (approx. 600 m east of this station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momoyama Station (approx. 600 m east of this station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momoyama Station (approx. 600 m east of this station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>京都府赤十字血液センター（献血ルーム伏見大手筋）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Red Cross Blood Center (a blood donation room at Fushimi-Otesuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Red Cross Blood Center (a blood donation room at Fushimi-Otesuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Red Cross Blood Center (a blood donation room at Fushimi-Otesuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>バスのりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus stops</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>京阪伏見桃山駅には、現在バス路線は乗り入れていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No bus route operates via Fushimi-momoyama Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No bus route operates via Fushimi-momoyama Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No bus route operates via Fushimi-momoyama Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>最寄バス停：京都市営バス御香宮前/京都市バス・京阪バス・京阪シティバス・京阪宇治バス西大手筋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nearest bus stops: Gokonomiya-mae (in front of Gokonomiya) by Kyoto City Bus/Nishi-Otesuji by Kyoto City Bus, Keihan Bus, Keihan City Bus and Keihan Uji Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nearest bus stops are Gokonomiya-mae (in front of Gokonomiya) by Kyoto City Bus/Nishi-Otesuji by Kyoto City Bus, Keihan Bus, Keihan City Bus and Keihan Uji Bus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nearest bus stops are Gokonomiya-mae (in front of Gokonomiya) by Kyoto City Bus/Nishi-Otesuji by Kyoto City Bus, Keihan Bus, Keihan City Bus and Keihan Uji Bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>御香宮前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokonomiya-mae (in front of Gokonomiya)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokonomiya-mae (in front of Gokonomiya)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokonomiya-mae (in front of Gokonomiya)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>バス停は駅前ではなく、駅から徒歩3分の国道24号沿いにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This bus stop is located not in front of the station but along National Highway 24, a three-minute walk from the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This bus stop is located not in front of the station but along National Highway 24, a three-minute walk from the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This bus stop is located not in front of the station but along National Route 24, a three-minute walk from the station.</e>
<cmt>国道→national route としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>京都市営バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>南8系統：（藤森神社経由）竹田駅 (京都府)東口行／横大路車庫行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route south 8: bound for Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station) (Kyoto Prefecture)(via Fujimori-jinja Shrine)/for Yokooji Shako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route south 8: Bound for Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station) (Kyoto Prefecture) (via Fujimori-jinja Shrine) and/or for Yokooji Shako</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route south 8: Bound for the east exit of Takeda Station (Kyoto Prefecture) (via Fujimori-jinja Shrine) / for Yokooji-shako Depot</e>
<cmt>and/or →/　としました。higashiguchi →east exit　としました。 Depot を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>西大手筋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishi-Otesuji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishi-Otesuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishi-Otesuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>京都市バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>19系統　（京阪国道経由）京都駅前/横大路車庫ゆき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 19: bound for Kyoto-ekimae (in front Kyoto Station) (via Keihan Kokudo (Keihan national road)/for Yokooji Shako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 19: Bound for Kyoto-ekimae (in front of Kyoto Station) (via Keihan Kokudo (Keihan National Road) and/or for Yokooji Shako</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 19: Bound for Kyoto Station (via Keihan Kokudo (Keihan National Road) / for Yokooji-shako Depot</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Stationとしました。Depot を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>20系統　宮前橋西詰ゆき（双方向ループ系統）/京阪中書島・伏見港公園　横大路車庫ゆき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 20: bound for Miyamae-bashi Nishizume (the west end of the Miyamae bridge) (operated in both directions in a loop)/for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima andFusimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 20: Bound for Miyamae-bashi Nishizume (the west end of Miyamae Bridge) (operated in both directions in a loop) and/or for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fusimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 20: Bound for Miyamae-bashi Nishizume (the west end of Miyamae Bridge) (operated in both directions in a loop) / for Yokooji-shako Depot through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>Depot を追加しました。Fushimi に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>22系統　南工業団地/京阪中書島・伏見港公園、横大路車庫ゆき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 22: bound for Minami Kogyo-danchi (the south industrial park)/for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fusimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 22: Bound for Minami Kogyo-danchi (the south industrial park) and/or for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fusimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 22: Bound for Minami Kogyo-danchi (the south industrial park) / for Yokooji-shako Depot through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>and/or →/　としました。Depot を追加しました。Fushimi に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>81系統　（竹田街道経由）京都駅前/京阪中書島・伏見港公園、横大路車庫ゆき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 81: bound for Kyoto-ekimae (in front of Kyoto Station) (via Takedakaido)/for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 81: Bound for Kyoto-ekimae (in front of Kyoto Station) (via Takedakaido) and/or for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 81: Bound for Kyoto Station (via Takeda-kaido Road) / for Yokooji-shako Depot through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Stationとしました。Depot を追加しました。and/or →/　としました。Takeda-kaido Road としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>特81系統　（竹田街道・竹田駅東口経由）竹田駅東口、京都駅前/京阪中書島・伏見港公園、横大路車庫ゆき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route special 81: bound for Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station) or for Kyoto-ekimae (in front of Kyoto Station) (via Takedakaido and Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station)/for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-koukoen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route special 81: Bound for Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station) or for Kyoto-ekimae (in front of Kyoto Station) (via Takedakaido and Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station) and/or for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-koukoen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route special 81: Bound for the east exit of Takeda Station (via Takeda-kaido Road and the east exit of Takeda Station) /for Yokooji-shako Depot through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>higashiguchi →east exit　としました。Depot を追加しました。and/or →/　としました。Takeda-kaido Road としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>南3系統　竹田駅西口/京阪中書島・伏見港公園　横大路車庫ゆき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route south 3: bound for Takedaeki-nihiguchi (the west entrance of Takeda Station)/for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route south 3: Bound for Takedaeki-nihiguchi (the west entrance of Takeda Station) and/or for Yokooji Shako through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route south 3: Bound for the west exit of Takeda Station / for Yokooji-shako Depot through Keihan Chushojima and Fushimi-ko-koen (the Fushimi port park)</e>
<cmt>nishiguchi →west exit　としました。and/or →/　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>南8系統　（藤森神社経由）竹田駅東口/横大路車庫ゆき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route south 8: bound for Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station)(via Fujimori-jinja Shrine)/Yokooji Shako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route south 8: Bound for Takedaeki-higashiguchi (the east entrance of Takeda Station) (via Fujimori-jinja Shrine) and/or for Yokooji Shako</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route south 8: Bound for the east exit of Takeda Station (via Fujimori-jinja Shrine)　/for Yokooji-shako Depot</e>
<cmt>higashiguchi →east exit　としました。Depot を追加しました。and/or →/　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>京阪バス・京阪シティバス・京阪宇治バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Bus/Keihan City Bus/Keihan Uji Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Bus/Keihan City Bus/Keihan Uji Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Bus/Keihan City Bus/Keihan Uji Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>6号経路（京阪バスのみの運行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The buses on path 6 are operated only by Keihan Bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The buses on path 6 are operated only by Keihan Bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The buses on path 6 are operated only by Keihan Bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>京阪バス山科営業所） 竹田駅西口行/醍醐バスターミナル行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Bus Yamashina Eigyosho (the Yamashina business office of Keihan Bus): bound for Takedaeki-nishiguchi (the west entrance of Takeda Station)/for Daigo Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Bus Yamashina Eigyosho (the Yamashina business office of Keihan Bus): Bound for Takedaeki-nishiguchi (the west entrance of Takeda Station) and/or for Daigo Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Bus Yamashina Eigyosho (the Yamashina business office of Keihan Bus): Bound for the west exit of Takeda Station / for Daigo Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>nishiguchi →west exit　としました。and/or →/　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>25号経路（京阪シティバス・京阪宇治バスの共同運行） 京阪中書島行/近鉄大久保行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Path 25 (operated by Keihan City Bus and Keihan Uji Bus jointly): bound for Keihan-Chushojima/for Kintetsu Okubo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Path 25 (jointly operated by Keihan City Bus and Keihan Uji Bus): Bound for Keihan-Chushojima and/or for Kintetsu Okubo</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Path 25 (jointly operated by Keihan City Bus and Keihan Uji Bus): Bound for Keihan-Chushojima / for Kintetsu Okubo</e>
<cmt>and/or →/　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>23系統（京阪宇治バスのみの運行） 京阪宇治バス宇治営業所行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 23 (operated only by Keihan Uji Bus): bund for Keihan Uji Bus Uji Eigyosho (the Uji business office of Keihan Uji Bus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 23 (operated only by Keihan Uji Bus): Bound for Keihan Uji Bus Uji Eigyosho (the Uji business office of Keihan Uji Bus)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 23 (operated only by Keihan Uji Bus): Bound for Keihan Uji Bus Uji Eigyosho (the Uji business office of Keihan Uji Bus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>1910年（明治43年）4月15日 京阪本線開通と同時に伏見駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 15, 1910: It started the operation as Fushima Station when Keihan Main Line started its operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 15, 1910: It started the operation as Fushima Station concurrently with the launch of the Keihan Main Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 15, 1910: It started the operation as Fushimi Station concurrently with the launch of the Keihan Main Line.</e>
<cmt>Fushimi に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>1915年（大正4年）11月11日 伏見桃山駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 11, 1915: Its name was changed to Fushimai-Momoyama Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 11, 1915: Its name was changed to Fushimai-Momoyama Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 11, 1915: Its name was changed to Fushimi-momoyama Station.</e>
<cmt>Fushimi-momoyama　に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>1916年（大正5年）4月1日 急行停車駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1916: Express trains started stopping at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1916: Express trains began making stops at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1916: Express trains began making stops at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>戦前は一貫して急行停車駅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the was, express trains always stopped at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the war, express trains always stopped at the station.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the war, express trains always stopped at the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>戦争末期に急行の運行が中止され、1946年の運行再開時に丹波橋に停車駅が変更される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the final days of the war, the operation of express trains was stopped, and when the operation of express trains restarted in 1946, the express trains became to stop at Tambabashi Station instead of this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the final days of the war, the operation of express trains was stopped, and when the operation of express trains restarted in 1946, the express trains began making stops at Tambabashi Station instead of here.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the final days of the war, the operation of express trains was stopped, and when the operation of express trains restarted in 1946, the express trains began making stops at Tanbabashi Station instead of here.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>1943年（昭和18年）10月1日 会社合併により京阪神急行電鉄（現在の阪急電鉄）の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1943: Due to the merging of companies concerned, it became a station of Keihanshin Express Railway (present Hankyu Railway)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1943: Due to the merger of the companies concerned, it became a station of the Keihanshin Express Railway (presently Hankyu Railway).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1943: Due to the merger of the companies concerned, it became a station of the Keihanshin Express Railway (presently Hankyu Railway).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="54">
<j>1949年（昭和24年）12月1日 会社分離により京阪電気鉄道の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1, 1949: Coresponding to the division of the company, it became a station of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1, 1949: Due to the division of the company, it became a station of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1, 1949: Due to the division of the company, it became a station of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="55">
<j>1962年（昭和37年）4月1日 駅東側に京阪スーパーマーケット桃山店開業（現在の「京阪ザ・ストア桃山店」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1962: The Momoyama store of the Keihan super-market (the present Momoyama store of KEIHAN THE STORE) was opened on the east side of this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1962: The Momoyama store of the Keihan supermarket (the present Momoyama store of KEIHAN THE STORE) was opened on the east side of this station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1962: The Momoyama store of the Keihan supermarket (the present Momoyama store of KEIHAN THE STORE) was opened on the east side of this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>1973年（昭和48年）12月9日 駅舎が地下化される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 9, 1973: The station house was moved undergound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 9, 1973: The station house was moved undergound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 9, 1973: The station house was moved underground.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="57">
<j>2008年（平成20年）1月 エレベーター2基新設、多目的トイレなどバリアフリー化工事完了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January, 2008: Two new elevators were installed, and the work to make its prmises barrier-free, such as installation of a multi-purpose lavatory, was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January, 2008: Two new elevators were installed, and the process of making the premises barrier-free, such as with the installation of a multipurpose lavatory, was completed.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January, 2008: Two new elevators were installed, and the process of making the premises barrier-free, such as with the installation of a multipurpose lavatory, was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>1945年に丹波橋駅での相互乗り入れが開始される以前は、この駅と桃山御陵前駅が京阪と奈良電気鉄道（→近鉄京都線）の連絡駅になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before both of the two lines started using Tambabashi Station in 1945, the Keihan line and the Nara Electric Railway line (→Kintetsu Kyoto Line) were connected with each other at this station and at Momoyamagoryo-mae Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before both of the lines started using Tambabashi Station in 1945, the Keihan Line and the Nara Electric Railway Line (→Kintetsu Kyoto Line) were interconnected at this station and Momoyamagoryo-mae Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before both of the lines started using Tanbabashi Station in 1945, the Keihan Line and the Nara Electric Railway Line (present Kintetsu Kyoto Line) were interconnected at this station and Momoyamagoryo-mae Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi に変更しました。→をpresent と変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また、その当時は京阪線の急行は当駅に停車し、丹波橋は通過していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, express trains on the Keihan line stopped at this station, not at Tambabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, express trains on the Keihan Line stopped at this station but not at Tambabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, express trains on the Keihan Line stopped at this station but not at Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="60">
<j>京阪ザ・ストア閉鎖までは車内放送の際に駅名の後に「京阪ザ・ストア前」と呼称していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before operation of KEIHAN THE STORE was stopped, the anouncement of &quot;KEIHAN THE STORE&quot; was made additionally succeeding to the announcemnet of the station name in the train cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before KEIHAN THE STORE ceased operation, the announcement of &quot;KEIHAN THE STORE&quot; was made additionally, succeeding the announcement of the station name in the train cars.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before KEIHAN THE STORE ceased operation, the announcement of &apos;KEIHAN THE STORE&apos; was made additionally, succeeding the announcement of the station name in the train cars.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としましｔ。あ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>京阪電気鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>京阪本線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>■K特急・■特急・■急行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ K-limited express trains ■ Limited express trains ■ Express trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ K-limited express trains ■ Limited express trains ■ Express trains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">K-Limited Express/Limited Express/Rapid Express</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>通過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not stop at this station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No stops are made at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No stops are made at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>■準急・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■ Semi-express trains ■ Local trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■ Semi-express trains ■ Local trains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Semi Express/Local</e>
<cmt>準急→Sub-express としました（阪急の場合）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="66">
<j>中書島駅 - 伏見桃山駅 - 丹波橋駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chushojima station - Fushimi-Momoyama Station - Tambabashi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chushojima station - Fushimi-Momoyama Station - Tambabashi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chushojima station - Fushimi-momoyama Station - Tanbabashi Station</e>
<cmt>Fushimi-momoyama, Tanbabashi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), Nnh(id:474), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), Etopirica(id:32491), Pixan(id:24280), 天然ガス(id:98149), Felicemente(id:43126), UE-PON2600(id:18149), Wikipedianet(id:9608), Wikindexan(id:10060), Ikaxer(id:61759), Memeja(id:110500), Yamanamann(id:9761), Shinkansen(id:13703), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Unamu(id:14627), Kone(id:377), Hirotaro(id:1437), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Alive(id:88260), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>