<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大宮駅 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omiya Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大宮駅（おおみやえき）は、京都市中京区四条通大宮西入ル錦大宮町127にある、阪急電鉄阪急京都本線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in 127, Nishiki Omiya-cho, Shijo-dori Omiya-nishi-iru, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, Omiya Station is a stop on the Hankyu Kyoto Line, which is operated by the Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omiya Station, located at 127, Nishiki Omiya-cho, Shijo-dori Omiya-nishi-iru, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, is a stop on the Hankyu Kyoto Line, which is operated by the Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omiya Station, located at 127, Nishiki Omiya-cho, Shijo-dori Omiya-nishi-iru, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, is a stop on the Hankyu Kyoto Line, which is operated by the Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>京都市下京区との境界に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is located on the boundary between Nakagyo Ward and Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is located on the boundary between Nakagyo Ward and Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is located on the boundary between Nakagyo Ward and Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>京福電気鉄道四条大宮駅とは、四条大宮交差点を挟んで駅舎が対峙している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station building is opposed to that of Shijo-Omiya Station operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co.,Ltd. over the intersection of Shijo-Omiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station building lies opposite Shijo-Omiya Station, operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., across the intersection of Shijo-Omiya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station building lies opposite Shijo-Omiya Station, operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd., across the intersection of Shijo-Omiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>下記のように1963年（昭和38年）まで終着駅だったこともあり、駅附近は往時の繁華街の雰囲気をとどめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described below, since the station was a terminal until 1963, the area around the station conveys the atmosphere of the downtown in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station was a terminal until 1963, as described below, so the area around the station conveys the atmosphere of the downtown from an earlier time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station was a terminal until 1963, as described below, so the area around the station conveys the atmosphere of the downtown from an earlier time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>かつては特別急行列車の停車駅だったが、2001年3月24日のダイヤ改正以降、昼間の閑散時に設定される特急（平日830～1530、休日830～1830）の通過駅となり、2007年3月17日のダイヤ改正以降は平日の朝晩に通勤特急が停車するのみで、休日は特急系統が全く停車しなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, Limited Express trains would stop at Omiya Station, but after the schedule revision of March 24, 2001, Limited Express trains came to pass the station during off-time in daytime (8:30-15:30 on weekdays and 8:30-18:30 on holidays), and then after the schedule revision of March 17, 2007, only (Commuter) Limited Express trains stop at the station in the morning and evening on weekdays, thus having no Limited Express trains stop at the station on holidays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, limited express trains would stop at Omiya Station, but after the schedule revision of March 24, 2001, those trains would pass the station during off-time in daytime (8:30-15:30 on weekdays and 8:30-18:30 on holidays); however, with the schedule revision of March 17, 2007, only (commuter) limited express trains would stop at the station in the morning and evening on weekdays, so no limited express trains stop at the station on holidays.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, limited express trains would stop at Omiya Station, but after the schedule revision of March 24, 2001, those trains would pass the station during off-time in daytime (8:30-15:30 on weekdays and 8:30-18:30 on holidays); however, with the schedule revision of March 17, 2007, only (commuter) limited express trains would stop at the station in the morning and evening on weekdays, so no limited express trains stop at the station on holidays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、当該時間帯は上下線とも桂駅で緩急接続する形となっており、乗り換えが必要ではあるが特急を利用できるよう配慮されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, both inbound and outbound trains variously connects at Katsura Station during the above time periods, by which passengers have to change trains but can take Limited Express trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, both inbound and outbound trains variously connect at Katsura Station during the above time periods, and consequently passengers have to change trains but can take limited express trains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, both inbound and outbound trains variously connect at Katsura Station during the above time periods, and consequently passengers have to change trains but can take limited express trains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし特急通過の影響は大きく、当該時間帯（特に昼間）での各駅停車（または準急）への駆け込み乗車が多発している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the passing of the Limited Express trains have resulted in the increase of passengers rushing to get on Local trains (or Semi Express trains) during the above time periods (especially during the day).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the passing of the limited express trains has resulted in the increase of passengers rushing to get on local trains (or semi-express trains) during the above time periods (particularly during the day).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the passing of the limited express trains has resulted in the increase of passengers rushing to get on local trains (or semi-express trains) during the above time periods (particularly during the day).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>河原町駅 (京都府)開業以前は、阪急電鉄の京都におけるターミナル駅であり、そのためか「京都大宮駅」と呼んでいたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) was opened, Omiya Station had been a terminal of the Hankyu Railway in Kyoto: Omiya Station was once called &apos;Kyoto Omiya Station.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the opening of Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture), Omiya Station was a terminal of the Hankyu Railway in Kyoto; in fact, it was once called &apos;Kyoto Omiya Station.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the opening of Kawaramachi Station (Kyoto Prefecture), Omiya Station was a terminal of the Hankyu Railway in Kyoto; in fact, it was once called &apos;Kyoto Omiya Station.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお1931年（昭和6年）開業の大宮駅～西院駅間は東京の東京地下鉄銀座線に次ぐ、日本で2番目の地下鉄である（架空電車線方式としては日本初であるが、架空電車線方式に限った駅部分付近の地下化に限っては宮城電気鉄道仙台駅（現在のJR仙石線仙台駅とは別位置)が先））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section between Omiya Station and Saiin Station, which was opened in 1931, is the second oldest subway in Japan after the Tokyo Metro Ginza Line in Tokyo (although it is the oldest in Japan as an overhead line system, Sendai Station of the Miyagi Electric Railway (its location is different from that of the current Sendai Station on the JR Senseki Line) is the oldest in terms of the underground construction near the portion of the station in the overhead line system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section between Omiya Station and Saiin Station, which opened in 1931, is the second-oldest subway in Japan after the Tokyo Metro Ginza Line in Tokyo; but although it is the oldest in Japan as an overhead-line system, Sendai Station of the Miyagi Electric Railway (its location is different from that of the current Sendai Station on the JR Senseki Line) is the oldest in terms of the underground construction near the portion of the station in the overhead-line system.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section between Omiya Station and Saiin Station, which opened in 1931, is the second-oldest subway in Japan after the Tokyo Metro Ginza Line in Tokyo; but although it is the oldest in Japan as an overhead-line system, Sendai Station of the Miyagi Electric Railway (its location is different from that of the current Sendai Station on the JR Senseki Line) is the oldest in terms of the underground construction near the portion of the station in the overhead-line system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>西院駅西の地下路線入り口上部には青銅製の鷲の像が取りつけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a bronze statue of eagle installed over the entrance of the underground passage to the west of the Saiin Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a bronze statue of an eagle above the entrance to the underground passage west of Saiin Station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a bronze statue of an eagle above the entrance to the underground passage west of Saiin Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>プラットホーム形状と配置2面2線のホームを持つ地下駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omiya Station is an underground station with two platforms serving two tracks (the form of platform and its arrangement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omiya Station is an underground facility with two platforms serving two tracks (the form of platform and its arrangement).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omiya Station is an underground facility with two separate platforms serving two tracks.</e>
<cmt>原文のwiki によると「相対式」ホームのようですので、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>四条通の真下にホームがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The platforms are just below Shijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The platforms are just below Shijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The platforms are just below Shijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>改札口は東西2か所設けられているが、西改札は一部利用できない時間帯がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ticket gates are installed on both east and west of the station; the west ticket gate is not available in a particular time period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ticket gates are located east and west of the station; however, the west ticket gate isn&apos;t available during a certain time period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ticket gates are located east and west of the station; however, the west ticket gate isn&apos;t available during a certain time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、西改札は2号線しか利用できないので、西改札から1号線へ行くのには東改札を経由しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the west ticket gate leads only to Track 2, passengers have to go through the east ticket gate to reach Track 1 from the west ticket gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the west ticket gate leads only to track 2, passengers must go through the east ticket gate in order to reach track 1 from the west ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the west ticket gate leads only to Track 2, passengers must go through the east ticket gate in order to reach Track 1 from the west ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>トイレは東改札口の外にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The toilet is located outside the east ticket gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The toilet is located outside the east ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The toilet is located outside the east ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>開業が昭和初期であり、東改札側は構造上エスカレータ、エレベーターが設置困難となっているため、車椅子利用者向けにコンベアが設置されている（西改札側にはエレベーターが設けられている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the station was opened in the early Showa era, it is difficult to install an escalator or elevator on the east ticket gate side due to the structure of the station; therefore, a conveyer is installed for passengers in wheelchairs (an elevator is installed in the west ticket gate side).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station opened in the early Showa era, so it&apos;s difficult to install an escalator or elevator on the east ticket gate side due to the structure of the station; therefore, a conveyer is installed for passengers in wheelchairs (an elevator is provided on the west ticket gate side).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station opened in the early Showa period, so it&apos;s difficult to install an escalator or elevator on the east ticket gate side due to the structure of the station; therefore, a conveyer is installed for passengers in wheelchairs (an elevator is provided on the west ticket gate side).</e>
<cmt>era →periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>かつてはホーム長が7両だったため、8両編成の電車は上り・下りとも進行方向最後尾1両のみドアを閉じ客扱いするドアカットを実施していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the length of the platform used to be equal to 7 cars, both inbound and outbound trains comprised of 8 cars had to keep the doors of the last car closed at the station in the direction of travel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the length of the platform used to be equal to seven cars, inbound and outbound trains comprised of eight cars had to keep the doors of the last car closed at the station in the direction of travel.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the length of the platform used to be equal to seven cars, inbound and outbound trains comprised of eight cars had to keep the doors of the last car closed at the station in the direction of travel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当時の車両にはその旨を記載したものが存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a notice on some of such cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the cars carried notices to that effect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the cars carried notices to that effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>後に10両対応化工事により8両にも対応できるようになり、当駅でのドアカットは消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The platform was later rebuilt to correspond to the trains comprised of 10 cars, thus making unnecessary for any train to keep doors closed at the station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The platform was later rebuilt to correspond to trains comprised of ten cars, thus making it unnecessary to keep the doors of any train closed at the station.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The platform was later rebuilt to correspond to trains comprised of ten cars, thus making it unnecessary to keep the doors of any train closed at the station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>地下ホームは、土木学会の「土木学会選奨土木遺産」（ランクA）に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The underground platform of this station is registered as &quot;The JSCE Civil Engineering Heritage&quot; (Rank A), which is designated by the Japan Society of Civil Engineers (JSCE).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The underground platform of this station is registered as a &quot;JSCE Civil Engineering Heritage&quot; (Rank A), which is designated by the Japan Society of Civil Engineers (JSCE).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The underground platform of this station is registered as a &apos;JSCE Civil Engineering Heritage&apos; (Rank A), which is designated by the Japan Society of Civil Engineers (JSCE).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of the station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conditions of usage</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger use</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>平成15年度の1日あたりの乗車人員は約18,342人（京都府統計書より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of passengers per day in 2003 was about 18,342 (adapted from Kyoto Prefecture Statistical Book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of passengers per day in 2003 was approximately 18,342 (according to the Kyoto Prefecture Statistical Book).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of passengers per day in fiscal year 2003 was approximately 18,342 (according to the Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Report).</e>
<cmt>統一しました。fiscal → fiscal yearに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>京福電気鉄道京福電気鉄道嵐山本線 四条大宮駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijo-Omiya Station on the Arashiyama Main Line, which is operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co.,Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijo-Omiya Station, on the Arashiyama Main Line, which is operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijo-Omiya Station, on the Arashiyama Main Line, which is operated by the Keifuku Electric Railroad Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>嵯峨野線 二条駅 (徒歩15分程度掛かるが、京都市内の阪急-JR間の連絡が乏しいため当駅で乗り換える客も見られる)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijo Station on the (JR) Sagano Line (It takes about 15 minutes on foot from Omiya Station, but some passengers change trains at Omiya Station because the connection between Hankyu Railway and JR in Kyoto City is poor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijo Station, on the (JR) Sagano Line, is a 15-minute walk from Omiya Station, but some passengers change trains at Omiya Station because the connection between Hankyu Railway and JR in Kyoto City is poor.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijo Station, on the (JR) Sagano Line, is a fifteen-minute walk from Omiya Station, but some passengers change trains at Omiya Station because the connection between Hankyu Railway and JR in Kyoto City is poor.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>壬生寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mibu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mibu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mibu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>京都四条大宮郵便局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Shijo Omiya post office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Shijo Omiya post office</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Shijo Omiya post office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>大宮通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omiya-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omiya-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omiya-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>四条通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>バスのりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus stop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>四条大宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijo Omiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijo Omiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijo Omiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>京都市営バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>京都バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Bus Co.,Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>西日本ジェイアールバス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West Japan JR Bus Company</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West Japan JR Bus Company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West Japan JR Bus Company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>京都駅行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>周山行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Shuzan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Shuzan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Shuzan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>京阪バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Bus Co.,Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Bus Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>82系統：五条京阪、国道大塚、大宅行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 82: for Gojo Keihan, Kokudo Otsuka, Oyake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 82: Bound for Gojo Keihan, Kokudo Otsuka, Oyake</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 82: Bound for Gojo Keihan, Kokudo Otsuka, Oyake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="36">
<j>83系統：祇園、川田、西野山団地、醍醐バスターミナル行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 83: for Gion, Kawata, Nishinoyama Danchi, Daigo Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 83: Bound for Gion, Kawata, Nishinoyama Danchi, Daigo Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 83: Bound for Gion, Kawata, Nishinomiya Danchi (Nishinomiya housing complex), Daigo Bus Terminal</e>
<cmt>団地の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="37">
<j>85系統：祇園、川田、西野山団地、大宅行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 85: for Gion, Kawata, Nishinoyama Danchi, Oyake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 85: Bound for Gion, Kawata, Nishinoyama Danchi, Oyake</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 85: Bound for Gion, Kawata, Nishinoyama Danchi, Oyake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>大阪空港交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Airport Transport Co.,Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Airport Transport Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Airport Transport Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="39">
<j>大阪国際空港行、関西国際空港行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Osaka International Airport, Kansai International Airport</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Osaka International Airport, Kansai International Airport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Osaka International Airport, Kansai International Airport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>1931年（昭和6年）3月31日 京阪電気鉄道新京阪線の京阪京都駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 31, 1931 the station was opened as Keihan Kyoto Station on the Shinkeihan Line, which was operated by the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 31, 1931: The station was opened as Keihan Kyoto Station on the Shinkeihan Line, which was operated by the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 31, 1931: The station was opened as Keihan Kyoto Station on the Shinkeihan Line, which was operated by the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>案内上は単に「京都」とすることも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the announcement, the station was referred to as just &apos;Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the announcement, the station was simply referred to as &apos;Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the announcement, the station was simply referred to as &apos;Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>1943年（昭和18年）10月1日 京阪神急行電鉄（現在の阪急電鉄）への合併に伴い、京阪神京都駅に改称（正式駅名）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, 1943 the station was renamed Keihanshin Kyoto Station (official station name) when the Keihan Electric Railway was merged into the Keihanshin Express Railway (currently Hankyu Railway).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1943: The station was renamed Keihanshin Kyoto Station (the official station name) when the Keihan Electric Railway was merged into the Keihanshin Express Railway (currently Hankyu Railway).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1943: The station was renamed Keihanshin Kyoto Station (the official station name) when the Keihan Electric Railway was merged into the Keihanshin Express Railway (currently Hankyu Railway).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>1949年（昭和24年）12月1日 京阪電気鉄道分離により阪急京都駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 1, 1949 the station was renamed Hankyu Kyoto Station as a result of the split of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1, 1949: The station was renamed Hankyu Kyoto Station due to the split of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1, 1949: The station was renamed Hankyu Kyoto Station due to the split of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="44">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）6月17日 大宮駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station was renamed Omiya Station on June 17, 1963.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 17, 1963: The station was renamed Omiya Station.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 17, 1963: The station was renamed Omiya Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>路線は河原町駅まで延伸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The line was extended to Kawaramachi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The line was extended to Kawaramachi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line was extended to Kawaramachi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>2001年（平成13年）3月24日 昼間は特急が通過するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 24, 2001 Limited Express trains came to stop at Omiya Station during the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 24, 2001, limited express trains began making stops at Omiya Station during the day.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 24, 2001: Limited express trains began passing the Omiya Station during the day.</e>
<cmt>通過する　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>阪急電鉄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>■京都本線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>■特急</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Limited Express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Limited express</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limited Express</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>通過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limited Express trains do not stop at Omiya Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Limited express trains don&apos;t stop at Omiya Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limited express trains don&apos;t stop at Omiya Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>■通勤特急・■快速急行・■準急・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■(Commuter) Limited Express ■Rapid Express ■Semi Express ■Local train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■(Commuter) limited express ■Rapid express ■Semi-express ■Local train</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commuter Limited Express/Rapid Express/Semi Express/Local</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="52">
<j>西院駅 - 大宮駅 - 烏丸駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saiin Station - Omiya Station - Karasuma Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saiin Station - Omiya Station - Karasuma Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiin Station - Omiya Station - Karasuma Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gargoyle(id:49233), Ogny(id:13549), Bakkai(id:7233), 城山(id:104901), Etopirica(id:32491), 松茸(id:27535), SHARU(id:86927), Wikipedianet(id:9608), Ikaxer(id:61759), Utsuda(id:605), Omodaka(id:17013), Fanvio(id:116155), MACHA-KUN(id:140454), Shinkansen(id:13703), ＋－(id:17104), 御所人間(id:143118), Rusk(id:9895), Soredewa(id:19771), YurikBot(id:18605), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Rislimric(id:54531), 鍛高譚(id:154933), Kone(id:377), Hirotaro(id:1437), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), 計記録(id:124500), 210.(id:9838), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Learnpoint(id:186718), Bsx(id:38434), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>