<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>七条駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shichijo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichijo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichijo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>七条駅（しちじょうえき）は京都府京都市東山区下堀詰町にある、京阪電気鉄道京阪本線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Horitsumecho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Shichijo Station is a stop on the Keihan Main Line, a Keihan Electric Railway Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in Horitsumecho, in the Higashiyama ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Shichijo Station is a stop on the Keihan Main Line, a Keihan Electric Railway Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in Shimo-Horitsumecho, in the Higashiyama Ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Shichijo Station is a stop on the Keihan Main Line of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>Shimo追加&quot;Higashiyama ward&quot;→&quot;Higashiyama Ward&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都における京阪電鉄のターミナル駅のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the terminal stations of Keihan Electric Railways located in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s one of the terminal stations of Keihan Electric Railways, located in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s one of the terminal stations of the Keihan Electric Railways, located in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>the追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>全ての列車が停車する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All trains stop at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All trains stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All trains stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>駅ホームのカラーリングは紫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The color tone of the station&apos;s platforms is purple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color tone of the station&apos;s platforms is purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color tone of the station&apos;s platforms is purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これは抵抗器の抵抗値を表すカラーコードで「7」を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the color code indicating the resistance value of resistance unitｓ and implies the numeral [7.」</e>
<cmt>七条の七が「７」である解説があって初めてこの項の存在する意味が解るかと考えます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the color code indicating the resistance value of resistance units; it implies the numeral &quot;7.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the color code indicating the resistance value of resistance units; it implies the numeral &apos;7.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>相対式2面2線のホームを持つ地下駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an underground station with two platforms opposite each other and two tracks in between.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s an underground station with two platforms opposite each other and two tracks in between.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s an underground station with two platforms opposite each other and two tracks in between.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>七条大橋東詰、川端通と七条通との交差点の直下に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located at Shichijo Ohashi Higashitsume immediately under the insection of Kawabata-dori Street and Shichijo-dori-Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s located at Shichijo Ohashi Higashitsume, directly beneath the intersection of Kawabata-dori and Shichijo-dori streets.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s located at Shichijo Ohashi Higashitsume, directly beneath the intersection of Kawabata-dori and Shichijo-dori streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>改札・ホームともに地下1階にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both ticket gates and platforms are installed at first underground level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ticket gates and platforms are installed on the first underground level.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ticket gates and platforms are installed on the first underground level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>ほかの京阪線の地下駅は地下1階が改札及びコンコース・地下2階がホームとなる2層形式だが、この駅は地下1階に改札およびホームを両方備える1層形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other underground stations on Keihan Line are of two level construction, i.e. ticket gates and concourse located at first underground level and platforms at second underground level, but this station is of one level with both ticket gates and platforms at first underground level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other underground stations on the Keihan Line are of two-level construction, so the ticket gates and concourse are located on the first underground level and platforms are on the second underground level; however, this station is of one level with both ticket gates and platforms on the first underground level.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other underground stations on the Keihan Line are of two-level construction, so the ticket gates and concourse are located on the first underground level and platforms are on the second underground level; however, this station is of one level with both ticket gates and platforms on the first underground level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため、改札口は各ホーム毎に独立して設けられており、改札内には互いのホームを結ぶ通路が存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to its structure, independent ticket gates are installed for each platform and a passageway linking the two platforms does not exist beyond ticket gates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to its structure, independent ticket gates are installed for each platform, and beyond the ticket gates there is no passageway linking the two platforms.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to its structure, independent ticket gates are installed for each platform, and beyond the ticket gates there is no passageway linking the two platforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1番線出町柳駅方面へは川端通西側の歩道の入口から、2番線淀屋橋駅方面へは川端通東側歩道の入口から、それぞれ入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access to Track No. 1 platform for Demachiyanagi Station is through the entrance on the westside pavement of Kawabata-dori Street and to Track No.2 for Yodoyabashi Station by way of the entrance on the eastside pavement of Kawabata-dori Street respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access to the Track No. 1 platform for Demachiyanagi Station is through the entrance on the west-side pavement of Kawabata-dori Street, while access to Track No. 2 for Yodoyabashi Station is by way of the entrance on the eastside pavement of Kawabata-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access to Platform 1 for Demachiyanagi Station is through the entrance on the west-side pavement of Kawabata-dori Street, while access to Platform 2 for Yodoyabashi Station is by way of the entrance on the eastside pavement of Kawabata-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>「No.番線」の表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし、改札外（地下）には反対側改札口への連絡通路が設けられているため、反対側の改札口に下りてしまっても地上に戻ることなく行くことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as an (underground) accessway link to ticket gates on the opposite side is available, it is possible to carry on without returning aboveground even after descending to opposite side ticket gates.</e>
<cmt>何処に“行く”のか判然としません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as an (underground) accessway link to ticket gates on the opposite side is available, it is possible to carry on without returning aboveground even after descending to the opposite-side ticket gates.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because an (underground) access linking the ticket gate to the opposite side is available outside each ticket gate, it is possible to go to the opposite-side ticket gate without returning aboveground even after descending to a ticket gate on the wrong side.</e>
<cmt>「改札外」　追加　「反対側の改札」をwrong-side ticket gateとしました（間違って降りてしまった、と解釈）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この通路は線路の下をくぐることで反対側へとつながっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This accessway is connected to the opposite side without going under the tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This accessway allows connection to the opposite side without going under the tracks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This access way allows connection to the opposite side by going under the tracks.</e>
<cmt>without→ by</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このような構造になった理由は、おそらく東福寺駅 - 七条駅間で地上線から地下線に切り替わるために土かぶりを浅くせざるを得ず、地下2層分の施設が造れないためだと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for such construction may probably have been caused by inevitable thin earth covering for the section between Tofukuji Station and Shichijo Station going underground (from above ground) making construction of a two level structure underground impossible</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for such construction may probably have been caused by the inevitable thin layer of earth covering the section between Tofukuji Station and Shichijo Station going underground (from aboveground), which made the construction of a two-level underground structure impossible.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for such construction may probably have been caused by the inevitable thin layer of earth covering the section between Tofukuji Station and Shichijo Station going underground (from aboveground), which made the construction of a two-level underground structure impossible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>なおこの構造のため、当時京阪で行っていた折り返し乗車（専用乗車券を購入することで例えば東福寺駅から一旦七条駅に向かい、京阪特急に乗り換えて淀屋橋駅に行くことができた）の料金収受を確実にできるという副産物もあった（現在折り返し専用乗車券は発売されておらず、七条駅で再度乗車券を購入する必要がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A spin-off effect of such construction was assured fare collection from passengers on turn-around trains operated by Keihan at the time (i.e. by purchasing a special ticket and once getting on at Tofukuji Station for Shichijo Station and transferring to a Kｅｉｈａｎ super express made it possible to go as far as Yodoyabashi Station.) (Special tickets for turnaround trains are currently not sold and purchasing a ticket once again at Shichijo Station is required.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A spin-off effect of such construction was the assurance of fare collection from passengers on the turnaround trains then being operated by Keihan (by purchasing a special ticket and getting on at Tofukuji Station for Shichijo Station and then transferring to a Keihan super express made it possible to go as far as Yodoyabashi Station) (special tickets for turnaround trains are currently not sold and it&apos;s necessary to purchase a ticket again at Shichijo Station).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A spin-off effect of such construction was the assurance of fare collection from passengers on the turnaround trains then being operated by Keihan (by purchasing a special ticket and getting on at Tofukuji Station for Shichijo Station and then transferring to a Keihan super express made it possible to go as far as Yodoyabashi Station) (special tickets for turnaround trains are currently not sold and it&apos;s necessary to purchase a ticket again at Shichijo Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、現在の特急（およびK特急）は中書島駅や丹波橋駅に停車し、優等列車が停まらない駅での利便性も確保されているため折り返し乗車の必要性もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boarding turn-around trains is no longer required as super express (including K-Ltd. express) trains now stop at Chushojima Station and Tambabashi Stations ensuring convenience of stations at which non-local trains do not stop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boarding turnaround trains is no longer required because super express (including K-Ltd. express) trains now stop at Chushojima Station and Tambabashi Stations, thereby ensuring the convenience of stations where non-local trains don&apos;t stop.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boarding turnaround trains is no longer required because super express (including K-Ltd. express) trains now stop at Chushojima Station and Tanbabashi Stations, thereby ensuring the convenience of stations where non-local trains don&apos;t stop.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Tambabashi&quot;→&quot;Tanbabashi&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>のりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boarding platforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boarding platforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boarding platforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>※両ホームとも有効長は8両。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">※Both platforms have an effective length to accommodate eight cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">※Each of the platforms has a length sufficient to accommodate eight cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">※Each of the platforms has a length sufficient to accommodate eight cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>駅は川端通と七条通との交差点の地下にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station is situated underground of the Kawabata-dori Street and Shichjo-dori Street crossing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station is situated underground, below the crossing of Kawabata-dori and Shichjo-dori streets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station is situated underground, below the crossing of Kawabata-dori and Shichjo-dori streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>駅のすぐ西を鴨川 (淀川水系)が流れ、七条大橋がかかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamo-gawa River flows immediately to the west of the station and Shichijo Ohashi Bridge spans the stream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamogawa River, spanned by the Shichijo Ohashi Bridge, flows immediately to the west of the station.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system), spanned by the Shichijo Ohashi Bridge, flows immediately to the west of the station.</e>
<cmt>Yodo-gawa River system追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>駅東側</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East side of the station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East side of the station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East side of the station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>京都国立博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>豊国神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyokuni-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyokuni-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyokuni-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>方広寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>耳塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimi-zuka (Ear mound)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimi-zuka (Ear mound)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimi-zuka (Ear mound)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>三十三間堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjusangendo Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjusangendo Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjusangendo Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>養源院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yogenin Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yogenin Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yogenin Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>智積院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chishakuin Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chishakuin Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chishakuin Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>妙法院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myohoin Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myohoin Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myohoin Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>京都女子大学・京都女子高等学校・京都女子中学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Women&apos;s University, Kyoto Girls&apos; Senior High School &amp; Kyoto Girls&apos; Junior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Women&apos;s University, Kyoto Girls&apos; Senior High School and Kyoto Girls&apos; Junior High School</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Women&apos;s University, Kyoto Girls&apos; Senior High School and Kyoto Girls&apos; Junior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ハイアットリージェンシー京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyatt Regency Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyatt Regency Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyatt Regency Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>駅西側（鴨川対岸）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West side of the station (opposite bank of Kamo-gawa River)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West side of the station (opposite bank of Kamo-gawa River)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West side of the station (opposite bank of the Kamo-gawa River)</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kamo-gawa River&quot;→&quot;the Kamo-gawa River&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>渉成園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosei-en Garden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosei-en Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosei-en Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>真宗本廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-shu Hombyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-shu Hombyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-shu Hombyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>JR京都駅 - 徒歩約15分（約1.1km）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Kyoto Station-some15 minutes on foot (approx.1.1km)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Kyoto Station, approximately 15 minutes on foot (about 1.1km)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Kyoto Station, approximately 15 minutes on foot (about 1.1 km)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>距離があるため、京都駅に発着するJR線に乗り換える客は丹波橋駅（近鉄丹波橋駅）から近鉄京都線経由や、東福寺駅からJR奈良線経由で行くのが一般的な経路だが、運賃節約のため七条駅 - 京都駅の徒歩乗り換えを利用する人も意外にいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there is quite a distance, the usual route taken by passengers transferring to JR Lines departing from/arriving at Kyoto Station go from Tambabashi Station (Kintetsu Tambabashi Station) via Kintetsu-Kyoto Line or from Tofukuji Station via JR-Nara Line, but the number of those who transfer by walking between Shichijo Station and Kyoto Station to economize on carfare is surprisingly large.</e>
<cmt>何処から何処までの　“距離”および何処に“行く”のか判然としません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the considerable distance, the usual route taken by passengers transferring to JR Lines departing from/arriving at Kyoto Station is to go from Tambabashi Station (Kintetsu Tambabashi Station) via Kintetsu-Kyoto Line or from Tofukuji Station via JR-Nara Line; surprisingly, however, many people transfer by walking between Shichijo Station and Kyoto Station to economize on carfare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the considerable distance, the usual route taken by passengers transferring to JR Lines departing from/arriving at Kyoto Station is to go from Tanbabashi Station (Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station) via Kintetsu Kyoto Line or from Tofukuji Station via the JR Nara Line; surprisingly, however, many people transfer by walking between Shichijo Station and Kyoto Station to economize on carfare.</e>
<cmt>Kintetsu Kyoto Line　JR Nara Lineとしました。&quot;Tambabashi&quot;→&quot;Tanbabashi&quot;に変更しました。(2箇所)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>京阪線から琵琶湖線・湖西線方面はかつては三条駅から京阪京津線に乗り換え、山科駅（京阪山科駅）で琵琶湖線・湖西線に乗り換えるのが普通だったが、京津線の御陵駅以西廃止、京都市営地下鉄東西線開通以降は運賃が高くなったことから、七条駅 - 京都駅の徒歩乗り換えに切り替えた人もいると思われる（それでも、市バスでの両駅間相互連絡は一応ある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To go to a destination on either the Biwako Line or Kosei Line via Keihan Line, the usual route in the past was to transfer to Keihan Keishin Line at Sanjo Station and change once again at Yamashina Station (Keihan Yamashina Line) to Biwako Line or Kosei Line, but as operations west of Goryo Station on Keishin Line were discontinued and fares hiked after Kyoto Municipal Subwaｙ Tozai Line began operations, it is regarded that some users have switched to walking the distance between Shichijo Station and Kyoto Station (but, nevertheless, City buses do continue to operate between the two stations.)</e>
<cmt>原文は多少舌足らずと思われる。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To go to a destination on either the Biwako Line or the Kosei Line via the Keihan Line, the usual route in the past was to transfer to the Keihan Keishin Line at Sanjo Station and change again at Yamashina Station (Keihan Yamashina Line) to the Biwako Line or Kosei Line; however, as operations west of Goryo Station on the Keishin Line were discontinued and fares hiked after the Kyoto Municipal Subway Tozai Line began operations, it is assumed that some users have chosen to walk the distance between Shichijo Station and Kyoto Station (nevertheless, city buses continue to operate between the two stations).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To go to a destination on either the Biwako Line or the Kosei Line via the Keihan Line, the usual route in the past was to transfer to the Keihan Keishin Line at Sanjo Station and change again at Yamashina Station (Keihan Yamashina Line) to the Biwako Line or Kosei Line; however, as operations west of Goryo Station on the Keishin Line were discontinued and fares hiked after the Kyoto Municipal Subway Tozai Line began operations, it is assumed that some users have chosen to walk the distance between Shichijo Station and Kyoto Station (nevertheless, city buses continue to operate between the two stations).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>ひと・まち交流館 京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitomachi Koryukan Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitomachi Koryukan Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitomachi Koryukan Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>柳原銀行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bank of Yanagihara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bank of Yanagihara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bank of Yanagihara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>バスのりば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus boarding stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus boarding stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus boarding stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>七条京阪前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nanajo Keihan-mae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nanajo Keihan-mae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nanajo Keihan-mae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>バス停は七条大橋東詰（七条通と川端通との交差点）の七条通沿いにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus stop is located along Shichijo-dori Street of Shichijo Ohashi Higashitsume (intersection of Shichijo-dori Street and Kawabata-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bus stop is located along Shichijo-dori Street of Shichijo Ohashi Higashitsume (intersection of Shichijo-dori and Kawabata-dori streets).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bus stop is located along Shichijo-dori Street of Shichijo Ohashi Higashitsume (intersection of Shichijo-dori and Kawabata-dori streets).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>駅名は「しちじょう」だが、バス停は「ななじょう」と読ませる（「一条」「四条」との混同を避けるため、停留所名が「七条大橋」であった市電時代からそのように呼ばれている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station name is 「Shichijo,」 but bus stop is read 「Nanajo」 (called so from the days when street cars were in operation and bus stop was called 「Nanajo Ohashi」 to avoid confusion with 「Ichijo」 and/or 「Shijo.」</e>
<cmt>漢字が読めない人に対する説明としては？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station name is &quot;Shichijo,&quot; but the bus stop is read &quot;Nanajo&quot; (as it has been called since the days when streetcars were in operation and the bus stop was called &quot;Nanajo Ohashi&quot; to avoid confusion with &quot;Ichijo&quot; and/or &quot;Shijo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station name is &apos;Shichijo,&apos; but the bus stop is read &apos;Nanajo&apos; (as it has been called since the days when streetcars were in operation and the bus stop was called &apos;Nanajo Ohashi&apos; in order to avoid confusion with &apos;Ichijo&apos; and/or &apos;Shijo.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>閉じ括弧追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、駅周辺や交差点を指す場合、地元では「しちじょう京阪」ではなく「ななじょう京阪」と呼ぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Again, when making reference to the vicinity of the station or intersection, locals frequently say 「Nanajo Kyoto」 and not 「Shichijo Kyoto.」</e>
<cmt>漢字が読めない人に対する説明としては？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Again, when making reference to the vicinity of the station or intersection, locals frequently say &quot;Nanajo Kyoto&quot; instead of &quot;Shichijo Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Again, when referring to the vicinity of the station or intersection, locals frequently say &apos;Nanajo Keihan&apos; instead of &apos;Shichijo Keihan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 Kyoto→ Keihan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>ただし、ななじょうは誤った読み方である(ななじょう　とは京都での七条の言い方である)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, referring to Shichijo as Nanajo is mistaken (Nanajo is how Shichijo is called in Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>漢字が読めない人に対する説明としては？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, referring to Shichijo as Nanajo is mistaken (Nanajo is how Shichijo is called in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, referring to Shichijo as Nanajo is mistaken (Nanajo is how Shichijo is called in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>京都市営バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>206系統：（東大路通経由）北大路駅方面／（京都駅経由）千本北大路方面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 206: For Kita Oji Station (via Todaiji-dori Street) /For Senbon Kitaojo (via Kyoto Station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 206: For Kita Oji Station (via Todaiji-dori Street); for Senbon Kitaojo (via Kyoto Station)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 206: For Kitaoji Station (via Higashioji-dori Street); for Senbon Kitaoji (via Kyoto Station)</e>
<cmt>Higashioji-doriとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>208系統：（東福寺経由）九条車庫方面／（西大路七条経由）西大路九条方面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route 208: For Kujo-shako (via Tofujuji Temple) /For Nishioji-Kujo (via Nishioji- Shichijo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route 208: For Kujo-shako (via Tofujuji Temple); for Nishioji-Kujo (via Nishioji-Shichijo)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route 208: For Kujo Shako depot (via Tofuku-ji Temple); for Nishioji-Kujo (via Nishioji-Shichijo)</e>
<cmt>Shako depotとしました。Tofuku-jiとしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>洛バス100系統：（清水寺、祇園経由）銀閣寺行／京都駅行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">RakuBus Route 100: For Ginkakuji (via Kiyomizudera, Gion) /Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">RakuBus Route 100: For Ginkakuji (via Kiyomizudera, Gion) /Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">RakuBus Route 100: For Ginkaku-ji Temple (via Kiyomizu-dera Temple, Gion) /Kyoto Station</e>
<cmt>Ginkaku-ji Temple、Kiyomizu-dera Temple としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>京阪本線の開業当初は、少し離れたところに大仏前駅（駅名の由来は京の大仏を参照）が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Keihan Main Line commenced operations, the Daibutsu-mae Station (refer to The Great Buddha of Kyoto regarding derivation of the station&apos;s name) was a short distance away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Keihan Main Line commenced operations, the Daibutsu-mae Station (refer to The Great Buddha of Kyoto regarding derivation of the station&apos;s name) was a short distance away.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Keihan Main Line commenced operations, the Daibutsu-mae Station (refer to The Great Buddha of Kyoto regarding derivation of the station&apos;s name) was a short distance away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その後、京都市が七条通を拡幅して市電を敷設することになったため、乗換の便を図るべく大仏前駅を廃止し、その翌日に七条通に面した当駅が開業した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, from Kyoto City deciding to widen Shichijo-dori Street and lay tracks for its trams, Daibutsu-mae Station was decommissioned for the sake of transfer convenience and this station facing Shichijo-dori Street inaugurated on the following day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, with Kyoto City&apos;s decision to widen Shichijo-dori Street and lay tracks for its trams, Daibutsu-mae Station was decommissioned for the sake of transfer convenience, and this station facing Shichijo-dori Street was inaugurated on the following day.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, with Kyoto City&apos;s decision to widen Shichijo-dori Street and lay tracks for its trams, Daibutsu-mae Station was decommissioned for the sake of transfer convenience, and this station facing Shichijo-dori Street was inaugurated on the following day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>1913年（大正2年）4月27日 - 開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opened on April 27, 1913.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opened on April 27, 1913.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 27, 1913: The station opened on.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="51">
<j>1916年（大正5年）4月1日 - 急行列車停車駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1916, became a station at which express trains stop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1916, became a station at which express trains stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1916: The station became a station at which express trains would stop.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>1935年（昭和10年）6月29日 - 『鴨川大水害』で駅施設に大きな被害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 「Great Kamo-gawa River Flooding」 which occurred on June 29, 1935 inflicted severe damage to station facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Great Kamogawa River Flood, which occurred on June 29, 1935, inflicted severe damage to station facilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 29, 1935: The &quot;Great Kamo-gawa River Flood,&quot; which occurred, inflicted severe damage on the station facilities.</e>
<cmt>Kamo-gawa 年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>1943年（昭和18年）10月1日 - 会社合併により京阪神急行電鉄（現：阪急電鉄）の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1943, became a Keihanshin-kyuko-dentsu (now Hankyu Corporation) station from amalgamation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1943 it became a Keihanshin-kyuko-dentsu (now Hankyu Corporation) station due to amalgamation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1943: The stationt became a Keihanshin-Kyuko-Dentsu (now Hankyu Corporation) station due to amalgamation.</e>
<cmt>Keihanshin-Kyuko-Dentsu としました。年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="54">
<j>1945年（昭和20年）9月15日 - 輸送混乱防止のため休止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Closed on Sept.15, 1945 to prevent potential transportation related complications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It closed on Sept.15, 1945 to prevent potential transportation-related complications.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 15, 1945: The station closed to prevent potential transportation-related complications.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="55">
<j>1946年（昭和21年）5月3日 - 営業再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 3, 1945, reopened for business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It reopened for business on May 3, 1945.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 3, 1945: The station reopened for business.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="56">
<j>1949年（昭和24年）12月1日 - 会社分離により京阪電気鉄道の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dec.1, 1949, became a Keihan Electric Railway station from corporate spinoff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 1, 1949 it became a Keihan Electric Railway station as the result of the corporate spinoff.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1, 1949: The station became a Keihan Electric Railway station as a result of the corporate spin-off.</e>
<cmt>spin-offとしました。年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="57">
<j>1950年（昭和25年）9月1日 - 特急停車駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sept. 1, 1950, became a station at which super express trains stop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 1, 1950 it became a station at which super express trains would stop.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 1, 1950: The station became a station at which super express trains would stop.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="58">
<j>1978年（昭和53年)10月1日 - 京都市電の全廃(9月30日)により京都市電との平面交差廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oct. 1, 1978, level crossings with Kyoto City trams disappear as a result of complete discontinuation (on Sept.30) of Kyoto City Trams.</e>
<cmt>交差の相手方の記述がありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1978 the level crossings with Kyoto City trams disappeared as a result of the complete discontinuation (on Sept. 30) of Kyoto City Trams.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1978: The level crossings with Kyoto City Trams disappeared as a result of the complete discontinuation (on September 30) of Kyoto City Trams.</e>
<cmt>Kyoto City Tramsとしました。年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="59">
<j>1984年（昭和59年）4月 - 地下化工事に伴い、線路を東側へ移動(疎水跡)、併せて三条行きホームを七条通り北側へ移動させ、七条通りを挟んで千鳥配置のホームを対抗式ホームへ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidental to commencement of underground works in April 1984, railway tracks were relocated to the east side (formerly a channel) and the platform for Sanjo relocated to the north on the opposite side of Shichijo-dori Street and platforms which used to be of zigzag configuration located on both sides of Shichijo-dori Street became platforms placed opposite each other with tracks in between.</e>
<cmt>実態不詳につき、あるいは誤解があるかもしれません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidental to the commencement of underground works in April 1984, the railway tracks were relocated to the east side (formerly a channel) and the platform for Sanjo was relocated to the north on the opposite side of Shichijo-dori Street; and platforms that once zigzagged on both sides of Shichijo-dori Street became platforms placed opposite each other with tracks in between.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1984: Incidental to the commencement of underground works, the railway tracks were relocated to the east side (formerly a channel) and the platform for Sanjo was relocated to the north on the opposite side of Shichijo-dori Street; and platforms that once zigzagged on both sides of Shichijo-dori Street became platforms placed opposite each other with tracks in between.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="60">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）5月24日 - 地下駅化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Underground station inaugurated on May 24, 1987.</e>
<cmt>”地下化”が限定的でなく、意味が明瞭ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The underground station was inaugurated on May 24, 1987.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 24, 1987: The underground station was inaugurated.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="61">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）7月15日 - 浸水事故で七条以北が終日運休、七条駅で折り返し運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operations north of Shichijo suspended whole day on July 15, 1987 due to inundation and shuttle service operated with Shichijo Station as turnaround station.</e>
<cmt>折り返し運転の七条駅の相手方駅名不詳。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Operations north of Shichijo were suspended for the entire day on July 15, 1987 due to inundation, and shuttle service operated with Shichijo Station as a turnaround station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 15, 1987: Operations north of Shichijo were suspended for the entire day due to inundation, and shuttle service operated with Shichijo Station as a turnaround station.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="62">
<j>1988年（昭和63年）5月10日 - 地下化工事竣工、地上線跡に川端通り開通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction works for conversion to a subway system completed on May 10, 1988 and land where former surface tracks existed was opened to the public as Kawabata-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction works for conversion to a subway system completed on May 10, 1988 and land where former surface tracks existed was opened to the public as Kawabata-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 10, 1988: Construction works for conversion to a subway system completed, and land where former surface tracks existed was opened to the public as Kawabata-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="63">
<j>1988年（昭和63年）9月1日 - 駅構内「終日禁煙」を実施。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">「No-smoking (throughout the day)」 within station premises put into effect on September 1, 1988.</e>
<cmt>英文に“終日”明記の必要性は？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A &quot;no smoking (throughout the day)&quot; rule was implemented within the station facilities on September 1, 1988.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1, 1988: The &apos;no smoking throughout the day&apos; rule was implemented within the station facilities.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="64">
<j>2008年（平成20年）3月　- 身障者対応エレベーター設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elevator facilities to support the handicapped installed in March, 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elevator facilities to support the handicapped were installed in March 2008.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 2008: Elevator facilities to support the handicapped were installed.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>京阪電気鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>京阪本線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>■K特急・■特急</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■K-Ltd. express・■Super express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■K-Ltd. express・■Super express</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">K-Ltd. Express/Super Express</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に・を/に変更しました。■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>丹波橋駅 - 七条駅 - 四条駅 (京阪)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tambabashi Station-Shichijo Station-Shijo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tambabashi Station-Shichijo Station-Shijo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanbabashi Station - Shichijo Station - Shijo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>space&quot;Tambabashi&quot;→&quot;Tanbabashi&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="69">
<j>■急行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Express train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Express train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Express</e>
<cmt>train削除■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="70">
<j>伏見稲荷駅 - 七条駅 - 五条駅 (京阪)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi-inari Station-Shichijo Station-Gojo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi-inari Station-Shichijo Station-Gojo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi-Inari Station - Shichijo Station - Gojo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>Inariとしました。 Space</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="71">
<j>■準急・■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">■Local express・■Local train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">■Local express・■Local train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local Express/Local</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に　普通はLocalとしました。・を/に変更しました。■を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="72">
<j>東福寺駅 - 七条駅 - 五条駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofukuji Station - Shichijo Station - Gojo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofukuji Station - Shichijo Station - Gojo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofukuji Station - Shichijo Station - Gojo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), SUCCESS(id:15934), Etopirica(id:32491), 天然ガス(id:98149), OwarinakiTabi(id:38610), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Wikipedianet(id:9608), Nsbtmsk(id:74877), Utsuda(id:605), Shinkansen(id:13703), Wideangle(id:100385), Kiyok(id:76023), Matsukaze(id:51778), Mooko(id:36162), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Unamu(id:14627), Mangos(id:10010), Hirotaro(id:1437), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Kurihaya(id:132524), 210.(id:9838), ASAMA501(id:91947), ちょろ(id:17218), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>