<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近鉄丹波橋駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station</e>
<cmt>公式ウェブでの駅名表記は&quot;Kintetsu-Tambabashi&quot;となっています。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近鉄丹波橋駅（きんてつたんばばしえき）は、京都府京都市伏見区桃山筒井伊賀東町にある、近畿日本鉄道近鉄京都線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Momoyama Tsutsui Iga Higashimachi, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station is a stop on Kintetsu Kyoto Line which is operated by Kinki Nippon Railway Co.,Ltd. (Kintetsu Corporation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station, located in Momoyama Tsutsui Iga Higashimachi, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line, which is operated by Kinki Nippon Railway Co., Ltd. (Kintetsu Corporation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station, located in Momoyama Tsutsui Iga Higashi-machi, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line, which is operated by Kinki Nippon Railway Co., Ltd. (Kintetsu Corporation).</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>京阪電気鉄道の丹波橋駅との乗り換え駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station is a stop to change trains between itself and Tanbabashi Station on Keihan Electric Railway (KER).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station is a stop at which passenger can change over to Tanbabashi Station on the Keihan Electric Railway (KER) or vice versa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station is a stop at which passenger can change over to Tanbabashi Station on the Keihan Electric Railway (KER) or vice versa.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>2002年から近鉄特急の停車駅となっているが、それ以前は年末年始の臨時特急のみの停車だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2002, Kintetsu Tanbabshi Station became a stop of the Kintetsu Limited Express train, but before that, merely the Special Limited Express service made a stop at this station at the beginning and the end of the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2002, Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station became a stop for the Kintetsu limited express train, but before that only the Special Limited Express service made stops at this station at the beginning and the end of the year.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2002, Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station became a stop for the Kintetsu limited express train, but before that only the Special Limited Express service made stops at this station at the beginning and the end of the year.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、1998年から2003年まで設定されていた快速急行の停車駅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And from 1998 to 2003, the Rapid Express made a stop at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period from 1998 to 2003, the rapid express made stops at this station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period from 1998 to 2003, the rapid express made stops at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>本項では近鉄丹波橋駅の前身である堀内駅に付いても記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article also explains Horiuchi Station that was precedent to Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article also describes Horiuchi Station, which preceded Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section also describes Horiuchi Station, which preceded Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。article →sectionに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>接続する鉄道路線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Connected Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Connected Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Connected Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>京阪電気鉄道 - 丹波橋駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway - Tanbabashi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway - Tanbabashi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway (KER): Tanbabashi Station</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。KERを追加しました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>京阪本線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure of the station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>相対式2面2線のプラットホームを持つ橋上駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station has two separate platforms &amp; two boarding areas, and the station building centers its functions on its second floor.</e>
<cmt>①「相対式2面2線のプラットホームを持つ」とは「相対式のプラットホーム２つ、乗り場を2つ持つ」という意味であり（WIKi 「プラットホーム」参照）、そこでは「プラットホーム」と「乗り場」を訳し分ける必要が生じるので、前者を&quot;platform&quot;後者を&quot;boarding area&quot;としました。　②「橋上駅」とは、「（改札口や乗車券売り場といった）その機能を2階部分に集中させた駅舎」のことであり（Wiki 「橋上駅」参照）、それを左でも訳したつもりです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station has two separate platforms and two boarding areas, and the station building centers its functions on the second floor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station has with two separate platforms that face each other with two sets of tracks running between, and the station building centers its functions on the second floor.</e>
<cmt>ホームの表現を変更しました（～platform with ～ tracksなど）Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ホーム有効長は6両。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The effective length of the platform is six car long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The effective length of the platform is equivalent to six train cars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The effective length of the platform is equivalent to six train cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>ホームとコンコースを結ぶエレベーターが設置されているが、出口には階段しかなく、ホーム南端にあるスロープか、京阪電鉄の丹波橋駅にあるエレベーターを利用することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An elevator exists between the platform and the concourse, but the station building has merely the stairs at its exits, so the disabled person including one in a wheelchair will use either the slope located at the southern end of the platform or the elevator built in KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>2行目の「階段しかなく」のあとに「車いすの利用者を含め身障者は」を補って訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An elevator is located between the platform and the concourse, but the station building has merely the stairs at its exits, so disabled persons (including those in wheelchairs) will use either the ramp at the southern end of the platform or the elevator provided in KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An elevator is located between the platform and the concourse, but the station building has merely the stairs at its exits, so disabled persons (including those in wheelchairs) will use either the ramp at the southern end of the platform or the elevator provided in KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>改札口は1ヶ所のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There merely exists one ticket gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is only one ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is only one ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>京阪電鉄の丹波橋駅とは連絡通路で結ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A passageway connects this station and KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A passageway interconnects this station and KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A passageway interconnects this station and KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。KERを追加しました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>自動改札機は東芝製が設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The manufacturer of the automatic ticket gate is Toshiba Social Infrastructure Systems Company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manufacturer of the automatic ticket gate is Toshiba Social Infrastructure Systems Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manufacturer of the automatic ticket gate is Toshiba.</e>
<cmt>Toshiba のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>赤い自動改札機（EG-2000）は出場時2枚一括処理、PiTaPa・ICOCAに対応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The red-colored ticket gate (EG-2000) can handle two IC cards at a time when a passenger gets out of it, and PiTaPa Card and ICOCA, both an IC card, are avilable for payment of railway fares at this ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>ICOCAは&quot;IC Operating Card&quot;の省略形であり、そこに既に&quot;Card&quot;が含まれていることから、PiTaPaと異なり英訳では&quot;Card&quot;を付していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The red-colored ticket gates (EG-2000) can handle two IC cards at a time when a passenger is exiting, and PiTaPa Card and ICOCA, both of which are IC cards, are available for payment of railway fares at this ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The red-colored ticket gates (EG-2000) can handle two IC cards at a time when a passenger is exiting, and PiTaPa Card and ICOCA, both of which are IC cards, are available for payment of railway fares at this ticket gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>全ての列車が停車する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All trains running on Kintetsu Kyoto Line make a stop at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All trains on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All trains on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line stop at this station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>特別急行券・定期乗車券とも購入可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can purchase both the limited express ticket and the commuter ticket.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Limited express and commuter tickets can be purchased here.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limited express and commuter tickets can be purchased here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="20">
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation of passengers&apos; use</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passenger usage statistics</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger use</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>2005年11月8日の調査結果によると、1日の利用客は52,365人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the research on November 8, 2005, the number of passengers a day at this station was 52,365.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a survey conducted on November 8, 2005, the number of passengers at the station was 52,365.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a survey conducted on November 8, 2005, the number of passengers at the station was 52,365.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この数字は...</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This figure was ranked as follows :</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This figure ranked the station as follows:</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This figure ranked the station as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="23">
<j>近鉄の全調査対象駅（323駅、但し調査当時の数）中、11位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all Kintetsu Corporation stations researched, which amounted to 323 at that time, Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station ranked the eleventh;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all Kintetsu Corporation stations researched (which amounted to 323 at that time), Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station ranked eleventh.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all Kintetsu Corporation stations researched (which amounted to 323 at that time), Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station ranked eleventh.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>京都線の駅（26駅、大和西大寺駅含む）の中では、3位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">of all stations on Kintetsu Kyoto Line, which amounted to 26 at that time including Yamato-Saidaiji Station, Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station ranked the third;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all stations on Kintetsu Kyoto Line (which amounted to 26 at that time, including Yamato-Saidaiji Station), Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station ranked third.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all stations on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line (which amounted to 26 at that time, including Yamato-Saidaiji Station), Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station ranked third.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Kintetsu Kyoto Line→the Kintetsu Kyoto Lineに変更しました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="25">
<j>京都府内の近鉄の駅（23駅）の中では、京都駅に次いで2位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">of all Kintetsu Corporation stations within Kyoto Prefecture, which amounted to 23 at that time, Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station was second only to Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all Kintetsu Corporation stations within Kyoto Prefecture (which amounted to 23 at the time), Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station was second only to Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all Kintetsu Corporation stations within Kyoto Prefecture (which amounted to 23 at the time), Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station was second only to Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="26">
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surroundings of the station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>伏見桃山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Momoyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Momoyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Momoyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>桓武天皇陵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanmu Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanmu Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanmu Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>京都教育大学附属幼稚園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kindergarten Attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kindergarten attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kindergarten attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>京都教育大学附属桃山小学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momoyama Elementary School Attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momoyama Elementary School, attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momoyama Elementary School, attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>京都教育大学附属桃山中学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momoyama Junior High School Attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momoyama Junior High School, attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momoyama Junior High School, attached to Kyoto University of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>京都府立桃山高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Momoyama Senior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Momoyama Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Momoyama Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>伏見京町北郵便局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Kyomachi-Kita post office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fushimi Kyomachi-Kita post office</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fushimi Kyomachi-Kita post office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bus stop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bus stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bus stop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>最寄バス停は、駅から徒歩5分の国道24号線沿いにある丹波橋通である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nearest bus stop to Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station is &quot;Tanbabashi-dori,&quot; which is a five minute walk from the station and faces National Highway No. 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nearest bus stop to Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station is &quot;Tanbabashi-dori,&quot; which is a five-minute walk from the station and faces National Highway No. 24.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nearest bus stop to Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station is &quot;Tanbabashi-dori,&quot; which is a five-minute walk from the station and faces National Highway No. 24.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>京都市営バス南8号系統：竹田駅 (京都府)東口行/横大路車庫行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus Route South No. 8 --For Takeda Station (Higashiguchi)/Yokooji Shako-mae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus Route South No. 8: For Takeda Station (Higashiguchi)/Yokooji Shako-mae</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus Route South No. 8: For Takeda Station (Kyoto Prefecture) Higashi-guchi (east exit)/Yokooji Shako-depot</e>
<cmt>京都府　を追加しました。Depot　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>1945年から1968年まで京阪電鉄の丹波橋駅に乗り入れ、相互直通運転を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1945 to 1968, the train of Kintetsu Kyoto Line directly connected with KER Tanbabashi Station, and the mutual extension operation was done.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1945 to 1968, the train of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line directly connected with KER Tanbabashi Station, and the mutual extension operation was conducted.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1945 to 1968, the train of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line directly connected with KER Tanbabashi Station, and the mutual extension operation was conducted.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>近鉄京都線の架線電圧1500V昇圧（1969年実施）を控え、駅構内の平面交差が列車増発の差し支えになることから京阪電鉄との共同使用をやめ、かつての堀内駅跡に近鉄丹波橋駅を設置して両路線を分離し、相互直通運転を廃止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In consideration of boosting the trolley voltage to 1500V, which was implemented in 1969, Kintetsu Kyoto Line ended its communal use of Tanbabashi Station with KER because the grade crossing on the station premises became the obstacle to the increase of its train service, and instead, Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station was set up independently on the site of former Horiuchi Station, so Kintetsu Kyoto Line and Keihan Main Line were separated, and the mutual extension operation was ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In consideration of the 1969 boost in trolley voltage to 1500V, the Kintetsu Kyoto Line ended its communal use of Tanbabashi Station with KER because the grade crossing on the station premises became the obstacle to the increasing its train service, and instead Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station was set up independently on the site of the former Horiuchi Station, so the Kintetsu Kyoto Line and Keihan Main Line were separated and the mutual extension operation was ended.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In consideration of the 1969 boost in trolley voltage to 1500V, the Kintetsu Kyoto Line ended its communal use of Tanbabashi Station with KER because the grade crossing on the station premises became the obstacle to the increasing of its train service, and instead Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station was set up independently on the site of the former Horiuchi Station, so the Kintetsu Kyoto Line and Keihan Main Line were separated and the mutual extension operation was ended.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>相互直通運転廃止から約10年間は双方の駅に相手駅の列車の案内装置が設置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For about ten years after the end of the mutual extension operation, both stations were equipped with the devices for guidance about the train service of each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For about ten years after the end of the mutual extension operation, both stations were equipped with devices for mutual guidance regarding their respective train services.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For about ten years after the end of the mutual extension operation, both stations were equipped with devices for mutual guidance regarding their respective train services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）11月15日 奈良電気鉄道京都～桃山御陵前間開通時に堀内駅として開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 15, 1928 - Nara Electric Railway began its operation in the section between Kyoto Station and Momoyamagoryomae Station, and at the same time Horiuchi Station opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 15, 1928: Nara Electric Railway began operating in the section between Kyoto Station and Momoyamagoryomae Station, and concurrently Horiuchi Station opened.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 15, 1928: Nara Electric Railway began operating in the section between Kyoto Station and Momoyamagoryomae Station, and concurrently Horiuchi Station opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>1945年（昭和20年）12月21日 京阪電気鉄道の丹波橋駅に乗り入れ開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 21, 1945 - The train of Kintetsu Kyoto Line began the direct connection with KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 21, 1945: The train of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line began the direct connection with KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 21, 1945: The train of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line began the direct connection with KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>堀内駅廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Horiuchi Station was closed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horiuchi Station was closed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horiuchi Station was closed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="43">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）10月1日 奈良電気鉄道が近畿日本鉄道に合併。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1, 1963 - Nara Electric Railway Co.,Ltd. was absorbed into Kinki Nippon Railway Co.,Ltd. (Kintetsu Corporation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1, 1963: Nara Electric Railway Co., Ltd., was absorbed into Kinki Nippon Railway Co., Ltd. (Kintetsu Corporation).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1, 1963: Nara Electric Railway Co., Ltd., was absorbed into Kinki Nippon Railway Co., Ltd. (Kintetsu Corporation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="44">
<j>1967年（昭和42年）3月29日 堀内駅跡に近鉄京都線専用ホーム・線路設置（約1年は丹波橋・（現）近鉄丹波橋の併用）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 29, 1967 - On the site of Horiuchi Station, the platform &amp; the track both for Kintetsu Kyoto Line only were established; for about a year after that, KER Tanbabashi Station &amp; the present Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station were both still used by the train of Kinki Nippon Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 29, 1967: On the site of Horiuchi Station, the platform and track for the Kintetsu Kyoto Line only were established; for about a year after that, KER Tanbabashi Station and the present Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station were both used by the train of the Kinki Nippon Railway.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 29, 1967: On the site of Horiuchi Station, the platform and track for the Kintetsu Kyoto Line only were established; for about a year after that, KER Tanbabashi Station and the present Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station were both used by the train of the Kinki Nippon Railway.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>京阪丹波橋駅への連絡通路も同時に設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And at the same time, the passageway between these two stations was also established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the passageway between these two stations was established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the passageway between these two stations was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="46">
<j>1968年（昭和43年）12月20日 京阪電気鉄道の丹波橋駅への乗り入れ廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 20, 1968 - The train of Kinki Nippon Railway ended the direct connection with KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 20, 1968: The train of the Kinki Nippon Railway ended its direct connection with KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 20, 1968: The train of the Kinki Nippon Railway ended its direct connection with KER Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。12月　に修正しました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>丹波橋駅を近畿日本丹波橋駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the present Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station, which was also named &quot;Tanbabashi Station&quot; until then, was renamed &quot;Kinki Nippon Tanbabashi Station.&quot;</e>
<cmt>京阪電気鉄道の丹波橋駅との混乱を避けるため「（現）近鉄丹波橋駅も、それまでは『丹波橋駅』と呼ばれていた」（Wiki 「近鉄京都線」・年表・1967年の記述参照）ことを補っています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the present Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station, which was also called &quot;Tanbabashi Station&quot; until then, was renamed as &quot;Kinki Nippon Tanbabashi Station.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the present Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station, which was also called &quot;Tanbabashi Station&quot; until then, was renamed as &quot;Kinki Nippon Tanbabashi Station.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="48">
<j>1970年（昭和45年）3月1日 近畿日本丹波橋駅を近鉄丹波橋駅に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 1, 1970 - &quot;Kinki Nippon Tanbabashi Station&quot; was renamed &quot;Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 1, 1970: &quot;Kinki Nippon Tanbabashi Station&quot; was renamed as &quot;Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1, 1970: &quot;Kinki Nippon Tanbabashi Station&quot; was renamed as &quot;Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="49">
<j>1998年（平成10年）3月17日 同日のダイヤ変更で新設された京都線快速急行の停車駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 17, 1998 - With the timetable revised on this date, the newly introduced Rapid Express of Kintetsu Kyoto Line began to make a stop at Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 17, 1998: With the timetable revision implemented on this date, the newly introduced rapid express of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line began stopping at Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 17, 1998: With the timetable revision implemented on this date, the newly introduced rapid express of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line began stopping at Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="50">
<j>2002年（平成14年）3月20日 特急停車駅に昇格。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 20, 2002 - Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station was upgraded to be the station which the Limited Express makes a stop at.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 20, 2002: Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station was upgraded to the status of a facility at which the limited express would stop.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 20, 2002: Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station was upgraded to the status of a facility at which the limited express would stop.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="51">
<j>2003年（平成15年）3月6日 同日のダイヤ変更により京都線快速急行廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 6, 2003 - With the timetable revised on this date, the operation of the Rapid Express of Kintetsu Kyoto Line was ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 6, 2003: With the timetable revision implemented on this date, the operation of the rapid express of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line ceased.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6, 2003: With the timetable revision implemented on this date, the operation of the rapid express of the Kintetsu Kyoto Line ceased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="52">
<j>2007年（平成19年）4月1日 PiTaPa使用開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 2007 - PiTaPa Card was made available at Kintetsu Tanbabshi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 2007: PiTaPa Card was made available at Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 2007: PiTaPa Card became usable at Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="53">
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next station</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="54">
<j>近畿日本鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinki Nippon Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinki Nippon Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinki Nippon Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>京都線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>近鉄特急</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintetsu Limited Express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kintetsu limited express</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintetsu Limited Express</e>
<cmt>大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>■急行・■準急（準急は当駅以南各駅に停車）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Express/ Semi-express : The Semi-express service makes a stop at every station from Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station and southward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Express/ Semi-express: The semi-express service makes a stop at every station from Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station southward.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Express/Semi-express: The semi-express service makes a stop at every station from Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station southward.</e>
<cmt>■を削除しました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>竹田駅 (京都府) - 近鉄丹波橋駅 - 桃山御陵前駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeda Station (in Kyoto Prefecture) - Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station - Momoyamagoryomae Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeda Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station - Momoyamagoryomae Station</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeda Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station - Momoyamagoryomae Station</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>■普通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>伏見駅 (京都府) - 近鉄丹波橋駅 - 桃山御陵前駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Station (in Kyoto Prefecture) - Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station - Momoyamagoryomae Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Kintetsu Tanbabashi Station - Momoyamagoryomae Station</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Kintetsu-Tanbabashi Station - Momoyamagoryomae Station</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashi　としました。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 東京特許許可局(id:7229), Bakkai(id:7233), Basedview(id:182448), 城山(id:104901), Etopirica(id:32491), UE-PON2600(id:18149), Sat.K(id:3751), KARS(id:43022), Ikaxer(id:61759), Memeja(id:110500), Utsuda(id:605), Aska-sacra(id:8180), Shinkansen(id:13703), Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), Sunen(id:10700), Goki(id:7107), Unamu(id:14627), Hirotaro(id:1437), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Mipu(id:5360), ジャスト宣言(id:33592), Hirohisat(id:128431), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>