<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Electric Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Electric Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都鉄道（きょうとてつどう）は、1893年（明治26年）に設立された民営鉄道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Electric Railway is a private rail company established in 1893.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Electric Railway is a private rail company established in 1893.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Electric Railway is a private rail company established in 1893.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現在の山陰本線の前身にあたる路線の一部を建設、運営した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former rail line from current San&apos;in Main Line was partly built and started its operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former rail line from current San&apos;in Main Line was partly built and started its operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former rail line from current Sanin Main Line was partly built and started its operation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;San&apos;in&quot;→&quot;Sanin&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>社長は田中源太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company president is Gentaro TANAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company president is Gentaro TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company president is Gentaro TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>明治時代、京都市に次ぐ京都府第二の都市であり、日本海側では貴重な商港を有する舞鶴市までの鉄道敷設が緊急の課題となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji period it was an important issue to have a railroad facilities to Maizuru City, the second largest city followed by Kyoto City in Kyoto-fu, having a valuable port on Japan sea/the Sea of Japan side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period it was an important issue to have railroad facilities to Maizuru City, the second-largest city followed by Kyoto City in Kyoto-fu, which had a valuable port on the Sea of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period it was an important issue to have railroad facilities to Maizuru City, the second-largest city (followed by Kyoto City in Kyoto Prefecture), which had a valuable commercial port on the Sea of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Prefecture, commercial portとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そこで田中源太郎、浜岡光哲らが発起人となり京都から舞鶴市までの鉄路敷設を目的に会社が設立され、1895年（明治28年）に京都駅から綾部市を経て、舞鶴に至る鉄道免許を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gentaro TANAKA and Kotetsu HAMAOKA established a company to lay railroad from Kyoto to Maizuru City, the rail license was granted to lay a railroad from Kyoto Station to Maizuru via Ayabe City in 1895.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gentaro TANAKA and Kotetsu HAMAOKA established a company to lay a railroad from Kyoto to Maizuru City, and in 1895 the rail license was granted to lay a railroad from Kyoto Station to Maizuru via Ayabe City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gentaro TANAKA and Kotetsu HAMAOKA established a company to lay a railroad from Kyoto to Maizuru City, and in 1895 the rail license was granted to lay a railroad from Kyoto Station to Maizuru via Ayabe City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、舞鶴への鉄道敷設計画は京都鉄道のほか、阪鶴鉄道（大阪～福知山～舞鶴）、摂丹鉄道（大阪～園部～舞鶴）で競合するものであり、舞鶴への鉄道免許は熱心な設置運動の賜物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To grant the rail license to Maizuru was the result of putting a big effort to do so, as there were other companies competing against Kyoto Electric Railway to lay a railroad to Maizuru such as Hankaku Railway/Hankaku Tetsudo (Osaka-Fukuchiyama-Maizuru), Setsutan Railway/Setsutan Tetsudo. (Osaka-Sonobe-Maizuru)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The granting of a rail license to Maizuru was the result of a great effort, since there were other companies competing against Kyoto Electric Railway to lay a railroad to Maizuru, such as Hankaku Railway/Hankaku Tetsudo (Osaka-Fukuchiyama-Maizuru) and Setsutan Railway/Setsutan Tetsudo (Osaka-Sonobe-Maizuru).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The granting of a rail license to Maizuru was the result of a great effort, since there were other companies competing against Kyoto Electric Railway to lay a railroad to Maizuru, such as Hankaku Railway/Hankaku Tetsudo (Osaka-Fukuchiyama-Maizuru) and Setsutan Railway/Setsutan Tetsudo (Osaka-Sonobe-Maizuru).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>断崖絶壁に線路を通し、トンネル8箇所、橋梁は50箇所を越える保津峡の難工事も苦心の末、1900年（明治33年）に京都～園部駅間が開業するが、園部以北へは資金難のため工事が遅々として進まず、政府は舞鶴鎮守府開庁に続き、京都から舞鶴へ通じる鉄道の建設は国策遂行上必要不可欠とし、未成部分の鉄道免許を取り消し、政府は自らの手で京都から舞鶴へ通じる鉄道を建設を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The railroad was put through sheer cliff, after the complicated construction work to build more than fifty bridges at Hozukyo Valley finished, the sector between Kyoto and Sonobe Station opened in 1900, the construction work north of Sonobe did not proceed due to cash flow problem, when Maizuru army base (or Maizuru navy base) opened the government decided it is necessary to lay railroad from Kyoto to Maizuru to carry out national policy, the license was taken away by the government for them to finish the work to lay railroad by themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railroad was put through sheer cliff, and after the complicated construction work to build more than 50 bridges at Hozukyo Valley finished, the sector between Kyoto and Sonobe Station opened in 1900; however, the construction work north of Sonobe did not proceed due to a cash-flow problem, when the Maizuru army base (or Maizuru naval base) opened, the government decided it was necessary to lay railroad from Kyoto to Maizuru in order to carry out national policy, so the license was taken away by the government and it became necessary to finish the work of laying the railroad by themselves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The railroad was put through a sheer cliff, and once the complicated construction work to build eight tunnels and more than 50 bridges at Hozukyo Valley was finished, the sector between Kyoto and Sonobe Station opened in 1900; however, the construction work north of Sonobe did not proceed due to a cash-flow problem, and when the Maizuru army base (or Maizuru naval base) opened, the government decided it was necessary to lay railroad from Kyoto to Maizuru in order to carry out national policy, took away the rail license and started the work to finish laying the railroad by itself.</e>
<cmt>eight tunnels 追加　一部文章修正（後半）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そして1910年（明治43年）に園部～綾部間の鉄道を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rail work completed between Sonobe and Ayabe in 1910.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rail work was completed between Sonobe and Ayabe in 1910.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rail work was completed between Sonobe and Ayabe in 1910.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>京都～園部間で営業を続けていた京都鉄道も1906年（明治39年）公布の鉄道国有法により1907年（明治40年）に阪鶴鉄道とともに国に買収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Electric Railway remained running operation between Kyoto and Sonobe, however after the announcement of Japanese Railway Nationalization Act in 1906, the Kyoto Electric Railway was bought up by the government together with Hankaku Railway (阪鶴鉄道) /Hankaku Tetsudo in 1907.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Electric Railway remained in operation between Kyoto and Sonobe, but the year after the announcement of the Japanese Railway Nationalization Act of 1906 the Kyoto Electric Railway was bought up by the government together with Hankaku Railway (阪鶴鉄道) /Hankaku Tetsudo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Electric Railway remained in operation between Kyoto and Sonobe, but the year after the announcement of the Japanese Railway Nationalization Act of 1906 the Kyoto Electric Railway was bought up by the government together with Hankaku Railway/Hankaku Tetsudo in 1907.</e>
<cmt>(阪鶴鉄道)削除in 1907 補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>1904年に本社屋を兼ねて造られた二条駅の駅舎は日本最古の木造駅舎で、1996年の同駅の高架化に伴い梅小路蒸気機関車館に移築され、資料展示館として利用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nijo Station post-house is one of the oldest in Japan built in 1904, which was used as an office, it was then moved to Umekoji Steam Locomotive Museum as it was to be built an elevated railroad at the same station, currently being used as a material museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nijo Station post house is one of the oldest in Japan (built in 1904); it was used as an office, but eventually it was moved to the Umekoji Steam Locomotive Museum as there was to be built an elevated railroad at the same station, which is currently used as a museum for materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijo Station is one of the oldest wooden-constructed post houses in Japan (built in 1904); it was used as an office, but eventually it was moved to the Umekoji Steam Locomotive Museum as there was to be built an elevated railroad at the same station in 1996, which is currently used as a museum for materials.</e>
<cmt>wooden-constructed追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporate history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corporate history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>既出ファイルと統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>1893年（明治26年）　設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1893.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established in 1893.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1893: It was established.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>京都市から舞鶴市までの鉄道敷設を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aim was to lay tracks between Kyoto City to Maizuru City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aim was to lay tracks between Kyoto City and Maizuru City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aim was to lay tracks between Kyoto City and Maizuru City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>1897年（明治30年）2月15日　二条駅～嵯峨嵐山駅間開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The line between Nijo Station and Saga Arashiyama Station opened on 15th February 1897.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The line between Nijo Station and Saga Arashiyama Station opened on February 15, 1897.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 15, 1897: The line between Nijo Station and Saga-Arashiyama Station opened.</e>
<cmt>Saga-Arashiyamaとしました。年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>二条駅、嵯峨駅開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijo Station and Saga Station established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijo Station and Saga Station were established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijo Station and Saga Station were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>1897年4月27日　大宮～二条間延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 27th April 1897 the stretching operation between Omiya Station and Nijo Station commenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 27, 1897 the extension work between Omiya Station and Nijo Station commenced.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 27, 1897: The extension work between Omiya Station and Nijo Station commenced.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大宮駅、丹波口駅開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omiya Station and Tanbaguchi Station established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omiya Station and Tanbaguchi Station were established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omiya Station and Tanbaguchi Station were established.</e>
<cmt>Tambaguchiとしました。&quot;Tambaguchi&quot;→&quot;Tanbaguchi&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>1897年11月16日　京都駅～大宮間延伸開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stretching operation between Kyoto Station and Omiya Station commenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stretching operation between Kyoto Station and Omiya Station commenced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 16, 1897: The extension work between Kyoto Station and Omiya Station commenced.</e>
<cmt>年号追加年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>鉄道作業局の京都駅乗り入れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ministry of Railway entered into Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Railways entered into Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Railways entered into Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>1898年（明治31年）1月1日　花園駅開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 1st January 1898 Hanazono Station was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1, 1898, Hanazono Station was established.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 1, 1898: Hanazono Station was established.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>1899年（明治32年）8月1日　大宮駅閉鎖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 1st August 1899 Omiya Station closed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1899, Omiya Station closed.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1899: Omiya Station closed.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>1899年8月15日　二条～園部駅間延伸開業し全通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 15th August 1899 the stretching operation completed between Nijo Station and Sonobe Station and opened the whole line for service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, 1899 the extension work was completed between Nijo Station and Sonobe Station and the entire line was opened for service.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 15, 1899: The extension work was completed between Nijo Station and Sonobe Station and the entire line was opened for service.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>亀岡駅、八木駅、園部駅開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kameoka Station, Yagi Station and Sonobe Station established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kameoka Station, Yagi Station and Sonobe Station were established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameoka Station, Yagi Station and Sonobe Station were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>1905年（明治38年）1月15日　大宮駅再開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 15th January 1905 Omiya Station re-established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 15, 1905, Omiya Station was re-established.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 15, 1905: Omiya Station was re-established.</e>
<cmt>年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>1907年（明治40年）8月1日　国有化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1st August 1907 Kyoto Electric Rail was nationalized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Electric Rail was nationalized on August 1, 1907.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1, 1907: Kyoto Electric Railway was nationalized.</e>
<cmt>Railwayとしました。年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="25">
<j>1909年（明治43年）10月12日　線路名称制定「京都線」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 12th October 1909 the name of the rail track was established as &quot;Kyoto Line&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the rail track was established as the &quot;Kyoto Line&quot; on October 12, 1909.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 12, 1909: The name of the rail track was established as the &apos;Kyoto Line.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正年表表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>路線・駅一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The list of rail track and stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The list of rail track and stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The list of rail track and stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>国有化直前の1907年7月31日現在の路線及び駅名を記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are the current name of rail tracks and stations as of 31st July 1907, just before the line was nationalized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were the current names of the rail tracks and stations as of July 31, 1907, just before the line was nationalized.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were the names of the rail tracks and stations as of July 31, 1907, just before the line was nationalized.</e>
<cmt>current削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>京都～園部（22.2M35.73km）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto - Sonobe (22.2M35.73km)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto - Sonobe (22.2M35.73km)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto - Sonobe (22.2M35.73km)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>京都駅 - 大宮駅 - 丹波口駅 - 二条駅 - 花園駅 (京都府) - 嵯峨嵐山駅 - 亀岡駅 - 八木駅 - 園部駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Omiya Station - Tanbaguchi Station - Nijo Station - Hanazono Station (Kyoto-fu) - Saga Arashiyama Station - Kameoka Station - Yagi Station - Sonobe Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Station - Omiya Station - Tanbaguchi Station - Nijo Station - Hanazono Station (Kyoto-fu) - Saga Arashiyama Station - Kameoka Station - Yagi Station - Sonobe Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Station - Omiya Station - Tanbaguchi Station - Nijo Station - Hanazono Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Saga-Arashiyama Station - Kameoka Station - Yagi Station - Sonobe Station</e>
<cmt>(Kyoto Prefecture) としました。&quot;Tambaguchi&quot;→&quot;Tanbaguchi&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Carriage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Carriage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling Stock</e>
<cmt>既出記事と統一</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>蒸気機関車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Steam trains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Steam trains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Steam trains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>形式3（1，2） - 1894年英ナスミス・ウィルソン社製・軸配置0-6-0(C)タンク機関車 - 2は1895年（開業前）に台湾総督府鉄道に譲渡と推定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style 3 (1,2) - Made by Nasmyth, Wilson &amp; Co. Ltd in England in 1894, the wheel arrangement 0-6-0 (C) tank locomotive - it is presumed 2 was given to Taiwan Governor-General Railway in 1895. (before starting the operation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style 3 (1, 2) - Made by Nasmyth, Wilson &amp; Co. Ltd. in England in 1894, the wheel arrangement 0-6-0 (C) tank locomotive - it is presumed that two were given to the Taiwan Governor-General Railway in 1895 (before starting the operation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style 3 (nos. 1, 2) - Made by Nasmyth, Wilson &amp; Co., Ltd. in England in 1894, the wheel arrangement 0-6-0 (C) tank locomotive - it is presumed that No. 2 was given to the Taiwan Governor-General Railway in 1895 (before operations began).</e>
<cmt>Co., Ltd.としました No. 2としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1の国有化後は、国鉄1100形蒸気機関車（1111）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After No.1 nationalized it became JNR steam locomotive Type 1100. (1111)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After No. 1 nationalized it became JNR steam locomotive type 1100. (1111).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kyoto Electric Railway was nationalized No. 1 became JNR steam locomotive type 1100 (1111).</e>
<cmt>京都鉄道の国有化後　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>形式1（2（2代），6，7） - 1898年、1903年英ナスミス・ウィルソン社製・軸配置2-4-2(1B1)タンク機→鉄道院国鉄400形蒸気機関車（643～645）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style 1 (2 (2 dai), 6,7) - Made by Nasmyth, Wilson &amp; Co. Ltd. in 1898, 1903 in England, the wheel arrangement 2-4-2 (1B1) tank locomotive -Railway Bureau JNR steam locomotive Type 400 (643-645)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style 1 (2 (2 dai), 6, 7) - Made by Nasmyth, Wilson &amp; Co. Ltd. in 1898, 1903 in England, the wheel arrangement 2-4-2 (1B1) tank locomotive - Railway Bureau JNR steam locomotive type 400 (643-645)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style 1 (No. 2 (second generation), 6, 7) - Made by Nasmyth, Wilson &amp; Co., Ltd. in 1898, 1903 in England, the wheel arrangement 2-4-2 (1B1) tank locomotive→Railway Bureau JNR steam locomotive type 400 (643-645)</e>
<cmt>Co., Ltd.としました 2代をsecond generationとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>形式2（3） - 1894年英ダブス社製・軸配置2-4-2(1B1)タンク機→鉄道院国鉄400形蒸気機関車（509）※官設鉄道から割譲？</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style 2 (3) - Made by Dubs &amp; Co in 1894 in England, the wheel arrangement 2-4-2 (1B1) tank locomotive - Railway Bureau JNR steam locomotive Type 400 (509), ※it was given from government own railway?)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style 2 (3) - Made by Dubs &amp; Co. in 1894 in England, the wheel arrangement 2-4-2 (1B1) tank locomotive - Railway Bureau JNR steam locomotive Type 400 (509), ※it was given from the government&apos;s own railway?)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style 2 (No. 3) - Made by Dubs &amp; Co. in 1894 in England, the wheel arrangement 2-4-2 (1B1) tank locomotive→Railway Bureau JNR steam locomotive Type 400 (509), ※it was given from the government&apos;s own railway?)</e>
<cmt>No.3としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>形式4（4，5） - 1897年米ピッツバーグ社製・軸配置4-4-0(2B)テンダー機関車 - 1905年山陽鉄道に譲渡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style (4,5) - Made by Pittsburgh Locomotive and Car Works in 1897 in United States, the wheel arrangement 4-4-0 (2B) tender engine (tender locomotive) - it was given to San&apos;yo Railway Company in 1905.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style (4, 5) - Made by Pittsburgh Locomotive and Car Works in 1897 in the United States, the wheel arrangement 4-4-0 (2B) tender engine (tender locomotive) - it was given to San&apos;yo Railway Company in 1905.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style 4 (nos. 4, 5) - Made by Pittsburgh Locomotive and Car Works in 1897 in the United States, the wheel arrangement 4-4-0 (2B) tender engine (tender locomotive)→it was given to Sanyo Railway Company in 1905.</e>
<cmt>Style 4としました。&quot;San&apos;yo&quot;→&quot;Sanyo&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>国有化後国鉄5200形蒸気機関車（5200，5201）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After it was nationalized it became JNR steam locomotive Type 5200 (5200, 5201)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After it was nationalized it became JNR steam locomotive type 5200 (5200, 5201).</e>
<cmt>case, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kyoto Electric Railway was nationalized it became JNR steam locomotive type 5200 (5200, 5201).</e>
<cmt>京都鉄道の国有化後　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Bakkai(id:7233), コタルス(id:143135), Cozy(id:132), Kone(id:377), Safkan(id:423), 210.(id:9838), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Mujaki(id:19193), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>