<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>K特急</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;K Limited Express (K-tokkyu)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu)&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>K特急（Kとっきゅう）は2003年に設定された京阪電気鉄道の列車種別の1つで、同社では最上位種別に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduced in 2003, &quot;K-tokkyu&quot; is a type of trains owned by Keihan Electric Railway Co.,Ltd, constituting the best type of trains in the company.</e>
<cmt>次の文章との関係上、「K特急」はローマ字表記にしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduced in 2003, &quot;K-tokkyu&quot; is a type of train owned by Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd., and represents the best type offered by the company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduced in 2003, &quot;K-tokkyu&quot; is a type of train owned by Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd., and represents the best type offered by the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>英文表記は「K-Ltd.Express」であり、「K」は公式には斜体で「K」と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its English translation is &quot;K Limited Express,&quot; and the letter &quot;K&quot; is formally written in italics (&quot;K&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its English translation is &quot;K-Limited Express,&quot; and the letter &quot;K&quot; is formally written in italics (&quot;K&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its English translation is &apos;K-Limited Express,&apos; and the letter &apos;K&apos; is formally written in italics (&apos;K&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>運行区間は出町柳駅-淀屋橋駅間と、私市駅→淀屋橋駅間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">K Limited Express is operated between Demachiyanagi Station and Yodoyabashi Station, and it is also operated from Kisaichi Station to Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The K-Limited Express is operated between Demachiyanagi Station and Yodoyabashi Station, and is also operated from Kisaichi Station to Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The K-Limited Express is operated between Demachiyanagi Station and Yodoyabashi Station, and is also operated from Kisaichi Station to Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この列車は京阪間直通通勤客向けに設定されているため、平日は始発K特急～朝ラッシュ時と夕方ラッシュ時～最終K特急まで30往復前後設定されているのに対し、土・休日は1本も無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This train is operated for the direct commuters between Kyoto and Osaka, so that on weekdays the round-trip train services are provided until the end of morning rush hour &amp; after the beginning of evening rush hour, totaling up about 30 round-trip services, but on weekends and holidays, there is no service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This train is operated for direct commuters between Kyoto and Osaka, so that on weekdays the round-trip train services are provided until the end of the morning rush hour and after the beginning of the evening rush hour, totaling approximately 30 round-trip services; however, on weekends and holidays there is no service.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This train is operated for direct commuters between Kyoto and Osaka, so that on weekdays the round-trip train services are provided until the end of the morning rush hour and after the beginning of the evening rush hour, totaling approximately 30 round-trip services; however, on weekends and holidays there is no service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>平日朝のK特急には女性専用車両が出町柳寄りの1両に設定されている（ただし、「おりひめ」を除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the weekday morning, there is a car for women only within K Limited Express (except for &quot;Orihime&quot; mentioned below), which is placed on the nearer side of the train to Demachiyanagi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the weekday mornings there is a car for women only within the K-Limited Express (except for &quot;Orihime&quot; mentioned below), which is placed on side of the train nearer to Demachiyanagi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the weekday mornings there is a car for women only within the K-Limited Express (except for &apos;Orihime&apos; mentioned below), which is placed on side of the train nearer to Demachiyanagi Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、朝に運転される淀屋橋行は枚方市駅にも停車する（この列車には列車番号の頭部に「B」を付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The train service operated in the morning for Yodoyabashi Station makes a stop at Hirakatashi Station; at the head of its train number, the letter &quot;B&quot; is attached;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The train service operated in the morning for Yodoyabashi Station makes a stop at Hirakatashi Station; the letter &quot;B&quot; is attached at the head of its train number;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The train service operated in the morning for Yodoyabashi Station makes a stop at Hirakatashi Station; the letter &apos;B&apos; is attached at the head of its train number;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>他のK特急は「A」である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">about the other trains, the letter &quot;A&quot; is attached at their heads of their train number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">for the other trains, the letter &quot;A&quot; is attached at the head of the train number.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">for the other trains, the letter &apos;A&apos; is attached at the head of the train number.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>「K」の意味は「京阪（電気鉄道）」(KEIHAN)の意味の「K」とされているが、当種別の位置付けから「快速特急（かいそくとっきゅう）」の「K」と見なす者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say the letter &quot;K&quot; in &quot;K Limited Express&quot; symbolizes &quot;Keihan (Electric Railway),&quot; but others say it symbolizes &quot;Kaisoku Tokkyu&quot; (Rapid Limited Express) as the type of the train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say the letter &quot;K&quot; in &quot;K-Limited Express&quot; symbolizes &quot;Keihan (Electric Railway),&quot; but others say it symbolizes &quot;Kaisoku Tokkyu&quot; (rapid limited express) as the type of train.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say the letter &apos;K&apos; in &apos;K-Limited Express&apos; symbolizes &apos;Keihan (Electric Railway),&apos; but others say it symbolizes &apos;Kaisoku Tokkyu&apos; (rapid limited express) as the type of train.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>又交野線直通K特急「おりひめ」の「K」は「交野市・私市」の頭文字の「K」と解釈している書籍も存在する（これは京阪間直通ではないため）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And there is also a book that says the letter &quot;K&quot; in &quot;K Limited Express Orihime,&quot; which directly connects with Katano Line, symbolizes &quot;Katanoshi Station&quot; or &quot;Kisaichi Station&quot;; this is because &quot;K Limited Express Orihime&quot; is not the through train between &quot;Kei&quot; (Kyoto) and &quot;Han&quot; (Osaka).</e>
<cmt>星座の「おりひめ」と区別し特急の名前であることを明確にするために、英訳では引用符を「K特急」の部分から付しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, a book asserts that the letter &quot;K&quot; in &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime,&quot; directly connects it with the Katano Line, symbolizing either &quot;Katanoshi Station&quot; or &quot;Kisaichi Station&quot;; this is because &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; isn&apos;t the through train between &quot;Kei&quot; (Kyoto) and &quot;Han&quot; (Osaka).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a book asserts that the letter &apos;K&apos; in &apos;K-Limited Express Orihime,&apos; which directly connects it with the Katano Line, symbolizes either &apos;Katanoshi Station&apos; or &apos;Kisaichi Station&apos;; this is because &apos;K-Limited Express Orihime&apos; isn&apos;t the through train between &apos;Kei&apos; (Kyoto) and &apos;Han&apos; (Osaka).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このように複数の意味を持たせていることから、実質的には、朝上りの枚方市停車パターンの便(通勤特急に相当)とそれ以外の便(快速特急に相当)を一括りにして、ひとつの種別として運用されているものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having these various meanings, K Limited Express in fact seems to lump the up train service in the morning that makes a stop at Hirakatashi Station, which constitutes the commuter limited express, together with the other train service, which constitutes the rapid limited express, thereby constituting one type of trains in operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having these various meanings, K-Limited Express seems to lump the up-train service in the morning that makes a stop at Hirakatashi Station, which constitutes a commuter limited express, together with the other train service that constitutes a rapid limited express, thus constituting one type of train in operation.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having these various meanings, K-Limited Express seems to lump the inbound-train service in the morning that makes a stop at Hirakatashi Station, which constitutes a commuter limited express, together with the other train service that constitutes a rapid limited express, thus constituting one type of train in operation.</e>
<cmt>上り→inbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>本項では主に列車種別面での記載を中心とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this article, the description of K Limited Express is mainly about its type of trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this article, the description of K-Limited Express is mainly in regard to the type of train.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this section, the description of K-Limited Express is mainly in regard to the type of train.</e>
<cmt>article→sectionに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>歴史関連は京阪特急を参照されたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the description related to its history, please refer to the article of &quot;Keihan Tokkyu (Keihan Limited Express).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For information on the description of its history, please refer to the article of &quot;Keihan Tokkyu (Keihan Limited Express).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For information on the description of its history, please refer to the article of &quot;Keihan Tokkyu (Keihan Limited Express).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>設定経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction process of K Limited Express</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction process of the K-Limited Express</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction process of the K-Limited Express</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>2003年9月6日のダイヤ改正で京阪特急停車駅を追加した際、平日（昼間時を除く）に限り従来の特急停車駅で運転する特急も残すことになり、この列車には新種別を設定する必要が出て来たことから設定されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 6, 2003, with the timetable revised, the number of stations at which Keihan Limited Express made a stop was increased, but some limited express services were decided to continue their conventional operation just on weekdays (not in operation during the daytime), so these services needed to be categorized as a new type of trains, and this was why K Limited Express was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 6, 2003, with the timetable revision, there was an increase in the number of stations at which the Keihan Limited Express stopped, but it was decided that some limited express services should continue the conventional operation only on weekdays (not in operation during the daytime), so these services had to be categorized as a new type of train, which is why the K-Limited Express was introduced.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 6, 2003, with the timetable revision, there was an increase in the number of stations at which the Keihan Limited Express stopped, but it was decided that some limited express services should continue the conventional operation only on weekdays (not in operation during the daytime), so these services had to be categorized as a new type of train, which is why the K-Limited Express was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため公式にはいちおう新種別と発表されているが実質的には種別名の変更である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So K Limited Express is formally publicized as a new type of a train, but in substance, it is a conventional train merely the type of which was changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the K-Limited Express is formally publicized as a new type of train, but essentially it&apos;s a conventional train in which only its type designation has been changed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the K-Limited Express is formally publicized as a new type of train, but essentially it&apos;s a conventional train in which only its type designation has been changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同様な例として、名鉄名古屋本線の「名鉄特急名鉄岐阜～豊橋間 快速特急・特急（一部特別車)（豊橋駅〜名鉄岐阜駅間の系統）」や京成本線の「快速特急京成電鉄「快特（快速特急）」」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are similar examples to K Limited Express, such as &quot;Meitetsu-tokkyu&quot; (Nagoya Railroad Rapid Limited Express &amp; Limited Express--some of the Limited Express is the special train) running on Nagoya Main Line in the section between Meitetsu Gifu Station and Toyohashi Station, or &quot;Kaisoku-tokkyu Keisei Dentetsu&quot; (Keisei Electric Railway Rapid Limited Express) running on Keisei Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are examples of similarity to the K-Limited Express, such as &quot;Meitetsu-tokkyu&quot; (Nagoya Railroad&apos;s rapid limited express and limited express--some of the limited express runs are special trains) running on Nagoya Main Line in the section between Meitetsu Gifu Station and Toyohashi Station, or the &quot;Kaisoku-tokkyu Keisei Dentetsu&quot; (Keisei Electric Railway&apos;s rapid limited express) running on the Keisei Main Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are examples of similarity to the K-Limited Express, such as &apos;Meitetsu-tokkyu&apos; (Nagoya Railroad&apos;s rapid limited express and limited express--some cars of a limited express train are those where seat reservation is required) running on Nagoya Main Line in the section between Meitetsu Gifu Station and Toyohashi Station, or the &apos;Kaisoku-tokkyu Keisei Dentetsu&apos; (Keisei Electric Railway&apos;s rapid limited express) running on the Keisei Main Line.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。名鉄の一部特急車とは、特急の一部車両が座席指定車である特急ですので、左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、京阪電気鉄道における新しい列車種別は1960年3月に設定された急行列車以来43年半振りであり、2003年9月8日月曜日よりK特急の運行を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, K Limited Express was introduced as a new type of a train for the first time in 43 years within Keihan Electric Railway after the limited express introduced in March of 1960, and the operation of K Limited Express was begun on September 8, 2003.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the K-Limited Express--which started operating on September 8, 2003--marked the first introduction of a new type of train in 43 years within the Keihan Electric Railway after the limited express introduced in March 1960.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the K-Limited Express--which started operating on September 8, 2003--marked the first introduction of a new type of train in 43 years within the Keihan Electric Railway after the express introduced in March 1960.</e>
<cmt>limited express→ express　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、私市始発、京阪交野線直通のK特急については一般公募により「おりひめ」という愛称が付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, about the kind of K Limited Express that starts from Kisaichi Station and directly connects with Keihan Katano Line, the nickname was sought among the public and was decided on &quot;Orihime.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in regard to the K-Limited Express that starts from Kisaichi Station and directly connects with the Keihan Katano Line, a nickname was requested from the public and &quot;Orihime&quot; was chosen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in regard to the K-Limited Express that starts from Kisaichi Station and directly connects with the Keihan Katano Line, a nickname was requested from the public and &apos;Orihime&apos; was chosen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは交野地区が「七夕」の地域であることもあり、約1,000通のうちの42票を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Partly because Katano Area is related to &quot;Tanabata&quot; (the Japanese traditional festival held on July 7), 42 votes were won out of about 1000 in a popularity vote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Partly because the Katano area is related to &quot;Tanabata&quot; (the Japanese traditional festival held on July 7), 42 votes were won out of approximately 1000 in a popularity vote.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Partly because the Katano area is related to &apos;Tanabata&apos; (the Japanese traditional festival held on July 7), 42 votes were won out of approximately 1000 in a popularity vote.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>運行概況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation of the operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Status of operation</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Status of operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>京阪本線・鴨東線K特急</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">K Limited Express running on Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The K-Limited Express running on the Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The K-Limited Express running on the Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>設定以来、平日のみ出町柳-淀屋橋で運行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since its introduction, the train service of K Limited Express has been operated merely on weekdays in the section between Demachiyanagi Station and Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since its introduction, the K-Limited Express train service has operated only on weekdays in the section between Demachiyanagi Station and Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since its introduction, the K-Limited Express train service has operated only on weekdays in the section between Demachiyanagi Station and Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>車両は基本的には特急形車両である8000系ないし3000系を使用するが、朝ラッシュ時には9000系、6000系、7200系も使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically the rolling stock used as the limited express is Keihan Electric Railway Series (KERS) 8000 &amp; KERS 3000, and during the morning rush hour, KERS 9000, KERS 6000 and KERS 7200 are also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, the train uses Keihan Electric Railway Series (KERS) 8000 &amp; KERS 3000 rolling stock, and during the morning rush hour the KERS 9000, KERS 6000 and KERS 7200 are also used.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, the train uses Keihan Electric Railway Series (KERS) 8000 &amp; KERS 3000 rolling stock, and during the morning rush hour the KERS 9000, KERS 6000 and KERS 7200 are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、9000系には予備車が無いので、検査入場等で使用不能になった時には9000系の運用も6000系ないし7200系で運用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, having no reserve rolling stock, KERS 9000 is replaced with KERS 6000 or with KERS 7200 when impossible to use for some reason, such as the inspection at the rolling stock yard.</e>
<cmt>「検査入場」とは「鉄道車両を検査のため車両所に入場させること」であり、左でもそう訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, having no reserve rolling stock, the KERS 9000 is replaced by the KERS 6000 or KERS 7200 when it can&apos;t be used for whatever reason, such as when it&apos;s being inspected at the stock yard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, having no reserve rolling stock, the KERS 9000 is replaced by the KERS 6000 or KERS 7200 when it can&apos;t be used for whatever reason, such as when it&apos;s being inspected at the stock yard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>朝ラッシュ時の淀屋橋行以外は、中書島駅・丹波橋駅が京都市内所在駅と言うこともあり、事実上の京阪間ノンストップ列車である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">K Limited Express running on this line is substantially the nonstop train between Kyoto and Osaka, except for the train running during the morning rush hour for Yodoyabashi Station, because Chushojima Station and Tanbabashi Station, which are both the stops of K Limited Express, are located in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The K-Limited Express running on this line is essentially a nonstop train between Kyoto and Osaka, except for the train running during the morning rush hour for Yodoyabashi Station, because Chushojima Station and Tanbabashi Station, at which the K-Limited Express stops, are located in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The K-Limited Express running on this line is essentially a nonstop train between Kyoto and Osaka, except for the train running during the morning rush hour for Yodoyabashi Station, because Chushojima Station and Tanbabashi Station, at which the K-Limited Express stops, are located in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Tanbabashi →Tambabashiとしました（京阪サイトより）。Tambabashi→Tanbabashiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、祇園祭・大文字五山送り火の時は夕方以降に臨時列車を走らせるために9000系の運用もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And on the occasion of Gion Festival and Daimonji Gozan Okuribi, KERS 9000 is operated as the special train after the evening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, during the Gion Festival and Daimonji Gozan Okuribi, the KERS 9000 is operated as the special train after the evening time period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, during the Gion Festival and Daimonji Gozan Okuribi (Mountain Bon Fire), the KERS 9000 is operated as the special train after the evening time period.</e>
<cmt>五山送り火の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>今後、代走及び臨時列車には京阪中之島線快速急行京阪電気鉄道用3000系（2代）も充当される予定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From now on, Keihan Nakanoshima Line Rapid Express whose rolling stock is KERS 3000 (the second generation) is due to be used as the temporary replacement train &amp; the special train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From now on, the Keihan Nakanoshima Line&apos;s rapid express, whose rolling stock is the KERS 3000 (second generation) will be used as the temporary replacement train and the special train.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From now on, the Keihan Nakanoshima Line&apos;s rapid express, whose rolling stock is the KERS 3000 (second generation) will be used as the temporary replacement train and the special train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>交野線直通K特急「おりひめ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;K Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&quot; directly connecting with Katano Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&quot; directly connecting with the Katano Line</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&apos; directly connecting with the Katano Line</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>JR片町線との対抗上設定された、私市発淀屋橋行の列車である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduced as the competitor with the train on JR Katamachi Line, &quot;K Limited Express Orihime&quot; is the train starting from Kisaichi Station for Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduced as a competitor to the train on the JR Katamachi Line, the &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; starts from Kisaichi Station bound for Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduced as a competitor to the train on the JR Katamachi Line, the &apos;K-Limited Express Orihime&apos; starts from Kisaichi Station bound for Yodoyabashi Station.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>定期列車では初めて京阪本線と交野線を直通する列車となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became the first regular train directly connecting Keihan Main Line with Katano Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first regular train to directly connect the Keihan Main Line with the Katano Line.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the first regular train to directly connect the Keihan Main Line with the Katano Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>使用車両は2600系である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rolling stock used is KERS 2600.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rolling stock used is KERS 2600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rolling stock used is KERS 2600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これは「特急」方向幕が用意されている（ただし、「K特急」表示は設定されていないので表示不可能）のと、ホーム有効長の関係で交野線内が5連までしか入線出来ないことが理由。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KERS 2600 is used because it is equipped with the rollsign of &quot;Limited Express,&quot; if not the rollsign of &quot;K Limited Express,&quot; and because platforms on Katano Line can accommodate the train made up of 5 cars at best owing to their effective length.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KERS 2600 is used because it&apos;s equipped with the rollsign &quot;Limited Express&quot; instead of the rollsign &quot;K-Limited Express,&quot; and because the platforms on the Katano Line can accommodate a train made up of five cars at most, owing to their effective lengths.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KERS 2600 is used because it&apos;s equipped with the rollsign &apos;Limited Express&apos; (the rollsign &apos;K-Limited Express&apos; is not equipped, therefore it cannot be displayed) and because the platforms on the Katano Line can accommodate a train made up of five cars at most, owing to their effective lengths.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。括弧内の訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、前面に「直通K特急 おりひめ」のヘッドマークを掲出して運転される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While in operation, the train hangs the signboard of &quot;Through K Limited Express Orihime&quot; on its front car.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While in operation, the train displays the signboard &quot;Through K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; in its front car.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While in operation, the train displays the signboard &apos;Through K-Limited Express Orihime&apos; in its front car.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、7200系も2本が5連組成可能であるが「おりひめ」に充当されたことはない（7200系は「K特急」の表示も可能）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two trains of KERS 7200 can have their rolling stock made up of 5 cars, but these trains have not been used as &quot;K Limited Express Orihime,&quot; but KERS 7200 is equipped with the rollsign of &quot;K Limited Express,&quot; so it can show the rollsign on its front car.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two trains of KERS 7200 can have their rolling stock made up of five cars, but these trains haven&apos;t been used as &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime&quot;; moreover, the KERS 7200 is equipped with the rollsign &quot;K-Limited Express,&quot; so it can show the rollsign on its front car.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two trains of KERS 7200 can have their rolling stock made up of five cars, but these trains haven&apos;t been used as &apos;K-Limited Express Orihime&apos;; moreover, the KERS 7200 is equipped with the rollsign &apos;K-Limited Express,&apos; so it can show the rollsign on its front car.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>京阪での5連は1900系もあるが、「K特急」（「特急」を含む）表示幕を装備していないため、基本的には入らないが、イベント時等には稀に運用に入り、その際には前面に特急鳩マークとヘッドマークの両方を掲出する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KERS 1900 is also the train made up of 5 cars, but it is equipped neither with the rollsign of &quot;K Limited Express&quot; nor with that of &quot;Limited Express,&quot; so this rolling stock is basically not in operation, but on the occasion of events or the like, it is exceptionally in operation and it hangs the limited express emblem of a pigeon and the signboard both on its front car.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The KERS 1900 train is also made up of five cars, but it&apos;s equipped neither with the rollsign &quot;K-Limited Express&quot; nor with &quot;Limited Express,&quot; so this rolling stock is basically not in operation, but on the occasion of events and the like it&apos;s exceptionally in operation, displaying the limited express emblem of a pigeon and the signboard in its front car.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The KERS 1900 train is also made up of five cars, but it&apos;s equipped neither with the rollsign &apos;K-Limited Express&apos; nor with &apos;Limited Express,&apos; so this rolling stock is basically not in operation, but on the occasion of events and the like it&apos;s exceptionally in operation, displaying the limited express emblem of a pigeon and the signboard in its front car.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>詳細は以下のとおり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details are as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>2003年9月8日 - 一番列車（1919-1920・特急色）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 8, 2003 - &quot;K Limited Express Orihime&quot; was operated for the first time : the rolling stock was Keihan Electric Railway Type (KERT) 1919/1920; the cars of the train were painted with the design of the limited express.</e>
<cmt>①括弧内の「1919-1920」は車両形をさすものです。　②「特急色」とは「車両には特急の塗装が施された」という意味に解されますので、そう訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 8, 2003: The &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; was operated for the first time; the rolling stock was Keihan Electric Railway Type (KERT) 1919/1920, and the cars of the train were painted with the design of the limited express.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 8, 2003: The &apos;K-Limited Express Orihime&apos; was operated for the first time; the rolling stock was Keihan Electric Railway Type (KERT) 1919/1920, and the cars of the train were painted with the design of the limited express.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>2004年3月12日 - 1900系復活特急塗装(1919-1920)さよならイベント（定期列車の運用変更）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 12, 2004 - The design of the limited express about KERT 1919/1920 was ended and the farewell event was held on this date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 12, 2004: The design of the limited express about KERT 1919/1920 was ended, and the farewell event was held on this date.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 12, 2004: The KERS 1900 (KERT 1919/1920) which was painted with the design of the limited express had a farewell event (due to the change of the regular trains).</e>
<cmt>カッコ内の翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>2004年7月7日、2005年7月7日、2006年7月7日 - 七夕イベント、（2004年は1919-1920、2005年は1917-1918、2006年は1929-1930）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 7, 2004/July 7, 2005/July 7, 2006 - &quot;K Limited Express Orihime&quot; was used in the event commemorating &quot;Tanabata&quot; : The rolling stock used in 2004 was KERT 1919/1920; that in 2005 was KERT 1917/1918; that in 2006 was KERT 1929/1930.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 7, 2004/July 7, 2005/July 7, 2006: &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; was used in the event commemorating &quot;Tanabata&quot;; the rolling stock used in 2004 was KERT 1919/1920, in 2005 it was KERT 1917/1918, and in 2006 it was KERT 1929/1930.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 7, 2004/July 7, 2005/July 7, 2006: &apos;K-Limited Express Orihime&apos; was used in the event commemorating &apos;Tanabata&apos;; the rolling stock used in 2004 was KERT 1919/1920, in 2005 it was KERT 1917/1918, and in 2006 it was KERT 1929/1930.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>2004年9月6日 - 前日の地震による運用変更・鳩マーク掲出なし（1919-1920・PiTaPa塗色）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 6, 2004 - The operation of the train was changed because of the earthquake the day before and the emblem of a pigeon was not hung on the front car; at that time, the cars of KERT 1919/1920 were painted with the design of PiTaPa Card (an IC card) for its promotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 6, 2004: The operation of the train was changed due to the earthquake the day before, and the emblem of a pigeon wasn&apos;t displayed on the front car; at that time the cars of KERT 1919/1920 were painted with the design of PiTaPa Card (an IC card) for the sake of its promotion.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 6, 2004: The operation of the train was changed due to the earthquake the day before, and the emblem of a pigeon wasn&apos;t displayed on the front car; at that time the cars of KERT 1919/1920 were painted with the design of PiTaPa Card (an IC card) for the sake of its promotion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>2005年7月8日 - ヘッドマークのデザイン変更（新ヘッドマークは前日の七夕伝説イベントで披露された）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 8, 2005 - The signboard design on the front car was changed; the new design was made public the day before in the event commemorating the folklore of &quot;Tanabata.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 8, 2005: The signboard design on the front car was changed; the new design was made public the day before at an event commemorating the folklore of &quot;Tanabata.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 8, 2005: The signboard design on the front car was changed; the new design was made public the day before at an event commemorating the folklore of &quot;Tanabata.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>2006年1月4日 - 車両故障によるダイヤ乱れにより、10000系がK特急「おりひめ」の1本に充当された（4連K特急初）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 4, 2006 - The rolling stock trouble caused the disruption of the train schedule, so one train of KERS 10000 was exceptionally used as K Limited Express &quot;Orihime&quot;; K Limited Express made up of 4 cars was used for the first time on this occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 4, 2006: The problem of rolling stock caused the disruption of the train schedule, so one train of KERS 10000 was exceptionally used as the K-Limited Express &quot;Orihime&quot;; it was the first time that a K-Limited Express made up of four cars was used.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 4, 2006: The problem of rolling stock caused the disruption of the train schedule, so one train of KERS 10000 was exceptionally used as the K-Limited Express &apos;Orihime&apos;; it was the first time that a K-Limited Express made up of four cars was used.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>2006年4月17日 - 前日付ダイヤ改定の祝賀列車(1917-1918)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 17, 2006 - The rolling stock of KERT 1917/1918 was operated for commemorating the timetable revision the day before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 17, 2006 - The rolling stock of KERT 1917/1918 was operated to commemorate the timetable revision implemented on the previous day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 17, 2006 - The rolling stock of KERT 1917/1918 was operated to commemorate the timetable revision implemented on the previous day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>2006年5月18日 - 1917-1918編成勇退記念</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 18, 2006 - KERT 1917/1918 was operated for the last time to commemorate their own retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 18, 2006: KERT 1917/1918 was operated for the last time to commemorate the retirement of that rolling stock.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 18, 2006: KERT 1917/1918 was operated for the last time to commemorate the retirement of that rolling stock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>2006年7月26日 - 突発的に1900系充当・鳩マーク掲出なし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 26, 2006 - KERS 1900 was unexpectedly used as &quot;K Limited Express Orihime&quot; : The limited express emblem of a pigeon was not hung; the rolling stock used was KERT 1919/1920; the cars of the train were painted with the general design; the subordinate signboard commemorating the fiftieth anniversary of the operation was hung on the front car.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 26, 2006: The KERS 1900 was unexpectedly used as &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime,&quot; but the limited express emblem of a pigeon wasn&apos;t displayed.</e>
<cmt>Split to two sentences 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 26, 2006: The KERS 1900 was unexpectedly used as &quot;K-Limited Express Orihime,&quot; but the limited express emblem of a pigeon wasn&apos;t displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>（1919-1920・一般色、50周年記念副標識取付）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rolling stock used was KERT 1919/1920, and the cars of the train were painted with the general design, and the subordinate signboard commemorating the fiftieth anniversary of the operation was displayed in the front car.</e>
<cmt>Split to two sentences 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rolling stock used was KERT 1919/1920, and the cars of the train were painted with the general design, and the subordinate signboard commemorating the fiftieth anniversary of the operation was displayed in the front car.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>2006年10月22日 - 鉄道の日記念のトーマストレイン10000系による臨時運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 22, 2006 - An extraordinary operation of KERS 10000, whose cars were painted with the design of Thomas the Tank Engine, was done to commemorate the Day of Railroads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 22, 2006 - An extraordinary operation of the KERS 10000, whose cars were painted with the design of &quot;Thomas the Tank Engine,&quot; was done to commemorate the &quot;Day of Railroads.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 22, 2006: An extraordinary operation of the KERS 10000, whose cars were painted with the design of &quot;Thomas the Tank Engine,&quot; was done to commemorate the &quot;Day of Railroads.&quot;</e>
<cmt>-　→:　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>おりひめおよび鉄道の日マスコットキャラ「テッピー」看板が付くが、幕は特急であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the front car, the train hung the signboards of &quot;Through K Limited Express Orihime&quot;and &quot;Teppi&quot; (a fictional mascot to commemorate the Day of Railroads), but the rollsign showed &quot;Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the front car, the train displayed the signboards of &quot;Through K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; and &quot;Teppi&quot; (a fictional mascot used to commemorate the Day of Railroads), but the rollsign indicated &quot;Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the front car, the train displayed the signboards of &quot;Through K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; and &apos;Teppi&apos; (a fictional mascot used to commemorate the Day of Railroads), but the rollsign indicated &quot;Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt>-　→:　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>（私市933→天満橋1014・休日初運行）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kisaichi Station 933→Tenmabashi Station 1014/in operation for the first time on a holiday)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kisaichi Station 933→Tenmabashi Station 1014/in operation for the first time on a holiday)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It departed Kisaichi Station at 9:33 and arrived at Tenmabashi Station at 10:14; in operation for the first time on a holiday)</e>
<cmt>9:33分発、10:14分着、と解釈し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>2007年1月21日 - トーマストレイン10000系最終運転日の臨時運転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 21, 2007 - An extraordinary operation of KERS 10000, whose cars were painted with the design of Thomas the Tank Engine, was done to commemorate the last operation of its own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 21, 2007: An extraordinary operation of the KERS 10000, the cars of which were painted with the design of &quot;Thomas the Tank Engine,&quot; was done to commemorate its last operation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 21, 2007: An extraordinary operation of the KERS 10000, the cars of which were painted with the design of &quot;Thomas the Tank Engine,&quot; was done to commemorate its last operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>おりひめおよびトーマストレイン引退記念「ありがとう」看板が付くが、幕は特急であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the front car, the train hung the signboards of &quot;Through K Limited Express Orihime&quot;and &quot;Thank you&quot; (for commemorating the retirement of itself), but the rollsign showed &quot;Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the front car, the train displayed the signboards &quot;Through K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; and &quot;Thank you&quot; (to commemorate the train&apos;s retirement, but the rollsign read &quot;Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the front car, the train displayed the signboards &quot;Through K-Limited Express Orihime&quot; and &apos;Thank you&apos; (to commemorate the train&apos;s retirement, but the rollsign read &quot;Limited Express.&quot;</e>
<cmt>-　→:　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>（私市1107→天満橋1144・休日2度目の運行）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kisaichi Station 1107→Tenmabashi Station 1144/in operation for the second time on a holiday)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kisaichi Station 1107→Tenmabashi Station 1144/in operation for the second time on a holiday)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It departed Kisaichi Station at 11:07 and arrived at Tenmabashi Station at 11:44; in operation for the second time on a holiday)</e>
<cmt>11:07分発、11:44分着、と解釈し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>2007年7月9日 - 2度目のヘッドマークデザイン変更（新ヘッドマークは前々日の七夕伝説イベントで披露された）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 9, 2007 - The signboard design on the front car was changed for the second time; the new design was made public two days before the date, or July 7, in the event commemorating the folklore of &quot;Tanabata.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 9, 2007: The signboard design on the front car was changed for the second time; the new design was made public two days before the date, or July 7, at the event commemorating the folklore of &quot;Tanabata.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 9, 2007: The signboard design on the front car was changed for the second time; the new design was made public two days before the date, or July 7, at the event commemorating the folklore of &quot;Tanabata.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>2006年4月16日改定では、朝ラッシュ時の発車時刻が各列車とも20分早められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 16, 2006, with the timetable revised, the departure time of each train during the morning rush hour was made 20 minute earlier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 16, 2006, with the timetable revised, the departure time of each train during the morning rush hour was made 20 minutes earlier.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 16, 2006: With the timetable revised, the departure time of each train during the morning rush hour was made 20 minutes earlier.</e>
<cmt>on →　:　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="51">
<j>車両の詳細は「使用車両」に記載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the details of the rolling stock, please refer to the description under the heading of &quot;Rolling stock used.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the details of the rolling stock, please refer to the description under the heading, &quot;Rolling stock used.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the details of the rolling stock, please refer to the description under the heading, &apos;Rolling stock used.&apos;</e>
<cmt>-　→:　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>停車駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stops</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>京阪本線・鴨東線K特急</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">K Limited Express running on Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The K-Limited Express running on the Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The K-Limited Express running on the Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>淀屋橋駅- 北浜駅 (大阪府) - 天満橋駅 - 京橋駅 (大阪府) - 枚方市駅（朝の淀屋橋行のみ停車） - 中書島駅 - 丹波橋駅 - 七条駅 - 四条駅 (京阪) - 三条駅 (京都府) - 出町柳駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodoyabashi Station - Kitahama Station (in Osaka Prefecture) - Tenmabashi Station - Kyobashi Station (in Osaka Prefecture) - Hirakatashi Station (for the train service in the morning bound for Yodoyabashi Station only) - Chushojima Station - Tanbabashi Station - Shichijo Station - Gion-shijo Station (Keihan) - Sanjo Station (in Kyoto Prefecture) - Demachiyanagi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodoyabashi Station - Kitahama Station (in Osaka Prefecture) - Tenmabashi Station - Kyobashi Station (in Osaka Prefecture) - Hirakatashi Station (for the train service in the morning bound for Yodoyabashi Station only) - Chushojima Station - Tanbabashi Station - Shichijo Station - Gion-shijo Station (Keihan) - Sanjo Station (in Kyoto Prefecture) - Demachiyanagi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodoyabashi Station - Kitahama Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Tenmabashi Station - Kyobashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Hirakatashi Station (for the train service in the morning bound for Yodoyabashi Station only) - Chushojima Station - Tanbabashi Station - Shichijo Station - Gion-shijo Station (Keihan) - Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Demachiyanagi Station</e>
<cmt>括弧内の　in　を削除しました。正式名称のため、Tambabashi としました。Tambabashi →Tanbabashi に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>交野線直通K特急「おりひめ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;K Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&quot; directly connecting with Katano Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&quot; directly connecting with the Katano Line</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&apos; directly connecting with the Katano Line</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>私市駅→河内森駅→交野市駅→郡津駅→村野駅→星ヶ丘駅 (大阪府)→宮之阪駅→枚方市駅→京橋駅 (大阪府)→天満橋駅→北浜駅 (大阪府)→淀屋橋駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kisaichi Station→Kawachimori Station→Katanoshi Station→Kozu Station→Murano Station→Hoshigaoka Station (in Osaka Prefecture)→Miyanosaka Station→Hirakatashi Station→Kyobashi Station (in Osaka Prefecture)→Tenmabashi Station - Kitahama Station (in Osaka Prefecture)→Yodoyabashi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kisaichi Station→Kawachimori Station→Katanoshi Station→Kozu Station→Murano Station→Hoshigaoka Station (in Osaka Prefecture)→Miyanosaka Station→Hirakatashi Station→Kyobashi Station (in Osaka Prefecture)→Tenmabashi Station - Kitahama Station (in Osaka Prefecture)→Yodoyabashi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kisaichi Station - Kawachimori Station - Katanoshi Station - Kozu Station - Murano Station - Hoshigaoka Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Miyanosaka Station - Hirakatashi Station - Kyobashi Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Tenmabashi Station - Kitahama Station (Osaka Prefecture) - Yodoyabashi Station</e>
<cmt>→を - に変更しました。括弧内の　in　を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>交野線内は各駅に停車する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the section of Katano Line, the train makes a stop at every station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the section of the Katano Line, the train stops at every station.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the section of the Katano Line, the train stops at every station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>使用車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolling stock used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>京阪本線・鴨東線K特急</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">K Limited Express running on Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The K-Limited Express running on the Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The K-Limited Express running on the Keihan Main Line and Keihan Oto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>京阪8000系電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 8000</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 8000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 8000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>京阪3000系電車（初代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 3000 : This is the first generation;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 3000: This is the first generation.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 3000: This is the first generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>8000系に編入予定）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is due to be incorporated into KERS 8000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is due to be incorporated into KERS 8000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is due to be incorporated into KERS 8000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="60">
<j>京阪9000系電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 9000</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 9000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 9000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>京阪6000系電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 6000</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 6000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 6000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>京阪7200系電車（7203Fを除く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 7200 (except for 7203F)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 7200 (except for 7203F)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 7200 (except for 7203F)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>3000系（2代）（9000系の代走及び一部列車での使用を予定）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KERS 3000 (the second generation) : This is due to be used as the temporary replacement train for KERS 9000 &amp; the special train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KERS 3000 (the second generation): This is due to be used as a temporary replacement train for the KERS 9000 and the special train.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KERS 3000 (the second generation): This is due to be used as a temporary replacement train for the KERS 9000 and the special train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>交野線直通K特急「おりひめ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;K Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&quot; directly connecting with Katano Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&quot; directly connecting with the Katano Line</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;K-Limited Express (K-tokkyu) Orihime&apos; directly connecting with the Katano Line</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>京阪2600系電車（0番台のうち5両編成のみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 2600 (only the rolling stock made up of 5 cars)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 2600 (only the rolling stock made up of five cars)</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 2600 (only five cars for the prototype)</e>
<cmt>Based on the information at the following link, I assume that ０番台 means the prototype train for a particular series. http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E6%96%B0%E5%B9%B9%E7%B7%9AN700%E7%B3%BB%E9%9B%BB%E8%BB%8A</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>京阪1900系電車（イベント時・代走）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 1900 : This is due to be used in the events or used as the temporary replacement train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 1900: This is due to be used during events or as a temporary replacement train.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 1900: This is due to be used during events or as a temporary replacement train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>京阪10000系電車（同上）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 10000 : This is the sama as the above</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway Series 10000: This is the same as the above.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway Series 10000: This is the same as the above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>発車メロディ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Departure melodies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Departure melodies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Departure melodies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>2007年6月17日より京阪本線（鴨東線）・交野線・宇治線の17駅にて向谷実作曲による新しい発車メロディが導入されたが、出町柳駅・京橋駅（上りのみ）・私市駅ではK特急専用の発車メロディーが存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 17, 2007, the new departure melodies composed by Minoru MUKAIYA were introduced into 17 stations on Keihan Main Line, Keihan Oto Line, Katano Line and Uji Line, and there exist the departure melodies for K Limited Express only, which are played at Demachiyanagi Station, Kyobashi Station (the platform of the up train only) and Kisaichi Station.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, 2007, the new departure melodies composed by Minoru MUKAIYA were introduced at 17 stations on the Keihan Main Line, Keihan Oto Line, Katano Line and Uji Line; there are departure melodies for the K-Limited Express only, which are played at Demachiyanagi Station, Kyobashi Station (the platform of the up train only) and Kisaichi Station.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 17, 2007, the new departure melodies composed by Minoru MUKAIYA were introduced at 17 stations on the Keihan Main Line, Keihan Oto Line, Katano Line and Uji Line; there are departure melodies for the K-Limited Express only, which are played at Demachiyanagi Station, Kyobashi Station (the platform of the inbound train only) and Kisaichi Station.</e>
<cmt>上り→inboundd としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>これらの曲はK特急が運転されない土休日は聞く事は不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You cannot hear these melodies on weekends and holidays because there is no service of K Limited Express on these days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You can&apos;t hear these melodies on weekends and holidays because there is no service of the K-Limited Express on those days.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can&apos;t hear these melodies on weekends and holidays because there is no service of the K-Limited Express on those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また、出町柳駅では、「京阪特急 (楽曲)出町柳から」 京橋駅では、「京阪特急 (楽曲)朝靄の京橋で乗り換え」が、流れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">at Demachiyanagi Station, the departure melody of &quot;Keihan Tokkyu - Demachiyanagi-kara&quot; (Keihan Tokkyu - from Demachiyanagi Station) is played, and at Kyobashi Station, the departure melody of &quot;Keihan Tokkyu - Asamoya no Kyobashi de Norikae&quot; (Keihan Tokkyu - Transfer at Kyobashi Station veiled in the morning haze) is played.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Demachiyanagi Station, the departure melody of &quot;Keihan Tokkyu - Demachiyanagi-kara&quot; (Keihan Tokkyu - from Demachiyanagi Station) is played, and at Kyobashi Station, the departure melody of &quot;Keihan Tokkyu - Asamoya no Kyobashi de Norikae&quot; (Keihan Tokkyu - Transfer at Kyobashi Station veiled in the morning haze) is played.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Demachiyanagi Station, the departure melody of &apos;Keihan Tokkyu - Demachiyanagi-kara&apos; (Keihan Tokkyu - from Demachiyanagi Station) is played, and at Kyobashi Station, the departure melody of &apos;Keihan Tokkyu - Asamoya no Kyobashi de Norikae&apos; (Keihan Tokkyu - Transfer at Kyobashi Station veiled in the morning haze) is played.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hirotaka(id:6342), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), FREEZA(id:68069), Sat.K(id:3751), Yanahan(id:2437), Keitanchi(id:126611), Iincho(id:47255), Rusk(id:9895), Special rapid(id:96013), Sunen(id:10700), 準急三条(id:25072), Mochi(id:9489), Sara-minori(id:139962), Mutumi06(id:82739), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Nanamix73(id:45303), 210.(id:9838), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), LCcar5800(id:105777), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), ADhirakata(id:101086), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>