<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>木津温泉駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitsu-onsen (hot spring) Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitsu-onsen (hot spring) Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitsu-onsen Station</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>木津温泉駅（きつおんせんえき）は、京都府京丹後市網野町木津にある、北近畿タンゴ鉄道北近畿タンゴ鉄道宮津線の鉄道駅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Kitsu Amino-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture, Kitsu-onsen (hot spring) Station is a stop on the Miyazu Line, which is operated by Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitsu-onsen (hot spring) Station, located in Kitsu Amino-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Miyazu Line, which is operated by Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitsu-onsen (hot spring) Station, located in Kitsu, Amino-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a stop on the Miyazu Line, which is operated by Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「きづ」とは濁らず「きつ」と読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pronounciation of &quot;木津&quot; is not &quot;Kizu&quot; but &quot;Kitsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pronounciation of &quot;木津&quot; is not &quot;Kizu&quot; but &quot;Kitsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pronunciation of &apos;木津&apos; is not &apos;Kizu&apos; but &apos;Kitsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本国有鉄道（国鉄）、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）時代は、丹後木津駅（たんごきつえき）と名乗っていたが、北近畿タンゴ鉄道へ移管された際に現在の駅名になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango-kitsu Station was its station name in the eras when the station was owned by Japanese National Railways (JR) or West Japan Railway Company (JR West), but the present station name became to be used when its ownership was transferred to Kitakinki Tango Railway..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango-kitsu Station was its station name in the eras when the station was owned by Japanese National Railways (JR) or West Japan Railway Company (JR West), but the present station name came to be used when its ownership was transferred to Kitakinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango-kitsu Station was its station name in the eras when the station was owned by Japanese National Railways (JNR) or West Japan Railway Company (JR West), but the present station name came to be used when its ownership was transferred to Kitakinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt>JNR としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>以前は、普通列車のみ停車し、夏季の海水浴シーズン及び、冬季の松葉ガニシーズンの時を除くと特急や一部の快速は通過していたが、2007年3月18日改正より、全ての列車が毎日停車するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, only local trains stopped and the limitted or some of the rapid trains did not stop at this station except in the summer sea-bathing season and in the winter matsuba-gani (literally pine-needle crab: actually snow crab) season, but now all trains stop at this station everyday according to the train schedule change made on March 18, 2007..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, only local trains stopped but the limited (or some of the rapid trains) didn&apos;t stop at this station except in the summer sea-bathing season and the winter matsuba-gani (literally pine-needle crab: actually snow crab) season, but now all trains stop at this station everyday according to the train schedule change implemented on March 18, 2007.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, only local trains stopped but the limited (or some of the rapid trains) didn&apos;t stop at this station except in the summer sea-bathing season and the winter matsuba-gani (literally pine-needle crab: in fact snow crab) season, but now all trains stop at this station everyday according to the train schedule change implemented on March 18, 2007.</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>網野駅と同様に地元の網野町観光協会の係員に、駅の管理と出改札業務を委託されているが、隣の丹後神野駅と同様、鉄道駅簡易委託駅となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As at Amisno Station, the management of the station and ticket-related jobs are entrusted to officers at the local Amino-cho tourist association, making it a station whose simple station jobs are outsourced as at the adjacent Tango-Kanno Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As at Amino Station, the management of the station and ticket-related work are entrusted to officers at the local Amino-cho Tourist Association, making it a station whose simple station jobs are outsourced as at the adjacent Tango-Kanno Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As at Amino Station, the management of the station and ticket-related work are entrusted to officers at the local Amino-cho Tourist Association, making it a station whose simple station jobs are outsourced as at the adjacent Tango-Kanno Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>駅構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s structure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station layout</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>単式1面1線のプラットホームを持つ地上駅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located on the ground level, with a platporm serving a track.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located on the ground level, with a platform serving a track.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located on the ground level, with a platform serving a track.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>かつては列車交換可能駅であったが、交換設備は撤去されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, up-trains and down-trains met here to switch the tracks, but the facilities to enable such a function have been removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, up trains and down trains met here to switch the tracks, but the facilities to enable such a function have been removed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, inbound trains and outbound trains met here to switch the tracks, but the facilities to enable such a function have been removed.</e>
<cmt>上り、下り→inbound, outbound としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>構内には、交換可能駅であった名残の相対式ホームが残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the premises, another platform, which was once used to enable such a track-switching function, still remains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another platform, which was once used to enable such a track-switching function, remains on the premises.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another platform, which was once used to enable such a track-switching function, remains on the premises.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>駅舎は改築こそされているものの、趣のある和風建築の駅舎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although reconstructed, the station house is an attractive Japanese-style one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although reconstructed, the station house is an attractive Japanese-style one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although reconstructed, the station house is an attractive Japanese-style one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>2007年4月1日、駅ホームに足湯「しらさぎの湯」が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of a footbath on the platform was completed on April 1, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of a footbath on the platform was completed on April 1, 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of a footbath named &apos;Shirasagi-no-yu&apos; on the platform was completed on April 1, 2007.</e>
<cmt>しらさぎの湯　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>原泉掛け流しで、午前9時～午後5時まで利用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The warm water of the footbath, usable from 9 am to 5 pm, comes directly from a hot spring source (so-called &quot;gensen kakenagashi&quot;in Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The warm water of the footbath, usable from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., comes directly from a hot-spring source (so-called &quot;gensen kakenagashi&quot; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The warm water of the footbath, usable from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., comes directly from a hot-spring source (so-called &quot;gensen kakenagashi&quot; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>利用は無料だが、鉄道利用者以外の利用には駅の入場券が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The footbath can be used free if you have a ticket on the train line, but if you have no such a ticket, you must purchase a platform ticket to use it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The footbath can be used free if you have a ticket on the train line, but if you don&apos;t have a ticket you must purchase a platform ticket in order to use the footbath.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The footbath can be used free if you have a ticket on the train line, but if you don&apos;t have a ticket you must purchase a platform ticket in order to use the footbath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>駅周辺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station&apos;s surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Station surroundings</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>外湯木津温泉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotoyu-Kitsu-onsen　（外湯木津温泉）</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotoyu-Kitsu-onsen　（外湯木津温泉）</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An open air bath of Kitsu-onsen Hot Spring</e>
<cmt>駅の周辺に、外湯があるようですので、左記のように変更しました。（参考サイト：http://www.tangokankou.jp/machiaruki/burabura/07.html）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>木津温泉の湯を使用した足湯（当駅構内）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A footbath using warm water from Kitsu-onsen Hot Spring (in the premises of this station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A footbath using warm water from Kitsu-onsen Hot Spring (within the premises of this station)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A footbath using warm water from Kitsu-onsen Hot Spring (within the premises of this station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ミニ行基像（当駅構内）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A small-sized statue of Gyoki (in the premises of this station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A small statue of Gyoki (in the premises of this station)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A small statue of Gyoki (in the premises of this station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>浜詰海水浴場（浜詰・当駅から タクシーで5～6分）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hamazume sea-bathing beach (in five to six minutes by taxi from Hashizume or this station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hamazume sea-bathing beach (about five or six minutes by taxi from Hashizume or this station)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hamazume sea-bathing beach (located in Hamazume, about five or six minutes by taxi from this station)</e>
<cmt>「浜詰が駅からタクシーで５、６分」と解釈し、左記のようにいたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>木津温泉（駅前・当駅下車 徒歩1～3分）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitsu-onsen Hot Spring (a 1- to 3-minute walk from this station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitsu-onsen Hot Spring (a walk of one to two minutes from this station)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitsu-onsen Hot Spring (a walk of one to two minutes from this station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>丹後木津郵便局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tango kitsu post office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tango Kitsu post office</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tango Kitsu post office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>京丹後市立橘小学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyotango City-run Tachibana Elementary School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tachibana Elementary School, run by Kyotango City</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyotango Municipal Tachibana Elementary School</e>
<cmt>municipal としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>京丹後市立橘中学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyotango City-run Tachibana Junior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tachibana Junior High School, run by Kyotango City</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyotango Municipal Tachibana Junior High School</e>
<cmt>municipal としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京丹後市立網野郷土資料館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyotango City Amino Local Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyotango City Amino Local Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyotango City Amino Local Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>国道178号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National highway 178</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Highway 178</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Route 178</e>
<cmt>国道→national routeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>タクシー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>日本交通 (福知山市)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon　Kotsu　Co.,　Ltd. (located in Fukuchiyama City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon　Kotsu　Co.,　Ltd. (located in Fukuchiyama City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Kotsu Co., Ltd. (Fukuchiyama City)</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="28">
<j>利用状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use situations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passenger usage statistics</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passenger use</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>2006年度の1日あたりの乗車人員は約123人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of persons getting on board at this station is approx. 123 a day in the fiscal 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fiscal 2006, the average daily number of persons who boarded at this station was 123.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fiscal year 2006, the average daily number of persons who boarded at this station was 123.</e>
<cmt>fiscal year としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>（京都府統計書より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(From statistics of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(From statistics of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to the Kyoto Prefecture Statistics Report)</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="31">
<j>宮津線沿線には海水浴場が多数あるが、木津温泉駅も例外ではなく、浜詰海水浴場（当駅から、タクシー利用で、5～6分）が近くにあり、特急列車も停車する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many sea-bathing beaches are located along the Miyazu Line, and with Kitsu-onsen Station as well being located near to the Famazume sea-bathing beach (in five to six minutes by taxi from the station), the limitted express trains stop at this station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many sea-bathing beaches are located along the Miyazu Line, and with Kitsu-onsen Station also located near to the Famazume sea-bathing beach (five or six minutes by taxi from the station), the limited express trains stop here.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many sea-bathing beaches are located along the Miyazu Line, and with Kitsu-onsen Station also located near to the Hamazume sea-bathing beach (five or six minutes by taxi from the station), the limited express trains stop here.</e>
<cmt>Hamazume に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="32">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="33">
<j>1931年（昭和6年）5月25日 峰豊線 網野～丹後木津（現・木津温泉）間が開業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 25, 1931: The Minetoyo Line started its operation between Amino and Tango-Kitsu (present Kitsu-onsen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 25, 1931: The Minetoyo Line started operating between Amino and Tango-Kitsu (the present-day Kitsu-onsen).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 25, 1931: The Minetoyo Line started operating between Amino and Tango-Kitsu (the present-day Kitsu-onsen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="34">
<j>1932年（昭和7年）8月10日 丹後木津～久美浜間が開業し全通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 10, 1932: The operation between Tango-Kitsu and Kumihama started, completing the planned construction of the line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 10, 1932: The operation between Tango-Kitsu and Kumihama started, completing the planned construction of the line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 10, 1932: The operation between Tango-Kitsu and Kumihama started, completing the planned construction of the line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>峰山線・峰豊線を宮津線に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names of Mineyam Line and Minetoyo Line were changed to Mineyam Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names of Mineyama and Minetoyo lines were changed to &quot;Mineyama Line.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of Mineyama and Minetoyo lines were changed to Miyazu Line.</e>
<cmt>miyazu line に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="36">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日 国鉄分割民営化により、西日本旅客鉄道（JR西日本）の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1987 - Due to the division and privitization of Japan National Railways, it became a station of West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1987: Due to the division and privatization of Japan National Railways, it became a station of West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1987: Due to the division and privatization of Japan National Railways, it became a station of West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="37">
<j>1990年（平成2年）4月1日 北近畿タンゴ鉄道への宮津線移管により、同鉄道の駅となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1, 1990 - The Miyazu Line was transferred to Kitakinki Tango Railway, and it became a station of the railway company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1, 1990: The Miyazu Line was transferred to Kitakinki Tango Railway, and it became a station of that railway company.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1, 1990: The Miyazu Line was transferred to Kitakinki Tango Railway, and it became a station of that railway company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、駅名が木津温泉に改められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The station name was changed to Kitsu-onsen Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The station name was changed to Kitsu-onsen Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The station name was changed to Kitsu-onsen Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>隣の駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighboring stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adjacent stations</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>北近畿タンゴ鉄道(KTR)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>宮津線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyazu Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyazu Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyazu Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>網野駅 - 木津温泉駅 - 丹後神野駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amino Stations - Kitsu-onsen Station - Tango-Kanno Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amino Stations - Kitsu-onsen Station - Tango-Kanno Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amino Station - Kitsu-onsen Station - Tango-Kanno Station</e>
<cmt>Station　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Bakkai(id:7233), Hikichimin Jr.(id:147077), Kaidai(id:15804), Memeja(id:110500), エアスマップIRE(id:13873), ShikiH(id:181574), DDatKYOTO(id:122010), 樒(id:35770), Rusk(id:9895), Yasu2006(id:93004), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), R28Bot(id:177951), Kone(id:377), 210.(id:9838), エアスマップＩＲＥ(id:17869), Sea of Japan(id:3230), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>