<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利周嵩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuko ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuko ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuko ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 周嵩（あしかが しゅうこう）は、戦国時代 (日本)の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuko ASHIKAGA was a priest who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuko ASHIKAGA was a priest who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuko ASHIKAGA was a priest who lived during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>表記を統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>足利将軍家の一族で、足利義輝、足利義昭の実弟である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a member of the Ashikaga Shogun family and a brother of Yoshiteru AHIKAGA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of the Ashikaga Shogun family and a brother of Yoshiteru AHIKAGA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of the Ashikaga Shogun family and a biological brother of Yoshiteru AHIKAGA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>統一リストをもとに補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>室町幕府の第12代将軍・足利義晴の末子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the youngest child of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA who was the 12th Shogun of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the youngest child of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, who was the twelfth Shogun of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the youngest child of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, who was the 12th Shogun of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼い頃から仏門に入り、鹿苑寺（金閣寺）の院主になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the Buddhist priesthood in his young days and became Inju (the chief of a temple) of the Rokuon-ji Temple (Kinkaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuko entered the Buddhist priesthood in his younger days and became the Inju (the chief of a temple) of the Rokuon-ji Temple (Kinkaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the Buddhist priesthood in his younger days and became the Inju (the chief of a temple) of the Rokuon-ji Temple (also known as Kinkaku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>永禄7年（1565年）5月19日、松永久秀・松永久通父子と三好三人衆によって兄で第13代将軍だった義輝が殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 7, 1564, his brother Yoshiteru, the 13th Shogun, was killed by Hisahide MATSUNAGA, his son Hisamichi MATSUNAGA and miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan).</e>
<cmt>永禄7年は1564年なので、(1565年)は誤記と判断しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 7, 1564, Shuko&apos;s brother Yoshiteru, the thirteenth Shogun, was killed by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and his son, Hisamichi MATSUNAGA, and the Miyoshi Sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 7, 1564, his brother Yoshiteru, the 13th Shogun, was killed by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and his son, Hisamichi MATSUNAGA, and the Miyoshi Sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan).</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、周嵩は逃亡しようとしたが捕捉されて殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Shuko tried to escape but was captured and killed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shuko tried to escape, he was ultimately captured and executed.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shuko tried to escape, he was ultimately captured and executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 平惣衛門(id:99387), ドルチェット(id:46458), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>