<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>万里小路藤房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>万里小路 藤房（までのこうじ ふじふさ、永仁4年（1296年） - 康暦2年/天授 (日本)6年3月28日 (旧暦)（1380年5月3日）?）は、鎌倉時代から南北朝時代 (日本)の公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI (1296 - May 3, 1380 (lunar calendar)) was a Japanese court noble who lived in the Kamakura period and the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI (1296 - May 3, 1380 (lunar calendar)) was a Japanese court noble who lived in the Kamakura period and the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI (1296 - May 11, 1380) was a Japanese court noble who lived in the Kamakura period and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に訂正しました。 (lunar calendar)削除しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。DynastiesをCourtsに訂正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は万里小路宣房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Nobufusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Nobufusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Nobufusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>後醍醐天皇の側近として仕えて、鎌倉幕府倒幕計画に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served the Emperor Godaigo as a close aide and take part in a plot to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served the Emperor Godaigo as a close aide and took part in a plot to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served the Emperor Godaigo as a close aide and took part in a plot to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>元弘の変では楠木正成の起用を勧めた人物と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he recommended to use Masashige KUSUNOKI in the Genko Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he recommended the use of Masashige KUSUNOKI in the Genko Incident.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he recommended the use of Masashige KUSUNOKI in the Genko Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後に捕えられて下総国に流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was caught and exiled to Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was caught and exiled to Shimofusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was caught and exiled to Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>Shimousa Provinceに訂正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>建武の新政後に復帰して中納言になるが、天皇の側近重用政治を諫めるも聞き入れなかったため、新政権に失望して出家して京郊外の岩倉に隠遁してそのまま行方不明となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the kenmu no shinsei (Kenmu Restoration), he returned and became a chunagon (middle counselor), but, although he admonished the Emperor for administration in which only close aides were treated favorably, and the Emperor did not hear it and, therefore, he got disappointed about the new government and he became a priest and retired and moved in Iwakura in the suburb of Kyoto and finally his whereabouts became unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the kenmu no shinsei (Kenmu Restoration), he returned and became a chunagon (middle counselor), but, although he admonished the Emperor for an administration in which only close aides were treated favorably, the Emperor would not hear it and, therefore, he became disappointed in the new government and became a priest, retiring and moving to Iwakura in the suburb of Kyoton where his final whereabouts became unknown.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the kenmu no shinsei (Kenmu Restoration), he returned and became a Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), but, although he admonished the Emperor for an administration in which only close aides were treated favorably, the Emperor would not hear it and, therefore, he became disappointed in the new government and became a priest, retiring and moving to Iwakura in the suburb of Kyoto where his final whereabouts became unknown.</e>
<cmt>中納言→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)余分なスペースを削除しました。Kyotoスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>一説には妙心寺2世住持・授翁宗弼と同一人物とも言われるが、他にも三河国死亡説・常陸国死亡説・出羽国死亡説（秋田郡山内松原村補陀寺二祖無等良雄とする菅江真澄の見解）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a certain view, Juo-Sohitsu, who was the second chief priest of the Myoshin-ji Temple, was the same person as Fujifusa MADENOKOJI and there are many different views that he died in Mikawa Province, he died in Hitachi Province, and he dies in Dewa Province (Masumi SUGAE&apos;s view that Fujifusa MADENOKOJI became the second chief priest of the Hoda-ji Temple in Matsubara mura, Sannnai, Akita-gun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a certain view, Juo-Sohitsu, who was the second chief priest of the Myoshin-ji Temple, was the same person as Fujifusa MADENOKOJI and there are many different views that he died in Mikawa Province, or in Hitachi Province, or that he died in Dewa Province (Masumi SUGAE&apos;s view that Fujifusa MADENOKOJI became the second chief priest of the Hoda-ji Temple in Matsubara mura, Sannnai, Akita-gun).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a certain view, Juo Sohitsu, who was the second chief priest of the Myoshin-ji Temple, was the same person as Fujifusa MADENOKOJI and there are many different views that he died in Mikawa Province, or in Hitachi Province, or that he died in Dewa Province (Masumi SUGAE&apos;s view that Fujifusa MADENOKOJI became the second chief priest, Muto Ryoyu of the Hoda-ji Temple in Matsubara mura, Sannnai, Akita-gun).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除しました。スペース補足しました。, Muto Ryoyu補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hatabon(id:146971), でここ(id:9565), Novo(id:87875), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), Law soma(id:45202), Himazin(id:22034), Nalc(id:139567), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>