<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利義視</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 義視（あしかが よしみ）は、室町時代中期から後期にかけての足利一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimi ASHIKAGA was a member of the ASHIKAGA clan from the mid to late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimi ASHIKAGA was a member of the ASHIKAGA clan from the mid- to late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimi ASHIKAGA was a member of the ASHIKAGA clan from the mid- to late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一時的に将軍継嗣になったこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one time he assumed the position of successor to the Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had once assumed the position of successor to the shogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had once assumed the position of successor to the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>第6代将軍・足利義教の第10子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 10th son of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the 6th Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the tenth son of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the sixth shogun.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the tenth son of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, the sixth shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は日野重光の娘・日野重子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Shigeko HINO, daughter of Shigemitsu HINO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Shigeko HINO, the daughter of Shigemitsu HINO.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Shigeko HINO, the daughter of Shigemitsu HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>第7代将軍・足利義勝と第8代将軍・足利義政の同母弟にあたり、堀越公方の足利政知は異母兄にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the younger brother by the same mother of the 7th Shogun Yoshikatsu ASHIKAGA and the 8th Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, and the elder brother by a different mother of Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo, quasi-shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the younger brother by the same mother of the seventh shogun Yoshikatsu ASHIKAGA and the eighth shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, and was the elder brother by a different mother of Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo, quasi-shogun.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the younger brother by the same mother of the seventh shogun Yoshikatsu ASHIKAGA and the eighth shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, and was the elder brother by a different mother of Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo, quasi-shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>子に第10代将軍となった足利義材（足利義稙）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son was Yoshiki ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane ASHIKAGA) who became the 10th Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son was Yoshiki ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane ASHIKAGA) who became the tenth shogun.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son was Yoshiki ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane ASHIKAGA) who became the tenth shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>はじめ天台宗浄土院 (京都市左京区)門跡として出家し、名は義尋（ぎじん）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First he became a priest of Jodoin Temple of the Tendai sect (Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City), and his name was Gijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First he became a priest of Jodoin Temple of the Tendai sect (Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City), and his name was Gijin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First he became a priest of Jodoin Temple of the Tendai sect (Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City), and his name was Gijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>嗣子に恵まれない兄・義政の後継となったが、後に兄に足利義尚が生まれると、将軍位をめぐって対立して応仁の乱を引き起こす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a successor of his older brother Yoshimasa who did not have any children, but after his older brother&apos;s son Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was born, here was a dispute over the position of the Shogun, and the Onin War broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a successor of his older brother Yoshimasa who did not have any children, but after his older brother&apos;s son Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was born there was a dispute over the position of the shogun, and the Onin War ensued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a successor of his older brother Yoshimasa who did not have any children, but after his older brother&apos;s son Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was born there was a dispute over the position of the shogun, and the Onin War ensued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>乱後は美濃に亡命し、甥の義尚と兄の義政の死後、子の義材を第10代将軍に擁立して自らは大御所（後見人）として幕政を牛耳ったが、兄の死から1年後に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war ended, he fled to Mino and after the death of his nephew Yoshihisa and his older brother Yoshimasa, he backed his son Yoshiki for the 10th Shogun and controlled shogunate politics as the doyen (guardian) until he died one year after his brother&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the end of the war he fled to Mino, and after the death of his nephew Yoshihisa and his older brother Yoshimasa he backed his son Yoshiki as the tenth shogun and controlled shogunal politics as the doyen (guardian) until his death, which came a year after that of his brother.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the end of the war he fled to Mino, and after the death of his nephew Yoshihisa and his older brother Yoshimasa he backed his son Yoshiki as the tenth shogun and controlled shogunal politics as the doyen (guardian) until his death, which came a year after that of his brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Personal History→Biographyに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>還俗から応仁の乱へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renouncing the cloth to the Onin War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renouncing the cloth to join the Onin War</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renouncing the cloth to join the Onin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>永享11年（1439年）1月18日、第6代将軍・足利義教の10男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on January 18th, 1439 as the 10th son of the 6th Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on January 18, 1439 as the tenth son of the sixth shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on February 11, 1439 as the tenth son of the sixth shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>はじめ出家して浄土院 (京都市左京区)の門跡となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First he became a priest of Jodoin Temple of theTendai sect (Sakyo-ward, Kyoto-city).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First he became a priest of Jodoin Temple of the Tendai sect (Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>sp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First he became a priest of Jodoin Temple of the Tendai sect (Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>寛正5年（1464年）に実子がなかった兄・義政に請われて僧侶から還俗して、義視を名乗り、兄の後継となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1464 he renounced the cloth as requested by his older brother Yoshimasa who did not have his own son, called himself Yoshimi and became his older brother’s successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1464 he renounced the cloth as requested by his older brother Yoshimasa, who had no son, called himself Yoshimi and became his brother&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1464 he renounced the cloth as requested by his older brother Yoshimasa, who had no son, called himself Yoshimi and became his brother&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして管領の細川勝元を後見人として次期将軍を約束され、義政の正室・日野富子の実妹を正室に迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promised to become the next Shogun with Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, Kanrei, the shogunal deputy of thhe Kanto region, as his guardian, and he took the younger sister of Yosimasa’s official wife Tomiko HINO by blood as his official wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promised to become the next shogun with the kanrei Katsumoto HOSOKAWA (the shogunal deputy of the Kanto region) as his guardian, and he took the younger blood-sister of Yoshimasa&apos;s official wife Tomiko HINO as his official wife.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promised to become the next shogun with the kanrei Katsumoto HOSOKAWA (the shogunal deputy of the Kanto region) as his guardian, and he took the younger blood-sister of Yoshimasa&apos;s official wife Tomiko HINO as his official wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>今出川の屋敷に住したため、今出川殿と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Imadegawa dono, because he lived in the Imadegawa residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Imadegawa dono because he lived in the Imadegawa residence.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Imadegawa dono because he lived in the Imadegawa residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが寛正6年（1465年）、義政と富子の間に実子の足利義尚が誕生すると、富子は義尚の将軍後継を望み、義視らと対立するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, Yoshimasa&apos;s biological son, was born to Yoshimasa and Tomiko in 1465, Tomiko desired the succession of Yoshihisa to the Shogunate and she started to oppose Yoshimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, Yoshimasa&apos;s biological son, was born to Yoshimasa and Tomiko in 1465, Tomiko desired the succession of Yoshihisa to the shogunate and she began to oppose Yoshimi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, Yoshimasa&apos;s biological son, was born to Yoshimasa and Tomiko in 1465, Tomiko desired the succession of Yoshihisa to the shogunate and she began to oppose Yoshimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>9月には義視謀反の噂が立つが、義視は勝元に無実を訴え、義尚の乳父であった伊勢貞親が讒訴の罪を問われ、貞親派が失脚する文正の政変が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September the Bunsho political change occurred which caused the Yoshimasa faction to lose its position, when it was rumoured that Yoshimi was contemplating a coup d’etat, but Yoshimi pleaded his innocence to Katsumoto, and Sadachika ISE, who was Yoshihisa’s breast-feed mother’s husband, was tried for slander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September the Bunsho political change occurred and caused the Yoshimasa faction to lose its position, when it was rumored that Yoshimi was contemplating a coup d&apos;état; however, Yoshimi pleaded his innocence to Katsumoto, and Sadachika ISE, who was the husband of Yoshihisa&apos;s wet nurse, was tried for slander.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September the Bunsho political change occurred and caused the Yoshimasa faction to lose its position, when it was rumored that Yoshimi was contemplating a coup d&apos;état; however, Yoshimi pleaded his innocence to Katsumoto, and Sadachika ISE, who was the husband of Yoshihisa&apos;s wet nurse, was tried for slander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>応仁元年（1467年）、足利将軍家の家督相続問題と畠山氏・斯波氏の家督相続問題などが関係して応仁の乱が発生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1467 the Onin War broke out, in connection with the problems concerning the succession to the headship of the Ashikaga Shogun familiy and the succession to the headships of the Hatakeyama family and the Shiba family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1467 the Onin War erupted in connection with the problems concerning the succession to the headship of the Ashikaga Shogun family as well as the succession to the headships of the Hatakeyama and Shiba families.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1467 the Onin War erupted in connection with the problems concerning the succession to the headship of the Ashikaga Shogun family as well as the succession to the headships of the Hatakeyama and Shiba families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>義視ははじめ勝元が率いる東軍に属したが、8月に周防国の大内政弘が上洛すると伊勢国の一色氏、北畠氏のもとへ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimi first belonged to the Eastern Force led by Katsumoto, but in August when Masahiro OUCHI of the Province of Suo went to Kyoto, he fled to the Isshiki family and Kitabatake family of the Province of Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimi first belonged to the eastern force led by Katsumoto, but in August, when Masahiro OUCHI of Suo Province went to Kyoto, he fled to the Isshiki and Kitabatake families of Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimi first belonged to the eastern force led by Katsumoto, but in September, when Masahiro OUCHI of Suo Province went to Kyoto, he fled to the Isshiki and Kitabatake families of Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>応仁2年（1468年）には義政の説得で伊勢から帰京するが、義政と対立して室町亭を脱走し、山名宗全（山名持豊）の西軍に与して文明 (日本)元年（1469年）には四国・九州の諸大名を味方につけようと奔走している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1468 he came back to Kyoto from Ise, persuaded by Yoshimasa, but he escaped from the Muromachi Tei, palace because he was opposed to Yoshimasa, and he supported the Western Force of Sozen YAMANA (Mochitoyo YAMANA), making every effort to win feudal lords of Shikoku and Kyusyu over to his side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1468 he came back to Kyoto from Ise, persuaded by Yoshimasa, but he escaped from the Muromachi Tei (palace) because he was opposed to Yoshimasa, and instead he supported the western force of Sozen YAMANA (Mochitoyo YAMANA), making every effort to win the feudal lords of Shikoku and Kyusyu over to his side.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1468 he came back to Kyoto from Ise, persuaded by Yoshimasa, but he escaped from the Muromachi Tei (palace) because he was opposed to Yoshimasa, and instead he supported the western force of Sozen YAMANA (Mochitoyo YAMANA), making every effort to win the feudal lords of Shikoku and Kyusyu over to his side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>文明5年（1473年）、山名宗全と細川勝元が相次いで死去したため、文明7年（1475年）に義政と講和する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a peace with Yoshimasa in 1475 because Sozen YAMANA and Katsumoto Hosokawa died one after another in 1473.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made peace with Yoshimasa in 1475, given that Sozen YAMANA and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA had both died in 1473.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made peace with Yoshimasa in 1475, given that Sozen YAMANA and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA had both died in 1473.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし兄との溝を埋めることは難しかったため、美濃の土岐成頼のもとに亡命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he fled to Shigenori TOKI of Mino because it was difficult to solve the differences between him and his older brother Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he fled to Shigenori TOKI of Mino because it was difficult to solve the differences between him and his older brother Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he fled to Shigenori TOKI of Mino because it was difficult to solve the differences between him and his older brother Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>復権から大御所へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Restoration to a Leading Figure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Restoration to a Leading Figure</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Restoration to a Leading Figure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>長享3年（1489年）に足利義尚が死去すると、義視は子の義材と共に上洛し、娘のいる京都三条の通玄寺に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA died in 1489, Yoshimi went to Kyoto with his son Yoshiki and entered Tsugen-ji Temple on Kyoto Sanjyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA died in 1489, Yoshimi went to Kyoto with his son Yoshiki and entered Tsugen-ji Temple on Kyoto Sanjyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA died in 1489, Yoshimi went to Kyoto with his son Yoshiki and entered Tsugen-ji Temple on Kyoto Sanjyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そしてここで出家して道存（どうぞん）と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And here he became a priest with the title of Dozon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There he became a priest with the title of Dozon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There he became a priest with the title of Dozon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>実は、義視は兄夫婦と長享元年（1487年）頃から和睦を模索し、子の義材を義政の養子として、継嗣の無かった義尚の継嗣にしていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Yoshimi was looking for reconciliation with his older brother and his brother&apos;s wife from around 1487, and let Yoshimasa adopt his son Yoshiki, making him the successor of Yoshihisa who did not have any successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Yoshimi began to seek reconciliation with his older brother and his brother&apos;s wife in about 1487, and he let Yoshimasa adopt his son Yoshiki, making him the successor of Yoshihisa, who had no natural successor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Yoshimi began to seek reconciliation with his older brother and his brother&apos;s wife in about 1487, and he let Yoshimasa adopt his son Yoshiki, making him the successor of Yoshihisa, who had no natural successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>実際、この年に義材は従五位下・左馬頭に叙位・任官されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, this year Yoshiki was conferred the Junior Fifth Court Rank and appointed to Samanokami, Minister of the horse office of the left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, this year Yoshiki was conferred the junior fifth court rank and appointed to Samanokami, (minister of the Horse Office of the Left).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, this year Yoshiki was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed to Samanokami (minister of the Horse Office of the Left).</e>
<cmt>従五位下→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade),スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>延徳2年（1490年）1月7日に兄・義政が病死すると、義視は日野富子と結託して7月5日に子の義材を第10代将軍に擁立し、自らは将軍の父として幕政を牛耳ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his older brother Yoshimasa died from a disease on January 7, 1490, Yoshimi backed up his son Yoshiki as the 10th Shogun on July 5, in collusion with Tomiko HINO, and he himself dominated the Shogunate politics as the father of Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his older brother Yoshimasa died of a disease on January 7, 1490, Yoshimi supported his son Yoshiki as the tenth shogun on July 5, in collusion with Tomiko HINO, and he himself dominated the shogunal politics as the father of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his older brother Yoshimasa died of a disease on February 5, 1490, Yoshimi supported his son Yoshiki as the tenth shogun on July 31, in collusion with Tomiko HINO, and he himself dominated the shogunal politics as the father of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし応仁の乱であれほど敵対していた日野富子と反りが合うわけもなく、次第に対立して義視は富子の邸宅である小川第を破壊したり、領地を差し押さえたりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there was no way he could get along with Tomiko HINO who used to be opposed to him in the Ohnin War so much, and Yoshimi gradually became opposed to Tomiko, destroyed Ogawadai manor, Tomiko&apos;s residence and seized her territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there was no way he could get along with Tomiko HINO, who had been so opposed to him in the Onin War, and Yoshimi gradually became opposed to Tomiko, destroying the Ogawadai manor (Tomiko&apos;s residence) and seizing her territory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there was no way he could get along with Tomiko HINO, who had been so opposed to him in the Onin War, and Yoshimi gradually became opposed to Tomiko, destroying the Ogawadai manor (Tomiko&apos;s residence) and seizing her territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>このため、富子は義材擁立に反感を持っていた管領・細川政元に接近したため、義視は政元との対立を不利と判断して、義材の将軍宣下の儀式を政元の屋敷で執り行なうなどの緩和策も示している（ただし、政元は将軍宣下の翌日に管領職を辞任している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Tomiko approached the Kanryo Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who felt hostile to the succession of Yoshiki and as Yoshimi decided that a confrontation with Masamoto was not to his advantage he proposed to hold the ceremony of the Emperor&apos;s declaration of Yoshiki as Shogun in Masamoto&apos;s residence (However, Masamoto quit the position of Kanryo the day after Yoshiki was declared Shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Tomiko approached the kanryo, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who felt hostile to the succession of Yoshiki, and because Yoshimi decided that a confrontation with Masamoto was not to his advantage he proposed holding the ceremony of the Emperor&apos;s declaration of Yoshiki as the shogun at Masamoto&apos;s residence (however, Masamoto quit the position of kanryo the day after Yoshiki was declared shogun).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Tomiko approached the kanryo, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who felt hostile to the succession of Yoshiki, and because Yoshimi decided that a confrontation with Masamoto was not to his advantage he proposed holding the ceremony of the Emperor&apos;s declaration of Yoshiki as the shogun at Masamoto&apos;s residence (however, Masamoto quit the position of kanryo the day after Yoshiki was declared shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last days</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Last Days</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Last Days</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>こうして細川政元と対立して状況が不利に陥る中での延徳3年（1491年）1月7日、奇しくも1年前に兄・義政が死んだのと同じ日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on January 7, 1491 when he was in a dispute with Masamoto HOSOKAWA and in a disadvantageous situation, by a curious coincidence he died on the same day as his older brother Yoshimasa did one year ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Curiously, on January 7, 1491, when he was in a dispute with Masamoto HOSOKAWA and in a disadvantageous situation, he died; it was exactly one year after the death of his older brother, Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Curiously, on February 24, 1491, when he was in a dispute with Masamoto HOSOKAWA and in a disadvantageous situation, he died; it was exactly one year after the death of his older brother, Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>享年53。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 53 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 53 years old.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 53 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dates are in the old calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dates given correspond to the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dates given correspond to the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>1464年（寛正5年）12月2日、還俗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renounced the cloth on December 2, 1464.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He renounced the cloth on December 2, 1464.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 2, 1464: He renounced the cloth.</e>
<cmt>He renounced the cloth on December 2, 1464.→December 2, 1464: He renounced the cloth.に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>従五位下に叙し、左馬頭に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to Jyugoi-ge, Junior Fifth Court Rank Low, and appointed Samonokami, Minister of the horse office of the left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Jyugoi-ge, junior fifth low court rank, and was appointed Samonokami (minister of the Horse Office of the Left).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), and was appointed Samonokami (minister of the Horse Office of the Left).</e>
<cmt>従五位下→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade),スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>1465年（寛正6年）1月5日、従四位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1465, promoted to Jyushii-ge, the Junior Fourth Rank Low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1465, he was promoted to Jyushii-ge, the junior fourth low court rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1465: He was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>従四位下→Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade)On January 5, 1465, he→January 5, 1465: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>左馬頭如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained Samonokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the post of Samonokami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the post of Samonokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>11月20日、元服し、義視を名乗り、禁色賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 20, had a coming-of-age ceremony, took the name Yoshimi and granted to wear the prohibited colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 20, had a coming-of-age ceremony, took the name Yoshimi and was allowed to wear the prohibited colors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 20, had a coming-of-age ceremony, took the name Yoshimi and was allowed to wear the prohibited colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>11月25日、参議に補任し、左近衛中将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 25, became Sangi, Councillor and also assumed Sakon&apos;e-no-chujyo, the Deputy General of Imperial Guard of the Left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 25, he became Sangi (councilor) and also assumed the post of Sakon&apos;e-no-chujyo (the deputy general of the Imperial Guard of the Left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 25, he became Sangi (councilor) and also assumed the post of Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>左近衛中将→Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>12月17日、従三位に昇叙し、権大納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 17, promoted to Jyusanni, Junior Third Court Rank and transferred to Gon-Dainagon, Junior Chief of the Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 17, he was promoted to Jyusanni, junior third court rank, and was transferred to Gon-Dainagon (the junior chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 17, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), and was transferred to Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>従三位→Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)権大納言→Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>1466年（文正元年）1月6日、従二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 6, 1466, promoted to Jyunii, Junior Second Court Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6, 1466, he promoted to Jyunii, junior second court rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 6, 1466: He promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>従二位→Junii (Junior Second Rank)On January 6, 1466, he→January 6, 1466: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>権大納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained Gon-Dainagon, Junior Chief of the Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the post o Gon-Dainagon (junior chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the post o Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>Gon-Dainagon (junior chief councilor of state)→Gon Dainagon</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>1467年（文正2年）1月5日、正二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1467, promoted to Shonii, Senior Second Court Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1467, he was promoted to Shonii, senior second court rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1467: He was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>正二位→Shonii (Senior Second Rank)On January 5, 1467, he→January 5, 1467: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>権大納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained Gon-Dainagon, Junior Chief of the Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the post of Gon-Dainagon (junior chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the post of Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>Gon-Dainagon (junior chief councilor of state)→Gon Dainagon</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>8月23日、伊勢国に出奔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 23, fled to the Province of Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 23, he fled to Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 23, he fled to Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>1468年（応仁2年）12月、解官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1468, dismissed from his offices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 1468, he was dismissed from his offices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1468: He was dismissed from his offices.</e>
<cmt>On December 1468, he→December 1468: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>1489年（長享3年）12月27日、出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 27, 1489, became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 27, 1489, he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 27, 1489: He became a priest.</e>
<cmt>On December 27, 1489, he→December 27, 1489: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="46">
<j>1490年（延徳2年）7月5日、准后宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 5, 1490, named a Jugo, the equivalent status to three Empresses by Imperial decree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 5, 1490, by imperial decree, he was designated as Jugo, with status equivalent to three empresses.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 5, 1490: By imperial decree, he was designated as Jugo, with status equivalent to three empresses.</e>
<cmt>On July 5, 1490, by→July 5, 1490: Byに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>1491年（延徳3年）1月7日、死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 7, 1491, passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7, 1491, he passed away.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 7, 1491: He passed away.</e>
<cmt>On January 7, 1491, he→January 7, 1491: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>2月24日、贈従一位太政大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 24, posthumously raised to Senior First Court Rank and Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 24, he was posthumously elevated to senior first court rank and grand minister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 24, he was posthumously elevated to Juichii Dajo Daijin (Junior First Rank Grand Minister of state).</e>
<cmt>従一位太政大臣→Juichii Dajo Daijin (Junior First Rank Grand Minister of state)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), ドルチェット(id:46458), やりたこ(id:113528), Ittyon(id:1348), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Doskoi 8(id:1070), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), スゥ(id:33856), Sorrysorry(id:102591), Johncapistrano(id:969), でここ(id:9565), Tanuki Z(id:612), Noche de la pena(id:166012), Yukichin(id:725), YurikBot(id:18605), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>