<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原鎌足</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kamatari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kamatari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kamatari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 鎌足（ふじわら の かまたり、推古天皇22年（614年） - 天智天皇8年10月16日 (旧暦)（669年11月14日））は、飛鳥時代の政治家で藤原氏の始祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kamatari (614 - November 14, 669) was a statesman who lived in the Asuka period and the earliest ancestor of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kamatari (614 - November 14, 669) was a statesman who lived in the Asuka period and the earliest ancestor of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kamatari (614 - November 17, 669) was a statesman who lived in the Asuka period and the earliest ancestor of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>November 14→November 17(グレゴリオ歴）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大化の改新以降に中大兄皇子（天智天皇）の腹心として活躍し、藤原氏繁栄の礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked as a trustworthy assistant of Naka no Oe no Oji (Emperor Tenchi) since the Taika Reforms and laid the foundation for prosperity of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked as a trustworthy assistant of Naka no Oe no Oji (Emperor Tenchi) since the Taika Reforms and laid the foundation for the prosperity of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked as a devoted assistant of Naka-no-Oe-no-Oji, later Emperor Tenchi, since the Taika Reforms and laid the foundation for the prosperity of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『藤氏家伝』には｢偉雅､風姿特秀」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is recorded as a &quot;great person, very distinguished in appearance&quot; in &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; (Biographies of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is recorded as a &quot;great person, very distinguished in appearance&quot; in &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; (Biographies of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is recorded as a &apos;great person, very distinguished in appearance&apos; in &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; (Biographies of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>&quot; →&apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>字は仲郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the nickname of Tsugio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the nickname Tsugio.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the nickname Tsugio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>元々は中臣氏の一族で初期の頃には中臣 鎌子（なかとみ の かまこ）と名乗っていた（欽明天皇朝で物部尾輿と共に排仏をおこなった中臣鎌子とは別人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally he was a member of the Nakatomi clan and called himself NAKATOMI no Kamako (a different person from NAKATOMI no Kamako who took part in Haibutsu (abolishment of Buddhism) with MONONOBE no Okoshi in Emperor Kinmei&apos;s era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally he was a member of the Nakatomi clan and called himself NAKATOMI no Kamako (a different person from NAKATOMI no Kamako who took part in Haibutsu (abolishment of Buddhism) with MONONOBE no Okoshi in Emperor Kinmei&apos;s era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally he was a member of the Nakatomi clan and took the name NAKATOMI no Kamako (NAKATOMI no Kamako who took part in the abolishment of Buddhism with MONONOBE no Okoshi in Emperor Kinmei&apos;s era was the other person.).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後中臣 鎌足（なかとみ の かまたり）に改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he changed his name to NAKATOMI no Kamatari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he changed his name to NAKATOMI no Kamatari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he changed his name to NAKATOMI no Kamatari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして臨終に際して大織冠とともに藤原姓を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in his last hours, he was granted the family name of Fujiwara along with the court rank of Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then in his last hours, he was granted the family name of Fujiwara along with the court rank of Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then in his deathbed, he was granted the family name of Fujiwara along with the court rank of the Grand Crown.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>つまり、生きていたころの彼を指す場合は「中臣鎌足」を用い、「藤原氏の祖」として彼を指す場合には「藤原鎌足」を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, &quot;NAKATOMI no Kamatari&quot; is used to refer to Kamatari when he was alive, but &quot;FUJIWARA no Kamatari&quot; is used to refer to him as the &quot;founder of the Fujiwara clan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, &quot;NAKATOMI no Kamatari&quot; is used to refer to Kamatari when he was alive, but &quot;FUJIWARA no Kamatari&quot; is used to refer to him as the &quot;founder of the Fujiwara clan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, &apos;NAKATOMI no Kamatari&apos; is used to refer to Kamatari when he was alive, but &apos;FUJIWARA no Kamatari&apos; is used to refer to him as the &apos;founder of the Fujiwara clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; →&apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>出生地について、『藤氏家伝』は大和国高市郡藤原（現在の橿原市）としているが、大原（現在の明日香村）や常陸国鹿島とする説（『大鏡』）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His place of birth is recorded as Fujiwara, Takaichi District, Yamato Province (present-day Kashihara City) according to &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot;, but there is also a theory holding that it was Ohara (present-day Asuka-mura) or Kashima, Hitachi Province (&quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His place of birth is recorded as Fujiwara, Takaichi District, Yamato Province (present-day Kashihara City) according to the Toshi Kaden, but there is also a theory holding that it was Ohara (present-day Asuka-mura) or Kashima, Hitachi Province (Okagami [The Great Mirror]).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His place of birth is recorded as Fujiwara, Takaichi County, Yamato Province (present-day Kashihara City) according &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot;, but there is also a theory holding that it was Ohara (present-day Asuka-mura) or Kashima, Hitachi Province (according to &quot;Okagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>早くから中国の史書に関心を持ち、『六韜』を暗記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He showed interest in Chinese history books from early on, and he memorized &quot;Rikuto&quot; (an ancient Chinese strategy book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He showed interest in Chinese history books from early on, and he memorized Rikuto (an ancient Chinese strategy book).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He showed interest in Chinese history books from childhood and memorized an ancient Chinese strategy book &quot;Rikuto&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>隋・唐に留学していた南淵請安が塾を開くとそこで儒教を学び、蘇我入鹿とともに秀才とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When MINABUCHI no Shoan, who had studied in Sui and Tang started a school, Kamatari learned Confucianism there, and he was regarded as being brilliant along with SOGA no Iruka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When MINABUCHI no Shoan, who had studied in Sui and Tang started a school, Kamatari learned Confucianism there, and he was regarded as being brilliant along with SOGA no Iruka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When MINABUCHI no Shoan, who had studied in China (Sui and Tang dynasties) started a school, Kamatari learned Confucianism there, and he was regarded as being brilliant as well as SOGA no Iruka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『日本書紀』によると644年（皇極天皇3年）に中臣氏の家業であった祭官につくことを求められたが、鎌足は固辞して摂津国三島の別邸に退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), in 644 he was sought to take on the job of an official who arranges festivals and rites, which was the family business of Nakatomi clan, but he refused firmly and retired to his second residence in Mishima, Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), in 644 he was sought to take on the job of an official who arranges festivals and rites, which was the family business of Nakatomi clan, but he refused firmly and retired to his second residence in Mishima, Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, in 644 he was sought to take on the post of an official who arranges festivals and rites, which was the family business of Nakatomi clan, but he refused flatly and retired to his second residence in Mishima, Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>密かに蘇我氏体制打倒の意志を固め、擁立すべき皇子を探した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He secretly strengthened the will to bring down Soga clan&apos;s powers and searched for an imperial prince to put up for this purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He secretly strengthened the will to bring down the Soga clan&apos;s powers and searched for an imperial prince to put up for this purpose.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He secretly strengthened his intention to bring down the Soga clan&apos;s powers and searched for an imperial prince to enthrone for this purpose.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>初めは軽皇子（孝徳天皇）に近づき、後に中大兄皇子に接近した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First he became close with Prince Karu (Emperor Kotoku), and later approached Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First he became close with Prince Karu (Emperor Kotoku), and later approached Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First he became close to Prince Karu (Emperor Kotoku), and then approached Naka no Oe no Oji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、蘇我一族内部の対立に乗じて、蘇我倉山田石川麻呂を味方に引き入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he took advantage of antagonism within the Soga clan and won SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro over to his side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he took advantage of antagonism within the Soga clan and won SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro over to his side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he took advantage of antagonism within the Soga clan and won SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro over to his side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>645年、中大兄皇子・石川麻呂らと協力して飛鳥板蓋宮（あすかのいたぶきのみや）にて、当時政権を握っていた蘇我入鹿を暗殺、入鹿の父の蘇我蝦夷を自殺に追いやった（乙巳の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 645, he conspired with Naka no Oe no Oji and Ishikawamaro and assassinated SOGA no Iruka, who was in power at that time, at Asuka no Itabuki no Miya Palace; Iruka&apos;s father, SOGA no Emishi, was driven to commit suicide (Isshi Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 645, he conspired with Naka no Oe no Oji and Ishikawamaro and assassinated SOGA no Iruka, who was in power at that time, at Asuka no Itabuki no Miya Palace; Iruka&apos;s father, SOGA no Emishi, was driven to commit suicide (Isshi Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 645, he conspired with Naka no Oe no Oji and Ishikawamaro and assassinated SOGA no Iruka, who was in power at that time, at Asuka no Itabuki no Miya Palace; Iruka&apos;s father, SOGA no Emishi, was driven to commit suicide (Isshi Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この功績から、内臣（うちつおみ）に任じられ、軍事指揮権を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of this achievement, he was appointed Uchitsuomi (government post) and gained control of military affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this achievement, he was appointed Uchitsuomi (government post) and gained control of military affairs.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this achievement, he was appointed a political adviser to the crown prince and gained control of military affairs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ただし、内臣は寵臣・参謀の意味で正式な官職ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Uchitsuomi referred to a favorite retainer or general staff and was not a formal job grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the position of Uchitsuomi was a favorite retainer or general staff and was not a formal job grade.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the position of political adviser was a court favorite or an adviser and not a formal job..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>その後、大化の改新を推進しようとする中大兄皇子の側近として、保守派の左大臣の阿倍内麻呂、右大臣の蘇我(倉山田)石川麻呂と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Kamatari worked as the close advisor of Naka no Oe no Oji, who was promoting the Taika Reforms, and conflicted with conservative ABE no Uchimaro, Minister of the Left, and SOGA (KURAYAMADA) no Ishikawamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Kamatari worked as the close advisor of Naka no Oe no Oji, who was promoting the Taika Reforms, and conflicted with conservative ABE no Uchimaro, Minister of the Left, and SOGA (KURAYAMADA) no Ishikawamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Kamatari worked as the close advisor of Naka no Oe no Oji, who was promoting the Taika Reforms, and conflicted with conservative ABE no Uchimaro, Minister of the Left, and SOGA (KURAYAMADA) no Ishikawamaro, Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>右大臣の　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>647年の新冠位制度では大錦冠（だいきんかん）を授与された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded Daikinkan cap rank under the new system which indicated court ranks by headgear colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded Daikinkan cap rank under the new system which indicated court ranks by headgear colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded Daikinkan rank in 647 under the new system of indicating court ranks by headgear colors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>649年に梯麻呂・石川麻呂が死去・失脚したあと勢力を伸ばし、654年（白雉5年）ごろには大紫冠（だいしかん）に昇格した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After ABE no Kurahashi no Maro died/fell from power in 649, Kamatari extended power and was promoted to Daishikan cap rank around 654.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After ABE no Kurahashi no Maro died and fell from power in 649, Kamatari extended power and was promoted to Daishikan cap rank around 654.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After ABE no Kurahashi no Maro and Ishikawamaro died and fell from power in 649, Kamatari extended power and was promoted to Daishikan rank around 654.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>669年、死の直前に天智天皇が見舞うと「生きては軍国に務無し」と語った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 669, when Emperor Tenchi paid him a visit just before his death, Kamatari said: &quot;I could not carry out my duty in military when I was alive&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 669, when Emperor Tenchi paid him a visit just before his death, Kamatari said: &quot;I could not carry out my duty in the military while I was alive&quot;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 669, when Emperor Tenchi visited Kamatari just before Kamatari&apos;s death, Kamatari said: &apos;I could not carry out my duty in the military while I was alive.&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>すなわち「私は軍略で貢献できなかった」と嘆いているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is to say, he lamented over &quot;not having contributed in strategic skills&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is to say, he lamented over &quot;not having contributed in strategic skills&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That means he lamented over &apos;not having contributed in strategic skills.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>天智天皇から大織冠を授けられ、内大臣に任じ、「藤原」のカバネを賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was granted Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown) by Emperor Tenchi, was appointed Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior), and was given the kabane (hereditary title used in ancient Japan to denote rank and political standing) of &quot;Fujiwara&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was granted the rank of Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown) by Emperor Tenchi, was appointed Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior), and was given the kabane (hereditary title used in ancient Japan to denote rank and political standing) of &apos;Fujiwara&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted the rank of Daishokkan, the Grand Crown, by Emperor Tenchi, was appointed Minister of the Interior, and was given the hereditary title of &apos;Fujiwara.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>鎌足の業績ははっきりしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamatari&apos;s accomplishments are not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamatari&apos;s accomplishments are not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamatari&apos;s accomplishments are not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>『藤氏家伝』には近江令の編纂を命じられたとされているが、これを疑問視する研究者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have been ordered to compile Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code) according to &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot;, but many researchers find this questionable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have been ordered to compile Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code) according to the Toshi Kaden, but many researchers find this questionable.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He might have been ordered to compile the Omi Administrative Code according to the Toshi Kaden, but many researchers find this questionable.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>墓所・祭所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave and Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave and Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave and shrine</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>死後、奈良県桜井市多武峯の談山神社に祭られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death, he was enshrined in Tanzan-jinja Shrine in Tonomine, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death, he was enshrined in Tanzan-jinja Shrine in Tonomine, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death, he was enshrined in Tanzanjinja Shrine in Tonomine, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>『多武峯縁起絵巻』には、鎌足が生まれたときにどこからか鎌をくわえた白い狐が現われ、生まれた子の足元に置いたため、その子を「鎌子」と名づけたと描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description in &quot;Tonomine engi emaki&quot; (Illustrated Scrolls of the Tonomine), when Kamatari was born, a white fox with a sickle in its mouth appeared from somewhere and left the sickle at the foot of the newborn baby, and thus the baby was named &quot;Kamako&quot; (&quot;kama&quot; meaning a sickle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the description in Tonomine Engi Emaki (Illustrated Scrolls of the Tonomine), when Kamatari was born, a white fox with a sickle in its mouth appeared from somewhere and left the sickle at the foot of the newborn baby, thus the baby was named Kamako (kama meaning a sickle).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a description in the illustrated scrolls &quot;Tonomine Engi Emaki&quot;, when Kamatari was born, a white fox with a sickle in its mouth appeared from somewhere and left the sickle at the foot of the newborn baby, thus the baby was named Kamako (kama meaning a sickle).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この逸話にちなみ、談山神社では鎌をくわえた白狐のお守りが売られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this anecdote, Omamori (a personal amulet) of a white fox with a sickle in its mouth is sold in Tanzan-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this anecdote, an Omamori (a personal amulet) of a white fox with a sickle in its mouth is sold in Tanzan-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this anecdote, an amulet of a white fox with a sickle in its mouth is sold in Tanzanjinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>墓処は定かではないが、『日本三代実録』天安 (日本)2年（858年）条には「多武峰墓を藤原鎌足の墓とし、十陵四墓の例に入れる」という記述があり、平安時代中ごろ成立と見られる『多武峯略記』などに「最初は摂津国安威（現在の大阪府茨木市）に葬られたが、後に大和国の多武峯に改葬された」との説が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his grave is not known exactly, according to the section on the second year of Tenan era (858) in &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts), there is a mention that &quot;Tonomine&apos;s grave shall be made the grave of FUJIWARA no Kamatari, as an example of Four Graves of Ten Imperial Mausoleums&quot;; according to &quot;Tonomine Ryakuki&quot; (Brief Records of Tonomine), there is a theory that he was &quot;buried in Ai, Settsu Province (present-day Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture) at first, but reburied later in Tonomine, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>【天安2年(858)条】→【section on the second year of Tenan era (858)】定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his grave is not known exactly, according to the section on the second year of the Tenan era (858) in the Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (the sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts), there is mention that &quot;Tonomine&apos;s grave shall be made the grave of FUJIWARA no Kamatari, as an example of Four Graves of Ten Imperial Mausoleums&quot;. According to Tonomine Ryakuki (Brief Records of Tonomine), there is a theory that he was buried in Ai, Settsu Province (present-day Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture) at first, but reburied later in Tonomine, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>run-on sentence; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his graveyard is not known exactly, according to the section on the second year of the Tenan era (858) in &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot;, there is mention that &apos;Tonomine&apos;s grave shall be made the grave of FUJIWARA no Kamatari, as one of Four Graves of Ten Imperial Mausoleums,&apos; and according to &quot;Tonomine Ryakuki&quot; (Brief Records of Tonomine), there is a theory that he was buried in Ai, Settsu Province (present-day Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture) at first, but reburied later in Tonomine, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>なお、昭和9年（1934年）に大阪府茨木市大字安威の阿武山古墳の発掘中に発見された埋葬人骨は藤原鎌足本人であるとする説も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that the human bones of burial, discovered during the excavation of Abuyama Tumulus in Oaza Ai, Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture are those of FUJIWARA no Kamatari himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory that the human bones of burial, discovered during the excavation of Abuyama Tumulus in Oaza Ai, Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture are those of FUJIWARA no Kamatari himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a hypothesis that the buried bones, discovered during the excavation of Abuyama Tumulus in Oaza Ai, Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture in 1934 are those of FUJIWARA no Kamatari himself.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>一方、『藤氏家伝』の記述に基づき、鎌足の墓は京都市山科区のどこかに存在するという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is also the theory Kamatari&apos;s grave exists somewhere in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City based on such mention in &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there is also the theory that Kamatari&apos;s grave exists somewhere in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City based on that mentioned in Toshi Kaden.</e>
<cmt>punctuation; wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, there is another hypothesis that Kamatari&apos;s grave exists somewhere in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City based on that mentioned in &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>和歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka (A Traditional Japanese Poem of Thirty-One Syllables)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka (A Traditional Japanese Poem of Thirty-One Syllables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka (A Traditional Japanese Poem of Thirty-One Syllables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>『万葉集』に2首所収。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two poems are included in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two poems are included in the Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His two poems are included in &quot;Manyoshu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>『歌経標式』に1首所収。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One poem is included in &quot;Kakyo Hyoshiki&quot; (A Formulary for Verse Based on the Canons of Poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One poem is included in the Kakyo Hyoshiki (A Formulary for Verse Based on the Canons of Poetry).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One poem is included in A Formulary for Verse Based on the Canons of Poetry, &quot;Kakyo Hyoshiki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>『万葉集』の1首は正室・鏡女王に送った物で、もう1首が鎌足が采女安見児（やすみこ）を得たことを喜ぶ歌である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the poems in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; was intended for his lawful wife, Kagami no Okimi, and the other poem expressed his joy of getting Yasumiko, who was umene (a maid-in-waiting at the court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the poems in the Manyoshu was intended for his lawful wife, Kagami no Okimi, and the other poem expressed his joy of winning the affections of Yasumiko, who was umene (a maid-in-waiting at the court).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the poems in the Manyoshu was intended for the lawful wife, Kagami no Okimi, and the other poem expressed his joy of winning the affections of Yasumiko, who was a maid-in-waiting at the court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>『われはもや安見児得たり皆人の得難にすとふ安見児得たり』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Warehamoya Yasumiko Etari Minahitono Ekatenisutofu Yasumiko Etari&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warehamoya Yasumiko Etari Minahitono Ekatenisutofu Yasumiko Etari</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warehamoya Yasumiko Etari Minahitono Ekatenisutofu Yasumiko Etari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>（私は安見児を得た、皆が手に入れられないと言っていたあの安見児を得たのだ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(I got Yasumiko, the Yasumiko whom everyone talked about not being able to get.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(I won the affections of Yasumiko--the same Yasumiko whom everyone said was unreachable.)</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(I won the affections of Yasumiko--the same Yasumiko whom anyone said was unreachable.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>采女とは、各国の豪族から天皇に献上された美女たちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umene referred to beautiful women who were presented to the emperor by Gozoku (local ruling families) of various provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umene referred to beautiful women who were presented to the emperor by Gozoku (local ruling families) of various provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umene referred to beautiful women who were presented to the emperor by local ruling families of various provinces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>数は多しといえども天皇の妻ともなる資格を持つことから、当時、采女への恋は命をもって償うべき禁忌であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was a large number of umene, since umene was also qualified to be an emperor&apos;s wife, fancying umene was considered taboo at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was a large number of umene, since umene were also qualified to be an emperor&apos;s wife, fancying an umene was considered taboo at that time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was a large number of umene, since umene were also qualified to be an emperor&apos;s wife, fancying an umene was considered taboo at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>鎌足の場合は、おそらく天智天皇に覚えが良かったことから、特別に采女を賜ったのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Kamatari, he received umene as a special case probably because he had won Emperor Tenchi&apos;s favor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Kamatari, he received an umene as a special case probably because he had won Emperor Tenchi&apos;s favor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Kamatari, he received an umene as a special case probably because he had won Emperor Tenchi&apos;s favor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>上の歌には万葉らしく、鎌足の二重の喜びが素直に表現されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above poem is characteristic of Manyo poem in that Kamatari&apos;s double happiness is expressed in a straightforward manner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above poem is characteristic of Manyo poems in that Kamatari&apos;s double happiness is expressed in a straightforward manner.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above poem is characteristic of Manyo poems in that Kamatari&apos;s twofold happiness is expressed in a straightforward manner.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>すなわち、恋を成就した歓びと、天皇が自分だけに特別な許可を与えたという名誉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is to say, he had the joy of succeeding in love and the honor of having been granted an exceptional permission by the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is to say, he had the joy of succeeding in love and the honor of having been granted exceptional permission by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That means he had the joy of succeeding in love and the honor of having been granted exceptional permission by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kanejan(id:78613), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 向日葵三十郎(id:45034), Tomzo(id:16777), Non-stop24(id:10471), Noir(id:45654), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), 陽一(id:92099), Lupinoid(id:68), 0wikipedian(id:9583), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), BAKU(id:55205), Robert De Smith(id:28533), Miho53sunflower(id:51393), Ryoji937(id:190619), Michey.M(id:906), 代言人(id:33675), しょかい(id:73826), Cadocco(id:137037), Shouichi(id:78888), こぶまき(id:38278), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), Bankokuya(id:91191), Outside147(id:64766), Mnd(id:15140), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), ArthurBot(id:265089), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nallimbot(id:230812), Sh(id:2707), KoshiMAX(id:75762), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Frozen-mikan(id:6130), VolkovBot(id:105371), Nidarin(id:6420), 午後紅茶(id:14285), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), 海兵(id:191500), はっち(id:19026), Antique1967(id:74701), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Ponsaku(id:31417), Alexbot(id:157199), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Junger(id:10282), 電田蒸(id:249216), 小太刀(id:18154), Zippin(id:9885), Minechi(id:17705), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>