<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>坂本財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKAMOTO no Takara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>坂本 財（さかもと の たから、生年不明 - 天武天皇2年5月29日 (旧暦)（673年））は、日本の飛鳥時代の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara (year of birth unknown-June 21,673) was one historical figure in the Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKAMOTO no Takara (year of birth unknown-June 21, 673) was a person from the Asuka Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>one historiacl figure in -&gt; a person from</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara (year of birth unknown-June 21, 673) was a person from the Asuka Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧仮名遣いでの読みは同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the way of old Japanese syllabary characters way of reading, it was read the same way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old Japanese syllabary characters, his name was pronounced in the same way.</e>
<cmt>read -&gt; pronounced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old Japanese syllabary characters, his name was pronounced in the same way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>姓（カバネ）は臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabane (hereditary title) was Omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Kabane (hereditary title) was Omi.</e>
<cmt>His を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Kabane (hereditary title) was Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>672年の壬申の乱で大海人皇子（天武天皇）側にたって戦い、河内から倭（大和）に来る敵を防いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAKAMOTO took sides with Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) at the Jinshin War in 672 defending Yamato Province against the enemy coming from Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jinshin War which broke out in 672, SAKAMOTO fought for Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) to defend the enemy coming from Kawachi Province to Yamato (Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt>（大和）は他のファイルと合わせ「大和国」として訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jinshin War which broke out in 672, SAKAMOTO fought for Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) to defend the enemy coming from Kawachi Province to Yamato (Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However they were defeated in battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he and his troops were defeated in the battle.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he and his troops were defeated in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>壬申の年の6月29日に大伴吹負が兵を挙げて飛鳥を占領し、つづいて北進したとき、坂本財はその軍の中にいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 2, 672 (the year of Mizunoe-Saru, one of the Oriental Zodiac), when OTOMO no Fukei took up arms and occupied Asuka Province then advanced northward, SAKAMOTO no Takara was with the troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 672, when OTOMO no Fukei rose in arms and occupied Asuka and advanced northward, SAKAMOTO no Takara was involved in the troops.</e>
<cmt>壬申の年（天武天皇元年）の6月29日は西暦672年8月1日です。飛鳥は地名（Capitalに近い位置づけ）と考え、Provinceは削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, 672, when OTOMO no Fukei rose in arms and occupied Asuka and advanced northward, SAKAMOTO no Takara was involved in the troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>稗田についたとき、おそらく7月2日、吹負は河内国から大軍が来るとの情報を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presumably, on July 5, 672 when the troops reached Hieda, Fukei obtained information that a large force would come from Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presumably on August 3, 672 when the troops reached Hieda, Fukei got the information of a large enemy force coming from Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>7月2日は西暦672年8月3日と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presumably on August 3, 672 when the troops reached Hieda, Fukei got the information of a large enemy force coming from Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>それで各数百人の三個部隊を割いてその方面の守りにあてた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, he organized three military units of some hundred each and despatched them to defend the district.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, Fukei organized three military units comprised of some hundred members for each and dispatched them to defend the attack from the direction of Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, Fukei organized three military units comprised of some hundred members for each and dispatched them to defend the attack from the direction of Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのうち竜田に向かった三百人の指揮官が、坂本財、長尾真墨、倉墻麻呂、民小鮪、谷根麻呂であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The commanders of the unit of three hundred heading to Tatsuda were SAKAMOTO no Takara, NAGAO no Masumi, KURAKAKI no Maro, 民小鮪, and TANI no NE Maro.</e>
<cmt>民小鮪　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKAMOTO no Takara, NAGAO no Masumi, KURAKAKI no Maro, TAMI no Oshibi, and TANI no Ne Maro were involved in the troops as the commanders of the 300-member unit that headed for Tatsuta.</e>
<cmt>民小鮪：たみのおしび</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara, NAGAO no Masumi, KURAKAKI no Maro, TAMI no Oshibi, and TANI no Ne Maro were involved in the troops as the commanders of the 300-member unit that headed for Tatsuta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>坂本らはその日平石野に宿営したが、高安城に敵軍がいると聞き、その山に登った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After SAKAMOTO and the others set up camp at Hiraishino on the same day, with obtaining information that the enemy was in Takayasu Castle which was located in mountain, they climbed the mountain to fight against them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they set up camps at Hiraishino on the same day, the commanders were informed that there was the enemy in Takayasunoki Castle, so they climbed the mountain where the castle was located to attack the enemy.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。高安城：「たかやすじょう」は戦国時代の城です。原文の時代の読みは「たかやすのき」です。古代の山城のため、Castleを追記しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they set up camps at Hiraishino on the same day, the commanders were informed that there was the enemy in Takayasunoki Castle, so they climbed the mountain where the castle was located to attack the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>近江軍（弘文天皇側の軍）は税倉を焼いて逃げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi forces (the army on the Emperor Kobun&apos;s side) fled from the castle setting fire to storehouses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi forces (the army on the Emperor Kobun&apos;s side) fled from the castle after setting fire to storehouses.</e>
<cmt>after を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi forces (the army on the Emperor Kobun&apos;s side) fled from the castle after setting fire to storehouses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>翌日（3日か）の朝、彼らは、西方の大津・丹比の両道に壱伎韓国が率いる大軍を見た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next morning (6th), SAKAMOTO and the others saw a large force in command of Repubric Korea along both Otsu and Tajihi streets in the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next morning (5th) they saw a large enemy force led by IKI no Karakuni approaching from both Otsu-chi Road and Tajihi-michi Road which were located on the west side of the castle.</e>
<cmt>文脈ではこの「翌日」は「7月3日」になりますが、日付は長尾真墨のファイルに合わせ、「7月4日」と考えています。このため、西暦672年8月5日としています。（3日か）は割愛しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next morning (5th) they saw a large enemy force led by IKI no Karakuni approaching from both Otsu-chi Road and Tajihi-michi Road which were located on the west side of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>城から下って衛我河を渡り、川の西で戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After coming down from the castle and crossing the Eiga gawa-river, they had a battle in the west of the river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They left the castle and advanced the troops across Egakawa River, and the battle broke out on the west side of the river.</e>
<cmt>衛我河：えがかわ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They left the castle and advanced the troops across Egakawa River, and the battle broke out on the west side of the river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>敗れて紀大音が懼坂に用意しておいた陣営に退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they were defeated in the battle, retreating to the camp which 紀大音 had arranged in 懼坂 beforhand.</e>
<cmt>紀大音　懼坂　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they were defeated and gathered at the camp which had been set up by KI no Oto in Kashikosaka after the withdrawal.</e>
<cmt>懼坂：かしこさか紀大音：きのおおとhttp://www.weblio.jp/content/%E7%B4%80%E5%A4%A7%E9%9F%B3</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they were defeated and gathered at the camp which had been set up by KI no Oto in Kashikosaka after the withdrawal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、勝った韓国軍の側では、河内国司守来目塩籠が大海人皇子側にくみするために軍を集めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the side of the victorious Korean Amy however, Shiogori KUME the governor of Kawachi Province was gathering the members of the army to take Prince Oama&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the troops of Karakuni, the winner, KUME no Shioko, Kawachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Kawachi Province), was gathering the troops to take the side of Prince Oama.</e>
<cmt>来目塩籠：くめのしおこ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the troops of Karakuni, the winner, KUME no Shioko, Kawachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Kawachi Province), was gathering the troops to take the side of Prince Oama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この計画は韓国に知られ、失敗を悟った塩籠は自殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">knowing this plot failed, Shiogori committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karakuni detected Shioko&apos;s betrayal, and Shioko committed suicide knowing that his plot was failed.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karakuni detected Shioko&apos;s betrayal, and Shioko committed suicide knowing that his plot was failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>中一日をおいて、おそらく5日に、近江軍はいくつもの道から押し寄せてきたため、坂本らは交戦せずに退却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day after tomorrow, possibly on 8, SAKAMOTO&apos;s their troops retreated without any battles, since Omi forces were surging from everywhere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two days later, probably on 7, the commanders decided to pull out their troops without fighting against the Omi forces as they saw the enemy attacking from every direction.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。日付は「7月6日」と考え、西暦672年8月7日としています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two days later, probably on 7, the commanders decided to pull out their troops without fighting against the Omi forces as they saw the enemy attacking from every direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>坂本財はこの後も大友吹負のもとで戦ったと考えられるが、その様子は『日本書紀』に現れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara was believed to have continued fighting under OTOMO no Fukei after this war however, nothing of his story appeared in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKAMOTO no Takara was believed to have continued fighting for OTOMO no Fukei after this battle, but nothing was mentioned about him in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara was believed to have continued fighting for OTOMO no Fukei after this battle, but nothing was mentioned about him in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>翌年の5月29日に大錦上の冠位で死んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 21 in the following year, SAKAMOTO left this world being in the rank of Onishiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away on June 21 the following year with his rank Daikinjo (the seventh grade of twenty-six of cap rank, which corresponds to Shoshii, Senior Fourth Rank and Jushii, Junior Fourth Rank of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code).</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。大錦上はWebの用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away on June 21 the following year with his rank Daikinjo (the seventh grade of twenty-six of cap rank, which corresponds to Shoshii, Senior Fourth Rank and Jushii, Junior Fourth Rank of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>壬申の年の功労によって、小紫の位を贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the rank of Koshiba was presented to SAKAMOTO for the services he provided in the year of Mizunoe-Saru (one of the Oriental Zodiac).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was conferred Shoshi (the sixth grade of twenty-six of cap rank, which corresponds to Jusanmi, Junior Third Rank of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) for his services in the Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt>壬申の年：壬申の乱としています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred Shoshi (the sixth grade of twenty-six of cap rank, which corresponds to Jusanmi, Junior Third Rank of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) for his services in the Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bow(id:16755), Kinori(id:443), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>