<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平将国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Masakuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Masakuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Masakuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 将国（平 將國・たいら の まさくに、生没年未詳）は、平安時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Masakuni (date of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Masakuni (date of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Masakuni (year of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>dateをyearに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>関東地方に武家政権の発祥とも言われる国家を建設し「新皇」を名乗った平将門の子と伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be a son of TAIRA no Masakado who established a government which was the origin of the military government in the Kanto region and identified himself as &apos;new emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be the son of TAIRA no Masakado who established a government that was the origin of the military government in the Kanto region and identified himself as &apos;new emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be the son of TAIRA no Masakado who established a government that was the origin of the military government in the Kanto region and identified himself as &apos;new emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>桓武天皇系坂東平氏6代目当主であり、信田氏の始祖で子の小太郎文国は信田氏を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the sixth head of Bando-Heishi (Taira clan) who was the descendants of the Emperor Kanmu, and his son Kotaro fumikuni (小太郎文国) became the progenitor of the Shinoda clan.</e>
<cmt>小太郎文国</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth head of Bando-Heishi (Taira clan) who was the descendants of Emperor Kanmu, and his son Kotaro fumikuni (小太郎文国) became the progenitor of the Shinoda clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth head of Bando-Heishi (Taira clan) who was the descendants of Emperor Kanmu, and his son Kotaro fumikuni (小太郎文国) became the progenitor of the Shinoda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>長兄には平良門がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshikado was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yoshikado was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshikado was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>父の「新皇」将門が、世に言う承平天慶の乱によって滅ぼされると、まだ幼少であった将国は、一族に担がれ二代新皇を称し再興を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father Masakado who was &apos;the new emperor&apos; was defeated in the Johei and Tengyo War, young Masakuni identified himself as the second new emperor by his family&apos;s support and tried to revive the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father Masakado, the new emperor,&apos; was defeated in the Johei and Tengyo War, young Masakuni identified himself as the second new emperor with his family&apos;s support and tried to revive the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father Masakado, the &apos;new emperor,&apos; was defeated in the Johei and Tengyo War, young Masakuni identified himself as the second new emperor with his family&apos;s support and tried to revive the government.</e>
<cmt>を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、守る将兵や乳母らとともに浮島に落ち延びたと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that he was defeated and escaped to the Uki-shima island (one of the islands in Matsushima Bay) with his officers, men, menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that he was defeated and escaped to the Uki-shima island (one of the islands in Matsushima Bay) with his officers, men, menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby) and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that he was defeated and escaped to the Uki-shima island (one of the islands in Matsushima Bay) with his officers, men, menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>戦乱が沈静化した後は、疲弊し荒れ果てた領地を回復させるため叔父の平良文の後見を得て、治世に心血を注いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war was over, he made efforts to rebuild the exhausted and devastated land by the support of his uncle TAIRA no Yoshifumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war was over, he made an effort to rebuild the exhausted and devastated land with the support of his uncle TAIRA no Yoshifumi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war was over, he made an effort to rebuild the exhausted and devastated land with the support of his uncle TAIRA no Yoshifumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後の足跡は不明であるが、後年、歴史上に見られる安倍晴明と同一人物であるという説が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his fate after that is not known, there is a famous theory that he was the same person as ABE no Seimei in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his fate after that is not known, there is a famous theory that he was the same person as ABE no Seimei in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his fate after that is not known, there is a famous theory that he was the same person as ABE no Seimei in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、将国が神のお告げで発見し、病や傷を癒したとされる紀北町の有久寺温泉などが伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in the Arikuji Hot spring at Kihoku Town there is a legend that Masakuni discovered the spring in accordance with an oracle of god and cured people&apos;s diseases and wounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in the Arikuji Hot spring at Kihoku Town there is a legend that Masakuni discovered the spring in accordance with an oracle of god and cured people&apos;s diseases and wounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in the Arikuji Hot spring at Kihoku Town there is a legend that Masakuni discovered the spring in accordance with an oracle of god and cured people&apos;s diseases and wounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), Clarin(id:60278), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>