<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松東院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shotoin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shotoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shotoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松東院（しょうとういん、天正3年（1575年） - 明暦3年（1657年））は安土桃山時代 - 江戸時代初期の有力なキリシタン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shotoin (1575 - 1657) was a powerful Christian from Azuchi Momoyama period to early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shotoin (1575 - 1657) was a powerful Christian from the Azuchi Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shotoin (1575 - 1657) was a powerful Christian from the Azuchi Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は日本最初のキリシタン大名として有名な大村純忠（五女）、夫は松浦久信。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Sumitada OMURA (fifth daughter), known as the first Christian daimyo (Christian feudal lord) in Japan, and her husband was Hisanobu MATSURA.</e>
<cmt>「松浦」の読みはこのファイル内では「まつら」に統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Sumitada OMURA (fifth daughter), known as the first Christian daimyo (Christian feudal lord) in Japan, and her husband was Hisanobu MATSURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the fifth daughter of Sumitada OMURA, who was known as the first Christian feudal lord in Japan; and her husband was Hisanobu MATSURA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>洗礼名は「メンシア」、実名は「その」とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christian name was &apos;Mencia&apos; and real name was &apos;Sono.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Christian name was &apos;Mencia&apos; and her real name was &apos;Sono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her Christian name was &apos;Mencia&apos; and her real name was &apos;Sono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1586年、勢威を増す龍造寺隆信に対して松浦氏と大村氏は連合を組み、その契約として松浦鎮信 (法印)の嫡子・松浦久信との間に婚儀が整う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586, Matsura clan and Omura clan formed a union against Takanobu RYUZOJI who was gaining power, and as part of the agreement, a wedding was arranged with Hisanobu MATSURA, the legitimate child of Shigenobu MATSURA (hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1586, the Matsura and Omura clans formed a union against Takanobu RYUZOJI who was gaining power, and as part of the agreement, a wedding was arranged with Hisanobu MATSURA, the legitimate child of Shigenobu MATSURA (Ho&apos;in [the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests]).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1586, the Matsura and Omura clans formed a union against Takanobu RYUZOJI, who was gaining power, and as part of the agreement, a wedding was arranged with Hisanobu MATSURA, the legitimate child of Shigenobu MATSURA (the highest rank among Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「この結婚は政略結婚であった」とイエズス会の書簡にも明記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is clearly stated in a letter by the Society of Jesus that &apos;this marriage was an strategic marriage.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is clearly stated in a letter by the Society of Jesus that &apos;this marriage was a strategic marriage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is clearly stated in a letter by the Society of Jesus that &apos;this marriage was a strategic marriage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、松浦鎮信は極度のキリシタン嫌いであったため、結婚当初から舅との不和に悩まされることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shigenobu MATSURA had an extreme dislike of Christians, and she suffered from discord with the father-in-law since the beginning of the marriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shigenobu MATSURA had an extreme dislike of Christians, and she suffered from discord with her father-in-law since the start of the marriage.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Shigenobu MATSURA had an extreme dislike of Christians, she suffered from discord with her father-in-law from the start of the marriage.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>夫・久信にも都度都度棄教を進められたが、彼女は「棄教するぐらいなら実家にかえる」（＝同盟破棄）と、駕籠を呼び実家に帰ろうとして応じなかったため、当時情勢の厳しかった松浦氏側は彼女の棄教をあきらめざるを得なかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was repeatedly advised by the husband, Hisanobu, to apostatize, but she resisted by calling for the palanquin to return home saying &apos;I would rather go home than apostatize&apos; (= invalidation of alliance), and the Matsura clan side who was in a difficult circumstance at the time had to give up her apostasy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was repeatedly advised by her husband, Hisanobu, to apostatize, but she resisted by calling for the palanquin to return home saying &apos;I would rather go home than apostatize&apos; (= invalidation of alliance). The Matsura clan side, who faced difficult circumstances at the time, had to give up on have her apostatize.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was repeatedly advised by her husband Hisanobu to abandon Christianity, but she resisted by calling for the palanquin to return home, saying &apos;I would rather go home than abandon Christianity&apos; (= cancelation of alliance); the Matsura clan side, who faced difficult circumstances at the time, had to give up the idea of having her abandon Christianity.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>この困難により逆に彼女の信仰は深まり、1591年、訪問したアレッサンドロ・ヴァリニャーノに絶賛される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This hardship rather strengthened her faith, and in 1591, was praised highly by Alessandro Valignano who was visiting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This hardship rather strengthened her faith, and in 1591, she was praised highly by Alessandro Valignano who was visiting.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This hardship strengthened her faith instead, and in 1591, she was praised highly by Alessandro VALIGNANO who was visiting Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年、待望の嫡子・松浦隆信 (宗陽)を産んだことで松浦氏家中に置いても重きを為すようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, she gained importance within the Matsura clan by giving birth to a long-awaited legitimate child, Takanobu MATSURA (Soyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, she gained importance within the Matsura clan by giving birth to a long-awaited legitimate child, Takanobu MATSURA (Soyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, she began to be esteemed highy within the Matsura clan as she gave birth to a long-awaited legitimate child Takanobu MATSURA (also known as Soyo).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後久信との間に松浦信清、松浦信辰らを儲ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She later gave birth to Nobukiyo MATSURA, Nobutatsu MATSURA, etc. with Hisanobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She later gave birth to Nobukiyo MATSURA, Nobutatsu MATSURA, etc. with Hisanobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She later gave birth to Nobukiyo MATSURA and Nobutatsu MATSURA with Hisanobu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>熱心なキリシタンであった彼女は、松浦氏家臣でこれまた熱心なキリシタンであった籠手田安経の未亡人（洗礼名「ドナ・イサベラ」）に命じて子供達全員に洗礼を授けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a devout Christian, she ordered the widow (Christian name &apos;Donna Isabella&apos;) of Yasutsune KOTEDA, who was a retainer of the Matsura clan and also a devout Christian, to have all of her children christened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a devout Christian, she ordered the widow (Christian name &apos;Donna Isabella&apos;) of Yasutsune KOTEDA, who was a retainer of the Matsura clan and also a devout Christian, to have all of her children baptised.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being a devout Christian, she ordered the widow (Christian name &apos;Donna Isabella&apos;) of a devout Christian retainer of the Matsura clan Yasutsune KOTEDA to have all of her children baptized.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、1602年に庇護者であった夫・久信が滞在中の京都で急死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1602, her husband, Hisanobu, who was her advocate died suddenly while staying in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1602, her husband, Hisanobu, who was her advocate died suddenly while staying in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in 1602, her husband Hisanobu, who was her advocate died suddenly while staying in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>長男・隆信が跡目を相続したものの、後見として再び政務を取り始めた舅・鎮信との対立や、キリシタン及び松浦氏に厳しい目を向ける江戸幕府との間で対応に苦慮することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eldest son, Takanobu, succeeded as the heir, but struggled in conflicts with the father-in-law, Shigenobu, who attended once again to government affairs as koken (guardian), and in responding to the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which had stern eyes for Christians and the Matsura clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eldest son, Takanobu, succeeded as the heir, but struggled in conflicts with the father-in-law, Shigenobu. Shigenobu attended once again to government affairs as koken (guardian), and, responded to the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which treated Christians and the Matsura clan sternly.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eldest son Takanobu succeeded as the heir, but she struggled in conflicts with her father-in-law Shigenobu, who attended once again to government affairs as Tadanobu&apos;s guardian, and in coping with the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which treated Christians and the Matsura clan sternly.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1599年には既に籠手田一族が平戸から追放されていたため、彼女が平戸藩のキリシタンを陰から支援していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By 1599, the Koteda family had already been exiled from Hirado, so she was secretly supporting the Christians in the domain of Hirado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By 1599, the Koteda family had already been exiled from Hirado, so she was secretly supporting Christians in the domain of Hirado.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Koteda family had already been exiled from Hirado by 1599, so she was secretly supporting Christians in the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし1630年、江戸幕府は隆信に彼女をはじめとする親族の江戸在住を命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1630, Edo bakufu ordered Takanobu to have her and the relatives to reside in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1630, the Edo bakufu ordered Takanobu to have her and the relatives reside in Edo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in 1630, the Edo bakufu ordered Takanobu to have his wife and relatives reside in Edo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>更に江戸では彼女は平戸藩の屋敷ではなく、浄土宗広徳寺に幽閉されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in Edo, she was confined in Kotoku-ji Temple of the Jodo Sect instead of a residence for the domain of Hirado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in Edo, she was confined in Kotoku-ji Temple of the Jodo Sect instead of a residence in the domain of Hirado.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in Edo, she was confined in Kotoku-ji Temple of the Jodo Sect instead of living in a residence of the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この一件は一見参勤交代制に伴う人質の江戸集住政策に見せかけ、実は熱心な平戸のキリシタンから有力支援者を切り離す幕府の作戦だったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident is believed to have been a strategy of the bakufu to disconnect powerful supporters from devout Christians in Hirado, under the pretense of a policy of central residence of hostages in Edo under the Sankin-kotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo) system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident is believed to have been a strategy of the bakufu to disconnect powerful supporters from devout Christians in Hirado, under the pretense of a policy of central residence of hostages in Edo under the Sankin-kotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo) system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident is believed to have been a strategy of the bakufu to disconnect powerful supporters from devout Christians in Hirado, under the pretext of a policy of central residence of hostages in Edo under the Sankin-kotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo) system.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、二度と平戸への帰国が許されることはなく、息子・隆信の死に目にもあえないまま広徳寺で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, she was never allowed to return to Hirado, and died in Kotoku-ji Temple without being able to see her son, Takanobu, when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, she was never allowed to return to Hirado, and died in Kotoku-ji Temple without being able to see her son, Takanobu, when he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, she was never allowed to return to Hirado, and died in Kotoku-ji Temple without being able to be present at her son Takanobu&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>83歳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>最期までキリスト教の信仰は捨てなかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that she did not give up her Christian faith until her death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that she clung fast to her Christian faith until her death.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that she adhered to her Christian faith until her death.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>墓所は平戸臨済宗正宗寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her graveyard is in Shoso-ji Temple of the Rinzai Sect in Hirado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her graveyard is in Shoso-ji Temple of the Rinzai Sect in Hirado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is in Shoso-ji Temple of the Rinzai Sect in Hirado.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また壱岐市の安国寺にも夫・久信の供養塔の隣に御拝塔が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, an ohaito (worship tower) remains next to the memorial tower of her husband, Hisanobu, in Ankoku-ji Temple in Iki City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, an ohaito (worship tower) remains next to the memorial tower of her husband, Hisanobu, in Ankoku-ji Temple in Iki City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a worship tower remains next to the memorial tower of her husband Hisanobu, in Ankoku-ji Temple in Iki City.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>拝塔の前にあるつくばいは「キリシタン水盤」として有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsukubai (stone wash basin found in Japanese gardens) in front of the haito is famous as the &apos;Christian laver.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsukubai (stone wash basin found in Japanese gardens) in front of the haito is famous as the &apos;Christian laver.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stone wash basin in front of the worship tower is famous as the &apos;Kirishitan Suiban&apos; (Christian laver).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>