<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>菅原文時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;SUGAWARA no Fumitoki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;SUGAWARA no Fumitoki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SUGAWARA no Fumitoki</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>菅原 文時（すがわら の ふみとき、昌泰2年（899年） － 天元 (日本)4年9月8日 (旧暦)（981年10月8日））は、平安時代中期の文人・政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in 899 and gone in 981, - in detail, the date he was gone is September 8 by the lunar calendar (October 8 by the solar calendar) - &quot;SUGAWARA no Fumitoki&quot; was a literary man &amp; a politician in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in 899 and passed away in 981, - in detail, the date he passed away is September 8 by the lunar calendar (October 8 by the solar calendar) - &quot;SUGAWARA no Fumitoki&quot; was a literary man &amp; a politician in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born in 899 and passed away on October 13, 981, SUGAWARA no Fumitoki was a literary man and a politician in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更し一部文章修正、クォーテーション削除、&amp;→andに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>祖父は菅原道真、父は菅原高視。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;SUGAWARA no Michizane&quot; was his grandfather, and &quot;SUGAWARA no Takami&quot; was his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;SUGAWARA no Michizane&quot; was his grandfather, and &quot;SUGAWARA no Takami&quot; was his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SUGAWARA no Michizane was his grandfather, and SUGAWARA no Takami was his father.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>菅三品と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michizane, Takami and Fumitoki are called &quot;Kansanbon,&quot; which means three &quot;菅s&quot; (kans).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michizane, Takami and Fumitoki are called &quot;Kansanbon,&quot; which means three &quot;菅s&quot; (kans).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michizane, Takami and Fumitoki are called &quot;Kansanbon,&quot; which means three &quot;菅s&quot; (kans).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>文章博士から内記・弁官・式部大輔などを歴任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumitoki held various positions, such as &quot;Monjo hakase&quot; (Professor of Literature), &quot;Naiki&quot; (Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), &quot;Benkan&quot; (the oversight department of the Dajokan responsible for controlling central and provincial governmental offices) and &quot;Shikibu taifu&quot; (Senior Assistant Minister of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumitoki held various positions, such as &quot;Monjo hakase&quot; (Professor of Literature), &quot;Naiki&quot; (Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), &quot;Benkan&quot; (the oversight department of the Dajokan responsible for controlling central and provincial governmental offices) and &quot;Shikibu taifu&quot; (Senior Assistant Minister of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumitoki held various positions, such as Monjo hakase (Professor of Literature), Naiki (Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Benkan (the oversight department of the Dajokan responsible for controlling central and provincial governmental offices) and Shikibu taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>954年（天暦8年）村上天皇が諸臣に政治に関し意見を求めた際、957年（天徳 (日本)元年）意見奉事3ヶ条を提出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 954, Emperor Murakami sought advice of politics from retainers, and in 957, Fumitoki offered his opinion composed of three clauses to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 954, Emperor Murakami sought political advice from retainers, and in 957, Fumitoki offered his opinion composed of three clauses to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 954, Emperor Murakami sought political advice from retainers, and in 957, Fumitoki offered his opinion composed of three clauses to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>981年（天元4年）1月に従三位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 981, Fumitoki got the investiture of &quot;Jusanmi&quot; (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 981, Fumitoki received the investiture of &quot;Jusanmi&quot; (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 981, Fumitoki received the investiture of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同年9月、83歳で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the same year, he died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, he died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of the same year, he died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>『袋草紙』には、文時が不出来と考えていた詩文の草案を、門弟の慶滋保胤が逆に絶賛した記事が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fukuro zoshi&quot; (Book of Folded Pages) carried an article that the draft verse and prose which Fumitoki himself regarded as poor were acclaimed as excellent in contrast by his disciple &quot;YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fukuro zoshi&quot; (Book of Folded Pages) carried an article of which the draft verse and prose were considred by Fumitoki himself to be poor, were acclaimed as excellent in contrast by his disciple &quot;YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fukuro Zoshi&quot; (Book of Folded Pages) carried an article of which the draft verse and prose were considred by Fumitoki himself to be poor, were acclaimed as excellent in contrast by his disciple YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane.</e>
<cmt>Fukuro Zoshiとし、YOSHISHIGE no Yasutaneのクォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『本朝文粋』のほか『扶桑集』『和漢朗詠集』に作品が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left behind his masterpieces in &quot;Honcho monzui&quot; (Anthology of waka and prose written in classical Chinese), &quot;Fuso shu&quot; (Chinese classics in the Heian period) and &quot;Wakan roei shu&quot; (Japanese and Chinese poems to sing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left behind his masterpieces in &quot;Honcho monzui&quot; (Anthology of waka and prose written in classical Chinese), &quot;Fuso shu&quot; (Chinese classics in the Heian period) and &quot;Wakan roei shu&quot; (Japanese and Chinese poems to sing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left behind his masterpieces in &quot;Honcho Monzui&quot; (Anthology of waka and prose written in classical Chinese), &quot;Fuso Shu&quot; (Chinese classics in the Heian period) and &quot;Wakan Roei Shu&quot; (Japanese and Chinese poems to sing).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の単語の頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 VoidAimai(id:212464), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>