<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>道場 (僧侶)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dojo (priest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dojo (priest)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dojo (priest)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>道場（どうじょう、生没年不詳）は、飛鳥時代の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dojo (dates of birth and death unknown) was a Buddhist priest in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dojo (dates of birth and death unknown) was a Buddhist priest in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dojo (dates of birth and death unknown) was a Buddhist priest in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本現報善悪霊異記において「道場法師」の名前で登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He appeared in Nihon genho zenaku ryoiki (set of three books of Buddhist stories, written in the late 8th and early 9th century, usually referred to as the Nihon Ryoiki) as &quot;Dojo Hoshi (Buddhist monk Dojo).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He appeared in &quot;Nihon Genho Zenaku Ryoiki&quot; (a set of three books of Buddhist stories, written in the late 8th and early 9th century, usually referred to as the Nihon Ryoiki) as &apos;Dojo Hoshi&apos; (Buddhist monk Dojo).</e>
<cmt>punctuation/ capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He appeared in &quot;Nihon Genho Zenaku Ryoiki&quot; (a set of three books of Buddhist stories, written in the late 8th and early 9th century, usually referred to as the Nihon Ryoiki) as &apos;Dojo Hoshi&apos; (Buddhist monk Dojo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>尾張国愛知郡 (愛知県)の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Aichi county in Owari Province (today&apos;s Aichi prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from Aichi County in Owari Province (today&apos;s Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>capitals (according to 用語統一リスト)*as the phrase &quot;was born&quot; appeared again in the next sentence, I changed this one to avoid repetition.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came from Aichi County in Owari Province (today&apos;s Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>6世紀後半敏達天皇の代、農夫であった父親が農作業の途中落ちてきた雷の命を助け、その結果、強力（ごうりき）の子として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Bidatsu in the latter half of the 6th century, he was born as a powerful baby to a farmer father who during the farming work helped a god of lightening who fell from the heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of Emperor Bidatsu in the latter half of the 6th century, he was born as a powerful baby as a result of his farmer father saving the life of a lightning spirit who had fallen during his farming work.</e>
<cmt>rewritten*I am not sure if 雷 means a god of lightning, so I changed it to spirit. -&gt;reference: http://ncode.syosetu.com/n7930l/4/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Bidatsu in the latter half of the 6th century, he was born as a powerful baby as a result of his farmer father saving the life of a lightning spirit who had fallen during his farming work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>10歳の頃、上洛して皇居の北東隅に住んでいた力のある王族と力比べをして勝った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was 10 years old, he went to Kyoto, challenged a muscular Imperial person who lived at a northeastern corner of the Imperial Palace for muscular power and defeated the man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was 10 years old, he went to Kyoto, challenged a muscular Imperial person who lived in the northeastern corner of the Imperial Palace to a test of strength and defeated the man.</e>
<cmt>article/punctuation/wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was 10 years old, he went to Kyoto, challenged a muscular Imperial person who lived in the northeastern corner of the Imperial Palace to a test of strength and defeated the man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後元興寺（飛鳥寺）の童子となり、鐘楼堂にすむ人食い鬼（元興寺 (妖怪)）を退治した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he became a doji (child acolyte of Buddhism) of Genko-ji (Asuka-ji) Temple and got rid of a man-eating ogre who lived in a shoro-do (bell tower) (Genko-ji Temple (specter)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he became a doji (child acolyte of Buddhism) of Gango-ji (Asuka-dera) Temple and got rid of Gagoze (monster), a man-eating ogre, which lived in a shoro-do (bell tower).</e>
<cmt>rewritten*pronunciation mistake corrected (元興寺): http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%85%83%E8%88%88%E5%AF%BA*pronunciation mistake corrected (飛鳥寺): http://kotobank.jp/word/%E9%A3%9B%E9%B3%A5%E5%AF%BA*元興寺, which appeared second time, is not the name of temple, it is the name of monster: http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%85%83%E8%88%88%E5%AF%BA_(%E5%A6%96%E6%80%AA)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he became a doji (child acolyte of Buddhism) of Gango-ji (Asuka-dera) Temple and got rid of Gagoze (monster), a man-eating ogre, which lived in a shoro-do (bell tower).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このときの鬼の髪の毛が元興寺に伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hair of the ogre beaten by him has been handed down to the present day at Genko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hair of the ogre which the doji defeated has been handed down to the present day at Gango-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>pronunciation corrected/wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hair of the ogre which the doji defeated has been handed down to the present day at Gango-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その童子は元興寺の優婆塞（うばそく＝在家のまま仏道修行をするもの）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The doji became Ubasoku (a person who practiced Buddhist without becoming a monk) of Genko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The doji became an ubasoku (a person who practiced Buddhism without becoming a monk) of Gango-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>article/grammar/ pronunciation corrected/ capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The doji became an ubasoku (a person who practiced Buddhism without becoming a monk) of Gango-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>王族が元興寺が所有する田に引水するのを妨害したが、童子はこの妨害を排除し衆僧に出家・得度することを許され、道場法師と称されるようになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial member beaten by the doji prevented Genko-ji Temple from drawing water to the temple&apos;s paddy fields, and the doji forced back the disturbance of the Imperial man and was allowed to receive a Buddhist ceremony to become a priest; it is believed that he therefore came to be called Dojo Hoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the ubasoku forced back an Imperial man preventing Gango-ji Temple from drawing water for the temple&apos;s rice paddies, so the ubasoku was allowed to receive a Buddhist ceremony to become a priest and came to be called Dojo Hoshi.</e>
<cmt>rewritten / ponunciation corrected/ spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the ubasoku forced back an Imperial man preventing Gango-ji Temple from drawing water for the temple&apos;s rice paddies, so the ubasoku was allowed to receive a Buddhist ceremony to become a priest and came to be called Dojo Hoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MIO(id:31681), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), R28Bot(id:177951), Zzzz(id:16596), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>