<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>富田近重</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikashige TOMIDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikashige TOMIDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikashige TOMIDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>富田 近重（とみだ ちかしげ）は、鎌倉時代の武蔵国児玉党（現在の埼玉県本庄市富田出身）の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikashige TOMIDA was a samurai who belonged to the Kodama party of Musashi Province (present-day Tomida, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) during the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikashige TOMIDA was a samurai who belonged to the Kodama party of Musashi Province (present-day Tomida, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>用語リストの表記に従い、Kamakura Period を Kamakura period に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikashige TOMIDA was a samurai who belonged to the Kodama party of Musashi Province (present-day Tomida, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>児玉党系富田氏の2代目。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikashige was the second family head of the TOMIDA clan, one of the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikashige was the second family head of the Tomida clan belonging to the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt>指示書の表記を参照し、TOMIDA clan を Tomida clan に変更し、また、上記を参照し、「児玉党系」の英訳を belonging to the Kodama Party に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikashige was the second family head of the Tomida clan belonging to the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly called Taro.</e>
<cmt>用語リスト等の表記にあわせ、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly called Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>富田氏館（武州）2代館主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikashige served as the second-generation owner of the TOMITA-clan Residence (Bushu [Musashi Province]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikashige was the second lord of the residence of the Tomida clan (Bushu (Musashi Province)).</e>
<cmt>「富田氏」を &quot;Tomida clan&quot;と表記しており、また、用語集にて「源氏館」を&quot;Genji yakata (residence of the Minamoto clan)&quot;と表記しているので、これを参考にし、「富田氏館」の英訳を変更しました。また、「館主」の英訳を&quot;lord&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikashige was the second lord of the residence of the Tomida clan (Bushu (Musashi Province)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>富田太郎近重は、児玉党系富田氏の祖である富田親家の嫡男として、武蔵国児玉郡富田村・富田氏館（現在の西富田堀の内）で生まれたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikashige Taro TOMIDA is considered to have been born as a legitimate son of Chikaie TOMIDA who was the founder of the TOMIDA clan of the Kodama Party in the TOMIDA Residence of Tomida Village, Kodama County, Musashi Province (present-day Horinouchi, Nishitomida).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikashige Taro TOMIDA is considered to have been born as a legitimate son of Chikaie TOMIDA who was the founder of the Tomida clan belonging to the Kodama Party, in the residence of the Tomida clan at Tomida Village, Kodama County, Musashi Province (present-day Horinouchi, Nishitomida).</e>
<cmt>用語集を参照し、「児玉党系」の英訳を belonging to the Kodama Party に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikashige Taro TOMIDA is considered to have been born as a legitimate son of Chikaie TOMIDA who was the founder of the Tomida clan belonging to the Kodama Party, in the residence of the Tomida clan at Tomida Village, Kodama County, Musashi Province (present-day Horinouchi, Nishitomida).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄弟は、惟近と六郎兵衛長家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brothers were Korechika and Rokurobe Nagaie.</e>
<cmt>惟近、六郎兵衛長家：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His brothers were Korechika and Rokurobe Nagaie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His brothers were Korechika and Rokurobe Nagaie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子息は、長男に富田近行がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest son was Chikayuki TOMIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first son was Chikayuki TOMIDA.</e>
<cmt>「長男」の表記を、first son に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first son was Chikayuki TOMIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>『吾妻鏡』によると、承久3年（1221年）の承久の乱で、鎌倉幕府（北条泰時）軍についた富田小太郎（近行）が宇治川の合戦で敵を1人討ち取る功績を上げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East, a chronicle of the early history of the Kamakura Bakufu), Chikayuki Kotaro TOMIDA, who served for the army (headed by Yasutoki HOJO) of the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), had an achievement of killing one enemy in the Battle of Uji River, one of the battles during the Jokyu War of 1221.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East, a chronicle of the early history of the Kamakura Bakufu), Chikayuki Kotaro TOMIDA, who fought by the side of the Kamakura bakufu army (headed by Yasutoki HOJO), rendered distinguished service of killing one enemy in the Battle of Uji-gwa River, one of the battles during the Jokyu War in 1221.</e>
<cmt>用語集等を参照し、「鎌倉幕府軍」及び「宇治川の戦い」の表記を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East, a chronicle of the early history of the Kamakura Bakufu), Chikayuki Kotaro TOMIDA, who fought by the side of the Kamakura bakufu army (headed by Yasutoki HOJO), rendered distinguished service of killing one enemy in the Battle of Uji-gwa River, one of the battles during the Jokyu War in 1221.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、富田太郎（近重）自身の名も記されている事から承久の乱で幕府軍として参戦し、活躍したものと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering that Chikashige Taro TOMIDA also appears in the chronicle, he joined the army of Bakufu during the Jokyu War to offer an excellent war service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering that the name &apos;Chikashige Taro TOMIDA&apos; also appears in Azuma Kagami, it is believed that he played an active role in the Jokyu War as a member of the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>「見られる」の訳を補い、また、簡潔にするため、後半部分の訳文を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering that the name &apos;Chikashige Taro TOMIDA&apos; also appears in Azuma Kagami, it is believed that he played an active role in the Jokyu War as a member of the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この時、兄弟の一人である六郎兵衛長家は、幕府軍ではなく、朝廷軍についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the War, one of Chikashige&apos;s brothers, Rokurobe Nagaie, supported the Imperial army, not the Bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>六郎兵衛長家：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the War, one of Chikashige&apos;s brothers, Rokurobe Nagaie, supported the Imperial army, not the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>用語リストを参照し、「幕府軍」の英訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the War, one of Chikashige&apos;s brothers, Rokurobe Nagaie, supported the Imperial army, not the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その為、長家は朝廷側として戦い、討ち死にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaie fought the War on the Imperial-Court side and got killed on the battle field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Nagaie fought by the side of the Imperial Court in the War and died on the battle field.</e>
<cmt>「その為」の訳を補い、用語集を参照し、「討ち死にする」の英訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Nagaie fought by the side of the Imperial Court in the War and died on the battle field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この他、『吾妻鏡』には、児玉刑部四郎、蛭川刑部三郎などの児玉党武士の名も見られ、活躍した（しかし、この戦で庄忠家が敵によって討ち取られている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other soldiers of the Kodama Party including Shiro Gyobu KODAMA and Saburo Gyobu HIRUKAWA also appear on &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, indicating they also actively fought in the War (however, Tadaie SHO was killed by opponents in the War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, other soldiers of the Kodama Party including Gyobushiro KODAMA and Gyobusaburo HIRUKAWA also appear in &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; and they also actively fought in the War (however, Tadaie SHO was killed by enemies in the War).</e>
<cmt>ダブル・クォーテーションの後のカンマの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, other soldiers of the Kodama Party including Gyobushiro KODAMA and Gyobusaburo HIRUKAWA also appear in &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; and they also actively fought in the War (however, Tadaie SHO was killed by enemies in the War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>