<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>滋野井公麗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinkazu SHIGENOI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinkazu SHIGENOI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinkazu SHIGENOI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>滋野井 公麗（しげのい きんかず、享保18年11月14日_(旧暦)（1733年12月19日）－天明元年9月7日_(旧暦)（1781年10月23日））、は江戸時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinkazu SHIGENOI (December 19, 1733 - October 23, 1781) was a noble who lived in the middle of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinkazu SHIGENOI (December 19, 1733 - October 23, 1781) was a noble who lived in the middle of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinkazu SHIGENOI (December 19, 1733 - October 23, 1781) was a noble who lived in the middle of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>滋野井実全の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child of Sanemasa SHIGENOI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a child of Sanemasa SHIGENOI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a child of Sanemasa SHIGENOI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に滋野井冬泰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuyuyasu SHIGENOI was his child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuyuyasu SHIGENOI was his child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuyuyasu SHIGENOI was his child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は五松亭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pseudonym was Goshotei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Goshotei.</e>
<cmt>this sounds more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Goshotei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>3歳で父が死去し、有職故実家としても名高かった祖父・滋野井公澄に育てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father died when he was three years old and he was brought up by this grandfather, Kinsumi SHIGENOI, who was famous as a specialist for Yusoku-kojitsu (knowledge of court rules, ceremony, decorum and records of the past).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father died when he was three years old and he was brought up by this grandfather, Kinsumi SHIGENOI, who was famous as a specialist in Yusoku-kojitsu (court rules, ceremony, decorum and records of the past).</e>
<cmt>deleted some unnecessary bits</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father died when he was three years old and he was brought up by this grandfather, Kinsumi SHIGENOI, who was famous as a specialist in Yusoku-kojitsu (court rules, ceremony, decorum and records of the past).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元文4年（1739年）に元服して従五位下侍従に任じられ、宝暦8年（1758年）に従三位参議となり、宝暦11年（1761年）に検非違使別当兼右兵衛督、宝暦13年（1763年）に正三位権中納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1739, he celebrated his attainment of manhood and appointed as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) jiju (a chamberlain), and, in 1758, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Sangi (councillor), and, in 1761, Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and, concurrently, Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), and, in 1763, he became Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1739, he came of age and was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and post of Jiju (a chamberlain), in 1758 was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Sangi (councilor), and in 1761 to Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and at the same time to Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), and, in 1763, he became Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1739, he came of age and was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and post of Jiju (a chamberlain), in 1758 was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Sangi (councilor), and in 1761 to Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and at the same time to Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), and, in 1763, he became Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明和5年（1768年）には正二位権大納言（兼大宰権帥）に昇ったが権大納言は同年中、兼務の権帥も安永5年（1776年）に退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1768, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) (concurrently, Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices)), but he resigned from Gon Dainagon within same year and concurrent position, Dazai gon no sochi in 1776.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1768, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) and Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) as well as Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices), but he resigned from Gon Dainagon that same year and from Dazai gon no sochi in 1776.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1768, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) and Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) as well as Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices), but he resigned from Gon Dainagon that same year and from Dazai gon no sochi in 1776.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>祖父の学術を引き継いで当代屈指の有職故実の大家とされ、和歌や絵画にも優れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succeeding his grandfather&apos;s academic knowledge, he was accepted as a great living specialist for Yusoku-kojitsu (knowledge of court rules, ceremony, decorum and records of the past) and he was also good at waka and painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succeeding his grandfather&apos;s academic knowledge, he was accepted as a great living specialist for Yusoku-kojitsu (knowledge of court rules, ceremony, decorum and records of the past) and he was also good at waka and painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succeeding his grandfather&apos;s academic knowledge, he was accepted as a great living specialist for Yusoku-kojitsu (knowledge of court rules, ceremony, decorum and records of the past) and he was also good at waka and painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>22歳で『狩衣至要鈔』を著した他、『禁秘御抄階梯』・『公事根源鈔階梯』・『諒闇装束之事』・『一上要覧』・『摂関要覧』・『彗星出現年々』・『滋草拾露』（個人全集）などの多くの書籍を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was twenty-two years old, he published &quot;狩衣至要鈔&quot; and, then, published many books including &quot;禁秘御抄階梯&quot;, &quot;公事根源鈔階梯&quot;, &quot;諒闇装束之事&quot;, &quot;一上要覧&quot;, &quot;摂関要覧&quot;, &quot;彗星出現年々&quot; and &quot;滋草拾露&quot; (personal complete works).</e>
<cmt>言及されている書籍名の読みが確認できないため、漢字のまま表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was twenty-two years old, he published &quot;狩衣至要鈔&quot; and, then, published many books including &quot;禁秘御抄階梯&quot;, &quot;公事根源鈔階梯&quot;, &quot;諒闇装束之事&quot;, &quot;一上要覧&quot;, &quot;摂関要覧&quot;, &quot;彗星出現年々&quot; and &quot;滋草拾露&quot; (personal complete works).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was twenty-two years old, he published &quot;狩衣至要鈔&quot; and, then, published many books including &quot;禁秘御抄階梯,&quot; &quot;公事根源鈔階梯,&quot; &quot;諒闇装束之事,&quot; &quot;一上要覧,&quot; &quot;摂関要覧,&quot; &quot;彗星出現年々&quot; and &quot;滋草拾露&quot; (personal complete works).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、門人も多く、大塚嘉樹（蒼梧）などを育てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had many disciples and he fostered Yoshiki (Sogo) OTSUKA and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had many disciples, and adopted Yoshiki (Sogo) OTSUKA, among others.</e>
<cmt>fostered-&gt;adopted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had many disciples, and fostered Yoshiki (Sogo) OTSUKA, among others.</e>
<cmt>fosterに戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>その一方で自尊心も強かったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it is told that he was a man of great self-respect</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it is told that he was a man of great self-respect.</e>
<cmt>missing full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it is told that he was a man of great self-respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>従来は三条家の庶流とされてきた滋野井家こそが真の嫡流であり、家格を羽林家から清華家に引き上げるべきであると唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He insisted that the Shigenoi family, which has been deemed as a branch, was the true main branch and, therefore, its social standing should be raised from the House of Urin to the House of Seiga.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He insisted that the Shigenoi family, which was considered a branch family, was the true main lineage, and therefore its social standing should be raised from the House of Urin to the House of Seiga.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He insisted that the Shigenoi family, which was considered a branch family, was the true main lineage, and therefore its social standing should be raised from the House of Urin to the House of Seiga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>強引なこじつけによる論争を起こして、関白近衛内前から叱責を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He caused a dispute based on forcefully labored argument, and he was rebuked by Uchisaki KONOE, who was Kanpaku (chancellor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started an argument due to his stubbornness, and he was rebuked by Uchisaki KONOE, who was Kanpaku (chancellor).</e>
<cmt>needed rewording to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started an argument due to his stubbornness, and he was rebuked by Uchisaki KONOE, who was Kanpaku (chancellor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>天明元年9月、青蓮院宮訪問の際に松茸として食したキノコを原因とする中毒によって急死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1781, he died suddenly because of intoxication by mushroom which he ate as matsutake (Tricholoma matsutake) when he visited Shorenin-no-miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1781, he died of poisoning by mushrooms, which he thought were matsutake, when he visited Shorenin-no-miya.</e>
<cmt>reworded to improve clarity, deleted parenthetical notation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1781, he died of poisoning by mushrooms, which he thought were matsutake, when he visited Shorenin-no-miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>墓所は京都市北区_(京都市)の天寧寺_(京都市)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave exists in the Tennei-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is at Tennei-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>exists-&gt;is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is at Tennei-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同時代の公卿で歴史家としても知られていた柳原紀光は、訃報を聞いて日記に「彼卿無漢才、於抄物日記等事者、博覧之人也」と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing about Kinkazu&apos;s death, Norimitsu YANAGIHARA, who was a noble and historian of the same period, commented in his diary &quot;彼卿無漢才、於抄物日記等事者、博覧之人也.&quot;</e>
<cmt>日記の記載内容を理解できないため、漢文のまま表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing about Kinkazu&apos;s death, Norimitsu YANAGIHARA, who was a noble and historian of the same period, commented in his diary &quot;彼卿無漢才、於抄物日記等事者、博覧之人也.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing of Kinkazu&apos;s death, Norimitsu YANAGIHARA, a court noble and historian who was contemporary with Kinkazu, made the following entry in his diary: &quot;Although not well-versed in Chinese literature, he wrote essays and diaries, and was generally quite knowledgeable.&quot;</e>
<cmt>漢文の意味については、仮訳になります。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>