<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原正光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masamitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Masamitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masamitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 正光（ふじわら の まさみつ、天暦11年（957年） - 長和3年2月29日 (旧暦)（1013年4月1日））は、平安時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masamitsu (956-April 1, 1013) was a court noble in the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>公卿→court noble *一般的名称として、下記にある官位の場合と区別しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Masamitsu (956-April 1, 1013) was a court noble in the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masamitsu (956-April 7, 1013) was a court noble in the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は関白藤原兼通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Kanemichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Kanemichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Kanemichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>極官は従三位・参議大蔵卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The highest rank he achieved was Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Sangi Okura-kyo (Royal Advisor and Minister of Treasury).</e>
<cmt>極官→the highest rank he achieved としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The highest rank he achieved was Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Sangi Okura-kyo (Royal Advisor and Minister of Treasury).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The highest rank he achieved was Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Sangi Okura-kyo (Royal Advisor and Minister of Treasury).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>兼通の六男として、藤原有年の娘を母として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the sixth son of Kanemichi, and his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Aritoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the sixth son of Kanemichi, and his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Aritoshi.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the sixth son of Kanemichi, and his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Aritoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>祖父の藤原師輔は当時右大臣であり、朝廷の実力者でもあった</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather, FUJIWARA no Morosuke was the Minister of the Right at that time and an important figure in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather, FUJIWARA no Morosuke, was the Minister of the Right at that time and an important figure in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather, FUJIWARA no Morosuke, was the Minister of the Right at that time and an important figure in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>が、上席には兄の藤原実頼が左大臣として健在であり、また兼通も二男でありこの時点で公卿にもなっておらず、正光の将来は不透明であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Masamitsu&apos;s future was not still promising, because Morosuke&apos;s elder brother was gripping the power in the higher post as the Minister of the Left, and Kanemichi, who was the second son, had not been appointed to a court noble at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Masamitsu&apos;s future was not still promising, because Morosuke&apos;s elder brother was gripping power in the higher post as the Minister of the Left, and Kanemichi, who was the second son, had not been appointed a court noble at that time.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Masamitsu&apos;s future was not still promising, because Morosuke&apos;s elder brother was gripping power in the higher post as the Minister of the Left, and Kanemichi, who was the second son, had not been appointed a court noble at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらに、師輔は天徳 (日本)4年（960年）には右大臣のまま亡くなってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Morosuke died in 960, while he was still in the post of the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Morosuke died in 960, while he was still in the post of Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Morosuke died in 960, while he was still in the post of Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>ところが、安和元年（968年）に摂政となっていた実頼が死去するとともに兼通の兄藤原伊尹が代わって摂政となり、さらに安和2年（969年）に円融天皇が即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the death of Sessho (regent) Sanemichi in 968, Kanemichi&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Koretada took the post of Sessho, and Emperor Enyu also took over the throne in 969.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the death of Sessho (regent) Sanemichi in 968, Kanemichi&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Koretada took the post of Sessho, and Emperor Enyu also took over the throne in 969.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the death of Sessho (regent) Sanemichi in 968, Kanemichi&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Koretada took the post of Sessho, and Emperor Enyu also took over the throne in 969.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>と、これらによる大規模な人事異動の中で、正光は新天皇の皇太子時代の小舎人であったことも幸いし、13歳にして殿上人を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this big-scale personal shuffle, Masamitsu was appointed to Tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) at age 13, thanks to the fact that Masamitsu was serving as a minor officer, while the new Emperor was the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this large-scale personal shuffle, Masamitsu was appointed Tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) at age 13, thanks to Masamitsu serving as a minor officer, while the new Emperor was the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this large-scale personal shuffle, Masamitsu was appointed Tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) at age 13, thanks to Masamitsu serving as a minor officer, while the new Emperor was the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また翌天禄元年（970年）には、従五位下近江少掾となり、兼通の遅くの子であったため、その昇進の余慶を受けて官途の始まりは順調だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he was appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Omi no shojo (provincial junior secretary of Omi Province), and as he was a son of Kanemichi&apos;s late years, Kanemichi&apos;s promotion also benefited his start as an official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he was appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Omi no shojo (provincial junior secretary of Omi Province), and, as he was a son of Kanemichi&apos;s late years, Kanemichi&apos;s promotion also benefited his start as an official.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he was appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Omi no shojo (provincial junior secretary of Omi Province), and, as he was a son of Kanemichi&apos;s late years, Kanemichi&apos;s promotion also benefited his start as an official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>兼通は天禄3年（973年）には、参議任官から4年で、伊尹の死をうけて関白に就任するという、異例の人事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Koretada&apos;s death, Kanemichi received an exceptional treatment and was assigned to Kanpaku in 973, only four years after taking the post of Sangi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Koretada&apos;s death, Kanemichi received exceptional treatment and was assigned to Kanpaku in 973, only four years after taking the post of Sangi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Koretada&apos;s death, Kanemichi received exceptional treatment and was assigned to Kanpaku in 973, only four years after taking the post of Sangi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため、正光も侍従、ついで左近衛少将に任じられ近江介を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this assignment, Masamitsu was also appointed to Jiju (a chamberlain), and subsequently to Sakone no shosho (minor captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) as well as 近江介Omi no suke (assistant governor of Omi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this assignment, Masamitsu was also appointed to Jiju (a chamberlain), and subsequently to Sakone no shosho (minor captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) as well as 近江介Omi no suke (assistant governor of Omi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this assignment, Masamitsu was also appointed to Jiju (a chamberlain), and subsequently to Sakone no shosho (minor captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) as well as Omi no suke (assistant governor of Omi Province).</e>
<cmt>近江介を除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに、5年で3度の昇叙の結果、位階も従四位下に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he was also promoted three times in five years and ranked up to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, he was also promoted three times in five years and promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, he was also promoted three times in five years and promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、貞元 (日本)2年（977年）に、関白任官後わずか5年で兼通が死去すると、以後の昇進は滞ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kanemichi died in 977 after only five years&apos; tenure of the post of Kanpaku, his promotion started to get stacked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kanemichi died in 977 after only five years&apos; tenure in the post of Kanpaku, and his promotions started to get stacked.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kanemichi died in 977 after only five years&apos; tenure in the post of Kanpaku, and his promotions started to get stacked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>この間、正光は兼通の弟で、兄弟仲の悪かった藤原兼家に接近したらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, it seems that Masamitsu sought a close association with Kanemichi&apos;s younger brother FUJIWARA no Kaneie, who had been on bad terms with Kanemichi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, it seems that Masamitsu sought a close association with Kanemichi&apos;s younger brother FUJIWARA no Kaneie, who had been on bad terms with Kanemichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, it seems that Masamitsu sought a close association with Kanemichi&apos;s younger brother FUJIWARA no Kaneie, who had been on bad terms with Kanemichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>永観2年（984年）に兼家の孫懐仁親王が東宮（皇太子）となると東宮昇殿を許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 984, when Kaneie&apos;s grand son Imperial Prince Yasuhito became the Crown Prince, Masamitsu was allowed into the Crown Prince&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 984, when Kaneie&apos;s grandson Imperial Prince Yasuhito became the Crown Prince, Masamitsu was allowed into the Crown Prince&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 984, when Kaneie&apos;s grandson Imperial Prince Yasuhito became the Crown Prince, Masamitsu was allowed into the Crown Prince&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>さらに寛和2年（986年）にその東宮が一条天皇として即位して、母藤原詮子が皇太后となると、皇太后宮権亮に就任し、兼家の近臣として認められている様子がうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamitsu was appointed to Kotaigogu gon no suke (provisional assistant master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s household), when the Crown Prince was enthroned to be Emperor Ichijo and the Emperor&apos;s mother FUJIRAWA no Senshi became Kotaigo (Empress Dowager), and this shows that he was recognized as one of the Kaneie&apos;s close retainers</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu was appointed Kotaigogu gon no suke (provisional assistant master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s household), when the Crown Prince was enthroned to become Emperor Ichijo and the Emperor&apos;s mother FUJIRAWA no Senshi became Kotaigo (Empress Dowager); this shows that he was recognized as one of the Kaneie&apos;s close retainers</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu was appointed Kotaigogu gon no suke (provisional assistant master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s household), when the Crown Prince was enthroned to become Emperor Ichijo and the Emperor&apos;s mother FUJIWARA no Senshi became Kotaigo (Empress Dowager); this shows that he was recognized as one of the Kaneie&apos;s close retainers.</e>
<cmt>FUJIRAWAをFUJIWARAに変更しました。ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同じ年、10年ぶりの昇叙によって従四位上となっているのも、この関係によるものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The promotion in the same year, in which he was ranked Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank,) also seems to have owned to this relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The promotion in the same year, in which he was ranked Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank), also seems to have been attributable to this relationship.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The promotion in the same year, in which he was ranked Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank), also seems to have been attributable to this relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この皇太后宮権亮は、5年後の正暦2年（991年）に円融上皇の崩御に伴い詮子が出家するとともに停止となったが、翌年には左近衛中将に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tenure of the position of Kotaigogu gon no suke finished five years after when Senshi entered the priesthood with Emperor Enyu&apos;s death in 991, but the next year he was appointed to Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His tenure in the position of Kotaigogu gon no suke finished after five years, when Senshi entered the priesthood with Emperor Enyu&apos;s death in 991, but the next year he was appointed to Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His tenure in the position of Kotaigogu gon no suke finished after five years, when Senshi entered the priesthood with Emperor Enyu&apos;s death in 991, but the next year he was appointed to Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>長徳2年（996年）、疫病の流行などで公卿が大幅に入れ替わるとともに、藤原道長が左大臣として首班となると、正光の兄の藤原顕光が次席の右大臣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owing to an epidemic prevalence, in 996 when a drastic shuffle of court personnel including Kugyo (the top court officials) was carried out, FUJIWARA no Michinaga came to take leadership as the Minister of the Left and Masamitsu&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Akimitsu sat next to Michinaga as the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>公卿→Kugyo (the top court officials) *官位の一種としての訳語を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owing to an epidemic, in 996, when a drastic shuffle of court personnel including Kugyo (the top court officials) was carried out, FUJIWARA no Michinaga came to take leadership as the Minister of the Left and Masamitsu&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Akimitsu sat next to Michinaga as the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owing to an epidemic, in 996, when a drastic shuffle of court personnel including Kugyo (the top court officials) was carried out, FUJIWARA no Michinaga came to take leadership as the Minister of the Left and Masamitsu&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Akimitsu sat next to Michinaga as the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この年の4月には正光は公卿に次いで重要な役職である蔵人頭に任じられ、さらに2年後の長徳4年（998年）には大蔵卿を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of that year, Masamitsu was appointed to Kurodo no to (head chamberlain), the second-tier position after Kugyo, and two year later, in 998 he was entrusted to be Okura-kyo (Minister of Treasury), as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of that year, Masamitsu was appointed to Kurodo no (head chamberlain), the second-tier position after Kugyo, and two year later, in 998, he was entrusted to be Okura-kyo (Minister of Treasury), as well.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of that year, Masamitsu was appointed to Kurodo no to (head chamberlain), the second-tier position after Kugyo, and two year later, in 998, he was entrusted to be Okura-kyo (Minister of Treasury), as well.</e>
<cmt>Kurodo no をKurodo no to に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、人脈としては兄である顕光よりは、兼家から引き続いてその子である道長に近かったようで、長保2年（1000年）に道長の娘である藤原彰子が中宮となると中宮亮に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he used his connection with Kaneie&apos;s son Michinaga, as he did with Michinaga, rather than counting on his elder brother Akimitsu, and in 1000, when Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Akiko became Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor), he was appointed to Chugu no suke (assistant master of the Consort&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>藤原彰子→FUJIWARA no Akiko *FUJIWARA no Shoshiとも言うようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he used his connection with Kaneie&apos;s son Michinaga, as he did with Michinaga, rather than counting on his elder brother Akimitsu, and in 1000, when Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Akiko, became Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor), he was appointed to Chugu no suke (assistant master of the Consort&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Check &quot;Michinaga, as he did with Michinaga&quot;; it seems that one of these &quot;Michinaga&quot;s should be changed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>のちに三条天皇の皇后藤原せい子の立后に際して、対立する中宮藤原妍子の父であった道長派の一員として、立后の儀式に出席するよう求めた使者に瓦礫を投げつけたりしていることが藤原実資の日記に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, in the occasion of the investiture of the Empress (Kogo) of Emperor Sanjo, FUJIWARA no Seiko, Masamitsu threw a piece of tile to a messenger who visited him to asked for his presence in the investiture ceremony, as Masamitsu was a sympathizer of Michinaga, the father of Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor) Fujiwara no Kenshi who antagonized Empress Seiko.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　藤原せい子→FUJIWARA no Seiko　*FUJIWARA no Seishiという読みもあるようです。　藤原妍子→Fujiwara no Kenshi *FUJIWARA no Kiyokoという読みもあるようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, on the occasion of the investiture of the Empress (Kogo) of Emperor Sanjo, FUJIWARA no Seiko, Masamitsu threw a piece of tile to a messenger who visited him to ask for his presence in the investiture ceremony, as Masamitsu was a sympathizer of Michinaga, the father of Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor) Fujiwara no Kenshi, who antagonized Empress Seiko.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, on the occasion of the investiture of the Empress (Kogo) of Emperor Sanjo, FUJIWARA no Seiko, Masamitsu threw a piece of tile to a messenger who visited him to ask for his presence in the investiture ceremony, as Masamitsu was a sympathizer of Michinaga, the father of Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor) Fujiwara no Kenshi, who antagonized Empress Seiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これは兄の一人である藤原時光が同様に宮中からの退出を道長に妨害された一条天皇の中宮藤原定子のために退出の上卿を務めたこととは対照的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His reaction was quite contrasting to that of 藤原時光FUJIWARA no Tokimitsu, one of his elder brothers, who served to facilitate the withdrawal of 藤原定子FUJIWARA no Teishi, the second consort of Emperor Ichijo (Chugu), from the Imperial Palace as Shokei (a high-ranking court noble) when Michinaga blocked her path.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。 藤原定子→FUJIWARA no Teishi　*FUJIWARA no Sadakoとも読むそうです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His reaction was quite contrasting to that of 藤原時光FUJIWARA no Tokimitsu, one of his elder brothers, who served to facilitate the withdrawal of 藤原定子FUJIWARA no Teishi, the second consort of Emperor Ichijo (Chugu), from the Imperial Palace as Shokei (a high-ranking court noble) when Michinaga blocked her path.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His reaction was quite contrasting to that of FUJIWARA no Tokimitsu, one of his elder brothers, who served to facilitate the withdrawal of FUJIWARA no Teishi, the second consort of Emperor Ichijo (Chugu), from the Imperial Palace as Shokei (a high-ranking court noble) when Michinaga blocked her path.</e>
<cmt>藤原時光、 藤原定子を除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ここに、兄弟で政権中枢である兼家-道長親子との距離のとり方の違いが表れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This anecdote shows the difference of the two brothers in how to keep the distance with Kaneie and his son Michinaga, who were the mainstay of politics at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This anecdote shows the difference between the two brothers in how to keep the distance with Kaneie and his son Michinaga, who were the mainstay of politics at that time.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This anecdote shows the difference between the two brothers in how to keep the distance with Kaneie and his son Michinaga, who were the mainstay of politics at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>その後、寛弘元年（1004年）2月には参議となり、同年10月には従三位に昇るなど、上級貴族の一員となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he became a member of the high-ranked aristocracy, being appointed to Sangi in February 1004, and ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, he became a member of the high-ranked aristocracy, being appointed to Sangi in February 1004, and ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, he became a member of the high-ranked aristocracy, being appointed to Sangi in February 1004, and ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし、その後は特に官位は変わることなく、顕光や時光などの兄に先立って長和3年に58歳で死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after that, without enjoying any outstanding promotion, he died at the age of in 1014, prior to the assignments of Akimitsu and Tokimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after that, without enjoying any outstanding promotion, he died at the age of in 1014, prior to the assignments of Akimitsu and Tokimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after that, without enjoying any outstanding promotion, he died at the age of 58 in 1014, prior to the assignments of Akimitsu and Tokimitsu.</e>
<cmt>58を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、「枕草子」には「大蔵卿ばかり耳とき人はなし」で始まる段があるが、これは正光のことを指しているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Makura no Soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book), there is an episode that begins with the phrase, &apos;there is no other quick-eared person like Okura-kyo (Minister of Treasure),&apos; and it is said that &apos;Okura-kyo&apos; referred to Masamitsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　「大蔵卿ばかり耳とき人はなし」→定訳不明：&apos;there is no other quick-eared person like Okura-kyo (Minister of Treasure),&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Makura no Soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book), there is an episode that begins with the phrase, &apos;there is no other quick-eared person like Okura-kyo (Minister of Treasure),&apos; and it is said that &apos;Okura-kyo&apos; referred to Masamitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;Makura no Soshi&apos; (the Pillow Book), there is an episode that begins with the phrase, &apos;there is no other quick-eared person like Okura-kyo (Minister of Treasure),&apos; and it is said that &apos;Okura-kyo&apos; referred to Masamitsu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この中で遠くに座っていた正光が、清少納言が隣にいた人でも聞き返してくるくらいの小声で言ったことを、しっかり聞き逃さなかったことが書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this story, Sei Shonagon wrote that when she was talking with a person next to her in so low voices that even this conversation partner needed to ask her to repeat what she said, Masamitsu, who was seated far away, did not fail to catch their dialogue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this story, Sei Shonagon wrote that when she was talking with a person next to her in such a low voice that even her conversation partner needed to ask her to repeat what she said, Masamitsu, who was seated far away, did not fail to catch their dialogue.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this story, Sei Shonagon wrote that when she was talking with a person next to her in such a low voice that even her conversation partner needed to ask her to repeat what she said, Masamitsu, who was seated far away, did not fail to catch their dialogue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 YOSHI438(id:174755), CalendrierChien(id:242664), Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>