<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原季通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Suemichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Suemichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Suemichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 季通（ふじわら の すえみち、生没年未詳）は平安時代末期の廷臣、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Suemichi (date of birth and death unknown) was a retainer of Imperial Court and a kajin (a waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) poet) who lived in the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Suemichi (date of birth and death unknown) was a retainer at the Imperial Court and a kajin (waka, the traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables, poet) who lived at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Parentheses removed, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Suemichi (year of birth and death unknown) was a retainer at the Imperial Court and a kajin (waka, the traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables, poet) who lived at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>date→year</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>権大納言藤原宗通の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Munemichi who was Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Munemichi who was Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Munemichi who was Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>権大納言の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は六条修理大夫藤原顕季の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Akisue who was Rokujo Shuri no daibu (a master of building and construction of the Palace from Rokujo Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Akisue who was Rokujo Shuri no daibu (a master of building and construction of the Palace from Rokujo Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Akisue who was Rokujo Shuri no daibu (a master of building and construction of the Palace from Rokujo Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同母兄弟に藤原伊通（太政大臣）、藤原成通、藤原重通らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brothers were FUJIWARA no Koremichi, who was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), FUJIWARA no Narimichi, FUJIWARA no Shigemichi and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His brothers were FUJIWARA no Koremichi, who was Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State), FUJIWARA no Narimichi, and FUJIWARA no Shigemichi among others.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His brothers were FUJIWARA no Koremichi, who was Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State), FUJIWARA no Narimichi, and FUJIWARA no Shigemichi among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正四位下、左少将、備後国守、肥後国守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Bingo no kuni no kami (Governor of Bingo Province) and Higo no kuni no kami (Governor of Higo) in Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of the Inner Palace Guards), Bingo no kuni no kami (Governor of Bingo Province) and Higo no kuni no kami (Governor of Higo) in the position of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of the Inner Palace Guards), Bingo no kuni no kami (Governor of Bingo Province) and Higo no kuni no kami (Governor of Higo) in the position of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>His official rank→He ピリオドの前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>和歌の才のみならず、琵琶、笛、箏などの管弦に巧みであり、白河上皇の信任が篤かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was good at not only waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) but also the strings such as biwa (Japanese lute), fue (Japanese flute) and So (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings), and was relied on deeply by the retired Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was good at not only waka, but also playing instruments such as the biwa (Japanese lute), fue (Japanese flute) and so (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings), and was relied on deeply by the retired Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Description of waka unnecessary. Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was good at not only waka, but also playing instruments such as the biwa (Japanese lute), fue (Japanese flute) and so (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings), and was relied on deeply by the Retired Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>retired→Retired</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、若年時に箏の弟子である藤原璋子（待賢門院、鳥羽天皇中宮）と密通したとの嫌疑を受け、その影響から官途の面では不遇であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was received with suspicions of adultery with FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Taikenmonin and the Empress of Emperor Toba), who was his disciple of So, in his young age, and as a result, he suffered a misfortune as a governmental official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was regarded as being guilty of adultery with FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Taikenmonin and the Empress of Emperor Toba), who was his disciple in regard to the so instrument, in his youth, and as a result, he was unsuccessful as a governmental official.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was regarded as being guilty of adultery with FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Taikenmonin and the Empress of Emperor Toba), who was his disciple in regard to the so instrument, in his youth, and as a result, he was unsuccessful as a governmental official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>康治元年（1142年）には、弟の成通、重通より官位が余りにも劣っていたことを藤原頼長に憐れまれ、そのはからいによって正四位下に叙せられたという（『台記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that FUJIWARA no Yorinaga showed compassion for his inferiority to his brothers Narimichi and Shigemichi in the official court rank, and gave him a rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) (&quot;Taiki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that FUJIWARA no Yorinaga showed compassion for his inferiority in official court rank to his brothers Narimichi and Shigemichi, and gave him a rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), according to the &quot;Taiki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that FUJIWARA no Yorinaga showed compassion for his inferiority in official court rank to his brothers Narimichi and Shigemichi, and gave him a rank of Shoshiinoge, according to &quot;the Taiki&quot; (Diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga).</e>
<cmt>diary→Diary(Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)　既出のため削除the を &quot; の中に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>保元3年（1158年）頃までは生存していたというが、その没年も明らかではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he lived until around 1158, but the year of his death is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he lived until around 1158, but the year of his death is not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he lived until around 1158, but the year of his death is not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>幼少の頃、兄の伊通とともに伯母の藤原全子の元を訪れた際、全子によって「兄の方は将来大臣になるが、弟は凡愚で終わるだろう」と評されたという（『古事談』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when he visited his aunt FUJIWARA no Matako with his brother Koremichi when he was young, she said, &apos;this elder brother will become a minister in future, but this little brother will end as a common person&apos; (&quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when he visited his aunt FUJIWARA no Matako with his brother Koremichi when he was young, she said, &apos;this elder brother will become a minister in future, but this little brother will end as a common person&apos;, according to &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when he visited his aunt FUJIWARA no Matako with his brother Koremichi when he was young, she said, &apos;this elder brother will become a minister in future, but this little brother will end as a common person&apos;, according to &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>果たして、政治面では生涯を通して非才・不遇であり、専ら文化・芸術面でのみ名を遺した人物となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, he did not show a talent and suffered a misfortune as a governmental official throughout life and left his name only in the area of culture and arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, he did not show talent and was unsuccessful as a governmental official throughout life and left his name only in the area of culture and arts.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, he did not show talent and was unsuccessful as a governmental official throughout life and left his name only in the area of culture and arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>歌人としては永久 (元号)4年（1116年）の鳥羽殿北面歌合に出詠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a kajin, he joined and read a waka in Tobadono hokumen utaawase (Hokumen poem contest in the Toba Palace) in 1116.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a kajin, he joined and read a waka in Tobadono hokumen utaawase (Hokumen poem contest in the Toba Palace) in 1116.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a kajin, he joined and read a waka in Tobadono hokumen utaawase (Hokumen poem contest in the Toba Palace) in 1116.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『千載和歌集』などに入選するほか、家集として『季通朝臣集』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While his waka was selected for &quot;Senzai waka shu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) and others, he left a personal collection of poetry, &quot;Suemichi Ason shu&quot; (Collection by Suemichi and Ason).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While his waka was selected for &quot;Senzai waka shu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) among others, he bequeathed a personal collection of poetry, &quot;Suemichi Ason shu&quot; (Collection by Suemichi and Ason).</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While his waka was selected for &quot;Senzai waka shu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) among others, he bequeathed a personal collection of poetry, &quot;Suemichi Ason shu&quot; (Collection by Suemichi Ason, second highest of the eight hereditary titles).</e>
<cmt>季通朝臣の訳、訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>