<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平盛子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Seishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Seishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Seishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 盛子（たいら の もりこ/せいし、保元元年（1156年）- 治承3年6月17日 (旧暦)（1179年7月23日））は、摂政・近衛基実の正室（北政所）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Seishi (1156 - July 23, 1179) was the legal wife (Kita no Mandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor) of Regent Motozane KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Seishi (1156 - July 23, 1179) was the legal wife (Kita no Mandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor) of Regent Motozane KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Seishi (1156 - July 30, 1179) was the legal wife (Kita no Mandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor) of Regent Motozane KONOE.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は平清盛、母は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was TAIRA no Kiyomori and her mother is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was TAIRA no Kiyomori and her mother is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was TAIRA no Kiyomori and her mother is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近衛基通の養母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the foster mother of Motomichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the foster mother of Motomichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the foster mother of Motomichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に高倉天皇准母として准三宮に叙せられ、白河殿・白河准后と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In her later life, she was granted Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) and named Shirakawa-dono or Shirakawa Jugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In her later life, she was granted Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) and named Shirakawa-dono or Shirakawa Jugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In her later life, she was granted Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) and named Shirakawa-dono or Shirakawa Jugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>BackgroundをCareerに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>保元の乱で摂関家は武力組織を解体され、その勢力を大幅に後退させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of Hogen Disturbance, Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) had their arms force disbanded, suffering a significant reduction in power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result of the Hogen Disturbance, Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) had their armed force disbanded, suffering a significant reduction in power.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result of the Hogen Disturbance, Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) had their armed force disbanded, suffering a significant reduction in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>苦境に立たされた大殿・藤原忠通は養女の藤原育子を二条天皇の中宮として摂関家再興を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Caught in a predicament, FUJIWARA no Tadamichi. Otono (Minister), tried to reconstruct Sekkan-ke by giving his adopted daughter in marriage as ochugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Caught in a predicament, FUJIWARA no Tadamichi. Otono (Minister), tried to reconstruct Sekkan-ke by giving his adopted daughter in marriage as ochugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Caught in a predicament, FUJIWARA no Tadamichi. Otono (Minister), tried to reconstruct Sekkan-ke by giving his adopted daughter in marriage as chugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>ochuguをchuguに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし長寛2年（1164年）2月19日、志半ばで没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 18, 1164, however, he died before achieving his ambition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 18, 1164, however, he died before achieving his ambition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 20, 1164, however, he died before achieving his ambition.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>清盛はこの機を捉え、4月10日、後継者で22歳の基実に9歳の盛子を嫁がせる（『愚管抄』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori saw this as an opportunity and gave 9-year-old Seishi away in marriage to 22-year-old Motozane who was the successor of the Sekkan-keon April 10 (&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori saw this as an opportunity and gave 9-year-old Seishi away in marriage to 22-year-old Motozane, who was the successor of the Sekkan-ke, on April 10 (&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool)).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori saw this as an opportunity and gave 9-year-old Seishi away in marriage to 22-year-old Motozane, who was the successor of the Sekkan-ke, on May 9 (&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool)).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>摂関家としても若年の基実は心もとなく、後ろ盾が必要な状況だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sekkan-ke also needed to have a backer of Motozane who was still young and not yet competent enough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sekkan-ke also needed to have a backer of Motozane who was still young and not yet sufficiently competent.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sekkan-ke also needed to have a backer of Motozane who was still young and not yet sufficiently competent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>摂関家政所は長寛2年（1164年）の段階ではまだ旧来の摂関家家司で構成されていた（『平安遺文』3284）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekkan-ke Mandokoro government office had had consisted of traditional Keishi (household superintendents) of Sekkan-ke (&quot;Heianibun&quot; 3284) by the year of 1164.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sekkan-ke Mandokoro government office had consisted of traditional Keishi (household superintendents) of Sekkan-ke (&quot;Heianibun&quot; 3284) by the year 1164.</e>
<cmt>omitted unnecessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sekkan-ke Mandokoro government office had consisted of traditional Keishi (household superintendents) of Sekkan-ke (&quot;Heianibun&quot; 3284) by the year 1164.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>翌長寛3年（1165年）には平宗盛・重衡が加わるなど平氏の進出が顕著となっている（『平安遺文』3350）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, TAIRA no Munemori and TAIRA no Shigehira took part in office in 1165, showing a striking advance of the Taira clan (&quot;Heianibun&quot; 3284).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, TAIRA no Munemori and TAIRA no Shigehira took office in 1165, showing a striking advance of the Taira clan (&quot;Heianibun&quot; 3284).</e>
<cmt>omitted unnecessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, TAIRA no Munemori and TAIRA no Shigehira took office in 1165, showing a striking advance of the Taira clan (&quot;Heianibun&quot; 3284).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>永万元年（1165年）7月28日、二条天皇が崩御する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 28, 1165, the Emperor Nijo passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 28, 1165, the Emperor Nijo passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 12, 1165, the Emperor Nijo passed away.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後を追うように基実も、翌永万2年（1166年）7月26日に24歳の若さで急死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 26, Motozane suddenly died young at the age of 24 as if following the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 26, Motozane suddenly died young at the age of 24 as if following the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 30, 1166, Motozane suddenly died young at the age of 24 as if following the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。Emperorのeを大文字にしました。 1166を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>基実の子・基通は7歳と幼少であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motozan&apos;s son, Motomichi, was still seven years old and too young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motozan&apos;s son, Motomichi, was still seven years old and too young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motozan&apos;s son, Motomichi, was still seven years old and too young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>後任の摂政には松殿基房が就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motofusa MATSUDONO succeeded the post of Sessho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motofusa MATSUDONO succeeded to the post of Sessho.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motofusa MATSUDONO succeeded to the post of Sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この時、摂関家家司の藤原邦綱は殿下渡領・勧学院領・御堂流寺院領を除く膨大な私的家領・代々の日記宝物・東三条殿を盛子が伝領するよう策動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this occasion, FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, Keishi of Sekkan-ke schemed to have Seishi take over a large volume of lands for private use of the family --excluding denka no watari-ryo (the land which the Fujiwara family hereditarily succeeded), Kangaku-in-ryo (the land for educational institutions), Midoryu-jiin-ryo (the land of Buddhist temples which belong to the family of FUJIWARA no Michinaga)--as well as diary treasures and Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace inherited from generation to generation..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, Keishi of Sekkan-ke schemed to have Seishi take over a large volume of land for private use of the family --excluding denka no watari-ryo (the land to which the Fujiwara family succeeded by inheritance), Kangaku-in-ryo (the land for educational institutions), Midoryu-jiin-ryo (the land of Buddhist temples which belong to the family of FUJIWARA no Michinaga)--as well as diary treasures and Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace inherited from generation to generation..</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, Keishi of Sekkan-ke schemed to have Seishi take over a large volume of land for private use of the family --excluding denka no watari-ryo (the land to which the Fujiwara family succeeded by inheritance), Kangaku-in-ryo (the land for educational institutions), Midoryu-jiin-ryo (the land of Buddhist temples which belong to the family of FUJIWARA no Michinaga)--as well as diary treasures and Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace inherited from generation to generation..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また自らは盛子の後見となった（『愚管抄』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also acted as a guardian for Seishi (&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also acted as a guardian for Seishi (&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also acted as a guardian for Seishi (&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この結果、清盛は盛子の父として、摂関家領荘園の実質的管理を継続することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, Kiyomori took over substantial control of ryo-shoen (private estates) of Sekkan-ke as the father of Seishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result, as the father of Seishi, Kiyomori took over substantial control of ryo-shoen (private estates) of Sekkan-ke.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result, as the father of Seishi, Kiyomori took over substantial control of ryo-shoen (private estates) of Sekkan-ke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一般的に平氏による「摂関家領の横領」と呼ばれる事件であるが、盛子が養母となっていた基通が成人するまでの一時的な措置という建前であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official stance of this scheme, generally called &quot;embezzlement of Shiteki-keryo,&quot;by the Taira clan was a temporary measures until Motomichi whose foster mother was Seishi came of age.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official stance of this scheme, generally called &quot;embezzlement of Shiteki-keryo,&quot; by the Taira clan was a temporary measure until Motomichi, whose foster mother was Seishi, came of age.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official stance of this scheme, generally called &apos;embezzlement of the estate of Sekkan-ke,&apos; by the Taira clan was a temporary measure until Motomichi, whose foster mother was Seishi, came of age.</e>
<cmt>Shiteki-keryoをthe estate of Sekkan-keに変更しました。&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>憲仁親王（後の高倉天皇）擁立のため平氏との連携を模索していた後白河天皇もこれを認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Goshirakawa, who were seeking alliance with the the Taira clan to help Imperial Prince Norihito (later Emperor Takakura) to the throne, approved this scheme.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Goshirakawa, who were seeking alliance with the the Taira clan to help Imperial Prince Norihito (later Emperor Takakura) to the throne, approved this scheme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Goshirakawa, who were seeking alliance with the Taira clan to help Imperial Prince Norihito (later Emperor Takakura) to the throne, approved this scheme.</e>
<cmt>重複していたtheを取り除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>10月10日の憲仁立太子の儀式は、盛子の住む摂関家の正邸・東三条殿で盛大に執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 10, the official investiture ceremony of the Crown Prince Norihito was held on a large scale at Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace, the main residence of Sekkanke where Seishi lived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10, the official investiture ceremony of Crown Prince Norihito was held on a large scale at Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace, the main residence of Sekkanke where Seishi lived.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 11, the official investiture ceremony of Crown Prince Norihito was held on a large scale at Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace, the main residence of Sekkanke where Seishi lived.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>わずか11歳で実質的な摂関家の家長となった盛子は、翌仁安 (日本)2年（1167年）11月10日、白河押小路殿に移って「白河殿」と称されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seishi, who became in effect the head of a family at the age of only eleven, moved to Shirakawa Oshikoji-dono on November, 10, 1167 and became called &quot;Shirakawa-dono Palace.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seishi, who in effect became the head of a family at the age of only eleven, moved to Shirakawa Oshikoji-dono on November, 10, 1167 and came to be called &quot;Shirakawa-dono Palace.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seishi, who in effect became the head of a family at the age of only eleven, moved to Shirakawa Oshikoji-dono on December 30, 1167 and came to be called &apos;Shirakawa-dono Palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>11月18日には憲仁の准母として従三位となり、准三宮を宣下された（『兵範記』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) as junbo (a woman who was given the status equivalent to the emperor&apos;s birth mother) of Norihito on November 18 and given the title of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) (&quot;Heihanki&quot; (diary of TAIRA no Nobunori), article of November 18).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) as junbo (a woman who was given the status equivalent to the emperor&apos;s birth mother) of Norihito on November 18 and given the title of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) (&quot;Heihanki&quot; (diary of TAIRA no Nobunori), entry of November 18).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) as junbo (a woman who was given the status equivalent to the Emperor&apos;s birth mother) of Norihito on January 7, 1168 and given the title of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) (&quot;Heihanki&quot; (diary of TAIRA no Nobunori), entry of November 18, 1167).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。Emperorのeを大文字にしました。日記はそのままの日付に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>後家となった盛子には藤原師長や基房との再婚の噂が流れた（『玉葉』仁安2年5月1日条、承安3年6月6日、11日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Seishi became a widow, a rumor was going around that she would get married to FUJIWARA no Moronaga or MATSUDONO (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) Articles of May 1, 1167, June 6 and 11 June 1179)).</e>
<cmt>「仁安2年5月1日条、承安3年6月6日、11日条」は新暦に直しました。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Seishi became a widow, a rumor was going around that she would marry FUJIWARA no Moronaga or MATSUDONO (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) entires of May 1, 1167, June 6 and 11 June 1179)).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Seishi became a widow, a rumor was going around that she would marry FUJIWARA no Moronaga or Motofusa (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) entries of May 1, 1167, June 6 and 11, 1173)).</e>
<cmt>MATSUDONOをMotofusaに変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。→日記の日付なので元に戻しました。entiresをentriesに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし結局は実現しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the rumor did not come true.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the rumor did not come true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the rumor did not come true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>夫の没後は、基通の養育の傍らで氏族内部の行事の遂行などを円滑にこなしていたが、治承3年（1179年）春より不食を煩った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her husband&apos;s death, she adeptly divided her time between education of Motomichi and holding ceremonies within the clan, but she fell ill since the spring 1179.</e>
<cmt>「不食を煩い」は、病にかかりと訳してあります。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her husband&apos;s death, she adeptly divided her time between educating Motomichi and holding ceremonies within the clan, but she fell ill in the spring 1179.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her husband&apos;s death, she adeptly divided her time between educating Motomichi and holding ceremonies within the clan, but she fell ill in the spring 1179.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>6月17日、白河押小路殿において夫と同じ24歳で死去した。。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 17, she died at Shirakawa Oshikoji-dono at the age of 24, the same age as her husband.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, she died at Shirakawa Oshikoji-dono at the age of 24, the same age as her husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 30, she died at Shirakawa Oshikoji-dono at the age of 24, the same age as her husband.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>九条兼実は「異姓の身で藤原氏の所領を押領したので春日大明神の神罰が下った」という世間の噂を「どうして14年間も罰が下らなかったのか」と一笑に付した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanezane KUJO laughed down the public rumor that a punishment by Kasuga Daimyojin came down on her because not a man but a woman obtained estates of the Fujiwara clan, saying &quot;if so, why she did not suffer such a punishment for fourteen years?&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanezane KUJO laughed down the public rumor that a punishment by Kasuga Daimyojin came down on her because not a man but a woman obtained estates of the Fujiwara clan, saying &quot;if so, why she did not suffer such a punishment for fourteen years?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanezane KUJO laughed down the public rumor that a punishment by Kasuga Daimyojin came down on her because not a man but a woman obtained estates of the Fujiwara clan, saying &apos;If so, why she did not suffer such a punishment for fourteen years?&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。Ifのiを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>理に任せて遺領を配分するなら関白・氏長者の基房が主要な荘園を伝領し、基通や他の基実子女にもそれぞれ分け与えるのが妥当であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the inherited estates had been divided reasonably, Motofusa, chief adviser to the Emperor and Uji no choja (the head of the clan) could have took over main private estates and each of Motomichi and other Motozane&apos;s sons and daughters could have been given properly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the inherited estates had been divided reasonably, Motofusa, chief adviser to the Emperor and Uji no choja (the head of the clan) could have taken over the main private estates and each of Motomichi and other Motozane&apos;s sons and daughters could have been given property.</e>
<cmt>spelling, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the inherited estates had been divided reasonably, Motofusa, chief adviser to the Emperor and Uji no choja (the head of the clan) could have taken over the main private estates and each of Motomichi and other Motozane&apos;s sons and daughters could have been given property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>残念ながらそうはならず、公家（高倉天皇）が全て伝領して藤氏の家門は滅亡するだろうと嘆いている（『玉葉』治承3年6月18日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanezan deplored that the reality was quite different; a Court noble (Emperor Takakura) took over all the estates and the Kamon (family) of Toji would fall (.&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) Article of June 18, 1179).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「治承3年6月18日」新暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanezan deplored that the reality was quite different; a Court noble (Emperor Takakura) took over all the estates and the Kamon (family) of Toji would fall (.&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) Article of June 18, 1179).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanezan deplored that the reality was quite different; a Court noble (Emperor Takakura) took over all the estates and the Kamon (family) of Toji would fall (.&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) Article of June 18, 1179).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。→日記の日付なので元に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>盛子が死去した時、清盛が厳島参詣で不在にも関わらず平氏の対応は迅速であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan swiftly took actions upon Seishi&apos;s death, although Kiyomori was out of office to visit Itsukushima.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan swiftly took actions upon Seishi&apos;s death, although Kiyomori was out of office visiting Itsukushima.</e>
<cmt>verb form</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan swiftly took actions upon Seishi&apos;s death, although Kiyomori was out of office visiting Itsukushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>わずか2日後の19日には、平時忠が中山忠親に「庄園一向に主上に附属し奉られ了はんぬ」と通告し（『山槐記』同日条）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 19, two days after her death, TAIRA no Tokitada informed Tadachika NAKAYAMA that 庄園一向に主上に附属し奉られ了はんぬ (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; (diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA) Article of June 19, 1179).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「庄園一向に主上に附属し奉られ了はんぬ」は意味不明のためそのままにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 19th, two days after her death, TAIRA no Tokitada informed Tadachika NAKAYAMA that 庄園一向に主上に附属し奉られ了はんぬ (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; (diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA) Article of June 19, 1179).</e>
<cmt>see comments1</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, two days after her death, TAIRA no Tokitada informed Tadachika NAKAYAMA that 庄園一向に主上に附属し奉られ了はんぬ (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; (diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA) Article of June 19, 1179).</e>
<cmt>On the 19th→On August 1グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。日記の日付は元に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>20日には兼実も「白川殿の所領已下の事、皆悉く内の御沙汰あるべし」という情報を入手している（『玉葉』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 20, Kanezane was informed that 白川殿の所領已下の事,皆悉く内の御沙汰あるべし (.&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) Article of June 18, 1179).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「白川殿の所領已下の事、皆悉く内の御沙汰あるべし」は意味不明のためそのままにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On 20, Kanezane was informed that 白川殿の所領已下の事,皆悉く内の御沙汰あるべし (.&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) Article of June 18, 1179).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 2, Kanezane was informed that 白川殿の所領已下の事,皆悉く内の御沙汰あるべし (.&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO) Article of June 20, 1179).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。→日記の日付なので元に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これは、盛子が准母となっていた高倉天皇の権威を盾に基房の抵抗を封じ込めると同時に、基通が成長して関白・氏長者になるまでの時間稼ぎと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose of this is considered to have contained resistance of Motofusa by using authority of Emperor Takakura, whose junbo was Seishi, and gained time until Motomichi grew up to become chief adviser to the Emperor and uji no choja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of this is considered to have been to contain the resistance of Motofusa by using the authority of Emperor Takakura, whose junbo was Seishi, and gaining time until Motomichi grew up to become chief adviser to the Emperor and uji no choja.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of this is considered to have been to contain the resistance of Motofusa by using the authority of Emperor Takakura, whose junbo was Seishi, and gaining time until Motomichi grew up to become chief adviser to the Emperor and uji no choja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>この措置に不満を募らせた基房は、氏長者として遺領相続の権利があることを後白河に訴える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dissatisfied with this measures, Motofusa appealed to Goshirakawa that he had right to succession as uji no choja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dissatisfied with these measures, Motofusa appealed to Goshirakawa that he had right to succession as uji no choja.</e>
<cmt>&quot;this&quot; to &quot;these&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dissatisfied with these measures, Motofusa appealed to Goshirakawa that he had right to succession as uji no choja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>『愚管抄』には「白川殿ウセテ一ノ所ノ家領文書ノ事ナド松殿申サルル旨アリ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool) says &quot;白川殿ウセテ一ノ所ノ家領文書ノ事ナド松殿申サルル旨アリ&quot;</e>
<cmt>「白川殿ウセテ一ノ所ノ家領文書ノ事ナド松殿申サルル旨アリ」は意味不明のためそのままにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool) says &quot;白川殿ウセテ一ノ所ノ家領文書ノ事ナド松殿申サルル旨アリ&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool) says &quot;白川殿ウセテ一ノ所ノ家領文書ノ事ナド松殿申サルル旨アリ&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>院モヤウヤウ御沙汰ドモアリケリ」とあり、基房の訴えを聞いた後白河が遺領問題に介入したとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it also say &quot;院モヤウヤウ御沙汰ドモアリケリ,&quot; Goshirakawa who accepted Motofusa&apos;s complain is believed to have intervened the inheritance issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it also says &quot;院モヤウヤウ御沙汰ドモアリケリ,&quot; Goshirakawa, who accepted Motofusa&apos;s complaint, is believed to have intervened in the inheritance issue.</e>
<cmt>see comment1</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it also says &apos;The Retired Emperor finally gave a command,&apos; Goshirakawa, who accepted Motofusa&apos;s complaint, is believed to have intervened in the inheritance issue.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>やがて「内の御沙汰」となったはずの盛子遺領は、院近臣・藤原兼盛が白河殿倉預に任じられて後白河の管理下に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The estates left by Seishi, which would have become &quot;内の御沙汰&quot; were put under control of Goshirakawa through appointment of FUJIWARA no Kanemori, In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) as Shirakawa-dono kuraazukari.</e>
<cmt>「内の御沙汰」は意味不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The estates left by Seishi, which would have become &quot;内の御沙汰&quot;, were put under the control of Goshirakawa through the appointment of FUJIWARA no Kanemori, In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) as Shirakawa-dono kuraazukari.</e>
<cmt>see comment1</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The estates left by Seishi, which would have become a &apos;private order,&apos; were put under the control of Goshirakawa through the appointment of FUJIWARA no Kanemori, In no Kinshin (the Retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) as Shirakawa-dono kuraazukari.</e>
<cmt>&quot;内の御沙汰&quot;を&apos;private order&apos;に変更しました。Retiredのｒを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これは高倉天皇領に対して、王家の家長の権限を行使したものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is believed that the head of a royal family exercised his power over the estates of the Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the head of a royal family exercised his power over the estates of the Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the head of a royal family exercised his power over the estates of the Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この時期、在位中の天皇の所領管理は後院が行っており、王家の家長である治天の君が後院を掌握していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time Goin Palace controlled estates of the emperor on the throne and Chiten no kimi (the retired emperor in power) held the command of Goin Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Goin Palace controlled estates of the emperor on the throne and Chiten no kimi (the retired emperor in power) held the command of Goin Palace.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Goin Palace controlled estates of the Emperor on the throne and Chiten no kimi (the Retired Emperor in power) held the command of Goin Palace.</e>
<cmt>Empeor、retiredをそれぞれ大文字から開始しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>盛子の死による摂関家領の帰属問題は、後白河と清盛の全面衝突を惹起することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disputes over possession of the estate of Sekkan-ke after the death of Seishi triggered all out conflicts between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disputes over possession of the estate of Sekkan-ke after the death of Seishi triggered all-out conflicts between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disputes over possession of the estate of Sekkan-ke after the death of Seishi triggered all-out conflicts between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), トホホ川(id:50502), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>