<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>相良長隆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagataka SAGARA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagataka SAGARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagataka SAGARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>相良　長隆（さがら　ながたか、1492年（明応元年） － 1526年6月25日（大永6年5月16日 (旧暦)））は、相良氏第13代当主・相良長毎の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagataka SAGARA (male, 1492 to June 25, 1526) was the second son of Nagatsune SAGARA, the thirteenth head of the SAGARA family.</e>
<cmt>調査</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagataka SAGARA (male, 1492 to June 25, 1526) was the second son of Nagatsune SAGARA, the thirteenth head of the SAGARA family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagataka SAGARA (1492 - July 5, 1526) was the second son of Nagatsune SAGARA, the thirteenth head of the Sagara family.</e>
<cmt>male, 削除しました。toをハイフンにしました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。Sagara familyと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第14代当主・相良長祗の庶兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagataka was an elder brother, born from a mistress of his father, of Nagamasa SAGARA, the fourteenth head of the SAGARA family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagataka was an elder brother, born from a mistress of his father, of Nagamasa SAGARA, the fourteenth head of the SAGARA family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagataka was an elder brother, born from a mistress of his father, of Nagamasa SAGARA, the fourteenth head of the Sagara family.</e>
<cmt>Sagara familyと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>10歳のときに出家して瑞賢と号し、京都東福寺で僧籍に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagataka SAGARA became a Buddhism priest at the age of ten with a pen name, Zuiken and entered the priesthood at Tofuku-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagataka SAGARA became a Buddhism priest at the age of ten with a pen name, Zuiken and entered the priesthood at Tofuku-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagataka SAGARA became a Buddhism priest at the age of ten with a pen name, Zuiken and entered the priesthood at Tofuku-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかしやがて帰国し、観音寺第12代住職となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he later on returned to his home province and became the twelfth chief priest of Kannon-ji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, later on he returned to his home province and became the twelfth chief priest of Kannon-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, later on he returned to his home province and became the twelfth chief priest of Kannon-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1524年、弟の長祗が相良長定に攻められて翌年に自殺すると、1526年に僧兵をかき集めて長定を破り、還俗して太郎長隆と名乗って相良氏の家督を継ごうとしたが、僧上がりの長隆に対して相良一族や家臣団は従おうとせず、長隆は正式に家督を継ぐこともできず、人吉城から逃亡し、永里城に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nagataka SAGARA&apos;s younger brother, Nagamasa was attacked by Nagasada SAGARA in 1524 and Nagamasa killed himself in the next year, Nagataka raked up the monk soldiers and, with them, beat down Nagasada in 1526 and, then, Nagataka returned to the secular life naming himself Taro-Nagataka and tried to succeed to the headship of the SAGARA family, however, the whole SAGARA family and their vassal groups would not obey Nagataka who had been a priest, and Nagataka could not formally succeed to the headship of the family, ran away from Hitoyoshi-jo castle, and went into Nagasato-jo castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nagataka SAGARA&apos;s younger brother, Nagamasa was attacked by Nagasada SAGARA in 1524 and Nagamasa killed himself the next year, Nagataka gathered up monk soldiers and, with them, beat down Nagasada in 1526, afterwhich he returned to the secular life naming himself Taro-Nagataka and tried to succeed to the headship of the SAGARA family, however, the whole SAGARA family and their vassal groups would not obey Nagataka who had been a priest, and Nagataka could not formally succeed to the headship of the family, thus he ran away from Hitoyoshi-jo castle, and went to Nagasato-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nagataka SAGARA&apos;s younger brother, Nagamasa was attacked by Nagasada SAGARA in 1524 and Nagamasa killed himself the next year, Nagataka gathered up monk soldiers and, with them, beat down Nagasada in 1526, after which he returned to the secular life naming himself Taro-Nagataka and tried to succeed to the headship of the Sagara family, however, the whole Sagara family and their vassal groups would not obey Nagataka who had been a priest, and Nagataka could not formally succeed to the headship of the family, thus he ran away from Hitoyoshi-jo Castle, and went to Nagasato-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。Sagara familyと訂正しました。Castle大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、一族の実力者上村頼興の後援を得た実兄の相良義滋に攻められて、自害に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Nagataka was attacked by his elder brother by blood, Yoshishige SAGARA who was backed up by an influential person of the SAGARA family, Yoriyoshi UEMURA, and Nagataka was driven to kill himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Nagataka was attacked by his elder brother, Yoshishige SAGARA who was backed up by an influential person of the Sagara family, Yoriyoshi UEMURA, and Nagataka was driven to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Nagataka was attacked by his elder brother, Yoshishige SAGARA who was backed up by an influential person of the Sagara family, Yoriyoshi UEMURA, and Nagataka was driven to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>享年35。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagataka died at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagataka died at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagataka died at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kuma83(id:31177), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>