<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原顕綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akitsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 顕綱（ふじわら の あきつな、長元2年（1029年） - 康和5年6月27日 (旧暦)（1103年8月1日））は平安時代後期の廷臣、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akitsuna (1029 - August 1, 1103) was a retainer of Imperial Court and poet who lived in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akitsuna (1029 - August 1, 1103) was a retainer of Imperial Court and poet who lived in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akitsuna (1029 - August 8, 1103) was a retainer of Imperial Court and poet who lived in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家藤原道綱流の出身で、参議藤原兼経の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came from the Michitsuna Fujiwara line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the third son of FUJIWARA no Kanetsune, Sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from the Michitsuna Fujiwara line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the third son of FUJIWARA no Kanetsune, Sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in the FUJIWARA no Michitsuna line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the third son of FUJIWARA no Kanetsune, Sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正四位下、丹波国守、讃岐国守、但馬国守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ranked Shoshiinoge (senior fourth rank, lower grade), and assumed Tanba no kuni no kami (the governor of Tanba Province), Sanuki no kuni no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province) and Tajima no kuni no kami (the governor of Tajima Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ranked Shoshiinoge (senior fourth rank, lower grade), and assumed the posts of Tanba no kuni no kami (the governor of Tanba Province), Sanuki no kuni no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province), and Tajima no kuni no kami (the governor of Tajima Province).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the posts of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ranked Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and assumed the posts of Tanba no kuni no kami (the governor of Tanba Province), Sanuki no kuni no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province), and Tajima no kuni no kami (the governor of Tajima Province).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称は讃岐入道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly called Sanuki no Nyudo (literally, a priest in Sanuki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly called Sanuki no Nyudo (literally, a priest in Sanuki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly called Sanuki no Nyudo (literally, a priest in Sanuki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>歌人として知られ、承暦2年（1078年）の内裏歌合などに出詠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Known as a poet, he participated and made waka poems in utaawase held in the Imperial Palace in 1078.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known as a poet, he participated and wrote waka poems in utaawase held in the Imperial Palace in 1078.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known as a poet, he participated and wrote waka poems in an Utaawase held in the Imperial Palace in 1078.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>家集として『讃岐入道集』（『顕綱朝臣集』）があり、『後拾遺和歌集』以下の勅撰和歌集に25首が入選している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sanuki no Nyudo shu&quot; (&quot;Akitsuna ason shu&quot;) is a collection of his waka poems, and his 25 waka poems are included in &quot;GoShui wakashu&quot; (Later gleanings of Japanese poems) and later Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sanuki no Nyudo shu&quot; (&quot;Akitsuna ason shu&quot;) is a collection of his waka poems, and 25 of his waka poems are included in &quot;GoShui wakashu&quot; (Later gleanings of Japanese poems) and later Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sanuki no Nyudo shu&quot; (&quot;Akitsuna ason shu&quot;) is a collection of his waka poems, and 25 of his waka poems are included in &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry) and later Chokusen wakashu (anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また古典にも造詣が深く、『万葉集』の書写などを通じてその伝承に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also well versed in Japanese classics and contributed to handing them down from generations to generations, for example, by copying &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (A collection of ten thousand leaves).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also well versed in Japanese classics and contributed to handing them down from generation to generation; for example, by copying &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (A collection of ten thousand leaves).</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also well versed in Japanese classics and contributed to handing them down from generation to generation; for example, by copying &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>母が禎子内親王の乳母であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the woman providing breast-feed to Imperial Princess Teishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the wet nurse to Imperial Princess Teishi.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the wet nurse to Imperial Princess Teishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>関係から後三条天皇に近く、次男の藤原有佐は、実は後三条天皇の落胤であったと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he had a close relationship with Emperor Gosanjo, and it is said that his second son, FUJIWARA no Arisuke, was actually an illegitimate child of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he had a close relationship with Emperor Gosanjo, and it is said that his second son, FUJIWARA no Arisuke, was actually an illegitimate child of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he had a close relationship with Emperor Gosanjo, and it is said that his second son, FUJIWARA no Arisuke, was in fact an illegitimate child of Emperor Gosanjo.</e>
<cmt>actually→in fact</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>