<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鷹司信子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鷹司 信子（たかつかさ のぶこ、慶安4年（1651年） - 宝永6年2月7日 (旧暦)（1709年3月17日））は、江戸幕府5代征夷大将軍徳川綱吉の正室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA (1651-March 17, 1709) was the lawful wife of Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the fifth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA (1651-March 17, 1709) was the lawful wife of Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the fifth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuko TAKATSUKASA (1651-March 17, 1709) was the lawful wife of Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the fifth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>左大臣従一位鷹司教平の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of Norihira TAKATSUKASA who was Sadaijin (minister of the left) Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daughter of Norihira TAKATSUKASA who was Sadaijin (minister of the left) Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of Norihira TAKATSUKASA who was Sadaijin (minister of the left) Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄に関白鷹司房輔、妹に霊元天皇中宮鷹司房子（新上西門院）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her elder brother was Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA, a chief adviser to the Emperor, and her younger sister was Fusako TAKATSUKASA, chugu (the second consort of an emperor) of the Emperor Reigen (Shinjosaimonin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her elder brother was Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA, a chief adviser to the Emperor, and her younger sister was Fusako TAKATSUKASA, chugu (the second consort of an emperor) of Emperor Reigen (Shinjosaimonin).</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her elder brother was Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA, a chief adviser to the Emperor, and her younger sister was Fusako TAKATSUKASA, chugu (the second consort of an emperor) of Emperor Reigen (Shinjosaimonin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、6代将軍徳川家宣の御台所近衛熙子とは再従姉妹の関係である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, she was the second cousin of Hiroko KONOE who was Midaidokoro (shogun or minister&apos;s wife) of the sixth Shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, she was a second cousin of Hiroko KONOE who was Midaidokoro (shogun or minister&apos;s wife) of the sixth Shogun, Ienobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>コンマ挿入、冠詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, she was a second cousin of Hiroko KONOE who was Midaidokoro (shogun or minister&apos;s wife) of the sixth Shogun, Ienobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>かつて綱吉の祖父・徳川秀忠は娘・徳川和子を後水尾天皇の中宮にする際に、とその母四辻与津子（お与津御寮人）の存在が障害であるとして二人を宮中から追放した上、与津子の親族を含む数人の公卿らを流刑に処した（「お与津御寮人事件」）という経緯があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a time in the past, there was an incident (the Incident of Oyotsu-Goryonin) that when Tsunayoshi&apos;s grandfather Hidetada TOKUGAWA made his daughter Masako TOKUGAWA chugu of the Emperor Gomizuo, he banished the Princess Umenomiya and her mother Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin) from the Imperial Court because they were obstacles for her and exiled some Kugyo (the top court officials) including her relatives.</e>
<cmt>「とその母」は調査の結果、「梅宮とその母」の梅宮の脱字と解釈して訳しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a time in the past, there was an incident (the Incident of Oyotsu-Goryonin) that when Tsunayoshi&apos;s grandfather Hidetada TOKUGAWA made his daughter, Masako TOKUGAWA, chugu of Emperor Gomizuo, he banished Princess Umenomiya and her mother Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin) from the Imperial Court because they were obstacles for Masako and exiled some Kugyo (the top court officials) including her relatives.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、混乱を防ぐためコンマ挿入、herの明確化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At a time in the past, there was an incident (the Incident of Oyotsu-Goryonin) that when Tsunayoshi&apos;s grandfather Hidetada TOKUGAWA made his daughter, Masako TOKUGAWA, chugu of Emperor Gomizuo, he banished Princess Umenomiya and her mother Yotsuko YOTSUTSUJI (Oyotsu-Goryonin) from the Imperial Court because they were obstacles for Masako and exiled some Kugyo (the top court officials) including her relatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このため信子と徳川氏との間には深い因縁があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there was a deep relationship between Nobuko and the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there was a deep relationship between Nobuko and the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there was a deep relationship between Nobuko and the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>寛文4年（1664年）、当時上野国館林藩主であった徳川綱吉と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1664 she married with Tunayoshi TOKUGAWA who was the lord of the Tatebayashi clan in the Ueno Province at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1664 she married Tunayoshi TOKUGAWA who was the lord of Tatebayashi Domain in Ueno Province at that time.</e>
<cmt>with削除、冠詞削除、clanをdomainに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1664 she married Tunayoshi TOKUGAWA who was the lord of Tatebayashi Domain in Ueno Province at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延宝8年（1680年）、綱吉の将軍就任により江戸城大奥に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the assignment of Tsunayoshi to Shogun in 1680, she entered O-oku (the inner halls of Edo Castle where the wife of the Shogun and her servants reside).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with Tsunayoshi&apos;s assumption of Shogun in 1680, she entered O-oku (the inner halls of Edo Castle where the wife of the Shogun and her servants reside).</e>
<cmt>「就任」を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with Tsunayoshi&apos;s assumption of Shogun in 1680, she entered O-oku (the inner halls of Edo Castle where the wife of the Shogun and her servants reside).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>綱吉生母・桂昌院とは不仲であったとされ、綱吉との夫婦仲については2人の間に子女は産まれなかったことなどから、不和であったとする説があるが詳細は不詳（ただし、歴代徳川幕府将軍で正室との間に子女を儲けた例の方が少ない点は留意する必要がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was regarded to have outs with Tsunayoshi&apos;s real mother Keishoin and Tsunayoshi because they did not have any child, but the detail is unclear (However, it should be paid attention that few successive Tokugawa bakufu Shogun had a child between their lawful wives).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is regarded to have had outs with Tsunayoshi&apos;s real mother Keishoin and Tsunayoshi because they did not have any child, but the detail is unclear (However, it should be paid attention that few successive Tokugawa bakufu Shogun had a child between their lawful wives).</e>
<cmt>時制変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is regarded to have had outs with Tsunayoshi&apos;s real mother Keishoin and Tsunayoshi because they did not have any child, but the detail is unclear (However, it should be paid attention that few successive Tokugawa bakufu Shogun had a child between their lawful wives).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、綱吉側室・瑞春院が世嗣・徳松生母として権勢をふるった事も快く思っていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, she did not feel good about Zuishunin, a concubine of Tsunayoshi, who had a power as a mother of his successor Tokumatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, she did not feel good about Zuishunin, a concubine of Tsunayoshi, who had power as the mother of his successor Tokumatsu.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更、冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, she did not feel good about Zuishunin, a concubine of Tsunayoshi, who had power as the mother of his successor Tokumatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため、綱吉の寵愛を於伝之方から離すため、新上西門院を通じて宮中で最も学問に秀でているとの呼び声が高い典侍・右衛門佐局を、御台所付上臈御年寄として大奥へ招聘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, in order to change Tsunayoshi&apos;s feeling of love for Oden no kata (於伝之方), she invited Uemon no suke no tsubone, that is, Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) who was said to shine academically best in the Imperial Court, as Joro (high rank woman servant in the Imperial Court) Otoshiyori (a lady who controls the servants in O-oku) under Midaidokoro through Shinjosaimonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, in order to change Tsunayoshi&apos;s feeling of love for Oden no kata, she invited Uemon no suke no tsubone, that is, Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) who was said to shine academically best in the Imperial Court, as Joro (high rank woman servant in the Imperial Court) Otoshiyori (a lady who controls the servants in O-oku) under Midaidokoro through Shinjosaimonin.</e>
<cmt>瑞春院と於伝之方が同一人物であることの記述が必要かと思いますが、原文に従い、「於伝之方」のみとしました。漢字表記削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, in order to change Tsunayoshi&apos;s feeling of love for Oden no kata, she invited Uemon no suke no tsubone, that is, Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) who was said to shine academically best in the Imperial Court, as Joro (high rank woman servant in the Imperial Court) Otoshiyori (a lady who controls the servants in O-oku) under Midaidokoro through Shinjosaimonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>更に大奥女中総支配を命ぜられた常盤井改め右衛門佐が、大典侍や清心院らを側室として京から呼び寄せ、公家派として於伝之方に対抗したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is said that Uemon no suke who changed the name from Tokiwai and was ordered to control all maids of O-oku called Daitenshi and Seishinin as concubines from Kyoto and fought with Oden no kata as Kuge (court noble) group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is said that Uemon no suke, who changed her name from Tokiwai and was ordered to control all maids of O-oku, called Daitenshi and Seishinin as concubines from Kyoto and fought with Oden no kata as Kuge (court noble) group.</e>
<cmt>冠詞をherに変更、理解を助けるためコンマ挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is said that Uemon no suke, who changed her name from Tokiwai and was ordered to control all maids of O-oku, called Daitenshi and Seishinin as concubines from Kyoto and fought with Oden no kata as Kuge (court noble) group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>宝永6年（1709年）、夫・綱吉の死から一月も経たないうちに死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1709 she died within one month after her husband Tsunayoshi had died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1709 Nobuko died within a month after her husband Tsunayoshi had died.</e>
<cmt>sheの明確化、oneを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1709 Nobuko died within a month after her husband Tsunayoshi had died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>享年59。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was 59 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was 59 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was 59 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>墓所は東京都台東区の寛永寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave was located in the Kanei-ji Temple at Taito Ward, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is located in Kanei-ji Temple at Taito Ward, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>現在形化、冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is located in Kanei-ji Temple at Taito Ward, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのあまりに急な死に、実は綱吉は信子と御台所付御年寄・伊豆局の手によって殺害され、信子はその後自害したという俗説（『日光邯鄲枕』）も残っているが、信憑性に乏しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her sudden death caused a common saying that Tsunayoshi was actually killed by Nobuko and Izu no tsubone, who was Otoshiyori under Midaidokoro and that Nobuko committed suicide later (&quot;Nikkokantanmakura&quot;), but this is unreliable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her sudden death caused a popular belief that Tsunayoshi was actually killed by Nobuko and Izu no tsubone who was Otoshiyori under Midaidokoro and then Nobuko committed a suicide later (&quot;Nikkokantanmakura&quot;), but this is unreliable.</e>
<cmt>「俗説」を変更、コンマ削除、thatをthenに変更、冠詞挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her sudden death caused a popular belief that Tsunayoshi was actually killed by Nobuko and Izu no tsubone who was Otoshiyori under Midaidokoro and then Nobuko committed a suicide later (&quot;Nikkokantanmakura&quot;), but this is unreliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Thomo(id:169717), 果心居士(id:248111), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Happy B.(id:111020), 飲んでも飲まれるな(id:120588), Sorrysorry(id:102591), Hatsune(id:26654), Shelling ford 221b(id:35237), N quaker(id:71025), YurikBot(id:18605), Chobot(id:20846), 史さん(id:25829), こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), Trashwriter(id:79181), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>