<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北郷忠能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi HONGO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi HONGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi HONGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北郷 忠能（ほんごう ただよし、天正18年2月6日 (旧暦)（1590年3月11日） - 寛永8年2月5日 (旧暦)（1631年3月7日））は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代初頭にかけての九州の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi HONGO (March 11, 1590 - March 7, 1631) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in Kyushuin from Azuchi-Momoyama period to early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi HONGO (March 11, 1590 - March 7, 1631) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in Kyushuin from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi HONGO (March 11, 1590 - March 7, 1631) was a military commander in Kyushu from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北郷氏12代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the twelfth family head of the Hongo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the twelfth family head of the Hongo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the twelfth head of the family of the Hongo clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幼名「長千代丸」、字は「次郎」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was &apos;Nagachiyomaru,&apos; and azana (adult males nickname) was &apos;Jiro.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was &apos;Nagachiyomaru,&apos; and his azana (adult males nickname) was &apos;Jiro.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was &apos;Nagachiyomaru,&apos; and his regular name was &apos;Jiro.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>父は11代当主・北郷忠虎、母は側室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was the eleventh family head, Tadatora HONGO, and mother was a concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was the eleventh family head, Tadatora HONGO, and his mother was a concubine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was the eleventh head of the family, Tadatora HONGO, and his mother was a concubine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）、父・忠虎が朝鮮出兵で客死したため5歳で家督を相続したが、幼児のため、政務は祖父の北郷時久が、軍務は叔父の北郷三久に後見されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1595, his father, Tadatora, died abroad during Japan&apos;s Invasion of Korea, and he took over as the head of the family at age 5, but since he was a young child, his grandfather, Tokihisa HONGO, acted as guardian for government affairs, and his uncle, Mitsuhisa HONGO, for military affairs,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1595, his father, Tadatora, died abroad during Japan&apos;s Invasion of Korea, and he took over as the head of the family at age 5, but since he was a young child, his grandfather, Tokihisa HONGO, acted as guardian for government affairs, and his uncle, Mitsuhisa HONGO, for military affairs,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1595, his father, Tadatora, died abroad during Japan&apos;s Invasion of Korea, and he took over as the head of the family at the age of five, but since he was a young child, his grandfather, Tokihisa HONGO, acted as guardian for government affairs, and his uncle, Mitsuhisa HONGO, for military affairs.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>翌文禄5年（1596年）にはその祖父も亡くなり、三久も朝鮮半島に駐屯中のため、実務は家老の小杉重頼にゆだねられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1596, the grandfather also died, and Mitsuhisa was stationed in the Korean Peninsula, so practical work was entrusted to the Karo (chief retainer), Shigeyori KOSUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1596, the grandfather also died, and Mitsuhisa was stationed on the Korean Peninsula, so practical work was entrusted to the Karo (chief retainer), Shigeyori KOSUGI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1596, the grandfather also died, and Mitsuhisa was stationed on the Korean Peninsula, so practical work was entrusted to the chief retainer, Shigeyori KOSUGI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>慶長4年（1599年）に庄内の乱が起こったが、乱の当事者・伊集院氏は北郷氏の故地である都城市を豊臣秀吉の肝いりで横領したと思われており、故郷を回復せんとするこのときの北郷氏家中の活躍はめざましかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1599, when the Shonai War erupted, the Ijuin clan, the central player of the war was believed to have embezzled Miyakonojo City, a place of connection for the Hongo clan, through the good of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and the efforts of the Hongo clan family to recover their hometown were impressive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1599, when the Shonai War erupted, the Ijuin clan, the central player of the war was believed to have embezzled Miyakonojo City, a place of connection for the Hongo clan, through the good of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and the efforts of the Hongo clan family to recover their hometown were impressive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Shonai War erupted in 1599, the Ijuin clan, the central player of the war was believed to have embezzled Miyakonojo City, a place of connection for the Hongo clan, through the introduction of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and the efforts of the Hongo clan family to recover their hometown were impressive.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>乱が島津本宗家側の勝利に終わったことにより北郷氏は故地・都城を回復することに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war ended with victory on the side of the head family of the Shimazu family, and the Hongo clan succeeded in recovering their place of connection, Miyakonojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war ended with victory on the side of the head family of the Shimazu family, and the Hongo clan succeeded in recovering their place of connection, Miyakonojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the war ended with victory on the side of the main branch of the originator of the Shimazu family, the Hongo clan succeeded in recovering their place of connection, Miyakonojo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>最もこの時幼少だった忠能は実際の軍務に携わることは全く無く、先頭に立ったのは叔父の三久であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tadayoshi, who was in his early childhood at that time, took no part in actual military affairs, and his uncle, Mitsuhisa, took the lead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tadayoshi, who was in his early childhood at the time, took no part in actual military affairs, rather his uncle, Mitsuhisa, took the lead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, Tadayoshi, who was in his early childhood at the time, took no part in actual military affairs, rather his uncle, Mitsuhisa, took the lead in the war.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>慶長10年（1605年）には家老の北郷久陸を追放するなど家中への統制策を強める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1605, he tightened the control over his family by expelling his Karo, Hisariku HONGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1605, he tightened control over his family by expelling his Karo, Hisariku HONGO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1605, he tightened control over his family by expelling his chief retainer, Hisariku HONGO.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このころから独り立ちして北郷家の当主としての実務も見るようになったと思われるが、朝鮮出兵・庄内の乱で実際に活躍した三久を当主とすべきという勢力と対立し、家中が紛糾し出すようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that around this time, he began overseeing the practical work on his own as the head of the Hongo family, but conflict with forces believing Mitsuhisa, who actually played an active role in Japan&apos;s Invasion of Korea and the Shonai War, should be the family head, began tangling the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that around this time, he began overseeing the practical work on his own as the head of the Hongo family, but conflict with forces believing Mitsuhisa, who actually played an active role in Japan&apos;s Invasion of Korea and the Shonai War, should be the family head, began tangling the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that around this time, he began overseeing the business on his own as the head of the Hongo family, although, the conflict with forces believing Mitsuhisa, who actually played an active role in Japan&apos;s Invasion of Korea and the Shonai War, should be the family head, introduced the power struggle into the family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>結局、島津本宗家の介入により、三久は別家として独立することで解決を見たが、この頃からたびたび家中に介入する島津本宗家との確執が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, it resolved with the intervention by the head family of the Shimazu family to have Mitsuhisa become independent as a separate family, but around this time, feud began with the head family of the Shimazu family who often intervened with the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, it was resolved with the intervention of the head family of the Shimazu family to have Mitsuhisa become independent as a separate family, but around this time, a feud began with the head family of the Shimazu family who often intervened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, it was resolved with the intervention of the main branch of the originator of the Shimazu family to make Mitsuhisa become independent as a separate family; however, around this time, a feud began with the main branch of the originator of the Shimazu family which often intervened.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>慶長12年（1607年）に島津氏最有力の分家で佐土原藩主となっていた島津以久の娘と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1607, he married the daughter of Yukihisa SHIMAZU, who was the most powerful branch family of the Shimazu clan, and had become the lord of the Sadowara domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1607, he married the daughter of Yukihisa SHIMAZU, who was the most powerful branch family of the Shimazu clan, and had become the lord of the Sadowara domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1607, he married the daughter of Yukihisa SHIMAZU, who was the most powerful branch of the Shimazu clan, and had become the lord of the Sadowara Domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>慶長17年（1612年）には江戸に向かい、徳川秀忠に島津本宗家を介することなく直に対面、馬を拝領されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1612, he headed to Edo, met directly with Hidetada TOKUGAWA without intervention by the head family of the Shimazu family, and received a horse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1612, he headed to Edo, met directly with Hidetada TOKUGAWA without any intervention by the head family of the Shimazu family, and received a horse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1612, he headed to Edo, met directly with Hidetada TOKUGAWA without any intervention of the main branch of the originator of the Shimazu family, and received a horse.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>島津忠恒とはきわめて不仲であり、家久から「家臣を大事にしない当主は上に立つ資格がない」という内容の詰問状を送られているが、家久自身が家臣の粛清をたびたび行っており、説得力はなかったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was in extremely bad terms with Tadatsune SHIMAZU, and received a letter from Iehisa questioning his actions saying &apos;family heads who do not cherish their vassals lack the credentials to lead,&apos; but it lacked persuasion because Iehisa himself frequently purged his vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was on extremely bad terms with Tadatsune SHIMAZU, and received a letter from Iehisa questioning his actions saying &apos;family heads who do not cherish their vassals lack the credentials to lead,&apos; but it lacked persuasion because Iehisa himself frequently purged his vassals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was on extremely bad terms with Tadatsune SHIMAZU, and received a letter from Iehisa questioning his actions saying &apos;family heads that do not treat their vassals with consideration lack the credentials to lead,&apos; but it lacked persuasion because Iehisa himself frequently purged his vassals.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>寛永8年（1631年）病死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died from a disease in 1631.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died from a disease in 1631.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died from a disease in 1631.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>享年42。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 42.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died at the age of 42.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 42.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>法名「二厳院殿剛嶽常金居士」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was &apos;二厳院殿剛嶽常金居士.&apos;</e>
<cmt>二厳院殿剛嶽常金居士→［正しい読み方が不明です］</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was &apos;二厳院殿剛嶽常金居士.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was &apos;jigenindengodokujokonkoji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>忠能の死後、北郷氏は早世する当主が相次ぎ、次第に島津本宗家に圧迫されるようになっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Tadayoshi, heads of family of the Hongo clan successively died young, and gradually became oppressed by the head family of the Shimazu family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Tadayoshi, heads of family of the Hongo clan successively died young, and gradually became oppressed by the head family of the Shimazu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Tadayoshi, heads of family of the Hongo clan successively died young, and gradually became oppressed by the main branch of the originator of the Shimazu family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episodes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episodes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episodes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>忠能は弓の達人として知られており、慶長13年（1608年）10月には方広寺大仏殿の前で通し矢を演じて賞賛され、現在都城が和弓の名産地となる基礎を築いたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi was known as a master of archery, and in October (old lunar calendar) 1608, he was acclaimed for his performance of Toshiya (long-range archery) in front of the Hoko-ji Temple Daibutsu-den Hall, which built the foundation for Miyakonojo to become the famous production area for Japanese bows today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi was known as a master of archery, and in October (old lunar calendar) 1608, he was acclaimed for his performance of Toshiya (long-range archery) in front of the Hoko-ji Temple Daibutsu-den Hall, which built the foundation for Miyakonojo to become a famous production area for Japanese bows today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi was known as a master of archery, and in November 1608, he was acclaimed for his performance of Toshiya (long-range archery) in front of the Hoko-ji Temple Daibutsu-den Hall, which built up the foundation of Miyakonojo as a famous production area for Japanese bows today.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>また徳田太兵衛は雑煮を詰まらせて死んだことで知られ、それはこの忠能に正月の挨拶に行ったときのこととされるが、年代にずれがあるようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Tahei TOKUDA is known to have died after choking on zoni (vegetable soup containing rice cakes), and it is believed this occurred while visiting Tadayoshi for New Year&apos;s, but the dates do not seem to match.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Tahei TOKUDA died after choking on zoni (vegetable soup containing rice cakes), and it is believed this occurred while visiting Tadayoshi for New Year&apos;s, but the dates do not seem to match.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Tahei TOKUDA died after choking on vegetable soup containing rice cakes, and it is believed this occurred while visiting Tadayoshi for New Year&apos;s, but the dates do not seem to match.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Goki(id:7107), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>