<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三条西季知</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suetomo SANJONISHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suetomo SANJONISHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suetomo SANJONISHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三条西 季知（さんじょうにし すえとも、文化 (元号)8年2月26日 (旧暦)（1811年3月20日） - 明治13年（1880年）8月24日）は、幕末の公卿で明治の高官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suetomo SANJONISHI (March 20th, 1811 ~ August 24th, 1880) was a Kugyo (a court noble of some class) of the end of Edo period and a High official of the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suetomo SANJONISHI (March 20th, 1811 ~ August 24th, 1880) was a Kugyo (a court noble of some class) during the end of the Edo period and a High official during the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suetomo SANJONISHI (March 20, 1811-August 24, 1880) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) during the end of the Edo period and a High official during the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>日付表記、記号を修正。「公卿」を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三条西実勲の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a son of Saneiso SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Saneiso SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Saneiso SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は三条実起の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is a daughter of Saneoki SANJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Saneoki SANJO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Saneoki SANJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>安政5年（1858年）、権中納言となり重んじられるが、文久3年（1863年）公武合体派の策略により、三条実美らと長州へ下向、いわゆる七卿落ちの一人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Gonchunagon (provisional middle counselor) in 1858, and trusted, however, he was obliged to leave the capital to Choshu by a conspiracy by those who advocate shogunate marital union with the Imperial Family, a man of so-called &quot;Shichikyo ochi&quot; (incident that seven Kugyo was expelled from Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Gonchunagon (provisional middle counselor) in 1858, and trusted, however, he was obliged to leave the capital to Choshu in a conspiracy by those who advocated shogunate marital union with the Imperial Family, a man of so-called &quot;Shichikyo ochi&quot; (incident when seven Kugyo were expelled from Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Gon chunagon (Provisional vice-councilor) in 1858, and trusted, however, he was obliged to leave the capital to Choshu in a conspiracy by those who advocated kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate), and thereby became a man of so-called Shichikyo ochi (the exile of the Seven nobles from Kyoto) in 1863.</e>
<cmt>「権中納言、公武合体派」「七卿落ちの一人となる」を修正。年号を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後さらに太宰府まで走り、やがて王政復古の大号令によって赦され、帰京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, he escaped to Dazaifu and was granted amnesty by the command of restoration of imperial rule, and returned home to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, he escaped to Dazaifu and was granted amnesty by the command restorating imperial rule, and returned home to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, he escaped to Dazaifu (local government office in Kyushu region) and was granted amnesty by the Decree for the Restoration of Imperial Rule, and returned home to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>｢大宰府、王政復古」を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>明治維新後、大納言、参与、神宮祭主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji restoration, he was designated to Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Sanyo (councilor) and Jingu saishu (head priest of the Ise Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji restoration, he was designated to Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Sanyo (councilor) and Jingu saishu (head priest of the Ise Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji restoration, he was designated to Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Sanyo (councilor) and Jingu saishu (head priest of the Ise Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>三条西家の当主だけあって歌道の宗匠として知られ、西四辻公業（大坂府知事）とともに明治天皇の歌道師範としても有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was a family head of the Sanjonishi family, he was known as a master of tanka poetry, and it is also famous that he was an instructor of tanka poetry of the Emperor Meiji as well as Kiminari NISHIYOTSUTSUJI (Governor of Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was a family head of the Sanjonishi family, he was known as a master of tanka poetry, and it is also famous that he was an instructor of tanka poetry of the Emperor Meiji as well as Kiminari NISHIYOTSUTSUJI (Governor of Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was a family head of the Sanjonishi family, he was known as a master of waka poetry, and it is also famous that he was an instructor of waka poetry of the Emperor Meiji as well as Kiminari NISHIYOTSUTSUJI (Governor of Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「歌道」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>季知自身は高松公祐に師事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suetomo was taught tanka by Kinsachi TAKAMATSU himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suetomo was taught tanka by Kinsachi TAKAMATSU himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suetomo was taught waka by Kinsachi TAKAMATSU himself.</e>
<cmt>「歌道」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>