<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原経宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsunemune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tsunemune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsunemune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 経宗（ふじわら の つねむね、元永2年（1119年）-文治5年2月28日 (旧暦)(1189年3月16日)）は平安時代末期の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (1119 - March 16, 1189) was a noble who lived in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (1119 - March 16, 1189) was a noble who lived in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (1119 - March 23, 1189) was a noble who lived in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正、Heian periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大炊御門家創始者の藤原経実の4男（あるいは5男）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth (or fifth) son of FUJIWARA no Tsunezane who was the founder of the Oinomikado family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth (or fifth) son of FUJIWARA no Tsunezane who was the founder of the Oinomikado family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth (or fifth) son of FUJIWARA no Tsunezane who was the founder of the Oinomikado family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原公実の女・藤原公子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Kimiko who was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was FUJIWARA no Kimiko who was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Kimiko who was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>異母兄に藤原経定・光忠、同母姉に源懿子 (後白河天皇妃)、子に藤原頼実がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had elder brothers from different mother, FUJIWARA no Tsunesada and FUJIWARA no Mitsutada, and an elder sister from the same mother, MINAMOTO no Yoshiko (Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s consort) and a child, FUJIWARA no Yorizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had elder brothers from a different mother, FUJIWARA no Tsunesada and FUJIWARA no Mitsutada, and an elder sister from the same mother, MINAMOTO no Yoshiko (Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s consort) and a child, FUJIWARA no Yorizane.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had elder brothers from a different mother, FUJIWARA no Tsunesada and FUJIWARA no Mitsutada, and an elder sister from the same mother, MINAMOTO no Yoshiko (Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s consort) and a child, FUJIWARA no Yorizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>前半生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Half of His Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Half of His Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Half of His Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>保安 (元号)4年（1123年）に叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1123, he was ennobled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1123, he was ennobled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1123, he was ennobled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大治3年（1128年）に昇殿を果たしてから、右少将・左中将を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was admitted to the imperial court in 1129, he held positions of Ushosho/Ukone no Shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Sachujo/Sakone no Chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in succession. [http://www.albany.edu/eas/205/rank%20chart.htm]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was admitted to the imperial court in 1129, he held positions of Ushosho/Ukone no Shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Sachujo/Sakone no Chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in succession. [http://www.albany.edu/eas/205/rank%20chart.htm]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was admitted to the imperial court in 1129, he held positions of Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in succession.</e>
<cmt>Ushosho/Ukone no Shosho→Ushosho、およびSachujo/Sakone no Chujo→Sachujoのみとし、[http://www.albany.edu/eas/205/rank%20chart.htm] 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>母の公子は藤原璋子の姉妹であり、天承元年（1131年）に父が没した後は閑院流の庇護を受けていたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother, Kimiko, was a sister of FUJIWARA no Shoshi and, after his father died in 1131, it is inferred that he was protected by the Kaninryu (Kanin branch).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother, Kimiko, was a sister of FUJIWARA no Shoshi and, after his father died in 1131, it is inferred that he was protected by the Kaninryu (Kanin branch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother, Kimiko, was a sister of FUJIWARA no Shoshi and, after his father died in 1131, it is inferred that he was protected by the Kaninryu (Kanin branch).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>康治元年（1142年）、近衛天皇の蔵人頭に抜擢される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1142, he was chosen for Kurodo no To (Head Chamberlain) for the Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1142, he was chosen for Kurodo no To (Head Chamberlain) for the Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1142, he was chosen for Kurodo no To (Head Chamberlain) for the Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし崇徳天皇の退位と待賢門院の出家によって閑院流は勢力を衰退させ、経宗の昇進も停滞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the Emperor Sutoku&apos;s abdication and Taikenmonin&apos;s renouncing the world, however, the Kanin branch gradually lost its power and Tsunemune&apos;s promotion was also stagnated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the Emperor Sutoku&apos;s abdication and Taikenmonin&apos;s renouncing the world, however, the Kanin branch gradually lost its power and Tsunemune&apos;s promotion also stagnated.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the Emperor Sutoku&apos;s abdication and Taikenmonin&apos;s renouncing the world, however, the Kanin branch gradually lost its power and Tsunemune&apos;s promotion also stagnated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>久安5年（1149年）、大納言の三条実行と源雅定がそれぞれ右大臣・内大臣に昇進して、大納言以下に欠員が生じたことによる玉突き人事の結果、経宗は31歳でようやく参議となり公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1149, Saneyuki SANJO and MINAMOTO no Masasada, who were Dainagon (Major Counselor) were promoted to Udaijin (minister of the right) and Naidaijin (mister of the center) respectively, vacancies occurred in positions of Dainagon and lower, and, due to a series of linked personnel changes as a result of such vacancies, Tsunemune finally became Sangi (Royal Advisor) at the age of thirty-one and took rank with court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1149, Saneyuki SANJO and MINAMOTO no Masasada, who were Dainagon (Major Counselor) were promoted to Udaijin (minister of the right) and Naidaijin (mister of the center) respectively, vacancies occurred in positions of Dainagon and lower, and, due to a series of linked personnel changes as a result of such vacancies, Tsunemune finally became Sangi (Royal Advisor) at the age of thirty-one and took rank with court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1149, Saneyuki SANJO and MINAMOTO no Masasada, who were Dainagon (chief councilor of state) were promoted to Udaijin (minister of the right) and Naidaijin (mister of the center) respectively, vacancies occurred in positions of Dainagon and lower, and, due to a series of linked personnel changes as a result of such vacancies, Tsunemune finally became Sangi (Royal Advisor) at the age of thirty-one and took rank with court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Dainagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）7月に近衛天皇が崩御したことで、経宗に転機が訪れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1155, the Emperor Konoe passed away and, because of this, the turning point of Tsunemune&apos;s life arrived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1155, the Emperor Konoe passed away and, because of this, the turning point of Tsunemune&apos;s life arrived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1155, the Emperor Konoe passed away and, because of this, the turning point of Tsunemune&apos;s life arrived.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大方の予想を裏切って即位した雅仁親王（後の後白河天皇）は、経宗と従兄弟の関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Masahito (later Emperor Goshirakawa), who was enthroned quite differently from what every one had expected, was a cousin of Tsunemune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Masahito (later Emperor Goshirakawa), who was enthroned quite differently from what every one had expected, was a cousin of Tsunemune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Masahito (later Emperor Goshirakawa), who was enthroned quite differently from what every one had expected, was a cousin of Tsunemune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに姉の懿子（源有仁養女）が産んだ守仁親王（後の二条天皇）の立太子で春宮権大夫に任じられ、外戚として政治的地位を上昇させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, when the Imperial Prince Morihito (later, the Emperor Nijo), who was born from Tsunemune&apos;s elder sister, Yoshiko (MINAMOTO no Arihito&apos;s adopted daughter) was formally installed as Crown Prince, he was appointed to Togu Gon no Daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) and his political position was heightened as a maternal relative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, when the Imperial Prince Morihito (later, the Emperor Nijo), who was born from Tsunemune&apos;s elder sister, Yoshiko (MINAMOTO no Arihito&apos;s adopted daughter) was formally installed as Crown Prince, he was appointed to Togu Gon no Daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) and his political position was heightened as a maternal relative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, when the Imperial Prince Morihito (later, the Emperor Nijo), who was born from Tsunemune&apos;s elder sister, Yoshiko (MINAMOTO no Arihito&apos;s adopted daughter) was formally installed as Crown Prince, he was appointed to Togu Gon no Daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) and his political position was heightened as a maternal relative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>大夫の藤原宗能は70歳を過ぎて高齢のため、経宗が実際に春宮坊を取り仕切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As FUJIWARA no Muneyoshi, who was Daibu, was already old over seventy, Tsunemune actually managed all by himself for Togubo (Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As FUJIWARA no Muneyoshi, who was Daibu, was already old, being over seventy, Tsunemune actually managed the Togubo (Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) by himself.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As FUJIWARA no Muneyoshi, who was Daibu, was already old, being over seventy, Tsunemune actually managed the Togubo (Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>官位の昇進も目覚しく、保元元年（1156年）4月に権中納言、9月には正三位に叙せられ右衛門督を兼任、保元2年（1157年）には検非違使別当、保元3年（1158年）には従二位・権大納言となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His promotion in office and rank also remarkable and he assumed the position of Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) in April 1156, and he was ranked at Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and assumed the position of Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) in September and, in 1157, he assumed the position of Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and he was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Dainagon in 1158.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His promotion in office and rank was also remarkable and he assumed the position of Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) in April 1156, and was ranked Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and assumed the position of Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) in September and, in 1157, he assumed the position of Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and he was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Dainagon in 1158.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His promotion in office and rank was also remarkable and he assumed the position of Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) in May 1156, and was ranked Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and assumed the position of Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) in September and, in 1157, he assumed the position of Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and he was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Dainagon in 1158.</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagon→統一表記に修正グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この時期に経宗は保元の乱で知足院に幽閉された藤原忠実を訪ねて、政務の機微について教えを乞い、摂関への野心を育んだという（『愚管抄』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, Tsunemune visited FUJIWARA no Tadazane, who had been confined in Chisoku-in Temple because of Hogen Disturbance, and asked for guidance on fine points of political affairs and reportedly grew ambition for the position of regent and adviser to the Emperor (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, Tsunemune visited FUJIWARA no Tadazane, who had been confined in Chisoku-in Temple because of Hogen Disturbance, and asked for guidance on fine points of political affairs and reportedly grew ambition for the position of regent and adviser to the Emperor (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, Tsunemune visited FUJIWARA no Tadazane, who had been confined in Chisoku-in Temple because of Hogen War, and asked for guidance on fine points of political affairs and reportedly grew ambition for the position of regent and adviser to the Emperor (&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool)).</e>
<cmt>「保元の乱」→統一事項に基づき、Hogen Warに修正、『愚管抄』の補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>平治の乱から失脚まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Heiji Disturbance to Falldown</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Heiji Disturbance to Falldown</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Heiji War to Falldown</e>
<cmt>Heiji Disturbance→Heiji Warに修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>保元3年（1158年）8月に二条天皇が践祚すると、政界は後白河院政派と二条親政派に二分される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1158, the Emperor Nijo ascended the throne and the political arena was divided into two, one for the insei (cloister government) by Goshirakawa and the other for direct administration by the Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1158, the Emperor Nijo ascended the throne and the political arena was divided into two, one for the insei (cloister government) by Goshirakawa and the other for direct administration by the Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1158, the Emperor Nijo ascended the throne and the political arena was divided into two, one for the Insei (cloister government) by Goshirakawa and the other for direct administration by the Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>他の表記と合わせ、insei→Inseiとしました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>後白河の側近としては藤原信西が政務に辣腕を奮い、それに対抗して藤原信頼の台頭も著しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a close aide to Goshirakawa, FUJIWARA no Shinzei displayed his uncommon shrewdness in politics and, opposing to Shinzei, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori showed a remarkable rise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a close aide to Goshirakawa, FUJIWARA no Shinzei displayed his uncommon shrewdness in politics and, in contrast to Shinzei, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori showed a remarkable rise.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a close aide to Goshirakawa, FUJIWARA no Shinzei displayed his uncommon shrewdness in politics and, in contrast to Shinzei, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori showed a remarkable rise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>経宗は院政派には自らの割り込む余地はないと判断したらしく、藤原惟方とともに親政派としての立場を鮮明にしていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Tsunemune judged that there is no room for him to appear on the scene in the Insei group, and he gradually made clear his standpoint as direct administration group together with FUJIWARA no Korekata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Tsunemune judged that there is no room for him to appear on the scene in the Insei group, and he gradually made clear his standpoint as direct administration group together with FUJIWARA no Korekata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Tsunemune judged that there is no room for him to appear on the scene in the Insei group, and he gradually made clear his standpoint as direct administration group together with FUJIWARA no Korekata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>政治の実権を握る信西一門に対する反感は根強いものがあり、親政派の中心である経宗・惟方は、院政派の信頼・藤原成親・源師仲らとともに反信西派を形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a strong antipathy to Shinzei and his group that assumed real political power, and Tsunemune and Korekata, who were the core member of the direct administration group, formed an anti-Shinzei group together with Nobuyori and FUJIWARA no Narichika and MINAMOTO no Moronaka, who belonged to the Insei group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a strong antipathy to Shinzei and his group which had assumed real political power, and Tsunemune and Korekata, who were the core member of the direct administration group, formed an anti-Shinzei group together with Nobuyori and FUJIWARA no Narichika and MINAMOTO no Moronaka, who belonged to the Insei group.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a strong antipathy to Shinzei and his group which had assumed real political power, and Tsunemune and Korekata, who were the core member of the direct administration group, formed an anti-Shinzei group together with Nobuyori and FUJIWARA no Narichika and MINAMOTO no Moronaka, who belonged to the Insei group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>平治元年（1159年）12月9日、反信西派は三条殿を襲撃してクーデターを断行、信西を殺害して政権を奪取した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 9, 1159, the anti-Shinzei group effected a coup d&apos;état and attacked Sanjo-dono and got power by killing Shinzei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 9, 1159, the anti-Shinzei group effected a coup d&apos;état and attacked Sanjo-dono and got power by killing Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 26, 1160, the anti-Shinzei group effected a coup d&apos;etat and attacked Sanjo-dono and got power by killing Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>coup d&apos;état→coup d&apos;etatとしました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>勝利を治めた反信西派だったが、主導権は源義朝の武力を背景とした信頼ら院政派が握っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the anti-Shizei group won, the leadership was in the hand of the Insei group including Nobuyori which had MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s military power in the background.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the anti-Shizei group won, the leadership was in the hand of the Insei group including Nobuyori which had MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s military power in the background.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the anti-Shizei group won, the leadership was in the hand of the Insei group including Nobuyori which had MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s military power in the background.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>信西殺害に成功して院政派と組む必要がなくなった経宗・惟方は、密かに平清盛と内通して二条を内裏から六波羅に脱出させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they succeeded to kill Shinzei, Tsunemune and Korekata had no need to cooperate with the Insei group any more and, therefore, they were secretly contacted TAIRA no Kiyomori and let the Emperor Nijo escape from the dairi (Imperial Palace) to Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they succeeded in killing Shinzei, Tsunemune and Korekata had no need to cooperate with the Insei group any more and, therefore, they secretly contacted TAIRA no Kiyomori and let the Emperor Nijo escape from the dairi (Imperial Palace) to Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they succeeded in killing Shinzei, Tsunemune and Korekata had no need to cooperate with the Insei group any more and, therefore, they secretly contacted TAIRA no Kiyomori and let the Emperor Nijo escape from the dairi (Imperial Palace) to Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>反逆者となった信頼・義朝らは敗北し、院政派は壊滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori, Yoshitomo, etc., who became traitors, were defeated and the Insei group was annihilated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori, Yoshitomo, etc., who became traitors, were defeated and the Insei group was annihilated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori, Yoshitomo, etc., who became traitors, were defeated and the Insei group was annihilated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>翌永暦元年正月、経宗・惟方は「世ヲバ院ニ知ラセマイラセジ、内ノ御沙汰ニアルベシ（院に政治の実権は渡さない、天皇が政務を執るべきだ）」と称して、後白河が八条堀河にあった藤原顕長邸の桟敷で外を見物していたところに、材木の板を打ち付けて視界を遮るという嫌がらせを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1160, telling &quot;We should not transfer political power to the Retired Emperor. The Emperor should directly administer political affairs,&quot; Tsunemune and Korekata harassed Goshirakawa, when the latter was looking outside from a stand in the mansion of FUJIWARA no Akinaga located in Hachijo Horikawa, by covering with wooden plates to obstruct Goshirakawa&apos;s field of vision.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1160, saying &quot;We should not transfer political power to the Retired Emperor. The Emperor should directly administer political affairs,&quot; Tsunemune and Korekata harassed Goshirakawa, when the latter was looking outside from a stand in the mansion of FUJIWARA no Akinaga located in Hachijo Horikawa, by covering with wooden plates to obstruct Goshirakawa&apos;s field of vision.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1160, saying &apos;We should not transfer political power to the Retired Emperor; the Emperor should directly administer political affairs,&apos; Tsunemune and Korekata harassed Goshirakawa, when the latter was looking outside from a stand in the mansion of FUJIWARA no Akinaga located in Hachijo Horikawa, by covering with wooden plates to obstruct Goshirakawa&apos;s field of vision.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、シングルクォーテーションに変更、文中にピリオドがあるため一文になるよう修正グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>親政確立を目指す経宗・惟方だったが、信頼らとともに信西殺害の首謀者であったことは誰の目にも明らかであり、やがてその責任を追及されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tsunemune and Korekata aimed to establish direct administration by the emperor, it was obvious to everybody that, together with Nobuyori, etc., they were the ringleaders of killing of Shinzei and later they were blamed for their responsibility on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tsunemune and Korekata aimed to establish direct administration by the emperor, it was obvious to everybody that, together with Nobuyori, etc., they were the ringleaders of killing of Shinzei and later they were blamed for their responsibility in the matter.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tsunemune and Korekata aimed to establish direct administration by the emperor, it was obvious to everybody that, together with Nobuyori, etc., they were the ringleaders of killing of Shinzei and later they were blamed for their responsibility in the matter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>後白河に「ワガ世ニアリナシハコノ惟方、経宗ニアリ。コレヲ思フ程イマシメテマイラセヨ」と命じられた清盛は、2月20日に郎等を内裏に派遣して経宗・惟方を逮捕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa ordered Kiyomori as &quot;Whether or not I can have political power depends on Korekata and Tsunemune. Teach them a lesson as much as you can&quot; and, on February 20, Kiyomori sent vassals to dairi (Imperial Palace) and arrested Tsunemune and Korekata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa ordered Kiyomori as &quot;Whether or not I can have political power depends on Korekata and Tsunemune. Teach them a lesson as much as you can&quot; and, on February 20, Kiyomori sent vassals to dairi (Imperial Palace) and arrested Tsunemune and Korekata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa ordered Kiyomori as &apos;Whether or not I can have political power depends on Korekata and Tsunemune. Teach them a lesson as much as you can.&apos; and, on April 5, Kiyomori sent vassals to dairi (Imperial Palace) and arrested Tsunemune and Korekata.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオド追加グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>二人は後白河の面前に引き出されて拷問を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of them were taken before Goshirakawa and tortured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of them were taken before Goshirakawa and tortured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both of them were taken before Goshirakawa and tortured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>28日、経宗は惟方とともに解官され、3月11日に阿波国に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 28, Tsunemune was dismissed together with Korekata and, on March 11, he was exiled to AWA Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On 28, Tsunemune was dismissed together with Korekata and, on March 11, he was exiled to AWA Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On 13, Tsunemune was dismissed together with Korekata and, on April 26, he was exiled to AWA Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>復権と左大臣就任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reinstatement and Assumption of the Position of Sadaijin (minister of the left)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reinstatement and Assumption of the Position of Sadaijin (minister of the left)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reinstatement and Assumption of the Position of Sadaijin (minister of the left)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>応保元年（1161年）9月、憲仁（後白河の第七皇子、後の高倉天皇）親王立太子の陰謀が発覚したことで、後白河上皇の政治介入は停止されて二条天皇による親政が確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1161, as the plot to institute the Imperial Prince Norihito (the seventh Imperial Prince of Goshirakawa) to the Crown Prince was revealed, intervention to political affairs by the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa was suspended and direct administration by the Emperor Nijo was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1161, as the plot to institute the Imperial Prince Norihito (the seventh Imperial Prince of Goshirakawa) to the Crown Prince was revealed, intervention to political affairs by the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa was suspended and direct administration by the Emperor Nijo was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1161, as the plot to institute the Imperial Prince Norihito (the seventh Imperial Prince of Goshirakawa) to the Crown Prince was revealed, intervention to political affairs by the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa was suspended and direct administration by the Emperor Nijo was established.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>翌年に経宗は召還されるが、帰京後は失脚したことへの反省からか慎重に行動していたようで、しばらくは目立った活動を見せなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune was called back next year, but, it seems that he behaved carefully after his return to Kyoto based on self-examination of having been overthrown and he did not show significant activity awhile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune was called back next year, but, it seems that he behaved carefully after his return to Kyoto based on self-examination of having been overthrown and he did not show significant activity for awhile.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune was called back next year, but, it seems that he behaved carefully after his return to Kyoto based on self-examination of having been overthrown and he did not show significant activity for awhile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）正月に本位に復し、閏10月に正二位・右大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1164, he returned to the previous rank and, in intercalary tenth month, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) and assumed the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1164, he returned to the previous rank and, in the intercalary tenth month, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) and assumed the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1164, he returned to the previous rank and, in the intercalary tenth month, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) and assumed the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>阿波国に配流された身であったことから「阿波大臣」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he had once been exile to Awa Province, he was called &quot;Awa no Otodo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he had once been exiled to Awa Province, he was called &quot;Awa no Otodo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he had once been exiled to Awa Province, he was called &apos;Awa no Otodo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これを見た藤原伊通は、かつて吉備真備が右大臣の任にあったことを引き合いに、「黍（吉備）の大臣に続いて粟（阿波）の大臣が現れたのだから、いずれは稗の大臣も現れるだろう」と皮肉を飛ばして、大いに人々を笑わせたという（『平治物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing this, FUJIWARA no Koremichi made a sarcastic comment, based on the fact that KIBI no Makibi was Udaijin, &quot;Following Kibi no Otodo, we now have Awa no Otodo. Soon or later, we will also have Hie no Otodo (Kibi, Awa and Hie are Japanese names of cereals included in the gokoku (five representative cereals in Japan)&quot; and made people laughing. (&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing this, FUJIWARA no Koremichi made a sarcastic comment, based on the fact that KIBI no Makibi was Udaijin, &quot;Following Kibi no Otodo, we now have Awa no Otodo. Soon or later, we will also have Hie no Otodo (Kibi, Awa and Hie are Japanese names of cereals included in the gokoku (five representative cereals in Japan)&quot; and made people laugh. (&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing this, FUJIWARA no Koremichi made a sarcastic comment, based on the fact that KIBI no Makibi was Udaijin, &apos;Following Kibi no Otodo, we now have Awa no Otodo, and soon or later, we will also have Hie no Otodo (Kibi, Awa and Hie are Japanese names of cereals included in the gokoku - five representative cereals in Japan)&apos; and made people laugh (&quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>文中にピリオドがあるため一文になるよう修正、カッコ内を一部修正、余分なスペースを消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>太政大臣の伊通は高齢であり、左大臣・松殿基房、内大臣・九条兼実は若年のため、経宗が実質的に太政官を取りまとめる形となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Dajodaijin, Koremichi, was very old and Sadaijin, Motofusa MATSUDONO, and Naidaijin, Kanezane KUJO, were too young, Tsunemune actually managed all for Daijokan (Grand Council of State) by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Dajodaijin, Koremichi, was very old and Sadaijin, Motofusa MATSUDONO, and Naidaijin, Kanezane KUJO, were too young, Tsunemune actually managed all for Daijokan (Grand Council of State) by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Dajodaijin, Koremichi, was very old and Sadaijin, Motofusa MATSUDONO, and Naidaijin, Kanezane KUJO, were too young, Tsunemune actually managed all for Daijokan (Grand Council of State) by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>永万元年（1165年）7月、二条天皇が崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1165, the Emperor Nijo passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1165, the Emperor Nijo passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1165, the Emperor Nijo passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>後継の六条天皇は幼少であり、翌年の摂政・近衛基実死去により二条親政派は瓦解する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his successor, the Emperor Rokujo, was very young, the group of the direct administration by the Emperor Nijo was collapsed by the death of Motozane KONOE, who was Sessho (regent), next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his successor, the Emperor Rokujo, was very young, the group of the direct administration by the Emperor Nijo was collapsed by the death of Motozane KONOE, who was Sessho (regent), next year.</e>
<cmt>Robert: This doesn&apos;t make much sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his successor, the Emperor Rokujo was still very young, the political faction supporting Emperor Nijo was collapsed by the death of Sessho (regent), Motozane KONOE in the following year.</e>
<cmt>the group of the direct administration by the Emperor Nijo→the political faction supporting Emperor Nijoとし、意味が明確になるよう訳文を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>同年10月10日、後白河は清盛の協力により憲仁親王の立太子を実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 10 in the same year, Goshirakawa realized the official investiture of the Imperial Prince Norihito to the Crown Prince thanks to cooperation by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10 in the same year, Goshirakawa realized the official investiture of the Imperial Prince Norihito to the Crown Prince thanks to cooperation by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 10 in the same year, Goshirakawa realized the official investiture of the Imperial Prince Norihito to the Crown Prince thanks to cooperation by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>翌月、清盛は内大臣となり、経宗は左大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next month, Kiyomori became Naidaijin, and Tsunemune Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next month, Kiyomori became Naidaijin, and Tsunemune Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next month, Kiyomori became Naidaijin, and Tsunemune Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>経宗は後白河上皇に対して「太上天皇与正帝無差別」（『兵範記』嘉応元年（1169年）12月15日条）と表明して恭順の姿勢を示し、平氏に対しても平重盛の妻・藤原経子と重盛の子・平宗実を猶子とするなど親密な関係を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune showed a signal of allegiance to the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa saying &quot;There should be no difference between the retired emperor and the emperor&quot; (&quot;Heihanki&quot;(diary of TAIRA no Nobuyori) and, with the TAIRA clan, he established close connection, for example, by adopting TAIRA no Munezane, who was the son of TAIRA no Shigemori and his wife, FUJIWARA no Keishi.</e>
<cmt>「太上天皇与正帝無差別」の個所は正確な意味が確認できておらず、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune showed a signal of allegiance to the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa saying &quot;There should be no difference between the retired emperor and the emperor&quot; (&quot;Heihanki&quot;(diary of TAIRA no Nobuyori) and, with the TAIRA clan, he established a close connection, for example, by adopting TAIRA no Munezane, who was the son of TAIRA no Shigemori and his wife, FUJIWARA no Keishi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune showed a signal of allegiance to the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa saying &apos;There should be no difference between the retired emperor and the emperor&apos; (Article for December 15, 1169 in &quot;Heihanki&quot;(diary of TAIRA no Nobuyori)) and, with the Taira clan, he established a close connection, for example, by adopting TAIRA no Munezane, who was the son of TAIRA no Shigemori and his wife, FUJIWARA no Keishi.</e>
<cmt>「嘉応元年（1169年）12月15日条」を訳出、the TAIRA clan→the Taira clanに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>経宗は以後、院御所議定に精力的に出席して後白河上皇の諮問に答え、政務に不慣れな平氏一門に助言を与えることで、双方から確固たる信頼を獲得することに成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Tsunemune actively attended the conference in the In no Gosho (retired emperor&apos;s palace) and acquired trust from the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa and the Taira clan by providing advice and suggestions to the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s inquiries and offering advice to the Taira clan that was not accustomed to political affairs of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, Tsunemune actively attended the conference in the In no Gosho (retired emperor&apos;s palace) and acquired trust from the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa and the Taira clan by providing advice and suggestions to the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s inquiries and offering advice to the Taira clan which was not accustomed to political affairs of state.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, Tsunemune actively attended the conference in the In no Gosho (retired emperor&apos;s palace) and acquired trust from the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa and the Taira clan by providing advice and suggestions to the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s inquiries and offering advice to the Taira clan which was not accustomed to political affairs of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="43">
<j>治承2年（1178年）12月15日、高倉天皇の第一皇子・言仁親王（安徳天皇）が立太子すると、経宗は東宮傅（とうぐうのふ）に選ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 15, 1178, when the Imperial Prince Kotohito, who was the first prince of the Emperor Takakura, was instituted to the Crown Prince (the Emperor Antoku), Tsunemune was chosen for Togu no Fu (head tutor of the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 15, 1178, when the Imperial Prince Kotohito, who was the first prince of the Emperor Takakura, was instituted to the Crown Prince (the Emperor Antoku), Tsunemune was chosen for Togu no Fu (head tutor of the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 15, 1178, when the Imperial Prince Kotohito, who was the first prince of the Emperor Takakura, was instituted to the Crown Prince (the Emperor Antoku), Tsunemune was chosen for Togu no Fu (head tutor of the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これについて兼実は「面縛の人を傅に任ず、未曾有のこと」（『玉葉』）と激しく非難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against this, Kanezane strongly criticized saying &quot;It had never been experienced that any person who punished became a tutor&quot;, (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanezane strongly criticized this saying &quot;It had never been experienced that any person who punished became a tutor&quot;, (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO))</e>
<cmt>Robert: &quot;It had never been experienced that any person who punished became a tutor&quot;, is a bit strange.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanezane strongly criticized this saying &apos;It had never been experienced that any person who was punished became a tutor,&apos; (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO)).</e>
<cmt>who punished→who was punishedとし、シングルクオーテーションに変更、カンマの位置を移動、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>経宗の地位は、治承三年の政変で後白河院政が停止されても揺らぐことはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune&apos;s position was not influenced even when Insei (Cloister Government) was suspended by the political change in 1179.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune&apos;s position was not influenced even when Insei (Cloister Government) was suspended by the political change in 1179.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune&apos;s position was not influenced even when Goshirakawa Cloister Government was suspended by the Coup of the Third Year of Jisho.</e>
<cmt>「後白河院政」→Goshirakawa Cloister Government、「治承三年の政変」→Coup of the Third Year of Jishoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>ただし以仁王の挙兵における公卿議定では、親平氏派の藤原隆季・土御門通親による興福寺追討の主張に同調しなかったことから、完全に平氏に従属することはなかったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the conference of nobles when Mochihto-o (Prince Mochihito) raised an army, as Tsunemune did not agree to the opinion of FUJIWARA no Takasue and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, who were pro-Taira clan, to subjugate the Kofuku-ji Temple, it seems that Tsunemune was not completely subordinated by the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the conference of nobles when Mochihto-o (Prince Mochihito) raised an army, as Tsunemune did not agree to the opinion of FUJIWARA no Takasue and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, who were pro-Taira clan, to subjugate the Kofuku-ji Temple, it seems that Tsunemune was not completely subordinated by the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the conference of nobles when Prince Mochihito raised an army, as Tsunemune did not agree to the opinion of FUJIWARA no Takasue and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, who were pro-Taira clan, to subjugate the Kofuku-ji Temple, it seems that Tsunemune was not completely subordinated by the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>Mochihto-o (Prince Mochihito)→Prince Mochihitoのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="47">
<j>院殿上除目の強行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forceful Execution of Jimoku (appointment ceremony) in the In&apos;s Palace (Retired Emperor&apos;s Palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forceful Execution of Jimoku (appointment ceremony) in the In&apos;s Palace (Retired Emperor&apos;s Palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forceful Execution of Jimoku (appointment ceremony) in the In&apos;s Palace (Retired Emperor&apos;s Palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）7月25日、平氏一門が都落ちする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 25, 1183, the Taira clan fled from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 25, 1183, the Taira clan fled from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 25, 1183, the Taira clan fled from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>7月30日の議定で経宗は、後白河の意を受けて院殿上での除目を主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the conference on July 30, Tsunemune insisted to execute Jimoku in In&apos;s palace in accordance with Goshirakawa&apos;s intension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the conference on July 30, Tsunemune insisted to execute Jimoku in In&apos;s palace in accordance with Goshirakawa&apos;s intension.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the conference on July 30, Tsunemune insisted to execute Jimoku in In&apos;s palace in accordance with Goshirakawa&apos;s intension.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>これに対して兼実は、宣旨をなし官符を請印するのは天皇の権限に属するとして強く反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanezane strongly opposed to this insisting that the authority to issue Senji (imperial decree) and stamp Kanpu (official notice from Daijokan) was solely given to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanezane strongly opposed to this insisting that the authority to issue Senji (imperial decree) and stamp Kanpu (official notice from Daijokan) was solely given to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanezane strongly opposed to this insisting that the authority to issue Senji (imperial decree) and stamp Kanpu (official notice from Daijokan) was solely given to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>経宗も「希代の権儀」であることは認めたが、他に方法のないことを理由に執拗に食い下がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune also acknowledged that those were &quot;exclusive rights and obligations,&quot; but he still insisted persistently for the reason that there was no other way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune also acknowledged that those were &quot;exclusive rights and obligations,&quot; but he still insisted persistently for the reason that there was no other way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune also acknowledged that those were &apos;exclusive rights and obligations,&apos; but he still insisted persistently for the reason that there was no other way.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>結局、外記の清原頼業らの「内示だけにとどめて、最終決定は新天皇が即位してから除目で行うべきだ」という意見が賛同を集めたことで、経宗もやむを得ず発言を撤回した（『玉葉』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, opinion of KIYOHARA no Yorinari, who was Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State) &quot;Decision should be limited to preliminary showing and final decision shall be made by Jimoku after enthronement of the new emperor&quot; met with many members&apos; approval, and the Tsunemune unwillingly withdrew his proposal. (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, KIYOHARA no Yorinari, who was Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State) opined that the &quot;Decision should be limited to preliminary showing and the final decision shall be made by Jimoku after enthronement of the new emperor&quot; which was met with approval by many members, and Tsunemune unwillingly withdrew his proposal. (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, KIYOHARA no Yorinari, who was Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State) opined that the &apos;Decision should be limited to preliminary showing and the final decision shall be made by Jimoku after enthronement of the new emperor&apos; which was met with approval by many members, and Tsunemune unwillingly withdrew his proposal (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース、ピリオド消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="53">
<j>ところが8月10日、経宗は院殿上除目を行うことを奏請し、後白河も同意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 10, however, Tsunemune petitioned to carry out Jimoku in In&apos;s palace and Goshirakawa agreed to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 10, however, Tsunemune petitioned to carry out Jimoku in In&apos;s palace and Goshirakawa agreed to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 10, however, Tsunemune petitioned to carry out Jimoku in In&apos;s palace and Goshirakawa agreed to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>内大臣・徳大寺実定は先の議定での決定を踏みにじる経宗の行動に憤り、後白河に反対意見を奏上しようとするが、兼実は「異議なし」と屈服した（『玉葉』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesada TOKDAIJI, who was Naidaijin, was angry about Tsunemune&apos;s act that trampled on the decision in the previous conference and tried to petition to Goshirakawa with opposing opinion but Kanezane gave up by replying &quot;No objection &quot;(Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesada TOKDAIJI, who was Naidaijin, was angry about Tsunemune&apos;s act, as it had trampled on the decision in the previous conference and tried to petition Goshirakawa to oppose the opinion but Kanezane gave up by replying &quot;No objection &quot;(Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesada TOKUDAIJI, who was Naidaijin, was angry about Tsunemune&apos;s act, as it had trampled on the decision in the previous conference and tried to petition Goshirakawa to oppose the opinion but Kanezane gave up by replying &apos;No objection&apos; (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Sanesada TOKDAIJI→Sanesada TOKUDAIJIに修正、一部シングルクォーテーションに変更、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>16日、後白河の主宰の下に除目が行われた結果、平氏一門が占めていた総計30ヶ国の国司には木曽義仲・源行家らを除いて、ほとんど院近臣が任じられることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 16, as a result of Jimoku that was presided by Goshirakawa, close vassals of the Retired Emperor occupied almost all of the positions of Kokushi (provincial governor) of thirty provinces in total that were occupied by members of the Taira clan with few exceptions including Yoshinaka KISO and MINAMOTO no Yukiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 16, as a result of Jimoku that was presided by Goshirakawa, close vassals of the Retired Emperor occupied almost all of the positions of Kokushi (provincial governor) of thirty provinces in total that were occupied by members of the Taira clan with few exceptions including Yoshinaka KISO and MINAMOTO no Yukiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 16, as a result of Jimoku that was presided by Goshirakawa, close vassals of the Retired Emperor occupied almost all of the positions of Kokushi (provincial governor) of thirty provinces in total that were occupied by members of the Taira clan with few exceptions including Yoshinaka KISO and MINAMOTO no Yukiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>この強引かつ露骨な人事を、兼実は「任人の体、殆ど物狂と謂ふべし。悲しむべし、悲しむべし」と記している（『玉葉』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to this willful and coarse personnel change, Kanazane recorded as &quot;We have to say this personnel appointment is crazy. It is a pity.&quot; (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to this willful and coarse personnel change, Kanazane was recorded as saying &quot;We have to say this personnel appointment is crazy. It is a pity.&quot; (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to this willful and coarse personnel change, Kanazane was recorded as saying &apos;We have to say this personnel appointment is crazy. It is a pity.&apos; (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="57">
<j>後白河は経宗の協力により政治の主導権を確立すると、後継天皇の選定に取り掛かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After securing political initiative thanks to cooperation by Tsunemune, Godaigo began selecting new emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After securing political initiative thanks to cooperation by Tsunemune, Godaigo began selecting a new emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After securing political initiative thanks to cooperation by Tsunemune, Goshirakawa began selecting a new emperor.</e>
<cmt>Godaigo→Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>20日、三宮（高倉の第三皇子・惟明親王）や義仲の推す北陸宮を退けて、丹後局（高階栄子）の夢想に現れた四宮（高倉の第四皇子・尊成親王、後鳥羽天皇）を践祚させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 20, Godaigo rejected Sannomiya (Takakura&apos;s third Imperial Prince Koreaki) and Hokuroku no miya, who was supported by YOshinaka, and enthroned Shinomiya (Takakura&apos;s fourth Imperial Prince Takahira; the Emperor Gotoba), who appeared in a dream of Tango no Tsubone (TAKASHINA no Eishi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 20, Godaigo rejected Sannomiya (Takakura&apos;s third Imperial Prince Koreaki) and Hokuroku no miya, who was supported by YOshinaka, and enthroned Shinomiya (Takakura&apos;s fourth Imperial Prince Takahira; the Emperor Gotoba), who appeared in a dream of Tango no Tsubone (TAKASHINA no Eishi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 20, Goshirakawa rejected Sannomiya (Takakura&apos;s third Imperial Prince Koreaki) and Hokuroku no miya, who was supported by Yoshinaka, and enthroned Shinomiya (Takakura&apos;s fourth Imperial Prince Takahira; the Emperor Gotoba), who appeared in a dream of Tango no Tsubone (TAKASHINA no Eishi).</e>
<cmt>Godaigo→Goshirakawa、YOshinaka→Yoshinakaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>神鏡も剣璽もない異例の践祚だったが、経宗は践祚次第を作成して実現のために尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was quite unusual Senso (accession to the throne) without divine mirror (sacred mirror which is one of the three sacred treasures) and sacred sword and jewels, Tsunemune prepared agenda for Senso and made efforts to materialize it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was quite unusual Senso (accession to the throne) without divine mirror (sacred mirror which is one of the three sacred treasures) and sacred sword and jewels, Tsunemune prepared agenda for Senso and made efforts to materialize it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was quite unusual Senso (accession to the throne) without divine mirror (sacred mirror which is one of the three sacred treasures) and sacred sword and jewels, Tsunemune prepared agenda for Senso and made efforts to materialize it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="60">
<j>朝の宿老、国の重臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Experienced Vassal of the Imperial Court and Key Vassal for the State</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Experienced Vassal of the Imperial Court and Key Vassal for the State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Experienced Vassal of the Imperial Court and Key Vassal for the State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>右大臣でありながら朝廷にほとんど出仕しなくなった兼実に対して、経宗は「朝の宿老」「国の重臣」（『玉葉』元暦元年（1184年）8月18日条）として後白河法皇を補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contract to Kanezane, who was Udaijin but did no attend the imperial court so often, Tsunemune supported the Cloistered Emperor as the experienced vassal of the Imperial Court and key vassal for the state (Article for August 18 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contract to Kanezane, who was Udaijin but did no attend the imperial court so often, Tsunemune supported the Cloistered Emperor as an experienced vassal of the Imperial Court and key vassal for the state (Article for August 18 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contract to Kanezane, who was Udaijin but did no attend the imperial court so often, Tsunemune supported the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa as an experienced vassal of the Imperial Court and key vassal for the state (Article for August 18, 1184 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「1184年」を訳出、原文の「後白河法皇」に合わせ、the Cloistered Emperor→the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>平氏滅亡後の文治元年（1185年）10月13日、源義経が頼朝追討の宣旨を下すように要請する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the downfall of the Taira clan, on October 13, 1185, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune petitioned for issuance of senji to subjugate Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the downfall of the Taira clan, on October 13, 1185, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune petitioned for that senji be issued in order to subjugate Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the downfall of the Taira clan, on October 13, 1185, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune petitioned for that Senji be issued in order to subjugate Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>前出の表記に合わせ、senji→Senjiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>躊躇する後白河に、経宗は「当時在京の武士、只義経一人なり。彼の申状に乖かれ若し大事出来の時、誰人敵対すべけんや。然らば申請に任せて沙汰あるべきなり」と進言し、頼朝の追討宣旨の上卿を勤めた（『玉葉』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Goshirakawa hesitated, Tsunemune proposed to issue it saying &quot;At present, Yoshitsune is the only one military commander in Kyoto. If You oppose to his proposal and he rebels, who can fight back? Therefore, you should issue senji as requested.&quot; and chaired the ceremony for the senji to subjugate Yoritomo (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Goshirakawa hesitated, Tsunemune proposed senji saying &quot;At present, Yoshitsune is the only one military commander in Kyoto. If you oppose his proposal and he rebels, who can fight back? Therefore, you should issue senji as requested.&quot; and chaired the ceremony for the senji to subjugate Yoritomo (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Goshirakawa hesitated, Tsunemune proposed senji saying &apos;At present, Yoshitsune is the only one military commander in Kyoto. If you oppose his proposal and he rebels, who can fight back? Therefore, you should issue senji as requested.&apos; and chaired the ceremony for the senji to subjugate Yoritomo (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="64">
<j>この行動が義経没落後に問題となり、頼朝の要求で設置された議奏公卿からは除かれることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the downfall of Yoshitsune, this action was deemed problematic and Tsunemune was excluded from Gijo Kugyo (Noble Council) that was established by Yoritomo&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the downfall of Yoshitsune, this action was deemed problematic and Tsunemune was excluded from Gijo Kugyo (Noble Council) that was established by Yoritomo&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the downfall of Yoshitsune, this action was deemed problematic and Tsunemune was excluded from Gijo Kugyo (Noble Council) that was established by Yoritomo&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>義経に同意したことで高階泰経・平親宗ら12名が解官されるが、経宗は追及されることはなく左大臣の地位にとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twelve nobles including TAKASHINA no Yasutsune and TAIRA no Chikamune were dismissed by reason of having agreed to Yoshitsune, but Tsunemune was not accused and remained in the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twelve nobles including TAKASHINA no Yasutsune and TAIRA no Chikamune were dismissed by reason of having agreed to Yoshitsune, but Tsunemune was not accused and remained in the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twelve nobles including TAKASHINA no Yasutsune and TAIRA no Chikamune were dismissed by reason of having agreed to Yoshitsune, but Tsunemune was not accused and remained in the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>文治5年（1189年）2月13日、病により官職を辞職し出家（法名は法性覚）、同月28日に薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 13, 1189, he resigned from official posts because of his illness and became a priest (Buddhist name was Hosshogaku(法性覚) [読み不明]) and he died on February 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 13, 1189, he resigned from official posts because of his illness and became a priest (Buddhist name was Hosshogaku(法性覚) [読み不明]) and he died on February 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 13, 1189, he resigned from official posts because of his illness and became a priest (Buddhist name was Hosshogaku(法性覚)) and he died on February 28.</e>
<cmt>Hosshogaku(法性覚) [読み不明]→Hosshogaku(法性覚)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>享年71。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was seventy-one years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was seventy-one years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was seventy-one years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>和歌にも通じていて『千載』『新勅撰集』などにも入集しており、また日記に『高門記』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also good at waka (=tanka; a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and his waka was chosen for &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot;/&quot;Senzaishu&quot;(7th imperial anthology) and &quot;Shinchokusen Wakashu&quot;/&quot;Shinchokusenshu&quot; (9th imperial anthology) and he left his diary &quot;Komonki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also good at waka (=tanka; a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and his waka was chosen for &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot;/&quot;Senzaishu&quot;(7th imperial anthology) and &quot;Shinchokusen Wakashu&quot;/&quot;Shinchokusenshu&quot; (9th imperial anthology) and he left his diary &quot;Komonki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also good at waka (=tanka; a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and his waka was chosen for &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot; (7th imperial anthology) and &quot;Shinchokusen Wakashu&quot; (9th imperial anthology) and he left his diary &quot;Komonki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>『千載』『新勅撰集』→ウェブ上で確認したところ、『千載和歌集』『新勅撰和歌集』となっていたため、&quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot;&quot;Shinchokusen Wakashu&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>法体の木像が京都市西方寺に所在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wooden statue in the appearance of a priest exists in Saiho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wooden statue in the appearance of a priest exists in Saiho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wooden statue in the appearance of a priest exists in Saiho-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>in Kyoto→in Kyoto Cityに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="70">
<j>経宗は二条天皇、平氏、後白河法皇と権力者の下を渡り歩いた印象が強いが、それが可能だったのも「公事ヨクツトメテ職者ガラモアリヌベカリケレバ（朝廷の政務をよくこなし、故実にも通じていた）」（『愚管抄』）という自らの能力に負うところが大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune gives a impression of a person who switched over among influential persons such as the Emperor Nijo, the Taira clan and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, but it was possible by his capability as commented &quot;&quot; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune gives off the impression of a person who switched between influential persons such as the Emperor Nijo, the Taira clan and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, which was made possible by his capability, referred to as his &quot;Gukansho&quot; nature.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune gives off the impression of a person who switched between influential persons such as the Emperor Nijo, the Taira clan and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, which was made possible by his capability, commented as &apos;He handled political affairs in the Imperial court well and had a thorough knowledge of ancient practices&apos; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「公事ヨクツトメテ職者ガラモアリヌベカリケレバ（朝廷の政務をよくこなし、故実にも通じていた）」→訳抜けのため訳出し、原文の内容に沿うよう訳文を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>一度は対立した清盛や後白河に重用されて、「左大臣一ノ上ニテ多年職者ニモチヰラレテゾ候ケル」（『愚管抄』）とあるように動乱の中で24年間も左大臣の地位にあり続けたことからも、その存在が無視できないものだったことがうかがわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the fact that even Kiyomori and Goshirakawa, with whom Tsunemune once confronted, gave him important positions and he stayed in the position of Sadaijin for twenty-four years in the disturbance as commented &quot;He was used by influential persons as Sadaijin for many years&quot; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;), we can infer that his existence could not be ignored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the fact that even Kiyomori and Goshirakawa, who were both once confronted by Tsunemune, gave him important positions and he stayed in the position of Sadaijin for twenty-four years even admist the disturbance, and was commented as &quot;He was used by influential persons as Sadaijin for many years&quot; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;), we can infer that his existence could not be ignored.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the fact that even Kiyomori and Goshirakawa, who were both once confronted by Tsunemune, gave him important positions and he stayed in the position of Sadaijin for twenty-four years even admist the disturbance, and was commented as &apos;He was used by influential persons as Sadaijin for many years&apos; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;), we can infer that his existence could not be ignored.</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="72">
<j>経宗は、永暦元年（1160年）正月から配流される翌月まで越後国を知行していたが、召還後の仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）正月から承安 (日本)元年（1171年）4月まで備中国を、承安元年から文治5年（1189年）に没するまで土佐国を知行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From January 1160 to the next month of his exile, Tsunemune was enfiefed Echigo Province and, after he called back, from January 1166 to April 1171, Bicchu Province and from 1171 until he died in 1189 Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From January 1160 to the next month of his exile, Tsunemune was enfiefed in Echigo Province and, after he was called back, from January 1166 to April 1171, he was enfiefed in Bicchu Province from 1171 until he died in 1189 in Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From January 1160 to the next month of his exile, Tsunemune was enfiefed in Echigo Province and, after he was called back, he was enfiefed in Bitchu Province from January 1166 to April 1171, and in Tosa Province from 1171 until he died in 1189.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu Province→Bitchu Province煮修正、および原文の意味が明確になるよう訳文を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>この土佐の所領がそのまま嫡子・頼実に相伝された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fief in Tosa was inherited by his heir Yorizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fief in Tosa was inherited by his heir Yorizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fief in Tosa was inherited by his heir Yorizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>頼実は太政大臣に昇進し、後世において大炊御門家は、清華家として安定した地位を確保することに成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorizane was promoted to Daijodaijin and, later, the Oimikado family succeeded to secure a stable postiion as Seigake (second rank of noble family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorizane was promoted to Daijodaijin and, later, the Oimikado family succeeded to secure a stable postiion as Seigake (second rank of noble family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorizane was promoted to Daijodaijin and, later, the Oinomikado family succeeded to secure a stable postiion as Seigake (second rank of noble family).</e>
<cmt>前出の表記に合わせ、the Oinomikado familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Career as an Official</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Career as an Official</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Career as an Official</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lunar calendar used for the dates</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lunar calendar used for the dates</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lunar calendar used for the dates</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>保安 (元号)4年（1123年）（5歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1123 (Five years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1123 (Five years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1123 (Five years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>2月19日従五位下（中宮・藤原璋子御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19, given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)(Given through FUJIWARA no Shoshi, who was Chugu (empress))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 19, given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)(Given through FUJIWARA no Shoshi, who was Chugu (empress))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19: Given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) (Given through FUJIWARA no Shoshi, who was Chugu (empress)).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、スペース追加、他の表記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>大治3年（1128年）（10歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1128 (Ten years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1128 (Ten years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1128 (Ten years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>正月24日左兵衛佐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 24, assumed the position of Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 24, assumed the position of Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 24: Assumed the position of Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、他の表記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>12月20日昇殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 20, admitted to the court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 20, admitted to the court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 20: Admitted to the court.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>大治5年（1130年）（12歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1130 (Twelve years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1130 (Twelve years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1130 (Twelve years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>正月5日従五位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, given the rank of Shogoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, given the rank of Shogoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: Given the rank of Shogoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="83">
<j>大治6年のち改元して天承元年（1131年）（13歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1131 (Fourteen years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1131 (Fourteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1131 (Fourteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>12月24日右少将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 24, assumed the position of Ushosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 24, assumed the position of Ushosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 24: Assumed the position of Ushosho.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="85">
<j>天承2年のち改元して長承元年（1132年）（14歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1132 (Fourteen years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1132 (Fourteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1132 (Fourteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>正月22日備中介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed the position of Bitchu no Suke (Assistant Governor of Bitchu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He assumed the position of Bitchu no Suke (Assistant Governor of Bitchu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 22: He assumed the position of Bitchu no Suke (Assistant Governor of Bitchu Province).</e>
<cmt>「正月22日」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="87">
<j>長承2年（1133年）（15歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1133 (Fifteen years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1133 (Fifteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1133 (Fifteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>正月2日正五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 2, given the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 2, given the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 2: Given the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、他の表記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>4月禁色勅許</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April, permitted by imperial permission to use kinjiki (literally, &quot;forbidden colors&quot;, seven colors traditionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April, permitted by imperial permission to use kinjiki (literally, &quot;forbidden colors&quot;, seven colors traditionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April: Permitted by imperial permission to use kinjiki (literally, &quot;forbidden colors&quot;, seven colors traditionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="90">
<j>長承4年のち改元して保延元年（1135年）（17歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1135 (Seventeen years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1135 (Seventeen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1135 (Seventeen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>正月5日従四位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, given the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, given the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: Given the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="92">
<j>保延3年（1137年）（19歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1137 (Nineteen years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1137 (Nineteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1137 (Nineteen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>正月5日従四位上（鳥羽上皇御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, given the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)(given through the Retired Emperor Toba).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, given the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)(given through the Retired Emperor Toba).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: Given the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) (given through the Retired Emperor Toba).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>正月20日美作介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 20, assumed the position of Mimasaka no Suke (Assistant Governor of Mimasaka Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 20, assumed the position of Mimasaka no Suke (Assistant Governor of Mimasaka Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 20: Assumed the position of Mimasaka no Suke (Assistant Governor of Mimasaka Province).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、他の表記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>9月25日正四位下（法金剛院行幸の賞）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 25, given the rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)(as an award in relation with Imperial visit to Hokongo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 25, given the rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)(as an award in relation with Imperial visit to Hokongo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 25: Given the rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) (as an award in relation with Imperial visit to Hokongo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="96">
<j>保延4年（1138年）（20歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1138 (Twenty years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1138 (Twenty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1138 (Twenty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>11月17日左中将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 17, assumed the position of Sachujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 17, assumed the position of Sachujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 17: Assumed the position of Sachujo.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="98">
<j>保延7年のち改元して永治元年（1141年）（23歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1141 (Twenty-three years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1141 (Twenty-three years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1141 (Twenty-three years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>12月7日新帝（近衛天皇）昇殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 7, permitted to enter the court by the new emperor (the Emperor Konoe)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 7, permitted to enter the court by the new emperor (the Emperor Konoe)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 7: Permitted to enter the court by the new emperor (the Emperor Konoe).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、他の表記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="100">
<j>永治2年のち改元して康治元年（1142年）（24歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1142 (Twenty-four years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1142 (Twenty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1142 (Twenty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>正月7日蔵人頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 23, assumed the position of Kurodo no To.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 23, assumed the position of Kurodo no To.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 7: Assumed the position of Kurodo no To.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、January 23→January 7に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>正月23日備前権介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 23, assumed the position of Bizen no Gon no Suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 23, assumed the position of Bizen no Gon no Suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 23: Assumed the position of Bizen no Gon no Suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="103">
<j>久安3年（1147年）（29歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1147 (Twenty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1147 (Twenty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1147 (Twenty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>正月28日播磨介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 28, assumed the position of Harima no Suke (Assistant Governor of Harima Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 28, assumed the position of Harima no Suke (Assistant Governor of Harima Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 28: Assumed the position of Harima no Suke (Assistant Governor of Harima Province).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="105">
<j>久安5年（1149年）（31歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1149 (Twenty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1149 (Twenty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1149 (Twenty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>7月28日参議に補任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 28, assumed the position of Sangi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 28, assumed the position of Sangi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 28: Assumed the position of Sangi.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>8月2日左中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 2, the position of Sachujo remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 2, the position of Sachujo remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 2: Retained his position as Sachujo.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「如元」→統一表記に基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="108">
<j>久安6年（1150年）（32歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1150 (Thirty-two years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1150 (Thirty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1150 (Thirty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>正月29日備中権守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 29, assumed the position of Bitchu no Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Bitchu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 29, assumed the position of Bitchu no Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Bitchu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 29: Assumed the position of Bitchu no Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Bitchu Province).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="110">
<j>仁平2年（1152年）（34歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1152 (Thirty-four years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1152 (Thirty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1152 (Thirty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>3月8日従三位（鳥羽法皇50歳の賀。美福門院別当）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 8, given the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)(Ceremony for the age of fifty of the Cloistered Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 8, given the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)(Ceremony for the age of fifty of the Cloistered Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 8: Given the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)(Ceremony for the age of fifty of the Cloistered Emperor Toba. Assumed the position of an attendant to Bifukumonin.)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>美福門院別当）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assumed the position of an attendant to Bifukumonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assumed the position of an attendant to Bifukumonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assumed the position of an attendant to Bifukumonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="113">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）（37歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1155 (Thirty-seven years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1155 (Thirty-seven years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1155 (Thirty-seven years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>正月28日讃岐権守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 28, assumed the position of Sanuki no Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Sanuki Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 28, assumed the position of Sanuki no Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Sanuki Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 28: Assumed the position of Sanuki no Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、他の表記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>9月23日春宮権大夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 23, Togu Gon no Daibu (acting chief secretary to the Crown Prince)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 23, Togu Gon no Daibu (acting chief secretary to the Crown Prince)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 23: Togu Gon no Daibu (acting chief secretary to the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、他の表記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="116">
<j>久寿3年のち改元して保元元年（1156年）（38歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1156 (Thirty-eight years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1156 (Thirty-eight years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1156 (Thirty-eight years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>4月6日権中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 6, Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 6, Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 6: Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>9月17日右衛門督兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 17, assumed also the position of Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 17, assumed also the position of Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 17: Assumed also the position of Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>正三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="120">
<j>保元2年（1157年）（39歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1157 (Thirty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1157 (Thirty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1157 (Thirty-nine years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>4月2日検非違使別当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 2, assumed the position of Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 2, assumed the position of Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 2: Assumed the position of Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>8月19日中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 19, assumed the position of Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 19, assumed the position of Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 19: Assumed the position of Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="123">
<j>保元3年（1158年）（40歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1158 (Forty years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1158 (Forty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1158 (Forty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>正月10日従二位（美福門院行幸の賞。春宮御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 10, given the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) (as an award in relation with the imperial visit by Bifukumonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 10, given the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) (as an award in relation with the imperial visit by Bifukumonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 10: Given the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) (as an award in relation with the imperial visit by Bifukumonin. Given through Togu (the Crown Prince)).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>春宮御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given through Togu (the Crown Prince).)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given through Togu (the Crown Prince).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given through Togu (the Crown Prince).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="126">
<j>2月21日権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 21, assumed the position of Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 21, assumed the position of Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 21: Assumed the position of Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>春宮権大夫如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Position of Togu Gon no Daibu remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Position of Togu Gon no Daibu remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Togu Gon no Daibu.</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一表記に基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="128">
<j>8月11日春宮権大夫辞任（二条天皇践祚）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 11, resigned from the position of Togu Gon no Daibu (enthronement of the Emperor Nijo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 11, resigned from the position of Togu Gon no Daibu (enthronement of the Emperor Nijo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 11: Resigned from the position of Togu Gon no Daibu (enthronement of the Emperor Nijo).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>12月17日正二位（即位叙位）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 17, given the rank of Shonii (giving rank related to enthronement)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 17, given the rank of Shonii (giving rank related to enthronement)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17: Given the rank of Shonii (giving rank related to enthronement).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="130">
<j>平治2年のち改元して永暦元年（1160年）（42歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1160 (Forty-two years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1160 (Forty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1160 (Forty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>2月28日解官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 28, dismissed from official positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 28, dismissed from official positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 28: Dismissed from official positions.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>3月11日阿波国に配流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 11, exiled to Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 11, exiled to Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 11: Exiled to Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="133">
<j>応保2年（1162年）（44歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1162 (Forty-four years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1162 (Forty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1162 (Forty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>3月7日召還</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 7, called back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 7, called back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 7: Called back.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="135">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）（46歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1164 (Fourth-six years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1164 (Fourth-six years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1164 (Fourth-six years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>正月21日正二位に復す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 21, returned to Shonii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 21, returned to Shonii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 21: Returned to Shonii.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>権大納言に還任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reappointed to Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reappointed to Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reappointed to Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="138">
<j>2月18日帯剣を許される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 18, permitted to carry a sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 18, permitted to carry a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 18: Permitted to carry a sword.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>閏10月23日右大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">twenty-third day of the Intercalary tenth month, assumed the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">twenty-third day of the Intercalary tenth month, assumed the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leap month October 23: Assumed the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>「閏10月23日」→他の日付表記に合わせ修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="140">
<j>永万2年のち改元して仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）（48歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1166 (Forty-eight years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1166 (Forty-eight years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1166 (Forty-eight years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>10月21日左大将兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 21, he assumed the position of Sadaisho/Sakone no Daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 21, he assumed the position of Sadaisho/Sakone no Daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 21: He assumed the position of Sadaisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Sadaisho/Sakone no Daisho→Sadaishoのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>11月11日左大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 11, he assumed the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 11, he assumed the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 11: He assumed the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>11月13日左大将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 13, the position of Sadaisho remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 13, the position of Sadaisho remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 13: Retained his position as Sadaisho.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「如元」→統一表記に基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>11月25日左馬寮御監</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 25, he assumed the position of Sameryo no Gogen (inspector of the left imperial stables).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 25, he assumed the position of Sameryo no Gogen (inspector of the left imperial stables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 25: He assumed the position of Sameryo no Gogen (inspector of the left imperial stables).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="145">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）（50歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1168 (Fifty years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1168 (Fifty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1168 (Fifty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>8月9日左大将辞任（病のため）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 9, he resigned from Sadaisho (because of his illness).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 9, he resigned from Sadaisho (because of his illness).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 9: He resigned from Sadaisho (because of his illness).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="147">
<j>承安 (日本)4年（1174年）（56歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1174 (Fifty-six years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1174 (Fifty-six years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1174 (Fifty-six years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>正月7日従一位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 7, given the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 7, given the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 7: Given the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="149">
<j>治承2年（1178年）（60歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1178 (Sixty years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1178 (Sixty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1178 (Sixty years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>12月15日東宮傅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 15, assumed the position of Togu no Fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 15, assumed the position of Togu no Fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 15: Assumed the position of Togu no Fu.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="151">
<j>治承4年（1180年）（62歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1180 (Sixty-two years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1180 (Sixty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1180 (Sixty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>2月21日東宮傅を辞任（安徳天皇践祚）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 21, resigned from the position of Togu no Fu (enthronement of the Emperor Antoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 21, resigned from the position of Togu no Fu (enthronement of the Emperor Antoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 21: Resigned from the position of Togu no Fu (enthronement of the Emperor Antoku).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="153">
<j>養和2年のち改元して寿永元年（1182年）（64歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1182 (Sixty-four years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1182 (Sixty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1182 (Sixty-four years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>11月23日輦車宣旨（てぐるまのせんじ）を賜る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 23, given a teguruma no senji (special permission from the Emperor to enter the imperial palace in a hand cart)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 23, given a teguruma no senji (special permission from the Emperor to enter the imperial palace in a hand cart)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 23: Given a teguruma no senji (special permission from the Emperor to enter the imperial palace in a hand cart).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>11月25日牛車宣旨（ぎっしゃのせんじ）を賜る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 25, given a gissha no senji (special permission to from the Emperor to enter the imperial palace in an ox-drawn cart)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 25, given a gissha no senji (special permission to from the Emperor to enter the imperial palace in an ox-drawn cart)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 25: Given a gissha no senji (special permission to from the Emperor to enter the imperial palace in an ox-drawn cart).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="156">
<j>文治5年（1189年）（71歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1189 (Seventy-one year old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1189 (Seventy-one year old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1189 (Seventy-one year old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>2月13日出家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 13, he became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 13, he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 13: He became a priest.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), BAKU(id:55205), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Kamitani(id:30757), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>