<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>黒田長政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa KURODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa KURODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa KURODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>黒田 長政（くろだ ながまさ）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期にかけての武将・大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa KURODA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early part of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa KURODA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa KURODA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>筑前国福岡藩の初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first lord of the Fukuoka Domain, Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first lord of the Fukuoka domain, in Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first lord of the Fukuoka Domain of Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>豊臣秀吉の軍師として仕えた事で有名な黒田孝高（官兵衛、如水）の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Yoshitaka (Kanbee, Josui) KURODA, who is famous for serving as the strategist for Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of Yoshitaka (Kanbee, Josui) KURODA, who was legendary as the strategist for Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Yoshitaka (Kanbee, Josui) KURODA, who was legendary strategist for Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いで一番の武功を挙げたことから、筑前福岡藩52万3000石高を与えられ、その初代藩主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For performing the greatest military exploits in the Battle of Sekigahara, he was granted Fukuoka Domain, Chikuzen Province, which yielded 523,000 koku in rice, and became its first lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In exchange for performing the greatest military exploits in the Battle of Sekigahara, he was granted the Fukuoka domain, Chikuzen Province, which yielded 523,000 koku in rice, and became its first lord.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In exchange for performing the greatest military exploits in the Battle of Sekigahara, he was granted the Fukuoka Domain of Chikuzen Province, which yielded 523,000 koku in rice, and became its first lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父孝高と同じくキリシタンであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like his father, Yoshitaka, he was a Christian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like his father, Yoshitaka, he was a Christian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like his father, Yoshitaka, he was a Christian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>織田家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of the Oda family&apos;s vassals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of the Oda family&apos;s vassals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of the Oda family&apos;s vassals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）12月3日、黒田孝高の嫡男として播磨国姫路城に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on December 31, 1568, at the Himeji-jo Castle in Harima Province, as the legitimate son of Yoshitaka KURODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on December 31, 1568, at the Himeji-jo Castle in Harima Province, as the legitimate son of Yoshitaka KURODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on December 31, 1568, at the Himeji-jo Castle in Harima Province, as the legitimate son of Yoshitaka KURODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天正5年（1577年）から織田信長の人質として、織田家家臣の羽柴秀吉（のちの豊臣秀吉）の居城・近江国長浜城 (近江国)にて過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1577, he lived in the Nagahama-jo Castle of Omi Province (Omi Province), the residential castle of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), a vassal of the Oda family, as a hostage of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1577, he lived in the Nagahama-jo Castle of Omi Province (Omi Province), the residential castle of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), a vassal of the Oda family, as a hostage of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1577, he lived in the Nagahama-jo Castle of Omi Province, the residential castle of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), a vassal of the Oda family, as a hostage of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天正6年（1578年）、信長に一度降伏した荒木村重が信長に反旗を翻したとき（有岡城の戦い）、父の孝高は村重を説得する為に伊丹城に乗り込んで拘束された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1578, when Murashige ARAKI, who once surrendered to Nobunaga, led a rebellion against Nobunaga (Battle of Arioka-jo Castle), the father, Yoshitaka, entered the Itami-jo Castle to persuade Murashige and was confined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1578, when Murashige ARAKI, who once surrendered to Nobunaga, led a rebellion against Nobunaga (the Battle of Arioka-jo Castle), the father, Yoshitaka, entered Itami-jo Castle in order to persuade Murashige but was instead confined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1578, when Murashige ARAKI, who once surrendered to Nobunaga, led a rebellion against Nobunaga (the Battle of Arioka-jo Castle), the father, Yoshitaka, entered Itami-jo Castle in order to persuade Murashige but was instead confined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この時、信長は孝高がいつまでたっても戻ってこない為、村重方に寝返ったと考えて長政を処刑しようとしたが、竹中重治の機転により、一命を助けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitaka did not return for a long time, Nobunaga thought he defected to Murashige&apos;s side, and tried to execute Nagamasa, but he escaped death thanks to the wit of Shigeharu TAKENAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitaka did not return for a long time, Nobunaga thought he had defected to Murashige&apos;s side and therefore tried to execute Nagamasa, but he escaped death thanks to the wit of Shigeharu TAKENAKA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitaka did not return for a long time, Nobunaga thought he had defected to Murashige&apos;s side and therefore tried to execute Nagamasa, but he escaped death thanks to the wit of Shigeharu TAKENAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天正10年（1582年）には秀吉の高松城 (備中国)攻めに従い、中国地方の毛利氏と戦った（備中高松城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, he fought against the Mori clan from the Chugoku region (Battle of Bichu Takamatsu-jo Castle), following Hideyoshi&apos;s attack against Takamatsu-jo Castle (Bicchu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, he fought against the Mori clan from the Chugoku region (the Battle of Bichu Takamatsu-jo Castle), following Hideyoshi&apos;s attack on Takamatsu-jo Castle (Bicchu Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, he fought against the Mori clan from the Chugoku region (the Battle of Bicchu Takamatsu-jo Castle), following Hideyoshi&apos;s attack on Takamatsu-jo Castle (Bicchu Province).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>羽柴（豊臣）家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of the Hashiba (Toyotomi) family&apos;s vassals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of the Hashiba (Toyotomi) family&apos;s vassals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of the Hashiba (Toyotomi) family&apos;s vassals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>天正10年（1582年）6月、本能寺の変で信長が死去すると、父と共に秀吉の家臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June (old lunar calendar) 1582, when Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident, he became a vassal of Hideyoshi, along with his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June (old lunar calendar) 1582, when Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident, he became a vassal of Hideyoshi, along with his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June (old lunar calendar) 1582, when Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident, he became a vassal of Hideyoshi, along with his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>天正11年（1583年）の賤ケ岳の戦いでも功を挙げて、河内国に450石を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He rendered distinguished service in the Battle of Shizukatake in 1583, and was granted 450 koku in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He rendered distinguished service in the Battle of Shizukatake in 1583, and was granted 450 koku in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He rendered distinguished service in the Battle of Shizukatake in 1583, and was granted 450 koku in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天正12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いでは父と共に大阪城の留守居を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he served as rusui (caretaker or keeper) of Osaka-jo Castle with his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he served as a rusui (caretaker or keeper) of Osaka-jo Castle along with his father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he served as a caretaker of Osaka-jo Castle along with his father.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その功績により、2000石を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was granted 2,000 koku for this achievement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was granted 2,000 koku for this achievement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted 2,000 koku for this achievement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>天正15年（1587年）の九州征伐では長政自身は日向国財部城攻めで功績を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kyushu Conquest in 1587, Nagamasa himself rendered distinguished service in the Siege of Takarabe-jo Castle in Hyuga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kyushu Conquest of 1587, Nagamasa himself rendered distinguished service in the Siege of Takarabe-jo Castle, in Hyuga Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kyushu Conquest of 1587, Nagamasa rendered distinguished service in the Siege of Takarabe-jo Castle, in Hyuga Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>戦後、父子の功績をあわせて豊前国中津市に12万5000石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, the father and son were granted 125,000 koku in Nakatsu City, Buzen Province for their achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, the father and son were granted 125,000 koku in Nakatsu City, Buzen Province for their achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, the father and son were granted 125,000 koku in Nakatsu City, Buzen Province for their achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天正17年（1589年）、父が隠居したために家督を相続し、同時に従五位、甲斐守に叙任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1589, he took over as head of the family when his father retired, and at the same time, was confered to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and Kai no kami (the governor of Kai Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1589, he took over as head of the family when his father retired, and at the same time he was conferred as Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and Kai no kami (Governor of Kai Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1589, he took over as head of the family when his father retired, and at the same time he was conferred as Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and Kai no kami (Governor of Kai Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>文禄元年（1592年）から行なわれた秀吉の朝鮮出兵である文禄・慶長の役にも渡海している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also took the voyage in the Bunroku-Keicho War, which was a dispatch of troops to Korea by Hideyoshi starting in 1592.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also took the voyage in the Bunroku-Keicho War, which was a dispatch of troops to Korea by Hideyoshi starting in 1592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also took the voyage in the Bunroku-Keicho War, which was a dispatch of troops to Korea started in 1592 by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>長政は5千人の軍役を課せられ、主将として三番隊を率いて一番隊の小西行長や二番隊の加藤清正等とは別の進路を取る先鋒となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa was assigned a military duty of five thousand troops, and led the third squad as captain, to be the spearhead taking a different path from Yukinaga KONISHI&apos;s first squad or Kiyomasa KATO&apos;s second squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa was assigned a military duty of 5,000 troops, and led the third squad as captain and the spearhead in an attack that diverged from Yukinaga KONISHI&apos;s first squad and Kiyomasa KATO&apos;s second squad.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa was assigned an army of 5,000 troops, and led the third squad as captain and spearheaded an attack, diverging from Yukinaga KONISHI&apos;s first squad and Kiyomasa KATO&apos;s second squad.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>釜山上陸後は金海、昌原、霊山、昌寧、厳風、茂渓津、星州、金山、秋風嶺、永同、文義、清州、竹山を進撃して5月7日にソウル特別市へ到達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After landing in Busan, they invaded Gimhae, Changwon, Yongsan, Changning, Gempu, Mokeitsu, Xingzhou, Jinshan, Chupungryeong, Jincheon, Mongi, Cheongju, and Zhu Shan, and arrived in Seoul Special City on June 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After landing in Busan, they invaded Gimhae, Changwon, Yongsan, Changning, Gempu, Mokeitsu, Xingzhou, Jinshan, Chupungryeong, Jincheon, Mongi, Cheongju, and Zhu Shan, and arrived in Seoul Special City on June 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After landing in Busan, they invaded Gimhae, Changwon, Yongsan, Changning, Gempu, Mokeitsu, Xingzhou, Jinshan, Chupungryeong, Jincheon, Mongi, Cheongju, Zhu Shan, and arrived Seoul Special City on June 16.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>5月初旬の漢城会議で黄海道を担当することとなった三番隊は平安道担当の一番隊と共に李氏朝鮮王の宣祖を追って開城を攻略し、平壌まで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third squad, which was assigned the Hwanghae Province at the Hancheng (Seoul) meeting in mid-June, chased the King of Yi Dynasty Korea, Sonjo, with the first squad, which was responsible for Pyeongan Province, conquered Kaesong, and reached Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third squad, which was assigned to Hwanghae Province at the Hancheng (Seoul) meeting in mid-June, chased the King of the Yi Dynasty (Korea), Sonjo, with the first squad, which was responsible for Pyeongan Province, subsequently conquered Kaesong and reached Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third squad, which was assigned to Hwanghae Province at the Hancheng (Seoul) meeting in mid-June, chased Sonjo, the King of the Yi Dynasty (Korea), with the first squad assigned to Pyeongan Province, subsequently conquered Kaesong and reached Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>6月初旬には黄海道の制圧に戻り、7月7日には海州を攻略した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In mid-July, they returned to conquer Hwanghae Province, and on August 14, conquered Haeju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In mid-July, they returned to conquer Hwanghae Province, and on August 14 they conquered Haeju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In mid-July, they returned to conquer Hwanghae Province, and on August 14 they conquered Haeju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>8月初旬の漢城会議で明の援軍を警戒して戦線を縮小して主要街道を固めることとなり、黒田長政は李廷馣の守る延安城を攻撃を行ったが攻略することが出来ず、以後黄海道の広範な制圧から転換して北方からの攻勢に対応するために主要街道沿いにある白川城・江陰城を守ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hancheng (Seoul) meeting in early September, decision was made to reduce the battle line and secure the main roads to look out for reinforcements by Ming, and Nagamasa KURODA attacked the Enan-jo Castle guarded by Ri Teian, but failed to conquer, and since then guarded the Shirakawa-jo Castle and Koin-jo Castle along the main roads to respond to attacks from the north instead of conquering the vast area of Hwanghae Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hancheng (Seoul) meeting of early September, the decision was made to reduce the battle line and secure the main roads in order to look out for reinforcements by Ming; Nagamasa KURODA attacked Enan-jo Castle, which was guarded by Ri Teian, but he failed to conquer it, whereupon he guarded the Shirakawa-jo and Koin-jo castles along the main roads in order to respond to attacks from the north instead of conquering the vast area of Hwanghae Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Hancheng (Seoul) meeting of early September, the decision was made to reduce the battle line and secure the main roads in order to look out for reinforcements by Ming Dynasty; Nagamasa KURODA attacked Enan-jo Castle, which was guarded by Ri Teian, but he failed to conquer it, whereupon he guarded the Shirakawa-jo and Koin-jo castles along the main roads in order to respond to attacks from the north instead of conquering the vast area of Hwanghae Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>同じく三番隊の大友義統は鳳山城・黄州城を拠点とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimune OTOMO, who was also assigned to the third squad was based in Hozan-jo Castle and Koshu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimune OTOMO, who was also assigned to the third squad, was based in Hozan-jo Castle and Koshu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimune OTOMO, who was also assigned to the third squad, was based in Hozan-jo Castle and Koshu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>文禄2年（1593年）正月に中央から派遣された李如松率いる明の大軍が小西行長等の守る平壌城を急襲し、落城寸前の状態から撤退してきた小西軍を長政は白川城に収用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 2, 1593, a large Ming army dispatched by the central government and led by Li Ru-song raided the Pyeongyang Castle guarded by Yukinaga KONISHI and others, and Konishi&apos;s troops, who retreated from the castle on the brink of falling, were sheltered in Shirakawa-jo Castle by Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 2, 1593, a large Ming army dispatched by the central government and led by Li Ru-song raided Pyeongyang Castle, which was being guarded by Yukinaga KONISHI and others, and Konishi&apos;s troops, who had retreated from the castle on the brink of falling, were sheltered by Nagamasa in Shirakawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 2, 1593, a large Ming army, dispatched by the central government and led by Li Ru-song, raided Pyeongyang Castle, which was being guarded by Yukinaga KONISHI and others, and Konishi&apos;s troops, who had retreated from the castle on the verge of fall, were sheltered by Nagamasa in Shirakawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>以後、明の攻勢を警戒して漢城へ集中した日本軍は碧蹄館の戦いで明軍を撃破し戦意を失った明軍と補給不足に悩む日本軍の戦いは停滞する中で、長政は幸州山城の戦いにも出陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Japanese army, gathered in Hancheng as a precaution against attacks by Ming, defeated the Ming army in the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan), and while the battle between the Ming army which lost its will to fight and the Japanese army which suffered shortage in supplies stagnated, Nagamasa took part in the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Japanese army, gathered in Hancheng as a precaution against attacks by Ming, defeated the Ming army in the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan), and amid the stagnation of the battle between the Ming army, which had lost its will to fight, and the Japanese army, which suffered a shortage of supplies, Nagamasa took part in the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army, later gathered in Hancheng as a precaution against attacks by Ming Dynasty, defeated the Ming army in the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan), and amid the stagnation of the battle between the Ming army (which had lost its will to fight) and the Japanese army (which suffered a shortage of supplies), Nagamasa took part in the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>和平交渉が進み、日本軍は4月に漢城を放棄して朝鮮半島南部へ布陣を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The peace talks moved forward, and the Japanese army abandoned Hancheng in May and built a formation in the southern part of the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peace talks moved forward, and in May the Japanese army abandoned Hancheng and created a formation in the southern part of the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peace talks moved forward, and in May, the Japanese army abandoned Hancheng and created a formation in the southern part of the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>6月には朝鮮南部の拠点である晋州城を攻略し（第二次晋州城攻防戦)、長政配下の後藤又兵衛が先陣争いで活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June and July, they conquered Jinju Castle, the stronghold in southern Korea (Second Siege of Jinju), and Matabee GOTO, under Nagamasa&apos;s command, played an active role in the fight for the vanguard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June and July, they conquered Jinju Castle, the stronghold in southern Korea (the Second Siege of Jinju), and Matabee GOTO, under Nagamasa&apos;s command, played an active role in the fight for the vanguard.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June and July, they conquered Jinju Castle, the stronghold in southern Korea (the Second Siege of Jinju), and Matabee GOTO played an active role in the fight for the vanguard under Nagamasa&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その後の南部布陣期の長政は機長城を守備することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the remaining years during which the formation was in the south, Nagamasa guarded the Kicho-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the remaining years during which the formation was in the south, Nagamasa guarded Kicho-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the remaining years during which Nagamasa took up the position in the south guarded Kicho-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>慶長元年（1596年）9月に日明和平交渉は大詰めを迎え、秀吉による明使謁見で双方の外交担当者による欺瞞が発覚して交渉が破綻すると秀吉は諸将に再出兵を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October and November of 1596, peace talks between Ming and Japan were in the final stage, but when fraud by diplomats on both sides was revealed during Minshi ekken (audience with envoy from Ming Dynasty) by Hideyoshi, and the negotiations failed, Hideyoshi once again ordered dispatch of troops to the warlords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October and November of 1596, peace talks between Ming and Japan were in the final stage, but when fraud by diplomats on both sides was revealed during the Minshi ekken (audience with an envoy from the Ming Dynasty) by Hideyoshi, and the negotiations failed, Hideyoshi once again ordered the dispatch of troops to the warlords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October and November of 1596, peace talks between Ming Dynasty and Japan were in the final stages, but when fraud by diplomats on both sides was revealed during the Minshi ekken (audience with an envoy from the Ming Dynasty) by Hideyoshi, and the negotiations failed, Hideyoshi once again ordered the warlords to dispatch troops.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）7月に元均率いる朝鮮水軍による攻勢があり、反撃により漆川梁海戦で朝鮮水軍を壊滅に追い込んだ日本軍は8月より主に全羅道から忠清道へ攻勢を掛けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August and September of 1597, there was an attack by the Korean army led by Won Gyun, and the Japanese army in response devastated the Korean army in the naval Battle of Chilcheollyang, and from September, attacked mainly the area between Jeolla-do and Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August and September of 1597, there was an attack by the Korean army led by Won Gyun, and in response the Japanese army devastated the Korean army in the naval Battle of Chilcheollyang; and beginning in September it attacked mainly the area between Jeolla-do and Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August and September of 1597, there was an attack by the Korean army led by Won Gyun; the Japanese army responded it by devastating the Korean army in the naval Battle of Chilcheollyang, and beginning to attack mainly the area between Jeolla-do and Chungchong-do from September.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>長政は再度5千人の軍役を課せられ右軍に属して黄石山城を攻略し、8月に全州で左軍と合流し、全州会議に従って各軍の進路を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa was assigned a military duty of five thousand troops again, belonged to the right army and conquered the Hwangsoksan Castle, joined with the left army in September and October in Chonju, and decided the path of each army in accordance with the Chonju conference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa was again assigned a military duty of 5,000 troops, joined the right army and conquered Hwangsoksan Castle, joined with the left army at Chonju in September and October, and decided the path of each army in accordance with the Chonju conference.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa was again assigned the army of 5,000 troops, joined the right army and conquered Hwangsoksan Castle, joined with the left army at Chonju in September and October, and decided the path of each army in accordance with the Chonju conference.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>長政は加藤清正や毛利秀元等と右軍を形成して忠清道の天安へ進出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa formed the right army with Kiyomasa KATO, Hidemoto MORI, etc., and invaded Tian An in Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa formed the right army with Kiyomasa KATO, Hidemoto MORI, etc., and invaded Tian An in Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa formed the right army with Kiyomasa KATO, Hidemoto MORI, and others and invaded Tian An in Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>日本軍の急激な侵攻を受けて、漢城では明軍が首都放棄も覚悟したが明軍経理の楊鎬が抗戦を決意し、派遣された明将の解生の軍と長政軍が忠清道の禝山で遭遇戦(禝山の戦い)を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to the sudden invasion by the Japanese army, in Hancheng, the Ming army was prepared to abandon the capital, but Yang Hao, the Ming army accountant decided to resist, and the troops of Ming&apos;s commander, Kaisei, and the troops of Nagamasa engaged in an encounter battle (Battle of Shokuzan) in Shokuzan of Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to the sudden invasion by the Japanese army, in Hancheng, the Ming army was prepared to abandon the capital, but the Ming army accountant Yang Hao decided to resist, and the troops of Ming&apos;s commander, Kaisei, and the troops of Nagamasa engaged in an encounter battle (the Battle of Shokuzan) in Shokuzan of Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to the sudden invasion by the Japanese army, the Ming army was prepared to abandon the capital in Hancheng, but the Ming army accountant Yang Hao decided to resist, and the troops of Ming&apos;s commander Kaisei, and the troops of Nagamasa engaged in an encounter battle (the Battle of Shokuzan) in Shokuzan of Chungchong-do.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>苦戦した長政は秀元の援軍もあり何とか戦場を確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa had a hard time, but was able to secure the battlefield with reinforcements from Hidemoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa had a hard time, but he was able to secure the battlefield with reinforcements from Hidemoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa had a bitter fight, but was able to secure the battlefield with reinforcements from Hidemoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>なお、禝山の戦いについては、日明ともに勝利を報じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the Battle of Shokuzan, both Japan and Ming report victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the Battle of Shokuzan, both Japan and Ming claimed victory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Japan and Ming Dynasty claimed victory for the Battle of Shokuzan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="37">
<j>その後、長政は秀元、清正と鎮州で会議を行い、竹山、尚州、慶山、密陽を経て梁山倭城を築城して守備についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Nagamasa held a meeting with Hidemoto and Kiyomasa in Chinshu, advanced from Zhu Shan, Sangju, Gyeongsan to Miryan, and constructed and guarded the Ryosanwa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Nagamasa held a meeting with Hidemoto and Kiyomasa in Chinshu, advanced from Zhu Shan, Sangju, Gyeongsan to Miryan, and constructed and guarded Ryosanwa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Nagamasa held a meeting with Hidemoto and Kiyomasa in Chinshu to advance through Zhu Shan, Sangju, Gyeongsan and Miryan, and to construct and guard Ryosanwa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>占領地を広げて冬営のために布陣していた日本軍に対し、12月末から経理楊鎬・提督麻貴率いる明軍が完成間近の蔚山倭城へ攻勢をかけ（第一次蔚山城の戦い）、加藤清正が苦戦すると西部に布陣していた日本軍は蔚山救援軍を編成して明軍を撃破した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ming army led by accountant Yang Hao and admiral Ma Gui attacked the nearly-completed Ulsan Japanese Castle from early February 1598 (First Battle of Ulsan) against the Japanese army who were expanding their demesne and building a formation for winter, and when Kiyomasa KATO struggled, the Japanese army based in the west formed a Ulsan rescue mission and defeated the Ming army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ming army, led by the accountant Yang Hao and admiral Ma Gui, attacked the nearly complete Ulsan Japanese Castle beginning in early February 1598 (the First Battle of Ulsan) against the Japanese army, which was expanding its domain and building a formation for winter, and when Kiyomasa KATO struggled the Japanese army based in the west formed an Ulsan rescue mission and defeated the Ming army.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ming army headed by the accountant Yang Hao and admiral Ma Gui attacked the nearly complete Ulsan Japanese Castle in early February 1598 (the First Battle of Ulsan) against the Japanese army, which was expanding its domain and building winter quarters, and when Kiyomasa KATO struggled against the Ming army the Japanese army based in the west formed reinforcements for Ulsan and defeated the Ming army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>長政はこの救援軍に六百人を派遣しており、後にその不活発さが秀吉から叱責されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa dispatched 600 troops to this rescue mission, and was later reprehended by Hideyoshi for the sluggish response.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa dispatched 600 troops to this rescue mission but was later reprimanded by Hideyoshi for the sluggish response.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa dispatched 600 troops to the reinforcements but was later reprimanded by Hideyoshi for that sluggish response.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>明の攻撃を受けた諸将は今後の防衛体制を整えるために蔚山倭城(最西方)、順天倭城(最東方)、梁山倭城(内陸部)の三城を放棄して戦線を縮小する案を秀吉に打診したが却下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to the attack by Ming, the warlords approached Hideyoshi with a proposal to abandon three castles, Ulsan Japanese Castle (westernmost), Suncheon Waeseong (easternmost), and Ryosanwa-jo Castle (inland), and narrow down the battle line, but it was rejected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to the attack by Ming, the warlords approached Hideyoshi with a proposal to abandon three castles--Ulsan Japanese Castle (westernmost), Suncheon Waeseong (easternmost) and Ryosanwa-jo Castle (inland)--and narrow down the battle line, but it was rejected.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to the attack by the Ming Dynasty, the warlords approached Hideyoshi with a proposal to abandon three castles (the westernmost Ulsan Japanese Castle, the easternmost Suncheon Waeseong and the inland Ryosanwa-jo Castle) narrowing down the battle line--but it was rejected.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>結局、長政の梁山倭城のみ放棄が認められ、以後撤退命令が出るまで長政は亀浦倭城へ移陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, only Nagamasa&apos;s Ryosanwa-jo Castle was allowed to be abandoned, and Nagamasa transferred and remained in Kupowein until the retreat order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, only Nagamasa&apos;s Ryosanwa-jo Castle was allowed to be abandoned, and Nagamasa transferred and remained in Kupowein until the order to retreat was given.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, Hideyoshi only allowed to abandon Nagamasa&apos;s Ryosanwa-jo Castle and transferred Nagamasa to Kupowein to remain until the order to retreat was given.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）9月に明将の麻貴率いる大軍の攻勢があったが、前年の教訓から明軍は不活発であり小競り合いに終わり（第二次蔚山城の戦い）、そのまま撤退を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1598, there was an attack by a large army led by Ming&apos;s commander Ma Gui, but the Ming army was sluggish due to lessons from the previous year, and it ended up as a limited war (Second Battle of Ulsan), leading to retreat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1598, there was an attack by a large army led by the Ming commander Ma Gui, but the Ming army was sluggish due to lessons from the previous year, and it ended up as a limited engagement (the Second Battle of Ulsan) that led to retreat.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1598, there was an attack by a large army led by a Ming commander Ma Gui, but due to lessons from the previous year, the Ming army was sluggish and it ended up as a limited engagement (the Second Battle of Ulsan) that led to retreat.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="43">
<j>このように長政は朝鮮では数々の武功を挙げたが、同時に吏僚である石田三成や小西行長らと対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described, Nagamasa performed many military exploits in Korea, but at the same time, he was in conflict with executive officers such as Mitsunari ISHIDA and Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described, Nagamasa had many military exploits in Korea, but at the same time he was in conflict with executive officers such as Mitsunari ISHIDA and Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described, Nagamasa had many military exploits in Korea, while being in conflict with executive officers such as Mitsunari ISHIDA and Yukinaga KONISHI in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）8月、秀吉が死去すると、三成ら文治派との対立路線から五大老の徳川家康に接近し、家康の養女（保科正直の娘）を正室に迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1598, when Hideyoshi died, he followed his opposition policy against Mitsunari and the Bunchi faction, and approached Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, a Godaigo (Council of Five Elders), and married the adopted daughter of Ieyasu (daughter of Masanao HOSHINA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1598, upon the death of Hideyoshi, he followed his opposition policy against Mitsunari and the Bunchi faction, and approached Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, a Godaigo (Council of Five Elders), and married the adopted daughter of Ieyasu (daughter of Masanao HOSHINA).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1598, upon the death of Hideyoshi, he followed his opposition policy against the Bunchi faction including Mitsunari and approached Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, one of Council of Five Elders, and married the adopted daughter of Ieyasu (daughter of Masanao HOSHINA).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>慶長4年（1599年）閏3月に前田利家が死去すると、福島正則や加藤清正ら武断派と共に石田三成を襲撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In leap March (old lunar calendar) 1599, when Toshiie MAEDA died, he attacked Mitsunari ISHIDA with Budan-ha (a political faction that is willing to resort to military means to achieve its aims) members such as Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In leap March (old lunar calendar) 1599, upon the death of Toshiie MAEDA, he attacked Mitsunari ISHIDA with Budan-ha (a political faction that is willing to resort to military means to achieve its aims) members such as Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In leap March (old lunar calendar) 1599, upon the death of Toshiie MAEDA, he attacked Mitsunari ISHIDA with Budan-ha (a political faction that is willing to resort to military means to achieve its aim) members such as Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）に家康が会津の上杉景勝討伐の兵を起すと家康に従って出陣し、出兵中に三成らが大坂で西軍を率いて挙兵すると、東軍武将として関ヶ原の戦いにおいて戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1600, when Ieyasu raised an army for subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI, he departed for the front along with Ieyasu, and in the meantime, when Mitsunari raised the West squad in Osaka, he fought in the Battle of Sekigahara as the East squad busho (Japanese military commander).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600, when Ieyasu raised an army for the subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI, he departed for the front along with Ieyasu, and in the meantime, when Mitsunari raised the western squad in Osaka, he fought in the Battle of Sekigahara as the busho (Japanese military commander) of the eastern squad.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600, when Ieyasu raised an army for the subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI, he departed for the front along with Ieyasu; in the meantime, when Mitsunari raised the western squad in Osaka, he fought in the Battle of Sekigahara as the military commander of the eastern squad.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>三成に対する恨みからか、本戦における黒田隊の活躍は凄まじかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to resentments toward Mitsunari, the performance of the Kuroda troops in this battle was extraordinary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to resentment toward Mitsunari, the performance of the Kuroda troops in this battle was extraordinary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The performance of the Kuroda troops in this battle was extraordinary, due to resentment toward Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>長政は調略においても西軍の小早川秀秋や吉川広家など諸将の寝返りを交渉する役目も務めており、それらの功により戦後、家康から一番の功労者として筑前名島（福岡）に52万3000石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of stratagem, Nagamasa negotiated with the West squad warlords such as Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA and Hiroie KIKKAWA to have them switch sides, and due to such achievements, he was granted 523,000 koku in Chikuzen Najima (Fukuoka) after the war by Ieyasu as rendering the most distinguished service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of strategy, Nagamasa negotiated with warlords of the western squad such as Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA and Hiroie KIKKAWA in order to have them switch sides, and due to such achievements he was granted 523,000 koku in Chikuzen Najima (Fukuoka) after the war by Ieyasu as having rendered the most distinguished service.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of strategy, Nagamasa negotiated with warlords of the western squad such as Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA and Hiroie KIKKAWA in order to have them switch sides; and due to such achievements, he was granted 523,000 koku in Chikuzen Najima (Fukuoka) by Ieyasu after the war as having rendered the most distinguished service.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>慶長8年（1603年）、従四位下、筑前守に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1603, he was confered to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chikuzen no kami (governor of Chikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1603, he was conferred as Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chikuzen no kami (governor of Chikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1603, he was conferred upon Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, governor of Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）の大坂の役では江戸城の留守居を務め、代理として嫡男の黒田忠之が出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Siege of Osaka in 1614, he served as rusui of Edo-jo Castle and his legitimate son, Tadayuki KURODA, departed for the front on his behalf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Siege of Osaka in 1614, he served as the rusui of Edo-jo Castle and his legitimate son, Tadayuki KURODA, departed for the front on his behalf.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Siege of Osaka in 1614, he served as the caretaker of Edo-jo Castle, and had his heir Tadayuki KURODA leave for the front on his behalf.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>翌年の大坂の役では2代征夷大将軍徳川秀忠に属して豊臣方と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Siege of Osaka the following year, he fought against the Toyotomi side under Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the second seii taishogun (lieterally, great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Siege of Osaka the following year, he fought against the Toyotomi side under Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the second seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Siege of Osaka the following year, under the second seii taishogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA, he fought against the Toyotomi side.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>元和 (日本)9年（1623年）8月4日、徳川秀忠の上洛に先立って早くに入京したが、まもなく発病して京都知恩寺で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29, 1623, he went to the capital (Kyoto) ahead of Hidetada TOKUGAWA, but soon developed a disease and died in Kyoto Chion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29, 1623, he went to the capital (Kyoto) ahead of Hidetada TOKUGAWA, but soon he developed a disease and died at Kyoto Chion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 29, 1623, he went to Kyoto prior to Hidetada TOKUGAWA; before long, he developed a disease and died at Kyoto Chion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>享年56。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at age 56.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at age 56.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age 56.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>後を長男・忠之が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest son, Tadayuki, succeeded him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eldest son, Tadayuki, succeeded him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eldest son Tadayuki succeeded him.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>父・孝高と違って知略の人物ではなく、武勇に優れた勇将であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was not a resourceful person like his father Yoshitaka, but was a brave general with distinguished bravery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wasn&apos;t a resourceful person like his father Yoshitaka, but he was a brave and distinguished general.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike his father Yoshitaka, he was a brave and distinguished general, not a resourceful person.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>但し、関ヶ原における調略を見ても分かる様に、知略が無かった訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as seen in his stratagem in Sekigahara, he was not without resourcefulness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as seen in his strategy for Sekigahara, he wasn&apos;t entirely lacking in resourcefulness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, he wasn&apos;t entirely lacking in resourcefulness, as proved in his strategy for Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>父ほどの知略は無かった、あるいは、父の知略がある意味人智を超えたものだった為地味に見られやすいが、智勇兼備の名将というべきであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was not as resourceful as his father, or his father&apos;s resourcefulness was somewhat beyond human knowledge, he is often seen as modest, but he was a great commander having both wisdom and courage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he wasn&apos;t as resourceful as his father, or since his father&apos;s resourcefulness was somewhat beyond human knowledge, he is often seen as modest, but he was a great commander gifted with wisdom and courage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he is often seen as modest since he wasn&apos;t as resourceful as his father, or since his father&apos;s resourcefulness was somewhat beyond human knowledge, he was a great commander gifted with wisdom and courage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>秀吉の死後は藤堂高虎に匹敵するかのように、家康に忠実に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi, he faithfully served Ieyasu, in a way comparable to Takatora TODO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Hideyoshi, he faithfully served Ieyasu in a way comparable to Takatora TODO.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi, he faithfully served Ieyasu in a way comparable to Takatora TODO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>蜂須賀正勝の娘と離縁して家康の養女と結婚し、さらに家康の命令で普請事業に全て従順に従っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He divorced the daughter of Masakatsu HACHISUKA and married the adopted daughter of Ieyasu, and followed all of the construction projects ordered by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He divorced the daughter of Masakatsu HACHISUKA and then married the adopted daughter of Ieyasu, and followed all the construction projects ordered by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He divorced the daughter of Masakatsu HACHISUKA and then married the adopted daughter of Ieyasu, following all the construction projects ordered by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>これにより、外様大名でありながらも優遇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, he received favorable treatment despite being a tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus he received favorable treatment despite being a tozama daimyo (non-hereditary feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, he received favorable treatment despite the status of a non-hereditary feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>長政が三成を恨んだのは、かつて父が失脚した一因に、三成との対立があったからだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Nagamasa resented Mitsunari, because one of the reasons for his father&apos;s downfall was his conflict with Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Nagamasa resented Mitsunari, because one of the reasons for his father&apos;s downfall was his conflict with Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Nagamasa resented Mitsunari, because one of the reasons for his father&apos;s downfall was conflict between his father and Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかしこれには後日談があり、関ヶ原の合戦後に三成への侮蔑の言葉を浴びせずに、馬を降りて敵軍の将として敬意の念を示したのは、長政と藤堂高虎だけだったとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a sequel to this theory is that after the battle in Sekigahara, it was only Nagamasa and Takatora TODO, who instead of despising Mitsunari, dismounted from their horses to show respect to the warlord of the enemy troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a sequel to this theory is that after the battle in Sekigahara it was only Nagamasa and Takatora TODO who, instead of despising Mitsunari, dismounted from their horses to show respect to the warlord of the enemy troops.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a sequel to this theory is that, after the battle in Sekigahara, it was only Nagamasa and Takatora TODO who dismounted from their horses to show respect to the warlord of the enemy troops, instead of despising Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>この時、長政は自らの服を三成にかけて手向けの言葉を送ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that Nagamasa covered Mitsunari with his own clothing and bid him farewell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Nagamasa covered Mitsunari with his own clothing and bid him farewell.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Nagamasa covered Mitsunari with his own clothing, and bid him farewell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="64">
<j>熟慮断行の気性であったようであり、父如水はそれを優柔不断のように見えたのか長政に「自分はかつて小早川隆景に物事の決断が早すぎるので慎重にしたほうがよいと言われたが、おまえはその逆だから注意しろ」との意味の言葉をかけたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was deliberate in counsel, prompt in action, which may have appeared as indecisive to his father, Josui, that he is said to have warned Nagamasa by telling him something like &quot;I have been told by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA to be cautious, because I make decisions too quickly, but you need to be careful because you are the opposite.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was deliberate in counsel and prompt in action, which may have seemed indecisive to his father, Josui, who it is said had warned Nagamasa by telling him something like, &quot;I have been told by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA to be cautious, because I make decisions too quickly, but you need to be careful because you are the opposite.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was deliberate in counsel and prompt in action, which may have seemed indecisive to his father Josui; it is said Josui warned Nagamasa by telling him something like, &quot;I have been told by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA to be cautious, because I make decisions too quickly, but you need to be careful because you are the opposite.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>長政はその言葉をヒントに後年「異見会」という家老と下級武士の代表を集め対等な立場で討論の上決断する仕組みを作ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa got a hint from those words and later established an &apos;objection conference&apos; system, where decisions were made by gathering representatives of Karo (chief retainer) and lower-ranking samurai and holding discussions at an equal level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa got a hint from those words and later established an &apos;objection conference&apos; system, where decisions were made by gathering representatives of Karo (chief retainer) and lower-ranking samurai and holding discussions at an equal level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clued by those words, Nagamasa later established an &apos;objection conference&apos; system, where decisions were made by representatives of chief retainers and lower-ranking samurai discussing the matters at an equal level.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>関ヶ原後、家康は長政の功労に手をとって喜んだとまで言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sekigahara, it is told that Ieyasu was so happy with Nagamasa&apos;s distinguished service, that he held his hand in joy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that, after Sekigahara, Ieyasu was so happy with Nagamasa&apos;s distinguished service that he held his hand in joy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that, after Sekigahara, Ieyasu was so happy with Nagamasa&apos;s distinguished service that he held his hand in joy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>帰郷してこの事を父如水に話すと、「その時左手は何をしていた」（即ちなぜその時左手に短刀を持って家康を刺さなかったかと言う意味）と詰問された話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he told this to his father, Josui, he was inquired severely &quot;What was your left hand doing at that time?&quot; (that is to say, why didn&apos;t you grab a short sword in your left hand and stab Ieyasu at that time?).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he told this to his father, Josui, he received the serious inquiry, &quot;What was your left hand doing at that time?&quot; (which is to say, &quot;Why didn&apos;t you grab a short sword in your left hand and stab Ieyasu at that time?&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he told this to his father Josui, he received the serious inquiry, &apos;What was your left hand doing at that time?&apos; (which is to say, &apos;Why didn&apos;t you grab a short sword with your left hand and stab Ieyasu at that time?&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>晩年には子の満徳丸（後の黒田忠之）の器量を心配して、いくつもの家訓（御定則）を与えている（御定則は後世の創作であるとも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, he was concerned about the capacity of his child, Mitsutokumaru (later Tadayuki KURODA), and provided him with many family precepts (gojosoku (family precepts)) (some say the gojosoku was invented in the later ages).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, he was concerned about the capacity of his child, Mitsutokumaru (later Tadayuki KURODA), and provided him with many family precepts (gojosoku (family precepts)) (some say the gojosoku was invented in a later age).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, he was concerned about the capacity of his child Mitsutokumaru (later Tadayuki KURODA), and provided him with many family precepts (some say the gojosoku was invented in a later age).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また、一時は忠之を廃して黒田長興を後継者にすることを考えたとまで言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is told that at one time, he considered excluding Tadayuki and assigning Nagaoki KURODA as the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is said that at one time he considered excluding Tadayuki and instead assigning Nagaoki KURODA as the successor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is said that once he considered excluding Tadayuki and instead, assigning Nagaoki KURODA as his successor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>後に忠之の時代に福岡藩が起こった事を考えると、この長政の心配は当たっていた事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that Fukuoka Domain was formed later during Tadayuki&apos;s years, proves that Nagamasa&apos;s concerns were legitimate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that the Fukuoka domain was formed later, during Tadayuki&apos;s years, proves that Nagamasa&apos;s concerns were legitimate.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that the Fukuoka Domain was formed later in the days of Tadayuki proves that Nagamasa&apos;s concerns were legitimate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="71">
<j>嫉妬深い一面があり、父如水が死去すると、黒田家随一の勇将で武功も多く、如水から大名なみの厚遇を与えられていた後藤又兵衛を追放し、さらに奉公構という措置を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has a jealous side, and when his father, Josui, died, he expelled Matabee GOTO, who was the bravest warlord in the Kuroda family, had many military exploits, and was receiving daimyo-level hospitality from Josui, and furthermore, carried out measures called hokokamae (a kind of punishment).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a jealous side, and when his father Josui died, he expelled Matabee GOTO, the bravest warlord in the Kuroda family, who had many military exploits and had received daimyo-level hospitality from Josui, and furthermore he carried out measures called hokokamae (a kind of punishment).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a jealous side: when his father Josui died, he expelled Matabei GOTO, the bravest warlord in the Kuroda retainers with many military exploits who had received daimyo-level hospitality from Josui; and furthermore, he carried out measures called hokokamae (a kind of punishment).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これは、長政が又兵衛の功績と、かつて如水に寵愛された事を嫉妬したからだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that this was due to Nagamasa&apos;s jealousy towards Matabee&apos;s great achievements and the affection he once received from Josui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was due to Nagamasa&apos;s jealousy over Matabee&apos;s great achievements and the affection he had once received from Josui.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this was due to Nagamasa&apos;s jealousy over Matabee&apos;s great achievements and the affection he had once received from Josui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="73">
<j>忠之が4歳の袴着式を迎えた時、母里友信は「父上以上の功名を挙げなさい」と言ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadayuki had his Hakamagishiki (ceremony fitting child with a hakama (Japanese skirt)) at four, it is told that Tomonobu MORI said to him, &quot;Achieve more than your father.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when Tadayuki had his Hakamagishiki (ceremony to fit a child with a hakama (Japanese skirt)) at age four, Tomonobu MORI said to him, &quot;Achieve more than your father.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when Tadayuki had his Hakamagishiki (ceremony to fit a child with a hakama (Japanese skirt)) at age four, Tomonobu MORI said to him, &apos;Achieve more than your father.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>それを知った長政は「父以上の功名とは何事だ」と激怒し、友信を殺そうとしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Learning this, Nagamasa was outraged saying &quot;How dare you say &apos;achieve more than your father&apos;&quot; and tried to kill Tomonobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Learning this, Nagamasa became outraged and said, &quot;How dare you say &apos;achieve more than your father,&apos;&quot; and tried to kill Tomonobu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Learning this, Nagamasa became outraged and said, &apos;How dare you say &apos;achieve more than your father,&apos;&apos; and tried to kill Tomonobu.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>ただし、周囲の取り成しで命は助けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life was saved by intervention by people around them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His life was saved by the intervention of people around them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His life was saved by the intervention of people around them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="76">
<j>死の床につき、家老宛に「徳川が天下を取れたのは、黒田父子の力によるもの」としたためた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his deathbed, he wrote to his Karo, &quot;Tokugawa was able to unify the country thanks to the power of the father and son of Kuroda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his deathbed, he wrote to his Karo, &quot;Tokugawa was able to unify the country, thanks to the power of the father and son of the Kuroda family.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his deathbed, he wrote to his chief retainers, &apos;Tokugawa was able to unify the country, thanks to the power of the father and son of the Kuroda family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いでの東軍勝利の影の功労者として、長政はこの戦いを生涯の誇りとしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the person who rendered distinguished service behind the scenes for the victory of the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara, Nagamasa considered this battle his life-long pride.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the person who rendered distinguished service behind the scenes for the victory of the eastern squad in the Battle of Sekigahara, Nagamasa considered this battle his lifelong pride.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the person who rendered distinguished service behind the scenes for the victory of the eastern squad in the Battle of Sekigahara, Nagamasa was proud of this battle for the rest of his life.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="78">
<j>バテレン追放令により、秀吉から改宗を迫られ、父の孝高が率先してキリスト教を棄教すると長政自らも改宗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When approached by Hideyoshi to convert under the edict expelling Jesuit missionaries, and his father, Yoshitaka, took the lead in giving up his Christian faith, Nagamasa also converted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When approached by Hideyoshi to convert under the edict expelling Jesuit missionaries, and knowing that his father Yoshitaka had taken the lead in giving up his Christian faith, Nagamasa also converted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When forced by Hideyoshi to convert with the edict for expelling Jesuit missionaries and his father Yoshitaka had taken the lead in giving up his Christian faith, Nagamasa also converted.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>徳川政権下では迫害者に転じ、領内でキリシタンを厳しく処罰したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Tokugawa government, he in turn became the oppressor, and strictly punished the Christians in the territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Tokugawa government, he in turn became the oppressor, and strictly punished the Christians in the territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Tokugawa government, he changed to be the oppressor, and strictly punished the Christians in his territory.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Londonbashi(id:19027), ドルチェット(id:46458), Nnh(id:474), Yasumi(id:44933), Reggaeman(id:6214), 0null0(id:582), Urania(id:7213), デュオ(id:40933), Lupinoid(id:68), Kotoito(id:21045), ブレイズマン(id:183852), HqB774PW0(id:311341), でここ(id:9565), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), Frei(id:12101), こぶまき(id:38278), Chacmool(id:202970), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Pinball1973(id:33613), Moltke(id:17553), 松茸(id:27535), GoGoDoll(id:131511), Nallimbot(id:230812), STBot(id:137943), Yanahan(id:2437), Ikizama(id:126094), Sorrysorry(id:102591), 小者(id:172526), Aboshi(id:9318), Kagetudo(id:163875), Yonoemon(id:55450), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), こいつぅ(id:2105), Louperibot(id:128971), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>