<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平島公方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirashima Kubo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirashima Kubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirashima Kubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平島公方（ひらしまくぼう）（又は阿波公方）は、血統的には室町幕府11代征夷大将軍・足利義澄の次男足利義維の末裔で、家柄的には、足利義視から義稙、そして義維と続く将軍家別家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirashima Kubo (or Awa Kubo) is traced pedigree to Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, the second son of Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA who is the 11th Seii Taishogun of Muromachi bakufu, and their family lineage is a branch family of the Shogun family succeeded by into Yoshimi, Yoshitane and Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirashima Kubo (or Awa Kubo) is descended from Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, the second son of Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA who was the 11th Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and their family lineage is a branch family of the Shogun family succeeded by Yoshimi, Yoshitane and Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA successively.</e>
<cmt>Seii Taishogun, bakufuの説明を加え、語句を少々変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirashima Kubo (or Awa Kubo) is descended from Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, the second son of Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA who was the 11th Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and their family lineage is a branch family of the Shogun family succeeded by Yoshimi, Yoshitane and Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA successively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>代々阿波国平島（阿南市那賀川町古津）に住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They lived in Hisashima, Awa Province (current Furutsu, Nakagawacho, Anan City) for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They lived in Hirashima, Awa Province (current Furutsu, Nakagawa-cho, Anan City) for generations.</e>
<cmt>NakagawachoをNakagawa-choとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They lived in Hirashima, Awa Province (current Furutsu, Nakagawa-cho, Anan City) for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、公方と称されるものの、この平島の系統で実際に将軍職に就任したのは第14代将軍足利義栄のみで、義栄以外の人物には将軍家一族という意味で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also note that who actually assumed the position of Shogun was only the 14th Shogun Yoshihide ASHIKAGA among the lineage of Hirashima even though they are called Kubo, so the word, Kubo, means the Shogun family for the other people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also note that only the 14th Shogun Yoshihide ASHIKAGA actually assumed the position of Shogun among the lineage of Hirashima even though they are called &quot;Kubo,&quot; so the word &quot;Kubo&quot; means the Shogun family for the other people.</e>
<cmt>前半の文の構造を変え、Kuboを&quot;&quot;で囲みました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also note that only the 14th Shogun Yoshihide ASHIKAGA actually assumed the position of Shogun among the lineage of Hirashima even though they are called &quot;Kubo,&quot; so the word &quot;Kubo&quot; means the Shogun family for the other people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengoku Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)</e>
<cmt>用語集の記載に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>御輿から堺公方まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Mikoshi to Sakai Kubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Mikoshi to Sakai Kubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Mikoshi to Sakai Kubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明応の政変に加え、永正の錯乱まで勃発すると、足利氏の将軍職争いに細川氏の管領職争いまで絡んだため、畿内の戦乱は複雑化し、長引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Eisho Disturbance (also known as the assassination of Masamoto HOSOKAWA) happened in addition to Meio Coup, the war in and around the capital became complicated and prolonged because the battle for shogunate was related to the battle for Kanrei shoku (a post of shogunal deputy) of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Eisho Disturbance (also known as the assassination of Masamoto HOSOKAWA) happened in addition to Meio Coup, the war in and around the capital became complicated and prolonged because the battle for shogunate of the Ashikaga clan was related to the battle for Kanrei shoku (a post of shogunal deputy) of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>shogunateの後に&quot;of the Ashikaga clan&quot;を付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Eisho Disturbance (also known as the assassination of Masamoto HOSOKAWA) happened in addition to Meio Coup, the war in and around the capital became complicated and prolonged because the battle for shogunate of the Ashikaga clan was related to the battle for Kanrei shoku (a post of shogunal deputy) of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>やがて将軍職が12代・足利義晴で1本化されようとも、細川氏では細川高国と細川晴元が、なおも管領職をかけて争い続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, shogunete was unified into the 12th Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, however, Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Harumoto HOSOKAWA still continued fighting over Kanrei shoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, shogunate was unified into the 12th Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, but Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Harumoto HOSOKAWA still continued fighting over Kanrei shoku.</e>
<cmt>howeverをbutにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, shogunate was unified into the 12th Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, but Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Harumoto HOSOKAWA still continued fighting over Kanrei shoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その際、義晴将軍を名目上であろうと担ぎだした場合には、現職の管領（高国側）が官軍となり、他方（晴元側）が賊軍となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, if Yoshiharu were haven as Shogun notionally, incumbent Kanrei (Takakuni side) would be Imperial army and the other side (Harumoto side) would be rebel army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this fight, if Yoshiharu was gotten to be as Shogun even though it was only in name, incumbent Kanrei (Takakuni side) would be a loyalist army and the other side (Harumoto side) would be a rebel army.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point in time, in the event that it was possible to raise up Yoshiharu as Shogun, even if in name only, the forces of the current Kanrei (a supporter of Takakuni) would become the loyalist army, while the other combatants (who were supporting Harumoto) would become the rebel army.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>そこで、足利義維が必要とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA was needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA was needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA was needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>足利義維を担ぐ事で、賊軍としての立場が和らぐのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA as Shogun mitigates the position as rebel army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Getting Yoshitaka to be as Shogun mitigates their severe situations as a rebel army.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succeeding in raising up Yoshitaka ASHIKAGA as Shogun would alleviate their position as the rebel army.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その義維としても、あわよくば将軍への道が拓けようというのだから、積極的に関わったとも察せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsuna is also considered to have got engaged positively because he would have been on track to becoming Shogun if circumstances had allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsuna was possibly engaged in it positively because he would be on track to becoming Shogun if circumstances allowed.</e>
<cmt>時制を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsuna was possibly engaged in it positively because he would be on track to becoming Shogun if circumstances allowed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして、大永7年（1527年）の桂川原の戦いで敗退した高国が、掌中の玉・義晴将軍を伴って近江国坂本へ逃亡したため、立場を逆転させた義維・晴元体制は、和泉国で新政権樹立の足掛かりを築くまでになる（堺公方）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the structure of Yoshitsuna and Yoshiharu, which reversed their stand because Takakuni, who was defeated at the Battle of Katsurakawara in 1527, escaped to Sakamoto, Omi Province with their treasure, Yoshiharu Shogun, got a toehold to establish a new government (Sakai Kubo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The team of Yoshitsuna and Harumoto (Sakai Kubo) got a toehold to establish a new government after their situation changed to their advantage since Takakuni was defeated at the battle of Katsuragawa in 1527, and escaped to Sakamoto, Omi Province with their valued person, Shogun Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>文章にカンマが多く、複雑に感じたので、直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The team of Yoshitsuna and Harumoto (Sakai Kubo) got a toehold to establish a new government after their situation changed to their advantage since Takakuni was defeated at the battle of Katsuragawa in 1527, and escaped to Sakamoto, Omi Province with their valued person, Shogun Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>堺公方の消滅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disappearance of Sakai Kubo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disappearance of Sakai Kubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disappearance of Sakai Kubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>挽回を期する管領・細川高国を摂津国にて撃破、自害にまで追い込んだ晴元であったが、この後は徐々に変心。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto, who had defeated Kanrei Takakuni HOSOKAWA aiming for regaining his power in Settsu Province and had forced Tatakuni to take a suicide, gradually changed his mind after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Harumoto had defeated Kanrei Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who tried to regain his power, at Setsu Province and forced Takakuni to commit suicide, he gradually started to change his mind after that.</e>
<cmt>文の構造が複雑に感じたので、直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Harumoto had defeated Kanrei Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who tried to regain his power, at Setsu Province and forced Takakuni to commit suicide, he gradually started to change his mind after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>空位となった管領の座に転がり込んだばかりか、突如として義維を棄て、義晴将軍を推戴する側に回ってしまったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto got the vacant position of Kanrei, and also he abandoned Yoshitsuna and stood on the side of being servile to Yoshiharu Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto got the vacant position of Kanrei, and also he abandoned Yoshitsuna and stood on the side of Shogun Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>of being servileを削りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto got the vacant position of Kanrei, and also he abandoned Yoshitsuna and stood on the side of Shogun Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかも、新管領・晴元は自らの保身に余念無く、それまで晴元軍の中核であった最有力被官・三好氏の弱体化を図り、和泉国の顕本寺 (堺市)を敵対宗派の一向一揆に襲わせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, new Kanrei Yoshimoto was absorbed in defensiveness, and he made Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers) of rival religion attack Kenpon-ji Temple in Izumi Province with an attempt to debilitate the Miyoshi clan which was the strongest hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Harumoto&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, new Kanrei Yoshimoto was absorbed in self-protection, and he made Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers) of rival religion attack Kenpon-ji Temple in Izumi Province with an attempt to debilitate the Miyoshi clan which was the strongest hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Harumoto&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>「しかも」は用語集に&quot;in addition&quot;とありましたが、この場合moreoverのほうが意味が近いと考え、訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, new Kanrei Yoshimoto was absorbed in self-protection, and he made Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers) of rival religion attack Kenpon-ji Temple in Izumi Province with an attempt to debilitate the Miyoshi clan which was the strongest hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Harumoto&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>顕本寺を根拠地としていた三好氏の総帥・三好元長は、義維を阿波国へ逃がし、自らは自害して果てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motonaga MIYOSHI, Sosui (commander-in-chief) of the Miyoshi clan setting up the base ground on Kenpon-ji Temple, let Yoshitsuna escape to Awa Province and killed himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motonaga MIYOSHI, Sosui (commander-in-chief) of the Miyoshi clan setting up the base ground on Kenpon-ji Temple, let Yoshitsuna escape to Awa Province and killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motonaga MIYOSHI, Sosui (commander-in-chief) of the Miyoshi clan setting up the base ground on Kenpon-ji Temple, let Yoshitsuna escape to Awa Province and killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>こうして、堺公方は消滅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Sakai Kubo was disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Sakai Kubo was disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Sakai Kubo was disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>将軍就任の夢を断たれた義維は、阿波平島で閉塞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsuna, who had his dream of assuming Shogun ended, was confined to Hirashima, Awa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsuna, who had his dream of assuming Shogun ended, was confined to Hirashima, Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsuna, who had his dream of assuming Shogun ended, was confined to Hirashima, Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>義維の血統が「平島公方」と呼ばれる起源となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the origin of the blood line of Yoshitsuna being called &apos;Hisashima Kubo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the origin of the blood line of Yoshitsuna being called &apos;Hirashima Kubo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>HisashimaをHirashimaに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the origin of the blood line of Yoshitsuna being called &apos;Hirashima Kubo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>義維から義栄へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Yoshitsuna to Yoshihide</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Yoshitsuna to Yoshihide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Yoshitsuna to Yoshihide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>元長の遺児・三好長慶は長い歳月をかけて亡父以上に勢力を伸ばすと、終には晴元を追い落とし、幕府の相伴衆に上り詰めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, a bereaved child of Motonaga, increased his power more than his dead father with a long time, and finally exceeded Harumoto and was promoted to Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun) of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, a bereaved child of Motonaga, increased his power more than his dead father&apos;s with a long time, and finally exceeded Harumoto and was promoted to Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun) of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>fatherをfather&apos;sにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, a bereaved child of Motonaga, increased his power more than his dead father&apos;s with a long time, and finally exceeded Harumoto and was promoted to Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun) of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>実質、幕政の中枢を握ったに等しい事態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In substance, he took the helm of state affairs of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In substance, he took the helm of state affairs of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In substance, he took the helm of state affairs of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>その間、平島公方の血統は三好氏の庇護を受け、いざと言う時の「切り札」として養われ続けていたとはいえ、将軍への道を拓かれずに過ごしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, the lineage of Hirashima Kubo was under the patronage of the Miyoshi clan and was sustained as &apos;chief card&apos; in the nick of time, but was passing the time without avenue for shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, the lineage of Hirashima Kubo was under the patronage of the Miyoshi clan and was sustained as &apos;chief card&apos; in the nick of time, but was passing the time without avenue for shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, the lineage of Hirashima Kubo was under the patronage of the Miyoshi clan and was sustained as &apos;chief card&apos; in the nick of time, but was passing the time without avenue for shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>やがて、長慶の死去に伴い、三好氏では三好三人衆による指導体制に移行されたが、幕政からの三好氏排除を目論む13代将軍・足利義輝への対応に苦慮するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, due to the death of Nagayoshi, the Miyoshi clan shifted their system to the leaderships by Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate), but they started to suffer through the correspondence to the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA who proposed exclusion of the Miyoshi clan from bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, due to the death of Nagayoshi, the Miyoshi clan shifted their system to the leaderships by Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate), but they started to suffer through the correspondence to the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA who proposed exclusion of the Miyoshi clan from bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, due to the death of Nagayoshi, the Miyoshi clan shifted their system to the leaderships by Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate), but they started to suffer through the correspondence to the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA who proposed exclusion of the Miyoshi clan from bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="27">
<j>困り果てた末に、永禄8年5月19日_(旧暦)（1565年6月17日）には二条城を襲撃、義輝将軍を弑逆するという暴挙に出た（永禄の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At their wits end, the Miyoshi clan attacked Nijo-jo Castle and perpetrated the tyranny of killing Yoshiteru Shogun on June 17, 1565 (Eiroku Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At their wits end, the Miyoshi clan attacked Nijo-jo Castle and kill their lord, Shogun Yoshiteru on June 27, 1565 (Eiroku Incident).</e>
<cmt>日付をグレゴリオ暦に直し、「弑逆するという暴挙」という部分を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At their wits end, the Miyoshi clan attacked Nijo-jo Castle and kill their lord, Shogun Yoshiteru on June 27, 1565 (Eiroku Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>将軍に退位を迫る事があっても、命を奪うまでの行為は言うなれば『禁じ手』であったが、平島公方の存在が実行に踏み切らせた一大事件でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though they would press Shogun for abdication, killing was &quot;prohibited strategy&quot; as it were, so it was a serious incident in which the existence of Hirahima Kubo let the Miyoshi clan move into the action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It sometimes happened to urge Shogun to abdicate, but killing Shogun was so-called &quot;prohibited strategy,&quot; so it can be said that it was a serious incident in which the existence of Hirashima Kubo let the Miyoshi clan move into the action.</e>
<cmt>前半部分を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It sometimes happened to urge Shogun to abdicate, but killing Shogun was so-called &quot;prohibited strategy,&quot; so it can be said that it was a serious incident in which the existence of Hirashima Kubo let the Miyoshi clan move into the action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>新将軍に迎えられるに当たって、堺公方消滅時には20歳余と若かった義維は既に60歳近くなっていたため除外され、その長子・足利義栄（左馬頭に叙任され、義栄へ改名）が擁立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hirashima Kubo was given a seat on new Shogun, Yoshitsuna, who was 20 years old at the time of disappearance of Sakai Kubo, was eliminated from the candidate because he was almost already 60 years old, and his son, Yoshihide ASHIKAGA (appointed as Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses) and changed his name to Yoshihide) was enthroned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hirashima Kubo was given a seat on new Shogun, Yoshitsuna, who was 20 years old at the time of disappearance of Sakai Kubo, was eliminated from the candidate because he was almost already 60 years old, and therefore, his son, Yoshichika ASHIKAGA (appointed as Sama no kami [Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses] and changed his name to Yoshihide) was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>ウェブ上では「その長子・足利義親」となっていたので、こちらに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hirashima Kubo was given a seat on new Shogun, Yoshitsuna, who was 20 years old at the time of disappearance of Sakai Kubo, was eliminated from the candidate because he was almost already 60 years old, and therefore, his son, Yoshichika ASHIKAGA (appointed as Sama no kami [Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses] and changed his name to Yoshihide) was enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ところが、三好三人衆が松永久秀との内部権力抗争に明け暮れ、義栄の将軍就任への働きを疎かにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate) was preoccupied with internal power struggles against Hisahide MATSUNAGA and ignored the action for Yoshihide&apos;s assumption to Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate) was preoccupied with internal power struggles against Hisahide MATSUNAGA and they didn&apos;t take any action for Yoshihide&apos;s assumption to Shogun.</e>
<cmt>おろそかにする、という部分を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate) was preoccupied with internal power struggles against Hisahide MATSUNAGA and they didn&apos;t take any action for Yoshihide&apos;s assumption to Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="31">
<j>結局、将軍に就けたのは永禄11年2月8日_(旧暦)（1568年3月16日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, it was on March 16, 1568 that Yoshihide became Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, it was on March 16, 1568 that Yoshihide became Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, it was on March 16, 1568 that Yoshihide became Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>前将軍・義輝襲撃から、2年半以上の歳月が流れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been two years since the attack to former Shogun Syoshiteru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been two years since the attack to former Shogun Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt>SyoshiteruをYoshiteruに直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been two years since the attack to former Shogun Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかもその間、義栄は入京さえ儘ならず、将軍宣下を受けても、なおも摂津国に留まり続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in the meantime, Yoshihide couldn&apos;t enter into Kyoto and stayed in Settsu Province after getting the Imperial proclamation to become Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in the meantime, Yoshihide couldn&apos;t enter into Kyoto and stayed in Settsu Province even after getting the Imperial proclamation to become Shogun.</e>
<cmt>Additionallyをmoreoverにし、evenを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in the meantime, Yoshihide couldn&apos;t enter into Kyoto and stayed in Settsu Province even after getting the Imperial proclamation to become Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>患っていた腫れ物を悪化させていた事も影響した、との説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that Yoshihide was getting worse his swelling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the fact that his tumor was getting worse affected his behavior.</e>
<cmt>上の文につながるように書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the fact that his tumor was getting worse affected his behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="35">
<j>しかも、将軍就任に向けて無駄に歳月を浪費した事態は、新体制を固めきれない三好政権には好ましくない結果をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Farther more, having spent time for assumption to Shogun brought undesirable result for the Miyoshi government which couldn&apos;t fix new system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, having wasted time for assumption to Shogun brought undesirable result for the Miyoshi government which couldn&apos;t fix new system.</e>
<cmt>Farther moreをFurthermoreにし、spentをwastedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, having wasted time for assumption to Shogun brought undesirable result for the Miyoshi government which couldn&apos;t fix new system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="36">
<j>同年9月、前将軍・義輝の実弟である足利義昭を推戴する織田信長が上洛軍を発したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the same year, Nobunaga ODA, who recommended Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, a younger brother of former Shogun Yoshiteru, as shogun, set Joraku army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October of the same year, Nobunaga ODA, who recommended Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, a younger brother of former Shogun Yoshiteru, as shogun, set the army heading for the capital.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。Joraku armyだとわかりづらいと判断し、&quot;Joraku&quot;を英語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October of the same year, Nobunaga ODA, who recommended Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, a younger brother of former Shogun Yoshiteru, as shogun, set the army heading for the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>近江国の六角氏を退けて進軍する織田氏とは、「義栄を戴いての決戦」を選択肢に残していた三好氏ではあったが、結局は阿波国への退避を選択した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan, who remained the option of &apos;the decisive battle with Yoshihide&apos; against the Oda clan advancing forward by avoiding the Rokkaku clan in Omi Province, finally selected the evacuation to Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miyoshi clan, who remained the option of &apos;the decisive battle with Yoshihide&apos; against the Oda clan advancing forward by avoiding the Rokkaku clan in Omi Province, finally selected the evacuation to Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan, who remained the option of &apos;the decisive battle with Yoshihide&apos; against the Oda clan advancing forward by avoiding the Rokkaku clan in Omi Province, finally selected the evacuation to Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>（義栄の病没により断念した可能性もある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(There is a possibility that they abandoned because of Yoshihide&apos;s death by disease.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(There is a possibility that they abandoned the battle because of Yoshihide&apos;s death by disease.)</e>
<cmt>abandonの目的語を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There is a possibility that they abandoned the battle because of Yoshihide&apos;s death by disease.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="39">
<j>その後も、織田氏への抵抗を幾度も示した三好氏ではあったが、戦局の悪化により畿内復権の道は閉ざされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Miyoshi clan showed the resistance to the Oda clan several times, but the load to reinstatement of Kinai region was closed due to the aggravation of the state of the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Miyoshi clan showed the resistance to the Oda clan several times, but the road to reinstatement of Kinai region was closed due to the aggravation of the state of the war.</e>
<cmt>loadをroadに書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Miyoshi clan showed the resistance to the Oda clan several times, but the road to reinstatement of Kinai region was closed due to the aggravation of the state of the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="40">
<j>義栄が死去しても、弟の足利義助によって家命は存続された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Yoshihide, the family was kept by his younger brother Yoshisuke ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Yoshihide, the family of Hirashima Kubo was kept by his younger brother Yoshisuke ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>the familyのあとに&quot;of Hirashima kubo&quot;を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Yoshihide, the family of Hirashima Kubo was kept by his younger brother Yoshisuke ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>だが、義昭政権の後ろ盾であった信長軍は三好氏が単体で退けるには強固であった点に加え、その後も没落していった三好氏との結びつきが余りにも強すぎた点を懸念されてか、平島公方は、その存在価値を次第に失っていったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in addition to the point that Nobunaga&apos;s army, which was the supporter of the Yoshiaki government, was too strong for the Miyoshi clan to avoid by themselves, there was fear that the relationship with the Miyoshi clan, who went to rack after that, was too close, so Hirashima Kubo gradually lost the existential value.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hirashima Kubo gradually lost the meaning of existence because not only was Nobunaga and his army, which was the supporter of the government led by Shogun Yoshiaki, too strong for the Miyoshi clan to stand down by themselves, but also there was the fear of the close-knit relationship between Hirashima Kubo and the Miyoshi clan, who went to rack after that.</e>
<cmt>not only, but alsoとしたほうが自然かと思い、書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hirashima Kubo gradually lost the meaning of existence because not only was Nobunaga and his army, which was the supporter of the government led by Shogun Yoshiaki, too strong for the Miyoshi clan to stand down by themselves, but also there was the fear of the close-knit relationship between Hirashima Kubo and the Miyoshi clan, who went to rack after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="42">
<j>織豊時代から江戸時代まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Shokuho Period (Oda-Toyotomi period) to the Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Shokuho Period (Oda-Toyotomi period) to the Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Shokuho Period (Oda-Toyotomi period) to the Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>織田信長に擁立された足利義昭とは対立関係にあった家系のため、安土桃山時代および江戸時代でも冷遇されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the family had adversary relationship with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who was fielded by Nobunaga Oda, they had been left in the cold in the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the family of Hirashima Kubo was in an adversary relationship with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who was supported by Nobunaga ODA, they had been treated coldly between the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>語句を少々変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the family of Hirashima Kubo was in an adversary relationship with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who was supported by Nobunaga ODA, they had been treated coldly between the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="44">
<j>江戸期以降では阿波徳島藩主・蜂須賀氏の客将として扱われたものの、その蜂須賀氏からは下級藩士並みの微禄しか受けられず、しかも足利氏の家名を平島氏に改姓させられるなどの一層の冷遇を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirashima Kubo was treated as Kyakusho (guest shogun) of the load of Awa Tokushima Domain, the Hachisuka clan, since the Edo period, however, they got nominal stipend as little as lower ranked feudal retainers from the Hachisuka clan, and also they were treated in bad way such as being changed their family name of Ashikaga to Hirashima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period, Hirashima Kubo was treated as Kyakusho (guest shogun) by the Hachisuka clan, the lord of Awa Tokushima Domain, but they were treated more coldly, such as getting nominal stipend as little as lower ranked feudal retainers from the Hachisuka clan, and being forced to change their family name from Ashikaga to Hirashima.</e>
<cmt>loadをlordに訂正しました。また、「下級藩士並みの微禄しか受けられず」という部分も「冷遇」の例示となるように文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period, Hirashima Kubo was treated as Kyakusho (guest shogun) by the Hachisuka clan, the lord of Awa Tokushima Domain, but they were treated more coldly, such as getting nominal stipend as little as lower ranked feudal retainers from the Hachisuka clan, and being forced to change their family name from Ashikaga to Hirashima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>同じ足利氏の後裔でも、大名・喜連川氏として存続できた鎌倉公方家の後裔とは対照的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite being a descendant of the Ashikaga clan, that is in contrast with the descendant of the Kamakura Kubo family who could endure as a daimyo Kitsuregawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, the descendant of the Kamakura Kubo could continue as the Kitsuregawa clan of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), though they were a descendant of the Ashikaga clan like Hirashima Kubo.</e>
<cmt>文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, the descendant of the Kamakura Kubo could continue as the Kitsuregawa clan of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), though they were a descendant of the Ashikaga clan like Hirashima Kubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="46">
<j>そのような不遇下でも、歴代当主の中には漢籍などに長けた者（義宜）などが多く、一大文化サロンのようなものを形成していたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such a misfortune, they have a lot of connoisseurs of Chinese classic books among the successive family heads such as Yoshinori, they established a kind of large cultural salon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though they were under such a misfortune, they have a lot of connoisseurs of Chinese classic books among the successive family heads including Yoshinori, and they used to establish a kind of large cultural salon.</e>
<cmt>上につながるよう文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though they were under such a misfortune, they have a lot of connoisseurs of Chinese classic books among the successive family heads including Yoshinori, and they used to establish a kind of large cultural salon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし文化_(元号)2年（1805年）、あまりの冷遇に耐えかねた9代足利義根は、遂に蜂須賀家から離反して阿波を去り、姓を足利に戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the ninth family head Yoshine ASHIKAGA, who couldn&apos;t stand for such a disfavor, finally broke away from the Hachisuka family and left from Awa, and changed their family name back to Ashikaga in 1805.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the ninth family head Yoshine ASHIKAGA, who couldn&apos;t stand for such a disfavor, finally broke away from the Hachisuka family and left from Awa, and changed their family name back to Ashikaga in 1805.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the ninth family head Yoshine ASHIKAGA, who couldn&apos;t stand for such a disfavor, finally broke away from the Hachisuka family and left from Awa, and changed their family name back to Ashikaga in 1805.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>その後は京都に居を定め、等持院など足利氏ゆかりの寺院からの援助で細々と食いつないでいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that they had lived in Kyoto, and earned a sparse living as being supported from temples associated with the Ashikaga clan such as Tojiin Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that they lived in Kyoto, and earned a sparse living as being supported from temples associated with the Ashikaga clan including Toji-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>語句を少々変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that they lived in Kyoto, and earned a sparse living as being supported from temples associated with the Ashikaga clan including Toji-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="49">
<j>平島在所時代の墓所は、西光寺（阿南市那賀川町）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The graveyard at the time of living in Hirashima located in Saiko-ji Temple (Nakagawacho, Anan City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The graveyard at the time of living in Hirashima located in Saiko-ji Temple (Nakagawa-cho, Anan City)</e>
<cmt>NakagawachoをNakagawa-choとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The graveyard at the time of living in Hirashima located in Saiko-ji Temple (Nakagawa-cho, Anan City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="50">
<j>明治以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>明治後、足利将軍家の正当な末裔として爵位を求めたが、領地であった阿波から離脱していたなどの理由をもって却下されたうえ士族にさえ成れず、平民身分とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They required a peerage as legitimate descendant of the Ashikaga Shogun Family, but it was rejected and also they couldn&apos;t become Shizoku (warrior class) but were given the social status of Heimin (commoner) because of the reasons such as having left from Awa where had been their territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji Period, they required a peerage as legitimate descendant of the Ashikaga Shogun Family, but not only was it rejected but also they couldn&apos;t become even a Shizoku (warrior class), namely, their social status was just a Heimin (commoner) because they left Awa which had been their territory.</e>
<cmt>「明治後」という部分を英訳に加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, they required a peerage as legitimate descendant of the Ashikaga Shogun Family, but not only was it rejected but also they couldn&apos;t become even a Shizoku (warrior class), namely, their social status was just a Heimin (commoner) because they left Awa which had been their territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="52">
<j>ただ、その足利家の直系として扱われていた喜連川氏が、養子を受け入れて存続していることに対し（傍系細川氏からの養子縁組）、初代源義康からの血を絶やさず受け継いでいるのは、この平島公方家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the Kitsuregawa clan, who was treated as direct line of the Ashikaga family, had accepted a adopted child (adoption with a collateral line, the Hosokawa clan), it is the Hirashima Kubo family that derived the blood from the first family load MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Kitsuregawa clan, who was treated as direct line of the Ashikaga family, had accepted adopted children (adoption from the Hosokawa clan, their collateral line) to have them succeed to the family, whereas the Hirashima Kubo family was directly descended from the first family lord MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu.</e>
<cmt>whereasを用いて対比の形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Kitsuregawa clan, who was treated as direct line of the Ashikaga family, had accepted adopted children (adoption from the Hosokawa clan, their collateral line) to have them succeed to the family, whereas the Hirashima Kubo family was directly descended from the first family lord MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="53">
<j>歴代平島公方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive Hirashima Kubo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive Hirashima Kubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive Hirashima Kubo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>足利義維（よしふね、別名　義維）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshifuna ASHIKAGA (another name, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA)</e>
<cmt>原文は、「利義冬（よしふね、別名　義維）」のようです。 http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%B9%B3%E5%B3%B6%E5%85%AC%E6%96%B9</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshifune ASHIKAGA (another name, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA)</e>
<cmt>YoshifunaをYoshifuneにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshifune ASHIKAGA (another name, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>足利義助（義栄の弟）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshisuke ASHIKAGA (a younger brother of Yoshihide)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshisuke ASHIKAGA (the younger brother of Yoshihide)</e>
<cmt>aをtheにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshisuke ASHIKAGA (the younger brother of Yoshihide)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>足利義種</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikazu/Yoshitane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikazu (Yoshitane) ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>/を()にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikazu (Yoshitane) ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>平島義次通称又八郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsugu HIRASHIMA a.k.a. Matahachiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsugu HIRASHIMA a.k.a. Matahachiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsugu HIRASHIMA, also known as Matahachiro</e>
<cmt>a.k.a をスペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>平島義景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikage HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikage HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikage HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>平島義辰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitatsu HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitatsu HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitatsu HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>平島義武通称熊八郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitake HIRASHIMA a.k.a Kumahachiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitake HIRASHIMA a.k.a Kumahachiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitake HIRASHIMA a.k.a Kumahachiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>平島義宜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinori HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinori HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinori HIRASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>足利義根　文化 (元号)2年（1805年）に京都へ移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshine ASHIKAGA moved to Kyoto in 1805</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshine ASHIKAGA moved to Kyoto in 1805</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshine ASHIKAGA moved to Kyoto in 1805</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="63">
<j>足利義俊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>足利義孝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>足利義廉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>義廉：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>足利進悟 （1908年 - 2003年）前全国足利氏ゆかりの会特別顧問</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingo ASHIKAGA (1908 - 2003), the former special adviser of Zenkoku Ashikagashi Yukari no Kai (national association of the Ashikaga clan)</e>
<cmt>進悟：読み方不明です。全国足利氏ゆかりの会：定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingo ASHIKAGA (1908 - 2003), the former special adviser of Zenkoku Ashikagashi Yukari no Kai (national association of the Ashikaga clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingo ASHIKAGA (1908 - 2003), the former special adviser of Zenkoku Ashikagashi Yukari no Kai (national association of the Ashikaga clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>足利義弘（現当主）現特別顧問　創造学園大学教授</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro ASHIKAGA (the present head of the family), the present special adviser of Zenkoku Ashikagashi Yukari no Kai, professor of University of creation; Art, Music &amp; Social Work</e>
<cmt>足利義弘（現当主）現全国足利氏ゆかりの会特別顧問　創造学園大学教授 http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%B9%B3%E5%B3%B6%E5%85%AC%E6%96%B9</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro ASHIKAGA (the present head of the family), the present special adviser of Zenkoku Ashikagashi Yukari no Kai, professor of Sozo Gakuen University (University of Creation; Art, Music &amp; Social Work).</e>
<cmt>「創造学園大学」のウェブサイトでは&quot;Sozo Gakuen University&quot;となっていたので、そちらを採用し、英訳（ウィキペディアによる）はカッコでくくりました。http://english.souzou.ac.jp/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro ASHIKAGA (the present head of the family), the present special adviser of Zenkoku Ashikagashi Yukari no Kai, professor of Sozo Gakuen University (University of Creation; Art, Music &amp; Social Work).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="68">
<j>足利家文書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashikagake Monjo (written material of the Ashikaga family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashikaga-ke Monjo (written materials of the Ashikaga family)</e>
<cmt>Ashikagakeをハイフンで区切り、materialを複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashikaga-ke Monjo (written materials of the Ashikaga family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>平島公方家に伝えられた中世・近世文書群である「阿波足利家文書」は、徳島県旧那賀川町で町史編纂にあたり調査が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awa Ashikagake Monjo&apos; (written material of the Awa-Ashikaga family), which is the written materials of the Medieval period and modern times passed down in the Hirashima Kubo family, was investigated by former Nakagawamachi, Tokushima Prefecture for compiling the town history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Awa Ashikaga-ke Monjo&quot; (the written materials of the Awa-Ashikaga family), which is the records of the Medieval period and modern times passed down in the Hirashima Kubo family, was investigated in former Nakagawa-cho, Tokushima Prefecture for compiling the town history.</e>
<cmt>旧那賀川町は「なかがわちょう」と読むようです。http://search.post.japanpost.jp/cgi-zip/zipcode.php?pref=36&amp;city=1363611</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Awa Ashikaga-ke Monjo&quot; (the written materials of the Awa-Ashikaga family), which is the records of the Medieval period and modern times passed down in the Hirashima Kubo family, was investigated in former Nakagawa-cho, Tokushima Prefecture for compiling the town history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>現在その一部は阿南市立阿波公方・民俗資料館に寄託され、常設展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now the part of the materials contributed to Anan Municipal Awakubo Minzoku Siryokan Museum, and it is held regular exhibitions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now the part of the materials contributed to Awa Kubo Minzoku Siryokan (Folk Museum of Awa Kubo) in Anan City, and it is permanent exhibition.</e>
<cmt>「阿南市立阿波公方・民俗資料館」の定訳なしです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now the part of the materials contributed to Awa Kubo Minzoku Siryokan (Folk Museum of Awa Kubo) in Anan City, and it is permanent exhibition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 瑞雲(id:27410), 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), 松茸(id:27535), Faso(id:11300), こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), Brownsugar(id:20678), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>