<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>多田仁綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noritsuna TADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noritsuna TADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noritsuna TADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>多田 仁綱（ただ のりつな、生年不詳 - 天福 (日本)2年6月14日 (旧暦)（1234年7月11日））は、鎌倉時代初期の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noritsuna TADA (year of birth unknown - July 11, 1234) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noritsuna TADA (year of birth unknown - July 11, 1234) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noritsuna TADA (year of birth unknown - July 11, 1234) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>摂津国の出身で、多田氏（摂津源氏）の一族とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Settsu Province and belonged to a family of the Tada clan (Settsu-Genji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Settsu Province and belonged to a family of the Tada clan (Settsu-Genji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Settsu Province and belonged to a family of the Tada clan (Settsu-Genji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>娘は大江広元室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter was wife of OE no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt>大江広元室はwife of OE no Hiromotoと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter was wife of OE no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter was wife of OE no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大江親広の外祖父にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a maternal grandfather of OE no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a maternal grandfather of OE no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a maternal grandfather of OE no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>文治5年（1189年）に大江広元が出羽国寒河江荘の地頭に任じられた際、広元の目代として寒河江に下向し同荘本楯（現在の山形県寒河江市本楯）、次いで吉川（同西村山郡西川町大字吉川）に居館を構えて統治にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When OE no Hiromoto was assigned to Jito (manager and lord of manor) in Sagae no so, Dewa Province, he left the capital for Sagae as mokudai (deputy) of Hiromoto and lived in Doso Mototate (present Mototate, Sagae City, Yamagata Prefecture) then in Yoshikawa (Oaza Yoshikawa, Nishikawa-machi, Nishimurayama-gun) for ruling.</e>
<cmt>同荘本楯はDoso Mototateとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When OE no Hiromoto was assigned to Jito (manager and lord of manor) in Sagae no so, Dewa Province, he left the capital for Sagae as mokudai (deputy) of Hiromoto and lived in Doso Mototate (present Mototate, Sagae City, Yamagata Prefecture) then in Yoshikawa (Oaza Yoshikawa, Nishikawa-machi, Nishimurayama-gun), to rule respective lands.</e>
<cmt>文末の for ruling.を、, to rule respective lands. と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When OE no Hiromoto was assigned to Jito (manager and lord of manor) in Sagae no so, Dewa Province, he left the capital for Sagae as mokudai (deputy) of Hiromoto and lived in Doso Mototate (present Mototate, Sagae City, Yamagata Prefecture) then in Yoshikawa (Oaza Yoshikawa, Nishikawa-machi, Nishimurayama-gun), to rule respective lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、承久の乱で京方に与して敗れた孫の親広が寒河江に落ち延びると、これを吉川の館に匿い保護したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his grandchild Chikahiro defeated on the Kyoto side in the Jokyu war and escaped to Sagae, he was sheltered and protected in the Yoshikawa&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he sheltered and protected his grandchild Chikahiro who sided with Kyoto, in his house at Yoshikawa, as Chikahiro lost in Jokyu war and escaped to Sagae.</e>
<cmt>文と「he」が誰を指すのかが分かりにくいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he sheltered and protected his grandchild Chikahiro who sided with Kyoto, in his house at Yoshikawa, as Chikahiro lost in Jokyu war and escaped to Sagae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>嘉禄元年（1225年）に広元が死去すると、父の死を悼んだ親広は吉川の館内に阿弥陀堂を建立し広元の遺骨を源満仲の念持仏と共に祀ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hiromoto died in 1225, Chikahiro who grieved over the death of his father built an Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) in the residence in Yoshikawa, enshrined the remains of Hiromoto with nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka, Nishitsuna entered into priesthood, called himself Genyu SHOA, and served as betto (administrator of a Buddhist temple) of this hall.</e>
<cmt>正阿源宥はGenyu SHOAとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hiromoto died in 1225, Chikahiro who grieved over the death of his father built an Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) in the residence of Yoshikawa, and enshrined the remains of Hiromoto with nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処the residence in Yoshikawa　をthe residence of Yoshikawa　と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hiromoto died in 1225, Chikahiro who grieved over the death of his father built an Amida-do Hall (temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) in the residence of Yoshikawa, and enshrined the remains of Hiromoto with nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仁綱も間もなく出家して正阿源宥と号し、この堂の別当を務めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after that Nishitsuna entered into priesthood, calling himself Genyu SHOA and served as betto (administrator of a Buddhist temple) of this hall.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処Soon after that からはじめ（「間もなく」）、called himselfからcalling himselfと変更しました（箇条書きのようになってしまうため）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after that Nishitsuna entered into priesthood, calling himself Genyu SHOA and served as betto (administrator of a Buddhist temple) of this hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>阿弥陀堂は仁治2年（1241年）に吉川館の鬼門とされる位置に移築され近世に至るまで存続したが明治維新後に解体となり、現在は跡地に親広と仁綱の墓が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amida-do Hall was moved to a position in the northeastern (unlucky) direction from the Yoshikawa residence in 1241 and survived until modern times, but was dismantled after Meiji Restoration and the graves of Chikahiro and Noritsuna new remain at the site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amida-do Hall was moved to kimon (&apos;demon&apos;s gate&apos;; the northeast of one&apos;s position, superstitiously believed to be unlucky) of the Yoshikawa residence in 1241, and continued until modern times, but was dismantled after Meiji Restoration and the graves of Chikahiro and Noritsuna now remain at the site.</e>
<cmt>「とされる位置」を「a position in」としていますが、特に必要ありません。「鬼門」を「kimon (&apos;demon&apos;s gate&apos;; the northeast of one&apos;s position, superstitiously believed to be unlucky)」と変更しました。Survivedをcontinuedと変更しました。New remainをnow remainの間違いであると思われるので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amida-do Hall was moved to kimon (&apos;demon&apos;s gate&apos;; the northeast of one&apos;s position, superstitiously believed to be unlucky) of the Yoshikawa residence in 1241, and continued until modern times, but was dismantled after Meiji Restoration and the graves of Chikahiro and Noritsuna now remain at the site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>