<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長尾景茂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagemochi NAGAO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagemochi NAGAO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagemochi NAGAO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長尾景茂（ながお かげもち）は鎌倉時代の相模国の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagemochi Nagao was a warrior of Sgami Province during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagemochi Nagao was a warrior of Sgami Province during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagemochi Nagao was a warrior of Sgami Province during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>公暁を討った長尾定景の嫡男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagemochi NAGAO was born as a legitimate son of Sadakage NAGAO, who had defeated Kugyo (the assassin of MONAMOTO no Sanetomo, the third shogun of the Kamakura shogunate).</e>
<cmt>公暁→（the assassin of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the third shogun of the Kamakura shogunate)を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagemochi NAGAO was born as a legitimate son of Sadakage NAGAO, who had defeated Kugyo (the assassin of MONAMOTO no Sanetomo, the third shogun of the Kamakura shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagemochi NAGAO was born as a legitimate son of Sadakage NAGAO, who had defeated Kugyo (the assassin of MONAMOTO no Sanetomo, the third shogun of the Kamakura shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>長尾家は当時三浦氏の郎党であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, the Nagao family was roto (originally signified warriors who had no blood ties to the band they joined) of the Miura clan (powerful Kamakura period warrior family of Sagami Province).</e>
<cmt>三浦氏→(powerful Kamakura period warrior family of Sagami Province) を補足しました/ C列のvassels→vassalsのスペルミスだと思われます/郎党→(originally signified warriors who had no blood ties to the band they joined)を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, the Nagao family was roto (originally signified warriors who had no blood ties to the band they joined) of the Miura clan (powerful Kamakura period warrior family of Sagami Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, the Nagao family was roto (originally signified warriors who had no blood ties to the band they joined) of the Miura clan (powerful Kamakura period warrior family of Sagami Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三浦氏は北条氏の外戚として勢威を振るっていたが、新たな北条家外戚となった安達氏との対立が激化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miura clan, enjoying its political dominance by taking advantage of being the maternal relatives of the Hojo clan (warrior family of the Kamakura period, hereditary regents of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feaudal government headed by a shogun), came into severe conflict with the Adachi clan, newly being maternal relatives of the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miura clan, enjoying its political dominance by taking advantage of being the maternal relatives of the Hojo clan (warrior family of the Kamakura period, hereditary regents of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), came into severe conflict with the Adachi clan, which also became the new maternal relatives of the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt>「newly being maternal relatives」の「being」は不自然に感じました。三浦氏と共に外戚となった、という意味を強調する意味で修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miura clan, enjoying its political dominance by taking advantage of being the maternal relatives of the Hojo clan (warrior family of the Kamakura period, hereditary regents of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), came into severe conflict with the Adachi clan, which also became the new maternal relatives of the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>宝治元年（1247年）、安達氏の後押しを得た執権・北条時頼は鎌倉で挙兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1247, Tokiyori HOJO took up arms with the aids of the Adachi clan in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストでは「挙兵する」→take up armsとなっており、そちらに準じました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1247, Tokiyori HOJO took up arms with the aids of the Adachi clan in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1247, Tokiyori HOJO took up arms with the aids of the Adachi clan in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>三浦一族とそれに味方する武士を族滅（宝治合戦）し、景茂らも自刃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiyori destroyed the entire Miura family and the warriors who sided with that family (called the Battle of Hoji), so that Kagemochi and his warriors committed suicide with their sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiyori destroyed the entire Miura family and the warriors who sided with that family (called the Battle of Hoji), and Kagemochi and his warriors committed suicide with their sword.</e>
<cmt>「so that」の用法が「so」などと同様の意味で用いられていますが、文法的には別の意味を表します。間違いではないようにも思いますが、この部分のせいで意味がよくわからなくなるため、単純な形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiyori destroyed the entire Miura family and the warriors who sided with that family (called the Battle of Hoji), and Kagemochi and his warriors committed suicide with their sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長尾一族はほとんど絶え、生き残りは景茂の子である長尾景忠など、わずかであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bottle of Hoji resulted in the death of almost every Nagao family member, who fought on the losing side, but it is said that there were only a few survivors of the Nagao family, such as a child of Kagemochi, Kagetada NAGAO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bottle of Hoji resulted in the death of almost all Nagao family members who fought in the battle, and it is considered there were only a few survivors of the Nagao family including Kagetada NAGAO, the child of Kagemochi.</e>
<cmt>英文で「but」を用いて二文を接続していますが、内容的に「but」で否定されるものではないと思います。できるだけ修正しないように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bottle of Hoji resulted in the death of almost all Nagao family members who fought in the battle, and it is considered there were only a few survivors of the Nagao family including Kagetada NAGAO, the child of Kagemochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>のちに長尾氏が上杉氏に使え始めたのは長尾基景や長尾景為の時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Time passing on, it was the time of 基景 NAGAO and Kagetame NAGAO when the Nagao clan served the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>基景→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagao clan began to serve the Uesugi clan around the time of Motokage NAGAO and Kagetame NAGAO.</e>
<cmt>推定ですが、「もとかげ」としました。文章を単純化しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagao clan began to serve the Uesugi clan around the time of Motokage NAGAO and Kagetame NAGAO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 出羽卒族(id:283926), 秋田城之介(id:95273), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>