<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>沖田総司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soji OKITA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soji OKITA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soji OKITA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>沖田 総司（おきた そうじ、天保13年（1842年）又は15年（1844年）夏の日 - 慶応4年5月30日 (旧暦)（1868年7月19日））（生年については2つの説があり、どちらも決定的な否定史料が見つかっていない。また、生誕時の月日に関しては特定できる史料が一切出ておらず、夏であったということしか分かっていない）は、江戸時代後期、幕末の新選組の隊士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soji OKITA (a certain day in 1842 or 1844 summer-July 19, 1868) was a member of Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) at the end of Edo Period (there are two traditions about the year of his birth, but no decisive historical materials of denying them have been found. Also, no historical materials to determine his birth date has been confirmed, and all what has been known was he was born in summer.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soji OKITA (summer, 1842 or 1844 - July 19, 1868) was a member of the Shinsengumi, a special police force in Kyoto, at the end of Edo Period (there are two theories about the year of his birth, but no decisive historical materials against either of them have been found. Also, no historical materials confirming his birth date have ever been identified, and all that is known is that he was born in summer).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soji OKITA (summer, 1842 or 1844 - July 19, 1868) was a member of the Shinsengumi, a special police force in Kyoto, at the end of Edo period (there are two theories about the year of his birth, but no decisive historical materials against either of them have been found. Also, no historical materials confirming his birth date have ever been identified, and all that is known is that he was born in summer).</e>
<cmt>用語統一セル5の文（）内の一部をセル４に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>副長助勤、一番隊組長、剣術師範。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukucho-jokin (third-rank of Shinsengumi,) leader of Ichibangumi and a master of swordplay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the Assistant Vice Commander, captain of the First Corps and a master of kenjutsu sword fighting.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the Assistant Vice Commander, captain of the First Corps and a master of kenjutsu sword fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は藤原を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real family name was Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real family name was Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real family name was Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>諱は春政、後に房良に。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Imina was Harumasa and later, Kaneyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Imina (original name) was Harumasa and later, Kaneyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Imina (original name) was Harumasa and later, Kaneyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幼名は宗次郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Sojiro in his childhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Sojiro.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Sojiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>父は陸奥国白河藩士の沖田勝次郎で長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Katsujiro OKITA, a clansman of the Shirakawa Domain, Mutsu Province, and Soji OKITA was the oldest son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of Katsujiro OKITA, a clansman of Shirakawa Domain in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Katsujiro OKITA, a clansman of Shirakawa Domain in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>2人の姉がおり、沖田家は姉の沖田みつが婿の沖田林太郎を迎えて相続させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had two older sisters, one of whom Mitsu OKITA got married with Rintaro OKITA to take over Okita family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had two older sisters, one of whom, Mitsu OKITA, married Rintaro OKITA, making him the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had two older sisters, one of whom, Mitsu OKITA, married Rintaro OKITA, making him the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>みつの曾孫の沖田哲也（1930年 -）は行政学者で明治大学政経学部名誉教授。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsu&apos;s great grand son Tetsuya OKITA (1930-) is a scholar of public administration and an emeritus professor of the department of politics and economics in Meiji University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsu&apos;s great grand son Tetsuya OKITA (1930-) is a scholar of public administration and an emeritus professor of the department of politics and economics at Meiji University.</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsu&apos;s great grand son Tetsuya OKITA (1930-) is a scholar of public administration and an emeritus professor of the department of politics and economics at Meiji University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸、白河藩屋敷（東京都港区）で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Shirakawa Domain residence in Edo (Minato Ward, Tokyo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Shirakawa Domain&apos;s Edo residence (Minato Ward, Tokyo.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Shirakawa Domain&apos;s Edo residence (Minato Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動 (東京都)原文から削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>父の勝次郎は4歳のときに死去し、母とも死別したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Katsujiro died when he was four years old, and it is thought that his mother died, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Katsujiro died when he was four years old, and it is thought that his mother also died when he was young.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Katsujiro died when he was four years old, and it is thought that his mother also died when he was young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>9歳頃に、江戸市谷に天然理心流の道場を開く近藤周三の内弟子となり、試衛館にて後に新選組結成の中核となる近藤勇、土方歳三らと同門になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of about nine, he was apprenticed to Shuzo KONDO who had a training hall of Tennenrishinryu in Ichigaya, Edo, and met Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA as a member of the training hall at Shieikan training hall, who would be central to the formation of Shinsengumi in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of about nine, he was apprenticed to Shuzo KONDO, who taught the Tennen Rishin-ryu style of martial arts at a dojo in Ichigaya, Edo, and it was here at the Shieikan dojo that he met fellow students Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA, who would later be central in the formation of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of about nine, he was apprenticed to Shuzo KONDO, who taught the Tennen Rishin-ryu style of martial arts at a dojo in Ichigaya, Edo, and it was here at the Shieikan dojo that he met fellow students Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA, who would later be central in the formation of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>若くして天然理心流塾頭を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as the school manager of Tennenrishinryu at his young age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though he was young, he served as the school manager of Tennenrishinryu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though he was young, he served as the school manager of Tennenrishinryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>沖田は無類の天才剣士であったと言われるが、江戸の頃の教え方はかなり荒っぽいものであったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that Okita was an incomparable swordsman genius and that the way of his teaching in Edo was considerably harsh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okita&apos;s genius with the sword is said to have been unequalled although his teaching style was rather rough.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okita&apos;s genius with the sword is said to have been unequalled although his teaching style was rather rough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後年になると穏やかな教え方へと変化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in his life, the way of his teaching was changed to the genial or moderate one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in his life, he softened his teaching style.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in his life, he softened his teaching style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>文久3年（1863年）の浪士組結成に参加して上洛、分裂後は近藤らに従い残留し、新選組を結成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the formation of the Roshi-gumi (an organization of masterless samurai) in 1863, he joined the group and left for Kyoto, and after the group was split, he remained with Kondo and formed Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined the Roshigumi (an organization of masterless samurai) upon its formation in 1863 and left for Kyoto, remaining there with Kondo and forming the Shinsengumi after the group split.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined the Roshigumi (an organization of masterless samurai) upon its formation in 1863 and left for Kyoto, remaining there with Kondo and forming the Shinsengumi after the group split.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>沖田の一番隊は常に重要な任務をこなし、剣豪ひしめく新選組の中でも一、二を争う程多くの人を斬ったと言われ、この時期では9月の芹沢鴨暗殺、内山彦次郎暗殺など手がけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichibantai (the first squad) to which Okita belonged played an important role all the time, and is thought to have killed many people as if they were the best in Shinsengumi with a lot of great swordsmen, and assassinated Kamo SERIZAWA and Hikojiro UCHIYAMA in September of that period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okita&apos;s First Corps was constantly tasked with important missions and, though the Shinsengumi was filled with expert swordsmen, often had the most number of kills, and was involved in the assassinations of Kamo SERIZAWA and Hikojiro UCHIYAMA in September, 1863.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity*As the translator changed the dates from the lunar calendar in cell D27, I wonder if &apos;October&apos; would be better than &apos;September&apos; here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okita&apos;s First Corps was constantly tasked with important missions and, although the Shinsengumi was filled with expert swordsmen, often had the most number of kills, and was involved in the assassinations of Kamo SERIZAWA and Hikojiro UCHIYAMA in October, 1863.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にthough →although</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>沖田が人を斬ったことを記す初めての記録は文久3年3月24日 (旧暦)の夜。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the record, when he put a person to the sward for the first time was the evening on May 11, 1863.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は全て新暦に変換しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okita&apos;s first recorded kill was on the evening of May 11, 1863.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okita&apos;s first recorded kill was on the evening of May 11, 1863.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>清河八郎の呼びかけに集まった浪士組の一番組に在籍していた殿内義雄だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Yoshio TONOUCHI who appeared at the call of Hachiro KIYOKAWA and he was a member of the Ichiban-gumi, Roshi-gumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His opponent was Yoshio TONOUCHI, a member of the Roshigumi&apos;s First Unit, who had come at Hachiro KIYOKAWA&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His opponent was Yoshio TONOUCHI, a member of the Roshigumi&apos;s First Unit, who had come at Hachiro KIYOKAWA&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>元治元年（1864年）6月5日 (旧暦)の池田屋事件で、討幕派数人を切り伏せ活躍したものの、直後に肺結核により喀血して倒れる（諸説あり）とされていたが、その後の新選組史において依然として活躍していることから、この日に肺結核が発症したとは考えにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that after he was active to attack and fight with some of the anti-Shogunate group in Ikedaya Incident on July 8, 1864, he fell down from hemoptysis in lung tuberculosis (there are other traditions,) but based on the subsequent Shinsengumi history, he continued to be active, and it is unreasonable to think that he developed lung tuberculosis on that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Ikedaya Incident of July 8, 1864, where he was involved in the killings of several members of the anti-Shogunate faction, he collapsed after coughing up blood from tuberculosis (according to many theories) but based on his subsequent involvement in the Shinsengumi, it is unreasonable to think that he developed lung tuberculosis on that day.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Ikedaya Incident of July 8, 1864, where he was involved in the killings of several members of the anti-Shogunate faction, he collapsed after coughing up blood from tuberculosis (according to many theories) but based on his subsequent involvement in the Shinsengumi, it is unreasonable to think that he developed lung tuberculosis on that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため熱中病により倒れたとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, there is a thought that he got sick from heat collapse, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, there is a theory that he collapsed from heat stroke.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, there is a theory that he collapsed from heat stroke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>慶応元年（1865年）2月、総長の山南敬助が脱走した事件では、追っ手として差し向けられ近江国草津市で捕らえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1865, he was directed to seize Keisuke YAMANAMI who was the general and ran away and caught him in Kusatsu City, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1865, he was sent after Shinsengumi Vice Commander Keisuke YAMANAMI, who had attempted to desert, and arrested him in Kusatsu City, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1865, he was sent after Shinsengumi Vice Commander Keisuke YAMANAMI, who had attempted to desert, and arrested him in Kusatsu City, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>山南は沖田の介錯で切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamanami committed seppuku with Kaisaku by Okita (assisting someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamanami committed suicide assisted by Okita.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamanami committed suicide assisted by Okita.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>沖田は山南を兄のように慕っていたとされるが、故郷への手紙では山南の死に関して軽く触れるに留められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Okita seemed to be fond of Yamanami as if he was his older brother, Okita only touched upon Yamanami&apos;s death in his letter sent to Okita&apos;s old home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Okita seemed to regard Yamanami as an older brother, he barely touched upon Yamanami&apos;s death in a letter he sent home.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Okita seemed to regard Yamanami as an older brother, he barely touched upon Yamanami&apos;s death in a letter he sent home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>第一線で活躍することがなくなるのは慶応3年（1867年）以降で、鳥羽伏見の戦いは参戦できず大阪に護送される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time he continued to be active in the front lines was until 1867, and then, he was escorted to Osaka without joining the Battle of Toba-Fushimi (At present, the tradition that he got injured on his way to the Battle of Toba-Fushimi and developed lung tuberculosis in a boat where he was escorted to Osaka is more solid.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active on the front lines until 1867, after which, unable to take part in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, he was escorted to Osaka (the most widely-accepted theory at present is that he was injured on his way to the Battle of Toba-Fushimi and developed tuberculosis on the boat he was being escorted to Osaka on).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active on the front lines until 1867, after which, unable to take part in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, he was escorted to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>（現在は、鳥羽伏見の戦いに向かう間に負傷し、大阪に護送される船中において肺結核を患ったとする説が有力である。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The most widely-accepted theory at present is that he was injured on his way to the Battle of Toba-Fushimi and developed tuberculosis on the boat he was being escorted to Osaka on.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>鳥羽伏見の敗戦後、隊士と共に海路江戸へ戻り、甲陽鎮撫隊に参加する（諸説あり）も中途での落伍を余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they lost the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, he was back to Edo by sea with other members, and though he joined Koyo Chinbutai (there are other traditions,) he was forced to drop out halfway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After defeat at the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, he sailed back to Edo with other members and though according to several theories he joined the Koyo Chinbutai (the successor to the Shinsengumi), he was forced to drop out halfway.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After defeat at the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, he sailed back to Edo with other members and although according to several theories he joined the Koyo Chinbutai (the successor to the Shinsengumi), he was forced to drop out halfway.</e>
<cmt>though →although</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>以後は幕臣の松本良順により千駄ヶ谷の植木屋に匿われたとされ、慶応4年（1868年）に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it is thought that Shogun&apos;s retainer Ryojun MATSUMOTO made arrangements for him to hide in a plant shop in Sendagaya, and Okita died in 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, it is thought that Ryojun MATSUMOTO, a retainer of the Shogun, made arrangements for him to hide in a plant shop in Sendagaya, where he died in 1868.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, it is thought that Ryojun MATSUMOTO, a retainer of the Shogun, made arrangements for him to hide in a plant shop in Sendagaya, where he died in 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>生年が明確で無いため享年については諸説あり、25～27と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his birth date is uncertain, there are several views of it, but he is believed to have died at the age of twenty five, twenty six or twenty seven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since his date of birth is uncertain, there are several opinions about how old he was when he died, but he is believed to have been between twenty-five and twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since his date of birth is uncertain, there are several opinions about how old he was when he died, but he is believed to have been between twenty-five and twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>慶応3年12月18日 (旧暦)、沖田が療養のため滞在していた近藤の妾宅を、元御陵衛士・阿部十郎、佐原太郎、内海次郎の3人が襲撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was recuperating at the house of Kondo&apos;s mistress on January 12, 1868, three former Goryo-eji (guards of Imperial mausoleums) Juro ABE, Taro SAHARA and Jiro UTSUMI attacked him in the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of their attack was to avenge the murder of their leader, Kashitaro ITO, by the Shinsengumi the previous month, but Okita had left for the Fushimi Magistrate&apos;s office and therefore escaped the attempt.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of their attack was to avenge the murder of their leader, Kashitaro ITO, by the Shinsengumi the previous month, but Okita had left for the Fushimi Magistrate&apos;s office and therefore escaped the attempt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>前月に彼らの指導的立場であった伊東甲子太郎を殺害した新選組への報復として狙われたものだが、沖田は伏見奉行所へと出立した後で難を逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose of their attack was to seek revenge for the murder of Kashitaro ITO as their leader by Shinsengumi in the previous month, but he left for Fushimi Magistrate&apos;s office and could escape from the attempt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the evening of the same day, Isami KONDO was shot and injured by Abe and the others on his way back from Nijo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the evening of the same day, Isami KONDO was shot and injured by Abe and the others on his way back from Nijo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>同日夕刻、阿部らは二条城から戻る途中の近藤勇を銃撃、負傷させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the evening on the same day, Isami KONDO was shot and got injured by Abe and other members when he was back from Nijo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the evening on the same day, Isami KONDO was shot and got injured by Abe and other members when he was back from Nijo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the evening on the same day, Isami KONDO was shot and got injured by Abe and other members when he was back from Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>近藤勇斬首から2ヶ月後、近藤勇の死も知らずに亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two months after Isami KONDO was beheaded, he died without knowing Isami KONDO&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two months after Isami KONDO was beheaded, Okita died, unaware of KONDO&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two months after Isami KONDO was beheaded, Okita died, unaware of KONDO&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>辞世の句は「動かねば闇にへだつや花と水」とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A poem he read at the time of his death was &apos;動かねば闇にへだつや花と水.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poem he composed on his deathbed reads &apos;In the dark, flowers and water cannot be discerned unless they move&apos;</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - translated poem but not sure how accurate it is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poem he composed on his deathbed reads &apos;In the dark, flowers and water cannot be discerned unless they move&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>墓所は、東京都港区元麻布三、専称寺ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is in Sensho-ji Temple in 3, Motoazabu, Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is in Sensho-ji Temple in Motoazabu 3 cho-me, Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - I assume &quot;麻布三&quot; means &quot;麻布三丁目&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is in Sensho-ji Temple in Motoazabu 3 cho-me, Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>専称寺による戒名は「賢光院仁誉明道居士」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) given by Sensho-ji Temple was 賢光院仁誉明道居士.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) given by Sensho-ji Temple is Kenkoinjinyomeido-koji.</e>
<cmt>*Changed kanji to romaji but I have no idea if it&apos;s right</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) given by Sensho-ji Temple is Kenkoinjinyomeido-koji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、沖田家累代墓碑には天然理心流の他、北辰一刀流の免許皆伝を得ていた旨も記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a statement on the grave stone of the generations of Okita family that they had Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency) for Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school as well as Tennenrishinryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inscription on the Okita family grave stone states that he held menkyo-kaiden (a document handed down by a teacher to the student he believes is most capable of carrying on his art) for the Hokushin Itto-ryu school as well as Tennen Rishin-ryuu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inscription on the Okita family grave stone states that he held menkyo-kaiden (a document handed down by a teacher to the student he believes is most capable of carrying on his art) for the Hokushin Itto-ryu school as well as Tennen Rishin-ryuu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>なお、没時年齢については沖田家累代墓碑の24歳、沖田家文書の25歳、『両雄士伝』（小島鹿之助）における上洛時の年齢（22歳）から計算した27歳の3説が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding his date of birth, there are three views, one of which is the age of twenty four based on the grave stone of the generations of Okita family, twenty five based on the documents held by Okita family, and twenty seven computed from the age of twenty two when he left for Kyoto that is described in &quot;Ryoyushiden&quot; (Shikanosuke KOJIMA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are three theories about his age when he died: twenty-four according to the Okita family grave stone; twenty-five according to documents held by the Okita family; and twenty-seven, if, as described in Shikanosuke KOJIMA&apos;s &quot;Ryoyushiden&quot;, he was twenty-two when he left for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are three theories about his age when he died: twenty-four according to the Okita family grave stone; twenty-five according to documents held by the Okita family; and twenty-seven, if, as described in Shikanosuke KOJIMA&apos;s &quot;Ryoyushiden&quot;, he was twenty-two when he left for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、終焉地も千駄ヶ谷のほか、今戸（台東区）説もあるが、現在では、今戸に一時逗留した後に千駄ヶ谷に移り、そこで亡くなったとする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, regarding the place of ending his life, there are two views, one of which is Sendagaya and another of which is Imado (Taito Ward), but at present, it is more solid that after he stayed in Imado to recuperate for a while, he moved to Sendagaya and died there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also two opinions about the place where he died, one being Sendagaya and the other Imado (Taito Ward), but at present, it is widely accepted that after staying in Imado to recuperate for a while, he moved to Sendagaya and died there.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also two opinions about the place where he died, one being Sendagaya and the other Imado (Taito Ward), but at present, it is widely accepted that after staying in Imado to recuperate for a while, he moved to Sendagaya and died there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>佐久間象山の息子三浦啓之助がある隊士にからかわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shozan SAKUMA&apos;s son, Keinosuke MIURA was made fun of by an officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozan SAKUMA&apos;s son, Keinosuke MIURA, had been made fun of by a fellow Shinsengumi officer.</e>
<cmt>*Added that they were Shinsengumi members for clarity.Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozan SAKUMA&apos;s son, Keinosuke MIURA, had been made fun of by a fellow Shinsengumi officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>後日、土方と沖田が碁を打っている側で三浦をからかった隊士を三浦が背後から斬りつけると、沖田は三浦が後ろから斬りつけた卑怯さに激怒し「この馬鹿野郎」と叫び三浦の襟首を引っつかんで頭を畳に押し付け引きずり回し、三浦は鼻の皮を真っ赤にすりむいたという話が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding this incident, there is a tradition that when Hijikata and Okita were playing a game of Go on a later day, Miura attacked the officer from behind by sword who had made fun of Miura, and Okita really got angry with his unfair way of attacking the man from behind and took him by the collar and pushed down his face on a Tatami mat saying &apos;You idiot&apos; until Miura got his nose raw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a story that a few days later, Hijikata and Okita were playing a game of Go when Miura attacked the officer who had made fun of him from behind and Okita, infuriated by the cowardly attack, grabbed Miura by the collar and, calling him a &apos;bloody idiot&apos;, pushed his face into the floor until his nose was raw.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - translated &quot;この馬鹿野郎&quot; as &quot;bloody idiot&quot;, &quot;you idiot&quot; seems a bit weak</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a story that a few days later, Hijikata and Okita were playing a game of Go when Miura attacked the officer who had made fun of him from behind and Okita, infuriated by the cowardly attack, grabbed Miura by the collar and, calling him a &apos;bloody idiot&apos;, pushed his face into the floor until his nose was raw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>凄腕の一番組長としての顔とは裏腹に、当の本人はいつも冗談を言っては笑っていた陽気な人物であったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contrary to the aspect of being an able head of the Ichiban-gumi, he seemed to be a cheerful person who said jokes and laughed all the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Belying his appearance as an able leader of the Ichiban-gumi, he was apparently a cheerful person who was always telling jokes and laughing.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Belying his appearance as an able leader of the Ichiban-gumi, he was apparently a cheerful person who was always telling jokes and laughing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>屯所界隈の子供達ともよく遊んであげていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He seemed to often play with children in his neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems he often played with children in his neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems he often played with children in his neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>作家の司馬遼太郎は新選組を題材とした作品を執筆する際、幼い頃に沖田に遊んでもらったという老婆を取材している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a novelist Ryotaro SHIBA was writing a book featuring Shinsengumi, he had interviews with an old woman who used to play with him when she was small (Based on the interviews in around 1960 and taking into consideration the Meiji Restoration in 1868, that woman seems to have been pretty old, but it means that people who really met Soji OKITA were still alive.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When novelist Ryotaro SHIBA was writing a book featuring the Shinsengumi, he interviewed an old woman who used to play with Okita when she was small (taking into account that the interview took place around 1960 and that the Meiji Restoration was in 1868, the woman must have been quite old, but it means that people who actually met Soji OKITA were still alive).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When novelist Ryotaro SHIBA was writing a book featuring the Shinsengumi, he interviewed an old woman who used to play with Okita when she was small.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>（取材が1960年前後とすると、明治維新が1868年なので、かなり高齢ではあるものの実際の沖田総司を目にした人々が生きていたことになる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Taking into account that the interview took place around 1960 and that the Meiji Restoration was in 1868, the woman must have been quite old, but it means that people who actually met Soji OKITA were still alive.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>近藤・土方など新選組についての酷評で知られる西村兼文ですら、山南敬助と並び沖田についても批判を残していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kanefumi NISHIMURA was known for severely criticizing Kondo and Hijikata in Shinsengumi, he left no critics of Okita as well as Keisuke YAMANAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kanefumi NISHIMURA was known for severely criticizing Kondo, Hijikata and other members of the Shinsengumi, he left no comments on Okita or Keisuke YAMANAMI.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kanefumi NISHIMURA was known for severely criticizing Kondo, Hijikata and other members of the Shinsengumi, he left no comments on Okita or Keisuke YAMANAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>これは西村が山南と沖田には悪意を持っていなかったことの表われと見られ、従って沖田は新選組に表立って敵対した者以外には人当たりの良い好人物であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This seems to tell that Nishimura had no bad feelings toward Yamanami and Okita, and Okita is believed to have been an easy-going man for people other than the individuals who were apparently hostile against Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This seems to show that Nishimura had no bad feelings towards Yamanami and Okita, and Okita is believed to have been easy-going towards people who were not hostile to the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This seems to show that Nishimura had no bad feelings towards Yamanami and Okita, and Okita is believed to have been easy-going towards people who were not hostile to the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>死の際には、植木屋の庭に現れる黒猫を斬ろうとして幾度となく失敗し、己の衰えを痛感した沖田は以下のようにと嘆いていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that just before his death, though he tried to put a black cat to the sword which often sneaked into the plant shop&apos;s yard, he failed it several times, and he really felt his deterioration and said &apos;Gosh, I couldn&apos;t put it to the sward!</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that just before his death, he tried several times to kill a black cat which often sneaked into the plant shop&apos;s yard but always missed and, realizing his own weakness, he said, &apos;Alas, I cannot kill it!</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that just before his death, he tried several times to kill a black cat which often sneaked into the plant shop&apos;s yard but always missed and, realizing his own weakness, he said as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>「ああ、斬れない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alas, I cannot kill it!&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>「婆さん（付添いの老婆）、俺は斬れないよ」（ただし、この話は子母沢寛による創作であると言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See! (he said to an old woman as a helper), I can not put it to the sward&apos; (this story is said to have been created by Kan SHIMOZAWA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See! (he said to the old woman who was attending him), I cannot kill it&apos; (this story is said to have been created by Kan SHIMOZAWA.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See! (he said to the old woman who was attending him), I cannot kill it&apos; (this story is said to have been created by Kan SHIMOZAWA.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="50">
<j>死の間際まで「（近藤）先生はどうされたのでしょうね、お便りは来ませんか？」と、師を気遣う言葉を幾度となく口にしたとも伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is a tradition that he said many times until the brink of death, caring of the master &apos;I am wondering how the master (Kondo) has been. Didn&apos;t we receive a letter from him?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a story that he was worried about Kondo and, up until his death, he repeatedly asked, &apos;I am wondering how the master (Kondo) has been. Didn&apos;t we receive a letter from him?&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a story that he was worried about Kondo and, up until his death, he repeatedly asked, &apos;I am wondering how the master (Kondo) has been. Didn&apos;t we receive a letter from him?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>近藤の死に関して周囲の者は固く口止めされていたため、沖田は近藤の死を知らずにこの世を去ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because people close to him were prohibited to disclose Kondo&apos;s death, he did not know it and passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because people close to him were prohibited from telling him about Kondo&apos;s death, he passed away without learning of it.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because people close to him were prohibited from telling him about Kondo&apos;s death, he passed away without learning of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>これに先立って、甲陽鎮撫隊が出陣する際に近藤が沖田を見舞うと、普段は明るい沖田がこのときだけは声を上げて泣いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another anecdote that when Kondo was still alive and visited Okita in bed before he setout in Koyo Chinbutai (a military unit formed specially for the campaign in Kai Province,) Okita exceptionally cried out on that occasion, though he was usually cheerful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another anecdote that when Kondo was still alive and visiting Okita in bed before setting out with the Koyo Chinbutai, the usually cheerful Okita on this occasion sobbed loudly.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another anecdote that when Kondo was still alive and visiting Okita in bed before setting out with the Koyo Chinbutai, the usually cheerful Okita on this occasion sobbed loudly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>一般に近藤、土方、沖田の3人が非常に親しく、特に土方と沖田は兄弟のような関係であったと思われているが、これも司馬遼太郎、子母澤寛の創作によるところが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has generally been thought that Kondo, Hijikata and Okita were very close to each other and in particular, Hijikata and Okita looked to have a siblings-like relationship, but this largely depends on the fictions created by Ryotaro SHIBA and Kan SHIMOZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally thought that Kondo, Hijikata and Okita were very close to each other, with Hijikata and Okita in particular being like brothers, but this is largely the result of novels by Ryotaro SHIBA and Kan SHIMOZAWA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally thought that Kondo, Hijikata and Okita were very close to each other, with Hijikata and Okita in particular being like brothers, but this is largely the result of novels by Ryotaro SHIBA and Kan SHIMOZAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>土方と沖田が特別親しかったことを示す資料自体は存在しないが、沖田が土方の手紙の執筆代理をした記録が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no materials to show that Hijikata and Okita were extremely close, but a record that Okita wrote a letter on behalf of Hijikata remains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no materials to show that Hijikata and Okita were extremely close, although there is a record of Okita writing a letter on behalf of Hijikata.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no materials to show that Hijikata and Okita were extremely close, although there is a record of Okita writing a letter on behalf of Hijikata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="55">
<j>新撰組と敵対していた阿部十郎のからは「近藤の高弟の沖田総司、大石鍬次郎という者はまことに残酷な人間でございまして、もとより国家朝廷のあるを知らぬようなもので」（『史談会速記録』）と、岡田以蔵などと同様に思想的背景を持たない“人殺しの道具”として非難されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juro ABE, a rival to Shinsengumi said &apos;Kondo&apos;s high-caliber disciples, Soji OKITA and Kuwajiro OISHI are very cruelhearted men and look like they from the beginning haven&apos;t realized even the existence of the state or Imperial Court&apos; (&quot;Shidankaisokkiroku&quot;) and criticized that the both had no ideological background and was used as &quot;a tool to kill people&quot; as well as Izo OKADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juro ABE, who was opposed to the Shinsengumi, said, &apos;Kondo&apos;s high-caliber disciples, Soji OKITA and Kuwajiro OISHI, are very cruelhearted men and, from the beginning, appear not to have realized even the existence of the state or the Imperial Court&apos; (&quot;Shidankaisokkiroku&quot;) and attacked them and Izo OKADA for having no ideological background and for being used as &quot;tools to kill people&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juro ABE, who was opposed to the Shinsengumi, said, &apos;Kondo&apos;s high-caliber disciples, Soji OKITA and Kuwajiro OISHI, are very cruelhearted men and, from the beginning, appear not to have realized even the existence of the state or the Imperial Court&apos; (&quot;Shidankaisokkiroku&quot;) and attacked them and Izo OKADA for having no ideological background and for being used as &quot;tools to kill people&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="56">
<j>また、沖田に剣技を教えられてた人には「荒っぽくて、すぐ怒る」というような性格で、師範の近藤より恐れられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, people who had training of sword techniques from Okita feared Okita more than Kondo his master, saying &apos;He is extremely harsh and gets mad soon.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to Okita&apos;s students, he was &apos;extremely harsh and quick-tempered&apos; and they feared him more than the master, Kondo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to Okita&apos;s students, he was &apos;extremely harsh and quick-tempered&apos; and they feared him more than the master, Kondo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>他に「刀で斬るな！体で斬れ！」と教えていた等の言い伝えもあり、その他の記録などを見ても記録にある素顔の沖田は巷に広がる優しく大人しいといったイメージとはずいぶん異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is another anecdote that he told his trainees &apos;Don&apos;t put people to the sword! Put them to your body!&apos; and his image based on other records differs a lot from his image of a gentle and calm person that is widely known in public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of Okita gained from anecdotes such as his telling his trainees, &apos;Don&apos;t kill people with your sword! Kill them with your body!&apos; and other records differs greatly from the gentle and calm image that is widely known in public.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of Okita gained from anecdotes such as his telling his trainees, &apos;Don&apos;t kill people with your sword! Kill them with your body!&apos; and other records differs greatly from the gentle and calm image that is widely known in public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>剣技</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sword technique</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sword Technique</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sword Technique</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>沖田の剣技で有名なのが「三段突き」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous sword technique of Okita is &apos;Sandantsuki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okita&apos;s most famous sword technique is the &apos;Sandantsuki&apos; (Three Stage Thrust).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okita&apos;s most famous sword technique is the &apos;Sandantsuki&apos; (Three Stage Thrust).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>天然理心流の平正眼(天然理心流は「平晴眼」と書く)の構えから踏み込みの足音が一度しか鳴らないのに、その間に3発の突きを繰り出したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he generated only one footstep heard from stepping out from the stance of Hiraseigan (平正眼) (&apos;平晴眼&apos; in Tennenrishinryu) in Tennenrishinryu, he gave three pushes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting from the Tennenrishin-ryu stance of &apos;hiraseigan&apos;, he delivered three thrusts in the time he was heard to take one step forward.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting from the Tennenrishin-ryu stance of &apos;hiraseigan&apos;, he delivered three thrusts in the time he was heard to take one step forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>即ち目にも止まらぬ速さで、相手は一突きもらったと思った瞬間、既に三度突かれていたとする描写が小説などに多数見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was often presented in stories that when other party felt one push in a blink of an eye, he actually had three pushes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often presented in novels as his opponent thinking he has been stabbed once when actually, in the blink of an eye, he has been stabbed three times.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often presented in novels as his opponent thinking he has been stabbed once when actually, in the blink of an eye, he has been stabbed three times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>実際の詳細は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, the details are unknown</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the exact details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the exact details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>『新選組遺聞』における佐藤宣の談話によれば、沖田の剣術の形は師匠の近藤そっくりで、掛け声までがよく似た細い甲高い声であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Sen SATO (佐藤宣) in &quot;Shinsengumi Ibun&quot; (exceptional matters,) Okita&apos;s swordplay style was the really same as his master Kondo and his voice of calling seemed very alike and thin and high-pitched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Sen SATO in &quot;Shinsengumi Ibun&quot;, Okita&apos;s sword style was identical to his master, Kondo&apos;s and even his thin, high-pitched yells were very alike.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Sen SATO in &quot;Shinsengumi Ibun&quot;, Okita&apos;s sword style was identical to his master, Kondo&apos;s and even his thin, high-pitched yells were very alike.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ただ、太刀先がやや下がり気味で前のめりの、近藤（腹を少し突き出し気味の平正眼）とやや異なる構えを取る癖があったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is thought that he had a habit of leaning his body forward and holding a sword with its edge slightly lowered, that was a bit different posture from Kondo (pushing his abdomen a little forward based on 平正眼.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is thought that he had a habit of leaning his body forward and holding his sword with the point slightly lowered, a slightly different posture to Kondo, who pushed his abdomen a little forward in the hiraseigan stance.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is thought that he had a habit of leaning his body forward and holding his sword with the point slightly lowered, a slightly different posture to Kondo, who pushed his abdomen a little forward in the hiraseigan stance.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>沖田の剣については、永倉新八が「土方歳三、井上源三郎、藤堂平助、山南敬助などが竹刀を持っては子供扱いされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding Okita&apos;s swordplay, Shinpachi NAGAKURA&apos;s statement is well known that &apos;Toshizo HIJIKATA, Genzaburo INOUE, Heisuke TODO and Keisuke YAMANAMI had a bamboo sword and were treated as a child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpachi NAGAKURA&apos;s statement that Okita&apos;s technique &apos;left Toshizo HIJIKATA, Genzaburo INOUE, Heisuke TODO, Keisuke YAMANAMI and the others looking like children playing with bamboo swords.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - This sentence is split halfway through quote and so the cell should be joined to the following one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpachi NAGAKURA&apos;s statement that Okita&apos;s technique &apos;left Toshizo HIJIKATA, Genzaburo INOUE, Heisuke TODO, Keisuke YAMANAMI and the others looking like children playing with bamboo swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>恐らく本気で立ち合ったら師匠の近藤もやられるだろうと皆が言っていた」（『永倉新八遺談』）と語ったことが知られているが、新選組内部以外からの声もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of people said that if Okita is seriously going to fight with his master, Kondo will be a loser.&apos; (&quot;Nagakura Shinpachi Idan,&quot;) and there are statements from people other than Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Everyone said that if Okita seriously fought his master, Kondo would lose,&apos; (&quot;Nagakura Shinpachi Idan,&quot;) is well-known but there are also comments to the same effect from outside the Shinsengumi&apos;s inner circle.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - This sentence is split halfway through quote and so the cell should be joined to the preceding one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Everyone said that if Okita seriously fought his master, Kondo would lose,&apos; (&quot;Nagakura Shinpachi Idan,&quot;) is well-known but there are also comments to the same effect from outside the Shinsengumi&apos;s inner circle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>小島鹿之助は新選組結成前（文久2年（1862年）7月）に「この人剣術は、晩年必ず名人に至るべき人なり」（『小島日記』）と述べているし、新選組に批判的な西村兼文は「近藤秘蔵の部下にして、隊中第一等の剣客なり」「天才的剣法者」（『壬生浪士始末記』）と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikanosuke KOJIMA mentioned before the formation of Shinsengumi (in July 1862) that &apos;He is a man who will for sure reach the level of master in sword play later in his life&apos; (&quot;Diary of Kojima (小島日記)&quot;,) and Kanefumi NISHIMURA with critical attitudes toward Shinsengumi stated that &apos;He is the greatest swordsman in Shinsengumi among Kondo&apos;s favorite disciples.&apos; (&quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikanosuke KOJIMA mentioned before the formation of Shinsengumi (in July 1862) that Okita &apos;is someone who will definitely reach the level of a master of the sword later in his life&apos; (&quot;Kojima Nikki&quot;) and Kanefumi NISHIMURA, although critical of the Shinsengumi, called him &apos;Kondo&apos;s most cherished follower and the best swordsman in his unit&apos; and &apos;a genius with the sword&apos; (&quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - the Japanese has &quot;隊中&quot; so chnaged &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; to &quot;unit&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikanosuke KOJIMA mentioned before the formation of Shinsengumi (in July 1862) that Okita &apos;is someone who will definitely reach the level of a master of the sword later in his life&apos; (&quot;Kojima Nikki&quot;) and Kanefumi NISHIMURA, although critical of the Shinsengumi, called him &apos;Kondo&apos;s most cherished follower and the best swordsman in his unit&apos; and &apos;a genius with the sword&apos; (&quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>さらに新選組と敵対した阿部十郎は「沖田総司、是がマァ、近藤の一弟子でなかなか能くつかいました」「沖田総司、大石鍬次郎という若者は、ただ腕が利くだけで、剣術などはよくつかいました」「大石鍬次郎、沖田総司、井上、是らは無闇に人を斬殺致しますので」（『史談会速記録』）など、殊に敵に回した場合に筆頭の脅威となる剣客であったことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Juro ABE who was a rival for Shinsengumi stated that &apos;Soji OKITA is Kondo&apos;s disciple and really excelled in a swordplay.&apos; &apos; Soji OKITA and Kamajiro OISHI are young but only tough and strong, and displayed great swordplays in many occasions.&apos; &apos;Kamajiro OISHI, Soji OKITA and Genzaburo INOUE, they killed people without reason.&apos; (&quot;Shidankaisokkiroku&quot;,) according to which, if they especially were enemies, they were the swordsmen who would have been primary threats.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juro ABE, who fought against the Shinsengumi, stated in &quot;Shidankaisokkiroku&quot; that &apos;As one of Kondo&apos;s students, Soji OKITA is an excellent swordsman&apos;, &apos; Soji OKITA and Kamajiro OISHI are young but have shown great skill with the sword on many occasions&apos; and &apos;Kamajiro OISHI, Soji OKITA and Genzaburo INOUE have killed people without reason&apos;, all of which shows it would have been extremely dangerous to make enemies of them.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juro ABE, who fought against the Shinsengumi, stated in &quot;Shidankaisokkiroku&quot; that &apos;As one of Kondo&apos;s students, Soji OKITA is an excellent swordsman&apos;, &apos; Soji OKITA and Kamajiro OISHI are young but have shown great skill with the sword on many occasions&apos; and &apos;Kamajiro OISHI, Soji OKITA and Genzaburo INOUE have killed people without reason&apos;, all of which shows it would have been extremely dangerous to make enemies of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>ちなみに千葉弥一郎（新徴組隊士で、沖田の義兄と同僚）の言葉に「われわれからみたらやっと目録（低い段位）くらいの腕前」と、唯一の否定的見解が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaichiro CHIBA (a member of Shinchogumi (Tokugawa Shogunate guard organization) and a colleague of Okita&apos;s brother-in-law) said &apos;Their skill and performance are just as low as Mokuroku (a low level) from our views.&apos; and this will be the only one negative opinion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only negative opinion was from Yaichiro CHIBA, a member of the Shinchogumi (the Shinsengumi&apos;s Edo counterpart) and a colleague of Okita&apos;s brother-in-law, who said, &apos;from our viewpoint, their skills are suitable for mokuroku (a low level)&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only negative opinion was from Yaichiro CHIBA, a member of the Shinchogumi (the Shinsengumi&apos;s Edo counterpart) and a colleague of Okita&apos;s brother-in-law, who said, &apos;from our viewpoint, their skills are suitable for mokuroku (a low level)&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>勿論、北辰一刀流免許皆伝の山南や目録の藤堂を子供扱いというのはさすがに永倉の言い過ぎであろうが、それだけ彼の剣技が凄まじかったということなのだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course, Nagakura&apos;s statement that Yamanami who accomplished Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency) for Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school and Todo who was almost in the Mokuroku level were treated as a child seems really extreme, but may imply how superb and outstanding his swordplay was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course, Nagakura&apos;s statement that Yamanami, who had attained &apos;menkyo-kaiden&apos; in the Hokushin Itto-ryu, and Todo, who was almost at the mokuroku level, were like children seems extreme, but may imply how superb and outstanding Okita&apos;s skill with the sword was.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course, Nagakura&apos;s statement that Yamanami, who had attained &apos;menkyo-kaiden&apos; in the Hokushin Itto-ryu, and Todo, who was almost at the mokuroku level, were like children seems extreme, but may imply how superb and outstanding Okita&apos;s skill with the sword was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>沖田の刀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okita&apos;s sword</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okita&apos;s Sword</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okita&apos;s Sword</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>小説などにおいて、沖田総司の所有する刀として「菊一文字則宗」の名が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presented in novels that swards owned by Soji OKITA were branded &apos;Kikuichimonji Norimune.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In novels, the sword owned by Soji OKITA is depicted as being a &apos;Kikuichimonji Norimune&apos; (swords made at the beginning of the thirteenth century).</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - added brief description of &quot;菊一文字&quot; swords</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In novels, the sword owned by Soji OKITA is depicted as being a &apos;Kikuichimonji Norimune&apos; (swords made at the beginning of the thirteenth century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>これは子母澤寛などの伝記により「沖田の刀は“菊一文字細身のつくり”」とされていたことから司馬遼太郎が著作『新撰組血風録』の中で創作した物語が広まったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First Kan SHIMOZAWA and other authors wrote &apos;Okita&apos;s swords are &quot;thin and Kikuichimonji one.&quot; in their authored biographies, and Ryotaro SHIBA created the story in &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; based on the descriptions in the biographies, which has become popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story gained popularity following its appearance in the novel &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA, who based it on descriptions in biograraphies such as that by Kan SHIMOZAWA, where the sword is described as being &apos;a thin Kikuichimonji one&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story gained popularity following its appearance in the novel &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA, who based it on descriptions in biograraphies such as that by Kan SHIMOZAWA, where the sword is described as being &apos;a thin Kikuichimonji one&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>しかし則宗作の刀は、日本刀が常用されていた当時でさえ非常に貴重な古刀であり、経済的にも実戦で多用する必要性からも沖田が所有した可能性はほとんど無いと推察され、研究者の間で取り上げられることはまず無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Norimune swords were very old and valuable ones even in that period when Japanese swords were regularly used, and there is an assumption that Okita should hardly own them from the economical viewpoints and the necessity of often using it in actual battles and this matter has hardly been discussed among researchers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, despite being a period when Japanese swords were everyday items, Norimune swords were extremely valuable old swords, and it is believed that, from an economical point of view and from the necessity of having to use it often in actual battles, Okita would hardly have been likely to own one, although the matter has hardly been discussed among researchers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, despite being a period when Japanese swords were everyday items, Norimune swords were extremely valuable old swords, and it is believed that, from an economical point of view and from the necessity of having to use it often in actual battles, Okita would hardly have been likely to own one, although the matter has hardly been discussed among researchers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>現在では沖田が所有した実際の刀で確認されているのは「加州清光」「大和守安定」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the swords actually owned by Okita, swords made by &apos;Kiyomitsu KASHU&apos; and &apos;Yasusada YAMATO NO KAMI&apos; have been confirmed to be held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okita is known to have owned swords made by Kiyomitsu KASHU and Yasusada YAMATO NO KAMI.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okita is known to have owned swords made by Kiyomitsu KASHU and Yasusada YAMATO NO KAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>あるいは、則宗以外にも幾つか存在した“菊に一”の紋を打った細身の刀の1つではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, in addition to Norimune swords, there were several other thin types of swords with a &quot;Kikuniichi&quot; crest, and it is thought that the sword may have been one of those types of swords.</e>
<cmt>”あるいは、則宗以外にも幾つか存在した“菊に一”の紋を打った細身の刀の1つではないか”は、上のどの刀を指しているのかよく分からないので、原文とおり英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the Norimune swords, there were several other thin types of swords with a &quot;Kikuniichi&quot; crest, and it is possible that Okita&apos;s sword may have been one of these.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - agree with the translator. Not sure about &quot;菊に一&quot;, unless it&apos;s a typo or something</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the Norimune swords, there were several other thin types of swords with a &quot;Kikuniichi&quot; crest, and it is possible that Okita&apos;s sword may have been one of these.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>いずれにせよ他の隊士と同様、在京中に何度か刀を交換した可能性も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any way, he was likely to often exchange his swords as other members did during his stay in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any event, like the other members of the Shinsengumi, he is likely to have exchanged his swords often during his stay in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any event, like the other members of the Shinsengumi, he is likely to have exchanged his swords often during his stay in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>美少年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handsome boy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Handsome Youth</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Handsome Youth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>作家司馬遼太郎の作品以降、沖田は小説・ドラマなど創作世界においては頻繁に美少年として描かれてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was presented in books authored by a writer Ryotaro SHIBA, he has often been introduced as a handsome boy in the fictive and creative world such as novels and TV dramas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since his appearance in Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s novels, he has often been depicted in fiction, including novels and TV series, as a handsome young man.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since his appearance in Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s novels, he has often been depicted in fiction, including novels and TV series, as a handsome young man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>沖田の容貌に関して、現在残っている沖田の肖像画は、沖田の姉のミツが孫、要氏を「総司にどこか似ている」と称したことから、昭和4年（1929年）に書かれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Okita&apos;s appearance, Mitsu, his older sister said that Kaname, her grandson &apos;somehow resembles to Soji,&apos; and an existing portrait of Okita was drawn in 1929.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okita&apos;s likeness can be seen in a portrait that was painted in 1929 based on a claim by his older sister, Mitsu, that her grandson, Kaname, &apos;somehow resembles Soji&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okita&apos;s likeness can be seen in a portrait that was painted in 1929 based on a claim by his older sister, Mitsu, that her grandson, Kaname, &apos;somehow resembles Soji&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>八木家の者や新選組に関わった人物の証言では、「美少年であった」とは書き残してはおらず、容姿に関する記述としては、「ヒラメ顔で笑うと愛嬌があり色黒」、「肩の張り上がった」、「猫背」「長身」と書かれたものが残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People from Yagi Family or involved in Shinsengumi left no words like &apos;He was a handsome boy.&apos; but instead, left the writing such as &apos;His face is like a flatfish and when laughing, he is attractive though his face is suntanned.&apos;, &apos;squared shoulders&apos;, &apos;rounded back&apos; and &apos;very tall&apos; (In &quot;Ryoma ni omakase!&quot; (Leave things to Ryoma) and &quot;Getsumeiseiki good-bye Shinsengumi, &quot;Okita was described as a person with the nature, aspects and characteristics close to the above.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no descriptions of him being &apos;a handsome youth&apos; from members of the Yagi family or from people connected to the Shinsengumi; instead, he is described as having a &apos;face like a flatfish, though tanned and not unnattractive when laughing&apos;, &apos;square shoulders&apos;, &apos;a rounded back&apos; and being &apos;very tall&apos; (In &quot;Ryoma ni omakase!&quot; (Leave things to Ryoma) and &quot;Getsumeiseiki - Sayonara Shinsengumi&quot;, the depiction of Okita was closer to the above.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no descriptions of him being &apos;a handsome youth&apos; from members of the Yagi family or from people connected to the Shinsengumi; instead, he is described as having a &apos;face like a flatfish, though tanned and not unnattractive when laughing&apos;, &apos;square shoulders&apos;, &apos;a rounded back&apos; and being &apos;very tall.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>（『竜馬におまかせ!』『月明星稀 - さよなら新選組』ではこの説に近い設定となっている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In &quot;Ryoma ni omakase!&quot; (Leave things to Ryoma) and &quot;Getsumeiseiki - Sayonara Shinsengumi&quot;, the depiction of Okita was closer to the above.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>この記述から浮かび上がる人物像として、美少年説に疑義を唱える指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the imagination of a man drawn from these descriptions, there are people raising the doubts about the handsome boy belief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image that emerges from these descriptions casts doubt on the &apos;handsome youth&apos; theory.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image that emerges from these descriptions casts doubt on the &apos;handsome youth&apos; theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>剣技の強さが伝承されながら労咳により夭逝してしまうというドラマ性に富むその生涯から、そのドラマ性をさらに演出する要素として司馬遼太郎は小説『燃えよ剣』をはじめ、その流れを汲んだ『幕末純情伝 (映画)』（美少女として描かれている）など多数の作品において沖田を美少年として描いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, taking advantage of the dramatic part of his life that while he was believed to have tough sword techniques, he died of lung tuberculosis at his young age, Ryotaro SHIBA presented Okita as a handsome boy in his many productions such as a novel &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; and &quot;Bakumatsu Junjoden (movie)&quot;(Okita was described as a handsome boy) to use such presentation as a factor useful to enhance those dramatic features.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryotaro SHIBA, wanting to enhance the drama (a young man killed by tuberculosis just as his skill with the sword is becoming legendary) in Okita&apos;s life and so made him a handsome young man in his novel &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;, which was followed by many other works, including the movie &quot;Bakumatsu Junjoden&quot; in which Okita was depicted as beatiful girl.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryotaro SHIBA, wanting to enhance the drama (a young man killed by tuberculosis just as his skill with the sword is becoming legendary) in Okita&apos;s life and so made him a handsome young man in his novel &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;, which was followed by many other works, including the movie &quot;Bakumatsu Junjoden&quot; in which Okita was depicted as beatiful girl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>沖田が美少年であるというイメージは、“剣にめっぽう強い上に明るい性格、その反面、病弱で色白の美少年”として演出されたイメージが一般的に定着した結果の誤解とも思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The image of Okita being a handsome boy seems to be a misunderstanding because the created image that &quot;he is very good at a swordplay, and is a cheerful but vulnerable boy and has light-skin&quot; has been rooted as a general image of him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of Okita as a handsome young man seems to come from the mistaken notion that the dramatized image of him as &quot;a powerful swordsman and cheerful but, at the same time, sickly and pale&quot; is the generally accepted image.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of Okita as a handsome young man seems to come from the mistaken notion that the dramatized image of him as &quot;a powerful swordsman and cheerful but, at the same time, sickly and pale&quot; is the generally accepted image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また、多数の映画など映像メディアにおいても常に若手二枚目俳優の役どころであった影響も大きいと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many movies and other screen media, young and nice looking actors performed for Okita all the time, that seems to have had a significant influence on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Okita is always played on the screen by young, good-looking actors is also thought to have had a significant influence on his image.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Okita is always played on the screen by young, good-looking actors is also thought to have had a significant influence on his image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>しかし「総司＝ヒラメ顔」説は、佐藤彦五郎のひ孫が、テレビで谷春雄の話に軽くノってつい口走ってしまったのが始まりらしいのだが、谷は「総司がヒラメ顔」というのは“のっぺらぼうという意味ではなくて、一族や兄弟の写真がみな目の間隔が寄っているから”と話している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the origin of the &apos;Soji&apos;s face is like a flatfish&apos; belief seemed to be a light jokey answer made by a great grand son of Hikogoro SATO when Haruo TANI said a lighthearted joke to him in a TV program, and according to Tani, &apos;Soji&apos;s face is like a flatfish&apos; does not mean his face is flat but the two eyes of other family members including his sisters in photos are closely-spaced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the origin of the &apos;Soji&apos;s face is like a flatfish&apos; belief seemed to be a light jokey answer made by a great grand son of Hikogoro SATO when Haruo TANI said a lighthearted joke to him in a TV program, and according to Tani, &apos;Soji&apos;s face is like a flatfish&apos; does not mean his face is flat but the two eyes of other family members including his sisters in photos are closely-spaced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the origin of the &apos;Soji&apos;s face is like a flatfish&apos; belief seemed to be a light jokey answer made by a great grand son of Hikogoro SATO when Haruo TANI said a lighthearted joke to him in a TV program, and according to Tani, &apos;Soji&apos;s face is like a flatfish&apos; does not mean his face is flat but the two eyes of other family members including his sisters in photos are closely-spaced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>ちなみに沖田哲也はこの説を完全に否定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tetsuya OKITA completely denied this thought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tetsuya OKITA completely rejected this idea.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tetsuya OKITA completely rejected this idea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>彼によれば、沖田家では総司の容姿について「色の白い、小さい男だった」という風に伝わっているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to him, in Okita family, Soji&apos;s appearance has been told like &apos;He was a light-skinned and small man.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to him, Soji was described within the Okita family as &apos;a light-skinned and small man&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to him, Soji was described within the Okita family as &apos;a light-skinned and small man&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>容貌・写真などについては、外部リンクも参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to his appearance and pictures, refer to external linkages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For likenesses and pictures, follow the external links.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For likenesses and pictures, follow the external links.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>沖田総司の恋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soji OKITA&apos;s romance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soji OKITA&apos;s Romance</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soji OKITA&apos;s Romance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>創作の世界で沖田は、司馬遼太郎の小説以降、一般に純情な青年として描かれることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fictive and creative areas following his appearance in Ryotaro Shiba&apos;s books, generally, Okita has often been presented as a pure and innocent young man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following his appearance in Ryotaro Shiba&apos;s books, Okita is generally often depicted in fiction as a pure and innocent young man.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following his appearance in Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s books, Okita is generally often depicted in fiction as a pure and innocent young man.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>町医者の娘とプラトニックな恋愛をするなどの描き方がほとんどで、実際に沖田の周囲では近藤や土方などのように花柳界の女性の影は見えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most products, he was described in the way like he had a platonic love with a daughter of a local doctor, and there is no story in which women from Karyukai (the world of the geisha) were around Okita like for Kondo and Hijikata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most works describe him as having a platonic relationship with the daughter of a local doctor, and in actual fact, he seems to have steered clear of women from Karyukai (the geisha district), unlike Kondo and Hijikata.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most works describe him as having a platonic relationship with the daughter of a local doctor, and in actual fact, he seems to have steered clear of women from Karyukai (the geisha district), unlike Kondo and Hijikata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>ただ、井上松五郎の文久3年（1863年）4月22日付の日記によると、土方、松五郎、井上源三郎と共に沖田が新町の廓九軒町吉田屋にて天神（遊女）を買うという記述が見られる為、必ずしも女遊びをしなかったというわけではないようだが自分が好意を持っている女性の話になるととても真面目だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the diary of Matsugoro INOUE on June 8, 1863, Hijikata, Matsugoro, Genzaburo INOUE and Okita philandered Yujo (prostitutes) at Yoshidaya in Kuken Town, and he did not necessarily experience such entertainment with women, but when it came to the woman he felt affection toward, he was very serious to talk about her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the June 8, 1863 entry of his Matsugoro INOUE&apos;s diary, Hijikata, Matsugoro, Genzaburo INOUE and Okita paid for prostitutes at the Yoshidaya in the Kuken-cho area of the Shinmachi courtesan&apos;s district, so it cannot be said that he never played around with women, although when talk turned to a woman he was fond of, he became very serious.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to the April 22, 1863 entry of his Matsugoro INOUE&apos;s diary, Hijikata, Matsugoro, Genzaburo INOUE and Okita paid for prostitutes at the Yoshidaya in the Kuken-cho area of the Shinmachi courtesan&apos;s district, so it cannot be said that he never played around with women, although when talk turned to a woman he was fond of, he became very serious.</e>
<cmt>June 8→April 22（日記の日付のため）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>また壬生光縁寺には過去帳に「沖田氏縁者」と書かれた女性の記録があり、これが沖田の恋人ではないかとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a record of a woman showing &apos;Okita&apos;s relative&apos; in a family register of deaths at Koen-ji Temple, Mibu and this woman is thought to have been Okita&apos;s lover.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The register of deaths at Koen-ji Temple lists as &apos;Okita&apos;s relative&apos; a woman who is thought to have been Okita&apos;s lover.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The register of deaths at Koen-ji Temple lists as &apos;Okita&apos;s relative&apos; a woman who is thought to have been Okita&apos;s lover.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>研究者によるとこの女性は石井秩という未亡人で、連れ子（娘）が1人居たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the researchers, this woman&apos; name was 石井秩 and she had a daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the researchers, the woman&apos;s name was Tsune ISHII and she had a daughter.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - not sure of the pronunciation of the name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the researchers, the woman&apos;s name was Tsune ISHII and she had a daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>沖田はこの女性との間に1女をもうけ、キョウという名を付けたという話もあるが、決め手に欠けるとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that that woman gave birth to a daughter of Okita and her name was Kyo, but it seems unauthentic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed, but unproven, that the woman gave birth to Okita&apos;s daughter, who was named Kyo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed, but unproven, that the woman gave birth to Okita&apos;s daughter, who was named Kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>なお、新選組にはもう1人「沖田承之進」（慶応元年4月、土方らが江戸で募集した隊士の1人）という沖田姓の隊士が居り、過去帳の「沖田氏」は承之進の方では無いか、との説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was another member called Jonoshin OKITA with the same family name of Okita (one of the members who were recruited by Hijikata in 1865) in Shinsengumi, and it is thought that &apos;Okita&apos; appearing in the family register of deaths may be Jonoshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was another Okita in the Shinsengumi, a man called Jonoshin OKITA, who had been recruited by Hijikata in 1865, and there is a theory that the &apos;Okita&apos; in the register of deaths may be Jonoshin.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was another Okita in the Shinsengumi, a man called Jonoshin OKITA, who had been recruited by Hijikata in Edo in 1865, and there is a theory that the &apos;Okita&apos; in the register of deaths may be Jonoshin.</e>
<cmt>in Edo補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>さらに、試衛館で手伝いをしていた女性（気が強い男勝りな性格だったようだ）に「結婚してくれ」と告白され、「修行中の身ですので」と断ったという逸話も残っている（その女性は断られたショックでか自殺未遂を起こし、その後近藤の口利きにより他家に嫁いだようだ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an old anecdote that a woman (who seemed to be a strong-minded and manly person) working in Shieikan training hall proposed him &apos;to marry with her&apos; but he turned down her proposal, saying &apos;I am still an apprentice&apos; (the woman attempted suicide possibly because of his rejection and got married with other man as a result of Kondo&apos;s introduction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an old anecdote that a woman (who was apparently a strong-willed and spirited person) working in the Shieikan dojo asked Okita to marry her but he turned down her proposal, saying &apos;I am still an apprentice&apos; (the woman attempted suicide, possibly because of his rejection, and later married another man after being introduced by Kondo).</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - removed quote marks from &quot;to marry her&quot; as its no longer a direct quote and it’s a bit difficult to get the nuance across</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an old anecdote that a woman (who was apparently a strong-willed and spirited person) working in the Shieikan dojo asked Okita to marry her but he turned down her proposal, saying &apos;I am still an apprentice&apos; (the woman attempted suicide, possibly because of his rejection, and later married another man after being introduced by Kondo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>この女性は近藤周平の許婚であったと言われる岩田コウという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is partly believed that this woman was Kou IWATA who is thought to have been Shuhei KONDO&apos;s fiancée.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that this woman was Kou IWATA, who is thought to have been Shuhei KONDO&apos;s fiancée.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;partlyPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that this woman was Ko IWATA, who is thought to have been Shuhei KONDO&apos;s fiancée.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="97">
<j>また、油小路にあった旅館里茂の娘・キンとは馴染であったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Kin, a daughter of Hotel Satomo in Aburakoji is thought to have been an old friend of his.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also thought to have been close to a girl called Kin, the daughter of the Satomo Inn on Aburakoji Street.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also thought to have been close to a girl called Kin, the daughter of the Satomo Inn on Aburakoji Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>発病時期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of developing the disease</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onset of Tuberculosis</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - not a direct translation but sounds better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onset of Tuberculosis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>沖田総司といえば、創作作品において必ずといって良いほど池田屋での戦闘中に激しく喀血し、倒れ込む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fictive products, Soji OKITA had a severe hemoptysis and fell down during the battle in the Ikedaya Incident without exception.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works of fiction always have Soji OKITA coughing up blood and collapsing during the fighting in the Ikedaya Incident.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works of fiction always have Soji OKITA coughing up blood and collapsing during the fighting in the Ikedaya Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>しかし現在は上述の通り、研究者の間ではこの説は取られていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as mentioned above, this anecdote has not been supported by the researchers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as mentioned above, this anecdote is not supported by researchers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as mentioned above, this anecdote is not supported by researchers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>同事件で沖田が喀血したと明記するのは『新選組始末記』（子母澤寛）のみで、沖田は事後の長州残党狩り（明保野亭事件参照）にも参加しているし、翌月の禁門の変にも近藤勇・土方歳三・武田観柳斎・永倉新八と共に出動していた記録（『甲子戦争記』西村兼文）があり、喀血するほど結核が進行していたら、無理を強いて出動させるとは思えないのがその理由である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons are that the description of Okita&apos;s blood spitting in that incident was presented only in &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kan SHIMOZAWA,) Okita joined in the post seizure of the Choshu remaining members (Refer to Akebonotei Jiken (Akebonotei Incident)) and there is a record (&quot;Koshi sensoki&quot;) that he joined Isami KONDO, Saizo HIJIKATA, Kanryusai TAKEDA and Shinpachi NAGAKURA for Kinmon Incident in the following month, and if the development of his tuberculosis might cause blood spitting for him, they would not have dared to let him go.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reasons include the fact that the description of Okita&apos;s coughing up blood only appears in Kan SHIMOZAWA&apos;s &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot;; Okita participated in the hunt for the remnants of the Choshu forces (see &quot;Akebonotei Jiken&quot;, the Akebonotei Incident); and there is a record (&quot;Koshi sensoki&quot; Kanefumi NISHIMURA) of him joining Isami KONDO, Saizo HIJIKATA, Kanryusai TAKEDA and Shinpachi NAGAKURA in the Kinmon Incident the following month, and if his tuberculosis was advanced enough to cause him to cough up blood, they would not have dared to let him go.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reasons include the fact that the description of Okita&apos;s coughing up blood only appears in Kan SHIMOZAWA&apos;s &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot;; Okita participated in the hunt for the remnants of the Choshu forces (see &quot;Akebonotei Jiken&quot;, the Akebonotei Incident); and there is a record (&quot;Koshi sensoki&quot; Kanefumi NISHIMURA) of him joining Isami KONDO, Saizo HIJIKATA, Kanryusai TAKEDA and Shinpachi NAGAKURA in the Kinmon Incident the following month, and if his tuberculosis was advanced enough to cause him to cough up blood, they would not have dared to let him go.</e>
<cmt>Kanefumi NISHIMURA補足カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="101">
<j>一方、慶応2年（1866年）頃、幕府典医松本良順が新選組を集団検診した際に「肺結核の者が1名居た」と記しており、これが沖田総司ではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another anecdote that after a group medical examination for Shinsengumi in around 1866, bakufu teni (bakufu doctor) Ryojun MATSUMOTO left a note that &apos;one of the members was infected by lung tuberculosis, and it is thought that the man may have been Soji OKITA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another anecdote that after the Shinsengumi&apos;s group medical examination in around 1866, the shogunate&apos;s doctor, Ryojun MATSUMOTO, left a note that &apos;one of the members had pulmonary tuberculosis&apos;, and it is thought that the man may have been Soji OKITA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another anecdote that after the Shinsengumi&apos;s group medical examination in around 1866, the shogunate&apos;s doctor, Ryojun MATSUMOTO, left a note that &apos;one of the members had pulmonary tuberculosis&apos;, and it is thought that the man may have been Soji OKITA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）には周囲が認識し得るほど発病していた模様で、2月頃罹病したとする『両雄実録』（小島鹿之助）、不動堂村へ屯所を移転した9月頃に大病を患ったとする『壬生浪士始末記』（西村兼文）、さらに10月13日付で小島鹿之助が近藤へ送った書簡にも沖田の異常を気遣う文面が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His disease seemed to be developed so much in 1867 that people around him could become aware of it, and according to &quot;Ryoyu jitsuroku&quot; (Shikanosuke KOJIMA,) he was infected in February, according to &quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kanefumi NISHIMURA,) he got significantly sick in around September when the quarters were moved in Fudodo Village, and there is a statement caring about Okita&apos;s abnormality in a letter dated October 13 which Shikanosuke sent to KONDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1867, the disease seems to have progressed enough that people around him noticed it; Shikanosuke KOJIMA in &quot;Ryoyu jitsuroku&quot; said he contracted it in February; according to Kanefumi NISHIMURA&apos;s &quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot;, he was seriously ill around September when the quarters were moved to Fudodo Village; and in a letter to KONDO dated October 13, Kojima wrote that he was worried about Okita&apos;s worsening condition.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1867, the disease seems to have progressed enough that people around him noticed it; Shikanosuke KOJIMA in &quot;Ryoyu jitsuroku&quot; said he contracted it in March; according to Kanefumi NISHIMURA&apos;s &quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot;, he was seriously ill around September when the quarters were moved to Fudodo Village; and in a letter to Kondo dated October 13, Kojima wrote that he was worried about Okita&apos;s worsening condition.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>以上から、沖田が戦闘に耐えがたいほど重篤な状態に陥ったのは、慶応3年秋～冬頃であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given the above, when Okita&apos;s health condition worsened so critical that he could not bear fighting was from autumn to winter in 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the above, when Okita&apos;s health condition worsened so critical that he could not bear fighting was from autumn to winter in 1867.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the above, when Okita&apos;s health condition worsened so critical that he could not bear fighting was from autumn to winter in 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>また病状の進行を速めたのは稽古の激しい運動の為、肺に負担をかけたせいもあるとの仮説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also thought that his extreme exercise might have caused his illness to worsen furthermore and consequently his lung got stressful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also thought that his intense exercise might have been an added burden on his lungs and aggravated his illness.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also thought that his intense exercise might have been an added burden on his lungs and aggravated his illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="105">
<j>なお、『新選組始末記』をはじめとする池田屋喀血・昏倒シーンの元となったのは永倉新八の『新選組顛末記』と考えられるが、こちらには吐血・喀血の文字こそ見られないものの沖田が昏倒したことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot; and the scenes of blood spitting and unconscious fall seem to have originated in &quot;Shinsengumi Tenmatsuki&quot; of Shinpachi NAGAKURA, and though the word of blood spitting is not found in that book, it is written that Okita fell unconscious.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scenes of Okita spitting blood and falling unconscious at the Ikedaya in works such as &quot;Shinsengumi Shimatsuki&quot; seem to have originated in Shinpachi NAGAKURA&apos;s &quot;Shinsengumi Tenmatsuki&quot;, which, while not mentioning spitting blood, does describe Okita falling unconscious.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scenes of Okita spitting blood and falling unconscious at the Ikedaya in works such as &quot;Shinsengumi Shimatsuki&quot; seem to have originated in Shinpachi NAGAKURA&apos;s &quot;Shinsengumi Tenmatsuki&quot;, which, while not mentioning spitting blood, does describe Okita falling unconscious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>初夏の蒸し暑い異常な高温下での激しい戦闘によって一時的に軽度の熱中症を起こした等、少なくとも近藤や永倉など周囲の者には肺の方の異常は感じさせない状態であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He may have suffered a light and temporary heat collapse since he was in the intense battle on the early but hot and humid summer day with extremely high temperature, and at least, it is thought that his health condition showed no clue for Kondo, Nagakura and other close people to think that his lung was bad.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He may have suffered a light and temporary heat stroke following the intense battle, which took place on a humid and extremely hot day in early summer, and it is thought that his condition did not raise any questions about his lungs for those close to him, including Kondo and Nagakura.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He may have suffered a light and temporary heat stroke following the intense battle, which took place on a humid and extremely hot day in early summer, and it is thought that his condition did not raise any questions about his lungs for those close to him, including Kondo and Nagakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Jono(id:2208), Nnh(id:474), Number(id:103039), Eskimbot(id:29676), 沖田そぉご(id:219143), でここ(id:9565), 赤い彗星(id:10296), らりた(id:1327), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), Anchinanami(id:12615), Kanoe(id:17203), Point136(id:211299), Morio(id:35464), Maakun(id:16735), こちみなお(id:197820), ゆーりん(id:164919), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Mnd(id:15140), とらでじこ(id:11570), いろはにほへと(id:89648), 立つのかよ(id:111350), ＫｏＺ(id:48584), Sh(id:2707), 彩華1226(id:64711), Rusk(id:9895), Alecs.bot(id:194707), Staffn(id:146882), SuisuiBot(id:10165), R28Bot(id:177951), おきた(id:18906), 蓮音(id:116603), NDR(id:5500), Junger(id:10282), King-wise(id:19033), 三日月(id:19540), Hotsuregua(id:99069), Zoominshiodome(id:149045), 田無稲子(id:63575), ブリキの太鼓叩き(id:3586), 味っ子(id:17086), Paseri0924(id:151116), 土方　誠(id:3651), たとゥ(id:25557), 認定者(id:99098), パの字(id:34188), Ponta2(id:129030), 平 誠(id:2586), Kone(id:377), TheMPD(id:17762), Suoh h(id:155314), KASAGI(id:24405), Seven(id:2130), 蘇州宇文宙武(id:121852), Nihonsi(id:255350), Nshn(id:90878), Yanahan(id:2437), Tekken(id:546), SAKURAJIMAc5(id:181266), Ro-(id:36890), 間久部緑郎(id:22345), Wuthering(id:208103), Hrowtr(id:280079), Carbucketty(id:253794), YurikBot(id:18605), 上田隼人(id:23104), 猫の足音(id:21737), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>