<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原清房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kiyofusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kiyofusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kiyofusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 清房（ふじわら の きよふさ、生没年未詳）は平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけての公家、廷臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kiyofusa (dates of birth and death unknown) was kuge (court noble) and retainer of Imperial Court who lived from the end of Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kiyofusa (dates of birth and death unknown) was kuge (court noble) and retainer of the Imperial Court who lived from the end of the Heian Period to the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kiyofusa (year of birth and death unknown) was kuge (court noble) and retainer of the Imperial Court who lived from the end of the Heian Period to the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>dates→year</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原房前を祖とする藤原北家の一門の勧修寺流の藤原盛憲を父とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Morinori from Kajuji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan of which ancestor was FUJIWARA no Fusasaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Morinori from the Kajuji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan of which FUJIWARA no Fusasaki was an ansestor.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Morinori from the Kajuji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan of which FUJIWARA no Fusasaki was an ansestor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>勧修寺清房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyofusa KAJUJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyofusa KAJUJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyofusa KAJUJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正五位下、蔵人、出羽国守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Kurodo (Chamberlain) and Dewa no kuni no kami (Governor of Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Kurodo (Chamberlain) and Dewa no kuni no kami (Governor of Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Kurodo (Chamberlain) and Dewa no kuni no kami (Governor of Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>祖父藤原顕憲の養子としてその家を継ぐという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to become an adopted son of his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Akinori to succeed to the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that he was likely to become an adopted son of his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Akinori, to succeed to the family&apos;s title.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that he was likely to become an adopted son of his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Akinori, to succeed to the family&apos;s title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>父盛憲、叔父藤原経憲はともに保元の乱で流罪となり、一時一家は没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though his father, Morinori and his uncle, FUJIWARA no Tsunenori were exiled in Hogen War and its family once fell, Kiyofusa served the Emperor Gotoba who his cousin, MINAMOTO no Zaishi married and made an effort to recover the luck of his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though his father, Morinori, and his uncle, FUJIWARA no Tsunenori, were exiled during the Hogen War and the family declined, Kiyofusa served the Emperor Gotoba who was his cousin, and MINAMOTO no Zaishi married and made an effort to recover the luck of the family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation. The sentence is a little long and wordy and would benefit from being broken up.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Morinori, and his uncle, FUJIWARA no Tsunenori, were exiled after the Hogen War and the family declined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処天皇が「従兄弟」になっていることと、「保元の乱の間に流罪になった」のは誤訳と考え,また、ＮＣコメントに従って原文訳文とも分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>清房は従姉妹の源在子が入内した後鳥羽天皇に近侍し家運の回復に努める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyofusa served the Emperor Gotoba whom MINAMOTO no Zaishi, his cousin, married and made an effort to recover the luck of the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、承久3年（1221年）の承久の乱の結果、後鳥羽上皇が隠岐国へ流罪となると、清房もこれに従い、出家の上隠岐へと下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the retired Emperor Gotoba was exiled to Oki Province as a result of Jokyu War in 1221, Kiyofusa entered into priesthood and went to Oki to follow him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the retired Emperor Gotoba was exiled to Oki Province as a result of the Jokyu War in 1221, Kiyofusa entered into the priesthood, going to Oki to follow him.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the Retired Emperor Gotoba was exiled to Oki Province as a result of the Jokyu War in 1221, Kiyofusa entered into the priesthood, going to Oki to follow him.</e>
<cmt>retired→Retired</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>次男の上杉重房は丹波国何鹿郡上杉庄（京都府綾部市上杉町周辺）を領して上杉重房となり、征夷大将軍の宗尊親王と共に関東の鎌倉へ下ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigefusa UESUGI, his second son became Shigefusa UESUGI after seizing Uesugi no sho, Ikaruga County, Tanba Province (now, Uesugi-cho area, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture) and went to Kamakura in Kanto region with Imperial Prince Munetaka, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigefusa UESUGI, his second son, became Shigefusa UESUGI after seizing Uesugi no sho, Ikaruga County, Tanba Province (now, Uesugi-cho area, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture) and went to Kamakura in the Kanto region with Imperial Prince Munetaka, seii taishogun (&quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigefusa UESUGI, his second son, became Shigefusa UESUGI after seizing Uesugi no sho, Ikaruga County, Tanba Province (now, Uesugi-cho area, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture) and went to Kamakura in the Kanto region with Imperial Prince Munetaka, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この重房が室町時代に関東管領・大名などを出す上杉氏の祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Shigefusa was the ancestor of the Uesugi clan from which later generated Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Shigefusa was the ancestor of the Uesugi clan from which later generated Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Shigefusa was the ancestor of the Uesugi clan from which later generated Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>