<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小宰相</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小宰相（こざいしょう、嘉応元年（1164年）？- 寿永3年（1184年）2月14日 (旧暦)）は平安時代末期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaisho (1164? ~ April 3, 1184 was a woman of the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaisho (1164? ~ April 3, 1184 was a woman who lived at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaisho (1164? - April 3, 1184 was a woman who lived at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>~ → -</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>刑部卿藤原憲方の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter the Minister of Justice, FUJIWARA no Norikata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daughter of the Minister of Justice, FUJIWARA no Norikata.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of the Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice), FUJIWARA no Norikata.</e>
<cmt>Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice)に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平通盛の妻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a wife of TAIRA no Michimori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a wife of TAIRA no Michimori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a wife of TAIRA no Michimori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>一ノ谷の戦いでの平通盛の死とその妻小宰相が後を追って入水したエピソードは、古典軍記物語『平家物語』で一章が割かれ、一ノ谷の戦いでの象徴的な悲話になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An episode that the death of Michimori at the Battle of Ichinotani and his wife Kozaisho drowned herself following his husband became a symbolic tragedy of the Battle of Ichnotani that spared an entire chapter of classical war chronicle, &quot;The Tale of the Heike.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An episode in which Michimori dies in the Battle of Ichinotani and his wife Kozaisho drowned herself following her husband became a symbolic tragedy of the Battle of Ichnotani and covered an entire chapter of the classical war chronicle, &quot;The Tale of the Heike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An episode in which Michimori dies in the Battle of Ichinotani and his wife Kozaisho drowned herself following her husband became a symbolic tragedy of the Battle of Ichnotani and covered an entire chapter of the classical war chronicle, &quot;The Tale of the Heike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>小宰相は統子内親王（鳥羽天皇の皇女で後白河天皇の同母姉）の女房で、宮中一の美女とうたわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaisho was a court lady served to Imperial Princess Muneko (Imperial princess of Emperor Toba and an elder sister-uterine of Emperor Goshirakawa) and was said to be the most beautiful woman in the court at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaisho was a court lady who served Imperial Princess Muneko (Imperial princess of Emperor Toba and an elder sister-uterine of Emperor Goshirakawa) and was said to be the most beautiful woman in the court at the time.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaisho was a court lady who served Imperial Princess Muneko (Imperial princess of Emperor Toba and an elder sister of Emperor Goshirakawa) and was said to be the most beautiful woman in the court at the time.</e>
<cmt>sister-uterine→sister</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>彼女が16歳のとき（治承3年（1179年）頃？）に法勝寺の花見にお供した際に、これを見た中宮亮通盛は彼女に一目ぼれした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time she accompanied Imperial Princess who went to see the cherry blossoms at Hosho-ji Temple when Kozaisho was 16 years old (around 1179?), Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household Michimori saw Kozaisho and fell in love with her at first sight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time she accompanied the Imperial Princess who went to see the cherry blossoms at Hosho-ji Temple when Kozaisho was 16 years old (around 1179?), the Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household Michimori saw Kozaisho and fell in love with her at first sight.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time she accompanied the Imperial Princess who went to see the cherry blossoms at Hosho-ji Temple when Kozaisho was 16 years old (around 1179?), the Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household Michimori saw Kozaisho and fell in love with her at first sight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、和歌や恋文をしきりに贈るが3年たっても小宰相は返事をしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he sent her waka poems and love letters at brief intervals, however, Kozaisho never replied to him for 3 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he sent her waka poems and love letters at brief intervals; however, over a period of 3 years, Kozaisho never replied to him.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he sent her waka poems and love letters at brief intervals; however, over a period of 3 years, Kozaisho never replied to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>これが最後と思い、文を書き使いに渡したが、折悪しく取次の女房がいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote a letter to her thinking it for the last one and handed it to a messenger, however, unluckily there was no usherette at her place at the time when the messenger visited.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote a letter to her thinking it would be the last one and handed it to a messenger; however, unluckily there was no usherette at her place at the time the messenger visited.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote a letter to her thinking it would be the last one and handed it to a messenger; however, unluckily there was no usherette at her place at the time the messenger visited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>使いが戻ろうとすると、ちょうど里から帰ってくる小宰相の車に行き合った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the messenger was on the way back, he happened to meet Kozaisho on her carriage who returned to the palace from her home</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the messenger was on the way back, he happened to meet Kozaisho in her carriage as she was returning to the palace from her home</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the messenger was on the way back, he happened to meet Kozaisho in her carriage as she was returning to the palace from her home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>使いは文を車に投げ入れて去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The messenger threw the letter into her carriage and left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The messenger threw the letter into her carriage and left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The messenger threw the letter into her carriage and left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>小宰相はとりあえず持ち帰ったが、御所で宮仕えしていたとき上西門院の前でこの文を取り落とし、女院はこれを拾って「あまり気が強いのもよくありませんよ」と、みじめな最後を遂げたという小野小町の例を出して、自ら硯を取り寄せて返事を書いてやるようにうながした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaisho took it back tentatively, however, she mistakenly dropped it just in front of Josaimonin (Imperial Princess Muneko) when served, and Josaimonin picked it up and said &quot;Too much strong-mindedness is not favored&quot; citing an example of ONO no Komachi who was said to have died a miserable death, and Josaimonin ordered to bring her an ink stone and prompted Kozaisho to write a reply to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaisho took the letter tentatively; however, she mistakenly dropped it just in front of Josaimonin (Imperial Princess Muneko) when served, and Josaimonin picked it up and said &quot;Too much strong-mindedness is not favored&quot; citing an example of ONO no Komachi who was said to have died a miserable death, and Josaimonin ordered an ink stone to be brought and prompted Kozaisho to write a reply to him.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaisho took the letter tentatively; however, she mistakenly dropped it just in front of Josaimonin (Imperial Princess Muneko) when served, and Josaimonin picked it up and said &quot;Too much strong-mindedness is not favored&quot; citing an example of ONO no Komachi who was said to have died a miserable death, and Josaimonin ordered an ink stone to be brought and prompted Kozaisho to write a reply to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>こうして女院の仲立ちで通盛と小宰相は結ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, Michimori and Kozaisho were united after the mediation of Josaimonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, Michimori and Kozaisho were united after the mediation of Josaimonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, Michimori and Kozaisho were united after the mediation of Josaimonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>恋愛の末に結ばれたので、ふたりはたいそう仲睦まじかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The couple was happy together very much as they were united after a romantic relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The couple was very happy together, as they were united after a romantic relationship.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The couple was very happy together, as they were united after a romantic relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>通盛は小宰相の他に政治的な必要で従兄の平宗盛の娘も妻にしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michimori married a daughter of his cousin, TAIRA no Munemori in political necessity other than Kozaisho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to marrying Kozaisho, Michimori married a daughter of his cousin, TAIRA no Munemori, out of political necessity.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to marrying Kozaisho, Michimori married a daughter of his cousin, TAIRA no Munemori, out of political necessity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>が、こちらはまだ12歳程度の幼い少女なので手をつけることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this wife was only a little girl of 12 something, therefore he never became intimate with her.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this wife was only a little girl of 12 something, and therefore he never became intimate with her.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this wife was only a little girl of 12 something, and therefore he never became intimate with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>やがて、治承・寿永の乱がはじまり、通盛は各地を転戦するが、平家は源義仲に大敗を喫し、寿永2年（1183年）ついに都落ちを余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, the Jisho-Juei War broke out and Michimori also fought in one place after another, however, the Heike clan suffered a crushing loss by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and in 1183, they were finally forced out from Kyo (the capital, namely Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, the Jisho-Juei War broke out and Michimori fought in one place after another; however, the Heike clan suffered a crushing loss to MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and in 1183, they were finally forced out from Kyo (the capital, namely Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, the Jisho-Juei War broke out and Michimori fought in one place after another; however, the Heike clan suffered a crushing loss to MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and in 1183, they were finally forced out from Kyo (the capital, namely Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>小宰相は通盛とともに海上を流浪した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaisho drifted on a boat at the sea with Michiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaisho drifted on a boat at sea with Michimori.</e>
<cmt>article, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaisho drifted on a boat at sea with Michimori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>平家は讃岐国屋島に本営を置き、やがて摂津国福原京にまで進出を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heike clan placed the headquarter at Yashima, Sanuki Province (today&apos;s Kagawa Province) and then fought back to Fukuhara-kyo (the capital once Heike clan transferred from Kyoto), Settsu Province (around today&apos;s Hyogo and Kyoto prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heike clan placed its headquarters at Yashima, Sanuki Province (today&apos;s Kagawa Province) and then fought back to Fukuhara-kyo (the capital once the Heike clan transferred from Kyoto), Settsu Province (around today&apos;s Hyogo and Kyoto prefectures).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heike clan placed its headquarters at Yashima, Sanuki Province (today&apos;s Kagawa Province) and then fought back to Fukuhara-kyo (the capital once the Heike clan transferred from Kyoto), Settsu Province (around today&apos;s Hyogo and Kyoto prefectures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>寿永3年（1184年）正月、義仲は鎌倉の源頼朝の弟の源範頼・源義経に滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1184, Yoshinaka was defeated by younger brothers of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamaukra, MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1184, Yoshinaka was defeated by younger brothers of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamaukra, MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1184, Yoshinaka was defeated by younger brothers of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamakura, MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>同年2月には範頼・義経は大軍を率いて福原へ迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of the year, Noriyori and Yoshitsune closed in on Fukuhara leading numerous army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of the year, Noriyori and Yoshitsune closed in on Fukuhara leading a large army.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of the year, Noriyori and Yoshitsune closed in on Fukuhara leading a large army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>合戦を前に、通盛は沖合の船団から妻を呼び寄せ「明日の戦で討ち死にする様な気がする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the battle began, Michiyori called his wife on a fleet of boats offshore to his base and said to her that &quot;I feel like I might die at the battle tomorrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the battle began, Michimori called his wife on a fleet of boats offshore to his base and said to her that &quot;I feel like I might die in the battle tomorrow.&quot;</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the battle began, Michimori called his wife on a fleet of boats offshore to his base and said to her that &quot;I feel like I might die in the battle tomorrow.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>私がそうなったら、君はどうする」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What would you if it comes true?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What would you if it comes true?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What would you do if it comes true?&quot;</e>
<cmt>doを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>小宰相は戦はいつものことだから、この言葉が本当だとは思わず、自分が身籠っていることを告げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaisho did not believe his words as the battles became everyday business, and she told him that she was pregnant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaisho did not believe his words, as the battles had become everyday business, and she told him that she was pregnant.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaisho did not believe his words, as the battles had become everyday business, and she told him that she was pregnant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>通盛は「わたしは30歳になるが、どうせなら男子であって欲しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimichi said with great delight that &quot;I&apos;m 30 years old now that I want a boy (as an heir) if it&apos;s true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimichi said with great delight that &quot;Now I&apos;m 30 years old I want a boy (as an heir) if it&apos;s true.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimichi said with great delight that &quot;Now I&apos;m 30 years old I want a boy (as an heir) if it&apos;s true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>幾月になるのか？船上のことだから、心配だなあ」と大そう喜んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How many months are you pregnant? I&apos;m worried that you are on a boat.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How many months are you pregnant? I&apos;m worried that you are on a boat.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How many months are you pregnant? I&apos;m worried that you are on a boat.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>そこへ平家随一の剛勇で知られた弟の平教経がやって来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then his younger brother, TAIRA no Noritsune who was known as one of the best men of adamantine courage among the Heike clan appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then his younger brother, TAIRA no Noritsune, who was known as one of the best men of adamantine courage among the Heike clan, appeared.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then his younger brother, TAIRA no Noritsune, who was known as one of the best men of adamantine courage among the Heike clan, appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>怒りながら「ここはこの教経が置かれるほどの危険な戦場ですぞ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ticked off his elder brother saying with anger that &quot;Here is such a dangerous place among the battlefield where the man like me is posted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ticked off his elder brother, saying with anger, &quot;Here is such a dangerous place among the battlefield where a man like me is posted.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ticked off his elder brother, saying with anger, &quot;Here is such a dangerous place among the battlefield where a man like me is posted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>そのような心がけではものの役に立ちますまいに」と兄を嗜めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a mind-set, you can&apos;t do your job well.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a mind-set, you can&apos;t do your job well.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a mind-set, you can&apos;t do your job well.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>通盛ももっともなことと思い妻を船へ帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michimori thought that his brother&apos;s words were right and let his wife go back to the fleet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michimori thought that his brother&apos;s words were right and let his wife go back to the fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michimori thought that his brother&apos;s words were right and let his wife go back to the fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>合戦は平家の大敗に終わり、一門の多くの者が討ち死にし、通盛もまた船へ帰ってこなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle ended in pasting of the Heike clan and a number of soldiers of the clan died and Michimori also never returned to his boat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle ended in pasting of the Heike clan; a number of soldiers of the clan died and Michimori never returned to his boat.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle ended in pasting of the Heike clan; a number of soldiers of the clan died and Michimori never returned to his boat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>屋島へ向かう平家の船団の中で小宰相は、夫が討たれたとは聞いてはいたが、何かの間違いであろうと、生きて帰ることもあるかもしれないと心細く夫の帰りを待ち続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way back to Yashima, Kozaisho waited helplessly for the return of his husband on the fleet although she heard his husband had been killed, thinking it must have been wrong and there was a possibility that he would return alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way back to Yashima, although Kozaisho heard that her husband had been killed, she waited helplessly for his return to the fleet, thinking it must have been wrong and there was a possibility that he would return alive.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way back to Yashima, although Kozaisho heard that her husband had been killed, she waited helplessly for his return to the fleet, thinking it must have been wrong and there was a possibility that he would return alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>小宰相が乗船している船に通盛の従者の滝口時員がやってきて、通盛が湊川で討死した旨と最後の奮戦の様子を報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A squire of Michimori, Tokikazu TAKIGUCHI came to her boat and reported that Michimori was killed at Minatogawa after his last and brave struggle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A squire of Michimori, Tokikazu TAKIGUCHI, came to her boat and reported that Michimori was killed at Minatogawa after his last brave struggle.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A squire of Michimori, Tokikazu TAKIGUCHI, came to her boat and reported that Michimori was killed at Minatogawa after his last brave struggle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これを聞いて小宰相は返事もできずに泣き伏し、夜が明けるまで起き上がることもできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having heard this, Kozaisho could not respond to it, and she was dissolved in tears and she could not get up by the time dawn broke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having heard this, Kozaisho could not respond to it; she was dissolved in tears and she could not get up by the time dawn broke.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having heard this, Kozaisho could not respond to it; she was dissolved in tears and she could not get up by the time dawn broke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>2月14日、船団が屋島に到着する夜、小宰相は乳母に「湊川の後、誰も夫と会った人はいませんでした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the night of April 3, when the fleet reached Yashima, Kozaisho said to her nan that &quot;There is no one who met my husband after the Battle of Minatogawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the night of April 3, when the fleet reached Yashima, Kozaisho said to her nan that &quot;There is no one who met my husband after the Battle of Minatogawa.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the night of April 3, when the fleet reached Yashima, Kozaisho said to her nanny that &quot;There is no one who met my husband after the Battle of Minatogawa.</e>
<cmt>nan→nanny</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>もう、夫は亡きものと覚悟しました」と言うと福原での夫との最後の対面のことを語り、「子を産んで形見として育てねばならないと思うが、悲しみは増すばかりで、亡き人の恋しさに苦しむよりは海の底へ入ろうと思い定めました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I&apos;m prepared to believe my husband&apos;s death&quot; and then talked about the last time she saw her husband at Fukuhara saying and asking that &quot;Though I think I must have my baby and raise it to keep in memory of him, but my sorrow only grows stronger and I&apos;m prepared to sink deep in the sea instead of suffering from the sadness I feel for my dead husband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I&apos;m prepared to believe my husband&apos;s death&quot;; she then talked about the last time she saw her husband at Fukuhara, saying and asking that &quot;Though I think I must have my baby and raise it to keep in memory of him, my sorrow only grows stronger and I&apos;m prepared to sink deep in the sea instead of suffering from the sadness I feel for my dead husband.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I&apos;m prepared to believe my husband&apos;s death&quot;; she then talked about the last time she saw her husband at Fukuhara, saying and asking that &quot;Though I think I must have my baby and raise it to keep in memory of him, my sorrow only grows stronger and I&apos;m prepared to sink deep in the sea instead of suffering from the sadness I feel for my dead husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>どうか夫と私の菩提を弔っておくれ」と頼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please pray to Buddha for the happiness of my dead husband and me.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please pray to Buddha for the happiness of my dead husband and me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please pray to Buddha for my late husband and me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>the happiness of を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="38">
<j>乳母は涙を抑えて「子を産んで育て、尼になって生きるべきです」と必死に止めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nan held back her tears and said &quot;You should have baby to raise it and you should keep on living as a nun&quot; and tried desperately to stop Kozaisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nan held back her tears and said &quot;You should have baby to raise it and you should keep on living as a nun&quot; and tried desperately to stop Kozaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nanny held back her tears and said &quot;You should have baby to raise it and you should keep on living as a nun&quot; and tried desperately to stop Kozaisho.</e>
<cmt>nan→nanny</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>小宰相もその場は「身を投げるといって、本当に身を投げる人はいませんよ」と思いとどまったように答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Kozaisho replied that as if she held back at the time saying &quot;No one actually drown oneself saying to do so.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Kozaisho replied that as if she held back at the time saying, &quot;No one actually drowns oneself after saying to do so.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Kozaisho replied that as if she held back at the time saying, &quot;No one actually drowns oneself after saying to do so.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="40">
<j>やがて、乳母がうたた寝すると小宰相は起き上がり、「南無西方極楽世界…どうか、別れた夫婦を極楽で会わせてください」と念仏を唱えると海に身を投げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the nan fell into a short sleep, Kozaisho got up and recited Buddhist invocation that &quot;I believe Western Land of Utmost Bliss…. Please let my husband and myself meet at the Paradise&quot;, and threw herself into the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the nan fell into a short sleep, Kozaisho got up and recited Buddhist invocation that &quot;I believe int he Western Land of Utmost Bliss…. Please let my husband and myself meet in Paradise,&quot; and threw herself into the sea.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the nanny fell into a short sleep, Kozaisho got up and recited Buddhist invocation that &quot;I believe in the Western Land of Utmost Bliss…. Please let my husband and myself meet in Paradise,&quot; and threw herself into the sea.</e>
<cmt>in the → in the</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="41">
<j>梶取りがこれを見かけて、乳母を起こして、みなで海を探し、ようやく小宰相の体を引き揚げたが、すでに死んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The steerer of the boat watched this and woke up the nan and then, all the people searched her in the sea and finally found Kozaisho and pulled up her on the boat, however, she was already dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The steerer of the boat watched this and woke up the nan; all the people searched for her in the sea and finally found Kozaisho and pulled her up on the boat; however, she was already dead.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The steerer of the boat watched this and woke up the nanny; all the people searched for her in the sea and finally found Kozaisho and pulled her up on the boat; however, she was already dead.</e>
<cmt>nan→nanny</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>乳母は通盛の鎧を亡骸に着せて、泣く泣く小宰相を海に沈めて葬った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nan invested her body with the armor of Michimori and sank it in the sea with tears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nan invested her body with the armor of Michimori and sank it in the sea with tears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nanny invested her body with the armor of Michimori and sank it in the sea with tears.</e>
<cmt>nan→nanny</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>その後、乳母は通盛の弟で僧侶になっていた中納言律師仲快のもとで剃髪出家して、通盛と小宰相の菩提を弔った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, the nan tonsured and became a nun under a younger brother of Michimori, Chunagon (middle counselor) Chukai RITSUSHI (Buddhist priest) who became a priest, and she prayed to Buddha for the happiness of Michimori and Kozaisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, the nan tonsured and became a nun under a younger brother of Michimori, Chunagon (middle counselor) Chukai RITSUSHI (Buddhist priest) who became a priest, and she prayed to Buddha for the happiness of Michimori and Kozaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, the nanny tonsured and became a nun under a younger brother of Michimori, Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) Chukai RITSUSHI (Buddhist priest) who became a priest, and she prayed to Buddha for the happiness of Michimori and Kozaisho.</e>
<cmt>nan→nanny(vice-councilor of state)に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="44">
<j>人々は、夫に先立たれた妻は尼になるのが普通なのに、後を追うとは珍しいことだと感心し「忠臣は二君に仕えず、貞女は二夫にまみえず」と（『史記』の故事をひいて）言い合った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People were very impressed with this case that although usually wives who were bereaved of their husbands became nuns, that Kozaisho followed her husband was remarkable saying each other that &quot;Royal subjects never serve to two Kings and chaste wives never marry two husbands&quot; (citing tradition from Shiki Chinese history book.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People were very impressed with this case; although wives who were bereaved of their husbands usually became nuns, Kozaisho following her husband was remarkable; people said to each other that &quot;Royal subjects never serve two two Kings and chaste wives never marry two husbands&quot; (citing tradition from Shiki Chinese history book.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People were very impressed with this case; although wives who were bereaved of their husbands usually became nuns, Kozaisho following her husband was remarkable; people said to each other that &quot;Royal subjects never serve two Kings and chaste wives never marry two husbands&quot; (citing tradition from &quot;Shiki,&quot; Chinese history book.)</e>
<cmt>two two→two</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="45">
<j>『建礼門院右京大夫集』にも上西門院の美人で有名だった女房が通盛の妻となり、夫の死の後を追ったことが「これまでにない契の深さよ」と京都でも評判になったと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in &quot;Kenrei Monin Ukyo no Daibu Shu&quot; (The poetic Memoirs of Lady Daibu), there is an entry that a rumor earned popularity in Kyoto that a court lady who was famous for her beauty served to Josaimonin became a wife of Michimori and followed after her husband when he died with the words that &quot;What a strong tie of a husband and a wife that has never ever been.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in &quot;Kenrei Monin Ukyo no Daibu Shu&quot; (The poetic Memoirs of Lady Daibu), there is an entry that a rumor earned popularity in Kyoto that a court lady who was famous for her beauty served Josaimonin, became a wife of Michimori, and followed after her husband when he died with the words, &quot;What a strong tie of a husband and a wife that has never ever been.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in &quot;Kenrei Monin Ukyo no Daibu Shu&quot; (The poetic Memoirs of Lady Daibu), there is an entry that a rumor earned popularity in Kyoto that a court lady who was famous for her beauty served Josaimonin, became a wife of Michimori, and followed after her husband when he died with the words, &quot;What a strong tie of a husband and a wife that has never ever been.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Yume149(id:17504), Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>