<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原伊周</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korechika</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Korechika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korechika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 伊周（ふじわらの これちか、天延2年（974年） - 寛弘7年1月28日 (旧暦)（1010年2月14日））は平安時代中期の廷臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korechika (974 - February 14, 1010) was a court official in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Korechika (974 - February 14, 1010) was a court official in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korechika (974 - February 14, 1010) was a court official in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>官名を以って帥内大臣・儀同三司と通称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly called Sochi no Naidaijin (Viceroy Minister of the Center) and Gidosanshi (designation equivalent to Jundaijin or the three ministers such as chancellor, minister of the left, and minister of the right) after his official title.</e>
<cmt>「帥内大臣」は定訳不明です。官名ではなく官職をもじってあだ名としたとも考えられます。「儀同三司」は准大臣に匹敵する名誉職のようですが、准大臣(deputy_minister)の訳語を充てて良いか判断が付きかねます。ご検討下さい。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly called Sochi no Naidaijin (Viceroy Minister of the Center) and Gidosanshi (designation equivalent to Jundaijin, or the three ministers: chancellor, minister of the left, and minister of the right) after his official title.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly called Sochi no Naidaijin (Viceroy Minister of the Center) and Gidosanshi (designation equivalent to Jundaijin, or the three ministers: chancellor, minister of the left, and minister of the right) after his official title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>天延2年（974年）、円融天皇代、藤原北家摂関流の上卿大納言藤原兼家の嫡男・兵衛佐藤原道隆と、内裏の内侍であった高階成忠女高階貴子の間に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 974, in the reign of Emperor Enyu, Korechika was born between Hyoe no suke (the assistant captain of the headquarters of the Middle Palace Guard) FUJIWARA no Michitaka, a legitimate son of Shokei (court noble who work at the Imperial Court as high rank post) Dainagon (chief councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Kaneie from the Sekkan family line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and TAKASHINA no Takako, who was a daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada and served as naishi (lady-in-waiting) at dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 974, during the reign of Emperor Enyu, Korechika was born between Hyoe no suke (the assistant captain of the headquarters of the Middle Palace Guard) FUJIWARA no Michitaka, a legitimate son of Shokei (court noble who work at the Imperial Court in a high-ranking post) Dainagon (chief councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Kaneie from the Sekkan family line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and TAKASHINA no Takako, who was a daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada and served as naishi (lady-in-waiting) at dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt>rwording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 974, during the reign of Emperor Enyu, Korechika was born between Hyoe no suke (the assistant captain of the headquarters of the Middle Palace Guard) FUJIWARA no Michitaka, a legitimate son of Shokei (court noble who work at the Imperial Court in a high-ranking post) Dainagon (chief councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Kaneie from the Sekkan (regents and advisers) family line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and TAKASHINA no Takako, who was a daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada and served as naishi (lady-in-waiting) at dairi (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>摂関　の補足を追加しました。ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>異母兄として「大千代君」の幼名を持つ藤原道頼がいたため、「小千代君」と名づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While FUJIWARA no Michiyori, his elder brother of a different mother, had been given a childhood name of &apos;Ochiyogimi&apos; (big-chiyogimi), he was named &apos;Kochiyogimi&apos; (small-chiyogimi.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While FUJIWARA no Michiyori, his elder brother of a different mother, had been given the childhood name of &apos;Ochiyogimi&apos; (big-chiyogimi), he was named &apos;Kochiyogimi&apos; (small-chiyogimi.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While FUJIWARA no Michiyori, his elder brother of a different mother, had been given the childhood name of &apos;Ochiyogimi&apos; (big-chiyogimi), he was named &apos;Kochiyogimi&apos; (small-chiyogimi).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同腹の弟妹に、一条天皇皇后藤原定子・中納言藤原隆家・小松僧都隆円・三条天皇東宮女御藤原原子・道隆三女（敦道親王室）・道隆四女（一条天皇御匣殿 (藤原道隆四女)）らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika had siblings of the same mother: empress to Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Teishi; Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Takaie; Komatsu Sozu Ryuen; nyogo (consort) of Emperor Sanjo from Crown Prince, FUJIWARA no Genshi; the third daughter of Michitaka (wife of Imperial Prince Atsumichi); and the fourth daughter of Michitaka (mikushige-dono (mistress of wardrobe) of Emperor Ichijo (the fourth daughter of FUJIWARA no Michitaka.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika had siblings of the same mother: empress to Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Teishi; Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Takaie; Komatsu Sozu Ryuen; nyogo (consort) of Emperor Sanjo from Crown Prince, FUJIWARA no Genshi; the third daughter of Michitaka (wife of Imperial Prince Atsumichi); and the fourth daughter of Michitaka (mikushige-dono (mistress of wardrobe) of Emperor Ichijo (the fourth daughter of FUJIWARA no Michitaka.))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika had siblings of the same mother: empress to Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Teishi; Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Takaie; Komatsu Sozu Ryuen; nyogo (consort) of Emperor Sanjo from Crown Prince, FUJIWARA no Genshi; the third daughter of Michitaka (wife of Imperial Prince Atsumichi); and the fourth daughter of Michitaka (mikushige-dono (mistress of wardrobe) of Emperor Ichijo (the fourth daughter of FUJIWARA no Michitaka.))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>寛和元年（985年）11月20日、12才で元服し、同日従五位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 8, 986 (November 20 in Kanna 1 according to the old calendar), he made genpuku (coming of age) ceremony at the age of 12, and on the same day, he was bestowed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt>「寛和元年（985年）」とありますが、寛和元年の「11月20日」は986年になっておりますので訂正して訳しました。尚、翌年の天皇即位に昇殿にできるように年末に元服を済ませ官位を頂いておいたという含みを考慮して、旧暦では１１月２０日にあたることを括弧内に付記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 8, 986 (November 20 in Kanna 1 according to the old calendar), he celebrated his genpuku (coming of age) ceremony at the age of 12, and on the same day, he was bestowed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 8, 986 (November 20, 985 in old lunar calendar), he celebrated his genpuku (coming of age) ceremony at the age of 12, and on the same day, he was bestowed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>翌年7月22日、一条天皇の即位式の日に昇殿し、ついで侍従・左兵衛佐に任ず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 3 in the same year (July 3 in Kanna 2 according to the old calendar), he entered into the Imperial Court on the day of the enthronement ceremony of Emperor Ichijo, and he was appointed jiju (chamberlain) and Sahyoue no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt>前文で寛和元年１１月２０日が既に986年になっておりますので「翌年」は「同年」として訳し、旧暦では翌年の７月２２日にあたることを括弧内に付記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 3 in the same year (July 3 in Kanna 2 according to the old calendar), he entered into the Imperial Court on the day of the enthronement ceremony of Emperor Ichijo, and he was appointed jiju (chamberlain) and Sahyoue no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 3 in the same year, he entered into the Imperial Court on the day of the enthronement ceremony of Emperor Ichijo, and he was appointed jiju (chamberlain) and Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>旧暦は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>永延元年（987年）9月4日近衛少将、翌2年正月15日禁色を聴される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 4, 987, he was appointed Konoe no shosho (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards), and on February 10, 988, he was allowed to wear kinjiki (forbidden colors; colors like a deep shade of dark red or purple that could be worn only by members of the Imperial family or high court nobles.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 4, 987, he was appointed Konoe no shosho (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards), and on February 10, 988, he was allowed to wear kinjiki (forbidden colors; colors like a deep shade of dark red or purple that could be worn only by members of the Imperial family or high court nobles.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 4, 987, he was appointed Konoe no shosho (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards), and on February 10, 988, he was allowed to wear kinjiki (forbidden colors; colors like a deep shade of dark red or purple that could be worn only by members of the Imperial family or high court noble).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>正暦元年（990年）5月8日、祖父兼家の後をついで父道隆が摂政に就任し、さらに同年10月中宮に同母妹定子が立つと、摂関家の嫡男としてその地位は飛躍的に上昇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 8, 990, his father Michitaka succeeded his grandfather Kaneie as Sessho (Regent), and in October 990, his younger sister of the same mother Teishi became chugu (the second consort of an emperor); accordingly, he was also promoted by leaps and bounds as the legitimate son of the Sekkan family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 8, 990, his father Michitaka succeeded his grandfather Kaneie as Sessho (Regent), and in October 990, his younger sister of the same mother Teishi became chugu (the second consort of an emperor); accordingly, he was also promoted by leaps and bounds as the legitimate son of the Sekkan family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 8, 990, his father Michitaka succeeded his grandfather Kaneie as Sessho (Regent), and in October 990, his younger sister of the same mother Teishi became chugu (the second consort of an emperor); accordingly, he was also promoted by leaps and bounds as the legitimate son of the Sekkan family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同年中に近衛中将・蔵人頭を経験し、正暦2年（991年）正月26日、参議となって公卿に列し、同7月27日従三位、9月7日には中納言に昇叙、更に翌3年8月28日、正三位大納言に進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year according to the old calendar, he was also appointed Konoe no chujo (Middle Captain of the Palace Guards) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain); on February 18, 991, he became Sangi (councilor) and ranked among court nobles; on November 13, 991, he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank); on October 22, 991, he was promoted to Chunagon; and on October 2, 992, he was promoted to Shosanmi Dainagon (Senior Third Rank, chief councilor of state.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year according to the old calendar, he was also appointed Konoe no chujo (Middle Captain of the Palace Guards) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain); on February 18, 991, he became Sangi (councilor) and ranked among court nobles; on November 13, 991, he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank); on October 22, 991, he was promoted to Chunagon; and on October 2, 992, he was promoted to Shosanmi Dainagon (Senior Third Rank, chief councilor of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was also appointed Konoe no chujo (Middle Captain of the Palace Guards) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain); on February 18, 991, he became Sangi (councilor) and ranked among court nobles; on September 13, 991, he was conferred Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank); on October 22, 991, he was promoted to Chunagon; and on October 2, 992, he was promoted to Shosanmi Dainagon (Senior Third Rank, chief councilor of state.)</e>
<cmt>一部グレゴリオ暦を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>その翌年、正暦5年（994年）8月28日、伊周は8歳年上の叔父藤原道長ら3人の先任者を飛び越えて内大臣に昇進（上席の右大臣は叔父藤原道兼）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 10 in the next year 994, Korechika was promoted to Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) jumping ahead of three predecessors including his eight years senior uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga (his another uncle FUJIWARA no Michikane was Udaijin (Minister of the Right), which ranked above Naidaijin.)</e>
<cmt>「その翌年」とありますが、前文最後の年月日は「3年8月28日」、この文章の年月日は「正暦5年（994年）8月28日」で、旧暦・西暦ともに翌々年にあたります。原文通りに訳しましたが、ご検討下さい。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10 in the next year 994, Korechika was promoted to Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) jumping ahead of three predecessors including his uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga who was eight years his senior (another uncle FUJIWARA no Michikane was Udaijin (Minister of the Right), which ranked above Naidaijin.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 10 in the next year 994, Korechika was promoted to Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) jumping ahead of three predecessors including his uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga who was eight years his senior (another uncle FUJIWARA no Michikane was Udaijin (Minister of the Right), which ranked above Naidaijin).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>時に21歳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika was 21 years old at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika was 21 years old at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika was 21 years old at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>道隆による強引な子息の官位引き上げは、一条天皇の生母藤原詮子（道隆の妹）をはじめとして、朝野上下の不満を募らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Michinaga raised his son to higher official ranks ignoring the competitors, resentment smoldered among all the people in and out of the Imperial Court from the biological mother of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Senshi (younger sister of Michitaka.) on down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Michinaga raised his son to higher official ranks ignoring the competitors, resentment smoldered among all the people in and out of the Imperial Court, from the biological mother of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Senshi (younger sister of Michitaka.) on down.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Michitaka raised his son to higher official ranks ignoring the competitors, resentment smoldered among all the people in and out of the Imperial Court, from the biological mother of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Senshi (younger sister of Michitaka) on down.</e>
<cmt>Michitaka に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>それは当時でこそ表面化することはなかったが、やがて道隆没後、人々の伊周への反発を招き、道長の政権奪取に絶好の下地を提供することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The resentment had not surfaced yet in those days, but after the death of Michitaka, it flared into open defiance against Korechika, which perfectly paved the way for Michinaga to seize political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The resentment had not surfaced yet in those days, but after the death of Michitaka, it flared into open defiance against Korechika, which perfectly paved the way for Michinaga to seize political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The resentment had not surfaced yet in those days, but after the death of Michitaka, it flared into open defiance against Korechika, which perfectly paved the way for Michinaga to seize political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>藤原実資などは、後に中関白家の没落に際し、「積悪の家、必ず余殃あり」と嘲ったほどであるから、この家に対する世人の冷たい目も知れよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People looked upon the downfall of Naka no kanpaku family afterwards with indifference -- as a good example of it, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke derided the family with a phrase &apos;The family that accumulated evil deeds would suffer misfortune.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People looked upon the downfall of Naka no kanpaku family afterwards with indifference -- as a good example of it, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke derided the family with a phrase &apos;The family that accumulated evil deeds would suffer misfortune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People looked upon the downfall of Naka no kanpaku family afterwards with indifference -- as a good example of it, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke derided the family with a phrase &apos;The family that accumulated evil deeds would suffer misfortune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>長徳元年（995年）2月始め、道隆は重病に陥るや、後任の執柄に伊周を強く押し、3月8日、一条天皇はまず関白道隆が内覧を行い、次いで内大臣伊周に内覧させるように命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of March in 995, upon falling seriously ill, Michitaka strongly recommended Korechika to succeed him as shippei (regent) -- On April 15, in response to that recommendation, Emperor Ichijo ordered Kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor) Michitaka to assume the title of Nairan (the honorary title of imperial document examiner) first and then have Naidaijin Korechika succeed to the tile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of March in 995, upon falling seriously ill, Michitaka strongly recommended Korechika to succeed him as shippei (regent) -- On April 15, in response to that recommendation, Emperor Ichijo ordered Kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor) Michitaka to assume the title of Nairan (the honorary title of imperial document examiner) first and then have Naidaijin Korechika succeed to the tile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of March in 995, upon falling seriously ill, Michitaka strongly recommended Korechika to succeed him as shippei (regent); on April 15, in response to that recommendation, Emperor Ichijo ordered Kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor) Michitaka to assume the title of Nairan (the honorary title of imperial document examiner) first and then have Naidaijin Korechika succeed to the tile.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これに対して伊周は、自分は関白から内覧の業務を内大臣に委ねることを伝えられており、宣旨の内容がこれに反すると抗議した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika opposed the order by alleging that the senji (imperial command) conflicted with what Kanpaku said to him to entrust the duty of Nairan to him, Naidaijin Korechika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika opposed the order by alleging that the senji (imperial command) conflicted with what Kanpaku said to him to entrust the duty of Nairan to him, Naidaijin Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika opposed the order by alleging that the senji (imperial command) conflicted with what Kanpaku said to him to entrust the duty of Nairan to him, Naidaijin Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため、翌日に改めて伊周をして文書内覧の宣旨を蒙らしめることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Korechika succeeded in receiving senji to assume the title of document Nairan anew on the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Korechika succeeded in receiving senji to assume the title of document Nairan anew on the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Korechika succeeded in receiving senji to assume the title of document Nairan anew on the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、この時下された宣命に、「関白病間」の語句があったのを、元は「関白病替」を望んでいた伊周は甚だ不満であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Korechika was quite displeased with senmyo (imperial edict) issued at that time because that included the phrase &apos;during the Kanpaku&apos;s illness&apos; while Korechika had wanted the phrase &apos;taking over Kanpaku because of Kanpaku&apos;s illness.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Korechika was quite displeased with a senmyo (imperial edict) issued at that time because it included the phrase &apos;during the Kanpaku&apos;s illness&apos; while Korechika had wanted the phrase &apos;taking over Kanpaku because of Kanpaku&apos;s illness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Korechika was quite displeased with a senmyo (imperial edict) issued at that time because it included the phrase &apos;during the Kanpaku&apos;s illness&apos; while Korechika had wanted the phrase &apos;taking over Kanpaku because of Kanpaku&apos;s illness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これを見た左少弁高階信順（伊周の母方の叔父）が、宣旨を作成した大外記中原致時に訂正を迫り、拒絶された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left) TAKASHINA no Nobuyori (Korechika&apos;s maternal uncle) saw this and pressed Daigeki (Senior Secretary) NAKAHARA no Munetoki who had drew up the senji to correct that but rejected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left) TAKASHINA no Nobuyori (Korechika&apos;s maternal uncle) saw this and pressed Daigeki (Senior Secretary) NAKAHARA no Munetoki who had drawn up the senji to correct that but rejected.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left) TAKASHINA no Nobuyori (Korechika&apos;s maternal uncle) saw this and pressed Daigeki (Senior Secretary) NAKAHARA no Munetoki who had drawn up the senji to correct that but rejected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これは伊周の驕りと捉えられ、やがて一条天皇の不興をも買い、己の政敵に付入る隙を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was interpreted as arrogance of Korechika, and in time, Korechika fell under the displeasure of Emperor Ichijo -- that gave his political opponents openings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was interpreted as arrogance of Korechika, and in time, Korechika fell under the displeasure of Emperor Ichijo -- that gave his political opponents openings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was interpreted as arrogance of Korechika, and in time, Korechika fell under the displeasure of Emperor Ichijo, which gave his political opponents openings.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからカンマに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また伊周は、内覧として倹約令を出したが、着物の裾の長さなど細部に至るまで厳しく掟を与えたため、公卿から批判の声が高く上がり、人々はその器量を疑った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Nairan, Korechika promulgated sumptuary laws, which strictly regulated in every details including the length of the train of kimono -- this was severely criticized by the court nobles, and people cast doubt on Korechika&apos;s capability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Nairan, Korechika promulgated sumptuary laws, which strictly regulated every detail, including the length of the train of kimono -- this was severely criticized by the court nobles, and people cast doubt on Korechika&apos;s capability.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Nairan, Korechika promulgated sumptuary laws, which strictly regulated every detail, including the length of the train of kimono; this was severely criticized by the court nobles, and people cast doubt on Korechika&apos;s capability.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>同4月5日、伊周は関白並みの随身兵仗を賜るも、同10日、最大の後ろ盾である父を失うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 12 in the same year, Korechika was bestowed on Zuijin (Imperial Guards) and Hyojo (armed soldiers) which was the privilege equivalent to Kanpaku, but on May 17, he lost his father, his strongest supporter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 12 in the same year, Korechika was bestowed Zuijin (Imperial Guards) and Hyojo (armed soldiers) which was a privilege equivalent to Kanpaku, but on May 17, he lost his father, his strongest supporter.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 12 in the same year, Korechika was bestowed Zuijin (Imperial Guards) and Hyojo (armed soldiers) which was a privilege equivalent to Kanpaku, but on May 17, he lost his father, his strongest supporter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>その後、17日間にも渡る関白の空位を経て、同月27日、道隆のすぐ下の同母弟である道兼が関白・藤氏長者に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a long interregnum (17 days) from that time, on June 3, Michikane, Michitaka&apos;s immediate younger brother of the same mother assumed the offices of Kanpaku and Toshi choja (head of the Fujiwara clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a long interregnum (17 days) from that time, on June 3, Michikane, Michitaka&apos;s immediate younger brother of the same mother, assumed the offices of Kanpaku and Toshi choja (head of the Fujiwara clan.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a long interregnum (17 days) from that time, on June 3, Michikane, Michitaka&apos;s immediate younger brother of the same mother, assumed the offices of Kanpaku and Toshi choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし、折りしも疫病に冒された彼は拝賀の僅か7日後、あっけなく薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michikane, having contracted an epidemic just at that time, suddenly died only seven days after the official celebration of the appointment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michikane, having contracted an epidemic just at that time, suddenly died only seven days after the official celebration of the appointment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michikane, having contracted an epidemic just at that time, suddenly died only seven days after the official celebration of the appointment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そこで、後継の関白を巡り、激しい闘争が道長と伊周の間に繰り広げられた挙句、5月11日、道長に文書内覧の宣旨が下り、翌月19日、彼は伊周を押し退けて右大臣に昇任、氏の長者並びに天下執行の宣旨を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Michinaga and Korechika fiercely struggled against each other to succeed to the seat of Kanpaku -- eventually on June 16, senji to assume the title of document Nairan was issued to Michinaga, and on July 24, Michinaga rose to Udaijin, thrusting aside Korechika, and received senji to assume the titles of Uji no choja (chieftain of family) and Tenka shikko (to administer the country.)</e>
<cmt>「天下執行」の読み方不明（てんかしっこう、てんげしっこう、てんかしぎょう、てんげしぎょう）です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Michinaga and Korechika fiercely struggled against each other to succeed to the seat of Kanpaku -- eventually on June 16, a senji to assume the title of document Nairan was issued to Michinaga, and on July 24, Michinaga rose to Udaijin, thrusting aside Korechika, and received a senji to assume the titles of Uji no choja (chieftain of family) and Tenka shikko (to administer the country.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Michinaga and Korechika fiercely struggled against each other to succeed to the seat of Kanpaku; eventually on June 16, a senji to assume the title of document Nairan was issued to Michinaga, and on July 24, Michinaga rose to Udaijin, thrusting aside Korechika, and received a senji to assume the titles of Uji no choja (chieftain of family) and Tenka shikko (to administer the country).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを外に移動しました。ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この辺りの子細について、『大鏡』は、伊周が一条天皇の寵愛深い妹の中宮を介し、御意を得ているのをかねてから快からず思っていた東三条院が、夜の御殿に押し入り、渋る一条天皇を泣いて説得したとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, the Great Mirror; a historical tale) described the circumstances behind that: Korechika have had audiences with Emperor Ichijo through his younger sister, the Emperor&apos;s favorite chugu -- with which Higashi Sanjoin (FUJIWARA no Akiko) had been displeased, and finally forced her way into the Emperor&apos;s residence at night and begged the hesitating Emperor in tears to give senji to Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, the Great Mirror; a historical tale) described the circumstances behind that: Korechika had had audiences with Emperor Ichijo through his younger sister, the Emperor&apos;s favorite chugu -- with which Higashi Sanjoin (FUJIWARA no Akiko) had been displeased, and finally forced her way into the Emperor&apos;s residence at night and begged the hesitating Emperor in tears to give a senji to Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, the Great Mirror; a historical tale), the circumstances behind that is as follows; Korechika had had audiences with Emperor Ichijo through his younger sister, the Emperor&apos;s favorite chugu, with which Higashi Sanjoin (FUJIWARA no Akiko) had been displeased, and finally forced her way into the Emperor&apos;s residence at night and begged the hesitating Emperor in tears to give a senji to Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからカンマに変更しました。According to ～　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>それ以前にも、石山寺に出かけた女院の車に近寄って愁訴した伊周を、供奉していた道長が叱責して退かせたといい、叔母に疎遠された伊周の憂いを窺わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also before that, there was another story that Korechika approached the palanquin of Nyoin (the Empress) on the way to Ishiyama-dera Temple and implored help, but Michinaga who attended Nyoin scolded Korechika and turned him away -- those stories told how Korechika felt miserable when he was given such cold receptions by his aunt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, before that, there was another story that Korechika approached the palanquin of Nyoin (the Empress) on the way to Ishiyama-dera Temple and implored help, but Michinaga, who attended Nyoin, scolded Korechika and turned him away -- those stories told how Korechika felt miserable when he was given such cold receptions by his aunt.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, before that, there was another story that Korechika approached the palanquin of Nyoin (the Empress) on the way to Ishiyama-dera Temple and implored help, but Michinaga, who attended Nyoin, scolded Korechika and turned him away; those stories told how Korechika felt miserable when he was given such cold receptions by his aunt.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>道長と伊周の間に蒔かれた争いの火種はなかなか燃え尽きず、同年夏以降、白熱化の一途を辿った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The struggle started between Michinaga and Korechika did not seem to cool down, rather, it heated up ever since the summer of the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The struggle that started between Michinaga and Korechika did not seem to cool down, rather, it heated up from the summer of the year.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The struggle that started between Michinaga and Korechika did not seem to cool down, rather, it heated up from the summer of the year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>7月24日、2人は仗座にて、氏長者の所領帳の所有をめぐって激しく口論、罵声が外まで聞こえて一座は恐れをなしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 27, Michinaga and Korechika started a quarrel over the possession of the land ledger of Uji no choja (common clan chieftain) in Joza (the headquarters of the inner palace guard inside the palace where court councils took place), which was so loud that their angry voices could be heard even outside the room and startled the whole company.</e>
<cmt>「仗座」は「仗議」（公卿の会議）が行われる部屋のことですが、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 27, Michinaga and Korechika started a quarrel over the possession of the land ledger of Uji no choja (common clan chieftain) in Joza (the headquarters of the inner palace guard inside the palace where court councils took place), which was so loud that their angry voices could be heard even outside the room and startled the whole company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 27, Michinaga and Korechika started a quarrel over the possession of the land ledger of Uji no choja in Joza (the headquarters of the inner palace guard inside the palace where court councils took place), which was so loud that their angry voices could be heard even outside the room and startled the whole company.</e>
<cmt>氏の長者　既出のため補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>3日後、伊周の同母弟・隆家の従者は道長の従者と都の大路にて乱闘し、翌月2日には道長の随身秦久忠が隆家方に殺害される事態に発展。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three days later, retainers of Takaie, Korechika&apos;s younger brother of the same mother, clashed with retainers of Michinaga on main street in Kyoto, which culminated in the incident on September 4 in which Michinaga&apos;s escort HATA no Hisatada was killed by Takaie&apos;s followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three days later, retainers of Takaie, Korechika&apos;s younger brother of the same mother, clashed with retainers of Michinaga on main street in Kyoto, which culminated in the incident on September 4 in which Michinaga&apos;s escort HATA no Hisatada was killed by Takaie&apos;s followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three days later, retainers of Takaie, Korechika&apos;s younger brother of the same mother, clashed with retainers of Michinaga on main street in Kyoto, which culminated in the incident on September 4 in which Michinaga&apos;s escort HATA no Hisatada was killed by Takaie&apos;s followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>同じ頃、道隆家の外戚、従二位高階成忠が道長を呪詛している噂も流れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that period, it was rumored that Junii (Junior Second Rank) TAKASHINA no Naritada, a maternal relative of Michitaka&apos;s family, was cursing Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that period, it was rumored that Junii (Junior Second Rank) TAKASHINA no Naritada, a maternal relative of Michitaka&apos;s family, was cursing Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that period, it was rumored that Junii (Junior Second Rank) TAKASHINA no Naritada, a maternal relative of Michitaka&apos;s family, was cursing Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし、焦燥して自滅の道を歩み始めた若い伊周・隆家兄弟に対し、老練な道長の方は気長に構え、しかも緻密な追い落とし策を練り始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The youthful brothers Korechika and Takaie grew impatient and moved toward self-destruction -- on the other hand, seasoned Michinaga took his time and started to concoct an elaborate plan to oust them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The youthful brothers Korechika and Takaie grew impatient and moved toward self-destruction -- meanwhile, seasoned Michinaga took his time and started to concoct an elaborate plan to oust them.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The youthful brothers Korechika and Takaie grew impatient and moved toward self-destruction; meanwhile, seasoned Michinaga took his time and started to concoct an elaborate plan to oust them.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>長徳2年（996年）は伊周兄弟にとって運命的な年であるのみならず、後期摂関時代史上、重要な一節といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">996 was not only the fateful year for Korechika and his brother but also marked the decisive turning point in the late sekkan period (regency period.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">996 was not only the fateful year for Korechika and his brother but also marked the decisive turning point in the late sekkan period (regency period.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">996 was not only the fateful year for Korechika and his brother but also marked the decisive turning point in the late sekkan period (regency period.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>いわゆる長徳の変は、故太政大臣恒徳公藤原為光の四女に通う花山天皇を、わが思い人為光三女目当てと誤解した伊周が弟隆家と謀って道すがら待ち伏せ、彼らの従者が放った矢が法皇の袖を突き通した一件に発端する（『小右記』によれば、法皇の従者の中に2名の死者が出たとも言う）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So-called Chotoku incident was provoked by an event: Korechika mistakenly believed that Emperor Kazan kept tryst with the Korechika&apos;s beloved third daughter of the late Dajo daijin (Grand minister of state) Kotokuko FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu, whereas the emperor kept tryst with the fourth daughter in fact, plotted with his brother Takaie to hid on the emperor&apos;s way, and their attendants shot arrows, one of which pierced the emperor&apos;s sleeve (according to &quot;Shoyuki&quot;(Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke), two attendants of the retired emperor (Kazan) died.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The so-called Chotoku incident was provoked by an event: Korechika mistakenly believed that Emperor Kazan had trysts with Korechika&apos;s beloved third daughter of the late Dajo daijin (Grand minister of state) Kotokuko FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu, whereas in fact the emperor had trysts with the fourth daughter, plotted with his brother Takaie to hide along the emperor&apos;s way, and their attendants shot arrows, one of which pierced the emperor&apos;s sleeve (according to &quot;Shoyuki&quot;(Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke), two attendants of the retired emperor (Kazan) died.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The so-called Chotoku Incident was provoked by an event: Korechika mistakenly believed that Emperor Kazan had trysts with Korechika&apos;s beloved third daughter of the late Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state) Kotokuko FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu, whereas in fact the emperor had trysts with the fourth daughter, plotted with his brother Takaie to hide along the emperor&apos;s way, and their attendants shot arrows, one of which pierced the emperor&apos;s sleeve (according to &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke), two attendants of the retired emperor (Kazan) died).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを外に移動しました。Chotoku Incident としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>当時、貴族間のこうした事件は決して珍しい事ではなかったが、退位したとは言え天皇に向けて矢を射掛けるという前代未聞の事件が問題にならない訳が無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although such incidents between nobles were not uncommon in those days, the unprecedented event of shooting an arrow at the emperor -- even though he had been retired -- could not avoid controversy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although such incidents between nobles were not uncommon in those days, the unprecedented event of shooting an arrow at the emperor -- even though he had been retired -- could not avoid controversy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although such incidents between nobles were not uncommon in those days, the unprecedented event of shooting an arrow at the emperor -- even though he had been retired -- could not avoid controversy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>1月16日 (旧暦)に起きた当事件への道長の反応は素早かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga immediately reacted to the incident which occurred on February 12, 996.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga immediately reacted to the incident, which occurred on February 12, 996.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga immediately reacted to the incident, which occurred on February 12, 996.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>同25日の県召除目除目で伊周の円座を撤することを命じ、一件が世上の噂に上るのを待って上意を動かした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga ordered to remove Korechika from membership in Agatameshi no jimoku (the ceremony of announcing the appointment of officials) which was to held on February 21, and when the incident sparked controversy, he appealed to the Emperor to take an action.</e>
<cmt>「県召除目」の後に「除目」が誤って挿入されているものと思われますので、訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga ordered that Korechika be removed from membership in Agatameshi no jimoku (the ceremony of announcing the appointment of officials) which was to held on February 21, and when the incident sparked controversy, he appealed to the Emperor to take action.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga ordered that Korechika be removed from membership in Agatameshi no jimoku (the ceremony of announcing the appointment of officials) which was to be held on February 21, and when the incident sparked controversy, he appealed to the Emperor to take action.</e>
<cmt>to be held としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>翌月2月5日には一条天皇が検非違使別当であった藤原実資に伊周邸の捜索を許可した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 2, Emperor Ichijo ordered Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the imperial Police) FUJIWARA no Sanesuke to raid Korechika&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 2, Emperor Ichijo ordered Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the imperial Police) FUJIWARA no Sanesuke to raid Korechika&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 2, Emperor Ichijo ordered Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the imperial Police) FUJIWARA no Sanesuke to raid Korechika&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>更に11日には陣定の最中に、天皇から頭中将藤原斉信に対して内大臣伊周・中納言隆家の罪名勘申の旨を有司に伝達するように命令が出されて道長に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further on March 8, at Jin no sadame (Cabinet Council), the Emperor ordered To no chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) FUJIWARA no Tadanobu to send the order to submit kanjin (a report requested from specialists concerning precedents for court rituals or other issues) on accusations against Naidaijin Korechika and Chunagon Takaie to court officials, and the order was brought to Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, on March 8, at Jin no sadame (Cabinet Council), the Emperor ordered To no chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) FUJIWARA no Tadanobu to send the order to submit a kanjin (a report requested from specialists concerning precedents for court rituals or other issues) on accusations against Naidaijin Korechika and Chunagon Takaie to court officials, and the order was brought to Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, on March 8, at Jin no sadame (Cabinet Council), the Emperor ordered To no chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) FUJIWARA no Tadanobu to send the order to submit a kanjin (a report requested from specialists concerning precedents for court rituals or other issues) on accusations against Naidaijin Korechika and Chunagon Takaie to court officials, and the order was brought to Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>『小右記』によれば、内覧の道長でさえ斉信の報告で初めて事実を知ったとされ、以後この事件の捜査は天皇の意向が優先され、道長らの決定が後追いするという展開で進められることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shoyuki&quot; described that even Michinaga, Nairan, had not heard of the order until he was reported by Tadanobu -- thereafter, the Emperor took initiative in investigating the incident, and the decisions made by Michinaga and the others followed suit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shoyuki&quot; described that even Michinaga, Nairan, had not heard of the order until he was notified by Tadanobu -- thereafter, the Emperor took initiative in investigating the incident, and the decisions made by Michinaga and the others followed suit.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; even Michinaga, Nairan, had not heard of the order until he was notified by Tadanobu; thereafter, the Emperor took initiative in investigating the incident, and the decisions made by Michinaga and the others followed suit.</e>
<cmt>According to ～　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>同4月1日、法琳寺の僧によって、国家にしか許されない大元帥法を伊周が私に修したことも奏上される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 26, a monk in the Horin-ji Temple reported to the Emperor that Korechika practiced privately Daigensuiho (the rite of prayer of Shingon esoteric Buddhism for protection of the country and the submission of enemies), which was forbidden to all but the state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 26, a monk in Horin-ji Temple reported to the Emperor that Korechika privately practiced Daigensuiho (the rite of prayer of Shingon esoteric Buddhism for protection of the country and the submission of enemies), which was forbidden to all but the state.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 26, a monk in Horin-ji Temple reported to the Emperor that Korechika privately practiced Daigensuiho (the rite of prayer of Shingon esoteric Buddhism for protection of the country and the submission of enemies), which was forbidden to all but the state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>同月24日に至り、花山法皇を射奉る不敬、東三条院呪詛、大元帥法を私に行うこと三カ条の罪状により、除目が行われ、内大臣伊周を大宰権帥に、中納言隆家を出雲国権守に貶める宣旨が下され、彼らの異母兄弟、外戚高階家、また中宮の乳母子源方理らも左遷されたり殿上の御簡を削られたりと、悉く勅勘を蒙った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 19, Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) took place based on three charges -- lese-majeste for shooting an arrow at Emperor Kazan, having cast a curse on Higashi Sanjoin, and having carried out privately Daigensuiho -- thereby senji was issued to demote Naidaijin Korechika to Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu officer) and Chunagon Takaie to Gon no kami (vice-protector) of Izumo Province and imperial reprimands were delivered to all of their half brothers by different mothers, maternal relative Takashina family, and a chugu&apos;s wet nurse&apos;s child MINAMOTO no Katamasa such that they were exiled or punished by salary reduction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 19, a Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) took place based on three charges -- lese-majeste for shooting an arrow at Emperor Kazan, having cast a curse on Higashi Sanjoin, and having carried out privately Daigensuiho -- thereby a senji was issued to demote Naidaijin Korechika to Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu officer) and Chunagon Takaie to Gon no kami (vice-protector) of Izumo Province, and imperial reprimands were delivered to all of their half brothers by different mothers, the maternal relative Takashina family, and a chugu&apos;s wet nurse&apos;s child MINAMOTO no Katamasa such that they were exiled or punished by salary reduction.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 19, a Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) took place based on three charges -- lese-majeste for shooting an arrow at Emperor Kazan, having cast a curse on Higashi Sanjoin, and having carried out privately Daigensuiho -- thereby a senji was issued to demote Naidaijin Korechika to Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu officer) and Chunagon Takaie to Gon no kami (vice-protector) of Izumo Province, and imperial reprimands were delivered to all of their half brothers by different mothers, the maternal relative Takashina family, and a chugu&apos;s wet nurse&apos;s child MINAMOTO no Katamasa such that they were exiled or punished by salary reduction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>折りしも懐妊中の中宮定子は先月始めから里第二条北宮に退出しており、衛門佐・惟宗允亮は御在所の西の対に在る伊周に配流の宣命を伝えたが、伊周は重病を称し、出立を拒んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, pregnant chugu Teishi had moved into her private residence called Nijo-Kitamiya (or Nijo no miya) at the beginning of the month before, and Korechika was staying at the western annex to her residence, where Emon no suke (Assistant Captain of Outer Palace Guards) KOREMUNE no Masasuke (or Tadasuke) delivered the senmyo into Hairu (exile) to Korechika -- Korechika refused to leave there under the pretext of being seriously ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, pregnant chugu Teishi had moved into her private residence called Nijo-Kitamiya (or Nijo no miya) at the beginning of the previous month, and Korechika was staying at the western annex to her residence, where Emon no suke (Assistant Captain of Outer Palace Guards) KOREMUNE no Masasuke (or Tadasuke) delivered the senmyo into Hairu (exile) to Korechika -- Korechika refused to leave, under the pretext of being seriously ill.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, pregnant chugu Teishi had moved into her private residence called Nijo-Kitamiya (or Nijo no miya) at the beginning of the previous month, and Korechika was staying at the western annex to her residence, where Emon no suke (Assistant Captain of Outer Palace Guards) KOREMUNE no Masasuke (or Tadasuke) delivered the senmyo into Hairu (exile) to Korechika; Korechika refused to leave, under the pretext of being seriously ill.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>彼は妹定子と相携えて離れず、度重なる勅命にも抗い、数日間膠着状態が続いたが、5月1日早朝になって、朝廷は宣旨を降し中宮御所の捜索を聴許。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika and his younger sister Teishi clung closely together and resisted the repeated imperial orders -- the situation ended in several days of stalemate, but eventually in the early morning of May 25, the Imperial Court issued senji to raid the chugu gosho (empress&apos;s palace; Nijo-Kitamiya.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika and his younger sister Teishi clung closely together and resisted the repeated imperial orders -- the situation ended in several days of stalemate, but eventually in the early morning of May 25, the Imperial Court issued a senji to raid the chugu gosho (empress&apos;s palace; Nijo-Kitamiya.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika and his younger sister Teishi clung closely together and resisted the repeated imperial orders; the situation ended in several days of stalemate, but eventually in the early morning of May 25, the Imperial Court issued a senji to raid the chugu gosho (empress&apos;s palace; Nijo-Kitamiya).</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>検非違使率いる武士どもが戸を壊し御所に乱入した後、中宮は屈辱に耐えられず自ら落飾、一同の悲泣の声は多数の見物人が聞くに忍びなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When many samurai (warriors) smashed the doors and broke into the imperial palace under the command of Kebiishi (police and judicial chief), chugu was so humiliated and abased that she cut off her hair to become a nun and those around her wailed so piteously and loudly as to cause heartrending grief in the hearts of the onlookers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When many samurai (warriors) smashed the doors and broke into the imperial palace under the command of Kebiishi (police and judicial chief), chugu was so humiliated and abased that she cut off her hair to become a nun and those around her wailed so piteously and loudly as to cause heartrending grief in the hearts of the onlookers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When many samurai (warriors) smashed the doors and broke into the imperial palace under the command of Kebiishi (police and judicial chief), chugu was so humiliated and abased that she cut off her hair to become a nun and those around her wailed so piteously and loudly as to cause heartrending grief in the hearts of the onlookers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その時捕まえられたのは隆家だけで、邸内に伊周の身柄は無かったが、事件の過程を詳らかに記す『栄花物語』「浦々の別れ」巻は、伊周が春日大社や木幡にある父の墓に参詣し、3日後僧形で帰ったと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Takaie was arrested and Korechika was not found in the palace at that time, but &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes; historical tales), the volume &apos;Uraura no wakare&apos; (leaving in shores) gave the details of the incident like this: Korechika visited Kasuga-taisha shrine and his father&apos;s tomb in Kohata, and three days after the raid, returned with his head shaven and attired as a monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Takaie was arrested and Korechika was not found in the palace at that time, but &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes; historical tales), the volume &apos;Uraura no wakare&apos; (leaving shores) gave the details of the incident as follows: Korechika visited Kasuga-taisha shrine and his father&apos;s tomb in Kohata, and three days after the raid, returned with his head shaven and attired as a monk.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Takaie was arrested and Korechika was not found in the palace at that time, but &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes; historical tales), the volume &apos;Uraura no wakare&apos; (leaving shores) gave the details of the incident as follows: Korechika visited Kasuga-taisha shrine and his father&apos;s tomb in Kohata, and three days after the raid, returned with his head shaven and attired as a monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>彼は数日後、配所に向けて出発した（5月15日伊周を播磨国に、隆家を但馬国に留める勅が発せられた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several days later, he left for haisho (the place where a criminal is sent) (On June 8, imperial orders were issued to confine Korechika in Harima Province and Takaie in Tajima Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several days later, he left for haisho (the place where a criminal is sent) (On June 8, imperial orders were issued to confine Korechika in Harima Province and Takaie in Tajima Province.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several days later, he left for haisho (the place where a criminal is sent) (on June 8, imperial orders were issued to confine Korechika in Harima Province and Takaie in Tajima Province).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>伊周の母貴子は出立の車に取り付いて同行を嘆願したが許されず、やがて病の床に就くことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika&apos;s mother Takako implored for permission to go with her son, clinging to the departing palanquin, but in vain -- shortly afterwards, she fell ill and confined to bed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika&apos;s mother Takako implored for permission to go with her son, clinging to the departing palanquin, but in vain -- shortly afterwards, she fell ill and was confined to bed.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika&apos;s mother Takako implored for permission to go with her son, clinging to the departing palanquin, but in vain; shortly afterwards, she fell ill and was confined to bed.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>十月初め、伊周は病む母を思って密かに入京し、中宮御所に匿ったが、平孝義らの密告によって同月11日には捕えられ、改めて大宰府へ護送された（当年の暮れに到着）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of November, Korechika, being anxious about his ill mother, returned to Kyoto stealthily and harbored in the chugu gosho, but TAIRA no Takayoshi and others laid information on that matter, and on November 29, Korechika was captured and sent back to Dazai-fu under guard (arrived there at the end of the year.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of November, Korechika, being anxious about his ill mother, returned to Kyoto stealthily and harbored in the chugu gosho, but TAIRA no Takayoshi and others laid information on that matter, and on November 29, Korechika was captured and sent back to Dazai-fu under guard (arrived there at the end of the year.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of November, Korechika, being anxious about his ill mother, returned to Kyoto stealthily and harbored in the chugu gosho, but TAIRA no Takayoshi and others laid information on that matter, and on November 29, Korechika was captured and sent back to Dazai-fu under guard (arrived there at the end of the year).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>そして貴子は10月末に薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the middle of December, Takako died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the middle of December, Takako died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the middle of December, Takako died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="54">
<j>同年12月には定子の腹から一条天皇第一皇女脩子内親王が出生し、帝が定子入内を強く望む一方、東三条女院の病気も一向に快方に向かわず、朝廷は遂に長徳3年（997年）4月5日、女院御悩による大赦に託けて大宰権帥伊周・出雲権守隆家兄弟の罪科を赦し、太政官符を以って召還することに決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 997, Teishi gave birth to Imperial Princess Shushi (or Nagako), the first Princess of Emperor Ichijo, and the Emperor yearned to have Teishi back in the Imperial Court as the Empress; on the other hand, Higashi Sanjo Nyoin (or Higashi Sanjoin) was hardly recovered yet from her illness -- At last on May 18, 997, the Imperial Court decided to pardon the brothers Dazai gon no sochi Korechika and Izumo gon no kami Takaie under the general amnesty on Nyoin gono (illness of Nyoin) to send them back by Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 997, Teishi gave birth to Imperial Princess Shushi (or Nagako), the first Princess of Emperor Ichijo, and the Emperor yearned to have Teishi back in the Imperial Court as the Empress; on the other hand, Higashi Sanjo Nyoin (or Higashi Sanjoin) was hardly recovered yet from her illness -- At last on May 18, 997, the Imperial Court decided to pardon the brothers Dazai gon no sochi Korechika and Izumo gon no kami Takaie under the general amnesty on Nyoin gono (illness of Nyoin) to send them back by Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 997, Teishi gave birth to Imperial Princess Shushi (or Nagako), the first Princess of Emperor Ichijo, and the Emperor yearned to have Teishi back in the Imperial Court as the Empress; on the other hand, Higashi Sanjo Nyoin (or Higashi Sanjoin) was hardly recovered yet from her illness; at last on May 18, 997, the Imperial Court decided to pardon the brothers Dazai gon no sochi Korechika and Izumo gon no kami Takaie under the general amnesty on Nyoin gono (illness of Nyoin) to send them back by Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。ハイフンからセミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>こうして伊周はその年の12月に帰洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Korechika came back to Kyoto in January 998.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Korechika came back to Kyoto in January 998.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Korechika came back to Kyoto in January 998.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="56">
<j>その後、長保元年（999年）11月7日、定子腹の第一皇子敦康親王が誕生し、伊周は一家再興の望みをかけて狂喜したが、奇しくも同じ日、入内後6日目の道長長女藤原彰子に女御の宣旨が下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, on December 22, 999, Teishi gave birth to Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, the first Prince, with whom Korechika, in a rapture of delight, put his hope of restoring the family; but on the same day, ironically enough, senji to become Nyogo was issued to FUJIWARA no Akiko, the first daughter of Michinaga, which was the sixth day after Akiko entered into the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, on December 22, 999, Teishi gave birth to Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, the first Prince, with whom Korechika, in a rapture of delight, put his hope of restoring the family; but on the same day, ironically enough, a senji to become Nyogo was issued to FUJIWARA no Akiko, the first daughter of Michinaga, which was the sixth day after Akiko entered into the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, on December 22, 999, Teishi gave birth to Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, the first Prince, with whom Korechika, in a rapture of delight, put his hope of restoring the family; but on the same day, ironically enough, a senji to become Nyogo was issued to FUJIWARA no Akiko, the first daughter of Michinaga, which was the sixth day after Akiko entered into the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>道長は蔵人頭藤原行成をして女院・一条天皇に働きかけ、翌長保2年2月25日、彰子を立后させて中宮と称し（定子は皇后に横滑り）、遂に前代未聞の一帝二后が現出したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga appealed to Nyoin and Emperor Ichijo for support, through Kurodo no to FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and on April 8, 1000, succeeded in having Akiko installed as the Empress and making her chugu (Teishi became an Empress (one rank higher than chugu)), which was the unprecedented one emperor and two empresses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga appealed to Nyoin and Emperor Ichijo for support, through Kurodo no to FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and on April 8, 1000, succeeded in having Akiko installed as the Empress and making her chugu (Teishi became an Empress (one rank higher than chugu)), which was the unprecedented situation of having one emperor and two empresses.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga appealed to Nyoin and Emperor Ichijo for support, through Kurodo no to FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and on April 8, 1000, succeeded in having Akiko installed as the Empress and making her chugu (Teishi became an Empress (one rank higher than chugu)), which was the unprecedented situation of having one emperor and two empresses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>心労に苛まれた定子はその年の暮れ、12月15日夜に第二皇女び子内親王（び＝女偏に美）を出産し、後産が降りぬままに翌日未明に崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under emotional stress, Teishi delivered Imperial Princess Bishi, the second Princess, on the night of January 18, 1001; however, before dawn of the next day, the afterbirth was delayed and Teishi died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under emotional stress, Teishi delivered Imperial Princess Bishi, the second Princess, on the night of January 18, 1001; however, before dawn of the next day, the afterbirth was delayed and Teishi died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under emotional stress, Teishi delivered Imperial Princess Bishi, the second Princess, on the night of January 18, 1001; however, before dawn of the next day, the afterbirth was delayed and Teishi died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その時、御産に奉仕していた伊周は妹の亡骸を抱き、声も惜しまず慟哭したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Korechika who was present during the delivery gathered his younger sister&apos;s dead body and wailed without restraint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Korechika, who was present during the delivery, gathered his younger sister&apos;s dead body and wailed without restraint.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Korechika, who was present during the delivery, gathered his younger sister&apos;s dead body and wailed without restraint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>皇后葬送の日、大雪の中を歩行して従った伊周が詠んだという歌が『続古今和歌集』に残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shokukokin Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry, Continued) contained the poem allegedly composed by Korechika making his way through heavy snowfall on the day of the Empress&apos;s funeral.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shokukokin Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry, Continued) contained the poem allegedly composed by Korechika while making his way through heavy snowfall on the day of the Empress&apos;s funeral.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;while&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Shokukokin Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry, Continued) there is a poem allegedly composed by Korechika while making his way through heavy snowfall on the day of the Empress&apos;s funeral.</e>
<cmt>In &quot;Shokokukin ～&quot; としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="61">
<j>長保3年（1001年）閏12月16日、6日後には崩御するような重病に悩まされた東三条院詮子は、一条天皇に甥伊周を本位（正三位）に復すよう促したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 7, 1002, Higashi Sanjoin Senshi, so seriously ill that she died six days later, asked Emperor Ichijo to restore her nephew Korechika his original title (Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).)</e>
<cmt>「1001年」とありますが、閏12月16日は1002年です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 7, 1002, Higashi Sanjoin Senshi, so seriously ill that she died six days later, asked Emperor Ichijo to restore her nephew Korechika his original title (Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 7, 1002, Higashi Sanjoin Senshi, so seriously ill that she died six days later, asked Emperor Ichijo to restore her nephew Korechika his original title (Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank)).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>これはいかにも、末弟を偏愛するあまり兄一家に過酷な措置を取った女院の最期の望みらしく、これ以上は無力な存在でしかない伊周を見限っての道長の意も汲んでいる（『権記』によれば、この前年の長保2年5月25日に道長が天皇に伊周復位の奏上を行ったものの、天皇が激しく激怒して断念したと記録されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was very likely for Nyoin -- who favored the youngest brother so much that she treated the elder brother&apos;s family harsh -- to make such a request at her last moment, and she might have gathered that Michinaga had become indifferent to Korechika who was no more competent (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary) recorded that Michinaga requested the Emperor to restore Korechika his original title on July 5, 1000, the year before, only to infuriate the Emperor and gave up the request.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was very likely for Nyoin -- who favored the youngest brother so much that she treated the elder brother&apos;s family harshly -- to make such a request at her last moment, and she might have gathered that Michinaga had become indifferent to Korechika who was no more competent (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary) recorded that Michinaga requested the Emperor to restore Korechika his original title on July 5, 1000, the year before, only to infuriate the Emperor and gave up the request.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was very likely for Nyoin -- who favored the youngest brother so much that she treated the elder brother&apos;s family harshly -- to make such a request at her last moment, and she might have gathered that Michinaga had become indifferent to Korechika who was no more competent (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary) recorded that Michinaga requested the Emperor to restore Korechika his original title on July 5, 1000, the year before, only to infuriate the Emperor and gave up the request).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>同5年9月22日、伊周は従二位に叙せられ、寛弘2年（1005年）2月25日正式に座次を大臣の下・大納言の上と定められ、翌月26日、改めて昇殿を聴され、11月13日には朝議に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 26, 1003, Korechika was invested with Junii (Junior Second Rank); on April 12, 1005, his precedence was officially decided to be lower than Daijin (Ministers) and upper than Dainagon (chief councilors of state); on May 13, 1005, he was permitted to enter into the Imperial Court again; and on December 22, 1005, he attended a Court Council.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 26, 1003, Korechika was invested with Junii (Junior Second Rank); on April 12, 1005, his precedence was officially decided to be lower than Daijin (Ministers) and higher than Dainagon (chief councilors of state); on May 13, 1005, he was permitted to enter into the Imperial Court again; and on December 22, 1005, he attended a Court Council.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 26, 1003, Korechika was invested with Junii (Junior Second Rank); on April 12, 1005, his precedence was officially decided to be lower than Daijin (Ministers) and higher than Dainagon (chief councilors of state); on May 13, 1005, he was permitted to enter into the Imperial Court again; and on December 22, 1005, he attended a Court Council.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>この間、寛弘元年秋には、道長が伊周作の「入宋 (王朝)僧寂照の旧房に到る」詩に唱和し、奏上して御製の詩を賜ったという、ささやかな交流の話も伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a story about a little friendship between them in this period: In the autumn of 1004, Michinaga joined the chorus of a poem composed by Korechika -- &apos;Priest Jakusho who went to Song dynasty finally returned to his old house&apos; -- and requested the Emperor to bestow him a poem composed by the Emperor and received one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a story about a little friendship between them in this period: In the autumn of 1004, Michinaga joined the chorus of a poem composed by Korechika -- &apos;Priest Jakusho who went to Song dynasty finally returned to his old house&apos; -- and requested the Emperor to bestow him a poem composed by the Emperor and received one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a story about a little friendship between them in this period: In the autumn of 1004, Michinaga joined the chorus of a poem composed by Korechika -- &apos;Priest Jakusho who went to Song dynasty finally returned to his old house&apos; -- and requested the Emperor to bestow him a poem composed by the Emperor and received one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="65">
<j>長保から寛弘初年にかけて、伊周が徐々に廟堂に復帰して行った背景には、なかなか皇子女を産まない中宮彰子に一条天皇が敦康親王を養わせ、道長もいざという時に備えて親王に奉仕を怠らなかったことが深く関係する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Choho era to the first year of Kanko era (from 999 to 1004), Korechika had gradually returned in Byodo (Imperial Court), which was deeply concerned with behind-the-scene circumstances like this: Emperor Ichijo made chugu Akiko, who had yet to give birth to a prince or princess, bring up Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, and Michinaga kept serving the Imperial Prince in case that the Imperial Prince succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Choho era to the first year of the Kanko era (from 999 to 1004), Korechika had gradually returned in Byodo (Imperial Court), which was deeply concerned with behind-the-scene circumstances like this: Emperor Ichijo made chugu Akiko, who had yet to give birth to a prince or princess, bring up Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, and Michinaga kept serving the Imperial Prince in case the Imperial Prince succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Choho era to the first year of the Kanko era (from 999 to 1004), Korechika had gradually returned in Byodo (Imperial Court), which was deeply concerned with behind-the-scene circumstances like this: Emperor Ichijo made chugu Akiko, who had yet to give birth to a prince or princess, bring up Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, and Michinaga kept serving the Imperial Prince in case the Imperial Prince succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>皇位継承の最短路線上にある親王の外舅である伊周に、世人は昼は道長に仕えても、夜は密かにその屋敷へ参上し続け、それが敦成親王（後の後一条天皇）の誕生後は絶えてなかったと、鎌倉時代の説話集『古事談』は伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past) in the Kamakura period contained such a story: As Korechika was a maternal uncle of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, who was the first prince in the line of succession to the imperial throne, people kept visiting the Korechika&apos;s residence secretly by night, while serving Michinaga by day -- but once Imperial Prince Atsuhira (later, Emperor Goichijo) was born, nobody visited the Korechika&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>最初の「親王」は明示されておりませんが「敦康親王」を指しますが、後の「敦成親王」との混同を避けるため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past) in the Kamakura period contained such a story: As Korechika was a maternal uncle of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, who was the first prince in the line of succession to the imperial throne, people kept visiting Korechika&apos;s residence secretly by night, while serving Michinaga by day -- but once Imperial Prince Atsuhira (later, Emperor Goichijo) was born, nobody visited Korechika&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past) written in the Kamakura period, people kept visiting Korechika&apos;s residence secretly by night, while serving Michinaga by day, as Korechika was a maternal uncle of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, who was the first prince in the line of succession to the imperial throne, but once Imperial Prince Atsuhira (later, Emperor Goichijo) was born, nobody visited Korechika&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>According to ～　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>確かに、寛弘5年（1008年）9月11日、彰子から一条天皇の第二皇子敦成親王が誕生したことは、甥の即位を強く望む伊周にとって致命的な打撃となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The birth of Imperial Prince Atsuhira, the second Imperial Prince of Emperor Ichijo by Akiko on October 18, 1008 dealt a death blow to Korechika who had strongly desired his nephew to ascend the throne indeed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The birth of Imperial Prince Atsuhira, the second Imperial Prince of Emperor Ichijo by Akiko on October 18, 1008 dealt a death blow to Korechika who had strongly desired his nephew to ascend the throne.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;indeed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The birth of Imperial Prince Atsuhira, the second Imperial Prince of Emperor Ichijo by Akiko on October 18, 1008 dealt a death blow to Korechika who had strongly desired his nephew to ascend the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>伊周は同年正月16日に大臣に准ぜられ封戸を賜り（准大臣の宣旨を蒙った伊周はそれ以後、儀同三司と自称）、朝議にも発言権が持てるようになったばかりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 2, 1008, Korechika was raised to a rank equivalent to Daijin (Minister) and granted salary (Korechika called himself Gidosanshi after he received senji to assume Jundaijin (Vice Minister)), and it was when he finally began to have a voice in the Court Council.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 2, 1008, Korechika was raised to a rank equivalent to Daijin (Minister) and granted salary (Korechika called himself Gidosanshi after he received senji to assume Jundaijin (Vice Minister)), and it was then that he finally began to have a voice in the Court Council.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 2, 1008, Korechika was raised to a rank equivalent to Daijin (Minister) and granted salary (Korechika called himself Gidosanshi after he received senji to assume Jundaijin (Vice Minister)), and it was then that he finally began to have a voice in the Court Council.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>落胆した彼は、敦成親王百日の儀に列席し、請われもしないのにあえて和歌序を執筆し、一座を驚かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discouraged Korechika attended Momoka no gi (first meal ceremony) of Imperial Prince Atsuhira, and wrote wakajo (poem preface; very important poetic genre) even though he was not asked to, which surprised the whole company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discouraged Korechika attended the Momoka no gi (first meal ceremony) of Imperial Prince Atsuhira, and wrote a wakajo (poem preface; very important poetic genre) even though he was not asked to, which surprised the whole company.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discouraged Korechika attended the Momoka no gi (first meal ceremony) of Imperial Prince Atsuhira, and wrote a wakajo (poem preface; very important poetic genre) even though he was not asked to, which surprised the whole company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>この時の序文は、『新撰朗詠集』に選ばれるほど素晴らしい出来であったが、時の人々は伊周の挙動を非難したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the wakajo wrote at that time was so splendid that it was selected for &quot;Shinsen Roei Shu&quot; (New Selection of Sung Poems), Korechika&apos;s that behavior was criticized by his contemporaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the wakajo written at that time was so splendid that it was selected for &quot;Shinsen Roei Shu&quot; (New Selection of Sung Poems), Korechika&apos;s behavior was criticized by his contemporaries.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the wakajo written at that time was so splendid that it was selected for &quot;Shinsen Roei Shu&quot; (New Selection of Sung Poems), Korechika&apos;s behavior was criticized by his contemporaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>同6年正月7日、正二位となるも、翌月20日には中宮と新生の皇子に対する呪詛事件が起き、伊周の叔母高階光子が入獄させられ、伊周は直ちに朝参を止められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 10, 1009, Korechika was invested with Shonii (Senior Second Rank); however, on March 25, a scandal of curses put on chugu and the newly-born Imperial Prince erupted, and Korechika&apos;s aunt TAKASHINA no Mitsuko was imprisoned and Korechika was forbidden to visit the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 10, 1009, Korechika was invested with Shonii (Senior Second Rank); however, on March 25, a scandal of curses put on chugu and the newly-born Imperial Prince erupted, and Korechika&apos;s aunt TAKASHINA no Mitsuko was imprisoned and Korechika was forbidden to visit the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 10, 1009, Korechika was invested with Shonii (Senior Second Rank); however, on March 25, a scandal of curses put on chugu and the newly-born Imperial Prince erupted, and Korechika&apos;s aunt TAKASHINA no Mitsuko was imprisoned and Korechika was forbidden to visit the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>その後4ヶ月も経たぬ6月13日には早くも一件落着して、伊周は朝参を聴され、また帯剣の殊遇も得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The case was closed on July 13, less than four months later, and Korechika was permitted to visit the Imperial Court and also treated so favorably as to be permitted to wear a sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The case was closed on July 13, less than four months later, and Korechika was permitted to visit the Imperial Court and also treated so favorably as to be permitted to wear a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The case was closed on July 13, less than four months later, and Korechika was permitted to visit the Imperial Court and also treated so favorably as to be permitted to wear a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>このような異常なまでに寛大な処理に照らすと、孫皇子の立太子目前に、道長が敦康親王の外戚家に追い討ちを企んだことが想定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from such extremely generous treatment, Michinaga supposedly had schemed to make a further attack on the weakened maternal family of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu immediately before Michinaga&apos;s grandson&apos;s Investiture of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from such extremely generous treatment, Michinaga supposedly had schemed to make a further attack on the weakened maternal family of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu immediately before Michinaga&apos;s grandson&apos;s Investiture of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from such extremely generous treatment, Michinaga supposedly had schemed to make a further attack on the weakened maternal family of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu immediately before Michinaga&apos;s grandson&apos;s Investiture of the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>その一方で、『政事要略』所収の事件に関する詔勅には一条天皇が名指しで伊周を非難した部分があり、伊周同様に敦康親王への皇位継承を望みながらも伊周に対しては長徳の変以来の不信が積み重ねられた一条天皇の複雑な感情も読み取ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, from the Imperial rescript on the incident contained in &quot;Seiji yoryaku&quot; (examples of the politics in the Heian period) in which Emperor Ichijo reprimanded Korechika by mentioning his name, Emperor Ichijo might have had mixed feelings about Korechika, while expecting Imperial Prince Atsuyasu to succeed the throne indeed as Korechika did, because Emperor Ichijo have had suspicions against Korechika since the Chotoku incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, from the Imperial rescript on the incident contained in &quot;Seiji yoryaku&quot; (examples of the politics in the Heian period) in which Emperor Ichijo reprimanded Korechika by mentioning his name, Emperor Ichijo might have had mixed feelings about Korechika, while expecting Imperial Prince Atsuyasu to succeed the throne as Korechika had done, because Emperor Ichijo had had suspicions against Korechika since the Chotoku incident.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, from the Imperial rescript on the incident contained in &quot;Seiji yoryaku&quot; (examples of the politics in the Heian period) in which Emperor Ichijo reprimanded Korechika by mentioning his name, Emperor Ichijo might have had mixed feelings about Korechika, while expecting Imperial Prince Atsuyasu to succeed the throne as Korechika had done, because Emperor Ichijo had had suspicions against Korechika since the Chotoku Incident.</e>
<cmt>Chotoku Incident としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="75">
<j>伊周は失意のうちに翌7年正月28日、37歳の壮年で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 20, 1010, Korechika died in despair in the prime of life at the age of 37.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 20, 1010, Korechika died in despair in the prime of life at the age of 37.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 20, 1010, Korechika died in despair in the prime of life at the age of 37.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>臨終に際し、彼は后がねに育てた2人の娘へ「くれぐれも、宮仕えをして、親の名に恥をかかせることをしてはならぬ」と、また息子藤原道雅に「人に追従して生きるよりは出家せよ」と遺言したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his last moments, Korechika said in his will to his two daughters whom he had brought up as candidates for empress, &apos;Be sure not to do anything to humiliate your father in the Imperial Court when you marry the emperor.&apos; and to his son FUJIWARA no Michimasa, &apos;It is better to become a priest than to suck around others.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his last moments, Korechika said in his will to his two daughters whom he had brought up as candidates for empress, &apos;Be sure not to do anything to humiliate your father in the Imperial Court when you marry the emperor.&apos; and to his son FUJIWARA no Michimasa, &apos;It is better to become a priest than to suck around others.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his last moments, Korechika said in his will to his two daughters whom he had brought up as candidates for empress, &apos;Be sure not to do anything to humiliate your father in the Imperial Court when you marry the emperor.&apos; and to his son FUJIWARA no Michimasa, &apos;It is better to become a priest than to suck around others.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>死後、その邸である室町第は群盗が入るほど荒廃し果てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Korechika died, his residence Muromachi-dai remained unoccupied so that robbers entered there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Korechika died, his residence Muromachi-dai remained unoccupied, and robbers entered there.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Korechika died, his residence Muromachi-dai remained unoccupied, and robbers entered there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>嫡男道雅（992年－1054年）は、三条院の皇女当子内親王との恋を引き裂かれて以後、官途にも恵まれず多くの乱行に及び、「荒三位」と渾名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika&apos;s legitimate son Michimasa (992 - 1054) was called &apos;Ara Sanmi&apos; (brutal third rank) because, after Michimasa was forcibly separated from his beloved Imperial Princess Toshi, an Imperial Princess of Sanjoin, he was not able to enter the government service and indulged in all sorts of violence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika&apos;s legitimate son Michimasa (992 - 1054) was called &apos;Ara Sanmi&apos; (brutal third rank) because, after Michimasa was forcibly separated from his beloved Imperial Princess Toshi, an Imperial Princess of Sanjoin, he was not able to enter the government service and indulged in all sorts of violence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika&apos;s legitimate son Michimasa (992 - 1054) was called &apos;Ara Sanmi&apos; (brutal third rank) because, after Michimasa was forcibly separated from his beloved Imperial Princess Toshi, an Imperial Princess of Sanjoin, he was not able to enter the government service and indulged in all sorts of violence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>僅かな慰みは、伊周の長女が道長の男藤原頼宗と結婚し、正室として重んぜられ、右大臣藤原俊家・大納言藤原能長（頼宗の弟大納言藤原能信の養子）をはじめとする多くの子を生んで伊周の血を永く伝えたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was some slight consolation to know that Korechika&apos;s eldest daughter married Michinaga&apos;s son FUJIWARA no Yorimune and was respected as his legal wife, and gave birth to many children including Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toshiie and Dainagon FUJIWARA no Yoshinaga (adopted into the family of Dainagon FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, a younger brother of Yorimune), having Korechika&apos;s line continued ever since.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was some slight consolation to know that Korechika&apos;s eldest daughter married Michinaga&apos;s son FUJIWARA no Yorimune and was respected as his legal wife, and gave birth to many children, including Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toshiie and Dainagon FUJIWARA no Yoshinaga (adopted into the family of Dainagon FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, a younger brother of Yorimune), and Korechika&apos;s line has continued ever since.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was some slight consolation to know that Korechika&apos;s eldest daughter married Michinaga&apos;s son FUJIWARA no Yorimune and was respected as his legal wife, and gave birth to many children, including Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toshiie and Dainagon FUJIWARA no Yoshinaga (adopted into the family of Dainagon FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, a younger brother of Yorimune), and Korechika&apos;s line has continued ever since.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="80">
<j>才名高かった母貴子から文人の血を享けた伊周は属文の卿相として、漢学に関しては一条朝随一の才能を公認され、早くから一条天皇に漢籍を進講した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika inherited his literature talent from his mother Takako, who was famous for her talent, and with his greatest talent of Sinology in the court of Emperor Ichijo having been officially approved as Shokubun no keisho (court nobles and state ministers who write the Chinese literature), he gave lectures on Kanseki (Chinese books) in the presence of the Emperor Ichijo from early period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika inherited his literature talent from his mother Takako, who was famous for her talent, and with his greatest talent of Sinology in the court of Emperor Ichijo having been officially approved as Shokubun no keisho (court nobles and state ministers who write the Chinese literature), he gave lectures on Kanseki (Chinese books) in the presence of the Emperor Ichijo from an early period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika inherited his literature talent from his mother Takako, who was famous for her talent, and with his greatest talent of Sinology in the court of Emperor Ichijo having been officially approved as Shokubun no keisho (court nobles and state ministers who write the Chinese literature), he gave lectures on Kanseki (Chinese books) in the presence of the Emperor Ichijo from an early period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>『本朝麗藻』『本朝文粋』『和漢朗詠集』に多くの秀逸な漢詩文を残し、その感慨に富む筆致は時に世人の涙を誘う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korechika left many superb Kanshi and Kanbun (Chinese poem and literature) in &quot;Honcho Reiso&quot;, &quot;Honcho Monzui&quot;(anthology of waka poems and prose written in classical Chinese), and &quot;Wakan Roeishu&quot; (Collection of Sung Japanese and Chinese poems), quite sentimental literary style of which had moved people to tears every now and then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korechika left many superb Kanshi and Kanbun (Chinese poem and literature) in &quot;Honcho Reiso&quot;, &quot;Honcho Monzui&quot; (anthology of waka poems and prose written in classical Chinese), and &quot;Wakan Roeishu&quot; (Collection of Sung Japanese and Chinese poems), the sentimental literary style of which had moved people to tears every now and then.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korechika left many superb Kanshi and Kanbun (Chinese poem and literature) in &quot;Honcho Reiso&quot;, &quot;Honcho Monzui&quot; (anthology of waka poems and prose written in classical Chinese), and &quot;Wakan Roeishu&quot; (Collection of Sung Japanese and Chinese poems), the sentimental literary style of which had moved people to tears every now and then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>歌集『儀同三司集』は散逸してしまったが、『後拾遺和歌集』以下の勅撰歌人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the collection of his poems &quot;Gidosanshishu&quot; (Collection of Gidosanshi) had been dispersed and lost, Korechika had been Chokusen kajin (poet selected by the emperor) after &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the collection of his poems &quot;Gidosanshishu&quot; (Collection of Gidosanshi) had been dispersed and lost, Korechika had been Chokusen kajin (poet selected by the emperor) after &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the collection of his poems &quot;Gidosanshishu&quot; (Collection of Gidosanshi) had been dispersed and lost, Korechika had been Chokusen kajin (poet selected by the emperor) after &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>またその容姿は端麗だったと、『枕草子』『栄花物語』などに見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documents including &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (literally, the Pillow Book; collection of essays) and &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; described Korechika as good-looking man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents including &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (literally, the Pillow Book; collection of essays) and &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; described Korechika as a good-looking man.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents including &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (literally, the Pillow Book; collection of essays) and &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; described Korechika as a good-looking man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>『大鏡』は彼の不遇を自身の器量不足に求めつつも、その学才が日本のような小国には勿体なかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Okagami&quot; described that his misfortune stemmed from his lack of capability, but also evaluates his academic ability too high for such a small country as Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Okagami&quot; described that his misfortune stemmed from his lack of capability, but also evaluates his academic ability too high for such a small country as Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Okagami,&quot; his misfortune stemmed from his lack of capability, but also evaluates his academic ability too high for such a small country as Japan.</e>
<cmt>according to ～　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="85">
<j>駿河国大森氏など、子孫を名乗る家もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some clans including the Omori clan in Suruga Province claimed descendants of Korechika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some clans, including the Omori clan in Suruga Province, claimed to be descendants of Korechika.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some clans, including the Omori clan in Suruga Province, claimed to be descendants of Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Dr jimmy(id:111486), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), 二八(id:10408), Cprobot(id:97843), Yume149(id:17504), Point136(id:211299), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Andee(id:20421), けんち(id:5147), 諸星団(id:72202), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>