<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平資盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Sukemori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Sukemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Sukemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 資盛（たいら の すけもり）は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Sukemori was a busho(Japanese military commander) lived in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Sukemori was a Japanese military commander (busho) who lived in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Sukemori was a Japanese military commander (busho) who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>period　小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平重盛の次男、母は藤原親盛の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of TAIRA no Shigemori and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Chikamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of TAIRA no Shigemori, and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Chikamori.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of TAIRA no Shigemori, and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Chikamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>位階は従三位まで昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted up to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attained the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attained the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>和歌に優れ「新勅撰和歌集」「風雅和歌集」に名を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He excelled in waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem) and earned his place in &quot;Shin chokusen wakashu&quot; (&quot;A new anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command&quot;) and &quot;Fuga wakashu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He excelled in the waka form of poetry (a 31-syllable verse in native Japanese script), and examples of his verse appear in two Imperial collectoins of waka poetry, &quot;Shin chokusen wakashu&quot; (&quot;A new anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command&quot;) and &quot;Fuga wakashu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar, I gather that there is a separate entry for &quot;waka&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He excelled in the waka form of poetry (a 31-syllable verse in native Japanese script), and examples of his verse appear in two Imperial collections of waka poetry, &apos;Shin chokusen wakashu&apos; (A new anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) and &apos;Fuga wakashu&apos; (Collection of Japanese Poetry of Elegance).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。風雅和歌集　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>叔母である平徳子に仕える優れた歌人の建礼門院右京大夫と恋仲であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was involved with Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu who was a excellent poet and served his aunt, TAIRA no Tokuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was romantically involved with Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu, who was an outstanding poet and in the service of his aunt, TAIRA no Tokuko.</e>
<cmt>grammar, meaning of 恋仲 somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was romantically involved with Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu, who was an outstanding poet and in the service of his aunt, TAIRA no Tokuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>平氏一門の全盛期に、当時13歳（もしくは10歳）の資盛が関わった殿下乗合事件は、『平家物語』に「これこそ、平家の悪行のはじまり」として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Denkanoriai Incident in which Sukemori was involved at the age of 13 (or 10) happened in the Taira clan&apos;s day and it was described that it was the beginning of the Taira clan&apos;s misdeeds in &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Denkanoriai Incident, in which Sukemori was involved at the age of 13 (or perhaps 10), occurred when the Taira clan was at the peak of its influence, and is described as representing the beginning of the Taira clan&apos;s misdeeds in &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Denkanoriai Incident, in which Sukemori was involved at the age of 13 (or perhaps 10), occurred when the Taira clan was at the peak of its influence, and is described as representing the beginning of the Taira clan&apos;s misdeeds in &quot;The Tale of the Heike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>嘉応2年（1170年）7月3日、摂政・松殿基房の車と行き違った時に下馬の礼をとらなかったため、基房の家来と乱闘騒ぎを起こして資盛は恥辱を受けて逃げ帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 3, 1170, since he didn&apos;t dismount a horse with courtesy when he went by a cow carriage of the regent, Motofusa MATSUDONO, he scuffled with a retainer of Motofusa, then he was affronted and ran away.</e>
<cmt>「車」は「牛車（=cow carriage）」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 3, 1170, he was involved in a scuffle with a retainer of the regent, MATSUDONO Motofusa, because he failed to dismount his horse and pay his respects to the regent, when their paths crossed on the road, the regent travelling in an ox-drawn carriage, upon which, being insulted by the confrontation, fled and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar, unclear as to where he fled to 逃げ帰った</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 23, 1170, he was involved in a scuffle with a retainer of the regent, MATSUDONO Motofusa, because he failed to dismount his horse and pay his respects to the regent, when their paths crossed on the road, the regent traveling in a carriage, upon which, being insulted by the confrontation, fled and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>ox-drawn を削除しました。旧暦で記載されていると判断し、グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これを知った父・平重盛が基房に対して徹底的な報復を行っている（殿下乗合事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, TAIRA no Shigemori heard of the event and thoroughly retaliated on Motofusa (It is called the Denkanoriai Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his father, TAIRA no Shigemori, heard of the event, he proceeded to exact a thorough retaliation on Motofusa, and this is what is referred to as the Denkanoriai Incident.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his father, TAIRA no Shigemori, heard of the event, he proceeded to execute a thorough retaliation on Motofusa, and this is what is referred to as the Denkanoriai Incident.</e>
<cmt>execute としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお平家物語においては報復を行ったのは祖父の平清盛となっているが、これは清盛を悪役、重盛を平氏一門の良識派として描写する『平家物語』の演出の都合上の創作と言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;, the person who performed retaliation was his grandfather, TAIRA no Kiyomori, but it is considered to be a creation for the interpretation of &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; which described Kiyomori as a bad guy and Shigemori as a decent guy of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The account recorded in &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; depicts Taira no Kiyomori, his grandfather, as the individual responsible to the retaliation; however, this is considered to be historically inaccurate, and to have been adopted to the thematic scheme in &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;, according to which Kiyomori is portrayed as a black sheep, whereas Shigemori is portrayed as an upstanding member of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The account recorded in &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; depicts TAIRA no Kiyomori, his grandfather, as the individual responsible to the retaliation; however, this is considered to be historically inaccurate, and to have been adopted to the thematic scheme in &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;, according to which Kiyomori is portrayed as a black sheep, whereas Shigemori is portrayed as an upstanding member of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>TAIRAと大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この時の九条兼実の日記『玉葉』には資盛を「嫡男」と記されており、また同年12月以前においては異母兄であるとされている平維盛よりも官位で上回っていた事から当初は重盛の嫡男として扱われていたと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;, a diary of Kanezane KUJO, Sukemori is described as &quot;progeny&quot; and from the fact that he surpassed TAIRA no Koremori, who is thought to have been his older brother with different mother. in the official rank before December of the same year, he is considered to have been treated as a progeny of Shigemori at first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;, the diary of Kanezane KUJO, Sukemori is described as being the individual who was to succeed to the position of head of the family, and from the fact that he had already surpassed TAIRA no Koremori, who is thought to have been his older brother by a different mother, in official rank before December of the same year, it is considered that he was treated as Shigemori&apos;s heir from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;, the diary of Kanezane KUJO, Sukemori is described as being the individual who was to succeed to the position of head of the family, and from the fact that he had already surpassed TAIRA no Koremori, who is thought to have been his older brother by a different mother, in official rank before December of the same year, it is considered that he was treated as Shigemori&apos;s heir from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>治承4年（1180年）年5月の以仁王の挙兵に際して、叔父の平知盛、平重衡、兄の維盛らと出陣し、源頼政と平等院で戦いこれを滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Mochihitoo rose in arms in May 1180, he went off to war with his uncle, TAIRA no Tomonori, TAIRA no Shigehira and his older brother, Koremori, then they fought against MINAMOTO no Yorifusa at Byodoin Temple and destroyed him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Mochihitoo rose in arms in May 1180, Sukemori went off to war with a troop including his uncle, TAIRA no Tomonori, TAIRA no Shigehira, Koremori, his older brother, and they engaged in battle with MINAMOTO no Yorifusa at Byodoin Temple, where they detroyed the enemy forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Prince Mochihito rose in arms in June 1180, Sukemori went off to war with a troop including his uncle, TAIRA no Tomonori, TAIRA no Shigehira, Koremori, his older brother, and they engaged in battle with MINAMOTO no Yorifusa at Byodoin Temple, where they destroyed the enemy forces.</e>
<cmt>Prince Mochihito としました。スペルを修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同年12月、知盛とともに近江国へ出陣して山本義経を破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December of the same year, he went off to war in Omi Province with Tomonori and defeated Yoshitsune YAMAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December of the same year, he went off to war in Omi Province with Tomonori, where they defeated Yoshitsune YAMAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of the same year, he went off to war in Omi Province with Tomonori, where they defeated Yoshitsune YAMAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>一門都落ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira Clan&apos;s Exile from the Capital</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira Clan&apos;s Departure from the Capital</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan&apos;s departure from the capital</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）7月、平氏は源義仲に敗れ都落ちを余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1183, the Taira clan was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka and they had to exile from the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1183, the Taira clan was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and were forced to leave the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1183, the Taira clan was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and were forced to leave the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『愚管抄』によれば、このときに資盛は寵愛されていた後白河法皇に都に残る許しを求めて拒絶されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot;, Sukemori asked the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, who favored him, to allow him to stay in the capital, but refused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Gukansho&quot;, Sukemori asked the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, with whom he was in favor, to allow him to stay in the capital, but was refused.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), Sukemori asked the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, with whom he was in favor, to allow him to stay in the capital, but was refused.</e>
<cmt>愚管抄の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『平家物語』の「太宰府落」で資盛は元重盛の家人であった豊後国の緒方惟義の説得工作に向かって追い返されているが、『玉葉』の寿永3年2月19日条に資盛と平貞能が豊後国の住人によって拘束された風聞が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;Dazaifuochi&apos; of &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;, Sukemori was turned back when he went to convince Koreyoshi OGATA who was ex-retainer of Shigemori in Bungo Province, but in the section of February 19, 1184 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;, it is recorded that Sukemori and TAIRA no Sadayoshi were detained by residents of Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the episode entitled, &quot;Dazaifuochi&quot; in &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;, Sukemori had gone to attempt to try to win over Koreyoshi OGATA, who had been a retainer of Shigemori&apos;s in Bungo Province, and was turned away; however, in the entry for February 19, 1184 in the &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;, Sukemori and TAIRA no Sadayoshi are said to have been detained by residents of Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar, this Japanese is too vague.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the episode entitled, &apos;Dazaifu ochi&apos; in &quot;The Tale of the Heike,&quot; Sukemori had gone to attempt to try to win over Koreyoshi OGATA, who had been a retainer of Shigemori&apos;s in Bungo Province, and was turned away; however, in the entry for April 8, 1184 in the &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; Sukemori and TAIRA no Sadayoshi are said to have been detained by residents of Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>寿永3年（1184年）正月、一時勢力を回復した平氏は摂津国・福原京まで進出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1184, the Taira clan temporarily gained strength back and advanced upon Fukuhara kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1184, the Taira clan temporarily regained their strength, and advanced on Fukuhara kyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, what is fukuhara kyo?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Febrary 1184, the Taira clan temporarily regained their strength, and advanced on Fukuhara-kyo (the capital built by TAIRA no Kiyomori) in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>Settsu Province　を追加しました。福原京の補足をしました。グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>正月末に義仲を滅ぼした源頼朝の代官源範頼・源義経の軍勢が平氏追討に向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of January, the troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, local governors of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who destroyed Yoshinaka went to hunt down and kill the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of January, the troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, local governors under MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who had destroyed Yoshinaka, were dispatched to pursue and subjugate the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of February, the troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori, a local governor under MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who had destroyed Yoshinaka, and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune were dispatched to pursue and subjugate the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>資盛は弟の平有盛、平師盛、平忠房と播磨国三草山に陣を置くが源義経の奇襲を受け、讃岐国・屋島へ敗走した（三草山の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukemori encamped in Mount Mikusa, Harima Province together with TAIRA no Arimori, TAIRA no Moromori and TAIRA no Tadafusa, but they were ambushed by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and routed to Yahima, Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukemori encamped on Mount Mikusa, Harima Province, along with TAIRA no Arimori, TAIRA no Moromori and TAIRA no Tadafusa; however, they were ambushed by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, whereupon they fled to Yahima, Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukemori encamped on Mount Mikusa, Harima Province, along with his brothers TAIRA no Arimori, TAIRA no Moromori and TAIRA no Tadafusa; however, they were ambushed by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, whereupon they fled to Yashima, Sanuki Province (Battle of Mikusayama).</e>
<cmt>弟、　三草山の戦い　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その直後の2月7日、一ノ谷の戦いで平氏は一門の多くを失う致命的な大敗を喫する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after that, on February 7, the Taira clan lost numbers of family members and suffered a crushing defeat in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after that, on February 7, the Taira clan lost numerous family members, suffering a defeat at the Battle of Ichinotani from which the clan would not recover.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after that, on March 27, the Taira clan lost numerous family members, suffering a defeat at the Battle of Ichinotani from which the clan would not recover.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>同年3月、一ノ谷の合戦前後に戦線を離脱した兄の維盛が那智の沖で入水自殺する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of the same year, his older brother, Koremori, who left from the battlefront around the time of the Battle of Ichinotani, drowned himself in the offing of Nachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of the same year, Sukemori&apos;s older brother, Koremori, who had left the battlefront around the time of the Battle of Ichinotani, drowned himself off the coast of Nachi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, 那智の沖で somewhat unlcear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of the same year, Sukemori&apos;s older brother, Koremori, who had left the battlefront around the time of the Battle of Ichinotani, drowned himself off the coast of Nachi.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この知らせを受けた資盛は大いに嘆き悲しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukemori heard the news and mourned so much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sukemori heard the news he was beside himself with grief.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sukemori heard the news he was beside himself with grief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>すでに弟の平清経が豊後国で入水自殺しており、一ノ谷では14歳の師盛が討ち死にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother, TAIRA no Kiyotsune already drowned himself in Bungo Province and Moromori was killed in Ichinotani at the age of 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother, TAIRA no Kiyotsune, had already drowned himself in Bungo Province, and Moromori had been killed in battle at Ichinotani at the age of 14.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother, TAIRA no Kiyotsune, had already drowned himself in Bungo Province, and Moromori had been killed in battle at Ichinotani at the age of 14.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>末弟の平忠房は維盛の戦線離脱の際に同行していたと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His youngest brother, TAIRA no Tadafusa is considered to have gone with Koremori when he left the battlefront.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that his youngest brother, TAIRA no Tadafusa, iaccompanied Koremori when he left the battlefront.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that his youngest brother, TAIRA no Tadafusa, accompanied Koremori when he left the battlefront.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>清経と維盛の入水を知った建礼門院右京大夫から慰める手紙を受け取った資盛は、「今はただ自分の命も今日明日の事なので、ものを思う事をやめようという心境です」と返事を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Sukemori received a letter of comfort from Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu who heard of the drowning of Kiyotsune and Koremori, he replied as &quot;I know that my life can come to an end at any moment, thus I&apos;m trying not to bother.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sukemori received a letter of comfort from Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu, who had heard of the drownings of Kiyotsune and Koremori, he sent a reply, &quot;I know that my life may come to an end at any moment, thus I&apos;m trying not to let things weight too heavily on my mind.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sukemori received a letter of comfort from Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu, who had heard of the drownings of Kiyotsune and Koremori, he sent a reply, &apos;I know that my life may come to an end at any moment, thus I&apos;m trying not to let things weight too heavily on my mind.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>兄弟の死については「あるほどが　あるにもあらぬ　うちになほ　かく憂きことを　見るぞかなしき」（生きていることが生きていることにもならない、この世のうちにあって、その上こんなつらい目にあうのは悲しいことです）と詠んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the death of brothers, he made a waka saying &quot;In this world, living doesn&apos;t mean living, moreover, it is lamentable to have such a bitter experience.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the death of his brothers, he composed a waka that reads, &quot;In this world, being alive does not mean to be living, even moreso, to have met with such bitter experience is to know despair.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, not sure about this waka translation, it&apos;s a somewhat prosaic waka</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the death of his brothers, he composed a waka that reads, &apos;In this world, being alive does not mean to be living, even more so, to have met with such bitter experience is to know despair.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これが右京大夫への最後の便りとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the last letter for Ukyo-no-daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was his last letter to Ukyo-no-daibu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was his last letter to Ukyo-no-daibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>同年12月、資盛は備前国児島で源範頼と戦い敗北（藤戸の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December of the same year, Sukemori was defeated by MINAMOTO no Noriyori in Kojima, Bizen Province (it is called the Battle of Fujito).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December of the same year, Sukemori was defeated by MINAMOTO no Noriyori at the Battle of Fujito in Kojima, Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January of the next year (December of the same year), Sukemori was defeated by MINAMOTO no Noriyori in Kojima, Bizen Province (Battle of Fujito).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>元暦2年（1185年）3月24日、平氏は壇ノ浦の戦いで敗れ、滅亡に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 24, 1185, the Taira clan was defeated in the Battle of Dannoura and went to ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 24, 1185, the Taira clan was defeated at the Battle of Dannoura and fell into ruin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 2, 1185, the Taira clan was defeated at the Battle of Dannoura and fell into ruin.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>平氏西走の道中、兄弟が次々と脱落していった中で最後まで一門として踏みとどまった資盛は、一人残った弟の有盛と従弟の平行盛とともに壇ノ浦の急流に身を投じて自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Taira clan was running towards western, many of his brothers dropped off, but Sukemori remained as the family member to the last and he committed suicide with his only remaining younger brother, Arimori and his cousin, TAIRA no Yukimori by throwing himself into the rapid of Dannoura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Taira clan was in flight westward, many of Sukemori&apos;s brothers withdrew from the train along the way; however, as one of the members of the family who continued onward to the final destination, Sukemori along with his only remaining younger brother, Arimori, and his cousin, TAIRA no Yukimori, committed suicide by throwing themselves into the rapids of Dannoura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Taira clan was in flight westward, many of Sukemori&apos;s brothers withdrew from the train along the way; however, as one of the members of the family who continued onward to the final destination, Sukemori along with his only remaining younger brother, Arimori, and his cousin, TAIRA no Yukimori, committed suicide by throwing themselves into the rapids of Dannoura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>享年25。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His died at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His died at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>（もしくは28）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(or 28)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(or perhaps, 28)</e>
<cmt>grammar, placement</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(or perhaps, 28)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>資盛の死を悲しんだ建礼門院右京大夫は供養の旅に出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu mourned the death of Sukemori and went on a consolation journey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mourning the death of Sukemori, Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu embarked on a consolation journey.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mourning the death of Sukemori, Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu embarked on a consolation journey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>彼女の作品『建礼門院右京大夫集』には彼女と資盛が交わした歌が多く残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In her work &quot;Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu-no-shu&quot;, there are many waka exchanged between her and Sukemori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A compilation of her works &quot;The Collected Poems of Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu&quot; (Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu-no-shu), contains many waka poems that were exchanged between her and Sukemori.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A compilation of her works &quot;The Collected Poems of Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu&quot; (Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu-no-shu), contains many waka poems that were exchanged between her and Sukemori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>奄美諸島の喜界島には資盛がこの島まで落ち延びたという伝説が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kikai Island of Amami Islands, there is a legend saying Sukemori was routed to the island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Kikai Island in the Amami Islands, a legend is told recounting that Sukemori, being defeated in battle, sought refuge on the island.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Kikai Island in the Amami Islands, a legend is told recounting that Sukemori, being defeated in battle, sought refuge on the island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="37">
<j>信長を輩出した織田氏は資盛の末裔を自称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oda clan produced Nobunaga call themselves the descendant of Sukemori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oda clan, to which Nobunaga belonged, claimed descent from Sukemori.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oda clan, to which Nobunaga belonged, claimed descent from Sukemori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>遺言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Will</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A final letter to his lover</e>
<cmt>grammar, terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A final letter to his lover</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>平氏一門の都落ち直前、密かに建礼門院右京大夫と会っていた資盛は、日頃からの口癖として彼女に以下のような事を言い残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before the Taira clan&apos;s exile from the capital, Sukemori met Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu secretly and left the following word with her as the habit of saying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before the Taira clan&apos;s banishment from the capital, Sukemori met Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu in secret, and left her with the following words, which seem to represent his habitual form of expression at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before the Taira clan&apos;s banishment from the capital, Sukemori met Kenreimonin-ukyo-no-daibu in secret, and left her with the following words, which seem to represent his habitual form of expression at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この頃の資盛は心の余裕のない様子だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukemori had no room in his heart around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Sukemori had no room in his heart around that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Sukemori had no room in his heart around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="41">
<j>「こういう世の中になったからには、自分の身が儚くなるであろう事は間違いないだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;In this world, there is no doubt that my life will end so quickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;In the sort of world it has become, it would not be a mistake to imagine that one&apos;s life is but a fleeting moment.</e>
<cmt>Not sure about this translation, poetic…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;In the sort of world it has become, it would not be a mistake to imagine that one&apos;s life is but a fleeting moment.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そうなったら、あなたは少しくらいは不憫に思ってくれるだろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If so, would you feel sorry for me a little?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If such should be my fate, would you pity me a little in your thoughts?</e>
<cmt>unclear as to the intent of the speaker to me, because of a lack of sufficient context and familiarity with their poetical exchanges</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If such should be my fate, would you pity me a little in your thoughts?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>たとえ何とも思わなくても、あなたと親しくなって長いつきあいだから、その情けで、後世を弔ってほしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if you think nothing of my death, you and me had a longstanding relationship, thus I want you to pray for my soul to God for pity&apos;s sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if you were to think nothing of my death, as we shared a longlasting close relationship, I want you to take pity on my, and pray for the repose of my soul in the afterlife.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if you were to think nothing of my death, as we shared a long-lasting close relationship, I want you to take pity on me, and pray for the repose of my soul in the afterlife.</e>
<cmt>my →me　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>もし、命が今しばらくあったとしても、今はいっさい昔の身とは思わないと心に堅く決めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if I live for a while, I firmly decided not to think of myself as old self.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If perchance, I should remain in this world for some time to come, I have decided resolutely not to think of myself as the same self I used to be.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If perchance, I should remain in this world for some time to come, I have decided resolutely not to think of myself as the same self I used to be.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そのわけは、それが不憫であるとか、名残が惜しい、あの人の事が気がかりなどと考え始めたら、思うだけでもきりがないであろうから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it will go on forever if I start to allow self-pity, hate to leave, or worry for someone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason being that whether it be out of self pity, the sorrow of parting, or concern for the wellbeing of someone dear, once I allow myself to indulge such sentimental reminiscence, there will be no end to it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason being that whether it be out of self pity, the sorrow of parting, or concern for the wellbeing of someone dear, once I allow myself to indulge such sentimental reminiscence, there will be no end to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>心弱さもどのようであるかと我ながら自信がないから、今後は何事も思い捨てて、どこの海にあってもあなたのところへ手紙を出したりするまいと決心しているので、おろそかに思って便りもしないとは思わないで下さい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I&apos;m not sure of the strength of my heart and decided to forget everything and not to write to you wherever I will be. So, please do not think like I don&apos;t write to you because of neglect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As I am have become uncertain of the strength of my heart, I&apos;ve resolved not to dwell on the things of the past, and not to send letters to your door of tidings from whatever port I may find myself at. I beseesch you think of my lack of correspondence as neglect or a lack of regard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As I have become uncertain of the strength of my heart, I&apos;ve resolved not to dwell on the things of the past, and not to send letters to your door of tidings from whatever port I may find myself at; I beseech you not to think of my lack of correspondence as neglect or a lack of regard.</e>
<cmt>not to を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>万事、もう今から死んだと同じの身になったと心を決めたはずなのに、やはりともすれば以前の気持ちになってしまいそうなのが、とても口惜しい。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I hate to admit it, but I might go back to the previous feeling though I would have decided to think of myself as dead.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though I&apos;d resolved to consider myself dead to the world from this point, I dread the moments when I allow myself to think of what might have been, and am on the verge of slipping into those feelings from the past.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although I&apos;d resolved to consider myself dead to the world from this point, I dread the moments when I allow myself to think of what might have been, and am on the verge of slipping into those feelings from the past.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="48">
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology of government posts and ranks</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lunar calendar used for the dates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dates follow the lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dates follow the lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>永万2年のち改元して仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1166</e>
<cmt>改元については訳出不要と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1166</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1166</e>
<cmt>上記セルにて「旧暦」と但し書きがあるため、これ以降は旧暦で表記しています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>11月21日従五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on November 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awarded the court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), on November 21.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 21: Awarded the court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>コロンから始まる表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>12月30日越前守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assumed the position of Echizen no kami on December 30.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assumed the position of govenor of Echizen Province (Echizen no kami), on December 30.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 30: Assumed the position of Echizen no kami (governor of Echizen Province).</e>
<cmt>官職名について、日本名（英語）としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="53">
<j>仁安4年のち改元して嘉応元年（1169年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1169</e>
<cmt>改元については訳出不要と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the year 1169</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1169</e>
<cmt>The　と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>正月5日従五位上（皇太后・平滋子御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) by TAIRA no Shigeko, the Empress Dowager.</e>
<cmt>御給とは与えられると意味なので、左記の訳語は使わず&quot;promoted to ～　by&quot;という形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to the court rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) by TAIRA no Shigeko, the Empress Dowager.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: Promoted to the court rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) by TAIRA no Shigeko, the Empress Dowager.</e>
<cmt>日付を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="55">
<j>嘉応3年のち改元して承安 (日本)元年（1171年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1171</e>
<cmt>改元については訳出不要と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1171</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1171</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>4月7日越前守重任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continued to assume the position of Echizen no kami on April 7.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reappointed to the position of Echizen no kami, on April 7.</e>
<cmt>grammar, use Japanese title or English?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 7: Reappointed to the position of Echizen no kami.</e>
<cmt>コロンから始まる表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="57">
<j>承安4年（1174年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1174</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1174</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1174</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>12月4日侍従兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also assumed the position of Jiju (chamberlain) December 4.</e>
<cmt>侍従→Jiju (chamberlain)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointed to the position of Jiju (chamberlain), on December 4, held concurrently with his other positions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 4: Appointed to the position of Jiju (chamberlain), held concurrently with his other positions.</e>
<cmt>コロンから始まる表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="59">
<j>承安5年のち改元して安元元年（1175年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1175</e>
<cmt>改元については訳出不要と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1175</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1175</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>正月22日越前守得替</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Got through Echizen no kami&apos;s term of office on January 22.</e>
<cmt>「得替」とは任期が終わって交替すること（大辞林）とあるので、ここでは任期満了という意味で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completed term as Echizen no kami, on January 22.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 22: Completed term as Echizen no kami.</e>
<cmt>コロンから始まる表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>12月8日正五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on December 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), on December 8.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 8: Promoted to the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="62">
<j>治承2年（1178年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1178</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1178</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1178</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>12月24日右近衛権少将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assumed the position of Ukonoegonshosho (major general of Imperial Guard) on December 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assumed the position of major general of Imperial Guard (Ukonoegonshosho), on December 24.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 24: Assumed the position of Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>官職名について、日本名（英語）としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>侍従を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned from the position of Jiju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resigned from the position of Jiju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resigned from the position of Jiju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="65">
<j>治承3年（1179年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1179</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1179</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1179</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>正月2日従四位下（上西門院御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) by Joseimonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to the court rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) by Joseimonin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 2: Promoted to the court rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) by Josaimonin.</e>
<cmt>Josaimonin　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="67">
<j>治承4年（1180年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1180</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1180</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1180</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>4月8日従四位上（高倉上皇の福原御幸）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) on April 8 (gyoko (royal visit) of the retired Emperor Takakura).</e>
<cmt>従四位上→Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)[用語リスト]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to the court rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), on April 8, the occasion of a royal visit (gyoko) by the retired Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 8: Promoted to the court rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), on the occasion of a royal visit (gyoko) by the retired Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>コロンから始まる表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="69">
<j>治承5年のち改元して養和元年（1181年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1181</e>
<cmt>改元については訳出不要と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1181</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1181</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>5月26日正四位下（上西門院御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) on May 26 by Joseimonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), on May 26, by Joseimonin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 26: Promoted to the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) by Josaimonin.</e>
<cmt>Josaimonin　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>10月12日右近衛権少将を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned from the position of Ukonoegonshosho on October 12.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resigned from the position of Ukonoegonshosho, on October 12.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 12: Resigned from the position of Ukone no Gon no shosho.</e>
<cmt>Ukone no Gon no shosho　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>10月29日右近衛権中将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assumed the position of Ukonoegonchujo (lieutenant general of Imperial Guard) on October 29.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointed to the position of lieutenant general of Imperial Guard (Ukonoegonchujo), on October 29.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 29: Appointed to the position of Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>官職名について、日本名（英語）としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="73">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1183</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1183</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1183</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>正月22日蔵人頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assumed the position of Kurodonoto (private secretary to the Emperor) on January 22..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointed to the position of private secretary to the Emperor (Kurodonoto), on January 22.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 22: Appointed to the position of Kurodo no to (reigning emperor&apos;s personal secretary).</e>
<cmt>官職名について、日本名（英語）としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>7月3日従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) on July 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), on July 3.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 3: Promoted to the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>コロンから始まる表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>右近衛権中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position of Ukonoegonchujo remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>「如元」は辞書等に記載がありませんが、Google等の使用例から元の役職をそのまま継続すると判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the position of Ukonoegonchujo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained the position of Ukone no Gon no chujo.</e>
<cmt>Ukone no Gon no chujo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="77">
<j>8月6日解官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Removed from government post on August 6.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dismissed from government posts, on August 6.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 6: Dismissed from government posts.</e>
<cmt>コロンから始まる表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Regard(id:12949), ノトス(id:42992), Cprobot(id:97843), ちちぶ(id:184715), PATMAN(id:145791), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), でここ(id:9565), Rusk(id:9895), Enosi(id:19649), Azusayumi7(id:21082), ゐ(id:795), Point136(id:211299), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Klesha(id:203751), Kouko0515(id:100370), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>