<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>アリス・ベーコン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alice Bacon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alice Bacon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alice Bacon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>アリス・メイベル・ベーコン（Alice Mabel Bacon、1858年～1918年5月1日）は、アメリカ合衆国人女性教育者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alice Mabel Bacon (1858 - May 1, 1918) is an American female educator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alice Mabel Bacon (1858 - May 1, 1918) was an American female educator.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alice Mabel Bacon (1858 - May 1, 1918) was an American female educator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父はコネチカット州 ニューヘイブン (コネチカット州)の牧師であったレオナルド・ベーコン、母はキャサリン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father is Leonard Bacon, a clergyman of New Haven, Connecticut, and mother is Catharine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Leonard Bacon, a clergyman of New Haven, Connecticut, and her mother was Catharine.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Leonard Bacon, a clergyman of New Haven, Connecticut, and her mother was Catharine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>キャサリンは後妻で、アリスは14人兄弟の末娘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Catharine was the second wife and Alice was the youngest girl of 14 children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Catharine was the second wife and Alice was the youngest daughter among their fourteen children.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Catharine was the second wife and Alice was the youngest daughter among their fourteen children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>父・レオナルドは牧師のほかイェール大学神学校の教師も勤め、南北戦争の時、いち早く奴隷制に反対する論陣を張るなど、人望が厚く地元の名士であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father Leonard, served as not only a clergyman but also a teacher at Yale Divinity School, was a respected local prominent figure, argued against slavery during the Civil War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father Leonard served as not only a clergyman but also a teacher at the divinity school of Yale University, and during the Civil War he took the initiative in supporting the campaign against slavery, therefore he was highly respected in the local.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。（登録用語よりも通常使われる形を優先します。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father Leonard served as not only a clergyman but also a teacher at the divinity school of Yale University, and during the Civil War he took the initiative in supporting the campaign against slavery, therefore he was highly respected in the local.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子沢山であったため生活は非常に苦しかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that they were in poverty, because they had a lot of children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that they were in poverty, because they had a lot of children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that they were in poverty, because they had a lot of children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1872年、日本から来た女子留学生の下宿先を探していた森有礼の申し出に応じて山川捨松を引き取ったのは日本政府から支払われる多額の謝礼が目当てであったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that they acceded Arinori MORI&apos;s offer when Arinori was looking for boarding houses for overseas female students from Japan, and took in Sutematsu YAMAKAWA, because of the large amount of the remuneration from the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that because they needed the large amount of the reward from the Japanese Government, they accepted boarding Sutematsu YAMAKAWA, a female student from Japan at the request of Arinori MORI who had been looking for a boarding house for her.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that because they needed the large amount of the reward from the Japanese Government, they accepted boarding Sutematsu YAMAKAWA, a female student from Japan at the request of Arinori MORI who had been looking for a boarding house for her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、レオナルド夫妻は捨松を娘同様に扱い、特に年齢の近かったアリスとは姉妹のように過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Bacons treated Sutematsu as their own daughter, and Sutematsu particularly spent time with Alice, who was similar in age, as if they were real sisters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Bacons treated Sutematsu as if she was their own daughter, and Sutematsu became familiar like sisters particularly with Alice the almost same age as her.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Bacons treated Sutematsu as if she was their own daughter, and Sutematsu became familiar like sisters particularly with Alice the almost same age as her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>アリスは地元の高校・ヒルハウスハイスクールを卒業したものの、経済的な事情で大学進学をあきらめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, Alice graduated from Hillhouse High School, a local high school, she gave up going to college due to their financial situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Alice graduated from a local school, Hillhouse High School, she gave up going to college due to their financial situation.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Alice graduated from a local school, Hillhouse High School, she gave up going to college due to their financial situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし1881年にハーバード大学の学士検定試験に合格し学士号を取得、1883年にハンプトン師範学校正教師となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1881, she passed the certificate exam for the bachelor degree of Harvard University, and in 1883, she began teaching at Hampton Institute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1881, she passed the certificate exam for the bachelor degree of Harvard University; and in 1883, she became a regular teacher of Hampton Institute.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1881, she passed the certificate exam for the bachelor degree of Harvard University; and in 1883, she became a regular teacher of Hampton Institute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1884年には大山捨松や津田梅子の招聘により華族女学校（後の学習院）英語教師として来日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884, she was invited to Japan by Sutematsu Oyama and Umeko TSUDA as an English teacher at Kazoku Jogakko (girls&apos; school for Kazoku new nobility) (later the Gakushuin School Corporation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884, she was invited to Japan by Sutematsu OYAMA and Umeko TSUDA as an English teacher at Kazoku Jogakko (Peeresses&apos; School, present Gakushuin School).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。華族女学校はPeeresses&apos; Schoolと紹介されることが多いようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884, she was invited to Japan by Sutematsu OYAMA and Umeko TSUDA as an English teacher at Kazoku Jogakko (Peeresses&apos; School, present Gakushuin School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>来日中の1年間の手紙をまとめたものを1894年『日本の内側』（日本語訳題『華族女学校教師が見た明治日本の内側』）として出版し反響を呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1894, She compiled a whole book of her letters she wrote in the year when she was in Japan, published as &quot;A Japanese Interior&quot; (Japanese title&quot; Inside of the Meiji Japan through the eyes of a teacher of Kazoku Jogakko&quot;), and it called forth an echo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1894, She compiled her letters she had written during staying in Japan for one year and published the book titled &quot;A Japanese Interior&quot; (Japanese title was &quot;Kazoku-jogakko-kyoshi ga mita Meiji Nihon no Uchigawa&quot; [A Interior of Japan of the Meiji period that a teacher of Kazoku Jogakko had seen]); and it produced a sensation.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1894, She compiled her letters she had written during staying in Japan for one year and published the book titled &quot;A Japanese Interior&quot; (Japanese title was &quot;Kazoku-jogakko-kyoshi ga mita Meiji Nihon no Uchigawa&quot; [A Interior of Japan of the Meiji period that a teacher of Kazoku Jogakko had seen]); and it produced a sensation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>帰国後はハンプトン師範学校校長となっていたが、1900年4月、大山捨松と津田梅子の再度の招聘により東京女子師範学校と女子英学塾（後の津田塾大学）の英語教師として赴任、1902年4月に任期満了で帰国するまで貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, she had been assigned to the principal of Hampton Institute after returning home, in 1900, she was once again invited to Japan by Sutematsu OYAMA and Umeko TSUDA, worked and made a contribution there as an English teacher of Tokyo Joshi Shihan Gakko (Tokyo Women&apos;s Normal School) and the Women&apos;s Institute for English Studies (later Tsuda College) until she left Japan in April 1902.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning to America, she became principal of Hampton Institute, however, in April of 1900 she was once again invited to Japan by Sutematsu OYAMA and Umeko TSUDA, and served Tokyo Joshi Shihan-gakko (Tokyo Teacher&apos;s School for Women) and Joshi Eigaku Juku (Women&apos;s English School, present Tsudajuku Collage) as an English teacher until her term of office expired and she left Japan in April of 1902.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ、訳語選択ミスがあります。女子英学塾はWomen&apos;s English School、津田塾大学ホームページに従います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to America, she became principal of Hampton Institute, however, in April of 1900 she was once again invited to Japan by Sutematsu OYAMA and Umeko TSUDA, and served Tokyo Joshi Shihan-gakko (Tokyo Teacher&apos;s School for Women) and Joshi Eigaku Juku (Women&apos;s English School, present Tsudajuku Collage) as an English teacher until her term of office expired and she left Japan in April of 1902.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>特に女子英学塾ではボランティアで教師を務め、梅子にかわって塾の家賃を代わりに支払うなど貢献は大であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She worked as a volunteer at the Women&apos;s Institute for English Studies and also paid the rent of the Institute instead of Umeko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially at Joshi Eigaku Juku, she rendered many services as she had worked without salary and even paid the rents for the head of the school, Umeko.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially at Joshi Eigaku Juku, she rendered many services as she had worked without salary and even paid the rents for the head of the school, Umeko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>帰国後も教育に身を捧げ、一生独身であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was involved only in education even after coming back, and she stayed single all her life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning to America, she kept devoting herself to education and she remained single all her life.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to America, she kept devoting herself to education and she remained single all her life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただし、渡辺光子と一柳満喜子というふたりの日本女性を養女とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she adopted two Japanese girls, Mitsuko WATANABE and Makiko HITOTSUYANAGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she adopted two Japanese girls, Mitsuko WATANABE and Makiko HITOTSUYANAGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she adopted two Japanese girls, Mitsuko WATANABE and Makiko HITOTSUYANAGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一柳満喜子は女子英学塾の教師になることを期待されていたが、帰国後ウィリアム・メレル・ヴォーリズと結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, Makiko HITOTSUYANAGI was counted on to be a teacher of the Women&apos;s Institute for English Studies, she got married with William Merrell Vories after coming back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Makiko HITOTSUYANAGI had been expected to become a teacher of Joshi Eigaku Juku, she married William Merrell Vories after she had returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Makiko HITOTSUYANAGI had been expected to become a teacher of Joshi Eigaku Juku, she married William Merrell Vories after she had returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>先述した『日本の内側』、それ以前に著した『日本の女性』（日本語訳題『明治日本の女たち』）は明治時代の日本の女性事情を偏見無く書いた史料として貴重であり、ルース・ベネディクトが『菊と刀』を執筆するときに参考文献とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;A Japanese Interior,&quot; mentioned earlier and &quot;Japanese Girls and Women (Japanese translation &quot;Japanese Girls and Women in the Meiji Period&quot;),&quot; written later on by Alice are the important historical souces that explain the situation of Japanese women in the Meiji period without prejudice; Ruth Benedict used it as reference literature to write &quot;The Chrysanthemum and the Sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her books &quot;A Japanese Interior&quot; mentioned above and &quot;Japanese Girls and Women&quot; (Japanese title was &quot;Meiji Nihon no Onna-tachi&quot; [Japanese Girls and Women of the Meiji Period]) written before &quot;A Japanese Interior&quot; are important historical materials that describe Japanese women of the Meiji period without prejudice; and Ruth Benedict referred to it to write &quot;The Chrysanthemum and the Sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her books &quot;A Japanese Interior&quot; mentioned above and &quot;Japanese Girls and Women&quot; (Japanese title was &quot;Meiji Nihon no Onna-tachi&quot; [Japanese Girls and Women of the Meiji Period]) written before &quot;A Japanese Interior&quot; are important historical materials that describe Japanese women of the Meiji period without prejudice; and Ruth Benedict referred to it to write &quot;The Chrysanthemum and the Sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ちなみに『日本の女性』の前書きには「生涯の友人・大山捨松に捧げる」という一文が添えられ、捨松とは死ぬ直前まで文通を交わしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a sentence added which said ‛To my companion for eternity, Sutematsu Oyama&apos; in the foreword of the book,&quot;A Japanese Interior,&quot; and Alice exchanged letters with Sutematsu until shortly before Alice&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>「生涯の友人・大山捨松に捧げる」には実際の言葉が当てはめられるべきだと考えますが，見つけることができなかったため、この日本語に対する訳となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that connection, in the preface of &quot;Japanese Girls and Women,&quot; she had written this sentence ‛to my lifelong friend, Sutematsu Oyama&apos; and she had been exchanging letters with Sutematsu until just before she died.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that connection, in the preface of &quot;Japanese Girls and Women,&quot; she had written this sentence ‛to my lifelong friend, Sutematsu Oyama&apos; and she had been exchanging letters with Sutematsu until just before she died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), PANYNJ(id:38638), Cprobot(id:97843), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Nonsvch(id:45650), Faso(id:11300), こぶまき(id:38278), Omitugi(id:137808), Point136(id:211299), Tomika(id:43050), Printum(id:52530), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>