<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>那須政高</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masataka NASU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masataka NASU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masataka NASU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>那須政高（なすまさたか、生没年不詳）は、鎌倉時代の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masataka NASU (dates of birth and death unknown) was samurai in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masataka NASU (dates of birth and death unknown) was samurai in Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>鎌倉時代の訳から定冠詞を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masataka NASU (dates of birth and death unknown) was samurai in Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名、中新井政高。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name was Masataka NAKAARAI.</e>
<cmt>「中新井」の読み方が確認できませんでしたが、「なかあらい」と推測して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name was Masataka NAKAARAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name was Masataka NAKAARAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>那須与一の弟、那須宗晴の末裔で備中国荏原庄などを領していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a descendant of Muneharu NASU, younger brother of NASU no Yoichi, and owned Ebara no sho (manor) in Bicchu Province and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a descendant of Muneharu NASU, a younger brother of NASU no Yoichi, while he owned Ebara no sho (manor) in Bicchu Province and other territories.</e>
<cmt>「那須与一の弟」の訳文に不定冠詞を追加しました。「and so on」で「〜などを」を意味するよう訳していますが、一つしか例が出ていない中でのこのフレーズの利用はおかしいです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a descendant of Muneharu NASU, a younger brother of NASU no Yoichi, while he owned Ebara no sho (manor) in Bicchu Province and other territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>足利尊氏が九州へ赴くとき、そして京へ戻る際に丁重なもてなしをしたことから新たに下野国中新郷を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takauji ASHIKAGA went to Kyushu region and returned to Kyoto, He gave Takauji hospitality and thus he was newly given 中新郷 in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>「中新郷」は読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NASU was newly given the territory of Nakashingo of Shimotsuke Province for his hospitality to Takauji ASHIKAGA when Takauji was on the way down to Kyushu region, and on the way returning to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「give Takauji hospitality」の用法は正しくは「give hospitality to Takauji」です。英文が日本語文と語順がそろっています。このため何が主語・主題になっているかがわかりづらく、また「thus」に頼って構文しています。この点留意し修正しました。「中新郷」ですが、現在のこの地域に新郷村が残っています。また、武蔵国（隣国）にも上新郷などの地名があります。これらから「しんごうむら」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NASU was newly given the territory of Nakashingo of Shimotsuke Province for his hospitality to Takauji ASHIKAGA when Takauji was on the way down to Kyushu region, and on the way returning to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これに喜んだ彼は中新井に改姓した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was glad for it and he changed his family name to NAKAARAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NASU was pleased with this treatment, thus he changed his family name to NAKAARAI for commemoration.</e>
<cmt>足利尊氏という別人物が登場した直後に「彼」を「he」としてしまうと、一瞬どちらか迷うことになります。再記述しました。「喜んだ」故に「改姓した」となっています。「glad」はその意味には単純すぎるため、「pleased」としました。「領地の拝領を喜んだ」ことを「it」のみで表していますが、単純にitで表せるものではないと思います。喜んだのはわかってもなぜ名前を変えるのかの説明が必要です。記念の改姓という意味で違約しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NASU was pleased with this treatment, thus he changed his family name to NAKAARAI for commemoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>その後彼の子孫は毛利氏に仕えた後福島正則に転仕、福島氏の改易後は帰農した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, his descendants served the Mori clan and then served Masanori FUKUSHIMA, and returned to farming after kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties) of the Fukushima clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, his descendants served the Mori clan first, then served under Masanori FUKUSHIMA; once the Fukushima clan received the penalty of kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties), they stopped serving to a master and returned to farming.</e>
<cmt>訳文ですと「転仕」の意味が盛り込まれていません。時間の流れを示してこの意味を持たせました。「帰農」に関して、原文には明記されていませんがその意味するところを意訳し、分かりやすくしました。（日本人にはわかる内容でも外国人には説明不足と感じたため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, his descendants served the Mori clan first, then served under Masanori FUKUSHIMA; once the Fukushima clan received the penalty of kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties), they stopped serving to a master and returned to farming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このとき江原と改姓した者、引き続き中新井、もしくは中新の姓で通した者がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, some changed their family name to EHARA and others continued to use NAKAARAI or 中新 as their family name.</e>
<cmt>「江原」の読み方は「えはら」か「えばら」か確認できませんでしたが、「えはら」と訳しました。「中新」は読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, some changed their family name to EHARA and others continued to use NAKAARAI (中新井 or 中新) as their family name.</e>
<cmt>「中新」も読みは「なかあらい」だと思います。英文だと違いがわかりませんので漢字を明記することで違いを示しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, some changed their family name to EHARA and others continued to use NAKAARAI (中新井 or 中新) as their family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>現在でも彼の一族の末裔は岡山県井原市を中心に多く残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even now, many descendants of his family survive mainly in Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, many descendants of his family remain mainly around Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>現在の訳での「Even now」を「Even today」としました。子孫が残っている事を「survive」とするのはどうでしょうか。「那須」の名前が残っている、という場合であれば用いることができると思いますが。「remain」を使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, many descendants of his family remain mainly around Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carp1(id:174572), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>