<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>柴司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukasa SHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukasa SHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukasa SHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>柴 司（しば つかさ、弘化元年2月14日 (旧暦)（1844年4月1日） - 元治元年6月12日 (旧暦)（1864年7月15日））は、幕末の京都に駐留していた会津藩士である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukasa SHIBA (male, April 1st, 1844 to July 15, 1864) was a warrior of Aizu clan, who stationed in Kyoto at the end of Edo Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukasa SHIBA (male, April 1st, 1844 to July 15, 1864) was a warrior of Aizu clan, who was stationed in Kyoto at the end of Edo Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukasa SHIBA (April 1st, 1844 - July 15, 1864) was a warrior of Aizu clan, who was stationed in Kyoto at the end of Edo Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>male, 削除しました。toをハイフンに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>姓は柴（しば）、諱（いみな）は次正（つぐまさ/つぎまさ）、幼名は又四郎（またしろう）のち司（つかさ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family name was SHIBA, his respectful name given after his death was Tsugumasa or Tsugimasa, and his given name used while he was young was Matashiro and, later, Tsukasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family name was SHIBA, his respectful name given after his death was Tsugumasa or Tsugimasa, and his given name used while he was young was Matashiro and, later, Tsukasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family name was Shiba, his respectful name given after his death was Tsugumasa or Tsugimasa, and his given name used while he was young was Matashiro and, later, Tsukasa.</e>
<cmt>Shiba小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>父は柴友右衛門次直、母は西郷氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIBA&apos;s father was Tomoemon-Tsugunao SHIBA and SHIBA&apos;s mother was from SAIGO family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIBA&apos;s father was Tomoemon-Tsugunao SHIBA and SHIBA&apos;s mother was from SAIGO family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukasa SHIBA&apos;s father was Tomoemon-Tsugunao SHIBA and his mother was from Saigo family.</e>
<cmt>Tsukasa補足しました。 SHIBA&apos;s をhisとしました。Saigo小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>他に、幾馬次俊、寛次郎次久、外三郎次元の3人の兄が居た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, SHIBA had three elder brothers, Ikuma-Tsugutoshi, Torajiro-Tsuguhisa, and Tosaburo-Tsugumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, SHIBA had three elder brothers, Ikuma-Tsugutoshi, Torajiro-Tsuguhisa, and Tosaburo-Tsugumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Ysukasa SHIBA had three elder brothers, Ikumatsugutoshi, Torajirotsuguhisa, and Tosaburotsugumoto.</e>
<cmt>Tsukasa補足しました。Ikumatsugutoshi, Torajirotsuguhisa, and Tosaburotsugumotoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元治元年、池田屋事件の残党狩りに追われる新選組に派遣された会津藩士の1人で、同年6月10日 (旧暦)、いわゆる明保野亭事件を起こし、会津藩と土佐藩の関係修復のため兄の介錯のもと切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIBA was one of the warriors of Aizu clan dispatched in 1864 to Shinsengumi which was chased by the troop which tried to capture the rest of the Shinsengumi members who caused Ikeda-ya incident, and SHIBA caused a so-called Akihono-tei incident on June 10 in the same year and committed harakiri aided by his elder brother to restore the relation between Aizu clan and Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIBA was one of the warriors of the Aizu clan dispatched in 1864 to the Shinsengumi which was being chased by troops which tried to capture the rest of the Shinsengumi members who caused the Ikeda-ya incident, and SHIBA caused a so-called Akihono-tei incident on June 10 in the same year and committed Seppuku, while aided by his elder brother to restore relations between the Aizu clan and Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukasa SHIBA was one of the warriors of the Aizu clan dispatched in 1864 to the Shinsengumi which was being chased by troops which tried to capture the rest of the Shinsengumi members who caused the Ikeda-ya incident, and he caused a so-called Akihono-tei incident on July 13 in the same year and committed Seppuku, while aided by his elder brother to restore relations between the Aizu clan and Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>Tsukasa補足しました。SHIBAをheに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>享年21。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIBA died at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIBA died at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukasa SHIBA died at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt>Tsukasa補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>武家社会のしがらみの中で犠牲となった形であるが、彼の死によって会津藩と土佐藩の衝突が回避され、その潔い最期に対して会津藩主松平容保から兄に褒章がくだされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though SHIBA seemed to be a victim of the complicated relation of interest in the samurai society, his death enabled avoidance of conflicts between Aizu clan and Tosa clan, and the head of Aizu clan, Katamori MATSUDAIRA honored his graceful last moment and, therefore, gave a medal to his elder brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though SHIBA seemed to be a victim of the complicated relation of interest in the samurai society, his death enabled avoidance of conflicts between the Aizu clan and Tosa clan, and the head of Aizu clan, Katamori MATSUDAIRA honored his graceful last moments and, therefore, gave a medal to his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though he seemed to be a victim of the complicated relation of interest in the samurai society, his death enabled avoidance of conflicts between the Aizu clan and Tosa clan, and the head of Aizu clan, Katamori MATSUDAIRA honored his graceful last moments and, therefore, gave a medal to his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>SHIBAをheに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>墓碑銘について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About epitaph</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About epitaph</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About epitaph</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>京都黒谷金戒光明寺の会津墓地にある柴司の墓碑銘には、上記の続柄や事件の経緯とともに「言い伝えによれば、死ぬことが難しいのではなく、立派な態度で死に臨むことが難しいという。柴司などは、本当に立派な態度で死を迎えた者だというべきだろう」、「もし柴司が6月12日に死ぬことなく、禁門の変に参戦していたなら、どれだけ活躍したであろうか。これはとても残念なことである」とその死を惜しまれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The passage in the epitaph of the grave of Tsukasa SHIBA in the graveyard for Aizu clan in Kinkaikoumyo-ji temple in Kurotani in Kyoto, regrets his death as saying, together with the record of his family and the details of the incidents as above, that &quot;according to a tradition, it is not difficult for one to die but it is difficult to face his/her own death with a resolute attitude. It should be said that each of persons including Tsukasa SHIBA faced his/her own death and died with a really resolute attitude&quot; and that &quot;if Tsukasa SHIBA did not die on June 12th and participated in Kinmon Coup, what an important role he would play in it! This is very regrettable.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The passage in the epitaph of the grave of Tsukasa SHIBA in the graveyard for Aizu clan in Kinkaikoumyo-ji temple in Kurotani in Kyoto, regrets his death as saying, together with the record of his family and the details of the incidents as above, that &quot;according to a tradition, it is not difficult for one to die but it is difficult to face his/her own death with a resolute attitude. It should be said that each person including Tsukasa SHIBA faced his/her own death and died with a really resolute attitude&quot; and that &quot;if Tsukasa SHIBA did not die on June 12th and participated in Kinmon Coup, what an important role he would play in it! This is very regrettable.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The passage in the epitaph of the grave of Tsukasa SHIBA in the graveyard for Aizu clan in Kinkaikomyo-ji Temple in Kurotani in Kyoto, regrets his death as saying, together with the record of his family and the details of the incidents as above, that &apos;according to a tradition, it is not difficult for one to die but it is difficult to face his/her own death with a resolute attitude. It should be said that each person including Tsukasa SHIBA faced his/her own death and died with a really resolute attitude&apos; and that &apos;if Tsukasa SHIBA did not die on July 15 and participated in Kinmon Coup, what an important role he would play in it! This is very regrettable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Kinkaikomyo-ji Templeに訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。余分なスペース削除しました。新暦に訂正しました。グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>法名・忠信院盡孝刃司居士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name given to SHIBA&apos;s Buddhist priesthood: Chushin-in-shinko-jinnshi-kyoshi (literally, a non-priest believer of Buddhism who made every effort to think and who was an excellent commander of swords in a temple of faith.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name given to SHIBA&apos;s Buddhist priesthood: Chushin-in-shinko-jinnshi-kyoshi (literally, a non-priest believer of Buddhism who made every effort to think and who was an excellent commander of swords in a temple of faith.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name given to Tsukasa SHIBA&apos;s Buddhist priesthood: Chushinin Shinkojinnshi Kyoshi (literally, a non-priest believer of Buddhism who made every effort to think and who was an excellent commander of swords in a temple of faith.)</e>
<cmt>Tsukasa補足しました。Chushin-in-shinko-jinnshi-kyoshiハイフン削除し語節を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), おきた(id:18906), Maakun(id:16735), NDR(id:5500), 上田隼人(id:23104), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>