<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>田川行文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukifumi TAKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukifumi TAKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukifumi TAGAWA</e>
<cmt>TAKAGAをTAGAWAに修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>田川 行文（たがわ ゆきふみ）は、出羽国田川郡 (羽前国)（現・鶴岡市田川）を本拠地として、田川郡郡司を自称した鎌倉時代の豪族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukifumi TAKAGA was a gozoku (a member of a local ruling family) who lived in the Kamakura period, who claimed to be the gunji (district manager) of Tagawa District with Tagawa District, Dewa Province (or Uzen Province as a result of the later division of the Province) (currently Tagawa District, Tsuruoka City) as his base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukifumi TAKAGA was a gozoku (a member of a local ruling family) who lived in the Kamakura period, who claimed to be the gunji (district manager) of Tagawa District, headquartered in Tagawa District, Dewa Province (or Uzen Province as a result of the later division of the Province) (currently Tagawa District, Tsuruoka City).</e>
<cmt>Tagawa District with Tagawa Districtと続いてしまうので、「Tagawa District,　headquartered in」と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukifumi TAGAWA was a gozoku (a member of a local ruling family) who lived in the Kamakura period, who claimed to be the gunji (district manager) of Tagawa District, headquartered in Tagawa District, Dewa Province (or Uzen Province as a result of the later division of the Province) (currently Tagawa District, Tsuruoka City).</e>
<cmt>TAKAGAをTAGAWAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>奥州藤原氏の郎党。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a roto (retainer) of the Oshu-Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a roto (retainer) of the Oshu-Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a roto (retainer) of the Oshu-Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一般的には、田川太郎（たがわ たろう）と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is commonly known as Taro TAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is commonly known as Taro TAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is commonly known as Taro TAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>文治5年（1189年）、鎌倉幕府の奥州征伐に際し、主君・藤原泰衡の命を受け、秋田致文と共に、越後国方面より北進してきた比企能員と、宇佐美実政の率いる幕府軍と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1189, when the Kamakura bakufu planned Oshu-seibatsu (the Kamakura bakufu&apos;s military campaign against the Fujiwara clan in northern Japan), Yukiumi was ordered by his lord FUJIWARA no Yasuhira to ally with Munebumi AKITA in order to fight against Yoshikazu HIKI, who marched to the north from Echigo province, and the Bakufu force led by Sanemasa USAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1189, when the Kamakura bakufu planned Oshu-seibatsu (the Kamakura bakufu&apos;s military campaign against the Fujiwara clan in northern Japan), Yukiumi was ordered by his lord FUJIWARA no Yasuhira to ally with Munebumi AKITA in order to fight against Yoshikazu HIKI, who marched to the north from Echigo province, and the Bakufu force led by Sanemasa USAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1189, when the Kamakura bakufu planned Oshu-seibatsu (the Kamakura bakufu&apos;s military campaign against the Fujiwara clan in northern Japan), Yukifumi was ordered by his lord FUJIWARA no Yasuhira to ally with Munebumi AKITA in order to fight against Yoshikazu HIKI, who marched to the north from Echigo province, and the Bakufu force led by Sanemasa USAMI.</e>
<cmt>YukiumiをYukifumiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>戦に敗れ、さらし首にされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukifumi lost the battle and his severed head was gibbeted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukifumi lost the battle and his severed head was gibbeted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukifumi lost the battle and his severed head was gibbeted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>行文の墓は、田川氏の菩提寺である蓮花寺があった所と言われる、鶴岡市田川字蓮花寺の北端にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukiumi&apos;s gravestone is located at the north end of Aza-Renka-dera Temple in Tagawa District, Tsuroka City, where Renka-dera Temple which, was the family temple of the Tagawa clan, was said to have been located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukiumi&apos;s gravestone is located at the north end of Aza-Renka-dera Temple in Tagawa District, Tsuroka City, where Renka-dera Temple which, was the family temple of the Tagawa clan, was said to have been located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukifumi&apos;s gravestone is located at the north end of Aza-Renka-dera Temple in Tagawa District, Tsuruoka City, where Renka-dera Temple which, was the family temple of the Tagawa clan, was said to have been located.</e>
<cmt>TsurukaをTsuruokaに修正しました。YukiumiをYukifumiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Blizzardbreaker(id:248394), Nekomiminarikin(id:199247), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>