<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原隆家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Takaie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Takaie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Takaie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 隆家（ふじわら の たかいえ、天元 (日本)2年（979年） - 寛徳元年正月1日（1044年2月2日））は、平安時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Takaie was a court noble during the Heian Period from 979 to February 2, 1044.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Takaie was a court noble during the Heian Period from 979 to February 2, 1044.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Takaie (979 - February 8, 1044) was a court noble during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一条天皇の摂関を務めた藤原道隆の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Michitaka, regent to Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Michitaka, regent to Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Michitaka, Sekkan (regents and advisers) to Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>極官は正二位中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The highest rank to which he was appointed was Shoniichunagon (Senior Second Rank of the Court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The highest rank to which he was appointed was Shoniichunagon (Senior Second Rank of the Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kyokkan (the most highest rank which one was appointed) was Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は阿古。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Ako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Ako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Ako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>永祚 (日本)元年（989年）1月29日、11歳で元服し従五位下侍従、正暦5年（994年）8月28日、非参議・従三位に叙され公卿に列す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following his coming of age ceremony on January 29, 989, 11 year old Takaie was appointed Jugoiinoge (chamberlain of the Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and on August 28, 994 was conferred hisangi (Junior Third Rank) and took his place at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following his coming of age ceremony on January 29, 989, 11-year-old Takaie was appointed Jugoiinoge (chamberlain of the Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and on August 28, 994 was conferred hisangi (Junior Third Rank) and took his place at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following his coming of age ceremony on March 14, 989, 11-year-old Takaie was appointed jiju (a chamberlain) of Jugoinoge (the Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and on October 10, 994 was conferred Hisangi (advisor at large) of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and took his place at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>父・道隆の死に先立ち、長徳元年（995年）4月6日に権中納言に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preceding the death of his father, Michitaka, he attained Gon-chunagon (Court Rank) on April 6, 995.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preceding the death of his father, Michitaka, he attained Gon-chunagon (Court Rank) on April 6, 995.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preceding the death of his father, Michitaka, he attained Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) on May 13, 995.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>翌2年4月24日、花山天皇奉射・東三条院呪詛・大元帥法を行った罪状三ヶ条を以って出雲国権守に左遷された（内大臣だった同母兄伊周は大宰権帥に左遷）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 24th of the following year he was demoted to local governor of Izumo Province over 3 charges that he criticized Emperor Kazan, place a curse on Higashi-sanjoin and participated in Daigensuiho (magic rituals of shingon esoteric Buddhism). (His older brother Korechika, advisor to the Emperor, was also demoted as Dazai-gonosochi (Vice Commander of Dazaifu)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 24th of the following year he was demoted to local governor of Izumo Province over 3 charges that he had criticized Emperor Kazan, had placed a curse on Higashi-sanjoin, and had participated in Daigensuiho (magic rituals of shingon esoteric Buddhism). (His older brother Korechika, advisor to the Emperor, was also demoted to Dazai-gonosochi (Vice Commander of Dazaifu)).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 19 of the following year, 996, he was demoted to Izumo no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Izumo Province) over three charges that he had criticized Emperor Kazan, had placed a curse on Higashi-sanjoin, and had participated in Daigensuiho (magic rituals of Shingon esoteric Buddhism) (His older half brother Korechika, Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior), was also demoted to Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これを長徳の変という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is referred to as the Chotoku Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is referred to as the Chotoku Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is referred to as the Chotoku Coup.</e>
<cmt>指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>翌年召還され、兵部卿に任じた後、長保4年（1002年）9月24日、権中納言に復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year he was summoned back to court and after being appointed as Hyobukyo (Chief of Military Affairs), he was reinstated to Court Rank on September 24, 1002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year he was summoned back to the court, and after being appointed Hyobukyo (Chief of Military Affairs), he was reinstated to Court Rank on September 24, 1002.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year he was summoned back to the court, and after being appointed Hyobukyo (Chief of Military Affairs), he was reinstated to Gon Chunagon on November 7, 1002.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寛弘4年（1007年）1月20日従二位、同9年正月27日按察使、長和3年（1014年）11月7日任大宰権帥、翌4年4月21日正二位と、徐々に宮廷社会で復帰していったが、官は中納言に止まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 20, 1007 he was appointed to Junii (Junior Second Rank), on January 27, 1012 Azechi (Supervisor of Local Administration) and on November 7, 1014 the Dazai-gonnosochi (vice commander of Dazaifu), on April 21, 1015 Shonii (Senior Second Rank), slowly making his return through court society, finally ending at Chunagon (court rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 20, 1007 he was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank), on January 27, 1012 appointed Azechi (Supervisor of Local Administration), and on November 7, 1014 the Dazai-gonnosochi (vice commander of Dazaifu); on April 21, 1015 he was promotoed Shonii (Senior Second Rank), slowly making his return through court society, finally ending at Chunagon (court rank).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 16, 1007 he was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank), on February 27, 1012 appointed Azechi (inspector of the provincial government), and on December 7, 1014 the Dazai gon no sochi; on May 17, 1015 he was promoted Shonii (Senior Second Rank), slowly making his return through court society, finally ending at Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>姉定子の生んだ敦康親王の立太子を拒否した一条天皇を「人非人」と非難したり、権力者藤原道長の嫌がらせに屈せず三条天皇皇后藤原せい子の皇后宮職を引き受けたりするなど、気骨のある人物として知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Criticizing Emperor Ichijo, who denied older sister&apos;s son Imperial Prince Atsuyasu&apos;s investiture as the crown prince as a &quot;brutish man&quot;, unyielding the face of harassment by the powerful FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and being responsible for the offices of Emperor Sanjo&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Seishi, Takaie was known as a person of true moral character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaie was known as a person of true moral character, criticizing Emperor Ichijo, who had denied older sister&apos;s son Imperial Prince Atsuyasu&apos;s investiture as the crown prince, as a &quot;brutish man&quot;; refusing to yield in the face of harassment by the powerful FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and being responsible for the offices of Emperor Sanjo&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Seishi.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaie was known as a person of true moral character, criticizing Emperor Ichijo, who had denied investiture of Imperial Prince Atsuyasu as the crown prince, who was a son of Sadako, Takaie&apos;s older sister, as a &apos;brutish man&apos;; refusing to yield in the face of harassment by the powerful FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and being responsible for the offices of Emperor Sanjo&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Seishi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>三条天皇代、眼病の治療の為、進んで大宰権帥を拝命し九州大宰府に下り、在任中の寛仁3年（1019年）、当地で刀伊の入寇を撃退し武名を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1019 during the reign of Emperor Sanjo, he voluntarily took up the post of Daizugonnosochi (Vice Commander of Dazaifu) in Kyushu in order to receive treatment for an eye disease, earning himself military fame for repulsing the attack of the Toi-no-nyuko (the Joshin tribe attacked Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1019, during the reign of Emperor Sanjo, he voluntarily took up the post of Daizugonnosochi (Vice Commander of Dazaifu) in Kyushu in order to receive treatment for an eye disease, earning himself military fame for repulsing the attack of the Toi-no-nyuko (the Joshin tribe attacked Japan).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Sanjo, he voluntarily took up the position of Dazai gon no sochi in Dazaifu, Kyushu in order to receive treatment for an eye disease, and during his service in 1019, earning himself military fame for repulsing the attack of Toi invasion (the Joshin tribe attacked Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本の領土に上陸した敵軍を撃退した日本最初の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Japanese to repel an enemy invader from its shores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first Japanese to repel an enemy invader from its shores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first Japanese to repel an enemy invader from its shores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、権帥の任期が終わり帰京した寛仁4年に、都に疱瘡（こんにちでいう天然痘）が大流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, upon completing his term of Gonnosochi (Vice Commander) and returning to Kyoto in 1020, smallpox was spreading throughout the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, upon completing his term as Gonnosochi (Vice Commander), he returned to Kyoto in 1020, and smallpox was spreading throughout the capital.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, upon completing his term as Gon no sochi, he returned to Kyoto in 1020, and smallpox was spreading throughout the capital.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>刀伊（女真族と考えられている）が大陸から持ち込んだもので、隆家の入京とともに流行したと噂された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rumor was circulated that the invading Joshin tribe carried smallpox to mainland Japan and that it began spreading upon Takaie&apos;s arrival in the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rumor was circulated that the invading Joshin tribe carried smallpox to mainland Japan and it began spreading upon Takaie&apos;s arrival in the capital.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rumor was circulated that the invading Toi (considered as Joshin tribe) carried smallpox to mainland Japan and it began spreading upon Takaie&apos;s arrival in the capital.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>天下の「さがな者」（荒くれ者）として有名であった隆家は、王権をかさに着る花山院との賭け事や、姉中宮の女房清少納言との応酬など、『大鏡』『枕草子』にも多彩な逸話が伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous for being a rough character, many colorful anecdotes about Takaie are related in the &quot;Okagami&quot; (Large Mirror) and &quot;Makura-no-soshi&quot;(The Pillow Book), including betting against the tyrannical Hanayama-in Temple, and trading witty remarks with Seishonagon, servant of the Empress Teishi.</e>
<cmt>Teishi (who is now chugu) is a sister of Takaie and Seishonagon is a court lady who served the Empress Teishi.&quot;王権をかさに着る&quot; means that a person becomes a bully even though he is a coward only because he is a person of authority.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaie is famous for being a rough character, and many colorful anecdotes about him are related in the &quot;Okagami&quot; (Large Mirror) and &quot;Makura-no-soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book), including his betting against the tyrannical Hanayama-in Temple, and exchanging witty remarks with Seishonagon, servant of the Empress Teishi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaie was famous for being &apos;Sagana mono&apos; (a rough character), and many colorful anecdotes about him are related in the &quot;Okagami&quot; (the Great Mirror) and &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book), including his betting against the tyrannical Kazanin (also referred as Cloistered Emperor Kazan), and exchanging witty remarks with Sei Shonagon, nyobo (a court lady) of his sister chugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>隆家の子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants of Takaie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of Takaie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of Takaie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>隆家の次男藤原経輔（1006年-1081年）は、正二位大納言となって水無瀬大納言と称せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaie&apos;s second son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke (1006-1081) Dainagon (Second Senior Rank Chief Councillor of State), was called Minase Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaie&apos;s second son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke (1006-1081) Dainagon (Second Senior Rank Chief Councillor of State), was called Minase Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaie&apos;s second son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke (1006 - 1081) Dainagon (chief councilor of state) of Shonii (Second Senior Rank), was called Minase Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>経輔の5世孫にあたる従三位忠隆女は近衛家の祖である近衛基実の室となって近衛基通を生み、その兄弟藤原信頼は後白河天皇の寵臣で平治の乱の首謀者として有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneyuki&apos;s fifth grandson Junior Third Rank Tadataka女 was the mother of the Konoe family and wife to Motozane KONOE, gave birth to Motomichi KONOE whose sibling FUJIWARA no Nobuyori was a favorite retainer of Emperor Gotoba and who became famous as the ringleader of the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneyuki&apos;s fifth grandchild, Junior Third Rank Tadataka, was the mother of the Konoe family and wife to Motozane KONOE, and gave birth to Motomichi KONOE, whose sibling FUJIWARA no Nobuyori was a favorite retainer of Emperor Gotoba and who became famous as the ringleader of the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneyuki&apos;s fifth grandchild, the daughter of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Tadataka, was a wife to Motozane KONOE, the founder of the Konoe family, and gave birth to Motomichi KONOE, whose sibling FUJIWARA no Nobuyori was a favorite retainer of Emperor Goshirakawa and who became famous as the ringleader of the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同じく経輔の5世孫にあたる修理職信隆女藤原殖子は後鳥羽天皇生母であり、その弟坊門信清は内大臣の位にまで昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another relation to fifth grandson and repairer of the Emperor&apos;s house Nobutaka, was daughter FUJIWARA no Shokushi, true mother to Emperor Gotoba and her brother being Nobukiyo Bomon, who rose to the rank of Minister of the Interior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another relation to fifth grandchild and repairer of the Emperor&apos;s house Nobutaka, was daughter FUJIWARA no Shokushi, true mother to Emperor Gotoba and her brother was Nobukiyo Bomon, who rose to the rank of Minister of the Interior.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another relation to fifth grandchild of Tsuneyuki, FUJIWARA no Shokushi was the daughter of Nobutaka of Shurishiki (Office of Palace Repairs)) and a real mother of Emperor Gotoba, and her brother was Nobukiyo BOMON, who rose to Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>隆家流は女系を伝って皇室・摂家にその血を残し、子孫は水無瀬流として後世、水無瀬家・七条家・町尻家・桜井家・山井家の五堂上家を出して明治維新に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takeie school female bloodline carries through the Imperial Household and the five main Fujiwara branch families, descending through the Minase school of the Minase family, the Shichijo family, the Machijiri family, the Sakurai family, the Yamanoi family and the 5 families of Toshoke, continuing up until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takeie school female bloodline carries through the Imperial Household and the five main Fujiwara branch families, descending through the Minase school of the Minase family, the Shichijo family, the Machijiri family, the Sakurai family, the Yamanoi family, and the 5 families of Toshoke, continuing up until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takaie linage female bloodline carries through the Imperial Household and Sekke (line of regents and advisers), and the descendants Minase linage later branched into five Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks); the Minase family, the Shichijo family, the Machijiri family, the Sakurai family, and the Yamanoi family, continuing up until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>ここでの「隆家流」は血筋を表しているため、linageを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、南北朝時代 (日本)に懐良親王を擁した肥後国の豪族菊池氏は隆家の後裔と自称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, the powerful Kikuchi clan of Higo Province who supported Imperial Prince Kanenaga during the Nanbokucho Period are self-styled descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, the powerful Kikuchi clan of Higo Province, who supported Imperial Prince Kanenaga during the Nanbokucho Period, are self-styled descendants.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, the powerful Kikuchi clan of Higo Province, who supported Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) were self-styled descendants.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Lonicera(id:20638), Novo(id:87875), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Himazin(id:22034), Snap55(id:89773), 伊集院聖(id:53199), BAKU(id:55205), Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Point136(id:211299), Ponsaku(id:31417), けんち(id:5147), Junger(id:10282), 諸星団(id:72202), 遠野能史(id:86555), 小太刀(id:18154), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>