<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原季行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sueyuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 季行（ふじわら の すえゆき、永久 (日本)2年（1114年） - 応保2年（1162年））は平安時代末期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyuki (1114-1162) was a Court noble who lived during the last days of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sueyuki (1114-1162) was a Court noble who lived during the last days of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyuki (1114-1162) was a Court noble who lived during the last days of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家藤原道綱流、刑部卿藤原敦兼の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third son of FUJIWARA no Atsukane who belonged to Michitsuna Fujiwara line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third son of FUJIWARA no Atsukane who belonged to the Michitsuna Fujiwara line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third son of FUJIWARA no Atsukane who belonged to the Michitsuna Fujiwara line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>従三位・大宰大弐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jusani (Junior Third Rank) at Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jusani (Junior Third Rank) at Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices).</e>
<cmt>大宰府→大宰大弐　ウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに訂正しました。Jusani→Jusanmi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>讃岐三位と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Announced himself as Sanuki no sanmi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Announced himself as Sanuki no sanmi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Called himself as Sanuki no sanmi.</e>
<cmt>Accnounced→Called</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>天治2年（1125年）叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joshaku (conferring a peerage) in 1125.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joshaku (conferring peerage) in 1125.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joshaku (conferring peerage) in 1125.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以後、諸国の国司や大宰大弐などを歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he successively held kokushi (provincial governors) in various districts and Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he successively held kokushi (provincial governors) in various districts and Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he successively held kokushi (provincial governors) in various districts and Dazai no daini.</e>
<cmt>大宰大弐の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>保元元年（1156年）には讃岐国守の職にあり、同年の保元の乱の後讃岐へと流罪になった崇徳上皇の護送を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1156: He was the Sanuki no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Sanuki), and was in charge of escorting the retired Emperor Sutoku when he was exiled to Sanuki after Hogen Disturbance in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1156: He was the Sanuki no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Sanuki), and was in charge of escorting retired Emperor Sutoku when he was exiled to Sanuki after Hogen Disturbance in the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1156, he was the Sanuki no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Sanuki), and was in charge of escorting Retired Emperor Sutoku when he was exiled to Sanuki after Hogen War in the same year.</e>
<cmt>Disturance→Warretired→Retired1156: He→In 1156, he</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>保元4年（1159年）、妻が乳母を務めていた高松院（姝子内親王）が二条天皇の中宮となると、中宮亮に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1159: He was assigned to Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) when Takamatsuin (Imperial Princess Shushi), whose menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) was his wife, became Emperor Nijo&apos;s chugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1159: He was assigned to Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) when Takamatsuin (Imperial Princess Shushi), whose menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby) was his wife, became Emperor Nijo&apos;s chugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1159, he was assigned to Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) when Takamatsuin (Imperial Princess Shushi), whose menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby) was his wife, became Emperor Nijo&apos;s chugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>1159: He→In 1159, he</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>平治元年（1159年）に従三位に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1159: He became Jusani (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1159: He became Jusani (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he became Jusanmi.</e>
<cmt>Jusani→Jusanmi 説明は削除1159: He→In the same year, he</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>娘の一人が藤原兼実の妻となり、九条良通、九条良経を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his daughters became FUJIWARA no Kanezane&apos;s wife, and gave a birth to Yoshimichi KUJO and Yoshitsune KUJO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his daughters became FUJIWARA no Kanezane&apos;s wife, and she gave a birth to Yoshimichi KUJO and Yoshitsune KUJO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his daughters became FUJIWARA no Kanezane&apos;s wife, and she gave birth to Yoshimichi KUJO and Yoshitsune KUJO.</e>
<cmt>a birth→birth</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このように摂関家とも良好な関係を築いた（この縁により良経は高松院の猶子となっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus he established a good relationship with Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), and Yoshitsune was adopted by Takamatsuin because of this bond.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus he established a good relationship with Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), and Yoshitsune was adopted by Takamatsuin because of this bond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus he established a good relationship with Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), and Yoshitsune was adopted by Takamatsuin because of this bond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>歌舞音曲に通じ、篳篥をよくしたことが伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was familiar with public music and dancing, and was said to play hichiriki (small double-reed wind instrument made of bamboo) often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was familiar with public music and dancing, and was said to play hichiriki (small double-reed wind instrument made of bamboo) often.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was familiar with public music and dancing, and was said to play hichiriki (small double-reed wind instrument made of bamboo) often.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また和歌にも秀で、千載集に一首が入選している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also excellent at waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), and one of his poem was selected to be in Senzaishu (poem collection of a thousand years).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also excellent at waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), and one of his poem was selected to be in Senzaishu (poem collection of a thousand years).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also excellent at waka (a traditional Japanese poem of 31 syllables), and one of his poems was selected to be in Senzaishu (poem collection of a thousand years).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更poem→poems</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>後世、その子孫から楊梅家・二条家・平松家 (道綱流)の3堂上家を出したが、いずれも室町時代に断絶している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His offsprings formed 3 Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks), the Yobai family, the Nijo family, and the Hiramatsu family (Michitsuna line), however each family line was ended in Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His offsprings formed 3 Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks), the Yobai family, the Nijo family, and the Hiramatsu family (Michitsuna line), however each family line ended during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His offsprings formed three Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks), the Yobai family, the Nijo family, and the Hiramatsu family (Michitsuna line), however each family line ended during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>