<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三善為康</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MIYOSHI no Tameyasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MIYOSHI no Tameyasu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MIYOSHI no Tameyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三善 為康（みよし の ためやす、永承4年（1049年）- 保延5年8月4日 (旧暦)（1139年8月29日））は、平安時代後期の貴族・算道家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MIYOSHI no Tameyasu (1049-August 29, 1139) was an aristocrat and Sando-ka (a professional of mathematics) who lived in the latter part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MIYOSHI no Tameyasu (1049-August 29, 1139) was an aristocrat and Sando-ka (a professional of mathematics) who lived in the latter part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MIYOSHI no Tameyasu (1049-August 29, 1139) was an aristocrat and Sando-ka (a professional of mathematics) who lived in the latter part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>博識で『朝野群載』や『二中歴』の元となった『懐中歴』・『掌中歴』など多くの著作を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a wide knowledge and wrote many books such as &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (Collected Official and Unofficial Writings) and &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; both of which were the origin of &quot;Nichureki&quot; (a dictionary written in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a wide knowledge-base and wrote many books such as &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (Collected Official and Unofficial Writings) and &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; both of which were the origin of &quot;Nichureki&quot; (a dictionary written in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a wide knowledge-base and wrote many books such as &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (Collected Official and Unofficial Writings) and &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; both of which were the origin of &quot;Nichureki&quot; (a dictionary written in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>越中国射水郡の豪族射水氏の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Imizu clan who was Gozoku (local ruling family) in the Imizu County, Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Imizu clan who was Gozoku (local ruling family) in Imizu County, Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Imizu clan who was Gozoku (local ruling family) in Imizu County, Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>治暦3年（1067年）に上洛して、三善為長のもとで算道を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1067 he went up to Kyoto and learned mathematics under Tamenaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1067 he went up to Kyoto and learned mathematics under Tamenaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1067 he went up to Kyoto and learned mathematics under Tamenaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後に為長の養子となり、三善氏を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he was adopted as a son by Tamenaga and succeeded the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he was adopted as a son by Tamenaga and succeeded the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he was adopted as a son by Tamenaga and succeeded the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後に紀伝道を兼修して省試及第を目指すが落第を重ねた（後年、『続千字文』跋詩の中で大学寮の紀伝道教育が漢詩を弄るだけの昇進のための道具となったと痛烈に批判している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he learned Kidendo (the study of the histories) at the same time and aimed to pass Shoshi (an examination held by Shikibu-sho for determining whether applicants are employable), but failed several times (Later, he severely criticized that the education of Kidendo in Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) fell into only a tool for promotion by playing with Chinese poetry in the ending poem of &quot;Zoku-senzimon&quot; (Chinese poertry written by Tameyasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he learned Kidendo (the study of history) at the same time and aimed to pass Shoshi (an examination held by Shikibu-sho for determining whether applicants are employable), but failed several times (Later, he severely criticized the education of Kidendo in Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) for being only a tool for promotion by playing with Chinese poetry in the ending poem of &quot;Zoku-senzimon&quot; (Chinese poetry written by Tameyasu).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he learned Kidendo (the study of history) at the same time and aimed to pass Shoshi (an examination held by Shikibu-sho for determining whether applicants are employable), but failed several times (Later, he severely criticized the education of Kidendo in Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) for being only a tool for promotion by playing with Chinese poetry in the ending poem of &quot;Shoku-senzimon&quot; (Chinese poetry written by Tameyasu).</e>
<cmt>Zoku→Shoku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>康和2年（1100年）に正六位上少内記となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1100 he was assigned to Shonaiki (an official working at Nakatsukasa (Ministry of the Central Office)) in Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1100 he was assigned to Shonaiki (an official working at Nakatsukasa (Ministry of the Central Office)) in Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1100 he was assigned to Shonaiki (an official working at Nakatsukasa (Ministry of the Central Office)) in Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>堀河天皇の時に抜擢されて算博士・諸陵頭を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era of the Emperor Horikawa, he was promoted to San hakase (Doctor of Numbers) and the head of shoryo (tombs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era of the Emperor Horikawa, he was promoted to San hakase (Doctor of Numbers) and the head of shoryo (tombs).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era of the Emperor Horikawa, he was promoted to San hakase (Doctor of Numbers) and the head of shoryo (tombs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>永久 (日本)4年（1116年）に『朝野群載』を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1116 he wrote &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (Collected Official and Unofficial Writings).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1116 he wrote &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (Collected Official and Unofficial Writings).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1116 he wrote &quot;Choya gunsai&quot;.</e>
<cmt>(Collected Official and Unofficial Writings) 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同5年11月16日 (旧暦)（1117年）と予報された月食の発生を否定する意見を述べたところ、的中させた（『殿暦』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He described an idea to deny the prediction of lunar eclipse which was forecasted to occur on December 18, 1117, and his idea turned out to be true (&quot;Denryaku&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Tadazane)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He believed that the predicted lunar eclipse which was forecasted to occur on December 18, 1117 would not occur, and his idea turned out to be true (&quot;Denryaku&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Tadazane)).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He believed that the predicted lunar eclipse which was forecasted to occur on December 18, 1117 would not occur, and his idea turned out to be true (&quot;Denryaku&quot; (Diary of FUJIWARA no Tadazane)).</e>
<cmt>diary→Diary</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大治 (日本)4年1月6日 (旧暦)（1129年）に81歳にして正五位下に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 3, 1129, when he was eighty-one years old, he was conferred Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 3, 1129, when he was eighty-one years old, he was conferred Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 3, 1129, when he was 81 years old, he was conferred Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、同年には暦道が、8月 (旧暦)に閏月を置くのは良くないとして退閏（改暦）を唱えた際には、宿曜道の隆算とともに、暦道の主張に根拠がないことを唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in the same year when rekido (a professional of calendar) insisted kaireki (changing of calendar) because it was not good to put a leap month on August, he insisted that the opinion of rekido had no reason with Ryusan (隆算) of Suiyodo (a type of astrology).</e>
<cmt>隆算</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in the same year when rekido (a professional dealing with calendars) insisted kaireki (changing of calendar) because it was not good to put a leap month on August, he insisted that the opinion of rekido had no reason with Ryusan (隆算) of Suiyodo (a type of astrology).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in the same year when rekido (a professional dealing with calendars) insisted kaireki (changing of calendar) because it was not good to put a leap month on August, he insisted that the opinion of rekido had no reason with Ryusan (隆算) of Suiyodo (a type of astrology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>晩年には強い阿弥陀信仰を抱き、天承年間には結縁のための勧進の一環として、大江匡房の『続本朝往生伝』を引き継いだ『拾遺往生伝』を著し、続いて『続拾遺往生伝』を執筆した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years he had a strong believing in Amitabha and in the Tensho era he wrote &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; which succeeded &quot;Zoku honcho ojoden&quot; (Sequel to the Accounts of Rebirth into the Pure Land) written by OE no Masafusa and consequently wrote &quot;Zoku Shui Ojo-den&quot; as one of the ways of kanjin (temple solicitation) for Kechien (making a connection with Buddha to rest spirit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years he had a strong believing in Amitabha and in the Tensho era he wrote &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; which succeeded &quot;Zoku honcho ojoden&quot; (Sequel to the Accounts of Rebirth into the Pure Land) written by OE no Masafusa and consequently wrote &quot;Zoku Shui Ojo-den&quot; as one of the ways of kanjin (temple solicitation) for Kechien (making a connection with Buddha to rest spirit).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years he had a strong believing in Amitabha and in the Tensho era he wrote &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; which succeeded &quot;Zoku honcho ojoden&quot; (Sequel to the Accounts of Rebirth into the Pure Land) written by OE no Masafusa and consequently wrote &quot;Zoku Shui Ojo-den&quot; as one of the ways of kanjin (temple solicitation) for Kechien (making a connection with Buddha to rest spirit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>91歳の長寿を保ち、亡くなる際には阿弥陀如来に向かって多年の念仏の功徳によって必ず引接を垂れ給わんことを祈請しながら没し、往生人（極楽往生した人）となったとされている（『本朝新修往生伝』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lived long until ninety-one years old and it is said that when he was dying he continued to pray for Amitabha to surely lead him to gokuraku jodo (the Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)) by kudoku (merit) of Buddhist invocation for a long time and became Ojo-nin (a person who achieved gokuraku ojo (peaceful death)) (&quot;Honcho shinshu Ojo-den&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lived long until ninety-one years old and it is said that when he was dying he continued to pray for Amitabha to surely lead him to gokuraku jodo (the Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)) by kudoku (merit) of Buddhist invocation for a long time and became Ojo-nin (a person who achieved gokuraku ojo (peaceful death)) (&quot;Honcho shinshu Ojo-den&quot;).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lived long until 91 years old and it is said that when he was dying he continued to pray for Amitabha to surely lead him to gokuraku jodo (the Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)) by kudoku (merit) of Buddhist invocation for a long time and became Ojo-nin (a person who achieved gokuraku ojo (peaceful death)) (&quot;Honcho shinshu Ojo-den&quot; (New collection of hagiographies of those born in the Pure Land)).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更for の前のスペース短縮朝新修往生伝の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>官歴には恵まれなかったが、晩年まで様々な著作を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he could not have good official ranks, he wrote various books even in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he could not have good official ranks, he wrote various books even in his later years.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he could not have good official ranks, he wrote various books even in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『朝野群載』（28巻）や『懐中歴』（10巻）・『掌中歴』（4巻）などが代表的なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works were such as &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (twenty-eight volumes), &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; (ten volumes) and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; (four volumes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works were such as &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (twenty-eight volumes), &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; (ten volumes), and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; (four volumes).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works were such as &quot;Choya gunsai&quot; (28 volumes), &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; (10 volumes), and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; (four volumes).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『懐中歴』・『掌中歴』は散逸したが、鎌倉時代に両書を元にして編纂された『二中歴』が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; were scattered and ultimately lost, &quot;Nichureki&quot; which was edited based on these books in the Kamakura period remains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; were scattered and ultimately lost, &quot;Nichureki&quot; which was edited based on these books in the Kamakura period remains.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;Kaichu-reki&quot; and &quot;Shochu-reki&quot; were scattered and ultimately lost, &quot;Nichureki&quot; which was edited based on these books in the Kamakura period remains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また児童向として『続千字文』・『童蒙頌韻』などの啓蒙書を執筆、更に本職である数学書『三元九紫法』を著したがこちらは散逸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he wrote books for children&apos;s education such as &quot;Zoku-senjimon&quot; and &quot;Domoshoin&quot; (a dictionary of Chinese characters) and a mathematics book &quot;Sangenkyushiho&quot;(三元九紫法) in which area he was professional, but the latter was scattered and ultimately lost.</e>
<cmt>三元九紫法の読み方、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he wrote books for children&apos;s education such as &quot;Zoku-senjimon&quot; and &quot;Domoshoin&quot; (a dictionary of Chinese characters) and a mathematics book &quot;Sangenkyushiho&quot;(三元九紫法) in which area he was professional, but the latter was scattered and ultimately lost.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he wrote books for children&apos;s education such as &quot;Shoku-senjimon&quot; and &quot;Domoshoin&quot; (a dictionary of Chinese characters) and a mathematics book &quot;Sangenkyushiho&quot;(三元九紫法) in which area he was professional, but the latter was scattered and ultimately lost.</e>
<cmt>Zoku→Shoku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>また、若い頃から観音菩薩、後に浄土教を厚く信仰したことで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he is known well to have strongly believed Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Buddhisattva) from his young age and later Jodo (Pure Land) sect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he is well known to have strongly believed in Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Buddhisattva) from a young age and later Jodo (Pure Land) sect.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he is well known to have strongly believed in Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Buddhisattva) from a young age and later Jodo (Pure Land) sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>仏教関連の著作も多く残しており、前述の『拾遺往生伝』・『後拾遺往生伝』をはじめ、『仏法感験記』・『六波羅蜜寺縁起』・『叡山根本大師伝』・『世俗往生決疑』（散逸）・『金剛般若験記』（散逸）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left many books on Buddhism such as &quot;Buppo Kangenki&quot; (仏法感験記), &quot;The engi (origin) of the Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple,&quot; &quot;The legend of Eizan Konpon Daishi,&quot; &quot;Sezoku Ojo Ketsugi&quot; (世俗往生決疑)(scattered and ultimately lost) and &quot;Kongo-Hannyagenki&quot;(金剛般若験記) (scattered and ultimately lost) as well as above &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; and &quot;Goshui Ojo-den.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。仏法感験記、世俗往生決疑、金剛般若験記の読み方、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left many books on Buddhism such as &quot;Buppo Kangenki&quot; (仏法感験記), &quot;The engi (origin) of the Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple,&quot; &quot;The legend of Eizan Konpon Daishi,&quot; &quot;Sezoku Ojo Ketsugi&quot; (世俗往生決疑)(scattered and ultimately lost), and &quot;Kongo-Hannyagenki&quot;(金剛般若験記) (scattered and ultimately lost) as well as the above &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; and &quot;Goshui Ojo-den.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left many books on Buddhism such as &quot;Buppo Kangenki&quot; (仏法感験記), &quot;The engi (origin) of the Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple,&quot; &quot;The legend of Eizan Konpon Daishi,&quot; &quot;Sezoku Ojo Ketsugi&quot; (世俗往生決疑)(scattered and ultimately lost), and &quot;Kongo-Hannyagenki&quot;(金剛般若験記) (scattered and ultimately lost) as well as the above &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; and &quot;Goshui Ojo-den.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>