<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近衞文麿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumimaro KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumimaro KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumimaro KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近衞 文麿（このえ ふみまろ、明治24年（1891年）10月12日 - 昭和20年（1945年）12月16日）は、日本の政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumimaro KONOE (October 12, 1891 - December 16, 1945) was a Japanese politician.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumimaro KONOE (October 12, 1891 - December 16, 1945) was a Japanese politician.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumimaro KONOE (October 12, 1891 - December 16, 1945) was a Japanese politician.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第5代貴族院議長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifth president of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fifth president of the Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;He was the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fifth president of the Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第34、38、39代内閣総理大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">34th, 38th and 39th prime minister of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 34th, 38th and 39th Prime Minister of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;He was the&quot;Capitalized &apos;p&apos; and &apos;m&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 34th, 38th and 39th Prime Minister of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>爵位は公爵であり、かつ摂家筆頭である近衛家の当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His title of peerage was duke, and he was also the family head of Konoe Family, which was the head of Sekke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His title was duke, and he was also the head of Konoe Family, the main Sekke, or Regent, Family.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;of peerage&quot;, &quot;family&quot;&quot;which was the head&quot;→&quot;the main&quot;Added &quot;, or Regent, Family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His title was a prince, and he was also the head of the Konoe family, the main Sekke, or Regent, Family.</e>
<cmt>公爵→Prince[用語集]Konoe Family→the Konoe familyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴・人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His history and character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and character</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;His&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography and Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>History and character→Biography and Personal Profileに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生い立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His upbringing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upbringing</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;His&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upbringing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>近衛文麿は1891年（明治24年）10月12日、公爵近衛篤麿と旧加賀藩で侯爵前田慶寧の三女・衍の間の長男として、東京市麹町区（現 千代田区）で生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumimaro KONOE was born on October 12, 1891, as the first son between Duke Atsumaro KONOE and En, the third daughter of Marquee Yoshiyasu MAEDA of former domain of Kaga, in Kojimachi Ward, Tokyo City (present-day Chiyoda Ward).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumimaro KONOE was born on October 12, 1891, the first son between Duke Atsumaro KONOE and En, the third daughter of Marquess Yoshiyasu MAEDA of the former domain of Kaga, in Kojimachi Ward, Tokyo City (present-day Chiyoda Ward).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;as&quot;&quot;Marquee&quot;→&quot;Marquess&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumimaro KONOE was born on October 12, 1891, the first son between Prince Atsumaro KONOE and En, the third daughter of Marquess Yoshiyasu MAEDA of the former domain of Kaga, in Kojimachi Ward, Tokyo City (present-day Chiyoda Ward).</e>
<cmt>公爵→Prince[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし母は文麿が幼いときに病没、篤麿は衍の妹・貞を後妻に迎えるが、文麿はこの叔母にあたる継母とはうまくいかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his mother died of an illness when he was young, and Atsumaro took En&apos;s younger sister, Sada, as the second wife, but Fumimaro did not get along with this step-mother, who was his aunt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his mother died of illness when he was young, and Atsumaro took En&apos;s younger sister, Sada, as his second wife, but Fumimaro did not get along with this step-mother, who was also his aunt.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;an&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;Added &quot;also&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his mother died of illness when he was young, and Atsumaro took En&apos;s younger sister, Sada, as his second wife, but Fumimaro did not get along with this step-mother, who was also his aunt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>父の篤麿はアジア主義を唱え、東亜同文会を興すなど活発な政治活動を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Atsumaro, advocated Asianism, and he was actively engaged in political movements such as establishing of the Toa-dobunkai nationalism group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Atsumaro, was a supporter of Pan-Asianism and was politically active, involved in the founding of groups such as the East Asia Common Culture Society (Toa Dobunkai).</e>
<cmt>&quot;advocated Asianism&quot;→&quot;was a supporter of Pan-Asianism&quot;Deleted &quot;he&quot;&quot;actively engaged in political movements&quot;→&quot;politically active&quot;&quot;such as establishing of the Toa-dobunkai nationalism group&quot;→&quot;, involved in the founding of groups such as the East Asia Common Culture Society (Toa Dobunkai)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Atsumaro, was a supporter of Pan-Asianism and was politically active, involved in the founding of groups such as the East Asia Common Culture Society (Toa Dobunkai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ところが、1904年（明治37年）に、篤麿は41歳の若さで死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1904, Atsumaro died at a young age of 41.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1904, Atsumaro died at the young age of 41.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1904, Atsumaro died at the young age of 41.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>文麿は12歳にして襲爵し近衛家の当主となるが、父が残した多額の借金をも相続することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumimaro inherited ancestral dignity at the age of 12, but he also inherited a large amount of debt that his father left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumimaro became a peer and head of the Konoe family at the age of 12, but he also inherited a large amount of debt that his father left.</e>
<cmt>&quot;inherited ancestral dignity&quot;→&quot;became a Peer and head of the Konoe family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumimaro became a peer and head of the Konoe family at the age of 12, but he also inherited a large amount of debt that his father left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>近衛の、どことなく陰がある反抗的な気質はこのころに形成された、と後に本人が述懐している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE&apos;s somewhat shadowy and rebellious temperament was formed during this period, as he himself reminisced later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE&apos;s somewhat shadowy and rebellious temperament was formed during this period, as he himself later reminisced.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;later&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe&apos;s somewhat shadowy and rebellious temperament was formed during this period, as he himself later reminisced.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>この苦境を救ったのは、同じ公家出身の政治家・西園寺公望である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one who helped him from this difficult situation was Kimmochi SAIONJI, who was a politician and also a court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was helped through this difficult time by fellow noble and politician, Kinmochi Saionji.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was helped through this difficult time by fellow noble and politician, Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>Saionji→SAIONJI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>西園寺は、篤麿とは政敵とも言える状況にあったが、文麿の聡明さは高く評価して援助を惜しまなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAIONJI, though it can be said that he was situated as a political enemy of Atsumaro, greatly admired Fumimaro&apos;s intelligence and he supported him unsparingly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it could be said that SAIONJI had been a political opponent of Atsumaro, he greatly admired Fumimaro&apos;s intelligence and willingly supported him. unsparingly.</e>
<cmt>&quot;SAIONJI, though it can be said that he was situated as a political enemy&quot;→&quot;Although it could be said that SAIONJI had been a political opponent&quot;Moved &quot;he&quot;&quot;unsparingly&quot;→&quot;willingly&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it could be said that Saionji had been a political opponent of Atsumaro, he greatly admired Fumimaro&apos;s intelligence and willingly supported him. unsparingly.</e>
<cmt>SAIONJI→Saionji</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>後に第一次世界大戦後のパリ講和会議に日本全権として参加した際にも近衛を秘書として伴っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when he attended Paris Peace Conference as a Japanese plenipotentiary after the First World War, he let KONOE accompany him as a secretary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when he attended the Paris Peace Conference as the chief Japanese delegate after the First World War, he let KONOE accompany him as a secretary.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;a Japanese plenipotentiary&quot;→&quot;the chief Japanese delegate&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when he attended the Paris Peace Conference as the chief Japanese delegate after the First World War, he let Konoe accompany him as a secretary.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>こうして文麿は、父のアジア主義よりも、西園寺の自由主義歴史的起源とその展開に感化されることとなったが、自らの後継者を育てたいという西園寺の思惑とは裏腹に、文麿は次第に目先の新しいものに目移りする無定見さを見せ始めるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Fumimaro became influenced by SAIONJI&apos;s historical origin of Liberalism and its development rather than by his father&apos;s Asianism, but in contrast to SAIONJI&apos;s motive of raising his successor Fumimaro gradually began to show signs of having no fixed principles and a propensity for being captivated by things that were new with short term goals.</e>
<cmt>無定見→chops and changes→having no fixed principles[英辞郎 on the Web, 英辞郎 on the Webには without any fixed principle となってますが、訳文の書き方ではそのままつかえないので having no fixed principles としました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Fumimaro was influenced more by SAIONJI&apos;s historical origins of Liberalism and its development rather than by his father&apos;s Pan-Asianism, but in contrast to SAIONJI&apos;s motive of raising his successor Fumimaro gradually began to show signs of having no fixed principles and a propensity for being captivated by things that were new with short term goals.</e>
<cmt>&quot;became influenced&quot;→&quot;was influenced more&quot;Added &quot;Pan-&quot;&quot;motive&quot;→&quot;hopes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Fumimaro was influenced more by Saionji&apos;s historical origins of Liberalism and its development rather than by his father&apos;s Pan-Asianism, but in contrast to Saionji&apos;s motive of raising his successor Fumimaro gradually began to show signs of having no fixed principles and a propensity for being captivated by things that were new with short term goals.</e>
<cmt>SAIONJI→Saionji</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>学習院中等科を修了後、華族の師弟は学習院高等科にそのまま進学するのが通例だが、当時第一高等学校 (旧制) の校長であった新渡戸稲造に感化され、一高を受験して進学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, children of new nobilities went on to attend Gakushuin High School after graduating from Gakushuin Junior High School, but because he was influenced by Inazo NITOBE, who was the headmaster of Daiichi High School (the first old-education-system high school) he went on to attend Ichiko (Daiichi High School).</e>
<cmt>師弟 = master and disciple, 子弟 = children, 原文の師弟は子弟の間違いだと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, children of the nobility went on to attend Gakushuin High School after graduating from Gakushuin Junior High School, but because he was influenced by Inazo NITOBE, who was the headmaster of Daiichi High School, he went on to attend that school instead.</e>
<cmt>&quot;new nobilities&quot;→&quot;the nobility&quot;Deleted &quot;(the first old-education-system high school)&quot;- unnecessary for most non-Japanese speakers&quot;Ichiko (Daiichi High School)&quot;→&quot;that school instead&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, children of the nobility went on to attend Gakushuin High School after graduating from Gakushuin Junior High School, but because he was influenced by Inazo NITOBE, who was the headmaster of Daiichi High School, he went on to attend that school instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>続いて東京帝国大学（戦後の東京大学）で哲学を学んだが飽き足らず、高名な経済学者であり、当時急速にマルクス経済学に傾倒しつつあった河上肇に学ぶため、京都帝国大学（戦後の京都大学）法学部に転学した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he studied philosophy at Tokyo Imperial University (The University of Tokyo after the war), but because he was unsatisfied he transferred to Kyoto Imperial University (Kyoto University after the war) School of Law in order to study under Hajime KAWAKAMI, who was quickly becoming committed to Marxist economics at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he studied philosophy at Tokyo Imperial University (renamed The University of Tokyo after the war), but because he was unsatisfied he transferred to Kyoto Imperial University (renamed Kyoto University after the war) School of Law in order to study under Hajime KAWAKAMI, who was quickly becoming committed to Marxist economics at the time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Then&quot;→&quot;After that&quot;Added &quot;renamed&quot; to both brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he studied philosophy at Tokyo Imperial University (renamed The University of Tokyo after the war), but because he was unsatisfied he transferred to Kyoto Imperial University (renamed Kyoto University after the war) School of Law in order to study under Hajime KAWAKAMI, who was quickly becoming committed to Marxist economics at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>在学中の1914年（大正3年）には、第三次『新思潮』に、オスカー・ワイルドの『社会主義下における人間の魂』を翻訳し、「社会主義論」として発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1914, while he was a student, he translated Oscar Wilde&apos;s &quot;The Soul of Man Under Socialism&quot; and published it as &quot;Theory of Socialism&quot; in the third &quot;Shin-Shicho&quot; magazine.</e>
<cmt>社会主義下における人間の魂→The Soul of Man Under Socialism [http://www.worldsocialism.org/articles/oscar_wilde_the_soul.php]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1914, while he was a student, he translated Oscar Wilde&apos;s &quot;The Soul of Man Under Socialism&quot; and published it as &quot;Theory of Socialism&quot; in the third &quot;Shin-Shicho&quot; magazine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1914, while he was a student, he translated Oscar Wilde&apos;s &quot;The Soul of Man Under Socialism&quot; and published it as &quot;Theory of Socialism&quot; in the third &quot;Shin-Shicho&quot; magazine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、これは発禁となり、近衛は宮内省に呼ばれて厳重注意された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this became banned and KONOE was summoned by the Imperial Household Ministry and was given a serious warning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the piece was banned, with KONOE being summoned by the Imperial Household Ministry and given a serious warning.</e>
<cmt>&quot;this became&quot;→&quot;the piece was&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;, with&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;being&quot;deleted &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the piece was banned, with Konoe being summoned by the Imperial Household Ministry and given a serious warning.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>なお東大時代には、のちに「宮中革新派」などと呼ばれて政界で活躍する木戸幸一（後に内大臣）や原田熊雄（後に西園寺公望秘書）などの華族の子弟と親交を深めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was at Todai he deepened friendship with children of new nobilities such as Koichi KIDO (later, Naidaijin), who later became an active member in the political world and was called &quot;reformist group of Imperial court&quot;, and Kumao HARADA (who later became Kimmochi SAIONJI&apos;s secretary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While at Tokyo University, he developed close friendships with children of the nobility such as Koichi KIDO (later, Naidaijin or Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal) and Kumao HARADA (who later became Kimmochi SAIONJI&apos;s secretary), both of whom later became active in the political world as members of the &quot;reformist group of the Imperial court&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;he was&quot;&quot;Todai&quot;→&quot;Tokyo University&quot;&quot;deepened friendship&quot;→&quot;developed close friendships&quot;&quot;new nobilities&quot;→&quot;the nobility&quot;Added &quot; or Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal&quot;Moved &quot;and Kumao HARADA (who later became Kimmochi SAIONJI&apos;s secretary)&quot;&quot;who&quot;→&quot;both of whom&quot;Deleted &quot;an&quot; and &quot;member&quot;&quot;and was called&quot;→&quot;as members of the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While at Tokyo University, he developed close friendships with children of the nobility such as Koichi KIDO (later, Naidaijin or Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal) and Kumao HARADA (who later became Kimmochi SAIONJI&apos;s secretary), both of whom later became active in the political world as members of the &apos;reformist group of the Imperial court.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>政界へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Into the Political World</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entry into Politics</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entry into Politics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>1916年（大正5年）、満25歳に達したことにより公爵として世襲である貴族院 (日本)議員になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1916, by turning 25 years of age he became a hereditary member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) as a duke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1916, when he turned 25, he became a hereditary member of the House of Peers as a duke.</e>
<cmt>&quot;by turning 25 years of age&quot;→&quot;when he turned 25,&quot;Deleted &quot;Kizoku&quot; and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1916, when he turned 25, he became a hereditary member of the House of Peers as a prince.</e>
<cmt>公爵→Prince[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1918年（大正7年）に、雑誌『日本及日本人』に論文「英米本位の平和主義を排す」を執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1918, he authored an article, &quot;Britain and the U.S.-Oriented Pacifism&quot; in &quot;Japan and the Japanese&quot; magazine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918, he authored an article, &quot;Reject Anglo-American-Based Pacifism&quot; in &quot;Japan and the Japanese&quot; magazine.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Britain and the U.S.-Oriented Pacifism&quot;→&quot;Reject Anglo-American-Based Pacifism&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918, he authored an article, &apos;Reject Anglo-American-Based Pacifism&apos; in &quot;Japan and the Japanese&quot; magazine.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1919年（大正8年）のパリ講和会議には全権西園寺公望に随行し、見聞を広めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, he accompanied Japanese plenipotentiary, Kimmochi SAIONJI, to Paris Peace Conference, and he broadened his knowledge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, he accompanied Japanese delegate, Kimmochi SAIONJI, to the Paris Peace Conference, broadening his knowledge.</e>
<cmt>&quot;plenipotentiary&quot;→&quot;delegate&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;and he broadened&quot;→&quot;broadening&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, he accompanied Japanese delegate, Kimmochi SAIONJI, to the Paris Peace Conference, broadening his knowledge.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>その後、1927年（昭和2年）には旧態依然とした所属会派の研究会_(貴族院)から離脱して木戸・徳川家達らとともに火曜会を結成して貴族院内に政治的な地盤を得るとともに、次第に西園寺から離れて院内革新勢力の中心人物となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in 1927, he broke away from the old-fashioned study group of the parliamentary group (the House of Peers) to which he belonged, formed Kayokai parliamentary group with KIDO and Iesato TOKUGAWA and established a political foundation within the House of Peers, and at the same time, he gradually broke away from SAIONJI and began to become a central figure in the innovative power in Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, in 1927, he broke away from the old-fashioned study group of his faction and formed the Kayokai faction with KIDO and Iesato TOKUGAWA, establishing a political base in the House of Peers, and at the same time, he gradually broke away from SAIONJI, becoming a central figure among the House of Peers&apos; reformers.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the parliamentary group (the House of Peers) to which he belonged&quot;→&quot;his faction&quot;Added &quot;and&quot; and &quot;the&quot;&quot;parliamentary group&quot;→&quot;faction&quot;&quot;and established&quot;→&quot;, establishing&quot;&quot;foundation&quot;→&quot;base&quot;&quot;within&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;and began to become&quot;→&quot;, becoming&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;among&quot;&quot;innovative power in Kizokuin (the House of Peers)&quot;→&quot;House of Peers&apos; reformers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in 1927, he broke away from the old-fashioned study group of his faction and formed the Kayokai faction with KIDO and Iesato TOKUGAWA, establishing a political base in the House of Peers, and at the same time, he gradually broke away from Saionji, becoming a central figure among the House of Peers&apos; reformers.</e>
<cmt>SAIONJI→Saionji</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>また摂家筆頭という血筋や、貴公子然とした端正な風貌（当時の日本人にあっては長身であった）に加えて、対英米協調外交に反対する現状打破主義的主張で、大衆的な人気も獲得し、早くから首相待望論が聞かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in addition to his noble and fine appearance (he was quite tall for a Japanese at the time) and the fact that he was from the top-ranking Sekke, he advocated overturning of the status quo, and he gained popularity among the masses and a long-awaited Prime Minister theory was heard from early on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in addition to his noble and handsome appearance (he was quite tall for a Japanese of the time) and the fact that he was from the top-ranking Sekke family, he advocated overturning the diplomatic status quo and was popular with the public and was soon being mentioned as a Prime Minister-in-waiting.</e>
<cmt>&quot;fine&quot;→&quot;handsome&quot;&quot;at&quot;→&quot;of&quot;Added &quot;family&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;Added &quot;diplomatic&quot;&quot;he gained popularity among the masses&quot;→&quot;was popular with the public&quot;&quot; a long-awaited Prime Minister theory was heard from early on&quot;→&quot;was soon being mentioned as a Prime Minister-in-waiting&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in addition to his noble and handsome appearance (he was quite tall for a Japanese of the time) and the fact that he was from the top-ranking Sekke family, he advocated overturning the diplomatic status quo and was popular with the public and was soon being mentioned as a Prime Minister-in-waiting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1933年（昭和8年）貴族院議長に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1933, he became the president of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1933, he was elected President of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>&quot;becamethe president&quot;→&quot;was elected President&quot;Deleted &quot;Kizokuin&quot; and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1933, he was elected President of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>1936年（昭和11年）の二・二六事件直後には岡田啓介首相の後継として初めての大命降下があったが、この時は健康問題を理由に辞退している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after the February 26th Incident in 1936, he was given an imperial command to succeed Prime Minister Keisuke OKADA, but he declined at the time using his health as an excuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the February 26th Incident in 1936, he received an imperial command to succeed Prime Minister Keisuke OKADA, but he declined at the time, using his health as an excuse.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was given&quot;→&quot;received&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the February 26th Incident in 1936, he received an imperial command to succeed Prime Minister Keisuke OKADA, but he declined at the time, using his health as an excuse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>辞退の真因に関しては各説あるが、近衛が親近感をもっていた大日本帝国陸軍皇道派の勢力が相沢事件とそれに続く二・二六事件により失墜していたことから、政権運営の困難を感じていたのではないかとの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories about the true reasons for his declination, but according to one theory, he might have been sensing difficulty in handling of the government because of the downfall of the forces of the Kodoha (the Imperial Way group) of army, Empire of Japan, after the Aizawa-jiken Incident and the February 26 Incident that followed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about the true reasons for his refusal, but according to one theory, he might have realized that the government would be difficult to handle following the defeat of the Army&apos;s ultranationalist Kodaha (Imperial Way) faction in the Aizawa Incident and the February 26 Incident that followed it.</e>
<cmt>Reworded 2nd part of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about the true reasons for his refusal, but according to one theory, he might have realized that the government would be difficult to handle following the defeat of the Army&apos;s ultranationalist Kodaha (Imperial Way) faction in the Aizawa Incident and the February 26 Incident that followed it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>第一次内閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Cabinet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>1937年（昭和12年）6月4日に、元老・西園寺の推薦の下で、各界の期待を背に第1次近衛内閣を組織した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June, 1937, upon recommendation by Genro (elder statesman) SAIONJI, he formed the first Konoe&apos;s cabinet, shouldering high expectations from various quarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1937, upon the recommendation of the Genro (elder statesman) SAIONJI, he formed the first Konoe&apos;s cabinet, shouldering high expectations from various quarters.</e>
<cmt>&quot;On&quot;→&quot;In&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;by&quot;→&quot;of the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1937, upon the recommendation of the Genro (elder statesman) SAIONJI, he formed the first Konoe&apos;s cabinet, shouldering high expectations from various quarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その直後には、「国内各論の融和を図る」ことを大義名分として、治安維持法違反の共産党員や二・二六事件の逮捕・服役者を大赦しようと主張して、周囲を驚愕させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after that, using &quot;in an attempt to reconcile the various opinions within the nation&quot; as the legitimate reason, he dismayed those around him by asserting to pardon those who were arrested and serving time for the February 26 Incident, and the Communist party members who violated the Maintenance of Public Order Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after, he dismayed those around him by granting an amnesty to Communist Party members who had violated the Maintenance of Public Order Law and detainees from the February 26 Incident, justifying his actions as &quot;an attempt to reconcile the various opinions within the nation&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order and reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after, he dismayed those around him by granting an amnesty to Communist Party members who had violated the Maintenance of Public Order Law and detainees from the February 26 Incident, justifying his actions as &apos;an attempt to reconcile the various opinions within the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この大赦論は、荒木貞夫が陸相時代に提唱していたもので、かれ独特の国体論に基づくものであったが、二・二六事件以降は皇道派将校の救済の意味も持つようになり、真崎甚三郎の救済にも熱心だった近衛は、首相就任前からこれに共感を示していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This amnesty theory was something Sadao ARAKI had advocated during the period when he was the Minister of Army and it was based on his own theory of national policy, but after the February 26 Incident it began to also imply saving of the commissioned officer of Kodoha (the Imperial Way group), and because KONOE was eager to save Jinzaburo MAZAKI he had shown signs of empathizing with this even before he became the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This amnesty theory had been advocated by Sadao ARAKI, based on his own theory of national policy, when he was the Minister of the Army but after the February 26 Incident, it began to also imply saving the commissioned officers of the Kodoha faction, and because KONOE was eager to save Jinzaburo MAZAKI, he had shown signs of empathizing with this even before becoming Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>Reworded first part of sentenceAdded &quot;the&quot;Moved commaDeleted &quot;of&quot;Made &quot;officer&quot; pluralAdded &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;(the Imperial Way group)&quot;Added &quot;faction&quot;&quot;he became the&quot;→&quot;becoming&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This amnesty theory had been advocated by Sadao ARAKI, based on his own theory of national policy, when he was the Minister of the Army but after the February 26 Incident, it began to also imply saving the commissioned officers of the Kodoha faction, and because Konoe was eager to save Jinzaburo MAZAKI, he had shown signs of empathizing with this even before becoming Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、西園寺は、荒木が唱えだした頃からこの論には反対であり、結局、大赦はならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, SAIONJI was against this theory ever since ARAKI began to advocate it, and in the end, pardon did not take place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, SAIONJI had been against the theory ever since ARAKI had begun to advocate it and in the end, the pardon did not take place.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was&quot;→&quot;had been&quot;&quot;this&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;began&quot;→&quot;had begun&quot;Deleted commaAdded &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Saionji had been against the theory ever since Araki had begun to advocate it and in the end, the pardon did not take place.</e>
<cmt>SAIONJI→SaionjiARAKI→Araki</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>7月7日に盧溝橋事件をきっかけに日中戦争（支那事変）が勃発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 7, Sino-Japanese War (Shina-jihen (Second Sino-Japanese War)) broke out, triggered by the Rokokyo Bridge Incident (the Marco Polo Bridge Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 7, the Second Sino-Japanese War (Shina-jihen) broke out, triggered by the Marco Polo Bridge Incident.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the Second&quot;Deleted &quot;(Second Sino-Japanese War)&quot;, &quot;the Rokokyo Bridge Incident&quot; and brackets - it&apos;s better known as the Marco Polo Bridge Incident in English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 7, the Second Sino-Japanese War (Shina-jihen) broke out, triggered by the Marco Polo Bridge Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>7月9日には、不拡大方針を閣議で確認。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 9, the localization policy was confirmed in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 9, a policy of nonexpansion was confirmed in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the localization policy&quot;→&quot;a policy of nonaggravation&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 9, a policy of nonexpansion was confirmed in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>7月11日には現地の松井久太郎大佐（北平特務機関長）と秦徳純（第二十九軍副軍長）との間で停戦協定が締結されたにもかかわらず、内地三個師団を派兵する「北支派兵声明」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 11, deployment of Naichi Sanko-shidan (three divisions of inland) troops called &quot;the statement to dispatch troops to North China&quot; was announced, even though there was an armistice agreement being concluded between Colonel Kyutaro MATSUI (head of secret military agency in Peiping), who was on site, and Shin Toku Jun (twenty-ninth vice captain of army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 11, the deployment of three divisions of troops from Japan was announced in the &quot;proclamation of troop dispatch to China&quot;, even though there was an armistice being concluded between Colonel Kyutaro MATSUI, head of the secret service in Peiping (Beijing), and Qin Dechun, Deputy Commander of the 29th Army.</e>
<cmt>Reworded first part of sentenceDeleted &quot;agreement&quot; and brackets&quot;secret military agency&quot;→&quot;the secret service&quot;Added &quot;(Beijing)Deleted &quot;on site&quot;&quot;Shin Toku Jun&quot;→&quot;Qin Dechun&quot;Deleted brackets&quot;twenty-ninth vice captain of army&quot;→&quot;Deputy Commander of the 29th Army&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 11, the deployment of three divisions of troops from Japan was announced in the &apos;proclamation of troop dispatch to China,&apos; even though there was an armistice being concluded between Colonel Kyutaro MATSUI, head of the secret service in Peiping (Beijing), and Qin Dechun, Deputy Commander of the 29th Army.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし、その後の国会では「事件不拡大」を言い続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at the parliament thereafter, he continued to maintain &quot;localization of the incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at parliament, KONOE continued to maintain the &quot;nonexpansion of the incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot; and &quot;thereafter&quot;&quot;he&quot;→&quot;KONOE&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;localization&quot;→&quot;nonexpansion&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at parliament, KONOE continued to maintain the &apos;nonexpansion of the incident.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>7月17日には、1千万円余の予備費支出を閣議決定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 17, payment of over 10 million yen from a reserve fund was approved in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 17, the use of over 10 million yen from a reserve fund was approved in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>&quot;payment&quot;→&quot;the use&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 17, the use of over 10 million yen from a reserve fund was approved in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>7月26日には、陸軍が要求していないにも拘らず、9700万円余の第一次北支事変費予算案を閣議決定し、7月31日には4億円超の第二次北支事変費予算を追加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 26, even though the Army did not request, the first budget for Hokushi-jihen (Sino-Japanese War) of over 9.7 million yen was approved in the cabinet meeting, and by July 31, the second budget for Hokushi-jihen (Sino-Japanese War) of 400 million yen was added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 26, even though the Army did not request it, the first budget for the Sino-Japanese War of over 97 million yen was approved in the cabinet meeting, and on July 31, the second budget for the Sino-Japanese War of 400 million yen was added.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;it&quot;Deleted &quot;Hokushi-jihen&quot; and bracketsAdded &quot;the&quot;&quot;9.7&quot;→&quot;97&quot;&quot;by&quot;→&quot;on&quot;Deleted &quot;Hokushi-jihen&quot; and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 26, even though the Army did not request it, the first budget for the Sino-Japanese War of over 97 million yen was approved in the cabinet meeting, and on July 31, the second budget for the Sino-Japanese War of 400 million yen was added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>8月2日には増税案を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 2nd, a proposal for a tax increase was announced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 2nd, a proposal for a tax increase was announced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 2, a proposal for a tax increase was announced.</e>
<cmt>nd削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この間に宋子文を通じて和平工作を行い、近衛と蒋との間で合意が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, he made a peace overture through So Shi Bun (Song Ziwen), and an agreement was reached between KONOE and CHIANG Kai-shek.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, he made a peace overture through Song Ziwen, and an agreement was reached between KONOE and CHIANG Kai-shek.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;So Shi Bun&quot; and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, he made a peace overture through Song Ziwen, and an agreement was reached between Konoe and CHIANG Kai-shek.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>国民政府側から特使を南京に送って欲しいとの電報が届くと、近衛は杉山元陸相に確認を取り、宮崎龍介を特使として上海に派遣することを決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon receiving a telegraph from the Nationalist Government requesting a special envoy to be sent, KONOE confirmed with Minister of Army Hajime SUGIYAMA and approved the dispatching of Ryusuke MIYASAKI to Shanghai as a special envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon receiving a telegraph from the Nationalist Government requesting a special envoy be sent to Nanjing, KONOE consulted with Minister of the Army Hajime SUGIYAMA and approved the dispatching of Ryusuke MIYASAKI to Shanghai.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;to&quot;Added &quot;to Nanjing&quot;&quot;confirmed&quot;→&quot;consulted&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;as a special envoy&quot; to avoid repetition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon receiving a telegraph from the Nationalist Government requesting a special envoy be sent to Nanjing, Konoe consulted with Minister of the Army Hajime SUGIYAMA and approved the dispatching of Ryusuke MIYASAKI to Shanghai.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ところが海軍を通じてこの電報を傍受した陸軍内の強硬派がこれを好感せず、憲兵を動かして宮崎を神戸港で拘束し東京へ送還してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the hard-liners within the Army, who intercepted this telegraph through the Navy, viewed the situation undesirable, so they mobilized the military police, restrained MIYASAKI at Port of Kobe and sent him back to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>神戸港→Kobe Bay→Port of Kobe[港なので Port にしました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, hard-liners within the Army, who intercepted the telegraph through the Navy, viewed the situation undesirable, so they dispatched the military police, who restrained MIYASAKI at the Port of Kobe and sent him back to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot; and &quot;, who&quot;&quot;this&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;mobilized&quot;→&quot;dispatched&quot;Added &quot;who&quot; and &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, hard-liners within the Army, who intercepted the telegraph through the Navy, viewed the situation undesirable, so they dispatched the military police, who restrained Miyazaki at the Port of Kobe and sent him back to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>MIYAZAKI→ Miyazaki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>このため折角の和平工作は立ち消えとなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the anticipated peace overture faded away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the anticipated peace initiative faded away.</e>
<cmt>&quot;overture&quot;→&quot;initiative&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the anticipated peace initiative faded away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>この件に関して杉山は関係者を一切処分しなかったばかりか、事情聴取すら行わず、結果的に事後了解を与えた形になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding this matter, not only did SUGIYAMA not deal with the people associated with this incident, he did not even conduct any investigations, and in the end, he gave an impression of having authorized the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SUGIYAMA, who failed to deal with the people involved or even conduct any investigations, gave the impression of having authorized the incident.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Regarding this matter, not only did&quot;&quot;not deal&quot;→&quot;, who failed to deal&quot;&quot; he did not&quot;→&quot;or&quot;&quot;associated with this incident&quot;→&quot;involved&quot;Deleted &quot;and in the end, he&quot;&quot;an&quot;→&quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugiyama, who failed to deal with the people involved or even conduct any investigations, gave the impression of having authorized the incident.</e>
<cmt>SUGIYAMA→Sugiyama</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>杉山本人も当初は明解な釈明が能わない有様で、以後近衛は杉山に強い不信感を抱くようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, SUGIYAMA himself was not able to give a clear account, and KONOE began to hold a strong sense of distrust against SUGIYAMA from this point onward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To begin with, SUGIYAMA himself was not able to give a clear account and, from this point onward, KONOE began to distrust SUGIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;At the beginning&quot;→&quot;To begin with&quot;Moved &quot;from this point onward&quot;&quot;to hold a strong sense of distrust against&quot;→&quot;distrust&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To begin with, Sugiyama himself was not able to give a clear account and, from this point onward, Konoe began to distrust Sugiyama.</e>
<cmt>SUGIYAMA→Sugiyamaスペース削除KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>8月8日には日支間の防共協定を目的とする要綱を取り決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By August 8, an outline aiming at an agreement to prevent communism was arranged between Japan and China.</e>
<cmt>日支間の防共協定→agreement of keep communism off between Japan and China→agreement to prevent communist between Japan and China[keep off を prevent に変更]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 8, Japan and China agreed on an outline of an Anti-Comintern Pact.</e>
<cmt>&quot;By&quot;→&quot;On&quot;&quot;aiming at an agreement to prevent communism&quot;→&quot;of an Anti-Comintern Pact&quot;Deleted &quot;between&quot;Moved &quot;Japan and China&quot;&quot;was arranged&quot;→&quot;agreed on&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 8, Japan and China agreed on an outline of an Anti-Comintern Pact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>8月9日に上海市で、蒋介石軍の挑発による上海事変が勃発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 9, Shanghai Jihen (Shanghai Incident) provoked by CHIANG Kai-Shek broke out in Shanghai City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 9, the Battle of Shanghai started, provoked by CHIANG Kai-Shek.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Shanghai Jihen&quot; and brackets&quot;Shanghai Incident&quot;→&quot;the Battle of Shanghai&quot; - The Shanghai Incident was in 1932 &quot;broke out in Shanghai City&quot;→&quot;started&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 9, the Battle of Shanghai started, provoked by CHIANG Kai-Shek.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>それに応じて、8月13日に、二個師団追加派遣を閣議決定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, on August 13, dispatching of additional two divisions was approved in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, on August 13, the cabinet approved the dispatch of an additional two divisions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was approved in the cabinet meeting&quot;→&quot;the cabinet approved&quot; and moved&quot;dispatching&quot;→&quot;dispatch&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, on August 13, the cabinet approved the dispatch of an additional two divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>8月15日には、海軍による南京市に対する渡洋爆撃を実行し、同時に、「今や断乎たる措置をとる」の声明を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 15, bombing over the sea against Nanjing City by the Navy took place, and at the same time, he announced his proclamation of &quot;now is the time to take decisive measures.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, the Navy launched bombing raids on Nanjing, and at the same time, KONOE announced &quot;now is the time to take decisive measures.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;bombing over the sea against Nanjing City by the Navy took place&quot;→&quot;the Navy launched bombing raids on Nanjing&quot;&quot;he&quot;→&quot;KONOE&quot;Deleted &quot;his proclamation of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 15, the Navy launched bombing raids on Nanjing, and at the same time, Konoe announced &apos;now is the time to take decisive measures.&apos;</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>8月17日には、不拡大方針を放棄すると閣議決定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 17, abandonment of localization policy was approved in the cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 17, the cabinet approved the abandonment of the nonaggression policy.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was approved in the cabinet meeting&quot;→&quot;the cabinet approved&quot; and movedAdded &quot;the&quot;&quot;localization&quot;→&quot;nonaggression&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 17, the cabinet approved the abandonment of the nonaggression policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="50">
<j>9月2日には「北支事変」という公式呼称を「支那事変」と変更を閣議決定し、戦域を拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By September 2nd, changing of the official term &quot;Hokushi-jihen (Sino-Japanese War)&quot; to &quot;Shina-jihen (China Incident)&quot; was approved in the cabinet meeting, and the theater of war was expanded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 2nd, the cabinet approved changing the official term from &quot;Hokushi-jihen (Sino-Japanese War)&quot; to &quot;Shina-jihen (China Incident)&quot;, and the theater of operations was expanded.</e>
<cmt>&quot;By&quot;→&quot;On&quot;&quot;was approved in the cabinet meeting&quot;→&quot;the cabinet approved&quot; and movedDeleted &quot;of&quot;&quot;war&quot;→&quot;operations&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 2, the cabinet approved changing the official term from &apos;Hokushi-jihen (Sino-Japanese War)&apos; to &apos;Shina-jihen (China Incident)&apos;, and the theater of operations was expanded.</e>
<cmt>nd削除原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>9月10日には、臨時軍事費特別会計法が公布され、「支那事変」が日清戦争、日露戦争、第一次世界大戦と同列の戦争と決定され、不拡大派の石原莞爾参謀本部作戦部長が失脚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 10, a special accounting law of extraordinary military spending was officially announced, and the &quot;Shina-jihen (China Incident)&quot; was approved as a war that was similar to Sino-Japanese War, Russo-Japanese War and the First World War, and Kanji ISHIWARA, Deputy Chief of Staff for Military Operations, Staff Headquarters, of the localization policy group was ousted.</e>
<cmt>臨時軍事費特別会計法→Special account of extraordinary military spending→special accounting law of extraordinary military spending[account をaccounting law に変更]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 10, a special accounting law of extraordinary military spending was officially announced, the &quot;Shina-jihen (China Incident)&quot; was declared a full-scale war, similar to the Sino-Japanese War, the Russo-Japanese War and the First World War, and Kanji ISHIWARA, Head of Operations at Staff Headquarters and a member of the nonaggression faction was ousted.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;and&quot;&quot;approved as&quot;→&quot;declared&quot;Added &quot;full scale&quot;&quot;that was&quot;→commaAdded &quot;the&quot;&quot; Deputy Chief of Staff for Military Operations, Staff Headquarters&quot;→&quot;Head of Operations at Staff Headquarters&quot;&quot;of the localization policy group&quot;→&quot;and a member of the nonaggression faction&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 10, a special accounting law of extraordinary military spending was officially announced, the &apos;Shina-jihen (China Incident)&apos; was declared a full-scale war, similar to the Sino-Japanese War, the Russo-Japanese War and the First World War, and Kanji ISHIWARA, Head of Operations at Staff Headquarters and a member of the nonaggression faction was ousted.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>12月13日に南京市攻略。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Invasion of Nanjing City tool place on December 13.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 13, Nanjing was invaded.</e>
<cmt>Beworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 13, Nanjing was invaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="53">
<j>翌1938年（昭和13年）1月11日には、御前会議で支那事変処理根本方針が決定され、ドイツの仲介による講和（トラウトマン工作）を求める方針だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 11 of the following year, 1938, basic policy of treatment of Shina-jihen was approved in a conference in the presence of the Emperor, and the plan was to seek peace mediated by Germany (Trautmann operation).</e>
<cmt>トラウトマン工作→Trautmann maneuvering→Trautmann operation[maneuvering を operation に変更]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 11 of the following year, 1938, the Imperial Conference approved a basic policy for dealing with the Sino-Japanese War, which involved seeking peace mediated by Germany (Trautmann Mediation).</e>
<cmt>&quot;basic policy of treatment of Shina-jihen&quot;→&quot;a basic policy for dealing with the Sino-Japanese War&quot; &quot;was approved in a conference in the presence of the Emperor,&quot;→&quot;the Imperial Conference approved&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 11 of the following year, 1938, the Imperial Conference approved a basic policy for dealing with the Sino-Japanese War, which involved seeking peace mediated by Germany (Trautmann Mediation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>しかし、1月14日に和平交渉の打切りを閣議決定し、1月16日に「爾後國民政府ヲ對手トセズ」の声明を国内外に発表し、講和の機会を閉ざした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, termination of peace negotiation was approved in the cabinet meeting on January 14, and on January 16, a proclamation of &quot;ignore after-the-fact Nationalist Government&quot; was announced both inside and outside the nation, which ended any opportunities for making peace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the termination of peace negotiations was approved in the cabinet meeting on January 14, and on January 16, a proclamation to &apos;ignore after-the-fact Nationalist Government&apos; was announced both inside and outside the nation, ending any opportunities for peace.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Made &quot;negotiation&quot; plural&quot;of&quot;→&quot;to&quot;&quot;after-the-fact&quot;→&quot;ignore any future&quot;&quot;which ended&quot;→&quot;ending&quot;Deleted &quot;making&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the termination of peace negotiations was approved in the cabinet meeting on January 14, and on January 16, a proclamation to &apos;ignore after-the-fact Nationalist Government&apos; was announced both inside and outside the nation, ending any opportunities for peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>更に、汪兆銘政権を樹立し、石原莞爾らの独自和平工作を完全に阻止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, O Cho Mei (Wang Zhaoming) administration was founded, which thwarted the personal peace operation of Kanji ISHIWARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Wang Zhaoming founded his pro-Japanese administration, thwarting the personal peace operation of Kanji ISHIWARA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;O Cho Mei&quot; and brackets&quot;administration was founded&quot;→&quot;founded his pro-Japanese administration&quot; - added &quot;pro-Japanese&quot; for clarity&quot;which thwarted&quot;→&quot;thwarting&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Wang Zhaoming founded his pro-Japanese administration, thwarting the personal peace operation of Kanji ISHIWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>5月5日には、支那事変のためとして、国家総動員法や電力国家管理法を成立させ、経済の戦時体制を導入し、日本の国家社会主義化が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 5, he enacted National General Mobilization Act and the Act of Government Control of Power and introduced the wartime structure of economics, and the national socialization of Japan began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 5, with the enactment of the National Mobilization Act and the Government Control of Power Act and the introduction of wartime economics, Japan entered a period of national socialisation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he enacted&quot;→&quot;with the enactment of the&quot;Deleted &quot;General&quot;Moved &quot;Act&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;&quot;introduced the&quot;→&quot;introduction of&quot;Deleted &quot;structure of&quot;&quot;and the national socialization of Japan began&quot;→&quot;Japan entered a period of national socialisation&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 5, with the enactment of the National Mobilization Act and the Government Control of Power Act and the introduction of wartime economics, Japan entered a period of national socialization.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>なお、国家総動員法や電力国家管理法は、ソビエト連邦の第一次五ヶ年計画の模倣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National General Mobilization Act and Act of Government Control of Power were both emulations of the First Five-Year Plan in the Soviet Union.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The National Mobilization Act and the Government Control of Power Act were both imitations of the Soviet Union&apos;s First Five-Year Plan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;Deleted &quot;General&quot;Moved &quot;Act&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;emulations&quot;→&quot;imitations&quot;&quot;in the Soviet Union&quot;→&quot;Soviet Union&apos;s&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The National Mobilization Act and the Government Control of Power Act were both imitations of the Soviet Union&apos;s First Five-Year Plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>3年後の1941年（昭和16年）に制定された国民学校令は、ナチス率いる当時のドイツのフォルクスシューレを模倣した教育制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kokumin gakko rei (Act of elementary schools) that was enacted 3 years later, in 1941, was an educational system that mimicked the Folks Schule (Grand School) in Nazi Germany at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Elementary Schools Edict that was enacted 3 years later in 1941, introduced an educational system that mimicked Nazi Germany&apos;s Folks Schule (Grand School).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kokumin gakko rei (Act of elementary schools)&quot;→&quot;Elementary Schools Edict&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;introduced&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;in Nazi Germany at the time&quot;→&quot;Nazi Germany&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Elementary Schools Edict that was enacted 3 years later in 1941, introduced an educational system that mimicked Nazi Germany&apos;s Folks Schule (Grand School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="59">
<j>この頃に近衛は、閑院宮陸軍参謀総長らに根回しをすることで杉山の更迭を成功させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, KONOE successfully ousted SUGIYAMA by laying the groundwork among Kan&apos;in-no-miya, armed forces chief of army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, KONOE successfully ousted SUGIYAMA after laying the groundwork with Army Staff Office General Secretary KAN&apos;IN-NO-MIYA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;by&quot;→&quot;after&quot;&quot;armed forces chief of army&quot;→&quot;Army Staff Office General Secretary&quot;Capitalized &quot;Kan&apos;in-no-miya&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, Konoe successfully ousted Sugiyama after laying the groundwork with Army Staff Office General Secretary Kaninnomiya.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeSUGIYAMA→SugiyamaKAN&apos;IN-NO-MIYA→Kaninnomiya</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>後任には小畑敏四郎を考えたが、摩擦が生じることを懸念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshishiro OBATA was considered as the successor, but there was a concern about friction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshishiro OBATA was considered as the successor, but there was concern he would cause friction.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;a&quot;&quot;about&quot;→&quot;he would cause&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshishiro OBATA was considered as the successor, but there was concern he would cause friction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>そこで不拡大派の支持があった板垣征四郎を迎えることを決意し、山東省の最前線にいた板垣への使者として民間人の古野伊之助を派遣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he decided to pick Seishiro ITAGAKI, who had the support of localization policy group, and he sent a civilian, Inosuke FURUNO, as a messenger to ITAGAKI, who was at the frontline in Shandong Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he decided to pick Seishiro ITAGAKI, who had the support of the nonaggression faction, and dispatched a civilian, Inosuke FURUNO, as a messenger to ITAGAKI, who was at the frontline in Shandong Province.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;he sen&quot;Added &quot;was dispatched&quot;&quot;localization policy group&quot;→&quot;the nonaggression faction&quot;&quot;sent&quot;→&quot;dispatched&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he decided to pick Seishiro ITAGAKI, who had the support of the nonaggression faction, and dispatched a civilian, Inosuke FURUNO, as a messenger to Itagaki, who was at the frontline in Shandong Province.</e>
<cmt>ITAGAKI→Itagaki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>この時期の内閣改造では、陸軍の非主流派や不拡大派の石原莞爾らが、以前閣僚にと考えていた人たちが主に入閣し、これにより軍部を抑える考えがあったものとされるが、板垣は結局「傀儡」となり失敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this cabinet shuffle during this period, the main people who became the cabinet members were the ones the fringe group of the Army and the localization policy group, including Kanji ISHIWARA, had in mind as cabinet members, and it can be considered that there was an intention to suppress the military by this, but in the end, ITAGAKI failed as a &quot;Kairai (as stupid as a post).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since during this cabinet reshuffle, most of those who became cabinet members were ones that the Army fringe and the nonaggression faction, including Kanji ISHIWARA, had in mind, it can be considered that there was an intention to suppress the military, but in the end, ITAGAKI was unsuccessful and regarded as a &quot;puppet.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Since&quot;&quot;In this cabinet shuffle during this period&quot;→&quot;during this cabinet reshuffle&quot;&quot; the main people&quot;→&quot;most of those&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;that&quot;&quot;fringe group of the Army&quot;→&quot;Army fringe&quot;&quot;localization policy group&quot;→&quot;nonaggression faction&quot;Deleted &quot;as cabinet members&quot;, &quot;and&quot;, &quot;by this&quot;&quot;failed as a &quot;Kairai (as stupid as a post).&quot;&quot;→&quot;was unsuccessful and regarded as a &quot;puppet&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since during this cabinet reshuffle, most of those who became cabinet members were ones that the Army fringe and the nonaggression faction, including Kanji ISHIWARA, had in mind, it can be considered that there was an intention to suppress the military, but in the end, Itagaki was unsuccessful and regarded as a &apos;puppet.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にITAGAKI→Itagaki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>この際に近衛は、宇垣一成を外相に迎えたが、宇垣の和平工作を十分に助けようとしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, KONOE welcomed Kazushige UGAKI as Foreign Minister, but he did not adequately help UGAKI&apos;s peace operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE also asked Kazushige UGAKI to be Foreign Minister, but he failed to adequately support UGAKI&apos;s peace overtures.</e>
<cmt>&quot;On this occasion&quot;→&quot;also&quot; and moved&quot;welcomed&quot;→&quot;asked&quot;&quot;as&quot;→&quot;to&quot;&quot; did not adequately help&quot;→&quot;failed to adequately support&quot;&quot;operation&quot;→&quot;overtures&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe also asked Kazushige UGAKI to be Foreign Minister, but he failed to adequately support Ugaki&apos;s peace overtures.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeUGAKI→Ugaki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>宇垣はこれに不満を覚え、また近衛が興亜院を設置しようとしたこともあり、9月に辞任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">UGAKI was frustrated about this, and also because KONOE made an attempt to establish Koain government organization, he resigned in September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">UGAKI resigned in September, frustrated about this and also about KONOE&apos;s attempt to establish the Koain (the East Asia Development Board).</e>
<cmt>&quot;because KONOE made an attempt&quot;→&quot;about KONOE&apos;s attempt&quot;Added &quot;(the East Asia Development Board)&quot;Deleted &quot;government organization&quot;Moved &quot;resigned in September&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ugaki resigned in September, frustrated about this and also about Konoe&apos;s attempt to establish the Koain (the East Asia Development Board).</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeUGAKI→Ugaki</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="65">
<j>8月には、麻生久を書記長とする社会大衆党を中心として、大日本党の結成を目指したが、時期尚早とみて中止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, he aimed to form Dainihon Party that centered on Shakai-taishu Party with Hisashi ASO as the chief clerk, but he abandoned the plan judging that it was premature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he tried to form the Dainihon Party centered on the Shakai-taishu Party with Hisashi ASO as the chief clerk, but abandoned the plan, judging that it was premature.</e>
<cmt>&quot;aimed&quot;→&quot;tried&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;that&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, he tried to form the Dainihon Party centered on the Shakai-taishu Party with Hisashi ASO as the chief clerk, but abandoned the plan, judging that it was premature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>これは、大政翼賛会へと至る独裁政党への第一歩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the very first step towards Taisei-Yokusankai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association) dictatorship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first step towards the Taisei-Yokusankai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association) totalitarian party.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;very&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;dictatorship&quot;→&quot;totalitarian party&quot; - although the Japanese has &quot;独裁&quot;, &quot;dictatorship party doesn&apos;t sound natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first step towards the Taisei-Yokusankai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association) totalitarian party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>11月3日に「東亜新秩序」声明を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 3rd, he announced the proclamation of &quot;new order in East Asia.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 3rd, he issued his &quot;new order in East Asia&quot; statement.</e>
<cmt>&quot;announced the proclamation of &quot;new order in East Asia.&quot;&quot;→&quot;issued his &quot;new order in East Asia&quot; statement.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 3rd, he issued his &apos;new order in East Asia&apos; statement.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>1939年（昭和14年）1月5日に内閣総辞職する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5, 1939, the cabinet members resigned en masse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1939, the cabinet members resigned en masse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 5, 1939, the cabinet members resigned en masse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>新体制の模索</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Search of the New Order</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Search of the New Order</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Search of the New Order</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>近衛の後を承けたのは前枢密院議長の平沼騏一郎だったが、平沼内閣には近衛内閣から法相（兼逓相）、文相、内相、外相、商工相（兼拓務相）、海相、陸相の七閣僚が留任したうえ、枢密院に転じた近衛自身も班列としてこれに名を連ねたため、あたかも首をすげ替えただけの様相を呈すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former chairman of Privy Council, Kiichiro HIRANUMA, was the one who succeeded KONOE, but in addition to the seven cabinet officials from Konoe cabinet, Minister of Law (and Minister of Communications and Transportation), Internal Minister, Foreign Minister, Minister of Commerce (and Minister of Colony), Minister of the Navy and Minister of Army continued on to Hiranuma Cabinet, KONOE who joined the Privy Council also added his name as Hanretsu (a minister without official announcement), it took on the appearance of replacing just the head.</e>
<cmt>平沼騏一郎→Ki&apos;ichiro HIRANUMA→Kiichiro HIRANUMA[Ki&apos;ichiro の &quot;&apos;&quot; を削除]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE was succeeded by former Chairman of the Privy Council, Kiichiro HIRANUMA, but with the Minister of Law (and Minister of Communications and Transportation), the Internal Minister, the Foreign Minister, the Minister of Commerce (and Minister of the Colonies), the Minister of the Navy and the Minister of the Army remaining in office, and KONOE himself joining the Privy Council and becoming a minister without portfolio), HIRANUMA&apos;s cabinet appeared the same as KONOE&apos;s with just a different head.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;was the one who succeeded KONOE&quot;→&quot;KONOE was succeeded by&quot; and moved&quot;in addition to the&quot;→&quot;with&quot; Deleted &quot;cabinet officials from Konoe cabinet,&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; before Ministers except those in brackets&quot;Colony&quot;→&quot;the Colonies&quot; &quot;continued on to Hiranuma Cabinet&quot;→&quot;remaining in office&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;, &quot;himself&quot;&quot;who joined&quot;→&quot;joining&quot;&quot;also added his name as Hanretsu (a minister without official announcement)&quot;→&quot;and becoming a minister without portfolio&quot;&quot;it took on the appearance of replacing just the head&quot;→&quot; HIRANUMA&apos;s cabinet appeared the same as KONOE&apos;s with just a different head&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe was succeeded by former Chairman of the Privy Council, Kiichiro HIRANUMA, but with the Minister of Law (and Minister of Communications and Transportation), the Internal Minister, the Foreign Minister, the Minister of Commerce (and Minister of the Colonies), the Minister of the Navy and the Minister of the Army remaining in office, and Konoe himself joining the Privy Council and becoming a minister without portfolio), Hiranuma&apos;s cabinet appeared the same as Konoe&apos;s with just a different head.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeHIRANUMA→Hiranuma</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>8月23日に独ソ不可侵条約が締結されると、防共を目的としたドイツとの同盟を模索していた平沼は衝撃を受け、「欧州の天地は複雑怪奇」という迷言を残して内閣総辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When German-Soviet Nonaggression Pact was concluded on August 23, HIRANUMA, who had been seeking an alliance with Germany with the goal of preventing communism, was shocked, and he resigned from the Prime Minister&apos;s position leaving the following words of nonsense, &quot;world of Europe is messed up beyond all recognition.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文の迷言は明言または明言の間違いだと思いますが、原文通りに訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the German-Soviet Nonaggression Pact was concluded on August 23, HIRANUMA, who had been seeking an alliance with Germany with the goal of preventing communism, was shocked and resigned from the Prime Minister&apos;s position, leaving the following words of nonsense, &quot;the whole of Europe is messed up beyond all recognition.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted comma and &quot;he&quot;Added comma&quot;world&quot;→&quot;the whole&quot;- I agree with the translator that &quot;迷言&quot; is probably a typo, but left it as it is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the German-Soviet Nonaggression Pact was concluded on August 23, Hiranuma, who had been seeking an alliance with Germany with the goal of preventing communism, was shocked and resigned from the Prime Minister&apos;s position, leaving the following words of nonsense, &apos;the whole of Europe is messed up beyond all recognition.&apos;</e>
<cmt>HIRANUMA→Hiranuma原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>その一週間後にはドイツがポーランドに侵攻、これを受けてイギリスやフランスがドイツに宣戦布告したことで第二次世界大戦が始る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One week later, Germany invaded Poland, and in response England and France declared war against Germany, and thus World War II started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One week later, World War II started when Germany invaded Poland, and in response England and France declared war against Germany.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;World War II&quot;Deleted &quot;, and thus&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One week later, World War II started when Germany invaded Poland, and in response England and France declared war against Germany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="72">
<j>平沼の後は陸軍出身の阿部信行と海軍出身の米内光政がそれぞれ短期間政権を担当したが、この間の近衛は新党構想の肉付けに専念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After HIRANUMA, Nobuyuki ABE from the Army and Mitsumasa YONAI from the Navy each held office for a short time, and KONOE, during this period, focused on adding details to the framework of his new political party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After HIRANUMA, Nobuyuki ABE from the Army and Mitsumasa YONAI from the Navy each held office for a short time, and KONOE, during this period, focused on adding details to the framework of his new political party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hiranuma, Nobuyuki ABE from the Army and Mitsumasa YONAI from the Navy each held office for a short time, and Konoe, during this period, focused on adding details to the framework of his new political party.</e>
<cmt>HIRANUMA→HiranumaKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>1940年（昭和15年）5月26日には、木戸幸一や有馬頼寧と共に、「新党樹立に関する覚書」を作成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 26, 1940, he wrote &quot;Memorandum on Forming a New Political Party&quot; with Koichi KIDO and Yoriyasu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 26, 1940, he wrote the &quot;Memorandum on Forming a New Political Party&quot; with Koichi KIDO and Yoriyasu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 26, 1940, he wrote the &apos;Memorandum on Forming a New Political Party&apos; with Koichi KIDO and Yoriyasu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>再度、ソビエト連邦共産党や国家社会主義ドイツ労働者党をモデルにした独裁政党の結成を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Again, he aimed to set up government by dictatorship, modeling after the Communist Party of the Soviet Union and national socialist German Workers Party (the Nazi Party).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Again, he aimed to set up a totalitarian party, modeled on the Communist Party of the Soviet Union and the National Socialist German Workers Party (the Nazi Party).</e>
<cmt>&quot;government by dictatorship&quot;→&quot;totalitarian party&quot;&quot;modeling after&quot;→&quot;modeled on&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;n&apos; and &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Again, he aimed to set up a totalitarian party, modeled on the Communist Party of the Soviet Union and the National Socialist German Workers Party (the Nazi Party).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>6月24日に「新体制声明」を発表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 24, he announced the &quot;Proclamation of the New Order.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 24, he issued the &quot;Proclamation of the New Order.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;announced&quot;→&quot;issued&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 24, he issued the &apos;Proclamation of the New Order.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>欧州でドイツが破竹の進撃を続けるなか、国内でも「バスに乗り遅れるな」という機運が高まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Germans continued to invade in full career in Europe, the momentum was also rising within Japan so as &quot;not to miss the bus.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Germany&apos;s advance continued unchecked in Europe, momentum was also rising within Japan &quot;not to miss the bus.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Germans continued to invade in full career&quot;→&quot;Germany&apos;s advance continued unchecked&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;, &quot;so as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Germany&apos;s advance continued unchecked in Europe, momentum was also rising within Japan &apos;not to miss the bus.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これを憂慮した昭和天皇が「海軍の良識派」として知られる米内を特に推して組閣させたという経緯があったのだが、陸軍がそれを好感する道理がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Showa, who became concerned with this, strongly supported YONAI, who was known as &quot;a man of good senses in the Navy&quot;, to form a cabinet, but there was no reason the Amy viewed this favorably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Showa, concerned about these events, strongly backed YONAI, who was known as &quot;a Navy man of good sense&quot;, to form a cabinet, but the Army had no reason to support this.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;who became&quot;&quot;with this&quot;→&quot;about these events&quot;&quot;supported&quot;→&quot;backed&quot;&quot;in the Navy&quot;→&quot;Navy&quot; and movedMade &quot;senses&quot; singular&quot; there was no reason the Amy viewed this favorably&quot;→&quot;the Army had no reason to support this&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Showa, concerned about these events, strongly backed Yonai, who was known as &apos;a Navy man of good sense,&apos; to form a cabinet, but the Army had no reason to support this.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にYONAI→Yonai</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>半年も経たない頃から、陸軍は政府に日独伊三国同盟の締結を執拗に要求。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within less than half a year, the Army demanded the government to form an alliance of Japan, Germany and Italy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Less than six months later, the Army demanded that the government form an alliance with Germany and Italy.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Within less than half a year&quot;→&quot;Less than six months later&quot;Added &quot;that&quot;deleted &quot;of&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;with&quot;Deleted &quot;Japan,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Less than six months later, the Army demanded that the government form an alliance with Germany and Italy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>米内がこれを拒否すると、陸軍は陸軍大臣の畑俊六を辞任させて後任を出さず、内閣は総辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When YONAI refused, the Army made Minister of Army, Shunroku HATA, resign and did not provide a successor, and the cabinet members resigned en masse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When YONAI refused, the Army made the Minister of the Army, Shunroku HATA, resign without providing a successor, and the cabinet members resigned en masse.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;and did not provide&quot;→&quot;without providing&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yonai refused, the Army made the Minister of the Army, Shunroku HATA, resign without providing a successor, and the cabinet members resigned en masse.</e>
<cmt>YONAI→Yonai</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>かわって大命が降下したのは、近衛だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial command assigned KONOE instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, KONOE was assigned by imperial command.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, Konoe was assigned by imperial command.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>この際、「最後の元老」であった西園寺は近衛を首班として推薦することを断っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding this matter, &quot;the last Genro&quot; SAIONJI refused to recommend KONOE as the head of the cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;the last Genro&quot; SAIONJI refused to recommend KONOE as the head of the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regarding this matter&quot;→&quot;However&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &apos;the last Genro&apos; Saionji refused to recommend Konoe as the head of the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>SAIONJI→Saionji原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="82">
<j>新党構想などの準備を着々と整え、満を持しての再登板に望むことになった近衛は、閣僚名簿奉呈直前の7月19日、荻窪の私邸･荻外荘でいわゆる「荻窪会談」を行い、入閣することになっていた松岡洋右（外相）、吉田善吾（海相）、東条英機（陸相）と「東亜新秩序」の建設邁進で合意している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having worked steadily on the preparations for the framework of the new political party, KONOE who was about to face a long-awaited comeback, had the &quot;Ogikubo Meeting&quot; at Tekigaiso, his private residence in Ogikubo, on July 19, just before presenting the list of the cabinet ministers, and he agreed with Yosuke MATSUOKA (Foreign Minister), who was going to be a cabinet member, Zengo YOSHIDA (Minister of the Navy) and Hideki TOJO (Minister of the Army) to work toward founding of the &quot;new order in East Asia.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having worked steadily on the preparations for the framework of the new political party, KONOE, who was about to face a long-awaited comeback, held the &quot;Ogikubo Meeting&quot; at Tekigaiso, his private residence in Ogikubo, on July 19, just before presenting the list of cabinet ministers, and he agreed with new cabinet members Yosuke MATSUOKA (Foreign Minister), Zengo YOSHIDA (Minister of the Navy) and Hideki TOJO (Minister of the Army) to work toward the founding of a &quot;new order in East Asia.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;had&quot;→&quot;held&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;who was going to be a cabinet member&quot;→&quot;new cabinet members&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having worked steadily on the preparations for the framework of the new political party, Konoe, who was about to face a long-awaited comeback, held the &apos;Ogikubo Meeting&apos; at Tekigaiso, his private residence in Ogikubo, on July 19, just before presenting the list of cabinet ministers, and he agreed with new cabinet members Yosuke MATSUOKA (Foreign Minister), Zengo YOSHIDA (Minister of the Navy) and Hideki TOJO (Minister of the Army) to work toward the founding of a &apos;new order in East Asia.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>第二次内閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Second Cabinet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Second Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Second Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>1940年7月22日に、第2次近衛内閣を組織した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 22, 1940, the Second Konoe cabinet was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 22, 1940, the second Konoe cabinet was formed.</e>
<cmt>Made &apos;s&apos; lower case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 22, 1940, the second Konoe cabinet was formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>7月26日に「基本国策要綱」を閣議決定し、「皇道の大精神に則りまづ日満支をその一環とする大東亜共栄圏の確立をはかる」（松岡外相の談話）構想を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 26, &quot;basic principle of national policy&quot; was approved in the cabinet meeting, and &quot;based on the spirit of Kodo, to establish the Great East Asia Co-prosperity Sphere which Japan, Manchuria and China form as a part of is planned&quot; (discourse by Matsuoka Foreign Minister) was announced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 26, the &quot;basic outline of national policy&quot; was approved by the cabinet, and the &quot;plan to establish, based on the spirit of the Imperial Way, the Greater East Asia Co-prosperity Sphere, of which Japan, Manchuria and China form one part&quot; (from a discourse by Matsuoka Foreign Minister) was announced.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;principle&quot;→&quot;outline&quot;&quot;in the cabinet meeting&quot;→&quot;by the cabinet&quot;Reworded 2nd part of sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 26, the &apos;basic outline of national policy&apos; was approved by the cabinet, and the &apos;plan to establish, based on the spirit of the Imperial Way, the Greater East Asia Co-prosperity Sphere, of which Japan, Manchuria and China form one part&apos; (from a discourse by Matsuoka Foreign Minister) was announced.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>新体制運動を展開し、全政党を自主的に解散させ、8月15日の民政党の解散をもって、日本に政党が存在しなくなり、議会制民主主義は死を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new order movement developed, all parties were voluntarily dissolved, and with the August 15th dissolution of Minsei Party (civil administration party) no political party existed in Japan, and parliamentary democracy came to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the new order movement developed, all political parties were made to disband, and with the August 15th dissolution of the Constitutional Democratic Party (Minseito), the last political party in Japan disappeared and parliamentary democracy came to an end.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;As&quot;, &quot;political&quot;&quot;voluntarily dissolved&quot;→&quot;made to disband&quot;&quot;(civil administration party)&quot;→&quot;Constitutional Democratic Party&quot; and moved&quot;Minsei Party&quot;→&quot;(Minseito)&quot;&quot;no political party existed in Japan,&quot;→&quot;, the last political party in Japan disappeared&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the new order movement developed, all political parties were made to disband, and with the August 15th dissolution of the Constitutional Democratic Party (Minseito), the last political party in Japan disappeared and parliamentary democracy came to an end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>しかし、一党独裁は日本の国体に相容れないとする「幕府批判論」もあって、会は政治運動の中核体という曖昧な地位に留まり、独裁政党の結成には至らず、10月12日に大政翼賛会の発足式で「綱領も宣言も不要」と新体制運動を投げ出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there was &quot;theory of criticism against Bakufu (feudal government)&quot; which said that one-party dictatorship was incompatible with Japanese national polity, and his group remained in an unspecific position as a nucleus of political activities and did not lead to the establishment of dictatorship, and on October 12, at the inaugural ceremony of Taisei-Yokusankai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association) he abandoned the new order movement saying &quot;neither the program or proclamation is necessary.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time however, due to the &quot;criticism of the Bakufu (feudal government)&quot;, which said that one-party rule was incompatible with Japanese politics, and the Association&apos;s position at the core political activities remaining unclear, totalitarianism failed to become established and on October 12, at the inauguration ceremony of Taisei-Yokusankai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association), he abandoned the new order movement saying &quot;neither the program or proclamation is necessary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;At the same time, &quot;&quot;there was&quot;→&quot;due to&quot;Deleted &quot;theory of&quot;&quot;against&quot;→&quot;of the&quot;Added comma&quot;dictatorship&quot;→&quot;rule&quot;&quot;national polity&quot;→&quot;politics&quot;&quot;his group&quot;→&quot;the Association&quot;&quot;unspecific&quot;→&quot;unclear&quot;Reworded middle of sentence&quot;inaugural&quot;→&quot;inaugaration&quot;Added cooma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time however, due to the &apos;criticism of the Bakufu (feudal government),&apos; which said that one-party rule was incompatible with Japanese politics, and the Association&apos;s position at the core political activities remaining unclear, totalitarianism failed to become established and on October 12, at the inauguration ceremony of Taisei-Yokusankai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association), he abandoned the new order movement saying &apos;neither the program or proclamation is necessary.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>また、新体制運動の核の一つであった経済新体制確立要綱が財界から反発を受け、小林一三商工相は経済新体制要綱の推進者である岸信介次官と対立、小林は岸を「アカ」と批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, new economic structure establishment principle, which was one of the nuclei of the new order movement, faced opposition from the financial world; Minister of Commerce and Industry, Ichizo KOBAYASHI, was in conflict with assistance administrator, Nobusuke KISHI, who was a supporter of new economic structure principle, and KOBAYASHI criticized KISHI as &quot;red.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the new economic policy outline, which was one of the key points of the new order movement, faced opposition from the financial world, with Ichizo KOBAYASHI, the Minister of Commerce and Industry, clashing with Vice-Minister, Nobusuke KISHI, the driving force behind the outline, whom KOBAYASHI criticized as &quot;a red.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;structure establishment principle&quot;→&quot;policy outline&quot;&quot;nuclei&quot;→&quot;key points&quot;Added &quot;with&quot;Moved &quot;Ichizo KOBAYASHI,&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;was in conflict with assistance administrator&quot;→&quot;clashing with Vice-Minister&quot;&quot;who was a supporter of new economic structure principle&quot;→&quot;the driving force behind the plan&quot;&quot;and KOBAYASHI criticized KISHI&quot;→&quot;whom KOBAYASHI criticized&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the new economic policy outline, which was one of the key points of the new order movement, faced opposition from the financial world, with Ichizo KOBAYASHI, the Minister of Commerce and Industry, clashing with Vice-Minister, Nobusuke KISHI, the driving force behind the outline, whom Kobayashi criticized as &apos;a red.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKOBAYASHI→Kobayashi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>近衛は革新官僚を「国体の衣を着けたる共産主義者」として敵視し、12月の平沼騏一郎の入閣で、経済新体制確立要綱を骨抜きにさせて決着を図り、平沼らは更に経済新体制確立要綱の原案作成者たちを共産主義者として逮捕させ、岸信介も辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE viewed the reformational government bureaucrat with hostility as &quot;communist put on national policy,&quot; and with entering of Kiichiro HIRANUMA in the cabinet in December he planned to settle the matter by watering down the new economic structure establishment principle, and furthermore, HIRANUMA arrested those who drafted the new economic structure establishment principle as communists, and Nobusuke KISHI also resigned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE was hostile to the reform bureaucrats, seeing them as &quot;communists in nationalist clothing,&quot; so when Kiichiro HIRANUMA joined the cabinet in December, he planned to settle the matter by watering down the new economic policy plan; in addtion, HIRANUMA had the authors of the plan arrested as communists, and Nobusuke KISHI resigned.</e>
<cmt>&quot; viewed the reformational government bureaucrat with hostility&quot;→&quot;was hostile to the reform bureaucrats, seeing them&quot;&quot;communist put on national policy&quot;→&quot;communists in nationalist clothing&quot;&quot;and with entering of Kiichiro HIRANUMA in&quot;→&quot;so when Kiichiro HIRANUMA joined&quot;&quot;structure establishment principle&quot;→&quot;policy plan&quot;&quot;, and furthermore&quot;→&quot;; in addtion&quot;&quot;arrested those who drafted the new economic structure establishment principle&quot;→&quot;had the authors of the plan arrested&quot;Deleted &quot;also&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe was hostile to the reform bureaucrats, seeing them as &apos;communists in nationalist clothing,&apos; so when Kiichiro HIRANUMA joined the cabinet in December, he planned to settle the matter by watering down the new economic policy plan; in addition, Hiranuma had the authors of the plan arrested as communists, and Nobusuke KISHI resigned.</e>
<cmt>スペルKONOE→Konoe原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にHIRANUMA→Hiranuma</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>この間、新体制推進派は閣僚を辞職し、平沼は大政翼賛会を公事結社と規定し、大政翼賛会の新体制推進派を辞職させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, the supporters of the new order resigned as cabinet members, and HIRANUMA prescribed Taisei-Yokusankai (Imperial Rule Assistance Association) as a Kojikessha (association seeking public interest), and he made the supporters of the new order within Taisei-Yokusankai resign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, the supporters of the new order resigned from the cabinet, and HIRANUMA designated the Imperial Rule Assistance Association a public interest association and made the supporters of the new order within the Association resign.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as cabinet members&quot;→&quot;from the cabinet&quot;&quot;prescribed&quot;→&quot;designated the&quot;Deleted &quot;Taisei-Yokusankai&quot;, brackets and &quot;as&quot;&quot;Kojikessha (association seeking public interest)&quot;→&quot;public interest association&quot;Deleted &quot;he&quot; &quot; Taisei-Yokusankai&quot;→&quot;the Association&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, the supporters of the new order resigned from the cabinet, and Hiranuma designated the Imperial Rule Assistance Association a public interest association and made the supporters of the new order within the Association resign.</e>
<cmt>HIRANUMA→Hiranuma</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="90">
<j>9月23日、北部仏印進駐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 23, Japan made an entry into northern French Indochina.</e>
<cmt>北部仏印→north of French Indochina→northern French Indochina[north of (の北) から northern (北部) に変更]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 23, the Japanese army advanced into northern French Indochina.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Japan made an entry&quot;→&quot;the Japanese army advanced&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 23, the Japanese army advanced into northern French Indochina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>9月27日に日独伊三国軍事同盟を締結。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 27, military alliance of Japan, Germany and Italy was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 27, the Tripartite Pact between Japan, Germany and Italy was signed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;military alliance of&quot;→&quot;the Tripartite Pact between&quot;&quot;formed&quot;→&quot;signed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 27, the Tripartite Pact between Japan, Germany and Italy was signed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="92">
<j>1941年（昭和16年）4月13日に日ソ中立条約を締結。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 13, 1941, Japan-Soviet Neutrality Pact was signed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 13, 1941, the Japan-Soviet Neutrality Pact was signed.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 13, 1941, the Japan-Soviet Neutrality Pact was signed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>近衛らは日米諒解案による交渉を目指すも、この内容が三国同盟を骨抜きにする点に松岡洋右は反発し、松岡による修正案がアメリカ合衆国に送られたが、アメリカは修正案を黙殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE aimed for a negotiation of a draft that&apos;s understood by Japan and the U.S., but Yosuke MATSUOKA objected against the point in the content that watered down the tripartite alliance, and the amendment proposed by MATSUOKA was sent to the United States of America, but the United States ignored the proposed amendment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE also hoped for negotiations with the U.S. based on the draft of a &apos;mutual understanding plan&apos; but Yosuke MATSUOKA, who objected to the parts that watered down the tripartite alliance, proposed an amendment version which was sent to the United States of America, where it was ignored.</e>
<cmt>&quot;aimed for a negotiation&quot;→&quot;also hoped for negotiations&quot;&quot;of a draft that&apos;s understood by Japan and the U.S&quot;&quot;of a draft that&apos;s understood by Japan and the U.S.,&quot;→&quot;with the U.S. based on the draft of a &apos;mutual understanding plan&apos;&quot;Added &quot;, who&quot;&quot;against the point in the content&quot;→&quot;to the parts&quot;&quot; and the amendment proposed by MATSUOKA &quot;→&quot;proposed an amendment version which&quot;&quot;but the United States ignored the proposed amendment&quot;→&quot;where it was ignored&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe also hoped for negotiations with the U.S. based on the draft of a mutual understanding plan but Yosuke MATSUOKA, who objected to the parts that watered down the tripartite alliance, proposed an amendment version which was sent to the United States of America, where it was ignored.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe原文に「」がないので&apos; &apos;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="94">
<j>6月22日に独ソ戦が勃発、ドイツ・イタリアと三国同盟を結んでいた日本は、独ソ戦争にどう対応するか、御前会議にかける新たな国策が直ちに求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 22, German-Soviet War broke out, and there was an immediate need for a new national policy to be discussed in a meeting held before the Emperor about how Japan, having signed the tripartite alliance, should deal with the German-Soviet War.</e>
<cmt>三国同盟→tripartite alliance</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 22, Germany invaded the Soviet Union, and an Imperial Council was immediately held to discuss how Japan, having signed the Tripartite Pact, should react to this development.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 22, Germany invaded the Soviet Union, and an Imperial Council was immediately held to discuss how Japan, having signed the Tripartite Pact, should react to this development.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>陸軍は独ソ戦争を、仮想敵国ソビエトに対し軍事行動をとる千載一遇のチャンスととらえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Army saw the German-Soviet War as a chance in a million to take military actions against the imagined enemy, the Soviet Union.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Army saw the German invasion as a one in a million chance to take military action against the hypothetical enemy, the Soviet Union.</e>
<cmt>&quot;German-Soviet War&quot;→&quot;German invasion&quot;&quot;chance in a million&quot;→&quot;one in a million chance&quot;Deleted &apos;s&apos;&quot;imagined&quot;→&quot;hypothetical&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Army saw the German invasion as a one in a million chance to take military action against the hypothetical enemy, the Soviet Union.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>一方海軍も、この機に資源が豊富な南方へ進出しようと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Navy, on the other hand, considered using this opportunity to advance to the south that was rich in resources.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Navy, on the other hand, considered using this opportunity to advance to the resource-rich south.</e>
<cmt>&quot;that was rich in resources&quot;→&quot;resource-rich&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Navy, on the other hand, considered using this opportunity to advance to the resource-rich south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>大本営政府連絡会議では松岡外相は三国同盟に基づいてソ連への挟撃を訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the liaison conference of Daihonei Seifu (Imperial Headquarters Government), Foreign Minister Matsuoka made an appeal for a pincer operation against the Soviet Union based on the tripartite alliance,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the liaison conference between the Government and Imperial General Headquarters, Foreign Minister Matsuoka made an appeal for a pincer operation against the Soviet Union based on the tripartite alliance.</e>
<cmt>&quot;of Daihonei Seifu (Imperial Headquarters Government)&quot;→&quot;between the Government and Imperial General Headquarters&quot;comma→full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the liaison conference between the Government and Imperial General Headquarters, Foreign Minister Matsuoka made an appeal for a pincer operation against the Soviet Union based on the tripartite alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="98">
<j>7月2日の御前会議で「情勢ノ推移ニ伴フ帝国国策要綱」が決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the meeting held before the Emperor on July 2nd, &quot;principle of Imperial policy according to process of circumstances&quot; was approved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Imperial Council of July 2nd, the &quot;outline of Imperial policy following changes in circumstances&quot; was approved.</e>
<cmt>&quot;meeting held before the Emperor on&quot;→&quot;Imperial Council of&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;principle&quot;→&quot;outline&quot;&quot;according to process of circumstances&quot;→&quot;following changes in circumstances&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Imperial Council of July 2, the &apos;outline of Imperial policy following changes in circumstances&apos; was approved.</e>
<cmt>nd削除原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>この国策の骨格は海軍が主張した南方進出と、松岡外相と陸軍が主張した対ソ戦の準備という二正面での作戦展開にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The framework of this national policy was based on the unfolding of tactics on two fronts: advancing to the south maintained by the Navy, and preparation toward a war against the Soviet Union maintained by the Army and Foreign Minister Matsuoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The framework of this national policy was based on military deployment on two fronts: an advance to the south advocated by the Navy, and preparation for war against the Soviet Union advocated by the Army and Foreign Minister Matsuoka.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the unfolding of tactics&quot;→&quot;military deployment&quot;&quot;advancing&quot;→&quot;an advance&quot;&quot;maintained&quot;→&quot;advocated&quot;&quot;toward a&quot;→&quot;for&quot;&quot;maintained&quot;→&quot;advocated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The framework of this national policy was based on military deployment on two fronts: an advance to the south advocated by the Navy, and preparation for war against the Soviet Union advocated by the Army and Foreign Minister Matsuoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>この決定を受けてソビエトに対しては7月7日いわゆる関東軍特種演習を発動し、演習名目で兵力を動員し、独ソ戦争の推移次第ではソビエトに攻め込むという作戦であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this decision, on July 7, the so-called Kanto Army Special Tactical Training was started against the Soviet Union, in which the troops were mobilized under the pretext of tactical training, and under this strategy the army would invade into the Soviet Union depending on how the German-Soviet War was shifting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this decision, on July 7, the so-called Kwantung Army Special Maneuvers was started, in which troops, under the pretext of tactical training, were mobilized in preparation for an invasion of the Soviet Union, depending on how the German invasion was progressing.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kanto Army Special Tactical Training was&quot;→&quot;Kwantung Army Special Maneuvers were&quot;Deleted &quot;against the Soviet Union&quot;, &quot;the&quot;Moved &quot;under the pretext of tactical training&quot;&quot;and under this strategy the army would invade into&quot;→&quot;in preparation for an invasion of&quot;&quot;-Soviet War was shifting&quot;→&quot;invasion was progressing&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this decision, on July 7, the so-called Kwantung Army Special Maneuvers was started, in which troops, under the pretext of tactical training, were mobilized in preparation for an invasion of the Soviet Union, depending on how the German invasion was progressing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>一方南方に対しては7月28日南部仏印への進駐を行なったが、これはアメリカによる経済制裁を招く結果となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, regarding the southern side, advancement into southern French Indochina took place on July 28, but this ended up triggering an economic sanction by the United States.</e>
<cmt>南部仏印→south of French Indochina→southern French Indochina[south of を southern に変更]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, to the south, the Army advanced into southern French Indochina on July 28, resulting in economic sanctions by the United States.</e>
<cmt>&quot;On the other hand&quot;→&quot;At the same time&quot;&quot;regarding the southern side,&quot;→&quot;to the south&quot;&quot;advancement&quot;→&quot;the Army advanced&quot;Deleted &quot;took place&quot;&quot;but this ended up triggering an&quot;→&quot;resulting in&quot;Made &quot;sanction&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, to the south, the Army advanced into southern French Indochina on July 28, resulting in economic sanctions by the United States.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>アメリカでの日本の経済活動がすべてアメリカ政府の管理下に置かれ、そして日本の南部仏印の進駐を確認した上で、石油の対日輸出が全面禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The economic activities of Japan conducted in the United States were placed entirely under the administration of the government of the United States, and after Japan&apos;s advancement to southern French Indochina was confirmed there was a total ban of oil export to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese assets in the United States were placed entirely under the administration of the U.S. Government, and after Japan&apos;s advancement into southern French Indochina was confirmed, there was a total ban on the export of oil to Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The economic activities of Japan conducted&quot;→&quot;Japanese assets&quot;&quot;government of the United States&quot;→&quot;U.S. Government&quot;&quot;to&quot;→&quot;into&quot;&quot;of oil export&quot;→&quot;on the export of oil&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese assets in the United States were placed entirely under the administration of the U.S. Government, and after Japan&apos;s advancement into southern French Indochina was confirmed, there was a total ban on the export of oil to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="103">
<j>これらを受けて近衛は7月18日に内閣総辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, KONOE and the cabinet members resigned en masse on July 18.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, KONOE and the cabinet members resigned en masse on July 18.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Konoe and the cabinet members resigned en masse on July 18.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>第三次内閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Third Cabinet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Third Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Third Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>1941年（昭和16年）7月18日に、第3次近衛内閣を組織。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 18, 1941, the Third Konoe Cabinet was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 18, 1941, the third Konoe cabinet was formed.</e>
<cmt>Made &apos;T&apos; and &apos;C&apos; lower case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 18, 1941, the third Konoe cabinet was formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>これは、アメリカの要求を飲んだかのように見せかけたもので、実際はもう既に足枷でしかなかった松岡洋右を更迭しただけで、殆ど変わっていないのが実情であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was done so to put on an appearance of accepting the demands made by the United States, but in reality, Yosuke MATSUOKA, who had become nothing but shackles, was merely forced out, and the actual condition was hardly changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This cabinet was formed to give the impression of complying with American demands but in fact, apart from the dismissal of Yosuke MATSUOKA, who had become a thorn in the side of the administration, the cabinet remained the same.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This cabinet was formed to give the impression of complying with American demands but in fact, apart from the dismissal of Yosuke MATSUOKA, who had become a thorn in the side of the administration, the cabinet remained the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>代わって外相には、南進論の豊田貞次郎海軍大将を任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Foreign Minister, Teijiro TOYODA, full admiral of the southing army, was assigned in stead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Admiral Teijiro TOYODA, a supporter of the Southern Expansion Doctrine, was selected to replace MATSUOKA as Foreign Minister.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Admiral Teijiro TOYODA, a supporter of the Southern Expansion Doctrine, was selected to replace Matsuoka as Foreign Minister.</e>
<cmt>MATSUOKA→Matsuoka</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>7月23日にすでにドイツに降伏していたフランスのヴィシー政権からインドシナの権益を奪い、7月28日に南部仏印進駐を実行し、7月30日にサイゴンへ入城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 23, Japan had taken the rights in Indochina from Regime de Vichy of France, who had already surrendered to Germany, advanced to south French Indochina on July 28, and entered the capital of Saigon on July 30.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan had taken the rights in Indochina from Vichy France, who had already surrendered to Germany, on July 23, advanced to south French Indochina on July 28, and entered the capital, Saigon, on July 30.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;on July 23&quot;&quot;Regime de Vichy of France&quot;→&quot;Vichy France&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan had taken the rights in Indochina from Vichy France, who had already surrendered to Germany, on July 23, advanced to south French Indochina on July 28, and entered the capital, Saigon, on July 30.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>しかしこれに対するアメリカの対日石油全面輸出禁止により日本は窮地に立たされることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because the United States put a total ban on oil export to Japan in response to this, Japan was placed in a very tight situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because of the resulting American oil embargo, Japan was placed in a very tight situation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the United States put a total ban on oil export to Japan in response to this&quot;→&quot;of the resulting American oil embargo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because of the resulting American oil embargo, Japan was placed in a very tight situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>9月6日の御前会議では、「帝国国策遂行要領」を決定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the meeting in front of the Emperor on September 6, &quot;guideline of Imperial policy execution&quot; was approved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Imperial Council of September 6, the &quot;guideline for the execution of Imperial policy&quot; was approved.</e>
<cmt>&quot;meeting in front of the Emperor on&quot;→&quot;Imperial Council of&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;for the&quot;Moved &quot;execution&quot;Added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Imperial Council of September 6, the &apos;guideline for the execution of Imperial policy&apos; was approved.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>アメリカ、イギリスに対する最低限の要求内容を定め、交渉期限を10月上旬に区切り、この時までに要求が受け入れられない場合、アメリカ、オランダ、イギリスに対する開戦方針が定めらた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The minimum demands to the United States and England were decided, the deadline for the negotiation period was set to early October, and in case the demands were not accepted by that time, a plan was laid down to start a war against the United States, the Netherlands and England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The minimum demands to the United States and Britain were decided, the deadline for the negotiation period was set for early October, and in case the demands were not accepted by that time, a plan was laid down to start a war against the United States, the Netherlands and Britain.</e>
<cmt>&quot;England&quot;→&quot;Britain&quot;&quot;to&quot;→&quot;for&quot;&quot;England&quot;→&quot;Britain&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The minimum demands to the United States and Britain were decided, the deadline for the negotiation period was set for early October, and in case the demands were not accepted by that time, a plan was laid down to start a war against the United States, the Netherlands and Britain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>御前会議の終わった9月6日の夜、近衛はようやく日米首脳会談による解決を決意し駐日アメリカ大使ジョセフ・グルーと極秘のうちに会談し、危機打開のため日米首脳会談の早期実現を強く訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the night of September 6, when the meeting in front of the Emperor ended, KONOE finally decided to seek solution through a Japan-U.S. summit and he had a secret meeting with the U.S. ambassador to Japan, Joesph Grew, and he made an intensive appeal for an early realization of a Japan-U.S. summit in order to circumvent any crises.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the night of September 6, when the Imperial Council ended, KONOE finally decided to seek a solution through a Japan-U.S. summit and held a secret meeting with the U.S. Ambassador to Japan, Joesph Grew, making an intensive appeal for a Japan-U.S. summit as soon as possible in order to circumvent any crises.</e>
<cmt>&quot;meeting in front of the Emperor&quot;→&quot;Imperial Council&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;&quot;he had&quot;→&quot;held&quot;Capitalized &apos;a&apos;&quot;and he made&quot;→&quot;making&quot;&quot;an early realization of&quot;→&quot;as soon as possible&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the night of September 6, when the Imperial Council ended, Konoe finally decided to seek a solution through a Japan-U.S. summit and held a secret meeting with the U.S. Ambassador to Japan, Joesph GREW, making an intensive appeal for a Japan-U.S. summit as soon as possible in order to circumvent any crises.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeGrew→GREW</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>事態を重く見たグルーは、その夜、直ちに首脳会談の早期実現を要請する電報を本国に打ち、国務省では日米首脳会談の検討が直ちに始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grew, who saw the importance of the situation, immediately sent a telegraph to the United States that night to request an early realization of a Japan-U.S. summit, and the Department of State immediately started to look into holding of a Japan-U.S. summit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grew, who saw the importance of the situation, immediately sent a telegraph to the United States that night to request an urgent summit, and the Department of State immediately started to look into holding a Japan-U.S. summit.</e>
<cmt>&quot;early realization of a Japan-U.S.&quot;→&quot;urgent&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grew, who saw the importance of the situation, immediately sent a telegraph to the United States that night to request an urgent summit, and the Department of State immediately started to look into holding a Japan-U.S. summit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>しかし、国務省では妥協ではなく力によって日本を封じ込めるべきだと考え、10月2日、アメリカ国務省は日米首脳会談を事実上拒否する回答を日本側に示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Department of State decided not to compromise, but instead, to contain Japan by force, and on October 2nd, Department of State indicated to Japan a response that effectively denied the Japan-U.S. summit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Department of State decided not to compromise but instead to contain Japan by force and, on October 2nd, indicated to Japan a response that effectively rejected a Japan-U.S. summit.</e>
<cmt>Moved commasDeleted &quot;Department of State&quot;&quot;denied the&quot;→&quot;rejected a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Department of State decided not to compromise but instead to contain Japan by force and, on October 2, indicated to Japan a response that effectively rejected a Japan-U.S. summit.</e>
<cmt>nd削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="114">
<j>陸軍はアメリカの回答をもって日米交渉も事実上終わりと判断し、参謀本部（陸軍管轄）は政府に対し、外交期限を10月15日とするよう要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Army viewed this response by the United States as the effective end to negotiations between Japan and the United States, and the staff headquarters (army&apos;s jurisdiction) demanded that the deadline for foreign diplomacy be set to October 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Army viewed this response as the effective end to negotiations between Japan and the United States, and the Staff Headquarters (under the army&apos;s jurisdiction) demanded that the deadline for foreign diplomacy be set to October 15.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;by the United States&quot;, &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;under the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Army viewed this response as the effective end to negotiations between Japan and the United States, and the Staff Headquarters (under the army&apos;s jurisdiction) demanded that the deadline for foreign diplomacy be set to October 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>外交期限の迫った10月12日、戦争の決断を迫られた近衛は豊田貞次郎外相、及川古志郎海相、東條英機陸相、鈴木貞一企画院総裁を荻外荘に呼び、対米戦争への対応を協議した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 12, just before the deadline for foreign diplomacy, KONOE, who was pressed for a decision on the war, invited Foreign Minister Teijiro TOYODA, Minister of the Navy Koshiro OIKAWA, Minister of Army Hideki TOJO and President of Kikakuin government organization Teiichi SUZUKI to Tekigaiso, and he conferred on how to deal with the war against the United States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 12, just before the deadline for foreign diplomacy, KONOE, who was being pressed for a decision on the war, invited Foreign Minister Teijiro TOYODA, Minister of the Navy Koshiro OIKAWA, Minister of the Army Hideki TOJO and the Director of the Planning Board, Teiichi SUZUKI to Tekigaiso, and he conferred on how to deal with war against the United States.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;being&quot;, &quot;the&quot;&quot;President of Kikakuin government organization&quot;→&quot;the Director of the Planning Board, &quot;&quot;and he conferred on&quot;→&quot;where they discussed&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 12, just before the deadline for foreign diplomacy, Konoe, who was being pressed for a decision on the war, invited Foreign Minister Teijiro TOYODA, Minister of the Navy Koshiro OIKAWA, Minister of the Army Hideki TOJO and the Director of the Planning Board, Teiichi SUZUKI to Tekigaiso, and he conferred on how to deal with war against the United States.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>いわゆる「荻外荘会談」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the so-called &quot;Tekigaiso Meeting.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the so-called &quot;Tekigaiso Meeting.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;It&quot;→&quot;This&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the so-called &apos;Tekigaiso Meeting.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>そこで近衛は対中撤兵による交渉に道を求めたが、これに反対する東条英機陸相は総辞職か国策要綱に基づく開戦を要求し、両者は東久邇宮稔彦王を次期首相に推すことで一致し、10月16日に内閣は投げ出され、10月18日に総辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE sought a path to a negotiation by withdrawing from China, but Minister of Army Hideki TOJO, who opposed this, demanded either a resignation of all cabinet members or to start a war based on the principles of national policy; the two of them agreed on recommending Naruhiko-o, Higashikuni-no-miya as the next prime minister, and on October 16, the cabinet was dismantled and the cabinet members resigned en masse on October 18.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE sought a path to a negotiation by withdrawing from China, but Minister of the Army Hideki TOJO, who opposed this, demanded either the resignation of all cabinet members or the start of war based on the national policy outline, so the two of them agreed on recommending Prince Naruhito Higashikuni as the next prime minister, and on October 16, the cabinet was dismantled, with the cabinet members resigning en masse on October 18.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;to&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;of&quot;&quot;principles of&quot;→&quot;outline&quot; and movedsemicolon→&quot;, so&quot;&quot;Naruhiko-o, Higashikuni-no-miya&quot;→&quot;Prince Naruhito Higashikuni&quot; - is what I think he&apos;s usually called in English&quot;and&quot;→&quot;, with&quot;&quot;resigned&quot;→&quot;resigning&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe sought a path to a negotiation by withdrawing from China, but Minister of the Army Hideki TOJO, who opposed this, demanded either the resignation of all cabinet members or the start of war based on the national policy outline, so the two of them agreed on recommending Prince Higashikuninomiya Naruhiko as the next prime minister, and on October 16, the cabinet was dismantled, with the cabinet members resigning en masse on October 18.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe東久邇宮稔彦王→Prince Higashikuninomiya Naruhiko</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>終戦工作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operation to End the War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moves to End the War</e>
<cmt>&quot;Operation&quot;→&quot;Moves&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moves to End the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="118">
<j>1941年（昭和16年）12月8日の太平洋戦争開始後は、共に軍部から危険視されていた元外務次官・駐英大使の吉田茂と接近するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Pacific War started on December 8, 1941, he became close to Shigeru YOSHIDA, former Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs and Ambassador to Great Britain, who was also viewed as dangerous by the military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Pacific War started on December 8, 1941, KONOE became close to Shigeru YOSHIDA, former Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs and Ambassador to Great Britain, who, like KONOE, was viewed as dangerous by the military.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he&quot;→&quot;KONOE&quot;&quot;was also&quot;→&quot;, like KONOE, was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Pacific War started on December 8, 1941, Konoe became close to Shigeru YOSHIDA, former Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs and Ambassador to Great Britain, who, like Konoe, was viewed as dangerous by the military.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>1942年（昭和17年）のシンガポール占領とミッドウェー海戦の大敗を好期と見た吉田は、近衛をスイスに派遣し、英米との交渉を行うことを持ちかけ、近衛も乗り気になったため、この案を木戸幸一に伝えるが、木戸が握り潰してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YOSHIDA, who saw the occupation of Singapore and the crushing defeat in the Battle of Midway Island in 1942 as an good opportunity, proposed to send KONOE to Switzerland and negotiate with Great Britain and the Unites States; because KONOE agreed this suggestion was conveyed to Koichi KIDO, but KIDO burked it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YOSHIDA, who saw the occupation of Singapore and the crushing defeat in the Battle of Midway in 1942 as a good opportunity, proposed sending KONOE to Switzerland and negotiating with Great Britain and the United States and because KONOE agreed, this suggestion was conveyed to Koichi KIDO, but KIDO rejected it.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Island&quot;&quot;an&quot;→&quot;a&quot;&quot;to send&quot;→&quot;sending&quot;&quot;negotiate&quot;→&quot;negotiating&quot;&quot;Unites&quot;→&quot;United&quot;semicolon→&quot;and&quot;Added comma&quot;burked&quot;→&quot;rejected&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida, who saw the occupation of Singapore and the crushing defeat in the Battle of Midway in 1942 as a good opportunity, proposed sending Konoe to Switzerland and negotiating with Great Britain and the United States and because Konoe agreed, this suggestion was conveyed to Koichi KIDO, but KIDO rejected it.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeYOSHIDA→Yoshida</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>近衛に注意すべきとの東條の意向に従ったものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he obeyed TOJO&apos;s advice to be cautious of KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he took TOJO&apos;s advice to be cautious of KONOE.</e>
<cmt>&quot;obeyed&quot;→&quot;took&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he took Tojo&apos;s advice to be cautious of Konoe.</e>
<cmt>TOJO→TojoKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="121">
<j>1943年（昭和18年）から、近衛とそのグループは、やがて「近衛上奏文」につながる軍部赤化論や共産革命脅威論を唱え始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1943, KONOE and his group began to talk about military reddening theory and theory to see communist revolution as a threat, which eventually led to &quot;Konoe address to the throne.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1943, KONOE and his group began to speak out about the &apos;reddening&apos; of the military and the threat of a communist revolution, which eventually led to &quot;Konoe&apos;s Address to the Throne.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;talk&quot;→&quot;speak out&quot;&quot;military reddening theory&quot;→&quot;the &apos;reddening&apos; of the military&quot;&quot;theory to see communist revolution as a threat&quot;→&quot;the threat of a communist revolution&quot;Added &quot;&apos;s&quot;Capitalized &apos;a&apos; and &apos;t&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1943, Konoe and his group began to speak out about the &apos;reddening&apos; of the military and the threat of a communist revolution, which eventually led to &apos;Konoe&apos;s Address to the Throne.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>発端は皇道派軍人の真崎甚三郎や小畑敏四郎たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ones who started this were soldiers of Kodoha (the Imperial Way group) such as Jinzaburo MAZAKI and Toshishiro OBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ones who started this were soldiers of the Imperial Way faction such as Jinzaburo MAZAKI and Toshishiro OBATA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Kodoha&quot; and brackets&quot;group&quot;→&quot;faction&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ones who started this were soldiers of the Imperial Way faction such as Jinzaburo MAZAKI and Toshishiro OBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>殖田俊吉もこれに共感し、吉田に近衛と会うべきと言われていた殖田は、小畑と共に近衛にこれを説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunkichi UEDA also shared the same view, and UEDA, who had been told by YOSHIDA that he should definitely meet with KONOE, explained his view to KONOE with OBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunkichi UEDA also shared the same view and after being told by YOSHIDA that he should definitely meet with KONOE, explained his view to KONOE along with OBATA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted comma&quot;UEDA, who had been told&quot;→&quot;after being&quot;Added &quot;along&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunkichi UEDA also shared the same view and after being told by Yoshida that he should definitely meet with Konoe, explained his view to Konoe along with OBATA.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeYOSHIDA→YoshidaOBATA→Obata</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>以降、近衛は、彼らグループの中心として、親ソ的な現在の陸軍首脳部を追うことで終戦を目指すようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, KONOE, as the central figure in their group, aimed to end the war by chasing the leaders of the current, pro-Soviet Union Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, KONOE, as the central figure in their group, aimed to end the war by ousting the then pro-Soviet leaders of the Army.</e>
<cmt>&quot;chasing&quot;→&quot;ousting&quot;&quot;current, pro-Soviet Union&quot;→&quot;then pro-Soviet&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Konoe, as the central figure in their group, aimed to end the war by ousting the then pro-Soviet leaders of the Army.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="125">
<j>1944年（昭和19年）7月9日のサイパン島陥落に伴い、東條内閣に対する退陣要求が強まったが、その際には「このまま東条に政権を担当させておくほうが良い。戦局は、誰に代わっても好転することはないのだから、最後まで全責任を負わせるようにしたらよい」と述べ、敗戦を見越したうえで、天皇に戦争責任が及びにくくする様に考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 9, 1944, with the fall of Saipan, there was an increasing demand for Tojo Cabinet to resign, but on that occasion, having foreseen the defeat in the war and speculating a way to make it difficult for the Emperor to be held responsible for the war, he stated the following: &quot;It&apos;s better to let TOJO have the administrative power. The war situation will not improve no matter who replaces him, so it&apos;s better to let him take all the responsibilities until the very end.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the fall of Saipan on July 9, 1944, there was an increasing demand for the Tojo cabinet to resign, but having foreseen defeat in the war and thinking of ways to make it difficult for the Emperor to be held responsible for the war, he stated, &quot;It&apos;s better to let TOJO have the administrative power. The war situation will not improve no matter who replaces him, so it&apos;s better to let him take all responsibility until the very end.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;On July 9, 1944,&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Made &apos;C&apos; lower caseDeleted &quot;on that occasion,&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;thinking of ways&quot;&quot;the following:&quot;→comma&quot;the responsibilities&quot;→&quot;responsibility&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the fall of Saipan on July 9, 1944, there was an increasing demand for the Tojo cabinet to resign, but having foreseen defeat in the war and thinking of ways to make it difficult for the Emperor to be held responsible for the war, he stated, &apos;It&apos;s better to let Tojo have the administrative power. The war situation will not improve no matter who replaces him, so it&apos;s better to let him take all responsibility until the very end.&apos;</e>
<cmt>TOJO→Tojo原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="126">
<j>1945年（昭和20年）2月14日に、近衛は昭和天皇に対して、早期和平を主張する「近衛上奏文」を奏上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 14, 1945, KONOE presented to Emperor SHOWA &quot;Konoe address to the throne&quot; that advocated an early realization of peace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 14, 1945, KONOE presented his &quot;Address to the Throne,&quot; that advocated an early realization of peace, to Emperor SHOWA.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;his&quot;&quot;Konoe address to the throne&quot;→&quot;Address to the Throne&quot;Moved &quot;to Emperor SHOWA&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 14, 1945, Konoe presented his &apos;Address to the Throne,&apos; that advocated an early realization of peace, to Emperor SHOWA.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="127">
<j>戦局が悪化するにつれ、近衛は独自の終戦工作を展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the war situation worsened KONOE developed his own plans to end the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the war situation worsened KONOE developed his own plans to end the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the war situation worsened Konoe developed his own plans to end the war.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>それは、スイス、スウェーデン、バチカンなどの中立国を仲介とするものではなく、ソ連による和平仲介だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was peacemaking by the Soviet Union, instead of using neutral countries such as Switzerland, Sweden or the Vatican as a mediator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of using neutral countries such as Switzerland, Sweden or the Vatican, he planned to have the Soviet Union act as peacemaker.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It was peacemaking by the Soviet Union,&quot;→&quot;he planned to have the Soviet Union act as peacemaker&quot; and movedDeleted &quot;as a mediator&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of using neutral countries such as Switzerland, Sweden or the Vatican, he planned to have the Soviet Union act as peacemaker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>しかし、近衛のモスクワ派遣は、スターリンに事実上拒否された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, KONOE&apos;s dispatch to Moscow was effectively refused by Stalin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, KONOE&apos;s dispatch to Moscow was effectively refused by Stalin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Konoe&apos;s dispatch to Moscow was effectively refused by Stalin.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>近衛の交渉案は、全ての海外の領土、琉球諸島、小笠原諸島、千島を放棄し、労働力として日本軍将兵を提供するものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE&apos;s negotiation plan was to disclaim all the territories overseas, such as Ryukyu Islands, Ogasawara Islands (Bonin Islands) and the Kuril Islands, and providing officers and soldiers of the Japanese Army as a labor force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE&apos;s negotiation plan was to disclaim all the territories overseas, the Ryukyu Islands, the Ogasawara Islands (Bonin Islands) and the Kuril Islands, and to offer officers and soldiers of the Japanese Army as a labor force.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;such as&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; before island names&quot;providing&quot;→&quot;to offer&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe&apos;s negotiation plan was to disclaim all the territories overseas, the Ryukyu Islands, the Ogasawara Islands (Bonin Islands) and the Kuril Islands, and to offer officers and soldiers of the Japanese Army as a labor force.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>戦犯容疑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charge of War Crimes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charge of War Crimes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charge of War Crimes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="131">
<j>1945年（昭和20年）8月15日に太平洋戦争が終結すると東久邇宮内閣で近衛は国務大臣を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Pacific War ended on August 15, 1945, KONOE worked as Minister of State in Higashikuni-no-miya Cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Pacific War ended on August 15, 1945, KONOE became Minister of State in the HIGASHIKUNI Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>&quot;worked as&quot;→&quot;became&quot;&quot;Higashikuni-no-miya Cabinet&quot;→&quot;HIGASHIKUNI cabinet&quot; - I think this is what it&apos;s usually called in English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Pacific War ended on August 15, 1945, Konoe became Minister of State in the Higashikuninomiya Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeHIGASHIKUNI→Higashikuninomiya</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>10月4日に、近衛は連合国軍最高司令官総司令部ダグラス・マッカーサーを訪ね、持論の軍部赤化論を説いて、開戦時には天皇を中心とした封建勢力や財閥はブレーキの役割を果たした、と主張し、皇室と財閥を除けば日本はたちまち赤化すると説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 4, KONOE visited Douglas MacArthur at the General Headquarters of the Allied Forces, talked about his own military reddening theory and asserted that at the start of the war, feudatory power centered around the Emperor and Zaibatsu, company syndicate, functioned as brakes, and that Japan would immediately redden if the Imperial family and Zaibatsu were removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 4, KONOE visited Douglas MacArthur at the General Headquarters of the Allied Forces (GHQ), talked about his own theory of the military turning communist and asserted that at the start of the war, the Zaibatsu industrial-commercial conglomerates and the feudal power centered around the Emperor functioned as brakes, and that Japan would immediately redden if the Imperial family and the Zaibatsu were removed.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(GHQ)&quot;&quot;military reddening theory&quot;→&quot;theory of the military turning communist&quot;&quot;feudatory&quot;→&quot;feudal&quot;Changed word order&quot;company syndicate&quot;→&quot;industrial-commercial conglomerates&quot;&quot;redden&quot;→&quot;turn communist&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 4, Konoe visited Douglas MacArthur at the General Headquarters of the Allied Forces (GHQ), talked about his own theory of the military turning communist and asserted that at the start of the war, the Zaibatsu industrial-commercial conglomerates and the feudal power centered around the Emperor functioned as brakes, and that Japan would immediately redden if the Imperial family and the Zaibatsu were removed.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>マッカーサー、サザーランド参謀長およびアチソン連合国軍最高司令官総司令部政治顧問はこれに肯き、近衛に憲法改定を託した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MacArthur, Assistant Chief of Staff Sutherland and Acheson, political adviser and top commander of the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers, agreed with this, and they put KONOE in charge of revising the constitution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MacArthur, Assistant Chief of Staff Sutherland and Acheson, political adviser to the Supreme Commander of the Allied Powers, agreed and they put KONOE in charge of revising the constitution.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and top&quot;→&quot;to the Supreme&quot; Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Deleted &quot;General Headquarters of the&quot;, &quot;with this,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MacArthur, Assistant Chief of Staff Sutherland and Acheson, political adviser to the Supreme Commander of the Allied Powers, agreed and they put Konoe in charge of revising the constitution.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="134">
<j>しかし、国内外の新聞では、戦時体制を敷いた近衛の責任問題の追及が激しくなり、白洲次郎たちは近衛がマッカーサーに憲法改定を託されたことを宣伝して回り、近衛を助けようと試みた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the newspapers inside and outside of Japan, pursuit intensified on the liability of KONOE who laid out the war structure, and people such as Jiro SHIRASU made an attempt to save KONOE by announcing that he was put in charge by MacArthur to revise the constitution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, newspapers both inside and outside of Japan intensified investigations into KONOE&apos;s responsibility for the war, and people such as Jiro SHIRASU attempted to save KONOE by announcing that he had been put in charge of revising the constitution by MacArthur.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;in the&quot;Added &quot;both&quot;Deleted &quot;, pursuit&quot;&quot;on the liability of KONOE who laid out the war structure&quot;→&quot;investigations into KONOE&apos;s responsibility for the war&quot;&quot;made an attempt&quot;→&quot;attempted&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;had been&quot;&quot; to revise the constitution&quot;→&quot;of revising the constitution&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, newspapers both inside and outside of Japan intensified investigations into Konoe&apos;s responsibility for the war, and people such as Jiro SHIRASU attempted to save Konoe by announcing that he had been put in charge of revising the constitution by MacArthur.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>しかし、メディアの反応を恐れたマッカーサーは、11月1日に、近衛の憲法改定にはGHQは関与しないとして、近衛を切り捨てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, MacArthur, who became afraid of media response, cut off KONOE stating that the GHQ (General Headquarters of the Allied Forces) would not be involved in the revising of the constitution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, MacArthur, who feared the media response, cut off KONOE, stating that GHQ (General Headquarters of the Allied Forces) would not be involved in revising the constitution.</e>
<cmt>&quot;became afraid of&quot;→&quot;feared&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; and commaDeleted &quot;the&quot;, &quot;(General Headquarters of the Allied Forces)&quot;, &quot;the&quot;, &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, MacArthur, who feared the media response, cut off Konoe, stating that GHQ (General Headquarters of the Allied Forces) would not be involved in revising the constitution.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>また近衛の責任追及も行われるようになり、砲艦に呼び出され軍部と政府の関係について質問があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, pursuit of KONOE&apos;s accountability also began, and he was summoned on the gunboat and questioned on the relationship between the government and the military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as investigations into KONOE&apos;s accountability seemed likely to continue, he was summoned to a gunboat and questioned on the relationship between the government and the military.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;as&quot;&quot;pursuit of&quot;→&quot;investigations into&quot;&quot;also began&quot;→&quot;seemed likely to continue&quot;Deleted &quot;and&quot;&quot;on the&quot;→&quot;to a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as investigations into Konoe&apos;s accountability seemed likely to continue, he was summoned to a gunboat and questioned on the relationship between the government and the military.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="137">
<j>近衛は、すでに1921年の演説で、統帥権によって将来軍部と政府が二元化しかねない危険性を説き、その後それは現実となったのだが、このような状況はアメリカ側には理解し難い内容であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his speech in 1921, KONOE had already talked about the danger of the likely split in the future between the military and the government because of the supreme command, and later that did become real, but such a situation was a difficult concept for the United States to understand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his speech of 1921, KONOE had already talked about the danger of the likely split in the future between the military and the government because of the Emperor&apos;s supreme command, which is what happend, but such a situation was a difficult concept for the United States to understand.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot;→&quot;of&quot;Added &quot;Emperor&apos;s&quot;&quot;and later that did become real&quot;→&quot;which is what happend&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his speech of 1921, Konoe had already talked about the danger of the likely split in the future between the military and the government because of the Emperor&apos;s supreme command, which is what happened, but such a situation was a difficult concept for the United States to understand.</e>
<cmt>スペルKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>しかし、昭和天皇への責任追及を避けるために、統帥権という語は口にできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he could not say the term &quot;supreme command&quot; in order to prevent the pursuit of accountability against Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in order to prevent the pursuit of accountability against Emperor Showa, he could not use the term &quot;supreme command.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;say&quot;→&quot;use&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in order to prevent the pursuit of accountability against Emperor Showa, he could not use the term supreme command.</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>近衛は、何も答えられなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE could no longer give any answers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE could no longer give any answers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe could no longer give any answers.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="140">
<j>近衛は『世界文化』に、「手記～平和への努力」を発表し、日中戦争の泥沼化と、太平洋戦争の開戦の全責任を軍部に転嫁し、自分は軍部の独走を阻止できなかったことが遺憾であると釈明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE published &quot;Diary - Efforts toward Peace&quot; in &quot;World Cultures&quot;, in which he shifted all the responsibilities for the muddles of Sino-Japanese War and the start of the Pacific War to the military, and explained that he regretted the fact that he was unable to stop the runaway military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE published &quot;A Diary - Efforts toward Peace&quot; in &quot;World Cultures&quot;, in which he shifted all the responsibilities for the quagmire of the Sino-Japanese War and the start of the Pacific War to the military, and explained that he regretted the fact that he was unable to stop the runaway military.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;A&quot;,&quot;muddles&quot;→&quot;quagmire&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe published &apos;A Diary - Efforts toward Peace&apos; in &quot;World Cultures&quot;, in which he shifted all the responsibilities for the quagmire of the Sino-Japanese War and the start of the Pacific War to the military, and explained that he regretted the fact that he was unable to stop the runaway military.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>1945年12月6日に、GHQからの逮捕命令を聞いて、A級戦犯として極東国際軍事裁判で裁かれることを知った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 6, 1945, he heard about the arrest warrant from the GHQ and learned that he would be tried as a class-A war criminal in Tokyo Tribunal of War Criminals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 6, 1945, he heard about the arrest warrant from GHQ and learned that he would be tried as a class-A war criminal at the Tokyo War Crimes Tibunal.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;in Tokyo Tribunal of War Criminals&quot;→&quot;at the Tokyo War Crimes Tibunal&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 6, 1945, he heard about the arrest warrant from GHQ and learned that he would be tried as a class-A war criminal at the Tokyo War Crimes Tribunal.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>巣鴨拘置所に出頭を命じられた最終期限日の1945年12月16日、荻外荘でシアン化カリウムを服毒して自殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ordered to present himself at Sugamo detention center, and on December 16, 1945, on the last day of the deadline, he committed suicide by swallowing potassium cyanide at Tekigaiso.</e>
<cmt>シアン化カリウム→kalium cyanide→potassium cyanide[kalium を potassium に変更]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 16, 1945, the deadline for him to present himself at Sugamo detention center he committed suicide by swallowing potassium cyanide at Tekigaiso.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 16, 1945, the deadline for him to present himself at Sugamo detention center he committed suicide by swallowing potassium cyanide at Tekigaiso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>昭和天皇に戦争責任が及ばないようにという、皇室の藩籬として、そして五摂家筆頭としての自覚が促した、苦渋の選択だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was an agonizing choice that was prompted by his awareness as the head of Gosekke and to keep the Imperial family safe by preventing the liability of the war from falling on Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was an agonizing choice, prompted by his awareness of his position as the head of Gosekke and to keep the Imperial family safe by preventing responsibility for the war from falling on Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;that was&quot;→commaAdded&quot; of his position&quot;&quot;the liability of&quot;→&quot;responsibility for&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was an agonizing choice, prompted by his awareness of his position as the head of Gosekke and to keep the Imperial family safe by preventing responsibility for the war from falling on Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="144">
<j>自殺の前日、次男の近衛通隆に遺書を口述筆記させ、「自分は多くの過ちを犯してきたが、戦犯として裁かれなければならないことに耐えられない…僕の志は知る人ぞ知る」と言い残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the day before his suicide, he dictated his will to his second son, Michitaka KONOE, and left the following words: &quot;I have made many mistakes, but I cannot stand being tried as a war criminal… only those people who understand, know my intentions.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the day before his suicide, he dictated his will to his second son, Michitaka KONOE, and left the following words: &quot;I have made many mistakes, but I cannot stand being tried as a war criminal… only those people who understand, know my intentions.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the day before his suicide, he dictated his will to his second son, Michitaka KONOE, and left the following words: &apos;I have made many mistakes, but I cannot stand being tried as a war criminal… only those people who understand, know my intentions.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="145">
<j>葬儀は1945年12月21日に行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His funeral was conducted on December 21, 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His funeral was held on December 21, 1945.</e>
<cmt>&quot;conducted&quot;→&quot;held&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His funeral was held on December 21, 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>墓は京都市の大徳寺にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is located at Daitoku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is located at Daitoku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is located at Daitoku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>荻外荘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekigaiso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekigaiso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekigaiso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="147">
<j>杉並区荻窪 (杉並区)の「荻外荘」（てきがいそう）は、元は大正天皇の侍医頭だった入澤達吉が所有していた郊外の別荘だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tekigaiso&quot; located in Ogikubo, Suginami Ward (Suginami Ward) originally was a second home in the suburbs that belonged to Tatsukichi IRISAWA, who was the head court physician of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>侍医頭→head of surgeons in ordinary to the King→head court physician[修正翻訳の方が内容と合ってると思います]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tekigaiso&quot; located in Ogikubo, Suginami Ward (Suginami Ward) was originally the suburban second home of Tatsukichi IRISAWA, the head court physician of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>&quot;originally was a second home in the suburbs that belonged to&quot;→&quot;was originally the suburban second home of&quot;Deleted &quot;who was &quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekigaiso&apos; located in Ogikubo, Suginami Ward (Suginami Ward) was originally the suburban second home of Tatsukichi IRISAWA, the head court physician of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>近衛は南に斜面をもった高台に立地し、近くは善福寺川から遠くは富士山までの景勝を一望のもとに見渡せるこの別荘に惚れ込んで、入澤を口説き落としてこれを買い受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE deeply fell in love with this house located on a hill with a sloping south side and a beautiful, sweeping view of Zempukuji-gawa River close by and Mt. Fuji in the distance, and he purchased it after persuading IRISAWA for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE fell deeply in love with this house located on a hill with a sloping south side and a beautiful, sweeping view of the near-by Zempukuji-gawa River and Mt. Fuji in the distance, and persuded IRISAWA to sell it.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;deeply&quot;&quot;close-by&quot;→&quot;the near-by&quot; and moved&quot;he purchased it after persuading IRISAWA for a long time&quot;→&quot;persuded IRISAWA to sell it&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe fell deeply in love with this house located on a hill with a sloping south side and a beautiful, sweeping view of the near-by Zempukuji-gawa River and Mt. Fuji in the distance, and persuaded Irisawa to sell it.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeIRISAWA→Irisawaスペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="149">
<j>名称の「荻外荘」は額面通りの「荻窪の外」で、特に故事成句に因むような深遠な意味はないということになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Tekigaiso&quot; means exactly as it is, &quot;outside of Ogikubo,&quot; and there is no deep meaning associated with any historical events or phrases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Tekigaiso&quot; literally means &quot;outside of Ogikubo,&quot; and there is no deep meaning associated with any historical events or phrases.</e>
<cmt>&quot;means exactly as it is,&quot;→&quot;literally means&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Tekigaiso&apos; literally means &apos;outside of Ogikubo,&apos; and there is no deep meaning associated with any historical events or phrases.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>しかし近衛に頼まれてこれを撰名したのは有職故実の奥義に通じた西園寺公望なので、実のところはどうなのかはよくわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in reality, it is not confirmed because the person to whom KONOE asked to select this name was Kimmochi SAIONJI, who was well-versed in the past customs of the imperial court and samurai families.</e>
<cmt>有職故実の奥義→esoteric of Yusoku-Kojitsu (well-versed in usages of the military households)→well-versed in the past customs of the imperial court and samurai families[辞林２１、三省堂、辞林２１の説明を英訳しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the person whom KONOE asked to select this name was Kimmochi SAIONJI, who was well-versed in the past customs of the imperial court and samurai families, it is open to speculation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in reality, it is not confirmed&quot;→&quot;, it is open to speculation&quot; and moved&quot;because&quot;→&quot;since&quot;Deleted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the person whom Konoe asked to select this name was Kinmochi SAIONJI, who was well-versed in the past customs of the imperial court and samurai families, it is open to speculation.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→KonoeKimmochi→Kinmmochi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="151">
<j>近衛家には目白（現在の新宿区下落合）に本邸があり、荻窪の方はあくまでも別邸なのだが、近衛はこの荻外荘がことのほか気に入った様子で、一度ここに住み始めると本邸の方へは二度と戻らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konoe family had its main residence in Mejiro (present-day Shimo-Ochiai, Shinjuku Ward), so the one in Ogikubo really was a second house, but because it seemed that he especially loved this Tekigaiso, once he began to live there he never went back to his main residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Konoe family had its main residence in Mejiro (present-day Shimo-Ochiai, Shinjuku Ward), so the one in Ogikubo was, strictly speaking, a second house, but KONOE seemed especially taken with Tekigaiso and once he began to live there he never went back to his main residence.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;&quot;really&quot;→&quot;, strictly speaking,&quot; and moved&quot; because it seemed that he especially loved this Tekigaiso,&quot;→&quot;KONOE seemed especially taken with Tekigaiso and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Konoe family had its main residence in Mejiro (present-day Shimo-Ochiai, Shinjuku Ward), so the one in Ogikubo was, strictly speaking, a second house, but Konoe seemed especially taken with Tekigaiso and once he began to live there he never went back to his main residence.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="152">
<j>総理大臣官邸の喧噪とはうってかわって静寂な荻外荘のたたずまいを、近衛は政治の場としても活用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE also used the quiet presence of Tekigaiso as his political stage, which was completely different from the bustle at the official residence of the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE also used the quiet presence of Tekigaiso, which was completely different from the bustle at the Prime Minister&apos;s official residence, as his political stage.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;which was completely different from the bustle at the official residence of the Prime Minister&quot;Made &quot;Prime Minister&quot;possessive and movedDeleted &quot;of the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe also used the quiet presence of Tekigaiso, which was completely different from the bustle at the Prime Minister&apos;s official residence, as his political stage.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>「東亜新秩序」の建設を確認した昭和15年7月19日の「荻窪会談」や、対米戦争の是非とその対応についてを協議した昭和16年10月15日の「荻外荘会談」などの特別な協議はもとより、時には定例会合の五相会議までをも荻外荘で開いており、第二次世界大戦前夜の重要な国策の多くがここで決定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only did he hold special conferences such as the &quot;Ogikubo Meeting&quot; on July 19, 1940, in which he confirmed the construction of &quot;new order in East Asia,&quot; and &quot;Tekigaiso Meeting&quot; on October 15, 1941, in which he negotiated the pros and cons of fighting and handling of the war against the U.S., he, at times, even held the regularly scheduled meetings of &quot;Meetings with the Five Ministers&quot; at Tekigaiso, and many important national policies were approved here, on the night before the Second World War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only did he hold special conferences such as the &quot;Ogikubo Meeting&quot; on July 19, 1940, in which he confirmed the construction of &quot;new order in East Asia,&quot; and &quot;Tekigaiso Meeting&quot; on October 15, 1941, in which he negotiated the pros and cons of war against the U.S., at times, he even held regularly scheduled top-level ministerial meetings at Tekigaiso and on the eve of the Second World War, many important national policies were approved here.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;fighting and handling of the&quot; moved &quot;he&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;meetings of &quot;Meetings with the Five Ministers&quot;&quot;→&quot;top-level ministerial meetings&quot;&quot;on the night before the Second World War&quot;→&quot;on the eve of the Second World War&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only did he hold special conferences such as the &apos;Ogikubo Meeting&apos; on July 19, 1940, in which he confirmed the construction of &apos;new order in East Asia,&apos; and &apos;Tekigaiso Meeting&apos; on October 15, 1941, in which he negotiated the pros and cons of war against the U.S., at times, he even held regularly scheduled top-level ministerial meetings at Tekigaiso and on the eve of the Second World War, many important national policies were approved here.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>昭和16年9月末に近衛から対米戦に対する海軍の見通しを訊かれた連合艦隊司令長官の山本五十六が、「是非やれと言われれば初めの半年や一年は随分と暴れてご覧に入れます。しかし、二年、三年となれば、全く確信は持てません」という有名な回答で近衛を悩ませたのも、この荻外荘においてであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also at this Tekigaiso, at the end of September, 1941, when Isoroku YAMAMOTO, navarch of combined fleet, who was asked by KONOE about the Navy&apos;s prospect on the fight against the U.S., worried KONOE with the famous words, &quot;If you say I must, I will show you how much damage we can inflict for the first half a year or a year. However, if it goes on for 2 to 3 years, I have no confidence.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also at Tekigaiso, at the end of September, 1941, that Commander in Chief of the Combined Fleet, Isoroku YAMAMOTO, who was asked by KONOE about the Navy&apos;s prospects in the fight against the U.S., worried KONOE with the famous words, &quot;If you say I must, I will show you how much damage we can inflict for the first half a year or a year. However, if it goes on for 2 to 3 years, I have absolutely no confidence.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;this&quot;&quot;when&quot;→&quot;that&quot;&quot;navarch of combined fleet&quot;→&quot;Commander in Chief of the Combined Fleet&quot; and movedMade &quot;prospect&quot; plural&quot;on&quot;→&quot;in&quot;Added &quot;absolutely&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also at Tekigaiso, at the end of September, 1941, that Commander in Chief of the Combined Fleet, Isoroku YAMAMOTO, who was asked by Konoe about the Navy&apos;s prospects in the fight against the U.S., worried Konoe with the famous words, &apos;If you say I must, I will show you how much damage we can inflict for the first half a year or a year. However, if it goes on for 2 to 3 years, I have absolutely no confidence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="155">
<j>こうした変則的な政治手法から「荻外荘」の三文字が新聞の紙面に踊る日は多く、この私邸の名称は日本の隅々にまで知れ渡るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From these unorthodox political styles, the three characters of &quot;Tekigaiso&quot; appeared often on the newspapers, and the name of this private residence came to be known throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this unorthodox way of conducting politics, the name &quot;Tekigaiso&quot; appeared often in the newspapers and became known throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;From these unorthodox political styles&quot;→&quot;Due to this unorthodox way of conducting politics&quot;&quot;three characters of&quot;→&quot;name&quot;&quot;on&quot;→&quot;in&quot; &quot;the name of this private residence came to be&quot;→&quot;became&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this unorthodox way of conducting politics, the name &apos;Tekigaiso&apos; appeared often in the newspapers and became known throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>後には吉田茂の「東京都庭園美術館」、鳩山一郎の「鳩山会館」、田中角榮の「田中角榮人間関係」などがやはり同じように第二の官邸のような機能をもつが、その先例はこの荻外荘に求めることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Shigeru YOSHIDA&apos;s &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Teien Art Museum&quot;, Ichiro HATOYAMA&apos;s &quot;Hatoyama Hall&quot; and Kakuei TANAKA&apos;s &quot;Tanaka Kakuei Human Relationship&quot; also functioned as official secondary residence of the prime minister, but their antecedent can be found in this Tekigaiso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Shigeru YOSHIDA&apos;s &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Teien Art Museum&quot;, Ichiro HATOYAMA&apos;s &quot;Hatoyama Hall&quot; and Kakuei TANAKA&apos;s &quot;Tanaka Kakuei Human Relationship&quot; also functioned as official secondary residences of the Prime Minister, but their antecedent can be found in Tekigaiso.</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;residence&quot; pluralCapitalized &apos;p&apos;, &apos;m&apos;Deleted &quot;this&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Shigeru YOSHIDA&apos;s &apos;Tokyo Metropolitan Teien Art Museum,&apos; Ichiro HATOYAMA&apos;s &apos;Hatoyama Hall&apos; and Kakuei TANAKA&apos;s &apos;Tanaka Kakuei Human Relationship&apos; also functioned as official secondary residences of the Prime Minister, but their antecedent can be found in Tekigaiso.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="157">
<j>荻窪一帯は空襲を免れたため、荻外荘は現在でも近衛が自らの命を絶った日とさほど変らない姿をこの地に留めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the Ogikubo area escaped the aerial attacks, still to this day, Tekigaiso&apos;s appearance remains hardly changed in its place ever since KONOE ended his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Ogikubo area escaped the bombing of Tokyo, Tekigaiso&apos;s appearance has remained virtually unchanged since KONOE ended his life there.</e>
<cmt>&quot;aerial attacks&quot;→&quot;bombing of Tokyo&quot; Deleted &quot;still to this day&quot;&quot;remains&quot;→&quot;has remained&quot;&quot;hardly changed&quot;→&quot;virtually unchanged&quot; Deleted &quot;in its place ever&quot;Added &quot;there&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Ogikubo area escaped the bombing of Tokyo, Tekigaiso&apos;s appearance has remained virtually unchanged since Konoe ended his life there.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>現在でも近衛家の私有地なので内部の見学はできないが、歴史の重みに満ちたその片鱗は塀の外からでも十分に垣間見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even to this day, it is a private property of the Konoe family so that the inside cannot be seen, but a partial view filled with historical atmosphere can be adequately glimpsed even through the outside fence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house remains the private property of the Konoe family and is not open for viewing, but a partial view of the historical atmosphere can be glimpsed through the outside fence.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Even to this day, it is a&quot;→&quot;The house remains the&quot;&quot;so that the inside cannot be seen&quot;→&quot;and is not open for viewing&quot;&quot;filled with&quot;→&quot;of the&quot;Deleted &quot;adequately&quot;, &quot;even&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The house remains the private property of the Konoe family and is not open for viewing, but a partial view of the historical atmosphere can be glimpsed through the outside fence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="159">
<j>荻外荘：</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekigaiso:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekigaiso:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekigaiso:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>杉並区荻窪 2-43</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2-43 Ogikubo, Suginami Ward</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2-43 Ogikubo, Suginami Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2-43 Ogikubo, Suginami Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>JR/丸の内線 荻窪駅 南口徒歩10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10 minute walk from the south exit of Ogikubo Station, JR/Marunouchi Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A 10 minute walk from the south exit of Ogikubo Station on the JR/Marunouchi Line</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;A&quot;, &quot; on the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A 10 minute walk from the south exit of Ogikubo Station on the JR/Marunouchi Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>近衛一族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konoe Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konoe Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="162">
<j>近衛氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konoe clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konoe clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>本姓は藤原氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His true surname was Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Konoe were descended from the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;His true surname was&quot;→&quot;The Konoe were descended from the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Konoe were descended from the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>藤原忠通の子近衛基実を始祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earliest ancestor is Motozane KONOE, a son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earliest ancestor was Motozane KONOE, a son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earliest ancestor was Motozane KONOE, a son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>江戸時代初期に嗣子を欠いたため、後陽成天皇の第四皇子が母方の叔父・近衛信尹の養子となり近衛信尋として近衛家を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the lack of family heir during early Edo period the fourth prince of Emperor Goyozei was adopted by the maternal uncle, Nobutada KONOE, and inherited the KONOE family as Nobuhiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the lack of a family heir during the early Edo period, the fourth son of Emperor Goyozei was adopted by his maternal uncle, Nobutada KONOE, and became the head of the KONOE family as Nobuhiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;a&quot;, &quot;the&quot; and comma&quot;prince&quot;→&quot;son&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;&quot;inherited&quot;→&quot;became the head of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the lack of a family heir during the early Edo period, the fourth son of Emperor Goyozei was adopted by his maternal uncle, Nobutada KONOE, and became the head of the Konoe family as Nobuhiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>文麿はその直系十一世孫にあたり、その血統は当時は大勢いた皇族よりもずっと天皇家に近かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumimaro was the 11th generation direct descendant, and at the time, genealogically speaking, he was far closer to the Emperor&apos;s family compared to the many members of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumimaro was the 11th generation direct descendant and at the time, he was a lot more closely related to the Emperor&apos;s family than many members of the Imperial family were.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;genealogically speaking&quot;&quot;far closer&quot;→&quot;a lot more closely related&quot;&quot;compared to the&quot;→&quot;than&quot;Added &quot;were&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumimaro was the eleventh generation direct descendant and at the time, he was a lot more closely related to the Emperor&apos;s family than many members of the Imperial family were.</e>
<cmt>11th→eleventh</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>「昭和天皇に拝謁した後の近衛が座っていた椅子の背もたれだけはいつも暖かかった」というのは、文麿が天皇に対して抱いていた親近感を示す有名なエピソードである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an interesting story that goes, &quot;the back of the chair on which KONOE sat after he had an audience with Emperor Showa was always warm,&quot; which demonstrates the closeness Fumimaro felt toward the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The well-known anecdote that &quot;the back of the chair on which KONOE sat after he had an audience with Emperor Showa was always warm,&quot; demonstrates the closeness Fumimaro felt toward the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;There is an interesting story that goes&quot;→&quot;The well-known anecdote that&quot;Deleted &quot;which&quot;- Left &quot;Emperor Showa&quot; as it is, though I think he might be better known as Emperor Hirohito, at least in the UK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The well-known anecdote that &apos;the back of the chair on which Konoe sat after he had an audience with Emperor Showa was always warm,&apos; demonstrates the closeness Fumimaro felt toward the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>家族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;His&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="168">
<j>妻の千代子とは、公爵という身分には珍しい恋愛結婚だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He married his wife, Chiyoko, for love, which was rare for someone with the status of a duke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married his wife, Chiyoko, for love, which was rare for someone with the status of a duke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married his wife, Chiyoko, for love, which was rare for someone with the status of a prince.</e>
<cmt>duke→prince</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>華族女学校で一番の美女だったという千代子を第一高等学校 (旧制)の学生だった文麿が見初めた一方的な一目惚れだったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumimaro, who was a student at Daiichi High School, single-sidedly fell in love at first sight when he saw Chiyoko, who was said to have been the most beautiful girl at Kazoku Jogakko (girls&apos; school for Kazoku new nobility).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumimaro, who was a student at Daiichi High School, fell in love at first sight when he saw Chiyoko, who was said to have been the most beautiful girl at the Kazoku Jogakko school for the daughters of peers.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;single-sidedly&quot;&quot;(girls&apos; school for Kazoku new nobility)&quot;→&quot;school for the daughters of peers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumimaro, who was a student at Daiichi High School, fell in love at first sight when he saw Chiyoko, who was said to have been the most beautiful girl at the Kazoku Jogakko school for the daughters of peers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>結婚当時は京都帝大在学中だったが、その生活は「学生結婚」という言葉にはそぐわないほど豪勢なものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though he was still at Kyoto Imperial University when they got married, their lives were unfittingly lavish for a &quot;student marriage.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though he was still at Kyoto Imperial University when they got married, their lives were unfittingly lavish for a &quot;student marriage.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though he was still at Kyoto Imperial University when they got married, their lives were unfittingly lavish for a &apos;student marriage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>結婚生活は円満だったが、当時の大身の例にもれず数人の妾を囲い、隠し子もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They had a happy marriage, but as with people of high social status of the time he had a number of concubines and he also had illegitimate children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They had a happy marriage, but as was common with people of high social status at the time, he had a number of concubines and illegitimate children.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;was common&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;at&quot;Added commaDeleted &quot;he also had&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They had a happy marriage, but as was common with people of high social status at the time, he had a number of concubines and illegitimate children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="172">
<j>次女の温子（よしこ）は1937年（昭和12年） 4月、当時まだ京都帝大在学中だった細川護貞と結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second daughter, Yoshiko, married Morisada HOSOKAWA who was still a student at Kyoto Imperial University, in April, 1937.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second daughter, Yoshiko, married Morisada HOSOKAWA who was still a student at Kyoto Imperial University, in April, 1937.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second daughter, Yoshiko, married Morisada HOSOKAWA who was still a student at Kyoto Imperial University, in April, 1937.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>その直後に父は総理となり、夫は総理秘書官となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after that, her father became the Prime Minister of Japan and her husband became the secretary to the prime minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after that, her father became the Prime Minister of Japan and her husband became his secretary.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;Deleted &quot;to the prime minister&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after that, her father became the Prime Minister of Japan and her husband became his secretary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>三年後の昭和15年（1940年）8月、父が総理に返り咲いて間もなく、温子は腹膜炎をこじらせて小石川の細川邸で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3 years later, in August, 1940, shortly after her father came back to power as the prime minister she died of complications from peritonitis and died at the house of Hosokasa in Koishikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3 years later, in August, 1940, shortly after her father began his second term as Prime Minister, she died of complications from peritonitis at the Hosokawa residence in Koishikawa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;after her father came back to power as the prime minister&quot;→&quot;after her father began his second term as Prime Minister,&quot;&quot;and died at the house of Hosokasa&quot;→&quot;at the Hosokawa residence&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3 years later, in August, 1940, shortly after her father began his second term as Prime Minister, she died of complications from peritonitis at the Hosokawa residence in Koishikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>享年23、夫と父に看取られての最期だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was 23, she was attended by her father and her husband at the time of her death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was attended by her father and her husband at the time of her death at the age of 23.</e>
<cmt>&quot;She was 23,&quot;→&quot;at the age of 23&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was attended by her father and her husband at the time of her death at the age of 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>この温子と護貞の短い結婚生活のなかで恵まれたのが、後に総理となる長男の細川護熙と、近衛家の養子となった次男の忠煇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the short marriage between Yoshiko and Morisada, they were blessed with the eldest son, Morihiro HOSOKAWA, who later became a prime minister, and the second son, Tadateru, who was later adopted by the KONOE Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the short marriage between Yoshiko and Morisada, they were blessed with two sons; the eldest, Morihiro HOSOKAWA, later became Prime Minister, and the second son, Tadateru, was later adopted by the KONOE Family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;two sons&quot;Deleted &quot;son&quot;, &quot;who&quot; and &quot;who&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the short marriage between Yoshiko and Morisada, they were blessed with two sons; the eldest, Morihiro HOSOKAWA, later became Prime Minister, and the second son, Tadateru, was later adopted by the Konoe Family.</e>
<cmt>KONOE→Konoe</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="177">
<j>不仲だった継母の貞は戦時中京都の別邸（現・陽明文庫所在地）に単独で疎開、そこで栄養失調により死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The step-mother, Sada, with whom he did not get along, evacuated alone to their alternate residence in Kyoto (where Yomei Bunko is currently located) during the war, and she passed away there because of malnutrition.</e>
<cmt>陽明文庫→Yomei paperback→Yomei Bunko[陽明文庫とはペーパーバックの本ではなく、資料館です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The step-mother, Sada, whom Fumimaro did not get along with, died from malnutrition after evacuating alone to their alternate residence in Kyoto (where the Yomei Bunko Library is currently located) during the war.</e>
<cmt>&quot;with whom he did not get along&quot;→&quot;whom Fumimaro did not get along with&quot;&quot;evacuated&quot;→&quot;after evacuating&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;Library&quot;Moved &quot;and she passed away there because of malnutrition&quot;Deleted &quot;and&quot;&quot;passed away&quot;→&quot;died&quot;Deleted &quot;there&quot;&quot;because of&quot;→&quot;from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The step-mother, Sada, whom Fumimaro did not get along with, died from malnutrition after evacuating alone to their alternate residence in Kyoto (where the Yomei Bunko Library is currently located) during the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>1945年8月15日のことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It happened on August 15, 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died on August 15, 1945.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It happened on&quot;→&quot;She died on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died on August 15, 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="179">
<j>実家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Side of the Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Parents and Siblings</e>
<cmt>Reworded but I feel it would be more natural merged with the 自家 section under the title &quot;Family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Parents and Siblings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="180">
<j>父：近衛篤麿（貴族院議長）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father: Atsumaro KONOE (president of Kizokuin (the House of Peers))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Father: Atsumaro KONOE (President of the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Kizoku&quot; and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Father: Atsumaro KONOE (President of the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="181">
<j>母：衍（旧加賀藩主 前田慶寧公爵の三女）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mother: En (third daughter of former lord of the Kaga domain, Yoshiyasu MAEDA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mother: En (third daughter of former Lord of Kaga Domain, Yoshiyasu MAEDA)</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;l&apos; and &apos;d&apos;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mother: En (third daughter of former Lord of Kaga Domain, Yoshiyasu MAEDA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="182">
<j>嫡子：文磨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heir: Fumimaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heir: Fumimaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heir: Fumimaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="183">
<j>継母：貞（前田慶寧の四女、実の叔母にあたる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Step mother: Sada (fourth daughter of Yoshiyasu MAEDA, biological aunt)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Step mother: Sada (fourth daughter of Yoshiyasu MAEDA, biological aunt)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Step mother: Sada (fourth daughter of Yoshiyasu MAEDA, biological aunt)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="184">
<j>異母妹：武子（大山巌公爵の次男 大山柏に嫁ぐ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger step-sister: Takeko (married Kashiwa OYAMA, the second son of Duke Iwao OYAMA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger step-sister: Takeko (married Kashiwa OYAMA, the second son of Duke Iwao OYAMA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Younger step-sister: Takeko (married Kashiwa OYAMA, the second son of Prince Iwao OYAMA)</e>
<cmt>duke→prince</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="185">
<j>異母弟：近衛秀麿（指揮者 作曲家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger step-brother: Hidemaro KONOE (conductor, composer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger step-brother: Hidemaro KONOE (conductor, composer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Younger step-brother: Hidemaro KONOE (conductor, composer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="186">
<j>異母弟：直麿（雅楽研究者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger step-brother: Naomaro KONOE (researcher of Gagaku, Japanese traditional music and dance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger step-brother: Naomaro KONOE (researcher of Gagaku, Japanese traditional music and dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Younger step-brother: Naomaro KONOE (researcher of Gagaku, Japanese traditional music and dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="187">
<j>異母弟：忠麿（→ 水谷川家を継ぐ、春日大社宮司）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger step-brother: Tadamaro KONOE (succeeded the Mizutanigawa Family, Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Kasugataisha Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger step-brother: Tadamaro KONOE (became head of the Mizutanigawa Family, Head Priest of Kasugataisha Shrine)</e>
<cmt>&quot;succeeded&quot;→&quot;became head of&quot;&quot;Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs)&quot;→&quot;Head Priest&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Younger step-brother: Tadamaro KONOE (became head of the Mizutanigawa Family, Head Priest of Kasugataisha Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="188">
<j>自家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Own Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spouse, Children and Grandchildren</e>
<cmt>Reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spouse, Children and Grandchildren</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="189">
<j>妻：千代子（元・豊後佐伯藩主 子爵・毛利高範の長女）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wife: Chiyoko (former lord of the Bungo-Saiki domain, Viscount Takanori MORI&apos;s eldest daughter)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wife: Chiyoko (eldest daughter of the former Lord of Bungo-Saiki Domain, Viscount Takanori MORI)</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;eldest daughter&quot;Added &quot;of the&quot;Capitalized &apos;l&apos; and &apos;d&apos;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wife: Chiyoko (eldest daughter of the former Lord of Bungo-Saiki Domain, Viscount Takanori MORI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="190">
<j>長男：近衛文隆（シベリア抑留中病死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First son: Fumitaka KONOE (died of an illness while he was detained in Siberia)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First son: Fumitaka KONOE (died of illness while detained in Siberia)</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;an&quot; and &quot;he was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First son: Fumitaka KONOE (died of illness while detained in Siberia)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="191">
<j>庶孫：東隆明（俳優）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grandchild born out of wedlock: Ryumei AZUMA (actor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grandchild born out of wedlock: Ryumei AZUMA (actor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grandchild born out of wedlock: Ryumei AZUMA (actor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="192">
<j>長女：野口昭子（島津公爵家当主 島津忠秀に嫁ぐが、整体・野口晴哉と駆け落ちして後に結婚）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eldest daughter: Akiko NOGUCHI (married Tadahide SHIMAZU, Head of Marquis of Shimazu Family, but she eloped with bodywork Haruchika NOGUCHI and later married him.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eldest daughter: Akiko NOGUCHI (married Marquis Tadahide SHIMAZU, Head of the Shimazu Family, but she eloped with chiropractor Haruchika NOGUCHI and later married him.)</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Marquis&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;bodywork&quot;→&quot;chiropractor&quot; - although not the exact meaning of 整体, I think it is good enough for most non-Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eldest daughter: Akiko NOGUCHI (married Prince Tadahide SHIMAZU, Head of the Shimazu Family, but she eloped with chiropractor Haruchika NOGUCHI and later married him.)</e>
<cmt>Marquis→Prince</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="193">
<j>次女：温子（細川侯爵家当主嫡男 細川護貞に嫁ぐ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second daughter: Yoshiko (married Morisada HOSOKAWA, heir to the Head of Marquis of Hosokawa Family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second daughter: Yoshiko (married Marquis Morisada HOSOKAWA, heir to the Head of the Hosokawa Family)</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Marquis&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second daughter: Yoshiko (married Marquis Morisada HOSOKAWA, heir to the Head of the Hosokawa Family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="194">
<j>外孫：細川護熙（内閣総理大臣）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotomago (grandchild from a daughter married into another family): Morihiro HOSOKAWA (Prime Minister)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grandchild: Morihiro HOSOKAWA (Prime Minister)</e>
<cmt>&quot;Sotomago&quot;→&quot;Grandchild&quot; - there isn&apos;t a distinction in English between grandchidren born to sons and those born to daughters so deleted the section in brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grandchild: Morihiro HOSOKAWA (Prime Minister)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="195">
<j>嫡孫：近衛忠てる（→ 近衛家を継ぐ、日本赤十字社社長）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legitimate grandchild: Tadateru HOSOKAWA (succeeded the Konoe Family, President of Japanese Red Cross Society)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legitimate grandchild: Tadateru HOSOKAWA (succeeded the Konoe Family, President of the Japanese Red Cross Society)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legitimate grandchild: Tadateru HOSOKAWA (succeeded the Konoe Family, President of the Japanese Red Cross Society)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="196">
<j>次男：近衛通隆（東京大学教授）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second son: Michitaka KONOE (professor of the University of Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second son: Michitaka KONOE (professor at the University of Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>&quot;of&quot;→&quot;at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second son: Michitaka KONOE (professor at the University of Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), R-h(id:46562), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Akoyano(id:56905), شيوعية(id:206578), 78(id:10935), Arpeggio(id:9385), PeachLover(id:56909), Takeler(id:51437), 日陰猫Joga(id:9749), 代言人(id:33675), IwaimBot(id:190695), BotMultichill(id:132395), Kanoe(id:17203), Point136(id:211299), とんちゃん2(id:39111), Aloha-vodka(id:22493), Klesha(id:203751), FlaBot(id:30804), F.V.E(id:33231), Stmmtmt(id:53085), Asia(id:14392), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Oxhop(id:2551), 浩(id:70121), たね(id:10372), Stanislaus(id:1806), Woyzzeck(id:8923), 松茸(id:27535), Okozuchi(id:48279), PixelBot(id:166734), Kome(id:46586), Memosa(id:131221), Robotje(id:11192), Sh(id:2707), 編集しても良いですか?(id:14251), 彩華1226(id:64711), MDR-SK(id:192066), 杉山真大(id:2297), Histwr(id:15646), Blueroses5327(id:97718), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), R28Bot(id:177951), 総督(id:124846), 海衛士(id:19229), Kawanobe(id:15459), Alexbot(id:157199), キヨンネ(id:56097), Straysheep(id:42448), Goodmoon(id:1219), Wiki0825(id:34646), 都の西西八王子(id:38026), 松浸史(id:78240), とっち(id:70461), MIsogi(id:20599), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), 陽一(id:92099), Tom-spring(id:42457), にごう(id:23317), Extrahitz(id:26245), BLUE MONDAY(id:96831), Kumatora(id:16941), Johncapistrano(id:969), パの字(id:34188), Tomo suzuki(id:11928), 氷鷺(id:73707), 下総大納言(id:43461), 玄史生(id:43670), Rei-bot(id:94097), こぶまき(id:38278), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Nopira(id:29335), KASAGI(id:24405), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Ujimotoryoga(id:29789), LERK(id:4460), Poe(id:16973), Lonicera(id:20638), PANYNJ(id:38638), Race(id:131322), Law soma(id:45202), Cuniculus(id:53663), 水野白楓(id:22811), うまやど(id:93760), Clarin(id:60278), Aboshi(id:9318), Ajtnk(id:18368), Kafuka1964(id:105407), ゐ(id:795), Mumur(id:58068), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Kuma83(id:31177), ささら(id:55949), Meat ball(id:19377), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>