<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>樋口兼光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanemitsu HIGUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanemitsu HIGUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanemitsu HIGUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>樋口 兼光（ひぐち かねみつ、生年不詳 - 元暦元年2月2日 (旧暦)（1184年3月15日））　は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanemitsu HIGUCHI (year of birth unknown-March 15, 1184) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanemitsu HIGUCHI (year of birth unknown - March 15, 1184) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanemitsu HIGUCHI (year of birth unknown - March 22, 1184) was a military commander during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中原兼遠の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of NAKAHARA no Kaneto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of NAKAHARA no Kaneto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of NAKAHARA no Kaneto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>今井兼平・巴御前の兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hi was an elder brother of Kanehira IMAI and Tomoe Gozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hi was an elder brother of Kanehira IMAI and Tomoe Gozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an elder brother of Kanehira IMAI and Tomoe Gozen (Lady Tomoe).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。巴御前→Tomoe Gozen (Lady Tomoe)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称・次郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly called Jiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly called Jiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly called Jiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正式な名のりは中原 兼光（なかはら の かねみつ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His formal name was NAKAHARA no Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His formal name was NAKAHARA no Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His formal name was NAKAHARA no Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>源義仲の乳母子にして股肱の臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a menotogo (the son of a menoto, a woman breastfeeding a highborn baby) of and a right-hand man to MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>源義仲の乳母子→文意がおかしいと思うのですが（乳母兄弟？）あえて原文どおりに訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a menotogo (the son of a menoto, a woman breastfeeding a highborn baby) of and a right-hand man to MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of wet nurse of as well as a right-hand man to MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>義仲四天王の一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of Yoshinaka Shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of Yoshinaka Shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the Four Most Loyal Retainers of Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>義仲の挙兵時から付き従い、倶利伽羅峠の戦いなどで重要な役割を果たす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He followed Yoshinaka since Yoshinaka rose up in arms, and played critical roles through wars including the battle of the Kurikara Pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He followed Yoshinaka since Yoshinaka rose up in arms, and he played a critical role through a number of wars including the battle of Kurikara Pass.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a retainer of Yoshinaka since Yoshinaka rose in arms, and he played a critical role in a number of wars including the battle of Kurikara Pass.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>義仲軍上洛後も法住寺合戦で後白河法皇を拘束するなどその片腕として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued to be active as his right hand after Yoshinaka came out to Kyoto; he captured Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa in the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to be active as his right hand after Yoshinaka went to Kyoto; he captured the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa in the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to be active as a right-hand man of Yoshinaka after Yoshinaka went to Kyoto such that he captured the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa in the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>元暦元年、義仲の敗死後、児玉党の薦めで降伏するも源頼朝の命により斬首。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1184, he accepted Kodama Party&apos;s advice and surrendered after Yoshinaka defeated and died in the war, after all, he was beheaded by the order of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1184, he accepted Kodama Party&apos;s advice and surrendered after Yoshinaka was defeated and died in the war, and finally, beheaded on orders of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1184, Yoshinaka was defeated and died in the war, HIGUCHI accepted Kodama Party&apos;s advice and surrendered, but finally, beheaded on orders of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その際、その武勇を惜しむ源範頼や源義経をはじめ、多くの人から助命嘆願があったが、これに公家達が猛反発を起こし、助命はかなわなかったと『平家物語』に載る（後述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike) stated that HIGUCHI was killed, even though many people including MINAMOTO no Noriyori, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune who were impressed by his heroism begged for his life; some court nobles were furiously opposed to saving his life, and his life couldn&apos;t be saved (to be described later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike) stated that HIGUCHI was killed, even though many people including MINAMOTO no Noriyori, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune who were impressed by his heroism begged for his life; some court nobles were furiously opposed to saving his life, and his life couldn&apos;t be saved (to be described later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heike Monogatari stated that HIGUCHI was killed, even though quite a few people including MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, who were impressed by his heroism, begged for his life, becauase some court nobles were furiously opposed to saving his life (to be described later).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>『吾妻鏡』の記述によれば、「武蔵国児玉の輩（ともがら）と親昵（しんぢつ）たるの間」とあり、親しい関係だったとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), it was stated `he was close to someone from the Kodama party, Musashi Province&apos;, which indicated that he was close to someone from the Kodama party.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), it was stated `he was close to someone from the Kodama party in Musashi Province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuma Kagami stated that &apos;he was close to someone from the Kodama Party in Musashi Province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>党の誰を指しているのかは不明だが、次の項には、児玉党本宗家5代目である庄家長が出てくる（この事から庄氏の誰かと思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was unknown who from the Kodama party was referred, and in the next section, the fifth generation of the head family of the Kodama party, Ienaga SHO appeared (from this, it is assumed it was someone from the Sho clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was unknown as to who it was from the Kodama party that was being referred to, and in the next section, the fifth generation of the head family of the Kodama party, Ienaga SHO appeared (from this, it is assumed it was someone from the Sho clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was unknown as to who it was from the Kodama party that was being referred to, and in the next section, the fifth generation of the head family of the Kodama party, Ienaga SHO appeared (from this, it is assumed it was someone from the Sho clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>『平家物語』における最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last described in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was last described in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His death described in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>以下に『平家物語』巻第九「樋口被斬」における樋口兼光の最期の様子を記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the last scene of Kanemitsu HIGUCHI in the ninth roll of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;, `Higuchi no kirare&apos; (The Execution of Higuchi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the last scene of Kanemitsu HIGUCHI in the ninth roll of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;, `Higuchi no kirare&apos; (The Execution of Higuchi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the last scene of Kanemitsu HIGUCHI in the ninth roll &apos;Higuchi no kirare&apos; (The Execution of Higuchi) of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>樋口は源行家を紀伊国名草に向かっていたが、都に戦ありと聞いて取って返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIGUCHI was leaving for Nakusa, Kii Province, but came back after he heard there was a battle in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「源行家を」の部分の文意が不明なため訳出しておりません。一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIGUCHI was leaving for Nakusa, Kii Province, but came back after he heard there was a battle in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIGUCHI was leaving for Nakusa, Kii Province, to put down MINAMOTO no Yukiie, but came back when he heard a battle broke out in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大渡の橋で今井兼平の下人に会い、木曾義仲も兼平も既にこの世にないことを知った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He met a jigenin (a lower rank of ancient Japanese nobility) of Kanehira IMAI on the Owatari no hashi Bridge, and learned Yoshinaka KISO and Kanehira were already dead.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He met a jigenin (a lower rank of ancient Japanese nobility) of Kanehira IMAI on the Owatari no hashi Bridge, and learned that Yoshinaka KISO and Kanehira were already dead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He met a servant of Kanehira IMAI on the Owatari Bridge and learned that Yoshinaka KISO and Kanehira were already dead.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>樋口は涙を流し、「これを聞きたまえ方々、主君に志を思い参らす人々は、これより早くいづこへも落ち行き、いかような仏道修行をもして、主君の菩提を弔いたまえ。兼光は都へ上り討ち死にし、冥途でも主君に面謁し、今井をももう一度みたいと思うためである」と述べて都へ上った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIGUCHI said in tears, `Those of you who heard this, who missed him as a lord, immediately go and settle in somewhere and pray for him to rest in peace whatever training you could do for him as a Buddhist. Kanemitsu will go up to Kyoto and die for the battle to meet your lord in the heaven, seeing IMAI is my wish.&apos;, and then he went up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIGUCHI said in tears, `Those of you who heard this, who missed him as a lord, immediately go and settle in somewhere and pray for him to rest in peace whatever you can do for him being trained as a Buddhist. Kanemitsu will go to Kyoto and die in battle to meet your lord in the heaven, seeing IMAI is my wish,&apos; and then he went to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIGUCHI said in tears, &apos;Those of you who heard this, who missed him as a lord, immediately go and settle in somewhere and pray for him to rest in peace by taking whatever hard Buddhist training you can. I will go to Kyoto and die in battle to meet my lord in the heaven, seeing my lord is my wish,&apos; and then he went to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>鳥羽離宮の南の門を過ぎるときに、その勢はわずか二十余騎になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he passed through the south gate of Toba Rikyu (Toba Imperial Villa), his force declined to only a little over twenty solders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he passed through the south gate of Toba Rikyu (Toba Imperial Villa), his force reduced to only a little over twenty solders.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he passed through the south gate of the Toba Imperial Villa, his force reduced to only a little over twenty solders.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後、何とか命ばかりは助けようと考える児玉党の説得に応じ、児玉党に降った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, he was persuaded by the Kodama Party that desperately wanted to save his life, and he decided to follow the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt>「児玉党に降った」は「児玉党に従った」と考え訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, he was persuaded by the Kodama Party who desperately wanted to save his life, and he decided to follow the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, he was persuaded by the Kodama Party who desperately wanted to save his life, and decided to follow the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>源範頼と義経は院に伺いをたてたところ、院中の公卿、局の女房、女童までも「木曾が法性寺を焼き滅ぼし、多くの高僧が亡くなったのは今井と樋口によるものであり、これを助けることは口惜しい」と述べたため死罪が決まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Noriyori, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune asked In if HIGUCHI could be saved, but court nobles in the palace, even nyobo (a court lady) and girls that worked in palace room said `It is impossible to save Higuchi because IMAI and HIGUCHI burnt out Hossho-ji Temple, which killed many high priests,&apos; thus he was proclaimed as a death sentence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Noriyori, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune asked In if HIGUCHI could be saved, but the court nobles in the palace, even nyobo (a court lady) and girls that worked in palace room said `It is impossible to save Higuchi because IMAI and HIGUCHI burnt down Hossho-ji Temple, and killed many high priests,&apos; thus he was given the death sentence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune asked the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa whether HIGUCHI could be saved, but the court nobles in the palace, even court ladies and girls that worked in palace room said, &apos;It is impossible to save HIGUCHI because IMAI and HIGUCHI burnt down Hossho-ji Temple and killed many high priests,&apos; thus he was given the death sentence.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>義仲と他五人の首が大路を渡される際、供をつとめることを頻りに申し出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshinaka and other five&apos;s heads were exposed in a street, HIGUCHI persistently offered to accompany them.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処「大路を渡される」→「大路にさらされる」と考えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshinaka and the other five&apos;s heads were exposed on the street, HIGUCHI persistently offered to accompany them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the heads of Yoshinaka and the other five were exposed on the street, HIGUCHI persistently offered to accompany them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>藍摺の直垂と立烏帽子の姿で従い、その次の日に斬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was with them in the indigo navy hitatare (a kind of court dress in old days) and in a tateeboshi (formal headwear with a peak for court nobles), and on the following day he was beheaded.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was with them in the indigo navy hitatare (a kind of court dress in old days) and in a tateeboshi (formal headwear with a peak for court nobles), and on the following day he was beheaded.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was with them in the indigo navy court dress and in a formal headwear with a peak for court nobles, and on the following day he was beheaded.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For your information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For your information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>後世、安土桃山時代に上杉家の謀臣として活躍した直江兼続は、兼光の子孫とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetsugu NAOE who was active as a tactful vassal of the Uesugi family in the Azuchi-Momoyama Period is said to be a descendant of Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetsugu NAOE who was active as a tactful vassal of the Uesugi family in the Azuchi-Momoyama Period is said to be a descendant of Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetsugu NAOE, who was active as a tactful vassal of the Uesugi family in the Azuchi-Momoyama period, is said to be a descendant of Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Suguri F(id:11127), 由布(id:209183), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 味っ子(id:17086), Cpro(id:28341), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>