<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原光子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mitsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 光子（ふじわら の みつこ、康平3年（1060年） - 保安 (元号)2年4月16日 (旧暦)（1121年5月4日））は、平安時代後期の女官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuko (1060 - May 4, 1121) was a court lady in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mitsuko (1060 - May 4, 1121) was a court lady in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuko (1060 - May 11, 1121) was a court lady in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>period. 小文字にしました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>但馬国守藤原隆方の娘で、藤原為房の姉妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of Tajima no kuni no kami (governor of Tajima Province) FUJIWARA no Takakata and a sister of FUJIWARA no Tamefusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daughter of Tajima no kuni no kami (Governor of Tajima Province) FUJIWARA no Takakata and a sister of FUJIWARA no Tamefusa.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of Tajima no kuni no kami (Governor of Tajima Province) FUJIWARA no Takakata and a sister of FUJIWARA no Tamefusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原公実の側妾となり、藤原通季、僧仁実、藤原実能、僧覚源、藤原公子、藤原実子、藤原璋子（待賢門院）をはじめ8人の子女を産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She became a mistress of FUJIWARA no Kinzane and gave birth to 8 children including FUJIWARA no Michisue, 僧仁実, FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, 僧覚源, FUJIWARA no Koshi, FUJIWARA no Jisshi, and FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Tai ken mon in).</e>
<cmt>「僧仁実」「僧覚源」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She became a mistress of FUJIWARA no Kinzane and gave birth to 8 children including FUJIWARA no Michisue, 僧仁実, FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, 僧覚源, FUJIWARA no Koshi, FUJIWARA no Jisshi, and FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Tai ken mon in).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She became a mistress of FUJIWARA no Kinzane and gave birth to 8 children including FUJIWARA no Michisue, Buddhist monk Ninjitsu, FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, Buddhist monk Kakugen, FUJIWARA no Koshi, FUJIWARA no Jisshi, and FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Taikenmonin).</e>
<cmt>Buddhist monk Ninjitsu, Buddhist monk Kakugen としました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>堀河天皇、鳥羽天皇の乳母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) of Emperor Horikawa and Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the menoto (woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) of Emperor Horikawa and Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the menoto (woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) of Emperor Horikawa and Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>寛治元年（1087年）、堀河天皇の乳母として典侍となり「中納言典侍」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in 1087, she became Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) as the menoto of Emperor Horikawa and was called Chunagon Naishi no suke (Secretary of middle councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">in 1087, she became Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) as the menoto of Emperor Horikawa and was called Chunagon Naishi no suke (Secretary and Middle Councilor).</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1087, she became Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) as the menoto of Emperor Horikawa and was called Chunagon Naishi no suke (Secretary and Middle Councilor).</e>
<cmt>文頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>康和4年（1102年）、従三位に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1102, she was appointed to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1102, she was appointed to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1102, she was appointed to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「弁三位」と呼ばれたのは、父隆方が弁官であったためと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was called &apos;Ben no sanmi,&apos; which may be because he father Takakata was benkan (official of the dajokan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was called &apos;Ben no sanmi,&apos; which may be because her father Takakata was benkan (an official of the Dajokan).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was called &apos;Ben no sanmi,&apos; which may be because her father Takakata was benkan (an official of the Dajokan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌5年1月、鳥羽天皇の乳母を兼任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In between February and March 1103, she also served as a menoto of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between February and March 1103, she also served as a menoto of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between February and March 1103, she also served as a menoto of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天仁元年（1108年）正三位に叙任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1108, she was appointed to shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1108, she was appointed Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1108, she was appointed Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>娘の実子が翌年正式に乳母となると、母の光子は大蔵三位と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When her daughter Jisshi officially became menoto next year, Mitsuko, as the mother, was called 大蔵三位.</e>
<cmt>「大蔵三位」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When her daughter Jisshi officially became menoto the following year, Mitsuko, as the mother, was called 大蔵三位.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When her daughter Jisshi officially became menoto the following year, Mitsuko, as the mother, was called Okura Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>大蔵三位 Okura Sanmi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天永3年（1112年）従二位に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1112, she was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1112, she was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1112, she was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>堀河・鳥羽両天皇の乳母として政界に隠然たる力を持ち、保安2年4月16日、62歳で薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As menoto of Emperor Horikawa and Emperor Toba, she had latent powers in the political world, but in May 11, 1121, deceased at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As menoto of Emperor Horikawa and Emperor Toba, she had latent powers in the political world, however on May 11 1121, she died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As menoto of Emperor Horikawa and Emperor Toba, she had latent powers in the political world, however on May 11 1121, she died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 YOSHI438(id:174755), Andee(id:20421), ウィキワッチー(id:224408), Snap55(id:89773), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>