<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原家政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Iemasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Iemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Iemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 家政（ふじわら の いえまさ、承暦4年（1080年） - 永久 (元号)3年4月8日 (旧暦)（1115年年5月3日））は平安時代末期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Iemasa (1080 - May 3, 1115) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived towards the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Iemasa (1080 - May 3, 1115) was a kugyo (top court official) during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Iemasa (1080 - May 10, 1115) was a kugyo (court noble) during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>関白藤原師通の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Moromichi, Kanpaku (the top adviser to the emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Moromichi, Kanpaku (the top adviser to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Moromichi, Kanpaku (the top adviser to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>異母兄弟に関白藤原忠実、左京大夫藤原家隆 (左京大夫)らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadazane, Kanpaku, and FUJIWARA no Ietaka, Sakyo no daibu (the master of the eastern capital offices), were his brothers from a mother different from his.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadazane, Kanpaku, and FUJIWARA no Ietaka, Sakyo no daibu (the master of the eastern capital offices), were his brothers from a mother different from his.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadazane, Kanpaku, and FUJIWARA no Ietaka, Sakyo no daibu (the master of the eastern capital offices), were his paternal half-brothers.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正三位・参議・左中将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Sangi (a councilor) and Sachujo (a middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards) at the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Sangi (councilor) and Sachujo (middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards) at the rank of Shosanmi (Senior 3rd Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Sangi (councilor) and Sachujo (middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards) at the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>三条悪宰相と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called himself Sanjoakusaisho (literally, a bad Sangi at Sanjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Sanjoakusaisho (literally, a bad Sangi at Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Sanjoakusaisho (literally, a bad Sangi at Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>寛治2年（1088年）に従五位下に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1088, he was awarded Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1088, he was awarded Jugoinoge (Junior 5th Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1088, he was awarded Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同8年（1094年）侍従となり、同年昇殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1094, he became jiju (a chamberlain), and was admitted to the court in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1094, he became jiju (chamberlain), and was admitted to the court in the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1094, he became jiju (chamberlain), and was admitted to the court in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>承徳2年（1098年）左中将、康和4年（1102年）参議、従三位と進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Sachujo (a middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards) in 1098, and advanced to Sangi (a councilor) at Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Sachujo (middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards) in 1098, and advanced to Sangi (councilor) at Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Sachujo (middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards) in 1098, and advanced to Sangi (councilor) at Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>永久元年（1113年）に正三位に至るが、2年後の同3年に36歳にして早世した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he was further promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1113, but died young in two years later, at the age of 36.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he was further promoted to Shosanmi (Senior 3rd Rank) in 1113, but died young two years later, at the age of thirty-six.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he was further promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1113, but died young two years later, at the age of thirty-six.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>父が早く他界した後は、祖父の藤原師実に養われていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, after his father died young, he was brought up by his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Morosane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, after his father died young, he was brought up by his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Morosane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, after his father died young, he was brought up by his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Morosane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『富家語』第138条には、師実が外出から戻った際にその足を洗う役目を、少年期の家政が務めていたことが語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described in the 138th section of &quot;Fukego&quot; (a collection of sayings of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu) that it was young Iemasa&apos;s role to clean Morosane&apos;s feet and legs when Morosane returned to his home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described in the 138th section of &quot;Fukego&quot; (a collection of sayings of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu) that it was young Iemasa&apos;s role to clean Morosane&apos;s feet and legs when Morosane returned to his home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described in the 138th section of &quot;Fukego&quot; (a collection of sayings of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu) that it was young Iemasa&apos;s role to clean Morosane&apos;s feet and legs when Morosane returned to his home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、粗暴で作法に疎かったとされ、『中右記』（嘉承元年正月7日条）には、その勅使から酒を賜った際の作法の誤りの酷さに非難を受けたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he acted rudely and was unfamiliar with etiquette, and it is described in &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (a diary written by FUJIWARA no Munetada) (in the section for February 19, 1106) that, when he was served with sake wine by an Imperial envoy, he behaved seriously disregarding the etiquette and was accused of the behavior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he acted rudely and was unfamiliar with etiquette, and it is described in &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (a diary written by FUJIWARA no Munetada) (in the section for February 19, 1106) that, when he was served with sake wine by an Imperial envoy, he behaved seriously disregarding the etiquette and was accused of bad behavior.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he acted rudely and was unfamiliar with etiquette, and it is described in &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (The Diary written by FUJIWARA no Munetada) (in the section for February 19, 1106) that, when he was served with sake wine by an Imperial envoy, he behaved seriously disregarding the etiquette and was accused of bad behavior.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>その子孫は室町家・法性寺家を称したが、室町時代に断絶している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants called their families as a Muromachi family or Hosshoji family, but their lines became extinct in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants called their families the Muromachi family or Hosshoji family, but their lines became extinct during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants called their families the Muromachi family or Hosshoji family, but their lines became extinct during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>