<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>久我建通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takemichi KOGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takemichi KOGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takemichi KOGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>久我 建通（こが たけみち、文化 (元号)12年2月1日 (旧暦)（1815年3月11日） - 明治36年（1903年）9月26日）は、江戸時代の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takemichi KOGA (March 11, 1815-September 26, 1903) was the kuge (aristocrat) of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takemichi KOGA (March 11, 1815-September 26, 1903) was an aristocrat of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takemichi KOGA (March 11, 1815 - September 26, 1903) was an aristocrat of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一条忠良の子、母は細川富子（細川斉茲の娘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the child of Tadayoshi ICHIJO, and his mother was Tomiko HOSOKAWA (the daughter of Narishige HOSOKAWA (also pronounced as Tatsuhiro)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Tadayoshi ICHIJO, and his mother was Tomiko HOSOKAWA (the daughter of Narishige HOSOKAWA, also pronounced as Tatsuhiro).</e>
<cmt>nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Tadayoshi ICHIJO, and his mother was Tomiko HOSOKAWA (the daughter of Narishige HOSOKAWA, also pronounced as Tatsuhiro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>久我通明の養子、養母は細川就（細川治年の娘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the adopted child of Michiaki KOGA, and his foster mother being Shu HOSOKAWA (the daughter of Harutoshi HOSOKAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the adopted child of Michiaki KOGA, and his foster mother was Shu HOSOKAWA (the daughter of Harutoshi HOSOKAWA).</e>
<cmt>being-&gt;was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the adopted child of Michiaki KOGA, and his foster mother was Shu HOSOKAWA (the daughter of Harutoshi HOSOKAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>室は鷹司麗子（鷹司政通の娘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legal wife was Reiko TAKATSUKASA (the daughter of Masamichi TAKATSUKASA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal wife was Reiko TAKATSUKASA (the daughter of Masamichi TAKATSUKASA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wife was Reiko TAKATSUKASA (the daughter of Masamichi TAKATSUKASA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に久我通久、愛宕通旭、北畠通城、通子（前田慶寧継室）、幸子（松平茂昭継室）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Michitsune KOGA, Michiteru OTAGI, Michishiro KITABATAKE, Michiko (keishitsu (second wife) of Yashiyasu MAEDA), Yukiko (keishitsu of Mochiaki MATSUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Michitsune KOGA, Michiteru OTAGI, Michishiro KITABATAKE, Michiko (second wife of Yashiyasu MAEDA), Yukiko (second wife of Mochiaki MATSUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Michitsune KOGA, Michiteru OTAGI, Michishiro KITABATAKE, Michiko (second wife of Yashiyasu MAEDA), Yukiko (second wife of Mochiaki MATSUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>翠君、素堂と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also referred as 翠君 and Sodo.</e>
<cmt>翠君、読み不明 [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also referred as 翠君 and Sodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also referred as Suikun and Sodo.</e>
<cmt>翠君→Suikunとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>京都で誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>文政5年（1822年）叙爵、文政9年（1826年）従三位、天保5年（1834年）正二位、嘉永5年（1852年）大納言と昇進を重ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received the josaku (conferring the peerage) in 1822, Jusanmi Rank (Junior Third Rank) in 1826, Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1834, and promoted to Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 1852.</e>
<cmt>文政9年（1856年）となってましたが、実際には1826年です。訂正させて頂きました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the peerage in 1822, Jusanmi Rank (Junior Third Rank) in 1826, Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1834, and was promoted to Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 1852.</e>
<cmt>was promoted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the peerage in 1822, Jusanmi Rank (Junior Third Rank) in 1826, Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1834, and was promoted to Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 1852.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>安政元年（1854年）議奏に就任し権力を握ったため、“権関白”と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a strong governmental power after being assigned to be giso (a position conveying what the congress decide to the emperor) in 1854 that he was referred as &quot;Gon Kanpaku&quot; (provisional chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held strong governmental power after being assigned to be giso (a messenger conveying the decisions of congress to the emperor) in 1854, and was referred as &quot;Gon Kanpaku&quot; (provisional chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held strong governmental power after being assigned to be giso (a messenger conveying the decisions of congress to the emperor) in 1854, and was referred as &quot;Gon Kanpaku&quot; (provisional chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>以後は朝幕間の調停に努め、条約勅許問題、和宮親子内親王降嫁問題などに関係した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served to negotiate between the bakufu (government by shogunate) and imperial court and took part in solving issues of imperial sanction and Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako Koka (marriage of an Imperial princess to a subject).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served to negotiate between the shogunate and the imperial court, and took part in solving issues of imperial sanction and the marriage of Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako to a commoner.</e>
<cmt>removed parenthetical asides</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served to negotiate between the shogunate and the imperial court, and took part in solving issues of imperial sanction and the marriage of Imperial Princess Kazunomiya Chikako to a commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>なお明治時代になってから建通は、廷臣八十八卿列参事件は自分が中心的役割を果たしたと証言しているが（孝明天皇紀）、「岩倉公実記」は中心は岩倉具視としており、解決をみない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takemichi claimed that he participated as the central figure in Teishin hachiju-hachi kyo ressan jiken (Demo of eighty-eight retainers of Imperial Court) when entering Meiji Era (the empress of Emperor Komei) but &quot;Diary of Kimizane IWAKURA&quot; stated Tomomi IWAKURA instead and uncertainties remain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takemichi claimed that he was the central figure in Demonstration of Eighty-eight Imperial Court Retainers at the start of the Meiji Era (the empress of Emperor Komei) but the &quot;Diary of Kimizane IWAKURA&quot; pointed to Tomomi IWAKURA instead and uncertainties remain.</e>
<cmt>participated as-&gt;was; when entering-&gt;at the start of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takemichi claimed that he was the central figure in Demonstration of Eighty-eight Imperial Court Retainers at the start of the Meiji era (the empress of Emperor Komei) but the &apos;Diary of Kimizane IWAKURA&apos; pointed to Tomomi IWAKURA instead and uncertainties remain.</e>
<cmt>era小文字にしました。原文に合せて&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>孝明天皇紀また安政5年（1858年）近衛大将、文久2年（1862年）内大臣、国事御用掛など要職を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also served important duties such as Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards) for Empress of Emperor Komei in 1858, naidaijin (Minister of Center) and Kokuji goyogakari (a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of the State affair) in 1862.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also filled important roles such as Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards) for the Empress of Emperor Komei in 1858, naidaijin (Minister of Center) and Kokuji goyogakari (a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of the State affair) in 1862.</e>
<cmt>served duties-&gt;filled roles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also filled important roles such as Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards) for the Empress of Emperor Komei in 1858, naidaijin (Minister of Center) and Kokuji goyogakari (a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of the State affair) in 1862.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし攘夷派に恨まれ、間もなく弾劾を受けて失脚、蟄居落飾処分となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was envied by the side that demanded expulsion of foreigners, demoted after impeachment that occurred soon after, and underwent house arrest and rakushoku (to take the tonsure and enter the priesthood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was envied by the side that demanded expulsion of foreigners, demoted after impeachment that occurred soon after, and underwent house arrest and entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>rakushoku... -&gt;entered the priesthood</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was envied by the side that demanded expulsion of foreigners, demoted after impeachment that occurred soon after, and underwent house arrest and entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>明治元年（1868年）赦免され、宮内省麝香間祇候や賀茂神社司、大教正などをつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was pardoned in 1868 and served as Jako no ma shiko (entitlement to the meritorious deeds for the Imperial restoration or noble) of the Imperial Household Ministry, official of Kamo jinja shrine, and Daikyosei (highest rank of a certain ministry at the beginning of Meiji Era that managed Japanese religious sects).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was pardoned in 1868 and served as Jako no ma shiko (entitlement to the meritorious deeds for the Imperial restoration or noble) of the Imperial Household Ministry, official of Kamo jinja shrine, and Daikyosei (minister over religions at the beginning of the Meiji Era).</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t like the “entitlement to.....” bit, but I don&apos;t know what to do with it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was pardoned in 1868 and served as Jako no ma shiko (entitlement to the meritorious deeds for the Imperial restoration or noble) of the Imperial Household Ministry, official of Kamo-jinja Shrine, and Daikyosei (minister over religions at the beginning of the Meiji era).</e>
<cmt>Kamo-jinja Shrineに訂正しました。era小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明治22年（1889年）従一位勲一等に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was rewarded with the jo rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and the First Order of Merit in 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was rewarded with the jo rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and the First Order of Merit in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was rewarded with the jo rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and the First Order of Merit in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 松茸(id:27535), Hat2867(id:67840), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>