<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鮫島重雄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeo SAMEJIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeo SAMEJIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeo SAMEJIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鮫島 重雄（さめじま しげお、嘉永2年9月6日 (旧暦)（1849年10月21日） - 昭和3年（1928年）4月17日）は、日本の大日本帝国陸軍軍人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeo SAMEJIMA (October 21, 1849 - April 17, 1928) was a military man of Imperial Japanese Army (IJA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeo SAMEJIMA (October 21, 1849 - April 17, 1928) was a military man of Imperial Japanese Army (IJA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeo SAMEJIMA (October 21, 1849 - April 17, 1928) was a military man of Imperial Japanese Army (IJA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>陸軍大将位階勲等金鵄勲章男爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Army General, Ranks and Orders, the Order of the Golden Kite, Baron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last official rank was army general and he was given the medal of the Golden Kite (according to Japanese Ranks and Orders) and the title of baron.</e>
<cmt>原文の日本語が通じないのでそのまま並べて訳すと通じません。わかりやすく直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His last official rank was army general and he was given the medal of the Golden Kite (according to Japanese Ranks and Orders) and the title of baron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>薩摩藩鮫島藤兵衛の次男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born as the second-born son of Tobei SAMEJIMA in Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the second son of Tobei SAMEJIMA in the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一させます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Tobei SAMEJIMA in the Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>御親兵として陸軍入り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joined the army as Goshimpei (army to convoy the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined the army as Goshinpei (a member of one of the Imperial Guards).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。この場合「ん」は「n」で大丈夫です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined the army as Goshinpei (a member of one of the Imperial Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1月から陸軍教導団に入営し、同6月伍長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he joined the Imperial Army&apos;s school, and in June, assumed office as Corporal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he entered the army Kyododan (school for noncommissioned officers); and in June, he became corporal.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。「教導団」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he entered the army Kyododan (school for noncommissioned officers); and in June, he became corporal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>3月陸軍士官学校 (日本)生徒、同9年陸軍少尉試補・東京鎮台附。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he joined the Military Academy, and in September, he was appointed as Probationary Second Lieutenant of Army to be stationed at Chinidai (garrison) in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he entered the Military Academy (Japan); and in September, he was appointed probationary second lieutenant of the Army to be stationed at Tokyo Chindai (standing garrison).</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一させます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he entered the Military Academy (Japan); and in September, he was appointed probationary second lieutenant of the Army to be stationed at Tokyo Chindai (standing garrison).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>台湾出兵に際して台湾蕃地征討軍に編入される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was incorporated to seitogun (expeditionary force) for Taiwan Banchi (the land where savages were living).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Expedition to Taiwan, he was transferred to Taiwan Banchi Seitogun (the expeditionary force to the unexplored territory of Taiwan).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ、訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Expedition to Taiwan, he was transferred to Taiwan Banchi Seitogun (the expeditionary force to the unexplored territory of Taiwan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>3月、陸軍工兵少尉に任官、2月から西南戦争に出征する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he was appointed as Second Lieutenant of Military Engineer, and in February, departed for the front of Seinan War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he was appointed second lieutenant of the army engineers; and in February, he departed for the front of the Seinan War (the Satsuma Rebellion in present Kagoshima Prefecture, Japan).</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一させます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he was appointed second lieutenant of the army engineers; and in February, he departed for the front of the Seinan War (the Satsuma Rebellion in present Kagoshima Prefecture, Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>4月に工兵中尉に進んで第1旅団参謀を命ぜられるが、同10月帰還する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, he moved on to Lieutenant of Military Engineer to be appointed as Staff Officer of the 1st Brigade, but in October, he returned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, he was raised to lieutenant of the army engineers and appointed staff officer of the First Brigade; however in October, he returned to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, he was raised to lieutenant of the army engineers and appointed staff officer of the First Brigade; however in October, he returned to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>2月から工兵第1大隊中隊に移り、3月参謀本部管西局員、4月工兵大尉、2月には近衛師団参謀を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, he joined the Company of the 1st Engineers Batallion, in March, a staff of Kansei Office in Staff Headquarters, in April, the Captain of Engineers and in February, a Staff Officer of Imperial Guard Division.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, he was assigned to the company of the first battalion of the army engineers; in March, he became staff of Kansei Office (the office in charge of overseeing the west) of the General Staff Office; in April, he was promoted to captain of the army engineers; and in February, he was appointed staff officer of the Imperial Guard Division.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス、訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, he was assigned to the company of the first battalion of the army engineers; in March, he became staff of Kansei Office (the office in charge of overseeing the west) of the General Staff Office; in April, he was promoted to captain of the army engineers; and in February, he was appointed staff officer of the Imperial Guard Division.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>7月に工兵第3大隊長心得、3月陸軍大学校副幹事心得を経、同5月工兵少佐に進んで陸軍大学校副幹事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Chief of the 3rd Batallion of Engineers in July and the acting vice-secretary general of Rikugun Daigakko (the Army War College) in March, he moved on to Major of Engineers in May to be a vice-secretary general of Rikugun Daigakko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became deputy commander of the third battalion of the army engineers in July, and became deputy vice-secretary of Army War College in March; in March of the same year, he was raised to major of the army engineers and became vice-secretary of Army War College.</e>
<cmt>誤訳、スペルミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became deputy commander of the third battalion of the army engineers in July, and became deputy vice-secretary of Army War College in March; in March of the same year, he was raised to major of the army engineers and became vice-secretary of Army War College.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>6月監軍部参謀。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, a Staff Officer of Kangunbu (an organization of Japanese Army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he became staff officer of the Army Supervision Department.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he became staff officer of the Army Supervision Department.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>近衛師団参謀を経て、6月18日工兵大佐・近衛師団参謀長に進んで4月から日清戦争に出征する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Staff Officer of Imperial Guard Division, he moved on to Colonel of Engineers and Chief Staff Officer of Imperial Guard Division on June 18, then he departed for the front of Sino-Japanese War in April.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving as staff officer of the Imperial Guard Division, on June 18, he was promoted to colonel of the army engineers and chief of staff of the Imperial Guard Division; and in April, he departed for the front of the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一させます。日清戦争にはtheがつくのが普通のようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving as staff officer of the Imperial Guard Division, on June 18, he was promoted to colonel of the army engineers and chief of staff of the Imperial Guard Division; and in April, he departed for the front of the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>日清戦後は中部都督部参謀長、9月28日には陸軍少将に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sino-Japanese War, he was appointed as the Chief Staff Officer of Chubu Totokubu (an organization of Japanese Army in charge of military planning and education, &apos;Chubu&apos; is one of the divided areas), and on September 28, as Army Major General.</e>
<cmt>http://wapedia.mobi/ja/%E9%83%BD%E7%9D%A3%E9%83%A8</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Sino-Japanese War, he was appointed chief of staff of the Chubu Division; and on September 28, he was appointed major general of the Army.</e>
<cmt>スタイル統一します。翻訳者が紹介する「都督部」の説明は普通の部署でも行われていることです。この場合普通の訳divisionで大丈夫です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Sino-Japanese War, he was appointed chief of staff of the Chubu Division; and on September 28, he was appointed major general of the Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>4月25日に由良要塞司令官に就任し、5月5日東京湾要塞司令官に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 25, he assumed office as Commandor of Yura Fortress, and May 5, transferred to Tokyo Bay Fortress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 25, he became commander of Yura Fortress; and on May 5, he was transferred to Tokyo Bay Fortress as commander.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一させます。スペルミス、訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 25, he became commander of Yura Fortress; and on May 5, he was transferred to Tokyo Bay Fortress as commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>9月5日に陸軍中将として大本営附を命ぜられて同10月日露戦争に出征する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 5, he was order to be attendant on the Imperial headquarters as Lieutenant General, and on October, daparted for the front of Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>「同10月日露戦争」の日にちが抜けています。WEB上も同様です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 5, he was appointed lieutenant general of the Army and assigned to the Imperial Headquarters; and in October of the same year, he departed for the front of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ（勘違い）があります。スタイルを統一させます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 5, he was appointed lieutenant general of the Army and assigned to the Imperial Headquarters; and in October of the same year, he departed for the front of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>戦中の12月1日第11師団 (日本軍)長を拝命し、4月1日勲一等旭日大綬章を受章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 1 in the wartime, he was appointed as Chief of the 11th Division (Japanese Army), and on April 1, received Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the war, on December 1, he was appointed chief of the 11th Division (Japanese Army); and on April 1, he received the first grade Grand Cordon of the Rising Sun.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war, on December 1, he was appointed chief of the 11th Division (Japanese Army); and on April 1, he received the first grade Grand Cordon of the Rising Sun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同7月6日第14師団 (日本軍)長に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 6, he was appointed as Chief of the 14th Division (Japanese Army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 6 of the same year, he was appointed chief of the 14th Division (Japanese Army).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 6 of the same year, he was appointed chief of the 14th Division (Japanese Army).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>9月21日、日清・日露戦役の軍功により男爵を授爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 21, he was given the title of baron for his achievement in Sino-Japanese War and Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 21, he was given the title of baron for his achievement in the Sino-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 21, he was given the title of baron for his achievement in the Sino-Japanese War and the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>9月6日、陸軍大将昇任と共に後備役編入となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 6, he was incorporated to Kobieki (one of military service that came after Geneki and Yobieki) accompagnied by the promotion to Army General.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 6, he was promoted to army general and at the same time he was transferred to reserve.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 6, he was promoted to army general and at the same time he was transferred to reserve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一させます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>重雄に後継者はなく、爵位は継承されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeo never had a heir, so his title could not be succeeded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeo never had a heir, so his title could not be succeeded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeo never had a heir, so his title could not be succeeded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>