<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>静御前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka Gozen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka Gozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka Gozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>静御前（しずかごぜん、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期、鎌倉時代初期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka Gozen (dates of birth and death unknown) is a women who lived at the end of the Heian Period and the initial part of the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka Gozen (dates of birth and death unknown) was a women who lived at the end of the Heian Period and the initial part of the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka Gozen (dates of birth and death unknown) was a women who lived at the end of the Heian period and the initial part of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>白拍子（遊女）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a shirabyoshi (dancer prostitute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a shirabyoshi (dancer prostitute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a shirabyoshi (dancer prostitute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は白拍子の磯禅師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was also a shirabyoshi named Iso no Zenji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother, Iso no Zenji, was also a shirabyoshi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother, Iso no Zenji, was also a shirabyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>源義経の愛妾。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beloved concubine of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune</e>
<cmt>愛妾ですが、(beloved) concubine としました。普通は「側室」と訳されますが、「めかけ」の意味で mistress とか、そういった単語を使うのは不釣り合いだと思いますので、「妻以外のきちんとした愛する女性」という意味で concubine にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beloved concubine of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beloved concubine of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>治承・寿永の乱後、兄の源頼朝と対立した義経が京を落ちて九州へ向かう際に同行するが、義経の船団は嵐に遭難して岸へ戻される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitsune, who had a conflict with his half-brother MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, left Kyoto and headed for Kyushu after the end of the Jisho Juei Rebellion, Shizuka Gozen also accompanied him, but his fleet was forced back to the shore by a storm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitsune, who had a conflict with his half-brother MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, left Kyoto and headed for Kyushu after the end of the Jisho Juei Rebellion, Shizuka Gozen also accompanied him, but his fleet was forced back to the shore by a storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitsune, who had a conflict with his half-brother MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, left Kyoto and headed for Kyushu after the end of the Jisho Juei Rebellion, Shizuka Gozen also accompanied him, but his fleet was forced back to the shore by a storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>吉野で義経と別れ京へ戻るが、途中で従者に持ち物を奪われ山中をさまよった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She parted from Yoshitsune in the mountains of Yoshino and decided to return to Kyoto, but since the attendants assigned to guard Shizuka stole all her belongings and abandoned her in the mountains, she didn&apos;t know which way to go and wandered astray in the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She parted from Yoshitsune in the mountains of Yoshino and decided to return to Kyoto, but since the attendants assigned to guard Shizuka stole all her belongings and abandoned her in the mountains, she didn&apos;t know which way to go and wandered astray in the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She parted from Yoshitsune in the mountains of Yoshino and decided to return to Kyoto, but since the attendants assigned to guard Shizuka stole all her belongings and abandoned her in the mountains, she didn&apos;t know which way to go and wandered astray in the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため山僧に捕らえられ京の北条時政に引き渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mountain priests, who were hunting for her, found Shizuka, arrested her for delivery to Tokimasa HOJO who was stationed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mountain priests, who were hunting for her, found Shizuka, and arrested her for delivery to Tokimasa HOJO, who was stationed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mountain priests, who were hunting for her, found Shizuka, and arrested her for delivery to Tokimasa HOJO, who was stationed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして文治2年（1186年）3月に母の磯禅師とともに鎌倉に送られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was then sent to Kamakura together with her mother Iso no Zenji in March 1186.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was then sent to Kamakura, together with her mother Iso no Zenji, in March 1186.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was then sent to Kamakura, together with her mother Iso no Zenji, in March 1186.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>同年4月8日、静は頼朝に鶴岡八幡宮社前で白拍子の舞を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was ordered to perform a shirabyoshi dance in front of the Tsurugaoka-hachimangu Shrine on April 8 in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was ordered to perform a shirabyoshi dance in front of the Tsurugaoka-hachimangu Shrine on April 8 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was ordered to perform a shirabyoshi dance in front of the Tsurugaoka-hachimangu Shrine on May 5 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>静は、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka sang a song of longing for Yoshitsune:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka sang a song of longing for Yoshitsune:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka sang a song of longing for Yoshitsune:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>「しづやしづ しづのをだまき くり返し 昔を今に なすよしもがな」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I remember my sweetheart call my name again and again. I wish I would go back those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I remember my sweetheart call my name again and again. I wish I would go back those days.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I remember my sweetheart call my name again and again. I wish I would go back those days.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「吉野山 峰の白雪 ふみわけて 入りにし人の 跡ぞ恋しき」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">My sweetheart went into deep snow in Mount Yoshino. I miss him so much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">My sweetheart went into deep snow in Mount Yoshino. I miss him so much.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;My sweetheart went into deep snow in Mount Yoshino. I miss him so much.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>と義経を慕う歌を唄い、頼朝を激怒させるが、妻の北条政子が「私が御前の立場であっても、あの様に謡うでしょう」と取り成して命を助けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That made Yoritomo extremely angry, but his wife Masako HOJO supported the feelings of Shizuka by saying &quot;If I were she, I would have sung a song in the same way&quot; and spared her life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That made Yoritomo extremely angry, but his wife, Masako HOJO, supported the feelings of Shizuka by saying, &quot;If I were she, I would have sung a song in the same way&quot; and spared her life.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That made Yoritomo extremely angry, but his wife, Masako HOJO, supported the feelings of Shizuka by saying, &quot;If I were she, I would have sung a song in the same way&quot; and spared her life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>『吾妻鏡』では、静の舞の場面を「誠にこれ社壇の壮観、梁塵（りょうじん）ほとんど動くべし、上下みな興感を催す。」と絶賛している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Azuma Kagami, a history book of the Kamakura Period, the scene of Shizuka&apos;s dancing is extolled as saying &quot;It was a splendid scene in a shrine; her performance moved everybody there.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Azuma Kagami, a history book of the Kamakura Period, the scene of Shizuka&apos;s dancing is extolled: &quot;It was a splendid scene in a shrine; her performance moved everybody there.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; a history book of the Kamakura period, the scene of Shizuka&apos;s dancing is extolled: &quot;It was a splendid scene in a shrine; her performance moved everybody there.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>この時、静は義経の子を身ごもっており、頼朝は女子なら助けるが、男子なら殺すと命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, she was pregnant with Yoshitsune&apos;s child, but Yoritomo ordered to save the baby if it is a girl but kill it if it is a boy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, she was pregnant with Yoshitsune&apos;s child, but Yoritomo ordered that the baby be saved if a girl but killedt if a boy.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, she was pregnant with Yoshitsune&apos;s child, but Yoritomo ordered that the baby be saved if a girl but killed if a boy.</e>
<cmt>killedｔスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>閏7月29日、静は男子を産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 29th of leap month July, she gave birth to a baby boy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 29th of leap month July, she gave birth to a baby boy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 21, she gave birth to a baby boy.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>安達清恒が赤子を受け取ろうとするが、静は泣き叫んで離さなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kiyotsune ADACHI was going to get the baby, Shizuka, crying in tears, wouldn&apos;t let him go.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kiyotsune ADACHI was going to get the baby, Shizuka, crying in tears, wouldn&apos;t let him go.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kiyotsune ADACHI was going to get the baby, Shizuka, crying in tears, wouldn&apos;t let him go.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>磯禅師が赤子を取り上げて清恒に渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Iso no Zenji took the baby off from her and gave him to Kiyotsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Iso no Zenji took the baby from her and gave him to Kiyotsune.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;off&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Iso no Zenji took the baby from her and gave him to Kiyotsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>赤子は由比ヶ浜に沈められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the baby boy was sunken in the water off Yuigahama beach.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the baby boy was sunken in the water off Yuigahama beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the baby boy was sunken in the water off Yuigahama beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>9月16日、静と磯禅師は京に帰された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 16, Shizuka and Iso no Zenji were allowed to return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 16, Shizuka and Iso no Zenji were allowed to return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 5, Shizuka and Iso no Zenji were allowed to return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>憐れんだ政子が多くの重宝を持たせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Masako, feeling sorry for them, gave plenty of valuables to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Masako, feeling sorry for them, gave them plenty of valuables.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Masako, feeling sorry for them, gave them plenty of valuables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>静のその後は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not know what happened to Shizuka after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known what happened to Shizuka after that.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known what happened to Shizuka after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>吾妻鏡における静御前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka Gozen in the Azuma Kagami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka Gozen in the Azuma Kagami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka Gozen in the Azuma Kagami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>※以下、『吾妻鏡』に静が登場する箇所の現代語訳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* The following descriptions are the translations in today&apos;s Japanese from the scenes where Shizuka was described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* The following descriptions are translations in today&apos;s Japanese from the scenes where Shizuka was described.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following descriptions are translations in today&apos;s Japanese from the scenes where Shizuka was described.</e>
<cmt>記号不要のため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>文治元年11月6日（1185年12月15日）都落ちした義経の一行が九州へ渡るべく大物浜（尼崎市）から乗船するが、暴風雨によって難破し一行は離散。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsune and his group, who escaped from Kyoto, set sail at Daimotsuhama, today&apos;s Amagasaki City, for Kyushu on December 16, 1185, but their ship wrecked and the group members got separated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune and his group, who escaped from Kyoto, set sail from Daimotsuhama, today&apos;s Amagasaki City, for Kyushu on December 16, 1185, but their ship wrecked and the group members were separated.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsune and his group, who escaped from Kyoto, set sail from Daimotsuhama, today&apos;s Amagasaki City, for Kyushu on December 6, 1185, but their ship wrecked and the group members were separated.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>義経に従っていたのは源有綱・堀景光・武蔵坊弁慶並びに妾の静のみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsune found himself only with MINAMOTO no Aritsuna, Kagemitsu HORI, Musashibo Benkei and his concubine Shizuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune found himself with only MINAMOTO no Aritsuna, Kagemitsu HORI, Musashibo Benkei, and his concubine Shizuka.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsune found himself with only MINAMOTO no Aritsuna, Kagemitsu HORI, Musashibo Benkei, and his concubine Shizuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>11月17日 義経が大和国吉野山に隠れているとの噂があるので、吉野山の執行（修行）僧兵によって捜索するも見つからなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 17, as the rumor said Yoshitsune hid himself in Mount Yoshino, Yamato Province, senior monk soldiers of Mt. Yoshino searched him in vain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 17, as the rumor said, Yoshitsune hid himself in Mount Yoshino, Yamato Province, as senior monk soldiers of Mt. Yoshino searched him in vain.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 17, as the rumor said, Yoshitsune hid himself in Mount Yoshino, Yamato Province, as senior monk soldiers of Mt. Yoshino searched him in vain.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>夜10時頃、義経の妾の静が藤尾坂を下り蔵王堂にたどり着く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 10 o&apos;clock in the night, Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine Shizuka walked down Fujiozaka and reached to Zaodo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 10 o&apos;clock in the night, Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine Shizuka walked down Fujiozaka and reached Zaodo.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 10 o&apos;clock in the night, Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine Shizuka walked down Fujiozaka Slope and reached Zao-do hall.</e>
<cmt>slope補足しました。ハイフン補足しました。hall補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その姿がいかにも怪しいので衆徒達はこれを見咎め、執行坊に連れてきて詳細を問う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She looked so suspicious, and the monks caught and took her to the temple&apos;s administrative office to interrogate her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She looked suspicious, and the monks caught and took her to the temple&apos;s administrative office to interrogate her.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;so&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She looked suspicious, and the monks caught and took her to the temple&apos;s administrative office to interrogate her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>静「私は九朗大夫判官の妾です。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She answered, &quot;I am the concubine of Kurodayu Hogan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She answered, &quot;I am the concubine of Kurodayu Hogan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She answered, &quot;I am the concubine of Kurodayu Hogan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大物浜より豫州（義経）はこの山に来ました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshu (Yoshitsune) came to this mountain from Daimotsuhama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshu (Yoshitsune) came to this mountain from Daimotsuhama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshu (Yoshitsune) came to this mountain from Daimotsuhama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>5日間逗留しましたが、衆徒蜂起の噂を聞いて、伊豫守は山伏の姿を借りて逐電してしまいました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iyo no kami stayed in the mountain for five days, but after he heard a rumor of monks rising in revolt, he was dressed in yamabushi (mountain priest) clothes and ran away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iyo no kami stayed in the mountain for five days, but after he heard a rumor of monks rising in revolt, he dressed in yamabushi (mountain priest) clothes and ran away.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iyo no kami stayed in the mountain for five days, but after he heard a rumor of monks rising in revolt, he dressed in yamabushi (mountain priest) clothes and ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その時数多くの金銀類をわたくしに与え、雑色男たちを付けて京に送ろうとされました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave me a lot of valuables and sent me back to Kyoto with attendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gave me a lot of valuables and sent me back to Kyoto with attendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gave me a lot of valuables and sent me back to Kyoto with attendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし彼らは財宝を奪い取り、深い峯雪の中に捨て置いて行ってしまったので、このように迷って来たのです。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the attendants robbed me of the treasure and abandoned me deep in the snowy mountain, and that&apos;s is how I got here astray.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the attendants robbed me of the treasure and abandoned me deep in the snowy mountain, and that&apos;s how I got here astray.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the attendants robbed me of the treasure and abandoned me deep in the snowy mountain, and that&apos;s how I got here astray.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="36">
<j>11月18日 静の証言によって義経を探す為、吉野の大衆はまた雪を踏み分け山を捜索する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 18, Yoshino&apos;s monks went into the snowy woods in search for Yoshitsune according to what Shizuka said.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 18, Yoshino&apos;s monks went into the snowy woods in search for Yoshitsune according to what Shizuka said.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 18, Yoshino&apos;s monks went into the snowy woods in search for Yoshitsune according to what Shizuka said.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>吉野執行は静を大変気の毒に思い、充分労ってから鎌倉へ差し出す事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshino Shugyo felt very sorry for her, had her rest to repair the body, and sent her to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshino Shugyo felt very sorry for her, had her rest to heal her body, and sent her to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshino Shugyo felt very sorry for her, had her rest to heal her body, and sent her to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>12月8日 吉野の執行が静を京都にいる北条時政の屋敷に送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 8, Yoshino Shugyo sent Shizuka to the residence of Tokimasa HOJO in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 8, Yoshino Shugyo sent Shizuka to the residence of Tokimasa HOJO in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 7, 1186, Yoshino Shugyo sent Shizuka to the residence of Tokimasa HOJO in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>義経を捜すための軍が吉野山に差し向けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army to hunt for Yoshitsune was sent to Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army to hunt for Yoshitsune was sent to Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army to hunt for Yoshitsune was sent to Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>12月15日 北条時政から鎌倉へ送られた手紙より静の証言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka&apos;s statement in a letter sent by Tokimasa HOJO to Kamakura on December 15:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka&apos;s statement in a letter sent by Tokimasa HOJO to Kamakura on December 15:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka&apos;s statement in a letter sent by Tokimasa HOJO to Kamakura on January 14:</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>「豫州が都を出て西海へ赴いた明け方、一緒に連れ立って大物浜に到着しました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I was with Yoshu as he left Kyoto to head for the western part of Japan, and we together arrived at Daimotsuhama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I was with Yoshu as he left Kyoto to head for the western part of Japan, and together we arrived at Daimotsuhama.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I was with Yoshu as he left Kyoto to head for the western part of Japan, and together we arrived at Daimotsuhama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>それから船が難破し海を渡ることが出来ませんでした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We wanted to sail westward but our ship wrecked, and we could not cross the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We wanted to sail westward but our ship wrecked, and we could not cross the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We wanted to sail westward but our ship wrecked, and we could not cross the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>その夜は天王寺で宿泊し、豫州はそこから逃げて姿を隠しました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that day, we stayed overnight at Tenno-ji Temple, and Yoshu ran away to hide himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that day, we stayed overnight at Tenno-ji Temple, and Yoshu ran away to hide himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that day, we stayed overnight at Tenno-ji Temple, and Yoshu ran away to hide himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>迎えを寄越すので一両日の間ここで待つように約束し、ただし約束の日を過ぎたらすぐさま立ち去るように言われました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He told me to stay here for a few days as he promised to send someone to pick me up, but if nobody came on the promised date, I was suggested to immediately leave the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He told me to stay here for a few days as he promised to send someone to pick me up, but if nobody came on the promised date, I was suggested to immediately leave the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He told me to stay here for a few days as he promised to send someone to pick me up, but if nobody came on the promised date, I was suggested to immediately leave the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しばらく待っていると、馬を送ってきたのでこれに乗り、どこへ行くかわからないまま三日目に吉野山に着きました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, men with horses appeared at the temple, and although I was not told where we would go, I travelled on horseback for a few days and arrived at Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>「複数の人が複数の馬とともに来た」と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, men with horses appeared at the temple, and although I was not told where we would go, I travelled on horseback for a few days and arrived at Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, men with horses appeared at the temple, and although I was not told where we would go, I travelled on horseback for a few days and arrived at Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>そこで五日間逗留し、それを最後にお別れしました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I stayed there for five days and then departed from him.</e>
<cmt>「それを最後にお別れした」は「吉野で義経と会い、そこで彼とお別れした」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I stayed there for five days and then departed from him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I stayed there for five days and then departed from him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その後の行方は知りません。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I don&apos;t know where he&apos;d gone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I don&apos;t know where he&apos;d gone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I don&apos;t know where he&apos;d gone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>私は深山の雪を凌ぎ、やっとのことで蔵王堂に着いたところ、吉野執行に捕らえられました。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I walked through the snow in the mountain trails and finally got to Zaodo, but then I was arrested by Yoshino&apos;s monks.</e>
<cmt>吉野執行は複数と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I walked through the snow in the mountain trails and finally got to Zaodo, but then I was arrested by Yoshino&apos;s monks.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I walked through the snow in the mountain trails and finally got to Zaodo, but then I was arrested by Yoshino&apos;s monks.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="49">
<j>12月16日 静を鎌倉へ召し出すよう時政に返書が送られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 16, Tokimasa received a letter from Kamakura that ordered him to send Shizuka to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 16, Tokimasa received a letter from Kamakura that ordered him to send Shizuka to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 15, Tokimasa received a letter from Kamakura that ordered him to send Shizuka to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="50">
<j>1月29日 義経の行方未だに分からず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 29, the whereabouts of Yoshitsune were still unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 29, the whereabouts of Yoshitsune were still unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Feburary 27, 1186, the whereabouts of Yoshitsune were still unknown.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>さらに問いただしたい事があるので、静を差し出すように北条時政に伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimasa HOJO was ordered to send Shizuka to Kamakura so that she could further be interrogated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokimasa HOJO was ordered to send Shizuka to Kamakura so that she could be interrogated further.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimasa HOJO was ordered to send Shizuka to Kamakura so that she could be interrogated further.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="52">
<j>2月13日 鎌倉に京都の時政から静を送る旨の返事が届く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 13, Kamakura received a letter from Tokimasa in Kyoto that he would send Shizuka to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 13, Kamakura received a letter from Tokimasa in Kyoto stating that he would send Shizuka to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;stating&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 21, Kamakura received a letter from Tokimasa in Kyoto stating that he would send Shizuka to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="53">
<j>3月1日 静、母の磯禅師と共に鎌倉に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 1, Shizuka and her mother Iso no Zenji arrived at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 1, Shizuka and her mother Iso no Zenji arrived at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 30, Shizuka and her mother Iso no Zenji arrived at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>安達新三郎の屋敷に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They entered the residence of ADACHI no Shinzaburo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They entered the residence of ADACHI no Shinzaburo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They entered the residence of ADACHI no Shinzaburo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="55">
<j>3月6日 すでに京都で時政に調べられたが、はなはだ信用できないとして再び問注所の役人に義経の行方を問われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 6, although Shizuka was already interrogated by Tokimasa in Kyoto, she was again asked about the whereabouts of Yoshitsune by officials of the Monchujo (Court of Justice in the Kamakura Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 6, although Shizuka had already been interrogated by Tokimasa in Kyoto, she was again asked about the whereabouts of Yoshitsune by officials of the Monchujo (Court of Justice in the Kamakura Period).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 4, although Shizuka had already been interrogated by Tokimasa in Kyoto, she was again asked about the whereabouts of Yoshitsune by officials of the Monchujo (Court of Justice in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>静「吉野の山中ではなく、その僧坊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka said, &quot;It was not in the mountains of Yoshino but at one of the temple quarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka said, &quot;It was not in the mountains of Yoshino but at one of the temple quarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka said, &quot;He was not in the mountains of Yoshino but at one of the temple quarters.</e>
<cmt>ItをHeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>しかし山の大衆蜂起の事を聞いて、そこから（義経は）山伏の姿になり、大峰に入ると言って僧に送られて山に入りました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsune heard about the uprising of monks of Yoshino, was dressed in a mountain priest&apos;s clothes, and went up into the mountain to enter Omine as monks saw him off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune heard about the uprising of monks of Yoshino, was dressed in a mountain priest&apos;s clothes, and went up into the mountain to enter Omine as monks saw him off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsune heard about the uprising of monks of Yoshino, was dressed in a mountain priest&apos;s clothes, and went up into the mountain to enter Omine as monks saw him off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>自分もまた跡を慕って一の鳥居の辺りまで行ったが、その僧に女人は大峰に入るべからずと叱られたので、やむなく都の方へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I also followed him and reached to Ichi no torii (first torii), but as one monk bashed me and said women were not allowed to enter Omine, I had no choice but to head for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I followed him and reached Ichi no torii (first torii), but as one monk bashed me and said women were not allowed to enter Omine, I had no choice but to head for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I followed him and reached Ichi no torii (first torii), but as one monk bashed me and said women were not allowed to enter Omine, I had no choice but to head for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>ところが同行していた雑色達が財宝を奪って逃げてしまい、蔵王堂に迷い着きました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the attendants who accompanied me took away my treasure and ran away, and that was how I wandered off into Zaodo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the attendants who accompanied me took away my treasure and ran away, and that was how I wandered off into Zaodo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the attendants who accompanied me took away my treasure and ran away, and that was how I wandered off into Zaodo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>」重ねて僧の名を尋ねるとそれは忘れたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was asked about the monk&apos;s name again, but she answered she forgot it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was asked about the monk&apos;s name again, but she answered that she had forgotten it.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was asked about the monk&apos;s name again, but she answered that she had forgotten it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>およそ京都での申し立てと今の言葉といささか違っているし、大峰に入ったと言っているが、多武峯に向かったあと隠れたとの噂があるので、それらにきっと虚偽があるだろうから重ねて取り調べるよう命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What she said in Kyoto is somewhat different from what she just said; she said Yoshitsune&apos;s group went into Omine, but word had it that they went toward Tanomine and laid low, which means she must have lied, and that was why they were ordered to interrogate her again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What she said in Kyoto is somewhat different from what she just said; she said Yoshitsune&apos;s group went into Omine, but word had it that they went toward Tanomine and laid low, which means she must have lied, and that was why they were ordered to interrogate her again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What she said in Kyoto is somewhat different from what she just said; she said Yoshitsune&apos;s group went into Omine, but word had it that they went toward Tanomine and laid low, which means she must have lied, and that was why they were ordered to interrogate her again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="62">
<j>3月22日 静再び子細を尋ねられるも、義経の行方は知らないというだけであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 22, Shizuka was again asked about more information but just answered she didn&apos;t know where Yoshitsune had gone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 22, Shizuka was again asked about more information but just answered that she didn&apos;t know where Yoshitsune had gone.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 20, Shizuka was again asked about more information but just answered that she didn&apos;t know where Yoshitsune had gone.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>義経の子を妊娠しているので出産ののち帰すとの沙汰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was told that since she was pregnant she would be allowed to leave after she delivers a baby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was told that since she was pregnant she would be allowed to leave after delivering a baby.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was told that since she was pregnant she would be allowed to leave after delivering a baby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="64">
<j>4月8日 頼朝と政子が鶴岡八幡宮に参拝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 8, Yoritomo and Masako visited Tsurugaoka-hachimangu Shrine for prayer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 8, Yoritomo and Masako visited Tsurugaoka-hachimangu Shrine for prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 5, Yoritomo and Masako visited Tsurugaoka-hachimangu Shrine for prayer.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>舞を行うよう控えの間から静を廻廊に召し出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka was ordered to move out of an anteroom to the corridor to perform a dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka was ordered to move out of an anteroom to the corridor to perform a dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka was ordered to move out of an anteroom to the corridor to perform a dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この事は以前から命じていたところ、病気のためと称して断ったり、わが身の不遇はあれこれ言う事は出来ないといえども、豫州（義経）の妾として晴れの場に出るのはすこぶる恥辱であると言って渋り続けていたが、政子が「天下の舞の名手がたまたまこの地に来て、近々帰るのに、その芸を見ないのは残念なこと」としきりに頼朝に勧め、「八幡大菩薩に備えるのだから」と言って静を説得。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although she was ordered to do so days ago, she hesitated to obey the order by using her illness as an excuse or saying it would be quite a disgrace for the concubine of Yoshitsune to appear on a gala occasion although she was not in a position to blame somebody for her misfortune, but Masako frequently recommended Yoritomo to see Shizuka&apos;s dance, saying &quot;It would be a great disappointment to miss the great performance of an excellent dancer while the dancer happens to be at this place and is going to return very soon,&quot; and persuaded Shizuka to do the dance by saying &quot;The dance is for dedication to Hachiman Daibosatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although she was ordered to do so days ago, she hesitated to obey the order, using her illness as an excuse or saying it would be quite a disgrace for the concubine of Yoshitsune to appear on a gala occasion although she was not in a position to blame somebody for her misfortune, but Masako frequently recommended Yoritomo to see Shizuka&apos;s dance, saying &quot;It would be a great disappointment to miss the great performance of an excellent dancer while the dancer happens to be at this place and is going to return very soon,&quot; and persuaded Shizuka to perform the dance by saying &quot;The dance is dedicated to Hachiman Daibosatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although she was ordered to do so days ago, she hesitated to obey the order, using her illness as an excuse or saying it would be quite a disgrace for the concubine of Yoshitsune to appear on a gala occasion although she was not in a position to blame somebody for her misfortune, but Masako frequently recommended Yoritomo to see Shizuka&apos;s dance, saying &quot;It would be a great disappointment to miss the great performance of an excellent dancer while the dancer happens to be at this place and is going to return very soon,&quot; and persuaded Shizuka to perform the dance by saying &quot;The dance is dedicated to Hachiman Daibosatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>別離からまだ日も浅く、気が塞いでるので舞う気にならないとその場になっても固辞するのを、再三の命によって舞う事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She refused to obey the order saying not many days passed since she departed from Yoshitsune and she still felt depressed and did not feel ready to dance, but she had to accept the order to dance because of repeated orders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She refused to obey the order, saying that not many days had passed since she departed from Yoshitsune and she still felt depressed and did not feel ready to dance, but she had to accept the order to dance because of repeated orders.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She refused to obey the order, saying that not many days had passed since she departed from Yoshitsune and she still felt depressed and did not feel ready to dance, but she had to accept the order to dance because of repeated orders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>（舞に関しては上記）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See the above for dance.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See the above for dance.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See the above for dance.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="69">
<j>5月14日 工藤祐経・梶原景茂・千葉常秀・八田朝重・藤原邦通ら御家人たちが下っ端の若者を連れて静の宿所に向かい宴会を催す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On may 15, gokenin (samurai under the direct supervision of shogun) including Suketsune KUDO, Kagemochi KAJIWARA, Tsunehide CHIBA, Asashige HATTA, and FUJIWARA no Kunimichi visited with low-ranking youngsters the place where Shizuka stayed and held a party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 15, gokenin (samurai under the direct supervision of shogun), including Suketsune KUDO, Kagemochi KAJIWARA, Tsunehide CHIBA, Asashige HATTA, and FUJIWARA no Kunimichi, visited, with low-ranking youngsters, the place where Shizuka stayed and held a party.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 10, gokenin (samurai under the direct supervision of shogun), including Suketsune KUDO, Kagemochi KAJIWARA, Tsunehide CHIBA, Asashige HATTA, and FUJIWARA no Kunimichi, visited, with low-ranking youngsters, the place where Shizuka stayed and held a party.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>磯禅師が舞を舞う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iso no Zenji performed a dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iso no Zenji performed a dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iso no Zenji performed a dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>酒に酔った景茂から艶言を投げかけられ、静は大泣きして「豫州（義経）は鎌倉殿の御兄弟、私はその妾です。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As drunken Kagemochi threw dirty words, Shizuka burst into tears, &quot;Yoshu (Yoshitsune) is the brother of Kamakura Dono (Yoritomo), and I am Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As drunken Kagemochi threw dirty words, Shizuka burst into tears, &quot;Yoshu (Yoshitsune) is the brother of Kamakura Dono (Yoritomo), and I am Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As drunken Kagemochi threw dirty words, Shizuka burst into tears, &quot;Yoshu (Yoshitsune) is the brother of Kamakura Dono (Yoritomo), and I am Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>御家人の身分でどうして普通の男女の事のように思われるのか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You are just a gokenin, and what you said about my relationship with Yoshitsune sounds like an ordinary love affair among men and women, but you are too vulgar to imply such a thing about us.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You are just a gokenin, and what you said about my relationship with Yoshitsune sounds like an ordinary love affair among men and women, but you are too vulgar to imply such a thing about us.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You are just a gokenin, and what you said about my relationship with Yoshitsune sounds like an ordinary love affair among men and women, but you are too vulgar to imply such a thing about us.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>豫州が落ちぶれなければ、あなたごときに対面する事さえできないはずなのに。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If Yoshu hadn&apos;t come down in the world, you wouldn&apos;t even have had the chance to see him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If Yoshu hadn&apos;t come down in the world, you wouldn&apos;t even have had the chance to see him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Yoshu hadn&apos;t come down in the world, you wouldn&apos;t even have had the chance to see him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>ましてやそのような艶言などもってのほかです。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Why on earth do you think you think you are given the authority to say such dirty words?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Why on earth do you think you think you are given the authority to say such dirty words?&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Why on earth do you think you think you are given the authority to say such dirty words?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="75">
<j>5月27日 夜、頼朝の長女大姫の依頼により、南御堂に舞を納めて禄を給う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka performed a dance at the Minami Mido Hall at the request of Ohime, Yoritomo&apos;s eldest daughter, on the night of May 27.</e>
<cmt>「南御堂というホールにて舞を舞った」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka performed a dance at the Minami Mido Hall at the request of Ohime, Yoritomo&apos;s eldest daughter, on the night of May 27.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka performed a dance at the Minami Mido Hall at the request of Ohime, Yoritomo&apos;s eldest daughter, on the night of June 23.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="76">
<j>閏7月29日（閏は2度目の7月）静男子を出産する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka delivered a baby boy on the 29th of leap month July (the second leap month July).</e>
<cmt>「二度目の閏7月」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka delivered a baby boy on the 29th of leap month July (the second leap month July).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka delivered a baby boy on the September 21.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これは豫州（義経）の息子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the son of Yoshu (Yoshitsune).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the son of Yoshu (Yoshitsune).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the son of Yoshu (Yoshitsune).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>出産を待ってから京に帰す事になっていたので、今日まで留め置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was decided she would be allowed to return to Kyoto after childbirth, she had been ordered to stay until that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it had been decided that she would be allowed to return to Kyoto after childbirth, she was ordered to stay until that day.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it had been decided that she would be allowed to return to Kyoto after childbirth, she was ordered to stay until that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>その父は関東に背き謀反を企て逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the baby&apos;s father stood against Kanto and fled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the baby&apos;s father stood against Kanto and fled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the baby&apos;s father stood against Kanto and fled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>その子が女子ならばすみやかに母に返されるが、男子であれば今は産着の中にあっても、将来に禍根を残す恐れがあるので、赤子のうちに命を絶つように決まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the baby was a girl, she would be immediately returned to her mother, but if it was a boy, there is a possibility that the sparing of the boy&apos;s life would invite a disaster in the future even though the baby was still in the baby clothes, and that was why it was already decided that the baby boy be killed as a baby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the baby was a girl, she would be immediately returned to her mother, but if it was a boy, there is a possibility that the sparing of the boy&apos;s life would invite a disaster in the future even though the baby was still in baby clothes, and that was why it had already been decided that the baby boy would be killed as a baby.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the baby was a girl, she would be immediately returned to her mother, but if it was a boy, there is a possibility that the sparing of the boy&apos;s life would invite a disaster in the future even though the baby was still in baby clothes, and that was why it had already been decided that the baby boy would be killed as a baby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>よって今日、安達新三郎に由比ヶ浜に捨てるよう命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today Shinzaburo ADACHI was ordered to dump the baby boy in the water off Yuigahama beach.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today Shinzaburo ADACHI was ordered to dump the baby boy in the water off Yuigahama beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today Shinzaburo ADACHI was ordered to dump the baby boy in the water off Yuigahama beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>これに先立ち新三郎が使いとして赤子を受け取ろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzaburo tried to take off the baby from Shizuka to fulfil his order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzaburo tried to take the baby from Shizuka to fulfill his order.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzaburo tried to take the baby from Shizuka to fulfill his order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>静はまったくこれを出さず、（赤子を）衣にまとい抱き臥し、叫喚数刻に及ぶが、安達は厳しく催促する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Shizuka tightly held the baby in the clothes, continued crying for a long time, and would never lose hold of the baby, but Adachi strongly demanded the baby be surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka tightly held the baby in the clothes, continued crying for a long time, and would never lose hold of the baby, but Adachi strongly demanded the baby be surrendered.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;but&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka tightly held the baby in the clothes, continued crying for a long time, and would never lose hold of the baby, but Adachi strongly demanded the baby be surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>磯禅師が恐縮し、赤子を取り上げて使いに渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iso no Zenji felt so intimidated that she took the baby off from Shizuka and gave him to Shinzaburo.</e>
<cmt>「使い」は新三郎と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iso no Zenji felt so intimidated that she took the baby from Shizuka and gave him to Shinzaburo.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;off&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iso no Zenji felt so intimidated that she took the baby from Shizuka and gave him to Shinzaburo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>この事は、政子が頼朝に嘆願し宥めたが叶わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masako petitioned to Yoritomo for the baby&apos;s life, only to fail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masako petitioned to Yoritomo for the baby&apos;s life, only to fail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masako petitioned to Yoritomo for the baby&apos;s life, only to fail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="86">
<j>9月16日 静母子帰洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka and her mother left Kamakura for Kyoto on September 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka and her mother left Kamakura for Kyoto on September 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka and her mother left Kamakura for Kyoto on November 5.</e>
<cmt>新暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>憐れんだ政子と大姫が多く重宝を賜う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Very much feeling for Shizuka, Masako and Ohime granted plenty of valuables to Shizuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Very much feeling for Shizuka, Masako and Ohime granted plenty of valuables to Shizuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Very much feeling for Shizuka, Masako and Ohime granted plenty of valuables to Shizuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="88">
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>静御前に関して史料による記録が見られるのは、上記の鎌倉幕府北条氏編纂である『吾妻鏡』のみであり、同時代の都の貴族の日記などで静に関する記録は一切見られない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only historical document that recorded the name of Shizuka Gozen is Azuma Kagami, a chronicle edited by the Hojo clan of the Kamakura Shogunate, Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun, and no journals of contemporary noble people contained any descriptions about Shizuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only historical document that records the name of Shizuka Gozen is Azuma Kagami, a chronicle edited by the Hojo clan of the Kamakura Shogunate, Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun, and no journals of contemporary noble people contain any descriptions about Shizuka.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only historical document that records the name of Shizuka Gozen is &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; a chronicle edited by the Hojo clan of the Kamakura Shogunate, Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun, and no journals of contemporary noble people contain any descriptions about Shizuka.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>吾妻鏡の記述以外のエピソードは、室町時代初期に書かれた『義経記』の創作によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episodes other than those in Azuma Kagami are fictions in Gikeiki, a military epic on Yoshitsune and his followers, established in the initial part of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episodes other than those in Azuma Kagami are works of fiction in Gikeiki, a military epic on Yoshitsune and his followers, established in the initial part of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episodes other than those in Azuma Kagami are works of fiction in &quot;Gikeiki,&quot; a military epic on Yoshitsune and his followers, established in the initial part of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>義経記によると、日照りが続いたので、後白河天皇は神泉苑の池で100人の僧に読経させたが効験がなかったので、100人の容顔美麗な白拍子に舞わせ雨を祈らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Gikeiki, Emperor Goshirakawa had 100 Buddhist priests chant sutras at the Shinsen-en Garden in Kyoto for prayer for rainfall because of a long spell of drought, but since the priests&apos; prayer did not work, the Emperor invited 100 beautiful looking shirabyoshi dancers to pray for rainfall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Gikeiki, Emperor Goshirakawa had 100 Buddhist priests chant sutras at the Shinsen-en Garden in Kyoto for prayer for rainfall because of a long spell of drought, but since the priests&apos; prayer did not work, the Emperor invited 100 beautiful shirabyoshi dancers to pray for rainfall.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;loking&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Gikeiki, Emperor Goshirakawa had 100 Buddhist priests chant sutras at the Shinsen-en Garden in Kyoto for prayer for rainfall because of a long spell of drought, but since the priests&apos; prayer did not work, the Emperor invited 100 beautiful shirabyoshi dancers to pray for rainfall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>99人まで効験がなかったが、静が舞うとたちまち黒雲が現れ、3日間雨が降り続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the 99th shirabyoshi, no prayer was honored, but when the last dancer, Shizuka, started dancing, dark clouds appeared and the rain fell for three consecutive days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the 99th shirabyoshi, no prayer was honored, but when the last dancer, Shizuka, started dancing, dark clouds appeared and the rain fell for three consecutive days.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the 99th shirabyoshi, no prayer was honored, but when the last dancer, Shizuka, started dancing, dark clouds appeared and the rain fell for three consecutive days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>静は法皇から「日本一」の宣旨を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuka was highly praised as &quot;Japan&apos;s No. 1&quot; in the Cloister Emperor&apos;s Imperial letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuka was highly praised as &quot;Japan&apos;s No. 1&quot; in the Cloister Emperor&apos;s Imperial letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuka was highly praised as &apos;Japan&apos;s No. 1&apos; in the Cloister Emperor&apos;s Imperial decree.</e>
<cmt>宣旨→imperial decreeに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>その時に、静を見初めた義経が召して妾にしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Yoshitsune, who was there at the ceremony, fell in love with her at first sight and asked her to become his concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Yoshitsune, who was there at the ceremony, fell in love with her at first sight and asked her to become his concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Yoshitsune, who was there at the ceremony, fell in love with her at first sight and asked her to become his concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="95">
<j>静の死については諸々の伝承があるがはっきりしたものはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a few legends on the death of Shizuka, but none are proven ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a few legends on the death of Shizuka, but none have been proven.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a few legends on the death of Shizuka, but none have been proven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>自殺説（姫川（乙部町）への投身、由比ヶ浜への入水など）や旅先での客死説（逃亡した義経を追ったもののうら若き身ひとつでの移動の無理がたたったというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are so many legends including the suicide theory (she threw herself into the Himekawa River, Otobe Town, or into the sea off Yuigahama beach) or death away from home (although she followed Yoshitsune who fled northward, she was still young, alone, and could not stand the hardship of travelling and died; there are various theories about the place of her death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many legends that include the suicide theory (she threw herself into the Himekawa River, Otobe Town, or into the sea off Yuigahama beach) or death away from home (although she followed Yoshitsune who fled northward, she was still young, alone, and could not stand the hardship of travelling and died; there are various theories about the place of her death).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many legends that include the suicide theory (she threw herself into the Himekawa River, Otobe Town, or into the sea off Yuigahama beach) or death away from home (although she followed Yoshitsune who fled northward, she was still young, alone, and could not stand the hardship of travelling and died; there are various theories about the place of her death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>静終焉の地については諸説ある）など列挙すればキリがないがいずれにせよまだ若年のうちに逝去したとする説が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is one thing commonly found in many of them: she died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is one thing commonly found in many of them: she died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is one thing commonly found in many of them: she died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="98">
<j>奈良県大和高田市の磯野は磯野禅尼の里で、静御前も母の里に戻って生涯を終えたとする伝説が伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isono, today&apos;s Yamatotakada City, Nara Prefecture, is the hometown of Iso no Zenji, and there is a legend that Shizuka Gozen also returned to her mother&apos;s hometown and lived there until her death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isono, today&apos;s Yamatotakada City, Nara Prefecture, is the hometown of Iso no Zenji, and there is a legend that Shizuka Gozen also returned to her mother&apos;s hometown and lived there until her death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isono, today&apos;s Yamatotakada City, Nara Prefecture, is the hometown of Iso no Zenji, and there is a legend that Shizuka Gozen also returned to her mother&apos;s hometown and lived there until her death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>また淡路島や埼玉県北葛飾郡栗橋町、山口県阿武郡阿東町、また、現在の福島県にいる義経を追うために通過したと伝えられる新潟県旧栃尾市にも静御前と伝えられる墓が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also many tombs of hers: one in Awaji Island, one at Kurihashi Town, Kitakatsushika-gun, Saitama Prefecture, and one at former Tochio City, Niigata Prefecture, where she is said to have passed on her way to search for Yoshitsune who was in today&apos;s Fukushima Prefecture at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also many tombs of hers: one on Awaji Island, one at Kurihashi Town, Kitakatsushika-gun, Saitama Prefecture, and one at former Tochio City, Niigata Prefecture, where she is said to have passed on her way to search for Yoshitsune who at the time was in today&apos;s Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also many tombs of hers: one on Awaji Island, one at Kurihashi Town, Kitakatsushika-gun, Saitama Prefecture, and one at former Tochio City, Niigata Prefecture, where she is said to have passed on her way to search for Yoshitsune who at the time was in today&apos;s Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>福島県郡山市には、義経の訃報を聞いた静御前が身を投げたと言われる美女池や、その供養のために建立された静御前堂がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a pond named Bijogaike, in Koriyama City, Fukushima Prefecture, which is believed to be the place she threw herself into the water after she heard the death of Yoshitsune, and a small temple named Shizuka Gozen Do, which was constructed in memory of her, stands nearby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a pond named Bijogaike, in Koriyama City, Fukushima Prefecture, which is believed to be the place she threw herself into the water after she heard of the death of Yoshitsune, and a small temple named Shizuka Gozen Do, which was constructed in memory of her, stands nearby.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a pond named Bijogaike, in Koriyama City, Fukushima Prefecture, which is believed to be the place she threw herself into the water after she heard of the death of Yoshitsune, and a small temple named Shizuka Gozen Do, which was constructed in memory of her, stands nearby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="101">
<j>長野県大町市大塩には、静御前が奥州と大塩を間違えてたたどり着き、そこで亡くなりその時、地面に刺さった杖から芽吹いたという、イヌザクラの巨木「静の桜」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Oshio, Omachi City, Nagano Prefecture, there stands a big tree called Shizuka no Sakura (Inuzakura in Japanese and academic name is Prunus buergeriana Miq.), which is believed to have sprung up from a stick Shizuka poked on the ground as she breathed her last at the place, Oshio, she erroneously reached for its name sounded like Oshu, a more north place Yoshitsune fled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Oshio, Omachi City, Nagano Prefecture, there stands a big tree called Shizuka no Sakura (Inuzakura in Japanese, scientific name is Prunus buergeriana Miq.), which is believed to have sprung up from a stick Shizuka poked on the ground as she breathed her last at the place, Oshio; she erroneously reached for its name and said Oshu, a place further to the north from the place to which Yoshitsune had fled.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Oshio, Omachi City, Nagano Prefecture, there stands a big tree called Shizuka no Sakura (Inuzakura in Japanese, scientific name is Prunus buergeriana Miq.), which is believed to have sprung up from a stick Shizuka poked on the ground as she breathed her last at the place, Oshio; she erroneously reached for its name and said Oshu, a place further to the north from the place to which Yoshitsune had fled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="102">
<j>茨城県古河市下辺見には、静御前が行き先を思案したとされる思案橋という橋がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Shimohemi, Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture, there is a bridge called Shian-bashi, which is believed to be the place where Shizuka Gozen dwelt on (&quot;shian&quot; in Japanese) which way to go.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Shimohemi, Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture, there is a bridge called Shian-bashi, which is believed to be the place where Shizuka Gozen had dwelt on (&quot;shian&quot; in Japanese) which way to go.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Shimohemi, Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture, there is a bridge called Shian-bashi, which is believed to be the place where Shizuka Gozen had dwelt on (&quot;shian&quot; in Japanese) which way to go.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 少量法律助言者(id:105707), Los688(id:12316), SKIer(id:114482), 経済準学士(id:22656), Masami.H(id:85549), MIsogi(id:20599), ちちぶ(id:184715), 味っ子(id:17086), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), Hatsune(id:26654), ＋－(id:17104), Arpeggio(id:9385), A6M4(id:14155), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 仲代陽子(id:69278), Loveless(id:129239), Kone(id:377), Bururururu(id:6753), 麦塚ほとり(id:54917), Hyper neo(id:57046), Trek011(id:7105), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>