<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石田三成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari ISHIDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石田 三成（いしだ みつなり）は、安土桃山時代の武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA was a feudal warlord in Azuchi-Momoyama era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari ISHIDA was a feudal warlord in the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA was a feudal warlord in the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>豊臣政権の五奉行の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the five major magistrates in Toyotomi&apos;s government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the five major magistrates in Toyotomi&apos;s government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the five major magistrates in Toyotomi&apos;s government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Life</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語統一リスト</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>秀吉の子飼い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi&apos;s retainer trained from boyhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Hideyoshi&apos;s retainer, trained from boyhood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Hideyoshi&apos;s retainer, trained from boyhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>永禄3年（1560年）、石田正継の次男として近江国坂田郡石田村（滋賀県長浜市石田町）で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1560, as the second son of Masatsugu ISHIDA in Ishida-mura, Sakata-gun in Omi-no-kuni (now, Ishida-cho, Nagahama City in Shiga Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1560 as the second son of Masatsugu ISHIDA in Ishida-mura, Sakata-gun in Omi-no-kuni (the present-day Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, in Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1560 as the second son of Masatsugu ISHIDA in Ishida-mura Village, Sakata County in Omi Province (the present-day Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>地名表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>石田村は古くは石田郷といって石田氏は郷名を苗字とした土豪であったとされている（また、観音寺で学習していたとも言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishida-mura was called Ishida-go and Ishida clan was a local ruling family who used the Go-mei (name of village) as family name. (He was said to study at Kannon-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishida-mura was called Ishida-go, and the Ishida clan was a local ruling family who used the Go-mei (the name of a village) as its family name (he was said to study at Kannon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishida Village was called Ishida-go(village), and the Ishida clan was a local ruling family who used the Go-mei (the name of a village) as its family name (he was said to study at Kannon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>地名表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>羽柴秀吉（のちの豊臣秀吉）が織田信長に仕えて近江国長浜城 (近江国)（長浜市）主となった天正2年（1574年）頃から秀吉の小姓として仕える（天正5年（1577年）説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later called Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) as a pageboy in about 1574 (1577 according to another theory), when Hideyoshi became a lord of Nagahama Castle in Omi-no-kuni (now Nagahama City) serving Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later called Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) as a pageboy in about 1574 (1577, according to another theory), when Hideyoshi became a lord of Nagahama Castle in Omi-no-kuni (now Nagahama City) serving Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later called Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) as a pageboy in about 1574 (1577, according to another theory), when Hideyoshi became a lord of Nagahama Castle in Omi Province (now Nagahama City) serving Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>地名表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>秀吉が信長の命令で中国攻めの総司令官として中国征伐に赴いたとき、これに従軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hideyoshi went on an expedition to Chugoku region as a commander of chief by order of Nobunaga, Ishida served in the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hideyoshi went on an expedition to the Chugoku region as a chief commander by order of Nobunaga, Ishida served in the war.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hideyoshi went on an expedition to the Chugoku region as a chief commander by order of Nobunaga, ISHIDA served in the war.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>天正10年（1582年）6月、信長が本能寺の変により横死し、次の天下人として秀吉が台頭すると、三成も秀吉の側近として次第に台頭してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga died an unnatural death in the Honnoji no Hen (Conspiracy of Honno-ji Temple) in June, 1582, Hideyoshi rose up as a Tenkabito (ruler of the country) and Mitsunari also gradually emerged as an aide of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga died an unnatural death in the Honnoji no Hen (the Conspiracy of Honno-ji Temple) in June 1582, Hideyoshi rose up as a tenkabito (ruler of the country) and Mitsunari gradually emerged as an aide of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga died an unnatural death in the Honnoji no Hen (the Conspiracy of Honno-ji Temple) in June 1582, Hideyoshi rose up as a tenkabito (ruler of the country) and Mitsunari gradually emerged as an aide of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天正11年（1583年）、賤ヶ岳の戦いに従軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari served in the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari served in the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari served in the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>柴田勝家軍の動向を探る偵察行動を担当、また先駈衆として一番槍の功名をあげたと「一柳家記」にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Hitotsuyanagi Kaki,&quot; he was in charge of spy mission on Katsuie SHIBATA&apos;s army and also performed a great feat of Ichiban-yari (spearmen&apos;s group) as one of the warriors in front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Hitotsuyanagi Kaki,&quot; he was in charge of a mission to spy on Katsuie SHIBATA&apos;s army and also performed a great feat of Ichiban-yari (spearmen&apos;s group) as one of the warriors on the front line.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Hitotsuyanagi Kaki,&quot; he was in charge of a mission to spy on Katsuie SHIBATA&apos;s army and also performed a great feat of Ichiban-yari (being the first to thrust a spear at an enemy soldier) as one of the warriors on the front line.</e>
<cmt>一番槍の説明を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天正12年（1584年）、小牧・長久手の戦いに従軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served in the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served in the battles of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served in the battles of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年、近江国蒲生郡の検地奉行を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he worked as Kenchi survey magistrate in Gamo-gun in Omi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That same year, he worked as a kenchi (survey magistrate) at Gamo-gun, in Omi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That same year, he worked as a kenchi (survey magistrate) at Gamo County in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>地名表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>豊臣政権下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under Toyotomi&apos;s government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Toyotomi&apos;s Government</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Toyotomi&apos;s Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>天正13年（1585年）7月11日、秀吉の関白就任に伴い、従五位治部省に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hideyoshi was appointed the chief adviser to the Emperor on July 11th, 1585, Mitsunari was given as Jugoi rank in Jibu-sho department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hideyoshi was appointed as the chief adviser to the Emperor on July 11, 1585, Mitsunari was given the rank of a jugoi in the Jibu-sho department.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hideyoshi was appointed as the chief adviser to the Emperor on July 11, 1585, Mitsunari was given the rank of a jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in the Jibu-sho department.</e>
<cmt>従五位の英訳を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、同年末に秀吉から近江水口4万石の城主に封じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of this year, he was appointed as the lord of Minakuchi, Omi with 40,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the year, he was appointed to serve as the lord of Minakuchi, in Omi, with 40,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the year, he was appointed to serve as the lord of Minakuchi, in Omi, with 40,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>天正14年（1586年）1月、当時智勇兼備の名将として名高かった島左近を4万石のうちの半分の2万石の知行を与えて召抱えたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to employ Sakon SHIMA, who was very famous for great commander having both wisdom and courage, at 20,000 koku chigyo fief which was the half amount of Mitsunari&apos;s chigyo fief in January, 1586.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that, in January 1586, he hired Sakon SHIMA, who was renowned as a commander having wisdom and courage, at a chigyo (fief) of 20,000 koku, which was the half amount of Mitsunari&apos;s chigyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that, in January 1586, he hired Sakon SHIMA, who was renowned as a commander having wisdom and courage, at a chigyo (fief) of 20,000 koku, which was the half amount of Mitsunari&apos;s chigyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>秀吉はこれに驚愕、そして賞賛し、島左近に三成への忠誠を促し、菊桐紋入りの羽織を与えた（ただし、佐和山19万石を得た時に家臣とした説、それとは別に秀吉からの寄騎であったとする説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Hideyoshi was impressed and praised for this, he gave a Haori (half-coat) with Kikukiri-mon crest to Sakon SHIMA to encourage the fealty for Mitsunari. [There are different theories; that Mitsunari employed Sakon when he was appointed as the lord of Sawayama with 190,000 koku, and that Sakon was a Yoriki (lower-ranked Samurai) who had supported Hideyoshi.]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Hideyoshi was impressed and praised for this, he gave a haori (half-coat) with the Kikukiri-mon crest to Sakon SHIMA in order to encourage fealty for Mitsunari (though other theories assert that Mitsunari employed Sakon when he was appointed as the lord of Sawayama with 190,000 koku, and that Sakon was a yoriki (lower-ranked samurai) who had supported Hideyoshi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Hideyoshi was impressed and praised for this, he gave a haori (half-coat) with the Kikukiri-mon crest to Sakon SHIMA in order to encourage fealty for Mitsunari (though other theories assert that Mitsunari employed Sakon when he was appointed as the lord of Sawayama with 190,000 koku, and that Sakon was a yoriki (lower-ranked samurai) who had supported Hideyoshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同年、越後の上杉景勝が秀吉に臣従を誓うために上洛してきたとき、これを斡旋した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Mitsunari helped Kagekatsu UESUGI from Echigo to come to see Hideyoshi and to pledge to serve as a vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Mitsunari helped Kagekatsu UESUGI from Echigo to visit Hideyoshi and pledge to serve as a vassal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Mitsunari helped Kagekatsu UESUGI from Echigo to visit Hideyoshi and pledge to serve as a vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、秀吉から堺奉行に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This year, he was appointed as Sakai-bugyo (magistrate of around Sakai) by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That year, he was appointed by Hideyoshi as a sakai-bugyo (magistrate around Sakai).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That year, he was appointed by Hideyoshi as a sakai-bugyo (magistrate around Sakai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>天正15年（1587年）、九州征伐に参陣するが、武功を挙げたわけではなく後方の兵糧・武具などの輜重を担当していたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went on an expedition to Kyushu in 1587, but he was said to be in charge of military goods to transport such as food provisions and weapons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went on an expedition to Kyushu in 1587, but he was said to be in charge of transporting military goods such as food provisions and weapons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went on an expedition to Kyushu in 1587, but he was said to be in charge of transporting military goods such as food provisions and weapons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし、先年の四国征伐と同様に九州征伐が比較的短期間で終わったことは、三成という有能な行政官僚が輜重を担当していたからだとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expedition to Kyushu finished in a short period as well as the expedition to Shikoku in the previous year because Mitsunari, who was a talented leader of bureaucrats, managed military goods transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expedition to Kyushu finished within a short period, as did the previous year&apos;s expedition to Shikoku, because Mitsunari, who was a talented leader of bureaucrats, had effectively managed the transport of military goods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expedition to Kyushu finished within a short period, as did the previous year&apos;s expedition to Shikoku, because Mitsunari, who was a talented leader of bureaucrats, had effectively managed the transport of military goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>九州征伐後、博多奉行となり博多復興に従事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the expedition to Kyushu, he became Hakata magistrate and worked for reconstruction of Hakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the expedition to Kyushu, he became a Hakata magistrate and worked on behalf of the reconstruction of Hakata.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the expedition to Kyushu, he became a Hakata magistrate and worked on behalf of the reconstruction of Hakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>天正16年（1588年）、島津義久の秀吉との謁見を斡旋する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari arranged Yoshihisa SHIMAZU&apos;s audience with Hideyoshi in 1588.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari arranged Yoshihisa SHIMAZU&apos;s audience with Hideyoshi in 1588.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari arranged Yoshihisa SHIMAZU&apos;s audience with Hideyoshi in 1588.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>天正17年（1589年）美濃国を検地する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He conducted Kenchi (survey of crop yields) in Mino-no-kuni in 1589.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He conducted kenchi (survey of crop yields) in Mino-no-kuni in 1589.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He conducted kenchi (survey of crop yields) in Mino Province in 1589.</e>
<cmt>地名表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>天正18年（1590年）の小田原征伐に参陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went on an expedition to Odawara in 1590.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went on an expedition to Odawara in 1590.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went on an expedition to Odawara in 1590.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>秀吉から後北条氏の支城の館林城、忍城攻撃を命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi gave Mitsunari an attack order of Tatebayashi Castle and Oshi Castle which were Gohojo clan&apos;s subsidiary castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi gave Mitsunari an order to attack the Tatebayashi and Oshi castles, which were subsidiary fortresses of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi gave Mitsunari an order to attack the Tatebayashi and Oshi Castles, which were subsidiary fortresses of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>castles→Castles</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>忍城攻めでは元荒川の水を城周囲に引き込む水攻めが行われ、その際の遺構が周囲に現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the event of the Oshi Castle attack, Mitsunari flooded the castle by carrying water from Moto-Arakawa River, and those remains are still existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the Oshi Castle attack, Mitsunari flooded the castle by carrying water from the Moto-Arakawa River, and the remains of the castle are still in existence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the Oshi Castle attack, Mitsunari flooded the castle by carrying water from the Moto-Arakawa River, and the remains of the castle are still in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>関東各地の後北条氏のほとんどの支城は本城である小田原城よりも先に陥落したが、忍城では小田原開城後の7月初旬まで戦闘が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most Gohojo clan&apos;s subsidiary castles in Kanto area fell before Odawara Castle which was the main castle fell, but even after the surrender of Odawara Castle, the attacking Oshi Castle continued till early July, 1590.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the Gohojo clan&apos;s subsidiary castles in the Kanto area had fallen prior to Odawara Castle, which was the main castle, but even after the surrender of Odawara Castle the attack on Oshi Castle continued till early July 1590.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the Gohojo clan&apos;s subsidiary castles in the Kanto area had fallen prior to Odawara Castle, which was the main castle, but even after the surrender of Odawara Castle the attack on Oshi Castle continued till early July 1590.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そのため、この城攻めは三成の戦下手の証拠であるとする書物が多いが、これには異説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, many documents say that the attacking Oshi Castle proves that Mitsunari was not good at fighting, but there are some heresies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, many documents say that the attack on Oshi Castle proves that Mitsunari was not good at fighting, but there are opposing theories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, many documents say that the attack on Oshi Castle proves that Mitsunari was not good at fighting, but there are opposing theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>なお三成は、常陸の佐竹義宣 (右京大夫)が秀吉に謁見するのを斡旋したり、奥州仕置の後、奥州の検地奉行を務めるなど着実に実績を重ねていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari had built up more and more works, such as arranging an audience with Hideyoshi for Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo-no-daibu, chief of Ukyoshiki government agency) who was from Hitachi and becoming Kenchi survey magistrate in Oshu after clamp down on Oshu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari had built up more and more works, such as arranging an audience with Hideyoshi for Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo-no-daibu, chief of Ukyoshiki government agency), who was from Hitachi, and becoming a kenchi (survey magistrate) in Oshu after the clamp-down on Oshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari had built up more and more works, such as arranging an audience with Hideyoshi for Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo-no-daibu, chief of Ukyoshiki government agency), who was from Hitachi, and becoming a kenchi bugyo(survey magistrate) in Oshu after the clamp-down on Oshu.</e>
<cmt>kenchi→kenchi bugyo原文が。で終わるように修正一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>有能な行政官僚としての功績は相変わらず大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari was a talented bureaucrat and rendered distinguish services.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari was a talented bureaucrat who rendered distinguish services.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari was a talented bureaucrat who rendered distinguish services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>文禄元年（1592年）、朝鮮出兵（文禄の役）が始まると朝鮮に渡海し、増田長盛、大谷吉継とともに朝鮮出兵の総奉行を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When dispatching troops to Korea (Bunroku no eki War), Mitsunari went to Korea as the So-bugyo magistrate with Nagamori MASHITA and Yoshitsugu OTANI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When dispatching troops to Korea (the Bunroku no eki War), Mitsunari went to Korea as the So-bugyo magistrate with Nagamori MASHITA and Yoshitsugu OTANI.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When dispatching troops to Korea (the Bunroku no eki War), Mitsunari went to Korea as the So-bugyo magistrate with Nagamori MASHITA and Yoshitsugu OTANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>文禄2年（1593年）、碧蹄館の戦い、幸州山城の戦いに参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan) and the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) in 1593.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan) and the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) in 1593.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in the Battle of Hekiteikan (ByeogJe Gwan) and the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) in 1593.</e>
<cmt>碧蹄館→hekiteikan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その後明軍の講和使謝用梓・徐一貫を伴って肥前・名護屋に戻るなど、明との講和交渉に積極的役割を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he went back to Hizen and Nagoya with SHA Yo Sho and Jo Ikkan who were emissaries of pacification in Ming army and had an active role in peace negotiations with Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he returned to Hizen and Nagoya with SHA Yo Sho and Jo Ikkan, who were emissaries of pacification in the Ming army, and had an active role in peace negotiations with Ming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he returned to Nagoya in Hizen Province with SHA Yo Sho and Jo Ikkan, who were emissaries of pacification in the Ming army, and had an active role in peace negotiations with Ming.</e>
<cmt>Hizen and Nagoya→Nagoya in Hizen province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、この行動は豊臣家中で福島正則ら武断派の反発を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Budan-ha (person who carried out politics by military means) that were known by Masanori FUKUSHIMA who was one of the Toyotomi Family was opposed to his conduct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the budan-ha (person who carried out politics by military means) who was known by Masanori FUKUSHIMA, one of the Toyotomi Family, was opposed to his conduct.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the budan-ha group (people who carried out politics by military means) which was known by Masanori FUKUSHIMA, one of the Toyotomi Family, was opposed to his conduct.</e>
<cmt>budan-ha→budan-ha group</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>文禄3年（1594年）、島津氏・佐竹氏の領国を奉行として検地する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari conducted Kenchi (survey of crop yields) in Shimazu clan&apos;s domain and Satake clan&apos;s domain as Kenchi survey magistrate in 1594.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari conducted kenchi (survey of crop yields) in the domains of the Shimazu and Satake clans as a survey magistrate in 1594.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari conducted kenchi (survey of crop yields) in the domains of the Shimazu and Satake clans as a survey magistrate in 1594.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）、秀吉の甥・豊臣秀次を謀反の嫌疑により糾問する（秀次事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari accused Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI of plotting a coup (called Hidetsugu Incident) in 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari accused Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, of plotting a coup (which became known as the Hidetsugu Incident) in 1595.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari accused Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, of plotting a coup (which became known as the Hidetsugu Incident) in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>秀次の死後、その旧領のうち近江7万石が三成の代官地になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hidetsugu&apos;s death, Mitsunari received Omi with 70,000 koku which was a part of Hidetsugu&apos;s domain as Daikanchi (place to govern).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hidetsugu&apos;s death, Mitsunari received Omi with 70,000 koku, which was a part of Hidetsugu&apos;s domain as a daikanchi (place to govern).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hidetsugu&apos;s death, Mitsunari received Omi with 70,000 koku, which was a part of Hidetsugu&apos;s domain as a daikanchi (place to govern).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、同年に近江佐和山19万4000石の所領を秀吉から与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he was also given a territory of Sawayama, Omi with 190,4000 koku by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Hideyoshi also gave him the territory of Sawayama, Omi, with 190,4000 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Hideyoshi also gave him the territory of Sawayama, Omi, with 194,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="38">
<j>慶長元年（1596年）、佐和山領内に十三ヶ条掟書、九ヶ条掟書を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He enacted Jusan-kajo no Okitegami (thirteen articles of rule) and Kyu-kajo no Okitegami (nine articles of rule) in his Sawayama domain in 1596.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He enacted Jusan-kajo no Okitegami (13 articles of rule) and Kyu-kajo no Okitegami (nine articles of rule) in his Sawayama domain in 1596.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He enacted Jusan-kajo no Okitegaki (13 articles of rule) and Kyu-kajo no Okitegaki (nine articles of rule) in his Sawayama domain in 1596.</e>
<cmt>okitegami→okitegaki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>明の講話使節を接待。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entertained an emissary of pacification from Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entertained an emissary of pacification from Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entertained an emissary of pacification from Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>同年、京都奉行に任じられ、秀吉の命令でキリシタン弾圧を命じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This year, he was appointed as Kyoto magistrate and was ordered to clamp down on Christian by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That year, he was appointed as Kyoto magistrate and was ordered by Hideyoshi to clamp down on Christians.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That year, he was appointed as Kyoto magistrate and was ordered by Hideyoshi to clamp down on Christians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ただし、三成はこのときに捕らえるキリシタンの数を極力減らしたり、秀吉の怒りをなだめて信徒たちが処刑されないように奔走するなどの情誼を見せたという（日本二十六聖人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this incident, Mitsunari showed friendly feeling such as trying to reduce the number of Christians to be caught and also placated Hideyoshi for not executing the Christians. (The Twenty-Six Martyrs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this incident, Mitsunari showed friendly feelings such as trying to reduce the number of Christians to be caught, and also placated Hideyoshi in order to prevent the execution of Christians (the 26 martyrs).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this incident, Mitsunari showed friendly feelings such as trying to reduce the number of Christians to be caught, and also placated Hideyoshi in order to prevent the execution of Christians (the 26 martyrs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）、慶長の役が始まると再び明・朝鮮との講和交渉に奔走するが不調に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Keicho-no-eki War started in 1597, he tried to make peace overtures to Ming and Korea again, but failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Keicho-no-eki War started in 1597, he tried again to make overtures of peace to Ming and Korea, but these efforts failed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Keicho-no-eki War started in 1597, he tried again to make overtures of peace to Ming and Korea, but these efforts failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）8月、豊臣秀吉が死去すると、朝鮮に在陣していた諸大名の撤兵に尽力したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to make effort to pull troops out from Korea in August, 1598 after Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that he had endeavored to pull troops out of Korea in August 1598, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that he had endeavored to pull troops out of Korea in August 1598, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>秀吉死後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi&apos;s Death</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>秀吉の死後、豊臣氏の家督は嫡男の豊臣秀頼が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death, his legitimate son Hideyori TOYOTOMI took over the family estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death, his legitimate son Hideyori TOYOTOMI took over the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death, his legitimate son Hideyori TOYOTOMI took over the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし、次の天下人の座を狙う関東250万石の大老・徳川家康が次第に台頭してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tairo (chief minister) Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who was lord of Kanto with 2,500,000 koku gradually rose up as a Tenkabito (ruler of the country.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tairo (Chief Minister) Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who was the lord of Kanto with 2,500,000 koku, gradually rose up as a tenkabito (ruler of the country).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tairo (Chief Minister) Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who was the lord of Kanto with 2,500,000 koku, gradually rose up as a tenkabito (ruler of the country).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>家康は覇権奪取のため、三成と敵対関係にあった福島正則や加藤清正、黒田長政らと、豊臣氏に無断で次々と縁戚関係を結んでゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu established relations by affinity between he and Mitsunari&apos;s adversaries such as Masanori FUKUSHIMA, Kiyomasa KATO and Nagamasa KURODA without permission of Toyotomi clan to gain the supremacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu established relations by affinity between himself and Mitsunari&apos;s adversaries, such as Masanori FUKUSHIMA, Kiyomasa KATO and Nagamasa KURODA, without the permission of Toyotomi clan, doing so in order to gain supremacy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu established relations by affinity between himself and Mitsunari&apos;s adversaries, such as Masanori FUKUSHIMA, Kiyomasa KATO and Nagamasa KURODA, without the permission of the Toyotomi clan, doing so in order to gain supremacy.</e>
<cmt>Toyotomi clan→the Toyotomi clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>慶長4年（1599年）1月、三成は家康の無断婚姻を「秀吉が生前の文禄4年（1595年）に制定した無許可縁組禁止の法に違反する」として、前田利家らと諮り、家康に問罪使を派遣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari consulted with Toshiie MAEDA and dispatched an envoy to be suspect of the crime to Ieyasu in January, 1599 because Ieyasu&apos;s relationship by affinity violated the law of the Act of banning marriage without authorization which Hideyoshi settled in 1595 before his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari consulted with Toshiie MAEDA and in January 1599 dispatched an envoy to Ieyasu in order to investigate the crime because Ieyasu&apos;s relationship by affinity violated the law of the act banning marriage without authorization, which Hideyoshi had instituted in 1595.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari consulted with Toshiie MAEDA and in January 1599 dispatched an envoy to Ieyasu in order to investigate the crime because Ieyasu&apos;s relationship by affinity violated the law of the act banning marriage without authorization, which Hideyoshi had instituted in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>家康も豊臣政権の中で孤立する不利を悟って、2月2日に利家・三成らと誓紙を交わして和睦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu sensed his disadvantage and came to terms with Toshiie and Mitsunari on February 2nd, exchanging the written oath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu sensed his disadvantage and came to terms with Toshiie and Mitsunari on February 2, exchanging a written oath.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu sensed his disadvantage and came to terms with Toshiie and Mitsunari on February 2, exchanging a written oath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>しかし、閏3月3日に家康と互角の勢力を持っていた大老・前田利家が病死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tairo (chief minister), Toshiie MAEDA who kept evenly balanced power with Ieyasu, died from disease on Intercalary March 3rd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tairo (Chief Minister) Toshiie MAEDA, who kept evenly balanced power with Ieyasu, died of a disease on the intercalary date of March 3.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tairo (Chief Minister) Toshiie MAEDA, who kept evenly balanced power with Ieyasu, died of a disease on the third day of intercalary third month.</e>
<cmt>閏3月3日の訳を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>その直後、三成と敵対関係にあった武断派の加藤清正、福島正則、黒田長政、細川忠興、浅野幸長、池田輝政、加藤嘉明の7将（史料によっては蜂須賀家政や藤堂高虎の名もある）が、三成の大坂屋敷を襲撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right after his death, Mitsunari&apos;s adversary group Budan-ha including seven lords; Kiyomasa KATO, Masanori FUKUSHIMA, Nagamasa KURODA, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Yoshinaga ASANO, Terumasa IKEDA and Yoshiaki KATO attacked Mitsunari&apos;s Osaka residence. (Iemasa HACHISUKA and Takatora TODO were also included according to some documents.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Right after his death, Mitsunari&apos;s adversary group Budan-ha, including seven lords--Kiyomasa KATO, Masanori FUKUSHIMA, Nagamasa KURODA, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Yoshinaga ASANO, Terumasa IKEDA and Yoshiaki KATO--attacked Mitsunari&apos;s Osaka residence (Iemasa HACHISUKA and Takatora TODO were also included, according to some documents).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Right after his death, Mitsunari&apos;s adversary group Budan-ha, including seven lords--Kiyomasa KATO, Masanori FUKUSHIMA, Nagamasa KURODA, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Yoshinaga ASANO, Terumasa IKEDA and Yoshiaki KATO--attacked Mitsunari&apos;s Osaka residence (Iemasa HACHISUKA and Takatora TODO were also included, according to some documents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし三成は事前に佐竹義宣の助力を得て大坂から脱出し、伏見城内に逃れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari escaped from Osaka to Fushimi Castle by Yoshinobu SATAKE&apos;s help in advance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari, however, had already escaped from Osaka to Fushimi Castle with the help of Yoshinobu SATAKE.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari, however, had already escaped from Osaka to Fushimi Castle with the help of Yoshinobu SATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この後7将と三成は伏見で睨みあう状況となるが、仲裁に乗り出した家康により和談が成立し、三成は五奉行からの退隠を承諾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Mitsunari was standoff with seven lords in Fushimi, however, they made peace by arrangement of Ieyasu and Mitsunari agreed on retirement giving up a title of five major magistrate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari then found himself in a standoff with seven lords in Fushimi, but they made peace through the arrangements of Ieyasu and Mitsunari agreed to retire, giving up the title to five major magistrates.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari then found himself in a standoff with seven lords in Fushimi, but they made peace through the arrangements of Ieyasu and Mitsunari agreed to retire, giving up the title to five major magistrates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>3月10日、三成は家康の次男・結城秀康に守られて、佐和山城に帰城した（この事件時、三成が単身で向島の家康の屋敷に難を逃れたとする書物が多いが、これらの典拠となっている資料は明治期以降の「日本戦史・関原役」などである）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari went back to Sawayama Castle guarded by the Ieyasu&apos;s second son, Hideyasu YUKI on March 10th. (There are some documents which say that Mitsunari escaped to Ieyasu&apos;s residence in Mukojima in this incident, however, their sources such as &quot;History of Japanese Warfare, Sekigahara-no-eki&quot; were written after Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari returned to Sawayama Castle guarded by the Ieyasu&apos;s second son, Hideyasu YUKI, on March 10 (some documents state that Mitsunari escaped to Ieyasu&apos;s residence in Mukojima in this incident but their sources, such as &quot;History of Japanese Warfare, Sekigahara-no-eki,&quot; were written after the Meiji period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari returned to Sawayama Castle guarded by the Ieyasu&apos;s second son, Hideyasu YUKI, on March 10 (some documents state that Mitsunari escaped to Ieyasu&apos;s residence in Mukojima in this incident but their sources, such as &quot;History of Japanese Warfare, Sekigahara-no-eki,&quot; were written after the Meiji period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>江戸期に成立した史料に三成が家康屋敷に赴いたことを示すものはない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no source written in Edo Period, which mentioned that Mitsunari visited Ieyasu&apos;s residence.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(There is no source written in the Edo period mentioned that Mitsunari had visited Ieyasu&apos;s residence.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There is no source written in the Edo period mentioned that Mitsunari had visited Ieyasu&apos;s residence.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>利家の死去・三成の蟄居により、家康の専横は再び活発になり、一旦白紙にしていた無断婚姻や秀吉の遺命で禁止されていた所領配分なども実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu acted arbitrarily again due to Toshiie&apos;s death and Mitsunari&apos;s staying at home, then, he promoted unauthorized marriages which had been called off once and conducted distribution of territory which Hideyoshi interdicted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu acted arbitrarily again due to Toshiie&apos;s death and because Mitsunari had remained at home, whereupon he promoted unauthorized marriages that had once been called off and conducted the distribution of territory in which Hideyoshi had interdicted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu acted arbitrarily again due to Toshiie&apos;s death and because Mitsunari had remained at home, whereupon he promoted unauthorized marriages that had once been called off and conducted the distribution of territory in which Hideyoshi had interdicted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>9月、家康が重陽の節句による祝意を秀頼に述べるため大坂に赴いたとき、三成の屋敷を宿所としたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Ieyasu stayed at Mitsunari&apos;s residence when Ieyasu went to Osaka to see Hideyori in celebration of his Chrysanthemum Festival in September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ieyasu stayed at Mitsunari&apos;s residence when Ieyasu went to Osaka to see Hideyori in celebration of his Chrysanthemum Festival in September.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ieyasu stayed at Mitsunari&apos;s residence when Ieyasu went to Osaka to see Hideyori in celebration of his Chrysanthemum Festival in September.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）7月、三成は家康を排除すべく、上杉景勝・直江兼続らと密かに挙兵の計画を図る（この密約は無かったという説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari hatched up a plan with Kagekatsu UESUGI and Kanetsugu NAOE to defeat Ieyasu in July 1600. (There is a theory that there was no such a secret plot.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari devised a plan along with Kagekatsu UESUGI and Kanetsugu NAOE to defeat Ieyasu in July 1600 (but one theory asserts that no such secret plot existed).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari devised a plan along with Kagekatsu UESUGI and Kanetsugu NAOE to defeat Ieyasu in July 1600 (but one theory asserts that no such secret plot existed).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>その後上杉勢が公然と家康に対して叛旗を翻し、家康は諸大名を従えて会津征伐に赴いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, as Uesugi&apos;s army stood in open rebellion against Ieyasu, Ieyasu went on an expedition to Aizu with feudal lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, as Uesugi&apos;s army stood in open rebellion against Ieyasu, Ieyasu went on an expedition to Aizu with various feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, as Uesugi&apos;s army stood in open rebellion against Ieyasu, Ieyasu went on an expedition to Aizu with various feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これを東西から家康を挟撃する好機として挙兵を決意した三成は、大谷吉継を味方に引き込もうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari made a decision to attack Ieyasu using this opportunity which could attack Ieyasu in a pincer movement from east and west, and tried to get Yoshitugu Otani on his side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari made a decision to attack Ieyasu, using it as an opportunity to effect a pincer strategy by closing in from the east and west, and tried to get Yoshitugu Otani on his side.</e>
<cmt>grammar, YOSHITSUGU</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari made a decision to attack Ieyasu, using it as an opportunity to effect a pincer strategy by closing in from the east and west, and tried to get Yoshitsugu OTANI on his side.</e>
<cmt>Yoshitsugu OTANI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>吉継は、家康と対立することは無謀であるとして反対したが、三成との友誼などもあって承諾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsugu thought that conflicting against Ieyasu was reckless and opposed Mitsunari, however, he accepted Mitsunari because of their affection as an acquaintance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsugu thought it would be reckless to have a conflict with Ieyasu and therefore opposed Mitsunari, but he accepted Mitsunari&apos;s plan because of their mutual affection as acquaintances.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsugu thought it would be reckless to have a conflict with Ieyasu and therefore opposed Mitsunari, but he accepted Mitsunari&apos;s plan because of their mutual affection as acquaintances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>7月12日、兄・正澄を奉行として近江愛知川に関所を設置し、家康に従って会津征伐に向かう後発の西国大名、鍋島勝茂や前田茂勝らの東下を阻止し、強引に自陣営（西軍）に与させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 12th, appointing his brother Masazumi as a magistrate and setting up the checkpoint at Echigawa, Omi, Mitsunari stopped Saikoku Daimyos (feudal lords in countries western from Kinki district) such as Katsushige NABESHIMA and Shigekatsu MAEDA to go on an expedition to Aizu under Ieyasu&apos;s command and gained them over into his side (West squad) forcefully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 12, having appointed his brother Masazumi as a magistrate and established the checkpoint at Echigawa, Omi, Mitsunari prevented the saikoku daimyo (feudal lords in countries west of the Kinki district) such as Katsushige NABESHIMA and Shigekatsu MAEDA from going on an expedition to Aizu under Ieyasu&apos;s command, and forcibly moved them over to his side (the western army).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 12, having appointed his brother Masazumi as a magistrate and established the checkpoint at Echigawa, Omi, Mitsunari prevented the saikoku daimyo (feudal lords in countries west of the Kinki district) such as Katsushige NABESHIMA and Shigekatsu MAEDA from going on an expedition to Aizu under Ieyasu&apos;s command, and forcibly moved them over to his side (the western army).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>7月13日、三成は諸大名の妻子を人質として大坂城内に入れるため軍勢を送り込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari sent army to take feudal lords&apos; family as hostages and to keep them in Osaka Castle on July 13th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 13, Mitsunari sent the army to take the feudal lords&apos; families as hostages and keep them in Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 13, Mitsunari sent the army to take the feudal lords&apos; families as hostages and keep them in Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>しかし加藤清正の妻をはじめとする一部には脱出され、さらに細川忠興の正室・細川ガラシャ（明智光秀の娘）に人質となることを拒絶され屋敷に火を放って死を選ぶという壮烈な最期を見せられて、人質作戦は中止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some wives escaped such as Kiyomasa KATO&apos;s wife and moreover, Garasha HOSOKAWA, who was Tadaoki HOSAKAWA&apos;s official wife and Mitsuhide Akechi&apos;s daughter, rejected to be taken as a hostage and committed suicide by setting fire on her residence and died a tragic death, therefore, this operation was failed and stopped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some of the wives escaped, including that of Kiyomasa KATO, and moreover, Garasha HOSOKAWA, who was Tadaoki HOSAKAWA&apos;s official wife and Mitsuhide Akechi&apos;s daughter, refused to be taken as a hostage and committed suicide by setting fire to her residence, which resulted in her tragic death; therefore, the operation was deemed a failure and stopped.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some of the wives escaped, including that of Kiyomasa KATO, and moreover, Garasha HOSOKAWA, who was Tadaoki HOSAKAWA&apos;s official wife and Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s daughter, refused to be taken as a hostage and committed suicide by setting fire to her residence, which resulted in her tragic death; therefore, the operation was deemed a failure and stopped.</e>
<cmt>Mitsuhide AKECHI（苗字を大文字に）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>7月17日、毛利輝元を西軍の総大将として大坂城に入城させ、同時に前田玄以・増田長盛・長束正家の三奉行連署からなる家康の罪状13か条を書き連ねた弾劾状を諸大名に公布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari appointed Terumoto MORI as a captain general of the West squad and made him to enter the Osaka Castle on July 17th, and also issued and sent feudal lords an impeachment letter with thirteen articles of the charge signed by three magistrates (Geni MAEDA, Nagamori Masuda and Masaie NATSUKA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari appointed Terumoto MORI as a captain general of the western army and instructed him to enter Osaka Castle on July 17, and he also sent to feudal lords an impeachment letter bearing thirteen articles of the charges signed by three magistrates (Geni MAEDA, Nagamori Masuda and Masaie NATSUKA).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari appointed Terumoto MORI as a captain general of the western army and instructed him to enter Osaka Castle on July 17, and he also sent to feudal lords an impeachment letter bearing thirteen articles of the charges signed by three magistrates (Geni MAEDA, Nagamori MASUDA and Masaie NATSUKA).</e>
<cmt>Nagamori MASUDA（苗字を大文字に）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>7月18日、西軍は家康の重臣・鳥居元忠が守る伏見城を攻めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The West squad attacked the Fushimi Castle which was protected by Ieyasu&apos;s main retainer Mototada TORII on July 18th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 18, the western army attacked Fushimi Castle, which was protected by Ieyasu&apos;s main retainer Mototada TORII.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 18, the western army attacked Fushimi Castle, which was protected by Ieyasu&apos;s main retainer Mototada TORII.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>しかし伏見城は堅固で鳥居軍の抵抗は激しく、容易に陥落しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Fushimi Castle didn&apos;t fall easily because of its impregnability and resistance of Torii&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Fushimi Castle didn&apos;t fall easily because of its impregnability and the resistance that Torii&apos;s army was able to mount.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Fushimi Castle didn&apos;t fall easily because of its impregnability and the resistance that Torii&apos;s army was able to mount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>そこで三成は、鳥居の配下に甲賀衆がいるのを見て、長束正家と共に甲賀衆の家族を人質にとって脅迫する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari and Masaie NATSUKA took families of Kogashu as hostages and threatened Kogashu (local samurai based on Koga-gun, Omi) who serviced under Torii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari and Masaie NATSUKA took the families of Kogashu as hostages and threatened the kogashu (local samurai based in Koga-gun, Omi) who served under Torii.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari and Masaie NATSUKA took the families of Kogashu as hostages and threatened the kogashu (local samurai based in Koga County, Omi) who served under Torii.</e>
<cmt>gun→County</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>8月1日、甲賀衆は三成の要求に従って城門を内側から開けて裏切り、伏見城は陥落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1st, as Kogashu accepted Mitsunari&apos;s request and opened the castle gate from inside, Fushimi Castle fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, as Kogashu accepted Mitsunari&apos;s request and opened the castle gate from the inside, Fushimi Castle fell.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, as Kogashu accepted Mitsunari&apos;s request and opened the castle gate from the inside, Fushimi Castle fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>8月2日、三成は伏見城陥落を諸大名に伝えるべく、毛利輝元や宇喜多秀家、さらに自らも連署して全国に公布する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 2nd, Mitsunari issued a declaration, which was cosigned by Mitsunari, Terumoto MORI and Hideie UKITA and meant about Fushimi Castle fall, to feudal lords across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 2, Mitsunari issued to feudal lords across the country a declaration, cosigned by Mitsunari, Terumoto MORI and Hideie UKITA, stating that Fushimi Castle had fallen.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 2, Mitsunari issued to feudal lords across the country a declaration, cosigned by Mitsunari, Terumoto MORI and Hideie UKITA, stating that Fushimi Castle had fallen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="70">
<j>8月からは伊勢方面の平定に務めたが、家康ら東軍の反転西上が予想以上に早かったため、三成は関ヶ原で野戦を挑むことを決める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Mitsunari had served to rule over Ise region since August, he made a decision to fight in Sekigahara field due to Ieyasu&apos;s quick inverting attack to west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Mitsunari had ruled over the Ise region since August, he made a decision to fight in the fields of Sekigahara due to Ieyasu&apos;s quick inverting attack to the west.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Mitsunari had ruled over the Ise region since August, he made a decision to fight in the fields of Sekigahara due to Ieyasu&apos;s quick inverting attack to the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>そして9月15日、東軍と西軍による天下分け目の戦いである関ヶ原の戦いが始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most famous fateful battle between the East squad and the West squad, the Battle of Sekigahara started on September 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the most famous and fateful battles between the eastern and western armies, the Battle of Sekigahara, started on September 15.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the most famous and fateful battles between the eastern and western armies, the Battle of Sekigahara, started on September 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>当初は西軍優勢であり、石田隊は6900人であったが、細川忠興・黒田長政・加藤嘉明・田中吉政ら兵力では倍以上の敵に攻められたものの、島左近・蒲生郷舎・舞兵庫らの奮戦もあって持ちこたえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, the West squad was dominant and Mitsunari&apos;s army 6,900 strong could hold out against more than twice army strong leaded by Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Nagamasa KURODA, Yoshiaki KATO and Yoshimasa TANAKA because Sakon SHIMA, Satoie GAMO and Hyogo MAI fought up bravely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the western army was dominant and Mitsunari&apos;s army of 6,900 could hold out against more than twice that number led by Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Nagamasa KURODA, Yoshiaki KATO and Yoshimasa TANAKA, because Sakon SHIMA, Satoie GAMO and Hyogo MAI fought so bravely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the western army was dominant and Mitsunari&apos;s army of 6,900 could hold out against more than twice that number led by Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Nagamasa KURODA, Yoshiaki KATO and Yoshimasa TANAKA, because Sakon SHIMA, Satoie GAMO and Hyogo MAI fought so bravely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>しかし西軍全体では戦意の低い部隊が多く、次第に不利となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, overall, the troops of the West squad had less will to fight and gradually became disadvantageous.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the troops of the western army generally had less will to fight and gradually found themselves at a disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the troops of the western army generally had less will to fight and gradually found themselves at a disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>最終的には小早川秀秋や脇坂安治らの裏切りによって西軍は総崩れとなり、三成は戦場から逃走して伊吹山に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last, the West squad was routed due to betrayal of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA and Yasuharu WAKIZAKA, therefore, Mitsunari escaped from the battle field to Mt. Ibuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At last, the western army was routed due to the betrayal of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA and Yasuharu WAKIZAKA; therefore, Mitsunari escaped from the battlefield to Mt. Ibuki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At last, the western army was routed due to the betrayal of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA and Yasuharu WAKIZAKA; therefore, Mitsunari escaped from the battlefield to Mt. Ibuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="75">
<j>その後、伊吹山の東にある相川山を越えて春日村に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he crossed the Mt. Aikawa which was located east side of the Mt. Ibuki and escaped to Kasuga-mura Village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then crossed Mt. Aikawa, located on the eastern side of Mt. Ibuki, and escaped to Kasuga-mura Village.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then crossed Mt. Aikawa, located on the eastern side of Mt. Ibuki, and escaped to Kasuga-mura Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>このとき、三成は極度の空腹から沢の水を飲み、生米を食べたため、下痢を起こしたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that at that time Mitsunari drank straight from the stream and ate uncooked rice from hunger, so he suffered from diarrhea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that at that time Mitsunari drank straight from the stream and ate uncooked rice to stave off his hunger, so he suffered from diarrhea.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that at that time Mitsunari drank straight from the stream and ate uncooked rice to stave off his hunger, so he suffered from diarrhea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その後、春日村から新穂峠を迂回して姉川に出た三成は、曲谷を出て七廻り峠から草野谷に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he went out the way to Shimbo-toge Pass and got to Ane-gawa River from Kasuga-mura Village, then, he entered Kusanotani through Magatani and Nanamawari-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he took the route out through Shimbo-toge Pass and reached the Ane-gawa River from Kasuga-mura Village, whereupon he entered Kusanotani through Magatani and the Nanamawari-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, from Kasuga-mura Village, he took the route out through Shimbo-toge Pass and reached the Ane-gawa River, whereupon he entered Kusanotani through Magatani and the Nanamawari-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>そして、小谷山の谷口から高時川の上流に出、古橋に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then went to the upstream of Takatoki-gawa River from a threshold of the valley and escaped to Furuhashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then traveled upstream of the Takatoki-gawa River from a threshold of the valley and escaped to Furuhashi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then traveled upstream of the Takatoki-gawa River from a threshold of the valley of Mt. Odani and escaped to Furuhashi.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Odani　を補う</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし9月21日、家康の命令を受けて三成を捜索していた田中吉政の追捕隊に捕縛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was caught by Yoshimasa TANAKA&apos;s troops who were searching Mitsunari under Ieyasu&apos;s command on September 21st.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on September 21 he was caught by Yoshimasa TANAKA&apos;s troops who had been searching for Mitsunari under Ieyasu&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on September 21 he was caught by Yoshimasa TANAKA&apos;s troops who had been searching for Mitsunari under Ieyasu&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="80">
<j>一方、9月18日に東軍の攻撃を受けて三成の居城・佐和山城は落城し、三成の父・正継をはじめとする石田一族の多くは討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sawayama Castle which was a residence of Mitsunari fell by the East squad attacks on September 18th and Mitsunari&apos;s father, Masatsugu and most Ishida family died in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sawayama Castle, which was a residence of Mitsunari, fell under attack by the eastern army on September 18, and Mitsunari&apos;s father Masatsugu and most of the Ishida family died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sawayama Castle, which was a residence of Mitsunari, fell under attack by the eastern army on September 18, and Mitsunari&apos;s father Masatsugu and most of the Ishida family died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="81">
<j>9月22日、大津城に護送されて大津城の門前で生き曝しにされ、その後家康と会見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 22nd, Mitsunari was escorted to Otsu Castle to be kept on public display and then met Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 22, Mitsunari was escorted to Otsu Castle to be kept on public display, after which he was brought before Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 22, Mitsunari was escorted to Otsu Castle to be kept on public display, after which he was brought before Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>9月27日、大坂に護送され、9月28日には小西行長、安国寺恵瓊らと共に大坂・堺を罪人として引き回された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 27th, he was escorted to Osaka and the next day he was pulled around in Osaka and Sakai as criminal as well as Yukinaga KONISHI and Ekei ANKOKUJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was escorted to Osaka on September 27, and the next day he was pulled through Osaka and Sakai as a criminal along with Yukinaga KONISHI and Ekei ANKOKUJI.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was escorted to Osaka on September 27, and the next day he was pulled through Osaka and Sakai as a criminal along with Yukinaga KONISHI and Ekei ANKOKUJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>9月29日、京都に護送され、奥平信昌（京都所司代）の監視下に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 29th, he was escorted to Kyoto and was placed under supervision of Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto), Nobumasa OKUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 29, he was escorted to Kyoto and was placed under the supervision of the Kyoto shoshidai (the local governor of Kyoto), Nobumasa OKUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 29, he was escorted to Kyoto and was placed under the supervision of the Kyoto shoshidai (the local governor of Kyoto), Nobumasa OKUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="84">
<j>10月1日、家康の命により六条河原で斬首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1st, he was decapitated at Rokujo-gawara, place of execution by Ieyasu&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, he was decapitated at Rokujo-gawara, the place of execution, by order of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 1, he was decapitated at Rokujo-gawara, the place of execution, by order of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>享年41。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 41 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 41 years old.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 41 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>首は三条河原に晒された後、生前親交のあった春屋宗園・沢庵宗彭に引き取られ京都大徳寺の三玄院に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his head was pilloried at Sanjo-gawara, it was taken under care of Soen SHUNOKU and Soho TAKUAN, who formed close relationship with Mitsunari and was buried at Sangenin in Daitoku-ji Temple, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his head was pilloried at Sanjo-gawara, it was placed in the care of Soen SHUNOKU and Soho TAKUAN, who had formed close relationships with Mitsunari, and was buried at Sangenin in Daitoku-ji Temple, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his head was pilloried at Sanjo-gawara, it was placed in the care of Soen SHUNOKU and Soho TAKUAN, who had formed close relationships with Mitsunari, and was buried at Sangenin in Daitoku-ji Temple, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>辞世の句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death haiku Japanese poem</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Japanese Haiku of Death</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Japanese Haiku of Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>筑摩江や　芦間に灯す　かがり火と　ともに消えゆく　我が身なりけり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">My life will soon be burnt out like the torches in the reed at Chikumae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">My life will soon be burnt out, like the torches in the reeds at Chikumae.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">My life will soon be burnt out, like the torches in the reeds at Chikumae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いで敗走した三成は近江（滋賀県）の古橋村に身を潜めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his defeat in the Battle of Sekigahara, he escaped and holed up in Furuhashi-mura Village, Omi (Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his defeat in the Battle of Sekigahara, he escaped and holed up in Furuhashi-mura Village, Omi (Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his defeat in the Battle of Sekigahara, he escaped and holed up in Furuhashi-mura Village, Omi (Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>そのときに村人たちに「このように逃れてきたのはふたたび家康と一戦を交え、天下を統一する所存であるからだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Mitsunari said to the villagers, &quot;The reason I escaped was for fighting with Ieyasu again and for ruling the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Mitsunari said to the villagers, &quot;The reason I escaped was for fighting with Ieyasu again and for ruling the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Mitsunari said to the villagers, &quot;The reason I escaped was for fighting with Ieyasu again and for ruling the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>統一の暁には、古橋から湖（琵琶湖）までの間を大きな平野となし、道は全部石畳にする」と言い、村人たちはこの言葉にひかれて石田三成を匿った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once ruling the country, I will build the wide field between Furuhashi and the Lake Biwa and will make all roads stone paved,&quot; and the villagers were attracted to what he said and harbored him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He said, &quot;Once I rule the country, I will build a wide field between Furuhashi and Lake Biwa and will make all roads stone-paved,&quot; so the villagers were attracted to what he said and harbored him.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He said, &quot;Once I rule the country, I will build a wide field between Furuhashi and Lake Biwa and will make all roads stone-paved,&quot; so the villagers were attracted to what he said and harbored him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>しかし隣村出身の与次郎太夫という者が裏切ったため三成は捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yojiro-dayu from nearby village betrayed him and Mitsunari was caught.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yojiro-dayu, of a nearby village, betrayed Mitsunari, and as a result he was captured.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yojiro-dayu, of a nearby village, betrayed Mitsunari, and as a result he was captured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="92">
<j>前田利家の死後、加藤清正・福島正則らが三成を襲撃するという事件が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Toshiie MAEDA&apos;s death, Mitsunari&apos;s adversaries such as Kiyomasa KATO and Masanori FUKUSHIMA attacked Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the death of Toshiie MAEDA, Mitsunari&apos;s adversaries such as Kiyomasa KATO and Masanori FUKUSHIMA attacked him.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the death of Toshiie MAEDA, Mitsunari&apos;s adversaries such as Kiyomasa KATO and Masanori FUKUSHIMA attacked him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>家康の仲裁よって三成は奉行を辞し佐和山城に蟄居することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari resigned the magistrate and stayed at his residence Sawayama Castle due to Ieyasu&apos;s arbitration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari resigned from the magistrate and stayed at his residence of Sawayama Castle due to Ieyasu&apos;s arbitration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari resigned from the magistrate and stayed at his residence of Sawayama Castle due to Ieyasu&apos;s arbitration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>三成が佐和山城への護送役をつとめた結城秀康に「無銘正宗」を贈ると、秀康はこれを喜び、「石田正宗｣と名付けて終生大切にしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari gave a sword called &quot;Mumei Masamune (sword without the Masamune&apos;s name)&quot; to Hideyasu Yuki who escorted him to Sawayama Castle, and Hideyasu loved it and took good care of it all his life naming it &quot;Masamune ISHIDA.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari gave a sword called &quot;Mumei Masamune (sword without the Masamune name)&quot; to Hideyasu Yuki, who had escorted him to Sawayama Castle; Hideyasu loved it and took good care of it all his life, calling it &quot;Masamune ISHIDA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari gave a sword called &quot;Mumei Masamune (sword without the Masamune&apos;s name)&quot; to Hideyasu Yuki, who had escorted him to Sawayama Castle; Hideyasu loved it and took good care of it all his life, calling it &quot;Masamune ISHIDA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Masamune&apos;s name</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この「正宗」は三成が秀吉から拝領したものといわれるが、江戸時代の享保期に出版された書物｢刀剣名物帳」では、毛利輝元が所持していたものを宇喜多秀家が買い取り、三成に贈ったと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sword &quot;Masamune&quot; was said to be given to Mitsunari by Hideyoshi, however, the document &quot;Token-Meibutsucho&quot; (special swords book) issued in Kyoho period of Edo era said that Hideie UKITA bought it from Terumoto MORI and gave it to Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;Masamune&quot; sword was said to be given to Mitsunari by Hideyoshi, but the document &quot;Token-Meibutsucho (Book of Special Swords)&quot; issued in the Kyoho era of the Edo period said that Hideie UKITA bought it from Terumoto MORI and then gave it to Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &quot;Masamune&quot; sword was said to be given to Mitsunari by Hideyoshi, but the document &quot;Token-Meibutsucho (Book of Special Swords)&quot; issued in the Kyoho era of the Edo period said that Hideie UKITA bought it from Terumoto MORI and then gave it to Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="96">
<j>徳川家康が三成に側室として送り込んだくノ一といわれるのが初芽局である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari&apos;s concubine, Hatsume-no-Tsubone was a Kunoichi, women Ninja (a group of secret agents) sent by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari&apos;s concubine, Hatsume-no-Tsubone, was a kunoichi (a female ninja and part of a group of secret agents) sent by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari&apos;s concubine, Hatsume-no-Tsubone, was a kunoichi (a female ninja and part of a group of secret agents) sent by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>しかし彼女はまっすぐな性格の三成に惚れてしまい、徳川を裏切り、ついに徳川方に殺されたといわれる（モデルとなった女性は実在するらしく、子孫を自称する人物がいるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as she loved Mitsunari who had straightforward character and betrayed Tokugawa, she was killed by Tokugawa side. (This Kunoichi was said to be existed and there are some people claimed to be her descendent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because she loved Mitsunari who had straightforward character, and betrayed Tokugawa, she was killed by the Tokugawa side (this Kunoichi was said to truly exist, and some have claimed to be her descendents).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because she loved Mitsunari who had straightforward character, and betrayed Tokugawa, she was killed by the Tokugawa side (this Kunoichi was said to truly exist, and some have claimed to be her descendents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>初芽という名前は北野源治の創作か？）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Hatsune may be created by Genji KITANO.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The name Hatsune may have been created by Genji KITANO.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The name Hatsume may have been created by Genji KITANO.)</e>
<cmt>Hatsune→Hatsume一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>が、落城の際に城から脱出し菩提を弔ったとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory said that she escaped in the event of castle fall and mourned Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory said that she escaped as the castle fell and mourned Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory said that she escaped as the castle fell and mourned Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="100">
<j>三成は秀吉から初めて200石（400石とも）の知行を賜った時、その全てを投げ打って渡辺勘兵衛（渡辺了とは別人）を召し抱え、家臣である彼の屋敷に起居したという逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Mitsunari received his first Chigyo fief 200 koku (or 400 koku) from Hideyoshi, as he used up all his Chigyo fief to hire Kanbe WATANABE (Satoru WATANABE was different person,) so that he lived in Kanbe&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Mitsunari received his first chigyo (fief) of 200 koku (or 400 koku) from Hideyoshi, he use used up his entire chigyo to hire Kanbe WATANABE (as distinct from Satoru WATANABE) so that he had to live in Kanbe&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Mitsunari received his first chigyo (fief) of 200 koku (or 400 koku) from Hideyoshi, he used up his entire chigyo to hire Kanbe WATANABE (as distinct from Satoru WATANABE) so that he had to live in Kanbe&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>use　を省く</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>勘兵衛は秀吉や柴田勝家から2万石の誘いを受けても「10万石でなければ仕える気はない」と断っていたほどの人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanbe was the person whom Hideyoshi and Katsuie SHIBATA had wanted and offered 20,000 koku fief, however, he said &quot;I will not serve with less than 100,000 koku,&quot; and rejected their offers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanbe was the person whom Hideyoshi and Katsuie SHIBATA had wanted and offered a fief of 20,000 koku, but he responded by saying, &quot;I will not serve for less than 100,000 koku,&quot; and rejected their offers.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanbe was the person whom Hideyoshi and Katsuie SHIBATA had wanted and offered a fief of 20,000 koku, but he responded by saying, &quot;I will not serve for less than 100,000 koku,&quot; and rejected their offers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>そのため、秀吉を大いに驚かせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi was very surprised that Kanbe accepted Mitsunari&apos;s offer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hideyoshi was very surprised that Kanbe had accepted Mitsunari&apos;s offer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi was very surprised that Kanbe had accepted Mitsunari&apos;s offer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>その後、勘兵衛は三成から何度も加増の話を受けるが、すべて断って終生200石（400石）で仕えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward Mitsunari had offered Kanbe to add his Chigyo fief, but Kanbe rejected it and had served for Mitsunari with 200 koku all his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Mitsunari offered Kanbe an addition to his chigyo, but Kanbe rejected it and served for Mitsunari for 200 koku all his life.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Mitsunari offered Kanbe an addition to his chigyo, but Kanbe rejected it and served for Mitsunari for 200 (or 400) koku all his life.</e>
<cmt>(or 400)を補う</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>島左近召し抱えのエピソードは、この話が入り交じって伝えられたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The episode about hiring Sakon SHIMA might be mixed with this anecdote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The episode about hiring Sakon SHIMA might have become intermixed with this anecdote.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The episode about hiring Sakon SHIMA might have become intermixed with this anecdote.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="105">
<j>文禄の役の際、幸州山城の戦いで負傷したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari was said to get injured in the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) in the Bunroku-no-eki War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that Mitsunari had been injured in the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) during the Bunroku-no-eki War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that Mitsunari had been injured in the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) during the Bunroku-no-eki War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>朝鮮の役には参加しないで日本国内の安全な場所にいたと誤解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was mistakenly thought that he didn&apos;t join the War in Korea but stayed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mistakenly, it was thought that he didn&apos;t join the War in Korea but instead remained in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mistakenly, it was thought that he didn&apos;t join the War in Korea but instead remained in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>しかし、実際には激戦の真っ直中にいたのである（余談だが、武功派とされた福島正則は、文禄の役でも殆ど戦いには参加せず、慶長の役では日本国内にいた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually he was in the middle of the battle. (As an aside, Masanori FUKUSHIMA who was in military exploit group didn&apos;t join the Battle of Bunroku-no-eki War so much and stayed in Japan during the Keicho-no-eki War.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, he was in the middle of the battle (incidentally, Masanori FUKUSHIMA, who was in a military reconnaissance group, didn&apos;t have much participation in the Battle of Bunroku-no-eki War but stayed in Japan during the Keicho-no-eki War).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, he was in the middle of the battle (incidentally, Masanori FUKUSHIMA, who was in a military reconnaissance group, didn&apos;t have much participation in the Battle of Bunroku-no-eki War, and stayed in Japan during the Keicho-no-eki War).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文を若干修正。原文の内容に沿うよう、訳文を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="108">
<j>斬首される前に三成は柿（干し柿）を勧められたが「柿を食べると身体に障る」と言って食べなかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Mitsunari was offered a persimmon (dried persimmon) before executed, he said, &quot;persimmons are not good for health,&quot; and didn&apos;t eat it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Mitsunari was offered a dried persimmon before his execution, he said, &quot;Persimmons aren&apos;t good for the health,&quot; and therefore refused to eat it.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Mitsunari was offered a dried persimmon before his execution, he said, &quot;Persimmons aren&apos;t good for the health,&quot; and therefore refused to eat it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>これに対して「すぐに死ぬ身が身体を気にする場合ではなかろう」と嘲笑されると、「大事を成す者は最期の最期まであきらめないものだ」と答えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said, &quot;you&apos;ll be executed soon and it is not time to worry your health,&quot; and was laughed at derisively, however, he answered, &quot;a person with great ambition never gives up.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was told, &quot;You&apos;ll be executed soon, so this isn&apos;t the time to worry about your health,&quot; and was laughed at derisively; but he simply answered, &quot;A person of great ambition never gives up.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was told, &quot;You&apos;ll be executed soon, so this isn&apos;t the time to worry about your health,&quot; and was laughed at derisively; but he simply answered, &quot;A person of great ambition never gives up.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="110">
<j>大谷吉継との間に衆道の契りがあったという伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he sodomized with Yoshitsugu OTANI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he had engaged in sodomy with Yoshitsugu OTANI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he had engaged in sodomy with Yoshitsugu OTANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>三杯の茶（三献茶）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three cups of tea for the lord</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three Cups of Tea for the Lord</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three Cups of Tea for the Lord</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>近江国観音寺にのどの渇きを覚えた秀吉が立ち寄り、寺小姓だった三成に茶を所望したのを出会いとするもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a legend that when Hideyoshi was thirsty, he stopped by Kannon-ji Temple in Omi to ask for tea and Mitsunari, who was a Tera-kosho (boy doing chores of a temple) at that time, served tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A legend states that once, when Hideyoshi was thirsty, he stopped by Kannon-ji Temple in Omi to ask for tea, and Mitsunari, who was a tera-kosho (boy doing the chores of a temple) at that time, served tea.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A legend states that once, when Hideyoshi was thirsty, he stopped by Kannon-ji Temple in Omi to ask for tea, and Mitsunari, who was a tera-kosho (boy doing the chores of a temple) at that time, served tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>史料が江戸時代のものであること等から、創作と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that this legend was a fiction because the historical data was written in Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that this legend was only fictional, because the historical data was written in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that this legend was only fictional, because the historical data was written in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>三成と淀殿及び高台院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari, Yodo-dono and Kodaiin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari, Yodo-dono and Kodaiin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari, Yodo-dono and Kodaiin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="113">
<j>一般的に広まっている誤解に、三成は旧主（浅井氏）の姫である淀殿を崇拝していたというものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was one of the widespread misconceptions that Mitsunari made an idol of Yodo-dono who was a daughter of the former master (Azai clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was one of the widespread misconceptions that Mitsunari had idolized Yodo-dono, who was a daughter of the former master (Azai clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was one of the widespread misconceptions that Mitsunari had idolized Yodo-dono, who was a daughter of the former master (Azai clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>これは両者が近江出身ということからイメージされたものと推測されるが、三成の石田家はたしかに近江の土豪だが浅井氏とは敵対関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason of the misconception is assumed that both Mitsunari and Yodo-dono were from Omi, however, Ishida Family was a local ruling family which was adversarial relationship with Azai clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for the misconception is assumed to be that both Mitsunari and Yodo-dono were from Omi, but the Ishida Family was a local ruling family that had an adversarial relationship with the Azai clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for the misconception is assumed to be that both Mitsunari and Yodo-dono were from Omi, but the Ishida Family was a local ruling family that had an adversarial relationship with the Azai clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>その意味ではむしろ「仇敵の姫」とも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this sense, she was not his idol but the &quot;adversary&apos;s princess.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this sense, she was not his idol but the &quot;adversary&apos;s princess.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this sense, she was not his idol but the &quot;adversary&apos;s princess.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="116">
<j>また、豊臣秀頼が豊臣秀吉の実子ではなく三成が淀殿と密通して生ませた子であるという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another misconception is that Hideyoshi was not Hideyori TOYOTOMI&apos;s father but Mitsunari was, who intrigued with Yodo-dono.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another misconception is that Hideyoshi was not Hideyori TOYOTOMI&apos;s father but Mitsunari was, having engaged in intrigue with Yodo-dono.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another misconception is that Hideyoshi was not Hideyori TOYOTOMI&apos;s father but Mitsunari was, having engaged in intrigue with Yodo-dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>しかし、淀殿不行跡の史料的根拠である「萩藩閥閲録」において、その風聞があったのは秀吉の死後で、かつ相手も大野治長と記載がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in &quot;Hagihan-batsuetsuroku (history book of Hagi domain),&quot; which was the basis of Yodo-dono&apos;s bad behavior, her affair rumor was mentioned that it had occurred after Hideyoshi&apos;s death and her lover was Harunaga Ono.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in &quot;Hagihan-batsuetsuroku (History Book of the Hagi Domain),&quot; which was the basis for portraying Yodo-dono&apos;s bad behavior, her rumored affair was mentioned as having occurred after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, and that her lover was Harunaga Ono.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in &quot;Hagihan-batsuetsuroku (History Book of the Hagi Domain),&quot; which was the basis for portraying Yodo-dono&apos;s bad behavior, her rumored affair was mentioned as having occurred after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, and that her lover was Harunaga Ono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>及びこの話の出典が江戸中期以降ということから、現在では三成や淀殿を貶めるために幕府の御用学者が捏造したとの説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, this historical data was issued after mid Edo era, therefore, the current widely held theory was that this story was created by scholar panders to the Edo government to demean Mitsunari and Yodo-dono.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, this historical data was issued after the mid-Edo period, and therefore the current widely held theory was that this story was created by scholars who pandered to the Edo government in order to demean Mitsunari and Yodo-dono.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, this historical data was issued after the mid-Edo period, and therefore the current widely held theory was that this story was created by scholars who pandered to the Edo government in order to demean Mitsunari and Yodo-dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>秀頼は1593年8月生まれであり、前年から朝鮮半島に赴いていた（文禄の役）三成が淀殿に子どもを産ませることは物理的に不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is physically impossible that Mitsunari became Hideyori&apos;s father because Hideyori was born in August, 1593 and Mitsunari went on an expedition to Korean Peninsula from the previous year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is physically impossible that Mitsunari became Hideyori&apos;s father because Hideyori was born in August, 1593 and Mitsunari had been on an expedition to the Korean Peninsula since the previous year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is physically impossible that Mitsunari became Hideyori&apos;s father because Hideyori was born in August, 1593 and Mitsunari had been on an expedition to the Korean Peninsula since the previous year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="120">
<j>その一方で近年、三成は秀吉の正室である高台院と親密であり、逆に秀頼の母として政治に介入する淀殿とその側近を嫌っていたとする、これまでの通説とは正反対の説も浮上している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, there is a recent theory that Mitsunari had very intimate relationship with Kodaiin who was Hideyoshi&apos;s official wife and that he disliked Yodo-dono and her close aides because she interfered in the politics as Hideyori&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrastingly, there is a recent theory that Mitsunari had a very intimate relationship with Kodaiin, who was Hideyoshi&apos;s official wife, and that he disliked Yodo-dono and her close aides because she had interfered in politics as Hideyori&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrastingly, there is a recent theory that Mitsunari had a very intimate relationship with Kodaiin, who was Hideyoshi&apos;s official wife, and that he disliked Yodo-dono and her close aides because she had interfered in politics as Hideyori&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>その論拠として、三成の三女辰姫は高台院の養女である【杉山家由緒書・岡家由緒書】こと、側近筆頭の孝蔵主は三成の縁戚で関ヶ原でも西軍のために大津城の開城交渉を行っていること、淀殿の周辺に三成ら西軍派の縁者がいないことなどがあげられる（詳しくは高台院を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basis of this theories are; Tatsuhime who was the third daughter of Mitsunari was adopted by Kodaiin according to &quot;Sugiyama-ke Yuishogaki (pedigree of Sugiyama Family) and Oka-ke Yuishogaki (pedigree of Oka Family),&quot; Kozosu who was top of asides of Kodaiin was Mitsunari&apos;s relative and negotiated to open Otsu Castle for the West squad in the Battle of Sekigahara and there were no Mitsunari&apos;s relatives around Yodo-dono. (For details, see Kodaiin.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basis of this theory is that Tatsuhime, who was the third daughter of Mitsunari, was adopted by Kodaiin according to &quot;Sugiyama-ke Yuishogaki (Pedigree of the Sugiyama Family)&quot; and &quot;Oka-ke Yuishogaki (Pedigree of Oka Family)&quot;; Kozosu, who was a top aid of Kodaiin, was Mitsunari&apos;s relative and negotiated to open Otsu Castle for the western army in the Battle of Sekigahara; and there were no Mitsunari&apos;s relatives in proximity to Yodo-dono (for details, see &quot;Kodaiin&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basis of this theory is that Tatsuhime, who was the third daughter of Mitsunari, was adopted by Kodaiin according to &quot;Sugiyama-ke Yuishogaki (Pedigree of the Sugiyama Family)&quot; and &quot;Oka-ke Yuishogaki (Pedigree of the Oka Family)&quot;; Kozosu, who was a top aid of Kodaiin, was Mitsunari&apos;s relative and negotiated to open Otsu Castle for the western army in the Battle of Sekigahara; and there were no Mitsunari&apos;s relatives in proximity to Yodo-dono (for details, see &quot;Kodaiin&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Oka Family→the Oka Family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>肖像画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portrait</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portrait</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>少なくとも3種類から4種類程度確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At least 3-4 types of portraits were identified as Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At least three or four types of portraits have been identified as depicting Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At least three or four types of portraits have been identified as depicting Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>ここでは特に、三成自身（と伝えられる）の頭蓋骨から復顔した肖像画を取り上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is about his portrait which was painted from his bone of the skull (said to be authentic).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is about the portrait that was painted based on his supposed skull (said to be authentic).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is about the portrait that was painted based on his supposed skull (said to be authentic).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いから約300余年を経た明治40年（1907年）、東京帝國大学の渡辺世佑が三成の伝記執筆のために、三玄院にある三成のものと思しき墓を発掘、京都帝國大学解剖学教室の足立文太郎が遺骨を鑑定調査した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1907 (more than 300 years after the Battle of Sekigahara), Yosuke WATANABE of Tokyo Imperial University excavated a tomb which was believed to Mitsunari&apos;s tomb, and Buntaro ADACHI in anatomia class of Kyoto Imperial University investigated and analyzed the skeleton.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1907, more than 300 years after the Battle of Sekigahara, Yosuke WATANABE, of Tokyo Imperial University, excavated a tomb believed to be that of Mitsunari, and Buntaro ADACHI, in the anatomy department of Kyoto Imperial University, investigated and analyzed the skeleton.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1907, more than 300 years after the Battle of Sekigahara, Yosuke WATANABE, of Tokyo Imperial University, excavated a tomb believed to be that of Mitsunari, and Buntaro ADACHI, in the anatomy department of Kyoto Imperial University, investigated and analyzed the skeleton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>その時に頭蓋骨の写真を撮影した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time he took a picture of the skull.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time he took a picture of the skull.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time he took a picture of the skull.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>調査の結果は「優男の骨格・頭形は木槌型・反っ歯・没年41歳相当」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of the investigation, he was a man with &quot;man of gentle manners bone structure, wooden mallet shape head, projecting tooth,. Year of death was around 41 years old.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result of the investigation, he was a &quot;man whose bone structure suggested a gentle manner, with a wooden-mallet-shaped head and projecting tooth... the age at death was around 41 years.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result of the investigation, he was a &quot;man whose bone structure suggested a gentle manner, with a wooden-mallet-shaped head and projecting tooth... the age at death was around 41 years.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>下って昭和51年（1976年）、末裔の一人である石田多加幸（写真家）からの依頼を受け、東京科学警察研究所元主任技官・長安周一が石膏復顔を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1976, at the request of Takayuki ISHIDA (photographer) who was one of Mitsunari&apos;s descendent, the former chief of engineering officials of Tokyo National Research Institute of Police Science, Shuichi NAGAYASU conducted reconstruction of facial features with plaster.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1976, at the request of Takayuki ISHIDA, a photographer and descendent of Mitsunari, Shuichi NAGAYASU, the former chief of engineering of the Tokyo National Research Institute of Police Science, used plaster to reconstruct the facial features.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1976, at the request of Takayuki ISHIDA, a photographer and descendent of Mitsunari, Shuichi NAGAYASU, the former chief of engineering of the Tokyo National Research Institute of Police Science, used plaster to reconstruct the facial features.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>それをもとに関西医科大学の石田哲郎の指導のもと、昭和55年（1980年）3月、日本画家前田幹雄の手によって石膏の復顔肖像画が制作された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1980, a Japanese-style painter Mikio MAEDA drew a portrait of Mitsunari from the reconstructed face with plaster under the direction of Tetsuro ISHIDA of Kansai Medical University.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1980, the Japanese-style painter Mikio MAEDA drew a portrait of Mitsunari from the plaster-reconstructed face under the direction of Tetsuro ISHIDA, of Kansai Medical University.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, 1980, the Japanese-style painter Mikio MAEDA drew a portrait of Mitsunari from the plaster-reconstructed face under the direction of Tetsuro ISHIDA, of Kansai Medical University.</e>
<cmt>Marchを補う。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>この肖像画は現在大坂城天守閣に保管されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This portrait is maintained in the castle keep of Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This portrait is maintained in the castle keep of Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This portrait is maintained in the castle keep of Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>同時に身長の推測も行い、156cmと試算された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari was about 156cm tall according to the analysis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari was approximately 156 centimeters tall, according to the analysis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari was approximately 156 centimeters tall, according to the analysis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>名臣・忠臣説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wise and steadfast retainer</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Wise and Steadfast Retainer</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Wise and Steadfast Retainer</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="131">
<j>三成は後世に、五人組 (日本史)の制度を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established Gonin-gumi settlement system (Japanese history) for posterity as neighborhood organizations system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established the Gonin-gumi settlement system (Japanese history) for posterity as a method of organizing neighborhoods.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established the Gonin-gumi settlement system (Japanese history) for posterity as a method of organizing neighborhoods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>これは、江戸時代を通じて農政の基本となった制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system was basis on agricultural policy during Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system was based on the agricultural policy of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system was based on the agricultural policy of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>徳川光圀は大日本史に「石田三成は非常に立派な人物だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA mentioned about him in Dainihonshi (Japanese History Book). &quot;Mitsunari was a fine man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA mentioned about him in Dainihonshi (Japanese History Book). &quot;Mitsunari was a fine man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA mentioned about him in Dainihonshi (Japanese History Book). &quot;Mitsunari was a fine man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>人はそれぞれ、その主君に尽くすのを義というのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is justice that each person serves for his lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is justice that each person serves his lord.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is justice that each person serves his lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>徳川家の敵といって三成の事を悪く言うのは良くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is wrong that we speak ill of Mitsunari because he was adversary of Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is wrong that we speak ill of Mitsunari because he was an adversary of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is wrong that we speak ill of Mitsunari because he was an adversary of the Tokugawa Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>君臣とも三成のように心がけるべきだ」と記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both lords and vassals should learn from him.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both lords and vassals should learn from him.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both lords and vassals should learn from him.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="137">
<j>豊臣秀吉が短期間で天下を統一できた理由のひとつとして、三成ら有能な行政官僚が常に後方補給などの輜重役を担当したことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reasons why Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI could rule the whole country was that he had talented bureaucrats such as Mitsunari and that they always managed military goods transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reasons that Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was able to rule the entire country was that he had talented bureaucrats such as Mitsunari and that they always accomplished the transport of military goods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reasons that Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was able to rule the entire country was that he had talented bureaucrats such as Mitsunari and that they always accomplished the transport of military goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>実際に文禄の役の際にも兵站度外視で無闇に戦線拡大する諸将を説得して漢城（ソウル）に集結させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, in the event of the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan) he persuaded feudal lords who widened battle lines ignoring military logistics and let them get together to Hancheng (Seoul).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, in the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan) he persuaded the feudal lords who had widened battle lines in ignorance of military logistics and let them come together at Hancheng (Seoul).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, in the Bunroku-no-eki War he persuaded the feudal lords who had widened battle lines in ignorance of military logistics and let them come together at Hancheng (Seoul).</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に合わせて訳文を修正。一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文を。で終わるように修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>碧蹄館の戦いでの勝利の基礎を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was the base of the triumph of the Battle of Hekitenkai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was the base of the triumph of the Battle of Hekitenkai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was the base of the triumph of the Battle of Hekiteikan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処Hekiteikan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="140">
<j>三成は佐和山で善政を敷いていたため領民から慕われ、三成の死後も佐和山の領民はその遺徳を偲んで、佐和山城付近に地蔵を築くなどしてその霊を慰めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Mitsunari governed wisely in Sawayama, he was beloved by his people and they set Ksitigarbhas near Sawayama Castle to comfort his spirit after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Mitsunari governed wisely in Sawayama, he was beloved by his people; after his death, they set ksitigarbhas near Sawayama Castle to comfort his spirit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Mitsunari governed wisely in Sawayama, he was beloved by his people; after his death, they set ksitigarbhas near Sawayama Castle to comfort his spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>なお、家康の重臣で三成死後に佐和山に入った井伊直政は関ヶ原での負傷が原因で三成刑死から2年後（慶長7年、1602年）に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu&apos;s main retainer, Naomasa II, who ruled Sawayama after Mitsunari&apos;s death, died from wounds of the Sekigahara two years after the execution of Mitsunari (1602).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu&apos;s main retainer, Naomasa II, who ruled Sawayama after Mitsunari&apos;s death, died from wounds of the Sekigahara two years after the execution of Mitsunari (1602).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu&apos;s main retainer, Naomasa II, who ruled Sawayama after Mitsunari&apos;s death, died from wounds of the Sekigahara two years after the execution of Mitsunari (1602).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="142">
<j>三成は領内の古橋村が飢饉に襲われたとき、年貢を免祖したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari was said to exempt villagers from customs when famine struck Furuhashi-mura Village in his domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari was said to exempt villagers from customs when famine struck Furuhashi-mura Village in his domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari was said to exempt villagers from customs when famine struck Furuhashi-mura Village in his domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>古橋には当時、三成の母の菩提寺である法華寺があったが、三成は手厚い保護を与えていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He provided generous support to his mother&apos;s family temple, Hokke-ji Temple which was in Furuhashi at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He provided generous support to the temple of his mother&apos;s family, Hokke-ji Temple, which was then located in Furuhashi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He provided generous support to the temple of his mother&apos;s family, Hokke-ji Temple, which was then located in Furuhashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="144">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）の豊臣秀次失脚時には、諸将が秀次を見限る中で三成は「秀次公無罪」と信じ、最後まで秀次の助命に動いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the event of downfall of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI in 1595, even though feudal lords abandoned him, Mitsunari begged for Hidetsugu&apos;s life till the end, believing innocence of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequent upon the downfall of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI in 1595, even though the feudal lords had abandoned him, Mitsunari begged for Hidetsugu&apos;s life till the end, believing in his innocence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequent upon the downfall of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI in 1595, even though the feudal lords had abandoned him, Mitsunari begged for Hidetsugu&apos;s life till the end, believing in his innocence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>秀次の家臣であった前野忠康（舞兵庫）ら若江八人衆はその三成の姿に感激し、以後、三成の麾下に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakae Hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI) such as Tadayasu MAENO (Hyogo MAI) were impressed by Mitsunari and they came under Mitsunari&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wakae hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI) such as Tadayasu MAENO (Hyogo MAI) were impressed by Mitsunari and thus aligned themselves under his command.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Wakae hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI) such as Tadayasu MAENO (Hyogo MAI) were impressed by Mitsunari and thus aligned themselves under his command.</e>
<cmt>wakae→Wakae</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>この際、細川幽斎と共同しようとしたが、三成が遠方の検地に赴いていた為、思うように動けなかったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that at that time Mitsunari wanted to act in concern with Yusai HOSOKAWA, however, he couldn&apos;t act well because he was in far off to conduct Kenchi survey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that at that time Mitsunari wanted to act in concert with Yusai HOSOKAWA, but he couldn&apos;t do so effectively because he was in a distant location conducting kenchi (surveys).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that at that time Mitsunari wanted to act in concert with Yusai HOSOKAWA, but he couldn&apos;t do so effectively because he was in a distant location conducting kenchi (surveys).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="147">
<j>三成は大一大万大吉と記された家紋を用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used a crest with &quot;Daiichi-Daiman-Daikichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His crest was that of &quot;Daiichi-Daiman-Daikichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His crest was that of &quot;Daiichi-Daiman-Daikichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>「万民が一人のため、一人が万民のために尽くせば太平の世が訪れる」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means &quot;when all people work for one and one works for all, that brings peaceful world.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means, &quot;When all people work for one and one works for all, it brings a peaceful world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means, &quot;When all people work for one and one works for all, it brings a peaceful world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>奸臣説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demoniac retainer</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Demonic Retainer</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Demonic Retainer</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="149">
<j>三成は不正を極度に嫌い、情実も介さず、常に自らの信念に基づいて豊臣政権の行政を司っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari hated injustice and implemented the Toyotomi government on the basis of moral without personal considerations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari hated injustice and implemented the Toyotomi government on the basis of morality without personal consideration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari hated injustice and implemented the Toyotomi government on the basis of morality without personal consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>ところが、そのあまりな謹厳実直な性格が、周囲からは融通のきかない傲岸不遜、横柄な態度と映った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was so serious and honest that he was perceived as arrogance and was not liked by feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was so serious and honest that he was perceived as arrogant and was disliked by feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was so serious and honest that he was perceived as arrogant and was disliked by feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>そのため諸大名からの人望を得られず、加藤清正ら武功派諸将の三成襲撃を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That caused Budan-ha (person who carries out politics by military means) such as Kiyomasa KATO to attack Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This caused budan-ha (persons carrying out politics by military means) such as Kiyomasa KATO to attack Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This caused budan-ha (persons carrying out politics by military means) such as Kiyomasa KATO to attack Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの前に、東軍諸大名から人質を取ろうとしたことも奸臣説を呼び込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Mitsunari tried to take hostages from the feudal lords of the East squad caused him demoniac retainer rumor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Mitsunari tried to take hostages from the feudal lords of the eastern army gave rise to the rumor of demonic behavior.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Mitsunari tried to take hostages from the feudal lords of the eastern army gave rise to the rumor of demonic behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="153">
<j>毛利輝元は「かの仁、当時、肝心の人にて、なかなか申すに及ばず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terumoto MORI said about Mitsunari, &quot;that man was an important person at that time but said few words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terumoto MORI said of Mitsunari, &quot;That man was an important person at the time, but he said few words.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terumoto MORI said of Mitsunari, &quot;That man was an important person at the time, but he said few words.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>大かた心得にて候（大いに気を使う）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It makes me nervous.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It makes me nervous.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It makes me nervous.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>島津義弘は「江州佐和山の城主・石田治部少輔、太閤公の股肱の臣として、その勢威、比肩の人なし」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU said about him, &quot;as Hideyoshi&apos;s right-hand man, the power of Chibu-sho Ishida, the castellan of Goshu-Sawayama is without parallel.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU said of him, &quot;As Hideyoshi&apos;s right-hand man, the power of Chibu-sho Ishida, the castellan of Goshu-Sawayama, is without parallel.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU said of him, &quot;As Hideyoshi&apos;s right-hand man, the power of Jibu-sho Ishida, the castellan of Goshu-Sawayama, is without parallel.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処Chibu→Jibu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>高野山の木食応其上人は「治少（治部少輔。三成の官位）、御奉行のその随一なる顔にて候つる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokujiki Ogo Jonin (St. Ogo MOKUJIKI) said, &quot;as to Chisho (Chibu-Sho title, Mitsunari&apos;s title), Gobugyo gets to be looked as the top of them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokujiki Ogo Jonin (St. Ogo MOKUJIKI) said, &quot;As to Chisho (Chibu-Sho title, Mitsunari&apos;s title), Gobugyo can be seen as the foremost of them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokujiki Ogo Jonin (St. Ogo MOKUJIKI) said, &quot;As to Jisho (Jibu-Sho title, Mitsunari&apos;s title), Gobugyo can be seen as the foremost of them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処Chibu→JibuChisho→Jisho</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>少しもそむけ候えば、たちまち身のさわりをなす仁にて候」と夫々評した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If he turns his face away even a little, the government will go wrong in a whisk.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If he turns his face away even a little, the government will go wrong in a whisk.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If he turns his face away even a little, the government will go wrong in a whisk.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="158">
<j>豊臣秀次のとき、三成は秀吉に対して、「御謀反調議ノタメニ、山々ニ在留セラル」と讒言し、これが秀吉に秀次排除を決意させたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Mitsunari slandered Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI saying to Hideyoshi &quot;He was staying in the mountains to plot a rebellion,&quot; and this made Hideyoshi decide to exclude Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Mitsunari slandered Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI by saying to Hideyoshi, &quot;He was staying in the mountains to plot a rebellion,&quot; and this made Hideyoshi decide to exclude Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Mitsunari slandered Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI by saying to Hideyoshi, &quot;He was staying in the mountains to plot a rebellion,&quot; and this made Hideyoshi decide to exclude Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="159">
<j>しかし現在は秀次の謀反説及び讒言説は否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, nowadays this theory such as Hidetsugu&apos;s rebellion and Mitsunari&apos;s slander is denied.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, today theories such as Hidetsugu&apos;s rebellion and Mitsunari&apos;s slander are discounted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, today theories such as Hidetsugu&apos;s rebellion and Mitsunari&apos;s slander are discounted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>三成は秀吉の意向を受けて働いただけであり、結果として事務処理をせざるをえなかった三成が秀吉の代わりに憎まれ役になったという事実があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari might work in a businesslike manner on Hideyoshi&apos;s disposition and might play the bad guy instead of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari might have worked in a businesslike manner on Hideyoshi&apos;s disposition, and might have played the bad guy instead of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari might have worked in a businesslike manner on Hideyoshi&apos;s disposition, and might have played the bad guy instead of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>しかしそれをもって「秀次を謀反の罪で直接糾弾したのは三成」と断言できるかどうかについては意見がわかれる（ただ、秀次事件の1週間前まで三成は関東・次いで九州の検地に赴いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this was not enough for asserting that &quot;it was Mitsunari to accuse Hidetsugu directly as a rebel&quot; and there is a disagreement about it. (Mitsunari had gone to Kanto and Kyushu to conduct Kenchi survey until a week before Hidetsugu incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this was not enough to assert that &quot;it was Mitsunari that accused Hidetsugu directly as a rebel,&quot; and there is disagreement about it (Mitsunari had gone to Kanto and Kyushu to conduct kenchi surveys until a week before the Hidetsugu incident).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this was not enough to assert that &quot;it was Mitsunari that accused Hidetsugu directly as a rebel,&quot; and there is disagreement about it (Mitsunari had gone to Kanto and Kyushu to conduct kenchi surveys until a week before the Hidetsugu incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>秀次に関わる殆どの人間が一門を除いて連座を免れている為、周到な根回しが必要だったのではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that a fully prepared plan was necessary to proceed Hidetsugu incident because most people concerned could avoid complicity except Hidetsugu&apos;s sept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that a fully prepared plan was needed in order to carry out the Hidetsugu plan, because most people concerned could avoid complicity except for Hidetsugu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that a fully prepared plan was needed in order to carry out the Hidetsugu plan, because most people concerned could avoid complicity except for Hidetsugu&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>side→family</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>これに従えば、三成には「アリバイ」が成立する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this sense, Mitsunari had an &quot;alibi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this sense, Mitsunari had an &quot;alibi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this sense, Mitsunari had an &quot;alibi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="164">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの際に、大谷吉継は三成に対して「お主（三成）が檄を飛ばしても普段の横柄ぶりから、豊臣家安泰を願うものすら内府（家康）の下に走らせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the event of the Battle of Sekigahara, Yoshitsugu OTANI said to Mitsunari, &quot;even if you (Mitsunari) give them a pep talk, your common imperiousness makes even those who wish peace and security of Toyotomi Family go under Naifu (Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event of the Battle of Sekigahara, Yoshitsugu OTANI said to Mitsunari, &quot;even if you (Mitsunari) give them a pep talk, your natural imperiousness makes even those who want peace and security of the Toyotomi Family go under Naifu (Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event of the Battle of Sekigahara, Yoshitsugu OTANI said to Mitsunari, &quot;even if you (Mitsunari) give them a pep talk, your natural imperiousness makes even those who want peace and security of the Toyotomi Family go under Naifu (Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>ここは安芸中納言（毛利輝元）か備前中納言（宇喜多秀家）を上に立て、お主は影に徹せよ」と諫言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, put Aki Chunagon (Terumoto MORI) or Bizen Chunagon (Hideie UKITA) to the front and you remain behind,&quot; and expostulated with him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, put Aki Chunagon (Terumoto MORI) or Bizen Chunagon (Hideie UKITA) to the front and you remain behind,&quot; and expostulated with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, put Aki Chunagon (Terumoto MORI) or Bizen Chunagon (Hideie UKITA) to the front and you remain behind,&quot; and expostulated with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>三成の立案した作戦を「それは作戦などではなく博打というものだ」と語ったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the Mitsunari&apos;s battle plan, Yoshitsugu said, &quot;it is not a battle plan but a gamble.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsugu said in reference to Mitsunari&apos;s battle plan, &quot;It isn&apos;t a battle plan but a gamble.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsugu said in reference to Mitsunari&apos;s battle plan, &quot;It isn&apos;t a battle plan but a gamble.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>三成は当初は諫言に従ったが、後にはいつもの横柄さに戻ってしまったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Mitsunari followed his advice for a time, he became arrogant as before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Mitsunari initially followed Yoshitsugu&apos;s advice, he became arrogant as before.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Mitsunari initially followed Yoshitsugu&apos;s advice, he became arrogant as before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="168">
<j>関ヶ原に至る東西両軍の戦いは七月一日の宇喜多秀家の独断での出陣式がきっかけであり、三成は準備不足であったことが指摘されている（義兄弟である真田昌幸の「どうして事前に相談してくれなかった」と三成に文句を言う手紙が現存しており、佐竹義宣 (右京大夫)、津軽為信、大谷吉継などその他の三成派も事前の相談を受けていなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the kick-off ceremony held by Hideie UKITA on July 1st on his own discretion led the Battle of Sekigahara involving both East and West squads and that Mitsunari was poorly prepared. (Mitsunari&apos;s brother-in-law, Masayuki SANADA complained to Mitsunari in his letter, &quot;why didn&apos;t you ask me beforehand?&quot; Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo-no-daibu), Tamenobu TSUGARU, Yoshitsugu OTANI and other Mitsunari faction were not asked for any advice beforehand, either.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the kick-off ceremony held by Hideie UKITA on July 1 at his own discretion led to the Battle of Sekigahara involving both the eastern and western armies, and that Mitsunari was poorly prepared (Mitsunari&apos;s brother-in-law, Masayuki SANADA, complained to Mitsunari in his letter, &quot;Why didn&apos;t you ask me beforehand?&quot; but Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo-no-daibu), Tamenobu TSUGARU, Yoshitsugu OTANI and others of the Mitsunari faction weren&apos;t consulted beforehand, either).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the kick-off ceremony held by Hideie UKITA on July 1 at his own discretion led to the Battle of Sekigahara involving both the eastern and western armies, and that Mitsunari was poorly prepared (Mitsunari&apos;s brother-in-law, Masayuki SANADA, complained to Mitsunari in his letter, &quot;Why didn&apos;t you ask me beforehand?&quot; but Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo-no-daibu), Tamenobu TSUGARU, Yoshitsugu OTANI and others of the Mitsunari faction weren&apos;t consulted beforehand, either).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="169">
<j>慶長4年（1599年）1月19日に、三成が徳川家康暗殺を計画している旨を、藤堂高虎が家康に注進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 19th, 1599, Takatora TODO informed Ieyasu of Mitsunari&apos;s assassination plot against Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 19, 1599, Takatora TODO informed Ieyasu of Mitsunari&apos;s plot to assassinate Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 19, 1599, Takatora TODO informed Ieyasu of Mitsunari&apos;s plot to assassinate Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>同年3月に暗殺に失敗したという説もある（重臣の島左近が勝手に計画したともされる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the assassination attempt was failed in March 1599. (There is another theory that Mitsunari&apos;s main retainer, Sakon SHIMA plotted on his own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the assassination plot was attempted but failed in March 1599 (while another theory asserts that Mitsunari&apos;s main retainer, Sakon SHIMA, plotted on his own).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the assassination plot was attempted but failed in March 1599 (while another theory asserts that Mitsunari&apos;s main retainer, Sakon SHIMA, plotted on his own).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="171">
<j>蒲生氏郷を毒殺し、後に蒲生家の騒動（蒲生騒動）及び蒲生家の弱体化を三成が謀ったとも言われたが、蒲生家の多くの旧臣が三成に仕え、三成のために死んでいるという反証もあり、現在は否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Mitsunari plotted killing Ujisato GAMO with poison, Gamo-sodo (Gamo Family&apos;s feud) and weakening of Gamo Family, however, many Gamo&apos;s former retainers served and died for Mitsunari and nowadays this theory is denied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Mitsunari plotted the poisoning of Ujisato GAMO, Gamo-sodo (the Gamo Family feud) and the resultant weakening of the Gamo Family, but many of Gamo&apos;s former retainers served and died for Mitsunari so today this theory is denied.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Mitsunari plotted the poisoning of Ujisato GAMO, Gamo-sodo (the Gamo Family feud) and the resultant weakening of the Gamo Family, but many of Gamo&apos;s former retainers served and died for Mitsunari so today this theory is denied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family tree</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Family Tree</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Family Tree</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="172">
<j>三男三女もしくは二男五女のほか庶子数人がいたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to have 3 sons and 3 daughters or 2 sons and 5 daughters besides children born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to have three sons and three daughters or two sons and five daughters besides the children born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to have three sons and three daughters or two sons and five daughters besides the children born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="173">
<j>長男：石田重家 - 関ヶ原の戦い後、徳川家康に助命され出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eldest son: Shigeie ISHIDA - After the Battle of Sekigahara, he was spared by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eldest son: Shigeie ISHIDA - After the Battle of Sekigahara, he was spared by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eldest son: Shigeie ISHIDA - After the Battle of Sekigahara, he was spared by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="174">
<j>次男：石田重成 - 津軽氏に匿われ杉山源吾を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second son: Shigenari ISHIDA - He was harbored by Tsugaru clan and gave himself another name Gengo SUGIYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second son: Shigenari ISHIDA - He was harbored by the Tsugaru clan and gave himself the name Gengo SUGIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second son: Shigenari ISHIDA - He was harbored by the Tsugaru clan and gave himself the name Gengo SUGIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>子孫は津軽家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendents became retainers of Tsugaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendents became retainers of Tsugaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendents became retainers of Tsugaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="176">
<j>娘：辰姫 - 高台院養女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daughter: Tatsuhime - She was adopted by Kodaiin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daughter: Tatsuhime - She was adopted by Kodaiin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daughter: Tatsuhime - She was adopted by Kodaiin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>弘前藩2代藩主津軽信枚の正室、のち満天姫（家康養女）降嫁により側室に降格。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She became an official wife of Nobuhiro TSUGARU who was the second lord of domain Hirosaki, however, she was demoted to concubine because Matehime (Ieyasu&apos;s adopted daughter) married Nobuhiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She became an official wife of Nobuhiro TSUGARU, the second lord of the Hirosaki domain, but she was demoted to the status of a concubine because Matehime (Ieyasu&apos;s adopted daughter) married Nobuhiro.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She became an official wife of Nobuhiro TSUGARU, the second lord of the Hirosaki domain, but she was demoted to the status of a concubine because Matehime (Ieyasu&apos;s adopted daughter) married Nobuhiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>子に3代藩主津軽信義。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her son Nobuyoshi TSUGARU was the third lord of domain Hirosaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her son, Nobuyoshi TSUGARU, was the third lord of the Hirosaki domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her son, Nobuyoshi TSUGARU, was the third lord of the Hirosaki domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="179">
<j>娘：某 - 石田家臣の山田某に嫁ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daughter: unknown - She married a certain Yamada who was a retainer of Ishida.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daughter: Unknown - She married a certain Yamada who was a retainer of Ishida.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daughter: Unknown - She married a certain Yamada who was a retainer of Ishida.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>山田某の叔母は家康の側室茶阿局でその縁から石田家没落後は妻（三成の娘）を連れ松平忠輝に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a certain Yamada&apos;s aunt was Ieyasu&apos;s concubine Cha&apos;a-no-Tsubone, he served for Tadateru MATSUDAIRA taking his wife (Mitsunari&apos;s daughter) after Ishida Family was ruined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a certain Yamada&apos;s aunt was Ieyasu&apos;s concubine Cha&apos;a-no-Tsubone, he served Tadateru MATSUDAIRA, taking his wife (Mitsunari&apos;s daughter) after the ruination of the Ishida Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a certain Yamada&apos;s aunt was Ieyasu&apos;s concubine Cha&apos;a-no-Tsubone, he served Tadateru MATSUDAIRA, taking his wife (Mitsunari&apos;s daughter) after the ruination of the Ishida Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>（異説有）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Another theory exists.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Another theory exists.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Another theory exists.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="182">
<j>娘：某 - 蒲生氏臣の岡重政室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daughter : unknown - She became a wife of Shigemasa OKA who was retainer of Gamo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daughter: Unknown - She became a wife of Shigemasa OKA, who was a retainer of the Gamo clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daughter: Unknown - She became a wife of Shigemasa OKA, who was a retainer of the Gamo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>重政が藩主蒲生忠郷の母振姫（家康の三女）の勘気に触れ切腹処分になると会津を離れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Shigemasa brought an anger of Furihime who was the lord Tadasato GAMO&apos;s mother (and the third daughter of Ieyasu) and had to commit Seppuku (suiside by disembowelment), she left Aizu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shigemasa became angry and distraught over Furihime, who was the lord Tadasato GAMO&apos;s mother (and the third daughter of Ieyasu) and had to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), she left Aizu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shigemasa aroused the displeasure of Furihime, who was the lord Tadasato GAMO&apos;s mother (and the third daughter of Ieyasu), and had to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), she left Aizu.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に合わせて訳文を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>子の岡吉右衛門の娘は徳川家光の側室自証院（三成の曾孫にあたる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daughter of Kichiemon OKA who was her son was a concubine of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, Jishoin (Mitsunari&apos;s great-granddaughter.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The daughter of her son, Kichiemon OKA, was a concubine of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA called Jishoin (Mitsunari&apos;s great-granddaughter).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The daughter of her son, Kichiemon OKA, was a concubine of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA called Jishoin (Mitsunari&apos;s great-granddaughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>お振の方は家光の長女千代姫を産み、尾張徳川家に嫁いだ千代姫の血が7代藩主徳川宗春まで続く（異説有）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ofuri-no-kata had a baby who was the first daughter of Iemitsu, Chiyohime. Chiyohime merried into Owari-Tokugawa Family and her family tree continued till the 7th lord Muneharu TOKUGAWA. (Another theory exists.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ofuri-no-kata had a baby called Chiyohime, who was the first daughter of Iemitsu; eventually, Chiyohime married into the Owari-Tokugawa Family and her family tree continued till the seventh lord Muneharu TOKUGAWA. (though another theory exists).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ofuri-no-kata had a baby called Chiyohime, who was the first daughter of Iemitsu; eventually, Chiyohime married into the Owari-Tokugawa Family and her family tree continued till the seventh lord Muneharu TOKUGAWA. (though another theory exists).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ypacaraí(id:11031), KMT(id:1772), Nnh(id:474), Hikichimin Jr.(id:147077), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Akoyano(id:56905), Kamakura(id:472), 未完(id:84727), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), Amagai(id:205398), Blowback(id:173308), A-Taul(id:41790), Koshoku(id:15691), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), Kouko0515(id:100370), Sea of Japan(id:3230), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Mnd(id:15140), 漬けマグロ(id:145695), たね(id:10372), Moltke(id:17553), 松茸(id:27535), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Masao(id:953), Kagetudo(id:163875), スティロウ(id:89199), D5(id:60352), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Boca samba(id:137526), ひろくん(id:79638), Wafer(id:27900), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), Alexbot(id:157199), Elthy(id:5957), King-wise(id:19033), Jmho(id:10472), TT(id:46431), ドルチェット(id:46458), てら1971(id:131768), Reggaeman(id:6214), デュオ(id:40933), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kotoito(id:21045), 冒涜的な利用者名(id:14641), Ryoji937(id:190619), A6M4(id:14155), 寒(id:53831), Otkoyg(id:49871), Sho-gun(id:74168), こぶまき(id:38278), Ryoske(id:34653), 竹麦魚(id:11012), ウラヌス(id:25954), 水野白楓(id:22811), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Yanahan(id:2437), Shinkansen(id:13703), Kamitani(id:30757), Aboshi(id:9318), YurikBot(id:18605), BUNBUN(id:63624), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 巴投(id:181114), これきん(id:51592), 歴史研究家(id:108842), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>