<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平家盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Iemori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Iemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Iemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 家盛（たいら の いえもり、保安 (元号)元年（1120年）？ - 久安5年（1149年））は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Iemori (1120 (?) - 1149) was a military commander in the end of the Heian Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Iemori (1120 (?) - 1149) was a military commander at the end of the Heian Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Iemori (1120 (?) - 1149) was a military commander at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>in Japan削除用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平忠盛の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iemori was the second son of TAIRA no Tadamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemori was the second son of TAIRA no Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemori was the second son of TAIRA no Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原宗兼の娘・池禅尼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Munekane Ike no zenni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Munekane Ike no zenni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Munekane Ike no zenni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>平清盛の異母弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iemori was a half-brother of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemori was a half-brother of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemori was a younger paternal half-brother of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同母弟に平頼盛がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yorimori was Iemori&apos;s brother by the same biological mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yorimori was Iemori&apos;s brother by the same biological mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yorimori was Iemori&apos;s younger brother.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>久安3年（1147年）に従五位下・常陸介、久安4年（1148年）には従四位下・右馬頭に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1147, Iemori was conferred Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, being assigned as</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1147, Iemori was conferred Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, being assigned as</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1147, Iemori was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned the position of Hitachi no suke (Assistant Governor of Hitachi Province), and in 1148, he was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned the position of Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of the Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>訳文が途中で終わっていたので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>兄・平清盛の地位を脅かすほどの存在だったが、保安元年（1149年）に鳥羽天皇に御供して熊野に赴く途中で病没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iemori exuded a powerful presence to threaten the position of his half-brother TAIRA no Kiyomori but died of illness on the way to Kumano while accompanying Emperor Toba in 1149.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemori exuded a powerful presence to threaten the position of his half-brother TAIRA no Kiyomori but died of illness on the way to Kumano while accompanying Emperor Toba in 1149.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemori exuded a powerful presence to threaten the position of his older half-brother TAIRA no Kiyomori but died of illness on the way to Kumano while accompanying Emperor Toba in 1149.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>平治の乱の際、源頼朝の容姿がこの家盛に似ていたために、池禅尼は頼朝の助命嘆願をしたのだと、『平治物語』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in Heiji Monogatari (the Tale of Heiji) that, since MINAMOTO no Yoritomo had a resemblance to Iemori in personal appearance, Ike no zenni begged for his life at the time of the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in Heiji Monogatari (the Tale of Heiji) that, since MINAMOTO no Yoritomo had a resemblance to Iemori in personal appearance, Ike no zenni begged for his life at the time of the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (the Tale of Heiji) that, since MINAMOTO no Yoritomo had a resemblance to Iemori in personal appearance, Ike no zenni begged for his life at the time of the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、長崎県の五島列島宇久島には清盛の弟の平家盛という名の人物が壇ノ浦の戦いの後、落ち武者狩りを逃れて移り住み、宇久次郎家盛と名乗って宇久氏（五島氏）の祖となったという伝承が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, there is a folklore in one of the Goto Islands Uku Island that, to elude the hunt for remnants of the defeated Heike clan after the Battle of Dan-no-ura, a younger brother of Kiyomori by the name of TAIRA no Iemori migrated to Uku Island under the assumed name of Jiro-Iemori UKU becoming the forefather of the Uku clan (the Goto clan).</e>
<cmt>宇久次郎家盛　－読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there is folklore in one of the Goto Islands, Uku Island, that, to elude the hunt for remnants of the defeated Heike clan after the Battle of Dan-no-ura, a younger brother of Kiyomori by the name of TAIRA no Iemori migrated to Uku Island under the assumed name of Jiro-Iemori UKU becoming the forefather of the Uku clan (the Goto clan).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there is folklore in one of the Goto Islands, Uku Island in Nagasaki Prefecture, that, to elude the hunt for remnants of the defeated Heike clan after the Battle of Dan-no-ura, a younger brother of Kiyomori by the name of TAIRA no Iemori migrated to Uku Island under the assumed name of Jiro-Iemori UKU becoming the forefather of the Uku clan (the Goto clan).</e>
<cmt>in Nagasaki Prefecture補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nnh(id:474), ゐ(id:795), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 味っ子(id:17086), 小者(id:172526), Atsasebo(id:95407), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>