<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐久間信盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobumori SAKUMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobumori SAKUMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobumori SAKUMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐久間信盛（さくま のぶもり）は、安土桃山時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobumori SAKUMA was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobumori SAKUMA was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobumori SAKUMA was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>織田信長の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a vassal of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a vassal of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a vassal of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>佐久間氏の当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a family head of the Sakuma clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a family head of the Sakuma clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a family head of the Sakuma clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>国司、右衛門尉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a provincial governor and in the position of Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a provincial governor and held the position of Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a provincial governor and held the position of Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に佐久間信栄、従兄弟に佐久間盛次（佐久間盛政、佐久間安政、柴田勝政、佐久間勝之の父）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuhide SAKUMA was one of his children, and Moritsugu SAKUMA was one of his cousins (also a father of Morimasa SAKUMA, Katsumasa SHIBATA, and Katsuyuki SAKUMA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuhide SAKUMA was one of his children, and Moritsugu SAKUMA (father of Morimasa SAKUMA, Katsumasa SHIBATA, and Katsuyuki SAKUMA) was one of his cousins.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuhide SAKUMA was one of his children, and Moritsugu SAKUMA (father of Morimasa SAKUMA, Katsumasa SHIBATA, and Katsuyuki SAKUMA) was one of his cousins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>尾張国に生まれ、織田信秀に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Owari Province and served Nobuhide ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Owari Province and served Nobuhide ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Owari Province and served Nobuhide ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼少の信長に重臣としてつけられ、信秀死後の家督相続問題でも一貫して信長に与し、織田信行謀反の際も信長方の武将として戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to a chief retainer of young Nobunaga, consistently on the side of Nobunaga during the problem of succession to the position of family head, and fought for Nobunaga during a rebellion caused by Nobuyuki ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as chief retainer of the young Nobunaga, consistently on his side during the time of his problems with succession to the position of family head, and he fought for him during a rebellion started by Nobuyuki ODA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as chief retainer of the young Nobunaga, consistently on his side during the time of his problems with succession to the position of family head, and he fought for him during a rebellion started by Nobuyuki ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その功により以後家臣団の筆頭格として扱われ、「退き佐久間」（殿軍の指揮を得意としたことに由来）といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was treated as the highest rank among vassal groups after that, and was called &apos;Shirizoki SAKUMA&apos; (Retreating SAKUMA) (named after his excellence in directing the lord&apos;s army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the highest rank among vassal groups afterwards, and was called &apos;Shirizoki SAKUMA&apos; (Retreating SAKUMA), named for his excellence in directing the lord&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the highest rank among vassal groups afterwards, and was called &apos;Shirizoki SAKUMA&apos; (Retreating SAKUMA), named for his excellence in directing the rear guard.</e>
<cmt>「殿軍」の訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>信長に従って各地を転戦し織田家の主だった合戦には全て参戦、近江国の六角氏との戦い（観音寺城の戦い）では、箕作城を落とすなどの戦功をあげ、長島一向一揆や越前国での対一向一揆戦でも活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following Nobunaga for the battles at various places, he participated in almost all the battles of the Oda family, and showed the distinguished war services in the battle against the Rokkaku clan in Omi Province, such as capturing the Mitsukuri-jo Castle, and also showed a great performance in the battle of Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) and the Ikko Ikki battle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following Nobunaga in various battles, he participated in almost all the battles of the Oda family, and showed distinguished war service in the battle against the Rokkaku clan in Omi Province, for instance, capturing Mitsukuri-jo Castle, and also gave great performances in the battle of Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) and the Ikko Ikki battle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Nobunaga in various battles, he participated in almost all the battles of the Oda family, and showed distinguished war service in the battle against the Rokkaku clan in Omi Province, for instance, capturing Mitsukuri-jo Castle, and also gave great performances in the battle of Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) and the Ikko Ikki battle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>浅井氏が織田氏に敵対した後は、柴田勝家と共に南近江を平定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Asai clan turned against the Oda clan, he conquered the southern Omi along with Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Asai clan turned against the Oda clan, he conquered the southern Omi along with Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Asai clan turned against the Oda clan, he conquered the southern Omi along with Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>比叡山焼き討ち (1571年)で武功を上げ元亀2年（1571年）11月には知行地として近江国の栗太郡を与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fire-attacked against Mt. Hiei (in 1571) and performed great military exploits, so he was given Kurita County, Omi Province as chigyo-chi (territory) in November, 1571.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He set Mt. Hiei afire (in 1571) and achieved great military exploits, so he was given Kurita County, Omi Province as chigyo-chi (territory) in November, 1571.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He set Mt. Hiei afire (in 1571) and achieved great military exploits, so he was given Kurita County, Omi Province as chigyo-chi (territory) in November, 1571.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>元亀3年（1572年）の三方ヶ原の戦いでは、平手汎秀と共に3,000の兵を率い、徳川家康8,000の援軍に赴くも、信盛は27,000の武田氏を目の当たりにし、ほとんど戦わずして退却。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Mikatagahara (in 1572), Nobumori reinforced 8,000 soldiers of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA with 3,000 soldiers together with Hirohide HIRATE, but he retreated without fighting almost any battles as soon as he looked at 27,000 soldiers of the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Mikatagahara (in 1572), Nobumori, together with Hirohide HIRATE, reinforced the 8,000 soldiers of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA with another 3,000 men, but he retreated without hardly any fighting as soon as he saw the 27,000 troops of the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Mikatagahara (in 1572), Nobumori, together with Hirohide HIRATE, reinforced the 8,000 soldiers of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA with another 3,000 men, but he retreated without hardly any fighting as soon as he saw the 27,000 troops of the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同じ援軍の将であった汎秀は家康軍と共に戦い戦死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirohide, who was a general of the same reinforcements, was killed in the battle, fighting with the Ieayasu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirohide, who was a general of the same reinforcement troops, was killed in the battle while fighting with Ieyasu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirohide, who was a general of the same reinforcement troops, was killed in the battle while fighting with Ieyasu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>天正元年（1573年）8月、戦場から離脱する朝倉義景軍の追撃を怠った織田家臣団の面々は、信長の叱責を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1573, the vassals of the Oda family received a reprimand from Nobunaga since they did not follow the army of Yosikage ASAKURA escaping from the battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, 1573, the vassals of the Oda family received a reprimand from Nobunaga since they did not follow the army of Yosikage ASAKURA escaping from the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, 1573, the vassals of the Oda family received a reprimand from Nobunaga since they did not follow the army of Yosikage ASAKURA escaping from the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その際信盛は涙を流しながら「さ様に仰せられ候共、我々程の内の者はもたれ間敷（そうは言われましても我々のような優秀な家臣団をお持ちにはなれますまい）」と弁明し、信長の怒りに油を注いだ（『信長公記』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Nobumori excused themselves with tears by saying, &quot;Whatever you say, no one would be able to have such excellent vassals as us,&quot; and this promoted Nobunaga&apos;s anger. (&quot;Shinchoko-ki&quot; [Biography of Nobunaga ODA])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobumori proceeded to excuse their behavior tearfully by saying, &quot;Whatever you say, no one would be able to have such excellent vassals as us,&quot; which fueled Nobunaga&apos;s anger (&quot;Shinchoko-ki&quot; [Biography of Nobunaga ODA]).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobumori proceeded to excuse their behavior tearfully by saying, &quot;Whatever you say, no one would be able to have such excellent vassals as us,&quot; which fueled Nobunaga&apos;s anger (&quot;Shinchoko-ki&quot; [Biography of Nobunaga ODA]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>天正4年（1576年）には、本願寺攻略戦の指揮官である塙直政の戦死を受け、後任として対本願寺戦の指揮官に就任、畿内7ヶ国の与力をつけられた信盛配下の軍団は、当時の織田家中で最大規模であったが、本願寺の熾烈な抵抗もあって戦線は膠着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1576, after the death of Naomasa BAN, commander of the war for capture of Hongan-ji Temple, Nobumori assumed the commander, and his cohorts which yoriki from seven Kinai provinces were given were the biggest among those of the Oda family, but the battle was deadlocked because of the strong resistance from Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1576, after the death of Naomasa BAN, commander of the battle to capture Hongan-ji Temple, Nobumori assumed the role of commander, and his cohorts which included yoriki (mounted warriors) received from seven Kinai provinces were the biggest among those of the Oda family, but the battle was deadlocked because of the strong resistance from Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1576, after the death of Naomasa BAN, commander of the battle to capture Hongan-ji Temple, Nobumori assumed the role of commander, and his cohorts which included yoriki (mounted warriors) received from seven Kinai provinces were the biggest among those of the Oda family, but the battle was deadlocked because of the strong resistance from Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天正8年（1580年）、信長自らが朝廷を動かし本願寺と和睦して、10年続いた戦に終止符を打った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1580, Nobunaga encouraged the Imperial Court and reconciled himself with Hongan-ji Temple after 10 years of war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 10 years of war, Nobunaga moved the Imperial Court and reconciled with Hongan-ji Temple in 1580.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 10 years of war, Nobunaga moved the Imperial Court and reconciled with Hongan-ji Temple in 1580.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この時点まで佐久間は近畿の地に織田家中で最大規模の軍団を統括し、信長相続前からの古参であることもあわせ、作家津本陽いわく”織田株式会社の副社長”ともいうべき位置にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this point, SAKUMA took command of the biggest army among the Oda family in the Kinki region, and taking account of the fact that he had been a senior member since Nobunaga&apos;s succession, he was in a position of what is called &quot;vice-president of Oda Joint-Stock Corporation&quot; as a novelist Yo TSUMOTO says.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this point, SAKUMA had taken command of the biggest army among the Oda family in the Kinki region, and taking account of the fact that he had been a senior member since Nobunaga&apos;s succession, he was in a position which was called the &quot;vice-president of Oda Joint-Stock Corporation,&quot; as novelist Yo TSUMOTO says.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this point, SAKUMA had taken command of the biggest army among the Oda family in the Kinki region, and taking account of the fact that he had been a senior member since Nobunaga&apos;s succession, he was in a position which was called the &quot;vice-president of Oda Joint-Stock Corporation,&quot; as novelist Yo TSUMOTO says.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>同年8月、信長から19ヶ条にわたる折檻状を突きつけられ、信盛は嫡男・佐久間信栄と共に高野山に追放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1580, he received a letter of chastisement consisting of 19 articles from Nobunaga, and was banished to Mt. Koya along with his legitimate son Nobuhide SAKUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, 1580, he received a letter of chastisement from Nobunaga consisting of 19 articles, and was banished to Mt. Koya along with his legitimate son Nobuhide SAKUMA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, 1580, he received a letter of chastisement from Nobunaga consisting of 19 articles, and was banished to Mt. Koya along with his legitimate son Nobuhide SAKUMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>譜代の筆頭老臣であり、最大規模の軍団長という立場からの突然の追放は内外に大きな衝撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was shocking inside and outside the Oda family that he was suddenly dismissed from the position of the roshin (old retainer) in the highest rank among fudai (hereditary vassals) and also from the commander of the biggest cohort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was shocking both inside and outside the Oda family that he was suddenly dismissed from the position of the roshin (old retainer) in the highest rank among fudai (hereditary vassals) and also as commander of the biggest cohort.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was shocking both inside and outside the Oda family that he was suddenly dismissed from the position of the roshin (old retainer) in the highest rank among fudai (hereditary vassals) and also as commander of the biggest cohort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その後高野山すら在住を許されずにさらに南に移動、佐久間家の郎党も次々に信盛親子を見捨てて去っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he proceeded to the south since he was not allowed to stay in Mt. Koya, and the retainers of the Sakuma family deserted Nobumori and his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he proceeded to the south since he was not allowed to stay in Mt. Koya, and the retainers of the Sakuma family deserted Nobumori and his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he proceeded to the south since he was not allowed to stay in Mt. Koya, and the retainers of the Sakuma family deserted Nobumori and his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>高野山に落ちるときはつき従う者二、三名、熊野に落ちるときは一名きりだったという（忠誠を感謝され信栄の帰参時には小者から士分となった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that only a few accompanied them when they went to Mt. Koya and only one to Kumano (Nobuhide thanked his loyalty and promoted him from komono [a lower servant] to the samurai class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that only a few accompanied them when they went to Mt. Koya and only one to Kumano (Nobuhide thanked his loyalty and promoted him from komono [a lower servant] to the samurai class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that only a few accompanied them when they went to Mt. Koya and only one to Kumano (Nobuhide thanked his loyalty and promoted him from komono [a lower servant] to the samurai class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>『信長公記』はこの間の佐久間親子の凋落をあわれみをもって記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shinchoko-ki&quot; describes the decline of Nobumori and Nobuhide with compassion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shinchoko-ki&quot; describes the decline of Nobumori and Nobuhide with compassion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shinchoko-ki&quot; describes the decline of Nobumori and Nobuhide with compassion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、信盛失脚後に近畿地区で大軍団を統率することになったのは明智光秀であり、苛烈な人事が家臣団に与えた動揺ともども、この追放は本能寺の変と密接に結びついて語られることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The man who came to lead the large force in the Kinki area after Nobumori was Mitsuhide AKECHI, and his banishment is often told, closely connected with the Honnoji Incident, together with the severe personnel affairs causing a disturbance to the vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The man who came to lead the largest force in the Kinki area after Nobumori was Mitsuhide AKECHI, and along with the severe human affairs which brought unrest to the vassals, this banishment was often said to be linked to the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The man who came to lead the largest force in the Kinki area after Nobumori was Mitsuhide AKECHI, and along with the severe human affairs which brought unrest to the vassals, this banishment was often said to be linked to the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>天正10年（1582年）1月16日紀伊国熊野市にて死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 16, 1582, he died in Kumano City, Kii Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 16, 1582, he died in Kumano City, Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 16, 1582, he died in Kumano City, Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>享年55。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at 55.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at 55.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at 55.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>法名は洞無桂巌または宗佑。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Doumukeigen or Souyu.</e>
<cmt>法名は音読みしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Doumukeigen or Souyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Doumukeigen or Souyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>直後に信栄は信忠付の家臣として帰参を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right after his death, Nobuhide was forgiven to return to the service as a vassal of Nobutada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Right after his death, Nobuhide was forgiven and allowed to return to service as a vassal of Nobutada.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Right after his death, Nobuhide was forgiven and allowed to return to service as a vassal of Nobutada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>資料による検証</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examination by Materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inspection of the Documents</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inspection of the Documents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>佐久間氏の武功を記録した佐久間軍記には、この追放について「だれかの讒言でもあったのではないか」という意味のことが書かれており、この書が成立した江戸初期でもそのような見方が存在していたことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sakuma military record which records the military exploits of the Sakuma clan suggests that there might have been a slander by someone for this banishment, so that we can know there was such a viewpoint during the early Edo Period, when this document was written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sakuma military record which documents the military exploits of the Sakuma clan suggests that there might have been slander by someone which caused this banishment, revealing that such a viewpoint existed during the early Edo Period, when the document was written.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sakuma military record which documents the military exploits of the Sakuma clan suggests that there might have been slander by someone which caused this banishment, revealing that such a viewpoint existed during the early Edo Period, when the document was written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、寛政重修諸家譜の佐久間信栄（正勝）の項には下記のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the article of Nobuhide (Masakatsu) SAKUMA in Kansei Choshu Shokafu (Genealogies of Vassals in Edo Bakufu) writes:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the article on Nobuhide (Masakatsu) SAKUMA in Kansei Choshu Shokafu (Genealogies of Vassals in Edo Bakufu) writes the following:</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the article on Nobuhide (Masakatsu) SAKUMA in Kansei Choshu Shokafu (Genealogies of Vassals in Edo Bakufu) writes the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>後明智光秀が讒により父信盛とともに高野山にのがる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Nobuhide ran to Mt. Koya with his father Nobumori by Mitsuhide AKECHI &apos;s slander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Nobuhide ran to Mt. Koya with his father Nobumori due to Mitsuhide AKECHI &apos;s slander.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Nobuhide ran to Mt. Koya with his father Nobumori due to Mitsuhide AKECHI &apos;s slander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>信盛死するののち、織田信長其咎なきことを知て後悔し、正勝をゆるして城介織田信忠に附属せしむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Nobumori, Nobunaga ODA knew his innocence and regretted it, and forgave Masakatsu and let him belong to the assistant governor Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Nobumori, Nobunaga ODA learned of his innocence and regretted the banishment, and forgave Masakatsu and let him go under the assistant governor Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Nobumori, Nobunaga ODA learned of his innocence and regretted the banishment, and forgave Masakatsu and let him go under the assistant governor Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>信長による19ヶ条の折檻状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Letter of Chastisement Consisting of 19 Articles by Nobunaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Letter of Chastisement Consisting of 19 Articles by Nobunaga</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Letter of Chastisement Consisting of 19 Articles by Nobunaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>一、佐久間信盛・信栄親子ともども天王寺に五年間在城しながら何ら功績もあげていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1. Nobumori SAKUMA and his son Nobuhide both stayed in Tennoji for five years, but accomplished no achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1. Nobumori SAKUMA and his son Nobuhide both stayed in Tennoji for five years, but accomplished nothing.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1. Nobumori SAKUMA and his son Nobuhide both stayed in Tennoji for five years, but accomplished nothing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>世間では不審に思っており、自分にも思い当たることがあり口惜しい思いをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People are doubting you, and I have something to remember about it and feel vexed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People are doubting you, and I too feel vexed as things come to mind.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People are doubting you, and I too feel vexed as things come to mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>一、何ら功績もあげていない信盛らの気持ちを推し量るに石山本願寺を大敵と考え、戦もせず、調略もせず、ただ城の守りを堅めておれば、幾年かもすればゆくゆく信長の威光によって引き下がるであろうという見通しだったのか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2. If I guess what Nobumori is thinking about, who has not accomplished any achievements, they might be thinking that Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple is a great enemy and that it will withdraw for Nobunaga&apos;s power in a few years even though you do not fight a battle and conceive a stratagem and if only you protect the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2. If I guess what Nobumori is thinking about, who has not accomplished anything, you might be thinking that Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple is a great enemy and that it will withdraw under Nobunaga&apos;s power in a few years even if you do not fight a battle or conceive a stratagem and if you just protect the castle.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2. If I guess what Nobumori is thinking about, who has not accomplished anything, you might be thinking that Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple is a great enemy and that it will withdraw under Nobunaga&apos;s power in a few years even if you do not fight a battle or conceive a stratagem and if you just protect the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>武者道というものはそういうものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the way of warrior is not such a thing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But this is not the way way of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But this is not the way of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>wayの削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>勝敗の機を見極め一戦を遂げれば、信長にとっても佐久間親子にとっても本意なことであったのに、一方的な思慮で持久戦に固辞し続けたことは分別もなく浅はかなことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you fought a battle after finding a chance to win, it would have been the intention of both Nobunaga&apos;s and the Sakuma&apos;s, but it was indiscreet and thoughtless that you adhered to a protracted battle on your own idea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fighting a battle after finding an opportunity to win would have been the intention of both Nobunaga&apos;s and the Sakuma&apos;s, but continuing to refuse any protracted battle based on your own arbitrary ideas was frivolous and in poor judgment.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fighting a battle after finding an opportunity to win would have been the intention of both Nobunaga&apos;s and the Sakuma&apos;s, but continuing to adhere to any protracted battle based on your own arbitrary ideas was frivolous and in poor judgment.</e>
<cmt>refuse→adhere to</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="40">
<j>一、明智光秀の働きはめざましく天下に面目をほどこし、豊臣秀吉の功労も比類なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3. The achievements of Mitsuhide AKECHI are astonishing and gaining his honor, and the services of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI are not incomparable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3. The achievements of Mitsuhide AKECHI are astonishing and earn him honor, while the services of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI are also incomparable.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3. The achievements of Mitsuhide AKECHI are astonishing and earn him honor, while the services of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI are also incomparable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>池田恒興は少禄の身であるが摂津花隈を時間も掛けず攻略し天下に名誉を施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneoki IKEDA has a small stipend, but he swiftly captured the Settsu Hanakuma Castle and won his honor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneoki IKEDA has a small stipend, but he swiftly captured the Settsu Hanakuma Castle and earned his honor.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneoki IKEDA has a small stipend, but he swiftly captured the Settsu Hanakuma Castle and earned his honor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これを以て奮起を発し一廉の働きをすべきであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By knowing these, you should rouse yourself up and do some services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You should rouse yourself to do superior service of the same sort.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You should rouse yourself to do superior service of the same sort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="43">
<j>一、柴田勝家もこれらの働きを聞いて、越前国一国を領有しながら手柄がなくては評判も悪かろうと気遣いし、この春加賀へ侵攻し平定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4. Katsuie SHIBATA heard these vassals&apos; achievements and worried about his reputation because he had not accomplished any achievements although he owned the whole Echizen Province, so he invaded and conquered Kaga Province this spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4. Katsuie SHIBATA heard of these vassals&apos; achievements and worried about his reputation because he had not had any significant achievements despite owning the entire Echizen Province, so he invaded and conquered Kaga Province this spring.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4. Katsuie SHIBATA heard of these vassals&apos; achievements and worried about his reputation because he had not had any significant achievements despite owning the entire Echizen Province, so he invaded and conquered Kaga Province this spring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="44">
<j>一、武力に不甲斐ない者は謀略などをこらし、相足らぬ所を報告し意見を聞きに来るのに、五年間それすらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5. Those who are not confident in their military power conceive stratagems, report what they are short of, and ask my suggestions, but you have not done them for five years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5. Those who are not confident in their military power conceive of stratagems, report what they are short of, and ask for my suggestions, but you have not done these things for five years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5. Those who are not confident in their military power conceive of stratagems, report what they are short of, and ask for my suggestions, but you have not done these things for five years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="45">
<j>一、信盛の与力・保田知宗の書状では本願寺に籠もる一揆衆を倒せば他の小城の一揆衆もおおかた退散するであろうとあり、信盛親子も連判している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">6. The letter from Nobumori&apos;s yoriki (assistant commander) says that if you defeat the enemy of the uprising entrenched into Hongan-ji Temple, the rest in other small castles will run away and the letter has the seals of Nobumori and Nobuhide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">6. A letter from Nobumori&apos;s yoriki (assistant commander) says that if you defeat the enemy of the uprising entrenched in Hongan-ji Temple, the rest in other small castles will run away, and the letter has the seals of Nobumori and Nobuhide.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">6. A letter from Nobumori&apos;s yoriki (assistant commander) Tomomune YASUDA says that if you defeat the enemy of the uprising entrenched in Hongan-ji Temple, the rest in other small castles will run away, and the letter has the seals of Nobumori and Nobuhide.</e>
<cmt>Tomomune YASUDA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>今まで一度もそうした報告もないのにこうした書状を送ってくるというのは、自分のくるしい立場をかわすためあれこれ理由を付け言い訳しているのではないか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You have never reported such a thing and just sent a letter, which means you are giving a plausible reason and excusing yourselves to dodge your difficult position, aren&apos;t you?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You have never reported such a thing and just sent a letter, which means you are giving a plausible reason and an excuse to get out of your difficult position, aren&apos;t you?</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You have never reported such a thing and just sent a letter, which means you are giving a plausible reason and an excuse to get out of your difficult position, aren&apos;t you?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>一、信盛は家中に於いては特別な待遇を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">7. Nobumori is receiving a special treatment among the vessels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">7. Nobumori is receiving special treatment among the vassals.</e>
<cmt>Wording and spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">7. Nobumori is receiving special treatment among the vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>三河国・尾張・近江国・大和国・河内国・和泉国に、根来衆を加えれば紀伊国にもと七ヶ国から与力をあたえられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given yoriki from seven provinces such as Mikawa Province, Owari Province, Omi Province, Kawachi Province, Izumi Province, and Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple) except originally from Kii Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Including the Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), he was given yoriki (mounted warriors) from seven provinces such as Mikawa Province, Owari Province, Omi Province, Kawachi Province, Izumi Province, and Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Including the Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), he was given yoriki (mounted warriors) from seven provinces such as Mikawa Province, Owari Province, Omi Province, Kawachi Province, Izumi Province, and Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これに自身の配下を加えれば、どんな一戦を遂げようともこれほど落ち度を取ることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adding your own vassals to this, you cannot lose any battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adding your own vassals to this, you should not be able to lose any battles.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adding your own vassals to this, you should not be able to lose any battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="50">
<j>一、水野信元死後の刈谷を与えておいたので家臣も増えたかと思えばそうではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5. I gave you Kariya after the death of Nobumoto MIZUNO, but there was no increase of vassals in number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5. I gave you Kariya after the death of Nobumoto MIZUNO, but there was no increase of the number of vassals.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5. I gave you Kariya after the death of Nobumoto MIZUNO, but there was no increase of the number of vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>水野の旧臣を追放しておきながら、跡目を新たに設けるでもなく、結局、追放した水野の旧臣の知行を信盛の直轄としてしまうのは言語道断。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You banished the old retainers of MIZUNO without establishing an heir, and it was a nonsense to privatize banished MIZUNO&apos;s chigyo (enfeoffment) and brought it under Nobumori&apos;s direct control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You banished the old retainers of MIZUNO without establishing an heir, eventually putting the banished MIZUNO chigyo (enfeoffment) under your direct control, which is outrageous.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You banished the old retainers of MIZUNO without establishing an heir, eventually putting the banished MIZUNO chigyo (enfeoffment) under your direct control, which is outrageous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="52">
<j>一、山崎の地も同様で信長の声かかりの者まで追放してしまう有様。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">6. The same thing goes to the Yamazaki region, and you banished the supporters of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">6. The same thing goes for the Yamazaki region, where you banished the supporters of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">6. The same thing goes for the Yamazaki region, where you banished the supporters of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これも先の刈谷と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, the same thing happened as in Kariya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, the same thing happened as in Kariya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, the same thing happened as in Kariya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="54">
<j>一、譜代の家臣に知行を加増してやったり与力を与えたり、新規に召し抱えたりしているなら未だいいがそれも無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">7. It is understandable if you increase your vassals&apos; chigyo, give them yoriki, or take them into your service, but you have not done them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">7. It is understandable if you increase your vassals&apos; chigyo, give them yoriki, or take them into your service, but you have not done these things.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">7. It is understandable if you increase your vassals&apos; chigyo, give them yoriki, or take them into your service, but you have not done these things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>ただ自身の蓄えを肥やすのみであり、天下の面目を失ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You just stored your own provisions and lost your honor from the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You just enriched your own stores and lost the honor you had in this world.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You just enriched your own stores and lost the honor you had in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これは唐・高麗・南蛮の国まで隠れもないことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This would be known even to the countries of Tang, Goryeo, and Nanban (Southeast Asian countries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This would be known even in the countries of Tang, Goryeo, and Nanban (Southeast Asian countries).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This would be known even in the countries of Tang, Goryeo, and Nanban (Southeast Asian countries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="57">
<j>一、先年、朝倉をうち破ったとき、戦機の見通しが悪いとしかったところものともせず、結局自身の正当性を吹聴し、あまつさえその場を立ち破るに至って信長も面目を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">8. Last year, when we defeated ASAKURA, I scolded you for your bad prospect of timings in the battle, but you insisted on your legitimacy and left your seat, so that you stained Nobunaga&apos;s honor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">8. Last year, when we defeated ASAKURA, you insisted on your legitimacy despite being scolded for your bad forecasting in the battle, and moreover you breached your position, staining Nobunaga&apos;s honor.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">8. Last year, when we defeated ASAKURA, you insisted on your legitimacy despite being scolded for your bad forecasting in the battle, and moreover you breached your position, staining Nobunaga&apos;s honor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>その口程もなくここに在陣し続けていまの働きの程は前代未聞である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite your big talk, you keep occupying your camp here and your inability is unprecedented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite your big talk, you keep occupying your camp here and your inability is unprecedented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite your big talk, you keep occupying your camp here and your inability is unprecedented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="59">
<j>一、甚九郎（信栄）の罪状を書き並べればきりがない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">9. The list of charges against Jinkuro (Nobuhide) would be endless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">9. The list of charges against Jinkuro (Nobuhide) would be endless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">9. The list of charges against Jinkuro (Nobuhide) would be endless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="60">
<j>一、大まかに言えば、第一に欲深く、気むずかしく、良い人を抱えようともしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10. Broadly saying, he is greedy to begin with, hard to please, and will not take good men into his service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">10. Broadly saying, he is greedy to begin with, hard to please, and will not take good men into his service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">10. Broadly saying, he is greedy to begin with, hard to please, and will not take good men into his service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>その上、いい加減な働きをすれば、行き着くところ親子共々武者の道を心得ていないからこのような事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, when he does not do the service well, these things happen since the parent and the son both do not understand the way of warrior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, when he does not perform his service well, these things happen since neither the father nor the son understand the way of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, when he does not perform his service well, these things happen since neither the father nor the son understand the way of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="62">
<j>一、与力を専ら使役し、他への取り次ぎや戦事にはこの与力で軍役を済まし自身の家臣を使わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">11. You mainly employ yoriki and only use yoriki for liaison with other warriors and for military services during battles, but you do not use your own vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">11. You mainly employ yoriki and only use yoriki for liaison with other warriors and for military services during battles, but you do not use your own vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">11. You mainly employ yoriki and only use yoriki for liaison with other warriors and for military services during battles, but you do not use your own vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>領地をただ遊ばせ無駄にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You are using your territory for nothing and wasting it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You are using your territory for nothing and wasting it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You are using your territory for nothing and wasting it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="64">
<j>一、信盛の与力や家臣たちまで信栄に遠慮している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">12. Yoriki and vassals of Nobumori are holding back from Nobuhide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">12. The yoriki and vassals of Nobumori are holding back from Nobuhide.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">12. The yoriki and vassals of Nobumori are holding back from Nobuhide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>自身の思慮を自慢し穏やかなふりをしても綿の中に針を隠し立てたような怖い扱いをするのでこの様になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was caused by your boasting of your consideration and your pretending to be mild despite your terrifying acts looking like a needle hidden in the cotton.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became like this because even as you boasted of your understanding and put on a genial act, your treatment was frightening, like a needle hidden in cotton.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became like this because even as you boasted of your understanding and put on a genial act, your treatment was frightening, like a needle hidden in cotton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="66">
<j>一、信長の代になり30年間奉公し信盛の活躍は比類なしと言われるような働きは一度もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">13. While you serve me 30 years since the generation of Nobunaga started, you have never done the services by which Nobumori&apos;s achievements are called incomparable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">13. While you have served me for 30 years since the generation of Nobunaga started, you have never performed services by which your achievements would be called incomparable.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">13. While you have served me for 30 years since the generation of Nobunaga started, you have never performed services by which your achievements would be called incomparable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="67">
<j>一、信長の生涯の内、勝利を失ったのは先年三方ヶ原の戦いへ援軍を使わした時で、勝ち負けの習いはあるのは仕方ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">14. During Nobunaga&apos;s life, the time when I lost a battle was when I sent the reinforcements for the Battle of Mikatagahara last year, and it is ordinary that someone wins and someone loses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">14. During Nobunaga&apos;s life, the time when I lost a battle was when I sent the reinforcements for the Battle of Mikatagahara last year, and it is ordinary that someone wins and someone loses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">14. During Nobunaga&apos;s life, the time when I lost a battle was when I sent the reinforcements for the Battle of Mikatagahara last year, and it is ordinary that someone wins and someone loses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>しかし、家康のこともあり、おくれをとったとしても兄弟・身内やしかるべき譜代衆が討死でもしていればその甲斐あって運良く戦死を免れたと人々も不審には思わなかっただろうに、一人も死者をだしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if you fell behind because of Ieyasu, if your brothers or family, or one of your fudai had died on the battle field, people would not have doubted you since you luckily scapegoated the dead, but nobody died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if you fell behind because of Ieyasu, if your brothers or family, or one of your fudai had died on the battle field, people would not have doubted you since you luckily scapegoated the dead, but nobody died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if you fell behind because of Ieyasu, if your brothers or family, or one of your fudai had died on the battle field, people would not have doubted you since you luckily scapegoated the dead, but nobody died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>あまつさえ、もう一人の援軍の将・平手汎秀を見殺しにして平然とした顔をしていることを以てしても、その思慮無きこと紛れもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is clear that you were thoughtless in consideration of the fact that you looked calm even after you saw Hirohide HIRATE, another commander of the reinforcements, died because you did not do any attempt to help him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is clear that you were thoughtless in consideration of the fact that you looked calm even after you saw that Hirohide HIRATE, another commander of the reinforcements, died because you did not make any attempt to help him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is clear that you were thoughtless in consideration of the fact that you looked calm even after you saw that Hirohide HIRATE, another commander of the reinforcements, died because you did not make any attempt to help him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="70">
<j>一、こうなればどこかの敵をたいらげ、汚名を濯いだ上帰参するか、どこかで討死するしかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">15. After all of these, all you have to do is conquer some enemy to vindicate your honor or die on a battle field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">15. After all of this, all you have to do is conquer some enemy to vindicate your honor or die on a battle field.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">15. After all of this, all you have to do is conquer some enemy to vindicate your honor or die on a battle field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="71">
<j>一、親子共々頭をまるめ、高野山にでも隠遁し連々と赦しを乞うのが当然であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">16. As a matter of course, Nobumori and Nobuhide should enter the priesthood and seclude yourselves into Mt. Koya to beg forgiveness constantly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">16. As a matter of course, Nobumori and Nobuhide should enter the priesthood and seclude themselves in Mt. Koya to beg perpetually for forgiveness.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">16. As a matter of course, Nobumori and Nobuhide should enter the priesthood and seclude themselves in Mt. Koya to beg perpetually for forgiveness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="72">
<j>信盛への評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public Estimation of Nobumori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public Estimation of Nobumori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public Estimation of Nobumori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="73">
<j>非難</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Criticism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Criticism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Criticism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>石山合戦が長期に及んだ点は、中国攻めにおける秀吉のように信長に対策を求める事もなく、陣中で茶会三昧の所業は無為の証左に他ならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason that the Ishiyama War was protracted was that he did not ask Nobunaga for a stratagem like Hideyoshi did for the war against China and that he was idle enough to hold tea ceremonies too many times at the front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason that the Ishiyama War was protracted was because he did not ask Nobunaga for a stratagem like Hideyoshi did for the war against China, and so he was idle enough to hold tea ceremonies too many times at the front.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason that the Ishiyama War was protracted was because he did not ask Nobunaga for a stratagem like Hideyoshi did for the war against China, and so he was idle enough to hold tea ceremonies too many times at the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>なお、後述の滝川一益や前田利家、この2人は確かな結果を出しているため比較対象には適切ではなく（利家は信盛とは地位・権限や態度にも大きな違いがある）、信盛が軍費をケチった為に本願寺勢に打撃をあたえられず、数年間もの間持たせ、またその費用を道楽につぎ込んだようにも見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazumasu TAKIGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA, later mentioned, are not appropriate for comparing with Nobumori since they won the adequate results (Toshiie is greatly different from Nobumori in position and authority), but it looks as if Nobumori could not damage the army of Hongan-ji Temple and let it last since he was stingy about the military costs and as if he spent that costs for pleasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazumasu TAKIGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA, later mentioned, are not appropriate for comparison with Nobumori since they produced adequate results (Toshiie is greatly different from Nobumori in position and authority), but it looks as if Nobumori could not damage the army of Hongan-ji Temple and let the situation drag on since he was stingy about the military costs, and as if he spent that money on pleasure.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Not sure about the translation here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazumasu TAKIGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA, later mentioned, are not appropriate for comparison with Nobumori since they produced adequate results (Toshiie is greatly different from Nobumori in position and authority), but it looks as if Nobumori could not damage the army of Hongan-ji Temple and let the situation drag on since he was stingy about the military costs, and as if he spent that money on pleasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="76">
<j>三方ヶ原の戦いの際の信盛の｢戦意喪失｣の末の逃亡は、真正面から戦闘をした家康や平手汎秀らの武士としての姿勢とは程遠いものがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobumori&apos;s escape after &apos;losing the will to fight&apos; at the Battle of Mikatagahara was far from the attitude of samurai which Ieyasu and Hirohide HIRATE took to face the battle from the front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobumori&apos;s escape after &apos;losing the will to fight&apos; at the Battle of Mikatagahara was far from the attitude of samurai which Ieyasu and Hirohide HIRATE took to face the battle from the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobumori&apos;s escape after &apos;losing the will to fight&apos; at the Battle of Mikatagahara was far from the attitude of samurai which Ieyasu and Hirohide HIRATE took to face the battle from the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>また、同盟者である家康を見殺しにしたとも見えるこの行動は、織田家の宿将ともいえる人物の行いとしては適切とはいえず、家康が死んだ場合の徳川家が敵側へと回る可能性を上げたり、同盟する者を減らすなどの織田家全体に関わる問題に発展した可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, his behavior which looks as if he had let Ieyasu die without attempting to help him was not an act appropriate for a person who was an experienced warrior of the Oda family, and it was possible that this might have led to a problem of all the Oda family if he had let the Tokugawa family be the enemy after Ieyasu&apos;s death or if the number of allies had decreased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, his behavior which looks as if he had let Ieyasu die without attempting to help him was not an act appropriate for a person who was an experienced warrior of the Oda family, and it was possible that this might have led to a problem for all of the Oda family if he had let the Tokugawa family become the enemy after Ieyasu&apos;s death, or if the number of allies had decreased.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, his behavior which looks as if he had let Ieyasu die without attempting to help him was not an act appropriate for a person who was an experienced warrior of the Oda family, and it was possible that this might have led to a problem for all of the Oda family if he had let the Tokugawa family become the enemy after Ieyasu&apos;s death, or if the number of allies had decreased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>このように、家康の判断等の過程はどうあれ同盟者への安全確認も満足にしなかったのは、間違いであったと言わざるを得ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whatever the process of his judgment on Ieyasu&apos;s matter is, it was his mistake not to confirm his ally&apos;s safety fully enough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whatever the process of his judgment on Ieyasu&apos;s matter was, it was his mistake not to confirm his ally&apos;s safety fully enough.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whatever the process of his judgment on Ieyasu&apos;s matter was, it was his mistake not to confirm his ally&apos;s safety fully enough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし、この点に関しては家康が無謀な策に打って出てしまった失敗も考慮しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for this, however, we need to take into account that Ieyasu made a reckless move.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for this, however, we need to take into account that Ieyasu made a reckless move.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for this, however, we need to take into account that Ieyasu made a reckless move.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>ちなみに、織田信長も金ヶ崎の戦いでは同様にただ一目散に逃亡したかのようであるが、退却戦である上に挟撃されるという状況ながら大した混乱もなく本隊は被害を小規模に留めており、この事からある程度の指示を与えてから僅かな手勢のみを引き連れて逃亡したのであり、見殺しにしたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, Nobunaga ODA also looks as if he ran away for his life at the Battle of Kanagasaki, but it was a retreating battle and the main forces had the least damages without any big confusions in the condition of being attacked from both sides, and from these facts we know Nobunaga ran away with his own small forces after giving a handful of directions and did not run away without trying to help the allies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, Nobunaga ODA also looks as if he ran away for his life at the Battle of Kanagasaki, but it was a full retreat without major damage or confusion while being attacked from both sides, and from these facts we know Nobunaga ran away with his own small forces after giving a handful of directions and did not run away without trying to help the allies.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, Nobunaga ODA also looks as if he ran away for his life at the Battle of Kanagasaki, but it was a full retreat without major damage or confusion while being attacked from both sides, and from these facts we know Nobunaga ran away with his own small forces after giving a handful of directions and did not run away without trying to help the allies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="81">
<j>我侭三昧やっておいて「私は職責を果たしている」と言い切れるものでは無く、朝倉攻めの際の弁明は過去の功績に胡座をかいた上での驕りと断じざるを得ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With all Nobumori&apos;s selfish behaviors, he would not have been able to say, &quot;I&apos;m doing my duty,&quot; and his excuses on the attack against Asakura was nothing other than his haughtiness, resting on his past achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With all Nobumori&apos;s selfish behaviors, he would not have been able to say, &quot;I&apos;m doing my duty,&quot; and his excuses for the attack against Asakura were nothing other than his haughtiness, resting on his past achievements.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With all Nobumori&apos;s selfish behaviors, he would not have been able to say, &quot;I&apos;m doing my duty,&quot; and his excuses for the attack against Asakura were nothing other than his haughtiness, resting on his past achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>実際、本願寺に対して有利に進めたわけではなく、誰もが認めるほどの結果を残さなかったのは事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, he did not gain an advantage over Hongan-ji Temple and did not win the results that anybody could appreciate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, he did not gain an advantage over Hongan-ji Temple and did not manage any appreciable results.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, he did not gain an advantage over Hongan-ji Temple and did not manage any appreciable results.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また、このような状況ながら前述の様に道楽ともいえる茶に傾倒したのも軽率であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under these circumstances, it was thoughtless that he devoted himself into tea ceremonies which could have been only for pleasure, as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under these circumstances, it was thoughtless that he would devote himself to tea ceremonies which could only have been for pleasure, as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under these circumstances, it was thoughtless that he would devote himself to tea ceremonies which could only have been for pleasure, as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="84">
<j>息子の信栄の不行状も父の驕りを見て育ったからのものであり、信盛の責任である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The misbehavior of his son Nobuhide came from his father&apos;s haughtiness, and Nobumori should be charged for this too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The misbehavior of his son Nobuhide came from his father&apos;s haughtiness, and Nobumori should be charged for this too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The misbehavior of his son Nobuhide came from his father&apos;s haughtiness, and Nobumori should be charged for this too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="85">
<j>擁護</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Defense</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Defense</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Defense</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>石山合戦の際に討伐に4年もかかった件については相手に鉄砲が多く力攻めが無理であり調略のきかない本願寺勢であること、海上封鎖ができず海から本願寺に兵糧を運びこめたことを考えれば致し方ないといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four yeas for subjugation at the Ishiyama War were never too long when we consider that a forcible attack could not be done because the enemy owned many guns, that stratagems were ineffective for the army of Hongan-ji Temple, and that the enemy could carry army provisions into Hongan-ji Temple from the sea, which could not be blockaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The four years it took for subjugation in the Ishiyama War was never too long when we consider that a forcible attack could not be carried out because the enemy owned many guns, that stratagems were ineffective on the army of Hongan-ji Temple, and that the enemy could carry army provisions into Hongan-ji Temple from the sea, which could not be blockaded.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The four years it took for subjugation in the Ishiyama War was never too long when we consider that a forcible attack could not be carried out because the enemy owned many guns, that stratagems were ineffective on the army of Hongan-ji Temple, and that the enemy could carry army provisions into Hongan-ji Temple from the sea, which could not be blockaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>また荒木村重の謀反が示すように、当時の畿内情勢は決して織田家にとって磐石の状態ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, as a rebellion of Murashige ARAKI shows, the situation of the Kinai region at that time was not firm enough for the Oda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, as the rebellion of Murashige ARAKI shows, the situation in the Kinai region at that time was not stable enough for the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, as the rebellion of Murashige ARAKI shows, the situation in the Kinai region at that time was not stable enough for the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="88">
<j>三方ヶ原の戦で味方を見殺しにした点についてはむしろあの状況で野戦に打って出た家康の状況判断に非がある（徳川軍は織田の援軍を含めれば籠城に必要な兵力をそろえていたため、籠城すれば敗戦とならなかった可能性が高い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the claim that Nobumori ran away without helping his ally at the Battle of Mikatagahara, the circumstantial judgment of Ieyasu, who decided to fight in an open field under that circumstances, was faultier (The army of TOKUGAWA had enough forces for besiegement if the reinforcements of ODA was counted, so it was highly possible not to lose the battle if he decided to be besieged).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the claim that Nobumori ran away without helping his ally at the Battle of Mikatagahara, the circumstantial judgment of Ieyasu, who decided to fight in an open field under those circumstances, was more at fault (TOKUGAWA&apos;s army had enough forces for besiegement if ODA&apos;s reinforcements were counted, so there was a high probability of not losing the battle if he decided to be besieged).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the claim that Nobumori ran away without helping his ally at the Battle of Mikatagahara, the circumstantial judgment of Ieyasu, who decided to fight in an open field under those circumstances, was more at fault (TOKUGAWA&apos;s army had enough forces for besiegement if ODA&apos;s reinforcements were counted, so there was a high probability of not losing the battle if he decided to be besieged).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>信盛が死んだ場合、対武田戦・本願寺戦の指揮をとる人物がいなくなり戦線に混乱を招く恐れがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If Nobumori had died, the person who had directed the battles against Takeda and Hongan-ji Temple would have been missing and there might have been a possibility to mess the battle line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If Nobumori had died, the person who had been directing the battles against Takeda and Hongan-ji Temple would have been missing and there might have been a possibility to disrupt the battle lines.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Nobumori had died, the person who had been directing the battles against Takeda and Hongan-ji Temple would have been missing and there might have been a possibility to disrupt the battle lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>これらのことを考えれば、戦わずして逃げたことは最善とはいえなくても許容範囲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering these points, his runaway without fighting was not the best but allowable.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering these points, his escape without fighting was not the best but understandable.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering these points, his escape without fighting was not the best but understandable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>（現に信盛の前任、塙直政が戦死したときに本願寺戦線が崩壊し、織田家そのものが崩壊しかけた。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(As a matter of fact, when Naomasa BAN, the predecessor of Nobumori, died in the battle, the battle line against Hongan-ji Temple collapsed and the Oda family itself was also about to collapse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(As a matter of fact, when Naomasa BAN, the predecessor of Nobumori, died in the battle, the battle line against Hongan-ji Temple collapsed and the Oda family itself was also about to collapse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As a matter of fact, when Naomasa BAN, the predecessor of Nobumori, died in the battle, the battle line against Hongan-ji Temple collapsed and the Oda family itself was also about to collapse.)</e>
<cmt>原文訳文に閉じ括弧を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>(また、金ヶ崎の戦いで信長自身が同様の行為をしているが、批判の対象とされてないことも考慮すべきである。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, at the Battle of Kanagasaki, Nobunaga himself did the same kind of thing, but the fact that his act is not under criticism should be considered.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, at the Battle of Kanagasaki, Nobunaga himself did the same kind of thing, but the fact that his act is not under criticism should be considered.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Besides, at the Battle of Kanagasaki, Nobunaga himself did the same kind of thing, but the fact that his act is not under criticism should be considered.)</e>
<cmt>原文訳文に開き括弧を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="93">
<j>朝倉攻めで口答えした件については、信盛が家来の長老格であるためその場を取り繕おうとしたのだろうとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His talking back on the issue of attacking Asakura must have been for patching things up for the moment since Nobumori was in the position of patriarch among the retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His talking back on the issue of attacking Asakura must have been in order to patch things up for the moment since Nobumori was in the position of patriarch among the retainers.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His talking back on the issue of attacking Asakura must have been in order to patch things up for the moment since Nobumori was in the position of patriarch among the retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>主君にいきすぎがあればそれを諌めることは家来の務めである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To remonstrate the lord when he goes too far is retainer&apos;s duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To remonstrate the lord when he goes too far is a retainer&apos;s duty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To remonstrate the lord when he goes too far is a retainer&apos;s duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>確かに信長にとって出すぎたまねには違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga might have thought it was none of Nobumori&apos;s business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga might have thought it was none of Nobumori&apos;s business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga might have thought it was none of Nobumori&apos;s business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>ただ、追放の理由としては弱すぎる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is too weak for the reason of the banishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But this is too flimsy a reason for banishment.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But this is too flimsy a reason for banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="97">
<j>家来を養わないことについては、信盛が勘定ができ必要以上の家臣を雇わなかったということだから高級幹部としてはむしろ美徳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The claim that he did not maintain his vassals means that he was strong in accounting and he did not employ vassals more than necessary, so it was rather a virtue as a high-ranking officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The claim that he did not maintain his vassals means that he was good at accounting and he did not employ any more vassals than necessary, so it was actually a virtue as a high-ranking officer.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The claim that he did not maintain his vassals means that he was good at accounting and he did not employ any more vassals than necessary, so it was actually a virtue as a high-ranking officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>家臣が少なかったことによる失敗は三方ヶ原の合戦しかないが、上述の通りこの失敗は家康の判断ミスが最大の原因である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The failure caused by a shortage of vassals was seen only in the Battle of Mikatagahara, but, as mentioned above, the main reason of this failure was Ieyasu&apos;s misjudgment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The failure caused by a shortage of vassals was seen only in the Battle of Mikatagahara, but, as mentioned above, the main reason for this failure was Ieyasu&apos;s misjudgment.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The failure caused by a shortage of vassals was seen only in the Battle of Mikatagahara, but, as mentioned above, the main reason for this failure was Ieyasu&apos;s misjudgment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>問題になっている石山合戦についても兵糧攻めに必要な人数はきちんとそろえており、塙直政のように囲みを破られる失態は犯していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the Ishiyama War taken up as a problem, Nobumori had enough forces for starving tactics, and he did not commit a blunder such as Naomasa BAN, whose siege was broken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the Ishiyama War which was brought up as an issue, Nobumori had enough forces for starvation tactics, and he did not commit a blunder such as Naomasa BAN, whose siege was broken.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the Ishiyama War which was brought up as an issue, Nobumori had enough forces for starvation tactics, and he did not commit a blunder such as Naomasa BAN, whose siege was broken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>また、各地の援軍もそつなくこなしている点も考えれば家臣を雇わなかった点については非難する理由とならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering that he did the military services as a reinforcement to the allies at various places without any mistakes, the fact that he did not employ vassals cannot be a reason to charge him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering that he performed military service as a reinforcement to the allies at various places without any mistakes, the fact that he did not employ vassals cannot be a reason to charge him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering that he performed military service as a reinforcement to the allies at various places without any mistakes, the fact that he did not employ vassals cannot be a reason to charge him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>なお、滝川一益や前田利家なども石高に比して家臣を養っていないが罰せられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA did not employ enough vassals for their stipend, but they were not punished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA did not employ enough vassals for their stipend, but they were not punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA did not employ enough vassals for their stipend, but they were not punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="102">
<j>信栄の行状が悪いことについても、たしかに親や一族の長としての責任は大きいが、信盛が職責を果たしている以上、追放の理由になるほどの問題とはいえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the misbehavior of Nobuhide, it is certain that his parents and family were hugely responsible, but as far as Nobumori was doing his duty, it cannot be a reason big enough for the banishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the misbehavior of Nobuhide, it is certain that his parents and family were hugely responsible, but as far as Nobumori was doing his duty, it cannot be a reason big enough for the banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the misbehavior of Nobuhide, it is certain that his parents and family were hugely responsible, but as far as Nobumori was doing his duty, it cannot be a reason big enough for the banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="103">
<j>こう考えると、折檻状の内容では追放の理由としては弱く、また、信盛自身に謀反の兆候があった証拠もないから、信長がそのような評価を下したとすれば信盛の運がなかった、あるいは信長の内心に理由があったという見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After considering these, the contents of a letter of chastisement are weak for the reason of Nobumori&apos;s banishment, and there is no evidence to show Nobumori was planning a rebellion, so Nobunaga&apos;s negative evaluation to Nobumori was just Nobumori&apos;s bad luck, or from another viewpoint it was Nobunaga&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After considering these points, the contents of the letter of chastisement are weak as a basis for Nobumori&apos;s banishment, and there is no evidence to show Nobumori was planning a rebellion, so Nobunaga&apos;s negative evaluation of Nobumori was just Nobumori&apos;s bad luck, or from another viewpoint, it was Nobunaga&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After considering these points, the contents of the letter of chastisement are weak as a basis for Nobumori&apos;s banishment, and there is no evidence to show Nobumori was planning a rebellion, so Nobunaga&apos;s negative evaluation of Nobumori was just Nobumori&apos;s bad luck, or from another viewpoint, it was Nobunaga&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>信盛の死後まもなく信栄の帰参が許されたのは信長が反省したと判断した、もしくは自身の評価の誤りを自覚してたからとも解釈できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason that Nobuhide was forgiven to return to the service of his master soon after the death of Nobumori is that Nobunaga judged he fully reflected his conducts or that, from another perspective, Nobunaga was aware that his evaluation was wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason that Nobuhide was forgiven and allowed to return to the service of his master soon after the death of Nobumori is that Nobunaga decided that he had fully reflected on his conduct or that, from another perspective, Nobunaga was aware that his previous evaluation was wrong.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason that Nobuhide was forgiven and allowed to return to the service of his master soon after the death of Nobumori is that Nobunaga decided that he had fully reflected on his conduct or that, from another perspective, Nobunaga was aware that his previous evaluation was wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="105">
<j>作家・樋口晴彦は著書『信長の家臣団―「天下布武」を支えた武将34人の記録』の中で、信盛が追放された理由は、畿内・美濃を織田家の直轄地とする信長の天下統一構想において双方に領地を持つ信盛の存在が邪魔になったためで、19ヶ条の折檻状は無条件で領地を取り上げるための言いがかりであったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A novelist Haruhiko HIGUCHI writes in his book &quot;Nobunaga no kashin-dan--&apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; wo sasaeta busho 34 nin no kiroku&quot; (The Vassals of Nobunaga--A Record of 34 Commanders Who Supported &apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; [a slogan that means that the samurai governs the whole world]) that the reason that Nobumori was banished was that Nobumori who held territory in both Kinai and Mino was an obstacle of Nobunaga who owned Kinai and Mino as the directly controlled land of the Oda family and also had an idea of unification of the whole country, and HIGUCHI also claims that a letter of chastisement consisting of 19 articles was Nobunaga&apos;s false accusation to confiscate Nobumori&apos;s territory with no conditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The novelist Haruhiko HIGUCHI writes in his book &quot;Nobunaga no kashin-dan--&apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; wo sasaeta busho 34 nin no kiroku&quot; (The Vassals of Nobunaga--A Record of 34 Commanders Who Supported &apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; [a slogan that means that the samurai governs the whole world]) that the reason that Nobumori was banished was that Nobumori, who held territory in both Kinai and Mino, was an obstacle to Nobunaga, who owned Kinai and Mino as the directly controlled land of the Oda family and also had an idea of unifying the whole country, and HIGUCHI also claims that the letter of chastisement consisting of 19 articles was Nobunaga&apos;s false accusation written in order to confiscate Nobumori&apos;s territory with no conditions.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The novelist Haruhiko HIGUCHI writes in his book &quot;Nobunaga no kashin-dan--&apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; wo sasaeta busho 34 nin no kiroku&quot; (The Vassals of Nobunaga--A Record of 34 Commanders Who Supported &apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; [a slogan that means that the samurai governs the whole world]) that the reason that Nobumori was banished was that Nobumori, who held territory in both Kinai and Mino, was an obstacle to Nobunaga, who owned Kinai and Mino as the directly controlled land of the Oda family and also had an idea of unifying the whole country, and HIGUCHI also claims that the letter of chastisement consisting of 19 articles was Nobunaga&apos;s false accusation written in order to confiscate Nobumori&apos;s territory with no conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>事実、信盛追放後にその領地は信長と信忠で分割されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Nobumori&apos;s territory was shared by Nobunaga and Nobutada after his banishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Nobumori&apos;s territory was shared by Nobunaga and Nobutada after his banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Nobumori&apos;s territory was shared by Nobunaga and Nobutada after his banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>そして、同じく畿内に領地を持つ明智光秀がこの追放劇に危機感を覚え、後に自身の領地である近江国坂本郡・丹波国の領地を召し上げられた事が本能寺の変のきっかけになったと分析している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to HIGUCHI&apos;s analysis, Mitsuhide AKECHI who also owned a territory in Kinai felt a sense of danger about Nobumori&apos;s banishment, and that Nobunaga confiscated Mitsuhide&apos;s territory, Sakamoto, Omi Province and Tanba Province, triggered the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to HIGUCHI&apos;s analysis, Mitsuhide AKECHI, who also owned territory in Kinai, felt a sense of danger about Nobumori&apos;s banishment, and that Nobunaga&apos;s confiscation of Mitsuhide&apos;s territory in Sakamoto, Omi Province and Tanba Province, triggered the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to HIGUCHI&apos;s analysis, Mitsuhide AKECHI, who also owned territory in Kinai, felt a sense of danger about Nobumori&apos;s banishment, and that Nobunaga&apos;s confiscation of Mitsuhide&apos;s territory in Sakamoto, Omi Province and Tanba Province, triggered the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="108">
<j>どちらにせよ、折檻状は命を惜しんで隠棲するか命を懸けて功績を挙げ挽回するかという道を選ばせており、少なくとも追放されたのは信盛自身が選択したことで信長自身が問答無用で追放したのではないことを考慮する必要がある（ちなみに前田利家は功績を挙げて挽回したくちである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, the letter let Nobumori choose to either go into seclusion for his life or retrieve his honor by making achievements at the risk of his life, and so the banishment was his choice and it should be taken into account that Nobunaga did not banish him without any choices (Toshiie MAEDA retrieved his honor by making an achievement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyway, the letter let Nobumori choose to either go into seclusion for the remainder of his life or regain his honor by making achievements at the risk of his life, and so the banishment was his choice and it should be taken into account that Nobunaga did not banish him without any choices (Toshiie MAEDA regained his honor by making an achievement).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyway, the letter let Nobumori choose to either go into seclusion for the remainder of his life or regain his honor by making achievements at the risk of his life, and so the banishment was his choice and it should be taken into account that Nobunaga did not banish him without any choices (Toshiie MAEDA regained his honor by making an achievement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>また、このことから林美作等よりも評価していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This suggests that Nobunaga&apos;s evaluation to Nobumori was higher than that of Mimasaka HAYASHI and other warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This suggests that Nobunaga&apos;s evaluation of Nobumori was higher than that of Mimasaka HAYASHI and other warriors.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This suggests that Nobunaga&apos;s evaluation of Nobumori was higher than that of Mimasaka HAYASHI and other warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), MD242(id:11277), Sat666(id:127263), Horlicks(id:62133), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), 麝香(id:89874), 松茸(id:27535), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Revth(id:12179), 蚯蚓(id:254651), ブレイズマン(id:183852), GAVVA(id:47103), Escarbot(id:59151), Kagetudo(id:163875), Aboshi(id:9318), Carkuni(id:79281), Nonnonba(id:124424), 海衛士(id:19229), スプライト(id:125926), 相馬小次郎(id:188976), Saltydog(id:9346), ５１６(id:45205), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>