<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺公能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 公能（とくだいじ きんよし、永久 (元号)3年（1115年） －永暦2年8月11日 (旧暦)（1161年9月2日））は平安時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI (1115 - September 2, 1161) was a court noble in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI (1115 - September 2, 1161) was a court noble in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinyoshi TOKUDAIJI (1115 - September 9, 1161) was Kugyo (the top court officials) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>公卿の定訳グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は徳大寺実能、母は藤原顕隆の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI, and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Akitaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI, and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Akitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Saneyoshi TOKUDAIJI, and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Akitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に徳大寺実定・実家・実守・藤原忻子（後白河天皇中宮）・藤原多子（近衛天皇皇后、二条天皇后）・坊門殿（後白河の寵愛を受けて、惇子内親王を産む）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included Sanesada, Saneie, Sanemori, Kinshi (empress of Emperor Goshirakawa), Masaruko (empress of Emperor Konoe and Emperor Nijo), and Bomon-dono (who was adored by Goshirakawa and gave birth to Imperial Princess Atsuko).</e>
<cmt>原文には、「徳大寺実定」、「藤原忻子」、「藤原多子」 とありますが、「徳大寺実定」、「藤原忻子」、「藤原多子」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語はそれぞれ「実定」、「忻子」、「多子」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Sanesada, Saneie, Sanemori, Kinshi (empress of Emperor Goshirakawa), Masaruko (empress of Emperor Konoe and Emperor Nijo), and Bomon-dono (who was adored by Goshirakawa and gave birth to Imperial Princess Atsuko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Sanesada, Saneie, Sanemori, Kinshi (empress of Emperor Goshirakawa), Masaruko (empress of Emperor Konoe and Emperor Nijo), and Bomon-dono (who was adored by Goshirakawa and gave birth to Imperial Princess Atsuko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>越中守・右少将・左中将・蔵人を経て、保延3年（1137年）に崇徳天皇の蔵人頭、翌年には参議となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being appointed to the positions of Ecchu no Kami (Governor of Ecchu Province), Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Kurodo (official of the Kurodo dokoro, or the Imperial Secretariat), he assumed the positions of Kurodo no To (head of the Kurodo dokoro) in 1137 and Sangi (Councilor) in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being appointed to the positions of Ecchu no Kami (Governor of Ecchu Province), Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Kurodo (official of the Kurodo dokoro, or the Imperial Secretariat), he assumed the positions of Kurodo no To (head of the Kurodo dokoro) in 1137 and Sangi (Councilor) in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being appointed to the positions of Ecchu no Kami (Governor of Ecchu Province), Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Kurodo (chamberlain), he assumed the positions of Kurodo no To (head chamberlain) in 1137 and Sangi (Councilor) of Emperor Sutoku in the following year.</e>
<cmt>蔵人、蔵人頭の定訳「崇徳天皇の」追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>閑院流全盛の中で権中納言・中納言・右衛門督・検非違使別当を歴任するが、崇徳退位と藤原璋子出家の影響を受けて昇進は停滞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the height of the Kanin-ryu (a Northern House faction of the Fujiwara clan), Kinyoshi assumed the positions of Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), Chunagon (Middle Counselor), Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards), and Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police); however, his advancement to a higher position was hindered due to the abdication of Sutoku and Taikenmon-in&apos;s (FUJIWARA no Shoshi&apos;s) entry into monkhood.</e>
<cmt>原文には、「藤原璋子」 とありますが、「藤原璋子」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語は「待賢門院」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the height of the Kanin-ryu (a Northern House faction of the Fujiwara clan), Kinyoshi assumed the positions of Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), Chunagon (Middle Counselor), Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards), and Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police); however, his advancement to a higher position was hindered due to the abdication of Sutoku and Taikenmon-in&apos;s (FUJIWARA no Shoshi&apos;s) entry into monkhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the height of the Kanin-ryu (a Northern House faction of the Fujiwara clan), Kinyoshi assumed the positions of Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state), Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards), and Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police); however, his advancement to a higher position was hindered due to the abdication of Sutoku and Taikenmonin&apos;s (FUJIWARA no Shoshi&apos;s) entry into monkhood.</e>
<cmt>権中納言、中納言の定訳-in&apos;s のハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後白河が即位すると娘の忻子は中宮となり、後白河在位中の保元元年（1156年）に右大将、保元2年（1157年）に権大納言と急速に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once Goshirakawa ascended the Imperial throne, Kinyoshi&apos;s daughter Kinshi became his empress and Kinyoshi was rapidly promoted to Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1156 and Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) in 1157.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once Goshirakawa ascended the Imperial throne, Kinyoshi&apos;s daughter Kinshi became his empress and Kinyoshi was rapidly promoted to Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1156 and Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) in 1157.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once Goshirakawa ascended the Imperial throne, Kinyoshi&apos;s daughter Kinshi became his empress and Kinyoshi was rapidly promoted to Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1156 and Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) in 1157.</e>
<cmt>権大納言の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>二条天皇の要請による多子の再入内に対しては、『平家物語』では積極的、『今鏡』では困惑と、態度に違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are differences as to the reaction caused by Emperor Nijo&apos;s request for Masaruko&apos;s reentry into the Dairi (Imperial Palace) to serve for him: in the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike), Kinyoshi is described to have reacted positively while in the &quot;Imakagami&quot; (The Mirror of the Present), he is portrayed to have been baffled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are differences as to the reaction caused by Emperor Nijo&apos;s request for Masaruko&apos;s reentry into the Dairi (Imperial Palace) to serve for him: in the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike), Kinyoshi is described to have reacted positively while in the &quot;Imakagami&quot; (The Mirror of the Present), he is portrayed to have been baffled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are differences as to the reaction caused by Emperor Nijo&apos;s request for Masaruko&apos;s reentry into the Dairi (Imperial Palace) to serve for him: in the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike), Kinyoshi is described to have reacted positively while in the &quot;Imakagami&quot; (The Mirror of the Present), he is portrayed to have been baffled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>永暦元年（1160年）7月に正二位右大臣となるが、翌年8月に現職のまま47歳で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was entitled to the Junior Second Court Rank, Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in July 1160, but died at the age of 47 as incumbent Udaijin in August of the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was entitled to the Junior Second Court Rank, Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in July 1160, but died at the age of 47 as incumbent Udaijin in August of the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was entitled to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in August 1160, but died at the age of 47 as incumbent Udaijin in September of the following year.</e>
<cmt>正二位、訂正旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>多芸多才で管弦・歌・朗詠等に優れ、歌に関しては義兄の藤原俊成や、かつての家人・西行と交渉が深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinyoshi excelled in various fields such as wind and string instruments, waka (traditional Japanese poetry), and recitation of poems; in the field of waka, in particular, he had close ties to his brother-in-law, FUJIWARA no Toshinari, and his former retainer, Saigyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinyoshi excelled in various fields such as wind and string instruments, waka (traditional Japanese poetry), and recitation of poems; in the field of waka, in particular, he had close ties to his brother-in-law, FUJIWARA no Toshinari, and his former retainer, Saigyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinyoshi excelled in various fields such as wind and string instruments, waka (traditional Japanese poetry), and recitation of poems; in the field of waka, in particular, he had close ties to his brother-in-law, FUJIWARA no Toshinari, and his former retainer, Saigyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『詞花和歌集』以下、勅撰集に32首が入集する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-two of his waka were collected in the Chokusenshu (anthology of poems collected by Imperial command) including the &quot;Shika Wakashu&quot; (collection of Japanese poems).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty-two of his waka were collected in the Chokusenshu (anthology of poems collected by Imperial command) including the &quot;Shika Wakashu&quot; (collection of Japanese poems).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty-two of his waka were collected in the Chokusenshu (anthology of poems collected by Imperial command) including the &quot;Shika Wakashu&quot; (a kind of anthology of poems collected by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>詞花和歌集の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), 松茸(id:27535), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>