<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石田正継</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsugu ISHIDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsugu ISHIDA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsugu ISHIDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石田 正継（いしだ まさつぐ、生年不詳 - 慶長5年9月17日 (旧暦)（1600年10月23日））は、安土桃山時代の戦国武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsugu ISHIDA (birth date unknown - October 23, 1600) was the busho (Japanese military commander) in the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsugu ISHIDA (birth date unknown - October 23, 1600) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>the&apos;→&apos;a&apos; &apos;in&apos;→&apos;of&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsugu ISHIDA (birth date unknown - October 23, 1600) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は石田為広（陸奥守仲成？清心？為厚？）といわれるが不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father is said to be Tamehiro ISHIDA (Mutsu-no-kami (Lord of Mutsu Province) Nakanari? Kiyomune? Tameatsu?) but uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father is said to have been Tamehiro (or maybe Nakanari, the Kami (Lord) of Mutsu Province; Kiyomune; or Tameatsu) but this is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderAdded &apos;or maybe&apos;Added &apos;this is&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father is said to have been Tamehiro (or maybe Nakanari, the Lord of Mutsu Province; Kiyomune; or Tameatsu) but this is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>Kami、()削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に石田正澄、石田三成などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children include Masazumi ISHIDA and Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Masazumi ISHIDA and Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>added &apos;d&apos; to &apos;include&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Masazumi ISHIDA and Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>左悟右衛門・藤右衛門・太郎右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His alias were Sagoemon, Touemon, Tarouemon.</e>
<cmt>左悟右衛門→Sagoemonと判断しました[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was also known as Sagoemon, Touemon, Tarouemon.</e>
<cmt>alias were&apos;→&apos;was also known&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His was also known as Sagoemon, Toemon, Taroemon.</e>
<cmt>u削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従五位下隠岐守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Oki-no-kami (Lord of Oki Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was a member of the Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade and the Kami (Lord) of Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>rank was&apos;→&apos;was a member of the&apos;Added &apos;and the&apos;Deleted &apos;Oki-no-kami&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His was a member of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and Oki no kami (Governor of Oki Province).</e>
<cmt>用語集より、従五位下→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)隠岐守→Oki no kami (Governor of Oki Province)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「正継」は三成出世後の名乗りであり、それ以前は政成・為成・晴成など名乗っていたらしいが、何れもはっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Masatsugu&quot; was the name he was called by after his son Mitsunari succeeded in life, and was supposedly called as Masanari, Tamenari, or Harunari prior to it but remains uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apparently originally called Masanari, Tamenari, or Harunari (though this is uncertain), &quot;Masatsugu&quot; was the name he used after his son, Mitsunari, became successful.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&apos;Supposedly&apos;→&apos;Apparently originally&apos;&apos;but remains uncertain&apos;→&apos;(though this is uncertain)&apos;&apos;succeeded in life&apos;→&apos;became successful&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apparently originally called Masanari, Tamenari, or Harunari (though this is uncertain), &apos;Masatsugu&apos; was the name he used after his son, Mitsunari, became successful.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>近江国坂田郡石田村（滋賀県長浜市石田町）の出身の地侍というが、京極氏の被官とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be ji-samurai (samurai who managed farms with peasants) from Ishida-mura (Ishida Village), Sakata-gun (Sakata District), Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province) (Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture), but there was also a theory that he was Hikan (samurai servant) of the Kyogoku clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be a ji-samurai (low-ranking farmer-samurai) from Ishida-mura, Sakata-gun, Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province) (present day Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture), but there is also a theory that he was Hikan (vassal) of the Kyogoku clan.</e>
<cmt>Changed definitions of Ji-zamurai and Hikan―I don&apos;t think &apos;hikan&apos; was confined to samurai.Added &apos;present day&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be a ji-samurai (low-ranking farmer-samurai) from Ishida-mura, Sakata-gun, Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province) (present day Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture), but there is also a theory that he was Hikan (vassal) of the Kyogoku clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>和歌や文学に造詣の深い才人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a profound knowledge for waka and literatures and excelled in those fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a profound knowledge of, and was very accomplished in, waka poetry and literature.</e>
<cmt>for&apos;→&apos;of&apos;&apos;excelled in those fields&apos;→&apos;was very accomplished in&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a profound knowledge of, and was very accomplished in, waka poetry and literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>子の三成が豊臣秀吉の家臣となるに及び、正継はとしてこれをよく補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once his son became the servant to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Masatsugu served as the magistrate and substituted for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his son, Mitsunari, became a retainer of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Masatsugu often acted as his advisor.</e>
<cmt>Once&apos;→&apos;after&apos;&apos;servant&apos;→&apos;retainer&apos;&apos;served as the magistrate and substituted for him&apos;→&apos;often acted as his advisor&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his son, Mitsunari, became a retainer of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Masatsugu often acted as his advisor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>三成が五奉行にまで出世し、佐和山城に封ぜられると、同時に正継も近江国内3万石の大名に取り立てられる（1595年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once Mitsunari was promoted to Go-bugyo (Five Commissioners) and lived in Sawayama-jo Castle, he became daimyo with 30,000 koku of Omi-no-kuni (1595).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Mitsunari was promoted to the Go-bugyo (Five Commissioners) and transferred to Sawayama-jo Castle, Masatsugu was made, in 1595, a daimyo worth 30,000 koku in Omi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>Once&apos;→&apos;When&apos;&apos;lived in&apos;→&apos;transferred to&apos;&apos;became&apos;→&apos;was made&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Mitsunari was promoted to the Go-bugyo (Five Commissioners) and transferred to Sawayama-jo Castle, Masatsugu was made, in 1595, a daimyo worth 30,000 koku in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>Omi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>以後は城代として、三成留守時の庶政を掌る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ruled as Jodai (the keeper of castle) and controlled shosei (politics) while Mitsunari was absent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Jodai, or castle caretaker, he was in charge of political affairs whenever Mitsunari was away.</e>
<cmt>Changed definition of Jodai.Deleted &apos;shosei&apos;Deleted &apos;He ruled&apos;&apos;controlled &apos;→&apos;in charge of&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Jodai, or castle caretaker, he was in charge of political affairs whenever Mitsunari was away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>朝鮮出兵に際しては、楠木正虎とともに肥前名護屋城に駐屯し、帳簿を担当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Japanese invasions of Korea, he resided with Masatora KUSUNOKI at Hizen-Nagoya-jo Castle and managed as an accountant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Japanese invasions of Korea, he was stationed, along with Masatora KUSUNOKI, at Hizen-Nagoya-jo Castle as an accountant.</e>
<cmt>resided&apos;→&apos;was stationed&apos;Added commasAdded &apos;along&apos;Deleted &apos;and managed&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Japanese invasions of Korea, he was stationed, along with Masatora KUSUNOKI, at Hizen-Nagoya-jo Castle as an accountant.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1600（慶長5）年関ヶ原の戦いでは西軍に与し、正澄とともに佐和山城にいて本丸を守備するも、小早川秀秋らの猛攻に遭って半日も持たずに敗退、落城に際して正継は自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He contributed to the Western Army during the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600 and protected the fortified castle with Masatora, but he was defeated within half a day under to furious attacks from Hideaki KOBAYAMA, and committed suicide with his sword when the falling of castle was apparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought with the Western Army during the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, defending the inner bailey of Sawayama-jo castle with Masazumi, but under Hideaki KOBAYAMA&apos;s furious attacks, the castle fell within half a day and Masatsugu committed suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>contributed to&apos;→&apos;fought with&apos;&apos;Masatori&apos;→&apos;Masazumi&apos;Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought with the Western Army during the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, defending the inner bailey of Sawayama-jo Castle with Masazumi, but under Hideaki KOBAYAMA&apos;s furious attacks, the castle fell within half a day and Masatsugu committed suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>Castle大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>墓所は京都市右京区の妙心寺で、当寺には正継の肖像画も所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grave site is located at Myoshin-ji Temple in Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City, and the same temple stores a portrait of Masatsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is located at Myoshin-ji Temple in Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City, which is also in possession of a portrait of Masatsugu.</e>
<cmt>The&apos;→&apos;HisDeleted &apos;site&apos;&apos;and the same temple stores&apos;→&apos;which is also in possession of&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is located at Myoshin-ji Temple in Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City, which is also in possession of a portrait of Masatsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), ５１６(id:45205), Raff(id:14006), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>