<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原仲実</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakazane</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nakazane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakazane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 仲実（ふじわら の なかざね、生年不詳 - 保安 (元号)2年12月23日 (旧暦)（1122年2月1日））は、平安時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakazane (date of birth unknown - February 1, 1122) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) in late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nakazane (date of birth unknown - February 1, 1122) was a Kugyo (top court official) who lived in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakazane (date of birth unknown - February 8, 1122) was a Kugyo (top court official) who lived in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は太政大臣藤原実季、兄（同母）は藤原公実。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Sanesue, and he has an elder brother-uterine FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of State) FUJIWARA no Sanesue, and he had an elder brother by the same mother FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of State) FUJIWARA no Sanesue, and he had an elder brother by the same mother FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に藤原実衡などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children include FUJIWARA no Sanehira etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children include FUJIWARA no Sanehira.</e>
<cmt>Made more formal.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children include FUJIWARA no Sanehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>承保3年（1076年）侍従、承暦2年（1078年）従五位上兼丹後守、永保元年（1081年）従四位下、備中守（これ以前に少将）、右中将、同4年（1084年）正四位下、寛治5年（1091年）兼中宮権亮、蔵人頭、同6年（1092年）参議、 同7年（1093年）左中将兼播磨権守、嘉保3年（1096年）従三位、永長2年（1097年）正三位、承徳2年（1098年）兼備中権守、康和4年（1102年）権中納言、同5年（1103年）正二位、永久 (元号)3年（1115年）権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a palace staff in 1076, Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Tango no kami (the governor of Tango Province) in 1078, Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1084, Chugu Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1091, Sangi (councillor) in 1092, Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Harima gon no kami (provisional governor of Harima Province) in 1093, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1096, Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1097, Bicchu gon no kami (provisional governor of Bicchu Province) in 1098, Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) in 1102, Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1103, and Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) in 1115.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined the palace staff in 1076, became Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Tango no kami (Governor of Tango Province) in 1078, Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1084, took the title Chugu Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1091, Sangi (councillor) in 1092, Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of the Inner Palace Guards) and Harima gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Harima Province) in 1093, rose to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1096, Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1097, became Bicchu gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Bicchu Province) in 1098, Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) in 1102, Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1103, and Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) in 1115.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalization.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined the palace staff in 1076, became Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Tango no kami (Governor of Tango Province) in 1078, Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1081, Bicchu no kami (Governer of Bicchu Province) and Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) before 1081, Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank) in 1084, took the title Chugu Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1091, Sangi (councillor) in 1092, Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of the Inner Palace Guards) and Harima gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Harima Province) in 1093, rose to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1096, Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1097, became Bicchu gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Bicchu Province) in 1098, Gon Chunagon (Provisional vice-counselor of state) in 1102, Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1103, and Gon Dainagon (Provisional chief counselor of state) in 1115.</e>
<cmt>Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1081, Bicchu no kami (Governer of Bicchu Province) and Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) before 1081, Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank) in 1084, に訂正、訳抜け補足しました。(Provisional vice-counselor of state)用語統一リストより訂正しました。(Provisional chief counselor of state)に訂正しました。Forth→Fourth</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>白河法皇の院近臣として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) of Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) to Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) to Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>