<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>加藤泰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tai KATO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tai KATO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tai KATO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>加藤 泰（かとう たい、1916年8月24日 - 1985年6月17日）は、日本の映画監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tai KATO (August 24, 1916-June 17, 1985) was a film director in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tai KATO (August 24, 1916-June 17, 1985) was a Japanese film director.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tai KATO (August 24, 1916-June 17, 1985) was a Japanese film director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>時代劇や任侠映画の監督として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He flourished as a director of period drama and films on men of chivalry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made mainly period dramas and yakuza films.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made mainly period dramas and yakuza films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>代表作に『沓掛時次郎 遊侠一匹』、『明治侠客伝 三代目襲名』、『緋牡丹博徒』シリーズなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His major works were &quot;Kutsukake Tokijiro yukyo ippiki&quot; (A chivalrious man, Tokijiro KUTSUKAGE), &quot;Meiji kyokakuden sandaime shumei (a story of professional gambler in Meiji, the third succession), series of &quot;Hibotanbakuto&quot; (A gambler with red tree peony), and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His major works include &quot;Kutsukake Tokijiro yukyo ippiki&quot; (Tokijiro KUTSUKAGE: Man of Honor), &quot;Meiji kyokakuden sandaime shumei (The Story of a Meiji Knight, the Third Generation), and the &quot;Hibotanbakuto&quot; (The Scarlet Peony Gambler) series.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - changed film titles but not sure if they hare official English versions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His major works include &quot;Kutsukake Tokijiro yukyo ippiki&quot; (Tokijiro KUTSUKAGE: Man of Honor), &quot;Meiji kyokakuden sandaime shumei&quot; (The Story of a Meiji Knight, the Third Generation), and the &quot;Hibotanbakuto&quot; (The Scarlet Peony Gambler) series.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴・人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography and character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography and character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography and Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>統一リストに従って修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>兵庫県神戸市の貿易商の家に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in the house of trademan in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born into a family of traders in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born into a family of traders in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母方の叔父に映画監督の山中貞雄がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A film director Sadao YAMANAKA was his maternal uncle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His maternal uncle was film director Sadao YAMANAKA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His maternal uncle was film director Sadao YAMANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1937年、東宝撮影所に入社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1937 he entered Toho Film Studios.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1937, he entered Toho Film Studios.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1937, he entered Toho Film Studios.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>八木保太郎に師事し、理研映画、満州映画協会を八木とともに転々とし、記録映画を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned from Yasutaro YAGI, and moved to Riken Film and Manchuria Film Association with Yagi and made documentary films.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned from Yasutaro YAGI, and moved with Yagi to Riken Film and Manchuria Film Association, where he made documentary films.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned from Yasutaro YAGI, and moved with Yagi to Riken Film and Manchuria Film Association, where he made documentary films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1946年、帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1946 he returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1946, he returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1946, he returned to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大映京都撮影所の助監督部に入社し、少年時代映画のとりことなるきっかけを作った伊藤大輔 (映画監督)監督作品につくこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered in the division of assistant director of Daiei Kyoto Studio and involved in making films directed by Daisuke ITO (a film director) whose films had taken him prisoner in his young age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Daiei Kyoto Studios as an assistant director and became involved in making films directed by Daisuke ITO, whose films had captivated him when he was a boy.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - translated &quot;助監督部&quot; as &quot;as an assistant director&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered Daiei Kyoto Studios as an assistant director and became involved in making films directed by Daisuke ITO, whose films had captivated him when he was a boy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、黒澤明監督『羅生門』では、印象的な予告編を手掛けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he made an impressive trailer of &quot;Rashomon&quot; directed by Akira KUROSAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also made a memorable trailer for Akira KUROSAWA&apos;s &quot;Rashomon&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also made a memorable trailer for Akira KUROSAWA&apos;s &quot;Rashomon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、大映の組合書記長を務めたことでレッド・パージの対象となり同社を解雇され、独立プロの宝プロダクションに転職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was fired by Daiei film company at the time of the Red Purge because he was the chief clerk of Daiei Labor Union, and moved to an indie Takara Production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was fired by Daiei during the &apos;Red Purge&apos; for being the chief clerk of Daiei Labor Union, and moved to an indie Takara Production.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was fired by Daiei during the &apos;Red Purge&apos; for being the chief clerk of Daiei Labor Union, and moved to an indie Takara Production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1951年に時代劇『剣難女難』で劇映画デビューする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951 he released his debut Jidaigeki-eiga (the period movie) &quot;KEN NAN JONAN &quot; (the calamity of being killed by the sword, trouble with women).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951, he released his debut period movie &quot;Kennan Jonan&quot; (Sword Trouble, Woman Trouble).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, he released his debut period movie &quot;Kennan Jonan&quot; (Sword Trouble, Woman Trouble).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>1956年、東映京都撮影所に移籍し、白塗りのスターが活躍するのが主流だった時代に、あえて主要キャストがノーメイクで出演する『風と女と旅鴉』、長谷川伸の名作を甦らせた『瞼の母』、そしてミュージカルやSF、リアルタイムの時代批判などさまざまな要素を詰め込んで「東映時代劇のヌーヴェルヴァーグ」と絶賛された異色作『真田風雲録』など、東映の看板スターだった萬屋錦之介と組んで数々の傑作を監督する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1956 he moved to Toei Kyoto Movie Studios and directed many masterpieces with Kinnosuke YOROZUYA who was a star of Toei such as &quot;Kaze to onna to tabigarasu&quot; (Wind and a woman and a traveling crow) in which main characters daringly appeared with no make up on in the age when a star generally put on Shironuri (white makeup), &quot;Mabuta no haha&quot; (Mother of My Dreams) which was a revival of the masterpiece of Shin HASEGAWA, and a unique work &quot;Sanada fuunroku&quot; (Tale of the Sanada Family) which received high reputation as &apos;Nouvelle Vague of Toei Jidaigeki&apos; including various factors of musical, critics against society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1956 he moved to Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, directing many masterpieces featuring Toei star Kinnosuke YOROZUYA, such as &quot;Kaze to onna to tabigarasu&quot; (The Wind, a Woman and a Traveling Crow), in which the main characters daringly appeared with no makeup on in an age when stars generally wore white Shironuri makeup; &quot;Mabuta no haha&quot; (Mother of My Dreams), a reworking of Shin HASEGAWA&apos;s novel; and the unique &quot;Sanada fuunroku&quot; (Tale of the Sanada Family), a highly regarded example of the &apos;New Wave of Toei Jidaigeki&apos;, which encompassed musicals, science fiction and social criticism.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1956 he moved to Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, directing many masterpieces featuring Toei star Kinnosuke YOROZUYA, such as &quot;Kaze to onna to tabigarasu&quot; (The Wind, a Woman and a Traveling Crow), in which the main characters daringly appeared with no makeup on in an age when stars generally wore white Shironuri makeup; &quot;Mabuta no haha&quot; (Mother of My Dreams), a reworking of Shin HASEGAWA&apos;s novel; and the unique &quot;Sanada fuunroku&quot; (Tale of the Sanada Family), a highly regarded example of the &apos;New Wave of Toei Jidaigeki,&apos; which encompassed musicals, science fiction and social criticism.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>東映が集団抗争時代劇から任侠路線へと移行する時期には、タイトルが加藤泰自身の代名詞ともなる最高傑作『沓掛時次郎 遊侠一匹』をものにし、新選組内部の抗争を描いたリアリズム時代劇『幕末残酷物語』などを撮り、そして、やくざの生きざまを独特の美意識と叙情で描いてその後の任侠映画に多大な影響を与えた『明治侠客伝 三代目襲名』を監督する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period when Toei shifted from mass vendetta Jidaigeki to men of chivalry, he directed &quot;Kutsukake Tokijiro yukyo ippiki,&quot; his masterpiece which title became a byword of Tai KATO, &quot;Brutal stories in the end of Edo Period&quot; which was a realism Jidaigeki to present an internal conflict of Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate), and &quot;Meiji kyokakuden sandaime shumei&quot; (a story of professional gambler in Meiji, the third succession) which presented the way of living of Japanese Mafia with a unique sense of beauty and lyric and gave a great impact on the later films on men of chivalry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During a period in which Toei shifted from mass vendetta period dramas to yakuza films, Kato directed &quot;Kutsukake Tokijiro yukyo ippiki,&quot; his masterpiece whose title became a byword for Tai KATO; &quot;Brutal Tales from the End of the Edo Period&quot; a realistic period drama about internal conflict in the Shinsengumi (a special police force at the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate); and &quot;Meiji kyokakuden sandaime shumei&quot; (The Story of a Meiji Knight, the Third Generation), which presented life in the Japanese Mafia with a unique sense of beauty and lyricism and greatly influenced later yakuza films.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During a period in which Toei shifted from mass vendetta period dramas to yakuza films, Kato directed &quot;Kutsukake Tokijiro yukyo ippiki,&quot; his masterpiece whose title became a byword for Tai KATO; &quot;Brutal Tales from the End of the Edo Period&quot; a realistic period drama about internal conflict in the Shinsengumi (a special police force at the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate); and &quot;Meiji kyokakuden sandaime shumei&quot; (The Story of a Meiji Knight, the Third Generation), which presented life in the Japanese Mafia with a unique sense of beauty and lyricism and greatly influenced later yakuza films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>その創作活動は1967年から1970年にピークを迎え、藤純子主演の『緋牡丹博徒』ではシリーズ中屈指の傑作である『お竜参上』を監督し、安藤昇を主演に迎え『男の顔は履歴書』や『懲役十八年』などのアクション映画を成功させ、大映の任侠スターだった江波杏子を東映に迎えて一種異様な怨念に彩られた復讐物語『昭和おんな博徒』を手掛けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His creative activities reached a peak from 1967 to 1970; he directed the masterpiece &quot;Oryu sanjo&quot; (Appearance of Oryu (a woman&apos;s name)) in the series of &quot;Hibotanbakuto&quot; in which Junko FUJI played the lead, made a success of action movie such as &apos;Man&apos;s face is a personal history&quot; and &quot;Eighteen-year sentence&quot; in which Noboru Ando played the lead, and directed &quot;Showa onna bakuto,&quot; a revenge story with a kind of strange curse in which Kyoko ENAMI, who was a star of the film of men of chivalry in Daiei and moved to Toei, played the lead.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His creative activities reached a peak from 1967 to 1970; he directed the masterpiece &quot;Oryu sanjo&quot; (The Appearance of Oryu), part of the &quot;Hibotanbakuto&quot; series, starring Junko FUJI; made successful action movies such as &quot;By a Man&apos;s Face Shall You Know Him&quot; and &quot;The Eighteen-year Sentence&quot; which starred Noboru Ando; and directed &quot;Showa onna bakuto&quot; (A Showa Lady Gambler), a revenge story featuring a strange curse in which Kyoko ENAMI, a star of of yakuza films who had moved from Daiei to Toei, played the lead.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - changed film titles but not sure if they hare official English versions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His creative activities reached a peak from 1967 to 1970; he directed the masterpiece &quot;Oryu sanjo&quot; (The Appearance of Oryu), part of the &quot;Hibotanbakuto&quot; series, starring Junko FUJI; made successful action movies such as &quot;By a Man&apos;s Face Shall You Know Him&quot; and &quot;The Eighteen-year Sentence&quot; which starred Noboru ANDO; and directed &quot;Showa onna bakuto&quot; (A Showa Lady Gambler), a revenge story featuring a strange curse in which Kyoko ENAMI, a star of yakuza films who had moved from Daiei to Toei, played the lead.</e>
<cmt>人名修正of重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>更に野村芳太郎、山田洋次ら松竹の映画監督たちとの交流から、佐藤允が復讐の連続殺人鬼を演じる異色サスペンス『皆殺しの霊歌』を監督した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he directed a unique suspense &quot;Minagoroshi no reika&quot; (aniihilation song) in which Makoto SATO performed a multiple killer for revenge from an exchange with other film directors of Shochiku such as Yoshitaro NOMURA and Yoji YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, following meetings with directors from Shochiku such as Yoshitaro NOMURA and Yoji YAMADA, he directed the unique suspense &quot;Minagoroshi no reika&quot; (Annihilation Song), in which Makoto SATO played a multiple killer out for revenge.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, following meetings with directors from Shochiku such as Yoshitaro NOMURA and Yoji YAMADA, he directed the unique suspense &quot;Minagoroshi no reika&quot; (Annihilation Song), in which Makoto SATO played a multiple killer out for revenge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>1970年代には松竹で大作シリーズ『宮本武蔵』『人生劇場』『花と龍』のほか、カルト映画の傑作とされる『江戸川乱歩の陰獣』を、東宝で『日本侠花伝』と『炎のごとく』を監督した以外は、テレビ時代劇の脚本が中心となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 1970&apos;s he mainly worked for making scenario for TV Jidaigeki except directing &quot;Inju of Ranpo EDOGAWA&quot; which was regarded as a masterpiece of occult film as well as big piece series such as &quot;Musashi MIYAMOTO,&quot; &quot;Life Game&quot; and &quot;Flower and Dragon&quot; in Shochiku, and &quot;Nihon kyoka den&quot; (A legend of men of chivalry in Japan) and &quot;Like flame&quot; in Toho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1970&apos;s, he mainly worked on scripts for TV period dramas, although he directed &quot;The Dark Side of Ranpo EDOGAWA&quot;, regarded as a masterpiece of occult cinema, and epic series such as &quot;Musashi MIYAMOTO,&quot; &quot;Life Game&quot; and &quot;Flower and Dragon&quot; for Shochiku, and &quot;Nihon kyoka den&quot; (Legend of the Yakuza) and &quot;Like a Flame&quot; for Toho.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - changed film titles but not sure if they hare official English versions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1970&apos;s, he mainly worked on scripts for TV period dramas, although he directed &quot;The Dark Side of Ranpo EDOGAWA,&quot; regarded as a masterpiece of occult cinema, and epic series such as &quot;Musashi MIYAMOTO,&quot; &quot;Life Game&quot; and &quot;Flower and Dragon&quot; for Shochiku, and &quot;Nihon kyoka den&quot; (Legend of the Yakuza) and &quot;Like a Flame&quot; for Toho.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1981年、佐渡の鬼太鼓座メンバーの若さと情熱を描いて「究極のドキュメンタリー」を目指した『ざ・鬼太鼓座』を監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1981 he directed &quot;The Ondekoza&quot; which aimed the &apos;ultimate documentary&apos; to present the youth and passion of the members of Ondekoza in Sado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1981, aiming to make the &apos;ultimate documentary&apos;, he directed &quot;The Ondekoza&quot; which showcased the youth and passion of the members of the Ondekoza drum troupe from Sado, Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - added information about 鬼太鼓座 not in the original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1981, aiming to make the &apos;ultimate documentary,&apos; he directed &quot;The Ondekoza&quot; which showcased the youth and passion of the members of the Ondekoza drum troupe from Sado, Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>加藤にとっては満映以来の記録映画であり、同時に彼の遺作ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the first documentary film for Kato since he made in Manchuria Film Association and was a posthumous work at the same time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Kato&apos;s first documentary film since he had worked for Manchuria Film Association and was released posthumously.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Kato&apos;s first documentary film since he had worked for Manchuria Film Association and was released posthumously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この作品は制作会社の事情により加藤の生前に日の目を見ることはなく、1994年にユーロスペースで開催された特集上映「加藤泰 男と女、情感の美学」で初公開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This work was not released during his living because of the condition of production company, and was released for the first time in the special showing of &apos;Tai KATO, man and woman, aesthetics of feeling&apos; which was held at a theater Eurospace in 1994.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The film, unreleased during his lifetime due to conditions at the production company, was shown for the first time in a special showing titled &apos;Tai KATO, Man and Woman, the Aesthetics of Feeling&apos; which was held at the Eurospace theater in 1994.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The film, unreleased during his lifetime due to conditions at the production company, was shown for the first time in a special showing titled &apos;Tai KATO, Man and Woman, the Aesthetics of Feeling&apos; which was held at the Eurospace theater in 1994.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>極端なまでのローアングルとクローズアップを特徴とする独自な映像スタイルは、加藤泰映画の代名詞として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His unique style of screen which is characterized by an extreme low angle and close-up is known as a byname of the films of Tai KATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His films are marked by his unique style, which is characterized by extreme low angle and close-up shots.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His films are marked by his unique style, which is characterized by extreme low angle and close-up shots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ローアングルについてはアスファルト舗装されている公道を掘り返してカメラを据え、電線が写った際には「電線を切れ」と言ったという凝り性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave himself up to the style of low angle so much as he had a public asphalt-paved road dug and placed a camera and said, &apos;Cut an electric cable&apos; when it was taken by camera.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was so obsessed with low angle shots that he is said to have dug up an asphalt-covered public road in order to position the camera and ordered an electric line that came into shot to be cut.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was so obsessed with low angle shots that he is said to have dug up an asphalt-covered public road in order to position the camera and ordered an electric line that came into shot to be cut.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、走る列車をその下からとらえた映像は、伝説化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the video of a running train which was taken under the train was legendized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the shots he took from under a moving train have achieved a legendary status.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the shots he took from under a moving train have achieved a legendary status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>晩年は、叔父・山中貞雄の業績をまとめるなど日本映画関係の著書を多数残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years he wrote many books on Japanese films such as an accomplishment of his uncle Sadao YAMANAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, he wrote many books on the work of his uncle, Sadao YAMANAKA, and other aspects of Japanese cinema.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, he wrote many books on the work of his uncle, Sadao YAMANAKA, and other aspects of Japanese cinema.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>次回作として井原西鶴原作の『好色五人女』映画化のシナリオ作業に取りかかるが、1985年に急逝した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he tried to make a film scenario for &quot;Koshoku gonin onna&quot; (Love stories about five women) which original author was Saikaku IHARA, but died suddenly in 1985.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died suddenly in 1985 while working on a script based on Saikaku IHARA&apos;s novel &quot;Koshoku gonin onna&quot; (Love Stories about Five Women).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died suddenly in 1985 while working on a script based on Saikaku IHARA&apos;s novel &quot;Koshoku gonin onna&quot; (Love Stories about Five Women).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>その独自のスタイルを貫いた映画は、死後も多くの映画ファンや評論家に絶賛され、特集上映もしばしば開催されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His films with a unique style have received high reputations by many film fan even after his death, and have often released as a special film.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His films with a unique style have been highly acclaimed by many film fans and critics even after his death, and have often been released as special editions.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His films, which have a unique style, have been highly acclaimed by many film fans and critics, even after his death, and special screenings of them have often been held.</e>
<cmt>have often been released as special editions.→special screenings of them have often been held</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Filmography</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Filmography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>監督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The works he directed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As director</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As director</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Diogenesis(id:13947), Gyokuran(id:65139), Okc(id:17021), けいとん(id:238188), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Tail furry(id:100962), Parole(id:12068), Yanahan(id:2437), Natsubon(id:1515), 明日の人(id:184696), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>