<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源景明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Kageakira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Kageakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Kageakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 景明（みなもと の かげあきら、生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期の官人・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Kageakira (date of birth and death unknown) was a government official and kajin (waka poet) who lived in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Kageakira (year of birth and death unknown) was a government official and a kajin (waka poet) who lived during the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Kageakira (year of birth and death unknown) was a government official and a kajin (waka poet) who lived during the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>光孝源氏是忠親王流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Koko-Genji (Minamoto clan), the line of Imperial Prince Koretada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He belonged to the line of Imperial Prince Koretada within the Koko-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He belonged to the line of Imperial Prince Koretada within the Koko-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>源兼光の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was MINAMOTO no Kanemitsu&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of MINAMOTO no Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of MINAMOTO no Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>右衛門尉・長門国守などを務め、従五位下に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards) and Nagato no kuni no kami (governor of Nagato Province), and rose to the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kageakira served at the Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards) and as Nagato no kuni no kami (Governor of Nagato Province), and rose to the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kageakira served as Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Nagato no kuni no kami (Governor of Nagato Province), and rose to the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>衛門府→右衛門尉　ウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>源兼澄や中務らの歌集に彼の名前が見え、彼ら有名歌人とも交流があったと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name appeared on the anthologies of Japanese poetry collected by MINAMOTO no Kanezumi, Nakatsukasa, etc.: it is presumed that he had exchange with these famous poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name appeared on the anthologies of Japanese poetry collected by MINAMOTO no Kanezumi, Nakatsukasa, etc. and it is believed that he had contact with those famous poets.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name appeared on the anthologies of Japanese poetry collected by MINAMOTO no Kanezumi, Nakatsukasa, etc. and it is believed that he had contact with those famous poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原頼忠の依頼で歌を詠んだこともあり、その時の歌が『拾遺和歌集』（歌番号173及び243）に収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He once created poems on the request of FUJIWARA no Yoritada, which poems were included in &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) (poem Nos. 173 and 243).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once he composed poems at the request of FUJIWARA no Yoritada, which were included in the &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) (poem Nos. 173 and 243).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once he composed poems at the request of FUJIWARA no Yoritada, which were included in &quot;the Shui wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems) (poem Nos. 173 and 243).</e>
<cmt>the を &quot; の中に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『拾遺和歌集』に6首、『新古今和歌集』（歌番号1066）に1首入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six of his poems were selected for &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; and one for &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) (poem No. 1066).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six of his poems were selected for the &quot;Shui wakashu&quot; and one for the &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) (poem No. 1066).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six of his poems were selected for &quot;the Shui wakashu&quot; and one for &quot;the Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) (poem No. 1066).</e>
<cmt>the を &quot; の中に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>あるかひも　なぎさに寄する　白波の　まなく物思ふ　わが身なりけり　（『新古今和歌集』恋一）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing waves lapping the shore over and over again, I feel a heartrendering sorrow. (&quot;Shinkokin Wakashu,&quot; Vol. Love 1)</e>
<cmt>原文を以下のように解釈し訳しました。「何度も岸に寄せる白波を見て、私の恋の切ない気持ちを思う。」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing waves lapping the shore over and over again, I feel a heart-rendering sorrow. (&quot;Shinkokin Wakashu,&quot; Vol. Love 1)</e>
<cmt>added hyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing waves lapping the shore over and over again, I feel a heart-rendering sorrow. (&quot;Shinkokin Wakashu,&quot; Vol. Love 1)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), Ks8823(id:130146), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>