<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>英照皇太后</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Dowager Eisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Dowager Eisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Dowager Eisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>英照皇太后（えいしょう こうたいごう、旧名：九条夙子（くじょう　あさこ）、天保4年11月13日 (旧暦)（1833年12月23日） - 明治30年（1897年）1月11日）は孝明天皇の女御にして明治天皇の嫡母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Dowager Eisho (maiden name: Asako KUJO, December 23, 1833 - January 11, 1897) was Emperor Komei&apos;s nyogo and Emperor Meiji&apos;s biological mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Dowager Eisho (maiden name: Asako KUJO, December 23, 1833 - January 11, 1897) was Emperor Komei&apos;s Nyogo (consort) and Emperor Meiji&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(consort)&quot;Deleted &quot;biological&quot; - I think most English speakers would assume she was the biological motherCapitalized &apos;n&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Dowager Eisho (maiden name: Asako KUJO, December 23, 1833 - January 11, 1897) was Emperor Komei&apos;s Nyogo (consort) and Emperor Meiji&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>Character→Personal Profileに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>父は関白左大臣九条尚忠（1798年 - 1871年）、母は賀茂神社氏人・南大路長尹の娘菅山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Hisatada KUJO (1798-1871), chief advisor to the Emperor and minister of the left, and her mother was Sugayama, a daughter of ujibito of Kamo-jinja Shrine, Choi MINAMIOJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Hisatada KUJO (1798-1871), Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) and Minister of the Left, and her mother was Sugayama, a daughter of Choi MINAMIOJI of the Kamo clan, founders of Kamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Kanpaku&quot; and bracketsCapitalized &quot;m&quot; and &quot;l&quot;Reworded 2nd part of sentence to explain &apos;ujibito&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Hisatada KUJO (1798-1871), Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) and Minister of the Left, and her mother was Sugayama, a daughter of Choi MINAMIOJI of the Kamo clan, founders of Kamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>左大臣九条道孝の実姉、貞明皇后の伯母にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was an older biological sister of Michitaka KUJO, Minister of the left, as well as an aunt of Empress Dowager Teimei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was an older sister of Michitaka KUJO, Minister of the Left, as well as an aunt of Empress Dowager Teimei.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;biological&quot;Capitalized &quot;l&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was an older sister of Michitaka KUJO, Minister of the Left, as well as an aunt of Empress Dowager Teimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>山城国愛宕郡下鴨村（現京都市左京区下鴨）の南大路家で誕生し、弘化2年（1845年）9月14日 (旧暦)、13歳の時に、2歳年上の東宮統仁親王（のちの孝明天皇）の妃となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born at the residence of Minamioji in Shimogamo Village, Otagi County, Province of Yamashiro, and on September 14, 1845, at the age of 13 she became a wife of the Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Osahito (later Emperor Komei), who was 2 years older than her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born at the Minamioji residence in Shimogamo Village, Otagi County, Province of Yamashiro (present-day Shimokamo, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto) and on September 14, 1845 (lunar calendar), at the age of 13, she became a wife of the Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Osahito (later Emperor Komei), who was 2 years older than her.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Minamoji&quot;Added present location name and &quot;(lunar calendar)&quot;Changed Japanese commas to English ones</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born at the Minamioji residence in Shimogamo Village, Otagi County, Province of Yamashiro (present-day Shimokamo, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto) and on October 14, 1845, at the age of 13, she became a wife of the Crown Prince, Imperial Prince Osahito (later Emperor Komei), who was 2 years older than her.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>結婚翌年には孝明天皇が即位し、嘉永元年（1848年）12月7日 (旧暦)従三位、同月12月15日 (旧暦)入内して女御宣下を被る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Komei was enthroned in the year following their marriage, and on December 7, 1848, she received the rank of ju-sammi, and on December 15 of the same year (lunar calendar) she officially entered the Imperial Palace and received the command to be a nyogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Komei was enthroned in the year following their marriage, and on December 7, 1848 (lunar calendar), she received the rank of ju-sammi, then on December 15 of the same year, she officially entered the Imperial Palace and was proclaimed &quot;Nyogo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;(lunar calendar)&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;then&quot;&quot;received the command to be a&quot;→&quot;was proclaimed&quot;Capitalized &apos;n&apos;Added inverted commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Komei was enthroned in the year following their marriage, and on January 1, 1849, she received Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), then on January 9 of the same year, she officially entered the Imperial Palace and was proclaimed Nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court).</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に従三位→Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)女御、説明補足→nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor))原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>孝明天皇は夙子の立后を望んだが、先ず准三宮に叙すべしという幕府の反対にあい、嘉永6年（1853年）5月7日 (旧暦)、夙子は正三位・准三宮に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Komei wanted Asako to become an empress, but he met Shogunate&apos;s opposition that maintained that she should first have the court rank of Jusangu, and on May 7, 1853 (lunar calendar) Asako was promoted to the ranks of Shosammi and Jusangu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Komei wanted Asako to become an empress, but he met Shogunate&apos;s opposition that maintained that she should first have the court rank of Jusangu, so on May 7, 1853 (lunar calendar), Asako was promoted to the ranks of Shosammi and Jusangu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot;→&quot;so&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Komei wanted Asako to become an empress, but he met Shogunate&apos;s opposition that maintained that she should first have the court rank of Jusangu, so on June 13, 1853, Asako was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Jusangu.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に正三位→Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>嘉永3年（1850年）に第一皇女順子内親王（1850年 - 1852年）、安政5年（1858年）に第二皇女富貴宮（1858年 - 1859年）を生んだが、いずれも幼児期に夭折したため、万延元年（1860年）7月10日 (旧暦)、勅令により9歳の第二皇子祐宮を「実子」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1850, she gave birth to the first princess, Imperial Princess Yoriko (1850-1852), and in 1858, she gave birth to the second princess, Fukinomiya (1858-1859), but because they both died in their infancy, on July 10, 1860 (lunar calendar), by the order of the Emperor she named the 9-year old second prince Sachinomiya as &quot;her own son.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1850, she gave birth to the first princess, Imperial Princess Yoriko (1850-1852), and in 1858, she gave birth to the second princess, Fukinomiya (1858-1859), but because they both died in their infancy, on July 10, 1860 (lunar calendar), by the order of the Emperor, she named the 9-year old second prince Sachinomiya as &quot;her own son.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1850, she gave birth to the first princess, Imperial Princess Yoriko (1850 - 1852), and in 1858, she gave birth to the second princess, Fukinomiya (1858 - 1859), but because they both died in their infancy, on August 26, 1860, by the order of the Emperor, she named the 9-year old second prince Sachinomiya as &apos;her own son.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース補足日付を新暦に原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>34歳で夫孝明天皇の急逝に遭い、明治天皇即位後、慶応4年（1868年）3月18日 (旧暦)、皇太后に冊立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 34 she encountered Emperor Komei&apos;s premature death, and after Emperor Meiji was enthroned, she was officially made into an empress dowager on March 18, 1868 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When she was 34, Emperor Komei died unexpectedly and, after Emperor Meiji was enthroned, she was officially made Empress Dowager on March 18, 1868 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>&quot;At the age of 34 she encountered Emperor Komei&apos;s premature death&quot;→&quot;When she was 34, Emperor Komei died unexpectedly&quot;Deleted &quot;into an&quot;Capitalized &quot;e&quot; and &quot;d&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When she was 34, Emperor Komei died unexpectedly and, after Emperor Meiji was enthroned, she was officially made Empress Dowager on April 10, 1868.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>東京奠都後、明治5年（1872年）、赤坂離宮に遷御、同7年、青山御所に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the capital was renamed Tokyo she moved to Akasaka Detached Palace in 1872, and in July of the same year, she moved to Aoyama Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>遷御は引越しをしたという意味で訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the capital was renamed Tokyo, she moved to Akasaka Detached Palace in 1872 then, in July of the same year, she moved to Aoyama Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;and&quot;→&quot;then&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the capital was renamed Tokyo, she moved to Akasaka Detached Palace in 1872 then, in July of the same year, she moved to Aoyama Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治21年（1888年）11月1日、勲一等宝冠章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 1, 1888, she received the First Order of the Precious Crown (Kunitto Hokansho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 1, 1888, she received the Order of the Precious Crown (Kunitto Hokansho), First Class.</e>
<cmt>&quot;First&quot;→&quot;First Class&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 1, 1888, she received the Order of the Precious Crown (Kunitto Hokansho), First Class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治30年（1897年）1月11日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 11, 1897, she passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died on January 11, 1897.</e>
<cmt>&quot;she passed away&quot;→&quot;she died&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died on January 11, 1897.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>同月1月30日に「英照皇太后」の追号を奉られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 30 of the same year, she was awarded the posthumous title of &quot;Empress Dowager Eisho&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 30 of the same year, she was awarded the posthumous title of &quot;Empress Dowager Eisho&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 30 of the same year, she was awarded the posthumous title of &apos;Empress Dowager Eisho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>御陵は京都市東山区今熊野の後月輪東北陵（のちのつきのわのとうほくのみささぎ）で、孝明帝と同所になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Imperial mausoleum is Nochino-Tsukinowano-Tohokuno-Misasagi in Imakumano, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, which is the same as that of Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Imperial mausoleum is Nochino-Tsukinowano-Tohokuno-Misasagi in Imakumano, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, where Emperor Komei is also entombed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;which is the same as that of Emperor Komei&quot;→&quot;where Emperor Komei ois also entombed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her Imperial mausoleum is Nochino-Tsukinowano-Tohokuno-Misasagi in Imakumano, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, where Emperor Komei is also entombed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、京都大宮御所は、皇太后夙子のために慶応3年（1867年）造営されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace was constructed for Empress Dowager Asako in 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace was constructed for Empress Dowager Asako in 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Omiya Imperial Palace was constructed for Empress Dowager Asako in 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Umebo(id:82785), Ganman(id:96316), YurikBot(id:18605), Geogie(id:143809), 代言人(id:33675), Stanislaus(id:1806), Cprobot(id:97843), こぶまき(id:38278), TAKASUGI Shinji(id:19129), けんち(id:5147), JunK(id:14563), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>