<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大村益次郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masujiro OMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masujiro OMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masujiro OMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大村 益次郎（おおむら ますじろう、 文政7年5月3日 (旧暦)（1824年5月30日） - 明治2年11月5日 (旧暦)（1869年12月7日））は、幕末期の長州藩（現・山口県）の医師、西洋学者、軍事学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masujiro OMURA [May 3, 1824 - November 5, 1869 on lunar calendar (May 30, 1824 - December 7, 1869)] - he was a physician, Western studies scholar and military theorist in Choshu Domain (now Yamaguchi Prefecture) in the end of Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masujiro OMURA (May 3, 1824 - November 5, 1869 lunar calendar, May 30, 1824 - December 7, 1869) was a physician, Western studies scholar and military theorist from Choshu Domain (now Yamaguchi Prefecture) at the end of the Edo era.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;- he&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;from&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;at&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masujiro OMURA (May 30, 1824 - December 7, 1869) was a physician, Western studies scholar and military theorist from Choshu Domain (now Yamaguchi Prefecture) at the end of the Edo era.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>長州征討と戊辰戦争で長州藩兵を指揮し、勝利の立役者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He commanded the force of Choshu Domain and became the architect of triumph in the Choshu War and the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He commanded Choshu forces in the Choshu War and the Boshin War, becoming the architect of triumph.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the force of Choshu Domain&quot;→&quot;Choshu forces&quot;Moved &quot;in the Choshu War and the Boshin War&quot;&quot;and became&quot;→&quot;becoming&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He commanded Choshu forces in the Choshu War and the Boshin War, becoming the architect of triumph.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初代の兵部省兵部大輔（後の陸軍次官）を務め、事実上の大日本帝国陸軍の創始者、あるいは陸軍建設の祖と見なされることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked as the hyobu taifu of Ministry of the Military (later vice minister of Army Ministry) and he is often regarded as the de facto founder of Imperial Japanese Army or the father of the Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked as the hyobu taifu of Ministry of the Military (later renamed Vice Minister of Army Ministry) and he is often regarded as the de facto founder of the Imperial Japanese Army or the father of the Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;renamed&quot; - I think it was the position that changed, I&apos;m not sure if he was actually called Vice Minister.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked as the hyobu taifu of Ministry of the Military (later renamed Vice Minister of Army Ministry) and he is often regarded as the de facto founder of the Imperial Japanese Army or the father of the Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は宗太郎、通称は蔵六、良庵（または亮庵）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Sotaro, nickname was Zoroku and Ryoan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Sotaro and his nicknames were Zoroku and Ryoan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;and his&quot;Made &quot;nickname&quot; and verb plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Sotaro and his nicknames were Zoroku and Ryoan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諱は永敏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His autonym was Nagatoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His formal name was Nagatoshi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;autonym&quot;→&quot;formal name&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His formal name was Nagatoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>位階は贈従三位、後に従二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank order was the second grade of the third rank of honor, then the second grade of the second rank of honor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the Third, and then the Second Rank at Court.</e>
<cmt>Reworded Sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held Sanmi (Third Rank), and then Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>三位→Sanmi (Third Rank)従二位→Junii (Junior Second Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家紋は丸に桔梗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family crest was a Chinese bellflower with a circle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family crest was a Chinese bellflower with a circle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family crest was a Chinese bellflower with a circle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Life→Biographyに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>村医</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rural physician</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rural physician</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rural physician</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>周防国吉敷郡鋳銭司村（すぜんじ）字大村（現・山口県山口市鋳銭司）に村医の村田孝益と妻むめの長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masujiro was born as the eldest son between rural physician Takamasu MURATA and his wife Mume in Suzenji Village Aza Omura, Yoshiki District, Suo Province (now Suzenji, Yamaguchi City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masujiro was born as the eldest son between a rural physician, Takamasu MURATA, and his wife Mume, in Suzenji Village Aza Omura, Yoshiki District, Suo Province (present-day Suzenji, Yamaguchi City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;a&quot; and commas&quot;now&quot;→&quot;present-day&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masujiro was born as the eldest son between a rural physician, Takamasu MURATA, and his wife Mume, in Suzenji Village Aza Omura, Yoshiki District, Suo Province (present-day Suzenji, Yamaguchi City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天保13年（1842年）、防府市の梅田幽斎に医学や蘭学を学び、翌年4月梅田の勧めで豊後国日田市の広瀬淡窓の門下となり、1844年6月まで学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1842, he learned medicine and rangaku from Yusai UMEDA in Hofu City and then, he studied under Tanso HIROSE who was from Hita City Bungo Province at Yusai&apos;s recommendation till June, 1844.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1842, he learned medicine and rangaku (Western studies) from Yusai UMEDA in Hofu City and, from April 1843, at Yusai&apos;s recommendation, he studied under Tanso HIROSE from Hita City, Bungo Province till June 1844.</e>
<cmt>Added explanation of &quot;rangaku&quot;&quot;then&quot;→&quot;from April 1843&quot;Moved &quot;at Yusai&apos;s recommendation&quot;Deleted &quot;who was &quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1842, he learned medicine and rangaku (Western studies) from Yusai UMEDA in Hofu City and, from April 1843, at Yusai&apos;s recommendation, he studied under Tanso HIROSE from Hita City, Bungo Province till July 1844.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>弘化3年（1846年）、大阪に出て緒方洪庵の適塾で学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Osaka in 1846 to study under Koan OGATA at his academy Tekijuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Osaka in 1846 to study under Koan OGATA at his Tekijuku academy.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;academy&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Osaka in 1846 to study under Koan OGATA at his Tekijuku academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>適塾在籍の間に長崎市で1年間遊学し、その後適塾の塾頭まで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While being on the register at Tekijuku, he went to Nagasaki City to study away from home for one year, then later he got promoted and became the head of the Tekijuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While enrolled at Tekijuku, he went to Nagasaki City on one year&apos;s sabbatical, and was later promoted to head of the Tekijuku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;being on the register&quot;→&quot;enrolled&quot;&quot;to study away from home for one year&quot;→&quot;on one year&apos;s sabbatical&quot;&quot;then later he got promoted and became the&quot;→&quot;and was later promoted to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While enrolled at Tekijuku, he went to Nagasaki City on one year&apos;s sabbatical, and was later promoted to head of the Tekijuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>嘉永3年（1850年）、父親に請われて帰郷し、村医となって村田良庵と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retuned home at his father&apos;s request in 1850 and became rural physician calling himself Ryoan MURATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned home at his father&apos;s request in 1850, becoming a rural physician and taking the name Ryoan MURATA.</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;returned&quot;&quot;and became&quot;→&quot;, becoming a&quot;&quot;calling himself&quot;→&quot;and taking the name,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned home at his father&apos;s request in 1850, becoming a rural physician and taking the name Ryoan MURATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>翌年、隣村の農家の娘琴子と結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next year he was married to Kotoko who was daughter of farmer in nearby village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year he was married to Kotoko, the daughter of a farmer from a nearby village.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Next&quot;→&quot;The following&quot;&quot;who was&quot;→&quot;, the&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;from a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year he was married to Kotoko, the daughter of a farmer from a nearby village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>だが口数が少なく無愛想で、村人が診てもらうと身体のしくみ等を何やら小難しい言葉でくどくどと説明したので「大阪で何の勉強したのやら」とあまり評判のよい医者ではなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a man of few words and brusque, also he explained examination results and body mechanism with difficult words excessively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was a brusque man of few words and tended to give tedious and difficult to understand diagnoses,</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;As&quot;Moved &quot;brusque&quot;Rewrote second part of sentence to join it with the next one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was a brusque man of few words and tended to give tedious and difficult to understand diagnoses, he was not popular with local people, who criticized him by asking, &apos;What did he study in Osaka?&apos;</e>
<cmt>２つに分けていた文を一つにまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>講武所教授</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Professor of Kobusho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military Academy Professor</e>
<cmt>&quot;of Kobusho&quot;→&quot;Military Academy&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military Academy Professor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>嘉永6年（1853年）、アメリカ合衆国のマシュー・ペリー提督率いる黒船が来航するなど、蘭学者の知識が求められる時代となり、大村は伊予国宇和島藩の要請で出仕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After arrival of the black ships of Commodore Matthew Perry of USA in 1853, men with rangaku knowledge were required and Omura served for Uwajima Domain, Iyo Province at the request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the arrival of Commodore Matthew Perry&apos;s black ships from the USA in 1853, there was a need for experts in Western studies and Omura was asked to serve in Uwajima Domain, Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Moved &quot;Commodore Matthew Perry&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;from the&quot; &quot;men with rangaku knowledge were required&quot;→&quot;there was a need for experts in Western studies&quot;&quot;served for Uwajima Domain, Iyo Province at the request&quot;→&quot;was asked to serve in Uwajima Domain, Iyo Province&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the arrival of Commodore Matthew Perry&apos;s black ships from the USA in 1853, there was a need for experts in Western studies and Omura was asked to serve in Uwajima Domain, Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このとき藩主伊達宗城は参勤交代で不在、家老も京都へ出張中であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the domain lord, Munenari DATE was not in the domain due to alternate attendance (sankin kotai) and the chief retainer went to Kyoto on business and not in the domain, either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the domain lord, Munenari DATE was in Edo, as required by the Shogun, and the chief retainer was away in Kyoto on business.</e>
<cmt>&quot;not in the domain due to alternate attendance (sankin kotai)&quot;→&quot;in Edo, as required by the Shogun&quot;&quot;went to&quot;→&quot;was away in&quot;Deleted &quot;and not in the domain, either&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the domain lord, Munenari DATE was in Edo, as required by the Shogun, and the chief retainer was away in Kyoto on business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>宇和島藩の役人たちは、2人扶年10両という低い禄高に決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officials of Uwajima Domain decided to pay him with a low stipend of two appanages and of 10 ryos per year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officials of Uwajima Domain decided to pay him with a low stipend of two servants and 10 ryos per year.</e>
<cmt>&quot;appanages&quot;→&quot;servants&quot; but unsure of &quot;扶&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officials of Uwajima Domain decided to pay him with a low stipend of two servants and 10 ryos per year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このあと帰ってきた家老は役人たちを叱責し、100石取の上士格御雇へ改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the chief retainer came back to the domain, he reprimanded the officials and changed Omura&apos;s stipend to 100 koku as for senior samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the chief retainer came back to the domain, he reprimanded the officials and changed Omura&apos;s stipend to 100 koku, the same as for senior samurai.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;, the same&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the chief retainer came back to the domain, he reprimanded the officials and changed Omura&apos;s stipend to 100 koku, the same as for senior samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>役人たちにしてみれば、高待遇との約束で来ていながら、役人に事情も説明せず汚い身なりで現れた益次郎に対して、親切心をもってした待遇であったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the stipend which officials fixed was good deal for Omura from officials point of view because he showed up with shabby dress without any explanation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears the officials thought they had given a good deal to Omura, who had shown up in shabby dress without any explanation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is said that&quot;→&quot;appears&quot;&quot;stipend which officials fixed was good deal for Omura from officials point of view because he&quot;→&quot;officials thought they had given a good deal to Omura, who&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;showed&quot;→&quot;had shown&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears the officials thought they had given a good deal to Omura, who had shown up in shabby dress without any explanation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>大村は宇和島藩で西洋兵学・蘭学の講義と翻訳を手がけ、1854年、55年には長崎へ赴いて軍艦製造の研究を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura gave lectures about the Western art of war and rangaku and their translation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura gave lectures on and translated Western knowledge and military theory and,</e>
<cmt>&quot;about the&quot;→&quot;on&quot;&quot;art of war&quot;→&quot;military theory&quot;&quot;and their translation&quot;→&quot;and translated and&quot; and moved&quot;rangaku&quot;→&quot;knowledge&quot; and movedAdded &quot;and,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura gave lectures on and translated Western knowledge and military theory and, in 1854 and 1855, he went to Nagasaki to study the construction of warships.</e>
<cmt>２つに分けていた文を一つにまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>長崎へは二宮敬作が同行したが、敬作は、文政年間に出島へ来航したドイツ人医師フィリップ・フランツ・フォン・シーボルトの弟子であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keisaku NINOMIYA accompanied Omura on the trip to Nagasaki, he was a student of German physician Philipp Franz von Siebold who came to Dejima in Bunsei period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura was accompanied on the trip to Nagasaki by Keisaku NINOMIYA, a student of the German physician Philipp Franz von Siebold, who had come to Dejima in the 1820s.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Keisaku NINOMIYA accompanied Omura on the trip to Nagasaki&quot;→&quot;Omura was accompanied on the trip to Nagasaki by Keisaku NINOMIYA&quot;Deleted &quot;he was&quot;&quot;came&quot;→&quot;had come&quot;&quot;Bunsei period&quot;→&quot;the 1820s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura was accompanied on the trip to Nagasaki by Keisaku NINOMIYA, a student of the German physician Philipp Franz von Siebold, who had come to Dejima in the 1820s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>Omura、敬作から、シーボルトの娘で産科修行をしていた楠本イネを紹介される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keisaku introduced him Ine KUSUMOTO who was a Siebold&apos;s daughter and practiced obstetrical service.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keisaku introduced him to Siebold&apos;s daughter, Ine KUSUMOTO, who was studying obstetrics.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;to&quot;Moved &quot;Siebold&apos;s daughter&quot;Deleted &quot;a&quot;&quot;and practiced obstetrical service&quot;→&quot;studying obstetrics&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keisaku introduced him to Siebold&apos;s daughter, Ine KUSUMOTO, who was studying obstetrics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>後年大村が襲撃された際、イネは大村を治療し、最期を看取っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in life when Omura was attacked, Ine treated him and she was by his bedside when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in life, when Omura was attacked, Ine treated him and she was by his bedside when he died.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in life, when Omura was attacked, Ine treated him and she was by his bedside when he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>宇和島では提灯屋の嘉蔵（かぞう）（後の前原巧山）とともに洋式軍艦の雛形を製造する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura produced a model of Western style warship with lantern maker, Kazo (later called Kozan MAEBARA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Back in Uwajima, Omura produced a model of a Western-style warship with the lantern maker, Kazo (later called Kozan MAEBARA).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Back in Uwajima,&quot;, &quot;a&quot;, hyphen and &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Back in Uwajima, Omura produced a model of a Western-style warship with the lantern maker, Kazo (later called Kozan MAEBARA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>ただし、わずかな差で国産初ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, their warship was not the first Japanese warship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was not very different from Japan&apos;s first Western-style warships.</e>
<cmt>&quot;their warship was not the first Japanese warship&quot;→&quot;it was not very different from Japan&apos;s first Western-style warships&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was not very different from Japan&apos;s first Western-style warships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>大村はこの謙虚で身分の低いほとんど無学の職人・嘉蔵の才能に驚かされたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura was very impressed by the talent of Kazo who was modest, uneducated and of low class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura was very impressed by the talent of Kazo who was modest, uneducated and of low class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura was very impressed by the talent of Kazo who was modest, uneducated and of low class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この頃村田蔵六と改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About this time, he changed his name to Zoroku MURATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About this time, he changed his name to Zoroku MURATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About this time, he changed his name to Zoroku MURATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>安政3年（1856年）4月、江戸に出て「鳩居堂」を開塾して蘭学・兵学・医学を教える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Edo to open an academy &quot;Kyukyodo&quot; in April, 1856 and taught rangaku, art of war and medical science.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1856, he went to Edo and opened the &quot;Kyukyodo&quot; academy, teaching rangaku, military theory and medicine.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;in April, 1856&quot;&quot;to open an&quot;→&quot;and opened the&quot;Moved &quot;academy&quot;&quot;and taught&quot;→&quot;, teaching&quot;&quot;art of war&quot;→&quot;military theory&quot;&quot;medical science&quot;→&quot;medicine&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1856, he went to Edo and opened the &apos;Kyukyodo&apos; academy, teaching rangaku, military theory and medicine.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にグレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>宇和島藩御雇の身分のまま、同時に徳川幕府の蕃書調所教授方手伝となり、月米20人扶持・年給20両を支給される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was hired by Uwajima Domain, he also worked for Tokugawa Shogunate as an assistant teacher at the Bansho Shirabesho and received monthly rice for 20 persons and annual income of 20 ryos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While still working for Uwajima Domain, he was also employed by the Tokugawa Shogunate as an assistant teacher at the Bansho Shirabesho institute for Western studies, receiving monthly rice for 20 persons and an annual income of 20 ryos.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he was hired by&quot;→&quot;still working for&quot;&quot;also worked for&quot;→&quot;was also employed by the&quot;Added &quot;institute for Western studies&quot;&quot;and received&quot;→&quot;, receiving&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While still working for Uwajima Domain, he was also employed by the Tokugawa Shogunate as an assistant teacher at the Bansho Shirabesho institute for Western studies, receiving monthly rice for 20 persons and an annual income of 20 ryos.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>安政4年（1857年）、幕府の講武所教授となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a teacher of the shoganate&apos;s martial art academy &quot;Kobusho&quot; in 1857.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857, he became a teacher at the shogunate&apos;s military academy.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;in 1857&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;at&quot;Spelling of &quot;Shogunate&apos;s&quot;&quot;martial art academy &quot;Kobusho&quot;&quot;→&quot;military academy&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857, he became a teacher at the shogunate&apos;s military academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>万延元年（1860年）、長州藩の要請により江戸在住のまま同藩士となり、扶持は年米25俵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a domain samurai with an annual stipend of 25 sacks of rice at the request of Choshu Domain in 1860, staying in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1860, at Choshu&apos;s request, he was made a samurai of Choshu with an annual stipend of 25 sacks of rice at, though he remained in Edo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He became a domain samurai&quot;→&quot;he was made a samurai of Choshu&quot;Changed word order&quot;staying&quot;→&quot;though he remained&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1860, at Choshu&apos;s request, he was made a samurai of Choshu with an annual stipend of 25 sacks of rice at, although he remained in Edo.</e>
<cmt>though→althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>文久2年（1862年）、幕府から委託されて英語、数学を教えていたジェームス・カーティス・ヘボンのもとで学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, he studied under James Curtis Hepburn, who taught English and math at the request of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862, he studied under James Curtis Hepburn, who had been asked by the government to teach taught English and math at the request of the government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;at the request of the government&quot;→&quot;who had been asked by the government to&quot; and moved&quot;taught&quot;→&quot;teach&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1862, he studied under James Curtis Hepburn, who had been asked by the government to teach taught English and math at the request of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>長州征討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Punitive expedition to Choshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choshu Expeditions</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choshu Expeditions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>文久3年（1863年）、萩市へ帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura came back to Hagi City in 1863.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura returned to Hagi City in 1863.</e>
<cmt>&quot;came back&quot;→&quot;returned&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura returned to Hagi City in 1863.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>西洋学兵学教授となり、博習堂での講義を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a teacher of Western art of war and gave lectures at Hakushudo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a teacher of Western military theory, giving lectures at the Hakushudo school.</e>
<cmt>&quot;art of war&quot;→&quot;military theory&quot;&quot;and gave&quot;→&quot;, giving&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;, &quot;school&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a teacher of Western military theory, giving lectures at the Hakushudo school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>長州藩ではその風貌から「火吹き達磨」のあだ名を付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got the nickname &quot;Hifuki Daruma (Firing Daruma)&quot; from his appearance in Choshu Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While in Choshu Domain, his appearance earned him the nickname &quot;Hifuki Daruma (Fire Breathing Daruma).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;his appearance&quot;&quot;He got&quot;→&quot;earned him&quot;&quot;firing&quot;→&quot;fire breathing&quot;Deleted &quot;from&quot;Moved &quot;in Choshu Domain&quot;Added &quot;while&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While in Choshu Domain, his appearance earned him the nickname &apos;Hifuki Daruma&apos; (Fire Breathing Daruma).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このあだ名は周布政之助が付けたとも高杉晋作が付けたとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Masanosuke SUFU or Shinsaku TAKASUGI gave this nickname to Omura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Masanosuke SUFU or Shinsaku TAKASUGI gave this nickname to Omura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Masanosuke SUFU or Shinsaku TAKASUGI gave this nickname to Omura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>長州藩では元治元年（1864年）の長州征討の結果、幕府へ恭順し保守派が政権を握ったが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the result of the punitive expedition to Choshu in 1864, Choshu Domain pledged fealty to the Tokugawa government and the conservatives took power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the punitive expedition to Choshu in 1864, Choshu Domain pledged fealty to the Tokugawa government and the conservatives took power.</e>
<cmt>&quot;At the&quot;→&quot;As a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the punitive expedition to Choshu in 1864, Choshu Domain pledged fealty to the Tokugawa government and the conservatives took power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>慶応元年（1865年）、高杉晋作らが下関市で挙兵して保守派を打倒、藩論を倒幕でまとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shinsaku TAKASUGI and his group rose in arms at Shimonoseki in 1865 and defeated the conservatives, and then, achieved the domain consensus to overthrow of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1865, forces led by Shinsaku TAKASUGI defeated the conservatives at Shimonoseki, leading to consensus in the domain to overthrow the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;in 1865&quot;Added &quot;forces led by&quot;Deleted &quot;and his group rose in arms&quot;Moved &quot;at Shimonoseki&quot;&quot;and then, achieved the domain consensus&quot;→&quot;leading to consensus in the domain&quot;&quot;of the government&quot;→&quot;the shogunate&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1865, forces led by Shinsaku TAKASUGI defeated the conservatives at Shimonoseki, leading to consensus in the domain to overthrow the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>高杉らは西洋式兵制を採用した奇兵隊の創設をはじめとする軍制改革に着手、大村にその指導を要請する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasugi undertook military reform such as creation of Kiheitai (irregular militia) and adopted the western style military. Takasugi asked Omura to train the military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi undertook military reforms such as the creation of the Kiheitai (irregular militia) and adopting a Western-style military, asking Omura to train them.</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;reform&quot; pluralAdded &quot;the&quot;&quot;adopted&quot;→&quot;adopting&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;&quot;. Takasugi asked&quot;→&quot;, asking&quot;&quot;the military&quot;→&quot;them&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi undertook military reforms such as the creation of the Kiheitai (irregular militia) and adopting a Western-style military, asking Omura to train them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>大村は馬廻役譜代100石取の上士となり、藩命により大村益次郎永敏と改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura became senior samurai of uma-mawariyaku with 100 koku and changed his name as Masujiro Nagatoshi OMURA at the request of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura was made a hereditary samurai of the elite umamawari corps senior samurai of uma-mawariyaku worth 100 koku and was ordered to change his name to Masujiro Nagatoshi OMURA..</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;.&quot;senior samurai of uma-mawariyaku&quot;→&quot;a hereditary samurai of the elite umamawari corps&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;worth&quot;&quot;changed his name as Masujiro Nagatoshi OMURA at the request of the domain&quot;→&quot;was ordered to change his name to Masujiro Nagatoshi OMURA&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura was made a hereditary samurai of the elite umamawari corps senior samurai of uma-mawariyaku worth 100 koku and was ordered to change his name to Masujiro Nagatoshi OMURA..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>明倫館兵学寮総官・教授として歩・騎・砲兵士官教育を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a director and teacher of Meirinkan Heigakuryo (military school), he educated for horse/foot soldiers and bombardiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a director and teacher of the Meirinkan Heigakuryo military school, he instructed cavalry, infantry and bombardiers.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;theDeleted brackets&quot;educated for&quot;→&quot;instructed&quot;&quot;horse&quot;→&quot;cavalry&quot;&quot;/foot&quot;→&quot;, infantry&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a director and teacher of the Meirinkan Heigakuryo military school, he instructed cavalry, infantry and bombardiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>大村は山口では普門寺を宿舎としていたため、普門寺塾や三兵塾と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Omura lived in the Fumon-ji Temple during staying in Yamaguchi Prefecture, the military school was called &quot;Fumon-ji juku&quot; or &quot;Sanpei juku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Omura lived in the Fumon-ji Temple while in Yamaguchi, the military school was called &quot;Fumon-ji juku&quot; or &quot;Sanpei juku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;during staying&quot;→&quot;while&quot;Deleted &quot;Prefecture&quot;&quot;called&quot;→&quot;known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Omura lived in the Fumon-ji Temple while in Yamaguchi, the military school was called &quot;Fumon-ji juku&quot; or &quot;Sanpei juku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>大村は西洋兵術書を翻訳したばかりでなく、それを現状に即し実戦に役立つようわかりやすく書き改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura translated Western military tactics and rewrote them to be used in actual warfare in an easy-to-understand way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura translated Western military tactics and rewrote them, making them more relevant to actual warfare and easy to understand.</e>
<cmt>&quot;to be used in actual warfare in an easy-to-understand way&quot;→&quot;making them more relevant to actual warfare and easy to understand&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura translated Western military tactics and rewrote them, making them more relevant to actual warfare and easy to understand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>さらにその教え方も無駄がなく的確であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, his way of teaching was simple and exact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, his way of teaching was simple and exact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, his way of teaching was simple and exact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>慶応2年（1866年）、幕府は長州征討を号令、6月に戦闘が開始される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shogunate commanded the punitive expedition to Choshu in 1866 and started the battle in June.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1866 the Shogunate ordered a second punitive expedition to Choshu, with operations starting in June.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;in 1866&quot;&quot;commanded&quot;→&quot;ordered&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;Added &quot;second&quot;&quot;and started the battle&quot;→&quot;, with operations starting&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1866 the Shogunate ordered a second punitive expedition to Choshu, with operations starting in July.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>大村は石見国口方面の実戦指揮を担当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura commanded military action in Iwami Province area against the Shogunate forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura commanded troops in the Iwami Province area.</e>
<cmt>&quot;military action&quot;→&quot;troops&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;against the Shogunate forces&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura commanded troops in the Iwami Province area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その才能は遺憾なく発揮され、優れた戦術により幕府側をことごとく撃破し、中立的立場を取った津和野藩を通過して浜田市まで進撃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exercising his talent thoroughly, he defeated every shogunate army with good tactics, went through the Tsuwano Domain which was in neutral and marched to Hamada City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exercising his talents thoroughly, his superior tactics crushed the shogunate forces, then he passed through neutral Tsuwano Domain and marched to Hamada City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he defeated every shogunate army with good tactics&quot;→&quot;his superior tactics crushed the shogunate forces&quot;Added &quot;then he&quot;&quot;went&quot;→&quot;passed&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Moved &quot;neutral&quot;Deleted &quot;which was in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exercising his talents thoroughly, his superior tactics crushed the shogunate forces, then he passed through neutral Tsuwano Domain and marched to Hamada City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>浜田城を陥落させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took control of Hamada Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took control of Hamada Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took control of Hamada Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>長州藩の旧知で蘭学者の青木周弼は大村を評して「その才知、鬼の如し」と語ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rangaku scholar in Choshu Domain, Shusuke AOKI who had known Omura said about him, &quot;Omura&apos;s sharp wit doesn&apos;t look like human.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rangaku scholar and long time acquaintance in Choshu Domain, Shusuke AOKI, said about him, &quot;his intelligence is unhuman.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;who had known Omura&quot;→&quot;long time acquaintance&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;from&quot;Reworded quote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rangaku scholar and long time acquaintance in Choshu Domain, Shusuke AOKI, said about him, &apos;his intelligence is unhuman.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>他の戦線でも長州藩は優勢に戦いを進め、事実上の勝利のもとに停戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choshu armies gained upper hand in other battle lines and effectively won the battle and ceased fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choshu armies gained the upper hand on other fronts, effectively winning the battle and brokering a ceasefire.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;in other battle lines and&quot;→&quot;on other fronts,&quot;&quot;won the battle and ceased fire&quot;→&quot;winning the battle and brokering a ceasefire&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choshu armies gained the upper hand on other fronts, effectively winning the battle and brokering a ceasefire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>戊辰戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boshin War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boshin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boshin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>明治元年（1868年）2月、王政復古 (日本)により成立した明治新政府の軍防事務局判事加勢として朝臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura was appointed a choshin of Gunbo Jimukyoku Hanji (the 3rd post of newly created military ministry) in the Meiji government of the imperial restoration in February, 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1868, Omura was appointed a choshin of Gunbo Jimukyoku Hanji (the 3rd post of the newly created military ministry) in the government of the newly restored to power Emperor Meiji..</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;in February, 1868&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;Meiji&quot;&quot;imperial restoration&quot;→&quot;newly restored to power Emperor Meiji.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1868, Omura was appointed a choshin of Gunbo Jimukyoku Hanji (the 3rd post of the newly created military ministry) in the government of the newly restored to power Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>4月には大坂から江戸に進駐し、江戸府判事を兼任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Edo (now Tokyo) from Osaka in April and held the additional post of Edo-fu Hanji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Edo (now Tokyo) from Osaka in April and was made a Justice of Edo-fu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;held&quot;→&quot;was given&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;&quot;held the additional post of&quot;→&quot;was made a&quot;&quot;Hanji&quot;→&quot;justice&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Edo (now Tokyo) from Osaka in April and was made a Justice of Edo-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>彰義隊の反乱に対して討伐軍を指揮し、わずか1日でこれを鎮圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura commanded the troops and put down the rebellion of Shogitai in a day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Ueno, troops commanded by Omura put down a rebellion by the Shogun&apos;s elite Shogitai in a single day.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence and added &quot;At the Battle of Ueno&quot; from the next sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Ueno, troops commanded by Omura put down a rebellion by the Shogun&apos;s elite Shogitai in a single day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この上野戦争の軍議で薩摩の海江田信義と対立、西郷が仲介に入る場面があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the military meeting of the Ueno War, he was opposed to Nobuyoshi KAIEDA from Satsuma Domain and Saigo stepped in between the two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura clashed with Satsuma&apos;s Nobuyoshi KAIEDA during the war council and Takamori SAIGO had to intervene.</e>
<cmt>&quot;military meeting&quot;→&quot;war council&quot;&quot;he was opposed to&quot;→&quot;clashed with&quot;Changed word orderAdded &quot;Takamori&quot; for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura clashed with Satsuma&apos;s Nobuyoshi KAIEDA during the war council and Takamori SAIGO had to intervene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この席上で大村が発した「君はいくさを知らぬ」の一言に、海江田信義が尋常ではない怒りを見せたこと等が、海江田による大村暗殺関与説の根拠となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Omura said to Kaieda in the meeting &quot;You don&apos;t know anything about the war&quot; infuriated Kaieda, and that is the basis of the theory that Kaieda was linked to the Omura assassination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaieda was infuriated when Omura told him, &quot;You don&apos;t know anything about the war&quot;, giving rise to the theory that Kaieda was linked to Omura&apos;s assassination.</e>
<cmt>Reworded first part of sentence&quot;and that is the basis of&quot;→&quot;giving rise to&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Made &quot;Omura&quot; possessive</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaieda was infuriated when Omura told him, &apos;You don&apos;t know anything about the war,&apos; giving rise to the theory that Kaieda was linked to Omura&apos;s assassination.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>同年5月、鎮台府の民政会計を任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1868, he was put in charge of civil administration and finance of Chindai-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1868, he was put in charge of Chindai-fu&apos;s civil finances.</e>
<cmt>&quot;civil administration and finance of Chindai-fu&quot;→&quot;Chindai-fu&apos;s civil finances&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1868, he was put in charge of Chindai-fu&apos;s civil finances.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>北関東で幕府残党勢力を鎮圧したのち、新政府軍の総司令官として東北地方、新潟で北部政府（奥羽越列藩同盟）と事実上の“南北戦争”である「東北戦争」を戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he put down the rebellion of Shogunate remnants in northern Kanto area, he fought in the &quot;Tohoku War&quot; as a commander-in-chief of new government against the northern government [Ouetsu Alliance (Reppan Domei)] in Tohoku region and Niigata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After defeating shogunate remnants in the northern Kanto area, he was the new government&apos;s commander-in-chief in the &quot;Tohoku War&quot; against the Northern Alliance (Ouetsu Reppan Domei) in Niigata and the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he put down the rebellion of&quot;→&quot;defeating&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;northern government&quot;→&quot;Northern Alliance&quot;- I think this is more common&quot;[Ouetsu Alliance (Reppan Domei)]&quot;→&quot;(Ouetsu Reppan Domei)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After defeating shogunate remnants in the northern Kanto area, he was the new government&apos;s commander-in-chief in the &apos;Tohoku War&apos; against the Northern Alliance (Ouetsu Reppan Domei) in Niigata and the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>北部政府の盟主、仙台藩らの降伏後、明治2年（1869年）、函館市五稜郭で幕府残党勢力の榎本軍も降伏し、戊辰戦争は終結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the northern government leader, Sendai Domain surrendered, the Shogunate remnants Enomoto troops also surrendered in Goryokaku Hakodate City and the Boshin War was ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the surrender of Northern Alliance leader, Sendai Domain, the remaining shogunate forces, led by Takeaki ENOMOTO, also surrendered at Goryokaku fortress in Hakodate City, bringing an end to the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>&quot;northern government&quot;→&quot;Northern Alliance&quot;&quot;surrendered&quot;→&quot;surrender of&quot; and moved&quot;the Shogunate remnants Enomoto troops&quot;→&quot;the remaining shogunate forces, led by Takeaki ENOMOTO&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;at&quot;Added &quot;fortress in&quot;&quot;and the Boshin War was ended&quot;→&quot;bringing an end to the Boshin War&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the surrender of Northern Alliance leader, Sendai Domain, the remaining shogunate forces, led by Takeaki ENOMOTO, also surrendered at Goryokaku fortress in Hakodate City, bringing an end to the Boshin War in 1869.</e>
<cmt>in 1869補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>兵制論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Argument of military system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dispute over military system</e>
<cmt>&quot;Argument of&quot;→&quot;Dispute over&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dispute over military system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>大村は戊辰戦争での功績により永世禄1500石を賜り、木戸孝允（桂小五郎）、大久保利通と並び新政府の幹部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura was rewarded the eternal stipend 1500 koku for performance in the Boshin War and hold an important position of the new government as well as Takayoshi KIDO (later called Kogoro KATSURA) and Toshimichi OKUBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura was rewarded for his performance in the Boshin War with a stipend for life of 1500 koku and, together with Takayoshi KIDO (later called Kogoro KATSURA) and Toshimichi OKUBO, became one of the leaders of the new government.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;with&quot;Moved &quot;for performance in the Boshin War&quot;Added &quot;his&quot;&quot;the eternal stipend&quot;→&quot;a stipend for life of&quot;&quot;as well as&quot;→&quot;together with&quot;Moved &quot;together with Takayoshi KIDO (later called Kogoro KATSURA) and Toshimichi OKUBO&quot;&quot;hold an important position&quot;→&quot;became one of the leaders&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura was rewarded for his performance in the Boshin War with a stipend for life of 1500 koku and, together with Takayoshi KIDO (later called Kogoro KATSURA) and Toshimichi OKUBO, became one of the leaders of the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>大村は軍制改革の中心を担い、1869年6月には政府の兵制会議で大久保らと旧征討軍の処理と中央軍隊の建設方法について論争を展開している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura was responsible for the military reform and at the military meeting in June, 1869, he argued about a treatment of former armies and an establishment method of centralized military with Okubo&apos;s group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura was responsible for military reform and at a military meeting in June 1869, he clashed with Okubo and others over the treatment of the defeated armies and the establishment of a centralized military.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;&quot;argued&quot;→&quot;clashed&quot;&quot;with Okubo&apos;s group&quot;→&quot;with Okubo and others&quot; and moved&quot;about a&quot;→&quot;over the&quot;&quot;former&quot;→&quot;the defeated&quot;&quot;an&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;method&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura was responsible for military reform and at a military meeting in July 1869, he clashed with Okubo and others over the treatment of the defeated armies and the establishment of a centralized military.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>兵制会議は6月21日から25日にかけて開催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military meeting was held from June 21st to 25th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meeting was held from June 21st to 25th.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;military&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meeting was held from July 29th to August 2nd.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>そこで、藩兵に依拠しない形での政府直属軍隊の創設を図る大村らと、鹿児島（薩摩藩）・山口（長州藩）・高知（土佐藩）藩兵を主体にした中央軍隊を編成しようとする大久保らとの間で激論が闘わされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura&apos;s group which insisted to create a domain-independent military under direct control of government and Okubo&apos;s group which insisted to reorganize a centralized military based on domain armies such as Kagoshima (Satsuma Domain), Yamaguchi (Choshu Domain) and Kochi (Tosa Domain) debated heatedly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was heated debate between Omura&apos;s group, which wanted to create a domain-independent military under direct control of the government, and Okubo&apos;s group, which wanted to reorganize a centralized military based on the armies of Kagoshima (Satsuma Domain), Yamaguchi (Choshu Domain) and Kochi (Tosa Domain).</e>
<cmt>&quot;debated heatedly&quot;→&quot;There was heated debate between&quot; and moved&quot;insisted&quot;→&quot;wanted&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;insisted&quot;→&quot;wanted&quot;&quot;domain&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;such as&quot;→&quot;on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was heated debate between Omura&apos;s group, which wanted to create a domain-independent military under direct control of the government, and Okubo&apos;s group, which wanted to reorganize a centralized military based on the armies of Kagoshima (Satsuma Domain), Yamaguchi (Choshu Domain) and Kochi (Tosa Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>この兵制論争中、6月21日段階での争点は、京都に駐留していた鹿児島・山口・高知藩兵の取り扱いをめぐってのものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the military argument on June 21, the point of issue was that a treatment of domain armies from Kagoshima, Yamaguchi and Kochi who had been staying in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 21, the argument concerned what to do with the armies of Kagoshima, Yamaguchi and Kochi, which had been staying in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;on June 21,&quot;&quot;in the military argument, the point of issue was that a treatment of domain armies from&quot;→&quot;the argument concerned what to do with the armies of&quot;&quot;who&quot;→&quot;, which&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 29, the argument concerned what to do with the armies of Kagoshima, Yamaguchi and Kochi, which had been staying in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>大村を支持する木戸も論争に加わり彼を援護したが、23日、大久保の主張に沿った形で、京都駐留の三藩兵が「御召」 として東下することが決定され、この問題については大久保派の勝利に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kido engaged in dispute and supported Omura, however, on June 23, this issue was resulted in Okubo group&apos;s victory that three domain&apos;s armies were to be hired by the government and moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this issue, Omura was supported by Kido but, on June 23, Okubo came out victorious when it was decided that the three domain&apos;s armies were to be hired by the government and moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kido engaged in dispute and supported Omura&quot;→&quot;On this issue, Omura was supported by Kido&quot;&quot;however&quot;→&quot;but&quot;&quot;this issue was resulted in Okubo group&apos;s victory&quot;→&quot;Okubo came out victorious when it was decided &quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this issue, Omura was supported by Kido but, on June 23, Okubo came out victorious when it was decided that the three domain&apos;s armies were to be hired by the government and moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>また23日の会議では、先の陸軍編制法の立案者である吉井友実も加わり、今後の兵卒素材についての議論も始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meeting on June 23, Tomozane YOSHII who drew up the plan of the act of army reorganization also engaged in dispute and argued about future military resources.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 23, Tomozane YOSHII, had drafted the Army Reorganization Act, also joined the dispute and the debate turned to the question of recruitment.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;In the meeting&quot;&quot;drew up the plan of the act of army reorganization&quot;→&quot;had drafted the Army Reorganization Act&quot;&quot;engaged in&quot;→&quot;joined the&quot;&quot;argued about&quot;→&quot;the debate turned to&quot;&quot;future military resources&quot;→&quot;the question of recruitment&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 31, Tomozane YOSHII, had drafted the Army Reorganization Act, also joined the dispute and the debate turned to the question of recruitment.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>ここでも大久保・吉井らの主張する「藩兵論」と大村や木戸が主張する「農兵論（一般徴兵論）」が激しく衝突し、議論は翌日も続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this matter, &quot;domain armies theory&quot; advocated by Okubo and Yoshii and &quot;universal conscription theory&quot; advocated by Omura and Kido were opposed to each other and the argument was continued to the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this matter, Okubo and Yoshii&apos;s &quot;domain armies theory&quot; was at odds with Omura and Kido&apos;s &quot;universal conscription theory&quot; and the argument carried over to the next day.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Okubo and Yoshii&quot; and &quot;Omura and Kido&quot; and made possessive&quot;were opposed to each other&quot;→&quot;was at odds&quot; &quot;was continued&quot;→&quot;carried over&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this matter, Okubo and Yoshii&apos;s &apos;domain armies theory&apos; was at odds with Omura and Kido&apos;s &apos;universal conscription theory&apos; and the argument carried over to the next day.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>しかしこれもまた、大久保派の意見が通り、この日、25日まで続く兵制論争がほぼ決着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This issue was also resulted in Okubo group&apos;s victory, and the controversy would continue till June 25 was almost settled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The result was another victory for Okubo and with this the dispute, although it would continue until June 25, was virtually settled.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The result was another victory for Okubo and with this the dispute, although it would continue until August 2, was virtually settled.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>大村の建軍構想は、この会議の結果、ことごとく退けられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura&apos;s military creation concept was rejected by the result of the meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The talks resulted in Omura&apos;s ideas on the creation of the military being comprehensively rejected.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The talks resulted in Omura&apos;s ideas on the creation of the military being comprehensively rejected.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>さらに25日には、大久保が大村の更迭を主張し始めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Okubo requested dismissal of Omura on June 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, on June 25, Okubo requested that Omura be dismissed.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;on June 25&quot;&quot;dismissal of Omura&quot;→&quot;that Omura be dismissed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, on August 2, Okubo requested that Omura be dismissed.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>憤懣やるかたない大村はほどなく辞表を提出したが、当時の政府内には、軍事に関して大村に代わるべき人物はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura got angry and tendered his resignation, however, there was no person who could replace with Omura who knew about act of war in the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura got angry and tendered his resignation but, at the time, there was nobody in the government qualified enough to replace him.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, however,&quot;→&quot;but&quot;Added &quot; at the time&quot;&quot;no person&quot;→&quot;nobody&quot;Moved &quot;in the government&quot;&quot;who could replace with Omura who knew about act of war&quot;→&quot;qualified enough to replace him&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura got angry and tendered his resignation but, at the time, there was nobody in the government qualified enough to replace him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>そのため木戸も、二官八省への官制改革が行われる前日の7月7日に大村と面会し、彼を慰留した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Kido met him on July 7, the day before tha reformation of governmental organization to &quot;Nikan Hashho (2 houses and 8 ministries), and begged him to stay in the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Kido met him on July 7, the day before the government was reorganized into &quot;Nikan Hashho&quot; (2 houses and 8 ministries), and begged him to stay in the government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;tha reformation of governmental organization to&quot;→&quot;the government was reorganized into&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Kido met him on August 14, the day before the government was reorganized into Nikan Hashho (2 houses and 8 ministries), and begged him to stay in the government.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また、改めて支持を約束し、軍務官を廃して新たに設置される兵部省に出仕することを求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kido also promised to support Omura and asked him to work in the newly created military ministry &quot;Hyobu-sho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kido also promised to support Omura and asked him to work in the newly created &quot;Hyobu-sho&quot; military ministry.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;military ministry&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kido also promised to support Omura and asked him to work in the newly created Hyobusho (military ministry).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除、説明を（）に、-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>その結果として、翌日大村は兵部大輔に就任することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Omura was appointed to the post of Hyobu-taifu (vice minister of military) the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Omura was appointed to the post of Hyobu-taifu (Vice Minister of the military) the next day.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;v&apos; and &apos;m&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Omura was appointed to the post of Hyobu taifu (senior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military) the next day.</e>
<cmt>Hyobu-taiyu、-削除、説明補足 (senior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>暗殺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>当時の兵部卿（後の陸軍大臣）は嘉彰親王であり、名目上だけの存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hyobukyo (later Ministry of the Army) of that time was Prince Yoshiakira, but he was figurehead ministry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hyobukyo (later Minister of the Army) of that time was Prince Yoshiakira, but he was minister in name only.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Ministry&quot;→&quot;Minister&quot;&quot;figurehead ministry&quot;→&quot;minister in name only&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hyobukyo (later Minister of the Army) of that time was Imperial Prince Yoshiakira, but he was minister in name only.</e>
<cmt>Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>大村は事実上、日本陸軍の建軍を指導することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura was effectively tasked with the creation of the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura was effectively tasked with the creation of the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura was effectively tasked with the creation of the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>大村は戊辰戦争で参謀として活躍した「門弟」である山田顕義を兵部大丞に推薦し、彼に下士官候補の選出を委任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura recommended Akiyoshi YAMADA, who was Omura&apos;s disciple and performed well in the Boshin War as Omura&apos;s staff, as hyobu taijo (rank of major) and asked him to choose candidates for noncommissioned officers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura recommended Akiyoshi YAMADA, a &apos;student&apos; of Omura who had been a staff officer in the Boshin War, as hyobu taijo (rank of major) and asked him to choose candidates for non-commissioned officer positions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;who was Omura&apos;s disciple and&quot;→&quot;a &apos;student&apos; of Omura who had been&quot;&quot;performed well in the Boshin War as Omura&apos;s staff&quot;→&quot;a staff officer in the Boshin War&quot;Deleted &quot;s&quot;Added hyphen and &quot;positions&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura recommended Akiyoshi YAMADA, a &apos;student&apos; of Omura who had been a staff officer in the Boshin War, as hyobu taijo (rank of major) and asked him to choose candidates for non-commissioned officer positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>山田は山口藩諸隊からを中心に約百名を選出し、9月5日からは京都に設けられた河東操練所において下士官候補の訓練を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada chose about 100 persons from all over the Yamaguchi Domain and started training them for noncommissioned officer at Kawahigashi Training Center in Kyoto from September 5.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamada chose about 100 people from all over Yamaguchi Domain and, from September 5, started training them as non-commissioned officers at Kawahigashi Training Center in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;persons&quot;→&quot;people&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;for&quot;→&quot;as&quot;Added hyphenMade &quot;officer&quot; pluralMoved &quot;from September 5&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamada chose about 100 people from all over Yamaguchi Domain and, from October 9, started training them as non-commissioned officers at Kawahigashi Training Center in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>また大村は、2年6月の段階で大阪に軍務官の大阪出張所を設置していたが、9月には同じく大阪に兵部省の兵学寮を設けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura settled a branch office of Gunmukan in Osaka in February 1869 and set the Heigakuryo (military school) of Hyobu-sho (Military ministry) in September, also in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>&quot;2年6月&quot;を明治2年と解釈し、1869年と訳しています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura established a branch of the Gunmukan (Office for Military Affairs) in Osaka in February 1869 and set up the government&apos;s Heigakuryo Military Academy in September, also in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>&quot;settled&quot;→&quot;established&quot;Deleted &quot;office&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; and definition of &quot;Gunmukan&quot;&quot;(military school)&quot;→&quot;Military Academy&quot;&quot;of Hyobu-sho (Military ministry)&quot;→&quot;government&apos;s&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura established a branch of the Gunmukan (Office for Military Affairs) in Osaka in July 1869 and set up the government&apos;s Heigakuryo Military Academy in October, also in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>February→Juneグレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>このほか京都宇治に火薬製造所を、また大阪に造兵廠を建設することも決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also decided the construction of powder manufacturing plant in Uji, Kyoto and weaponry plant in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also decided to build a gunpowder manufacturing plant in Uji, Kyoto and an arms factory in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the construction of&quot;→&quot;to build a&quot;&quot;powder&quot;→&quot;gunpowder&quot;&quot;weaponry plant&quot;→&quot;an arms factory&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also decided to build a gunpowder manufacturing plant in Uji, Kyoto and an arms factory in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>このように大村が建軍の中核を東京から関西へと移転させたことについては、大阪がほぼ日本の中心に位置しており、国内の事変に対応しやすいという地理上の理由のほかに、自身の軍制改革に対する大久保派の妨害から脱するという政治的思惑によるものも大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason he moved the base of creation of Japanese army from Tokyo to Kansai was not only geographical reason that Osaka was located in center of Japan and easy to deal with domestic issues but also political reason that he wanted to escape from Okubo group&apos;s interference which were opposed to Omura&apos;s military reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His reason for moving the nucleus of the creation of the Japanese army from Tokyo to Kansai was not only that Osaka&apos;s central location made it easier to deal with domestic issues, but also for the political reason that he wanted to escape from the interference of Okubo, who was opposed to Omura&apos;s military reforms.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The reason he moved&quot;→&quot;His reasons for moving&quot;&quot;base&quot;→&quot;nucleus&quot;Deleted &quot;geographical reason&quot;&quot;Osaka was located in center of Japan and easy&quot;→&quot;Osaka&apos;s central location made it easier&quot;Moved &quot;interference&quot;&quot;which were&quot;→&quot;, who was&quot;Made &quot;reform&quot; plural&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His reason for moving the nucleus of the creation of the Japanese army from Tokyo to Kansai was not only that Osaka&apos;s central location made it easier to deal with domestic issues, but also for the political reason that he wanted to escape from the interference of Okubo, who was opposed to Omura&apos;s military reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>そのほか、大村が東北平定後の西南雄藩の動向を警戒し、その備えとして大阪を重視したとの証言もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is said that after quelling the Tohoku War he was beware of Southwest strong domains and moved the military basis to Osaka for corresponding to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is said that after quelling the Tohoku War, he was wary of the powerful southwestern domains and stressed Osaka&apos;s importance in guarding against them.</e>
<cmt>&quot;beware&quot;→&quot;wary&quot;&quot;Southwest strong domains&quot;→&quot;the powerful southwestern domains&quot;&quot;moved the military basis to Osaka for corresponding to them&quot;→&quot;stressed Osaka&apos;s importance in guarding against them&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is said that after quelling the Tohoku War, he was wary of the powerful southwestern domains and stressed Osaka&apos;s importance in guarding against them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="82">
<j>このように着々と既成事実を構築していた明治2年9月4日、大村は京都三条木屋町上ルの旅館で刺客に襲われ重傷を負った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In times of establishment of army, Omura was attacked by assassin at an inn located Sanjo Kiyamachi agaru in Kyoto on September 4, 1869 and badly injured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While working to establish the army, Omura was attacked by an assassin at an inn in Kyoto on September 4, 1869 and badly injured.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In times of establishment of army&quot;→&quot;While working to establish the army&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;Deleted &quot;located Sanjo Kiyamachi agaru&quot; - not sure the address is necessary for most English people</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While working to establish the army, Omura was attacked by an assassin at an inn in Kyoto on October 8, 1869 and badly injured.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>兇徒が所持していた「斬奸状」は、大村襲撃の理由が彼の急進開化主義に対する強い反感にあったことを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the assassin&apos;s &quot;Zankan-jo&quot; (written reasons), he had hardened antipathy toward Omura&apos;s radical reformation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the assassins&apos; &quot;Zankan-jo,&quot; or statement of reasons for carrying out an assassination, they they were strongly opposed to Omura&apos;s radical reforms.</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;assassin&quot; plural&quot;(written reasons)&quot;→&quot;or statement of reasons for carrying out an assassination&quot;&quot;he had hardened antipathy→&quot;they were strongly opposed to &quot;&quot;reformation&quot;→&quot;reforms&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the assassins&apos; &apos;Zankan-jo,&apos; or statement of reasons for carrying out an assassination, they were strongly opposed to Omura&apos;s radical reforms.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にthey削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>辛くも一命をとりとめた大村は山口藩邸に移送され、数日間の治療を受けた後、大坂の病院に入院し蘭医ボードウィンの手術を受けるが、11月5日容態が悪化し死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura escaped death and was moved to the official residence of Yamaguchi Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura escaped death and was moved to the official residence in Yamaguchi Domain and</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;in&quot;Deleted full stopAdded &quot;and&quot;Remade one sentence with cell F121</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura escaped death and was moved to the official residence in Yamaguchi Domain and after receiving treatment for a few days, he entered a hospital in Osaka where he was operated on by the Dutch physician Bauduin but his condition deteriorated and he died on December 7.</e>
<cmt>1つの文にまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>享年46。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 46 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 46 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 46 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>墓所は山口市鋳銭司村にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His tomb is in Suzenji-mura Village, Yamaguchi City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His tomb is in Suzenji-mura Village, Yamaguchi City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His tomb is in Suzenji-mura Village, Yamaguchi City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>明治21年（1888年）孫（養子の嫡男）の大村寛人は益次郎の功により子爵を授爵、華族に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandson Hiroto OMURA (son of Masujiro&apos;s adopted son) was awarded a title of Viscount for Masujiro&apos;s achievement and joined the ranks of nobility in 1888.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandson Hiroto OMURA (the son of Masujiro&apos;s adopted son) was awarded a title of Viscount for Masujiro&apos;s achievement and joined the ranks of nobility in 1888.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandson Hiroto OMURA (the son of Masujiro&apos;s adopted son) was awarded a title of Viscount for Masujiro&apos;s achievement and joined the ranks of nobility in 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>大村の軍制構想は山田顕義、船越衛、曽我祐準、原田一道等大村派によってまとめられ、同年11月18日には兵部少輔久我通久と山田の連署で『兵部省軍務ノ大綱』として太政官に提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura&apos;s military concept was organized by Omura group including Akiyoshi YAMADA, Mamoru FUNAKOSHI, Sukenori SOGA and Ichido HARADA, and that was submitted to the Council of State as &quot;Outline of the Responsibilities of the Ministry of the Military&quot; cosigned by hyobu shoyu Michitsune KOGA and Yamada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura&apos;s ideas for the military were completed by the Omura faction including Akiyoshi YAMADA, Mamoru FUNAKOSHI, Sukenori SOGA and Ichido HARADA, who submitted the &quot;Outline of the Responsibilities of the Ministry of the Military&quot;, cosigned by Hyobu Shoyu Michitsune KOGA and Yamada, to the Council of State on November 18.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Omura&apos;s military concept was organized by Omura group&quot;→&quot;Omura&apos;s ideas for the military were completed by the Omura faction&quot;Changed word orderAdded &quot;November 18 of the same year&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura&apos;s ideas for the military were completed by the Omura faction including Akiyoshi YAMADA, Mamoru FUNAKOSHI, Sukenori SOGA and Ichido HARADA, who submitted the &quot;Outline of the Responsibilities of the Ministry of the Military,&quot; cosigned by Hyobu Shoyu Michitsune KOGA and Yamada, to the Council of State on November 18.</e>
<cmt>&quot;移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>大村の「農兵論」は彼の後継者である大村派へ引き継がれ、明治4年に辛未徴兵として施行されるも同年内には中止となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura&apos;s &quot;universal conscription theory&quot; was succeeded to Omura group and the Shinbi Draft was implemented in 1871, however, it was cancelled in a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura&apos;s &quot;universal conscription theory&quot; was taken over by his successors in the Omura faction and conscription was begun in 1871, though it was cancelled later the same year.</e>
<cmt>&quot;succeeded to Omura group&quot;→&quot;taken over by his successors in the Omura faction&quot;&quot;the Shinbi Draft was implemented&quot;→&quot;conscription was begun&quot;&quot;however,&quot;→&quot;though&quot;&quot;in a year&quot;→&quot;later the same year&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura&apos;s &apos;universal conscription theory&apos; was taken over by his successors in the Omura faction and conscription was begun in 1871, although it was cancelled later the same year.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にthough→althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>その後、陸軍省内の主導権が山田等大村派から山県有朋らに引き継がれた後、明治6年（1873年）に徴兵令として続くこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the initiative in the military minister was moved to Aritomo YAMAGATA&apos;s group, the Shinbi Draft was continued in 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After leadership of the Military Ministry passed from Yamada&apos;s group to Aritomo YAMAGATA&apos;s group, conscription was reintroduced in 1873.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the initiative in&quot;→&quot;leadership of&quot;&quot;military minister&quot;→&quot;Military Ministry&quot;&quot;was moved to&quot;→&quot;passed from Yamada&apos;s group to&quot;&quot;the Shinbi Draft was continued&quot;→&quot;conscription was reintroduced&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After leadership of the Military Ministry passed from Yamada&apos;s group to Aritomo YAMAGATA&apos;s group, conscription was reintroduced in 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>維新戦争後に西からの反乱（西南戦争）を予言していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to predict the rebellion from west (Seinan War) after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to have predicted the western rebellion (Seinan War) after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>&quot;predict&quot;→&quot;have predicted&quot;&quot;from west&quot;→&quot;western&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to have predicted the western rebellion (Seinan War) after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>西郷隆盛を全く評価していなかった1人であり（大隈重信も同様）、西郷を建武の新政で反旗を翻した足利尊氏に見立てていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the persons (including Shigenobu OKUMA) who didn&apos;t appreciate Takamori SAIGO at all and likened Saigo to Takauji ASHIKAGA who rose in revolt at Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the people (including Shigenobu OKUMA) who didn&apos;t appreciate Takamori SAIGO at all and likened him to Takauji ASHIKAGA, who rose up in revolt during the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>&quot;persons&quot;→&quot;people&quot;&quot;Saigo&quot;→&quot;him&quot;&quot;rose in revolt at&quot;→&quot;rose up in revolt during the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the people (including Shigenobu OKUMA) who didn&apos;t appreciate Takamori SAIGO at all and likened him to Takauji ASHIKAGA, who rose up in revolt during the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>まだ若かった西園寺公望は大村に師事しており、京都にいた西園寺が大村を訪問しようとしたとき、旧友に会ったために訪問できなくなったところ、そのとき大村は刺客に襲われ、西園寺は巻き込まれずに済んだという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kinmochi SAIONJI was young, he studied under Omura and was going to visit Omura in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The young Kinmochi SAIONJI, who later became Prime Minister, studied under Omura and decided to call on him in Kyoto but,</e>
<cmt>Added explanation of who Saionji wasRewrote sentence to make it one with cell F136</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The young Kinmochi SAIONJI, who later became Prime Minister, studied under Omura and decided to call on him in Kyoto but, he met an old friend and didn&apos;t visit Omura, and therefore escaped being caught up in the assassination attempt on Omura.</e>
<cmt>１つの文にまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="94">
<j>日本初の軍歌・行進曲とされる、品川弥二郎作詞の「トコトンヤレ節」（宮さん宮さん）の作曲者とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was a composer of the first Japanese military march &quot;Tokotonyare-bushi&quot; (Miyasan Miyasan) lyrics by Yajiro SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was the composer of the first Japanese military march &quot;Tokotonyare-bushi&quot; (Miyasan Miyasan), lyrics by Yajiro SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was the composer of the first Japanese military march &apos;Tokotonyare-bushi&apos; (Miyasan Miyasan), lyrics by Yajiro SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>もっとも、当時の日本人の音楽感性の面から、成立年代をもっと後年とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But considering about Japanese musical sensibility of that time, there is another theory that the march was composed much later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But considering Japanese musical sensibility of that time, there is another theory that the march was composed much later.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;about&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But considering Japanese musical sensibility of that time, there is another theory that the march was composed much later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>大村益次郎に関する碑や像など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statues and monuments related to Masujiro OMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statues and monuments related to Masujiro OMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues and monuments related to Masujiro OMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>靖国神社に大村益次郎の銅像がある（日本初の西洋式銅像）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze statue of Masujiro OMURA was placed in Yasukuni-jinja Shrine (the first Western style sculpture in Japan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bronze statue of Masujiro OMURA, the first Western-style sculpture in Japan, was placed in Yasukuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot;→&quot;A&quot;Moved &quot;(the first Western style sculpture in Japan)&quot;Added hyphenChanged brackets to commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bronze statue of Masujiro OMURA, the first Western-style sculpture in Japan, was placed in Yasukuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="97">
<j>大阪市西区 (大阪市)江戸堀の江戸堀フコク生命ビル前に「大村益次郎先生寓地址」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Omura Masujiro sensei guchi ato&quot; (monument of Omura&apos;s provisional residence) is in front of Edobori Fukoku Seimei Building at Edobori, Nishi-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Omura Masujiro sensei guchi ato&quot; (monument of Omura&apos;s provisional residence) is in front of Edobori Fukoku Seimei Building at Edobori, Nishi-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Omura Masujiro sensei guchi ato&apos; (monument of Omura&apos;s provisional residence) is in front of Edobori Fukoku Seimei Building at Edobori, Nishi-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="98">
<j>大阪市中央区 (大阪市)上町交差点に「兵部大輔大村益次郎卿殉難報國之碑」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hyobu taifu Omura Masujiro kyo junnan hokoku no hi&quot; (monument of his deathplace) is at the Uemachi Crossing in Chuo-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hyobu taifu Omura Masujiro kyo junnan hokoku no hi&quot; (monument of his deathplace) is at the Uemachi Crossing in Chuo-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Hyobu taifu Omura Masujiro kyo junnan hokoku no hi&apos; (monument of his deathplace) is at the Uemachi Crossing in Chuo-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="99">
<j>大阪市北区同心町の龍海寺に「大村兵部大輔埋腿骨之地」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Omura Hyobu taifu mai taikotsu no chi&quot; (burial monument of Omura&apos;s thigh) is in the Ryukai-ji Temple, Doshincho Kita-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Omura Hyobu taifu mai taikotsu no chi&quot; (burial monument of Omura&apos;s femur) is in the Ryukai-ji Temple, Doshincho Kita-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;thigh&quot;→&quot;femur&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Omura Hyobu taifu mai taikotsu no chi&apos; (burial monument of Omura&apos;s femur) is in the Ryukai-ji Temple, Doshin-cho Kita-ku, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>遺言により師の緒方洪庵の側に片方の足が埋葬されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His another thigh was buried next to the tomb of his teacher Koan OGATA according to his will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His other femur, in accordance with his will, was buried next to the tomb of his teacher, Koan OGATA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;another&quot;→&quot;other&quot;&quot;thigh&quot;→&quot;femur&quot;&quot;according to his will&quot;→&quot;in accordance with his will&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His other femur, in accordance with his will, was buried next to the tomb of his teacher, Koan OGATA.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="101">
<j>京都府中京区木屋町に大村益次郎遭難の碑がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Omura Masujiro sonan hi&quot; (monument of the place he was attacked) is in Kiyamachi, Nakagyo-ku, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Omura Masujiro sonan hi&quot; (monument of the place he was attacked) is in Kiyamachi, Nakagyo-ku, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura Masujiro sonan hi (monument of the place he was attacked) is in Kiyamachi, Nakagyo-ku, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="102">
<j>生誕地の鋳銭司村には西南戦争の翌年に顕彰碑が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year of the Seinan War, his award monument was placed in his birthplace Suzenji-mura Village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year after the Seinan War, a commemorative plaque was erected in birthplace, Suzenji-mura Village.</e>
<cmt>&quot;next year of&quot;→&quot;year after&quot;&quot;his award monument&quot;→&quot;a commemorative plaque&quot;&quot;placed&quot;→&quot;erected&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year after the Seinan War, a commemorative plaque was erected in birthplace, Suzenji-mura Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>大村益次郎の登場する作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works in which Masujiro OMURA appears</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works in which Masujiro OMURA appears</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works in which Masujiro OMURA appears</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>伝記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biographies</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biographies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="104">
<j>丹潔編『大村益次郎』（マツノ書店、1999年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Kiyoshi TAN, Matsuno Shoten, 1999</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Kiyoshi TAN, Matsuno Shoten, 1999</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Kiyoshi TAN, Matsuno Shoten, 1999</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="105">
<j>糸屋寿雄『大村益次郎』（中央公論社、1989年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Toshio ITOYA, Chuo Koronsha, 1989</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Toshio ITOYA, Chuo Koronsha, 1989</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Toshio ITOYA, Chuo Koronsha, 1989</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="106">
<j>史料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical records</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical records</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical records</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="107">
<j>村田峰次郎編『大村益次郎先生事蹟』（マツノ書店、2001年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Record of OMURA Masujiro-sensei&quot; by Minejiro MURATA, Matsuno Shoten, 2001</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Record of OMURA Masujiro-sensei&quot; by Minejiro MURATA, Matsuno Shoten, 2001</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Record of OMURA Masujiro-sensei&quot; by Minejiro MURATA, Matsuno Shoten, 2001</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="108">
<j>内田伸編『大村益次郎文書』（マツノ書店、1977年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Documents of OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Noboru UCHIDA, Matsuno Shoten, 1977</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Documents of OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Noboru UCHIDA, Matsuno Shoten, 1977</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Documents of OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Noboru UCHIDA, Matsuno Shoten, 1977</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="109">
<j>内田伸編『大村益次郎史料』（マツノ書店、2000年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Historical Records of OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Noboru UCHIDA, Matsuno Shoten, 2000</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Historical Records of OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Noboru UCHIDA, Matsuno Shoten, 2000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Historical Records of OMURA Masujiro&quot; by Noboru UCHIDA, Matsuno Shoten, 2000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="110">
<j>論文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Research paper</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research papers</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research papers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="111">
<j>竹本知行「大村益次郎の建軍構想-『一新之名義』と仏式兵制との関連を中心に-」（『軍事史学』第42巻第1号、2006年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&apos;s vision of the establishment of the military: With the focus on the relationship between &apos;Isshin-no-meigi&apos; and the French style military system&quot; by Tomoyuki TAKEMOTO, &quot;History of Military&quot; volume 42 No.1, 2006</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;OMURA Masujiro&apos;s vision of the establishment of the military: With the focus on the relationship between &apos;Isshin-no-meigi&apos; and the French-style military system&quot; by Tomoyuki TAKEMOTO, &quot;History of Military&quot; volume 42 No.1, 2006</e>
<cmt>Added hyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;OMURA Masujiro&apos;s vision of the establishment of the military: With the focus on the relationship between &quot;Isshin-no-meigi&quot; and the French-style military system&apos; by Tomoyuki TAKEMOTO, &quot;History of Military&quot; volume 42 No.1, 2006</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に原文の『』に合わせ&apos;を&quot;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="112">
<j>小説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Novel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Novels</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="113">
<j>『花神 (小説)』（司馬遼太郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kashin (Flower god)&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kashin (Flower god)&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kashin&quot; (Flower god) by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt>書名の訳&quot;の外へ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="114">
<j>『鬼謀の人』（『人斬り以蔵』に収録、司馬遼太郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kibo no hito&quot; [included on &quot;Hitokiri Izo (Izo the killer)] by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kibo no hito&quot; [included on &quot;Hitokiri Izo (Izo the killer)] by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kibo no hito&quot; (included on &quot;Hitokiri Izo&quot; (Izo the killer)) by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt>[]→()&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="115">
<j>テレビドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TV drama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TV dramas</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TV dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="116">
<j>『花神 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（NHK大河ドラマ）…中村梅之助</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kashin (Flower god)&quot;, NHK period drama, played by Umenosuke NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kashin (Flower god)&quot;, NHK period drama, played by Umenosuke NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kashin&quot; (Flower god), NHK period drama, played by Umenosuke NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>書名の訳&quot;の外へ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="117">
<j>『奇兵隊 (テレビドラマ)』（日本テレビ放送網年末時代劇スペシャル）…片岡鶴太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kiheitai,&quot; year-end special period drama, Nippon Television Network, played by Tsurutaro KATAOKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kiheitai&quot;, year-end special period drama, Nippon Television Network, played by Tsurutaro KATAOKA</e>
<cmt>Moved comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kiheitai,&quot; year-end special period drama, Nippon Television Network, played by Tsurutaro KATAOKA</e>
<cmt>&quot;移動スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="118">
<j>『翔ぶが如く (NHK大河ドラマ)』（NHK大河ドラマ）…平田満</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tobuga gotoku&quot; NHK period drama, played by Mitsuru HIRATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tobuga gotoku&quot;, NHK period drama, played by Mitsuru HIRATA</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tobuga gotoku,&quot; NHK period drama, played by Mitsuru HIRATA</e>
<cmt>&quot;移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="119">
<j>映画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movies</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="120">
<j>『長州ファイブ』…原田大二郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Choshu Five&quot; played by Daijiro HARADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Choshu Five&quot;, played by Daijiro HARADA</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Choshu Five,&quot; played by Daijiro HARADA</e>
<cmt>&quot;移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="121">
<j>漫画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="122">
<j>『風雲児たち』（みなもと太郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fuunji tachi&quot; by Taro MINAMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fuunji tachi&quot; by Taro MINAMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fuunji tachi&quot; by Taro MINAMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="123">
<j>『陽だまりの樹』（手塚治虫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hidamari no ki&quot; by Osamu TEZUKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hidamari no ki&quot; by Osamu TEZUKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hidamari no ki&quot; by Osamu TEZUKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="124">
<j>『お〜い!竜馬』（武田鉄矢原作、小山ゆう作画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Oi! Ryoma&quot; written by Tetsuya TAKEDA, illustrated by Yu KOYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Oi! Ryoma&quot; written by Tetsuya TAKEDA, illustrated by Yu KOYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Oi! Ryoma&quot; written by Tetsuya TAKEDA, illustrated by Yu KOYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="125">
<j>舞台</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="126">
<j>『彦馬がゆく』…（三谷幸喜）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;HIKOMA, THE HERO&quot; [http://www.parco-play.com/web/play/hikoma/], by Koki MITANI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;HIKOMA, THE HERO&quot; [http://www.parco-play.com/web/play/hikoma/], by Koki MITANI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;HIKOMA, THE HERO,&quot; by Koki MITANI</e>
<cmt>[http://www.parco-play.com/web/play/hikoma/]削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 みょうじ(id:124419), Tommy6-bot(id:171289), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Nnh(id:474), 松浸史(id:78240), Reggaeman(id:6214), 陽一(id:92099), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Extrahitz(id:26245), Paseri0924(id:151116), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Mishika(id:276), Greenland4(id:114494), Kareha(id:36360), Johncapistrano(id:969), パの字(id:34188), Nisiguti(id:534), OSY(id:35563), Hage@hage(id:62085), 代言人(id:33675), An-chan(id:14590), Adonis(id:24011), こぶまき(id:38278), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), Nipisiquit(id:62077), Bankokuya(id:91191), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Kentin(id:6768), Pinball1973(id:33613), クロウ(id:21337), PANYNJ(id:38638), Rambler(id:59491), 松茸(id:27535), Sat.K(id:3751), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Cave cattum(id:41235), Inukawa(id:842), Aboshi(id:9318), T9(id:44052), Rusk(id:9895), 動く(id:110360), 貘(id:106080), 上田隼人(id:23104), Wakkubox(id:30396), Alexscho(id:67230), Chac(id:21208), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>