<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>島津義久</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>島津 義久（しまづ よしひさ）は、戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa SHIMAZU was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama Period through the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa SHIMAZU was a military commander who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama Period through the Sengoku (Warring States) Period.</e>
<cmt>after checking a number of this topics, it has become apparent that there are terms which have been rendered in Roma-ji that do not represent a phenomenon having a degree of cultural specificicity that would merit the term being romanized. In this entry, the term &quot;busho&quot;, for example. There is also inconsistent capitalization of &quot;Period of Warring States&quot;, and it is also rendered simply as warring states period. Furthermore, if you want to call it the Sengoku Period, then the parenthetical remark should be inserted after the term Sengoku, I would assume. In any case, a decision on this and paralell cases would be helpful.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa SHIMAZU was a military commander who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama period through the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→統一リストの表記に修正、仕様書に基づきPeriodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>薩摩国の守護大名・戦国大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a provincial constable feudal lord of then, became a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period</e>
<cmt>守護大名と戦国大名は同時になれるものではないので、「薩摩国の守護大名から戦国大名になった」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the constabular feudal lord of Satsuma Province, and became a daimyo (feudal lord) in the Sengoku Period</e>
<cmt>perhaps some explanation of the meaning of &quot;constabular fuedal lord&quot; would be desirable.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) of Satsuma Province, and became a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>「守護大名」の表記を修正、「戦国大名」→統一リストの表記に修正、文末のピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>島津氏の第16代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 16th family head of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 16th family head of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 16th head of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>familyを削除し、16th head of the Shimazu clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>3人の弟を使いこなし、九州を制覇した名将である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a great commander who conquered Kyushu by managing his three brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is a renowned as a great general, who managed to subjugate Kyushu through the deft maneuvering of his three brothers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is a renowned as a great general, who managed to subjugate Kyushu through the deft maneuvering of his three brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>家系は源頼朝の長庶子ともいわれる島津忠久を祖とする島津氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a descendant of the Shimazu clan whose ancestor was Tadahisa SHIMAZU considered to be MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s eldest child born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt>原文が不自然なので、「源頼朝の長庶子ともいわれる島津忠久を祖とする島津氏の子孫」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family was descended from the Shimazu clan, whose progenitor, Tadahisa SHIMAZU, is considered to have been the eldest child of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family was descended from the Shimazu clan, whose progenitor, Tadahisa SHIMAZU, is considered to have been the eldest child of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, born out of wedlock..</e>
<cmt>文末のピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>島津氏の第16代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 16th family head of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 16th family head of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 16th head of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>familyを削除し、16th head of the Shimazu clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>室町幕府の薩摩国守護職・大隅国守護職・日向国守護職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed the Shugoshoku Title of Satsuma Province, Osumi Province and Hyuga Province in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as the constabular administrator of provinces of Satsuma, Osumi and Hyuga under the Muromachi bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the Shugoshiki (post of provincial constable) of provinces of Satsuma, Osumi and Hyuga under the Muromachi (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>「守護職」の表記を修正、「室町幕府」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>第15代当主・島津貴久の嫡男として伊作城に生まれ、幼名は虎寿丸と名づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the progeny of Takahisa SHIMAZU, the 15th family head, in Izaku Castle and his childhood name was Torajumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Izaku Castle, as the first son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, the 15th family head of the Shimazu clan, and his childhood name was Torajumaru.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Izaku-jo Castle, as the first son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, the 15th head of the Shimazu clan, and his childhood name was Torajumaru.</e>
<cmt>Izaku-jo Castleとし、family削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>通称は又三郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly called Matasaburo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He usually went by the name Matasaburo.</e>
<cmt>gammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He usually went by the name Matasaburo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>元服して忠良。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Genpuku ceremony (coming-of-age ceremony), he changed his name to Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his Genpuku (coming-of-age) ceremony, his name was changed to Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his Genpuku (coming-of-age) ceremony, his name was changed to Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に第13代将軍・足利義輝からの偏諱を受け、義辰、後に義久と改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he received one character from the name of Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the 13th Shogun, and changed his name to Yoshitatsu, then Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he received one character from the name of Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the 13th Shogun, changing his name to Yoshitatsu, and then to Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he received one character from the name of Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the 13th Shogun, changing his name to Yoshitatsu, and then to Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>幼少時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>天文2年（1533年）2月9日、第15代当主・島津貴久の長男として伊作城で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the first son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, the 15th family head, in Izaku Castle on February 9, 1533.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on February 9, 1533, as the first son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, who was the 15th family head of the Shimazu clan, in Izaku Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on March 14, 1533, as the first son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, who was the 15th head of the Shimazu clan, in Izaku-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Izaku-jo Castleとし、family削除February 9→March 14に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>幼少の頃は大人しい性格だったこと、そして三人の弟がいずれも勇猛で優秀だったことから「愚兄賢弟の生きた見本」という陰口を叩かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was shy as a child and all of his three younger brothers were brave and brilliant thus, he was called &quot;Living showcase of a foolish older brother and a smart younger&quot; in his back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was shy and reserved as a child, whereas his three younger brothers were all outgoing and bright; it is said that some people called them, &quot;a living showcase of a foolish older brother and a smart younger brothers&quot; behind their backs.</e>
<cmt>somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was shy and reserved as a child, whereas his three younger brothers were all outgoing and bright; it is said that some people called them, &apos;a living showcase of a foolish older brother and a smart younger brothers&apos; behind their backs.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし祖父の島津忠良は「義久は三州の総大将たるの材徳自ら備わり、義弘は雄武英略を以て傑出し、歳久は始終の利害を察するの智計並びなく、家久は軍法戦術に妙を得たり」と兄弟の個性を見抜いた評価を下しており、義久に期待していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his grandfather, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU detected the brothers&apos; characters and said, &quot;Yoshihisa is a person of virtue by nature a supreme commander in three countries. Yoshihiro has outstanding power and wisdom. Toshihisa is the cleverest at inferring the whole interest in holoscopic view and Iehisa is skilled at art of warfare.&quot;, which shows that he expected from Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his grandfather, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, detected the brothers&apos; characters and said, &quot;Yoshihisa is a person of virtue by nature, having the character to rule over three countries; Yoshihiro has martial vigor and outstanding powers of reason; Toshihisa is unrivalled in his ability to grasp the big picture of a situation, discerning the inherent advantages and disadvantages; and Iehisa is skilled at art of warfare&quot;, showing the expectations he had for Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt>can&apos;t find 雄武 in a dictionary, and the definition of 英略 is vague, 「すぐれたはかりごと」…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his grandfather, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, detected the brothers&apos; characters and said, &apos;Yoshihisa is a person of virtue by nature, having the character to rule over three countries; Yoshihiro has martial vigor and outstanding powers of reason; Toshihisa is unrivalled in his ability to grasp the big picture of a situation, discerning the inherent advantages and disadvantages; and Iehisa is skilled at art of warfare,&apos; showing the expectations he had for Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>義久は初名を祖父と同じ忠良と名乗り、祖父の娘を正室に迎えている事からも分かるように、祖父から大きな影響を受けたものと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the fact that Yoshihisa identified himself as Tadayoshi at first and took his grandfather&apos;s daughter for his legal wife, it can be presumed that he was greatly influenced by his grandfather.</e>
<cmt>「初名」という名詞を使うと、文章が不自然になるので、「最初は～と名乗っていた」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the fact that Yoshihisa adopted the name Tadayoshi at first, thereby identifying himself with his grandfather, and later took his grandfather&apos;s daughter for his legal wife, it can be presumed that he was greatly influenced by his grandfather.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the fact that Yoshihisa adopted the name Tadayoshi at first, thereby identifying himself with his grandfather, and later took his grandfather&apos;s daughter for his legal wife, it can be presumed that he was greatly influenced by his grandfather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>三州統一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Domination of three countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dominion over three states</e>
<cmt>it is not clear how 州 should be translated here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dominion over Three States</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>父・貴久に従い薩摩、大隅の国人衆と戦い、勝利して彼らを平定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied his father, Takahisa to fight against Kokujin-shu in Satsuma and Osumi and took control of them by winning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accompanied his father, Takahisa, to fight against the Kokujin-shu of Satsuma and Osumi; they were victorious and successfully pacified those areas.</e>
<cmt>Satsuma and Osumi are provinces</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accompanied his father, Takahisa, to fight against the Kokujin-shu (local lords) of Satsuma and Osumi Provinces; they were victorious and successfully pacified those areas.</e>
<cmt>Kokujin-shuの補足追加、Satsuma and Osumi Provincesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>永禄9年（1566年）、父の隠居により家督を相続し、島津家第16代当主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1566, he inherited the family estate due to his father&apos;s retirement and became the 16th family head of the Shimazu Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1566, his father went into retirement, and Yoshihisa succeeded him as the 16th family head of the Shimazu Family.</e>
<cmt>family is capitalized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1566, his father went into retirement, and Yoshihisa succeeded him as the 16th head of the Shimazu family.</e>
<cmt>16th family head of the Shimazu Family→16th head of the Shimazu familyに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この頃、日向の伊東義祐との抗争が激化し、元亀3年（1572年）5月、伊東義祐は弟・伊東祐安に3000余人の軍勢で島津方に侵攻するよう命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, the struggle against Yoshisuke ITO in Hyuga intensified and in May 1572, Yoshisuke ITO ordered Sukeyasu ITO to invade Shimazu&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, the struggle against Yoshisuke ITO in Hyuga intensified, and in May 1572, Yoshisuke ITO ordered Sukeyasu ITO to invade the Shimazu camp.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, the struggle against Yoshisuke ITO in Hyuga intensified, and in June 1572, Yoshisuke ITO ordered Sukeyasu ITO to invade the Shimazu camp.</e>
<cmt>May →Juneに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義久の弟・島津義弘はわずか300余人を率いて出陣し、木崎原に兵を伏せて、誘い込んで強襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa&apos;s younger brother, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU went off to war with only 300-odd soldiers and laid an ambush in Kizakibaru to lure and storm the enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa&apos;s younger brother, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU went off to war at the head of a force only slightly stronger than 300 men, leading them to Kizakibaru to wait in ambush for the enemy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa&apos;s younger brother, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU went off to war at the head of a force only slightly stronger than 300 men, leading them to Kizakibaru to wait in ambush for the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>島津軍は敵の総大将・祐安を初め名のある武者だけで160余人、500の首級を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army severed 500 troops&apos; heads including 160-odd famous warriors such as the supreme commander, Sukeyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimazu&apos;s army took 500 heads in the ensuing battle, including those of some 160 famous warriors, such as the commanding general, Sukeyasu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, don&apos;t like &quot;supreme commander&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army took 500 heads in the ensuing battle, including those of some 160 famous warriors, such as the commanding general, Sukeyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この木崎原の戦いは九州の桶狭間といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Kizakibaru is called the Battle of Okehazama in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Kizakibaru is called the Kyushu&apos;s Battle of Okehazama.</e>
<cmt>unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Battle of Kizakibaru is called the Kyushu&apos;s &apos;Battle of Okehazama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>The→Thisとし、Battle of Okehazamaにクォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>伊東氏は「惣四十八城」を誇った伊東方の支城主が次々と離反し、衰退の一途を辿る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the Ito clan, Shijoshu(bureau castellan) of the So-Sijuhachi-jo (forty-eight castles) who were on the Ito side broke away one after another and followed a course of decline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the Ito clan, the Shijoshu (lord of a branch castle) of the So-Sijuhachi-jo (forty-eight castles), who had been on the Ito side, broke away one after another, leading the clan into decline.</e>
<cmt>grammar. There would seem to be a need for an introduction of the &quot;Shijoshi&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the Ito clan, the Shijoshu (lord of a branch castle) of the &apos;So-Sijuhachi-jo&apos; (forty-eight castles), who had been on the Ito side, broke away one after another, leading the clan into decline.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>伊東義祐は豊後国の大友義鎮を頼って亡命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshisuke ITO found an asylum in Bungo Province where Yoshishige OTOMO ruled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshisuke ITO found an asylum in Bungo Province, which was under the rule of Yoshishige OTOMO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshisuke ITO found an asylum in Bungo Province, which was under the rule of Yoshishige OTOMO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これにより三州統一という島津氏の悲願が達成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This event enabled the Shimazu clan to realize the domination of three countries, which was their ardent wish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This event enabled the Shimazu clan to achieve their long held desire to have dominion over three states.</e>
<cmt>again, 州</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This event enabled the Shimazu clan to achieve their long held desire to have dominion over three states.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>耳川の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Mimi-kawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Mimi-kawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Mimi-kawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>伊東義祐が亡命したことにより大友宗麟が天正6年（1578年）10月、大軍を率いて、日向に侵攻してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Yoshisuke ITO went into exile, Sorin OTOMO invaded Hyuga with many troops in October 1578.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Yoshisuke ITO had been sent into exile, Sorin OTOMO invaded Hyuga with a large force in October 1578.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Yoshisuke ITO had been sent into exile, Sorin OTOMO invaded Hyuga with a large force in November 1578.</e>
<cmt>October →Novemberに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>宗麟は務志賀（延岡市無鹿）に止まり、田原親賢が総大将となり、田北鎮周・佐伯惟教ら43000を率いて、戦いの指揮を取ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sorin abided in Mushika (present-day Mushika, Nobeoka City) and Chikakata TAWARA became a supreme commander leading 43,000 troops such as Shigekane TAKITA and Korenori SAIKI, and assumed the leadership of the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sorin stayed in Mushika (present-day Mushika, Nobeoka City), while Chikakata TAWARA became commanding general, leading 43,000 troops, including Shigekane TAKITA and Korenori SAIKI, and took charge of directing the battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sorin stayed in Mushika (present-day Mushika, Nobeoka City), while Chikakata TAWARA became commanding general, leading 43,000 troops, including Shigekane TAKITA and Korenori SAIKI, and took charge of directing the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>島津軍は山田有信を高城に、後方の佐土原に島津家久を置いていたが、大友軍が日向に侵攻すると家久らも高城に入城し、城兵は3000余人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army deployed Arinobu YAMADA in Takajo and Iehisa SHIMAZU in Sadowara at the back, but when Otomo&apos;s army invaded Hyuga, Iehisa and the troops also entered Takajo Castle, then the total number of the castle guards was over 3,000.</e>
<cmt>「高城に入城し」は、「高城城に入城し」と読み替えて訳しました。城兵→castle guard[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shimazu army deployed Arinobu YAMADA toTakajo, and Iehisa SHIMAZU to Sadowara, bringing up the rear; however, when Otomo&apos;s army invaded Hyuga, the Iehisa contingent also entered Takajo Castle, bringing the total number of the castle guards to more than 3,000.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shimazu army deployed Arinobu YAMADA toTakajo, and Iehisa SHIMAZU to Sadowara, bringing up the rear; however, when Otomo&apos;s army invaded Hyuga, the Iehisa contingent also entered Takajo-jo Castle, bringing the total number of the castle guards to more than 3,000.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオド削除、Takajo-jo Castleとしました。(参照: http://www.hb.pei.jp/shiro/hyuuga/takajyo-jyo/)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>大友軍は高城を囲み、両軍による一進一退の攻防が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomo&apos;s army surrounded Takajo Castle and the seesaw battle between both armies continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otomo&apos;s army surrounded Takajo Castle, and the battle see-sawed back and forth between the two sides.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otomo&apos;s army surrounded Takajo-jo Castle, and the battle see-sawed back and forth between the two sides.</e>
<cmt>Takajo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>11月、義久は2万余人の軍勢を率いて出陣し、佐土原に着陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, Yoshihisa went off to war leading 20,000 troops and arrived the camp in Sadowara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, Yoshihisa set off to join the war at the head of a force of 20,000 troops, and set up camp in Sadowara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Yoshihisa set off to join the war at the head of a force of 20,000 troops, and set up camp in Sadowara.</e>
<cmt>November→Decemberに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>島津軍は大友軍に奇襲をかけて成功し、小丸川を挟んで大友軍の対岸の根城坂に着陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army successfully bore down on Otomo&apos;s army and arrived the camp in Nejiro-zaka across the Omaru-gawa River from the camp of Otomo&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimazu&apos;s army launched a successful raid against the Otomo army, and set up camp on the Nejirozaka (a hillside) across the Omaru-gawa River from the camp of the Otomo army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army launched a successful raid against the Otomo army, and set up camp on the Nejirozaka (a hillside) across the Omaru-gawa River from the camp of the Otomo army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>大友軍は宗麟がいないこともあり、団結力に欠けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomo&apos;s army lacked a bond of solidarity since Sorin wasn&apos;t there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due in part to the absence of Sorin, the Otomo army was somewhat lacking in esprit de corps.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due in part to the absence of Sorin, the Otomo army was somewhat lacking in esprit de corps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大友軍の田北鎮周が無断で島津軍を攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigekane TAKITA of Otomo&apos;s army attacked Shimazu&apos;s army without leave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigekane TAKITA of the Otomo army launched an attack against the Shimazu army, without consulting his commander.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigekane TAKITA of the Otomo army launched an attack against the Shimazu army, without consulting his commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これに佐伯宗天が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korenori SAIKI followed him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korenori SAIKI then followed him.</e>
<cmt>presumably another Otomo busho</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soten (Korenori) SAIKI then followed him.</e>
<cmt>Korenori SAIKIとありますが、原文は「佐伯宗天」であるため、前出の「佐伯惟教」＝「佐伯宗天」ということがわかるよう、Soten (Korenori) SAIKIとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>無秩序に攻めてくる大友軍を相手に義久は「釣り野伏せ」という戦法を使い、川を越えて追撃してきた大友軍に伏兵を次々と出し、大友軍を壊滅させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa used a tactic called &quot;Tsuri-Nobuse&quot; against Otomo&apos;s army which attacked disorderly and ambushed Otomo&apos;s army which chased across the river, then wiped out Otomo&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa employing a tactic called &quot;Tsuri-Nobuse&quot; against the marauding Otomo forces, who were attacking in disarray from across the river, sent wave after wave of troops to lie in ambush for the Otomo marauders,eventually wiping them out.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa employing a tactic called &apos;Tsuri-Nobuse&apos; (a tactic using three forces in which one lets the enemy advance (tsuri) while the rest two hide lying low on both sides (nobuse), which will eventually come out and surround the enemy) against the marauding Otomo forces, who were attacking in disarray from across the river, sent wave after wave of troops to lie in ambush for the Otomo marauders, eventually wiping them out.</e>
<cmt>Tsuri-Nobuseの補足を追加、シングルクォーテーションに変更、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>島津方は田北鎮周・佐伯宗天など主だった武将を初め2000から3000の首級を挙げた（耳川の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army severed from 2,000 to 3,000 troops&apos; heads including major busho such as Shigekane TAKITA and Soten SAIKI (it is called the Battle of Mimi-kawa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimazu&apos;s army took 2,000 to 3,000 heads in the fighting, (the Battle of Mimi-kawa), including those of senior commanders, such as Shigekane TAKITA and Soten SAIKI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army took 2,000 to 3,000 heads in the fighting, (the Battle of Mimi-kawa), including those of senior commanders, such as Shigekane TAKITA and Soten SAIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>沖田畷の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Okitanawate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Okitanawate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Okitanawate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>耳川の戦いで大友氏が衰退すると、肥前国の龍造寺隆信が台頭してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Otomo clan declined in the Battle of Mimi-kawa, then Takanobu RYUZOJI of Hizen Province became conspicuous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Otomo clan fell into decline after suffering defeat at the Battle of Mimi-kawa, and Takanobu RYUZOJI of Hizen Province subsequently rose to prominence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Otomo clan fell into decline after suffering defeat at the Battle of Mimi-kawa, and Takanobu RYUZOJI of Hizen Province subsequently rose to prominence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>龍造寺隆信の圧迫に耐えかねた有馬晴信が八代にいた義弘・家久に援軍を要請してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harunobu ARIMA could no longer put up with the oppression by Takanobu RYUZOJI and asked Yoshihiro and Ieshisa who were in Yatsushiro for reinforcements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he could no longer tolerate the oppressive measures being forced upon him by Takanobu RYUZOJI, Harunobu ARIMA asked Yoshihiro and Ieshisa, who were garrisoned in Yatsushiro, to send reinforcements.</e>
<cmt>slightly unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he could no longer tolerate the oppressive measures being forced upon him by Takanobu RYUZOJI, Harunobu ARIMA asked Yoshihiro and Ieshisa, who were garrisoned in Yatsushiro, to send reinforcements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>それに応えた島津軍は天正10年（1582年）、龍造寺方の千々石城を攻め落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army responded to the needs and captured Chijiwa Castle of RYUZOJI&apos;s army in 1582.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shimazu came to the aid of Harunobu, and their army captured Chijiwa Castle from RYUZOJI&apos;s army in 1582.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shimazu came to the aid of Harunobu, and their army captured Chijiwa-jo Castle from RYUZOJI&apos;s army in 1582.</e>
<cmt>Chijiwa-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>翌年、有馬氏の親戚である安徳城主・安徳純俊が龍造寺氏に背いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, Sumitoshi ANTOKU, the castellan of Antoku Castle and relative of the Arima clan, betrayed the Ryuzoji clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, Sumitoshi ANTOKU, lord of Antoku Castle and relative of the Arima clan, betrayed the Ryuzoji clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, Sumitoshi ANTOKU, lord of Antoku-jo Castle and relative of the Arima clan, betrayed the Ryuzoji clan.</e>
<cmt>Antoku-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>島津軍は八代に待機していた新納忠堯・川上忠堅ら1000余人が援軍として安徳城に入り、深江城を攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Shimazu&apos;s army, over 1,000 warriors including Tadataka NIRO and Tadakata KAWAKAMI who were standing by in Yatsushiro entered Antoku Castle as reinforcements and attacked Fukae Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A force of more than 1,000 men from the Shimazu army, including Tadataka NIRO and Tadakata KAWAKAMI, who had been standing by atYatsushiro, entered Antoku Castle as reinforcements, and proceeded to launch an attack on Fukae Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A force of more than 1,000 men from the Shimazu army, including Tadataka NIIRO and Tadakata KAWAKAMI, who had been standing by atYatsushiro, entered Antoku-jo Castle as reinforcements, and proceeded to launch an attack on Fukae-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Tadataka NIRO→Tadataka NIIROとし、Antoku-jo Castle、Fukae-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>天正12年（1584年）、義久は家久を総大将として島原に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1584, Yoshihisa sent Iehisa to Shimabara as supreme commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1584, Yoshihisa dispatched Iehisa to Shimabara as commanding general.</e>
<cmt>grmmar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1584, Yoshihisa dispatched Iehisa to Shimabara as commanding general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>家久は島原湾を渡海し、安徳城に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iehisa took a voyage across Shimabara Bay and entered Antoku Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iehisa travelled by ship across Shimabara Bay, and entered Antoku Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iehisa travelled by ship across Shimabara Bay, and entered Antoku-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Antoku-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>有馬勢と合わせて5000余りで、龍造寺軍2万5000（一説には6万）という圧倒的兵力に立ち向かうことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had to face Ryozoji&apos;s 25,000 troops (some people say it was 60,000) with 5,000 troops including Arima force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had to face Ryozoji&apos;s army of 25,000 troops (by some accounts, 60,000) with a force of 5,000 troops, including the Arima contingent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had to face Ryozoji&apos;s army of 25,000 troops (by some accounts, 60,000) with a force of 5,000 troops, including the Arima contingent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>家久は沖田畷と呼ばれる湿地帯にて、龍造寺隆信を初め、一門・重臣など3000余人を討ち取り、見事に勝利した（沖田畷の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iehisa&apos;s army killed over 3000 troops including Takanobu RYUZOJI, his family and main retainers in a wetland called Okitanawate and successfully rode to victory (it is called the Battle of Okitanawate).</e>
<cmt>家久が単独で3000人を討ち取ったわけではないと考え、家久軍として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iehisa&apos;s army killed more than 3000 enemy troops, including Takanobu RYUZOJI, his family and main retainers in fighting at a wetland called Okitanawate (the Battle of Okitanawate), winning a decisive victory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iehisa&apos;s army killed more than 3000 enemy troops, including Takanobu RYUZOJI, his family and main retainers in fighting at a wetland called Okitanawate, winning a decisive victory (the Battle of Okitanawate).</e>
<cmt>(the Battle of Okitanawate) の位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>ほどなくして龍造寺氏は島津氏の軍門に降ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shortly, the Ryozoji clan surrendered to the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shortly thereafter, the Ryozoji clan surrendered to the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly thereafter, the Ryozoji clan surrendered to the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>九州制覇の夢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dream for Attainment of Kyushu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dream for the Unification of Kyushu</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dream for the Unification of Kyushu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>天正12年（1584年）、龍造寺氏が島津氏の軍門に降り、肥後国の隈部親永・隈部親泰父子、筑前国の秋月種実、筑後国の筑紫広門らが、次々と島津氏に服属や和睦していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1584, the the Ryozoji clan surrendered to the Shimazu clan, then Chikanaga KUMABE and Chikanaga KUMABE (parent and child) in Higo Province, Tanesada AKIZUKI in Chikuzen Province and Hirokado TSUKUSHI in Chikugo Province submitted themselves to or made peace with the Shimazu clan in succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Ryozoji clan surrendered to the Shimazu clan, in 1584, the Chikanaga KUMABE and Chikanaga KUMABE (father and son with name written differently but having the same pronunciation) of Higo Province, Tanesada AKIZUKI in Chikuzen Province, and Hirokado TSUKUSHI in Chikugo Province submitted to or made peace with the Shimazu clan in succession.</e>
<cmt>grammar, include characters of the homonym namesHere the term Province is used in 1st translation…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Ryozoji clan surrendered to the Shimazu clan, in 1584, the Chikanaga KUMABE and Chikayasu KUMABE (father and son) of Higo Province, Tanesada AKIZUKI in Chikuzen Province, and Hirokado TSUKUSHI in Chikugo Province submitted to or made peace with the Shimazu clan in succession.</e>
<cmt>「隈部親泰」→Chikayasu KUMABE に訂正 (参照: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E9%9A%88%E9%83%A8%E8%A6%AA%E6%B3%B0)、および (father and son with name written differently but having the same pronunciation)→(father and son)のみに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>翌年肥後国の阿蘇惟光を下し、九州で残すところは大友氏のみになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A year later, he defeated Koremitsu ASO in Higo Province and the rest in Kyushu was the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A year later, Yoshihisa defeated Koremitsu ASO in Higo Province, leaving the only territory unconquered in Kyushu as that of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A year later, Yoshihisa defeated Koremitsu ASO in Higo Province, leaving the only territory unconquered in Kyushu as that of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし、ここで豊臣秀吉から書状が届けられたが、それはこれ以上九州での戦争を禁じるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he received a letter from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI at this point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at this point Yoshihisa received an order from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI forbidding further armed conflict in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, combined with following sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at this point Yoshihisa received an order from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI forbidding further armed conflict in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>島津家中でも論議を重ねたが、義久は大友氏の所領の筑前国の攻撃を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shimazu family discussed that, but Yoshihisa ordered to attack Chikuzen Province which was the territory of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shimazu family deliberated Hedeyoshi&apos;s order, but in the end, Yoshihisa decided to order an attack on Chikuzen Province, the territory of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shimazu family deliberated Hedeyoshi&apos;s order, but in the end, Yoshihisa decided to order an attack on Chikuzen Province, the territory of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>天正14年（1586年）、島津忠長・伊集院忠棟を大将とした2万余人が高橋紹運の篭る岩屋城を落とした（岩屋城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586, over 20,000 troops headed by Tadanaga SHIMAZU and Tadamune IJUIN, who were commanders, captured Iwaya Castle where Joun TAKAHASHI barricaded (it is called the Battle of Iwaya Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A force of more than 20,000 troops under the command of Tadanaga SHIMAZU and Tadamune IJUIN captured Iwaya Castle, where Joun TAKAHASHI had been barricaded (the Battle of Iwaya Castle).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A force of more than 20,000 troops under the command of Tadanaga SHIMAZU and Tadamune IJUIN captured Iwaya-jo Castle, where Joun TAKAHASHI had been barricaded (the Battle of Iwaya-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>Iwaya-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>義久は肥後側から義弘を大将にした3万700余人、日向側から家久を大将にした1万余人に豊後攻略を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa ordered 30,700-odd troops of Higo headed by Yoshihiro and 10,000-odd troops of Hyuga headed by Iehisa to capture Bungo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa ordered some 30,700 troops from Higo Province, under the command of Yoshihiro, and some 10,000 troops from Hyuga Province, under the command of Iehisa, to capture Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Province&quot; Consistency..</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa ordered some 30,700 troops from Higo Province, under the command of Yoshihiro, and some 10,000 troops from Hyuga Province, under the command of Iehisa, to capture Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>しかし、義弘は直入郡の諸城の攻略に手間取ったため、大友氏の本拠地を攻めるのは家久だけになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshihiso was slow to capture castles in Naoiri-gun, thus only Iehisa&apos;s troops attacked the home of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro, however, had been slower in capturing castles in Naoiri-gun than anticipated; therefore, only Iehisa&apos;s troops was able to attack the home base of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro, however, had been slower in capturing castles in Naoiri-gun than anticipated; therefore, only Iehisa&apos;s troops was able to attack the home base of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>家久は大友方の鶴賀城を攻め落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iehisa&apos;s troops captured Tsuruga Castle of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iehisa&apos;s troops capture Tsuruga Castle, stronhold of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iehisa&apos;s troops capture Tsuruga-jo Castle, stronhold of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>Tsuruga-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>ここで大友軍の援軍として仙石秀久、長宗我部元親、長宗我部信親、十河存保ら総勢6000余人の豊臣連合軍の先発隊が九州に上陸し、大野川を挟んで家久と対陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, the advance contingent of allied forces of Toyotomi consisted of 6,000 troops including Hidehisa SENGOKU, Motochika CHOSOKABE, Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO landed in Kyushu as reinforcements and encamped across the Ono-gawa River facing Iehisa&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, the advance contingent of allied forces under Toyotomi, consisting of 6,000 troops, including Hidehisa SENGOKU, Motochika CHOSOKABE, Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO, landed in Kyushu as reinforcements to the beseiged Otomo clan, and encamped across the Ono-gawa River facing Iehisa&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, the advance contingent of allied forces under Toyotomi, consisting of 6,000 troops, including Hidehisa SENGOKU, Motochika CHOSOKABE, Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO, landed in Kyushu as reinforcements to the beseiged Otomo clan, and encamped across the Ono-gawa River facing Iehisa&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>合戦は敵味方4000余りが討死した乱戦であったが、長宗我部信親、十河存保が討死し、豊臣連合軍が総崩れとなり大勝した（戸次川の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collectively over 4,000 troops of both sides were killed in the battle, but the allied forces of Toyotomi was routed due to the death of Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO (it is called the Battle of Hetsugi-gawa River).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A combined total of more than 4,000 troops from both sides died in the fighting (the Battle of Hetsugi-gawa River), including Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO, with the allied forces of Toyotomi being routed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A combined total of more than 4,000 troops from both sides died in the fighting (the Battle of Hetsugi-gawa River), including Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO, with the allied forces of Toyotomi being routed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>秀吉の九州征伐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conquest of Kyushu by Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conquest of Kyushu by Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conquest of Kyushu by Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>天正15年（1587年）、豊臣軍の先鋒・豊臣秀長率いる10万余人が豊前国に到着したのを皮切りに、豊臣秀吉率いる12万余人が小倉に上陸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, firstly, 100,000 troops, the spearhead of Toyotomi&apos;s army headed by Hidenaga TOYOTOMI arrived in Buzen Province, then 120,000 troops headed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI landed in Kokura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1587, a force 100,000 strong, the vanguard of Toyotomi&apos;s army, under the command of Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, arrived in Buzen Province, followed by a force numbering 120,000 men, under the command of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, landed in Kokura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1587, a force 100,000 strong, the vanguard of Toyotomi&apos;s army, under the command of Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, arrived in Buzen Province, followed by a force numbering 120,000 men, under the command of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, landed in Kokura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>豊臣軍の上陸を知った豊後の義弘・家久らは退陣を余儀なくされ、大友軍に追撃されながら退却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro and Iehisa in Bungo were forced to step down due to the landing of Toyotomi&apos;s army and backed off being chased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Bungo, the forces of Yoshihiro and Iehisa were forced to withdraw while being pursued by the Otomo army, knowing that Toyotomi&apos;s army had landed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Bungo, the forces of Yoshihiro and Iehisa were forced to withdraw while being pursued by the Otomo army, knowing that Toyotomi&apos;s army had landed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>豊前・豊後・筑前・筑後・肥前・肥後の諸大名や国人衆は一部を除いて、次々と豊臣方に下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from a part, most feudal lords and kokujin-shu in Buzen, Bungo, Chikuzen, Chikugo, Hizen and Higo surrendered to Toyotomi side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for a small number of the daimyo and kokujin-shu in Buzen, Bungo, Chikuzen, Chikugo, Hizen and Higo Provinces surrendered the Toyotomi forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for a small number of the daimyo and kokujin-shu in Buzen, Bungo, Chikuzen, Chikugo, Hizen and Higo Provinces surrendered the Toyotomi forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>秀長軍は山田有信ら1500余人が籠る高城を囲んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidenaga&apos;s army surrounded Takajo Castle where 1,500 troops such as Arinobu YAMADA barricaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidenaga&apos;s army surrounded Takajo Castle, where 1,500 troops, including Arinobu YAMADA, had barricaded themselves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidenaga&apos;s army surrounded Takajo-jo Castle, where 1,500 troops, including Arinobu YAMADA, had barricaded themselves.</e>
<cmt>Takajo-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また秀長は高城川を隔てた根白坂に陣を構え、後詰してくる島津軍に備えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Hidenaga encamped in Nejirozaka across the Takajo-gawa River in preparation for the support arms of Shimazu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hidenaga set up defensive positions on Nejirozaka across the Takajo-gawa River to meet any Shimazu forces that were coming to join the fray.</e>
<cmt>後詰 is unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Hidenaga set up defensive positions on Nejirozaka across the Takajo-gawa River to meet any Shimazu forces that were coming to join the fray.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>島津軍は後詰として、義弘・家久など2万余人が根白坂に一斉に攻め寄せたが、島津軍は多くの犠牲を出し、敗走した（根白坂の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army, over 20,000 troops including Yoshihiro and Iehisa invaded Nejirozaka, but numbers of them were killed and routed (it is called the Battle of Nejirozaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimazu&apos;s army of over 20,000 strong, including Yoshihiro and Iehisa, launched an assault against the forces entrenched on the Nejirozaka; howerver, they were repulsed, suffering heavy casualties, and eventualy were routed in the fighting (the Battle of Nejirozaka).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army of over 20,000 strong, including Yoshihiro and Iehisa, launched an assault against the forces entrenched on the Nejirozaka; howerver, they were repulsed, suffering heavy casualties, and eventualy were routed in the fighting (the Battle of Nejirozaka).</e>
<cmt>スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>主力が消耗する前に和睦に持ち込もうという義久の判断で、伊集院忠棟を人質として秀長に和睦を申し入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the discretion of Yoshihisa, they made proposals for peace to Hidenaga in exchange for the hostage of Tadamune IJUIN before consuming main force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the bulk of his force were decimated, Yoshihisa, deciding that discretion was the better part of valor, proposed a cessation of hostilities to Hidenaga, offering in exchange for the hostage Tadamune IJUIN.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the bulk of his force were decimated, Yoshihisa, deciding that discretion was the better part of valor, proposed a cessation of hostilities to Hidenaga, offering in exchange for the hostage Tadamune IJUIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>義久はこれを機に剃髪、名を龍伯と改めているが、家督を義弘に譲ったかは明らかになっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa did teihatsu (tonsure) and changed his name to Ryuhaku at the time, but it is unclear whether he transferred the family estate to Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this juncture, Yoshihisa took the tonsure, and assumed the Buddhist name Ryuhaku, but it is unclear as to whether he transferred the family estate to Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this juncture, Yoshihisa took the tonsure, and assumed the Buddhist name Ryuhaku, but it is unclear as to whether he transferred the family estate to Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>義久は川内市の泰平寺 (薩摩川内市)で秀吉と会見し、正式に降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa met Hideyoshi at Taihei-ji Temple in Sendai City (present-day Satsumasendai City) and officially surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa had an audience with Hideyoshi at Taihei-ji Temple in Sendai City (present-day Satsumasendai City) at which he formaly surrendered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa had an audience with Hideyoshi at Taihei-ji Temple in Sendai City (present-day Satsumasendai City) at which he formaly surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>義久が降伏したものの、義弘・歳久・新納忠元・桂忠詮・北郷時久らは抗戦を続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yoshihisa surrendered, Yoshihiro, Toshihisa, Tadamoto NINO, Tadanori KATSURA and Tokihisa HONGO coutinued to resist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Yoshihisa surrendered, others, including Yoshihiro, Toshihisa, Tadamoto NINO, Tadanori KATSURA and Tokihisa HONGO coutinued to resist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Yoshihisa surrendered, others, including Yoshihiro, Toshihisa, Tadamoto NIIRO, Tadanori KATSURA and Tokihisa HONGO coutinued to resist.</e>
<cmt>Tadamoto NINO→Tadamoto NIIROに修正 (参照: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%96%B0%E7%B4%8D%E5%BF%A0%E5%85%83)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>義久はこれらの開城を秀吉に約束することにより、島津氏は薩摩と大隅、日向諸縣郡を安堵されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Yoshihisa&apos;s promising Hideyoshi to surrender these castles, the Shimazu clan was assured of the dominium of Satsuma, Osumi and Norokata-gun.</e>
<cmt>「安堵する」は、ある場所の領有権が保証されることという意味で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By agreeing to relinquish several castles to Hideyoshi, Yoshihisa, gained assurances from Hideyoshi that the Shimazu clan would have dominion over Satsuma, Osumi and Norokata-gun Provinces.</e>
<cmt>which castles?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By agreeing to relinquish several castles to Hideyoshi, Yoshihisa, gained assurances from Hideyoshi that the Shimazu clan would have dominion over Satsuma and Osumi Provinces and Morokata-gun, Hyuga Province.</e>
<cmt>「諸縣（もろかた）郡」の読みの誤りを訂正し、Satsuma, Osumi and Norokata-gun Provinces→Satsuma and Osumi Provinces and Morokata-gun, Hyuga Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>豊臣政権下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under Toyotomi&apos;s government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Toyotomi&apos;s administration</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Toyotomi&apos;s Administration</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>秀吉は島津氏に対して、義久に薩摩を、義弘に大隅を、義弘の嫡男・島津久保に日向諸縣郡をそれぞれ分割して安堵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi assured the Shimazu clan of the dominium separately: Satsuma for Yoshihisa, Osumi for Yoshihiro and Morokata-gun, Hyuga for Yoshihiro&apos;s progeny, Hisayasu SHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi granted the Shimazu clan certain dominion over the three separate Provinces as follows: Satsuma was to be the domain of Yoshihisa; Osumi the domain of Yoshihiro; and Morokata-gun, Hyuga the domain of Yoshihiro&apos;s heir, Hisayasu SHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt>grammar, Provinces</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi granted the Shimazu clan certain dominion over the three separate provinces as follows: Satsuma was to be the domain of Yoshihisa; Osumi the domain of Yoshihiro; and Morokata-gun, Hyuga the domain of Yoshihiro&apos;s heir, Hisayasu SHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt>Provinces→provincesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>秀吉は九州平定後、天下を統一し、諸大名に対して朝鮮への出兵を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After conquering Kyushu, Hideyoshi brought the whole country under his rule and ordered feudal lords to send troops to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After pacifying Kyushu, Hideyoshi proceeded to bring the entire country under his unified rule, and then ordered the daimyo to dispatch troops for an invasion of Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammra, somewhat unclear, to broad of a timeframe in a single sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After pacifying Kyushu, Hideyoshi proceeded to bring the entire country under his unified rule, and then ordered the daimyo to dispatch troops for an invasion of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>しかし、島津氏の総大将は当主と見なされていた義久ではなく弟の義弘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the supreme commander of the Shimazu clan was not Yoshihisa who was considere to be the family head, but his yonger brother, Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ranking military commander of the Shimazu clan at this time, however, was not Yoshihisa, who was considere to be the head of the family, but his yonger brother, Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>family→ clan</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ranking military commander of the Shimazu clan at this time, however, was not Yoshihisa, who was considere to be the head of the clan, but his yonger brother, Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>the head of the family→the head of the clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>義久とその家臣団には、反豊臣政権の空気が強く関心が薄かったため出兵する気がなかったというのが山本博文の説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirofumi YAMAMOTO considers that Yoshihisa and his retainers were Anti-Toyotomi, thus they had little interest in sending troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirofumi YAMAMOTO considers Yoshihisa and his retainers to have been opposed to the administration of Toyotomi, and they would therefore have had little interest in contributing troops for this plan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, and again, insuffiently detailed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirofumi YAMAMOTO considers Yoshihisa and his retainers to have been opposed to the administration of Toyotomi, and they would therefore have had little interest in contributing troops for this plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この説はともかく、他大名と異なり豊臣秀吉に抗戦した後の降伏・臣従という経緯であったためか、島津家には方広寺の大仏殿建立など過大な負担が要求されることが多かった上に、矢継ぎ早に朝鮮出兵への命令、更にその時に起こった梅北一揆で歳久が一方的に秀吉に処罰を申し渡され処刑せざるを得なかった事件など、義久はじめ島津家臣団と秀吉政権の間に確執があったのは事実のようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Putting this theory aside, maybe bacause the Shimazu clan surrendered and served as vassal after they resisted Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI unlike in the case of other feudal lords, the Shimazu clan was requested excessive burden such as the construction of Daibutsu-den(the Great Buddha hall) of Hoko-ji Temple, furthermore, they got immediate order of sending troops to Korea and there was an incident that Yoshihisa was ordred to execute Toshihisa by Hideyoshi and he had no other choice, which shows that there was a feud between the retainers of the Shimazu clan including Yoshihisa and the Hideyoshi administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Putting this theory aside for the moment, perhas they had become vassals of Toyotomi only after have first resisted him with arms, unlike the other daimyo, the fact that there were a number of excessive demands made upon the Shimazu clan, such as the construction of Daibutsu-den(the Great Buddha hall) of Hoko-ji Temple, that they were ordered to immediately dispatch troops to Korea, and that there was an incident in which Yoshihisa was ordred to execute Toshihisa by Hideyoshi because of the Unekita ikki (an uprising), leaving him no choice but to comply, show that Yoshihisa and other members of the Shimazu clan were at odds with the Hideyoshi administration.</e>
<cmt>Unekita ikki</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Putting this theory aside for the moment, perhas they had become vassals of Toyotomi only after have first resisted him with arms, unlike the other daimyo, the fact that there were a number of excessive demands made upon the Shimazu clan, such as the construction of Daibutsu-den (the Great Buddha hall) of Hoko-ji Temple, that they were ordered to immediately dispatch troops to Korea, and that there was an incident in which Yoshihisa was ordred to execute Toshihisa by Hideyoshi because of the Umekita Uprising (an uprising by a retainer of the Shimazu family, Kunikane UMEKITA), leaving him no choice but to comply, show that Yoshihisa and other members of the Shimazu clan were at odds with the Hideyoshi administration.</e>
<cmt>Unekita ikki (an uprising)→Umekita Uprisingに修正し、補足を追加、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>これに対して秀吉は義弘が文禄・慶長の役から帰国すると知行替えを行い、義久に大隅、日向諸縣郡を与え、義弘に鹿児島など主要部のある薩摩を与え、当主のように扱った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Hideyoshi changed Chigyo (dominion) after returning from the Bunroku and Keicho no eki War: He granted Osumi and Morokata-gun, Hyuga for Yoshihisa, and Satsuma including main part such as Kagoshima for Yoshihiro and treated him like a family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, after Yoshihiro after returned from the Bunroku and Keicho no eki War, Hideyoshi realigned the assignment of dominions among the Shimazu, granting Osumi and Morokata-gun, Hyuga to Yoshihisa, and the important parts of Satsuma, including Kagoshima, to Yoshihiro, treating him like a family head.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, after Yoshihiro after returned from the Bunroku and Keicho Wars, Hideyoshi realigned the assignment of dominions among the Shimazu, granting Osumi Province and Morokata-gun, Hyuga Province to Yoshihisa, and the important parts of Satsuma Province, including Kagoshima, to Yoshihiro, treating him like a family head.</e>
<cmt>the Bunroku and Keicho no eki War→the Bunroku and Keicho Warsとし、Osumi Province、Hyuga Province、Satsuma Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>更に義久の知行地とした大隅国内に多数の秀吉直轄領（御蔵入地）や太閤検地奉行となった石田三成や細川幽斎の領地をおくなどの嫌がらせを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hedeyoshi harassed Yoshihisa by deploying number of his direct control territories (Okurairichi) and territories of Mitsunari ISHIDA and Yusai HOSOKAWA who were Taiko-Kenchi survey magistrate in Osumi Province which was Yoshihisa&apos;s Chigyo-chi (territory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hideyoshi harassed Yoshihisa by appropriating (as Okurairichi) a number of territories in Osumi Province, which was part of Yoshihisa&apos;s domain, and territories of Mitsunari ISHIDA and Yusai HOSOKAWA who had been Taiko-Kenchi survey magistrates, under his direct control.</e>
<cmt>unclear, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Hideyoshi harassed Yoshihisa by placing a number of territories under his direct control (called Okurairichi) and territories of Mitsunari ISHIDA and Yusai HOSOKAWA who had been Taiko-kenchi bugyo (land survey magistrates) in the Osumi Province, which was part of Yoshihisa&apos;s domain.</e>
<cmt>「太閤検地奉行」の表記を変更、および原文の内容に沿わないため全体を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>しかし、領内での実権は依然として義久が握っていた（これを「双殿体制」と言う）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshihisa still assumed control within his territory (it is called &quot;Siden-taise system&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshihisa retained control within his territory, under a system called &quot;Siden-taise&quot;.</e>
<cmt>it is not clear that there is a need for the Romanized term &quot;Siden-taisei&quot;. If you keep it, you need to explain why.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshihisa retained control within his territory (called &apos;Siden-taisei,&apos; or a system of diarchy).</e>
<cmt>under a system called &quot;Siden-taise&quot;→ (called &apos;Siden-taisei,&apos; or a system of diarchy) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>ちなみに義久には男児が無かったため、義弘の嫡男・久保に3女・亀寿を娶わせ養子とすることで後継者と定めていたが、久保が早世したため秀吉の命により久保の弟・島津忠恒に亀寿を再嫁させて後継者とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Yoshihisa had no son, he selected Hisayasu, Yoshihiro&apos;s progeny as successor by making him get married to his third daughter, Kameju, and adopting him, but Hisayasu died young and he made Kameju to get remarried with Hisayasu&apos;s younger brother, Tadatsune and made him a succesor by Hideyoshi&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Yoshihisa did not have a son, he selected Hisayasu, Yoshihiro&apos;s oldest son to be his successor, arranging to have him marry his third daughter, Kameju, and adopting him; however; Hisayasu died young, and Yoshihisa had Kameju remarry, this time to Hisayasu&apos;s younger brother, Tadatsune, and made him succesor by order of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Yoshihisa did not have a son, he selected Hisayasu, Yoshihiro&apos;s oldest son to be his successor, arranging to have him marry his third daughter, Kameju, and adopting him; however; Hisayasu died young, and Yoshihisa had Kameju remarry, this time to Hisayasu&apos;s younger brother, Tadatsune, and made him succesor by order of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="76">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）、関ヶ原の戦いにおいても義久は本国から動かず、義弘が指揮を取って西軍に加担をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Yoshihisa didn&apos;t move from his home land and Yoshihiro directed to join the West squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Yoshihisa did not mobilize, but stayed at his home base, leaving it to Yoshihiro to lead the Shimazu contingent of the western army.</e>
<cmt>「指揮を取って西軍に加担」is somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the occasion of the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Yoshihisa did not mobilize, but stayed at his home base, leaving it to Yoshihiro to lead the Shimazu contingent of the western army.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>戦いで西軍が総崩れとなるものの、義弘はわずか1000余人で敵中突破を見事成功させ、東軍に追撃されながらも薩摩へ帰還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the West squad was routed in the battle, Yoshihiro successfully broke through the enemy with merely 1,000-odd troops and returned to Satsuma, although they were chased byt the East squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the western army was routed in the battle, leading a relativelyt small force of only slightly more than 1,000 men, Yoshihiro successfully attacked, breaking through the enemy ranks, and successfully returned to Satsuma, with the eastern army in pusruit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the western army was routed in the battle, leading a relativelyt small force of only slightly more than 1,000 men, Yoshihiro successfully attacked, breaking through the enemy ranks, and successfully returned to Satsuma, with the eastern army in pusruit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>義久は戦後処理として徳川家康と粘り強い交渉を行い、結果的に島津氏は本領安堵という破格の処置を受けることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the battle, Yoshihisa negotiated patiently with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and got a preferential treatment which was Honryo Ando (assurance for dominium of one&apos;s territory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle, Yoshihisa negotiated diligently with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, securing preferential treatment in the form of granted assurance of continued dominion over the territory under control of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle, Yoshihisa negotiated diligently with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, securing preferential treatment in the form of granted assurance of continued dominion over the territory under control of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Late life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Late life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>徳川幕府の領土安堵後の慶長7年（1602年）、当主の座を正式に島津忠恒に譲り渡して隠居したが、以後も江戸幕府と都度都度書状をやりとりするなど絶大な権威を持ち、死ぬまで家中に発言力を保持していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1602, after Honryo Ando by the Tokugawa Shogunate, he officially transferred the position of family head to Tadatsune SHIMAZU and retired, however, he kept so much power that he exchanged letters with the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in each case and carried a lot of weight within the family until his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1602, after successfully concluding negotiations with the Tokugawa Shogunate, he officially transferred the position of family head to Tadatsune SHIMAZU, and retired; however, he retained significant influence, as evidenced in his exchanging correspondences with the Edo bakufu, and was continually sought out for counsel within the family until his death.</e>
<cmt>hasn&apos;t &quot;bakufu&quot; been defined already?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1602, after successfully concluding negotiations with the Tokugawa Shogunate, he officially transferred the position of family head to Tadatsune SHIMAZU, and retired; however, he retained significant influence, as evidenced in his exchanging correspondences with the Edo bakufu, and was continually sought out for counsel within the family until his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>しかし、娘・亀寿と忠恒の不仲などから忠恒との関係は次第に悪化したと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the relationwhip with Tadatsune was gradually worsened since his daughter, Kameju, got into bad terms with Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his relationwhip with Tadatsune gradually worsened, as his daughter, Kameju, and Tadatsune were not getting along well in their marriage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his relationwhip with Tadatsune gradually worsened, as his daughter, Kameju, and Tadatsune were not getting along well in their marriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>忠恒・亀寿夫妻の間には1人も子が無かったことから外孫の島津久信を忠恒の次の後継者に据えようとしたが失敗したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It it said that Tadatsune and Kameju had no children and they tried to put Hisanobu SHIMIZU, his daughter&apos;s son, in Tadatsune&apos;s successor, but it failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It it said that Tadatsune and Kameju did not have even one child, and that they therefore tried to have Hisanobu SHIMAZU, his daughter&apos;s son, installed as Tadatsune&apos;s successor, but failed.</e>
<cmt>unclear, grammar, again, here SHIMIZU→ShimAzu外孫is not clear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It it said that Tadatsune and Kameju did not have even one child, and that they therefore tried to have Hisanobu SHIMAZU, his daughter&apos;s son, installed as Tadatsune&apos;s successor, but failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>また、義弘・忠恒親子が積極的に推進した琉球出兵にも反対していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he opposed sending troops to Ryukyu which was actively driven by Yoshihiro and Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Yoshihisa opposed sending troops to Ryukyu which had been actively supported by Yoshihiro and Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Yoshihisa opposed sending troops to Ryukyu which had been actively supported by Yoshihiro and Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>慶長16年（1611年）1月21日、国分城 (大隅国)にて病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 21, 1611, he died from a disease in Kokubu Castle (Osumi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21, 1611, he died from of illness, in Kokubu Castle (Osumi Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 5, 1611, he died from of illness, in Kokubu-jo Castle (Osumi Province).</e>
<cmt>Kokubu-jo Castleとしました。January 21→March 5に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>享年79。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 79.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was 79 years old.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 79 years old.</e>
<cmt>His→Heとしました。 (既に前文にdiedとあり、統一リストの&quot;Died at the age of&quot;の表記にはしておりません)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>辞世の句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death haiku (Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death haiku (Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Farewell Poem</e>
<cmt>記載されている句は&quot;haiku&quot;ではないため、訳語を修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>「世の中の　米（よね）と水とを　くみ尽くし　つくしてのちは　天つ大空」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I served my life in devotion; After that, I found the empty sky over my head.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I applied myself with dedication in the world, now I found the empty sky over my head.&quot;</e>
<cmt>difficult poem…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I applied myself with dedication in the world, now I found the empty sky over my head.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality/Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality/Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality/Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>本領安堵後、徳川家康に伏見城へ招かれ九州をほぼ統一した時の話を請われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Honryo Ando, he was invited to Fushimi Castle by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and requested to tell of the time when he almost conquered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After negotiating continued dominionover the territories under the Shimazu clan, Yoshihisa was invited by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to Fushimi Castle, and asked to recount the time when he almost conquered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After negotiating continued dominionover the territories under the Shimazu clan, Yoshihisa was invited by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to Fushimi-jo Castle, and asked to recount the time when he almost conquered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>Fushimi-jo Castleとし、余分なスペースを消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>話す事はないと断ったが、家康や家康の家臣が強く要請するので渋々、「義弘をはじめとする3人の弟たちや、新納忠元らの家臣団が相反することなく一致団結して戦ってくれたので、私が先頭に立ち戦に出たことはなく、ただ鹿児島の城にて留守番をしていただけのことです」と答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He declined the request because he doesn&apos;t have much to say, but Ieyasu and his retainers strongly requested, then he reluctantly answered, &quot;It is the honor of my brothers such as Yoshihiro and the retainers including Tadamoto NINO who had a united effort to fight the battle without conflicting. I&apos;d never been at the vanguard of the battle but just looked after the castle in Kagoshima.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he declined the request, claiming there he didn&apos;t have much to say, Ieyasu and his retainers persisted, so he eventually relented, offerring the response, &quot;The honor rightfully belongs to my three brothers, starting with Yoshihiro, and our retainers, such as Tadamoto NINO, who put up a unified front in fighting the battles, without internal dissent, I never led the troops in battle, but just looked after the castle in Kagoshima.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though he declined the request, claiming there he didn&apos;t have much to say, Ieyasu and his retainers persisted, so he eventually relented, offerring the response, &apos;The honor rightfully belongs to my three brothers, starting with Yoshihiro, and our retainers, such as Tadamoto NIIRO, who put up a unified front in fighting the battles, without internal dissent, I never led the troops in battle, but just looked after the castle in Kagoshima.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Tadamoto NINO→Tadamoto NIIROに修正、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>義久自身遠慮もあったのだろうが、恥ずかしいことと認識していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It maybe because Yoshihisa was reserved, but also he seems to have perceived it as dishonor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa may simply have been refraining from making the visit, but he also seems to have felt somewhat shamed by the fact that he did not engage in the battles.</e>
<cmt>the Japanese text is too vague</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa may simply have been refraining from making the visit, but he also seems to have felt somewhat shamed by the fact that he did not engage in the battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>しかし、義久が帰ったあとに家康は家臣らに次のように言ったという逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is an anecdote that after Yoshihisa left, Ieyasu told his retainers, &quot;The commander is a man who has a talent for directing the best way to his retainers without thrusting himself into matters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is an anecdote that after Yoshihisa left, Ieyasu told his retainers, &quot;The commander is a man who has a talent fordeftly directing his retainers to the greatest effect, without thrusting himself into matters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is an anecdote that after Yoshihisa left, Ieyasu told his retainers as follows:</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>「大将自ら動くことなく、家臣をうまく使う優れた采配を持っている。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The commander is a man who has a talent fordeftly directing his retainers to the greatest effect, without thrusting himself into matters.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>「これこそ大将の鏡である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a paragon of commander.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is a paragon of commander.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is a paragon of commander.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="92">
<j>この時代の戦国武将には珍しく、義久本人の当時の肖像画は残存しておらず容貌に関しては不明であるが、鹿児島県薩摩川内市の泰平寺 (薩摩川内市)には後世になってから作られた義久降伏の銅像がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rare for the busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period that his portrait of that time isn&apos;t remaining and his apperance is unknown, however, there is a statue of Yoshihisa&apos;s surrender built after ages in Taihei-ji Temple in Satsumasendai City, Kagoshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>（薩摩川内市）は不要と考えて訳出していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa&apos;s is a rare case in that no portrait exists for him, a military commander of the Sengoku Period, and that his countenance is unknown; however, there is a statue of depicting Yoshihisa&apos;s surrender, which was made several generation later, in the Taihei-ji Temple in Satsumasendai City, Kagoshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa&apos;s is a rare case in that no portrait exists for him, a military commander of the Sengoku period, and that his countenance is unknown; however, there is a statue of depicting Yoshihisa&apos;s surrender, which was made several generation later, in the Taihei-ji Temple in Satsumasendai City, Kagoshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>義久は智勇に優れていただけではなく、細川幽斎から古今伝授を受けたり、関白・近衛前久との親交が厚かったなど、教養人でもあったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yoshihisa had not just wisdom and courage, but also he was educated person, for example, he was taught about Kokin-shu (collection of Japanese poems) and maitained close relations with Sakihisa KONOE, a chief adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yoshihisa had not just wisdom and courage, but also he was also a learned person, having, for example, received lectures on the Kokin-shu (a collection of waka poems) from Yusai HOSOKAWA, and maitained close relations with Sakihisa KONOE, a chief adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar, ommissions in 1st translation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yoshihisa had not just wisdom and courage, but also he was also a learned person, having, for example, received lectures on the Kokin-shu (a collection of waka poems) from Yusai HOSOKAWA, and maitained close relations with Sakihisa KONOE, a chief adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="94">
<j>天正14年（1586年）、義久は豊臣秀吉から大友宗麟との和睦と豊臣氏への臣従を迫られたが、1月11日に出した書状では宛名を細川幽斎にして和睦・臣従を拒むという返信を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586, Yoshihisa was pressed to make peace with Sorin OTOMO and serve as a vassal to the Toyotomi clan, but he sent a reply saying that he refused to make peace or serve as a vassal to Yusai HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1586, Yoshihisa was pressed to make peace with Sorin OTOMO and serve as a vassal to the Toyotomi clan, but he sent a reply addressed to to Yusai HOSOKAWA saying that he refused to make peace or serve as a vassal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1586, Yoshihisa was pressed to make peace with Sorin OTOMO and serve as a vassal to the Toyotomi clan, but he sent a reply addressed to to Yusai HOSOKAWA saying that he refused to make peace or serve as a vassal.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>義久は名族・島津氏の自尊心がかなり強かったらしく、秀吉のような成り上がり者を通信相手に選ばなかったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa seems to have been proud of honorable family, the Shimazu clan, thus he didn&apos;t choose upstart like Hideyoshi as communicator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa seems to have been proud of his family and the Shimazu clan, viewing Hideyaoshi as something of an upstart, and therefore choosing not to enter into corresponse with him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa seems to have been proud of his family and the Shimazu clan, viewing Hideyaoshi as something of an upstart, and therefore choosing not to enter into corresponse with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>家族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>祖父島津忠良の娘（叔母）を妻に迎え、死別後は種子島時尭の娘を後妻とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took a daughter of his grandfather, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU (his aunt) for his legal wife and after the bereavement, he got remarried with a daughter of Tokitaka TANEGASHIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took a daughter of his grandfather, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU (his aunt) for his legal wife and after mourning her early death, he remarried to a daughter of Tokitaka TANEGASHIMA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took a daughter of his grandfather, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU (his aunt) for his legal wife and after mourning her early death, he remarried to a daughter of Tokitaka TANEGASHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>義久には側室を持った記載はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no record showing that Yoshihisa had a concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no record showing that Yoshihisa had a concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no record showing that Yoshihisa had a concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>しかし、「上井覚兼日記」天正11年3月13日（旧暦）の記載に御料様の記載があることや、『薩藩旧記雑録』に所収された慶長4年頃の島津家の領地の配分について 義久内儀義弘内儀分という記載があることから、2人の正室没後に後妻の存在が確認されているが、正室ではないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the record of March 13, 1583 in &quot;UWAI, Kakuken Nikki (Diary of Kakuken UWAI)&quot; referred to Goryo-sama and the territory distribution of the Shimazu clan around 1599 printed in &quot;Sappan Kyuki-zatsuroku&quot; referred to Yoshihisa&apos;s Naigi (wife), it is confirmed that he got remarried after the death of 2 legal wives, but she is considered not to have been a legal wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because a record dated March 13, 1583 in &quot;UWAI, Kakuken Nikki (Diary of Kakuken UWAI)&quot; refers to Goryo-sama and the territorial distribution of the Shimazu clan around 1599, printed in the Sappan Kyuki-zatsuroku (Miscellaneaous Records of old Satsuma) and to Yoshihisa&apos;s Naigi (wife), it is confirmed that he again remarried after the death of his second legal wife, but she is considered not to have been a legal wife.</e>
<cmt>grammar, Sappan Kyuki-zatsuroku (English description) (Miscellaneous Records of old Satsuma) Aslo, the status of the 後妻 is not clear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because a record dated March 13, 1583 in &apos;UWAI, Kakuken Nikki&apos; (Diary of Kakuken UWAI) refers to Goryo-sama and the territorial distribution of the Shimazu clan around 1599, printed in the &quot;Sappan Kyuki-zatsuroku&quot; (Miscellaneaous Records of old Satsuma) and to Yoshihisa&apos;s Naigi (wife), it is confirmed that he again remarried after the death of his second legal wife, but she is considered not to have been a legal wife.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、位置を移動、&quot;Sappan Kyuki-zatsuroku&quot;にクォーテーション追加、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>この女性は『新城島津家文書』のなかに、「一之臺」と記載されている人物と同一ではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This woman is considered to have been the one who was described as &apos;Ichinodai&apos; in &quot;Shinjo-Shimazu-ke Bunsho&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This woman is considered to have been the same person referred to as &apos;Ichinodai&apos; in the Shinjo-Shimazu-ke Bunsho (History of the New Castle of the Shimazu).</e>
<cmt>Shinjo-Shimazu-ke Bunsho</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This woman is considered to have been the same person referred to as &apos;Ichinodai&apos; in the &quot;Shinjo-Shimazu-ke Bunsho&quot; (History of the Shinjo-Shimazu family).</e>
<cmt>Shinjo-Shimazu-ke Bunshoにクォーテーション追加、および補足を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>そのほか、「本藩人物志」鮫島宗堯の項に、義久の側室とされる小侍従なる女性が木脇祐光に下げ渡された後に男児を生んだ（鮫島宗堯）としていることから、落胤説もあるが公式史料には登場せず、小侍従の存在を含めて信憑性は低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to the section of Munetaka SAMEJIMA in &quot;Honpan-Jinbutsushi&quot;, Yoshihisa&apos;s concubine called Kojijyu gave birth to a male infant after she was granted to Sukemitsu KIWAKI, thus there is a theory of Rakuin (child born out of wedlock), but she doesn&apos;t appear in official historical materials and the credibility including the existense of concubine is low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to the section on Munetaka SAMEJIMA in the Honpan-Jinbutsushi (Personages of Satsuma), there was a concubine of Yoshihisa&apos;s called Kojijyu who bore a male child after she was granted to Sukemitsu KIWAKI, giving rise to the theory that there was a child born out of wedlock, but she does not appear in official historical records, and the credibility of the account, including the existense of a concubine, is low.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to the section on Munetaka SAMEJIMA in the &apos;Honpan-Jinbutsushi&apos; (Personages of Satsuma), there was a concubine of Yoshihisa&apos;s called Kojijyu who bore a male child after she was granted to Sukemitsu KIWAKI, giving rise to the theory that there was a child born out of wedlock, but she does not appear in official historical records, and the credibility of the account, including the existense of a concubine, is low.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave Sites</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>鹿児島市内の福昌寺 (鹿児島市)に歴代島津家当主らと共に宝筐印塔がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a Hokyoin-to (Buddhist stupa) of him and successive family heads of the Shimazu family at Fukusho-ji Temple in Kagoshima City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a Hokyoin-to (Buddhist stupa) memorializing Yoshihisa and successive heads of the Shimazu family at Fukusho-ji Temple in Kagoshima City.</e>
<cmt>head of family</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a Hokyoin-to (Buddhist stupa) memorializing Yoshihisa and successive heads of the Shimazu family at Fukusho-ji Temple in Kagoshima City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>他にも霧島市国分の金剛寺跡には遺体の一部（歯と伝えられる）が祀られた三重石塔、京都市の今熊野観音寺には平田増宗、山田有栄らと共に慶長五年に建てた逆修塔がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is a Sanju-sekito (three-story stone pagoda) which enshrines a part of his body (said to be tooth) at the ruins of Kongo-ji Temple in Kokubu, Kirishima City and there is a Gyakushu-to (a grave built before someone&apos;s death) built by him with Masumune HIRATA and Arinaga YAMADA in 1600 at Imakumano-Kannon-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is a three-story stone pagoda which enshrines a relic of his body (said to be tooth) at the ruins of Kongo-ji Temple in Kokubu, Kirishima City, and there is a Gyakushu-to (a memorial stone erected for onself before death) that had been built to memorialize himself, Masumune HIRATA, Arinaga YAMADA and others in 1600 at Imakumano-Kannon-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>some elements unclear, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is a three-story stone pagoda which enshrines a relic of his body (said to be tooth) at the ruins of Kongo-ji Temple in Kokubu, Kirishima City, and there is a Gyakushu-to (a memorial stone erected for onself before death) that had been built to memorialize himself, Masumune HIRATA, Arinaga YAMADA and others in 1600 at Imakumano-Kannon-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>また、高野山にも供養塔がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, a Kuyo-to(memorial tower) is in Koyasan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a Kuyo-to (memorial tower) on Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a Kuyo-to (memorial tower) on Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>1564年(永禄7）　従五位下修理大夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1564, given the rank of Jugoi-no-ge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assumed the position of Shuri-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1564, Yoshihisa was given the rank of Jugoi-no-ge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assumed the position of Shuri-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1564: Yoshihisa was given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assumed the position of Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Jugoinogeとし、Shuri-no-kami→Shuri no daibuとし、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>1581年(天正9・5月3日_(旧暦)）　従四位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1581, promoted to the rank of Jushi-no-ge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1581, he was promoted to the rank of Jushi-no-ge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1581: He was promoted to the rank of Jushinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Jushiinogeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works featuring Yoshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works featuring Yoshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works featuring Yoshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>桐野作人『島津義久』（PHP研究所PHP文庫、2005年）　ISBN 4569664199</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shimazu Yoshihisa&quot; (Sakijin KIRINO, PHP books, PHP Interface, 2005, ISBN 4569664199)</e>
<cmt>書籍のタイトルなので、あえて日本語の姓名の順に表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shimazu Yoshihisa&quot; (Sakijin KIRINO, PHP books, PHP Interface, 2005, ISBN 4569664199)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shimazu Yoshihisa&quot; (Sakijin KIRINO, PHP books, PHP Interface, 2005, ISBN 4569664199)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>『黄金の日日』（NHK大河ドラマ、演：中村靖之介 (初代)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ogon no Hibi (the Golden days)&quot; (NHK Taiga drama series, performed by Seinosuke NAKAMURA (the first actor)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ogon no Hibi (The Golden Days)&quot; (NHK Taiga drama series, starring Seinosuke NAKAMURA in the lead role).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ogon no Hibi&quot;(The Golden Days) (NHK Taiga drama series, starring Seinosuke NAKAMURA the First).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動、「初代」→異なる解釈で訳されているため、「初代・中村靖之介」となるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>『琉球の風 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（NHK大河ドラマ、演：室田日出男）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryukyu no Kaze (Winds of Ryukyu)&quot; (NHK Taiga drama series, performed by Hideo MUROTA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryukyu no Kaze (Winds of Ryukyu)&quot; (NHK Taiga drama series, staring Hideo MUROTA)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryukyu no Kaze&quot; (Winds of Ryukyu) (NHK Taiga drama series, staring Hideo MUROTA)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ドルチェット(id:46458), DragonBot(id:161936), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shinyafortune(id:42940), ＤＦ．Ｋｉｎｇ(id:48817), Revth(id:12179), Hesolla(id:207896), 小者(id:172526), Kagetudo(id:163875), らりた(id:1327), Archivist(id:52904), Azusayumi7(id:21082), ゐ(id:795), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 上(id:14148), こぶまき(id:38278), けんち(id:5147), Maakun(id:16735), Louperibot(id:128971), 竜造寺和英(id:98841), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>