<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源順子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Junshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Junshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Junshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 順子（みなもと の じゅんし／みなもと の のぶこ、貞観 (日本)17年（875年） - 延長 (元号)3年4月4日 (旧暦)（925年5月4日））藤原忠平の室で、藤原実頼の母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Junshi (also called MINAMOTO no Nobuko, 875 - May 4, 925) was the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadahira and the mother of FUJIWARA no Saneyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Junshi (also called MINAMOTO no Nobuko, 875 - May 4, 925) was the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadahira and the mother of FUJIWARA no Saneyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Junshi (also called MINAMOTO no Nobuko, 875 - May 4, 925) was the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadahira and the mother of FUJIWARA no Saneyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>史料によって、「傾子」（『大鏡裏書』『一代要記』）や、「頎子」（『皇代暦』）の記載があるが、この2者については「順子」の草書体が誤ったものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though some historical materials describe &apos;傾子&apos; (&quot;Okagamiuragaki (annotation of the Great Mirror Tale)&quot; and &quot;Ichidai Yoki (summary chronicle of each reign)&quot;) and &apos;頎子&apos; (&quot;Kodaireki (a chronicle)&quot;), these two are considered to be mistakes by wrongly taking the cursive script of &apos;Junshi (順子).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though some historical materials describe &apos;傾子&apos; (&quot;Okagamiuragaki (annotation of the Great Mirror Tale)&quot; and &quot;Ichidai Yoki (summary chronicle of each reign)&quot;) and &apos;頎子&apos; (&quot;Kodaireki (a chronicle)&quot;), these two are considered to be mistakes by mistakingly taking the cursive script of &apos;Junshi (順子).&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though some historical materials describe &apos;傾子&apos; (&quot;Okagamiuragaki&quot; (annotation of the Great Mirror Tale) and &quot;Ichidai Yoki&quot; (summary chronicle of each reign)) and &apos;頎子&apos; (&quot;Kodaireki&quot; (a chronicle)), these two are considered to be mistakes by mistakingly taking the cursive script of &apos;Junshi (順子).&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>順子が忠平の室になったのは、実頼が生まれる昌泰3年（900年）以前で、『古事談』に、忠平と順子の婚儀は、忠平が大弁参議のときに朱雀院西対で行われたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junshi became Tadahira&apos;s wife before Saneyori was born in 900, and &quot;Kojidan (Talks of the Past)&quot; says that the wedding of Tadahira and Junshi was held at the West wing of the Suzaku-in imperial villa when Tadahira was Daiben-Sangi (Major controller and councillor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junshi became Tadahira&apos;s wife before Saneyori was born in 900, and &quot;Kojidan (Talks of the Past)&quot; says that the wedding of Tadahira and Junshi was held at the West wing of the Suzaku-in imperial villa when Tadahira was Daiben-Sangi (Major controller and councillor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junshi became Tadahira&apos;s wife before Saneyori was born in 900, and &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past) says that the wedding of Tadahira and Junshi was held at the West wing of the Suzaku-in imperial villa when Tadahira was Daiben-Sangi (Major controller and councillor).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>延長2年（924年）には、順子五十の算賀が行われたが（『紀貫之集』）、同年末に重病に罹り、翌延長3年4月、51歳で卒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 924, the longevity celebration on Junshi&apos;s 50th birthday was held, but she suffered from serious illness in the same year, and died at 51 in April in 925, the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 924, the longevity celebration on Junshi&apos;s 50th birthday was held, but she suffered from serious illness in the same year, and died at 51 in April in 925, the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 924, the longevity celebration on Junshi&apos;s 50th birthday was held, but she suffered from serious illness in the same year, and died at 51 in May 925, the following year.</e>
<cmt>冒頭の新暦表記にあわせ、in April in 925→in May 925に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>『公卿補任』や『本朝皇胤紹運録』は、宇多天皇の皇女としているが、順子と宇多天皇の年齢差が僅か9歳であることから、兄弟関係であったとしても、父子関係であったとは考え難い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though &quot;Kugyobunin (directory of court nobles)&quot; and &quot;Honcho koin jounroku (the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in Muromachi period)&quot; says that she was a princess of Emperor Uda, the age difference between Junshi and Emperor Uda was only 9 years, so it is possible that they were a brother and sister, but unlikely that they were a father and a daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though &quot;Kugyobunin (directory of court nobles)&quot; and &quot;Honcho koin jounroku (the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in Muromachi period)&quot; says that she was a princess of Emperor Uda, the age difference between Junshi and Emperor Uda was only 9 years, so it is possible that they were a brother and sister, but unlikely that they were a father and a daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and &quot;Honcho Koin Jounroku&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s family tree, made in Muromachi period) says that she was a princess of Emperor Uda, the age difference between Junshi and Emperor Uda was only nine years, so it is possible that they were a brother and sister, but unlikely that they were a father and a daughter.</e>
<cmt>&quot;9&quot;をスペルアウト、クォーテーションの位置を移動、&quot;Honcho Koin Jounroku&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、順子は「菅原の君」と呼ばれていたことから（『大和物語』）、光孝天皇の後宮（更衣 (女官)か）で菅原是善の女である菅原類子を順子の母と擬定し、のちに宇多天皇の養女になったとする見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Junshi was called &apos;Sugawara no kimi&apos; (&quot;Yamato monogatari (Tales of Yamato)&quot;), there is an theory that Junshi&apos;s mother was SUGAWARA no Tomoko, who was a kokyu (wife, possibly a court lady called koi) of Emperor Koko and a daughter of SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi, and she was adopted by Emperor Uda later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Junshi was called &apos;Sugawara no kimi&apos; (&quot;Yamato monogatari (Tales of Yamato)&quot;), there is an theory that Junshi&apos;s mother was SUGAWARA no Tomoko, who was a kokyu (wife, possibly a court lady called koi) of Emperor Koko and a daughter of SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi, and she was adopted by Emperor Uda later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Junshi was called &apos;Sugawara no kimi&apos; (&quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Yamato)), there is an theory that Junshi&apos;s mother was SUGAWARA no Tomoko, who was a kokyu (wife, possibly a court lady called koi) of Emperor Koko and a daughter of SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi, and she was adopted by Emperor Uda later.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Yamato Monogatari&quot;とし、クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>類子を光孝天皇の後宮とする根拠は、当時無位であった類子が、光孝天皇践祚直後の元慶8年（884年）2月26日に従五位下に叙し、同日に光孝天皇女御であり宇多天皇の母である班子女王（父は桓武天皇皇子仲野親王）が従三位に叙しているからである（『日本三代実録』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basis that Tomoko was a wife of Emperor Koko is that Tomoko, who had no rank at that time, was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on February 26, 884 right after the accession of Emperor Koko, and Princess Hanshi (her father was Prince Nakano, son of Emperor Kanmu), who was a nyogo (wife) of Emperor Koko and the mother of Emperor Uda, was ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) (&quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basis that Tomoko was a wife of Emperor Koko is that Tomoko, who had no rank at that time, was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on February 26, 884 right after the accession of Emperor Koko, and Princess Hanshi (her father was Prince Nakano, son of Emperor Kanmu), who was a nyogo (wife) of Emperor Koko and the mother of Emperor Uda, was ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) (&quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basis that Tomoko was a wife of Emperor Koko is that Tomoko, who had no rank at that time, was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on March 30, 884 right after the accession of Emperor Koko, and Princess Hanshi (her father was Imperial Prince Nakano, son of Emperor Kanmu), who was a nyogo (wife) of Emperor Koko and the mother of Emperor Uda, was ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) (&quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts)).</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正、Prince Nakano→Imperial Prince Nakanoとし、クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、この説を採った場合には類子の兄弟である菅原道真と宇多天皇・藤原忠平の三者間の深い関係を想定することが可能となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of adopting this theory, it is possible to picture the deep relationships among Michizane SUGAWARA who was Tomoko&apos;s brother, Emperor Uda and Tadahira FUJIWARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this theory were to be adopted, it is possible to picture the deep relationships among Michizane SUGAWARA who was Tomoko&apos;s brother, Emperor Uda and Tadahira FUJIWARA.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this theory were to be adopted, it is possible to picture the deep relationships among SUGAWARA no Michizane who was Tomoko&apos;s brother, Emperor Uda and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>Michizane SUGAWARA→SUGAWARA no Michizaneとし、前出の表記に合わせ、Tadahira FUJIWARA→FUJIWARA no Tadahiraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Tekuli(id:43395), Masyu(id:31065), 蘇民(id:87832), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 平惣衛門(id:99387), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>