<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>道嶋嶋足</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MICHISHIMA no Shimatari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MICHISHIMA no Shimatari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MICHISHIMA no Shimatari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>道嶋 嶋足（みちしま の しまたり、生年不詳 - 延暦2年（783年）1月8日）は奈良時代の武人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MICHISHIMA no Shimatari (year of birth unknown - February 17, 783) was a warrior in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MICHISHIMA no Shimatari (year of birth unknown – January 8, 783 in old lunar calendar) was a warrior of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>他のこの時代の記事と同じく、旧暦のままに直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MICHISHIMA no Shimatari (year of birth unknown – Februay 17, 783) was a warrior of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>はじめは丸子嶋足、次いで牡鹿嶋足と姓を改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was initially MARUKO no Shimatari, and was later changed to OSHIKA no Shimatari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was initially MARUKO no Shimatari, and was later changed to OSHIKA no Shimatari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was initially MARUKO no Shimatari, and was later changed to OSHIKA no Shimatari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>陸奥国（後の陸前国）牡鹿郡の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Oshika County, Mutsu Province (later Rikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt>郡→用語統一リストによりCounty と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Oshika County, Mutsu Province (later Rikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt>用語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Oshika County, Mutsu Province (later Rikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>容貌雄壮で武事に通じ騎射を善くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a manly personal appearance, and was proficient in martial arts and good at Kisha (shooting arrows on horseback).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a man of brave and lively appearance, and was proficient in martial arts and good at Kisha (shooting arrows on horseback).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a man of brave and lively appearance, and was proficient in martial arts and good at Kisha (shooting arrows on horseback).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>天平勝宝5年（753年）大初位下だった丸子嶋足は牡鹿連の姓を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 753, MARUKO no Shimatari, whose court rank was Daihatsuinoge (Greater Initial Rank, Lower Grade) at the time, received the family name of Oshika no Muraji.</e>
<cmt>大初位下→用語統一リストより”Daihatsuinoge&quot;と訳しましたが、同じく用語統一リストのコメント欄にある参照ＵＲＬ（http://www.temcauley.staff.shef.ac.uk/rank.shtml）では”Daishoige&quot;と記載されています。インターネット検索でも”Daishoige”または”Daisoige&quot;の方が多くヒットします。姓→kabaneではなくfamily name と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 753, MARUKO no Shimatari at the rank of Daishoige (Greater Initial Rank, Lower Grade) received the family name and kabane of Oshika no Muraji.</e>
<cmt>奈良時代の「大初位下」は通常「だいしょいげ」「だいしょいのげ」「だいそいげ」「だいそいのげ」と読みます。登録単語は間違いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 753, MARUKO no Shimatari at the rank of Daishoige (Greater Initial Rank, Lower Grade) received the family name and kabane of Oshika no Muraji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天平宝字年間に嶋足は授刀衛将曹に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Tenpyo hoji era, Shimatari was appointed Shoso (assistant lieutenant) of Jyutoei (Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>将曹→Shoso (asstant lieutenant)と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Tenpyohoji era (757-765), Shimatari was appointed Shoso (assistant secretary) of Jyutoei (Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。「天平宝字」は続けて「Tenpyohoji」、「将曹」はせいぜい「secretary」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Tenpyohoji era (757-765), Shimatari was appointed Shoso (assistant secretary) of Jyutoei (Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>天平宝字8年（764年）9月、藤原仲麻呂の子の藤原訓儒麻呂が勅使を襲撃して玉璽と駅鈴を奪おうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, 764, FUJIWARA no Kusumaro, who was a child of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, attacked an imperial envoy to take away an imperial seal and ekirei (a bell needed for the exercise of imperial power).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, 764 (in old lunar calendar), FUJIWARA no Kusumaro, who was a child of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, attacked an imperial envoy to take away gyokuji (imperial seal) and ekirei (bell needed for the exercise of imperial power).</e>
<cmt>月を旧暦のままにして説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, 764, FUJIWARA no Kusumaro, who was a child of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, attacked an imperial envoy to take away gyokuji (imperial seal) and ekirei (bell needed for the exercise of imperial power).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>嶋足は授刀衛少尉坂上苅田麻呂とともに勅命を受けて馳せかけて、訓儒麻呂を射殺した（藤原仲麻呂の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving an imperial order, Shimatari and SAKANOUE no Karitamaro, Shojo (junior lieutenant) of Jyutoei, hastened there and shot Kusumaro to death (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Receiving an imperial order, Shimatari and SAKANOUE no Karitamaro, Shojo (junior lieutenant) of Jyutoei, hastened there and shot Kusumaro to death (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving an imperial order, Shimatari and SAKANOUE no Karitamaro, Shojo (junior lieutenant) of Jyutoei, hastened there and shot Kusumaro to death (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この功により従四位下勳二等を授かり、宿禰姓を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this distinguished service, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Kun nito (Order of Second Class), and received the kabane of Sukune.</e>
<cmt>(宿禰)姓→kabaneと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this distinguished service, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Kun nito (Order of Second Class), and received the kabane of Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this distinguished service, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Kun nito (Order of Second Class), and received the kabane of Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>授刀少将兼相模国守、近衛府員外中将に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was concurrently appointed Juto no shosho (minor captain of the Division of Inner Palace Guards), Sagami no kuni no kami (a governor of Sagami Province) and supernumerary chujo (middle captain) of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was concurrently appointed Juto-no-shosho (minor captain of the Division of Inner Palace Guards), Sagami no kuni no kami (governor of Sagami Province) and ingai-chujo (supernumerary middle captain) of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was concurrently appointed Juto-no-shosho (minor captain of the Division of Inner Palace Guards), Sagami no kuni no kami (governor of Sagami Province) and ingai-chujo (supernumerary middle captain) of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>道嶋と本姓を改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed his main name to Michishima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his family name to Michishima.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his family name to Michishima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>天平神護2年（766年）正四位上に進み、その後、内廐頭、下総国、播磨国などの国司を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 766, he was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and subsequently served as uchiumayagashira (内廐頭) and kokushi (provincial governor) of Shimousa Province, Harima Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>内廐頭→uchiumayagashira［正しい読み方が不明です］</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 766, he was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and subsequently served as uchi-no-umaya-no-kami (manager of stables of the Imperial Palace) and Kuni-no-mikotomochi (provincial governor) of Shimousa Province, of Harima Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 766, he was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and subsequently served as uchi-no-umaya-no-kami (manager of stables of the Imperial Palace) and Kuni-no-mikotomochi (provincial governor) of Shimousa Province, of Harima Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>陸奥在地のいわゆる蝦夷系豪族で中央官僚として立身できたのは嶋足だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among so-called local ruling families related to Emishi (northerners), who lived in the local area of Mutsu Province, Shimatari was the only person who advanced in life as a central government bureaucrat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among people from powerful families of so-called Emishi (northerners) who had ruled the local area of Mutsu Province for generations, Shimatari was the only person who succeeded as bureaucrat of the central government.</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among people from powerful families of so-called Emishi (northerners) who had ruled the local area of Mutsu Province for generations, Shimatari was the only person who succeeded as bureaucrat of the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 味っ子(id:17086), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), Libertas(id:40611), たね(id:10372), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>