<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原良相</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 良相（ふじわら の よしみ/よしあう、弘仁4年（813年）- 貞観 (日本)9年10月10日 (旧暦)（867年11月9日））は、平安時代前期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshimi (813 - November 9, 867) was a court noble who lived in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshimi (813 - November 9, 867) was a court noble who lived in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshimi (813 - November 13, 867) was a court noble who lived in the first half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>西三条大臣と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called himself Nishisanjo no otodo (literally, a minister at west Sanjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Nishisanjo-no-otodo (literally, the minister of west Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>HyphensArticlePreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Nishisanjo no otodo (literally, the minister of west Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、Nishisanjo-no-otodoのハイフンを消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal history</e>
<cmt>Pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>834年（承和 (日本)元年）に蔵人になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 834, he became Kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 834, he became Kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 834, he became Kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>承和の変に際して左少将として近衛府を率いて兵仗を収める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Jowa Incident (the incident in the Jowa era), he led Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards) as Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and succeeded in making arms laid down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jowa Incident, as Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of the Inner Palace Guards), he led the Konoefu (Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards) and succeeded in pacifying the soldiers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jowa Incident, as Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of the Inner Palace Guards), he led the Konoefu (Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards) and succeeded in pacifying the soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>848年（嘉祥元年）に参議となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Sangi (councilor) in 848.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a Sangi (councilor) in 848</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised to rejoin to cells F12, F13</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a Sangi (councilor) in 848.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加原文がピリオドで終わるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>右大弁などを経て、851年（仁寿元年）従三位中納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 851, he became Chunagon (middle counselor) at the rank of Jusani (Junior Third Rank) after assuming Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and other positions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and after serving as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right), he became Chunagon (Middle Counselor) with the rank of Jusani (Junior Third Rank) in 851 and</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cells F11, F13Capital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right), he became Chunagon (Vice-Councilor of State) with the rank of Jusani (Junior Third Rank) in 851.</e>
<cmt>Chunagon→統一表記に修正、文頭の頭文字を大文字に変更、文末のand削除、ピリオド追加原文がピリオドで終わるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>857年（天安 (日本)元年）右大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he became Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 857.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">then, in 857, became Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cells F11, F12</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in 857, he became Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に変更、&quot;he&quot;追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>859年（天安3年）正二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 859, he was awarded Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 859, he was awarded Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 859, he was awarded Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>清和天皇に娘の藤原多美子を入内させ、また周囲からの人望も厚かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had his daughter, FUJIWARA no Tamiko, enter the court as a consort of Emperor Seiwa, and was also popular among persons around him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he had his daughter, FUJIWARA no Tamiko, enter the court as a consort of Emperor Seiwa, and was also popular among his peers,</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cell F17</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had his daughter, FUJIWARA no Tamiko, enter the court as a consort of Emperor Seiwa, and was also popular among his peers.</e>
<cmt>Because削除、カンマ→ピリオドに変更原文がピリオドで終わるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このことから、政権の首座にあった兄藤原良房からは常に警戒される存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he was always watched cautiously by FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa who positioned at the head of the central government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">he was always watched cautiously by his brother, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, who was the main figure in the government.</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cell F16Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he was always watched cautiously by his brother, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, who was the main figure in the government.</e>
<cmt>Therefore追加原文の冒頭を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>866年（貞観8年）の応天門の変に際し、伴善男の告発を受け一旦は左大臣源信 (公卿)の逮捕命令を下す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Otenmon incident in 866, he once ordered, receiving an accusation from TOMO no Yoshio, that Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Makoto (a court noble) should be captured.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Otenmon Incident in 866, after receiving a complaint from TOMO no Yoshio, he ordered the arrest of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Makoto (a court noble),</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cell F19</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Otenmon Incident in 866, after receiving a complaint from TOMO no Yoshio, he ordered the arrest of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Makoto (a court noble).</e>
<cmt>カンマ→ピリオドに変更原文がピリオドで終わるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、信の無実を訴えた良房によってこれを阻止され、以降は影響力を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the execution of this order was prevented by Yoshifusa who advocated the innocence of Makoto, and thereafter, his influence was lost.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">but the order was canceled by Yoshifusa, who vouched for Makoto&apos;s innocence and thereafter, Yoshimi&apos;s influence was lost.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to rejoin to cell F20</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the order was canceled by Yoshifusa, who vouched for Makoto&apos;s innocence and thereafter, Yoshimi&apos;s influence was lost.</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に変更原文の冒頭を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>翌867年（貞観9年）に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 867, the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 867, the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 867, the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>贈正一位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded Shoichii (Senior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously awarded Shoichii (Senior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;posthumously&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously awarded Shoichii (Senior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>今昔物語集に収録された説話の中では、次のように記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following story about him is included in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu) (The Tale of Times Now Past).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following story about him is included in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu (The Tale of Times Now Past).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following story about him is included in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動原文の一部が抜かれ空白になっていたため語句を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一旦病を得て死去し地獄で閻魔大王の目前に引き据えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became ill and died once, and was placed in front of Enma Daio (the King of Hell) in the hell.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, he became ill and died, and came before Enma Daio, or Yama, the King of Hell,</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cell F25Added Sanskrit name of &quot;閻魔大王&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, he became ill and died, and came before Enma Daio, or Yama, the King of Hell.</e>
<cmt>カンマ→ピリオドに変更原文がピリオドで終わるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、小野篁の執り成しによって赦され冥界から帰還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was absolved due to ONO no Takamura&apos;s mediation and restored his life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">but was absolved due to ONO no Takamura&apos;s mediation and returned from the realm of the dead.</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cell F24</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was absolved due to ONO no Takamura&apos;s mediation and returned from the realm of the dead.</e>
<cmt>but→However, heとしました。原文の冒頭・文末を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>息子の藤原常行は順調に出世し若くして大納言まで昇ったものの早世してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsuneyuki, his son, raised his positions smoothly in the government, reaching the post of Dainagon (Major Counselor) at a young age, but could not live long.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tsuneyuki, his son, rose smoothly in the government, reaching the post of Dainagon (Major Counselor) at a young age, but died young</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to rejoin to cell F28</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsuneyuki, his son, rose smoothly in the government, reaching the post of Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) at a young age, but died young.</e>
<cmt>Dainagon→統一表記に修正、カンマ→ピリオドに変更原文がピリオドで終わるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後公卿を輩出できず、大鏡では子孫の不振ぶり語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, not many of his family line became court nobles, and Okagami (literally, The Great Mirror: a historical story book written in the latter half of the Heian period) describes how the statues of his descendents remained low.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and thereafter, not many of the family line became court nobles, and the &quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, The Great Mirror: a historical story book written in the latter half of the Heian period) describes how his descendents remained low status.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to rejoin to cell F29</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, not many of the family line became court nobles, and the Okagami (literally, The Great Mirror: a historical story book written in the latter half of the Heian period) describes how his descendents remained low status.</e>
<cmt>文頭のand削除、Thereafterとし、原文に合わせ&quot;Okagami&quot;のクォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), UMBRO(id:100484), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>