<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千葉時胤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitane CHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitane CHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitane CHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千葉 時胤（ちば ときたね、建保6年8月11日 (旧暦)（1218年9月2日） - 仁治2年9月17日 (旧暦)（1241年10月23日））は、鎌倉時代前期の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitane CHIBA (September 2, 1218-October 23, 1241) was a warrior in early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitane CHIBA (September 2, 1218 - October 23, 1241) was a warrior in early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>年号のハイフン前後にスペースを加えたマイナーチェンジです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitane CHIBA (September 2, 1218 - October 23, 1241) was a warrior in early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>千葉氏第7代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the seventh family head of the CHIBA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the seventh family head of the CHIBA clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the seventh family head of the CHIBA clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『千葉大系図』によれば、千葉成胤の3男とされてきたが、近年になって千葉胤綱（成胤長男）の長男とする見方が有力視されている（県史『千葉県の歴史 通史編 中世』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chiba Taikeizu,&quot; the genealogical chart of the Chiba clan, shows that he was the third son of Naritane CHIBA, however, in recent years, it is generally understood that he was the first son of Tanetsuna CHIBA (the first son of Naritane) (according to &quot;Chibaken no Rekishi: Tshushi-hen Chusei&quot;[The history of Chiba Prefecture: the general history of the medieval period]).</e>
<cmt>「成胤」は「なりたね」、「胤綱」は「たねつな」と読んでいます。また、「千葉県の歴史」についてはローマ字表記とし、英訳を付け足しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the genealogical chart of the Chiba clan, &quot;Chiba Taikeizu,&quot; Tokitane was supposed to be the third son of Naritane CHIBA; however, it is considered likely that he was instead the first son of Tanetsuna CHIBA (the first son of Naritane) in recent years (according to &quot;Chibaken no Rekishi: Tshushi-hen Chusei&quot; [The history of Chiba Prefecture: the general history of the medieval period]).</e>
<cmt>原文では「〜が有力視されている」としているところを、訳文では「〜と一般的に理解されている」となっており、意味が異なっていると思います。原文にあわせ、訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the genealogical chart of the Chiba clan, &quot;Chiba Taikeizu,&quot; Tokitane was supposed to be the third son of Naritane CHIBA; however, it is considered likely that he was instead the first son of Tanetsuna CHIBA (the first son of Naritane) in recent years (according to &quot;Chibaken no Rekishi: Tshushi-hen Chusei&quot; [The history of Chiba Prefecture: the general history of the medieval period]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>千葉成胤が没した建保6年（1218年）に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1218, the same year Naritane CHIBA died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1218, the same year Naritane CHIBA died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1218, the same year Naritane CHIBA died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>安貞2年（1228年）、胤綱の死により、千葉介を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to Tanetsuna&apos;s death, he assumed the position of Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province) in 1228.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to Tanetsuna&apos;s death, he assumed the position of Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province) in 1228.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to Tanetsuna&apos;s death, he assumed the position of Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province) in 1228.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>嘉禎元年（1235年）、京都において平経高（『平戸記』著者）邸に「千葉介某の手の者」が乱入した（原因は経高の子平経氏と千葉氏家臣の間の女性問題であるという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1235, &quot;a man who worked for the Chiba no suke office&quot; broke in the residence of TAIRA no Tsunetaka (the author of &quot;Heikoki&quot; [Diary of TAIRA no Tsunetaka]) in Kyoto (the cause is believed to be the fact that Tsunetaka&apos;s son TAIRA no Tsuneuji and a vassal of the CHIBA clan were at odds with each other over a woman).</e>
<cmt>「手の者」は単数という前提で翻訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1235, &quot;a man who worked for the Chiba no suke office&quot; broke into the residence of TAIRA no Tsunetaka (the author of &quot;Heikoki&quot; [Diary of TAIRA no Tsunetaka]) in Kyoto (the cause is considered to be the discord between Tsunetaka&apos;s son TAIRA no Tsuneuji and a vassal of the CHIBA clan over a woman).</e>
<cmt>「乱入」の訳、「broke in」を「broke into」に変更しました。女性問題の訳文部分の冗長な説明を簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1235, &quot;a man who worked for the Chiba no suke office&quot; broke into the residence of TAIRA no Tsunetaka (the author of &quot;Heikoki&quot; [Diary of TAIRA no Tsunetaka]) in Kyoto (the cause is considered to be the discord between Tsunetaka&apos;s son TAIRA no Tsuneuji and a vassal of the CHIBA clan over a woman).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この時の千葉介はまだ13歳の時胤であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitane, who was only 13 years old at the time, served as the Chiba no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this incident occurred, it was Tokitane at the position of the Chiba no suke, who was only 13 years old.</e>
<cmt>原文を倒置して訳す理由はないと思います。原文に即して訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this incident occurred, it was Tokitane at the position of the Chiba no suke, who was only 13 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌2年（1236年）に下総国一宮である香取社造営（遷宮）の宣旨を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, in 1236, he received an imperial decree to transfer Katori-jingu Shrine, the highest-ranking shrine in Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt>「香取社」は「香取神宮」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year in 1236, he received an imperial decree to transfer (install the sacred symbol of a deity in a new shrine) the highest ranked shrine in Shimousa Province, Katori-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>遷宮は単に場所を移すという意味以上のものがありますので、説明の追加を行ないました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year in 1236, he received an imperial decree to transfer (install the sacred symbol of a deity in a new shrine) the highest ranked shrine in Shimousa Province, Katori-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>それが完了しない仁治2年（1241年）に24歳の若さで没し、子の千葉頼胤が後を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he died at age of 24 in 1241 before the transfer of the shrine completed, and his son Yoritane CHIBA took over the assignment.</e>
<cmt>「頼胤」は「よりたね」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he died at age of 24 in 1241 before the transfer of the shrine completed, and his son Yoritane CHIBA took over the assignment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he died at age of 24 in 1241 before the transfer of the shrine completed, and his son Yoritane CHIBA took over the assignment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>時胤の系譜の問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issues concerning Tokitane&apos;s genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issues concerning Tokitane&apos;s genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issues concerning Tokitane&apos;s genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>千葉氏の系譜の初期のものと考えられる『神代本千葉系図』などの古い系図では、時胤を胤綱の長男とし、同じ系統の伊豆山権現『般若院系図』では、その弟に頼胤の後見を務めた（次郎）を配置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the old series of genealogy including &quot;Jindaihon Chiba Keizu&quot; (the original genealogical charts of the Chiba clan), which is believed to show the early stages of the Chiba clan, say that Tokitane was the son of Tanetsuna, and in &quot;Hannyain Keizu,&quot; which was written by Gongen IZUSAN and falls in the same series, Yasutane CHIBA, who acted as guardian of Yoritane, is described as his younger brother.</e>
<cmt>「泰胤」は「やすたね」と読んでいます。また、「同じ系統」とは、「〜などの古い系図」に連なるものとして訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old series of genealogy including &quot;Jindaihon Chiba Keizu&quot; (the original genealogical charts of the Chiba clan), which is considered to be the early edition of the Chiba clan genealogy, describe that Tokitane was the eldest son of Tanetsuna, while &quot;Hannyain Keizu&quot; that falls in the same series edited by Gongen IZUSAN places Yasutane CHIBA as Tokitane&apos;s younger brother, who acted as the guardian of Yoritane.</e>
<cmt>「千葉市の系譜の初期のものと考えられる」の訳を、「千葉市の系譜の初期の段階を示していると考えられる」としています。問題はないと思いましたが、一応原文にならい修正しました。「時胤を胤綱の長男とし」の「長男」の説明が欠けていましたので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old series of genealogy including &quot;Jindaihon Chiba Keizu&quot; (the original genealogical charts of the Chiba clan), which is considered to be the early edition of the Chiba clan genealogy, describe that Tokitane was the eldest son of Tanetsuna, while &quot;Hannyain Keizu&quot; that falls in the same series edited by Gongen IZUSAN places Yasutane CHIBA as Tokitane&apos;s younger brother, who acted as the guardian of Yoritane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ところが、『吾妻鏡』によれば、胤綱の享年は21であり、建保6年当時はまだ11歳に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East&quot;), Tanetsuna was only 21 years old when he died, which means he was only 11 years old in 1218.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East&quot;), Tanetsuna was only 21 years old when he died, which means he was only 11 years old in 1218.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East&quot;), Tanetsuna was only 21 years old when he died, which means he was only 11 years old in 1218.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そこで江戸時代に『千葉大系図』が作成された際に先行系図に誤りがあるとして胤綱と時胤を兄弟として父を成胤とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, Tsunetane and Tokitane were described as the sons of Naritane in &quot;CHIBA Taikeizu&quot; when it was compiled in Edo period, with the reason being that any preceding genealogies were inaccurate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it was considered the preceding genealogies of the Chiba clan edited in earlier days had consisted of errors; when &quot;CHIBA Taikeizu&quot; (the Complete CHIBA clan genealogy) was compiled in Edo period, Tsunetane and Tokitane were described as brothers and the sons of Naritane.</e>
<cmt>前項目を引き継ぐ目的の「So,」は口語的です。「Thus」をもちいました。「先行系図に誤りがあるとして」の訳部分が不自然なものでしたので修正しました。「胤綱と時胤を兄弟として父を成胤とした」の訳文が、「胤綱と時胤は成胤の息子達」となっています。これにより意味するものは原文と同じですが、一応原文に即した形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it was considered the preceding genealogies of the Chiba clan edited in earlier days had consisted of errors; when &quot;CHIBA Taikeizu&quot; (the Complete CHIBA clan genealogy) was compiled in Edo period, Tsunetane and Tokitane were described as brothers and the sons of Naritane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ところが、時胤の生まれた年に成胤は死去しており、時胤に「次郎泰胤」と名乗る弟がいるのも誤りであるとして、泰胤を成胤の次郎すなわち「胤綱の弟・時胤の兄」とする系図に&quot;修正&quot;を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was also pointed out that Tokitane could not have a brother who called himself as &quot;Jiro Yasutane&quot; (the second son of Yasutane) because Naritane died in the same year Tokitane was born, so &quot;corrections&quot; were made to the genealogy that stated that Yasutane was the second son of Naritane, meaning, Yasutane was &quot;the younger brother of Tanetsuna and the older brother of Tokitane.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was also pointed out that Tokitane could not have a brother who called himself as &quot;Jiro Yasutane&quot; (the second son of Yasutane) because Naritane died in the same year Tokitane was born; thus &quot;corrections&quot; were made once again to the genealogy stating Yasutane as the second son of Naritane--in other words, the genealogy to describe Yasutane as the &quot;younger brother of Tanetsuna and the older brother of Tokitane.&quot;</e>
<cmt>前項目同様、「so」を用いた二文の接続を避けました。「；」によりいったん区切り、文章を始める形で明確に意味が伝わるようにしました。thatを繰り返し用いて分節化するのを避けました。コンマを用いた「meaning,」による説明追加を、ダッシュと「in other words,」によるより明確な形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was also pointed out that Tokitane could not have a brother who called himself as &quot;Jiro Yasutane&quot; (the second son of Yasutane) because Naritane died in the same year Tokitane was born; thus &quot;corrections&quot; were made once again to the genealogy stating Yasutane as the second son of Naritane--in other words, the genealogy to describe Yasutane as the &quot;younger brother of Tanetsuna and the older brother of Tokitane.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは当時『吾妻鏡』が比較的信憑性が高い歴史書として重んじられてきたことによる部分が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is largely because &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; had been valued as a relatively credible source of historical information at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This major change was made largely because &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; had been valued as a relatively credible source of historical information at the time.</e>
<cmt>「これは」をItとして始めていますが、分かりにくいため内容的に再記述すべきだと考え、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This major change was made largely because &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; had been valued as a relatively credible source of historical information at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、近年になって鎌倉時代後期の創建であるとは言え、創建当時から千葉氏と密接なつながりを有した本土寺の過去帳に胤綱の享年を31とする記述があることが問題視され、『吾妻鏡』が編纂された時に原史料からの引用を誤って「年二十一」（安貞2年5月28日庚子条）としてしまったものを更に『千葉大系図』の編者が信じて引用して、これに合わせる形で&quot;修正&quot;を行ったものと考えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, an entry in a family register of deaths kept at Hondo-ji Temple, which had been closely associated with the Chiba clan since the time of its foundation in late Kamakura period, recently became a subject of discussion because it said that Tanetsuna died when he was 31 years old, so it came to be considered that when &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; was compiled, the editors mistakenly cited Tanetsuna&apos;s age of death as &quot;21 years old&quot; (May 28 koshijo, 1228) from original historical materials and the editors of &quot;Chiba Taikeizu&quot; believed the information and made a &quot;correction&quot; accordingly.</e>
<cmt>「庚子条」の定訳が見つかりませんでした。また、「吾妻鏡」と「千葉大系図」の編者はそれぞれ複数という理解で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was regarded as noteworthy and subject of discussion yet again in recent years that Hondo-ji Temple, which had been closely associated with the Chiba clan since the time of its foundation in late Kamakura period, kept its history record and it contains an entry stating Tanetsuna&apos;s age of death as 31; thus it was concluded that the age of Tanetsuna&apos;s death was incorrectly cited as &quot;21&quot; (May 28 koshijo, 1228) when &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; was compiled referring the original historical materials, and the editors of &quot;Chiba Taikeizu&quot; believed the information on Azuma Kagami and made a &quot;correction&quot; accordingly.</e>
<cmt>原文がいろいろな例を行ったり来たり。。。構成がなっていないのが最大の原因ですが、何度も文頭を「However」で始めなくてはならないので、構文を考え繰り返しの「however」の利用を抑えました。「本土寺の過去帳」が訳文では「本土寺が残してきた死者名簿」となっていました。多少意味が異なると思いますので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was regarded as noteworthy and subject of discussion yet again in recent years that Hondo-ji Temple, which had been closely associated with the Chiba clan since the time of its foundation in late Kamakura period, kept its history record and it contains an entry stating Tanetsuna&apos;s age of death as 31; thus it was concluded that the age of Tanetsuna&apos;s death was incorrectly cited as &quot;21&quot; (May 28 koshijo, 1228) when &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; was compiled referring the original historical materials, and the editors of &quot;Chiba Taikeizu&quot; believed the information on Azuma Kagami and made a &quot;correction&quot; accordingly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、時胤が胤綱の長男でないとした場合、鎌倉時代後期に千葉氏関係者によって書かれたと言われている『源平闘諍録』に千葉氏の当主が長男に継承され続けたとする記述との矛盾や胤綱の没後「兄」である泰胤が千葉氏を継承できなかったことの説明が付かないという点で問題点が発生するため、「時胤は胤綱の長男・泰胤の兄」が実際の正しい系譜であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is now generally understood that Tokitane was the first son of Tanetsuna and the older brother of Yasutane because if Tokitane was not the son of Tanetsuna, entries found in &quot;Genpei Tojoroku&quot; (a record of Genpei battles), which is believed to be authored by members of the Chiba clan in late Kamakura period, that say that the title of family head of the Chiba clan had continued to be passed down to the eldest son of the clan would be inconsistent, while the fact that Yasutane could not take over the Chiba clan after Tanetsuna&apos;s death even though he was the &quot;older brother&quot; would be inexplicable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is now generally considered as the actual and correct genealogy that &quot;Tokitane was the eldest son of Tanetsuna and the elder brother of Yasutane,&quot; because those descriptions in &quot;Genpei Tojoroku&quot; (a record of Genpei battles) considered to be authored by the members of the Chiba clan in late Kamakura period and stating the title of the Chiba clan to be successively passed down to the eldest son of the Chiba family would be inconsistent, or the fact that Yasutane could not take over the Chiba clan after Tanetsuna&apos;s death even though he was the &quot;elder brother&quot; would be inexplicable.</e>
<cmt>原文が非常に複雑で、どうしても訳文も複雑になります。できるだけ平易になるように修正しましたが、文章が分割されていなかったのでそれでも複雑なものになってしまいました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now generally considered as the actual and correct genealogy that &quot;Tokitane was the eldest son of Tanetsuna and the elder brother of Yasutane,&quot; because those descriptions in &quot;Genpei Tojoroku&quot; (a record of Genpei battles) considered to be authored by the members of the Chiba clan in late Kamakura period and stating the title of the Chiba clan to be successively passed down to the eldest son of the Chiba family would be inconsistent, or the fact that Yasutane could not take over the Chiba clan after Tanetsuna&apos;s death even though he was the &quot;elder brother&quot; would be inexplicable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>なお、胤綱が31歳で没したとすれば、時胤は21歳の時の子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And if Tanetsuna had passed away at age of 31, it would mean that Tokitane was born when he was 21 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If Tanetsuna had passed away at age of 31, it would mean that Tokitane was born when he was 21 years old, and logically explained.</e>
<cmt>最後に「そうすれば、筋の通った説明となる」の意味を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Tanetsuna had passed away at age of 31, it would mean that Tokitane was born when he was 21 years old, and logically explained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), Dr jimmy(id:111486), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>