<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>都貞継</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MIYAKO no Sadatsugu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MIYAKO no Sadatsugu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MIYAKO no Sadatsugu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>都 貞継（みやこ の さだつぐ、延暦10年（791年）－仁寿2年5月22日_(旧暦)（852年6月13日））は、平安時代前期の官人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MIYAKO no Sadatsugu (791-June 13, 852) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) who lived in the early part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MIYAKO no Sadatsugu (791-June 13, 852) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) who lived in the early part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MIYAKO no Sadatsugu (791-June 13, 852) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) who lived in the early part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>桑原秋成の子で都腹赤の実弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of KUWAHARA no Akinari and a brother of MIYAKO no Haraka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of KUWAHARA no Akinari and a brother of MIYAKO no Haraka.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of KUWAHARA no Akinari and a brother of MIYAKO no Haraka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>都良香の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of MIYAKO no Yoshika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of MIYAKO no Yoshika.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of MIYAKO no Yoshika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>弘仁13年（822年）、兄・腹赤ら一族とともに上請してカバネを桑原公から都宿禰に改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 822 he asked the emperor to change his kabane (official status title) from Kuwaharako (桑原公) to Miyako no Sukune with his family including his brother Haraka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 822 he asked the emperor to change his kabane (official status title) from Kuwaharako (桑原公) to Miyako no Sukune with his family including his brother Haraka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 822 he asked the emperor to change his kabane (official status title) from Kuwaharako (桑原公) to Miyako no Sukune with his family including his brother Haraka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天長6年（824年）に中務省に任じられて以後、因幡国掾_(国司)、式部省、備前国掾、主計助などを歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was assigned to an official of Ministry of Central Affairs in 824, he held positions such as the jo (provincial governor) of the Inaba Province, an official of Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonial), the jo of the Bizen Province and Kazuenosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was assigned to an official of Ministry of Central Affairs in 824, and held positions such as the jo (provincial governor) of Inaba Province, an official of Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonial), the jo of Bizen Province and Kazuenosuke.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was assigned to an official of Ministry of Central Affairs in 824, and held positions such as the jo (provincial governor) of Inaba Province, an official of Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonial), the jo of Bizen Province and Kazuenosuke (Director of Account Office).</e>
<cmt>主計助の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>従五位下主計頭在任中に悪瘡のため62歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was in charge of Kazue no kami (the head of budget bureau) in the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he died of bad blotch at the age of sixty-two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was in charge of Kazue no kami (the head of budget bureau) in the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he died of a bad rash at the age of sixty-two.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was in charge of Kazue no kami (the head of budget bureau) in the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he died of a bad rash at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『日本文徳天皇実録』の卒伝には、吏部（式部省）の職務に精通して、後に同省の職務に就く者は彼の元を訪れて旧儀を習ったことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the obituary described in &quot;Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku&quot; (fifth of the six classical Japanese history texts), he knew well about the duties of Ribu (Shikibu-sho) so that a person who was assigned to the official of Shikibu-sho visited him to learn his ways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the obituary described in &quot;Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku&quot; (fifth of the six classical Japanese history texts), he knew much about the duties of Ribu (Shikibu-sho) so that a person who was assigned to the official of Shikibu-sho visited him to learn his ways.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the obituary described in &quot;Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku&quot; (fifth of the six classical Japanese history texts), he knew much about the duties of Ribu (Shikibu-sho) so that a person who was assigned to the official of Shikibu-sho visited him to learn his ways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 春秋君(id:174988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>