<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長井宗秀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munehide NAGAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munehide NAGAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munehide NAGAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長井 宗秀（ながい むねひで、1265年（文永2年） - 1327年12月20日（嘉暦2年11月7日 (旧暦)））は鎌倉時代の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munehide NAGAI (1265 - December 20, 1327) was a personality in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munehide NAGAI (1265 - December 20, 1327) was a person in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>ｐersonalityは確かに名士、有名人などの意味がありますが、多くの場合性格などの意味、またはラジオetcのパーソナリティなどの意味で使われているので、単にpersonまたはmanとした方が分かりやすいと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munehide NAGAI (1265 - December 20, 1327) was a person in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>長井時秀の子で、父が評定衆となった年に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Tokihide NAGAI and born in the year when his father became hyojoshu (a member of Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Tokihide NAGAI and born in the year when his father became hyojoshu (a member of Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Tokihide NAGAI and born in the year when his father became hyojoshu (a member of Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>18歳で引付衆、宮内権大輔となり、1293年（永仁元年）5月 (旧暦)に29歳で越訴頭人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) and Kunaigondaifu at the age of 18, and became Ossotonin (the head of legal institutions of Kamakura bakufu and Muromachi bakufu) at the age of 29, and when Sadatoki HOJO abolished Hikitsukeshu in courts, established Shisso, held the final judgment right, and changed the shogunate government from a council system to Tokuso dictatorship, he became Shisso.</e>
<cmt>宮内権大輔はKunaigondaifuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) and Kunai no Gon no Taifu (provisional senior assistant minister of Imperial Household Ministry) at the age of 18, and became Ossotonin (the head of legal institutions of Kamakura bakufu and Muromachi bakufu) in May 1293, when he was 29 years old.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処&quot;and&quot; が続き文が分かりにくいので分割しました。宮内権大輔の読みはKunai（またはKudai） no Gon no Taifuです。また訳はKunai no Gon no Taifu (provisional senior assistant minister of Imperial Household Ministry)です。年月&quot;1293年5月&quot;が訳抜けです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) and Kunai no Gon no Taifu (provisional senior assistant minister of Imperial Household Ministry) at the age of 18, and became Ossotonin (the head of legal institutions of Kamakura bakufu and Muromachi bakufu) in May 1293, when he was 29 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同年10月 (旧暦)に北条貞時が裁判機関の引付衆を廃し、執奏を設置してその最終判決権を掌握して幕政を合議制から得宗独裁へと変えたとされる際には、その執奏に就任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Shisso in October 1293 (in old lunar calendar) when Sadatoki HOJO abolished the court system Hikitsukeshu and established Shisso to seize the authority of final judgments and to shift the shogunate government from the council system to Tokuso (the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan) dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処&quot;同年10月 (旧暦)&quot;が訳抜けです。文が箇条書きのようで分かりにくいので、書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Shisso in October 1293 (in old lunar calendar) when Sadatoki HOJO abolished the court system Hikitsukeshu and established Shisso to seize the authority of final judgments and to shift the shogunate government from the council system to Tokuso (the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan) dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>執奏7人の中で北条氏以外では2名だけであり、更に7人の中で北条師時に次ぐ若さであり、北条貞時政権の重要メンバーであったことが解る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were only two Shisso who were not the Hojo clan, among the seven Shisso, and he was the second youngest following Sadatoki HOJO, indicating that he was an important member of the Sadatoki HOJO regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were only two Shisso who were not the Hojo clan, among the seven Shisso, and he was the second youngest following Sadatoki HOJO, indicating that he was an important member of the Sadatoki HOJO regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were only two Shisso who were not the Hojo clan, among the seven Shisso, and he was the second youngest following Sadatoki HOJO, indicating that he was an important member of the Sadatoki HOJO regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>またその2年後には寄合衆、及び復活した評定衆に在任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two years later, he became Yoriaishu (a member of the top decision making organ) and the restored Hyojoshu and it is considered that he probably joined Yoriaishu in May, 1293.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two years later, he became Yoriaishu (a member of the top decision making organ) and a restored hyojoshu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処先出の評定衆はHyojoshuではなくhyojoshuです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two years later, he became Yoriaishu (a member of the top decision making organ) and a restored hyojoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>おそらくは1293年（永仁元年）5月段階から寄合衆に加わっていたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that he had joined Yoriaishu in May 1293.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処it is considered で始まっているので、probably は省略しました。he joined → he had joinedとしました。May, 1293の「、」を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that he had joined Yoriaishu in May 1293.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後も1309年（延慶 (日本)2年）3月15日 (旧暦)に七番引付頭人を辞すまで、幕府、あるいは得宗家の重職についている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he held an important post of the bakufu or the Tokuso family until he resigned number 7 Hikitsuke tonin (chairman of the court of justice) on March 15, 1309.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he held an important post of the bakufu or the Tokuso family until he resigned Nanaban hikitsuke tonin (the seventh head of the legal office) on March 15, 1309.</e>
<cmt>七番引付頭人を；number 7 Hikitsuke tonin (chairman of the court of justice) からNanaban hikitsuke tonin (the seventh head of the legal office) に変更しました。Seventh head, seventh chiefmanといういみなので、number 7と入ると、頭から数えて7番目、という誤解があるかと思います。The seventh head of Hikitsuke toninでも可です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he held an important post of the bakufu or the Tokuso family until he resigned Nanaban hikitsuke tonin (the seventh head of the legal office) on March 15, 1309.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>『吾妻鏡』に於ける大江広元の顕彰記事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A commending article of OE no Hiromoto in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, and &apos;important documents and kikigaki (account of what one hears) from Kyoto in and after the Juei and Genryaku eras, petitions of people, records of suits from samurai families in Rakuchu (inside the capital), Nanto, and Hokurei, shikimoku (law codes in the itemized form, which were used in the medieval Japan) of articles of works of ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor) and the lords of manors in and after the Bunji era, and documents, such as shidai (one of component parts of a Noh play) and orders of deeds of valor of eastern samurai at battles of the Taira clan&apos; in the days of OE no Hiromoto in the article dated December 5, 1232, were scattered, and Yasutoki HOJO collected and transferred them to Yasuhide NAGAI, and judging from the estimated time of compilation, Munehide NAGAI was considered as one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;.</e>
<cmt>東士はeastern samuraiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munehide NAGAI was considered as one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), judging from a commending article of OE no Hiromoto in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), the estimated time of compilation and facts that &apos;important documents and kikigaki (account of what one hears) from Kyoto in and after the Juei and Genryaku eras, petitions of people, records of suits from samurai families in Rakuchu (inside the capital), Nanto, and Hokurei, shikimoku (law codes in the itemized form, which were used in the medieval Japan) of articles of works of ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor) and the lords of manors in and after the Bunji era, and documents and letters on details of war exploits (or distinguished services) of eastern samurai in the Battles of the Taira clan&apos; included in the article for December 5, 1232, which was the time of OE no Hiromoto, were scattered and Yasutoki HOJO had these documents collected and handed to Munehide NAGAI.</e>
<cmt>原文が長く分かりにくい上に分割できないため、訳文が分かりにくかったので、文の結論である『長井宗秀も『吾妻鏡』の編纂者のひとりとされる』を先に記載し、次にその理由を続けました。また文の構成を多少分かりやすくするため、理由の順番を前後させました。『吾妻鏡』の補足が抜けています。「shidai (one of component parts of a Noh play)」は誤訳です。用語集で「勲功次第注文＝letter on details of exploits of war (or distinguished services)」とありますので、「平氏合戦の時東士勲功の次第・注文等の文書」の訳にはこちらを使用します。「at battles of the Taira clan」を「in the Battles of the Taira clan」とします。「北条泰時がこれを集めさせ」なので、「Yasutoki HOJO had these documents collected」と直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an article of OE no Hiromoto praising Munehide NAGAI in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして同1232年（貞永元年）12月5日 (旧暦)条の、大江広元の頃の「寿永・元暦以来京都より到来する重書並びに聞書、人々の款状、洛中及び南都・北嶺以下、武家より沙汰し来たる事の記録、文治以後の領家・地頭所務條々の式目、平氏合戦の時東士勲功の次第・注文等の文書」が分散してしまった為、北条泰時がこれを集めさせ、目録とともに長井泰秀に渡したとある件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the December 5, 1232 entry of the &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; written at the same time as Oe&apos;s article, records that &apos;important documents and kikigaki (accounts of what one hears) from Kyoto in and after the Juei and Genryaku eras, petitions of people, records of suits from warrior families from within the capital (Kyoto), from the southern capital (Nara), from Mt. Hiei, as well as the shikimoku (legal codes in itemized form, used during medieval Japan) of articles of the works of absentee proprietors and lords of private estates in and after the Bunji era, and documents and letters on details of war exploits (or distinguished service) of eastern warriors in the Battles against the Taira clan&apos; were all scattered to the winds, so Yasutoki HOJO had these documents collected and handed over to Munehide NAGAI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そして推定される編纂年代から、この長井宗秀も『吾妻鏡』の編纂者のひとりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the abovementioned facts, the estimated compilation date of the &quot;Azuma kagami&quot; also suggests that Munehide NAGAI was probably one of the its compilers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ktmchi(id:113301), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>