<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>籾井教業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinari MOMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinari MOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinari MOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>籾井 教業（もみい のりなり、大永7年（1527年） - 天正4年（1576年））は、戦国時代 (日本)の丹波国の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinari MOMI (1524 - 1576) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Japan) in Tanba-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinari MOMI (1524 - 1576) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Japan) in Tanba-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinari MOMI (1527 - 1576) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>1527に訂正しました。Period小文字にしました。戦国時代の説明 (period of warring states)補足しました。Tanba Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「丹波の赤鬼」こと赤井直正と並んで武勇に優れたため、「青鬼」と呼ばれたというが、実在には疑問もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He excelled at a martial art as much as Naomasa AKAI who was called as Red ogre of Tanba and seemed to be called Blue orge, but the existence remains skeptical.</e>
<cmt>文字通り英訳しましたが、”実在には疑問もある”は、何の実在か定かでありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He excelled at the martial arts as much as Naomasa AKAI (called the Red ogre of Tanba) and it has been said that we he was called the Blue orge, but this is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He excelled at the martial arts as much as Naomasa AKAI (called the &apos;Red ogre of Tanba&apos;) and it has been said that he was called the &apos;Blue orge,&apos; but his existence is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&apos; &apos;を補足しました。we削除しました。”実在には疑問もある”は、後述より「籾井教業が実在する人物であったかどうか疑問である」の意味と解釈しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>籾井氏は16世紀に丹波国多紀郡の篠山盆地に割拠した新興の豪族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momi clan was an emerging gozoku who occupied the Sasayama basin in Tanba-no-kuni Taki-gun and expanded its power of influence there in the 16th century, and Momi Castle (currently, Sasayama City area) they were residing was located in a key spot the Sasayama basin was about to meet the Sanindo which ran from Kyoto through Tanba and to the San-in district in ancient and medieval times.</e>
<cmt>山陰道の英訳は、Sanindoに変更しました。ネットで検索すると多く使用されています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Momi clan was an emerging gozoku who occupied the Sasayama basin in Tanba-no-kuni Taki-gun and expanded its power of influence there in the 16th century. They resided in Momi Castle (currently, in the Sasayama City area), which was located in a key spot in the Sasayama basin was about to meet the Sanindo which ran from Kyoto through Tanba and to the San-in district in ancient and medieval times.</e>
<cmt>wording; I don`t really understand the red lettering, and I am not sure how it fits into the rest of the text. Can the translator break this passage up into two or more sentences?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Momi clan was an emerging gozoku (local ruling family) who occupied the Sasayama basin in Taki-gun, Tanba Province and expanded its power of influence there in the 16th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理。豪族の説明補足しました。丹波国多紀郡の表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>居城の籾井城（現在の篠山市域）は古代・中世に京都から丹波を経て山陰地方に向かう山陰道が篠山盆地に差し掛かる箇所にあたる要衝であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They resided in Momi Castle (located in the present-day Sasayama City area), which was located in a key spot near the Sasayama basin along the Sanin-do Road, a road which ran from Kyoto through Tanba to the Sanin region in ancient and medieval times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理。Sanin-do Roadに訂正しました。Sanin regionに訂正しました。ハイフン削除、Saninに訂正しました。NCのコメントに対応して書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>教業は篠山盆地の中心を抑える八上城（篠山市域）の波多野氏と姻戚関係にあり、その旗下の武将としてともに足利義昭に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinari had marital relationships with the Hatano clan in Yagami Castle (within Sasayama City) which was controlling the center of the Sasayama basin, and worked for Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as Hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) busho (warlord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinari had marital relationships with the Hatano clan in Yagami Castle (within Sasayama City) which controlled the center of the Sasayama basin, and worked for Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as the Hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) busho (warlord).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinari had marital relationships with the Hatano clan in Yagami Castle (within Sasayama City) which controlled the center of the Sasayama basin, and worked for Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as the Hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) busho (warlord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>1575年、義昭を追放して自身に反抗する丹波の諸将の討伐に取り掛かった織田信長は、明智光秀に命じて丹波の経略に取り掛からせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga ODA ousted Yoshiaki, he began with subduing several busho (warlords) in Tanba who were opposed to him, and directed Mitsuhide AKECHI to control and govern Tanba in 1575.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga ODA ousted Yoshiaki, he began to subdue several busho (warlords) in Tanba who opposed him, and instructed Mitsuhide AKECHI to govern Tanba in 1575.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga ODA ousted Yoshiaki, he began to subdue several busho (warlords) in Tanba who opposed him, and instructed Mitsuhide AKECHI to govern Tanba in 1575.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>丹波への入り口にあたる籾井城は明智勢の猛攻を受け、翌年秋に陥落、籾井氏は没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momi Castle which was composing a gateway to Tanba was heavily attacked from Akechi&apos;s forces and collapsed in autumn of the following year, resulting in the ruin of the Momi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momi Castle, serving as a gateway to Tanba, was heavily attacked by Akechi&apos;s forces, and collapsed in autumn of the following year, resulting in the downfall of the Momi clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momi Castle, serving as a gateway to Tanba, was heavily attacked by Akechi&apos;s forces, and collapsed in autumn of the following year, resulting in the downfall of the Momi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>最後の籾井城主は籾井綱利で、当時まだ20代の若さであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last castellan of Momoi Castle was Tsunatoshi MOMI and he was still young in his twenties at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The final castellan of Momoi Castle was Tsunatoshi MOMI. At the time of his position he was still young--in his twenties.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The final castellan of Momi Castle was Tsunatoshi MOMI, who was still in his twenties at the time of his position.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則のため、一文に訂正しました。Momi Castleに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>これに対し、一般に流布したところによると、最後の籾井城主は籾井教業といい、青鬼と呼ばれた勇猛な武将であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the general circulation, however, the last castellan of Momi Castle was Norinari MOMI and he was a courageous warrior called Blue ogre.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conventional knowledge holds, however, that the last castellan of Momi Castle was Norinari MOMI, and he was a courageous warrior called the Blue ogre.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conventional knowledge holds, however, that the last castellan of Momi Castle was Norinari MOMI, and he was a courageous warrior called the Blue ogre.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして彼は、明智光秀ではなく豊臣秀吉によって籾井城を攻撃されて、落城、戦死したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it is believed that he died in war because Momi Castle was destroyed by the attack of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI rather than Mitsuhide AKECHI, but this story is based on Momi-ke nikki (Diary of Momi Family), other sources, etc. that have been believed to be personally written by the offspring of former retainers of the Hatano clan and the Momi clan who survived in a civilian society through the Edo era, and seems difficult to be all considered historical facts.</e>
<cmt>下のように理解しました。旧臣→old retainers→former retainers</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he died in war, because Momi Castle was destroyed by an attack from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI rather than Mitsuhide AKECHI. However, this story is based on the Momi-ke nikki (Diary of Momi Family), as well as other sources etc. that may have been personally written by the descendents of former retainers of the Hatano clan and the Momi clan who survived as civilians through the Edo era, and may not be considered as historically accurate.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he died in war, because Momi Castle was destroyed by an attack from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI rather than Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則のため、コンマ補足、howeverを小文字にしました。原文の『』に合わせて&quot; &quot;補足しました。→一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この話は江戸時代に民間で生き延びた波多野氏、籾井氏の旧臣の子孫が書き残したという『籾井家日記』などの野史によるもので、すべてを史実と受けとることは難しいとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this story is based on the &quot;Momi-ke nikki&quot; (Diary of Momi Family), as well as other sources etc. that may have been personally written by the descendents of former retainers of the Hatano clan and the Momi clan who survived as civilians through the Edo era, and may not be considered as historically accurate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Safkan(id:423), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Raff(id:14006), Cprobot(id:97843), Jmho(id:10472), Aboshi(id:9318), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>