<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原忠文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadabumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadabumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadabumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 忠文（ふじわら の ただぶみ、貞観 (日本)15年（873年） - 天暦元年6月26日 (旧暦)（947年7月16日））は、平安時代の参議で民部卿を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadabumi (873 - July 16, 947) was a councilor in the Heian era who served as Mimbu-kyo (chief of ministry of taxation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadabumi (873 - July 16, 947) was a councilor in the Heian era who served as Mimbu-kyo (head of the Ministry of Taxation).</e>
<cmt>&quot;chief&quot;→&quot;head&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;m&apos; and &apos;t&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadabumi (873 - July 16, 947) was a councilor in the Heian period who served as Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>Heian era→Heian periodに修正、「民部卿」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は藤原氏藤原式家の参議藤原枝良（845年-917年、祖父は左大臣藤原緒嗣、父は藤原春津）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Edayoshi (845 - 917), who was from the Fujiwara-shiki family of the Fujiwara clan with his father being FUJIWARA no Harutsu and his grandfather FUJIWARA no Otsugu who served as Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Edayoshi (845 - 917), who was from the Fujiwara-shiki family of the Fujiwara Clan, with his grandfather being FUJIWARA no Harutsu and his great-grandfather FUJIWARA no Otsugu who served as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added comma &quot;father&quot;→&quot;grandfather&quot;, &quot;grandfather&quot;→&quot;great-grandfather&quot; to avoid confusionCapitalized &apos;M&apos; and &apos;L&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Edayoshi (845 - 917), who was a councilor from the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara clan, with his grandfather being FUJIWARA no Harutsu and his great-grandfather FUJIWARA no Otsugu who served as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>「参議」を訳出、「藤原式家」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は息長息継の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Okitsugu OKINAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Okitsugu OKINAGA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Okitsugu OKINAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>宇治民部卿とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Uji-no-Mimbu-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as Uji-no-Mimbu-kyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;called&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Uji no Minbukyo.</e>
<cmt>Uji no Minbukyoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>左馬頭・修理大夫などを経て939年（天慶2年）に参議に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went up the ladder of success and became a councilor in 939 after serving as Sama-no-kami (head of Samaryo) and Shuri-daibu (chief of Shuri-shoku government organization).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving as Sama-no-kami (head of the Imperial Stables of the Left) and Shuri-daibu (in charge of palace repairs and construction), he became a councilor in 939.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;He went up the ladder of success and&quot;Moved &quot;after serving as Sama-no-kami (head of Samaryo) and Shuri-daibu (chief of Shuri-shoku government organization)&quot;&quot;Samaryo&quot;→&quot;the Imperial Stables of the Left&quot;&quot;chief of Shuri-shoku government organization&quot;→&quot;in charge of palace repairs and construction&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving as Sama no kami (head of the Imperial Stables of the Left) and Shuri daibu (in charge of palace repairs and construction), he became a councilor in 939.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンをとり、Sama no kami、Shuri daibuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>翌940年（天慶3年）関東で乱を起した平将門を追討するため征東大将軍に任じられたが、関東に到着する前に将門は討たれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year (940), he was designated Seito-taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;) to quell the rebellion in Kanto (the east of Japan) staged by TAIRA no Masakado, but when he arrived there, he found himself too late because Masakado had already been killed by someone else.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, 940, he was designated Seito-taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;) to quell the rebellion in Kanto (eastern Japan) staged by TAIRA no Masakado, but before he arrived, Masakado was killed.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;in&quot;brackets→commas&quot;the east of&quot;→&quot;eastern&quot;&quot;when he arrived there, he found himself too late because Masakado had already been killed by someone else&quot;→&quot;before he arrived, Masakado was killed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, 940, he was designated Seito-taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;) to quell the war in Kanto (eastern Japan) staged by TAIRA no Masakado, but before he arrived, Masakado was killed.</e>
<cmt>乱→warに統一のため、the rebellion→the warとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>941年（天慶4年）には瀬戸内海で反乱を打つため征西大将軍となり、藤原純友を討っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 941, he was again appointed Siesei-taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) to suppress an uprising in Seto Inland Sea led by FUJIWARA no Sumitomo, and this time, he successfully attacked him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 941, he was appointed Siesei-taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) to suppress an uprising in the Seto Inland Sea led by FUJIWARA no Sumitomo, and this time, he was successful.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;again&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;he successfully attacked him&quot;→&quot;he was successful&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 941, he was appointed Seisei-taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) to suppress an uprising in the Seto Inland Sea led by FUJIWARA no Sumitomo, and this time, he was successful.</e>
<cmt>Siesei-taishogun→Seisei-taishogunに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>参議民部卿正四位下に至り、947年に没している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a councilor who served as Mimbu-kyo (chief of ministry of taxation) and was given Shoshii-no-ge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) before he died in 947.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a councilor and Mimbu-kyo and was given Shoshii-no-ge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) before he died in 947.</e>
<cmt>&quot;who served as&quot;→&quot;and&quot;Deleted &quot;(chief of ministry of taxation)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a councilor and Minbukyo and was given Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) before he died in 947.</e>
<cmt>Minbukyo, Shoshiinogeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、中納言正三位を贈られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he died, he was given Shosammi (Senior Third Rank) and the post of vice councilor of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously promoted to Shosammi (Senior Third Rank) and Vice Councilor of State.</e>
<cmt>&quot;After he died, he was given&quot;→&quot;He was posthumously promoted to&quot;Deleted &quot;the post of&quot;Capitalized &apos;v&apos;, &apos;c&apos;, &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Shosanmiとし、「中納言」を統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>馬・鷹の名手であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was good at riding a horse and game hawking.</e>
<cmt>この場合、「鷹」を鷹狩りと解釈しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was good at horse riding and falconry.</e>
<cmt>&quot;riding a horse&quot;→&quot;horse riding&quot;&quot;game hawking&quot;→&quot;falconry&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was good at horse riding and falconry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、藤原実頼の反対で平将門の乱鎮圧の恩賞が得られず、忠文の没後実頼の子孫にたたったという言い伝えが残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a story, Tadabumi, who had not been rewarded for subduing the rebellion of Masakado TAIRA due to the opposition made by FUJIWARA no Saneyori, cursed his decedents after he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a story, Tadabumi, who had not been rewarded for subduing the rebellion of Masakado TAIRA due to opposition from FUJIWARA no Saneyori, cursed Saneyori&apos;s descendants after he died.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;made by&quot;→&quot;from&quot;&quot;his&quot;→&quot;Saneyori&apos;s&quot;Spelling of &quot;descendants&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a story, Tadabumi, who had not been rewarded for subduing the TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s War due to opposition from FUJIWARA no Saneyori, cursed Saneyori&apos;s descendants after he died.</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、rebellion of Masakado TAIRA→TAIRA no Masakado&apos;s Warとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このことから悪霊民部卿とも呼ばれ、忠文の霊を慰めるため宇治に末多武利神社が創建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This caused people to call Tadabumi Akuryo-Mimbukyo (Mimbu-kyo, the evil sprit) and to build the Matafuri-jinja shrine in Uji to sooth his spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, people called Tadabumi &apos;Akuryo-Mimbukyo (Mimbu-kyo, the evil sprit)&apos; and built the Matafuri-jinja shrine in Uji to soothe his spirit.</e>
<cmt>&quot;This caused&quot;→&quot;As a result,&quot;&quot;to call&quot;→&quot;called&quot;Added inverted commas&quot;to build&quot;→&quot;built&quot;Spelling of &quot;soothe&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, people called Tadabumi &apos;Akuryo-Minbukyo (Minbukyo, the evil sprit)&apos; and built the Matafuri-jinja Shrine in Uji to soothe his spirit.</e>
<cmt>Minbukyo, Matafuri-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 らりた(id:1327), Nnh(id:474), 代言人(id:33675), Hannah(id:15935), Cprobot(id:97843), Loveless(id:129239), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), BAKU(id:55205), Chrysalid(id:89267), Kouko0515(id:100370), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>