<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原継縄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsugutada</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tsugutada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsugutada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 継縄（ふじわら の つぐただ、神亀4年（727年） - 延暦15年7月16日 (旧暦)（796年8月27日））は、奈良時代後期から平安時代初頭の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsugutada (727 – Aug. 27, 796) was a courtier from the late Nara Period to the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tsugutada (727 – Aug. 27, 796) was a courtier from the late Nara Period to the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tsugutada (727 – August 27, 796) was a courtier from the late Nara period to the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Aug.→Augustに修正、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原南家の祖左大臣藤原武智麻呂の孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the grandchild of Sadaijin FUJIWARA no Muchimaro, who was the founder of the Fujiwara Nanke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the grandchild of Sadaijin FUJIWARA no Muchimaro, who was the founder of the Fujiwara Nanke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the grandchild of Sadaijin (minister of the left) FUJIWARA no Muchimaro, who was the founder of the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Sadaijinの補足追加、「藤原南家」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>右大臣藤原豊成の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toyonari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toyonari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Udaijin (minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Toyonari.</e>
<cmt>Udaijinの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正二位・右大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Udaijin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Udaijin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>贈従一位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumously awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumously awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumously awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>桃園右大臣あるいは中山を号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Momozono Udaijin or Nakayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Momozono Udaijin or Nakayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Momozono Udaijin or Nakayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出生から藤原仲麻呂の乱まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From birth to the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From birth to the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From birth to the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro War</e>
<cmt>統一事項より、FUJIWARA no Nakamaro Rebellion→FUJIWARA no Nakamaro Warに修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>天平宝字7年（763年）37歳で従五位下となり、信濃守に任官した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 763 at the age of 37 and was appointed Shinano no kami (Governor of Shinano Province).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 763 at the age of 37 and was appointed Shinano no kami (Governor of Shinano Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 763 at the age of 37 and was appointed the Governor of Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>Shinano no kami (Governor of Shinano Province)→the Governor of Shinano Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天平宝字8年（764年）藤原仲麻呂の乱が起こると、大宰員外帥に左遷されていた父豊成が右大臣に復位すると同時に越前守に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro Rebellion occurred in 764, he became Echizen-mori at the same time his father, Toyonari, returned as Udaijin after being shunted off as Dazaiingaisochi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro Rebellion occurred in 764, he became Echizen-mori at the same time his father, Toyonari, returned as Udaijin after being shunted off as Dazaiingaisochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro War occurred in 764, he became the Governor of Echizen Province at the same time his father, Toyonari, returned as Udaijin after being shunted off as Dazai ingai no sochi (ex-officio governor general of Dazai-fu, Kyushu Government Office).</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA no Nakamaro Warとし、Echizen-mori→the Governor of Echizen Provinceに修正、「大宰員外帥」の表記を修正、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原仲麻呂は北陸道への逃亡を企てており越前は軍事的に重要な場所であった点から、軍事目的の任命であったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakamaro was planning on an escape via the Hokuriku road and Echizen was strategically important place and hence this is thought to be an order due to military reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nakamaro was planning on an escape via the Hokuriku road and Echizen was a strategically important place and hence this is thought to be an order due to military reason.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakamaro was planning on an escape via the Hokuriku-do Road and Echizen was a strategically important place and hence this is thought to be an order due to military reason.</e>
<cmt>Hokuriku road→Hokuriku-do Roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>道鏡政権・光仁朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dokyo government, Emperor Konin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dokyo government, Emperor Konin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dokyo Government, Reign of Emperor Konin</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更、Emperor Konin→Reign of Emperor Koninとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>道鏡政権下で叙位・任官を重ね、天平神護2年（766年）に参議、光仁天皇即位後の宝亀2年（771年）従三位に昇叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Dokyo government, he continued to be promoted and in 766, he became Sangi and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 771 after the succession of Emperor Konin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Dokyo government, he continued to be promoted and in 766, he became Sangi and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 771 after the succession of Emperor Konin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Dokyo government, he continued to be promoted and in 766, he became Sangi (royal advisor) and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 771 after the succession of Emperor Konin.</e>
<cmt>Sangiの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、左兵衛督・兵部卿を兼任するなど軍事畑を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later was jointly appointed to military positions such as Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards),Hyobu-kyo (chief of Hyobu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later was jointly appointed to military positions such as Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), Hyobu-kyo (chief of Hyobu).</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later was jointly appointed to military positions such as Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), Hyobu-kyo (chief of Hyobu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>宝亀11年（780年）中納言昇進後に陸奥国で蝦夷の族長伊治呰麻呂が反乱し、按察使紀広純を殺害する事件がおきると（宝亀の乱）、これを鎮圧すべく征東大使に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 780, after promotion to Chunagon, the chief of the Emishi in Michinokuni rebelled and murdered the Azechi (inspector of the provincial government)i KI no Hirozumi (Hoki Rebellion), he was appointed as Seiito taishi to settle this rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 780, after promotion to Chunagon, the chief of the Emishi in Michinokuni rebelled and murdered the Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) i KI no Hirozumi (Hoki Rebellion), he was appointed as Seiito taishi to settle this rebellion.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 780, after promotion to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), the chief of the Emishi KOREHARI no Azamaro rebelled in Mutsu Province and murdered the Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) KI no Hirozumi (Hoki War), and Tsugutada was appointed as Seito Taishi (great general who subdues the eastern barbarians) to settle this rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Chunagon→統一リストに基づき修正、「伊治呰麻呂」→訳漏れのため訳出、Michinokuni→Mutsu Provinceに修正し位置を移動、不要な&quot;i&quot;を削除、Hoki Rebellion→Hoki Warに修正、and追加、he→Tsugutadaとしました。Seiito taishi→Seito Taishiに修正、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし継縄は準備不足などを理由にして京から出発しようとせず、遂に大使を罷免されてしまった（後任大使は藤原小黒麻呂）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tsugutada refused to leave Kyoto stating lack of preparation as a reason and was finally excused from his post as Taishi (the post was given to FUJIWARA no Oguronomaro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tsugutada refused to leave Kyoto stating lack of preparation as a reason and was finally excused from his post as Taishi (the post was given to FUJIWARA no Oguronomaro).</e>
<cmt>formatted text to wrap around</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tsugutada refused to leave Kyoto stating lack of preparation as a reason and was finally excused from his post as Taishi (the post was given to FUJIWARA no Oguronomaro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし特に叱責を受けたり左遷されるなどの処分は受けていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he did not get any reprimands or demotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he did not receive any reprimands or demotions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he did not receive any reprimands or demotions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>桓武朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanmu Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanmu Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reign of Emperor Kanmu</e>
<cmt>Reign of Emperor Koninに合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>桓武天皇即位後は、延暦4年（785年）の藤原種継暗殺や、桓武の皇后藤原乙牟漏・夫人藤原旅子の相次ぐ死により藤原式家の勢力が衰えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the succession of Emperor Kanmu, FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu was assassinated in 785, and Kanmu&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Otomuro and wife, FUJIWARA no Tabiko died in succession and the Fujiwara Shikike&apos;s power declined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the succession of Emperor Kanmu, FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu was assassinated in 785, and Kanmu&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Otomuro and wife, FUJIWARA no Tabiko died in succession and the Fujiwara Shikike&apos;s power declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the succession of Emperor Kanmu, FUJIWARA no Tanetsugu was assassinated in 785, and Kanmu&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Otomuro and wife, FUJIWARA no Tabiko died in succession and the power of the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara clan declined.</e>
<cmt>the Fujiwara Shikike&apos;s power→the power of the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そのため、叙位任官も順調で、大納言を経て更に中務卿と左京大夫を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore he was steadily promoted and after becoming Chunagon, he further jointly held Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) and Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore he was steadily promoted and after becoming Chunagon, he further jointly held Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) and Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore he was steadily promoted and after becoming Dainagon (chief councilor of state), he further jointly held Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) and Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去Chunagon→Dainagon (chief councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>延暦9年（790年）右大臣にのぼり、皇太子傅・中衛大将を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 790 he reached the position of Udaijin and also was Kotaishi fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) and Nakanoetaisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 790 he reached the position of Udaijin and also was Kotaishi fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) and Nakanoetaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 790 he reached the position of Udaijin and also was Kotaishi fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) and Chue no daisho (Major Captain of the Imperial Guard).</e>
<cmt>Nakanoetaisho→Chue no daishoに修正、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>彼が太政官筆頭にいた時期の重要事項として、延暦11年（792年）全国の兵士を廃止して健児を置いたことがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An important event during the time he was at the top of the Dajokan was that he abolished the national soldier system in placed Kenji in 792.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An important event during the time he was at the top of the Dajokan was that he abolished the national soldier system in Kenji in 792.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An important event during the time he was at the top of the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) was that he abolished the national soldier system and placed Kondei (&apos;stalwart youth&apos;) in 792.</e>
<cmt>Ｄａｊｏkan→Daijokanに修正・補足追加、「健児を置いた」の解釈が異なるため、訳文を修正しました。(参考: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=04S4YdDarD0C&amp;pg=PA180&amp;dq=kondei+stalwart+youth&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=4#v=onepage&amp;q=kondei%20stalwart%20youth&amp;f=false)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>延暦13年（794年）の平安京遷都に深く関わったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was deeply involved in the move to Heiankyo in 794.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was deeply involved in the move to Heiankyo in 794.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was deeply involved in the move to Heiankyo in 794.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>『続日本紀』の編纂者として挙げられているが彼の生前には一部分しか出来上がっておらず、実際に関与した部分は少なかったと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is considered as an editor of the &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) but only part of it was finished while he was alive so it is thought that he was actually involved in only a small part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is considered as an editor of the &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) but only part of it was finished while he was alive so it is thought that he was actually involved in only a small part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is considered as an editor of the &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) but only part of it was finished while he was alive so it is thought that he was in fact involved in only a small part.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去actually →in fact</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また夫人が渡来系氏族出身であったためか、同じく百済系渡来氏族出身とされる高野新笠を母に持つ桓武天皇からの個人的信頼が厚かった政治家の一人であり、天皇が継縄の邸に訪れることもしばしばであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to be one of the politicians who had the personal trust of Emperor Kanmu and that Kanmu frequently visited his residence because his wife was from a Torai clan and Kanmu&apos;s mother, TAKANO no Niigasa, is said to be from a Torai clan originally from Kudara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to be one of the politicians who had the personal trust of Emperor Kanmu and that Kanmu frequently visited his residence because his wife was from a Torai clan and Kanmu&apos;s mother, TAKANO no Niigasa, is said to be from a Torai clan originally from Kudara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to be one of the politicians who had the personal trust of Emperor Kanmu and that Kanmu frequently visited his residence because his wife was from a immigrant family and Kanmu&apos;s mother, TAKANO no Niigasa, is said to be from a immigrant family originally from Kudara (Paekche).</e>
<cmt>「渡来系氏族」→a Torai clanとありますが、意味が不明確なため、a immigrant familyとし、Kudaraの英語表記を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その際に百済王氏一族を率いて百済楽を演奏させたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one event, he had the Kudara O clan perform Kudaragaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one event, he had the Kudara O clan perform Kudaragaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one event, he had the Kudaranokonikishi clan perform Kudara-gaku (music of Paekche).</e>
<cmt>the Kudara O clan→the Kudaranokonikishi clanに修正、Kudara-gakuとし、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『日本後紀』の薨伝によれば、凡庸な人物であるが人柄はよかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the koden (memorial records) in &apos; Nihon Koki&apos; (Later Chronicle of Japan), he was an ordinary man, but had a good personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the koden (memorial records) in &apos; Nihon Koki&apos; (Later Chronicle of Japan), he was an ordinary man, but had a good personality.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the koden (memorial records) in &quot;Nihon Koki&quot; (Later Chronicle of Japan), he was an ordinary man, but had a good personality.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションに変更、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>没後に従一位が贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was posthumously given Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously given Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously given Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Corruptresearcher(id:9264), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Point136(id:211299), 春秋君(id:174988), Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>