<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一色数馬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazuma ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuma ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuma ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一色 数馬（いっしき かずま、生年不詳 - 天正18年（1590年））は、安土桃山時代の武将・国人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazuma ISSHIKI (? - 1590) was an Azuchi-Momoyama period military commander and statesman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuma ISSHIKI (? - 1590) was an Azuchi-Momoyama period military commander and statesman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuma ISSHIKI (year of birth unknown - 1590) was an Azuchi-Momoyama period military commander and Kokujin (local samurai)とする。</e>
<cmt>?→year of birth unknown国人の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>現在の千葉県野田市木野崎に城を構え、付近を領地としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He erected a castle in what today is Kinosaka in the city of Noda in Chiba Prefecture, and had dominion over the surrounding territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He erected a castle in what today is Kinosaka in the city of Noda in Chiba Prefecture, and had dominion over the surrounding territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He erected a castle in what today is Kinosaki in the city of Noda in Chiba Prefecture, and had dominion over the surrounding territory.</e>
<cmt>Kinosaka→Kinosaki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後北条氏に属しており、天正18年（1590年）、小田原の役にともなう豊臣軍の侵攻を受け、現在の野田市木野崎付近で交戦したものの敗北し、付近の寺院に逃れ自害したと言い伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He belonged to the Gohojo clan, and participated with them in the 1590 battle of Odawara, in which he bore the brunt of the invasion by (Hideyoshi) Toyotomi&apos;s army; he was defeated in a battle that took place near modern-day Kinosaka in the city of Noda, after which it is said he fled to a nearby temple and there ended his own life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He belonged to the Gohojo clan, and participated with them in the 1590 battle of Odawara, in which he bore the brunt of the invasion by (Hideyoshi) Toyotomi&apos;s army; he was defeated in a battle that took place near modern-day Kinosaka in the city of Noda, after which it is said he fled to a nearby temple and there ended his own life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He belonged to the Gohojo clan, and participated with them in the 1590 battle of Odawara, in which he bore the brunt of the invasion by (Hideyoshi) Toyotomi&apos;s army; he was defeated in a battle that took place near modern-day Kinosaki in the city of Noda, after which it is said he fled to a nearby temple and there ended his own life.</e>
<cmt>Kinosaka→Kinosaki</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Blueroses5327(id:97718), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>