<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日高 (僧侶)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko (Buddhist priest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko (a Buddhist priest)</e>
<cmt>冠詞追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko (a Buddhist priest)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日高（にちこう、正嘉元年（1257年）- 正和3年4月26日_(旧暦)（1314年6月9日））は、鎌倉時代後期の日蓮宗の僧侶で法華経寺第2代貫首とされている人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko (1257 - June 9, 1314) was a priest of Nichiren school of Buddhism and supposedly the second Kanju (or Kanshu, meaning the head priest) of Hokekyo-ji Temple, who lived in the later Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko (1257-June 9, 1314) was a priest of Nichiren sect of Buddhism and supposedly the second Kanju (or Kanshu, meaning the head priest) of Hokekyo-ji Temple, who lived in the later Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン前後のスペース削除、schoolをsectに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko (1257-June 9, 1314) was a priest of Nichiren sect of Buddhism and supposedly the second Kanju (or Kanshu, meaning the head priest) of Hokekyo-ji Temple, who lived in the later Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日蓮面授の弟子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko was a direct disciple of Nichiren from whom important teachings had been passed down by word of mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko was a direct disciple of Nichiren from whom important teachings had been passed down by word of mouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko was a direct disciple of Nichiren from whom important teachings had been passed down by word of mouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は下総国千葉氏の家臣で日蓮の有力な壇越であった太田乗明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko&apos;s father was Jomyo OTA who was a feudal retainer to the Chiba clan of Shimousa Province and was Nichiren&apos;s powerful supporter (&apos;Danetsu&apos; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>講談社日本人名大辞典等では「大田」の字が使われています。http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%97%A5%E9%AB%98</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko&apos;s father was Jomyo OTA who was a feudal retainer of the Chiba clan of Shimousa Province and was Nichiren&apos;s powerful supporter (&apos;Danetsu&apos; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>前置詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko&apos;s father was Jomyo OTA who was a feudal retainer of the Chiba clan of Shimousa Province and was Nichiren&apos;s powerful supporter (&apos;Danetsu&apos; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称は帥（そつ）公。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko was commonly called Sotsu-ko (literally, Lord Leader).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko was commonly called Sotsu-ko (literally, Lord Leader).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko was commonly called Sotsu-ko (literally, Lord Leader).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>太田乗明は同僚の富木常忍（日常）とともに迫害されていた日蓮を自領のある下総国八幡荘（現在の千葉県市川市）に受け入れた事で知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomyo OTA became known after accepting Nichiren, who and his colleague Jonin (Tsunenobu) TOKI (who was called Nichijo as Buddhist priest) had been under persecution, to his territory in Yawatanosho of Shimousa Province (present-day Ichikawa City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomyo OTA, together with his colleague Jonin (Tsunenobu) TOKI (who was called Nichijo as Buddhist priest), became known after accepting Nichiren, who had been under persecution, to his territory in Yawatanosho of Shimousa Province (present-day Ichikawa City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>富木は太田の同僚であるので、そのように訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomyo OTA, together with his colleague Jonin (Tsunenobu) TOKI (who was called Nichijo as Buddhist priest), became known after accepting Nichiren, who had been under persecution, to his territory in Yawatanosho of Shimousa Province (present-day Ichikawa City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その際、乗明は中山にあった持仏堂を寄進して「本妙寺」とし、常忍は中山の隣村である若宮に「法花寺」を造営した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When inviting Nichiren in, Jomyo donated a Jibutsu-do (temple building enshrining a Buddhist statue for private, individual worship) in Nakayama for a &quot;Honmyo-ji Temple,&quot; and built a new &quot;Hokke-ji Temple&quot; in Wakamiya, a village next to Nakayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When inviting Nichiren in, Jomyo donated a Jibutsu-do (temple building enshrining a Buddhist statue for private, individual worship) named &apos;Honmyo-ji Temple&apos;in Nakayama, and Jonin built &apos;Hokke-ji Temple&apos; in Wakamiya, a village next to Nakayama.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマーク変更、「常忍」を追加、a newを削除、forをnamedに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When inviting Nichiren in, Jomyo donated a Jibutsu-do (temple building enshrining a Buddhist statue for private, individual worship) named &apos;Honmyo-ji Temple&apos;in Nakayama, and Jonin built &apos;Hokke-ji Temple&apos; in Wakamiya, a village next to Nakayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この両寺が後の法華経寺の基となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those two temples (i.e. the Honmyo-ji Temple and the Hokke-ji Temple), were to become the base of the future Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those two temples (i.e. the Honmyo-ji Temple and the Hokke-ji Temple), were to become the base of later Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>futureをlaterに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those two temples (i.e. the Honmyo-ji Temple and the Hokke-ji Temple), were to become the base of later Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>日高は身延山に隠棲した日蓮の世話係をしながらその教説を直接学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko took care of Nichiren, who lived in seclusion in Mt. Minobu, while learning Nichiren&apos;s teachings directly from him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko took care of Nichiren, who lived in seclusion in Mt. Minobu, while learning Nichiren&apos;s teachings directly from him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko took care of Nichiren, who lived in seclusion in Mt. Minobu, while learning Nichiren&apos;s teachings directly from him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>弟子入りの時期については建治元年（1275年）が通説とされているが、それ以前の文永9年（1272年）に日蓮によって書かれたとされている「弁殿御消息」の中において、日蓮が日高を「そつ」と呼んでいた事が分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly believed that Nichiko became the pupil of Nichiren in 1275, and there remains such a passage in the &quot;Bendono Goshosoku&quot; (a collection of letters from Nichiren to Ben no ajari [acarya or Master Ben, referring to Nissho]), whose authorship is attributed to Nichiren, that Nichiren called Nichiko &quot;Sotsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>弁殿御消息参考：[1] http://www.mitene.or.jp/~hokkekou/gosyo/benndonogosyousoku.htm [2] http://www.nichirenshoshu.or.jp/page/jpn/link/kyogaku/gosho/017.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly believed that Nichiko became the pupil of Nichiren in 1275, and there remains such a passage in the &quot;Bendono Goshosoku&quot; (a collection of letters from Nichiren to Ben no ajari [acarya or Master Ben, referring to Nissho]) in 1272, which is attributed to Nichiren, that Nichiren called Nichiko &quot;Sotsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>年号抜けを追加、whichに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly believed that Nichiko became the pupil of Nichiren in 1275, and there remains such a passage in the &quot;Bendono Goshosoku&quot; (a collection of letters from Nichiren to Ben no ajari [acarya or Master Ben, referring to Nissho]) in 1272, which is attributed to Nichiren, that Nichiren called Nichiko &quot;Sotsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この生活は自らの手で師・日蓮の死を看取る26歳の時まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko continued taking care of his master Nichiren until the time when he was 26 and attended the master on his deathbed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko continued taking care of his master Nichiren until the time when he was 26 and attended the master on his deathbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko continued taking care of his master Nichiren until the time when he was 26 and attended the master on his deathbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、日高は帰国して本妙寺に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nichiren&apos;s death, Nichiko returned home and entered the Honmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nichiren&apos;s death, Nichiko returned home and entered Honmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nichiren&apos;s death, Nichiko returned home and entered Honmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その頃、富木常忍は出家して「日常」と名乗って法花寺で布教活動にあたっていたが、日高は父親との縁から日常とも師弟関係を結んで法花寺の仕事も手伝うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time Jonin (Tsunenobu) TOKI, who had entered Buddhist priesthood and called himself &apos;Nichijo,&apos; was actively engaged in the propagation of Buddhism at the Hokke-ji Temple, and Nichiko became the pupil of Nichijo, with whom he had a common acquaintance in his father Jomyo OTA, and started to assist Nichijo at the Hokke-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Jonin (Tsunenobu) TOKI, who had entered Buddhist priesthood and called himself &apos;Nichijo,&apos; was actively engaged in the propagation of Buddhism at Hokke-ji Temple, and Nichiko became the pupil of Nichijo, with whom he had a common acquaintance to his father Jomyo OTA, and started to assist Nichijo at Hokke-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>前置詞変更、冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Jonin (Tsunenobu) TOKI, who had entered Buddhist priesthood and called himself &apos;Nichijo,&apos; was actively engaged in the propagation of Buddhism at Hokke-ji Temple, and Nichiko became the pupil of Nichijo, with whom he had a common acquaintance to his father Jomyo OTA, and started to assist Nichijo at Hokke-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>永仁7年（1299年）に日常が病死すると、その遺言により本妙寺に留まったまま法花寺の貫首に就任し、以後両寺院の貫首は同一人物が務める規則が成立して、後の中山法華経寺への発展の基礎となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1299 Nichijo died of illness, who left a will to designate Nichiko to an office of Kanju (or Kanshu, the head priest) of the Hokke-ji Temple while remaining at the Honmyo-ji Temple, thereby establishing a rule that a single individual be appointed Kanju of the both Honmyo-ji and Hokke-ji Temples since then, which laid the foundation of development of the two temples to be united to form the single Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1299, Nichijo died of illness, who left a will to designate Nichiko to the office of Kanju (or Kanshu, the head priest) of Hokke-ji Temple while remaining at Honmyo-ji Temple, thereby establishing a rule that a single individual was appointed Kanju of both Honmyo-ji and Hokke-ji Temples since then, which laid the foundation for development of the two temples to be united to form single Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、過去化、ofをforに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1299, Nichijo died of illness, who left a will to designate Nichiko to the office of Kanju (or Kanshu, the head priest) of Hokke-ji Temple while remaining at Honmyo-ji Temple, thereby establishing a rule that a single individual was appointed Kanju of both Honmyo-ji and Hokke-ji Temples since then, which laid the foundation for development of the two temples to be united to form single Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>日高は日蓮面授の弟子としてその教えを広める事に力を尽くす一方、日常の旧主であり、千葉氏当主の継承権のある千葉胤貞を俗別当に迎えて下総国千田荘の多くの土地の寄進を受けて末寺の拡大と寺院財政の安定化を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiko, on one hand, devoted himself to dissemination of Nichiren&apos;s teachings that he had been taught direct by word of mouth, and on the other hand, greatly contributed to development of his temples by inviting Tanesada CHIBA, who was the former employer of the late Nichijo and was a potential successor to head of the Chiba clan, to an office of Zoku betto (lay administrator) for the purposes of increasing branch temples in number based on Tanesada&apos;s donation of plentiful landholdings in Sendasho, Shimousa Province, and stabilizing the finance of his temples.</e>
<cmt>千田荘は千田庄と書くことのほうが多いようです。また、読みは、「せんだしょう・せんだのしょう」の他、「ちだのしょう」（根拠は不明）もあるようです。http://21dzk.l.u-tokyo.ac.jp/INBUDS/search.php?m=trdd&amp;usid=40325&amp;a=</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiko, on one hand, devoted himself to dissemination of Nichiren&apos;s teachings that he had been taught directly by word of mouth, and on the other hand, greatly contributed to development of his temples by inviting Tanesada CHIBA, who was the former employer of Nichijo and was a potential successor to head of the Chiba clan, to an office of Zoku betto (lay administrator) for the purposes of increasing branch temples in number based on Tanesada&apos;s donation of plentiful landholdings in Sendasho, Shimousa Province, and stabilizing the finance of his temples.</e>
<cmt>the late削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiko, on one hand, devoted himself to dissemination of Nichiren&apos;s teachings that he had been taught directly by word of mouth, and on the other hand, greatly contributed to development of his temples by inviting Tanesada CHIBA, who was the former employer of Nichijo and was a potential successor to head of the Chiba clan, to an office of Zoku betto (lay administrator) for the purposes of increasing branch temples in number based on Tanesada&apos;s donation of plentiful landholdings in Sendasho, Shimousa Province, and stabilizing the finance of his temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、自分の後継者には胤貞の猶子である日祐を選んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Nichiko nominated Nichiyu, who was a yushi (a nephew or an adopted son) of Tanesada, to be the next head priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Nichiko nominated Nichiyu, who was a yushi (a nephew or an adopted son) of Tanesada, to be the next head priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, Nichiko nominated Nichiyu, who was a yushi (a nephew or an adopted son) of Tanesada, to be the next head priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>日祐は後に名僧として名を残して中山門流を確立した功績は、今日でも高く評価されているところであり日高の弟子を見る目は確かなものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiyu is known as a distinguished priest due to his achievement of establishing the Nakayama-monryu school, which is still highly estimated today, thus proving that Nichiko had a sharp eye for his pupils.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiyu is known as a distinguished priest due to his achievement of establishing the Nakayama-monryu school, which is still highly estimated today, thus proving that Nichiko had a sharp eye for his pupils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiyu is known as a distinguished priest due to his achievement of establishing the Nakayama-monryu school, which is still highly estimated today, thus proving that Nichiko had a sharp eye for his pupils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、同時に千葉胤貞との密着は胤貞自身が盟主として擁立された千葉氏の家督争いに門流を直接巻き込む事になってしまい、結果的に世俗勢力や他宗との関係を保ちながら門流の維持を優先する路線を選択することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiyu, however, left a bitter legacy such that his close adherence to Tanesada CHIBA entangled his school in conflict over succession of the Chiba family head among the potential successors, which resulted in his school adopting a policy which gave priority to carry on while having a cooperative relationship with secular power and the other sects.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiyu, however, left a bitter legacy such that his close adherence to Tanesada CHIBA entangled his school in conflict over succession of the Chiba family head among the potential successors, which resulted in his school adopting a policy which gave priority to carry on the school while having a cooperative relationship with secular powers and the other sects.</e>
<cmt>複数化、余分スペースの削除、目的語補完しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiyu, however, left a bitter legacy such that his close adherence to Tanesada CHIBA entangled his school in conflict over succession of the Chiba family head among the potential successors, which resulted in his school adopting a policy which gave priority to carry on the school while having a cooperative relationship with secular powers and the other sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これが後に同門流から出た日親の不受不施義より激しく非難の対象としてあげられる遠因ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became a remote cause of severe criticism by Nisshin who was a future generation preceptor of the Nakayama-monryu school and known as a passionate supporter of the Fuju-fuse-gi (a slogan of &quot;Accept nothing from non-believers and give nothing to them&quot;).</e>
<cmt>不受不施義：[1] http://kotobank.jp/word/%E4%B8%8D%E5%8F%97%E4%B8%8D%E6%96%BD%E6%B4%BE [2] http://books.google.com/books?id=LMmX8OJ4RLUC&amp;pg=PA295&amp;dq=Nisshin,+fuju+fuse&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=wu4fTP-ZDomqcbGC-O4M&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Nisshin%2C%20fuju%20fuse&amp;f=false</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became a remote cause of severe criticism by Nisshin who was a future generation preceptor of the Nakayama-monryu school and known as a passionate supporter of the Fuju-fuse-gi (a slogan of &quot;Accept nothing from non-believers and give nothing to them&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became a remote cause of severe criticism by Nisshin who was a future generation preceptor of the Nakayama-monryu school and known as a passionate supporter of the Fuju-fuse-gi (a slogan of &quot;Accept nothing from non-believers and give nothing to them&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), R28Bot(id:177951), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>