<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大石良雄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshio OISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大石 良雄（おおいし よしお／よしたか）は、播磨国赤穂藩の筆頭家老。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI was Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) of Ako Domain in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshio OISHI held the rank of Hittokaro (the head of chief retainers) of Ako Domain in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI held the rank of Hittokaro (the head of chief retainers) of Ako Domain in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元禄赤穂事件で名を上げ、これを題材とした忠臣蔵で有名になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gained prominence in Genroku Ako Incident and this is a subject matter of Chushingura (The treasury of Loyal Retainers), which made him famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gained prominence during the Genroku Ako Incident, recounted in the Chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers), which made him famous.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gained prominence during the Genroku Ako Incident, recounted in the Chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers), which made him famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>内蔵助（くらのすけ 内藏助）は通称であり、内蔵寮の次官のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke (a position of the Bureau of Palace Storehouses) is a common name and refers to undersecretary of Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke (a position of the Bureau of Palace Storehouses) is a common name and refers to the undersecretary of Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke (a position of the Bureau of Palace Storehouses) is a common name and refers to the undersecretary of Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses).</e>
<cmt>「Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>諱は良雄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Yoshio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first name was Yoshio.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first name was Yoshio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本姓は藤原氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main name was Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last name was Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His last name was Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>家紋は右二ツ巴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest was Migi-Futatsudomoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family crest was the Migi-Futatsudomoe.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family crest was the Migi-Futatsudomoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place of origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birthplace</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birthplace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>大石家は藤原秀郷の末裔小山氏の一族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OISHI family was one of Oyama clan, who were descendants of FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The OISHI family was a branch of the Oyama clan, who were descendants of FUJIWARA Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The OISHI family was a branch of the Oyama clan, who were descendants of Hidesato FUJIWARA.</e>
<cmt>「FUJIWARA Hidesato」を「Hidesato FUJIWARA」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>代々近江国守護佐々木氏のもとで栗太郡大石庄（滋賀県大津市大石東町・大石中町）の下司職をつとめていたため、大石を姓にするようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For generations the family was a local official to manage a shoen estate of Kurita gun Oishi sho (Oishi-Higashi cho, Oishi-Naka cho in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) under Sasaki clan, Omi-no-kuni shugo (Military Commissioner of Omi-no-kuni) and thus the family name became OISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For generations the family managed the Kurita estate of Oishi manor (currently Oishi-Higashi cho and Oishi-Naka cho districts in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) under the Omi-no-kuni shugo (Military Commissioner of Omi-no-kuni) of the Sasaki clan, and thus the family name became OISHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For generations the family managed the Kurita estate of Oishi manor (currently Oishi-Higashi cho and Oishi-Naka cho districts in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) under the Omi-no-kuni shugo (Military Commissioner of Omi-no-kuni) of the Sasaki clan, and thus the family name became OISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、大石氏は応仁の乱などで没落したが、大石良信の代には豊臣秀次に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Oishi clan declined in Onin war and so on, but Yoshinobu OISHI served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu OISHI served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, although subsequently the Oishi clan chose not fight in conflicts such as the Onin war.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu OISHI served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, although subsequently the Oishi clan chose not fight in conflicts such as the Onin war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>秀次失脚後、良信の庶子にして次男の大石良勝（良雄の曽祖父）は京で仏門に入れられたが、京を脱走し江戸で浪人した後、浅野家に仕えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hidetsugu&apos;s downfall, Yoshikatsu OISHI (Yoshio&apos;s great-grandfather), who was a child born out of wedlock and the second son of Yoshinobu, was made to enter the Buddhist priesthood in Kyoto, but he escaped from Kyoto and became ronin(masterless samurai) in Edo and after that, he came to serve Asano clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hidetsugu&apos;s defeat, Yoshikatsu OISHI (Yoshio&apos;s great-grandfather and the illegitimate second son of Yoshinobu), was made to enter the Buddhist priesthood in Kyoto, whereupon he escaped to Edo and became ronin(masterless samurai) in Edo where he came to serve the Asano clan.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hidetsugu&apos;s defeat, Yoshikatsu OISHI (Yoshio&apos;s great-grandfather and the illegitimate second son of Yoshinobu), was made to enter the Buddhist priesthood in Kyoto, whereupon he escaped to Edo and became ronin(masterless samurai) in Edo where he came to serve the Asano clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>良勝は、大坂夏の陣での戦功が著しかったため、浅野長政の三男浅野長重（長矩の曽祖父で常陸国真壁・笠間藩主）の永代家老に取り立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Yoshikatsu had done a distinguished war service in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), he was appointed to permanent Karo (chief retainer) of Nagashige ASANO (Naganori ASANO&apos;s great-grandfather and the lord of Kasama Domain, Hitachi Province Makabe) who was the third son of Nagamasa ASANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Yoshikatsu had distinguished himself during the Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), he was appointed permanent Karo (chief retainer) of Nagashige ASANO (the great-grandfather of Naganori ASANO and lord of Kasama Domain and the Hitachi Province Makabe), the third son of Nagamasa ASANO.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Yoshikatsu had distinguished himself during the Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), he was appointed permanent Karo (chief retainer) of Nagashige ASANO (the great-grandfather of Naganori ASANO and lord of Kasama Domain and the Hitachi Province Makabe), the third son of Nagamasa ASANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>長重の長男・長直は赤穂に転封されたので、大石家も赤穂に移ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naganao, the first son of Nagashige, was made to change the territory in Ako and accordingly Oishi family moved to Ako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oishi family relocated to the Ako region when Naganao, the first son of Nagashige, was assigned to that region.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oishi family relocated to the Ako region when Naganao, the first son of Nagashige, was assigned to that region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>良勝の長男大石良欽も赤穂藩浅野家の筆頭家老となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka OISHI, the first son of Yoshikatsu, also became Hitto karo of Ako Domain, Asano family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka OISHI, the first son of Yoshikatsu, also became the Hittokaro (the head of chief retainers) of the Ako Domain of the Asano family.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka OISHI, the first son of Yoshikatsu, also became the Hittokaro (the head of chief retainers) of the Ako Domain of the Asano family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また良勝の次男大石良重も家老となり、浅野長直（長矩の祖父）の息女鶴姫を妻に賜っており、その子の二人はいずれも浅野長直に分知されて幕府旗本（浅野長恒と浅野長武）になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshishige OISHI, the second son of Yoshikatsu, also became karo and married with Tsuruhime, the daughter of Naganao ASANO (Naganori&apos;s grandfather), and their two children, whose domains were subdivided by Naganao ASANO, became bakufu hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Nagatsune ASANO and Nagatake ASANO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshishige OISHI, the second son of Yoshikatsu, also attained the rank of karo (chief retainer) and married Tsuruhime, the daughter of Naganao ASANO (Naganori&apos;s grandfather); their two children, Nagatsune ASANO and Nagatake ASANO, whose domains were subdivided by Naganao ASANO, became bakufu hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshishige OISHI, the second son of Yoshikatsu, also attained the rank of karo (chief retainer) and married Tsuruhime, the daughter of Naganao ASANO (Naganori&apos;s grandfather); their two children, Nagatsune ASANO and Nagatake ASANO, whose domains were subdivided by Naganao ASANO, became bakufu hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>大石良欽は鳥居忠勝（鳥居元忠の子）の娘を娶り、その間に権内良昭を長男として儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka OISHI married with the daughter of Tadakatsu TORII (Mototada TORII&apos;s son) and had Yoshiaki GENNAI as their first son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka OISHI married the daughter of Tadakatsu TORII (Mototada TORII&apos;s son) and gave birth to Yoshiaki GENNAI, their first son.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka OISHI married the daughter of Tadakatsu TORII (Mototada TORII&apos;s son) and gave birth to Yoshiaki GENNAI, their first son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その大石良昭と備前国岡山藩の重臣池田由成（天城3万2,000石を領する大名並みの陪臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki OISHI and a senior vassal of Okayama Domain, Bizen Province, Yoshishige IKEDA&apos;s (daimyo (Japanese feudal lord)-like baishin (indirect vassal) who governed Amagi 3,2000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki OISHI, became the indirect vassal of Yoshishige IKEDA, a senior vassal of Okayama Domain, wielding power similar to a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), who governed the Amagi region (valued at 32,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki OISHI, became the indirect vassal of Yoshishige IKEDA, a senior vassal of Okayama Domain, wielding power similar to a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), who governed the Amagi region (valued at 32,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また実際には岡山藩池田家の本家筋に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in fact, he was in the line of head family of Ikeda clan of Okayama Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was, in fact, in line to head the Ikeda clan of the Okayama Domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was, in fact, in line to head the Ikeda clan of the Okayama Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>詳しくは池田氏や岡山藩を参照のこと）の娘池田熊子の間に長男として生まれたのがこの大石内蔵助良雄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, see Ikeda clan or Okayama Domain.) daughter, Kumako IKEDA had Kura no Suke OISHI Yoshio as their first son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, see Ikeda clan or Okayama Domain.) daughter, Kumako IKEDA had Kura no Suke OISHI Yoshio as their first son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, see Ikeda clan or Okayama Domain.) daughter, Kumako IKEDA had Kuranosuke Yoshio OISHI as their first son.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke OISHI Yoshio」を「Kuranosuke Yoshio OISHI」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>幼名は松之丞（一説に竹太郎）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Matsunojo (Taketaro in one theory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a child he went by the name of Matsunojo or possibly Taketaro.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a child he went by the name of Matsunojo or possibly Taketaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>第6代将軍御台所近衛熙子とは大石の一族、小山氏が代々近衛家諸太夫を勤める縁戚関係でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroko KONOE, the sixth shogun midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman), was one member of Oishi clan and was in relationship with Oyama clan who successively served Konoe Family Tayu (geisha of the highest rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroko KONOE, the sixth shogun midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman), was a member of the Oishi clan and served as a Tayu (geisha of the highest rank) of the Konoe family to the Oyama clan.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroko KONOE, the sixth shogun midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman), was a member of the Oishi clan and served as a Tayu (geisha of the highest rank) of the Konoe family to the Oyama clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このため、熙子の弟、近衛家熈が義士碑に揮毫している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, Iehiro KONOE, Hiroko&apos;s younger brother, did kigo (write with a brush) for the monument of gishi (loyal retainer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Iehiro KONOE, Hiroko&apos;s younger brother, produced kigo (calligraphy) for their monument of gishi (loyal retainer).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Iehiro KONOE, Hiroko&apos;s younger brother, produced kigo (calligraphy) for their monument of gishi (loyal retainer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>松の廊下の刃傷まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until Ninjo (scar by sword) on matsu no roka (literally, a corridor of pine trees).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until Ninjo (scar by sword) on matsu no roka (literally, a corridor of pine trees).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until Ninjo (scar by sword) on matsu no roka (literally, a corridor of pine trees).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>万治2年（1659年）、大石良昭の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the first son of Yoshiaki OISHI in 1659.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the first son of Yoshiaki OISHI in 1659.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the first son of Yoshiaki OISHI in 1659.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>幼名は松之丞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Matsunojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a child he went by the name as Matsunojo.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a child he went by the name as Matsunojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>延宝元年（1673年）9月6日、父良昭が34歳の若さで亡くなったため、祖父・大石良欽の養子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 6 in 1673 his father Yoshiaki died at the age of 34 and he was adopted to his grandfather Yoshitaka OISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 6,1673, his father Yoshiaki died at the age of 34 and was adopted by his grandfather Yoshitaka OISHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 6, 1673, his father Yoshiaki died at the age of 34 and was adopted by his grandfather Yoshitaka OISHI.</e>
<cmt>「1673」の前にスペースを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>またこの年に元服して喜内（きない）と称するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He celebrated his coming of age (genpuku) the same year and started to call himself &apos;Kinai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳出されていなかったので訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>延宝5年（1677年）1月26日、良雄が19歳のおりに祖父良欽が死去し、その遺領1,500石と内蔵助（くらのすけ）の通称を受け継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 26 in 1677 when Yoshio was nineteen years old, his grandfather Yoshitaka died and he succeeded to the property inheritance 1,500 koku and the common name Kura no suke (a position of the Bureau of Palace Storehouses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 26, 1677, upon the death of his grandfather Yoshitaka, Yoshio inherited at the age of nineteen 1,500 koku and the common name Kura no Suke (a position of the Bureau of Palace Storehouses).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 26, 1677, upon the death of his grandfather Yoshitaka, Yoshio inherited at the age of nineteen 1,500 koku and the common name Kuranosuke (a position of the Bureau of Palace Storehouses).</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また赤穂藩の家老見習いになり、大叔父の大石良重の後見を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he became an apprentice of chief retainer of Ako Domain and was looked after by his grand-uncle Yoshishige OISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then became an apprentice of the chief retainer of Ako Domain and was looked after by his grand-uncle Yoshishige OISHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then became an apprentice of the chief retainer of Ako Domain and was looked after by his grand-uncle Yoshishige OISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>延宝7年（1679年）、21歳のときに正式な筆頭家老となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1679 he became an official Hitto karo at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He officially became Hittokaro (head of the chief retainer) at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He officially became Hittokaro (head of the chief retainer) at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>天和 (日本)3年（1683年）5月18日には内蔵助の後見をしていた良重も世を去り、いよいよ独立しなければならなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 18 in 1683 Yoshishige, who had acted as guardian for Kura no suke, passed away and he had to be independent finally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 18, 1683, Yoshishige, who had acted as his guardian, passed away, finally forcing Kura no Suke to be independent.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 18, 1683, Yoshishige, who had acted as his guardian, passed away, finally forcing Kuranosuke to be independent.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし平時における大石は凡庸な家老だったようで、「行灯その他行灯に関わる事項」と渾名されていたことは有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in peace time, OISHI seems to have been a mediocre chief retainer and he was famous for being nicknamed &apos;andon (paper-covered lamp stand) and the others, articles on andon.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unfortunately, in peace time OISHI appeared to have been a mediocre chief retainer and he was famously nicknamed &apos;the miscellany of articles surrounding a paper lamp stand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unfortunately, in peace time OISHI appeared to have been a mediocre chief retainer and he was famously nicknamed &apos;the miscellany of articles surrounding a paper lamp stand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>したがって藩政は老練で財務に長けた家老大野知房が牛耳っていたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the administration of the Domain was dominated by a chief retainer Tomofusa OONO who was experienced and good at finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the administration of the Domain fell to the control of a chief retainer Tomofusa OONO who was experienced and good at finance.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the administration of the Domain fell to the control of a chief retainer Tomofusa ONO who was experienced and good at finance.</e>
<cmt>「 OONO」を「ONO」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>貞享4年（1686年）には豊岡藩京極氏筆頭家老、石束毎公の18歳の娘香林院と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1686 he married with Korinin who was eighteen years old and a daughter of Tsuneyoshi ISHIZUKA, Hitto karo of Kyogoku clan, Toyooka Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1686, he married Korinin who was eighteen years old and a daughter of Tsuneyoshi ISHIZUKA, Hittokaro of the Kyogoku clan of Toyooka Domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1686, he married Korinin who was eighteen years old and a daughter of Tsuneyoshi ISHIZUKA, Hittokaro of the Kyogoku clan of Toyooka Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>元禄元年（1688年）、彼女との間に長男松之丞（後の大石主税）を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1688 they had the first son Matsunojo (later, Chikara OISHI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1688 they had their first son Matsunojo (later known as Chikara OISHI).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1688 they had their first son Matsunojo (later known as Chikara OISHI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>さらに元禄3年（1690年）には長女大石くう、元禄4年（1691年）には次男大石吉之進（吉千代とも）が生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, they had the first daughter Kuu in 1690 and the second son Kichinoshin OISHI (also, Kichichiyo) in 1691.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their first daughter, Kuu, was born in 1690 followed by their second son Kichinoshin OISHI (also known as Kichichiyo) in 1691.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their first daughter, Kuu, was born in 1690 followed by their second son Kichinoshin OISHI (also known as Kichichiyo) in 1691.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>また元禄6年（1693年）には大石内蔵助は、京都にあったようで伊藤仁斎に入門して儒学を学んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in 1693 Kura no Suke OISHI seems to have been in Kyoto and studied Confucianism under Jinsai ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that in 1693 Kura no Suke OISHI began his study of Confucianism in Kyoto under Jinsai ITO.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that in 1693 Kuranosuke OISHI began his study of Confucianism in Kyoto under Jinsai ITO.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また前年に奥村重舊に入門し、東軍流を学んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the previous year he became a disciple of Shigemoto OKUMURA and learned Togun-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The previous year he had become a disciple of Shigemoto OKUMURA of the Togun-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The previous year he had become a disciple of Shigemoto OKUMURA of the Togun-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>元禄7年（1694年）2月、備中松山藩水谷氏が改易となった際、主君浅野長矩（浅野内匠頭）が収城使に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Mizutani clan of Bicchu-matsuyama Domain underwent Kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties) in February 1694, the lord Naganori ASANO (Asano Takumi no Kami) was appointed to the messenger of castle management.</e>
<cmt>「収城使」を、the messenger of castle managementとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Mizutani clan of Bicchu-matsuyama Domain underwent Kaieki (the forfeiture of samurai rank and properties) in February 1694, the lord Naganori ASANO (Asano Takumi no Kami) was appointed to the position of messenger of castle management.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Mizutani clan of Bicchu-matsuyama Domain underwent Kaieki (the forfeiture of samurai rank and properties) in February 1694, the lord Naganori ASANO (Asano Takumi no Kami) was appointed to the position of messenger of castle management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>内蔵助は先発して、改易に不満で徹底抗戦の姿勢を見せていた松山城 (備中国)に単身入り、水谷家家老鶴見内蔵助を説得して無事に城を明渡させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke departed in advance and entered Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province), who were dissatisfied with Kaieki and showed the attitude of do-or-die resistance, and persuaded Kura no suke TSURUMI, Mizutani clan&apos;s chief retainer, to surrender the castle in peace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke went in advance to Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province), where those dissatisfied with the Kaieki policy displayed an attitude of do-or-die resistance, and persuaded Kura no Suke TSURUMI, the chief retainer of the Mizutani clan, to surrender the castle in peace.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kura no Suke went in advance to Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province), where those dissatisfied with the Kaieki policy displayed an attitude of do-or-die resistance, and persuaded Kuranosuke TSURUMI, the chief retainer of the Mizutani clan, to surrender the castle in peace.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>二人が偶然同じ「内蔵助」であったことから「両内蔵助の対決」として世間で評判になったという逸話もあるが、残念ながらこれは討ち入り事件後に創作された話らしく、明確な資料に基づいているわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As both of them were accidentally &apos;Kura no suke,&apos; there was the anecdote of &apos;face-off of the two Kura no sukes&apos; in the world, but regrettably it seems to have been a fictionally created one after the raid incident and has no clear ground of documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As both of them happened to be named &apos;Kura no Suke,&apos; there exists an anecdote of a &apos;face-off between the two Kura no Sukes&apos;, although it appears to be a myth created after the seige as no evidence to support this currently exists.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As both of them happened to be named &apos;Kuranosuke,&apos; there exists an anecdote of a &apos;face-off between the two Kuranosukes&apos;, although it appears to be a myth created after the seige as no evidence to support this currently exists.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>城の受け取りが無事に済むと内匠頭は赤穂へ帰国したが、内蔵助は在番として留まり、翌年に安藤重博が新城主として入城するまでの一年半余り、松山城の管理を任せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the surrendering of the castle in peace, Takumi no Kami went back to Ako, but Kura no suke stayed there as zaiban and for about one year and half until Shigehiro ANDO entered the castle as a new castle lord in the next year, Kura no suke was in charge of the management of Matsuyama-jo castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the surrendering of the castle in peace, Takumi no Kami went back to Ako, but Kura no Suke stayed on and administered Matsuyama-jo Castle for about a year and half until Shigehiro ANDO became the new castle lord the following year.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the surrendering of the castle in peace, Takumi no Kami went back to Ako, but Kuranosuke stayed on and administered Matsuyama-jo Castle for about a year and half until Shigehiro ANDO became the new castle lord the following year.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>元禄8年（1695年）8月に赤穂へ帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went back to Ako in August 1695.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Ako in August 1695.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Ako in August 1695.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>元禄12年（1699年）には次女るりが生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second daughter Ruri was born in 1699.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second daughter Ruri was born in 1699.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second daughter Ruri was born in 1699.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>元禄13年（1700年）6月には内匠頭が参勤交代により赤穂を発つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takumi no kami left Ako for Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) in June 1700.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takumi no kami left Ako for Edo to participate in Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) in June 1700.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takumi no kami left Ako for Edo to participate in Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) in June 1700.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この時が内蔵助が主君と相見える最後の機会となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is the last time when Kura no suke saw his lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is the last time Kura no Suke saw his lord.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is the last time Kuranosuke saw his lord.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>そして運命の元禄14年（1701年）が訪れ、2月4日に江戸にある内匠頭は、東山天皇の使者として江戸へ下向する予定の勅使達の接待役を幕府より命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fatal year of 1701 came and on February 4, Takumi no kami in Edo was ordered by bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to be a person in charge of the entertainment for Imperial envoy who would leave the capital to Edo as messengers of Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 4 of the fateful year of 1701, Takumi no kami was appointed in Edo by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) head of entertainment for Imperial envoys travelling from the capital to Edo as messengers of Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 4 of the fateful year of 1701, Takumi no kami was appointed in Edo by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) head of entertainment for Imperial envoys travelling from the capital to Edo as messengers of Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>接待指南役は高家肝煎・吉良義央であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The instructor of the entertainment was Yoshinaka KIRA, Koke-kimoiri (performing good offices for nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conductor of entertainment was Yoshinaka KIRA of the Koke-kimoiri (performing good offices for nobles).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conductor of entertainment was Yoshinaka KIRA of the Koke-kimoiri (performing good offices for nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>内匠頭刃傷と浅野家お家断絶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takumi no kami&apos;s Ninjo and the extinction of Asano family line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takumi no kami&apos;s Ninjo and the extinction of the Asano family line.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takumi no kami&apos;s Ninjo and the extinction of the Asano family line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>元禄14年（1701年）3月14日、江戸城では勅使が持ってきた勅旨に対して将軍が奉答するという勅答の儀が執り行われるはずであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 14 in 1701 in Edo-jo castle, the ceremony of Emperor&apos;s reply was to be done, where Shogun would answer the Imperial paper brought by Imperial envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceremony for Imperial decree was set for March 14, 1701 at Edo-jo castle, whereupon the Shogun would respond to the Imperial proclamation brought by the Emperor&apos;s envoy.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ceremony for Imperial decree was set for March 14, 1701 at Edo-jo Castle, whereupon the Shogun would respond to the Imperial proclamation brought by the Emperor&apos;s envoy.</e>
<cmt>「 Edo-jo castle」を「Edo-jo Castle」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかしこの儀式が始まる直前、江戸城松之大廊下において勅使接待役にある浅野内匠頭が吉良上野介に対して刃傷におよんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, just before the ceremony, Asano Takumi no Kami, who was a person in charge of the entertainment for Imperial envoy, tried to cut Kira Kozuke no Suke down with a sword on matsu no roka in Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, just before the ceremony, Asano Takumi no Kami, the head of entertainment for Imperial envoy, tried to cut Kozuke no Suke KIRA down with a sword in the matsu no roka (the hallway of pines) in Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, just before the ceremony, Asano Takumi no Kami, the head of entertainment for Imperial envoy, tried to cut Kozukenosuke Suke KIRA down with a sword in the matsu no roka (the hallway of pines) in Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>「 Kozuke no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>尊皇心の厚い征夷大将軍として知られる徳川綱吉は朝廷との儀式を台無しにされたことに激怒し、内匠頭を大名としては異例の即日切腹に処し、さらに赤穂浅野家をお家断絶とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, who was Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) and had reverence for the emperor, was very angry because the ceremony with Imperial Court was spoiled and immediately ordered Takumi no Kami to commit Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) extraordinarily as daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and furthermore ordered the extinction of Asano family line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Greatly angered by this disruption to the ceremony, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, who was Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) and had reverence for the emperor, immediately ordered Takumi no Kami to commit Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and furthermore ordered the extinction of Asano family line, which was an unprecedented punishment for a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Greatly angered by this disruption to the ceremony, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, who was Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) and had reverence for the emperor, immediately ordered Takumi no Kami to commit Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and furthermore ordered the extinction of Asano family line, which was an unprecedented punishment for a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>一方、上野介には何の咎めもなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Kozuke no suke was not blamed for this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Kozuke no suke escaped blame for the incident.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kozukenosuke escaped blame for the incident.</e>
<cmt>「 Kozuke no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>早水藤左衛門と萱野三平の第一の急使、足軽飛脚による第二の急使、原惣右衛門と大石瀬左衛門の第三の急使、町飛脚による第四・第五・第六の急使、と次々に赤穂藩邸から国許赤穂市へ情報が送られ、3月28日までには刃傷事件・浅野内匠頭切腹・赤穂藩改易といった情報が出揃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stream of information came from Ako Domain&apos;s hantei (residence maintained by a daimyo in Edo) to hometown Ako City, such as the first dispatch of Tozaemon HAYAMI and Sampei KAYANO, the second one of ashigaru (common foot soldier) and express messenger, the third one of Soemon HARA and Sezaemon OISHI, and the fourth, fifth and sixth ones of town express messenger, and until March 28 information such as the affair of sword fight, Seppuku of Asano Takumi no Kami and Kaieki of Ako Domain arrived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stream of information came from Ako Domain&apos;s hantei (residence maintained by a daimyo in Edo) to the provincial capitol of Ako: the first dispatch came from Tozaemon HAYAMI and Sampei KAYANO, the second from an ashigaru (common foot soldier) and express messenger, the third from Soemon HARA and Sezaemon OISHI, and the fourth, fifth and sixth from town express messengers, until, by March 28, information such as the assassination attempt, the Seppuku of Asano Takumi no Kami and the Kaieki of Ako Domain arrived.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stream of information came from Ako Domain&apos;s hantei (residence maintained by a daimyo in Edo) to the provincial capitol of Ako: the first dispatch came from Tozaemon HAYAMI and Sampei KAYANO, the second from an ashigaru (common foot soldier) and express messenger, the third from Soemon HARA and Sezaemon OISHI, and the fourth, fifth and sixth from town express messengers, until, by March 28, information such as the assassination attempt, the Seppuku of Asano Takumi no Kami and the Kaieki of Ako Domain arrived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>27日から3日間にかけて赤穂にいる家臣に総登城の号令がかけられ、赤穂城内は江戸幕府の処置に不満で徹底抗戦を主張する篭城派と、開城すべきとする恭順派に分かれて紛糾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the vassals in Ako were ordered to come to the castle for three days from 27, and in Ako-jo castle there were the faction insisting on holding the castle, who were dissatisfied with the treatment by Edo bakufu and urging of resistance to the bitter end and the deference faction, who were insisting on surrendering the castle to the bakufu, and they were in a mess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the vassals in Ako were ordered to come to the castle for a three day stay from 27th, where they divided into two factions: one made up of those who were dissatisfied with their treatment at the hands of the Edo bakufu and insisted on holding the castle, urging of resistance to the bitter end, and another faction who were insistent on surrendering the castle.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the vassals in Ako were ordered to come to the castle for a three day stay from 27th, where they divided into two factions: one made up of those who were dissatisfied with their treatment at the hands of the Edo bakufu and insisted on holding the castle, urging of resistance to the bitter end, and another faction who were insistent on surrendering the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>恭順派の大野九郎兵衛は、篭城派の原惣右衛門・岡島八十右衛門などと激しく対立し、4月12日には赤穂から逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurobei Oono of the deference faction was in fierce conflict with Soemon HARA and Yasoemon OKAJIMA and so on, of the faction of holding the castle, and he escaped from Ako on April 12.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurobei Oono of the deference faction was in fierce conflict with Soemon HARA, Yasoemon OKAJIMA and those of the stalwart faction and eventually fled Ako on April 12.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurobei ONO of the deference faction was in fierce conflict with Soemon HARA, Yasoemon OKAJIMA and those of the stalwart faction and eventually fled Ako on April 12.</e>
<cmt>「 Kurobei Oono」を「Kurobei ONO」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>こうした中、内蔵助は篭城殉死希望の藩士たちから義盟の血判書を受け取り、城を明渡した上で浅野内匠頭の弟浅野長広を立てて浅野家再興を嘆願し、あわせて吉良上野介の処分を幕府に求めることで藩論を統一する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kura no suke accepted the paper with a seal of blood of the feudal retainers&apos; alliance, who hoped for holding the castle and following their master to the grave and he unified the opinion of the Domain people in that after surrendering the castle and pushing Nagahiro ASANO, younger brother of Asano Takumi no Kami, up to the lord, and the restoration of Asano family was petitioned and at the same time, the reprimand of Kira Kozuke no Suke was asked for.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Kura no Suke accepted the paper bearing the seal of blood of the feudal retainers&apos; alliance (who hoped for holding the castle and following their master to the grave) and unified the opinion of the people of his Domain in agreeing to the surrender of the castle and punishment of Nagahiro ASANO, younger brother of Asano Takumi no Kami, while simultaneously petitioning for the restoration of Asano family and the reprimand of Kozuke no Suke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kuranosuke accepted the paper bearing the seal of blood of the feudal retainers&apos; alliance (who hoped for holding the castle and following their master to the grave) and unified the opinion of the people of his Domain in agreeing to the surrender of the castle and punishment of Nagahiro ASANO, younger brother of Asano Takumi no Kami, while simultaneously petitioning for the restoration of Asano family and the reprimand of Kozukenosuke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 Kurobei Oono」を「Kurobei ONO」に修正しました。「 Kozuke no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。余分なスペースの削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また内蔵助は、紙くず同然になるであろう赤穂藩の藩札の交換に応じて赤穂の経済の混乱を避け、また藩士に対しても分配金を下に厚く上に軽くするなどの配分をおこなって、家中が分裂する危険の回避につとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Kura no suke tried to avoid Ako&apos;s economic confusion by exchanging han bills of Ako Domain which would be heaps of worthless paper and to avoid the danger of the family&apos;s split by apportioning the distribution money heavily to the lower and lighter to the upper for the feudal retainers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Kura no suke tried to alleviate Ako&apos;s economic confusion by redeeming han bills of Ako Domain which would be heaps of worthless paper and to avoid family dissention by reapportioning the distribution money increasing the amount to the lower ranks and lightening the amount distributed to the upper ranks of the feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Kuranosuke tried to alleviate Ako&apos;s economic confusion by redeeming han bills of Ako Domain which would be heaps of worthless paper and to avoid family dissention by reapportioning the distribution money increasing the amount to the lower ranks and lightening the amount distributed to the upper ranks of the feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>かつての「昼行燈」ぶりが信じられないような適切な処置であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an unbelievably appropriate treatment, though he was once called &apos;hiru-andon&apos; (daytime lamp with a paper shade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was unbelievably astute solution considering he had once been called &apos;hiru-andon&apos; (a daytime lamp with a paper shade).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was unbelievably astute solution considering he had once been called &apos;hiru-andon&apos; (a daytime lamp with a paper shade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>また、内蔵助は物頭の月岡治右衛門と多川九左衛門を江戸に派遣して、幕府収城目付荒木政羽らに浅野家再興と吉良上野介処分を求めた嘆願書をとどけさせた（しかしこの二人は任を誤り、江戸家老安井彦右衛門に手渡し、美濃大垣藩主戸田氏定の手紙を持って帰ってくる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Kura no suke sent Jiemon TSUKIOKA and Kyuzaemon TAGAWA, who were Monogashira (Military Commanders), to Edo and had them hand over the petition for the restoration of Asano family and reprimand of Kira Kozuke no Suke, to Masahane ARAKI and so on, the bakufu&apos;s castle management metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers) (However, the two mistakenly handed over it to Hikoemon YASUI, Edo family&apos;s chief retainer, and brought back with the letter by Ujisada TODA, the lord of Mino-Ogaki Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke sent Jiemon TSUKIOKA and Kyuzaemon TAGAWA, who were Monogashira (Military Commanders), to Edo and had them hand over the petition for the restoration of Asano family and the reprimand of Kozuke no Suke KIRA, to Masahane ARAKI the bakufu&apos;s castle management metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers) (However, the two mistakenly handed it over to Hikoemon YASUI, the Edo family&apos;s chief retainer, and brought back a letter by Ujisada TODA, lord of Mino-Ogaki Domain).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke sent Jiemon TSUKIOKA and Kyuzaemon TAGAWA, who were Monogashira (Military Commanders), to Edo and had them hand over the petition for the restoration of Asano family and the reprimand of Kozukenosuke KIRA, to Masahane ARAKI the bakufu&apos;s castle management metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers) (However, the two mistakenly handed it over to Hikoemon YASUI, the Edo family&apos;s chief retainer, and brought back a letter by Ujisada TODA, lord of Mino-Ogaki Domain).</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 Kozuke no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>4月18日、荒木十郎右衛門らが赤穂に到着すると、内蔵助自身も浅野家再興と吉良上野介処分について三度の嘆願を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Juroemon ARAKI arrived in Ako on April 18, Kura no suke himself petitioned the restoration of Asano family and the reprimand of Kira Kozuke no Suke KIRA three times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Juroemon ARAKI arrived in Ako on April 18, Kura no suke himself petitioned three times for the restoration of the Asano family and the reprimand of Kozuke no Suke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Juroemon ARAKI arrived in Ako on April 18, Kuranosuke himself petitioned three times for the restoration of the Asano family and the reprimand of Kozukenosuke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 Kozuke no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>こうした内蔵助の努力もあって荒木個人の協力は得られたようで、江戸帰還後に荒木は老中にその旨を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With such Kura no suke&apos;s effort, he got the collaboration of ARAKI himself and after going back to Edo ARAKI told that to the chief retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ARAKI joined forces with Kura no Suke&apos;s effort and personally reported their collaboration to the chief retainer upon his return to Edo.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ARAKI joined forces with Kuranosuke&apos;s effort and personally reported their collaboration to the chief retainer upon his return to Edo.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースの削除「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>翌日4月19日、隣国竜野藩の藩主脇坂安照と備中足守藩の藩主木下公定率いる収城軍勢に赤穂城を明け渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 19 in the next year, Ako-jo castle was surrendered to the castle management army led by Yasuteru WAKISAKA, the lord of neighbouring province Tatsuno Domain, and Kinsada KINOSHITA, the lord of Bicchu Province Ashimori Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 19 the following year, Ako-jo castle was surrendered to the castle management army led by Yasuteru WAKISAKA, lord of the Tatsuno Domain in the neighbouring province, and Kinsada KINOSHITA, lord of Ashimori Domain of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 19 the following year, Ako-jo Castle was surrendered to the castle management army led by Yasuteru WAKISAKA, lord of the Tatsuno Domain in the neighbouring province, and Kinsada KINOSHITA, lord of Ashimori Domain of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>「 Ako-jo castle」を「Ako-jo Castle」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>赤穂城退去後は遠林寺において藩政残務処理にあたり、この間は幕府から29人扶持を支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they left Ako-jo castle, they did the remaining domain duties in Enrin-ji temple and meanwhile they were given fuchi (stipend) for 29 people by bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they left Ako-jo castle, they did the remaining domain duties in Enrin-ji temple and meanwhile they were given fuchi (stipend) for 29 people by bakufu.</e>
<cmt>The subject of this sentence is unclear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they left Ako-jo Castle, they did the remaining domain duties in Enrin-ji Temple and meanwhile they were given fuchi (stipend) for 29 people by bakufu.</e>
<cmt>「 Ako-jo castle」を「Ako-jo Castle」に修正しました。「 Enrin-ji temple」を「Enrin-ji Temple」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>5月21日に残務処理もあらかた終わり、6月25日、ついに内蔵助は生まれ故郷赤穂を後にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 21 the duties were almost done and on June 25 Kura no suke finally left his hometown Ako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 21 Kura no Suke had nearly completed his duties and on June 25 he finally left his birthplace of Ako.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 21 Kuranosuke had nearly completed his duties and on June 25 he finally left his birthplace of Ako.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>お家再興、江戸急進派との軋轢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Restoration of the family and conflict with Edo radical faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Restoration of the family and conflict with Edo radical faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Restoration of the family and conflict with Edo radical faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>赤穂退去後、内蔵助は家族とともに京都市山科区に隠棲し、ここから旧赤穂藩士たちと連絡をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After leaving Ako, Kura no suke went into seclusion with his families in Yamashina ward in Kyoto City and he got in touch with old Ako feudal retainers from there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After leaving Ako, Kura no suke went into seclusion with his family in Kyoto City&apos;s Yamashina ward from there and got in touch with the old Ako feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After leaving Ako, Kuranosuke went into seclusion with his family in Kyoto City&apos;s Yamashina ward from there and got in touch with the old Ako feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>内蔵助が山科を選んだのは、大石家が近衛家の親族であるとともに、大石家の叔父進藤源四郎の一族進藤長之（近衛家家臣）が管理していた土地だったためと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Kura no suke chose Yamashina seems to be that Oishi family was in relationship by blood and marriage with Konoe family and Nagayuki SHINDO (vassal in Konoe family), who was one family member of Genshiro SHINDO, his uncle in Oishi family, managed the place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Kura no suke chose Yamashina seems because of the matrimonial and familial ties between the Oishi family and the Konoe family (Nagayuki SHINDO (vassal of the Konoe family), was a relative of Genshiro SHINDO, his uncle on the Oishi side, who was the caretaker).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Kuranosuke chose Yamashina seems because of the matrimonial and familial ties between the Oishi family and the Konoe family (Nagayuki SHINDO (vassal of the Konoe family), was a relative of Genshiro SHINDO, his uncle on the Oishi side, who was the caretaker).</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。余分なスペースの削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>しかし、この頃から早くも浅野家遺臣たちの意見は二つに分かれはじめていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, early from that time, opinions were divided among old Asano family&apos;s retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, early on, opinion was divided amongst the elder Asano family retainers.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, early on, opinion was divided amongst the elder Asano family retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>一つは奥野定良（1,000石組頭）・進藤源四郎（400石足軽頭）・小山良師（300石足軽頭）・岡本重之（400石大阪留守居役）ら高禄取りを中心にしたお家再興優先派、もう一つは堀部武庸（200石江戸留守居役）・高田郡兵衛（石馬廻役）・奥田重盛（150石武具奉行）ら腕自慢の家臣を中心に、小禄の家臣たちに支持された吉良上野介への仇討ち優先派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one is the restoration of family faction centring on those who got a high salary such as Sadayoshi OKUNO (1,000 koku kumigashira (a head of the group)), Genshiro SHINDO (400 koku ashigarugashira (literally, ashigaru head, retained warriors given control ashigaru)), Yoshikazu KOYAMA (300 koku ashigarugashira), Shigeyuki OKAMOTO (400 koku Osaka rusuiyaku (a person representing the master during his absence)) and so on, and the other is the adauchi faction, where revenge for Kira Kozuke no Suke was prioritized, centring on the forceful vassals such as Taketsune HORIBE (200 koku Edo rusuiyaku), Gunbei TAKADA (200 koku Umamawariyaku (body guard)), Shigemori OKUDA (150 koku arms bugyo (magistrate)) and so on and supported by the small stipend vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One area of contention regarded the fact that some members from certain branches of the family received a higher salary such as Sadayoshi OKUNO who received 1,000 koku as kumigashira (group leader), and Genshiro SHINDO who received 400 koku as ashigarugashira (head of the ashigaru) who retained warriors controlling the ashigaru, Yoshikazu KOYAMA who received 300 koku as ashigarugashira, and Shigeyuki OKAMOTO who received 400 koku as Osaka rusuiyaku (a regent) amongst others, as opposed to the Adauchi faction, which prioritized avenging Kura no Suke, primarily powerful vassals such as Taketsune HORIBE who received 200 koku as Edo rusuiyaku, Gunbei TAKADA who received 200 koku as Umamawariyaku (body guard), and Shigemori OKUDA who received 150 koku as arms bugyo (magistrate) amongst others who were supported by a smaller stipend.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One area of contention regarded the fact that some members from certain branches of the family received a higher salary such as Sadayoshi OKUNO who received 1,000 koku as kumigashira (group leader), and Genshiro SHINDO who received 400 koku as ashigarugashira (head of the ashigaru) who retained warriors controlling the ashigaru, Yoshikazu KOYAMA who received 300 koku as ashigarugashira, and Shigeyuki OKAMOTO who received 400 koku as Osaka rusuiyaku (a regent) amongst others, as opposed to the Adauchi faction, which prioritized avenging Kozukenosuke KIRA, primarily powerful vassals such as Taketsune HORIBE who received 200 koku as Edo rusuiyaku, Gunbei TAKADA who received 200 koku as Umamawariyaku (body guard), and Shigemori OKUDA who received 150 koku as arms bugyo (magistrate) amongst others who were supported by a smaller stipend.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースの削除「avenging Kura no Suke」を「avenging Kozukenosuke KIRA」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>それぞれの派の特徴として、前者は赤穂詰めの家臣が多く、後者は江戸詰めの家臣であることが多かったため、後者を江戸急進派とも呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both had respective characters and many of the former were the vassals in Ako and many of the latter were the ones in Edo and thus the latter was called Edo radical faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both had displayed characters representative of their factions: Many were formerly vassals located in Ako while several of the those who formerly acted as representative in Edo became members of the radical Edo faction.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both had displayed characters representative of their factions: Many were formerly vassals located in Ako while several of the those who formerly acted as representative in Edo became members of the radical Edo faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>一党の頭目たる大石内蔵助自身は、どっちつかずの態度で分裂を回避しながら、実際にはお家再興に力を入れて、江戸急進派に時節到来を待つよう促すという立場をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no Suke OISHI, a head of one faction, was in a neutral attitude and avoided the split and actually did his best to restore the family and suggested the Edo radical faction to wait for the time for revenge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke OISHI, the head of one faction, adopted a neutral attitude by avoiding the split and did his best to restore the family by suggesting that the radical Edo faction bide their time for revenge.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke OISHI, the head of one faction, adopted a neutral attitude by avoiding the split and did his best to restore the family by suggesting that the radical Edo faction bide their time for revenge.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>赤穂を立ち去る前には遠林寺住職祐海を江戸へ送って、将軍徳川綱吉やその生母桂昌院に影響力を持っていた神田護持院の隆光大僧正などに浅野家再興の取り成しを依頼し、7月には小野寺十内とともに浅野長矩の従兄弟にあたる戸田氏定と浅野家再興を議するために、美濃国大垣城を訪れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before leaving Ako he sent Yuma, a chief priest in Enrin-ji temple, to Edo and asked Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA and daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) Takamitsu in Kanda-Goji-in temple, who had an influence over Tsunayoshi&apos;s real mother Keishoin, and so on for mediation of the restoration of Asano family, and in July he visited Ogaki-jo castle.in Mino Province with Junai ONODERA to discuss the Asano family restoration with Ujisada TODA, who was a cousin of Naganori ASANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before leaving Ako he sent Yuma, a chief priest of Enrin-ji temple, to Edo and asked the Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA and the daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) Takamitsu at Kanda-Goji-in temple, who had influence over Tsunayoshi&apos;s birth mother Keishoin for mediation in the restoration of the Asano family; he then visited Ogaki-jo castle in Mino province with Junai ONODERA to discuss the ASANO family restoration with a cousin of Naganori ASANO, Ujisada TODA.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before leaving Ako he sent Yuma, a chief priest of Enrin-ji Temple, to Edo and asked the Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA and the daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) Takamitsu at Kanda-Goji-in Temple, who had influence over Tsunayoshi&apos;s birth mother Keishoin for mediation in the restoration of the Asano family; he then visited Ogaki-jo Castle in Mino province with Junai ONODERA to discuss the Asano family restoration with a cousin of Naganori ASANO, Ujisada TODA.</e>
<cmt>「 Enrin-ji temple」を「Enrin-ji Temple」に修正しました。「 Kanda-Goji-in temple」を「Kanda-Goji-in Temple」に修正しました。「 Ogaki-jo castle」を「Ogaki-jo Castle」に修正しました。「 the ASANO family」を「the Asano family」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また先に嘆願した荒木政羽からも大石へ「浅野家お家再興の望みあり」という書状が届いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And OISHI received the letter saying &apos;there&apos;s a hope for the Asano family restoration&apos; from Masahane ARAKI who had petitioned earlier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OISHI then received a letter from Masahane ARAKI which read &apos;there is hope for the Asano family restoration&apos; which had been petitioned for earlier.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OISHI then received a letter from Masahane ARAKI which read &apos;there is hope for the Asano family restoration&apos; which had been petitioned for earlier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>しかし、お家再興よりも吉良上野介の首を挙げることを優先する堀部安兵衛ら江戸急進派は、この間も大石に江戸下向を促す書状を再三にわたり送り付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, however, Edo radical faction such as Yasube HORIBE and so on, who prioritized the decapitation of Kira Kozuke no Suke over the restoration of the family, repeatedly sent OISHI the letters to ask him to move down to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the radical faction in Edo, including Yasube HORIBE, which had prioritized the decapitation of Kozu no Suke KIRA over family restoration repeatedly sent letters to OISHI requesting that he relocate to Edo.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the radical faction in Edo, including Yasube HORIBE, which had prioritized the decapitation of Kozukenosuke KIRA over family restoration repeatedly sent letters to OISHI requesting that he relocates to Edo.</e>
<cmt>「 Kozu no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。「 relocate」を「relocates」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>内蔵助は江戸急進派鎮撫のため、9月下旬に原惣右衛門（300石足軽頭）・潮田又之丞（200石絵図奉行）・中村勘助（100石祐筆）らを江戸へ派遣、続いて進藤源四郎と大高源五（20石5人扶持腰物方）も江戸に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To suppress Edo radical faction, in late September Kura no suke sent Soemon HARA (300 koku ashigarugashira), Matanojo USHIODA (200 koku pictorial map bugyo (magistrate)), Kansuke NAKAMURA (100 koku yuhitsu (private secretary)) and so on to Edo, and sent Genshiro SHINDO and Gengo OTAKA (20 koku fuchi warriors who dealt with costumes, swords, knives and so on) to Edo, too.</e>
<cmt>「腰物方」を、warriors who dealt with costumes, swords, knives and so onとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To suppress radical Edo faction, Kura no Suke sent Soemon HARA who received 300 Koku as ahigaruno ushira, Matanojo USHIODA who received 200 koku as bugyo (magistrate) and Kansuke NAKAMURA who received 100 koku as yuhitsu (private secretary), amongst others, to Edo in late September as well as Genshiro SHINDO and Gengo OTAKA who received 20 koku each and were fuchi warriors responsible for armament.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To suppress radical Edo faction, Kuranosuke sent Soemon HARA who received 300 Koku as ahigaruno ushira, Matanojo USHIODA who received 200 koku as bugyo (magistrate) and Kansuke NAKAMURA who received 100 koku as yuhitsu (private secretary), amongst others, to Edo in late September as well as Genshiro SHINDO and Gengo OTAKA who received 20 koku each and were fuchi warriors responsible for armament.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>しかし彼らは逆に安兵衛に論破されて急進派になってしまったため、10月、大石が自身で江戸へ下向した（第一次大石東下り）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the contrary, they were persuaded to be Edo radical faction members by Yasube and in October OISHI himself went to Edo (the first Oishi&apos;s going down to Edo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The were converted, however, to the radical Edo faction by Yasube when OISHI went to Edo, the first of his clan to do so.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The were converted, however, to the radical Edo faction by Yasube when OISHI went to Edo, the first of his clan to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>大石は江戸三田（東京都港区 (東京都)三田 (東京都港区)）の前川忠大夫宅で堀部と会談し、浅野内匠頭の一周忌になる明年3月に決行を約束した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OISHI had a meeting with HORIBE in the house of Tadashi MAEKAWA tayu (Minato-ward Tokyo Prefecture (Tokyo Prefecture) Mita (Minato-ward Tokyo Prefecture) and promised to stand up for Asano Takumi no Kami in the next March which was first anniversary of his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OISHI had a meeting with HORIBE in the house Tadashi MAEKAWA tayu of Tokyo&apos; Minato-ward in which he promised to stand up for Takumonokami ASANO the following March which happened to be the first anniversary of his death.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OISHI had a meeting with HORIBE in the house Tadashi MAEKAWA tayu of Tokyo&apos; Minato-ward in which he promised to stand up for Takumonokami ASANO the following March which happened to be the first anniversary of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>またこの時、かつて赤穂藩を追われた不破数右衛門が一党に加えてほしいと参じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also at that time, Kazuemon FUWA, who was once expelled from Ako Domain, wished to join the standing up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Kazuemon FUWA, once expelled from AKO domain, expressed his interest in joining the uprising.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Kazuemon FUWA, once expelled from AKO domain, expressed his interest in joining the uprising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>大石は内匠頭の眠る泉岳寺へ参詣した際に主君の墓前で不破の帰参と同志へ加えることの許可を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When OISHI visited Sengaku-ji temple where there was the grave of Takumi no Kami, he got the approval of FUWA&apos;s coming back and joining the membership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon visiting the grave of Takuminokami at Sengaku-ji temple, OISHI received the approval of FUWA re-entering the radical Edo faction.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon visiting the grave of Takuminokami at Sengaku-ji Temple, OISHI received the approval of FUWA re-entering the radical Edo faction.</e>
<cmt>「 temple」を「Temple」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>この江戸下向で荒木や内匠頭正室の瑤泉院とも会っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this moving down to Edo, he met ARAKI and Yozenin, the seishitsu (legal wife) of Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon arriving in Edo, he met ARAKI and the wife of Takuminokami, Yozenin.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon arriving in Edo, he met ARAKI and the wife of Takuminokami, Yozenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>江戸で一通りやるべきことを終えた大石は、12月には京都へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OISHI, who had finished all the duties, went back to Kyoto in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OISHI returned to Kyoto in December upon the completion of his duties.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OISHI returned to Kyoto in December upon the completion of his duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>帰京後、嫡男大石主税を元服させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After going back to Kyoto, he made Chikara OISHI, his legitimate son, reach the manhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon return to Kyoto, he raised his son Chikara OISHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon return to Kyoto, he raised his son Chikara OISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>大石主税は盟約に加わることを望み、内蔵助はこれを許した（妊娠中の妻りく、長女くう、次男吉之進、次女るりは翌年元禄15年（1702年）4月に妻の実家の豊岡市へ帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikara OISHI wished to join the compact and Kura no suke admitted it (his pregnant wife Riku, the first daughter Kuu, the second son Kichinoshin and the second daughter Ruri were sent back to Toyooka city where there was his wife&apos;s family home in the next April, 1702.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikara OISHI was admitted to the radical Edo faction by his father Kura no Suke whereupon his pregnant wife Riku, his first daughter Kuu, his second son Kichinoshin, his second daughter Ruri were sent to his wife&apos;s hometown in Toyoka the following April, 1702.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikara OISHI was admitted to the radical Edo faction by his father Kuranosuke whereupon his pregnant wife Riku, his first daughter Kuu, his second son Kichinoshin, his second daughter Ruri were sent to his wife&apos;s hometown in Toyoka the following April, 1702.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>りくは7月に大三郎を出産。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Riku gave birth to Daisaburo in July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Riku gave birth to Daisaburo that July.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Riku gave birth to Daisaburo that July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>この子はのちに広島藩に仕えることになる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This child came to serve Hiroshima Domain afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The child then came to serve the Hiroshima domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The child then came to serve the Hiroshima domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="83">
<j>しかし、この帰京後から、内蔵助の廓などでの放蕩がひどくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After going back to Kyoto, however, Kura no suke&apos;s debauchery life was prominent in Kuruwa (red-light district) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon returning to Kyoto, Kura no Suke became famous for a life of debauchery in the red light district of Kuruwa.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon returning to Kyoto, Kuranosuke became famous for a life of debauchery in the red light district of Kuruwa.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースの削除「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>仮名手本忠臣蔵の影響で、これは吉良家や上杉家の目を欺くための演技であるというのが半ば定説化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the influence of Kanadehon Chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers), it mostly becomes a commonly-accepted myth that his debauchery life was an act for deceiving Kira family or Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based upon the influence of the Kanadehon Chushigura (The Treasure of Loyal Retainers), it is a commonly accepted myth that his debauchery was a ruse for deceiving the Kira and Uesugi families.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based upon the influence of the Kanadehon Chushigura (The Treasure of Loyal Retainers), it is a commonly accepted myth that his debauchery was a ruse for deceiving the Kira and Uesugi families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>しかし内蔵助はもともと赤穂藩時代から自由気ままな遊び人であり、本当に楽しんでいた面もあった可能性は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kura no suke was originally a pleasure-seeker as free as a bird from the age of Ako Domain and there was a high possibility for him to enjoy it really.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was known that Kura no Suke was a free spirit since his days in Ako, and thus there is a high probability that he was truly a seeker of pleasure.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was known that Kura no Suke was a free spirit since his days in Ako, and thus there is a high probability that he was truly a seeker of pleasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>最近の忠臣蔵のドラマでも、「人間内蔵助」を描こうとして後者に描かれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent Chushingura (The treasury of Loyal Retainers) dramas, &apos;human Kura no suke&apos; have often been depicted like the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent performances presented by the Chushingura (the Treasury of Loyal Retainers) he has often been depicted as such.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent performances presented by the Chushingura (the Treasury of Loyal Retainers) he has often been depicted as such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>（一方そもそも放蕩の事実はないとする説も有力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(On the other hand, there was also a dominant theory of no fact of debauchery life right from the start.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there prevails a theory in which he did not live a life of excess.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there prevails a theory in which he did not live a life of excess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>内蔵助放蕩の根拠「江赤見聞記」は落合勝信の著と見られるが、脱盟者の進藤源四郎と小山源五左衛門が言ったことをそのまま載せたものとみられており、「堀部筆記」にもまるで出てこないことから）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ground of Kura no suke&apos;s debauchery life is seen in Katsunobu OCHIAI&apos;s book, but the book seems to have described what the dropouts from the compact, such as Genshiro SHINDO and Gengozaemon KOYAMA, said as they did, and there is no description concerning this also in &apos;HORIBE&apos;s note.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An account of Kura no Suke&apos;s debauchery is depicted in a book written by Katsunobu Ochiai, yet this seems to have been compiled from accounts of those who had left the radical Edo faction, such as Genshiro SHINDO and Gengozaemon KOYAMA&lt; although none of this was mentioned in Horibe&apos;s account.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An account of Kuranosuke&apos;s debauchery is depicted in a book written by Katsunobu OCHIAI, yet this seems to have been compiled from accounts of those who had left the radical Edo faction, such as Genshiro SHINDO and Gengozaemon KOYAMA, although none of this was mentioned in Horibe&apos;s account.</e>
<cmt>「 &lt;」を「,」に修正しました。「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 Katsunobu Ochiai」を「Katsunobu OCHIAI」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="89">
<j>この年の年末からは脱盟者も出始めており、その一人は江戸急進派の中心人物・高田郡兵衛であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that year&apos;s end some began to drop out and one of them was Gunbe TAKADA, a central figure of Edo radical faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the end of that year, some began to drop out of the struggle, amongst them Gunbe TAKADA, who had been a central figure of the radical Tokyo faction.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the end of that year, some began to drop out of the struggle, amongst them Gunbe TAKADA, who had been a central figure of the radical Tokyo faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>これは江戸急進派の顔を失わせる結果となり、その発言力を弱めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, this led to losing face of Edo radical faction and weakened the influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a loss of face for the radical Tokyo faction and weakened their influence.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a loss of face for the radical Tokyo faction and weakened their influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>内蔵助はこれを好機として元禄15年（1702年）2月の山科と円山での会議において「大学様の処分が決まるまで決起しない」ことを決定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke took advantage of this to decide &apos;the standing up would be postponed until after the punishment of the Great Learning,&apos; in the meeting in Yamanashi and Maruyama (Mt. Maruyama) in February 1702.</e>
<cmt>「大学様」が意味不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke took advantage of their leaving to decide that &apos;the uprising will be postponed until after the punishment of the Great Teaching&apos; at a meeting in Yamanashi and Maruyama (Mt. Maruyama) in February 1702.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke took advantage of their leaving to decide that &apos;the uprising will be postponed until after the punishment of the Great Teaching&apos; at a meeting in Yamanashi and Maruyama (Mt. Maruyama) in February 1702.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>吉田忠左衛門（200石加東郡郡代）と近松勘六（馬廻250石）を江戸に派遣して江戸急進派にこれを伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sent Chuzaemon YOSHIDA (200 koku Kato-gun Gundai (Intendant of a region or administrator of a town)) and Kanroku CHIKAMATSU (Umamawariyaku 250 koku) to Edo and told this to Edo radical faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sent Chuzaemon YOSHIDA who received 200 koku as Kato-gun Gundai (Intendant of a region or an administer of a town) and Kanroku CHIKAMATSU who received 250 kuku as Umamawariyaku to Edo to tell of this radical Edo faction.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sent Chuzaemon YOSHIDA who received 200 koku as Kato-gun Gundai (Intendant of a region or an administer of a town) and Kanroku CHIKAMATSU who received 250 kuku as Umamawariyaku to Edo to tell of this radical Edo faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>しかし江戸急進派は納得せず、内蔵助をはずして独自に決起することを模索しつつ、ついに6月には江戸急進派の頭目堀部安兵衛が自ら京都へ乗り込んでくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Edo radical faction was not satisfied with this and sought to stand up independently from Kura no suke and finally Yasube HORIBE himself, the chief of Edo radical faction, came to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the radical Edo faction was unsatisfied and sought independence from Kura no Suke, thus the leader of the radical Edo faction, Yasube HORIBE, relocated to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the radical Edo faction was unsatisfied and sought independence from Kuranosuke, thus the leader of the radical Edo faction, Yasube HORIBE, relocated to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>「もはや大石は不要」として内蔵助を斬り捨てるつもりだったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he would kill Kura no suke with a sword saying &apos;OISHI is not necessary anymore.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that he would kill Kura no Suke with a sword, uttering the words &apos;OISHI is no longer necessary&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that he would kill Kuranosuke with a sword, uttering the words &apos;OISHI is no longer necessary&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。ピリオドを付けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>しかしちょうどこの頃、遠林寺の祐海などを通じて内蔵助もお家再興が難しい情勢を知っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, just at that time, Kura no suke came to know the difficulty of the restoration of the family through Yuma in Enrin-ji temple and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was at that moment that Kura no Suke came to learn from Yuma of Enrin-ji temple of the difficulty regarding the restoration of the family.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was at that moment that Kuranosuke came to learn from Yuma of Enrin-ji Temple of the difficulty regarding the restoration of the family.</e>
<cmt>「 temple」を「Temple」に修正しました。「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>7月18日、ついに幕府は浅野長広にたいして広島藩お預かりを言い渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last on July 18, the bakufu ordered Nagahiro ASANO to be a custody in Hiroshima Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, on July 18, the bakafu (feudal government) appointed Nagahiro ASANO custodian of Hiroshima domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, on July 18, the bakafu (feudal government) appointed Nagahiro ASANO custodian of Hiroshima domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>ここにお家再興は絶望的となり、幕府への遠慮は無用となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the restoration of the family became hopeless and the consideration for the bakufu became unnecessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus it became unnecessary for the bakafu (feudal government) to concern itself as the restoration of the family became hopeless.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus it became unnecessary for the bakafu (feudal government) to concern itself as the restoration of the family became hopeless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>討ち入り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The raid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Attack</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Attack</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>御家再興は絶望的となったのを受けて、7月28日、内蔵助は堀部安兵衛なども呼んで円山会議を開催し、吉良上野介を討つことを決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accepting the hopeless restoration of the family, on July 28 Kura no suke invited Yasube HORIBE and so on, held Maruyama Meeting and decided the raid on Kira Kozuke no Suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accepting the restoration of the family as hopeless, Kura no Suke invited Yasube HORIBE on July 28 to the Meeting of Maruyama to plan the attack on Kozu no Suke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accepting the restoration of the family as hopeless, Kuranosuke invited Yasube HORIBE on July 28 to the Meeting of Maruyama to plan the attack on Kozukenosuke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 Kozu no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>安兵衛はこれを江戸の同志達に伝えるべく江戸へ戻っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasube went back to Edo to tell this to the comrades.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasube went back to Edo to tell this to his comrades.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasube went back to Edo to tell this to his comrades.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>また8月には貝賀友信（蔵奉行10両2石3人扶持）、大高源五らに神文返し（盟約の誓紙＝神文の返還）を実施し、死にたくない者は脱盟するようそれとなく促した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in August he did Shinbun-kaeshi (written oath of the compact = return of Shinbun) for Tomonobu KAIGA (kura bugyo (the magistrate of storehouse) 10 ryo 2 koku 3 fuchi), Gengo OTAKA and so on and suggested those who did not want to die to drop out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That, August, he signed the Shimbun-keashi (a written oath agreeing to the return of the Shimbun) for Tomonobu KAIGA who received 10 ryo, 2 koku, 3 fuchi as kura bugyu (storehouse magistrate) and Gengo OTAKA and suggested those who do not want to die to drop out.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That, August, he signed the Shimbun-keashi (a written oath agreeing to the return of the Shimbun) for Tomonobu KAIGA who received 10 ryo, 2 koku, 3 fuchi as kura bugyu (storehouse magistrate) and Gengo OTAKA and suggested those who do not want to die to drop out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>このときに奥野定良・進藤俊式・小山良師・岡本重之・長沢六郎右衛門・灰方藤兵衛・多川九左衛門ら、お家再興優先派が続々と脱盟していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time the restoration of the family faction dropped out one right after the other, such as Sadayoshi OKUNO, Toshimoto SHINDO, Yoshimoro OYAMA, Shigeyuki OKAMOTO, Rokuroemon NAGASAWA, Tobe HAIKATA, Kyuzaemon TAGAWA and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time the faction for family restoration (sadayoshi OKUNO, Toshimoto SHINDO, Yoshimoro OYAMA, Shigeyuki OKAMOTO, Rokuroemon NAGASAWA, Tobe HAIKATA, and Kyuzaemon TAGAWA) dropped out one by one.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time the faction for family restoration (sadayoshi OKUNO, Toshimoto SHINDO, Yoshimoro OYAMA, Shigeyuki OKAMOTO, Rokuroemon NAGASAWA, Tobe HAIKATA, and Kyuzaemon TAGAWA) dropped out one by one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>これを「神文返し」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called &apos;Shinbun-kaeshi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is known as &apos;Shinbun-kaeshi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is known as &apos;Shinbun-kaeshi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>一方、なお盟約に残った同志たちは次々と江戸へ下向していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the comrades, who remained in the compact, continuously went down to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet, those comrades who honoured the compact continued to spend time in Edo.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, those comrades who honoured the compact continued to spend time in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>9月19日には大石主税が山科を発ち、さらに10月7日には内蔵助自身も垣見五郎兵衛と名乗って江戸へ下向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 19 Chikara OISHI left Yamashina, and on October 7 Kura no suke, calling himself Gorobe KAKIMI, went down to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikara OISHI left Yamashina on September 19; Kura no Suke then left for Edo on October 7 under the name Gorobe KAKIMI.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikara OISHI left Yamashina on September 19; Kuranosuke then left for Edo on October 7 under the name Gorobe KAKIMI.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>忠臣蔵ものの物語では、「道中で本物の垣見五郎兵衛が出現して内蔵助と会見、五郎兵衛は内蔵助たちを吉良上野介を討たんとする赤穂浪士と察して、自分が偽物だと詫びる」という挿話が入るが、もちろんこれは創作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story of Chushingura, there is an episode that &apos;on the way real Gorobe KAKIMI appeared and met Kura no suke and Gorobe noticed that Kura no suke and so on were Ako Roshi (lordless samurai of Ako domain) who tried to make a raid on Kira Kozuke no Suke and apologized for his being a fake,&apos; but it is a fiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Chushingura, there is a story that tells of a meeting between Kura no Suke and the real Gorobe KAKIMI in which &apos;Gorobe recognized that Kura no Suke and troupe were the Ako Roshi (masterless samurai of Ako domain) who had tried to attack Kozu no Suke KIRA whereupon Kura no Suke apologized for being an impostor&apos;, but, of course, this fiction.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Chushingura, there is a story that tells of a meeting between Kuranosuke and the real Gorobe KAKIMI in which &apos;Gorobe recognized that Kuranosuke and troupe were the Ako Roshi (masterless samurai of Ako domain) who had tried to attack Kozukenosuke KIRA whereupon Kuranosuke apologized for being an impostor&apos;, but, of course, this fiction.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 Kozu no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="106">
<j>大石は10月26日には川崎平間村軽部五兵衛宅に滞在して、ここから同志達に第一訓令を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 26 OISHI stayed at the house of Gohe KARUBE in Hirama village, Kawasaki and from there he issued the first directive to the comrades.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OISHI stopped at the house of Gohe KARUBE in Hirama village, Kawasaki, on October 26, and from there issued his first directive to his comrades.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OISHI stopped at the house of Gohe KARUBE in Hirama village, Kawasaki, on October 26, and from there issued his first directive to his comrades.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>さらに11月5日に内蔵助一行は江戸に入り、日本橋近くの石町三丁目の小山屋に住居を定めると、同志に吉良邸を探索させ、吉良邸絵図面を入手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And on November 5 Kura no suke party entered Edo, stayed in the house in Koyamaya in Ishimachi 3-chome near Nihonbashi, made the comrades search around Kira-tei Residence and got the pictorial map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke and his group arrived in Edo November 5 and took up lodging in a house in Koyama Ishimachi 3-chome near Nihonbashi, whereupon he ordered his comrades to search the Kira-tei residence until they found a visual map of the place.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke and his group arrived in Edo November 5 and took up lodging in a house in Koyama Ishimachi 3-chome near Nihonbashi, whereupon he ordered his comrades to search the Kira-tei Residence until they found a visual map of the place.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 residence」を「Residence」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>また吉良上野介在邸確実の日を知る必要もあり、内蔵助旧知の国学者荷田春満や同志大高源五が脇屋新兵衛として入門していた茶人山田宗偏から12月14日に吉良邸で茶会がある情報を入手させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it was necessary for them to know the exact date when Kira Kozuke no Suke was in the residence and Kura no suke made them get the information of tea party which would be held in Kira-tei Residence on December 14 through Sihen YAMADA, chajin (a master of tea ceremony), of whom, KADA no Azumamaro, a scholar of Japanese classical literature and an old friend of Kura no suke, or the comrade Gengo OTAKA as Shinbei WAKIYA were disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was essential for them to know the exact date when they could expect that Kozuke no suke KIRA would be in residence at the Kira-tei; they learned from Shihen Yamada, a chajin (master of tea ceremony) that a tea ceremony would be held at he residence on December 14, of whom Azumamaro KADA, a scholar of classical Japanese literature and an old friend of Kura no Suke and his comrade Gengo OTAKA acting as Shinbei WAKIYA were disciples.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was essential for them to know the exact date when they could expect that Kozukenosuke KIRA would be in residence at the Kira-tei; they learned from Shihen Yamada, a chajin (master of tea ceremony) that a tea ceremony would be held at his residence on December 14, of whom Azumamaro KADA, a scholar of classical Japanese literature and an old friend of Kuranosuke and his comrade Gengo OTAKA acting as Shinbei WAKIYA were disciples.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 Kozuke no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。「 he residence」を「his residence」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>内蔵助は確かな情報と判断し、討ち入りは同日夜と決する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke judged this as a correct information and decided the raid to be at night on the same day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke judged the information to be correct and set the attack for the night following the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke judged the information to be correct and set the attack for the night following the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>討ち入りの大義名分を記した口上書を作成し、12月2日、頼母子講を装って深川八幡の料亭で全ての同志達を集結させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a verbal note describing the legitimate reason for the raid and collected the comrades in a fancy Japanese-style restaurant in Fukagawa, Hachiman, disguising as Tanomoshi-ko (beneficial association) on December 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Voicing his justification for the attack, he gathered his comrades at high class restaurant in the Fukugawa area of Hachiman disguised as a Tanomoshi-ko (charity) on December 2.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Voicing his justification for the attack, he gathered his comrades at high class restaurant in the Fukugawa area of Hachiman disguised as a Tanomoshi-ko (charity) on December 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>これが最終会議となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the last meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was their last meeting.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was their last meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>討ち入り時の綱領「人々心覚」が定められ、その中で武器、装束、所持品、合言葉、吉良の首の処置など事細かに定め、さらに「吉良の首を取った者も庭の見張りの者も亡君の御奉公では同一。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The program of the raid &apos;everybody Shinkaku&apos; was decided, which minutely specified the arms, costumes, belongings, the secret password and the treatment of Kira&apos;s head and furthermore decided &apos;those who would get Kira&apos;s head and those who would act as a lookout in the garden were the same in the sacrifice for the deceased lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details of the attack codenamed &apos;remember your heart, everyone&apos; were decided minutely down to the type of arms, garb, equipment, and secret password, as well as who would receive the head of KIRA, how it would be treated, and that those who would act as lookouts in the garden would also do so at the sacrifice of the deceased lord.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details of the attack codenamed &apos;remember your heart, everyone&apos; were decided minutely down to the type of arms, garb, equipment, and secret password, as well as who would receive the head of KIRA, how it would be treated, and that those who would act as lookouts in the garden would also do so at the sacrifice of the deceased lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>よって自分の役割に異議を唱えない」ことを定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, everybody should not object to its role.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it was decided that each shall accept their role.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it was decided that each shall accept their role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="114">
<j>12月15日未明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before dawn on December 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Predawn on December 15.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Predawn on December 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>47人の赤穂浪士は本所吉良屋敷に討ち入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">47 Ako Roshis made a raid on Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of a private estate) Kira-tei Residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">47 Ako Roshis attacked the Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of a private estate) of Kira-tei Residence.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">47 Ako Roshis attacked the Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of a private estate) of Kira-tei Residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>表門は内蔵助が大将となり、裏門は嫡男大石主税が大将となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the front gate Kura no suke was Daisho (Major Captain) and on the back gate the legitimate son Chikara OISHI was Daisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke was Daisho (Major Captain) for the front gate while the legitimate heir Chikara OISHI was Daisho for the back gate.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke was Daisho (Major Captain) for the front gate while the legitimate heir Chikara OISHI was Daisho for the back gate.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>2時間近くの激闘の末に、浪士たちは遂に吉良上野介を探し出し、これを討ち果たして、首級を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a fierce battle for nearly two hours, Ako Roshis finally searched out Kira Kozuke no Suke, killed him and got the severed head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a fierce battle lasting nearly two hours, the Ako Roshi cornered Kozu no Suke KIRA, killed him, and severed his head.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a fierce battle lasting nearly two hours, the Ako Roshi cornered Kozukenosuke KIRA, killed him, and severed his head.</e>
<cmt>「 Kozu no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>本懐を果たした内蔵助たち赤穂浪士一行は江戸市中を行進し、浅野内匠頭の墓がある泉岳寺へ引き揚げると、吉良上野介の首級を亡き主君の墓前に供えて仇討ちを報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke and Ako Roshis, who had done Honkai, marched around Edo, went back to Sengaku-ji temple where there is the grave of Asano Takumi-no-Kami, put the severed head of Kira Kozuke no Suke in front of the deceased lord&apos;s grave and reported the revenge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke and the Ako Roshi upon fulfilling their desire for revenge, marched around Edo, returned to Sengaku-ji temple to the grave of Takuminokami ASANO and placed the severed head of Kozu no Suke KIRA in front of their deceased lord&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke and the Ako Roshi upon fulfilling their desire for revenge, marched around Edo, returned to Sengaku-ji Temple to the grave of Takuminokami ASANO and placed the severed head of Kozukenosuke KIRA in front of their deceased lord&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 temple」を「Temple」に修正しました。「 Kozu no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Final Moments</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Final Moments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>内蔵助は、吉田兼亮・富森正因の二名を大目付仙石久尚の邸宅へ送り、口上書を提出して幕府の裁定に委ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke sent the two, Kanesuke YOSHIDA and Masayori TOMINOMORI, to the house of Hisanao SENGOKU, Ometsuke (chief inspector of the Edo shogunate), and had them hand over the verbal note to him and entrusted the judgment to bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke sent Kanesuke YOSHIDA and Masayori TOMINOMORI to the house of the Ometsuke (cheif inspector of the Edo shogunate) Hisanao SENGOKU to deliver his dictated message entrusting judgement to the bakafu (feudal government).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke sent Kanesuke YOSHIDA and Masayori TOMINOMORI to the house of the Ometsuke (cheif inspector of the Edo shogunate) Hisanao SENGOKU to deliver his dictated message entrusting judgement to the bakafu (feudal government).</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>午後6時頃、幕府から徒目付の石川弥一右衛門、市野新八郎、松永小八郎の三人が泉岳寺へ派遣されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around six o&apos;clock in the evening, the three Kachi-metsuke title (job to do night duty and inspection), Yaichiemon ISHIKAWA, Shinhachiro ICHINO and Shohachiro MATSUNAGA were sent to Senkaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around six o&apos;clock that evening, the three Kachi-metsuke (night inspectors), Yaichiemon ISHIKAWA, Shinhachiro ICHINO, and Shohachiro MATSUNAGA, were sent to Senkaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around six o&apos;clock that evening, the three Kachi-metsuke (night inspectors), Yaichiemon ISHIKAWA, Shinhachiro ICHINO, and Shohachiro MATSUNAGA, were sent to Senkaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「 temple」を「Temple」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>内蔵助らは彼らの指示に従って仙石久尚の屋敷へ移動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following their instruction, Kura no suke moved to the house of Hisanao SENGOKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke relocated to the residence of Hisanao SENGOKU upon their orders.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke relocated to the residence of Hisanao SENGOKU upon their orders.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>幕府は赤穂浪士を4つの大名家に分けてお預けとし、内蔵助は肥後国熊本藩主細川綱利の屋敷に預けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakufu entrusted Ako Roshis to four Daimyo families (feudal lord family) and Kura no suke was left to the care of the house of Tsunatoshi HOSOKAWA, Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bakafu (feudal government) entrusted the Ako Roshi to four Daimyo families (families of feudal lords); Kura no Suke was left to the care of the house of Tsunayoshi HOSOWAWA of Kumamoto domain, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bakafu (feudal government) entrusted the Ako Roshi to four Daimyo families (families of feudal lords); Kuranosuke was left to the care of the house of Tsunayoshi HOSOKAWA of Kumamoto domain, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。「 HOSOWAWA」を「HOSOKAWA」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>長男主税は松平定直の屋敷に預けられたため、この時が息子との今生の別れとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first son Chikara was left to the house of Sadanao MATSUDAIRA and that was the last time he saw his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first son was left to the house of Sadanao MATSUDAIRA; it was the last time he saw his son.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first son was left to the house of Sadanao MATSUDAIRA; it was the last time he saw his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>仇討ちを義挙とする世論の中で、幕閣は助命か死罪かで揺れたが、天下の法を曲げる事はできないとした荻生徂徠などの意見を容れ、将軍綱吉は陪臣としては異例の上使を遣わせた上での切腹を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was public sentiment that the revenge was a heroic deed and the bakufu wavered between their mercy and death sentence, but the opinion of Sorai OGYU, who said the law of the world could not be distorted, was applied and Shogun Tsunayoshi exceptionally sent an envoy of the shogun to them as baishin (indirect vassal) and ordered them to commit Seppuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was much public sentiment that the revenge was a heroic deed as the bakafu (feudal government) wavered between mercy and a death sentence, but the opinion of Sorai OGYU was upheld which stated that the law of the world may not be distorted thus Shogun Tsunayoshi sent an envoy to them as baishin (indirect vassals) ordering them to commit seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was much public sentiment that the revenge was a heroic deed as the bakafu (feudal government) wavered between mercy and a death sentence, but the opinion of Sorai OGYU was upheld which stated that the law of the world may not be distorted thus Shogun Tsunayoshi sent an envoy to them as baishin (indirect vassals) ordering them to commit seppuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="125">
<j>元禄16年（1703年）2月4日、4大名家に切腹の命令がもたらされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 4, 1703 the order of Seppuku was delivered to four Daimyo families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 4, 1703 the order of Seppuku was delivered to four Daimyo families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 4, 1703 the order of Seppuku was delivered to four Daimyo families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>同日、幕府は吉良家当主吉良義周（吉良左兵衛、吉良上野介の養子）の領地没収と信濃国流罪の処分を決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day the bakufu decided the forfeit the lands and the deportation to Shinano Province of Kira family head Yoshimasa KIRA (Sahei KIRA, the adopted son of Kira Kozuke no Suke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that same day, the bakafu (feudal government) decided that the land of the Kira family should be forfeited and that the head of the Kira family, Yoshimasa KIRA (Sahei KIRA, the adopted son of Kozu no Suke KIRA), should be deported to Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that same day, the bakafu (feudal government) decided that the land of the Kira family should be forfeited and that the head of the Kira family, Yoshimasa KIRA (Sahei KIRA, the adopted son of Kozukenosuke KIRA), should be deported to Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>「 Kozu no Suke」を「Kozukenosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>細川邸に派遣された使者は、内蔵助と面識がある幕府目付荒木正羽であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The envoy sent to the house of Hosokawa was Masahane ARAKI, the bakufu&apos;s metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers), who was acquainted with Kura no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The envoy sent to the house of Hosokawa was Masahane ARAKI, the bakufu&apos;s metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers), who was acquainted with Kura no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The envoy sent to the house of Hosokawa was Masahane ARAKI, the bakufu&apos;s metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers), who was acquainted with Kuranosuke.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>内蔵助は細川家家臣安場一平の介錯で切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke committed Seppuku by Kaishaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him) of Ippei YASUBA, a vassal of Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kura no Suke, with the assistance of Ippei YASUBA, a vassal of the Hosokawa family acting as his second, committed seppuku by kaishaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke, with the assistance of Ippei YASUBA, a vassal of the Hosokawa family acting as his second, committed seppuku by kaishaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him).</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>享年45。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at 45.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 45.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 45.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>亡骸は主君浅野内匠頭と同じ高輪泉岳寺に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His dead body was buried in the same Takanawa Sengaku-ji temple as his lord Asano Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His body was buried in the same temple, Takanawa Sengaku-ji temple, as his lord Takuminokami ASANO.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His body was buried in the same temple, Takanawa Sengaku-ji Temple, as his lord Takuminokami ASANO.</e>
<cmt>「 temple」を「Temple」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>法名は忠誠院刃空浄剣居士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was 忠誠院刃空浄剣居士.</e>
<cmt>「忠誠院刃空浄剣居士」、読み方不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was 忠誠院刃空浄剣居士.</e>
<cmt>The reading of this name is unclear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was 忠誠院刃空浄剣居士.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>辞世の句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death haiku (Japanese poem).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death haiku</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death haiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="132">
<j>大石内蔵助の辞世の句一般には1として知られるが一部文献には2とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke OISHI&apos;s death haiku is known generally as 1 but as 2 in some documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some documents, Kura no Suke OISHI produced two death haiku although it is generally thought that he produced only one.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some documents, Kuranosuke OISHI produced two death haiku although it is generally thought that he produced only one.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>あら楽し 思ひは晴るる 身は捨つる 浮世の月に かかる雲なし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How happy I am for attaining my desire at the sacrifice of life and there being no cloud over the moon of the floating world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Happy at attaining my desire upon the sacrifice of life, the moon sits cloudless above the floating world</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Happy at attaining my desire upon the sacrifice of life, the moon sits cloudless above the floating world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>あら楽や 思ひははるる 身は捨つる 浮世の月に かかる雲なし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How easy I am for attaining my desire at the sacrifice of life and there being no cloud over the moon of the floating world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I rest easy upon attaining my desire at he sacrifice of life, the moon sits cloudless over the floating world</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I rest easy upon attaining my desire at he sacrifice of life, the moon sits cloudless over the floating world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>- 『介石記』、『江赤見聞記』、『義人遺草』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- &quot;Kaiseki-ki&quot; (Story of Ako Roshi), &quot;Goseki-kenbunki&quot; (Record of personal experiences of Goseki) and &quot;Gijin-iso&quot; (Righteous men&apos;s posthumous papers).</e>
<cmt>『介石記』を&quot;Kaiseki-ki&quot; (Story of Ako Roshi)、『江赤見聞記』を&quot;Goseki-kenbunki&quot; (Record of personal experiences of Goseki)、『義人遺草』を&quot;Gijin-iso&quot; (Righteous men&apos;s posthumous papers)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- &quot;Kaiseki-ki&quot; (The Story of Ako Roshi), &quot;Goseki-kenbunki&quot; (A Record of the Personal Experiences of Goseki) and &quot;Gijin-iso&quot; (The Posthumous Papers of Righteous Men).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- &quot;Kaiseki-ki&quot; (The Story of Ako Roshi), &quot;Goseki-kenbunki&quot; (A Record of the Personal Experiences of Goseki) and &quot;Gijin-iso&quot; (The Posthumous Papers of Righteous Men).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="136">
<j>しかしながら上記は浅野内匠頭の墓に対してのもので、実際には次が辞世の句とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the above haikus were for the grave of Asano Takumi no Kami and in fact the following is said to have been his death haiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hovever, the above poems were produced for the grave of Takuminokami ASANO while the following is said be his actual death haiku.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hovever, the above poems were produced for the grave of Takuminokami ASANO while the following is said to be his actual death haiku.</e>
<cmt>「 said be」を「said to be」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="137">
<j>極楽の 道はひとすぢ 君ともに 阿弥陀をそへて 四十八人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road to the Buddhist paradise is straight with you, having Amida, we forty-eight persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road to Buddhist paradise is straight for you, as, with Amida, we number 48</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road to Buddhist paradise is straight for you, as, with Amida, we number 48</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>人物評</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assessment of his personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An assessment of his personality</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An assessment of his personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="138">
<j>「内蔵助生質静にして言葉少な也」東條守拙（赤穂浪士9士の預かりを担当した三河国岡崎藩主水野忠之の家臣）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kura no suke was characteristically quiet and had few words&apos; by Morisetsu TOJO (the vassal of Tadayuki MIZUNO, the lord of Okazaki Domain Mikawa Province, who was in charge of custody of nine Ako Roshis).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morisetsu TOJO (the vassal of Tadayuki MIZUNO, lord of Okazaki domain, Mikawa province who held custody of nine of the Ako Roshi) described Kura no Suke as &apos;characteristically quiet, a man of few words&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morisetsu TOJO (the vassal of Tadayuki MIZUNO, lord of Okazaki domain, Mikawa province who held custody of nine of the Ako Roshi) described Kuranosuke as &apos;characteristically quiet, a man of few words&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="139">
<j>「良雄人となり温寛にして度あり」栗山潜峰（同時代の水戸学者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio&apos;s personality was well-tempered and restrained&apos; by Senbo KURIYAMA (his contemporary scholar of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senbo KURIYAMA, who studied Mitogaku (the style of learning cultivated in Mito domain) along with Yoshio, described him as &apos;well-tempered and restrained&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senbo KURIYAMA, who studied Mitogaku (the style of learning cultivated in Mito domain) along with Yoshio, described him as &apos;well-tempered and restrained&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="140">
<j>「良雄人となり簡静にして威望あり」室鳩巣（同時代の儒学者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio&apos;s personality was quiet and dignified&apos; by Kyuso MURO (his contemporary Confucian scholar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyuso MURO, with whom Yoshio studied Confucianism, described him as &apos;quiet and dignified&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyuso MURO, with whom Yoshio studied Confucianism, described him as &apos;quiet and dignified&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="141">
<j>「良雄人となり和易樸矜飾を喜ばず、国老に任ずといえども事に於いて預ること鮮し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio&apos;s personality was quiet and modest and did not strike an attitude though he was Karo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshi was quiet and modest didn&apos;t have much of an attitude for a Karo (chief retainer).&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshio was quiet and modest didn&apos;t have much of an attitude for a Karo (chief retainer).&apos;</e>
<cmt>「 Yoshi」を「Yoshio」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>しかも内実豪潔にして忠概を存じ最も族人に厚し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, his inner mind was large and loyal, especially for his family members&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he was broad-minded and loyal, especially to his family members.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he was broad-minded and loyal, especially to his family members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>」三宅観瀾（同時代の水戸学者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">by Kanran MIYAKE (his contemporary scholar of Mitogaku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kanran MIYAKE, his contemporary in the study of Mitogaku.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kanran MIYAKE, his contemporary in the study of Mitogaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="144">
<j>物静かで飾り気のない性格だが、内面は厚く人望があった事が窺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he was quiet and modest but big-hearted and respected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that we was quiet and honest, big-hearted and respected.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that we was quiet and honest, big-hearted and respected.</e>
<cmt>「 was」を「were」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="145">
<j>身長は157cm程度だと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His body height is said to have been about 157 cm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have been about 157 cm tall.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have been about 157 cm tall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>頭蓋骨の調査でこめかみの筋肉と下顎が発達していたことから庶民的な顔つきだったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The research of bone of his skull revealed the development of the muscle of temple and under jaw, which means his face was that of common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research done on bone from his skull analyzing the musculature of the temple and under jaw has revealed that his facial structure was like that of most people.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research done on bone from his skull analyzing the musculature of the temple and under jaw has revealed that his facial structure was like that of most people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="147">
<j>岡山などにある逸話では、実は内蔵助は、備前岡山藩池田家家老池田玄蕃の子で、はじめは池田久馬と名乗っていたが、大石良欽の養子入りをしたなどという話が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains an anecdote in Okayama and so on, that in fact Kura no suke was the son of Genba IKEDA, the chief retainer of IKEDA family of Okayama Domain, Bizen Province, and firstly he identified himself as Kyuma IKEDA but was adopted to Yoshitaka OISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An anecdote exist in Okayama that Kura no Suke was, in fact, the son of Genba IKEDA, the chief retainer of the IKEDA family of Okayama domain, Bizen province originally going by the name of Kyuma IKEDA and was later adopted by Yoshitaka OISHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An anecdote exist in Okayama that Kuranosuke was, in fact, the son of Genba IKEDA, the chief retainer of the IKEDA family of Okayama domain, Bizen province originally going by the name of Kyuma IKEDA and was later adopted by Yoshitaka OISHI.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>しかし良雄が切腹前に幕府に出した親類書には、「一、養父・実祖父　二十八年以前正月病死大石内蔵助　一、実父三十一年前九月病死大石権内」となっていることから、養子説の信憑性は低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the document of Yoshio&apos;s kinship submitted to bakufu before his Seppuku, &apos;1, foster father and real grand father died of illness on New Year&apos;s day twenty-eight years ago Kura no suke OISHI, 1, real father died of illness in September thirty-one years ago Gennai OISHI,&apos; which means the low credibility of his adopted child theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the document of Yoshi&apos;s kinship, which was submitted to the bakafu (feudal government) prior to his seppuku states &apos;1. His foster father and real grandfather, Kura no Suke OISHI, died of illness on New Year&apos;s Day 28 years ago, 1. His real father, Gennai OISHI, died of illness in September 31 years ago&apos;, which reduces the credibility of the adopted child theory.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the document of Yoshi&apos;s kinship, which was submitted to the bakafu (feudal government) prior to his seppuku states &apos;1. His foster father and real grandfather, Kuranosuke OISHI, died of illness on New Year&apos;s Day 28 years ago, 1. His real father, Gennai OISHI, died of illness in September 31 years ago&apos;, which reduces the credibility of the adopted child theory.</e>
<cmt>「 Kura no Suke」を「Kuranosuke」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>おそらく生母の出自にまつわって生じた俗説と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably, it seems to be a popular saying from the origin of his real mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible that this account of his lineage was passed on by his birth mother.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible that this account of his lineage was passed on by his birth mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>しかし地元の岡山などでは現在に至るまで広く信じられているようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the local areas in Okayama and so on it seems to be believed until now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To this day, it is still believed in the local areas of Okayama.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To this day, it is still believed in the local areas of Okayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>赤穂浪士終焉の地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place where Ako Roshi died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death place of the Ako Roshi.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death place of the Ako Roshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>大石良雄外十六人忠烈の跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of place where Yoshio OISHI and sixteen Ako Roshis died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of the location where Yoshio OISHI and sixteen Ako Roshi died.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of the location where Yoshio OISHI and sixteen Ako Roshi died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="151">
<j>- 東京都港区 (東京都)高輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture (Tokyo Prefecture) Takanawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takanawa, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takanawa, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>水野監物邸跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remain of the house of Kenmotsu MIZUNO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of the house of Kenmotsu MIZUNO.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of the house of Kenmotsu MIZUNO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="152">
<j>- 東京都港区 (東京都)芝 (東京都港区)五丁目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture (Tokyo Prefecture) Shiba (Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) 5 chome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiba 5 chome, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiba 5 chome, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>大石主税良金ら十士切腹の地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place where Chikara OISHI Yoshikane and ten Ako Roshis committed Seppuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The place where Chikara OISHI, Yoshikane, and ten Ako Roshi committed Seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The place where Chikara OISHI, Yoshikane, and ten Ako Roshi committed Seppuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="153">
<j>- 東京都港区 (東京都)三田 (東京都港区)二丁目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture (Tokyo Prefecture) Mita (Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) 2 chome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mita 2 chome, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mita 2 chome, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>毛利甲斐守邸跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remain of the house of Mori Kai no kami (Mori, Governor of Kai Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of the house of Kainokami MORI (Mori, Governor of Kai Province).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of the house of Kainokami MORI (Mori, Governor of Kai Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="154">
<j>- 東京都港区 (東京都)六本木六丁目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Minato Ward, Tokyo Prefecture (Tokyo Prefecture) Roppongi 6 chome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roppongi 6 chome, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Wording Change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roppongi 6 chome, Minato Ward, Tokyo, (Tokyo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 てら1971(id:131768), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), Extrahitz(id:26245), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Ykosub(id:2877), 味っ子(id:17086), Tribot(id:186681), 百人(id:16483), Toto-tarou(id:16648), A-Taul(id:41790), Koshoku(id:15691), Knua(id:66861), Loveless(id:129239), Kone(id:377), 百楽天(id:5266), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Yas(id:739), Kouko0515(id:100370), KASAGI(id:24405), Tak1701d(id:109054), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Blackhouse(id:65078), Kentin(id:6768), Izayohi(id:13095), ととりん(id:31982), Bergmann(id:85282), 水野白楓(id:22811), GoGoDoll(id:131511), Tiyoringo(id:70026), わがまま小皇帝(id:39717), Yanahan(id:2437), Seibuabina(id:37532), 総州之毛豆(id:26880), Kagetudo(id:163875), Watamas(id:12730), Ibex(id:19412), Rusk(id:9895), Carkuni(id:79281), ゐ(id:795), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Umiyuri(id:194367), Safkan(id:423), Junger(id:10282), Louperibot(id:128971), きまま(id:183217), MiraModreno(id:212669), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>