<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宗金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokin</e>
<cmt>用語共有登録訳語の表記</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宗金（そうきん、生年不詳 - 1455年（康正元年））は、室町時代中期の博多の大商人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokin (宗金) (year of birth unknown - 1455) is a potential merchant in Hakata at the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokin (宗金) (year of birth unknown - 1455) was a merchant in Hakata in the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokin (year of birth unknown - 1455) was a merchant in Hakata in the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>漢字は不要かと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>子は宗性春。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son is So-seijun.</e>
<cmt>宗性春→Seijun So [http://kotobank.jp/word/宋性春]。宗が苗字、性春が名前のようですので通常ならSeijun SO　となるのですが、父親（宗金）をSokinと表記しているので、同じ方式でSoseijunとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son was So-seijun.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son was So-seijun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>初めは九州探題渋川満頼、その後大友氏の配下で明や李氏朝鮮との貿易で活躍した。、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active in the trade with Ming and the Yi Dynasty Korea, firstly under the Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) Mitsuyori SHIBUKAWA, and then under the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>九州探題→Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) [http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=九州探題&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=05239074468000], 渋川満頼→Mitsuyori SHIBUKAWA [日本大百科全書（小学館）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active in trade with Ming Dynasty and the Yi Dynasty in Korea, firstly under the Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) Mitsuyori SHIBUKAWA, and then under the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active in trade with the Ming Dynasty in China and the Yi Dynasty in Korea, firstly under the Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) Mitsuyori SHIBUKAWA, and then under the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1419年（応永26年）の応永の外寇後に訪れた李氏朝鮮の使者宋希璟を接待し、共に京へと赴いて幕府との仲介役を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1419, he received and entertained Song Gik-yeong (宋希璟), the delegate dispatched from the Yi Dynasty Korea after the foreign invasion in the Oei Era, and accompanied him to Kyoto to play the reconciliatory role between he and the Japan&apos;s feudal government (Bakufu).</e>
<cmt>李氏朝鮮は、the Joseon Dynasty [英辞郎 on the WEB]という言い方もあります。　宋希璟→Song Gik-yeong [http://www.absoluteastronomy.com/topics/Oei_Invasion], 幕府→Japan&apos;s feudal government (Bakufu) [英辞郎 on the WEB]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1419, he received and entertained Song Gik-yeong (宋希璟), the delegate dispatched from the Yi Dynasty in Korea after the foreign invasion of the Oei Era, and accompanied him to Kyoto to play a reconciliatory role between him and Japan&apos;s feudal government (Bakufu).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1419, he received and entertained Song Gik-yeong, the delegate dispatched from the Yi Dynasty in Korea after the foreign invasion of the Oei Era, and accompanied him to Kyoto to play a reconciliatory role between him and Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>漢字は不要かと思います。「Japan&apos;s feudal government (Bakufu)」→「Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>室町幕府6代征夷大将軍足利義教や斯波氏・渋川氏・大友氏・少弐氏などの使節として朝鮮貿易を代行し、1425年（応永32年）には朝鮮から貿易を許す印である図書を与えられ、受図書人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an envoy of the 6th Muromachi shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA Yoshimitsu as well as of other feudal clans, such as Shiba clan, Shibukawa clan, Otomo clan, Shoni clan, he worked as the representative in the trade with Korea, and in 1425 he was granted the special privileges evidence in trading (Tosho), sign of trade pammision of Korea, and appointed as Jutoshonin.</e>
<cmt>図書→定訳不明the special privileges evidence in trading (Tosho)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an envoy of the 6th Muromachi shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, Yoshimitsu as well as of other feudal clans, such as the Shiba clan, Shibukawa clan, Otomo clan, Shoni clan, worked as the representative in trade with Korea, and in 1425 he was granted special privileges in trading (Tosho), and the sign of trade permission with Korea, and was appointed as Jutoshonin.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an envoy of the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Muromachi bakufu, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, as well as of other feudal clans, such as the Shiba clan, Shibukawa clan, Otomo clan, and Shoni clan, he worked as the representative in trade with Korea, and in 1425 he was granted special privileges in trading (Tosho), which was the sign of trade permission with Korea, and was appointed as Jutoshonin (Japanese given Korean government evidence to be granted special privileges in trading).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1436年（永享8年）の遣明船にも関与する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1436, he was also involved in the project of Envoy Ship Dispatched to Ming China (Kenminsen).</e>
<cmt>遣明船→Envoy Ship Dispatched to Ming China (Kenminsen) [http://www.lahosken.san-frabcusci.ca.us/departures/Japan1/3.html参照]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1436, he was also involved in the project of envoy ships dispatched to Ming China (Kenminsen).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1436, he was also involved in the project of Kenminsen (envoy ships dispatched to Ming China).</e>
<cmt>「envoy ships dispatched to Ming China (Kenminsen)」→「Kenminsen (envoy ships dispatched to Ming China)」としました。余分なスペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>文宗 (朝鮮王)が李氏朝鮮第5代国王に即位（1450年）した際には祝いに駆けつけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Munjong (Korea) ascended to the Throne (1450) as the 5th Emperor of the Yi Dynasty Korea, he hasten to visit Korea to celebrate the enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Munjong (Korea) ascended to the Throne (1450) as the 5th Emperor of the Yi Dynasty in Korea, he hastened to visit Korea to celebrate the enthronement.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Munjong (Korea) ascended to the Throne (1450) as the 5th Emperor of the Yi Dynasty in Korea, he hastened to visit Korea to celebrate the enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>妙楽寺 (福岡市)の僧であったと言われており、公卿山科教言の日記『教言卿記』にも同名の僧が登場するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was a Buddhist monk of Myoraku-ji Temple (Fukuoka City) and a monk of the same name appears in the diary of Kugyo (Court noble) Noritoki YAMASHINA, &quot;Noritoki Kyo Ki&quot; (diary of Noritoki YAMASHINA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was a Buddhist monk of Myoraku-ji Temple (Fukuoka City) and a monk of the same name appears in the diary of Kugyo (Court noble) Noritoki YAMASHINA, &quot;Noritoki Kyo Ki&quot; (diary of Noritoki YAMASHINA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was a Buddhist monk of Myoraku-ji Temple (Fukuoka City) and a monk of the same name appears in the diary of Kugyo (Court noble) Noritoki YAMASHINA, &quot;Noritoki Kyo Ki&quot; (diary of Noritoki YAMASHINA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Pontafon(id:33761), たね(id:10372), Smallers(id:74093), 代言人(id:33675), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>