<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日置蓑麻呂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HEKI no Minomaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HEKI no Minomaro</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HEKI no Minomaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日置蓑麻呂（へきのみのまろ、704年生～没年不明)は奈良時代～平安時代の官人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HEKI no Minomaro (704-date of death unknown) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) who lived from the Nara period to Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HEKI no Minomaro (704-date of death unknown) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) who lived from the Nara period to Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HEKI no Minomaro (704-year of death unknown) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) who lived from the Nara period to Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「没年不明」→統一リストに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>姓は造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His surname was Miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His surname was Miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title used in ancient Japan) was Miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt>「姓」→意味を明確にするため表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に栄井蓑麻呂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he changed the name to SAKAI no Minomaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he changed his name to SAKAI no Minomaro.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he changed his name to SAKAI no Minomaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>左京三条三坊戸主の日置男成の戸口。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 戸口 of HEKI no Onari (男成) who was the head of a family in Sakyo Sanjo Sanbo.</e>
<cmt>戸口、男成の読み方、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 戸口 of HEKI no Onari (男成) who was the head of a family in Sakyo Sanjo Sanbo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 戸口 of HEKI no Onari (男成) who was the head of a family in Sakyo Sanjo Sanbo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天平宝字8年に栄井宿禰に改姓し、経師を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 764 he changed the surname to SAKAI no Sukune and worked as kyoji (a craftsman who mounts calligraphy or paintings on scroll or sliding doors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 764 he changed his surname to SAKAI no Sukune and worked as kyoji (a craftsman who mounts calligraphy or paintings on scroll or sliding doors).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 764 he changed his surname and kabane to Sakai no Sukune and worked as kyoji (a craftsman who mounts calligraphy or paintings on scroll or sliding doors).</e>
<cmt>「栄井宿禰に改姓し」の部分を修正、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天平宝字3年ころに少初位下になり、学才を認められ、延暦2年までに正五位下に昇進、その間、丹波員外目・大内記・丹波介・丹波守・図書頭・大学頭・東宮学士・陰陽頭などを歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he became Shosoige (the lowest court rank) around 759, he was admitted to be a talented scholar and promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) until 783, during which period he held positions such as Tanba no inge no sakan (supernumerary official of Tanba Province), Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Tanba no suke (assistant governor of Tanba Province), Tanba no kami (the governor of Tanba Province), Zusho no kami (Director of the Bureau of Drawings and Books), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince) and Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he became Shosoige (the lowest court rank) around 759, he was admitted to be a talented scholar and promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) until 783, during which period he held positions such as Tanba no inge no sakan (supernumerary official of Tanba Province), Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Tanba no suke (assistant governor of Tanba Province), Tanba no kami (the governor of Tanba Province), Zusho no kami (Director of the Bureau of Drawings and Books), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince), and Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he became Shosoige (the lowest court rank) around 759, he was admitted to be a talented scholar and promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) until 783, during which period he held positions such as Tanba no inge no sakan (supernumerary official of Tanba Province), Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Tanba no suke (assistant governor of Tanba Province), Tanba no kami (the governor of Tanba Province), Zusho no kami (Director of the Bureau of Drawings and Books), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince), and Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>