<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>黒田孝高</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka KURODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka KURODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka KURODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>黒田 孝高／黒田 如水（くろだ よしたか／くろだ じょすい）は戦国時代 (日本)、安土桃山時代、江戸時代前期にかけての武将・大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka KURODA also known as Josui KURODA was a military commander and feudal lord during the period spanning over the Civil War era (Japan), the Azuchi-Momoyama Period and the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka KURODA, also known as Josui KURODA, was a military commander and feudal lord during the period spanning over the Civil War era (Japan), the Azuchi-Momoyama Period and the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka KURODA, also known as Josui KURODA, was a military commander and feudal lord during the period spanning over the Sengoku period (period of Warring States), the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→統一リストの表記に修正、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>豊前国中津城主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the lord of Nakatsu-jo Castle in the Buzen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the lord of Nakatsu-jo Castle in the Buzen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Nakatsu-jo Castle in the Buzen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>孝高は諱で通称の官兵衛、並びに出家後の如水の号で有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka was his real name but his common name Kanbei and his Buddhist name Josui which he took up after entering the priesthood are well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka was his real name but his common name Kanbei and his Buddhist name Josui, which he took up after entering the priesthood, are well known.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka was his real name but his common name Kanbei and his Buddhist name Josui, which he took up after entering the priesthood, are well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>豊臣秀吉の側近として仕え、調略や他大名との交渉などに活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as his close aide playing an active role in covert operations to induce defection and to negotiate with other feudal lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as his close aide by playing an active role in covert operations to induce defection and to negotiate with other feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as his close aide by playing an active role in covert operations to induce defection and to negotiate with other feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ドン・シメオンという洗礼名を持つキリシタン大名でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Christian feudal lord with a baptismal name of Don Simeon.</e>
<cmt>http://www.reference.com/browse/Kuroda+Kanbei</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Christian feudal lord with the baptismal name of Don Simeon.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Christian feudal lord with the baptismal name of Don Simeon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出身</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>天文15年11月29日（1546年12月22日）、黒田職隆の嫡男として姫路に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born the legitimate heir of Mototaka KURODA in Himeji on December 22, 1546.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the legitimate heir of Mototaka KURODA in Himeji on December 22, 1546.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the legitimate heir of Mototaka KURODA in Himeji on January 1, 1547.</e>
<cmt>December 22, 1546→January 1, 1547に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>黒田氏は、『寛政重修諸家譜』などによれば近江国伊香郡黒田村（現在の滋賀県伊香郡木ノ本町黒田）の武家出身とされるが定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to some documents such as &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu,&quot; the Kuroda clan originated from the samurai class in Kuroda Village, Ika County, the Province of Omi (presently Kuroda, Kinomoto Town, Ika County, Shiga Prefecture), it remains uncertain.</e>
<cmt>「郡」の英訳は&apos;county&apos;ですので、そちらで統一します。以下同じです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some documents such as Kansei Choshu Shokafu, the Kuroda clan was said to originate from the samurai class in Kuroda Village, Ika County, the Province of Omi (presently Kuroda, Kinomoto Town, Ika County, Shiga Prefecture), but this remains uncertain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some documents such as &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (genealogies of vassals in the Edo bakufu, Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the Kuroda clan was said to originate from the samurai class in Kuroda Village, Ika County, Omi Province (presently Kuroda, Kinomoto-cho, Ika-gun, Shiga Prefecture), but this remains uncertain.</e>
<cmt>Kansei Choshu Shokafu→クォーテーション・補足を追加、住所表記を一部修正(ただし現在は「伊香郡木ノ本町黒田」→「長浜市木之本町黒田」に変更済、参照: http://www.post.japanpost.jp/cgi-zip/zipcode.php?pref=25&amp;city=1255021&amp;id=95498&amp;merge=3)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>孝高の祖父・黒田重隆の代に播磨に入り、御着城（現在の姫路市東部）を中心に播州平野に勢力を持っていた小大名の小寺政職に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kuroda clan came to Harima during the time of Yoshitaka&apos;s grandfather Shigetaka KURODA and worked for Masamoto KODERA who was a minor feudal lord having power in the Banshu plain with Gichaku-jo Castle (presently Eastern Himeji City) being at its center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuroda clan came to Harima during the time of Yoshitaka&apos;s grandfather Shigetaka KURODA and worked for Masamoto KODERA who was a minor feudal lord having power in the Banshu plain with Gichaku-jo Castle (presently Eastern Himeji City) being at its center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuroda clan came to Harima during the time of Yoshitaka&apos;s grandfather Shigetaka KURODA and worked for Masamoto KODERA who was a minor feudal lord having power in the Banshu plain with Gichaku-jo Castle (presently Eastern Himeji City) being at its center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>政職は黒田氏を高く評価し、重隆を重臣として姫路城代に任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto had a high opinion of the Kuroda clan and appointed Shigetaka as a senior executive and the chief of staff of Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto had a high opinion of the Kuroda clan and appointed Shigetaka as a senior executive and the chief of staff of Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto had a high opinion of the Kuroda clan and appointed Shigetaka as a senior executive and the chief of staff of Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>重隆の子職隆には自らの養女を嫁がせ、小寺の名字を名乗らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto additionally gave his adoptive daughter in marriage to Shigetaka&apos;s son Mototaka and had Mototaka go by the family name of KODERA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto additionally gave his adoptive daughter in marriage to Shigetaka&apos;s son Mototaka and had Mototaka go by the family name of KODERA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto additionally gave his adoptive daughter in marriage to Shigetaka&apos;s son Mototaka and had Mototaka go by the family name of KODERA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>播州時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Banshuu Years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Banshuu Years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Banshu (Harima Province) Years</e>
<cmt>Banshuu→Banshuとし、補足を追加</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>永禄10年（1567年）頃、孝高は家督を継ぎ、櫛橋伊定の娘を正室に迎え、姫路城代となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1567, becoming head of the family, Yoshitaka married a daughter of Koresada KUHASHI and assumed the post of the chief of staff of Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1567, becoming head of the family, Yoshitaka married a daughter of Koresada KUHASHI and assumed the post of the chief of staff of Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1567, becoming head of the family, Yoshitaka married a daughter of Koresada KUHASHI and assumed the post of the chief of staff of Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>天正元年（1573年）、小寺氏など播磨の小大名たちは畿内で勢力を拡大する織田信長と山陰地方・山陽地方に勢力を張る毛利輝元の2つの大勢力に挟まれることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, minor feudal lords in the Harima region such as the Kodera clan became wedged between the 2 major powers including Nobunaga ODA, who was expanding his power base in Kinai (the term referring to 5 provinces around Kyoto including Yamashiro, Yamato, Kawachi, Izumi and Settsu) and Terumoto MORI who had established his stronghold in the Sanin and Sanyo regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, minor feudal lords in the Harima region, such as the Kodera clan, became wedged between the two major powers including Nobunaga ODA, who was expanding his power base in Kinai (the term referring to five provinces around Kyoto including Yamashiro, Yamato, Kawachi, Izumi and Settsu) and Terumoto MORI, who had established his stronghold in the Sanin and Sanyo regions.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, minor feudal lords in the Harima region, such as the Kodera clan, became wedged between the two major powers including Nobunaga ODA, who was expanding his power base in Kinai (the term referring to five provinces around Kyoto including Yamashiro, Yamato, Kawachi, Izumi and Settsu) and Terumoto MORI, who had established his stronghold in the Sanin and Sanyo regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天正3年（1575年）、信長は羽柴秀吉（豊臣秀吉）に命じて播磨に進駐させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1575, Nobunaga ordered Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) to station in Harima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1575, Nobunaga ordered Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) to stay in Harima.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1575, Nobunaga ordered Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) to stay in Harima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>信長の才能を高く評価していた孝高は早くから主君・政職に織田家への臣従を勧め、近隣勢力も説得していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appreciating Nobunaga&apos;s ability, Yoshitaka recommended his lord Masamoto to render homage and service to the Oda family from early on and, in addition, persuaded the powerful people in the neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appreciating Nobunaga&apos;s ability, Yoshitaka recommended his lord Masamoto to render homage and service to the Oda family from early on and, in addition, persuaded the powerful people in the neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appreciating Nobunaga&apos;s ability, Yoshitaka recommended his lord Masamoto to render homage and service to the Oda family from early on and, in addition, persuaded the powerful people in the neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>織田家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retainer years under the Oda family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His years as a retainer under the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Years as a Retainer under the Oda Family</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが天正6年（1578年）、播磨の大勢力である三木城主別所長治が織田氏に反旗を翻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1578, however, the lord of Miki-jo Castle Nagaharu BESSHO who was the heavy weight in Harima rose in revolt against the Oda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1578, however, the lord of Miki-jo Castle Nagaharu BESSHO, who was the heavy weight in Harima, rose in revolt against the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1578, however, the lord of Miki-jo Castle Nagaharu BESSHO, who was the heavy weight in Harima, rose in revolt against the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>the Oda clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これに他の播磨の勢力は大きく動揺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This reeled the other powers in Harima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This reeled the other powers in Harima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This reeled the other powers in Harima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに織田家の重臣で摂津国を任されていた荒木村重が信長に対して謀反を起こし、有岡城（兵庫県伊丹市）に立て籠もった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Murashige ARAKI, who was a Nobunaga&apos;s senior retainer and had been made in charge of the Province of Settsu, rebelled against Nobunaga and locked him and his people in Arioka-jo Castle (Itami City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Murashige ARAKI, who was a Nobunaga&apos;s senior retainer and had been made in charge of the Province of Settsu, rebelled against Nobunaga and locked him and his people in Arioka-jo Castle (Itami City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, Murashige ARAKI, who was a Nobunaga&apos;s senior retainer and had been made in charge of the Settsu Province, rebelled against Nobunaga and locked him and his people in Arioka-jo Castle (Itami City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Province of Settsu→Settsu Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>このとき、孝高は村重を翻意させるため有岡城に乗り込んだが交渉は成功せず、捕縛されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka got inside of Arioka-jo Castle to urge Murashige to reconsider but the negotiation broke down and he was captured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka got inside of Arioka-jo Castle to urge Murashige to reconsider but the negotiations broke down and he was captured.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka got inside of Arioka-jo Castle to urge Murashige to reconsider but the negotiations broke down and he was captured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1年後、有岡城は落城し孝高は家臣の栗山利安によって救出されたが、劣悪な環境の土牢に長期に渡って押し込められていたため脚部の関節に障害が残り、歩行がやや不自由になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A year later, Arioka-jo Castle fell whereby Yoshitaka was rescued by Toshiyasu KURIYAMA but since Yoshitaka had been confined in a dungeon of extremely poor living conditions for a prolonged period, he developed leg joint problems leaving him with a minor walking difficulty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A year later, Arioka-jo Castle fell, whereby Yoshitaka was rescued by Toshiyasu KURIYAMA but since Yoshitaka had been confined in a dungeon with extremely poor living conditions for a prolonged period, he developed leg joint problems leaving him with a minor walking difficulty.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A year later, Arioka-jo Castle fell, whereby Yoshitaka was rescued by Toshiyasu KURIYAMA but since Yoshitaka had been confined in a dungeon with extremely poor living conditions for a prolonged period, he developed leg joint problems leaving him with a minor walking difficulty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このため、以後は合戦の指揮も馬上ではなく輿に乗って行うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he consequently started to command riding a litter and not horseback in the battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he consequently started to command while riding in a palenquin rather than horseback in the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he consequently started to command while riding in a palenquin rather than horseback in the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>村重の謀反の際、主君の小寺政職も同調して信長から離反したため、信長の嫡男・織田信忠によって討伐された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Murashige rebelled, since his lord Masamoto KODERA also revolted against Nobunaga in concurrence with Murashige, Masamoto was conquered by Nobunaga&apos;s heir Nobutada ODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Murashige rebelled, since his lord, Masamoto KODERA, also revolted against Nobunaga in concurrence with Murashige, Masamoto was conquered by Nobunaga&apos;s heir Nobutada ODA</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Murashige rebelled, since his lord, Masamoto KODERA, also revolted against Nobunaga in concurrence with Murashige, Masamoto was conquered by Nobunaga&apos;s heir Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>孝高は謀反人の名字を名乗ることをよしとせず、本来の黒田の名字に改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking a dim view of having the surname of a rebel, Yoshitaka returned to his original family name of KURODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking a dim view of having the surname of a rebel, Yoshitaka returned to his original family name of KURODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking a dim view of having the surname of a rebel, Yoshitaka returned to his original family name of KURODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>救出された孝高は信長から播磨国内に1万石を与えられ、秀吉の与力となって参謀として活躍するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rescued Yoshitaka was given a property with ten thousand koku in the Province of Harima and began to play an active role as an aide to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rescued Yoshitaka was given a property with ten thousand koku in the Province of Harima and began to play an active role as an aide to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rescued Yoshitaka was given a property with ten thousand koku in the Harima Province and began to play an active role as an aide to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Province of Harima→Harima Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>天正8年（1580年）、「姫路城は播州統治の適地である」として居城を秀吉に提供し、自身は飾東郡の国府山城に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1580, Yoshitaka offered his castle to Hideyoshi saying, &apos;Himeji-jo Castle is the ideal place to govern Banshu (the Province of Harima)&apos; and moved to Kozan-jo Castle in Shikito county.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1580, Yoshitaka offered his castle to Hideyoshi saying, &apos;Himeji-jo Castle is the ideal place to govern Banshu (the Province of Harima)&apos; and moved to Kozan-jo Castle in Shikito county.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1580, Yoshitaka offered his castle to Hideyoshi saying, &apos;Himeji-jo Castle is the ideal place to govern Banshu&apos; and moved to Kozan-jo Castle in Shikito county.</e>
<cmt>(the Province of Harima) を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>天正9年（1581年）、秀吉は因幡の鳥取城を兵糧攻めで落城させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1581, Hideyoshi captured Tottori-jo Castle in Inaba using starvation tactics.</e>
<cmt>『兵糧攻め』は&apos;starvation tactics&apos; を使うのが一般的です.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1581, Hideyoshi captured Tottori-jo Castle in Inaba using siege tactics.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1581, Hideyoshi captured Tottori-jo Castle in Inaba using siege tactics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>策略により周辺の米を買い占めた上で完全に包囲して兵糧の補給を絶ったため、鳥取城内は飢餓で凄惨極まりない状況に追い込まれて3ヶ月で降伏を余儀なくされたが、この作戦を秀吉に献策したのは孝高だったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on strategy, since Hideyoshi had Tottori-jo Castle completely surrounded and cut its food supply after buying up all the rice in the area, people in Tottori-jo Castle were devastated by starvation that left them with no other options but to surrender in 3 months, it is said that it was Yoshitaka who suggested this idea to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on strategy, since Hideyoshi had Tottori-jo Castle completely surrounded and cut its food supply after buying up all the rice in the area, people in Tottori-jo Castle were devastated by starvation that left them with no other options but to surrender in 3 months. It is said that it was Yoshitaka who suggested this idea to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on strategy, since Hideyoshi had Tottori-jo Castle completely surrounded and cut its food supply after buying up all the rice in the area, people in Tottori-jo Castle were devastated by starvation that left them with no other options but to surrender in three months; it is said that it was Yoshitaka who suggested this idea to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;3&quot;をスペルアウト、二文に分かれているため一文になるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>また天正10年（1582年）、毛利氏の部将・清水宗治が守る備中高松城攻略に際し秀吉は巨大な堤防を築いて水攻めにしたが、この作戦を献策したのも孝高だったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in 1582, during the campaign to capture Takamatsu-jo Castle in Bicchu, which the military commander for the Mori clan Muneharu SHIMIZU was in charge of, Hideyoshi had colossal dikes built to flood the castle and it is said that it was again Yoshitaka who suggested this strategy to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in 1582, during the campaign to capture Takamatsu-jo Castle in Bicchu, which the military commander for the Mori clan, Muneharu SHIMIZU, was in charge of, Hideyoshi had colossal dikes built to flood the castle and it is said that it was again Yoshitaka who suggested this strategy to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in 1582, during the campaign to capture Takamatsu-jo Castle in Bitchu, which the military commander for the Mori clan, Muneharu SHIMIZU, was in charge of, Hideyoshi had colossal dikes built to flood the castle and it is said that it was again Yoshitaka who suggested this strategy to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu→Bitchuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>豊臣家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retainer years under the Toyotomi family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Years as retainer under the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Years as a Retainer under the Toyotomi Family</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更、a Retainerとし、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>高松城攻めの最中、京都で本能寺の変が起こり、信長が横死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Takamatsu-jo Castle campaign, the Incident at Honno-ji Temple took place and Nobunaga died a violent death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Takamatsu-jo Castle campaign, the Incident at Honno-ji Temple took place and Nobunaga died a violent death.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Takamatsu-jo Castle campaign, the Incident at Honno-ji Temple took place and Nobunaga died a violent death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>信長の死を知った孝高は秀吉に対して、「御運が開かれる機会が参りましたな」と進言したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, learning of Nobunaga&apos;s death, Yoshitaka said to Hideyoshi, &quot;Your lucky opportunity has arrived, hasn&apos;t it?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that upon learning of Nobunaga&apos;s death, Yoshitaka said to Hideyoshi, &quot;Your lucky opportunity has arrived, hasn&apos;t it?&quot;</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that upon learning of Nobunaga&apos;s death, Yoshitaka said to Hideyoshi, &apos;Your lucky opportunity has arrived, hasn&apos;t it?&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そして、秀吉が毛利輝元と和睦し中国大返しを行なったのも、孝高の進言によると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Hideyoshi made peace with Terumoto MORI and turned around in Chugoku (the area covering the present 5 prefectures including Okayama, Hiroshima, Tottori, Shimane and Yamaguchi) leading his army back to Kyoto based on the suggestion offered by Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Hideyoshi made peace with Terumoto MORI and turned around in Chugoku (the area covering the present five prefectures including Okayama, Hiroshima, Tottori, Shimane and Yamaguchi) leading his army back to Kyoto based on the suggestion offered by Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Hideyoshi made peace with Terumoto MORI and turned around in Chugoku (the area covering the present five prefectures including Okayama, Hiroshima, Tottori, Shimane and Yamaguchi) leading his army back to Kyoto based on the suggestion offered by Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>天正11年（1583年）の賤ヶ岳の戦い、天正12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いにも参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in the battle of Shizugatake in 1583 and the battle of Komaki Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in the battle of Shizugatake in 1583 and the battle of Komaki Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583 and the Battle of Komaki Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt>battleの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>天正13年（1585年）には四国征伐に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participated in the campaign to conquer Shikoku (one of the islands making up Japan covering 4 prefectures including Tokushima, Ehime, Kagawa and Kochi) in 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participated in the campaign to conquer Shikoku (one of the islands making up Japan covering four prefectures including Tokushima, Ehime, Kagawa and Kochi) in 1585.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participated in the campaign to conquer Shikoku (one of the islands making up Japan covering four prefectures including Tokushima, Ehime, Kagawa and Kochi) in 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>このとき、孝高は敵将・長宗我部元親の策略を見抜いて、次々と敵城を陥落させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, predicting the strategies of the enemy commander Motochika CHOSOKABE, Yoshitaka too control of the castles on the enemy side one after the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, predicting the strategies of the enemy commander Motochika CHOSOKABE, Yoshitaka took control of the castles on the enemy side one after the other.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, predicting the strategies of the enemy commander Motochika CHOSOKABE, Yoshitaka took control of the castles on the enemy side one after the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>天正14年（1586年）、従五位下勘解由使に叙任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586, he was assigned as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank Lower Grade) Kageyushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1586, he was assigned as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank Lower Grade) Kageyushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1586, he was assigned as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank Lower Grade) Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners).</e>
<cmt>Kageyushiの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>天正15年（1587年）の九州征伐では毛利氏、宇喜多氏などの軍勢の戦目付として、戦勝に貢献している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kyushu campaign in 1587, he worked as a supervisor for the troops of the Mori clan and the Ukita clan contributing to their victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kyushu campaign in 1587, he worked as a supervisor for the troops of the Mori clan and the Ukita clan contributing to their victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kyushu Campaign in 1587, he worked as a supervisor for the troops of the Mori clan and the Ukita clan contributing to their victory.</e>
<cmt>campaignの頭文字を大文字に変更、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>九州平定後、豊前中津で12万5000石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After restoring order in Kyushu, he was awarded 12,500 koku in Nakatsu, Buzen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After restoring order in Kyushu, he was awarded 12,500 koku in Nakatsu, Buzen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After restoring order in Kyushu, he was awarded 125,000 koku in Nakatsu, Buzen Province.</e>
<cmt>Buzen→Buzen Provinceとしました。12,500→125,000に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>国人勢力の城井鎮房・野中鎮兼らが一揆を起こすが孝高はこれを鎮圧し、翌年4月には城井氏を謀殺することで領内の平定に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some influential Kokujin (warriors living in the respective province) including Shigefusa KII and Shigekane NONAKA rose in revolt but were put down by Yoshitaka who subsequently had Kii murdered and successfully brought the territory under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some influential Kokujin (warriors living in the respective province) including Shigefusa KII and Shigekane NONAKA rose in revolt but were put down by Yoshitaka who subsequently had Kii murdered and successfully brought the territory under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some influential Kokujin (warriors living in the respective province) including Shigefusa KII and Shigekane NONAKA rose in revolt but were put down by Yoshitaka who subsequently had Kii murdered and successfully brought the territory under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="38">
<j>この少し前、孝高は高山右近らの勧めによってキリスト教の洗礼を受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not long before that time, Yoshitaka was baptized as a Christian at the suggestion of Ukon Takayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not long before that time, Yoshitaka was baptized as a Christian at the suggestion of Ukon Takayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not long before that time, Yoshitaka was baptized as a Christian at the suggestion of Ukon TAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>Ukon Takayama→Ukon TAKAYAMAに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし、天正15年（1587年）7月に秀吉がキリスト教禁教令を出すと高山右近らがこれに反抗して追放される中、孝高は率先して棄教した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1587, however, while Ukon Takayama and the other Christians defied the Anti-Christian Decree issued by Hideyoshi and were subsequently banished as punishment, Yoshitaka led the way in renouncing the faith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1587, however, while Ukon Takayama and the other Christians defied the Anti-Christian Decree issued by Hideyoshi and were subsequently banished as punishment, Yoshitaka led the way in renouncing the faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1587, however, while Ukon TAKAYAMA and the other Christians defied the Anti-Christian Decree issued by Hideyoshi and were subsequently banished as punishment, Yoshitaka led the way in renouncing the faith.</e>
<cmt>Ukon Takayama→Ukon TAKAYAMAに修正July →Augustに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>秀吉の側近である孝高の棄教は、宣教師やキリスト教を信仰する諸大名に大きな衝撃を与えたことがルイス・フロイスの書簡から窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is detected in the letters written by Luis Frois that Yoshitaka&apos;s renunciation of the faith sent shock waves among the missionary priests and various Christian feudal lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is detected in the letters written by Luis Frois that Yoshitaka&apos;s renunciation of the faith sent shock waves among the missionary priests and various Christian feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is detected in the letters written by Luis FROIS that Yoshitaka&apos;s renunciation of the faith sent shock waves among the missionary priests and various Christian feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>Luis Frois→Luis FROISに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>天正17年（1589年）、家督を嫡男の黒田長政に譲って隠居し、如水軒と号した（※これ以降は如水と記述する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1589, Yoshitaka transfer the headship of the family to his heir Nagamasa KURODA and went into the retirement thereafter referring himself to as Josuiken (* hereinafter Yoshitaka will be referred to as Josui).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1589, Yoshitaka transferred the headship of the family to his heir Nagamasa KURODA and went into retirement thereafter referring himself to as Josuiken (*hereinafter Yoshitaka will be referred to as Josui).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1589, Yoshitaka transferred the headship of the family to his heir Nagamasa KURODA and went into retirement thereafter referring himself to as Josuiken (hereinafter Yoshitaka will be referred to as Josui).</e>
<cmt>&quot;*&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>家督を譲った後も、如水は秀吉の側近として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After transferring the headship of the family to his son, Josui continued to serve Hideyoshi as his close aide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After transferring the headship of the family to his son, Josui continued to serve Hideyoshi as his close aide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After transferring the headship of the family to his son, Josui continued to serve Hideyoshi as his close aide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>天正18年（1590年）の小田原征伐では小田原城に入って北条氏政・北条氏直父子を説得し、無血開城させる功績を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Odawara campaign in 1590, Josui went inside Odawara-jo Castle to successfully persuade Ujimasa HOJO and his son Ujinao HOJO to a bloodless surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Odawara campaign in 1590, Josui went inside Odawara-jo Castle to successfully persuade Ujimasa HOJO and his son Ujinao HOJO to a bloodless surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Odawara Campaign in 1590, Josui went inside Odawara-jo Castle to successfully persuade Ujimasa HOJO and his son Ujinao HOJO to a bloodless surrender.</e>
<cmt>campaignの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>このとき、北条氏直から日光一文字の名刀を与えられている（国宝、福岡市博物館所蔵）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He, thereat, was presented with a celebrated sword Nikko Ichiminji by Ujinao HOJO (a collection of the Fukuoka City Museum designated as a national treasure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He, thereafter, was presented with the celebrated sword Nikko Ichiminji by Ujinao HOJO (a collection of the Fukuoka City Museum designated as a national treasure).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He, thereafter, was presented with the celebrated sword Nikko Ichimonji by Ujinao HOJO (a collection of the Fukuoka City Museum designated as a national treasure).</e>
<cmt>Ichiminji→Ichimonjiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>文禄元年（1592年）から秀吉の朝鮮出兵（文禄・慶長の役）に参加するが、文禄2年（1593年）に五奉行の石田三成との間に確執を生じ秀吉の怒りを買ったために、如水円清と号して出家・引退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Josui participated in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion campaigns to Chosen (Korea) (Bunroku no eki and Keicho no eki) starting in 1592 but, after invoking the wrath of Hideyoshi by feuding with one of the five magistrates Mitsunari ISHIDA, he retired taking up a retirement name of Josui Ensei in 1593.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Josui participated in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion campaigns to Chosen (Korea) (Bunroku no eki and Keicho no eki) starting in 1592; but, after invoking the wrath of Hideyoshi by feuding with one of the five magistrates Mitsunari ISHIDA, he retired taking the name of Josui Ensei in 1593.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Josui participated in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion campaigns to Korea (the Bunroku and Keicho Wars) starting in 1592; but, after invoking the wrath of Hideyoshi by feuding with one of the five magistrates Mitsunari ISHIDA, he retired taking the name of Josui Ensei in 1593.</e>
<cmt>Chosenは日本語読みのため、Koreaのみとし、Bunroku no eki and Keicho no eki→the Bunroku and Keicho Warsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="46">
<j>その後、中津城で悠々自適の隠居生活を送ったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It Is said that, thereafter, Josui lived at Nakatsu-jo Castle enjoying his retirement at leisure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It Is said that, thereafter, Josui lived at Nakatsu-jo Castle enjoying his retirement at leisure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It Is said that, thereafter, Josui lived at Nakatsu-jo Castle enjoying his retirement at leisure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）8月、豊臣秀吉が死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1598, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1598, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1598, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died.</e>
<cmt>August →Septemberに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>如水は同年12月に上洛し、伏見屋敷に居住したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Josui came to Kyoto in December of that year and stayed at his residence in Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Josui came to Kyoto in December of that year and stayed at his residence in Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Josui came to Kyoto in December of that year and stayed at his residence in Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この頃、如水が吉川広家に宛てた書状が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A letter that Josui wrote to Hiroie KIKAWA around that time remains in existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A letter that Josui wrote to Hiroie KIKAWA around that time remains in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A letter that Josui wrote to Hiroie KIKAWA around that time remains in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>「かようの時は仕合わせになり申し候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In times like this, I feel delighted.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In times like this, I feel delighted.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In times like this, I feel delighted.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>「はやく乱申すまじく候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dare I say that there will be a war in the near future.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dare I say that there will be a war in the near future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dare I say that there will be a war in the near future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>「そのお心得にて然るべき候」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I suggest that you will be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I suggest that you will be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I suggest that you will be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="53">
<j>これは、如水が遠からず天下の覇権をめぐって大乱が起きると予想していたことを窺わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It suggests that Josui anticipated a major upheaval over supremacy in the country was going to happen in not too distant future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It suggests that Josui anticipated a major upheaval over supremacy in the country and that this was going to happen in the not too distant future.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It suggests that Josui anticipated a major upheaval over supremacy in the country and that this was going to happen in the not too distant future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）、徳川家康らが会津の上杉景勝討伐のため東へ向かうと石田三成らが家康の非を鳴らして挙兵し（西軍）、関ヶ原の戦いが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1600, after Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and his allies moved their troops to defeat Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu, Mitsunari ISHIDA and his allies denounced Ieyasu and moved their troops (the West) against him and thus the Battle of Sekigahara began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600, after Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and his allies moved their troops to defeat Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu, Mitsunari ISHIDA and his allies denounced Ieyasu and moved their troops (the West) against him and thus the Battle of Sekigahara began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600, after Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and his allies moved their troops to defeat Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu, Mitsunari ISHIDA and his allies denounced Ieyasu and moved their troops (the West) against him and thus the Battle of Sekigahara began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>嫡男・長政は家康の養女を正室として迎えていたことから秀吉の死去前後から家康に与し、豊臣恩顧の大名を多く家康方に引き込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the wife of Josui&apos;s heir Nagamasa was an adoptive daughter of Ieyasu, Nagamasa became an ally of Ieyasu around the time of Hideyoshi&apos;s death and recruited many of daimyo from the Toyotomi side to the Ieyasu side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the wife of Josui&apos;s heir Nagamasa was an adoptive daughter of Ieyasu, Nagamasa became an ally of Ieyasu around the time of Hideyoshi&apos;s death and recruited many daimyo from Toyotomi&apos;s side to Ieyasu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the wife of Josui&apos;s heir Nagamasa was an adoptive daughter of Ieyasu, Nagamasa became an ally of Ieyasu around the time of Hideyoshi&apos;s death and recruited many daimyo from Toyotomi&apos;s side to Ieyasu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>さらに後藤基次ら黒田軍の主力を率いて家康に同行、関ヶ原本戦で武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, leading the best force of the Kuroda army, Nagamasa accompanied Ieyasu and rendered distinguished service in the main battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, leading the best force of the Kuroda army, Nagamasa accompanied Ieyasu and rendered distinguished service in the main battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, leading the best force of the Kuroda army, Nagamasa accompanied Ieyasu and rendered distinguished service in the main battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="57">
<j>この頃、如水は九州にいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Josui was in Kyushu in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Josui was in Kyushu in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Josui was in Kyushu in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>石田三成の挙兵を知った如水は、家康方（東軍）として行動を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Learning that Mitsunari ISHIDA started to move his troops, Josui began his course of action as an ally of Ieyasu (the East).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Learning that Mitsunari ISHIDA started to move his troops, Josui began his course of action as an ally of Ieyasu (the East).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Learning that Mitsunari ISHIDA started to move his troops, Josui began his course of action as an ally of Ieyasu (the East).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>兵力の大半は長政が率いていたため如水は金蔵を開いて領内の百姓などに支度金を与え、1万人ほどの速成軍を作り上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the majority of the Kuroda army was with Nagamasa, giving peasants in the Kuroda territory outfit allowance from his safe, Josui quickly put together a new army of approximately 10,000 men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the majority of Kuroda&apos;s army was with Nagamasa, giving peasants in the Kuroda territory an outfit allowance from his treasury, Josui quickly put together a new army of approximately 10,000 men.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the majority of Kuroda&apos;s army was with Nagamasa, giving peasants in the Kuroda territory an outfit allowance from his treasury, Josui quickly put together a new army of approximately 10,000 men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>如水はこの兵力を率いて9月9日 (旧暦)（10月15日）、豊後国に侵攻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leading this army, Josui invaded the Province of Bungo on October 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leading this army, Josui invaded the Province of Bungo on October 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leading this army, Josui invaded the Bungo Province on October 15.</e>
<cmt>Province of Bungo→Bungo Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>同日、再興を目指して西軍に与した大友義統が毛利輝元の支援を受けて豊後に攻め込み、東軍の細川忠興の飛び地である杵築城を包囲攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that day, backed by Terumoto MORI, Yoshimune OTOMO, who had joined the West with an aspiration to rebuild the family fortune, moved his army into the Province of Bungo and siege Kitsuki-jo Castle of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA who belong to the East.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that day, backed by Terumoto MORI, Yoshimune OTOMO, who had joined the West with aspirations to rebuild the family fortune, moved his army into the Province of Bungo and siege Kitsuki-jo Castle of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA who belong to the East.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that day, backed by Terumoto MORI, Yoshimune OTOMO, who had joined the West with aspirations to rebuild the family fortune, moved his army into the Bungo Province and siege Kitsuki-jo Castle of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA who belong to the East.</e>
<cmt>Province of Bungo→Bungo Provinceとし、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>城将・松井康之と有吉立行は如水に援軍を要請、如水はこれに応じ9月13日 (旧暦)（10月19日）、石垣原（現在の別府市）で大友義統軍と衝突した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The commanders Yasuyuki MATSUI and Tatsuyuki ARIYOSHI at Kitsuki-jo Castle asked Josui for reinforcements and, in response, Josui moved his army and clashed with the army of Yoshimune OTOMO on October 19.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The commanders Yasuyuki MATSUI and Tatsuyuki ARIYOSHI at Kitsuki-jo Castle asked Josui for reinforcements and, in response, Josui moved his army and clashed with the army of Yoshimune OTOMO on October 19.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The commanders Yasuyuki MATSUI and Tatsuyuki ARIYOSHI at Kitsuki-jo Castle asked Josui for reinforcements and, in response, Josui moved his army and clashed with the army of Yoshimune OTOMO at Ishigakibaru (presently Beppu City) on October 19.</e>
<cmt>「石垣原（現在の別府市）で」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>黒田二十四騎に数えられる母里友信らの活躍もあって、黒田軍は大友軍に勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kuroda army was victorious over the Otomo army due in part to contribution by one of the 24 Kuroda Cavalries Tamonobu MORI and the other warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuroda army was victorious over the Otomo army due in part to contributions by one of the 24 Kuroda Cavalries Tamonobu MORI and the other warriors.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuroda army was victorious over the Otomo army due in part to contributions by one of the 24 Kuroda Cavalries Tamonobu MORI and the other warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="64">
<j>その後、如水は西軍に属した熊谷直盛の安岐城、垣見一直の富来城、太田一吉の臼杵城、毛利高政の角牟礼城と日隈城、毛利勝信の小倉城、毛利信友の香春岳城などを次々と落としていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Josui began to capture various castles belonging to the feudal lords that had joined the West including Naomori KUMAGAI&apos;s Aki-jo Castle, Kazunao KAKIMI&apos;s Tomiki-jo Castle, Kazuyoshi OTA&apos;s Usuki-jo Castle, Takamasa MORI&apos;s Tsunomure-jo Castle and Hinokuma-jo Castle, Katsunobu MORI&apos;s Kokura-jo Castle, Nobutomo MORI&apos;s Kawaradake-jo Castle one after the other.</e>
<cmt>毛利「信友」読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Josui began to capture various castles belonging to the feudal lords that had joined the West including Naomori KUMAGAI&apos;s Aki-jo Castle, Kazunao KAKIMI&apos;s Tomiki-jo Castle, Kazuyoshi OTA&apos;s Usuki-jo Castle, Takamasa MORI&apos;s Tsunomure-jo Castle and Hinokuma-jo Castle, Katsunobu MORI&apos;s Kokura-jo Castle, Nobutomo MORI&apos;s Kawaradake-jo Castle one after the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Josui began to capture various castles belonging to the feudal lords that had joined the West including Naomori KUMAGAI&apos;s Aki-jo Castle, Kazunao KAKIMI&apos;s Tomiki-jo Castle, Kazuyoshi OTA&apos;s Usuki-jo Castle, Takamasa MORI&apos;s Tsunomure-jo Castle and Hinokuma-jo Castle, Katsunobu MORI&apos;s Kokura-jo Castle, Nobutomo (信友) MORI&apos;s Kawaradake-jo Castle one after the other.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明のため、「Nobutomo (信友)」 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>そして11月に入り加藤、立花、鍋島勢を加えた4万の軍勢で九州最後の敵勢力である島津討伐に向かったが11月12日に肥後の水俣まで進軍したとき、徳川家康と島津との和議成立による停戦命令を受け居城に戻り、軍を解散した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early November, leading 40,000 men including the armies of Kato, Tachibana and Nabeshima, Josui moved the troops to defeat Shimazu, who was the last enemy force remaining in Kyushu, but, on November 12, received a cease-fire order issued as a result of a reconsiliation agreement reached between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Shimazu whereby he returned to his castle and his army was dismissed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early November, leading 40,000 men including the armies of Kato, Tachibana and Nabeshima, Josui moved the troops to defeat Shimazu, who was the last enemy force remaining in Kyushu, but, on November 12, received a cease-fire order issued as a result of a reconsiliation agreement reached between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Shimazu whereby he returned to his castle and his army was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early December, leading 40,000 men including the armies of Kato, Tachibana and Nabeshima, Josui moved the troops to defeat Shimazu, who was the last enemy force remaining in Kyushu, but, on December 17 when his army advanced toward Minamata, Higo Province, he received a cease-fire order issued as a result of a reconsiliation agreement reached between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Shimazu whereby he returned to his castle and his army was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>「肥後の水俣まで進軍したとき」を訳出するため文章を一部修正、余分なスペース消去November→Decemberに変更しました。November 12→December 17に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="66">
<j>如水のねらいは九州を統一し、その兵力を率いて東上し家康に決戦を挑んで天下を取ることにあったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Josui&apos;s ultimate objective was to take on Ieyasu for the supremacy by putting Kyushu under his command to lead its military might to east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Josui&apos;s ultimate objective was to take on Ieyasu for supremacy by putting Kyushu under his command to lead its military might to east.</e>
<cmt>wording; spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Josui&apos;s ultimate objective was to take on Ieyasu for supremacy by putting Kyushu under his command to lead its military might to east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>息子の長政の活躍により、関ヶ原の合戦が短期に終結したのは皮肉な巡り合わせと言えるかも知れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is irony in that his son Nagamasa&apos;s successful performance contributed to ending the Battle of Sekigahara in the short period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is irony in that his son Nagamasa&apos;s successful performance contributed to ending the Battle of Sekigahara in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is irony in that his son Nagamasa&apos;s successful performance contributed to ending the Battle of Sekigahara in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="68">
<j>しかし、本気で天下を取ろうとしたのであれば息子の長政と綿密な打ち合わせが必要であり、それをしなかったのは如水の手腕を考えれば手落ちというより不審である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If, however, Josui was indeed serious about seizing the supreme power, it would have required a thorough consultation with his son Nagamasa and, considering Josui&apos;s finess, it seems more puzzling than being dismissed as an oversight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If, however, Josui was indeed serious about seizing supreme power, it would have required a thorough consultation with his son Nagamasa and, considering Josui&apos;s finess, it seems more puzzling than being dismissed as an oversight.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If, however, Josui was indeed serious about seizing supreme power, it would have required a thorough consultation with his son Nagamasa and, considering Josui&apos;s finess, it seems more puzzling than being dismissed as an oversight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>そのため、天下を狙う野望を持っていたというのは見せかけで如水は家康に脅威を感じさせ、一方で息子の長政が家康に忠誠を尽くすことにより黒田家の存続と繁栄を狙った深謀遠慮であるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In light of the above, some argue that it was a calculated affectation to put pressure on Ieyasu by acting as if to have an ambition for the supremacy to ensure that Ieyasu appreciated the Kuroda family&apos;s capability and the fidelity of Josui&apos;s son Nagamasa whereby Ieyasu would treat the Kuroda family accordingly which would lead to the continued existence and prosperity of the Kuroda family in the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In light of the above, some argue that it was cunning calculation to put pressure on Ieyasu by acting as if he had ambition for supremacy to ensure that Ieyasu appreciated the Kuroda family&apos;s capability and the fidelity of Josui&apos;s son Nagamasa. Because, Ieyasu would treat the Kuroda family accordingly, and this would lead to the continued existence and ultimate prosperity of the Kuroda family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In light of the above, some argue that it was cunning calculation to put pressure on Ieyasu by acting as if he had ambition for supremacy to ensure that Ieyasu appreciated the Kuroda family&apos;s capability and the fidelity of Josui&apos;s son Nagamasa; because, Ieyasu would treat the Kuroda family accordingly, and this would lead to the continued existence and ultimate prosperity of the Kuroda family.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="70">
<j>これに関しては以下のような逸話が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the following anecdote in reference to the foregoing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reference to this, there exists the following anecdote.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reference to this, there exists the following anecdote.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="71">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの後、帰郷した長政が「家康殿は右手を取って功労を褒めてくれた」と自慢したのに対し、如水は「その時、お前の左手は何をしていた（何故空いている手で家康を殺さなかったのか）」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, when Nagamasa came home and proudly said, &quot;Esquire Ieyasu took my right hand and praised my work,&quot; Josui said to his son, &quot;What was your left hand doing then (Why didn&apos;t you kill Ieyasu with the other hand)?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara, when Nagamasa came home and proudly said, &quot;Esquire Ieyasu took my right hand and praised my work,&quot; Josui said to his son, &quot;What was your left hand doing then (Why didn&apos;t you kill Ieyasu with the other hand)?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, when Nagamasa came home and proudly said, &apos;Esquire Ieyasu took my right hand and praised my work,&apos; Josui said to his son, &apos;What was your left hand doing then (Why didn&apos;t you kill Ieyasu with the other hand)?&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これを聞いて長政は絶句した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This left Nagamasa speechless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This left Nagamasa speechless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This left Nagamasa speechless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="73">
<j>このような逸話が広く世間に流布していた事実からは、逆に本気で天下を狙っていたとは考えにくい（本気だったならば固く秘密にしたであろう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conversely, in view of the fact that this sort of anecdote was in public circulation, it seems all the more unlikely that Josui was seriously after the supreme power (since, if he was, he would have kept it in the strictest secrecy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conversely, in view of the fact that this sort of anecdote was in public circulation, it seems even more unlikely that Josui was seriously pursuing supreme power (since, if he was, he would have kept it in the strictest secrecy).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conversely, in view of the fact that this sort of anecdote was in public circulation, it seems even more unlikely that Josui was seriously pursuing supreme power (since, if he was, he would have kept it in the strictest secrecy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>むしろ陰謀家の如水に対比することで、長政の家康に対する忠誠を強調した逸話と考えることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rather, it seems that this anecdote served to emphasize Nagamasa&apos;s fidelity to Ieyasu by contrasting with the scheming Josui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather, it seems that this anecdote served to emphasize Nagamasa&apos;s fidelity to Ieyasu by contrasting with the scheming Josui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather, it seems that this anecdote served to emphasize Nagamasa&apos;s fidelity to Ieyasu by contrasting with the scheming Josui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>関ヶ原の合戦の後、長政は家康から勲功第一として筑前名島（福岡）で52万3000石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Nagamasa was awarded the territory of Chikuzen Najima (Fukuoka) with 523,000 koku in recognition of the top deed of valor by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Nagamasa was awarded the territory of Chikuzen Najima (Fukuoka) with 523,000 koku in recognition of the top deed of valor by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Nagamasa was awarded the territory of Chikuzen Najima (Fukuoka) with 523,000 koku in recognition of the top deed of valor by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>如水も中津城から福岡城に移り、そこでその後は政治に関与することなく隠居生活を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Josui also moved from Nakatsu-jo Castle to Fukuoka-jo Castle and thereafter lived in retirement without getting involved in politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Josui also moved from Nakatsu-jo Castle to Fukuoka-jo Castle and thereafter lived in retirement completely outside politics.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Josui also moved from Nakatsu-jo Castle to Fukuoka-jo Castle and thereafter lived in retirement completely outside politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>慶長9年3月20日（1604年4月19日）、京都伏見藩邸にて死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 19, 1604, Josui died at the official residence of the Fushimi clan in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 19, 1604, Josui died at the official residence of the Fushimi clan in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 19, 1604, Josui died at the official residence of the Fushimi clan in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>享年59。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age at death was 59.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at age 59.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 59.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>一般に伝えられる孝高の活躍については、軍師の活躍をよりきらびやかに描こうとする江戸時代の軍記物などで誇張された部分も多いと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the career of Yoshitaka, it is said that there are many exaggerations in military epics written in the Edo Period in order to glamorize military strategists in action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to the career of Yoshitaka, it is said that there are many exaggerations in military epics written in the Edo Period in order to glamorize military strategists in action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to the career of Yoshitaka, it is said that there are many exaggerations in military epics written in the Edo period in order to glamorize military strategists in action.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>竹中重治（半兵衛）と共に秀吉の双璧と謳われ、「両兵衛」・「二兵衛」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and Shigeharu TAKENAKA (Hanbei TAKENAKA) were referred to as the twin jewels of Hideyoshi and were called the &quot;Double Hanbei&quot; or the &quot;Two Hanbei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He and Shigeharu TAKENAKA (Hanbei TAKENAKA) were referred to as the twin jewels of Hideyoshi and were called the Double Hanbei or the Two Hanbei.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He and Shigeharu TAKENAKA (Hanbei TAKENAKA) were referred to as the twin jewels of Hideyoshi and were called the Double Hanbei or the Two Hanbei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>徳川秀忠は孝高を「今世の張良なるべし」と評した（名将言行録）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetaka TOKUGAWA said that Yoshitaka was &apos;Choryo (a brilliant military strategist in ancient China) of today&apos; (Meisho genkoroku (The Sayings and Doings of Famous Warriors))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetaka TOKUGAWA said that Yoshitaka was the Choryo (a brilliant military strategist in ancient China) of today (Meisho genkoroku (The Sayings and Doings of Famous Warriors)).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetaka TOKUGAWA said that Yoshitaka was the Choryo (a brilliant military strategist in ancient China) of today (Meisho Genkoroku (The Sayings and Doings of Famous Warriors)).</e>
<cmt>Meisho Genkorokuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="82">
<j>孝高は梅毒により、頭部に醜い瘡があったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yoshitaka had ugly scars caused by syphillis he contracted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yoshitaka had ugly scars caused by the syphillis he contracted.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yoshitaka had ugly scars caused by the syphillis he contracted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="83">
<j>虎視眈々と天下を狙う野心家として描かれることが多いが、実際には主君を裏切ったことは一度もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was portrayed to be ambitious aiming to assume the supreme power, Yoshitaka never betrayed his lord once.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was portrayed to be ambitious aiming to grab supreme power, Yoshitaka never once betrayed his lord.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was portrayed to be ambitious aiming to grab supreme power, Yoshitaka never once betrayed his lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>小寺政職は「裏切った」のではなく「裏切られた」のである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was &apos;betrayed&apos; by Masamoto KODERA rather than &apos;betraying&apos; Masamoto, and, with respect to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA during the Battle of Sekigahara, both Yoshitaka and Masamoto were vassals under the Toyotomi family with no master-servant relationship between them, belonging to the East as allies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was betrayed by Masamoto KODERA rather than betraying Masamoto. And, with respect to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA during the Battle of Sekigahara, both Yoshitaka and Masamoto were vassals under the Toyotomi family with no master-servant relationship between them, belonging to the East as allies.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was betrayed by Masamoto KODERA rather than betraying Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>また、関ヶ原の合戦の際の徳川家康に関しても2人は同じ豊臣家の家臣であって主従ではなく建前上は同じ東軍であったから、敵対すらしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, with respect to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA during the Battle of Sekigahara, both Yoshitaka and Masamoto were vassals under the Toyotomi family with no master-servant relationship between them, belonging to the East as allies.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>坂口安吾は「天才ではあるが、ただの戦争マニアであって野心は二流」と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ango SAKAGUCHI said of Yoshitaka, &quot;Although he was brilliant, he was nothing more than a warmonger with a second rate aspiration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ango SAKAGUCHI said of Yoshitaka, &quot;Although he was brilliant, he was nothing more than a warmonger with a second rate aspiration.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ango SAKAGUCHI said of Yoshitaka, &apos;Although he was brilliant, he was nothing more than a warmonger with a second rate aspiration.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>本能寺の変で織田信長が死去したとき、孝高は秀吉に対して「御運が開かれる機会が参りましたな」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, when Nobunaga died during the Incident at Honno-ji Temple, Yoshitaka said to Hideyoshi, &quot;Your lucky opportunity has arrived, hasn&apos;t it?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, when Nobunaga died during the Incident at Honno-ji Temple, Yoshitaka said to Hideyoshi, &quot;Your lucky opportunity has arrived, hasn&apos;t it?&quot;</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, when Nobunaga died during the Incident at Honno-ji Temple, Yoshitaka said to Hideyoshi, &apos;Your lucky opportunity has arrived, hasn&apos;t it?&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>これ以後、秀吉は孝高の智謀を恐れるようになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, thereafter, Hideyoshi began to fear Yoshitaka&apos;s Machiavellian mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, thereafter, Hideyoshi began to fear Yoshitaka&apos;s Machiavellian mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, thereafter, Hideyoshi began to fear Yoshitaka&apos;s Machiavellian mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>秀吉が多くの功績を立てた孝高に対して、大坂から遠く離れた豊前の中津でわずか12万石しか与えなかった（加藤清正・福島正則ら他の子飼い大名と比べると小封と言える）のも、それを示していると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the fact that Hideyoshi awarded Yoshitaka, who had numerous achievelents, with a territory of Nakatsu in the Province of Bingo far away from Osaka with only 12,000 koku (which seems like a stingy package in comparison to what Hideyoshi gave to the other daimyo such as Kiyosama KATO or Masanori FUKUSHIMA who had been with Hideyoshi forever) proves it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that the fact that Hideyoshi awarded Yoshitaka, who had numerous achievelents, with the territory of Nakatsu in the Province of Bingo far away from Osaka with only 12,000 koku (which seems like a stingy package in comparison to what Hideyoshi gave to the other daimyo such as Kiyosama KATO or Masanori FUKUSHIMA, who had always been with Hideyoshi) proves this.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that the fact that Hideyoshi awarded Yoshitaka, who had numerous achievelents, with the territory of Nakatsu in the Buzen Province far away from Osaka with only 120,000 koku (which seems like a stingy package in comparison to what Hideyoshi gave to the other daimyo such as Kiyosama KATO or Masanori FUKUSHIMA, who had always been with Hideyoshi) proves this.</e>
<cmt>Province of Bingo→Buzen Provinceに修正12,000 koku→120,000 kokuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>秀吉が孝高を恐れたことを示す史料として、次のようなものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some historical sources documenting Hideyoshi&apos;s apprehension toward Yoshitaka as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some historical sources documenting Hideyoshi&apos;s apprehension toward Yoshitaka as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some historical sources documenting Hideyoshi&apos;s apprehension toward Yoshitaka as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="91">
<j>「秀吉、常に世に怖しきものは徳川と黒田なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Hideyoshi is always afraid of in this word include TOKUGAWA and KURODA.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What Hideyoshi is always afraid of in this world include TOKUGAWA and KURODA.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What Hideyoshi is always afraid of in this world include TOKUGAWA and KURODA.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>「然れども、徳川は温和なる人なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, TOKUGAWA is a gentleperson.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, TOKUGAWA is a gentleperson.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, TOKUGAWA is a gentleperson.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>「黒田の瘡天窓は何にとも心を許し難きものなりと言はれしとぞ」（名将言行録）。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That scarred-head KURODA cannot be trusted with any matters.&apos; (Meisho genkoroku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That scarred-head KURODA cannot be trusted with any matters.&apos; (Meisho genkoroku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That scarred-head KURODA cannot be trusted with any matters&apos; (Meisho Genkoroku).</e>
<cmt>Meisho Genkorokuとし、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="94">
<j>孝高が長政に家督を譲って隠居したのは44歳のときであるが、働き盛りの年齢で隠居したのは秀吉に恐れられていることを知って身の安全を図ったためと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka was 44 when he transferred the headship of the family to Nagamasa and it is said that he retired in his prime to secure his personal safety knowing that Hideyoshi was apprehensive about him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka was 44 when he transferred the headship of the family to Nagamasa and it is said that he retired in his prime to secure his personal safety knowing that Hideyoshi was apprehensive about him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka was 44 when he transferred the headship of the family to Nagamasa and it is said that he retired in his prime to secure his personal safety knowing that Hideyoshi was apprehensive about him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>次のような逸話が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="96">
<j>秀吉が家臣に「わしに代わって、次に天下を治めるのは誰だ」と尋ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi asked his vassals, &quot;Who is going to govern the country after me?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi asked his vassals, &quot;Who is going to govern the country after me?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi asked his vassals, &apos;Who is going to govern the country after me?&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>家臣たちは徳川家康や前田利家の名前を挙げたが秀吉は黒田官兵衛（孝高）を挙げ、「官兵衛がその気になれば、わしが生きている間にも天下を取るだろう」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vassals mentioned Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Tshiie MAEDA but Hideyoshi mentioned Kanbei KURODA (Yoshitaka) and said, &quot;If Kanbei so decides, he will assume the supremacy while I am still around.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vassals mentioned Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA but Hideyoshi mentioned Kanbei KURODA (Yoshitaka) and said, &quot;If Kanbei so decides, he will assume supremacy while I am still around.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vassals mentioned Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Toshiie MAEDA but Hideyoshi mentioned Kanbei KURODA (Yoshitaka) and said, &apos;If Kanbei so decides, he will assume supremacy while I am still around.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>側近は「官兵衛殿は10万石程度の大名に過ぎませんが」と聞き返したところ、秀吉は次のように言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His close aide asked Hideyoshi, &apos;But my lord, Esquire Kanbei is a daimyo with only 10,000 koku,&apos; and Hideyoshi said, &apos;None of you knows what he really is cable of.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His close aide asked Hideyoshi, &apos;But my lord, Esquire Kanbei is a daimyo with only 10,000 koku,&apos; and Hideyoshi said, &apos;None of you knows what he really is cable of.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His close aide asked Hideyoshi, &apos;But my lord, Esquire Kanbei is a daimyo with only 100,000 koku,&apos; and Hideyoshi said as follows:</e>
<cmt>10,000 koku→100,000 kokuに変更しました。Split_Sample例に従って、 &apos;None of you knows what he really is cable of. の部分を分割して、Hideyoshi saidをHideyoshi said as follows:に変更しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>「お前たちはやつの本当の力量をわかっていない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">None of you knows what he really is cable of.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>「やつに100万石を与えたらとたんに天下を奪ってしまう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If I gave him 1 million koku, he will snatch the power from me right away.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If I gave him 1 million koku, he will snatch the power from me right away.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If I gave him one million koku, he will snatch the power from me right away.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;1&quot;をスペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>これを伝え聞いた官兵衛は身の危険を感じて隠居を申し出たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, hearing about this exchange through his gravepine, Kanbei offered to retire for fear of his personal safety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, hearing about this exchange through word of mouth, Kanbei offered to retire for fear of his personal safety.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, hearing about this exchange through word of mouth, Kanbei offered to retire for fear of his personal safety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="102">
<j>これはわざと情報を流すことで周囲の反応を見ようとしたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he deliberately circulated information about his retirement to see how the people around him would react.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that he deliberately circulated information about his retirement to see how the people around him would react.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that he deliberately circulated information about his retirement to see how the people around him would react.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>一方、隠居は三成ら若い人材の台頭なども理由と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, however, the rise of young staff such as Mitsunari is said to have been the other reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, however, the rise of young staff such as Mitsunari is said to have been the other reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, however, the rise of young staff such as Mitsunari is said to have been the other reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="104">
<j>晩年は家臣に対して冷たく振舞ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanbei was supposed to be cold towards his retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanbei was said to be cold towards his retainers.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanbei was said to be cold towards his retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>これは殉死者を出さないためとも、当主の長政に家臣団の忠誠を向けさせるためとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was cold towards his retainers on purpose so that they would not kill themselves on the death of Kanbei or so that his retainers would devote their fidelity to Nagamasa who was the head of the Kuroda clan at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was cold towards his retainers on purpose so that they would not kill themselves on the death of Kanbei, or so that his retainers would devote their fidelity to Nagamasa who was the head of the Kuroda clan at that time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was cold towards his retainers on purpose so that they would not kill themselves on the death of Kanbei, or so that his retainers would devote their fidelity to Nagamasa who was the head of the Kuroda clan at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="106">
<j>村重謀反のとき、信長は翻意するよう説得に向かった孝高が帰ってこないのは村重に寝返ったからだと判断し、人質として預けられていた長政を殺害するように命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Murashige rose in revolt, Yoshitaka was sent to persuade him to reconsider but, with Yoshitaka not returning for a prolonged period of time, Nobunaga jumped to the conclusion that Yoshitaka had defected to the Murashige side and ordered to kill Nagamasa who was left with Nobunaga as a hostage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Murashige rose in revolt, Yoshitaka was sent to persuade him to reconsider but, with Yoshitaka not returning for a prolonged period of time, Nobunaga jumped to the conclusion that Yoshitaka had defected to the Murashige side and ordered to kill Nagamasa who was left with Nobunaga as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Murashige rose in revolt, Yoshitaka was sent to persuade him to reconsider but, with Yoshitaka not returning for a prolonged period of time, Nobunaga jumped to the conclusion that Yoshitaka had defected to the Murashige side and ordered to kill Nagamasa who was left with Nobunaga as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>しかし重治（半兵衛）は密かに長政を匿った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeharu (Hanbei) however secretly gave harbor to Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeharu (Hanbei) however secretly gave harbor to Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeharu (Hanbei) however secretly gave harbor to Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>このため、重治への感謝の気持を忘れないために黒田家は家紋に竹中家の家紋を用いた（この家紋とは黒餅の事を指す。黒餅とは石高の加増を願う家紋である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To remember their gratitude towards Shigeharu, the Kuroda family consequently adopted the family crest of the Takenaka family as theirs (this family crest refers to Kuromochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To remember their gratitude towards Shigeharu, the Kuroda family consequently adopted the family crest of the Takenaka family as theirs (this family crest refers to Kuromochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To remember their gratitude towards Shigeharu, the Kuroda family consequently adopted the family crest of the Takenaka family as theirs (this family crest refers to Kuromochi. Kuromochi is a family crest to hope for an increase in the amount of koku).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去カッコ文が分割されているためこちらに集約しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="109">
<j>遺訓として「人に媚びず、富貴を望まず」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last words were &quot;Do not try to gain other people&apos;s favor and do not wish for wealth.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last words were &quot;Do not try to gain other people&apos;s favor and do not wish for wealth.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His last words were &apos;Do not try to gain other people&apos;s favor and do not wish for wealth.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Bakkai(id:7233), ドルチェット(id:46458), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), Reggaeman(id:6214), ふんかさい(id:62417), Cprobot(id:97843), Lupinoid(id:68), 直正(id:13317), Sgi1962(id:80778), ムカイ(id:72972), 百人(id:16483), でここ(id:9565), 丁度氷(id:64000), Pontafon(id:33761), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), 怪蘇(id:45514), Bobmarley(id:51598), 絵鞠(id:56670), Kz(id:18320), ５１６(id:45205), Chao35(id:34986), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Snakeeye(id:41100), ZERO(id:3727), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Carbuncle(id:346), DOERAX(id:25212), GoGoDoll(id:131511), FAT26(id:9460), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), STBot(id:137943), 吾川一郎(id:208905), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Aboshi(id:9318), Rusk(id:9895), Boca samba(id:137526), 高山右近(id:134881), YurikBot(id:18605), KSKS(id:97637), こいつぅ(id:2105), Kuma83(id:31177), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>