<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>結城宗広</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munehiro YUKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munehiro YUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munehiro YUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>結城 宗広（ゆうき むねひろ、1266年（文永3年） － 1339年1月1日（延元3年/暦応元年11月21日 (旧暦)））は、鎌倉時代から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munehiro YUKI (born in 1266, birth date unknown - January 1, 1339) was a military commander who lived from the Kamakura period through the period of the northern and southern dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munehiro YUKI (born in 1266, birth date unknown - January 1, 1339) was a military commander who lived from the Kamakura period through the period of the northern and southern dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munehiro YUKI (born in 1266, birth date unknown - January 9, 1339) was a military commander who lived from the Kamakura period through the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>用語統一リスト55グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は結城祐広。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sukehiro YUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sukehiro YUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Sukehiro YUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は熱田範広（大宮司）の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Norihiro ATSUTA (a high priest of a great shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Norihiro ATSUTA (a high priest of a great shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Norihiro ATSUTA (a high priest of a great shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は上野介。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official post was Kozuke no suke (court official).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official post was Kozuke no suke (court official).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official post was Kozuke no suke (court official).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に結城親朝と結城親光がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Chikatomo YUKI and Chikamitsu YUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Chikatomo YUKI and Chikamitsu YUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Chikatomo YUKI and Chikamitsu YUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>位階は正三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>はじめ北条氏の忠実な家臣として南奥州方面の政務を任されたが、後醍醐天皇から討幕の綸旨を受けると朝廷側に寝返って新田義貞と共に1333年に鎌倉に攻め入り、鎌倉幕府を滅ぼしてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was first appointed to be in charge of political affairs in the Minami-Oshu area as a loyal vassal of the Hojo clan, but when he received an order from Emperor Godaigo to attack the shogunate, he switched his side to the Imperial Court, invaded Kamakura City in 1333 with Yoshisada NITTA, and destroyed the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was first appointed to be in charge of political affairs in the Minami-Oshu area as a loyal vassal of the Hojo clan, but when he received an order from Emperor Godaigo to attack the shogunate, he switched sides to the Imperial Court, invaded Kamakura City in 1333 with Yoshisada NITTA, and destroyed the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was first appointed to be in charge of political affairs in the southern Oshu area as a loyal vassal of the Hojo clan, but when he received an order from Emperor Godaigo to attack the shogunate, he switched sides to the Imperial Court, invaded Kamakura in 1333 with Yoshisada NITTA, and destroyed the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Minami→southernCityを省く</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その功績により、後醍醐天皇から厚い信任を受けて北畠顕家が多賀城に入ると、諸郡奉行に任じられて共に奥州方面の統治を任されるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Akiie KITABATAKE won the strong trust of Emperor Godaigo and was permitted to live in the Kaga-jo Castle due to his performance on the battlefield, Munehiro was appointed to district magistrate and also the ruler of the Oshu area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Akiie KITABATAKE won the strong trust of Emperor Godaigo and was permitted to live in the Kaga-jo Castle due to his performance on the battlefield, Munehiro was appointed to district magistrate and also the ruler of the Oshu area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Akiie KITABATAKE won the strong trust of Emperor Godaigo and was permitted to live in Taga-jo Castle due to his performance on the battlefield, Munehiro was appointed to district magistrate and also the ruler of the Oshu area.</e>
<cmt>用語修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1336年、足利尊氏が京都に攻め入って同地を一時、支配下に置くと顕家と共に軍を率いて足利軍を攻め、朝廷軍の京都奪還で大いなる功績を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, when Takauji ASHIKAGA invaded Kyoto City and temporarily seized the area, Munehiro together with Akiie led an army to attack the Ashikaga force to let the Imperial Army troops recapture Kyoto City, resulting in distinguished performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, when Takauji ASHIKAGA invaded Kyoto City and temporarily seized the area, Munehiro together with Akiie led an army to attack the Ashikaga force to let the Imperial Army troops recapture Kyoto City, resulting in distinguished performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, when Takauji ASHIKAGA invaded Kyoto and temporarily seized the area, Munehiro together with Akiie led an army to attack the Ashikaga force to let the Imperial Army troops recapture Kyoto, resulting in distinguished performance.</e>
<cmt>Cityを省く</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、九州に逃れた尊氏が再起を果たして西上して来ると、顕家と共に足利軍と懸命に戦ったが、1338年に顕家が高師直と戦って敗死したために軍は壊滅し、宗広は命からがら後醍醐天皇がいる吉野へと逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takauji who had retreated to Kyushu reorganized his force and advanced again to the capital, Munehiro&apos;s army was destroyed because Akiie died in the battle against KO no Moronao in 1338, and Muheniro then fled for his life to Yoshino where Emperor Godaigo was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takauji who had retreated to Kyushu reorganized his force and advanced again to the capital, Munehiro&apos;s army was destroyed because Akiie died in the battle against KO no Moronao in 1338, and Muheniro then fled for his life to Yoshino where Emperor Godaigo was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takauji who had retreated to Kyushu reorganized his force and advanced again to the capital, Munehiro&apos;s army was destroyed in spite of their desperate fight together with Akiie&apos;s army, because Akiie died in the battle against KO no Moronao in 1338, and Muheniro then fled for his life to Yoshino where Emperor Godaigo was.</e>
<cmt>訳文を原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、宗広は南朝勢力再起のために、北畠親房と共に海路から奥州へ向かおうとしたが、海上で遭難して伊勢国で立往生し、間もなく同地で発病して病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munehiro then took a sea route to Oshu with Chikafusa KITABATAKE in order to recover the power of the Southern Dynasty, but the ship was wrecked and they were stuck in Ise Province, and shortly after, Munehiro fell ill there and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munehiro then went by sea to Oshu with Chikafusa KITABATAKE in order to recover the power of the Southern Dynasty, but the ship was wrecked and they were stuck in Ise Province, and shortly after, Munehiro fell ill there and died.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munehiro then went by sea to Oshu with Chikafusa KITABATAKE in order to recover the power of the Southern Court, but the ship was wrecked and they were stuck in Ise Province, and shortly after, Munehiro fell ill there and died.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>墓所は津市の結城神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is at the Yuki-jinja Shrine in Tsu City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is at the Yuki-jinja Shrine in Tsu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is at Yuki-jinja Shrine in Tsu City.</e>
<cmt>theを省く</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>または伊勢市の光明寺 (伊勢市)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, it may be at the Komyo-ji Temple in Ise City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or, it may be at the Komyo-ji Temple in Ise City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or, it may be at Komyo-ji Temple in Ise City.</e>
<cmt>theを省く</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宮城県多賀城市の多賀城神社にも祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also enshrined at the Tagajo-jinja Shrine in Tagajo City of Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also enshrined at the Tagajo-jinja Shrine in Tagajo City of Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also enshrined at Tagajo-jinja Shrine in Tagajo City of Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>theを省く</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>宗広は南朝に最後まで忠実な武将であったが、その息子・結城親朝が北朝 (日本)に通じて親房を攻めるという皮肉な事態が発生する事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Munehiro was a military commander loyal to the Southern Dynasty throughout his life, it was ironic that his son Chikatomo YUKI became an ally of the Northern Dynasty and attacked Chikafusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Munehiro was a military commander loyal to the Southern Dynasty throughout his life, it was ironic that his son Chikatomo YUKI became an ally of the Northern Dynasty and attacked Chikafusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Munehiro was a military commander loyal to the Southern Court throughout his life, it was ironic that his son Chikatomo YUKI became an ally of the Northern Dynasty and attacked Chikafusa.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、家督は当初親朝が分家していたために親朝の子・結城顕朝を後継者としていたが、宗広の死後に顕朝が白河結城の家督と所領を父に献じたために親朝が継承している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note that, since Chikamoto was in a branch family, Chikamoto&apos;s son Akitomo YUKI was appointed to take over the family headship, but after Munehiro died, Akitomo gave the headship of the Shirakawa Yuki clan and territories to his father, Chikamoto; therefore, Chikamoto took over the family headship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that, since Chikamoto was in a branch family, Chikamoto&apos;s son Akitomo YUKI was appointed to take over the family headship, but after Munehiro died, Akitomo gave the headship of the Shirakawa Yuki clan and territories to his father, Chikamoto; therefore, Chikamoto took over the family headship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that, since Chikamoto was in a branch family, Chikamoto&apos;s son Akitomo YUKI was appointed to take over the family headship, but after Munehiro died, Akitomo gave the headship of the Shirakawa Yuki clan and territories to his father, Chikamoto; therefore, Chikamoto took over the family headship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), N yotarou(id:60870), MIsogi(id:20599), 代言人(id:33675), 海衛士(id:19229), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Charenji(id:7908), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>