<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>河越重房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigefusa KAWAGOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigefusa KAWAGOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigefusa KAWAGOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>河越 重房（かわごえ しげふさ、仁安 (日本)4年（1169年）? - 文治元年11月12日 (旧暦)（1185年12月5日））は平安時代末期の武蔵国入間郡河越館の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigefusa KAWAGOE (1169? - December 5, 1185) was a military commander who lived in the Kawagoe Yakata, Iruma-gun, Musashi Province during the last days of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigefusa KAWAGOE (1169? - December 5, 1185) was a military commander who lived in the Kawagoe Yakata, Iruma-gun, Musashi Province during the last days of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigefusa KAWAGOE (1169? - December 12, 1185) was a military commander who lived in the Kawagoe Yakata, Iruma County, Musashi Province during the last days of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。Iruma-gun→Iruma Countyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>河越重頼の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an heir of Shigeyori KAWAGOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an heir of Shigeyori KAWAGOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an heir of Shigeyori KAWAGOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は小太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Kotaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Kotaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Kotaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>姉妹に源義経の正室である郷御前がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sister, Sato Gozen, was the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sister, Sato Gozen, was the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sister, Sato Gozen, was the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弟に河越重時、河越重員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetoki KAWAGOE and Shigekazu KAWAGOE were his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetoki KAWAGOE and Shigekazu KAWAGOE were his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetoki KAWAGOE and Shigekazu KAWAGOE were his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>寿永3年（1184年）1月の源義仲追討で、父・河越重頼と共に源範頼・源義経の軍に属して京都に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of hunting down Yoshinaka KISO in January 1184, he went to Kyoto belonging to the troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune together with his father Shigeyori KAWAGOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of hunting down Yoshinaka KISO in January 1184, he and his father Shigeyori KAWAGOE joined the troop of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and went to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of hunting down Yoshinaka KISO in February 1184, he went to Kyoto belonging to the troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune together with his father Shigeyori KAWAGOE.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>都に入ると範頼・義経・重頼・重房他数騎で後白河天皇が幽閉されていた六条殿に駆けつけ、仙洞御所の警護にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After arriving at Kyoto, Noriyori, Yoshitsune, Shigeyori, Shegefusa and other several horse men, rushed to Rokujo Palace where the Emperor Goshirakawa was confined and they guarded the Sento Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After arriving at Kyoto, Noriyori, Yoshitsune, Shigeyori, Shegefusa and other several horsemen rushed to the Rokujo Palace where Emperor Goshirakawa was confined and guarded the Sento Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After arriving at Kyoto, Noriyori, Yoshitsune, Shigeyori, Shegefusa and other several horsemen rushed to the Rokujo Palace where Emperor Goshirakawa was confined and guarded the Sento Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>『源平盛衰記』ではこの時16歳とされ、300騎を率いて義仲勢を相手に奮戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Genpei Seisuiki,&quot; Shigefusa was 16 years old at that time and he fought hard with the troops of Yoshinaka leading 300 horse men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Genpei Seisuiki,&quot; Shigefusa was 16 years old at that time and he fought hard with the troops of Yoshinaka by leading 300 horsemen.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Genpei Seisuiki,&quot; Shigefusa was 16 years old at that time and he fought hard with the troops of Yoshinaka by leading 300 horsemen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>義経と共に法皇の前で名乗りを上げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He introduced himself in front of the Cloistered Emperor together with Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He introduced himself in front of the Cloistered Emperor together with Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He introduced himself in front of the Cloistered Emperor together with Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>文治元年（1185年）、源頼朝と源義経が対立し、義経が後白河法皇から頼朝追討の宣旨を受けると、義経の舅にあたる父・重頼も頼朝から敵対視されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1185 MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune were opposed each other and when Yoshitsune received the imperial decree to search and kill MINAMOTO no Yoritomo from the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, his father Shigeyori was also came to be regarded as an enemy from Yoritomo because Shigeyori was the father-in-law of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1185, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune were opposed each other and when Yoshitsune received an imperial decree to search and kill MINAMOTO no Yoritomo from the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, his father Shigeyori also came to be regarded as an enemy by Yoritomo because Shigeyori was the father-in-law of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1185, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune were opposed each other and when Yoshitsune received an imperial decree to search and kill MINAMOTO no Yoritomo from the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, his father Shigeyori also came to be regarded as an enemy by Yoritomo because Shigeyori was the father-in-law of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年10月23日、重房は義経の縁戚である事を理由に、鎌倉での勝長寿院本堂落慶供養の随兵から外される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the October 23 of the same year, Shigefusa was excluded from the group of soldiers who were in charge of guarding the dedication ceremony at the main hall of Shochoju-in Temple in Kamakura for the reason of his being relative of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 23 of the same year, Shigefusa was excluded from the group of soldiers who were in charge of guarding the dedication ceremony at the main hall of Shochoju-in Temple in Kamakura for the reason that he was a relative of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 23 of the same year, Shigefusa was excluded from the group of soldiers who were in charge of guarding the dedication ceremony at the main hall of Shochoju-in Temple in Kamakura for the reason that he was a relative of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同年11月12日、重頼は所領を没収され、間もなく重房と共に誅殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the November 12 of the same year, Shigeyori was forfeited his territory and before long was killed for punishment along with Shigefusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 12 of the same year, the territory of Shigeyori was forfeited and he and Shigefusa were killed for punishment before long.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 12 of the same year, the territory of Shigeyori was forfeited and he and Shigefusa were killed for punishment before long.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更して、最初の日付に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>『平家物語』では一ノ谷の戦いで平経正を討取り、平知盛が逃がした名馬・井上黒（河越黒）をとらえて後白河院に献上する活躍を見せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), the scene in which Shigefusa felled TAIRA no Tsunemasa in the Battle of Ichi no Tani is described; also the scene in which he captures the fine horse Inoueguro (Kawagoeguro) with his quick action that TAIRA no Tomonori let loose is described; it is said that he dedicated the horse to the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), there is a scene in which Shigefusa felled TAIRA no Tsunemasa in the Battle of Ichi no Tani and also a scene in which he captured a fine horse Inoueguro (Kawagoeguro) that TAIRA no Tomonori failed to catch and it is said that he dedicated the horse to the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), there is a scene in which Shigefusa felled TAIRA no Tsunemasa in the Battle of Ichi no Tani and also a scene in which he captured a fine horse Inoueguro (Kawagoeguro) that TAIRA no Tomonori failed to catch and it is said that he dedicated the horse to the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>平家滅亡後、義経から捕虜となった平宗盛の子・8歳の平能宗を預かり、処刑するにあたって涙する場面が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the fall of the TAIRA clan, TAIRA no Yoshimune, the eight years old of the son of TAIRA no Munemori was captured and was with Shigefusa; the scene, in which he sheds tears before Yoshimune is executed, is depicted in the book also.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the fall of the TAIRA clan, TAIRA no Yoshimune, an eight-year-old son of TAIRA no Munemori, was captured and transferred to Shigefusa from Yoritomo; a scene, in which he shed tears before he executed Yoshimune, is also depicted in the book.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the fall of the TAIRA clan, TAIRA no Yoshimune, an eight-year-old son of TAIRA no Munemori, was captured and transferred to Shigefusa from Yoritomo; a scene, in which he shed tears before he executed Yoshimune, is also depicted in the book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), Nalc(id:139567), 小者(id:172526), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>