<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宇都宮泰綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna UTSUNOMIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna UTSUNOMIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna UTSUNOMIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宇都宮 泰綱（うつのみや やすつな）は鎌倉時代前・中期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna UTSUNOMIYA was the Samurai in early and middle of Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna UTSUNOMIYA was a samurai during the early and middle Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna UTSUNOMIYA was a samurai during the early to middle Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府の御家人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)of Kamakura bakufu. (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)to the Kamakura bakufu. (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the an immediate vassal to the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>宇都宮氏第六代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixth family head of the Utsunomiya clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth family head of the Utsunomiya clan</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth head of the Utsunomiya clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は宇都宮頼綱、母は北条時政の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, and his mother was Tokimasa HOJO&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, and his mother was Tokimasa HOJO&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, and his mother was Tokimasa HOJO&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>1238年、将軍・九条頼経に仕えて上洛し下野守に叙任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1238 he came to Kyoto to serve Shogun, Yoritsune KUJO and was appointed to Shimotsuke no kami. (the governor of Shimotsuke Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1238 he came to Kyoto to serve the shogun, Yoritsune KUJO and was appointed to Shimotsuke no kami. (the governor of Shimotsuke Province)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1238 he came to Kyoto to serve the shogun, Yoritsune KUJO, and was appointed to the governor of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>泰綱が吾妻鏡に登上する1230年頃の官職の記述が従五位下相当の修理職となっているから、下野守に任ぜられる前の1230年頃には既に従五位下の官位を余されており、その官位のまま下野守に任ぜられたものと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering there was a record of Yasutsuna in Azuma Kagami (The Mirror of the East) that his official rank of Shurishiki (Office of Palace Repairs) was equivalent to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) around 1230, he was presumed to be in the rank of Jugoinoge and was appointed to Shimotsuke no kami by keeping the rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the fact that there was a record of Yasutsuna in Azuma Kagami (The Mirror of the East) stating that his official rank of Shurishiki (Office of Palace Repairs) was equivalent to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) around 1230, it is presumed that he maintained the rank of Jugoinoge and was eventually appointed to Shimotsuke no kami.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the fact that there was a record of Yasutsuna in Azuma Kagami (The Mirror of the East) stating that his official rank was Shurishiki (Office of Palace Repairs), which was equivalent to Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, around 1230, it is presumed that he maintained that rank and was eventually appointed to the governor of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後1241年に下野守を満了した折には従五位上に昇進したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he finished his duty as Shimotsuke no kami in 1241, it is said he was promoted to Jugoinojo. (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After finishing his duty as Shimotsuke no kami in 1241, it is said he was promoted to Jugoinojo. (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After finishing his duty as the governor of Shimotsuke in 1241, it is said he was promoted to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1243年、幕府評定衆の一人に任じられた後は、没するまでその職に在り続け幕政で重きを成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1243 he was appointed one of Bakufu hyoteishu (an organization employing the council system in Bakufu), after that he remained in his position until he died and acted important role in the politics in the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1243 he was appointed as one of the Bakufu hyoteishu (an organization employing the council system in Bakufu), after that he remained in his position until he died and played an important role in politics in the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1243 he was appointed a member of the Councillors of the Bakufu; after that he remained in his position until he died and played an important role in politics in the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1249年頃には幕府内職位として美濃国の守護職も与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1249 he was given the position of shugoshiki (post of provincial constable) of Mino Province as the position within bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1249 he was given the position of shugoshiki (post of provincial constable) of Mino Province as a position within bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1249 he was given the position of provincial constable of Mino Province as a position within bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一方、官位の方も1246年に正五位下に昇進したようであるが、その後については不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it is said his rank was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), however there was no record after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it is said he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), however there are no records stating what happened after this fact</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it is said he was promoted to Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade in 1246, however there are no records stating what happened after this fact.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1261年11月1日、父・宇都宮頼綱の後を追うように59歳にて京都で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 1, 1261, he died in Kyoto when he was fifty nine years old, as if he followed his father, Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 1, 1261, he died in Kyoto when he was fifty nine years old, following in his father&apos;s footsteps, Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 1, 1261, he died in Kyoto when he was 59 years old, following in his father&apos;s footsteps, Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>歌人としても優れており、宇都宮歌壇を盛り立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as a poet, he played an active part in Utsunomiya poetry circle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as a poet, and played an active part in the Utsunomiya poetry circle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as a waka poet, and played an active part in the Utsunomiya poetry circle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>玉葉和歌集や続拾遺和歌集には泰綱の作品が数多く修められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Gyokuyo Wakasyu, &quot;Jeweled Leaves Collection.&quot; and Shoku Shui Wakashu (12th imperial anthology), there are many poems of Yasutsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Gyokuyo Wakasyu, &quot;Jeweled Leaves Collection.&quot; and Shoku Shui Wakashu (12th imperial anthology), there are many poems by Yasutsuna.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of Yasutsuna&apos;s poems were contained in Gyokuyo Wakasyu (Jeweled Leaves Collection) and Shoku Shui Wakashu (12th imperial anthology).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>吾妻鏡では、下野守を満了した後の泰綱を「下野前司」と記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), after Yasutsuna finished his duty as Shimotsuke no kami, he was called as &apos;the former governor of Shimotsuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), after Yasutsuna finished his duty as Shimotsuke no kami, he was called &apos;the former governor of Shimotsuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), after Yasutsuna finished his duty as the governor of Shimotsuke Province, he was called &apos;the former governor of Shimotsuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Province補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>年譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronicle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronicle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronicle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>1203年（建仁3年）－ 出生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1203.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1203.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1203.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>1235年8月21日（文暦2年6月29日 (旧暦)）- 九条頼経の新御堂参りの行列に寺門内御剣役として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied Yoshitsune KUJO as Jimonnai gokenyaku when there was a procession to visit Shin mi-do on August 21, 1235.</e>
<cmt>寺門内御剣役→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accompanied Yoshitsune KUJO as Jimonnai gokenyaku any time there was a procession to visit Shin mi-do on August 21, 1235.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accompanied Yoshitsune KUJO as a sword-bearer within the precincts during a procession to visit a new temple on August 21, 1235.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>1236年9月12日（嘉禎2年8月4日 (旧暦)）－ 新造御所（若宮大路御所）に移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 12, 1236, he moved to Shinzo Gosho. (Wakamiyaoji Gosho (imperial palace))</e>
<cmt>新造御所→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 12, 1236, he moved to Shinzo Gosho. (Wakamiyaoji Gosho (imperial palace))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 12, 1236, he moved to the Imperial Palace in Wakamiyaoji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>頼経、北条泰時御亭から新御所へ徒歩で移動し、南門より入られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsune walked from the residence of Yasutoki HOJO to shingosho, and he entered inside from the south gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritsune walked from the residence of Yasutoki HOJO to shingosho, and entered from the south gate.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritsune walked from the residence of Yasutoki HOJO to the new palace, and entered the palace from the south gate.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>泰綱、これに御後布衣（五位六位）の一人として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune as one of 御後布衣. (五位六位)</e>
<cmt>御後布衣 五位六位→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune as one of 御後布衣. (五位六位)</e>
<cmt>OK, unsure of reading.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune as one of the higher-ranked servants to Yoritsune (fifth and sixth ranks).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>1237年7月23日（嘉禎3年6月23日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経、大慈寺の郭内に新たに精舎を建立し、その供養参りの行列に御後の布衣として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 23, 1237, Yoritsune built new Shoja (a hall where priests practice asceticism, like a temple) within theDaiji-ji Temple, and Yasutsuna accompanied the procession to pray for the Shoja as 御後の布衣.</e>
<cmt>御後の布衣→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 23, 1237, Yoritsune built new Shoja (a hall where priests practice asceticism, like a temple) within the Daiji-ji Temple, and Yasutsuna accompanied the procession to pray for the Shoja as 御後の布衣.</e>
<cmt>Edited for spacing issues, unsure of reading.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 23, 1237, Yoritsune had built a new monastery within the Daiji-ji Temple, and Yasutsuna, as a higher-ranked servant, accompanied the Yoritsune&apos;s procession to visit the monastery to hold a memorial serivce.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>1238年2月21日（嘉禎4年1月28日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経一行、上洛のため鎌倉を発つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsune&apos;s procession left Kamakura for Kyoto on February 21, 1238.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritsune&apos;s procession left Kamakura for Kyoto on February 21, 1238.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritsune&apos;s procession left Kamakura for Kyoto on February 21, 1238.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これに随行して京に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession and entered to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession and entered Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna went up to Kyoto, accompaning the procession.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>1238年3月11日（嘉禎4年2月17日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経一行、京に入り六波羅御所に到着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsuna&apos;s procession entered into Kyoto and arrived at 六波羅御所 on March 11, 1238.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritsuna&apos;s procession entered Kyoto and arrived at 六波羅御所 on March 11, 1238.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritsuna&apos;s procession entered Kyoto and arrived at the Imperial Palace in Rokuhara on March 11, 1238.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>泰綱、行列の御所随兵62番として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as No.62 of 御所随兵 and entered to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>御所随兵→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as No.62 of 御所随兵 and entered Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as No. 62 attendant warrior to Yoritsune and entered Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>1238年3月21日（嘉禎4年2月27日 (旧暦)）－ 泰綱、下野守に任ぜられる（官位は従五位下または従五位上であったと推定される）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 21, 1238, Yasutsuna was appointed to Shimotsuke no kami. (the official rank was presumed to be Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) or Jugoinojo. (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 21, 1238, Yasutsuna was appointed to Shimotsuke no kami. (the official rank was presumed to be Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) or Jugoinojo. (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 21, 1238, Yasutsuna was appointed to the governor of Shimotsuke Province (The official rank was presumed to be Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade or Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Province補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>1238年3月22日（嘉禎4年2月28日 (旧暦)）－ 公家に馬を献上するための行列の随兵2番として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 22, 1238, he accompanied the procession as No. 2 随兵 to give horse to the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>随兵→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 22, 1238, he accompanied the procession as No. 2 随兵 to present a horse or horses to the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 22, 1238, he accompanied the procession to present a horse to the court noble as No. 2 attendant warrior.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>1238年7月24日（嘉禎4年6月5日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経の春日大社参詣の行列に水干の2番として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 24, 1238, he accompanied the procession of Yoritsune&apos;s visit to Kasugataisha Shrine as No. 2 Suikan.</e>
<cmt>水干→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 24, 1238, he accompanied Yoritsune&apos;s procession to Kasugataisha Shrine as No. 2 Suikan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 24, 1238, he accompanied Yoritsune&apos;s procession to Kasugataisha Shrine as No. 2 servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>1240年3月頃（延応2年2月頃）－ 泰綱、下野守の職を満了し、従五位上に昇進したものと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around March 1240, Yasutsuna finished his duty as Shimotsuke no kami, he was presumed to be promoted to Jugoinojo. (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around March 1240, Yasutsuna finished his duty as Shimotsuke no kami, he was presumed to be promoted to Jugoinojo. (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around March 1240, Yasutsuna finished his duty as the governor of Shimotsuke Province, and he was presumed to be promoted to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>1241年2月3日（仁治2年1月14日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経の鶴岡八幡宮参詣に供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied Yoritsune&apos;s visit to pray for Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine on February 3, 1241.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accompanied Yoritsune&apos;s visit to pray for Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine on February 3, 1241.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accompanied Yoritsune to the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine on February 3, 1241.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>1241年10月8日（仁治2年8月25日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経、新北斗堂を建立し、その供養のために参堂する行列に御後として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 8, 1241, Yoritsune built Shin hokutodo and Yasutsuna accompanied the procession to pray for Shin hokutodo as 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 8, 1241, Yoritsune built Shin hokutodo and Yasutsuna accompanied the procession to pray for Shin hokutodo as 御後.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 8, 1241, Yoritsune had built Shin hokutodo, and Yasutsuna, as a servant, accompanied the Yoritsune&apos;s procession to visit the Shin hokuto-do.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>1241年12月14日（仁治2年11月4日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経、武蔵野開発の方違えのため武蔵国鶴見へ御渡しする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 14, 1241, Yoritsune went to Tsurumi in Musashi Province by ship for katatagae. (to stay the night in a place situated at another point of the compass when one&apos;s destination from home lies in an ill-starred direction)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 14, 1241, Yoritsune went to Tsurumi in Musashi Province by ship due to katatagae. (to stay the night in a place situated at another point of the compass when one&apos;s destination from home lies in a direction of ill fortune)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 14, 1241, in order to start the development of Musashino area, Yoritsune went to Tsurumi in Musashi Province by ship for changing the direction to enter the development site to avoid the direction of ill fortune (katatagae).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。in小文字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その行列に念人として随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied to the above procession as 念人.</e>
<cmt>念人→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied the above procession as 念人.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the above procession as an attendant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="33">
<j>1243年2月頃（仁治4年1月頃）- 評定衆に任ぜられる（生涯在職したとされる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around February 1243, Yasutnsna was appointed to hyojoshu. (a member of Council of State) (he was presumed that he was in this position until he died.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around February 1243, Yasutnsna was appointed to hyojoshu. (a member of Council of State) (it was presumed that he was in this position until he died.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around February 1243, Yasutsuna was appointed to a member of Council of State (It was presumed that he was in this position until he died).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="34">
<j>1243年2月16日（仁治4年1月19日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経の鶴岡八幡宮参詣に供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 16, 1243, Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune&apos;s visit to Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 16, 1243, Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune&apos;s visit to Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 16, 1243, Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune to visit the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="35">
<j>1243年3月24日（寛元元年2月26日 (旧暦)）- 北条時頼御亭において、御物沙汰日結番の1番（3、9、13、17、23日）に決まったとの沙汰が有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an instruction (an order) that No. 1 of 御物沙汰日結番 (3, 9, 13, 17, 23) was decided at the residence of Tokiyori HOJO on March 24, 1243.</e>
<cmt>御物沙汰日→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an instruction (an order) that the No. 1 御物沙汰日結番 (3, 9, 13, 17, 23) was decided at the residence of Tokiyori HOJO on March 24, 1243.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the residence of Tokiyori HOJO, on March 24, 1243, Yasutsuna was order to atttend at the trial on the days of the rotation No. 1 (3rd, 9th, 13th, 17th, 23rd).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="36">
<j>1243年9月9日（寛元元年7月17日 (旧暦)）－ 御共結番の中旬となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 9, 1243, Yasutsuna became middle of 御共結番.</e>
<cmt>御共結番→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 9, 1243, Yasutsuna became a middle 御共結番.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 9, 1243, working days for Yasutsuna as attendant was decided as the middle ten days of a month.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。working小文字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="37">
<j>1243年10月26日（寛元元年9月5日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経が後藤基綱大倉家へ入御されるのに随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 26, 1243, Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune to visit Okura family and Mototsuna GOTO.</e>
<cmt>後藤基綱大倉家→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 26, 1243, Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune to visit Okura family and Mototsuna GOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 26, 1243, Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsune to visit Okura family and Mototsuna GOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="38">
<j>1244年6月4日（寛元2年4月21日 (旧暦)）－ 将軍家の嫡子である藤原頼嗣の元服式に評定衆として参列、献杯する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 4, 1244, Yasutsuna attended as hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) of the coming-of-age ceremony of FUJIWARA no Yoritsugu, who was the successor of Shogun family and he offered a cup of sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 4, 1244, Yasutsuna attended as hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) for the coming-of-age ceremony of FUJIWARA no Yoritsugu, who was a successor to the Shogun family and offered a cup of sake.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 4, 1244, Yasutsuna attended as a member of Council of State for the coming-of-age ceremony of FUJIWARA no Yoritsugu, who was a successor to the Shogun family, and offered Yoritsugu a cup of sake.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この座にて、元服の儀が無事に終了した事、頼嗣が新たな官位に叙任されたこと、征夷大将軍に奉じられた事が申し述べられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the coming-of-age ceremony, it was announced that the ceremony was sorely conducted and finished, and Yoritsugu was given new official rank, and appointed as Seii Taishogun. (Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the coming-of-age ceremony, it was announced that the ceremony was conducted and finished in a satisfactory manner, and Yoritsugu was given a new official rank, and appointed as Seii Taishogun. (Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the coming-of-age ceremony, it was announced that the ceremony was conducted and finished in a satisfactory manner, and Yoritsugu was given a new official rank, and appointed as Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="40">
<j>1244年9月25日（寛元2年8月15日 (旧暦)）－ 頼経、将軍頼嗣を伴って鶴岡八幡宮の放生会に参列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsune accompanied Shogun, Yoritsugu who attended Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritsune accompanied the shogun, Yoritsugu who attended Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 25, 1244, Yoritsune took the shogun Yoritsugu to attend the ritual for releasing living beings at Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>泰綱、行列の御後の布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="42">
<j>1246年2月頃（寛元4年1月頃）- 正五位下に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) around February 1246.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) around February 1246.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna was promoted to Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, around February 1246.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="43">
<j>1246年10月3日（寛元4年8月15日 (旧暦)）－ 頼嗣、鶴岡八幡宮の放生会に参列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 3, 1246, Yoritsugu attended Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 3, 1246, Yoritsugu attended Hojoe (a ritual for releasing living beings) at Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 3, 1246, Yoritsugu attended the ritual for releasing living beings at Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>泰綱、行列の御後の布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied Yotitsugu &apos;s procession as 御後of 布衣.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied Yotitsugu &apos;s procession as 御後of 布衣.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsugu&apos;s procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="45">
<j>1247年8月6日（宝治元年6月27日 (旧暦)）－ 評定が開かれて列席する（仏寺吉事の沙汰があり、大納言法印隆弁が鶴岡八幡宮別当職に補任される）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 6, 1247, Yasutsuna attended verdict. (There was an occasion of good fortune for Buddhist rituals and a chief councilor of state, Hoin Ryuben was appointed to Bettoshoku of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 6, 1247, Yasutsuna attended a verdict ritual. (It was an occasion of good fortune for Buddhist rituals and a chief councilor of state, Hoin Ryuben was appointed to Bettoshoku of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 6, 1247, Yasutsuna attended a verdict (It was an occasion of good fortune for Buddhist rituals, and a chief councilor of state, Hoin Ryuben was appointed to the office of head of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオド位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="46">
<j>1248年2月2日（宝治元年12月29日 (旧暦)）- 宝治合戦の恩賞の沙汰があるとともに京都大番役の結番があり、泰綱も21番として3ヶ月間洛中にて警邏に当たることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 2, 1248, there was an occasion of reward for Battle of Hoji, and there was 結番 of Kyoto Obanyaku, Yasutsuna joined in the patrol as No. 21 while staying in Kyoto for three months.</e>
<cmt>結番→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 2, 1248, there was an occasion to reward certain individuals over the Battle of Hoji, and there was 結番 of Kyoto Obanyaku, and Yasutsuna joined in the patrol as No. 21 while staying in Kyoto for three months.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 2, 1248, there was an occasion to reward certain individuals over the Battle of Hoji, and it was the working day for the Imperial guard service in Kyoto; Yasutsuna joined the patrol as No. 21 guard for three months in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="47">
<j>1248年2月5日（宝治2年1月3日 (旧暦)）－ 頼嗣、御行始の儀のため左親衛御亭に入御し、泰綱も供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 5, 1248, Yoritsugu went to sashine ontei (residence of sashine) for Miyukihajime no gi (ritual for the first going out of the Emperor) and Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 5, 1248, Yoritsugu went to sashine ontei (residence of sashine) for Miyukihajime no gi (ritual for the first excursion by the Emperor) and Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsugu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 5, 1248, Yoritsugu went to the residence of sashine for the ritual for the first excursion, and Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsugu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="48">
<j>1248年2月9日（宝治2年1月7日 (旧暦)）－ 廣御出居に於いて評定衆の着座の順番を取り決める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 9, 1248, the sitting order of hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) at 廣御出居 was decided.</e>
<cmt>廣御出居→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 9, 1248, the sitting order of hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) at 廣御出居 was decided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 9, 1248, the sitting order of the members of Council of State at the hall in the shogun&apos;s residence was decided.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>泰綱は若座の下より2番目となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna&apos;s sitting order was the second from the end of 若座.</e>
<cmt>若座→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna&apos;s sitting order was the second from the end of 若座.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna&apos;s sitting order was the second from the end of the wakaza (literally, seat for youth).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="50">
<j>1248年8月27日（宝治2年8月1日 (旧暦)）－ 左親衛が春日部実景亭に渡り、泰綱も隠岐行義とともに参会、囲碁の勝負について決する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 27, 1248, Sashine went to 春日部実景亭, Yasutsuna went there as well with Yukiyoshi OKI to have match of Igo. (board game of capturing territory)</e>
<cmt>春日部実景亭→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 27, 1248, Sashine went to 春日部実景亭, Yasutsuna went there as well with Yukiyoshi OKI to have a match of Igo. (board game of capturing territory)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 27, 1248, Sashine went to the residence of Sanekage KASUKABE, and Yasutsuna went there as well with Yukiyoshi OKI to have a match of Igo board game.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="51">
<j>1249年（宝治3年または建長元年）- 美濃国守護に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 1249 Yasytsuna was appointed to provincial constable of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On 1249 Yasytsuna was appointed to provincial constable of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1249 Yasutsuna was appointed provincial constable of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="52">
<j>1250年5月5日（建長2年3月25日 (旧暦)）－ 頼嗣、御方違のため相州御亭に入御する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 5, 1250, Yoritsugu entered to Soshu gyotei for onkatatagae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 5, 1250, Yoritsugu entered to Soshu gyotei for onkatatagae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 5, 1250, Yoritsugu entered the shogun&apos;s residence in Sagami Province for changing the direction (katatagae).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>泰綱、布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritsuna accompanied that entrance to the residence as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="54">
<j>1250年6月17日（建長2年5月9日 (旧暦)）－ 頼嗣、御方違のため相州御亭に入御する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 17, 1250, Yoritsugu entered to Soshu gyotei for onkatatagae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, 1250, Yoritsugu entered Soshu gyotei for onkatatagae.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 17, 1250, Yoritsugu entered the shogun&apos;s residence in Sagami Province for changing the direction (katatagae).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>泰綱は佐渡前司、刑部大輔入道等と予め御所にて待つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna waited at Imperial Palace beforehand with the former official of Sado Province and Gyobu no taifu Nyudo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna waited at the Imperial Palace beforehand with the former official of Sado Province and Gyobu no taifu Nyudo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for spacing issues</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna, together with the former governor of Sado Province, the vice-minister of the judicial department Nyudo, and others, waited for Yoritsugu at the Imperial Palace beforehand.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="56">
<j>1250年12月12日（建長2年11月11日 (旧暦)）－ 夜に入り、塩谷朝業の郎党が若宮大路で確論をもって乱闘を起こす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December12, 1250, there was an incident Tomonari SHIONOYA&apos;s roto (retainer) had an argument and caused a brawl at Wakamiya-oji Street at night.</e>
<cmt>確論→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December12, 1250, there was an incident Tomonari SHIONOYA&apos;s roto (retainer) had an argument and caused a brawl at Wakamiya-oji Street at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 12, 1250, there was an incident in the night when Tomonari SHIONOYA&apos;s retainers had an argument and caused a brawl on the Wakamiya-oji Street.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また泰綱の郎党等が国方の者と称して蜂起し、この喧嘩を増大させようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutusna&apos;s retainer called themselves as government force and rise in revolt to make this incident worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutusna&apos;s retainers revolted while identifying themselves as a government force in an attempt to worsen the situation.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna&apos;s retainers revolted while identifying themselves as a government force in an attempt to increase the brawl.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>時に塩谷氏の郎党は主人（塩谷親朝）の忌日も過ぎておらず、幕府もまた精進しているところであったが、公私にわたり立場も弁えずに奇怪な企てや狼藉を働くのは重科に相当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not long ago after the head of Shionoya clan (Chikatomo SHIONOYA) died and the bakufu did not do anything drastic, and it was considered grave offense to act irresponsibly without consideration whether it was in public or private, by making strange plot or causing violence, Yasutusna was asked to suppress the incident and he let the retainers to stop the violence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it occured not long after the head of Shionoya clan (Chikatomo SHIONOYA) died and the bakufu had not taken any drastic measures, it was considered a grave offense to act irresponsibly without consideration whether in public or private, through plotting or acts of violence. Yasutusna was asked to suppress the incident and he made the retainers stop the violence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it occurred not long after the head of Shionoya clan (Chikatomo SHIONOYA) died and the bakufu had not taken any drastic measures, it was considered a grave offense to act irresponsibly without consideration both in public and private, through strange behavior and violence.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>泰綱はこれを誡めるべきであるとの沙汰があり、泰綱はこれを鎮静させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna was ordered to suppress the incident and made the retainers stop the violence.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="60">
<j>1251年1月30日（建長3年1月1日 (旧暦)）－ 頼嗣、若君御前等を伴い御行始めの儀のため、相州御亭に入御する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 30, 1251, Yoritsugu went to Soshu gyotei with Wakagimi gozen to attend Miyukihajime no gi. (ritual for the first going out of the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>　 若君御前→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 30, 1251, Yoritsugu went to Soshu gyotei with Wakagimi gozen to attend Miyukihajime no gi. (ritual for the first going out of the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritsugu entered the shogun&apos;s residence in Sagami Province for the ritual for the first excursion with the young shogun and others.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>泰綱、将軍御方としてこれに供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as 将軍御方.</e>
<cmt>将軍御方→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession as 将軍御方.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied them as the attendants of shogun.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="62">
<j>1251年1月31日（建長3年1月2日 (旧暦)）- 北条義時が頼嗣に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は御行騰（むかばき、馬具）を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 31, 1251, Yoshitoki HOJO gave oban to Yoritsugu, and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 31, 1251, Yoshitoki HOJO gave oban to Yoritsugu, and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 31, 1251, Yoshitoki HOJO gave a feast to Yoritsugu, and Yasutsuna presented harness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="63">
<j>1251年12月10日（建長3年10月19日 (旧暦)）－ 頼嗣、二品を伴って新築した相州御亭に入御し御泊りになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 10, 1251, Yoritsugu, accompanied with Nihon, entered and stayed at Soshu gyotei which was newly built.</e>
<cmt>二品→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 10, 1251, Yoritsugu, accompanied with Nihon, entered and stayed at Soshu gyotei which was newly built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 10, 1251, Yoritsugu, accompanied the second court rank for Imperial Princes, and then entered and stayed at the newly built shogun&apos;s residence in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>泰綱は二品御方としてこれに供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsugu as 二品御方.</e>
<cmt>二品御方→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsugu as 二品御方.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied Yoritsugu as the attendants of Nihon.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="65">
<j>1252年5月17日（建長4年4月1日 (旧暦)）－ 征夷大将軍を辞任して京に戻った頼嗣に替わり、宗尊親王が京から下向される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 17, 1252, after Yoritsugu resigned Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo, Imperial Prince Munetaka was sent from Kyoto as successor of Yoritsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 17, 1252, after Yoritsugu resigned Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo, Imperial Prince Munetaka was sent from Kyoto as a successor to Yoritsugu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 17, 1252, after Yoritsugu resigned from shogun, Imperial Prince Munetaka came down from Kyoto as a successor to Yoritsugu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この日、片瀬 (藤沢市)の宿を御発ちになったので、先女房等や御輿、公卿、随兵等が行列をなしてこれを迎え、相州御亭に入御される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Prince Munetaka left the hotel in Katase (Fujisawa City), there was a procession of people such as sakinyobo, 御輿, court nobles, 随兵 to welcome the Prince to enter into Soshu gyotei.</e>
<cmt>先女房 御輿→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Prince Munetaka left the hotel in Katase (Fujisawa City), there was a procession of people such as sakinyobo, 御輿, court nobles, 随兵 to welcome the Prince to enter Soshu gyotei.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Prince Munetaka left the hotel in Katase (Fujisawa City), a procession of court ladies, palanquins, court nobles, attendant warriors and others welcomed the Prince to enter the residence of the shogun in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>泰綱は奥州、相州等とともに予め相州御亭の庭上にてこれを待った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutusna waited for the Prince beforehand with Oshu and Soshu in the garden of Soshu gyotei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutusna waited for the Prince beforehand with Oshu and Soshu in the garden of Soshu gyotei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna waited for the Prince beforehand with the govrnors of Mutsu Province and Sagami Province in the garden of the residence of the shogun in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="68">
<j>1252年5月19日（建長4年4月3日 (旧暦)）- 足利義正の親王に椀飯を沙汰するにあたり、泰綱は刻限を申した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 19, 1252, when there was an occasion for the Prince of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA to have Oban, Yasutsuna suggested appointed time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 19, 1252, when there was an occasion for Prince of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA to have Oban, Yasutsuna suggested an appointed time.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 19, 1252, when there was an occasion for the Prince of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA to give a feast, Yasutsuna suggested an appointed time.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="69">
<j>1252年5月30日（建長4年4月14日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王の鶴岡八幡宮への御参始がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 30, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 30, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 30, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>泰綱、これに供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied the Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied the Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="71">
<j>1252年12月20日（建長4年11月11日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王が寝所としていた相州御亭から新御所へ徒歩にて移転する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 20, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka walked from his place at the Shoshu gyotei to the new Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 20, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka walked from his place at the Shoshu gyotei to the new Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 20, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka walked from the residence of the shogun in Sagami Province where he had stayed to the new Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>泰綱、この行列に供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied this procession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied the procession.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna attended the procession.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="73">
<j>1252年12月29日（建長4年11月20日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王が新御所へ移られて初めて、奥州亭に入御する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 29, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka entered the 奥州亭 for the first time since he moved to the new Palace.</e>
<cmt>奥州亭→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 29, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka entered the 奥州亭 for the first time since he moved to the new Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 29, 1252, Imperial Prince Munetaka entered the residence of the shogun in Mutsu Province for the first time since he moved to the new Palace.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>泰綱、この行列に布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied this procession as 布衣.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied this procession as 布衣.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna attended this procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="75">
<j>1253年1月24日（建長4年12月17日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王が新御所へ移られて初めて、鶴岡八幡宮に参詣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 24, 1253, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine for the first time since he moved to the new Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 24, 1253, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine for the first time since he moved to the new Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 24, 1253, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine for the first time since he moved to the new Palace.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>泰綱、この行列に御後の布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied this procession as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied this procession as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna attended this procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="77">
<j>1253年2月9日（建長5年1月3日 (旧暦)）－ 奥州が宗尊親王に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は御行騰を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 9, 1253, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 9, 1253, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 9, 1253, the govrnor of Mutsu Province held a feast to Imperial Prince Munetaka, and Yasutsuna presented harness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="78">
<j>1253年2月27日（建長5年1月21日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王が鶴岡八幡宮に参詣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 27, 1253, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 27, 1253, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 27, 1253, Imperial Prince Munetaka visited the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>泰綱、これに御後の布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna attended the procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="80">
<j>1254年1月28日（建長6年1月1日 (旧暦)）－ 相州が宗尊親王に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は御行騰を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 28, 1254, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 28, 1254, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 28, 1254, the governor of Sagami Province held a feast to Imperial Prince Munetaka, and Yasutsuna presented harness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>親王、この後御行始めの儀のため相州御亭に移り、泰綱も布衣としてこれに供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince moved to Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi and Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Prince moved to Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi and Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Prince moved to the residence of the shogun in Sagami Province for the ritual of the first excursion, and Yasutsuna accompanied this as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="82">
<j>1254年1月30日（建長6年1月3日 (旧暦)）－ 奥州が宗尊親王に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は御行騰を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 30, 1254, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 30, 1254, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 30, 1254, the governor of Mutsu Province held a feast to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented harness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="83">
<j>1254年2月18日（建長6年1月22日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王が鶴岡八幡宮に参詣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 18, 1254, Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 18, 1254, Munetaka visited Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 18, 1254, Munetaka visited the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>泰綱、これに御後として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 御後.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna attended the procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="85">
<j>1256年2月7日（建長8年1月3日 (旧暦)）- 足利利氏が宗尊親王に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は御調度を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 7, 1256, Toshiuji ASHIKAGA gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 7, 1256, Toshiuji ASHIKAGA gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 7, 1256, Toshiuji ASHIKAGA held a feast to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented harness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="86">
<j>1256年2月9日（建長8年1月5日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王、御行始めの儀のため相州御亭に移り、泰綱も布衣としてこれに供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 9, 1256, the Imperial Prince moved to Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi and Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 9, 1256, the Imperial Prince moved to Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi and Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 9, 1256, the Imperial Prince moved to the residence of the shogun in Sagami Province to attend the ritual for the first excursion, and Yasutsuna attended the procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="87">
<j>1256年7月2日（建長8年6月2日 (旧暦)）- 鎌倉街道中道にて夜討盗賊が蜂起し、往来する旅人を煩わしていることから、沿線の地頭等にこれを警固するようにとの御教書が沙汰される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there was burglar around The Nakatsumichi Kamakura-kaido Road (one of the three Kamakura-kaido Roads) and robbed the travelers coming and going to the area causing problems, migyosho (a document for informing people of the decision of Third Rank or upper people) was issued on July 2, 1256, to Military Land Steward around this area to protect people from burglar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since there were burglars around the Nakatsumichi Kamakura-kaido Road (one of the three Kamakura-kaido Roads) who robbed travelers coming and going from the area, migyosho (a document for informing people of decisions cast by those of Third Rank or higher) was issued on July 2, 1256, to the Military Land Steward around the area to protect people from such acts.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there were burglars around the Nakatsumichi Kamakura-kaido Road (one of the three Kamakura-kaido Roads) who robbed travelers coming and going from the area, a document for informing people of decisions was issued on July 2, 1256, to the Military Land Steward around the area to protect people from such acts.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>泰綱、この地頭等24名の一人としてこの沙汰を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna received above order as one of Millitary Land Steward out of twenty four.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna received the above order as one Millitary Land Steward out of twenty four.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna was one Military Land Steward out of the twenty four to receive the above order.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="89">
<j>1256年7月29日（建長8年6月29日 (旧暦)）－ 泰綱等、本年の鶴岡八幡宮の放生会に供奉する人事が申し伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 29, 1256, personnel was announced to accompany Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine on this year including Yasutsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 29, 1256, personnel which included Yasutsuna were announced to accompany the Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 29, 1256, the members including Yasutsuna were announced to attend the ritual for releasing the living beings at the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="90">
<j>1257年1月24日（康元2年1月1日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王、御行始めの儀のため相州御亭に移り、泰綱も布衣としてこれに供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 24, 1257, the Imperial Prince moved to Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi and Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 24, 1257, the Imperial Prince moved to Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi and Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 24, 1257, the Imperial Prince moved to the residence of the shogun in Sagami Province to attend the ritual for the first excursion and Yasutsuna accompanied this as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="91">
<j>1257年1月25日（康元2年1月2日 (旧暦)）－ 奥州が宗尊親王に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は御調度を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 25, 1257, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 25, 1257, Oshu gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 25, 1257, the governor of Mutsu Province held a feast to Imperial Prince Munetaka, and Yasutsuna presented a harness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="92">
<j>1257年3月20日（康元2年2月26日 (旧暦)）- 北条時宗の元服の儀が行われ、泰綱は御矢を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 20, 1257, there was a coming-of-age ceremony for Tokimune HOJO and Yasutsuna was present to shoot an arrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 20, 1257, there was a coming-of-age ceremony for Tokimune HOJO and Yasutsuna was present to shoot an arrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 20, 1257, there was a coming-of-age ceremony for Tokimune HOJO and Yasutsuna presented an arrow.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="93">
<j>1257年4月29日（正嘉元年4月7日 (旧暦)）－ 泰綱、御所にて蹴鞠会を行うべき旨を申し上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 29, 1257, Yasutsuna suggested to organize Kemari Party at the Impaerial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 29, 1257, Yasutsuna suggested that a Kemari Party be organized at the Impaerial Palace.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 29, 1257, Yasutsuna suggested that a Kemari Meet should be held at the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="94">
<j>1257年5月1日（正嘉元年4月9日 (旧暦)）－ 御所にて御鞠会が行われ、泰綱は布衣で参じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 1, 1257, the Kemari Party was held and Yasutsuna attended as 布衣,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 1, 1257, the Kemari Party was held and Yasutsuna attended as 布衣,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 1, 1257, the Kemari Meet was held and Yasutsuna attended as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>露払いの後、宗尊親王も御布衣にて立たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After outrider, Imperial Prince Munetaka stood in front of the public with 御布衣 costume, firstly Yasutsuna passed Princekusubemari (a smoked ball) which was stringed to a branch of maple tree to the Prince, then Munenori NANBA passed agemari to the Prince.</e>
<cmt>御布衣→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the purification ritual, Imperial Prince Munetaka stood in front of the public in his 御布衣 costume. First Yasutsuna passed the Prince a kusubemari (a smoked ball) which was stringed to a branch of maple trees, after which Munenori NANBA passed agemari to the Prince.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the purification ritual, Imperial Prince Munetaka stood in front of the public in the court nobles&apos; informal clothes.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>まず泰綱が燻鞠をカエデの枝に付けて親王に進め、難波宗教が上鞠を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First Yasutsuna passed the Prince a smoked ball which was stringed to a maple branch, after which Munenori NANBA played as an expert player who kicked off the game.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="97">
<j>1257年10月1日（正嘉元年8月15日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王、鶴岡八幡宮の放生会に御出になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, 1257, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1257, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 1, 1257, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended the ritual for releasing the living beings at the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>泰綱、これに御後の布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna attended the procession as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="99">
<j>1257年11月15日（正嘉元年10月1日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王、大慈寺の供養に参られ、泰綱も御後の布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 15, 1257, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended to pray for Daiji-ji Temple and Yasutsuna accompanied him as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 15, 1257, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended to conduct prayers at Daiji-ji Temple and Yasutsuna accompanied him as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 15, 1257, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended to the memorial service at the Daiji-ji Temple and Yasutsuna accompanied him as a commoner servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="100">
<j>1258年1月4日（正嘉元年11月22日 (旧暦)）－ 藤次左衛門入道の家で失火し、若宮大路ほか、泰綱宅や花山院長雅宅等を焼いて田楽辻子で鎮火する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 14, 1258, there was a fire at 藤次左衛門入道&apos;s house, which was spread to,若宮大路 and Yasutsuna and Nagamasa KAZANIN&apos;s houses were burned down, the fire was put off at Dengakuzushi.</e>
<cmt>藤次左衛門入道、若宮大路→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 14, 1258, there was a fire at 藤次左衛門入道&apos;s house, which spread to 若宮大路 and Yasutsuna and Nagamasa KAZANIN&apos;s houses, which were burned down until the the fire was put out at Dengakuzushi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 14, 1258, a fire broke out from the residence of Toji no Saemon no Nyudo, and spread over the Wakamiya-oji Street and the residences including the Yasutsuna&apos;s and the Nagamasa KAZANIN&apos;s, which were burned down until the fire was put out at Dengakuzushi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="101">
<j>1258年2月12日（正嘉2年1月1日 (旧暦)）- 北条時頼が宗尊親王に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は西座にて侍す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 12, 1258, Tokiyori HOJO gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna waited at Nishi-za. (a western hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 12, 1258, Tokiyori HOJO gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka while Yasutsuna waited at Nishi-za. (a western hall)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 12, 1258, Tokiyori HOJO held a feast to Imperial Prince Munetaka, and Yasutsuna waited at the western hall.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="102">
<j>1258年2月13日（正嘉2年1月2日 (旧暦)）- 北条重時が宗尊親王に椀飯を沙汰し、泰綱は御調度を献じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 13, 1258, Shigetoki HOJO gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 13, 1258, Shigetoki HOJO gave Oban to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented mukabaki. (harness).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 13, 1258, Shigetoki HOJO held a feast to Imperial Prince Munetaka and Yasutsuna presented a harness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>親王、この後御行始めの儀のため相州禅室御亭に移り、泰綱も布衣としてこれに供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince moved to Zen room of Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi and Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt>相州禅室御亭→読み方、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Prince moved to the Zen room of Soshu gyotei to attend Miyukihajime no gi during which Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the feast, the Imperial Prince moved to the Zen room of the residence of the shogun in Sagami Province to attend the ritual for the first excursion, during which Yasutsuna attended as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="104">
<j>1258年5月30日（正嘉2年4月19日 (旧暦)）－ 勝長寿院で供養があり、宗尊親王が渡る行列に御後布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 30, 1258, there was a memorial service held at Shochoju-in Temple, and Yasutusna accompanied the procession of Imperial Prince Munetaka as 御後布衣.</e>
<cmt>　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 30, 1258, there was a memorial service held at Shochoju-in Temple, and Yasutusna accompanied the procession of Imperial Prince Munetaka as 御後布衣.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 30, 1258, there was a memorial service held at the Shochoju-in Temple, and Yasutsuna attended the procession of Imperial Prince Munetaka as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="105">
<j>1258年9月20日（正嘉2年8月15日 (旧暦)）－ 宗尊親王、鶴岡八幡宮の放生会に御出になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 20, 1258, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 20, 1258, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended Hojoe (the ritual for releasing living beings) of Tsurugaoka Hachimangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 20, 1258, Imperial Prince Munetaka attended the ritual for releasing the living beings at the Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>泰綱、これに御後の布衣として供奉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna accompanied this as 布衣 of 御後.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna attended this as a higher-ranked servant.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="107">
<j>1261年11月24日（弘長元年11月1日 (旧暦)））－ 京都にて逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsuna died on November 24, 1261 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsuna died on November 24, 1261 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsuna died on November 24, 1261 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>齢59歳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was fifty nine years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was fifty nine years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 59.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>下野守　正五位下　藤原朝臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province), Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Fujiwara Ason</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province), Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Fujiwara Ason</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The governor of Shimotsuke Province, Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Fujiwara Ason.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dr jimmy(id:111486), FCTR2(id:213046), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), IwaimBot(id:190695), Yanahan(id:2437), Point136(id:211299), Junger(id:10282), Suisui(id:69), Y mon(id:192749), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>