<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>住友友純</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoito SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoito SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoito SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>住友 友純（すみとも ともいと、元治元年12月21日 (旧暦)（1865年1月18日） - 大正15年（1926年）3月2日）は住友家15代目当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoito SUMITOMO (January 18, 1865 - March 2, 1926) was the fifteenth family head of the Sumitomo family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoito SUMITOMO (January 18, 1865 - March 2, 1926) was the fifteenth family head of the Sumitomo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoito SUMITOMO (January 18, 1865-March 2, 1926) was the fifteenth family head of the Sumitomo family.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>茶人、風流人としても有名で号を春翠と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also famous as a master of tea ceremony and a man of refined taste and his pseudonym was Shunsui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also famous as a master of tea ceremony and a man of refined taste, and was also known as Shunsui.</e>
<cmt>got rid of “pseudonym”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also famous as a master of tea ceremony and a man of refined taste, and was also known as Shunsui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>男爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Baron.</e>
<cmt>made this a sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Baron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>生い立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>background is singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従一位右大臣徳大寺公純の第6子として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the sixth child Kinzumi TOKUDAIJI, who was Juichii (Junior First Rank) udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the sixth child of Kinzumi TOKUDAIJI, who was Juichii (Junior First Rank) udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>“of”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the sixth child of Kinzumi TOKUDAIJI, who was Juichii Udaijin (Junior First Rank, Minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>「従一位右大臣」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は千世浦斐子（末弘氏）で、幼名を隆麿と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Chiyoura Ayako (Suehiro clan)[千世浦斐子 読み不明] and his childhood name was Takamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Chiyoura Ayako (Suehiro clan), and his childhood name was Takamaro.</e>
<cmt>comments belong in the “comment” column</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Chiyoura Ayako (Suehiro clan), and his childhood name was Takamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>兄に従二位権中納言徳大寺実則、正三位右中将西園寺公望、従四位中院通規、弟に母方の末弘家を継いだ末弘威麿らあり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had elder brothers including Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who was Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), Kinmochi SAIONJI, who was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Michinori NAKANOIN, who was Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and a younger brother, Takemaro SUEHIRO, who inherited the Suehiro family which was their mothers parents&apos; home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had elder brothers including Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who was Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), Kinmochi SAIONJI, who was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Michinori NAKANOIN, who was Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and a younger brother, Takemaro SUEHIRO, who inherited the Suehiro family which was their mother&apos;s parents&apos; home.</e>
<cmt>missing apostrophe</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had elder brothers including Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who was Junii Gon Chunagon (Junior Second Rank, Provisional vice-councilor of state), Kinmochi SAIONJI, who was Shosanmi Uchujo (Senior Third Rank, Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Michinori NAKANOIN, who was Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and a younger brother, Takemaro SUEHIRO, who inherited the Suehiro family which was their mother&apos;s parents&apos; home.</e>
<cmt>「従二位権中納言、正三位右中将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>洛北田中村徳大寺家別業清風館で誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Seifukan, which was betsugyo (villa) of the Tokudaiji family in Tanaka Village in Rakuhoku (north of the capital of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Seifukan, which was a villa of the Tokudaiji family in Tanaka Village in Rakuhoku (north of the capital of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>removed parenthetical notation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Seifukan, which was a villa of the Tokudaiji family in Tanaka Village in Rakuhoku (north of the capital of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>慶応4年9月8日、明治と改元、江戸城を東京城と改め、天皇御東行、議定、行政、神祗など七官の制が布かれ、徳大寺実則は三条実美、岩倉具視とともに議定に任じ東京に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 23, 1868, the name of the era was changer to Meiji, Edo-jo Castle was renamed Tokyo-jo Castle, the Emperor moved to Tokyo, the organization of seven departments such as Gijon, Goosey and Jingo, was adopted, and Snakestone TOKUDAIJI was appointed to Gijon together with Anatomy SANJO and Tomomi IWAKURA and moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 23, 1868, the name of the era was changed to Meiji, Edo-jo Castle was renamed Tokyo-jo Castle, the Emperor moved to Tokyo, the organization of seven departments such as Gijon, Gyosei and Jingo, was adopted, and Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI was appointed to Gijon together with Sanetomi SANJO and Tomomi IWAKURA and moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 23, 1868, the name of the era was changed to Meiji, Edo-jo Castle was renamed Tokyo-jo Castle, the Emperor moved to Tokyo, the organization of seven departments such as Gijo, Gyosei and Jingi, was adopted, and Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI was appointed to Gijo together with Sanetomi SANJO and Tomomi IWAKURA and moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>「議定、神祗」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>明治2年7月議定の職が無くなり、三条実美は右大臣、実則は岩倉具視とともに議定より大納言に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1869, the post of Gijon was abolished and Anatomy SANJO was transferred to udaijin (minister of the right) and Sanetsune, together with Tomomi IWAKURA, was transferred from Gijo to Dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1869, the post of Gijon was abolished and Sanetomi SANJO was transferred to udaijin (minister of the right) and Sanetsune, together with Tomomi IWAKURA, was transferred from Gijo to Dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1869, the post of Gijo was abolished and Sanetomi SANJO was transferred to Udaijin (Minister of the right) and Sanetsune, together with Tomomi IWAKURA, was transferred from Gijo to Dainagon (Chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>日付を修正。udaijin を大文字に。「議定、大納言」を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>隆麿の次兄西園寺公望は一時越後府の知事となったが辞し、長崎に遊学、4年正月に政府のフランス留学生として外遊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamaro&apos;s second elder brother, Kinmochi SAIONJI temporarily assumed the position of the Governor of Echigo Prefecture, but he resigned from it and study away from home to Nagasaki and, in January, 1872, traveled abroad as a government sponsored student sent to France.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamaro&apos;s second elder brother, Kinmochi SAIONJI temporarily assumed the position of the Governor of Echigo Prefecture, but he resigned from it and went to study in Nagasaki until, in January, 1872, he traveled abroad as a government sponsored student sent to France.</e>
<cmt>edited for grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamaro&apos;s second elder brother, Kinmochi SAIONJI temporarily assumed the position of the Governor of Echigo Prefecture, but he resigned from it and went to study in Nagasaki until, in February 1871, he traveled abroad as a government sponsored student sent to France.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>隆麿の父公純は東京奠都にも反対で、清風館に幽閉され、茶事に遊ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamaro&apos;s father, Kinzumi, was against Tokyo Tento (transfer of the national capital to Tokyo) and he was confined in Seifukan and enjoyed chaji (the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamaro&apos;s father, Kinzumi, was against Tokyo Tento (transfer of the national capital to Tokyo) and he was confined in Seifukan and enjoyed chaji (the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamaro&apos;s father, Kinzumi, was against Tokyo Tento (transfer of the national capital to Tokyo) and he was confined in Seifukan and enjoyed chaji (the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>実則が家督をつぐことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was decided that Sanetsune take over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was decided that Sanetsune would take over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>added “would”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was decided that Sanetsune would take over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>隆麿は父の膝下にあって、父より日本書紀を学び、詩経、書経をよみ、国語、小学、貞観政要をよむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamaro stayed with this father and learned Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) from his father and read Shijing (Book of Odes) and Shujing (Book of History) as well as Kokugo (Book of History from ancient China), Shogaku (Chinese textbook for beginner published in 1187) and Joganseiyo (a book written about Taiso, the second Emperor of Tang Dynasty in China).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamaro stayed with this father and learned Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) from his father and read Shijing (Book of Odes) and Shujing (Book of History) as well as Kokugo (Book of History from ancient China), Shogaku (Chinese textbook for beginner published in 1187) and Joganseiyo (a book written about Taiso, the second Emperor of Tang Dynasty in China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamaro stayed with this father and learned Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) from his father and read Shijing (Book of Odes) and Shujing (Book of History) as well as Kokugo (Book of History from ancient China), Shogaku (Chinese textbook for beginner published in 1187) and Joganseiyo (a book written about Taiso, the second Emperor of Tang Dynasty in China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>明治16年11月、隆麿20歳の時父公純没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1883, his father Kinzumi died when Takamaro was twenty years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1883, his father Kinzumi died when Takamaro was twenty years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1883, his father Kinzumi died when Takamaro was twenty years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>明治17年東京神田錦町に移り、徳大寺邸に入り、学習院に入学した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884, he moved to Kanda Nishikicho in Tokyo and lived in the mansion of Tokudaiji and entered Gakushuin (school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884, he moved to Kanda Nishikicho in Tokyo and lived in the mansion of Tokudaiji and entered Gakushuin (school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884, he moved to Kanda Nishikicho in Tokyo and lived in the mansion of Tokudaiji and entered Gakushuin (school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明治18年西園寺公望は特命全権公使としてオーストリア及びドイツに駐在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1885, Kinmochi AIONJI resided in Austria and Germany as an envoy extraordinary, and Takamaro became a in 1885</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1885, Kinmochi AIONJI resided in Austria and Germany as an envoy extraordinary.</e>
<cmt>it looked like this sentence had been edited, and a bit that should have been deleted was left in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1885, Kinmochi SAIONJI resided in Austria and Germany as an envoy extraordinary.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>隆麿は明治18年に学習院中学科生となり、20年法律選科に入り、のち五年級にまですすむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamaro became a pupil in Chugakuka (middle school) of Gakushuin in 1885, and entered Horitsusenka (law faculty) in 1887 and later reached the fifth grade.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamaro became a middle school student at Gakushuin in 1885, and entered the law faculty in 1887 and later reached the fifth grade.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand why “chugakuka” was rendered as a transliteration</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamaro became a middle school student at Gakushuin in 1885, and entered Horitsu senka (the law faculty) in 1887 and later reached the fifth grade.</e>
<cmt>「法律選科」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>住友への入家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joining the Sumitomo family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joining the Sumitomo family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joining the Sumitomo family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>住友家では、明治23年5月、別子銅山200年の祝賀式を新居浜で、次いで6月、祭典を別子山であげ、10月には大阪で祝賀会を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sumitomo family held in May 1890 a celebration party in Niihama for two hundredth anniversary of the Besshidozan copper mine and, in June, a festival in Besshiyama and, in October, a celebratory party in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sumitomo family held in May 1890 a celebration party in Niihama for the two hundredth anniversary of the Besshidozan copper mine and, in June, a festival in Besshiyama and, in October, a celebratory party in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>added a definite article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sumitomo family held in May 1890 a celebration party in Niihama for the two hundredth anniversary of the Besshi dozan copper mine and, in June, a festival in Besshiyama and, in October, a celebratory party in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>「別子銅山」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのあと11月23日、住友家１２代吉左衛門友親（48歳）が死去し、ついで同月30日、１３代吉左衛門友忠（19歳）が没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, on November 23, the twelfth family head of the Sumitomo family, Kichizaemon Tomochika (forty-eight years old) died, and, then, on November 30, the thirteenth family head, Kichizaemon Tomotada (nineteen years old) died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, on November 23, the twelfth family head of the Sumitomo family, Kichizaemon Tomochika (48 years old) died, and, then, on November 30, the thirteenth family head, Kichizaemon Tomotada (19 years old) died.</e>
<cmt>The standards sheet specifies that numbers are supposed to be rendered in arabic numerals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, on November 23, the twelfth family head of the Sumitomo family, Kichizaemon Tomochika (48 years old) died, and then, on November 30, the thirteenth family head, Kichizaemon Tomotada (19 years old) died.</e>
<cmt>コンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>とりあえず12月には住友友親の母登久が14世をつぐことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tentatively, in December, it was decided that Tomochika SUMITOMO&apos;s mother, Toku, inherit as the fourteenth family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tentatively, in December, it was decided that Tomochika SUMITOMO&apos;s mother, Toku, would be the fourteenth family head.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tentatively, in December, it was decided that Tomochika SUMITOMO&apos;s mother, Toku, would be the fourteenth family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>明治維新の混乱期を切り抜け、再建に努力してきた住友総理事広瀬宰平は、その甥で補佐の地位にあった伊庭貞剛と協力し、その後継者の選定にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo soriji (leader of Sumitomo group), Saihei HIROSE, who coped with and came through confusion of Meiji Restoration and made effort to reestablish, carried out selection of the successor, in cooperation with his nephew and, at the same time, assistant, Teigo IBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumitomo soriji (leader of Sumitomo group), Saihei HIROSE, who coped with and came through the confusion of the Meiji Restoration and madean effort to reestablish the company, carried out a selection of the successor, in cooperation with his nephew and, at the same time, assistant, Teigo IBA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumitomo soriji (leader of Sumitomo group), Saihei HIROSE, who coped with and came through the confusion of the Meiji Restoration and made an effort to reestablish the company, carried out a selection of the successor, in cooperation with his nephew and, at the same time, assistant, Teigo IBA.</e>
<cmt>スペースを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そして徳大寺家の一子隆麿に着目し、それを迎えることにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He focused on a child of the Tokudaiji family, Takamaro, and decided to receive him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He focused on a child of the Tokudaiji family, Takamaro, and decided to accept him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He focused on a child of the Tokudaiji family, Takamaro, and decided to accept him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>内大臣秘書官日高秩父が侍従長 徳大寺実則の右筆の職にあり、この日高が最初この縁談を見つけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chichibu HIDAKA, who was a secretary to naidaijin (minister of the center), was in the position of Yuhitsu (amanuensis) for Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who was Grand Chamberlain, first found this adoption arrangement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chichibu HIDAKA, a secretary to naidaijin (minister of the center), in the position of Yuhitsu (amanuensis) for Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, Grand Chamberlain, first found this adoption arrangement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chichibu HIDAKA, a secretary to Naidaijin (minister of the center), in the position of Yuhitsu (amanuensis) for Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, Grand Chamberlain, first found this adoption arrangement.</e>
<cmt>naidaijin を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ついで宮内省の侍医 岩佐純が宮内卿であり、侍従長であった徳大寺実則と親しく、媒酌に立つことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, as Jun IWASA, who was a court physician of the Department of the Imperial Household, was close to Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who was Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) and Grand Chamberlain, and acted as a go-betweener.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, as Jun IWASA, a court physician in the Department of the Imperial Household, was close to Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) and Grand Chamberlain, he acted as a go-between.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, as Jun IWASA, jii (a court physician) in Kunaisho (the Imperial Household Ministry), was close to Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) and Grand Chamberlain, he acted as a go-between.</e>
<cmt>「宮内省の侍医」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>伊庭貞剛は、隆麿の人物を調査し、三宅坂山王神社付近の旗亭で、徳大寺実則、西園寺公望、中院通規の三兄と隆麿を招じ、住友家の内情を詳しく説明して入家を請うた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teigo IBA checked Takamaro&apos;s personality and invited Takamaro and his three elder brothers, Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, Kinmochi SAIONJI and Michinori NAKANOIN to a restaurant near Sanno-jinja Shrine at Miyakezaka and explained the inside details of the Sumitomo family and as requested Takamaro&apos;s joining the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teigo IBA checked Takamaro&apos;s personality and invited Takamaro and his three elder brothers, Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, Kinmochi SAIONJI and Michinori NAKANOIN to a restaurant near Sanno-jinja Shrine at Miyakezaka and explained the inside details of the Sumitomo family and requested that Takamaro joini the family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teigo IBA checked Takamaro&apos;s personality and invited Takamaro and his three elder brothers, Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, Kinmochi SAIONJI and Michinori NAKANOIN to a restaurant near Sanno-jinja Shrine at Miyakezaka and explained the inside details of the Sumitomo family and requested that Takamaro join the family.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>かくて明治25年4月18日、隆麿（29歳）は住友登久の養嗣子となり、長女満寿（19歳）に配されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end, on April 18, 1891, Takamaro (twenty-nine years old) was adopted as an adoptive heir of Toku SUMITOMO and tied up with her first daughter, Masu (nineteen years old).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end, on April 18, 1891, Takamaro (twenty-nine years old) was adopted as an heir of Toku SUMITOMO and tied up with her first daughter, Masu (nineteen years old).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end, on April 18, 1892, Takamaro (twenty-nine years old) was adopted as an heir of Toku SUMITOMO and tied up with her first daughter, Masu (nineteen years old).</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この直前に隆麿は学習院法律選科5年生で退学している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before this, Takamaro left Horitsusenka of Gakushuin when he was in the fifth grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before this, Takamaro left Horitsusenka of Gakushuin where he was in the fifth grade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before this, Takamaro left Horitsu senka of Gakushuin where he was in the fifth grade.</e>
<cmt>「法律選科」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>以来大阪鰻谷の住友本邸に住むことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he lived in the principal residence of the Sumitomo family in Unagidani, Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he lived in the principal residence of the Sumitomo family in Unagidani, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he lived in the principal residence of the Sumitomo family in Unagidani, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>第15代住友吉左衛門を襲名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the name, Kichizaemon SUMITOMO as the fifteenth one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded the name, Kichizaemon SUMITOMO as the fifteenth one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded the name, Kichizaemon SUMITOMO as the fifteenth one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>明治26年4月、住友15世をつぎ、隆麿を改め、住友吉左衛門友純と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1892, he succeeded as the fifteenth head of the Sumitomo family and changed his name from Takamaro to Kichizaemon-Tomoito SUMITOMO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1892, he succeeded as the fifteenth head of the Sumitomo family and changed his name from Takamaro to Kichizaemon-Tomoito SUMITOMO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1893, he succeeded as the fifteenth head of the Sumitomo family and changed his name from Takamaro to Kichizaemon-Tomoito SUMITOMO.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>のちに春翠と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he used a pseudonym, Shunsui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he used a pseudonym, Shunsui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was also known as Shunsui.</e>
<cmt>5 と一致するように修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>明治26年4月28日相続の式をあげ、以来家業を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 28, 1892, he held a ceremony of inheritance and he succeeded family businesses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 28, 1892, he held a ceremony of inheritance and he succeeded the family businesses.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 28, 1893, he held a ceremony of inheritance and he succeeded the family businesses.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>別子銅山を経営し、神戸市に銅貿易をなし、また再製茶及び樟脳製造業を行い、滋賀県坂田郡醒ヵ井村において生糸業を営む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He managed Besshidozan copper mine, engaged in trade of copper, operated businesses of producing saiseicha (remanufactured tea) and camphore and carried out raw silk business in Samegai Village, Sakata County, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He managed the Besshidozan copper mine, engaged in trading copper, operated the business of producing saiseicha (remanufactured tea) and camphore and carried out raw silk business in Samegai Village, Sakata County, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He managed the Besshi dozan copper mine, engaged in trading copper, operated the business of producing saiseicha (remanufactured tea) and camphor and carried out raw silk business in Samegai Village, Sakata County, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「別子銅山」を修正。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>広瀬宰平が総理人としてあり、実際の経営に当たるが、友純は別子銅山を巡視し、各社を視察し、庄司炭坑を買収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saihei HIROSE, as the sorinin (general manager) was in charge of actual operation, but Tomoito made a tour of inspection, made on-site inspection of each company and acquired Shoji Tanko coal mine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saihei HIROSE, as the sorinin (general manager) was in charge of actual operations, but Tomoito made an inspection tour, making on-site inspections of each company and acquired the Shoji Tanko coal mine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saihei HIROSE, as the sorinin (general manager) was in charge of actual operations, but Tomoito made an inspection tour to Besshi dozan copper mine, making on-site inspections of each company and acquired the Shoji Tanko coal mine.</e>
<cmt>「別子銅山」をを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、友純入籍の後、困難な事態が発生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After entry of Tomoito in the family register, however, difficult situations occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the entry of Tomoito in the family register, however, difficulties occurred.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the entry of Tomoito in the family register, however, difficulties occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>別子銅山で技師金矢某の事件があり、明治19年金矢と支配人広瀬坦は罰せられ、山根製錬所の監督大島供清も罰せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Besshidozan copper mine, an incident of an engineer, KANAYA so &amp; so, occurred, and, in 1885, KANAYA and Hiroshi HIROSE [広瀬坦 正しい読み不明], who was shihainin (manager), were punished and kantoku (manager) of Yamane Seirensho (smelting works), Tomokiyo OSHIMA [大島供清 正しい読み不明] was also punished..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Besshidozan copper mine, an incident concerning an engineer, KANAYA so &amp; so, occurred, and, in 1885, KANAYA and Hiroshi HIROSE [広瀬坦 正しい読み不明], who was shihainin (manager), were punished and the kantoku (manager) of Yamane Seirensho (smelting works), Tomokiyo OSHIMA [大島供清 正しい読み不明] was also punished..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Besshi dozan copper mine, an incident concerning an engineer, KANAYA so &amp; so, occurred, and in 1886, KANAYA and Hiroshi HIROSE, who was shihainin (manager), were punished and the kantoku (manager) of Yamane Seirensho (smelting works), Tomokiyo OSHIMA was also punished..</e>
<cmt>「別子銅山」を修正。コンマを削除。年号を修正。「大島供清」の読みを確認。「広瀬坦（ヒロシ)?」の読み方不明。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>25年2月、別子支配人広瀬坦は辞し、宰平の甥久保盛明がかわる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1891, Tan HIROSE, who was shihainin of Besshi, resigned and Saihei&apos;s nephew, Moriaki KUBO succeeded the job.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1891, Tan HIROSE, who was shihainin of Besshi, resigned and Saihei&apos;s nephew, Moriaki KUBO succeeded the job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1892, Hiroshi HIROSE, who was shihainin of Besshi, resigned and Saihei&apos;s nephew, Moriaki KUBO succeeded the job.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正。「広瀬坦（ヒロシ)?」を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし大島供清は宰平を失脚させるため、郷里尾道に帰り、5万円の借用を願う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in order to bring down Saihei, Tomokiyo OSHIAMA went back to his hometown, Onomichi, and requested a loan of fifty thousand yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in order to bring down Saihei, Tomokiyo OSHIAMA went back to his hometown, Onomichi, and requested a loan of fifty thousand yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in order to bring down Saihei, Tomokiyo OSHIMA went back to his hometown, Onomichi, and requested a loan of fifty thousand yen.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>忠隈炭坑の買収に宰平の非行ありとし、供清は退身勧告をなし、宰平に拒絶され、ついに宰平の弾劾上申書を家長に提出する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomokiyo made a recommendation for retirement on the ground that Saihei made a wrong act in acquisition of Tadakuma Tanko (coal mine) and, after Saihei refused, he submitted a written report of impeachment to the family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomokiyo recommended retirement on the grounds that Saihei made a mistake in acquiring Tadakuma Tanko (coal mine) and, after Saihei refused, he submitted a written report of impeachment to the family head.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomokiyo recommended retirement on the grounds that Saihei made a mistake in acquiring Tadakuma Tanko (coal mine) and, after Saihei refused, he submitted a written report of impeachment to the family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>伊庭貞剛は単身別子山に上り、人々を鎮めるべく支配人久保盛明にかわる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teigo IBA alone visited and took over for the shihainin, Moriaki KUBO to calm down people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teigo IBA alone visited and took over for the shihainin, Moriaki KUBO to calm the people down.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teigo IBA alone visited and took over for the shihainin, Moriaki KUBO to calm the people down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="43">
<j>さらに新居浜に煙害問題があり、宰平弾劾が重なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there was smoke pollution problem occurred in Niihama and impeachment on Saihei was doubled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there was a smoke pollution problem occurring in Niihama, and the call for impeaching Saihei was doubled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there was a smoke pollution problem occurring in Niihama, and the call for impeaching Saihei was doubled.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>友純は大島供清を須磨別邸に引見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoito made Tomokiyo OSHAMA come to Suma bettei (villa) and met him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoito made Tomokiyo OSHAMA come to Suma bettei (villa) and met him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoito made Tomokiyo OSHIMA come to Suma bettei (villa) and met him.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>供清は宰平退身の上申書をもって友純の前に出たが友純の説論をうけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomokiyo met Tomoito with his report for retirement of Saihei, but he was reproved by Tomoito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomokiyo met Tomoito with his report for the retirement of Saihei, but he was reproved by Tomoito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomokiyo met Tomoito with his report for the retirement of Saihei, but he was reproved by Tomoito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>住友家にとり総理事あるいは最高幹部の人事は重大であり、まして宰平は大黒柱的存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the Sumitomo family, personnel affairs for the soriji and other top management was very important and, in addition, Saihei was an existence like a central pillar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Sumitomo family, personnel affairs for the soriji and other top management was very important and, in addition, Saihei was like a central pillar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Sumitomo family, personnel affairs for the soriji and other top management was very important and, in addition, Saihei was like a central pillar.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし友純は西園寺公望の力を借りて宰平の辞表を受け取り、同時に大島をも罷免して、喧嘩両成敗の形をもって取り収める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tomoito settled the situation in the form of &quot;Where there is a quarrel, both parties are to be punished,&quot; by receiving the letter of resignation from Saihei thanks to help by Kinmochi SAIONJI and dismissing OSHIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tomoito settled the situation in the form of &quot;Where there is a quarrel, both parties are to be punished,&quot; by receiving the letter of resignation from Saihei thanks to help of Kinmochi SAIONJI and dismissing OSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tomoito settled the situation in the form of kenka ryoseibai (in a quarrel, both parties are to blame), by receiving the letter of resignation from Saihei thanks to help of Kinmochi SAIONJI and dismissing OSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>「喧嘩両成敗」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>あとは、宰平の甥伊庭貞剛につがすということで、おそらく宰平を納得させたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he convinced Saihei by making Saihei&apos;s nephew, Teigo IBA, succeed Saihei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that he convinced Saihei by making Saihei&apos;s nephew, Teigo IBA, succeed Saihei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that he convinced Saihei by making Saihei&apos;s nephew, Teigo IBA, succeed Saihei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="49">
<j>銀行の開業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opening a bank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opening a bank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opening a bank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>住友家では明治28年には本店を富島町より中之島5丁目に移し、同所に住友銀行を開業し、神戸支店、川口、兵庫出張所をおいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1894, the Sumitomo family moved its honten (principal place of business) from Tomishmacho to Nakanoshima 5-chome and opened Sumitomo Bank at the same place and deployed Kobe Branch, Kawaguchi Branch and Hyogo Office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1894, the Sumitomo family moved its honten (principal place of business) from Tomishmacho to Nakanoshima 5-chome and opened Sumitomo Bank at the same place and deployed the Kobe Branch, Kawaguchi Branch and Hyogo Office.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1895, the Sumitomo family moved its honten (principal place of business) from Tomishimacho to Nakanoshima 5-chome and opened Sumitomo Bank at the same place and deployed the Kobe Branch, Kawaguchi and Hyogo Offices.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正。スペルを訂正。「川口、兵庫出張所」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>重任局という重役室は中之島営業場の奥の一隅にあ.り、卓を囲んだ重役の中に友純は硝子をへだてて営業場を見渡す位置に占めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An executive suite called Juninkyoku was located at a corner in the back of Nakanoshima Eigyosho (business office).and, among executives surrounding a table, Tomoito occupied the position to look over the operation room through a glass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An executive suite called Juninkyoku was located at a corner in the rear of the Nakanoshima Eigyosho (business office).and, among executives surrounding the table, Tomoito occupied the position to look over the operation room through a glass window.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An executive suite called Juninkyoku was located at a corner in the rear of the Nakanoshima Eigyojo (business office) and, among executives surrounding the table, Tomoito occupied the position to look over the operation room through a glass window.</e>
<cmt>「営業場」を修正。ピリオドを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>銀行の業績は住友に対する社会の信用のもっとも直接の顕現になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The performance of the bank was most direct manifestation of the trust to Sumitomo by the society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The performance of the bank was the most direct manifestation of the trust to Sumitomo by society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The performance of the bank was the most direct manifestation of the trust to Sumitomo by society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>また銀行は地元を本拠とする新規の業であったので、友純の関心は銀行に特に深かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, since the banking business was a new business operated on local basis, Tomoito had especially deep interest in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, since the banking business was a new business operated on local basis, Tomoito had an especially deep interest in it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, since the banking business was a new business operated on local basis, Tomoito had an especially deep interest in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>銀行の支店長会議も鰻谷の洋館で開かれるのが常例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was usual that the meeting of branch mangers of the bank was held in the yokan (Western-style building) in Unagidani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was usual that the meeting of branch mangers of the bank was held in the yokan (Western-style building) in Unagidani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was usual that the meeting of branch mangers of the bank was held in the yokan (Western-style building) in Unagidani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>友純は大阪の実業界の地位を高めるため率先して努力していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoito endeavored taking the lead to heighten the position of the business circle of Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoito endeavored to take the lead to heighten the position of business circles in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoito endeavored to take the lead to heighten the position of business circles in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="56">
<j>明治29年には家法の改正をなし、30年には理事伊庭貞剛を総理事心得とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1895, he amended the family code and, in 1896, promoted Teigo IBA, who had been riji (director), to soriji kokoroe (acting general director).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1895, he amended the family code and, in 1896, promoted Teigo IBA, who had been riji (director), to soriji kokoroe (acting general director).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, he amended the family code and, in 1897, promoted Teigo IBA, who had been riji (director), to soriji kokoroe (acting general director).</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>33年総理事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1899, he assumed the position of soriji (general director).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1899, he assumed the position of soriji (general director).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1900, he assumed the position of soriji (general director).</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>従来の家長、総理人、支配人、副支配人、理事で構成していた重任局も廃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also abolished Juninkyoku which consisted of the family head, sorinin, sihainin, fuku-shihainin (acting manager) and riji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also abolished Juninkyoku which consisted of the family head, sorinin, sihainin, fuku-shihainin (acting manager) and riji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also abolished Juninkyoku which consisted of the family head, sorinin, sihainin, fuku-shihainin (acting manager) and riji.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>総理人を総理事としたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed sorinin to soriji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed sorinin to soriji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed sorinin to soriji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="60">
<j>欧米漫遊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Travel to Europe and America</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Travel to Europe and America</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Travel to Europe and America</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>明治30年4月、友純は欧米漫遊の途につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1896, Tomoito departed for his travel to Europe and America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1896, Tomoito departed for his travel to Europe and America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1897, Tomoito departed for his travel to Europe and America.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>サンフランシスコ、シカゴ、ニューヨークより5月パリにつき、ロンドンに向かい、欧州諸国をめぐって10月3日マルセイユ出帆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through San Francisco, Chicago and New York, he arrived in Paris in May and headed to London and, after visiting European countries his ship departed Marseille on October 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through San Francisco, Chicago, and New York, he arrived in Paris in May and headed to London and, after visiting the European countries his ship departed Marseille on October 3.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through San Francisco, Chicago, and New York, he arrived in Paris in May and headed to London and, after visiting the European countries his ship departed Marseille on October 3.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>パリでは西園寺公望の病気を見舞っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Paris, he visited Kinmochi SAIONJI to inquire after his conditionl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Paris, he visited Kinmochi SAIONJI to inquire after his conditionl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Paris, he visited Kinmochi SAIONJI to inquire after his condition.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>各地で美術館、博物館を見、欧米の富豪が公共施設に力をつくし、慈善事業に私財を出すのに感銘をうける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He visited many museums of art and other museums and he was impressed to know that rich people in Europe and America make every effort for public facilities and expend private funds philanthropic works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He visited many museums of art and other museums and he was impressed to know that rich people in Europe and America made every effort to promote public facilities and expend private funds for philanthropic work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He visited many museums of art and other museums and he was impressed to know that rich people in Europe and America made every effort to promote public facilities and expend private funds for philanthropic work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>随行は松村豊吉、鈴木馬左也、吉田真一であり、218日間の旅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attendants were Toyokichi MATSUMURA, Masaya SUZUKI and Shinichi YOSHIDA and it was a trip for 218 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attendants were Toyokichi MATSUMURA, Masaya SUZUKI and Shinichi YOSHIDA and it was a trip for 218 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attendants were Toyokichi MATSUMURA, Masaya SUZUKI and Shinichi YOSHIDA and it was a trip for 218 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>とくにシカゴ美術館で、この建物の保存にアメリカの富豪マーシャル・フィールドが100万ドルを寄付したことを知り、深く心に期すところがあり、自ら社会的使命の１つとして公共用の施設を建設したいとの希望をもつに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I particular, in the Art institute of Chicago, he learned that an American rich man, Marshall FIELD donated for conservation of this building and he made up his mind and reached to wish that, as his social mission, to build social facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I particular, in the Art institute of Chicago, he learned that an American rich man, Marshall FIELD donated to conserve this building and he made up his mind that, his mission was to build social facilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, in the Art institute of Chicago, he learned that an American rich man, Marshall FIELD donated one million dollars to conserve this building and he made up his mind that, his mission was to build social facilities.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正。「100万ドル」を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>帰朝後は生活様式も洋風にし、社交術も身につけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After coming back to Japan, he Westernized his living style and learned the art of social intercourse.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After coming back to Japan, he Westernized his living style and learned the art of social intercourse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After coming back to Japan, he westernized his living style and learned the art of social intercourse.</e>
<cmt>Westernized を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また住友の有能な職員を外国に学ばせることにしたのも友純の意向を反映している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was reflection of Tomoito&apos;s intention that capable employees of Sumitomo were sent abroad to study.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was reflection of Tomoito&apos;s intention that capable employees of Sumitomo were sent abroad to study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it was reflection of Tomoito&apos;s intention that capable employees of Sumitomo were sent abroad to study.</e>
<cmt>「また」を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="69">
<j>友純の晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoito&apos;s late years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoito&apos;s late years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoito&apos;s late years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>明治38年から別子、四阪島を巡察した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1904, he made tours of inspection to Besshi and Shisakajima Islands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1904, he made tours of inspection to Besshi and Shisakajima Islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1905, he made tours of inspection to Besshi and Shisaka jima Islands.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正。「四阪島」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>39年1月、実兄の西園寺公望は内閣総理大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1905, his real elder brother, Kinmochi SAIONJI became the prime minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1905, his real elder brother, Kinmochi SAIONJI became the prime minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1906, his real elder brother, Kinmochi SAIONJI became the prime minister.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>同年4月、勲二等瑞宝章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1905, he was conferred the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold and Silver Star.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1905, he was conferred the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold and Silver Star.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1906, he was conferred the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold and Silver Star.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>東京麻布区鳥居坂に別邸を設ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He acquired a villa in Toriizaka, Azabu Ward, Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He acquired a villa in Toriizaka, Azabu Ward, Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He acquired a villa in Toriizaka, Azabu Ward, Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>40年5月、別子銅山巡察。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1906, he made a tour of inspection to Besshidozan copper mine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1906, he made a tour of inspection to the Besshidozan copper mine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1907, he made a tour of inspection to the Besshi dozan copper mine.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正。「別子銅山」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>41年11月、本店及び銀行本店を大阪市東区北浜の新館に移し、42年1月、住友本店を住友総本店とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1907, honten (head office) and ginko honten (head office of the bank) were moved to a new building in Kitahama, Higashi Ward, Osaka City and, in January 1908, Sumitomo honten was changed into Sumitomo sohonten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1907, honten (head office) and ginko honten (head office of the bank) were moved to a new building in Kitahama, Higashi Ward, Osaka City and, in January 1908, Sumitomo honten was changed into Sumitomo sohonten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1908, honten (head office) and ginko honten (head office of the bank) were moved to a new building in Kitahama, Higashi Ward, Osaka City and, in January 1909, Sumitomo honten was changed into Sumitomo sohonten.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>44年6月には伸銅場中之島分工場を廃し、安治川本工場に合併する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1910, Nakanoshima Bunkojo of Shindojo was abolished and merged into Ajigawa Honkojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1910, Nakanoshima Bunkojo of Shindojo was abolished and merged into Ajigawa Honkojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1911, Nakanoshima Bunkojo of Shindojo was abolished and merged into Ajigawa Honkojo.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>明治44年8月25日、男爵を授けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 25, 1910, he was raised to a baron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 25, 1910, he was raised to a baron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 25, 1911, he was raised to a baron.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>44年8月、住友電線製造業を分離し、住友電線製造所を設ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1910, Sumitomo Densen Seizogyo (Sumitomo cable manufacturing business) was separated and Sumitomo Densen Seizosho (Sumitomo cable manufacturing company) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1910, Sumitomo Densen Seizogyo (Sumitomo cable manufacturing business) was separated and Sumitomo Densen Seizosho (Sumitomo cable manufacturing company) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1911, Sumitomo Densen Seizogyo (Sumitomo cable manufacturing business) was separated and Sumitomo Densen Seizosho (Sumitomo cable manufacturing company) was established.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>大正元年2月、銀行の組織を1500万円の株式会社にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1912, the organization of the bank was transformed into a joint-stock company with the capital of fifteen million yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1912, the organization of the bank was transformed into a joint-stock company with a capital of fifteen million yen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1912, the organization of the bank was transformed into a joint-stock company with a capital of fifteen million yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>同年5月、別子銅山、四阪島を巡視。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1912, he made a tour of inspection to Besshidozan copper mine and Shisakajima Islands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1912, he made a tour of inspection to Besshidozan copper mine and Shisakajima Islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1912, he made a tour of inspection to Besshi dozan copper mine and Shisaka jima Islands.</e>
<cmt>「別子銅山、四阪島」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>同年12月、大阪商工会顧問。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1912, advisor of Osaka Shokokai (chamber of commerce and industry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1912, advisor of Osaka Shokokai (chamber of commerce and industry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1912, he was appointed as an advisor of Osaka Shokokai (chamber of commerce and industry).</e>
<cmt>コンマを削除。文章のスタイルに修正。ピリオドを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>大正2年肥料製造所を愛媛県新居浜町に設ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1913, Hiryo Seizosho (fertilizer manufacturing company) was established in Niihama Town, Ehime Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1913, Hiryo Seizosho (fertilizer manufacturing company) was established in Niihama Town, Ehime Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1913, Hiryo Seizosho (fertilizer manufacturing company) was established in Niihama Town, Ehime Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>May を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>大正3年1月、広瀬宰平没（87歳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January1914, Saihei HIROSE died (eighty-seven years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January1914, Saihei HIROSE died (eighty-seven years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1914, Saihei HIROSE died (eighty-seven years old).</e>
<cmt>スペースを挿入。ピリオドを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>大正4年、住友私立職工養成所を設立し、友純はその理事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1915, Sumitomo Shiritsu Shokko Yoseisho (Sumitomo private mechanics education center) and Tomoito became its riji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1915, Sumitomo Shiritsu Shokko Yoseisho (Sumitomo private mechanics education center) and Tomoito became its riji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1915, Sumitomo Shiritsu Shokko Yoseisho (Sumitomo private mechanics education center) and Tomoito became its riji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>大正5年7月、分家住友忠輝住吉村 (兵庫県)に移居。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1916, Tadateru SUMITOMO of cadet family moved to Sumiyoshi Village (Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1916, Tadateru SUMITOMO of cadet family moved to Sumiyoshi Village (Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1916, Tadateru SUMITOMO of branch family moved to Sumiyoshi Village (Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「分家」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>大正5年10月、住友寛一相続人廃除。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1916, Kanichi SUMITOMO was excluded from heirs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1916, Kanichi SUMITOMO was excluded from the heirs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1916, Kanichi SUMITOMO was excluded from the heirs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>分家届出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A cadet family was registered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A cadet family was registered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch family was registered.</e>
<cmt>「分家」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>同年11月上海に住友洋行をおき、住友製品の販売を開始し、6年7月には天津にもおく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1916, Sumitomo Yoko was established in Shanghai and commenced sales of Sumitomo products and, in July 1917, he visited Tianjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1916, Sumitomo Yoko was established in Shanghai and commenced sales of Sumitomo products and, in July 191, he visited Tianjin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1916, Sumitomo Yoko was established in Shanghai and commenced sales of Sumitomo products and, in July 1917, another Sumitomo Yoko was established in Tianjin.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正。「天津にもおく」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>6年7月銀行資本金を3000万円に増額し、株式の一部を公開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1917, the capital of the bank was increased to thirty million yen and listed a part of stocks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1917, the capital of the bank was increased to thirty million yen and listed a part of it&apos;s stocks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1917, the capital of the bank was increased to thirty million yen and listed a part of it&apos;s stocks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>大正7年12月、東北大学鉄鋼研究所創立費ならびに事業費寄付を願出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1918, he made an application of donation of expenses for establishment and operation of the Institute for Steels Research, Tohoku University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1918, he made an application to donate expenses for establishment and operation of the Institute for Steel Research, Tohoku University.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1918, he made an application to donate expenses for establishment and operation of the Institute for Steel Research, Tohoku University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>8年2月、理化学研究所監事及び評議員に委嘱される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1919, he was appointed to kanji (supervisor) and hyogiin (trustee) of the Rikagaku Kenkyusho (RIKEN).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1919, he was appointed to kanji (supervisor) and hyogiin (trustee) of the Rikagaku Kenkyusho (RIKEN).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1919, he was appointed to kanji (supervisor) and hyogiin (trustee) of the Rikagaku Kenkyusho (RIKEN).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>8年、岸本製鉄所を買収し住友伸銅所尼崎工場とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, He acquired Kishimoto Seitetsusho and made it into Amagasaki plant of Sumitomo Shindosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, He acquired Kishimoto Seitetsusho and made it into the Amagasaki plant of Sumitomo Shindosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, He acquired Kishimoto Seitetsusho and made it into the Amagasaki plant of Sumitomo Shindosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>8年12月、大阪北港株式会社を創立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1919, he established Osaka Kitako Kabushikikaisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1919, he established Osaka Kitako Kabushikikaisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, 1919, he established Osaka Kitako Kabushiki kaisha.</e>
<cmt>「株式会社」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>大正9年には住友鋳鋼所を株式会社住友製鋼所とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1920, he changed Sumitomo Chukosho changed into Kabushikikaisha Sumitomo Seikosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1920, he changed Sumitomo Chukosho into Kabushikikaisha Sumitomo Seikosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1920, he changed Sumitomo Chukosho into Kabushiki kaisha Sumitomo Seikosho.</e>
<cmt>「株式会社」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>大正10年2月には住友合資会社（資本金1億5000万円）を設立し、総本店の事業を継承して、その社長となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1921, he established Sumitomo Goshikaisha (capital: 150 million yen) to inherit business of Sohonten and he assumed the position of the president.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1921, he established Sumitomo Goshikaisha (capital: 150 million yen) to inherit the business of Sohonten and he assumed the position of the president.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1921, he established Sumitomo Goshi kaisha (capital: 150 million yen) to inherit the business of Sohonten and he assumed the position of the president.</e>
<cmt>「合資会社」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>同年5月には私立大阪住友病院を設立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1921, he established Shiritu Osaka Sumitomo Byoin (Sumitomo Osaka privately established hospital).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1921, he established the Shiritu Osaka Sumitomo Byoin (Sumitomo Osaka privately established hospital).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1921, he established the Shiritu Osaka Sumitomo Byoin (Sumitomo Osaka privately established hospital).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>大正11年には府立大阪図書館を増築完成し、大阪府に寄贈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I 1922, expansion of Furitsu Osaka Toshokan (Osaka library established by Osaka Prefecture) was completed and it was donated to Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1922, expansion of Furitsu Osaka Toshokan (Osaka library established by Osaka Prefecture) was completed and it was donated to Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1922, expansion of Furitsu Osaka Toshokan (Osaka library established by Osaka Prefecture) was completed and it was donated to Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>大正12年8月、株式会社住友ビルディング設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1923, he established Kabushikikaisha Sumitomo Building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1923, he established the Kabushikikaisha Sumitomo Building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1923, he established the Kabushiki kaisha Sumitomo Building.</e>
<cmt>「株式会社」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>同月倉庫を資本金1500万円の株式会社に組織変更する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same month, he reorganized Soko into a joint-stock company with the capital of fifteen million yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same month, he reorganized Soko into a joint-stock company with the capital of fifteen million yen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same month, he reorganized Soko into a joint-stock company with the capital of fifteen million yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>大正14年、本邸を兵庫県武庫郡住吉村 (兵庫県)に移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1925, he moved the principle residence of the family to Sumiyoshi Village, Muko County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1925, he moved the principle residence of the family to Sumiyoshi Village, Muko County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1925, he moved the principle residence of the family to Sumiyoshi Village, Muko County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>同年6月、肥料製造所を資本金300万円の株式会社にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1925, he changed Hiryo Seizosho into a joint-stock company with the capital of three million yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1925, he changed Hiryo Seizosho into a joint-stock company with the capital of three million yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1925, he changed Hiryo Seizosho into a joint-stock company with the capital of three million yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>同年7月、資本金2000万円の住友信託株式会社を設立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1925, he established Sumitomo Trust &amp; Banking Co., Ltd. with the capital of twenty million yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1925, he established Sumitomo Trust &amp; Banking Co., Ltd. with the capital of twenty million yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1925, he established the Sumitomo Trust and Banking Co., Ltd. with the capital of twenty million yen.</e>
<cmt>「住友信託株式会社」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>同年10月、総理事中田錦吉退職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1925, Kinkichi NAKATA, who was soriji, resigned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1925, Kinkichi NAKATA, who was soriji, resigned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1925, Kinkichi NAKATA, who was soriji, resigned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>理事湯川寛吉が総理事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kankichi YUKAWA, who was riji, assumed the position of soriji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kankichi YUKAWA, who was riji, assumed the position of soriji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kankichi YUKAWA, who was riji, assumed the position of soriji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>同年11月から友純病にふす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From November 1925, Tomoito fell ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From November 1925, Tomoito fell ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From November 1925, Tomoito fell ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>昭和元年3月2日逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 2, 1926, he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 2, 1926, he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 2, 1926, he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>享年63歳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was sixty-three years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was sixty-three years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was sixty-three years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>昭和元年3月9日、住友厚が吉左衛門を襲名し、5月1日、吉左衛門が襲爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 9, 1926, Atsushi SUMITOMO succeeded the name of Kichiｚaemon and， on May 1, Kichizaemon was ennobled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 9, 1926, Atsushi SUMITOMO succeeded the name of Kichiｚaemon and， on May 1, Kichizaemon was ennobled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 9, 1926, Atsushi SUMITOMO succeeded the name of Kichizaemon and, on May 1, Kichizaemon was ennobled.</e>
<cmt>書式を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lupinoid(id:68), Point136(id:211299), U3002(id:66126), 伊(id:146699), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>