<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺実維</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanefusa TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanefusa TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanefusa TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 実維（とくだいじ さねふさ、寛永13年3月1日 (旧暦)（1636年4月6日） - 天和 (日本)2年9月11日 (旧暦)（1682年10月11日））は、江戸時代前期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanefusa TOKUDAIJI (April 6, 1636-October 11, 1682) was a high-rank Court noble in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanefusa TOKUDAIJI (April 6, 1636-October 11, 1682) was a high-rank Court noble in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanefusa TOKUDAIJI (April 6, 1636-October 11, 1682) was a high-rank Court noble in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明正天皇（109代）・後光明天皇（110代）・後西天皇（111代）・霊元天皇（112代）の四帝にわたって仕え、官位は正二位内大臣まで進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Emperor Meisho, Emperor Gokomyo, Emperor Gosai, and Emperor Reigen in a row, and his official court rank culminated at Shonii Naidaijin (Senior Second Rank, Inner Minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Emperor Meisho (109th), Emperor Gokomyo (110th), Emperor Gosai (111th), and Emperor Reigen (112th) in a row, and his official court rank culminated at Shonii Naidaijin (Senior Second Rank, Inner Minister).</e>
<cmt>（109代）（110代）（111代）（112代）を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Emperor Meisho (109th), Emperor Gokomyo (110th), Emperor Gosai (111th), and Emperor Reigen (112th) in a row, and his official court rank culminated at Shonii Naidaijin (Senior Second Rank, Inner Minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は左大臣徳大寺公信。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Kinnobu TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Kinnobu TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Kinnobu TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は長州藩主毛利秀就の養女（岩国藩主吉川広正の娘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a adopted daughter of Hidenari MORI, lord of the Choshu Domain (a daughter of Hiromasa KIKKAWA, lord of the Iwakuni Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a adopted daughter of Hidenari MORI, the lord of the Choshu Domain (a daughter of Hiromasa KIKKAWA, the lord of the Iwakuni Domain).</e>
<cmt>「the」を追記。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a adopted daughter of Hidenari MORI, the lord of the Choshu Domain (a daughter of Hiromasa KIKKAWA, the lord of the Iwakuni Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正室は権大納言藪嗣孝の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife a daughter of Dainagon (a chief councilor of state) Tsugutaka YABU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a daughter of Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state) Tsugutaka YABU.</e>
<cmt>「was」を追記。原文の「大納言」は、ウィキでは「権大納言」になっています。「大納言」はリンク先のようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state) Tsugutaka YABU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>子に徳大寺公逸・徳大寺公観、養子に内大臣徳大寺公全がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included Kinhashi TOKUDAIJI and Kinshime TOKUDAIJI, and his adopted son included Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) Kintomo TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>徳大寺公逸, 徳大寺公観　 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Kinhashi TOKUDAIJI and Kinshime TOKUDAIJI, and his adopted son included Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) Kintomo TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Kinhashi TOKUDAIJI and Kinshime TOKUDAIJI, and his adopted son included Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) Kintomo TOKUDAIJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>寛永14年（1637年）に叙爵して以降清華家当主として早いスピードで累進し、侍従・左近衛少将・左近衛中将を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1637, when he was created an official court rank, Sanefusa was on express track of promotion as the head of seigake (the second highest family status for court nobles) and held many positions, including jiju (a chamberlain), Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1637, when he was conferred an official court rank, Sanefusa was on the express track of promotion as the head of seigake (the second highest family status for court nobles) and held many positions, including jiju (a chamberlain), Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>created を使った＆見たことがないので、「conferred」に変更しました。「express」の前に「the」を入れました。ウィキで確認すると、「近衛府・近衛府」はリンク先で、「左近衛少将・左近衛中将」が正しいようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1637, when he was conferred an official court rank, Sanefusa was on the express track of promotion as the head of seigake (the second highest family status for court nobles) and held many positions, including jiju (a chamberlain), Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>承応2年（1653年）には従三位となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1653, he was created Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and joined the realm of kugyo (high-rank Court nobles).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1653, he was conferred Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and joined the realm of kugyo (high-rank Court nobles).</e>
<cmt>created を使った＆見たことがないので、「conferred」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1653, he was conferred Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and joined the realm of kugyo (high-rank Court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>権中納言を経て、寛文元年（1661年）に権大納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After working as Chunagon (Middle Councillor), he was appointed as Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After working as Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state), he was appointed as Gon Dainagon in 1661.</e>
<cmt>「1661年」を追記。原文にある「中納言」「大納言」は、ウィキでは「権中納言」「権大納言」となっており、「中納言」「大納言」はリンク先のようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After working as Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), he was appointed as Gon Dainagon in 1661.</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state)→Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寛文9年（1669年）には右近衛大将・右馬寮御監となったが、寛文10年（1670年）には辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to Konoefu Meryo (Bureau of Horses at the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards) in 1669, but he stepped down in 1670.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to Konoefu Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Umaryo gogen (Inspector of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses) in 1669, but he stepped down in 1670.</e>
<cmt>原文の「近衛府・馬寮」は、ウィキでは「右近衛大将・右馬寮御監」と記載されており、「近衛府・馬寮」はリンク先のようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to Konoefu Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Umaryo gogen (Inspector of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses) in 1669, but he stepped down in 1670.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>寛文11年（1671年）に内大臣に就任するも翌年に辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed the post of Naidaijin in 1671 but resigned in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He assumed the post of Naidaijin in 1671 but resigned in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumed the post of Naidaijin in 1671 but resigned in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>