<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原斉信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 斉信（ふじわら の ただのぶ、康保4年（967年） - 長元8年3月23日 (旧暦)（1035年5月3日））は、平安時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu (967 to May 9, 1035) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) who lived during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>長元8年3月23日は西暦1035年5月9日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu (967 to May 9, 1035) was a Kugyo (top court official) who lived during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu (967 to May 9, 1035) was a Kugyo (top court official) who lived during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>太政大臣藤原為光の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu, who held the title of Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu, who held the title of Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu, who held the title of Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正二位、権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held the titles of Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the title of Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the title of Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Major Counselor→chief councilor of state</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>政治能力に欠ける同母兄の藤原誠信とは反対に、若年時より切れ者の能吏として頭角を現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike his elder brother-uterine, FUJIWARA no Sanenobu, who lacked the competence as a politician, he distinguished himself as a competent politician since he was young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike his elder brother-uterine, FUJIWARA no Sanenobu, who lacked competence as a politician, he distinguished himself as a competent politician since he was young.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike his elder brother-uterine, FUJIWARA no Sanenobu, who lacked competence as a politician, he distinguished himself as a competent politician since he was young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>蔵人頭や、藤原道長の娘の中宮藤原彰子の中宮大夫を勤める等、道長からの信任も篤かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through his careers as a Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) and a Chugu daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) serving for the Empress FUJIWARA no Shoshi who was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, he gained the deep confidence of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through his careers as a Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) and a Chugu daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) serving Empress FUJIWARA no Shoshi who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, he gained the deep confidence of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through his careers as a Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) and a Chugu daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) serving Empress FUJIWARA no Shoshi who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, he gained the deep confidence of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>長保3年（1001年）には道長の強い薦めを受けて、誠信を差し置いて権中納言に就任する（この際、誠信はこれを恨んで憤死したと伝わる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Backed by the strong recommendation of Michinaga, he defeated Sanenobu and assumed the position of Gon Dainagon (the legend has it that Sanenobu died of indignation after the resentful defeat).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Backed by the strong recommendation of Michinaga, he defeated Sanenobu and assumed the position of Gon Dainagon (the legend has it that Sanenobu died of indignation after a resentful defeat).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Backed by the strong recommendation of Michinaga, he defeated Sanenobu and assumed the position of Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) (the legend has it that Sanenobu died of indignation after a resentful defeat).</e>
<cmt>Dainagon→Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>道長の腹心の一人として一条天皇の治世を支え、藤原公任、藤原行成、源俊賢とともに『一条朝の四納言』と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a trustworthy assistant of Michinaga who supported the reign of the Emperor Ichijo, and regarded as one of the &quot;Four superior court nobles in the court of Emperor Ichijo&quot; along with FUJIWARA no Kinto, FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and MINAMOTO no Toshikata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a trustworthy assistant of Michinaga who supported the reign of Emperor Ichijo, and was regarded as one of the &quot;Four superior court nobles in the court of Emperor Ichijo&quot; along with FUJIWARA no Kinto, FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and MINAMOTO no Toshikata.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a trustworthy assistant of Michinaga who supported the reign of Emperor Ichijo, and was regarded as one of the &quot;Four superior court nobles in the court of Emperor Ichijo&quot; along with FUJIWARA no Kinto, FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and MINAMOTO no Toshikata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>和歌や漢詩、朗詠、管絃にも通じ、当代随一の文化人としての名声も高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has a mastery of Chinese poetry, Roei recitation, Kangen music, and renowned as the greatest culturati of the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had mastered Chinese poetry, Roei recitation, Kangen music, and was renowned as the most cultured of the day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had mastered Chinese poetry, Roei recitation, Kangen music, and was renowned as the greatest cultural figures of the day.</e>
<cmt>most cultured をgreatest cultural figuresに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>清少納言との交流でも知られ、枕草子の中にもたびたび登場し、その艶やかな振る舞いを描写されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known for his exchanges with Sei Shonagon and frequently appears in &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) which depicts his lovesome episodes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known for his exchanges with Sei Shonagon and frequently appeared in &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) which depicted his romantic episodes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known for his exchanges with Sei Shonagon and frequently appeared in &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) which depicted his romantic episodes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 中右(id:50196), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Law soma(id:45202), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>