<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>岩倉恒具</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetomo IWAKURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetomo IWAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetomo IWAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>岩倉 恒具（いわくら つねとも、元禄14年7月24日 (旧暦)（1701年8月27日） - 宝暦10年7月29日 (旧暦)（1760年9月8日））は、江戸時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetomo IWAKURA (August 27, 1701 - September 8, 1760) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) in the middle period of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetomo IWAKURA (August 27, 1701 - September 8, 1760) was a Kugyo (top court official) during the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetomo IWAKURA (August 27, 1701 - September 8, 1760) was a Kugyo (top court official) during the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に中御門天皇（114代）から桃園天皇（116代）の3代にわたって朝廷に仕え、官位は従二位権中納言まで昇った（薨去後に正二位追贈）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He mainly served to Imperial Court of 3 generations of Emperors, which are from Emperor Nakamikado (114th) through Emperor Momozono (116th), and his official court rank was raised to Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) (his rank was raised to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) after his death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He mainly served the Imperial Court for three generations of Emperors, from Emperor Nakamikado (114th) through Emperor Momozono (116th), and his official court rank was raised to Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) (his rank was raised to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) after his death).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He mainly served the Imperial Court for three generations of Emperors, from Emperor Nakamikado (114th) through Emperor Momozono (116th), and his official court rank was raised to Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) (his rank was raised to Shonii [Senior Second Rank] after his death).</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は岩倉乗具。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Noritomo IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Noritomo IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Noritomo IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>弟に千種有敬（千種家養子）・植松賞雅（植松家養子）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Arinori CHIGUSA (adopted child of the Chigusa family) and Takamasa UEMATSU (adopted child of the Uematsu family) as his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had Arinori CHIGUSA (the adopted child of the Chigusa family) and Takamasa UEMATSU (the adopted child of the Uematsu family) as his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had Arinori CHIGUSA (the adopted child of the Chigusa family) and Takamasa UEMATSU (the adopted child of the Uematsu family) as his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>養子に岩倉尚具がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Naotomo IWAKURA as his adopted child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had Naotomo IWAKURA as his adopted child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had Naotomo IWAKURA as his adopted child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>宝永元年（1704年）に従五位下に叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1704, he was conferred a peerage as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1704, he was conferred peerage as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1704, he was conferred peerage as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>初め具備と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was first named Tomonari (具備).</e>
<cmt>具備→読み不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was first named Tomonari (具備).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was first named Tomonari (具備).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正徳 (日本)4年（1714年）に元服とともに従五位上侍従となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he made genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) in 1714, he was also conferred as Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) jiju (a chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he made genpuku (celebrated coming of age) in 1714, he was also conferred Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) jiju (a chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he celebrated his coming-of-age ceremony in 1714, he was also conferred Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade), jiju (a chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>元服　英語の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>享保3年（1718年）に正五位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1718, he was conferred as Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1718, he was conferred Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1718, he was conferred Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>享保4年（1719年）に恒具と改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1719, he changed his name to Tsunetomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1719, he changed his name to Tsunetomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1719, he changed his name to Tsunetomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後も累進し、左近衛少将と右近衛中将を経て、享保17年（1732年）に従三位に達して公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made progress after that, also, and after being appointed as Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he reached Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and became to be counted as one of Kugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made progress after that, also, and after being appointed Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he reached Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and became counted as one of the Kugyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made progress after that, also, and after being appointed Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he reached Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1732 and became counted as one of the Kugyo.</e>
<cmt>1732を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、正三位・参議・左近衛中将を経て宝暦3年（1753年）に従二位権中納言となったが、宝暦8年（1758年）には宝暦事件に連座。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, after being conferred as Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and being appointed as Sangi (Councillor) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was conferred as Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), but in 1758, he was implicated in the Horeki Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being conferred as Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and being appointed as Sangi (Councillor) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), but in 1758, he was implicated in the Horeki Incident.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being conferred as Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and being appointed as Sangi (Councilor) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) in 1753, but in 1758, he was implicated in the Horeki Incident.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。1753を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>宝暦10年（1760年）に薨去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1760.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1760.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1760.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>享年60。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 60.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 60.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 60.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明治24年（1891年）に名誉回復し、正二位を追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1891, he regained his honor and was additionally conferred as Shonii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1891, he regained his honor and was additionally conferred Shonii.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1891, he regained his honor and was additionally conferred Shonii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>実子がないため、弟植松賞雅の子尚具を養子に迎えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he did not have biological child, he adopted Naotomo, son of his younger brother Takamasa UEMATSU, as his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he did not have biological child, he adopted Naotomo, son of his younger brother Takamasa UEMATSU, as his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he did not have biological child, he adopted Naotomo, son of his younger brother Takamasa UEMATSU, as his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>