<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原仲平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakahira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nakahira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakahira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原仲平（ふじわら の なかひら　貞観 (日本)17年（875年）－天慶8年（945年）9月1日 (旧暦)）は平安時代の廷臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakahira (born in 875, birth date unknown - September 1, 945 (by the lunar calendar)) was a courtier who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nakahira (born in 875, birth date unknown - September 1, 945 (by the lunar calendar)) was a courtier who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakahira (875 - October 14, 945) was a retainer of the Imperial Court who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>昭宣公藤原基経の三男で、母は仁明天皇の皇子人康親王の娘・操子女王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of Shosenko (posthumous title to honor the past performance) FUJIWARA no Mototsune and his mother was Princess Soshi, a daughter of Imperial Prince Saneyasu who was a son of Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of Shosenko (posthumous title to honor past performance) FUJIWARA no Mototsune, and his mother was Princess Soshi, a daughter of Imperial Prince Saneyasu, who was a son of Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of Shosenko (posthumous title to honor past performance) FUJIWARA no Mototsune, and his mother was Princess Soshi, a daughter of Imperial Prince Saneyasu, who was a son of Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>贈太政大臣藤原時平の同母弟、摂政関白太政大臣藤原忠平の同母兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the same mother, he had an older brother FUJIWARA no Tokihira, who was raised to Grand Minister after death, and also a younger brother FUJIWARA no Tadahira, who was a regent, chief advisor to the Emperor, and the Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the same mother, he had an older brother FUJIWARA no Tokihira, who was promoted to Grand Minister after death, and also a younger brother FUJIWARA no Tadahira, who was a regent, chief advisor to the Emperor, and the Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the same mother, he had an older brother FUJIWARA no Tokihira, who was promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) after his death, and also a younger brother FUJIWARA no Tadahira, who held the posts of Sessho (regent), Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) and Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt>役職名の表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>姉妹に、宇多天皇夫人藤原温子・醍醐天皇皇后藤原穏子がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sisters were FUJIWARA no Atsuko who was a wife of Emperor Uda and FUJIWARA no Onshi who was a wife of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sisters were FUJIWARA no Atsuko, who was a wife of Emperor Uda, and FUJIWARA no Onshi, who was a wife of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sisters were FUJIWARA no Atsuko, who was a wife of Emperor Uda, and FUJIWARA no Onshi, who was a wife of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>左京一条にある枇杷第を伝領し、枇杷左大臣と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he took over the Biwa-dai Palace in the Sakyoichijo district, he was called Biwa Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he took over the Biwa-dai Palace in the Sakyoichijo district, he was called Biwa Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he took over the Biwa-dai Palace in the Sakyoichijo district, he was called Biwa Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>光孝天皇の加冠によって元服した長兄時平と対照的に、寛平2年（890年）、宇多天皇の加冠により殿上で元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to the eldest brother Tokihira whose coming-of-age ceremony was carried out by Emperor Koko, his coming-of-age ceremony was carried out at the court by Emperor Uda in 890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the eldest brother Tokihira, whose coming-of-age ceremony was carried out by Emperor Koko, his coming-of-age ceremony was carried out at the court by Emperor Uda in 890.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to the eldest brother Tokihira, whose coming-of-age ceremony was carried out by Emperor Koko, his coming-of-age ceremony was carried out at the court by Emperor Uda in 890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>昌泰2年（899年）に昇殿し、延喜元年（901年）蔵人頭、同17年保明親王の春宮大夫に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was permitted to enter the Imperial Court in 899, and was appointed to Kuroudo no To (emperor&apos;s personal secretary) and then to Togu Daibu (grand master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Household) in 901.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was permitted to enter the Imperial Court in 899, and was appointed Kuroudo no To (emperor&apos;s personal secretary) and then Togu Daibu (grand master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Household) in 901.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was permitted to enter the Imperial Court in 899, and was appointed Kurodo no to (emperor&apos;s personal secretary) in 901 and then Togu Daibu (grand master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Household) for Imperial Prince Yasuakira in 917.</e>
<cmt>917年、保明親王　を追加しました。Kurodo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>按察使大納言、近衛大将を経て、朱雀天皇代、承平 (日本)3年（933年）右大臣、同八年左大臣に転じ、後に成明親王（村上天皇）の東宮傅を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After serving as Azechi (Examination Commissioner), Dai Nagon (Chief Councilor of State), and Konoe Taisho (Major Captain of the Imperial Guard), he was reappointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right) and then to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 933, and he later additionally served as a Togu-Fu (tutor) for Imperial Prince Nariakira (Emperor Murakami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving as Azechi (Examination Commissioner), Dai Nagon (Chief Councilor of State), and Konoe Taisho (Major Captain of the Imperial Guard), he was reappointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right) and then Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 933, and he later additionally served as a Togu-Fu (tutor) for Imperial Prince Nariakira (Emperor Murakami)</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving as Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) of Dainagon (a chief councilor of state) and Konoe Taisho (Major Captain of the Imperial Guard), he was reappointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 933 and then Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 938 during the reign of Emperor Suzaku, and he later additionally served as a Togu no fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) for Imperial Prince Nariakira (Emperor Murakami)</e>
<cmt>年数などを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>位階の方は正二位に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted as high as Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted as high as Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted as high as Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>次男でありながら末弟の忠平に比べ二十年も大臣昇進が遅れ、終生彼の後塵を拝した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was the second son, he was promoted to minister 20 years later than the youngest brother, Tadahira, and he therefore was always behind his youngest brother throughout his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was the second son, he was promoted to minister 20 years later than the youngest brother, Tadahira, and he therefore throughout his life he was always behind his youngest brother.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was the second son, he was promoted to minister 20 years later than the youngest brother, Tadahira, and therefore throughout his life he was always behind his youngest brother.</e>
<cmt>ダブっているhe を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>温和敦厚な人柄と伝わる仲平も、こればかりは心苦く思っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakahira was said to be gentle and compassionate, but was bitter about this promotion issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakahira was said to be gentle and compassionate, but was bitter about this promotion issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakahira was said to be gentle and compassionate, but was bitter about this promotion issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>延喜十九年、醍醐天皇の勅命を奉じて大宰府に下り、奉行として当所の太宰府天満宮の社殿を造営。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 919, following the imperial command issued by Emperor Daido, he went to Dazaifu (under the ritsuryo system, it was a government office with jurisdiction over Kyushu, Iki and Tsushima) and constructed the main building of the Dazaifu Tenmmangu Shrine as a shogunate administrator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 919, following the imperial command issued by Emperor Daido, he went to Dazaifu (under the ritsuryo system, it was a government office with jurisdiction over Kyushu, Iki and Tsushima) and constructed the main building of the Dazaifu Tenmmangu Shrine as a shogunate administrator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 919, following the imperial command issued by Emperor Daigo, he went to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) and constructed the main building of the Dazaifu Tenmangu Shrine as a bugyo (shogunate administrator).</e>
<cmt>Daigo に修正しました。bugyo を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>呉越王に天慶3年（940年）に書を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 940, he sent a letter to the King of Wu-yueh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 940, he sent a letter to the King of Wu-yueh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 940, he sent a letter to the King of Wu-yueh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>歌人として優れ、『古今和歌集』には若年でありながら入集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an excellent poet and his poems were selected for &quot;Kokin Wakashu (Anthology of Japanese Verses Ancient and Modern)&quot; when he was still young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an excellent poet and his poems were selected for &quot;Kokin Wakashu (Anthology of Japanese Verses Ancient and Modern)&quot; when he was still young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an excellent poet and his poems were selected for &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (Anthology of Japanese Verses Ancient and Modern) when he was still young.</e>
<cmt>&quot; の位置を括弧の前に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>姉温子の女官伊勢 (歌人)との恋愛でも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known for his love affair with Ise (a poet), who was a court lady of his older sister, Atsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known for his love affair with Ise (a poet), who was a court lady of his older sister, Atsuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also known for his love affair with Ise (a poet), who was a court lady of his older sister, Atsuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、仲平の死後、名邸枇杷第は女系を伝って、のちに藤原道長が入手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, after Nakahira&apos;s death, the famous Biwa-dai Palace was passed down through the female line and then was acquired by FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, after Nakahira&apos;s death, the famous Biwa-dai Palace was passed down through the female line and then was acquired by FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, after Nakahira&apos;s death, the famous Biwa-dai Palace was passed down through the female line and then was acquired by FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yume149(id:17504), Point136(id:211299), Yonoemon(id:55450), やりたこ(id:113528), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Nzero(id:18138), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>