<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉村公三郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaburo YOSHIMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaburo YOSHIMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaburo YOSHIMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉村 公三郎（よしむら こうざぶろう、1911年9月9日 - 2000年11月7日）は、昭和期の映画監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kozaburo YOSHIMURA (Sept. 9, 1911 – Nov. 7, 2000) is a movie director of the Showa Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kozaburo YOSHIMURA (Sept. 9, 1911 – Nov. 7, 2000) was a movie director during the Showa Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kozaburo YOSHIMURA (September 9, 1911 – November 7, 2000) was a movie director during the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>年月の表記を他の記事とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>4人の子供を儲け、長男はNHK解説委員の吉村秀實。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had four children and his eldest son is the NHK commentator, Hidemi YOSHIMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had four children and his eldest son is the NHK commentator, Hidemi YOSHIMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had four children and his eldest son is the NHK commentator, Hidemi YOSHIMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯・人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life and Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life and Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life and Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>統一リストに従って修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>滋賀県大津市に、新聞記者で後に広島市を務めた吉村平造の息子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture as the son of Heizo YOSHIMURA, a journalist who later became Major of Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture as the son of Heizo YOSHIMURA, a journalist who later became the Mayor of Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture as the son of Heizo YOSHIMURA, a journalist who later became the Mayor of Hiroshima City.</e>
<cmt>「City」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父の転勤により東京の小梅小学校に転校、1924年に岐阜県立大垣中学に入学、しかし、中学4年の時、東京の私立日本中学（現・日本学園高校）に転校し、翌年に卒業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He transferred to Koume Primary School in Tokyo due to his father&apos;s relocation. He entered Gifu Prefectural Ogaki Junior High School in 1924 but transferred to the private Nihon Junior High School (currently Nihon Gakuen High School) in Tokyo when he was in the 4th grade of junior high school and graduated the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He transferred to Koume Primary School in Tokyo due to his father&apos;s relocation. He entered Gifu Prefectural Ogaki Junior High School in 1924, but transferred to the private Nihon Junior High School (currently Nihon Gakuen High School) in Tokyo when he was in the 4th grade of junior high school and graduated the next year.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He transferred to Kome Primary School in Tokyo Prefecture due to his father&apos;s relocation, then entered Gifu Prefectural Ogaki Junior High School in 1924, but transferred to the private Nihon Junior High School (currently Nihon Gakuen High School) in Tokyo Prefecture when he was in the fourth grade of junior high school and graduated the next year.</e>
<cmt>「Prefecture」を補足し、1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1929年に親戚のつてで松竹蒲田撮影所に助手見習いとして入社した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1929, with the help of a relative, he entered the Shochiku Kabata Studios as a assistant apprentice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1929, with the help of a relative, he entered the Shochiku Kabata Studios as an assistant apprentice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1929, with the help of a relative, he entered the Shochiku Kamata Film Studio as an assistant apprentice.</e>
<cmt>「Shochiku Kamata Film Studio」としました。[http://bookwebpro.kinokuniya.co.jp/booksea.cgi?ISBN=9780824831820]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>入社以来、島津保次郎の下で助監督として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After joining the studio, he was active as the assistant director under Yasujiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After joining the studio, he was active as an assistant director under Yasujiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After joining the studio, he was active as an assistant director under Yasujiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1932年に軍隊に入隊、当時は築地小劇場の手伝いやデモに参加したことから要注意人物とマークされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1932 he joined the army but was considered a suspicious person because he helped at the Chikuji Small Theater and participated in demonstrations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1932 he joined the army but was considered a suspicious person because he helped at the Small Chikuji Theater and participated in demonstrations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1932 he joined the army but was considered a suspicious person because he helped at the Tsukiji Sho-Gekijo (Tsukiji Small Theater) and participated in demonstrations.</e>
<cmt>「Tsukiji Sho-Gekijo (Tsukiji Small Theater)」としました。[http://www.chuo-kanko.or.jp/english/spot/spot_02.html]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一年後に除隊し、1934年、当時10歳の高峰秀子が主役のナンセンス短編喜劇『ぬき足さし足・非常時商売』で監督デビューするが、評価は低かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After one year,he dropped out of the army. In 1934, he made his debut as a director with the short nonsense comedy, &quot;Nukiashi Sashiashi Hijoji Shobai (emergency business of soft walker)&quot;, starring the 10-year-old Hideko TAKAMINE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After one year,he dropped out of the army. In 1934, he made his debut as a director with the short nonsense comedy, &quot;Nukiashi Sashiashi Hijoji Shobai&quot; (emergency business of a soft walker), starring the 10-year-old Hideko TAKAMINE.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After one year, he dropped out of the army, then in 1934, he made his debut as a director with the short nonsense comedy, &quot;Nukiashi Sashiashi Hijoji Shobai&quot; (emergency business of a soft walker), starring the 10-year-old Hideko TAKAMINE, which was underestimated.</e>
<cmt>「評価は低かった」を補足し、1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>以降は島津をはじめ、同じく島津門下生の五所平之助、豊田四郎や成瀬巳喜男の助監督を務めて、ついに監督昇進の命が下り、1939年に『女こそ家を守れ』で本格的に監督デビュー、続いて東宝に移った島津保次郎が撮る予定だった岸田國士原作の『暖流 (小説)』を撮り、新人離れした見事な演出でベスト・テン7位に選ばれるなど好評を博した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he worked as an assistant director with Shimazu, and Shimazu&apos;s students such as Heinosuke GOSHO, Shiro TOYODA and Miko NARUSE. He was finally promoted as director and made his actual debut as a director with &quot;Onna koso iewo mamore (It is women who guard a home)&quot; in 1939. The next film, &quot;Danryu (a novel)&quot;, was based on a novel with the same name by Kunio KISHIDA and was originally scheduled to be directed by Yasujiro SHIMAZU. It was a popular and fabulous production that was way beyond what was expected from his youth and was selected 7th place in the Best Ten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he worked as an assistant director with Shimazu, and Shimazu&apos;s students such as Heinosuke GOSHO, Shiro TOYODA and Miko NARUSE. He was finally promoted as director and made his actual debut as a director with &quot;Onna koso iewo mamore&quot; (It is women who guard the home)&quot; in 1939. The next film, &quot;Danryu&quot; (a novel), was based on a novel with the same name by Kunio KISHIDA and was originally scheduled to be directed by Yasujiro SHIMAZU. It was a popular and fabulous production that was way beyond what was expected from his youth and was selected as 7th place in the Best Ten.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he worked as an assistant director with Shimazu, and Shimazu&apos;s students such as Heinosuke GOSHO, Shiro TOYODA and Mikio NARUSE and was finally promoted as director to make his actual debut as a director with &quot;Onna koso iewo mamore&quot; (It is women who guard the home)&quot; in 1939, and the next film, &quot;Danryu&quot; (warm current), based on a novel with the same name by Kunio KISHIDA and originally scheduled to be directed by Yasujiro SHIMAZU, which was a popular and fabulous production that was way beyond what was expected from his youth and was selected as seventh place in the ten best films.</e>
<cmt>「暖流」の英訳他、数箇所を補足・変更し、1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この作品を機に、本作の高峰三枝子や『安城家の舞踏会』の原節子、『偽れる盛装』の京マチ子など主演女優の魅力を引き出す能力に定評がある「女性映画の巨匠」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning with this film, he was called &quot;Master of Woman&apos;s Films&quot; because he became noted for his talent in drawing out the appeal of star actresses starting with Mieko TAKAMINE of this film and others such as Setsuko HARA in &quot;Anjoke no Butokai (Ball of the Anjo family)&quot; and Machiko KYO in &quot;Itsuwareru Seiso (Clothes of Deception)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning with this film, he was called a &quot;Master of Woman&apos;s Films&quot; because he became noted for his talent in drawing out the appeal of star actresses starting with Mieko TAKAMINE of this film and others such as Setsuko HARA in &quot;Anjoke no Butokai&quot; (Ball of the Anjo family) and Machiko KYO in &quot;Itsuwareru Seiso&quot; (Clothes of Deception).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning with this film, he was called a &quot;Master of Woman&apos;s Films&quot; because he became noted for his talent in drawing out the appeal of star actresses starting with Mieko TAKAMINE of this film and others such as Setsuko HARA in &quot;Anjoke no Butokai&quot; (Ball of the Anjo family) and Machiko KYO in &quot;Itsuwareru Seiso&quot; (Clothes of Deception).</e>
<cmt>「&quot;」にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに翌年、上原謙主演の戦意高揚映画『西住戦車長伝』を監督、ベスト・テン2位に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, he directed the military propaganda film &quot;Nishizumi Senshacho den (a story of Lieutenant Nishizumi)&quot;starred by Ken Uehara, and reached second place in the Best Ten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, he directed the military propaganda film &quot;Nishizumi Senshacho den&quot; (The Story of Lieutenant Nishizumi) starring Ken Uehara, and took second place in the Best Ten.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, he directed the military propaganda film &quot;Nishizumi Senshacho den&quot; (The Story of Lieutenant Nishizumi) starring Ken Uehara, and took second place in the ten best films.</e>
<cmt>「&quot;」にし、「ten best films」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また戦時中は1942年に『間諜未だ死せず』、1943年に『開戦の前夜』といった国策色の強い映画ながら、アメリカ映画ばりのサスペンス調の演出で人気を呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the war, he produced &quot;Kancho imada shisezu (the spy has not yet died)&quot;in 1942 and &quot;Kaisen no zenya (the eve of stating the war)&quot; in 1943. Both were films tinged with national policy, but were popular because of its highly suspenseful production similar to American movies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the war, he produced &quot;Kancho imada shisezu&quot; (the spy has not yet died) in 1942 and &quot;Kaisen no zenya&quot; (the eve of stating the war) in 1943. Both were films tinged with national policy, but were popular because of its highly suspenseful production similar to American movies.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war, he created &quot;Kancho Imada Shisezu&quot; (The Spy Is Not Yet Deed) in 1942 and &quot;Kaisen no Zenya&quot; (On the Eve of War) in 1943 which, although both strongly nationalist, were popular because of the suspense in the style of American films.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1943年10月、撮影中に赤紙が届き、出征。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Oct. 1943, draft papers arrived while he was filming and he served in the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Oct. 1943, draft papers arrived while he was filming and he then served in the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1943, he received his draft papers while filming, and left for the front.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>軍隊では機関銃隊の小隊長として南方戦線に派遣され、のちにタイ王国のバンコク駐屯の第18方面軍司令部情報部を経て終戦時は辻政信が部長の情報部にいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the army, he served as a platoon leader of a machine-gun platoon and was sent to the Southern Lines. Later, he was affiliated with the Information division at the headquarters of the 18th Army that was based in Bangkok, Kingdom of Thai. At the end of the war, he was in the Information division head by Masanobu TSUJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the army, he served as a leader of a machine-gun platoon and was sent to the Southern Lines. Later, he was affiliated with the Information Division at the headquarters of the 18th Army that was based in Bangkok, the Kingdom of Thailand. At the end of the war, he was in the Information Division head by Masanobu TSUJI.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While in the army, he served as a leader of a machine-gun unit and was dispatched to the southern front, later moving to the 18th Area Army Headquarters Intelligence Department stationed in Bangkok in the Kingdom of Thailand, and ending the war at the intelligence department headed by Masanobu TSUJI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>南方戦線より復員後の1947年、没落華族を描いて新しい社会の到来を印象付けた『安城家の舞踏会』を撮り、好評を博し、キネマ旬報ベストテン1位に輝く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning from the Southern Lines in 1947, he filmed &quot;Anjoke no Butokai (Ball of the Anjo family)&quot;, which impressed upon the arrival of a new society through the eyes of downfallen nobility. This film was popular and reached the top place in the Best Ten of the Kinema Junpo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning from the Southern Lines in 1947, he filmed &quot;Anjoke no Butokai&quot; (Ball of the Anjo family), which depicted the arrival of a new society through the eyes of downfallen nobility. This film was popular and reached the top position in the Best Ten of the Kinema Junpo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being demobilized from the southern front, in 1947 he filmed &quot;Anjoke no Butokai&quot; (The Ball of the Anjo Family) which depicted the decline of a noble family and signified the arrival of a new society and was met with a good reaction; ranking number one in the Kinema Junpo magazine&apos;s top ten.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>以後、この作品の脚本を書いた新藤兼人とのコンビで多くの名作を制作することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he often worked together with the scriptwriter of this film, Kaneto SHINDO and produced many masterpieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he often worked together with the scriptwriter of this film, Kaneto SHINDO and produced many masterpieces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later worked as a pair with Kaneto SHINDO who wrote the screenplay for this film and the two went on to create a number of masterpieces.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、1950年には、その新藤兼人と映画制作会社「近代映画協会」を設立し、作品は主に大映で配給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1950, he established the film production company, Kindai Eiga Kyokai (Modern Movie Association) together with Kaneto SHINDO, and its films were mainly distributed by Daiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1950, he established the film production company, Kindai Eiga Kyokai (Modern Movie Association) together with Kaneto SHINDO, and its films were mainly distributed by Daiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1950, he established the &apos;Kindai Eiga Kyokai&apos; (Modern Film Association) production company together with Kaneto SHINDO, and its films were mainly distributed by the Daiei Motion Picture Company.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1951年に『偽れる盛装』で毎日映画コンクール監督賞を受賞している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951, he was awarded the director prize of the Mainichi Film Awards with &quot;Itsuwareru Seiso&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951, he was awarded the director prize of the Mainichi Film Awards with &quot;Itsuwareru Seiso&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, he won the award for best director at the Mainichi Film Awards for &quot;Itsuwareru Seiso&quot; (Clothes of Deception).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、この年には松竹大船撮影所に見学に来ていた岸惠子をスカウトした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also during 1951, he discovered Keiko KISHDA who had been visiting the Shochiku Ofuna Studios.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also during 1951, he discovered Keiko KISHDA who had been visiting the Shochiku Ofuna Studios.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he discovered Keiko KISHI who had been visiting the Shochiku Ofuna Film Studio.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>以後、1952年には監督した『源氏物語』がカンヌ国際映画祭に出品され、杉山公平が撮影賞を受賞している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1952, &quot;Genji Monogatari (Tales of Genji)&quot;, which he had directed, was taken to the Cannes Film Festival and Kohei SUGIYAMA won the best cinematographer award.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1952, &quot;Genji Monogatari (Tales of Genji),&quot; which he had directed, was taken to the Cannes Film Festival and Kohei SUGIYAMA won the best cinematographer award.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1952, &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji) which he had directed, was taken to the Cannes Film Festival and Kohei SUGIYAMA won the award for best cinematographer.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>精力的に作品を発表し、男女の心理描写に優れた手腕を発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made many films, especially talented at portraying the emotional relationship between men and women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made many films, especially talented at portraying the emotional relationship between men and women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made many films, and was especially talented at portraying the emotional relationships between men and women.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1956年、経営が行き詰った近代映画協会を離れ（新藤兼人の要望で名義だけは残した）、大映に入社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1956, he left the Kindai Eiga Kyokai, which was having financial problems (he left his name only because of the strong wishes of Kanteo SHINDO), and entered Daiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1956, he left the Kindai Eiga Kyokai, which was having financial problems (he left his name only because of the strong wishes of Kanteo SHINDO), and entered Daiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1956, he left Kindai Eiga Kyokai, which was having financial problems (he left only his name because of the wishes of Kaneto SHINDO), and joined Daiei.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>1963年に脳出血、1972年に胃を全摘出するなどして体力の限界を感じたのか、田中正造を描いた1974年の『襤褸の旗』を最後に映画の製作から遠ざかり、以後は文筆業を主な仕事にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1963, he had a cerebral hemorrhage and had his entire stomach removed in 1972. Due to these health problems and feeling the limit of his physical strength, he quit film production after &quot;Boro no hata (rag banner)&quot; in 1974. After this, he made writing his main occupation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1963, he had a cerebral hemorrhage and had his entire stomach removed in 1972. Due to these health problems and feeling the limit of his physical strength, he quit film production after &quot;Boro no hata&quot; (rag banner) in 1974. After this, he made writing his main occupation.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may have been that he reached the limit of his physical strength after suffering a cerebral hemorrhage in 1963 and having a full gastrectomy in 1972, but he left film industry after his final work, the 1974 film &quot;Ranru no Hata&quot; (Ragged Flags) depicting Shozo TANAKA, and made writing his main occupation.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文に合わせて修正、用語補足修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1976年、紫綬褒章、1982年、勲四等旭日小綬章を受章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received the Shiju hosho (medal of honor with purple ribbon) in 1976 and Kun Yonto Kyokujitsu Shojusho (Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun) in 1982.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the Shiju hosho (medal of honor with purple ribbon) in 1976 and Kun Yonto Kyokujitsu Shojusho (Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun) in 1982.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the Shiju Hosho (Order of the Purple Ribbon) in 1976 and the Order of the Rising Sun, Gold Rays with Rosette in 1982.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1985年に牛原虚彦、1994年に乙羽信子が亡くなった際にはそれぞれ葬儀委員長を務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He acted as the head of the funeral ceremonies for Kiyohiko USHIHARA in 1985 and Nobuko OTOWA in 1994.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He acted as the head of funeral ceremonies for Kiyohiko USHIHARA in 1985 and Nobuko OTOWA in 1994.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the master of ceremonies at the funerals of Kiyohiko USHIHARA in 1985 and Nobuko OTOWA in 1994.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1997年に妻と死別した後も随筆・寄稿や講演会出演などで健在ぶりを示していたが2000年11月27日に急性心不全のため逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after he was widowed in 1997, he was energetic in writing essays, contributing articles and making appearances at talks, but on Nov. 27, 2000, he died from acute heart failure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after he was widowed in 1997, he was energetically writing essays, contributing articles and making appearances to lecture, but on Nov. 27, 2000, he died from acute heart failure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after he was widowed in 1997, continued to write essays, contribute articles and conduct lectures as if in good health, but on November 27, 2000, he died from acute heart failure.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>享年89。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 89.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 89.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 89.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松岡徳次郎(id:218163), MikeAz800o(id:58193), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Okapia2(id:98589), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), 氷室浩次(id:180895), Ranma9617(id:148386), 兇状旅(id:137772), Hinonbey(id:56556), NDR(id:5500), 青山コロハ(id:118527), 雲南(id:61460), Calvero(id:38360), 松木完之(id:26818), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>