<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>服部半蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>服部 半蔵（はっとり はんぞう）は、戦国時代 (日本)から江戸時代初期にかけて松平氏〜徳川氏の麾下で活躍した武士で、代々「半蔵」を仮名 (通称)の名乗りとした服部半蔵家の歴代当主たちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI were samurais working directly under the Matsudaira clan and the Tokugawa clan during the Edo Period, and refers to the successive family heads of the Hattori clan who assumed the name of &apos;Hanzo&apos; for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo HATTORI was samurai working under the command of Matsudaira clan and the Tokugawa clan from the Sengoku period (period of warring states) to the early Edo Period, and refers to the successive family heads of the Hattori clan who assumed the name of &apos;Hanzo&apos; for generations.</e>
<cmt>were samurais→was samuraiとしました。（下記にあるように服部半蔵は襲名されており、同時に何人もの服部半蔵が存在したわけではないので、単数形でよいのではないかと思われたのと、「7人の侍」の英語が「seven samurai」なので、複数形であるにしてもsamuraiは単複同形と理解してよいと思われたからです。）directly under→under the command of｢戦国時代から･･･初期にかけて」が抜けていました(during the Edo Periodだけの表記でした）ので補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI was samurai working under the command of Matsudaira clan and the Tokugawa clan from the Sengoku period (period of warring states) to the early Edo Period, and refers to the successive family heads of the Hattori clan who assumed the name of &apos;Hanzo&apos; for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、歴代の当主は石見守（いわみのかみ）という官名の名乗りも持ち、服部石見守とも称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These family heads also had the title of Iwami no kami (governor of Iwami Province) and sometimes called themselves HATTORI Iwami no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These family heads also had the title of Iwami no kami (governor of Iwami Province) and sometimes called themselves HATTORI Iwami no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These family heads also had the title of Iwami no kami (governor of Iwami Province) and sometimes called themselves HATTORI Iwami no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>忍者のイメージがあるが、本当に忍者だったのは初代だけであり（ただし詳細は不明）、2代目以降は忍者でない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Hattori clan has popularly been recognized as a ninja group, only the founder of the clan was a ninja (details are unknown) and the rest were not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hanzo HATTORI has popularly been recognized as a ninja, only the first was a ninja (details are unknown) and the rest were not.</e>
<cmt>服部家ではなく服部半蔵の話なので、the Hattori clan→Hanzo HATTORI、ninja group→ninjaにし、the founder of the clan→the firstました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hanzo HATTORI has popularly been recognized as a ninja, only the first was a ninja (details are unknown) and the rest were not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴代の服部半蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successors of Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who assumed the name of Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>｢服部半蔵の後継者｣と理解されそうなので、書き直してみました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who assumed the name of Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>初代　服部半蔵（半三）保長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Hanzo: Yasunaga Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Hanzo: Yasunaga Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Hanzo: Yasunaga Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>生没年不詳　伊賀出身の忍者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his dates of birth and death are unknown, Yasunaga was a ninja from Iga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his dates of birth and death are unknown, Yasunaga was a ninja from Iga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his dates of birth and death are unknown, Yasunaga was a ninja from Iga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>伊賀を出て室町幕府12代将軍足利義晴に、続いて三河にて松平清康に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having left Iga Province, Yasunaga served under Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th shogun of Muromachi bakufu, and later Kiyoyasu MATSUDAIRA of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having left Iga Province, Yasunaga served under Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th shogun of Muromachi bakufu, and later Kiyoyasu MATSUDAIRA of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having left Iga Province, Yasunaga served under Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th shogun of Muromachi bakufu, and later Kiyoyasu MATSUDAIRA of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>2代目　服部半蔵正成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second Hanzo: Masashige Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second Hanzo: Masashige Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second Hanzo: Masashige Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>徳川家康に仕えた、伊賀流同心の支配役。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA as the head of Iga-school doshin (police constable of Iga Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige served for Ieyasu TOKUGAWA as the head of Iga-school doshin (police constable of Iga Province).</e>
<cmt>forを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA as the head of Iga-school doshin (police constable of Iga Province).</e>
<cmt>for を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>いわゆる「服部半蔵」として世間でよく知られるのは彼の事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The so-called &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos;, popular among people, refers to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the popularly known &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos;.</e>
<cmt>辞書によるとso-calledには疑わしいニュアンスが含まれるとあるので、書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the popularly known &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>だがあくまで伊賀同心は配下の一部門であり、自身は甲冑を着て足軽を率いた武士である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in reality, the Iga-doshin was no more than one security section of vassals and Masashige was also merely an armored samurai who organized ashigaru (common foot soldiers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in reality, the Iga-doshin was no more than one section of vassals and Masashige was also merely an armored samurai who led ashigaru (common foot soldiers).</e>
<cmt>securityに相当する言葉は原文になかったので取りました。｢率いた」だけですので、organized→ledにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in reality, the Iga-doshin was no more than one section of vassals and Masashige was also merely an armored samurai who led ashigaru (common foot soldiers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>槍の名手として知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a well-known spearman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known to be good at handling spears.</e>
<cmt>well-knownは「名手として知られた」とは意味が違う気がします。書き直してみました。&quot;spear master&quot;なども考えられます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known to be good at handling spears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>3代目　服部半蔵正就</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third Hanzo: Masanari Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third Hanzo: Masanari Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third Hanzo: Masanari Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>父である正成の死後、伊賀同心200人の支配を引継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father, Masashige, died, Masanari inherited the Iga-doshin consisting of 200 constables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father, Masashige, died, Masanari succeeded him to control 200 members of the Iga-doshin.</e>
<cmt>引き継いだのは伊賀同心の「支配」ですので、後半をそのように書き直してみました。またinherited→succeededにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father, Masashige, died, Masanari succeeded him to control 200 members of the Iga-doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし徳川家から指揮権を預けられたに過ぎない伊賀同心を家来扱いしたために配下の同心たちの反発を招き、ついに伊賀同心が寺に篭って正就の解任を要求する騒ぎに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the police constables of the Iga-doshin rose in revolt against Masanari in a temple, demanding a dismissal of Masanari from the post, because Masanari, who was given a temporal command over the Iga-doshin from the Tokugawa family, treated them as retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the members of the Iga-doshin shut themselves up in a temple, demanding a dismissal of Masanari from the post, because Masanari, who was only given a command over the Iga-doshin from the Tokugawa family, treated the members of the Iga-dosin as his retainers.</e>
<cmt>police constables→membersにしました。Retainersの前にhisをつけました。「篭って」いますが「反乱騒ぎをした」わけではないのでrose in revolt･･･→shut themselves up としました。Temporal→onlyにして位置を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the members of the Iga-doshin shut themselves up in a temple, demanding a dismissal of Masanari from the post, because Masanari, who was only given a command over the Iga-doshin from the Tokugawa family, treated the members of the Iga-dosin as his retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため正就は伊賀流同心の支配の役目は解かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident divested Masanari of his commander role of the Iga-doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this incident, Masanari dismissed as the commander of Iga-doshin.</e>
<cmt>divested→dismissed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this incident, Masanari was dismissed as commander of Iga-doshin.</e>
<cmt>was dismissedとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>後、大坂の役で行方不明になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Masanari went missing in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Masanari went missing in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Masanari went missing in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>4代目　服部半蔵正重</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth Hanzo: Masashige Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth Hanzo: Masashige Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth Hanzo: Masashige Hanzo HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>兄の後を継いで服部半蔵を襲名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige succeeded his older brother and assumed the name of Hanzo HATTORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige succeeded his older brother to assume the name of Hanzo HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>and→to不定詞でつなぎました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige succeeded his older brother to assume the name of Hanzo HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>舅である大久保長安に巻き込まれて大久保長安事件で失脚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fell from grace in the Okubo Nagayasu Incident with his father-in-law, Nagayasu OKUBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fell from grace in the Okubo Nagayasu Incident with his father-in-law, Nagayasu OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fell from grace in the Okubo Nagayasu Incident with his father-in-law, Nagayasu OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後各地を転々とした後、松平定綱に召し抱えられて二千石を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having moved across Japan, Masashige finally found a new master, Sadatsuna MATSUDAIRA, and given a land of 2,000 goku (556 cubic meters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having moved across Japan, Masashige finally met Sadatsuna MATSUDAIRA, who gave him a land of 2,000 goku (556 cubic meters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>found→metにし、a new masterは原文にないので削除しました。And given→, who gave himとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having moved across Japan, Masashige finally met Sadatsuna MATSUDAIRA, who gave him a land of 2,000 koku (556 cubic meters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>goku→koku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これにより桑名藩の家老として服部半蔵家は存続する（大服部家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This let the Hanzo-Hattori clan (aka. The O-Hattori clan) survive by holding the post of a chief retainer of the Kuwana Domain.</e>
<cmt>大服部家：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the Hanzo-Hattori clan survive by holding the post of a chief retainer of the Kuwana Domain (the large Hattori family).</e>
<cmt>「大服部家」は（私の意見ですが）「大きな意味での服部家」ではないかと思われたので、そのように訳してみました。また、このカッコは文全体にかかると解釈し、文末にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus the Hanzo-Hattori clan survive by holding the post of a chief retainer of the Kuwana Domain (the large Hattori family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>また、服部正就の妻は桑名藩主松平定勝の姉であり、その子・服部源右衛門正辰も桑名藩に仕えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the wife of Masanari was the older sister of Sadakatsu MATSUDAIRA, the lord of the Kuwana Domain, Masanari&apos;s son, Masatoki Genemon HATTORI, also worked for the Kuwana Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the wife of Masanari was the older sister of Sadakatsu MATSUDAIRA, the lord of the Kuwana Domain, Masanari&apos;s son, Masatoki Genemon HATTORI, also worked for the Kuwana Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the wife of Masanari was the older sister of Sadakatsu MATSUDAIRA, the lord of the Kuwana Domain, Masanari&apos;s son, Masatoki Genemon HATTORI, also worked for the Kuwana Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>血統から藩主一族の扱いを受け、服部半蔵家以上に優遇されている（小服部家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatoki was treated like a family member of the domain lord for his blood and his clan (the Sho-Hattori clan) was given even better treatment than the Hanzo-Hattori clan (the O-Hattori clan).</e>
<cmt>小服部家：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatoki was treated like a family member of the domain lord for his blood and his clan was treated better than the Hanzo-Hattori clan (the small Hattori family).</e>
<cmt>これは「小さな意味での服部家」だと思われましたので、そのように訳してみました。｢血統から」→for his bloodは、正確な意味を反映していない気がします。Evenに相当する意味合いはないと思われましたので削除し、treated betterとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his pedigree, Masatoki was treated like a family member of the domain lord, and his clan was treated better than the Hanzo-Hattori clan (the small Hattori family).</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>フィクションの中の服部半蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI in fictions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo HATTORI in fictions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI in fictions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>歴史上の服部半蔵は伊賀者の統率者であっても自身の忍者としての性格は薄いが、現代では服部半蔵は最も名の知れた伊賀忍者のひとりとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although historic &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos; were not so much a ninja but a leader of Igamono (generic name to call local samurais of Iga Province), he is now recognized as one of the most famous Iga ninjas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos; in the history was not so much a ninja but a leader of Igamono (generic name to call local samurai of Iga Province), he is now recognized as one of the most famous Iga ninjas.</e>
<cmt>HanzoHATTORI、samuraiとも単数にしました。historic→in the historyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although historically &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos; was less a ninja than a leader of Igamono (a generic name referring to the local samurai of Iga Province), he is now recognized as one of the most famous Iga ninjas.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>このため、服部半蔵という名前の忍者が登場する小説、時代劇、漫画、ゲームなどは数知れず存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there are numerous novels, historical plays, mangas, and games featuring a ninja called Hanzo HATTORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why there have been numerous novels, historical plays, mangas, and games in which a ninja called Hanzo HATTORI appears.</e>
<cmt>therefore→That is whyにしました。また、以下の記載より、漫画、映画などはちょっと過去に遡るので現在完了形にしました。「が登場する」はfeaturingと違う気がしましたので、in which･･･appearsにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why there have been numerous novels, historical plays, mangas, and games in which a ninja called Hanzo HATTORI appears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>以下にいくつか例を紹介する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are some of the examples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The followings are some of the examples.</e>
<cmt>following→followingsにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The followings are some of the examples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>以前は体制（幕府）側という立ち位置から悪役に用いられる作品が多かったが、現在は必ずしもそうではなくなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, Hanzo HATTORI was portrayed as a villain for his anti-government stance in many works, but it is not necessarily the case now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, many works portrayed Hanzo HATTORI as a villain for his anti-government stance, but it is not necessarily the case now.</e>
<cmt>many worksを主語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, many works portrayed Hanzo HATTORI as a villain for his anti-government stance, but it is not necessarily the case now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>伊賀の影丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iga no Kagemaru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iga no Kagemaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iga no Kagemaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>5代目の頭首として登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this story, Hanzo HATTORI appears as the fifth head.</e>
<cmt>主語が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this story, Hanzo HATTORI appeared as the fifth head.</e>
<cmt>In this story→原文にない言葉ですが、削除せずに用いました。ウィキペディアの「伊賀の影丸」によると、過去の漫画のようですので、動詞を過去形にしました。（他も同様にしました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this story, Hanzo HATTORI appeared as the fifth head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>主人公・影丸ら隠密に指令を出して徳川家への謀反や不穏な動きを事前に防ぐ役目を務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo serves as an undercover to give orders to the main character, Kagemaru, to prevent any suspicious movements including a rebellion against the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>主語が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo gave orders secletly to the main character, Kagemaru, and others to prevent any suspicious movements beforehand including a rebellion against the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>serves as an undercover to→省略し、secletlyを挿入しました。影丸「ら」なのでand othersを入れました。（Preventがあるので不要かと思われましたが）｢事前の｣に相当するbeforehandを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo gave orders secletly to the main character, Kagemaru, and others to prevent any suspicious movements beforehand including a rebellion against the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>サスケ (漫画)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasuke (manga)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasuke (manga)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasuke (manga)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>主人公・サスケに敵対する公儀隠密の首領として服部半蔵が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, Hanzo HATTORI is the boss of a shogunate spy group and fights against the main character, Sasuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo HATTORI appeared as the boss of a shogunate spy group and fought against the main character, Sasuke.</e>
<cmt>In the story, →原文にないので省略しました。ウィキペディアの「サスケ」によると、過去の漫画のようなので、動詞を過去形にしました。Was→appeared asにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI appeared as the boss of a shogunate spy group and fought against the main character, Sasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>舞台の時期は史実の服部半蔵家が取り潰された前後にあたるが、この時期を舞台として真田幸村配下の忍者と、徳川氏の覇権と忍者の世界の制覇を目論む半蔵率いる徳川忍軍の暗闘というモチーフは、忍者ものの物語の定番といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This manga adopts a typical ninja storyline; the story is set in before and after the historic Hanzo-Hattori clan was ruined and features three main motifs, ninjas controlled by Yuimura SANADA, the hegemony of the Tokugawa clan and fights behind the scenes by the shogunate spy group led by Hanzo who aims to reign over the ninja world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This manga adopted the typical ninja storyline; the story was set in before and after the historic Hanzo-Hattori clan had been ruined and featured three main motifs, namely ninjas controlled by Yukimura SANADA, the hegemony of the Tokugawa clan and fought behind the scenes by the shogunate spy group led by Hanzo who aimed to reign over the ninja world.</e>
<cmt>上記同様、動詞を過去形に（過去形は過去分詞系に）しました。Typicalの前の冠詞をtheにしました。Motifsの後にnamelyを入れました。Yuimura→Yukimuraに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This manga adopted the typical ninja storyline; the story was set in before and after the historic Hanzo-Hattori clan had been ruined and featured three main motifs, namely ninjas controlled by Yukimura SANADA, the hegemony of the Tokugawa clan and fought behind the scenes by the shogunate spy group led by Hanzo who aimed to reign over the ninja world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>忍者ハットリくん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninja Hattori-kun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninja Hattori-kun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninja Hattori-kun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>主人公のハットリくん（ハットリカンゾウ）は、服部半蔵の子孫という設定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, the main character, Hattori-kun (Kanzo HATTORI), is introduced as a descendant of Hanzo HATTORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main character, Hattori-kun (Kanzo HATTORI), was introduced as a descendant of Hanzo HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>In the story, →原文にないので省略しました。ウィキペディアの「忍者ハットリくん」によると、過去の漫画のようですので、動詞を過去形にしました。（他も同様にしました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main character, Hattori-kun (Kanzo HATTORI), was introduced as a descendant of Hanzo HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>服部半蔵・影の軍団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI - Kage no Gundan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo HATTORI - Kage no Gundan (Shadow Warriors)</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアの「服部半蔵・影の軍団」によると、「Shadow Warrior」と呼ばれているようですので、カッコ内に付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI - Kage no Gundan (Shadow Warriors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>服部半蔵家の改易後、服部半蔵を名乗る頭領とその配下の伊賀忍軍が影の世界で活躍していたという設定で、半蔵が主人公として登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, even after the Hanzo-Hattori clan was punished by Kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties), the Iga shogunate spy group and its leader, Hanzo HATTORI (main character), are still active in the dark side of the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo appeared as the main character in the setting that even after the Hanzo-Hattori clan had been punished by Kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties), the Iga shogunate spy group and its leader, Hanzo HATTORI, were still active in the dark side of the world.</e>
<cmt>In the story, →原文にないので省略しました。ウィキペディアの「服部半蔵・影の軍団」によると、過去の番組のようですので、動詞を過去形に、過去形は過去完了形にしました。（他も同様にしました。）｢という設定で･･･登場する｣の部分の訳がありませんでしたので、冒頭に追加し(main character)を取りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo appeared as the main character in the setting that even after the Hanzo-Hattori clan had been punished by Kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties), the Iga shogunate spy group and its leader, Hanzo HATTORI, were still active in the dark side of the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後、江戸の様々な年代で千葉真一扮する伊賀の頭領（名前は半蔵など）が活躍するという内容でシリーズ化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, this manga was made into a series, in which a Iga leader (named Hanzo or others) was involved in various incidents taken place during the Edo Period (the role was played by Shinichi CHIBA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, this TV program was made into a series, in which a Iga leader (named Hanzo or others) was involved in various incidents taken place during the Edo Period (the role was played by Shinichi CHIBA).</e>
<cmt>漫画ではなくテレビ番組のようですので、TV programにしました。「involved in･･･」には｢活躍する｣の意味が反映されていない気がしましたが、適切な言葉が浮かびませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This TV program was later made into a series, in which an Iga leader (often but not always named Hanzo) was actively involved in various incidents that took place during the Edo Period (the role was played by Shinichi CHIBA).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="39">
<j>キル・ビル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kill Bill</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kill Bill</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kill Bill</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="40">
<j>現代の沖縄で、引退し、寿司屋を営んでいる服部半蔵が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, Hanzo HATTORI has retired from ninja and runs a sushi restaurant in present-day Okinawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this movie, Hanzo HATTORI retired from ninja and ran a sushi restaurant in present-day Okinawa.</e>
<cmt>In the story→In this movieにしました(原文にない言葉ですが｢登場する｣の代わりとして用いました)。ウィキペディアの「Kill Bill」によると、過去の映画のようですので、動詞を過去形にしました。（他も同様にしました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this movie, Hanzo HATTORI retired from ninja and ran a sushi restaurant in present-day Okinawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>監督のクウェンティン・タランティーノが上記「影の軍団」シリーズのファンであったため、同じ千葉真一に半蔵役として出演依頼したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The director of the movie, Quentin Tarantino, was a big fan of the &apos;Kage no Gundan&apos; series and requested Shinichi CHIBA, who acted in the series, to perform the same character, Hanzo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The director of the movie, Quentin Tarantino, was an admirer of the &apos;Kage no Gundan (Shadow Warrior)&apos; series and requested Shinichi CHIBA, who acted in the series, to perform the same character, Hanzo.</e>
<cmt>big fan→admirerにしました。Who acted･･･は原文にありませんが、残しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The director of the movie, Quentin Tarantino, was an admirer of the &apos;Kage no Gundan (Shadow Warrior)&apos; series and requested Shinichi CHIBA, who acted in the series, to perform the same character, Hanzo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="42">
<j>サムライスピリッツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAMURAI SPIRITS</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAMURAI SPIRITS</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAMURAI SPIRITS</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="43">
<j>伊賀忍軍の頭領・服部半蔵 (サムライスピリッツ)が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, Hanzo HATTORI is introduced as the leader of a Iga shogunate spy group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this game Hanzo HATTORI is introduced as the leader of a Iga shogunate spy group.</e>
<cmt>「サムライスピリッツ」はゲームのようですので、In the story→In this gameとしました。(原文にはない言葉ですが、このまま用いました。）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this game Hanzo HATTORI is introduced as the leader of a Iga shogunate spy group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>サムライスピリッツの舞台は江戸時代中期の寛政期なので実在の服部半蔵三代とは時代が異なるが、「服部半蔵・影の軍団」と同様、幕府の忍者軍団の頭領としてのイメージが採用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAMURAI SPIRITS is set in the Kansei era (mid Edo Period), a different time period when the historic Hanzo HATTORI lived, but used the typical image of Hanzo as the leader of a shogunate spy group, as did &apos;Hanzo HATTORI - Kage no Gundan&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The setting of SAMURAI SPIRITS is in the Kansei era (mid Edo Period), a different time period when the Hanzo HATTORI really lived, but it adopted the typical image of Hanzo as the leader of a shogunate spy group, as did &apos;Hanzo HATTORI - Kage no Gundan&apos;.</e>
<cmt>～is set→The setting of ～isにしました。Historic→reallyにしてlivedの前に入れました。（「実在の」の意味はtheで反映されていると思われます。）used→adoptedに、主語をitにして挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The setting of SAMURAI SPIRITS is in the Kansei era (mid Edo Period), a different time period when the Hanzo HATTORI really lived, but it adopted the typical image of Hanzo as the leader of a shogunate spy group, as did &apos;Hanzo HATTORI - Kage no Gundan&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また同シリーズ作中においても、初代「服部半蔵」から息子である「服部真蔵」へ「半蔵」の名が襲名されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the series, the name &apos;Hanzo&apos; is also handed down from the first &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos; to his son, &apos;Shinzo HATTORI&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the other games of the same series, the name &apos;Hanzo&apos; is also handed down from the first &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos; to his son, &apos;Shinzo HATTORI&apos;.</e>
<cmt>同シリーズ作なので、同じシリーズの他のゲーム（数は不明）なので、冒頭を書き直してみました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the series, the name &apos;Hanzo&apos; is also handed down from the first &apos;Hanzo HATTORI&apos; to his son, &apos;Shinzo HATTORI&apos;.</e>
<cmt>元に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>ワールドヒーローズ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">WORLD HEROES</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">WORLD HEROES</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">WORLD HEROES</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="47">
<j>世界の歴史上の人物をモチーフにしたキャラクターによる対戦型格闘ゲームに登場する、日本の忍者をモデルとするキャラクターのうちのひとりとして服部半蔵 (ワールドヒーローズ)が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this versus beat&apos;em-up game, various characters in the motif of historical persons from around the world are introduced, and Hanzo HATTORI also appears as a character modeled on Japanese ninja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this versus beat&apos;em-up game which uses historical persons from around the world as a motif, Hanzo HATTORI appears as a character modeled on Japanese ninja (World Heroes).</e>
<cmt>「対戦型格闘ゲーム」→「versus beat&apos;em-up game」の適否が不確かです。(用語集では｢対戦型ゲーム｣→「multiplayer game」となっています。）原文に沿って訳語の言葉を用いて書き直してみました。カッコ内ワールドヒーローズが抜けていましたので補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this versus beat&apos;em-up game which uses historical persons from around the world as a motif, Hanzo HATTORI appears as a character modeled on Japanese ninja (World Heroes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="48">
<j>あずみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="49">
<j>あずみでは服部半蔵家の改易後、徳川家直属の忍者で伊賀忍軍の統領として暗躍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this story, after the Hanzo-Hattori clan was punished by Kaieki, Hanzo works as a ninja and a leader of a Iga shogunate spy group under the Tokugawa clan and is actively involved in various incidents behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this story, after the Hanzo-Hattori clan had been be punished by being deprived of one&apos;s fief, Hanzo worked as a ninja and a leader of a Iga shogunate spy group under the Tokugawa clan and was actively involved in various incidents behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアの「あずみ」によると、過去の番組のようですので、動詞を過去形に、過去形は過去完了形にしました。「punished by Kaieki」→「be punished by being deprived of one&apos;s fief｣(用語集の記載の1つを用いました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this story, after the Hanzo-Hattori clan had been be punished by being deprived of one&apos;s fief, Hanzo worked as a ninja and a leader of a Iga shogunate spy group under the Tokugawa clan and was actively involved in various incidents behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="50">
<j>信長の野望シリーズシリーズ、伊忍道 打倒信長など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nogunaga no Yabo series and Inindo Dato Nobunaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nogunaga no Yabo (Nobunata&apos;s Ambition) series and Inindo Dato Nobunaga (Inindo: Way of the Ninja)</e>
<cmt>両者ともウィキペディアの英語ページにあったタイトルをカッコ内に入れて追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nogunaga no Yabo (Nobunata&apos;s Ambition) series and Inindo Dato Nobunaga (Inindo: Way of the Ninja)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="51">
<j>これらのコーエーの戦国時代を舞台にしたゲームでは、半蔵は実在の服部正成に基づく徳川氏の家臣として登場するが、いずれも忍者として設定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These game series of Koei Games are set in the Sengoku Period in which Hanzo is a ninja and a vassal of the Tokugawa clan modeled on historic Masanari HATTORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these Koei&apos;s game series which have their setting in the Sengoku Period, Hanzo was a ninja and a vassal of the Tokugawa clan modeled on historic Masanari HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>of Koei Games →Koei&apos;sにしてtheseの後に挿入しました。～are set→which have their setting inにしました。Is→wasにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these Koei&apos;s game series which have their setting in the Sengoku Period, Hanzo was a ninja and a vassal of the Tokugawa clan modeled on historic Masanari HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="52">
<j>戦国無双および無双OROCHI</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengoku Muso and Muso OROCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengoku Muso (Samurai Warriors) and Muso OROCHI (Warriors Orochi)</e>
<cmt>両者ともウィキペディアの英語ページにあったタイトルをカッコ内に入れて追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengoku Muso (Samurai Warriors) and Muso OROCHI (Warriors Orochi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="53">
<j>半分は実在の服部正成に基づいて徳川家康直々の忍者という設定になっているが、関ヶ原の戦いや大坂の役に参戦し暗躍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the games, Hanzo is about fifty-percent modeled on Masanari HATTORI and works directly under Ieyasu Tokugawa as a ninja, and is actively involved in the Battle of Sekigahara and Siege of Osaka behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the game story, Hanzo is partly modeled on Masanari HATTORI and works directly under Ieyasu Tokugawa as a ninja, and is actively involved in the Battle of Sekigahara and Siege of Osaka behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt>In the games→In the game storyとし、原文にない言葉ですが、削除せず用いました。原文「半分は～設定になっている」の意味が不明でしたが、partly modeledにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the game story, Hanzo is partly modeled on Masanari HATTORI and works directly under Ieyasu Tokugawa as a ninja, and is actively involved in the Battle of Sekigahara and Siege of Osaka behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>徳川家家臣として本多忠勝と同じく評されており、真田幸村や風魔小太郎と激しく敵対している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo is evaluated as strong as Tadakatsu HONDA as a vassal of the Tokugawa family, and fiercely confronts Yukimura SANADA and Kotaro FUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo is rated same as Tadakatsu HONDA as a vassal of the Tokugawa family, and fiercely confronts Yukimura SANADA and Kotaro FUMA.</e>
<cmt>evarulated→ratedにしました。「強く」とは原文にありませんでしたので、as strongは削除し、sameとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo is rated same as Tadakatsu HONDA as a vassal of the Tokugawa family, and fiercely confronts Yukimura SANADA and Kotaro FUMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="55">
<j>甲賀忍法帖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koga Ninpo-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koga Ninpo-cho (Shinobi: Heart Under Blade)</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアの英語ページにあったタイトルをカッコ内に入れて追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koga Ninpo-cho (Shinobi: Heart Under Blade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="56">
<j>数ある忍法帖シリーズをものした山田風太郎の最初の「忍法帖」作品で、代表作のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the first and one of the most popular Ninpo-cho series written by Futaro YAMADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first and one of the most popular Ninpo-cho series written by Futaro YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアの「甲賀忍法帳」によると、過去の漫画のようですので、動詞を過去形に、過去形は過去完了形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the first and one of the most popular Ninpo-cho series written by Futaro YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>徳川忍組頭として半蔵が登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, Hanzo is the leader of the Tokugawa ninja group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo appeared as the leader of the Tokugawa ninja group.</e>
<cmt>In the storyを削除し、is→appeared asとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo appeared as the leader of the Tokugawa ninja group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>徳川家三代将軍を決める果し合いのため、徳川家康の命により甲賀と伊賀の間に結ばれた「不戦の約定」を解いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to determine the third shogun of the Tokugawa family, Hanzo receives an order from Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and cancels the &apos;non-belligerency pact&apos; between Koga and Iga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to determine the third shogun of the Tokugawa family, Hanzo, under the order from Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, canceld the &apos;non-belligerency pact&apos; between Koga and Iga.</e>
<cmt>Receivesに相当する語は原文にありませんので、under theにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to determine the third shogun of the Tokugawa family, Hanzo, under the order from Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, canceld the &apos;non-belligerency pact&apos; between Koga and Iga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>2003年の漫画版である「バジリスク 〜甲賀忍法帖〜」、2005年の劇場映画「SHINOBI-HEART UNDER BLADE-」にも同じ役柄で登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo also appears as the same character in the cartoon version, &apos;BASILISK -Koga Ninpo cho-&apos; of 2003 and the movie version, &apos;SHINOBI-HEART UNDER BLADE-&apos; of 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo also appeared as the same character in the cartoon version, &apos;BASILISK -Koga Ninpo cho-&apos; of 2003 and the movie version, &apos;SHINOBI-HEART UNDER BLADE-&apos; of 2005.</e>
<cmt>動詞を過去形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo also appeared as the same character in the cartoon version, &apos;BASILISK -Koga Ninpo cho-&apos; of 2003 and the movie version, &apos;SHINOBI-HEART UNDER BLADE-&apos; of 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>（原作では二代目。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In the original, he is introduced as the second Hanzo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In the original, he was introduced as the second Hanzo.</e>
<cmt>動詞を過去形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In the original, he was introduced as the second Hanzo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>「バジリスク」では年代を考慮し四代目ということに変更）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;BASILISK&apos;, he is introduced as the fourth Hanzo, changed based on the time period of the cartoon.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;Basilisk&apos;, he was introduced as the fourth Hanzo, changed based on the time period of the cartoon.)</e>
<cmt>「バジリスク」は過去の漫画のようですので、動詞を過去形にしました。また、ウィキペディアの「バジリスク」の項より、表記をBasiliskにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;Basilisk&apos;, he was introduced as the fourth Hanzo, changed based on the time period of the cartoon.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="62">
<j>人造人間キカイダー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinzo ningen KIKAI-da</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinzo ningen KIKAI-da (Android Kikaider)</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアの英語ページにあったタイトルをカッコ内に入れて追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinzo ningen KIKAI-da (Android Kikaider)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="63">
<j>半蔵の子孫を自称する私立探偵が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, a private detective who introduces himself as a descendant of Hanzo appears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this program, a private detective who introduced himself as a descendant of Hanzo appeared.</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアの「人造人間キカイダー」によると、過去の漫画のようですので、動詞を過去形に、過去形は過去完了形にしました。In the story→In this programにしました。(原文にはない言葉ですが、削除せず用いました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this program, a private detective who introduced himself as a descendant of Hanzo appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ちなみに名前は服部半平。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name is Hanpei HATTORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was Hanpei HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>動詞を過去形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was Hanpei HATTORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="65">
<j>兵馬地獄旅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyoma Jigoku tabi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyoma Jigoku tabi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyoma Jigoku tabi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="66">
<j>「伊賀の影丸」と同じ横山光輝の漫画。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a serial cartoon drawn by Mitsuteru YOKOYAMA who also drew a cartoon &apos;Iga no Kagemaru&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a serial cartoon drawn by Mitsuteru YOKOYAMA who also drew a cartoon &apos;Iga no Kagemaru&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「兵馬地獄旅」は過去の漫画のようですので、動詞を過去形にしました。Serialは原文にない言葉ですが、実際3巻まであるようなので、残しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a serial cartoon drawn by Mitsuteru YOKOYAMA who also drew a cartoon &apos;Iga no Kagemaru&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>こちらのほうは史実の服部半蔵の描写に近く、伊賀者の統率者であっても自身は忍者ではない、武将としての服部半蔵が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo in this story is portrayed as a military commander, which is more characteristically similar to historic Hanzo HATTORI who was a leader of Igamono, not a ninja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo in this story was portrayed as a military commander, which was more characteristically similar to historic Hanzo HATTORI who had been a leader of Igamono, not a ninja.</e>
<cmt>動詞を過去形に、過去形は過去分詞形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo in this story was portrayed as a military commander, which was more characteristically similar to historic Hanzo HATTORI who had been a leader of Igamono, not a ninja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>服部正就が改易されたいきさつについての史実を元にした話であり、正就の解任を要求した伊賀同心の中心人物である主人公・兵馬に対し、恨みを抱く服部正就が刺客を放って命を狙うというストーリーになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story is based on the historical fact of how Masanari HATTORI was punished by Kaieki, and in the story, Masanari HATTORI tries to assassinate Hyoma, the main character, from a grudge, because Hyoma plays the central role among the Iga doshin in its request of the dismissal of Masanari from the supervisor&apos;s post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story was based on the historical fact of how Masanari HATTORI had been punished by Kaieki, and in the story, Masanari HATTORI tried to assassinate Hyoma, the main character, from a grudge, because Hyoma played the central role among the Iga doshin in its request of the dismissal of Masanari from the supervisor&apos;s post.</e>
<cmt>動詞を過去形に、過去形は過去分詞形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story was based on the historical fact of how Masanari HATTORI had been punished by Kaieki, and in the story, Masanari HATTORI tried to assassinate Hyoma, the main character, from a grudge, because Hyoma played the central role among the Iga doshin in its request of the dismissal of Masanari from the supervisor&apos;s post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="69">
<j>必殺!5 黄金の血</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hissatsu!5 Ogon no chi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hissatsu!5 Ogon no chi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hissatsu!5 Ogon no chi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="70">
<j>半蔵の子孫を自称する服部孫太夫という武士が登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story, Magodayu HATTORI, who designates himself as a descendant of Hanzo, appears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this movie, Magodayu HATTORI, who designated himself as a descendant of Hanzo, appeared.</e>
<cmt>「必殺!5 黄金の血」は過去の映画のようですので、動詞を過去形にしました。In the story→In this movieにしました。(原文にはない言葉ですが、削除せず用いました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this movie, Magodayu HATTORI, who designated himself as a descendant of Hanzo, appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>閑職らしく、「忍者の栄光、今いずこ」と言って嘆いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He laments for the lack of work by saying &apos;the glorious days of ninja is gone&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lameneded for the lack of work by saying &apos;the glorious days of ninja has gone&apos;.</e>
<cmt>動詞を過去形にし、セリフの中は現在完了形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lameneded for the lack of work by saying &apos;the glorious days of ninja has gone&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="72">
<j>ゴエモン 新世代襲名!</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goemon Shin Sedai Shumei!</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goemon Shin Sedai Shumei!</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goemon Shin Sedai Shumei!</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="73">
<j>最初のボスキャラクター。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI appears as the first boss character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanzo HATTORI appears as the first boss character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzo HATTORI appears as the first boss character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Asura2007(id:78364), S.S.Exp.Hashimoto(id:4001), 北斗白影(id:113612), Sheepech(id:111676), 野菜汁酢(id:70556), Aoiya(id:44787), Lupinoid(id:68), 立つのかよ(id:111350), Mercurius(id:57130), 怪盗蓬月(id:132496), R463(id:150079), ジャビ(id:88014), Helgo(id:93832), KSKS(id:97637), Safkan(id:423), Mamegaoka(id:140855), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>