<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条実雅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemasa ICHIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemasa ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemasa ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一条 実雅（いちじょう さねまさ、建久7年（1196年） - 安貞2年4月1日_(旧暦)（1228年5月6日））は、鎌倉時代初期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemasa ICHIJO (1196 - May 6, 1228) was a court noble in the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemasa ICHIJO (1196 - May 6, 1228) was a court noble of the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make slightly less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemasa ICHIJO (1196 - May 13, 1228) was a court noble of the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一条能保の子で母は藤原有恒の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son between Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and a daughter of FUJIWARA no Aritsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Aritsune.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Aritsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>姉婿である西園寺公経の猶子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by Kintsune SAIONJI, his elder sister&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Kintsune SAIONJI, his elder sister&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Kintsune SAIONJI, his elder sister&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>建保7年（1219年）、鎌倉幕府征夷大将軍源実朝の右大臣就任の鶴岡八幡宮参詣に随従してその暗殺を目にする事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1219, when attending the visit to Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine where the inauguration ceremony of the Minister of the Right was held for MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Sanemasa witnessed the assassination of Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1219, while visiting Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine to attend Shogun INAMOTO no Sanetomo&apos;s inauguration as Minister of the Right, Sanemasa witnessed Sanetomo&apos;s assassination.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, wordiness -deleted &quot;Kamakura bakufu&quot; and changed &quot;Seii taishogun&quot; to &quot;Shogun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1219, while visiting Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine to attend the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), MINAMOTO no Sanetomo&apos;s inauguration as Minister of the Right, Sanemasa witnessed Sanetomo&apos;s assassination.</e>
<cmt>INAMOTO→MINAMOTOとし、「鎌倉幕府征夷大将軍」を訳出するため訳文を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後、姉の孫にあたる九条頼経が次の将軍に決まったためにそのまま鎌倉に滞在してその補佐を行うこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, since Yoritsune KUJO, his elder sister&apos;s grandchild, was appointed as the next shogun, Sanemasa kept on staying in Kamakura, and assisted Yoritsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, with the appointment of Yoritsune KUJO, his elder sister&apos;s grandchild, as the next shogun, Sanemasa remained in Kamakura to assist him.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, with the appointment of Yoritsune KUJO, his elder sister&apos;s grandchild, as the next shogun, Sanemasa remained in Kamakura to assist him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>貞応元年（1221年）には参議に任じられ、執権北条義時の娘を妻に迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as Sangi (councillor) in 1221, and married a daughter of regent Yoshitoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Sangi (councillor) in 1221, and married a daughter of regent Yoshitoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Sangi (councillor) in 1221, and married a daughter of regent Yoshitoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが、元仁元年（1224年）、妻の母方の伯父である伊賀光宗が政変を起こして次期執権の北条泰時を倒そうとしたいわゆる「伊賀氏の乱」が発覚、その際光宗は自分の姪の婿にあたる実雅を九条頼経に代わる新将軍に立てようとしていたことも発覚、実雅は妻と離別させられた上で越前国に流刑となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1224, because a coup of trying to defeating the next regent Yasutoki HOJO caused by Mitsumune IGA, brother of his wife&apos;s mother, what is called the &quot;War of the Iga clan,&quot; came to light, and Mitsumune&apos;s intention to make Sanemasa, his niece&apos;s husband, the new shogun on behalf of Yoritsune KUJO at that time also came to light, Sanemasa was forced to divorce his wife, and exiled to Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1224, following the discovery of the &quot;Iga Clan rebellion&quot;, a coup to defeat the next regent, Yasutoki HOJO, planned by Mitsumune IGA, brother of Sanemasa&apos;s wife&apos;s mother, and because Mitsumune&apos;s intention to make Sanemasa, his niece&apos;s husband, the new shogun on behalf of Yoritsune KUJO at the same time also came to light, Sanemasa was forced to divorce his wife, and then exiled to Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1224, following the discovery of the &apos;Iga Clan War,&apos; a coup to defeat the next regent, Yasutoki HOJO, planned by Mitsumune IGA, brother of Sanemasa&apos;s wife&apos;s mother, and because Mitsumune&apos;s intention to make Sanemasa, his niece&apos;s husband, the new shogun on behalf of Yoritsune KUJO at the same time also came to light, Sanemasa was forced to divorce his wife, and then exiled to Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>「伊賀氏の乱」→統一事項に基づき、Iga Clan Warとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更、カンマの位置を移動、</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>4年後、配流先にて変死を遂げたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he died an unnatural death there four years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he died an unnatural death there four years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he died an unnatural death there four years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BuxWV(id:169145), ひろくん(id:79638), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>