<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近衛基平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohira KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohira KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohira KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近衛 基平（このえ もとひら、寛元4年（1246年） - 文永5年11月19日 (旧暦)（1268年12月24日））は、鎌倉時代中期の関白。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohira KONOE (1246 - December 24, 1268) was Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohira KONOE (1246 - December 24, 1268) was Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohira KONOE (1246 - December 31, 1268) was Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は摂政近衛兼経。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sessho (regent) Kanetsune KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sessho (regent) Kanetsune KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Sessho (regent) Kanetsune KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は摂政九条道家の娘九条仁子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Jinshi, a daughter of Sessho (regent) Michiie KUJO.</e>
<cmt>原文には、「九条仁子」 とありますが、「九条仁子」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語は「仁子」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Jinshi, a daughter of Sessho (regent) Michiie KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Jinshi, a daughter of Sessho Michiie KUJO.</e>
<cmt>(regent) 既出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>深心院関白あるいは西谷殿と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Shinjin-in Kanpaku and Nishitani-dono (西谷殿).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Shinjin-in Kanpaku and Nishitani-dono (西谷殿).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Shinjinin Kanpaku and Nishitani-dono (西谷殿).</e>
<cmt>深心院のハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>正室に西園寺公相女を迎えたが、彼女との間に子はなかったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohira took a daughter of Kinsuke SAIONJI as his lawful wife, but he was said to have fathered no child with her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohira took a daughter of Kinsuke SAIONJI as his lawful wife, but he was said to have fathered no child with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohira took a daughter of Kinsuke SAIONJI as his lawful wife, but he was said to have fathered no child with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>側室に久我通能女・一条実有女・洞院実雄女・近衛兼経女（基平の異母妹）らがいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His concubines included a daughter of Michiyoshi KOGA, a daughter of Saneyoshi ICHIJO, a daughter of Saneo TOIN, and a daughter (Motohira&apos;s half sister) of Kanetsune KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His concubines included a daughter of Michiyoshi KOGA, a daughter of Saneyoshi ICHIJO, a daughter of Saneo TOIN, and a daughter (Motohira&apos;s half sister) of Kanetsune KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His concubines included a daughter of Michiyoshi KOGA, a daughter of Saneyoshi ICHIJO, a daughter of Saneo TOIN, and a daughter (Motohira&apos;s half sister) of Kanetsune KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に近衛家基・近衛兼教・覚昭・尋基・近衛位子（亀山天皇女御・新陽明門院）・鷹司兼忠室がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Iemoto, Kanenori, Kakunyo, Jinki, Ishi (a consort of Emperor Kameyama, called Shinyomeimon-in), and a wife of Kanetada TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>原文には、「近衛家基」、「近衛兼教」、「近衛位子」 とありますが、「近衛家基」、「近衛兼教」、「近衛位子」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語はそれぞれ「家基」、「兼教」、「位子」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Iemoto, Kanenori, Kakunyo, Jinki, Ishi (a consort of Emperor Kameyama, called Shinyomeimon-in), and a wife of Kanetada TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Iemoto, Kanenori, Kakusho, Jinki, Ishi (a consort of Emperor Kameyama, called Shinyomeimon-in), and a wife of Kanetada TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>Kakunyo→Kakusho</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>建長6年（1254年）正月叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first month of 1254, Motohira was awarded the rank of the peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first month of 1254, Motohira was awarded the rank of the peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first month of 1254, Motohira was awarded the rank of the peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>侍従・右近中将などを経て、翌年の建長7年（1255年）7月に従三位非参議に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being appointed to the positions of Jiju (Chamberlain) and Ukon no Chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was awarded the Junior Third Court Rank, non-Councilor, in July 1255 of the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being appointed to the positions of Jiju (Chamberlain) and Ukon no Chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was awarded the Junior Third Court Rank, non-Councilor, in July 1255 of the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being appointed to the positions of Jiju (Chamberlain) and Ukon no Chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was awarded the Junior Third Court Rank, Hisangi (advisor at large), in August 1255 of the following year.</e>
<cmt>非参議の定訳グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同年6月権中納言に任命され、累進して正嘉2年（1258年）11月内大臣になり、弘長元年（1261年）3月右大臣になり、弘長3年（1263年）正月従一位となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year, Motohira was appointed to Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), and was promoted to Naidaijin (Inner Minister) in November 1258 and then to Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in March 1261; in the first month of 1263, he was awarded the Junior First Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, Motohira was appointed to Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), and was promoted to Naidaijin (Inner Minister) in November 1258 and then to Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in March 1261; in the first month of 1263, he was awarded the Junior First Rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of the same year, Motohira was appointed to Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state), and was promoted to Naidaijin (Inner Minister) in December 1258 and then to Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in April 1261; in the second month of 1263, he was awarded the Junior First Rank.</e>
<cmt>権中納言の定訳グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>文永2年（1265年）10月左大臣になり、文永4年（1267年）12月関白・藤氏長者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in October 1265, and in December 1267, he assumed the positions of Kanpaku and Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in October 1265, and in December 1267, he assumed the positions of Kanpaku and Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in November 1265, and in December 1267, he assumed the positions of Kanpaku and Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>文永5年（1268年）11月19日、関白在職のまま23歳で赤痢のため薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 19, 1268, he died of dysentery at the age of 23 as incumbent Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 19, 1268, he died of dysentery at the age of 23 as incumbent Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 31, 1268, he died of dysentery at the age of 23 as incumbent Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>大河ドラマ『北条時宗 (NHK大河ドラマ)』では基平は元 (王朝)（モンゴル）への返書を非として亀山天皇の眼前で切腹自害し、北条時輔の介錯を受ける硬派な関白として登場するが、勿論フィクションである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the annual year-long historical drama series &quot;Tokimune HOJO,&quot; Motohira was depicted as uncompromising Kanpaku as could be seen in the scene where he committed seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) with Tokisuke HOJO&apos;s aid of kaishaku (a merciful blow on to the neck by a second with a sword), insisting that Tokimune not respond to the letter from Yuan (Mongolia); however, the story is, of course, fictional.</e>
<cmt>原文には、「北条時宗 (NHK大河ドラマ)」 とありますが、「(NHK大河ドラマ)」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語は「北条時宗」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。原文には、「元 (王朝)（モンゴル）」 とありますが、「(王朝)」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語は「元 （モンゴル）」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the annual year-long historical drama series &quot;Tokimune HOJO,&quot; Motohira was depicted as an uncompromising Kanpaku as could be seen in the scene where he committed seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) aided by Tokisuke HOJO&apos;s act of kaishaku (a merciful blow on to the neck by a second with a sword), insisting that Tokimune not respond to the letter from Yuan (Mongolia); however, the story is, of course, fictional.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the annual year-long historical drama series &quot;Tokimune HOJO,&quot; Motohira was depicted as an uncompromising Kanpaku as could be seen in the scene where he committed seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) aided by Tokisuke HOJO&apos;s act of kaishaku (a merciful blow on to the neck by a second with a sword) in front of Emperor Kameyama, insisting that Tokimune not respond to the letter from Yuan (Mongolia); however, the story is, of course, fictional.</e>
<cmt>「亀山天皇の眼前で」追記。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), YOSHI438(id:174755), 伏儀(id:142093), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>