<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>黒田長堅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata KURODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata KURODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata KURODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>黒田　長堅（くろだ　ながかた、1770年（明和7年） － 1784年3月30日（天明4年2月10日 (旧暦)））は、筑前国福岡藩秋月藩の第7代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata KURODA (male, 1770 to March 30, 1784) was the seventh lord of Fukuoka domain and Akizuki domain in Chikuzen province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata KURODA (male, 1770 to March 30, 1784) was the seventh lord of Fukuoka domain and Akizuki domain in Chikuzen province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata KURODA (1770 - March 30, 1784) was the seventh lord of Fukuoka Domain and Akizuki Domain in Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>male, 削除しました。toをハイフンにしました。Domain, Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称は貞之助、千之助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s by-names were Sadanosuke and Sennosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata&apos;s by-names were Sadanosuke and Sennosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s by-names were Sadanosuke and Sennosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は山崎義俊（長堅は次男）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s father was Yoshitoshi YAMAZAKI (Nagakata was his second son).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata&apos;s father was Yoshitoshi YAMAZAKI (Nagakata was his second son).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s father was Yoshitoshi YAMAZAKI (Nagakata was his second son).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は第5代藩主・黒田長邦の娘・此子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s mother was Konoko, a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA, the fifth lord of the domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata&apos;s mother was Konoko, a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA, the fifth lord of the domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s mother was Konoko, a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA, the fifth lord of the domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>官位なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata had no administrative title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata had no administrative title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata had no administrative title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1774年11月18日、先代藩主黒田長恵の末期養子として家督を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 18, 1774, Nagakata succeeded to the headship of the family as a son adopted at the deathbed of Nagae KURODA, the sixth lord of the domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 18, 1774, Nagakata succeeded the headship of the family as a son adopted at the deathbed of Nagae KURODA, the sixth lord of the domains.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 18, 1774, Nagakata succeeded the headship of the family as a son adopted at the deathbed of Nagae KURODA, the sixth lord of the domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>父は交代寄合御礼衆の山崎義俊であったものの、母は黒田長邦の娘であったため、末期養子に迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Nagakata&apos;s father was Yoshitoshi YAMAZAKI who was a kotai-yoriai-onreishu, Nagakata&apos;s mother was a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA and, therefore, Nagakata was adopted as a son adopted at the deathbed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Nagakata&apos;s father was Yoshitoshi YAMAZAKI who was a kotai-yoriai-onreishu, Nagakata&apos;s mother was a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA and, therefore, Nagakata was adopted as a son adopted at the deathbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Nagakata&apos;s father was Yoshitoshi YAMAZAKI who was a kotaiyoriai onreishu (a special high rank among a family status of samurai warriors), Nagakata&apos;s mother was a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA and, therefore, Nagakata was adopted as a son adopted at the deathbed.</e>
<cmt>交代寄合→kotaiyoriai (alternate yoriai, a family status of samurai warriors in the Edo period)御礼衆→onreishu (twenty family with a special high rank among kotaiyoriai)より、koｔaiyoriai onreishu (a special high rank among a family status of samurai warriors)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>つまり、女系で黒田氏の血統に属していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, Nagakata belonged to the maternal line, the line of the KURODA family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, Nagakata belonged to the maternal line, the line of the KURODA family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, Nagakata belonged to the maternal line, the line of the Kuroda family.</e>
<cmt>Kuroda familyに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>1784年2月10日、江戸で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata died in Edo on February 10, 1784.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata died in Edo on February 10, 1784.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata died in Edo on February 10, 1784.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>享年15。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>法号は霊雲院光岳道照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s Buddhist name after his death was Reiun-in-kogaku-dosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata&apos;s Buddhist name after his death was Reiun-in-kogaku-dosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s Buddhist name after his death was Reiunin Kogaku Dosho.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>徳川将軍家に拝謁すること無く死んでしまい、かつまた子女もいなかったため、幕府による養子縁組許可のおりる見込みはなく、秋月藩黒田家はお家断絶の危機に見舞われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata died without having been granted any audience with the TOKUGAWA shogunate and he had no child and, therefore, there was no possibility for the KURODA family of Akizuki clan to be permitted, by the shogunate, to adopt any child and the KURODA family faced the crisis, that is, dying out of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata died without having been granted any audience with the TOKUGAWA shogunate and he had no child and, therefore, there was no possibility for the KURODA family of Akizuki clan to be permitted, by the shogunate, to adopt any child and the KURODA family faced a crisis, that is, dying out as a family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata died without having been granted any audience with the Tokugawa shogunate and he had no child and, therefore, there was no possibility for the Kuroda family of Akizuki clan to be permitted, by the shogunate, to adopt any child and the Kuroda family faced a crisis, that is, dying out as a family.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa小文字にしました。Kuroda familyに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、秋月藩は本藩と相談し、公家唐橋在家の三男豊煕を身代わりにすることを計画した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Akizuki clan consulted with the main clan, Fukuoka clan and planned to appoint the third son, Toyoteru of KARAHASHIARI family, a court noble, as a substitute of Nagakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Akizuki clan consulted with the main clan, Fukuoka clan and planned to appoint the third son, Toyoteru of KARAHASHIARI family, a court noble, as a substitute of Nagakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Akizuki clan consulted with the main clan, Fukuoka clan and planned to appoint a court noble Ariie KARAHASHI&apos;s third son, Toyoteru as a substitute of Nagakata.</e>
<cmt>唐橋在家→Ariie KARAHASHIなのでa court noble Ariie KARAHASHI&apos;s third son, Toyoteruとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>黒田長貞の娘は唐橋存家に嫁いでおり、豊煕はその子どもであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A daughter of Nagasada KURODA had married to KARAHASHIARI family and Toyoteru was her child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A daughter of Nagasada KURODA had married to KARAHASHIARI family and Toyoteru was her child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A daughter of Nagasada KURODA had married Ariie KARAHASHI and Toyoteru was their child.</e>
<cmt>唐橋在家→Ariie KARAHASHIなのでmarried Ariie KARAHASHIとし、their childとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、豊煕と長堅をすりかえる計画は中止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the plan to secretly replace Nagakata with Toyoteru was cancelled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the plan to secretly replace Nagakata with Toyoteru was cancelled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the plan to secretly replace Nagakata with Toyoteru was cancelled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>次いで、秋月藩は本藩と相談し、長堅の死亡を隠し、隠居願いを提出し、養子を迎えることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Akizuki clan consulted with the main clan and determined to hide the death of Nagakata, submit an application for permitting Nagakata&apos;s retirement, and have an adopted son for Nagakata..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Akizuki clan consulted with the main clan and determined to hide the death of Nagakata, submit an application to permit Nagakata&apos;s retirement, and have an adopted son for Nagakata..</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Akizuki clan consulted with the main clan and determined to hide the death of Nagakata, submit an application to permit Nagakata&apos;s retirement, and have an adopted son for Nagakata..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>具体的には、秋月種茂の次男を養嗣子黒田長舒（秋月種頴の母は黒田長邦の娘）として迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More specifically, the second son of Taneshige AKIZUKI was adopted as an adopted succeeding son, Naganobu KURODA (the mother of Tanenogi AKIZUMI was a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More specifically, the second son of Taneshige AKIZUKI was adopted as an adopted succeeding son, Naganobu KURODA (the mother of Tanenogi AKIZUMI was a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More specifically, the second son of Taneshige AKIZUKI was adopted as an adopted succeeding son, Naganobu KURODA (the mother of Tanenogi AKIZUMI was a daughter of Nagakuni KURODA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>こうした工作により、「寛政重修諸家譜」には「長堅長ずといへども重病ののち行歩かなはずして拝謁することあたはず」と御目見のできなかった事情を記し、さらに本家の幼少の黒田斉隆に代わり長崎警備の「奉仕にたへたるものをえらびて家を継しめむ」ことを願いを許可されたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above operations, it was written in Kansei-jushu-shokefu that the reason why he could not see any one was that &quot;though Nagakata had grown up, he was seriously sick and, as a result, he could not walk and could not give audience&quot; and that his application for permission to &quot;select some one to succeed his family who could bear the serving as&quot; a guard in Nagasaki instead of Naritaka KURODA who was from the main family and was young was permitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above operations, it was written in Kansei-jushu-shokefu that the reason why he could not see any one was that &quot;though Nagakata had grown up, he was seriously sick and, as a result, he could not walk and could not give audience&quot; and that his application for permission to &quot;select some one to succeed his family who could bear the serving as&quot; a guard in Nagasaki instead of Naritaka KURODA who was from the main family and was young was permitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above operations, it was written in &apos;Kansei-jushu-shokefu&apos; that the reason why he could not see any one was that &apos;though Nagakata had grown up, he was seriously sick and, as a result, he could not walk and could not give audience&apos; and that his application for permission to &apos;select some one to succeed his family who could bear the serving as&apos; a guard in Nagasaki instead of Naritaka KURODA who was from the main family and was young was permitted.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後の履歴は、1785年3月17日に隠居し、同年9月17日に16歳で死去となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s personal history after that is said that he retired on March 17, 1785 and died on September 17 in the same year at the age of 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagakata&apos;s personal history after that is said that he retired on March 17, 1785 and died on September 17 in the same year at the age of 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagakata&apos;s personal history after that is said that he retired on March 17, 1785 and died on September 17 in the same year at the age of 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>