<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原保輔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasusuke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasusuke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasusuke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 保輔（ふじわら の やすすけ、? - 永延2年6月17日 (旧暦)（988年8月7日））は、平安時代中期の官人であり盗賊の首領とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasusuke (date of birth unknown -August 7, 988) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) in the mid-Heian period, who was regarded as a mastermind of the brigands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasusuke (date of birth unknown -August 7, 988) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) in the mid-Heian period, who was regarded as a mastermind of the brigands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasusuke (year of birth unknown -August 7, 988) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) and also regarded as a ringleader of robbers in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原南家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>祖父は大納言藤原元方、父は従四位下藤原致忠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather was FUJIWARA no Motokata, who was Dainagon (Major Counselor), and his father was FUJIWARA no Munetada, who was in Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather was FUJIWARA no Motokata, who was Dainagon (Major Counselor), and his father was FUJIWARA no Munetada, who was in Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather was Dainagon (chief councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Motokata, and his father was FUJIWARA no Munetada of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は正五位下・右兵衛尉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and U-hyoenokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and U-hyoenokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the official court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and the office of Uhyoe no jo (third-ranked official of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>『尊卑分脈』によれば、「強盗の張本、本朝第一の武略、追討の宣旨を蒙ること十五度」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble), &apos;he was the mastermind of burglary and received an imperial decree of military operation and exile fifteen times.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble), &apos;he was a master of burglary and received an imperial decree of military operation and exile fifteen times.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble), he was &apos;a ringleader of robberies and the most excellent military strategist in Japan and an imperial decree of dispatching punitive force against him was issued 15 times.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。表記、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>985年（寛和元年）、源雅信の土御門殿で開かれた大饗において、藤原季孝に対する傷害事件を起こす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 985 he hurt FUJIWARA no Suetaka at the grand banquet held at the Tsuchimikado-dono Palace of MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 985 he hurt FUJIWARA no Suetaka at the grand banquet held at the Tsuchimikado-dono Palace of MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 985 he inflicted bodily injury on FUJIWARA no Suetaka at the grand banquet held at the Tsuchimikado-dono Palace of MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>さらに、以前兄藤原斉明を追捕した検非違使源忠良を射たり、988年（永延2年）閏5月には藤原景斉・茜是茂の屋敷への強盗を行うなどの罪を重ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he repeated the crime such as shooting up MINAMOTO no Tadayoshi, who was kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and captured his brother FUJIWARA no Tadaakira before, and robbing into the residence of FUJIWARA no Kagenari and Koreshige AKANE on May 988.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he repeated crimes such as killing MINAMOTO no Tadayoshi, who was kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and had previously captured his brother FUJIWARA no Tadaakira, and robbing the residence of FUJIWARA no Kagenari and Koreshige AKANE on May 988.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he committed various other crimes such as shooting an arrow at kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) MINAMOTO no Tadayoshi who had once captured Yasusuke&apos;s older brother FUJIWARA no Tadaakira, and robbing the residences of FUJIWARA no Kagenari and Koreshige AKANE in June 988.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらの罪状により、保輔に対する捜索は続けられ、朝廷より保輔を追捕した者には恩賞を与えると発表され、さらには保輔の父藤原致忠が検非違使に連行・監禁された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of these crimes, the search for Yasusuke had been continued and the Imperial Court released that a person who captured Yasusuke would be given a reward, and furthermore, FUJIWARA no Munetada, Yasusuke&apos;s father, was taken away and placed in confinement by kebiishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of these crimes, the search for Yasusuke continued and the Imperial Court announced that the person who captured Yasusuke would be given a reward. Furthermore, FUJIWARA no Munetada, Yasusuke&apos;s father, was taken away and placed in confinement by kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pursuit of Yasusuke was continued on charges of these crimes and the Imperial Court announced that the person who captured Yasusuke would be given a reward; furthermore, Yasusuke&apos;s father FUJIWARA no Munetada was arrested and placed in confinement by kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この状況に危機感を持った保輔は同年6月14日に北花園寺で剃髪出家したが、まもなく以前の手下であった足羽忠信によって捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasusuke, who expressed a sense of crisis against this situation, became a priest at the North Keon-ji Temple on June 14, 988, but was soon captured by ASHIHA no Tadanobu, who was his old vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasusuke, who expressed a sense of crisis against this situation, became a priest at the North Keon-ji Temple on June 14, 988, but was soon captured by ASHIHA no Tadanobu, who was his old vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasusuke, driven by a sense of impending crisis under such circumstances, took the tonsure at the North Keon-ji Temple on August 4 in the same year, but was soon captured by his former subordinate ASHIHA no Tadanobu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、逮捕の際、保輔は自らの腹部を刀で傷つけて自害を図り、翌日その傷がもとで獄中で没したという（『続古事談』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is said that he committed suicide by hurting his stomach with a sword at the time of arrest, and that he died on the next day caused by that wound (&quot;Zoku kojidan&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is said that he committed suicide by disembowlement at the time of arrest, and that he died the next day (&quot;Zoku kojidan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he attempted to disembowel himself at the time of arrest and died of the wound the next day in jail (&quot;Zoku kojidan&quot;(Ancient Matters)).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>『宇治拾遺物語』には、保輔が自分の屋敷の蔵の床下に穴を掘り、商人を蔵に呼びつけて物を買ったそばからこの穴に突き落として殺していた、という説話が語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), there is a story that Yasusuke made a hole under the floor of the storehouse in his residence and pushed a merchant off into the hole and killed soon after he called a merchant to the storehouse and bought something.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), there is a story that Yasusuke made a hole under the floor of the storehouse in his residence and pushed a merchant off into the hole, killing him. Soon after he called a merchant to the storehouse and bought something.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of Tales from Uji) contained a story in which Yasusuke made a hole under the floor of the storehouse in his residence, called merchants there one after another, bought goods and killed them by pushing them down the hole.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>後世『今昔物語集』などに見える盗賊の袴垂（はかまだれ）と同一視され、袴垂保輔という伝説的人物となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After ages, he was regarded as the same person as Hakamadare, a brigand seen in the tales such as &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu (Tales of Times Now and Then collection)&quot; and became a legendary figure as Yasusuke HAKAMADARE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later times, he was regarded as the same person as Hakamadare, a brigand seen in the tales such as &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu (Tales of Times Now and Then collection)&quot; and became a legendary figure as Yasusuke HAKAMADARE.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later times, he was regarded identical with Hakamadare, a robber described in the tales such as &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (Tales of Times Now and Then collection) and became a legend Yasusuke HAKAMADARE.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。不要なピリオドなどを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 代言人(id:33675), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>