<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鷹司輔煕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鷹司 輔煕（たかつかさ すけひろ、名の表記は輔&amp;amp20958、輔熈とも、文化 (元号)4年11月7日 (旧暦)（1807年12月5日） - 明治11年（1878年）11月19日）は、江戸時代末期（幕末）の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA (his first name is written in kanji &quot; 輔&amp;amp20958&quot; or &quot;輔熈,, December, 5, 1807 - November 19, 1878) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) in the late Edo era (end of Edo Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA (his first name is written in kanji &quot; 輔&amp;amp20958&quot; or &quot;輔熈,, December, 5, 1807 - November 19, 1878) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) during the late Edo era (end of Edo Period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA (his first name is written in kanji 輔凞 or 輔熈,, December, 5, 1807 - November 19, 1878) was a kugyo (the top court officials) during the late Edo period (last days of the Tokugawa shogunate).</e>
<cmt>ウェブより漢字を補足し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>孝明天皇時代の関白、藤原氏摂関家鷹司家の当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Served as Kanpaku in the age of Emperor Komei, he was the family head of the Takatsukasa family, one of the Sekkan regent families of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Served as Kanpaku during the age of Emperor Komei, he was the family head of the Takatsukasa family, one of the Sekkan regent families of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Served as Kanpaku during the age of Emperor Komei, he was the family head of the Takatsukasa family, one of the Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>出家時の法名は随楽。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given &quot;Zuiraku&quot; of Homyo (Buddhist names), when he became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given &quot;Zuiraku&quot; of Homyo (Buddhist names), when he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given Zuiraku of Homyo (Buddhist names), when he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は関白鷹司政通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Masamichi TAKATSUKASA, Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>嫡母は水戸藩主徳川治紀の娘・徳川清子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His chakubo (legitimate mother) was Kiyoko TOKUGAWA, a daughter of the lord of the Mito Domain, Harutoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His chakubo (legitimate mother) was Kiyoko TOKUGAWA, a daughter of the lord of the Mito Domain, Harutoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His chakubo (legitimate mother) was Kiyoko TOKUGAWA, a daughter of the lord of the Mito Domain, Harutoshi TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>文化4年（1807年）誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in 1807</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in 1807</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1807: He was born.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>文化14年2月（1817年）元服、叙位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Had a Genpuku ceremony (coming-of -age) and granted Joi (investiture) in February 1817</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Had a Genpuku ceremony (coming-of -age) and granted Joi (investiture) in February 1817</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1817: Had a genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age), and granted Joi (the conferment of a court rank).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>文政元年（1818年）5月従三位となり公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed as Kugyo (the top court officials).in May 1818.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed Kugyo (the top court officials).in May 1818.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 1818: Granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed kugyo.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>嘉永元年（1848年）3月内大臣、翌年正月には従一位に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to Naidaijin (minister) in March 1848 and granted Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to Naidaijin (minister) in March 1848 and granted Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1848: Promoted to Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior) and granted Juichii (Junior First Rank) in January, the following year.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>安政4年（1857年）2月右大臣に転ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to Udaijin (minister of the right).in February 1857</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to Udaijin (minister of the right).in February 1857</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 1857: Promoted to Udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>落飾、復帰、関白へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Priest, comeback, and Kanpaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Priest, comeback, and Kanpaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Priest, Comeback, and Kanpaku</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>安政5年（1858年）、日米修好通商条約締結への勅許をめぐり、朝廷と江戸幕府が対立するにおよび、水戸藩や福井藩の藩士に説得され、条約勅許不同意および征夷大将軍継嗣問題における一橋派の意見に同意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Imperial court and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) had an disagreement over an imperial sanction for the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan, he was persuaded by statesman of the Mito clan and the Fukui clan to disagree on the Emperor&apos;s sanction for the treaty and to agree with the Hitotsubashi faction on the successor matter of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Imperial court and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) had an disagreement over an imperial sanction for the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan, he was persuaded by statesman of the Mito clan and the Fukui clan to disagree on the Emperor&apos;s sanction for the treaty and to agree with the Hitotsubashi faction on the successor matter of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1858, when the Imperial court and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) had an disagreement over an imperial sanction for the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan, he was persuaded by statesman of the Mito clan and the Fukui clan to disagree on the Emperor&apos;s sanction for the treaty and to agree with the Hitotsubashi group on the successor matter of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>左大臣近衛忠煕や内大臣三条実万とともに献策して、水戸藩へ勅諚を賜るよう運動する（戊午の密勅）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Working with Sadaijin (minister of the left) Tadahiro KONOE and Naidaijin(minister) Sanetsumu SANJO, he played a key role in submitting a plan to the emperor to give the Mito clan an imperial decree (Bogo no micchoku (a secret imperial decree)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Working with Sadaijin (minister of the left) Tadahiro KONOE and Naidaijin (minister) Sanetsumu SANJO, he played a key role in submitting a plan to the emperor to give the Mito clan an imperial decree (Bogo no micchoku - a secret imperial decree).</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Working with Sadaijin (minister of the left) Tadahiro KONOE and Naidaijin Sanetsumu SANJO, he played a key role in submitting a plan to the emperor to give the Mito clan an imperial decree (Bogo no mitchoku - a secret imperial decree).</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため、同年大老に就任した井伊直弼の安政の大獄の一環で、幕府の内請により翌安政6年（1859年）辞官を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, he was forced to resign in 1359 by an informal decision of the Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in a series of Ansei no taigoku (the Ansei Purge) conducted by Naosuke Ii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result, he was forced to resign in 1359 by an informal decision of the Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in a series of Ansei no taigoku (the Ansei Purge) conducted by Naosuke Ii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result, in a series of Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate) conducted by Naosuke II who was appointed Tairo (chief minister) in the same year, he was forced to resign in 1859 by an informal decision of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>年号補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>やむを得ず同年5月落飾し法名「随楽」を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He inevitably became a priest and given a Buddhist name &quot;Zuiraku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He inevitably became a priest and was given the Buddhist name &quot;Zuiraku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He inevitably became a priest and was called his Buddhist name as &apos;Zuiraku&apos; in June, the same year.</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>桜田門外の変で井伊亡き後もしばらく謹慎を続けたが、文久2年（1862年）4月に宥免され、謹慎を解かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Naosuke Ii was assassinated in am incident outside the Sakurada Gate, he remained suspended as a priest for a while until given forgiveness in April 1862</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Naosuke Ii was assassinated in the am incident outside the Sakurada Gate, he remained suspended as a priest for a while until forgiven in April 1862</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Ii was assassinated in the Sakuradamongai Incident, he remained suspended as a priest for a while until forgiven in April 1862.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同5月還俗を命じられ、12月には新設の国事御用掛に補任されて朝政に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ordered to return to the secular world in May in 1862, and restored to the government of the court as Kokuji goyogakari (an official in the government) in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ordered to return to the secular world in May in 1862, and restored to the government of the court as Kokuji goyogakari (an official in the government) in December.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ordered to return to the secular world in May, 1862, and restored to the government of the court as the new post, Kokuji goyogakari (a general official of the Imperial Household in charge of the State affair) in January 1863 (December in old calendar).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にすると年をまたぐため旧暦表示を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>翌文久3年（1863年）には近衛忠煕の後を受けて関白に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took over Tadahiro KONOE as Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) in 1863.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took over Tadahiro KONOE as Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) in 1863.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took over Tadahiro KONOE as Kanpaku in the following year, 1863.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>幕末政局と輔煕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Political situation at the end of Edo Period and Sukehiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Political situation at the end of Edo Period and Sukehiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Political Situation at the End of Edo Period and Sukehiro</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>関白在任中、朝廷は長州藩と結びついた尊王攘夷過激派の三条実美・姉小路公知らが次第に発言力を拡大させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his service as Kanpaku, Sanetomi SANJO and Kintomo ANEKOJI, radical activists of the Sonnojoi (Revere the Emperor and expel the foreigners) started to gradually increase their influences over the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his service as Kanpaku, Sanetomi SANJO and Kintomo ANEKOJI, radical activists of the Sonnojoi (Revere the Emperor and expel the foreigners) started to gradually increase their influence over the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his service as Kanpaku, Sanetomi SANJO and Kintomo ANEKOJI, who were radical activists of the Sonno Joi (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and connected to the Choshu clan, started to gradually increase their influence over the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>孝明天皇が将軍徳川家茂を伴っての賀茂神社・石清水八幡宮行幸が行われ、文久3年8月には大和国行幸、譲位親征が企図された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Komei made gyoko (imperial visit) to Kamo-jinja Shrine and Iwashimizu-hachimangu Shrine accompanied by Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA and, in addition, he was requested to made another imperial visit to Yamato Province and to make an imperial departure for the front in August, 1863.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Komei made gyoko (an imperial visit) to Kamo-jinja Shrine and Iwashimizu-hachimangu Shrine accompanied by Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA and, in addition, he was requested to make another imperial visit to Yamato Province and to make an imperial departure for the front in August, 1863.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Komei made gyoko (an imperial visit) to Kamo-jinja Shrine and Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine accompanied by Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA and, in addition, he was requested to make another imperial visit to Yamato Province and to make an imperial departure for the front in September, 1863.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、尊攘派の増長に孝明天皇は不快感を表し、公武合体派の久邇宮朝彦親王らは、京都所司代松平容保および薩摩藩と組んで八月十八日の政変を強行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Emperor showed his unpleasant feeling about growing power of the Sonnojoi party, and thereby Kuni no miya Imperial Prince Asahiko and the reconciliatory party between the imperial court and the shogunate carried out Coups of August eighteenth jointly with Katamori MATSUDAIRA of Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto) and the Satsuma clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Emperor showed his unpleasant feelings about the growing power of the Sonnojoi party, and thereby Kuni no miya Imperial Prince Asahiko and the reconciliatory party between the imperial court and the shogunate carried out the Coups of August eighteenth jointly with Katamori MATSUDAIRA of Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto) and the Satsuma clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Emperor Komei showed his unpleasant feelings about the growing power of the Sonno Joi party, and thereby Imperial Prince Kuninomiya Asahiko of kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) and others forced through the Coup of August 18, jointly with Katamori MATSUDAIRA of Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto) and the Satsuma clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>輔煕は関白の座にありながらこの政局に関与できず、また三条らの帰京を運動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukehiro, though serving as Kanpaku, was not able to involve in this political situation, and in addition, he planed to have SANJO and his colleagues return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukehiro, though serving as Kanpaku, was not able to be involved in this political situation, and in addition, he planed to have SANJO and his colleagues return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukehiro, though serving as Kanpaku, was not able to be involved in this political situation, and in addition, he planed to have Sanjo and his colleagues return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そのため、12月には島津久光の建言により関白を免ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result the government, receiving an proposal of Hisamitsu SHIMAZU dismissed him from Kanpaku in December 1863.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result the government, receiving a proposal from Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, dismissed him from Kanpaku in December 1863.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result, the government, receiving a proposal from Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, dismissed him from Kanpaku in January 1864 (December in old calendar).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直すと年をまたぐため、旧暦を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>翌元治元年（1864年）7月に起きた禁門の変に際しては、鷹司邸は久坂玄瑞や寺島忠三郎ら長州藩兵が立て篭もり、会津・薩摩・幕府軍の攻撃をうけて焼失する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kinmon) that occurred in July of the following year (1864), theTakatsukasa House was attacked by the armies of Aizu, Satsuma and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to burn down because samurai of the Choshu clan including Gensui KUSAKA and Chuzaburo TERASHIMA shutted themselves in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kinmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kinmon) that occurred in July of the following year (1864), theTakatsukasa House was attacked by the armies of Aizu, Satsuma and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to burn down because samurai of the Choshu clan including Gensui KUSAKA and Chuzaburo TERASHIMA shut themselves inside it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kinmon Incident that occurred in August of the following year (1864), the Takatsukasa&apos;s residence was attacked by the armies of Aizu, Satsuma and the bakufu to burn down because samurai of the Choshu clan including Gensui KUSAKA and Chuzaburo TERASHIMA shut themselves inside it.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これにより鷹司家は長州藩と気脈を通じているとの嫌疑をかけられ、輔煕は参朝を停止され謹慎処分となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, he was ordered to be suspended and banned from the court because of a suspicion that he had an understanding with the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, he was ordered suspended and was banned from the court because of a suspicion that he had an understanding with the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led the Takatsukasa family fall under suspicion of understanding with the Choshu clan and Sukehiro was banned from the court and suspended.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>諸大夫の青木吉順は京都町奉行に逮捕された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu AOKI,Shodaibu (courtier) was arrested by the town magistrates of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu AOKI,Shodaibu (courtier) was arrested by the town magistrates of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu AOKI, Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than kugyo) was arrested by the town magistrates of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>慶応2年（1866年）暮れの孝明天皇崩御、および翌慶応3年（1867年）明治天皇（明治天皇）の践祚にともなう大赦により赦免される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a demise of Emperor Komei in December 1866 and Senso (accession) of Emperor Meiji in the following year (1867), he was given remission under an amnesty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a demise of Emperor Komei in December 1866 and Senso (accession) of Emperor Meiji during the following year (1867), he was given remission under an amnesty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a demise of Emperor Komei in January 1867 (December 1866 in old calendar) and Senso (ascend to the throne) of Emperor Meiji in 1867, he was given remission under an amnesty.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にすると年をまたぐため旧暦表示を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし同年12月の王政復古の大号令で摂関職が廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the posts of Sekkan shiki (regents) were abolished in the Restoration of Imperial Rule enacted in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the posts of Sekkan shiki (regents) were abolished in the Restoration of Imperial Rule enacted in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Sekkan shiki (the position of regents and advisers) were abolished in the Decree for the Restoration of Imperial Rule in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>再び参朝を停止させられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the abolishment, he was banned from the court again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the abolishment, he was banned from the court again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the abolishment, he was banned from the court again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ただし、翌月（慶応4年（1868年）正月）には解除され、2月には新政府の議定となり、制度事務局督に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after such a ban was lifted in the next month (January 1868), the new government agreed to appoint him as Captain of institution secretariat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after such a ban was lifted in the next month (January 1868), the new government agreed to appoint him as Captain of institution secretariat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after such a ban was lifted in the next month (January 1868), he assumed the position of gijo (official post) of the new government and appointed as Captain of institution secretariat.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>閏4月には神祇官知事となり、9月には再び議定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the intercalary fourth month of 1868, he assumed governor of Jingikan chiji (Shinto commissioner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the intercalary fourth month of 1868, he assumed governorship of Jingikan chiji (Shinto commissioner).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1868, he assumed the position of governor of Jingikan chiji (Shinto commissioner), and reappointed gijo in October.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>明治2年（1869年）には留守長官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, he took the post of Rusu chokan (chief secretary at absence).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, he took the post of Rusu chokan (chief secretary during his absence).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, he took the post of rusu chokan (a person representing the chief officer during his absence).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>12月、麝香間祗候を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he was assigned to Jako no ma shiko (personal attendant in Jako room) in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he was assigned to Jako no ma shiko (personal attendant in the Jako room) in December.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he was assigned to Jako no ma shiko (emperor&apos;s personal attendant in Jako room) in January 1870 (December in old calendar).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にすると年をまたぐので旧暦表示を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>明治5年（1872年）8月、隠居。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1872, he was retired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1872, he retired.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1872, he retired.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>子の鷹司輔政は早世したため、九条尚忠の子鷹司煕通を養子とし、鷹司家を継がせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his son Sukemasa TAKATSUKASA died young, a son of Hisatada KUJO was adopted into the TAKATSUKASA family to name Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA and succeed the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his son Sukemasa TAKATSUKASA died young, a son of Hisatada KUJO was adopted into the TAKATSUKASA family to name Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA and succeed the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his son Sukemasa TAKATSUKASA died young, Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA, a son of Hisatada KUJO, was adopted and succeed the TAKATSUKASA family.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>同11年（1878年）7月に没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA died in July 1878</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA died in July 1878</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in July 1878.</e>
<cmt>4行目の記述と年月に相違がありますが、原文のまま訳出しています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>享年72。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>嵯峨野の二尊院に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried at Nison-in Temple in Sagano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried at Nison-in Temple in Sagano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried at Nison-in Temple in Sagano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career and job grades</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official Record</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>1817年（文化14年）　元服、叙位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1817, Genpuku ceremony, Joi (investiture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1817, Genpuku ceremony, Joi (investiture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1817: Genpuku ceremony, Joi</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="44">
<j>1818年（文政元年）　従三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1818 Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1818 Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1818: Jusanmi</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="45">
<j>1848年（嘉永元年）　内大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1848, Naidaijin (minister)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1848, Naidaijin (minister)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1848: Naidaijin</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="46">
<j>1849年（嘉永2年）　従一位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1848, Naidaijin (minister)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1848, Naidaijin (minister)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1849: Juichii</e>
<cmt>ウェブより原文、訳文を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="47">
<j>1857年（安政4年）　右大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1857, Udaijin (minister of the right)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857, Udaijin (minister of the right)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1857: Udaijin</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="48">
<j>1859年（安政6年）　辞職、落飾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1859, resignation and becoming a priest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1859, resignation and becoming a priest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1859: Resignation and becoming a priest</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="49">
<j>1862年（文久2年）　復帰、国事御用掛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, Kokuji goyogakari (an official in the government)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862, Kokuji goyogakari (an official in the government)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1862: Returned and assumed the position of Kokuji goyogakari</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="50">
<j>1863年（文久3年）　関白</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1863: Kanpaku</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="51">
<j>1864年（元治元年）　辞職、謹慎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, Resignation and suspension</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, Resignation and suspension</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1864: Resignation and suspension</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DCyokohama(id:26779), BOTarate(id:185620), トホホ川(id:50502), 伏儀(id:142093), TakuyaMurata(id:156), 10cm(id:147838), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>