<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原兼隆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanetaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanetaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanetaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 兼隆（ふじわら の かねたか、 寛和元年（985年）- 天喜元年（1053年））は平安時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanetaka (985 – 1053) was a noble in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanetaka (985 – 1053) was a noble during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanetaka (985–1053) was Kugyo (a Court noble) during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正。「公卿」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>関白藤原道兼の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was born the second son of Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Michikane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the second son of Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Michikane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the second son of Kanpaku (a chief advisor to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Michikane.</e>
<cmt>｢関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原遠量の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetaka&apos;s mother was the daughter of FUJIWRA no Takazu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetaka&apos;s mother was the daughter of FUJIWRA no Takazu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetaka&apos;s mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Takazu.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>妻は源扶義の娘、藤原宣孝の娘（通称大弐三位、母は紫式部）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wives included the daughter of MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi and the daughter of FUJIWARA no Nobutaka (commonly known as Daini no Sanmi and her mother was Murasaki Shikibu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wives included the daughter of MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi and the daughter of FUJIWARA no Nobutaka (commonly known as Daini no Sanmi and her mother was Murasaki Shikibu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wives included the daughter of MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi and the daughter of FUJIWARA no Nobutaka (commonly known as Daini no Sanmi and her mother was Murasaki Shikibu).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に藤原兼房 (中宮亮)らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetaka&apos;s children included FUJIWARA Kanefusa (Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetaka&apos;s children included FUJIWARA Kanefusa (Chugu no suke - Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetaka&apos;s children included FUJIWARA Kanefusa (Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)).</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>正二位、中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Shonii Chunagon (Senior Second Rank, vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>文章のスタイルに修正。「中納言」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>粟田左衛門督と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mnemonic name was Awata saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mnemonic name was Awata saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mnemonic name was Awata saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>福足君と呼ばれた兄が夭折したため、嫡男として育てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his older brother commonly known as福足君 died young, Kanetaka was raised as the heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since his older brother commonly known as福足君 died young, Kanetaka was raised as the heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since his older brother commonly known as Fukutari gimi died young, Kanetaka was raised as the heir.</e>
<cmt>「福足君(ふくたりぎみ)」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>父の道兼は長徳元年（995年）に関白に就任するが、在任僅か二週間にも満たずに急死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Michikane was appointed as Kanpaku (Regent) in 995 but died suddenly in less than 2 weeks of his appointment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Michikane was appointed as Kanpaku (Regent) in 995 but died suddenly in less than 2 weeks after his appointment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Michikane was appointed as Kanpaku in 995 but died suddenly in less than two weeks after his appointment.</e>
<cmt>｢関白」を修正。「二週間」の表記を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、権力の座は叔父の藤原道長に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, power shifted to his uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, power shifted to his uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, power shifted to his uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同じく道長を叔父とする従兄弟の藤原伊周・藤原隆家兄弟はこれに反抗したが、兼隆はそのような動きを見せることなく、以後道長の側近としての道を歩んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korechika and his brother FUJIWARA no Takaie who were also nephews of Michinaga rebelled against their uncle but Kanetaka, showing no such move, pursued his career as Michigana&apos;s close aide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Korechika and his brother FUJIWARA no Takaie, who were also nephews of Michinaga, rebelled against their uncle, but Kanetaka, making no such move, pursued his career as Michigana&apos;s close aide.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korechika and his brother FUJIWARA no Takaie, who were also nephews of Michinaga, rebelled against their uncle, but Kanetaka, making no such move, pursued his career as Michigana&apos;s close aide.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>長保4年（1002年）に従三位右中将に昇任して公卿に列し、寛弘5年（1008年）参議、長和2年（1013年）正三位、寛仁5年（1021年）左衛門督、治安 (元号)3年（1023年）中納言、同4年（1024年）正二位という具合に順調に出世。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1002, Kanetaka was promoted to Jusanmi Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards at Junior Third Rank) joining the ranks, subsequently advancing to Sangi (Councilor) in 1008, Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1013, Saemon no kami Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in 1021, Chunagon in 1023, and Shonii (Senior Second Rank). in 1024 at a steady rate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1002, Kanetaka was promoted to Jusanmi Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards at Junior Third Rank) joining the ranks, subsequently advancing to Sangi (Councilor) in 1008, Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1013, Saemon no kami Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in 1021, Chunagon in 1023, and Shonii (Senior Second Rank). in 1024 at a steady rate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1002, Kanetaka was promoted to Jusanmi Uchujo (Junior Third Rank, Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) joining Kugyo, subsequently advancing to Sangi (Councilor) in 1008, Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1013, Saemon no kami in 1021, Chunagon in 1023, and Shonii in 1024 at a steady rate.</e>
<cmt>｢従三位右中将、公卿、左衛門督、中納言、正二位」を修正。「を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>長元8年（1035年）に中納言を辞任し、寛徳3年（1046年）に出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetaka resigned from the post of Chunagon in 1035 and entered priesthood in 1046.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetaka resigned from the post of Chunagon in 1035 and entered priesthood in 1046.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetaka resigned from the post of Chunagon in 1035 and entered priesthood in 1046.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>藤原実資の日記『小右記』の中では粗暴な一面も描かれており、長和2年（1013年）に自家の厩舎人を殴殺させたこや、その翌年実資の下女の家を破壊、掠奪せしめたことなどが記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The violent side of Kanetaka was described in the journal of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke &quot;Shoyuki&quot; with the related episodes including having Umaya no toneri (stable keeper) at his residence beaten to death in 1013, and destroying and looting the house of Sanesuke&apos;s female servant in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The violent side of Kanetaka was described in the journal of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke &quot;Shoyuki&quot; with the related episodes including having Umaya no toneri (stable keeper) at his residence beaten to death in 1013, and destroying and looting the house of Sanesuke&apos;s female servant in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The violent side of Kanetaka was described in &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) with the related episodes including having Umaya no toneri (stable keeper) at his residence beaten to death in 1013, and destroying and looting the house of Sanesuke&apos;s female servant in the following year.</e>
<cmt>『小右記』を修正。アポストロフィを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また『大鏡』においては、敦明親王の皇太子辞退に関与したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in &quot;Okagami (The Great Mirror),&quot; it is alleged that Kanetaka was instrumental in Imperial Prince Atsuakira&apos;s declining the appointment as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in &quot;Okagami (The Great Mirror),&quot; it is alleged that Kanetaka was instrumental in Imperial Prince Atsuakira&apos;s declining the appointment as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror), it is alleged that Kanetaka was instrumental in Imperial Prince Atsuakira&apos;s declining the appointment as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、後世の系図では宇都宮氏の祖にも擬せられるが、この点については諸説があり必ずしも定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, according to the historical genealogy, Kanetaka was likened to the ascendant of the Utsunomiya Clan but opinion is divided on this account and it is not necessarily certain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, according to the historical genealogy, Kanetaka was likened to the ascendant of the Utsunomiya Clan, but opinion is divided on this account and it is not certain.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, according to the historical genealogy, Kanetaka was likened to the ascendant of the Utsunomiya Clan, but opinion is divided on this account and it is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>