<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐々木高秀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahide SASAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahide SASAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahide SASAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐々木 高秀/京極 高秀（ささき たかひで/きょうごく たかひで）は室町時代初期の守護大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahide SASAKI/Takahide KYOGOKU was a Shugo Daimyo (Territorial Lord as Military Commissioner) during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahide SASAKI/Takahide KYOGOKU was a Shugo Daimyo (Territorial Lord as Military Commissioner) during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahide SASAKI (also known as Takahide KYOGOKU) was a Shugo Daimyo (Territorial Lord as Military Commissioner) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>(also known as Takahide KYOGOKU) に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>嘉暦元年（1328年）、室町幕府の成立に大きく貢献する佐々木道誉の三男として生まれ、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahide was born in 1328 as the third son of Doyo SASAKI, who contributed greatly to the establishment of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahide was born in 1328 as the third son of Doyo SASAKI, who contributed greatly to the establishment of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahide was born in 1328 as the third son of Doyo SASAKI, who contributed greatly to the establishment of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>興国6年/康永4年（1345年）に行われた後醍醐天皇を弔う天龍寺の法要に参列している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attended the memorial service for Emperor Godaigo in 1345 at Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attended the memorial service for Emperor Godaigo in 1345 at Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attended the memorial service for Emperor Godaigo in 1345 at Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>その後、長兄の佐々木秀綱は正平 (日本)8年/文和2年（1353年）に、次兄の佐々木秀宗は正平3年/貞和4年（1348年）にそれぞれ戦死したため、佐々木氏支流京極氏の嗣子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest brother Hidetsuna SASAKI and older brother Hidemune SASAKI died in battle in 1353 and 1348, respectively, leaving him a heir to the Kyogoku clan, the branch family of Sasaki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eldest brother, Hidetsuna SASAKI, and older brother Hidemune SASAKI died in battle in 1353 and 1348, respectively, leaving him heir to the Kyogoku clan, a branch family of the Sasaki clan.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eldest brother, Hidetsuna SASAKI, and older brother Hidemune SASAKI died in battle in 1353 and 1348, respectively, leaving him heir to the Kyogoku clan, a branch family of the Sasaki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>正平16年/康安元年（1361年）には侍所司を務めており、父の諫言により失脚し南朝 (日本)方として京に攻め入ろうとしていた細川清氏と、摂津国忍常寺において500余騎を持って対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1362, he was serving as the Samuraidokoro no Tsukasa (a samurai office), and led a force of some 500 soldiers to the Ninjo-ji Temple in Settsu Province to confront Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, who had lost his position because of his father&apos;s resistance to the bakufu and was on his way to attack Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1362, while serving as Samuraidokoro no Tsukasa (a samurai office), he led a force of some 500 soldiers to Ninjo-ji Temple in Settsu Province to confront Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, who had lost his position because of his father&apos;s resistance to the bakufu and was on his way to attack Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1361, while serving as Samuraidokoro no Tsukasa (a samurai office), he led a force of some 500 soldiers to Ninjo-ji Temple in Settsu Province to confront Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, who had lost his position because of his father&apos;s resistance to the bakufu and was on his way to attack Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>In 1361に訂正しました。スペース削除しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処のため、原文の文末を訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>戦わずにこれを通した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahide let Hosokawa&apos;s force pass by without a fight.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahide let Hosokawa&apos;s force pass by without a fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahide let Hosokawa&apos;s force pass by without a fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>正平20年/貞治4年（1365年）、佐々木氏一門の宗家である六角氏の当主、六角氏頼が唯一の跡取を早世により失ったため、高秀は子の京極高詮を養嗣子として六角氏に出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1365, Ujiyori ROKKAKU, the head of the Sasaki clan, lost his only heir at young age; therefore, Takahide sent Takanori KYOGOKU to be adopted by the Rokkaku family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1365, Ujiyori ROKKAKU, the head of the Sasaki clan, lost his only heir at a young age; therefore, Takahide sent Takanori KYOGOKU to be adopted by the Rokkaku family.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1365, Ujiyori ROKKAKU, the head of the Sasaki clan, lost his only heir at a young age; therefore, Takahide sent Takanori KYOGOKU to be adopted by the Rokkaku family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし氏頼は、四年後に新たに亀寿丸、後の六角満高をもうけ、その翌年には死去してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ujiyori had a son Kamejumaru, later called Mitsutaka ROKKAKU, after adopting Takanori and died the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after adopting Takanori, Ujiyori had a son Kamejumaru, later called Mitsutaka ROKKAKU, and died the following year.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after adopting Takanori, Ujiyori had a son Kamejumaru, later called Mitsutaka ROKKAKU, and died the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このため跡目争いが生じ、細川頼之が管領を務めていた幕府は、高詮に対して、亀寿丸が成人するまでの後見役を命じ、六角氏が代々務めていた近江国守護へと任じて争いを収めるが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This caused a dispute concerning the next heir, and the bakufu, in which Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA was serving as Kanrei (a high political post in feudal Japan) ordered Takanori to be the conservator until Kamejumaru came of age, and appointed him Omi no Kuni Shugo (Military Commissioner of Omi Province) which had been held for generation by the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This caused a dispute concerning the next heir, and the bakufu, in which Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA was serving as Kanrei (a high political post in feudal Japan), ordered Takanori to be the conservator until Kamejumaru came of age, and appointed him Omi no Kuni Shugo (Military Commissioner of Omi Province) which had been held for generations by the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This caused a dispute concerning the next heir, and the bakufu, in which Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA was serving as Kanrei (a high political post in feudal Japan), ordered Takanori to be the conservator until Kamejumaru came of age, and appointed him Omi no kuni Shugo (Military Commissioner of Omi Province) which had been held for generations by the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>Omi no kuni小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>わずか7年後の天授 (日本)3年/永和 (日本)3年（1377年）に高詮は近江守護職を解かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only 7 years later in 1377, Takanori was relieved from his position as Omi no Kuni Shugo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only 7 years later, in 1377, Takanori was relieved from his position as Omi no Kuni Shugo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only 7 years later, in 1377, Takanori was relieved from his position as Omi no kuni Shugo.</e>
<cmt>Omi no kuni小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この一件は高秀と細川頼之との確執を深め、後の康暦の政変へと繋がっていったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident deepened the antagonism between Tahahide and Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, which is considered to have been the root cause of the Koryaku no Seihen (Coup of Koryaku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident deepened the antagonism between Tahahide and Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, which is considered to have been the root cause of the Koryaku no Seihen (Coup of Koryaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident deepened the antagonism between Tahahide and Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, which is considered to have been the root cause of the Koryaku no Seihen (Coup of Koryaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>なおこの間、正平23年/応安元年（1368年）に評定衆へと加わり、従四位下大膳大夫に任ぜられ、文中2年/応安6年（1373年）には父が亡くなり家督を継いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Takahide joined the Hyojo shu (Councilors), was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed Daizen Daibu (Master of the Office of the Palace Table), and when his father died in 1373, he headed the family estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Takahide joined the Hyojo shu (Councilors), was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed Daizen Daibu (Master of the Office of the Palace Table), and when his father died in 1373, he headed the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Takahide joined the Hyojo shu (Councilors) in 1368, was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed Daizen Daibu (Master of the Office of the Palace Table), and when his father died in 1373, he headed the family estate.</e>
<cmt>in 1368補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>天授5年/康暦元年（1379年）に起こった康暦の政変では、美濃国の土岐頼康と共に細川頼之の管領罷免を求め近江で兵を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Koryaku no Seihen that occurred in 1379, he sought post of Kanrei along with Yoriyasu TOKI of Mino Province, and formed a force in Omi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Koryaku no Seihen that occurred in 1379, he sought the post of Kanrei along with Yoriyasu TOKI of Mino Province, and formed a force in Omi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Koryaku no Seihen that occurred in 1379, he sought the post of Kanrei along with Yoriyasu TOKI of Mino Province, and formed a force in Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>征夷大将軍足利義満から追討令を受けた六角氏と近江で戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They fought against the Rokkaku clan force sent by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), to search and kill Takahide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They fought against the Rokkaku clan force sent by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), to search and kill Takahide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They fought against the Rokkaku clan force sent by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), to search and kill Takahide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そうした中、鎌倉公方の足利氏満も反乱の構えを見せたため、恐れをなした義満は高秀らを許し、高秀は京に上り服従を誓う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, seeing that Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Kamakura Kubo (the shogunal headquarters in Kamakura) also intended to revolt, Yoshimitsu forgave Takahide&apos;s group and Takahide pledge to follow shogun order in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, seeing that Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Kamakura Kubo (the shogunal headquarters in Kamakura), also intended to revolt, Yoshimitsu forgave Takahide&apos;s group and Takahide pledged to follow shogun orders in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, seeing that Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, the Kamakura Kubo (the shogunal headquarters in Kamakura), also intended to revolt, Yoshimitsu forgave Takahide&apos;s group and Takahide pledged to follow shogun orders in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その翌日、斯波義将、土岐頼康らと共に大軍で花の御所を包囲し、再び頼之の罷免を迫り成し遂げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On day following, however, Takahide formed a huge force with Yoshiyuki (Yoshimasa) SHIBA and Yoriyasu TOKI, surrounded Hana no Gosho (Flower Palace), and succeeded in removing Yoriyuki once again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the day following, however, Takahide formed a huge force with Yoshiyuki (Yoshimasa) SHIBA and Yoriyasu TOKI, surrounded Hana no Gosho (Flower Palace), and succeeded in removing Yoriyuki once again.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the day following, however, Takahide formed a huge force with Yoshiyuki (Yoshimasa) SHIBA and Yoriyasu TOKI, surrounded Hana no Gosho (Flower Palace), and succeeded in removing Yoriyuki once again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>元中7年/明徳元年（1390年）に義満の命により、美濃国の土岐康行を討ち、翌年の元中8年/明徳2年（1391年）に64歳で亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1390, on the orders of Yorimitsu, Takahide subjugated Yasuyuki TOKI of Mino Province, and the year after, in 1391, he died at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1390, on the orders of Yorimitsu, Takahide subjugated Yasuyuki TOKI of Mino Province, and the year after, in 1391, he died at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1390, on the orders of Yoshimitsu, Takahide subjugated Yasuyuki TOKI of Mino Province, and the year after, in 1391, he died at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>YorimitsuをYoshimitsuに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>和歌を好み新千載和歌集、新拾遺和歌集、新後拾遺和歌集に入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He loved Waka poetry and some of his poems are included in the &quot;Shin Senzai Wakashu,&quot; &quot;Shin Shui Wakashu&quot; and &quot;Shin Goshui Wakashu&quot; collections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He loved Waka poetry, and some of his poems are included in the &quot;Shin Senzai Wakashu,&quot; &quot;Shin Shui Wakashu,&quot; and &quot;Shin Goshui Wakashu&quot; collections.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He loved Waka poetry, and some of his poems are included in the &quot;Shin Senzai Wakashu,&quot; &quot;Shin Shui Wakashu,&quot; and &quot;Shin Goshui Wakashu&quot; collections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>長男の京極高詮を嫡子とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His oldest son Takanori KYOGOKU was his successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His oldest son, Takanori KYOGOKU, was his successor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His oldest son, Takanori KYOGOKU, was his successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>三男の尼子高久には近江国尼子郷を与え、高久は後に出雲国の戦国大名となる尼子氏の祖となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He awarded his third son, Takahisa AMAGO Amago-go, Omi Province and Takahisa became the patriarch of the Amago clan, and he later became daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period of Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He awarded his third son, Takahisa AMAGO Amago-go, Omi Province, and Takahisa became the patriarch of the Amago clan and later became daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) of Izumo Province in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He awarded his third son, Takahisa AMAGO Amago-go, Omi Province, and Takahisa became the patriarch of the Amago clan and later became daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) of Izumo Province in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Oxhop(id:2551), Yonoemon(id:55450), Nnh(id:474), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 俊(id:14924), 水野白楓(id:22811), UMBRO(id:100484), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>