<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原道兼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michikane</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michikane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michikane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 道兼（ふじわら の みちかね、応和元年（961年）-長徳元年5月8日 (旧暦)（995年6月13日））は、平安時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michikane (961 - June 13, 995) was a court noble in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michikane (961 - June 13, 995) was a court noble in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michikane (961 - June 13, 995) was a court noble in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原兼家の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原中正女時姫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Tokihime, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nakamasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Tokihime, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nakamasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Tokihime, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nakamasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同母の兄弟姉妹に藤原道隆、藤原道長、藤原超子、藤原詮子がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His siblings by the same mother were FUJIWARA no Michitaka, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, FUJIWARA no Choshi, and FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His siblings by the same mother were FUJIWARA no Michitaka, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, FUJIWARA no Choshi, and FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His siblings by the same mother were FUJIWARA no Michitaka, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, FUJIWARA no Choshi, and FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>別称は、粟田殿、二条殿、町尻殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Awata dono, Nijo dono, and Machijiri dono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Awata dono, Nijo dono, and Machijiri dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Awata dono, Nijo dono, and Machijiri dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>父兼家の意を受けて花山天皇を唆して出家退位させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He induced Emperor Kazan to take the tonsure and abdicate under his father Kaneie&apos;s instructions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under his father Kaneie&apos;s instructions, he induced Emperor Kazan to take the tonsure and abdicate.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under his father Kaneie&apos;s instructions, he induced Emperor Kazan to take the tonsure and abdicate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一条天皇が即位すると外祖父の兼家は摂政となり、道兼も栄達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the accession of Emperor Ichijo, the Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather Kaneie became sessho (Regent) and Michikane was also raised to a higher rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the accession of Emperor Ichijo, the Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather Kaneie became sessho (Regent) and Michikane was also promoted to a higher rank.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the accession of Emperor Ichijo, the Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather Kaneie became sessho (Regent) and Michikane was also promoted to a higher rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>兼家が死去すると道兼の期待に反して長兄の道隆が関白となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kaneie died, Michikane&apos;s eldest brother Michitaka became kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor) contrary to Michikane&apos;s expectation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kaneie died, Michikane&apos;s eldest brother Michitaka became kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor), contrary to Michikane&apos;s expectation.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kaneie died, Michikane&apos;s eldest brother Michitaka became kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor), contrary to Michikane&apos;s expectation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>5年後に道隆が病死すると、待望の関白になるが、その僅か数日後に病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Michitaka died of illness five years later, Michikane accepted the long-awaited appointment to kanpaku but died of illness only several days later the assumption of office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Michitaka died of illness five years later, Michikane accepted the long-awaited appointment to kanpaku but died of illness only several days after assuming the office.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Michitaka died of illness five years later, Michikane accepted the long-awaited appointment to kanpaku but died of illness only several days after assuming the office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため「七日関白」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was thus nicknamed the &apos;Nanuka Kanpaku&apos; (Seven Day Regent.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was thus nicknamed the &apos;Nanuka Kanpaku&apos; (Seven Day Regent.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was thus nicknamed the &apos;Nanoka Kanpaku&apos; (Seven Day Regent).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>藤原北家の藤原兼家の三男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the third son of the FUJIWARA no Kaneie of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the third son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the third son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>雄傑で鬚が多く、狷介な性格だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michikane was a host in himself and an obstinate man with a heavy beard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michikane was a host in himself and an obstinate man with a heavy beard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michikane was a great and obstinate man with a heavy beard.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。(check欄に記載されていたコメントは「trans2」「comment」に続けてコピーしました（太字部分））</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>永観2年（984年）8月、花山天皇が即位すると蔵人左少弁となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 984, when Emperor Kazan ascended the throne, Michikane became kurodo no sashoben (chamberlain, minor controller of the left.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 984, when Emperor Kazan ascended the throne, Michikane became kurodo no sashoben (chamberlain, minor controller of the left.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 984, when Emperor Kazan ascended the throne, Michikane became kurodo no sashoben (Court Rank, caring food, clothe and house of Emperor).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>東宮（皇太子）には父兼家の娘の詮子を母とする一条天皇が立てられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Crown Prince (the Prince Imperial), Emperor Ichijo whose mother was Senshi, a daughter of Michikane&apos;s father Kaneie, was named.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Ichijo, whose mother was Senshi, a daughter of Michikane&apos;s father Kaneie, was named the Crown Prince (the Prince Imperial).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Ichijo, whose mother was Senshi, a daughter of Michikane&apos;s father Kaneie, was named Togu (the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>花山天皇は兼家の亡兄伊尹の娘の藤原懐子を母としており、伊尹の子の権中納言藤原義懐が天皇を補佐して朝政を執った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kazan&apos;s mother was FUJIWARA no Kaishi, a daughter of Kaneie&apos;s elder brother the deceased Koretada, thereby Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, a son of Koretada, governed the Imperial Court by assisting the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kazan&apos;s mother was FUJIWARA no Kaishi, a daughter of Kaneie&apos;s elder brother, the deceased Koretada, whereby Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, a son of Koretada, governed the Imperial Court by assisting the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kazan&apos;s mother was FUJIWARA no Kaishi, a daughter of Kaneie&apos;s elder brother, the deceased Koretada, whereby Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, a son of Koretada, governed the Imperial Court by assisting the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このため、兼家は懐仁親王の早期の即位を望んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the circumstances, Kaneie earnestly desired early enthronement of Imperial Prince Yasuhito (also known as Kanehito.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the circumstances, Kaneie earnestly desired early enthronement of Imperial Prince Yasuhito (also known as Kanehito.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the circumstances, Kaneie earnestly desired early enthronement of Imperial Prince Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>花山天皇は情緒的な性格で、寵愛していた女御藤原忯子が死去すると深く嘆き、思い悩むようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kazan was so emotional that he was grief-stricken and depressed over the death of FUJIWARA no Shishi, his beloved nyogo (high rank lady serving at court.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kazan was so emotional that he was grief-stricken and depressed over the death of FUJIWARA no Shishi, his beloved nyogo (high rank lady serving at court.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kazan was so emotional that he was grief-stricken and depressed over the death of FUJIWARA no Shishi, his beloved nyogo (high rank lady serving at court).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>蔵人として近侍していた道兼は元慶寺（花山寺）の厳久とともに仏の教えを説き、出家を勧めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michikane, who attended upon Emperor Kazan as kurodo, expounded the teachings of Buddha to the Emperor with Genkyu of the Gankei-ji Temple (Kazan-ji Temple) and induced the Emperor to take the tonsure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michikane, who attended upon Emperor Kazan as kurodo, expounded the teachings of Buddha to the Emperor with Genkyu of the Gankei-ji Temple (Kazan-ji Temple) and induced the Emperor to take the tonsure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michikane, who attended upon Emperor Kazan as kurodo, expounded the teachings of Buddha to the Emperor with Genkyu of the Gankei-ji Temple (also known as Kazan-ji Temple) and induced the Emperor to take the tonsure.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>道兼がともに出家することを約束すると天皇もその気になってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Michikane promised Emperor Kazan to take the tonsure with him, the Emperor got serious about that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Michikane promised Emperor Kazan to take the tonsure with him, the Emperor became serious about it.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Michikane promised Emperor Kazan to take the tonsure with him, the Emperor became serious about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>寛和2年（986年）6月23日丑の刻、道兼は花山天皇を密かに内裏から抜け出させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At two o&apos;clock in the morning of August 6, 986, Michikane led Emperor Kazan to slip out of the dairi (the Imperial Palace precincts.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At two o&apos;clock in the morning of August 6, 986, Michikane led Emperor Kazan to slip out of the dairi (the Imperial Palace precincts.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At two o&apos;clock in the morning of August 6, 986, Michikane led Emperor Kazan to slip out of the dairi (the Imperial Palace precincts).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>道兼は天皇が途中で足を止めるのをかき口説き、山科区の元慶寺まで連れてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor wavered on the way to the Gankei-ji Temple, Michikane persuaded the Emperor to go on the way and managed to take the Emperor to the Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Emperor wavered on the way to the Gankei-ji Temple, Michikane persuaded the Emperor to continue and managed to take the Emperor to the Temple.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Emperor wavered on the way to the Gankei-ji Temple in Yamashina Ward, Michikane persuaded the Emperor to continue and managed to take the Emperor to the Temple.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>天皇は厳久に戒を受けて剃髪した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor accepted the basic Buddhist precepts from Genkyu and took the tonsure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor accepted the basic Buddhist precepts from Genkyu and took the tonsure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor accepted the basic Buddhist precepts from Genkyu and took the tonsure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ところが、道兼は「父に告げずに出家すれば不幸になると思い立ちました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the last moment, Michikane said &apos;It occurred to me that if I take the tonsure without telling it to my father, I will suffer some kind of retribution for the sin of having deceived my father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the last moment, Michikane said &apos;It occurred to me that if I take the tonsure without telling my father, I will suffer some kind of retribution for the sin of having deceived my father.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the last moment, Michikane said &apos;It occurred to me that if I take the tonsure without telling my father, I will suffer some kind of retribution for the sin of having deceived my father.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>父に別れを告げ、出家前の姿を一目見せたいと思います」と言うや、寺から立ち去ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I decided to see my father to bid farewell for the last time as a layman.&apos; and executed himself and went home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He said, &quot; I&apos;ve decided to see my father to bid farewell for the last time as a layman&quot; and excused himself and went home.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He said, &apos;I&apos;ve decided to see my father to bid farewell for the last time as a layman&apos; and excused himself and went home.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>天皇は騙されたと知るが、すでに手遅れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor realized that he was deceived, but it was too late.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor realized that he had been deceived, but it was too late.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor realized that he had been deceived, but it was too late.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>一方、宮中では兼家と兄の道隆が東宮の即位の準備を手早く済ませていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Michikane&apos;s father Kaneie and elder brother Michitaka had promptly prepared for the enthronement of the Crown Prince in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Michikane&apos;s father Kaneie and elder brother Michitaka had promptly prepared for the enthronement of the Crown Prince in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Michikane&apos;s father Kaneie and elder brother Michitaka had promptly prepared for the enthronement of the Togu in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>翌朝、義懐と左中弁藤原惟成が元慶寺に駆けつけるが、出家した天皇の姿を見て絶望し、彼らも出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next morning, Yoshichika and Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) FUJIWARA no Koreshige (or Korenari) rushed to the Gankei-ji Temple only to find the tonsured Emperor, and they also tonsured in despair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next morning, Yoshichika and Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) FUJIWARA no Koreshige (or Korenari) rushed to Gankei-ji Temple only to find the tonsured Emperor, and they also tonsured in despair.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next morning, Yoshichika and Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) FUJIWARA no Koreshige (or Korenari) rushed to Gankei-ji Temple only to find the tonsured Emperor, and they also tonsured in despair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>幼い懐仁親王が即位（一条天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Yasuhito ascended the throne (as Emperor Ichijo) at an early age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Yasuhito ascended the throne (as Emperor Ichijo) at an early age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Yasuhito ascended the throne (as Emperor Ichijo) at an early age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>外祖父の兼家は摂政に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather Kaneie was appointed to the office of sessho (Regent).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather, Kaneie, was appointed to the office of sessho (Regent).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather, Kaneie, was appointed to the office of sessho (Regent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>兼家の息子たちも昇進させられ、功労者の道兼は同年7月参議となったのを皮切りに、10月には従三位権中納言。11月、正三位、永延元年（987年）従二位、永祚 (日本)2年（989年）正二位権大納言と累進を重ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie&apos;s sons were also raised to higher ranks -- among others, Michikane who contributed to the enthronement was raised to higher ranks successively, starting at raised to sangi (Councillor) in August of the same year, further to Jusanmi Gon Chunagon (Junior Third Rank, Provisional Middle Counselor) in November, to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in December, to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 987, and to Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional Major Counselor) in 989.</e>
<cmt>「10月には従三位権中納言。」の句点で文章が区切られ、次のセルに移行しておりますが、この句点の後「11月、正三位、」と文章は続いておりますので、一つの文章としてセルをまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie&apos;s sons were also promoted to higher ranks -- among others, Michikane, who had contributed to the enthronement, was promoted to higher ranks successively, starting at promotion to sangi (Councillor) in August of the same year, further to Jusanmi Gon Chunagon (Junior Third Rank, Provisional Middle Counselor) in November, to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in December, to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 987, and to Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional Major Counselor) in 989.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie&apos;s sons were also promoted to higher ranks; among others, Michikane, who had contributed to the enthronement, was promoted to higher ranks successively, starting at promotion to sangi (Councilor) in August of the same year, further to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) in November, to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in December, to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 987, and to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state) in 989.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>正暦元年（990年）兼家が病んだのち死去すると、後任の関白には長兄の道隆が任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 990, when Kaneie fell ill and died, Michitaka, the eldest brother of Michikane, was appointed as successor to the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 990, when Kaneie fell ill and died, Michitaka, the eldest brother of Michikane, was appointed successor to the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 990, when Kaneie fell ill and died, Michitaka, the eldest brother of Michikane, was appointed successor to the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>『大鏡』によると、自分は父に功があったのだから、当然に関白を継ぐべきだと望んでいたのに道隆が後継に選ばれたことを甚だ憎み、父の喪中であるにもかかわらず客を集めては遊興にふけったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, the Great Mirror; a historical tale), Michikane resented the Michitaka&apos;s succession to his father against his reasonable expectation of following his father as kanpaku because of the services he had rendered to his father, and pursued pleasures by inviting guests even though he was in mourning for his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, the Great Mirror; a historical tale), Michikane resented Michitaka&apos;s succession to his father against his reasonable expectation of following his father as kanpaku because of the services he had rendered to his father, and pursued pleasures by inviting guests even though he was in mourning for his father.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror), Michikane resented Michitaka&apos;s succession to his father against his reasonable expectation of following his father as kanpaku because of the services he had rendered to his father, and pursued pleasures by inviting guests even though he was in mourning for his father.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="33">
<j>道隆の政権下で、同2年（991年）内大臣、同5年（994年）右大臣へと進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Michitaka&apos;s administration, Michikane elevated to naidaijin (Minister of the Center) in 991 and to udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 994.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Michitaka&apos;s administration, Michikane was elevated to naidaijin (Minister of the Center) in 991 and to udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 994.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Michitaka&apos;s administration, Michikane was elevated to naidaijin (Minister of the Center) in 991 and to udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 994.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>長徳元年（995年）兄の関白道隆が重い病に伏した、道隆は後継の関白に嫡男の内大臣藤原伊周を望むがこれは許されず、4月10日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 995, when Michikane&apos;s elder brother, kanpaku Michitaka fell seriously ill, Michitaka wanted his legitimate son naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika to succeed him as kanpaku, but it was not allowed and he died on May 17.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 995, when Michikane&apos;s elder brother, kanpaku Michitaka, fell seriously ill, Michitaka wanted his legitimate son naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika to succeed him as kanpaku, but this was not allowed and he died on May 17.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 995, when Michikane&apos;s elder brother, kanpaku Michitaka, fell seriously ill, Michitaka wanted his legitimate son naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika to succeed him as kanpaku, but this was not allowed and he died on May 17.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>4月27日に道兼は関白宣下を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 3, Michikane was raised by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 3, Michikane was promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 3, Michikane was promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>ところが、ほどなく道兼は病になり、5月8日に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironically, though, Michikane succumbed to illness before long and died on June 13.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironically, though, Michikane succumbed to illness before long and died on June 13.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironically, though, Michikane succumbed to illness before long and died on June 13.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>世に「七日関白」（在任は7日ではない、一説には宮廷に関白として初参内してから7日目であったからだともいう。なお、道兼は関白在任中に1度だけ陣定を開催している）と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michikane was called &apos;Nanuka Kanpaku&apos; (Seven Day Regent) (although Michikane&apos;s tenure was not seven days. According to a source, he died on the seventh day from his first visit to the Imperial Palace as kanpaku. Incidentally, Michikane held Jin no sadame (official aristocratic council held at the headquarters of the inner palace guard) only once in his tenure.)</e>
<cmt>セルB41と同様に、「7日目であったからだともいう。」の句点で文章が区切られ、次のセルに移行しておりますが、この句点の後「なお、道兼は」と文章は続いておりますので、一つの文章としてセルをまとめました。また、「七日関白」は初出ではありませんが、7日の説明として最初の場所であることを考慮し、念のためセルD14と同様の英訳を括弧内に示しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michikane was called &apos;Nanuka Kanpaku&apos; (Seven Day Regent) (Although Michikane&apos;s tenure was not seven days; according to a source, he died on the seventh day from his first visit to the Imperial Palace as kanpaku. Incidentally, Michikane held Jin no sadame (official aristocratic council held at the headquarters of the inner palace guard) only once in his tenure.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michikane was called &apos;Nanoka Kanpaku&apos; (Although Michikane&apos;s tenure was not seven days; according to a source, he died on the seventh day from his first visit to the Imperial Palace as kanpaku. Incidentally, Michikane held Jin no sadame (official aristocratic council held at the headquarters of the inner palace guard) only once in his tenure.)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>死後、正一位太政大臣を追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was posthumously conferred Shoichii Dajo Daijin (Senior First Rank, General Minister of state.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously conferred Shoichii Dajo Daijin (Senior First Rank, General Minister of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously conferred Shoichii (Senior First Rank) Dajo Daijin (General Minister of state).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>子女には、宇都宮氏の祖となった中納言藤原兼隆、一条天皇の女御となった藤原尊子がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children are Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Kanetaka who was to found the Utsunomiya clan, and FUJIWARA no Takako who was to become nyogo(consort) of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Kanetaka, who was to found the Utsunomiya clan, and FUJIWARA no Takako, who was to become nyogo (consort) of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Kanetaka, who was to found the Utsunomiya clan, and FUJIWARA no Takako, who was to become nyogo (consort) of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Record of office and rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Record of office and rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of Office and Rank</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>天延3年（975年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 975</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 975</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">975</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>1月7日 (旧暦)：従五位下に叙位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 25: Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 25: Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 25: Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>天元 (日本)2年（979年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 979</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 979</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">979</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>12月2日 (旧暦)：侍従に任官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 28: Installed as palace staff.</e>
<cmt>後述の蔵人と訳し分けるためにpalace staffとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 28: Installed as member of palace staff.</e>
<cmt>inserted &quot;member of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 28: Installed as member of palace staff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>天元3年（980年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 980</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 980</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">980</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>昇殿を許される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Granted shoden (access to the administration chambers in the Seiryo den Hall in the imperial court.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Granted shoden (access to the administration chambers in the Seiryo den Hall in the imperial court.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Granted shoden (access to the administration chambers in the Seiryo den Hall in the imperial court).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>天元6年（983年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 983</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 983</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">983</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>1月27日 (旧暦)：弾正少弼に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 19: Transferred to danjo-shohitsu (junior assistant President of the Board of Censors.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 19: Reassigned as danjo-shohitsu (junior assistant President of the Board of Censors.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 19: Reassigned as danjo-shohitsu (junior assistant President of the Board of Censors).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>永観2年（984年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 984</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 984</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">984</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>1月10日 (旧暦)：蔵人に補任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19: Appointed to the office of kurodo (Chamberlain.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 19: Appointed to the office of kurodo (Chamberlain.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19: Appointed to the office of kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>8月25日 (旧暦)：従五位上に昇叙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 27: Raised to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 27: Promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 27: Promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>8月27日 (旧暦)：新帝（花山天皇）蔵人に補任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 29: Appointed to the office of kurodo of the new Emperor (Emperor Kazan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 29: Appointed to the office of kurodo of the new Emperor (Emperor Kazan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 29: Appointed to the office of kurodo of the new Emperor (Emperor Kazan).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>10月10日 (旧暦)：正五位下に昇叙し、蔵人如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 10: Raised to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as remained in the position of kurodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 10: Promoted to noge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as retained the position of kurodo.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 10: Promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as retained the position of kurodo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>10月30日 (旧暦)：左少弁に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 30: Appointed to Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 30: Appointed to Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 30: Appointed to Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>蔵人如元か?</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether remained in the office of kurodo or not is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether or not he retained the office of kurodo is unknown.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether or not he retained the office of kurodo is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="56">
<j>寛和2年（986年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 986</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 986</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">986</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>6月23日 (旧暦)：蔵人頭に補任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 6: Appointed to the office of kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 6: Appointed to the office of kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 6: Appointed to the office of kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>7月5日 (旧暦)：従四位下に昇叙し、蔵人頭如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 17: Raised to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) as remained in the office of kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 17: Promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) as retained the office of kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 17: Promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) as retained his position as kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>7月16日 (旧暦)：右近衛権中将に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 28: Appointed to the office of Ukonoe no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 28: Appointed to the office of Ukonoe no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 28: Appointed to the office of Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>蔵人頭如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the office of kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the office of kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="61">
<j>7月20日 (旧暦)：参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 1: Appointed to the office of sangi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 1: Appointed to the office of sangi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1: Appointed to the office of sangi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="63">
<j>8月13日 (旧暦)：美作権守を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 24: Served concurrently as Mimasaka gon no kami (provisional governor of Mimasaka Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 24: Assigned additional post of Mimasaka gon no kami (provisional governor of Mimasaka Province.)</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 24: Assigned additional post of Mimasaka gon no kami (provisional governor of Mimasaka Province).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>10月15日 (旧暦)：従三位に昇叙し、権中納言に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 24: Raised to Jusanmi and transferred to Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 24: Promoted to Jusanmi and reassigned to position of Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 24: Promoted to Jusanmi and reassigned to position of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>11月22日 (旧暦)：正三位に昇叙し、権中納言如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 30: Raised to Shosanmi as remained in the office of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 30: Promoted to Shosanmi as retained the office of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 30: Promoted to Shosanmi as retained his position as Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>寛和3年（987年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 987</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 987</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">987</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>11月11日 (旧暦)：従二位に昇叙し、権中納言如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 9: Raised to Junii as remained in the position of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 9: Promoted to Junii and retained the position of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 9: Promoted to Junii and retained his position as Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>永延3年改元して永祚 (日本)元年（989年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 989 (the era name was changed from Eien to Eiso.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 989 (era name changed from Eien to Eiso.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">989</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>2月23日 (旧暦)：権大納言に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 6: Transferred to Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 6: Reassigned to position of Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 6: Reassigned to position of Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>3月4日 (旧暦)：皇太后宮（藤原兼家の娘、藤原詮子）大夫を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 17: Served concurrently as Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household (Empress Dowager was FUJIWARA no Senshi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 17: Assigned additional post of Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household (Empress Dowager was FUJIWARA no Senshi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.))</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 17: Assigned additional position of Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household (Empress Dowager was FUJIWARA no Senshi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kaneie)).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>4月5日 (旧暦)：正二位に昇叙し、権大納言・皇太后宮大夫如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 17: Raised to Shonii as remained in the offices of Gon Dainagon and Kotaigo gu no daibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 17: Promoted to Shonii and retained offices of Gon Dainagon and Kotaigo gu no daibu</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 17: Promoted to Shonii and retained his position as Gon Dainagon and Kotaigo gu no daibu</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>永祚2年改元して正暦元年（990年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 990 (the era name was changed from Eiso to Shoryaku.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 990 (era name changed from Eiso to Shoryaku.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">990</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>6月10日 (旧暦)：右近衛大将を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 9: Served concurrently as Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 9: Assigned additional duty of Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 9: Assigned additional duty of Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>正暦2年（991年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 991</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 991</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">991</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>9月7日 (旧暦)：内大臣に転任し、右近衛大将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 22: Transferred to naidaijin as remained in the office of Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 22: Reassigned to post of to naidaijin and retained the office of Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 22: Reassigned to position of to naidaijin and retained his position as Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>正暦5年（994年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 994</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 994</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">994</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>8月28日 (旧暦)：右大臣に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 10: Transferred to Udaijin (Minister of the Right.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 10: Reassigned to post of Udaijin (Minister of the Right.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 10: Reassigned to position of Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>9月7日：右近衛大将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 19: Remained in the office of Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 19: Retained the office of Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 19: Retained his position as Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>正暦6年改元して長徳元年（995年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 995 (the era name was changed from Shoryaku to Chotoku.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 995 (era name changed from Shoryaku to Chotoku.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">995</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>4月27日 (旧暦)：関白宣下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 3: Raised by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 3: Promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 3: Promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>4月28日 (旧暦)：藤氏長者宣下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 4: Raised by Imperial edict to Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 4: Promoted by Imperial edict to Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 4: Promoted by Imperial edict to Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>5月8日 (旧暦)：薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 3: Died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 13: Died.</e>
<cmt>changed datecheck date; trans 1 says June 3, previously (D51) stated as June 13</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 13: Died.</e>
<cmt>(check欄に記載されていたコメントは「trans2」「comment」に続けてコピーしました（太字部分））</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>享年43</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="84">
<j>5月25日 (旧暦)：贈正一位太政大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 30: Posthumously conferred Shoichii Dajo Daijin (Senior First Rank Grand Minister.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 30: Posthumously conferred Shoichii Dajo Daijin (Senior First Rank Grand Minister.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 30: Posthumously conferred Shoichii Dajo Daijin (Senior First Rank Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Lonicera(id:20638), Nnh(id:474), China(id:10362), Novo(id:87875), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), 水野白楓(id:22811), 三浦大輔(id:93377), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), 伊集院聖(id:53199), YurikBot(id:18605), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), NPD(id:58640), Point136(id:211299), 伏儀(id:142093), Junger(id:10282), 小川尚明(id:93076), Kouko0515(id:100370), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>