<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>細川澄元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumimoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>細川 澄元（ほそかわ　すみもと）は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was a war lord and daimyo in the Period of Warring States of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Warring States period よりは Period を前におきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was a war lord and daimyo during the Warring States Period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot;→&quot;during&quot;Deleted &quot;of Japan&quot;Moved &quot;Period&quot; - I think this is more common than &quot;Period of Warring States&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was a war lord and daimyo during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→the Sengoku period (period of warring states)[用語統一のため]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>細川政元の養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an adopted son of Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an adopted son of Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an adopted son of Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>細川晴元の父に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>相伴衆の格式であった阿波細川氏（下屋形）の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Awa HOSOKAWA Clan (based in Shimoyakata), which had the rank of Shobanshu, one of important ranks in the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Awa HOSOKAWA Clan (based in Shimoyakata), which held the rank of Shobanshu, an important rank in the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>&quot;had&quot;→&quot;held&quot;&quot;one of&quot;→&quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Awa HOSOKAWA Clan (based in Shimoyakata), which held the rank of Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun).</e>
<cmt>阿波細川氏→the Awa Hosokawa clan相伴衆→Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>延徳元年（1489年）、細川義春の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born to Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA in 1489.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born to Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA in 1489.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born to Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA in 1489.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>父・義春は阿波国守護であったが、早世していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Yoshiharu was a Shugo of the Awa Province but died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Yoshiharu, was the Shugo of Awa Province but died young.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Yoshiharu, was the Shugo of Awa Province but died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このため祖父の細川成之に養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he was raised by his grandfather Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently he was raised by his grandfather, Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Then&quot;→&quot;Subsequently&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently he was raised by his grandfather, Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>当時、管領として幕政を牛耳っていた細川政元には実子が無く、九条家から養子に迎えた細川澄之を家督継承者に定めていたが、これを廃嫡し、文亀3年（1503年）5月に養子として迎えられた澄元が家督継承者に指名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who controlled the shogunate government as Kanrei in those days, had an adopted son Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA from the KUJO Family as the successor of Kanrei as he had no biological child, but disinherited Sumiyuki and newly adopted Sumimoto as the heir to the family title in May 1503.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The childless Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who at the time controlled the shogunate government as Kanrei, had adopted Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA from the KUJO Clan to be his successor but in May 1503, he disinherited Sumiyuki and adopted Sumimoto as the heir to the family title.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in those days&quot;→&quot;at the time&quot;&quot;he had no biological child&quot;→&quot;the childless&quot;Deleted &quot;an&quot;, &quot;son&quot;&quot;Family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;&quot;as the&quot;→&quot;to be his&quot;Moved dateDeleted &quot;newly&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The childless Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who at the time controlled the shogunate government as Kanrei (shogunal deputy), had adopted Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA from the Kujo clan to be his successor but in May 1503, he disinherited Sumiyuki and adopted Sumimoto as the heir to the family title.</e>
<cmt>管領、説明補足→kanrei (shogunal deputy)the KUJO Clan→the Kujo clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ところが、これが原因で澄之・澄元は家督をめぐって抗争するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this caused conflicts between Sumiyuki and Sumimoto about who to succeed the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this caused conflict between Sumiyuki and Sumimoto over who should be family head.</e>
<cmt>&quot;But&quot;→&quot;However&quot;Deleted &quot;s&quot;&quot;about&quot;→&quot;over&quot;&quot;to succeed the family&quot;→&quot;should be family head&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this caused conflict between Sumiyuki and Sumimoto over who should be family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>永正3年（1506年）から永正4年（1507年）にかけて、政元の命令で澄之と共に丹後国の一色義有を攻めたが、敗北している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1506 to 1507, Sumimoto attacked Yoshinari ISSHIKI of the Tango Province together with Sumiyuki at the order of Masamoto but lost in the attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1506 to 1507, under Masamoto&apos;s orders, Sumimoto and Sumiyaki attacked Yoshinari ISSHIKI of Tango Province but were defeated.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderDeleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;lost in the attack&quot;→&quot;were defeated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1506 to 1507, under Masamoto&apos;s orders, Sumimoto and Sumiyaki attacked Yoshinari ISSHIKI of Tango Province but were defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>永正4年（1507年）6月23日、政元が香西元長や薬師寺長忠ら澄之の支持者によって暗殺されると、6月24日には澄元も澄之の家臣に屋敷を襲われ、三好之長と共に近江国甲賀に逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 23, 1507, Masamoto was assassinated by the supporters of Sumiyuki, such as Motonaga KOZAI or Nagatada YAKUSHIJI, and the vassals of Sumiyuki then attacked the residence of Sumimoto, but Sumimoto survived the attack and escaped to Koga in the Omi Province together with Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 23, 1507, Masamoto was assassinated by Sumiyuki&apos;s supporters, including Motonaga KOZAI and Nagatada YAKUSHIJI, and on June 24, Sumiyuki&apos;s vassals attacked the residence of Sumimoto, who managed to escape to Koga in Omi Province together with Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;such as&quot;→&quot;including&quot;&quot;or&quot;→&quot;and&quot;&quot;but Sumimoto survived the attack and escaped&quot;→&quot;who managed to escape&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 11, 1507, Masamoto was assassinated by Sumiyuki&apos;s supporters, including Motonaga KOZAI and Nagatada YAKUSHIJI, and on August 12, Sumiyuki&apos;s vassals attacked the residence of Sumimoto, who managed to escape to Koga in Omi Province together with Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして近江の国人の力を借りて勢力を盛り返し、8月1日には京都に侵攻して澄之とその支持者を討ち取り、8月2日には第11代将軍・足利義澄に対して細川家の家督継承を承認させたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having regained the power with the help of Omi residents, Sumimoto entered Kyoto on August 1, killed Sumiyuki and his supporters and had the 11th Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA approve his inheritance of the HOSOKAWA Family on August 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having regained strength with the help of Omi residents, Sumimoto entered Kyoto on August 1, killed Sumiyuki and his supporters and, on August 2, had the 11th Shogun, Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, approve his inheritance of the HOSOKAWA Clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the power&quot;→&quot;strength&quot;Moved dates&quot;Family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having regained strength with the help of Omi residents, Sumimoto entered Kyoto on September 17, killed Sumiyuki and his supporters and, on September 18, had the eleventh Shogun, Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, approve his inheritance of the HOSOKAWA Clan.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に11th→ eleventhClan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>ところが澄元は若年だったため、家宰であった三好之長の実力が逆に大きくなり始め、澄元は之長と対立して一時は阿波に帰国しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But since Sumimoto was still young, his regent Yukinaga MIYOSHI became more powerful, and that made him become antagonistic to Yukinaga and temporarily think of returning to Awa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Sumimoto&apos;s youth meant that his right hand man, Yukinaga MIYOSHI, actually became more powerful, and this made him temporarily think about returning to Awa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was still young&quot;→&quot;youth&quot;- I&apos;m not sure of a good translation for &quot;家宰&quot;, though &quot;regent&quot; is usually only for heads of stateReworded sentence&quot;think of&quot;→&quot;think about&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Sumimoto&apos;s youth meant that his right hand man, Yukinaga MIYOSHI, in fact became more powerful, and this made him temporarily think about returning to Awa.</e>
<cmt>actually→in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このときには足利義澄の説得もあって帰国はとどまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he decided not to return home partly because he was pursuaded not to by Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he decided not to return home, partly at Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA&apos;s urging.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he was pursuaded not to by Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA&quot;→&quot;partly at Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA&apos;s urging&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he decided not to return home, partly at Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA&apos;s urging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>このような京都における一連の内乱が、周防国に流れていた第10代将軍・足利義稙義尹（義材より改名）のもとに知らされると、義尹は大内義興に擁立されて上洛を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the news of those series of internal strifes in Kyoto reached to the 10th Shogun Yoshitada (renamed from Yoshiki) ASHIKAGA in exile in the Suo Province,Yoshitada began marching to Kyoto with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When news of the chain of events in Kyoto reached the 10th Shogun, Yoshitada (renamed from Yoshiki) ASHIKAGA, in exile in Suo Province, he began marching for Kyoto, supported by Yoshioki OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;those series of internal strifes&quot;→&quot;the chain of events&quot;&quot;Yoshitada&quot;→&quot;he&quot;&quot;to&quot;→&quot;for&quot;&quot;with the support of&quot;→&quot;supported by&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When news of the chain of events in Kyoto reached the tenth Shogun, Yoshitada (renamed from Yoshiki) ASHIKAGA, in exile in Suo Province, he began marching for Kyoto, supported by Yoshioki OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>10th→tenth</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>澄元は義興との和睦を画策したが、同じく政元の養子で澄之討伐に協力した細川高国が大内方に寝返ったため、決裂してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Sumimoto tried to reconcile with Yoshioki, his trial was aborted because Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who was another adopted son of Masamoto and cooperated with the fight against Sumiyuki, betrayed Sumimoto and took sides with OUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Sumimoto attempted to hold peace talks with Yoshioki, they broke down because Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who was another adopted son of Masamoto and had cooperated in the fight against Sumiyuki, betrayed Sumimoto and took sides with OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;tried to reconcile&quot;→&quot;attempted to hold peace talks&quot;&quot;his trial was aborted&quot;→&quot;they broke down&quot;Added &quot;had&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Sumimoto attempted to hold peace talks with Yoshioki, they broke down because Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who was another adopted son of Masamoto and had cooperated in the fight against Sumiyuki, betrayed Sumimoto and took sides with OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>永正5年（1508年）4月、細川高国が京都に侵攻を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni HOSOKAWA started inroad to Kyoto in April 1508.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni HOSOKAWA marched into Kyoto in April 1508.</e>
<cmt>&quot;started inroad to&quot;→&quot;marched into&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni HOSOKAWA marched into Kyoto in May 1508.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このとき、摂津の伊丹元扶や丹波の内藤貞正らも呼応したために澄元は敗北し、之長や将軍・足利義澄と共に近江に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Motosuke ITAMI in Settsu and Sadamasa NAITO in Tanba acted in concert with Takakuni&apos;s inroad, Sumimoto was defeated by those combined forces and fled to Omi together with Yukinaga and Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto was defeated by the combined forces of Motosuke ITAMI of Settsu and Sadamasa NAITO of Tanba and fled to Omi together with Yukinaga and Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto was defeated by the combined forces of Motosuke ITAMI of Settsu and Sadamasa NAITO of Tanba and fled to Omi together with Yukinaga and Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そして6月、足利義尹が大内義興に擁されて上洛すると、義稙（義尹より改名）によって澄元の家督は剥奪され、代わって高国の家督継承が承認されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitada ASHIKAGA entered Kyoto with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI in June, Yoshitane (renamed from Yoshitada) deprived Sumimoto of his right to the HOSOKAWA family and approved Takakuni&apos;s inheritance of the HOSOKAWA family instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitane (renamed from Yoshitada) ASHIKAGA entered Kyoto with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI in June, he deprived Sumimoto of his right to be head of the HOSOKAWA Clan, giving it instead to Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>Although the Japanese has &quot;義尹&quot;, I think he&apos;d actually changed his name in 1501Added &quot;to be head of&quot;&quot;Family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;&quot;and approved Takakuni&apos;s inheritance of the HOSOKAWA family instead&quot;→&quot;giving it instead to Takakuni&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitane (renamed from Yoshitada) ASHIKAGA entered Kyoto with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI in July, he deprived Sumimoto of his right to be head of the HOSOKAWA clan, giving it instead to Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦にClan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>ところが大内義興と足利義稙が対立し始めたため、澄元と之長は永正6年（1509年）に京都に侵攻したが、逆に高国と義興の反撃を受けて敗北（如意ケ嶽の戦い）し澄元と之長は阿波に逃走する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But as Yoshioki OUHI began confronting to Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, Sumimoto and Yukinaga made an inroad to Kyoto in 1509 but lost in the battle (Battle of Nyoigatake) in the face of the countercharge of Takakuni and Yoshioki and escaped to Awa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1509, as Yoshioki OUCHI&apos;s relationship with Yoshitane ASHIKAGA soured, Sumimoto and Yukinaga attacked Kyoto in the Battle of Nyoigatake but were defeated by Takakuni and Yoshioki&apos;s counterattack and escaped to Awa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;But&quot;→&quot;However&quot;&quot;began confronting to Yoshitane ASHIKAGA&quot;→&quot;&apos;s relationship with Yoshitane ASHIKAGA soured&quot;&quot;made an inroad to&quot;→&quot;attacked&quot;&quot;lost in the face of the countercharge of Takakuni and Yoshioki&quot;→&quot;were defeated by Takakuni and Yoshioki&apos;s counterattack&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1509, as Yoshioki OUCHI&apos;s relationship with Yoshitane ASHIKAGA soured, Sumimoto and Yukinaga attacked Kyoto in the Battle of Nyoigatake but were defeated by Takakuni and Yoshioki&apos;s counterattack and escaped to Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>永正8年（1511年）には足利義澄、細川政賢（典厩家）と連携して京都に侵攻する（船岡山の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1511, Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA joined forces with Masakata HOSOKAWA (Tenkyu Family) and entered Kyoto (Battle of Funaokayama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1511, Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA joined forces with Masakata HOSOKAWA (of the Tenkyu branch) and entered Kyoto (Battle of Funaokayama).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;of the&quot;&quot;Family&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1511, Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA joined forces with Masakata HOSOKAWA (of the Tenkyu branch) and entered Kyoto (Battle of Funaokayama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし戦いの最中に義澄が病死したこともあって、大内義興の反撃を受けて大敗を喫し、政賢は戦死し、澄元は摂津に逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But partly because of the death of Yoshizumi by an illness during the battle, Sumimoto suffered a major loss in the face of the countercharge of Yoshioki OUCHI; consequently Masakata was killed in action, and Sumimoto fled to Settsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, partly because of the death of Yoshizumi from illness during the battle, Sumimoto suffered a major loss in the face of a countercharge by Yoshioki OUCHI; consequently Masakata was killed in action, and Sumimoto fled to Settsu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;by an&quot;→&quot;from&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;by&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, partly because of the death of Yoshizumi from illness during the battle, Sumimoto suffered a major loss in the face of a countercharge by Yoshioki OUCHI; consequently Masakata was killed in action, and Sumimoto fled to Settsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>永正15年（1518年）8月、大内義興が周防に帰国すると、永正16年（1519年）に澄元と之長は摂津に侵攻する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshioki OUCHI returned to Suo in August 1518, Sumimoto and Yukinaga made an inroad to Settsu in 1519.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1518, Yoshioki OUCHI returned to Suo and, in 1519, Sumimoto and Yukinaga attacked Settsu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;When&quot;→&quot;After&quot;&quot;made an inroad to&quot;→&quot;attacked&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1518, Yoshioki OUCHI returned to Suo and, in 1519, Sumimoto and Yukinaga attacked Settsu.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>永正17年（1520年）1月に入ると、澄元に呼応して山城で土一揆が発生し、さらに将軍・足利義稙も澄元に通じて裏切ったため、細川高国は単独で近江坂本に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1520, since a peasant uprising occurred in Yamashiro in coordination with the movement of Sumimoto and Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA turned against Takakuni in favor of Sumimoto, Takakuni HOSOKAWA singly fled to Sakamoto in the Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1520, following a peasant uprising in Yamashiro in support of Sumimoto, Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA turned against Takakuni HOSOKAWA in favor of Sumimoto, with Takakuni fleeing alone to Sakamoto in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;since&quot;→&quot;following&quot;&quot;coordination with the movement&quot;→&quot;support&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Moved &quot;HOSOKAWA&quot;&quot;singly&quot;→&quot;alone&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1520, following a peasant uprising in Yamashiro in support of Sumimoto, Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA turned against Takakuni HOSOKAWA in favor of Sumimoto, with Takakuni fleeing alone to Sakamoto in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これにより、澄元政権が成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This marked the start of the Sumimoto administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This marked the start of Sumimoto&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This marked the start of Sumimoto&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="26">
<j>ところが5月、高国は大軍を集めて京都に侵攻する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May Takakuni raised a large army and started inroad to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, Takakuni raised a large army and marched into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Added comma,&quot;started inroad to&quot;→&quot;marched into&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, Takakuni raised a large army and marched into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これに対して澄元・之長らは兵を集めることができず、之長は捕らえられて自害させられ、澄元も摂津伊丹城に敗走し、政権は短期間で崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Sumimoto and Yukinaga failed to gather soldiers, and Yukinaga was arrested and forced to kill himself, while Sumimoto fled to the Itami Castle in Settsu; his administration collapsed in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sumimoto and Yukinaga were unable to raise an army and Yukinaga was arrested and forced to kill himself, while Sumimoto fled to Itami Castle in Settsu; his administration collapsed in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;But&quot;→&quot;However&quot;&quot;failed to gather soldiers,&quot;→&quot;However&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sumimoto and Yukinaga were unable to raise an army and Yukinaga was arrested and forced to kill himself, while Sumimoto fled to Itami Castle in Settsu; his administration collapsed in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そして失意のうちに病に倒れた澄元は、まもなく高国の攻撃を受けて播磨国に逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disappointed and disease-stricken Sumimoto soon had to again escape to the Harima Province because of the attach by Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disappointed and disease-stricken Sumimoto soon had to escape again to Harima Province following Takakuni&apos;s offensive.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;because of the attack by Takakuni&quot;→&quot;following Takakuni&apos;s offensive&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disappointed and disease-stricken Sumimoto soon had to escape again to Harima Province following Takakuni&apos;s offensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>最終的には永正17年（1520年）6月10日に阿波勝瑞城にて死去した。享年32。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ultimately he died in the Awa Shozui Castle on June 10, 1520 at the age of 32.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「享年３２」をくっつけました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at Awa Shozui Castle on June 10, 1520 at the age of 32.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Ultimately&quot;&quot;in the&quot;→&quot;at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at Awa Shozui Castle on July 4, 1520 at the age of 32.</e>
<cmt>日付を新暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>後を子の細川晴元が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was succeeded by his son Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was succeeded by his son, Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was succeeded by his son, Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Rusk(id:9895), ドルチェット(id:46458), Ittyon(id:1348), YurikBot(id:18605), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Aotake(id:34929), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), ブレイズマン(id:183852), ５１６(id:45205), 小川尚明(id:93076), 常陸介(id:176100), Sanmari(id:1707), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>