<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小笠原長重</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige OGASAWARA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige OGASAWARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige OGASAWARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小笠原 長重（おがさわら ながしげ、慶安3年5月7日 (旧暦)（1650年6月5日） - 享保17年8月1日 (旧暦)（1732年9月19日））は、江戸時代の譜代大名、老中。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige OGASAWARA (male, June 5, 1650 to September 19, 1732) was fudai-daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) and roju (a person in charge of general affairs directly under shogun) in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige OGASAWARA (male, June 5, 1650 to September 19, 1732) was a fudai-daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) and a roju (a person in charge of general affairs directly under the shogun) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige OGASAWARA (June 5, 1650 to September 19, 1732) was a fudai-daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) and a roju (a person in charge of general affairs directly under the shogun) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>male, を除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三河国三河吉田藩第3代藩主、のち武蔵国岩槻藩初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige was the third lord of Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province and, later on, the first lord of Iwatsuki Domain in Musashi Province..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige was the third lord of the Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province and, later on, the first lord of the Iwatsuki Domain in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige was the third lord of the Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province and, later on, the first lord of the Iwatsuki Domain in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>忠知系小笠原家4代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige was the fourth head of the OGASAWARA family of Chuchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige was the fourth head of the OGASAWARA family of the Chuchi clan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige was the fourth head of the OGASAWARA family of the Chuchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>慶安3年(1650年)5月7日、三河吉田第2代藩主・小笠原長矩の次男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige was born on May 7, 1650 as the second son of Nagatsugu OGASAWARA who was the second lord of Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige was born on May 7, 1650 as the second son of Nagatsugu OGASAWARA who was the second lord of the Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige was born on June 5, 1650 as the second son of Nagatsugu OGASAWARA who was the second lord of the Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>寛文4年(1664年)3月22日将軍徳川家綱に謁見。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 22, 1664, Nagashige was allowed to paid a visit to the Shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 22, 1664, Nagashige was allowed an audience with the Shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 18, 1664, Nagashige was allowed an audience with the Shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以降譜代大名の次男坊として幕府に出仕し、寛文10年(1670年)7月11日中奥小姓に就任し、12月28日には切米500俵を支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Nagashige worked for the bakufu (the samurai government) as a second son of a fudai-daimyo and was appointed as chuoku-kosho (a servant of semi-deep portion of the castle) on July 11, 1670 and, on December 28, was supplied with 500 pyo (originally, hyo, a unit of rice amount equivalent to 60 kg/hyo) of kirimai (seasonally supplied special salary rice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Nagashige worked for the bakufu (the samurai government) as a second son of a fudai-daimyo and was appointed as chuoku-kosho (a servant in the semi-deep portion of the castle) on July 11, 1670 and, on December 28th, was supplied with 500 pyo (originally, hyo, a unit of rice amount equivalent to 60 kg/hyo) of kirimai (seasonally supplied special salary rice).</e>
<cmt>Unsure what &quot;Semi-deep portion of the castle&quot; implies.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Nagashige worked for the bakufu (the samurai government) as a second son of a fudai-daimyo and was appointed as chuoku-kosho (a servant in the semi-deep portion of the castle) on August 26, 1670 and, on February 7th, was supplied with 500 pyo (originally, hyo, a unit of rice amount equivalent to 60 kg/hyo) of kirimai (seasonally supplied special salary rice).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寛文12年(1672年)4月25日御側小姓に移り、12月28日従五位下佐渡守に叙任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 25, 1672, Nagashige moved to osoba-kosho (a servant working beside the shogun) and was ranked at Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed as the governor of Sato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 25, 1672, Nagashige transferred to the position of osoba-kosho (a servant working beside the shogun) and was given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed as the governor of Sato Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 22, 1672, Nagashige transferred to the position of osoba-kosho (a servant working beside the shogun) and was given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed as the governor of Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>SatoをSadoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>延宝5年(1677年)11月6日延寿国吉の刀を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 6, 1677, a sword of Kuniyoshi ENJU was presented to Nagashige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 6, 1677, a sword of Kuniyoshi ENJU was presented to Nagashige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 30, 1677, a sword of Kuniyoshi ENJU was presented to Nagashige.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延宝6年(1678年)3月31日には、父長矩の死去で長重の兄の小笠原長祐が家督を相続し三河吉田藩主となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 31, 1678, due to the death of his father, Nagatsugu, Nagashige&apos;s elder brother, Nagasuke OGASAWARA succeeded their father as the head of the family and became the lord of the Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 31, 1678, due to the death of his father, Nagatsugu, Nagashige&apos;s elder brother, Nagasuke OGASAWARA succeeded their father as the head of the family and became the lord of the Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 21, 1678, due to the death of his father, Nagatsugu, Nagashige&apos;s elder brother, Nagasuke OGASAWARA succeeded their father as the head of the family and became the lord of the Yoshida Domain in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>長重の方は、延宝8年(1680年)将軍家綱の薨去のために職を免ぜられ、一時寄合旗本に列したが、翌天和 (日本)元年(1681年)7月6日には御書院番の番頭として復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige on the other hand was fired due to passing away of the Shogun Ietusna and joined yoriai-hatamoto for a while, however, on July 6, 1681 in the next year, he returned to bakufu as bangashira of goshoin-ban (the chief of the governmental library).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige on the other hand was dismissed due to the passing away of the Shogun Ietsuna and joined yoriai-hatamoto for a time, however, on July 6, 1681 in the next year, he returned to the bakufu as bangashira of goshoin-ban (the chief of the governmental library).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige on the other hand was dismissed due to the passing away of the Shogun Ietsuna and joined yoriai-hatamoto for a time, however, on August 19, 1681 in the next year, he returned to the bakufu as bangashira of goshoin-ban (the chief of the governmental library).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天和2年(1682年)5月21日切米1000俵を加増されて都合1500俵となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 21, 1682, Nagashige obtained an increase of his kirimai by 1,000 pyo which made the total of kirimai 1,500 pyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 21, 1682, Nagashige obtained an increase of his kirimai by 1,000 pyo, which made the total of his kirimai 1,500 pyo.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 26, 1682, Nagashige obtained an increase of his kirimai by 1,000 pyo, which made the total of his kirimai 1,500 pyo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>貞享2年(1685年)7月9日兄長祐の子であった長千代が早世したことにより、急きょ弟の長重が兄の養子となり、12日これまで支給されていた1500俵を幕府に返還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 9, 1685, Nagachiyo, a child of Nagasuke who was Nagashige&apos;s elder brother died young and, therefore, Nagashige was suddenly adopted by this elder brother of his and, Nagashige on 12th returned the 1,500 pyo of kirimai which had been supplied to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 9, 1685, Nagachiyo, a child of Nagasuke died young and, therefore, Nagashige, who was Nagaksuke&apos;s younger brother, was suddenly adopted by his elder brother and, Nagashige on the 12th returned the 1,500 pyo of kirimai which had been supplied to him.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 8, 1685, Nagachiyo, a child of Nagasuke died young and, therefore, Nagashige, who was Nagaksuke&apos;s younger brother, was suddenly adopted by his elder brother and, Nagashige on the 11th returned the 1,500 pyo of kirimai which had been supplied to him.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元禄3年(1690年)6月17日兄長祐の遺領を相続、同年10月10日に三河吉田藩4万5000石の第4代藩主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 17, 1690, Nagashige succeeded to the territory of the late elder brother, Nagasuke and, on October 10, was appointed as the fourth lord of Yoshida Domain annually producing 45,000 koku (a unit of amount of rice: one koku of rice could feed one person for one year) of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, 1690, Nagashige succeeded the territory of the late elder brother, Nagasuke and, on October 10th, was appointed as the fourth lord of the Yoshida Domain, which annually produced 45,000 koku (a unit of amount of rice: one koku of rice could feed one person for one year) in the Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 22, 1690, Nagashige succeeded the territory of the late elder brother, Nagasuke and, on November 10th, was appointed as the fourth lord of the Yoshida Domain, which annually produced 45,000 koku (a unit of amount of rice: one koku of rice could feed one person for one year) in the Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>幕府内の役職では。元禄3年(1690年)12月3日に奏者番兼寺社奉行となり、元禄4閏年(1691年)8月26日に京都所司代に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the positions in bakufu, Nagashige was appointed on December 3, 1690, as soshaban (a person in charge of delivering shogun&apos;s gifts to visitors who could directly see shogun in annual big events) and jisha-bugyo (temple-shrine police chief) and, on August 26, 1691, as Kyoto-shoshidai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for his positions in the bakufu, Nagashige was appointed on December 3, 1690, as a soshaban (a person in charge of delivering shogun&apos;s gifts to visitors who could directly see the shogun during annual big events) and jisha-bugyo (temple-shrine police chief) and, on August 26, 1691, as the Kyoto-shoshidai.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for his positions in the bakufu, Nagashige was appointed on January 1, 1691, as a soshaban (a person in charge of delivering shogun&apos;s gifts to visitors who could directly see the shogun during annual big events) and jisha-bugyo (temple-shrine police chief) and, on September 18, 1691, as the Kyoto-shoshidai.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>またこの時に従四位下侍従の官位を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Nagashige was ranked at Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and jiju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Nagashige held the ranks of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Jiju.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Nagashige held the ranks of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Jiju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>10月10日、任務で京都へ赴く際に将軍徳川綱吉から備前兼長の刀と時服五領、羽織一領、黄金二十枚を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 10, when Nagashige was traveling to Kyoto on business,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10th, when Nagashige was traveling to Kyoto on business,</e>
<cmt>Translation incomplete.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 9th, when Nagashige was traveling to Kyoto on business, the Shogun, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA gave him a sword of Bizen Kanenaga, a haori (a Japanese half-coat) and 20 gold.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。欠落部の翻訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>11月25日はじめて参内して東山天皇に拝謁。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige visited the Imperial Place for the first time on November 25 and met the Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige visited the Imperial Palace for the first time on November 25th and met the Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige visited the Imperial Palace for the first time on January 13th and met the Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天皇から天盃を下賜された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor presented an imperial cup to Nagashige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor presented an imperial cup to Nagashige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor presented an imperial cup to Nagashige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>元禄10年(1697年)閏2月6日には有栖川宮幸子女王が入内があり、東山天皇からその慶賀として京都所司代としては異例の従四位上へ昇進させてもよいという叡慮が長重にあったが拝辞している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 6 in 1697, Arisugawa no Miya Sachiko Queen entered the Imperial Palace and, as a gift to celebrate this entrance, the Emperor Higashiyama presented a permission for Nagashige to get promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) being irregular as Kyoto-shoshidai, however, Nagashige humbly turned it down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 6th in 1697, Arisugawa no Miya Sachiko Queen entered the Imperial Palace and, as a gift to celebrate this entrance, the Emperor Higashiyama presented permission for Nagashige to be promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) this being irregular for a Kyoto-shoshidai, however, Nagashige humbly turned it down.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 26th in 1697, Arisugawa no Miya Sachiko Queen entered the Imperial Palace and, as a gift to celebrate this entrance, the Emperor Higashiyama presented permission for Nagashige to be promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) this being irregular for a Kyoto-shoshidai, however, Nagashige humbly turned it down.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>4月19日、京都所司代として在京のままで幕府から老中の任命を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 19, Nagashige was appointed as roju by the bakufu being in Kyoto as Kyoto-shoshidai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 19th, Nagashige was appointed as roju by the bakufu while being in Kyoto as Kyoto-shoshidai.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 7th, Nagashige was appointed as roju by the bakufu while being in Kyoto as Kyoto-shoshidai.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、この際に1万石加増転封され武蔵岩槻藩主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time additionally, 10,000 koku of rice was added to his salary and was transferred to the lord of Iwatsuki Domain in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time additionally, 10,000 koku of rice was added to his salary and was transferred to the lord of Iwatsuki Domain in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time additionally, 10,000 koku of rice was added to his salary and was transferred to the lord of Iwatsuki Domain in Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>元禄15年(1702年)12月14日討ち入りの前日に開かれていた吉良家茶会には主賓として出席している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 14, 1702, Nagashige attended as the main guest the tea party held by the KIRA family on the eve of the raid on KIRA&apos;s mansion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 14, 1702, Nagashige attended as the guest of honor the tea party held by the KIRA family on the eve of the raid on KIRA&apos;s mansion.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 30, 1703, Nagashige attended as the guest of honor the tea party held by the KIRA family on the eve of the raid on KIRA&apos;s mansion.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>宝永2年(1705年)8月27日、江戸城西の丸に入った徳川家宣に従って西の丸老中に転じ、1万石加増で都合6万石を知行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 27, 1705, Nagashige followed Ienobu TOKUGAWA who entered nishi-no-maru (west building) of Edo-jo castle and was transferred to nishi-no-maru roju and his salary was increased by 10,000 koku which made the total amount of his salary rice be 60,000 koku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 27, 1705, Nagashige followed Ienobu TOKUGAWA who entered the nishi-no-maru (west building) of Edo-jo castle and was transferred to the position of nishi-no-maru roju and his salary was increased by 10,000 koku which made the total amount of his salary in rice 60,000 koku</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 14, 1705, Nagashige followed Ienobu TOKUGAWA who entered the nishi-no-maru (west building) of Edo-jo castle and was transferred to the position of nishi-no-maru roju and his salary was increased by 10,000 koku which made the total amount of his salary in rice 60,000 koku</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>宝永6年(1709年)5月18日眼病のため職を辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 18, 1709, Nagashige resigned his position due to a disease of his eyes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 18, 1709, Nagashige resigned his position due to suffering from an eye disease.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 25, 1709, Nagashige resigned his position due to suffering from an eye disease.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>翌年宝永7年(1710年)5月18日には隠居して嫡男の小笠原長煕に家督を譲る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 18, 1710, Nagashige retired and let his own son, Nagateru OGASAWARA succeed him as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 18, 1710, Nagashige retired and let his own son, Nagateru OGASAWARA succeed him as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 14, 1710, Nagashige retired and let his own son, Nagateru OGASAWARA succeed him as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>享保期になると8代将軍徳川吉宗は支持基盤強化のために譜代大名、特に老中経験者たちの前官礼遇という形をとり、すでに隠居していた酒井忠挙、稲葉正往と共に長重の3人を、前代の遺老、学識豊かな経験者としてとくに優遇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kyoho period started, the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA made a system of zenkan-reigu (to welcome retired persons to the field they had experienced) for fudai-daimyo, especially, the persons who had experienced roju in order to enhance the basis of shogun&apos;s political support, and treated especially kindly three persons that were Nagashige together with Tadanori SAKAI and Masayuki INABA who had already retired, as the remaining persons who had experienced the previous generation and who had rich academic knowledge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kyoho period started, the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA made a system of zenkan-reigu (to welcome retired persons to the field they had experience in) for fudai-daimyo, especially, the persons who had experience as roju in order to enhance the basis of the shogun&apos;s political support, and treated especially kindly three people, which included Nagashige together with Tadanori SAKAI and Masayuki INABA who had already retired, as the remaining persons who had experienced the previous generation and who had rich academic knowledge.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kyoho period started, the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA made a system of zenkan-reigu (to welcome retired persons to the field they had experience in) for fudai-daimyo, especially, the persons who had experience as roju in order to enhance the basis of the shogun&apos;s political support, and treated especially kindly three people, which included Nagashige together with Tadataka SAKAI and Masayuki INABA who had already retired, as the remaining persons who had experienced the previous generation and who had rich academic knowledge.</e>
<cmt>TadanoriをTadatakaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>長重にも時々登城して御用部屋（老中の執務室）に顔を出すように指示があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was ordered also for Nagashige to sometimes come to the castle and show up in the goyo-beya (the office of roju).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige was also ordered to sometimes come to the castle and make an appearance in the goyo-beya (the office of roju).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige was also ordered to come occasionally to the castle and make an appearance in the goyo-beya (the office of roju).</e>
<cmt>sometimesをoccasionallyに変更し、位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>享保7年(1722年)7月22将軍吉宗から鷹狩で捕獲した鷚（ひばり）を下賜された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 22, 1722, the shogun Yoshimune presented Nagashige a lark that he caught during falconry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 22, 1722, the shogun Yoshimune presented Nagashige a lark that he caught during falconry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 2, 1722, the shogun Yoshimune presented Nagashige a lark that he caught during falconry.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="29">
<j>享保17年(1732年)8月1日に江戸で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige died on August 1, 1732 in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige died on August 1, 1732 in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige died on September 19, 1732 in Edo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>享年83。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>墓所は東京都文京区本駒込の竜光寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige&apos;s grave is located in Ryuko-ji temple in Honkomagome in Bunkyo Ward in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige&apos;s grave is located at the Ryuko-ji temple in Honkomagome in Bunkyo Ward in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige&apos;s grave is located at the Ryuko-ji temple in Honkomagome in Bunkyo Ward in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>法名は竺仙院英嶽崇雄居士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhism name was Jikusen-in-eigakushuyu-koji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist name was Jikusen-in-eigakushuyu-koji.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Jikusen-in-eigakushuyu-koji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、愛知県豊橋市の臨済寺 (豊橋市)にも廟が有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a mausoleum for Nagashige in Rinzai-ji temple (Toyohashi City) in Toyohashi City in Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a mausoleum for Nagashige at the Rinzai-ji temple (Toyohashi City) in Toyohashi City in Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a mausoleum for Nagashige at the Rinzai-ji temple (Toyohashi City) in Toyohashi City in Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>剣術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese fencing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese fencing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">swordplay</e>
<cmt>Japanese fencingをswordplayに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>大名ながら、若い頃から剣術は新陰流、小野派一刀流の達人で、その剣風は若い頃から「手強風」と呼ばれて恐れられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Nagashige was daimyo, he was good at Japanese fencing since he was young in Shinkage-ryu school and Itto-ryu school in Ono faction, and it is said that his fencing manner was feared being called &apos;tough style&apos; since he was young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Nagashige was a daimyo, he was also good at Japanese fencing and from when he was young he trained at the Shinkage-ryu school and Itto-ryu school in Ono faction, and it is said that his fencing manner was feared being called &apos;tough style&apos; since he was young.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Nagashige was a daimyo, he was also good at swordplay and from when he was young he trained at the Shinkage-ryu school and Itto-ryu school in Ono faction, and it is said that his swordplay manner was feared being called &apos;tough style&apos; since he was young.</e>
<cmt>Japanese fencing、fencingをswordplayに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、家宣政権では、綱吉時代に廃止された新陰流と一刀流の年始の稽古はじめの儀式や、御前での演武などの儀式の復活に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ienobu administration, Nagashige made efforts to revive the ceremonies such as: the practice-starting ceremony in the new year season of the Shinkage-ryu school and Itto-ryu school which had been abolished in the days of Tsunayoshi; exhibition matches in front of the shogun; etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Ienobu administration, Nagashige made efforts to revive ceremonies such as: The practice-starting ceremony in the new year season of the Shinkage-ryu school and Itto-ryu school which had been abolished in the days of Tsunayoshi; exhibition matches in front of the shogun; etc.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Ienobu administration, Nagashige made efforts to revive ceremonies such as: The practice-starting ceremony in the new year season of the Shinkage-ryu school and Itto-ryu school which had been abolished in the days of Tsunayoshi; exhibition matches in front of the shogun; etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>宝永6年(1709年)には辻月丹に入門し無外流も修行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1709, Nagashige became a disciple of Tsukitan TSUJI and practiced Mugai-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1709, Nagashige became a disciple of Tsukitan TSUJI and practiced Mugai-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1709, Nagashige became a disciple of Tsukitan TSUJI and practiced Mugai-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>Personal historyをCareerに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>1650年（慶安3年）　江戸で生まれる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1650: Nagashige was born in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1650: Nagashige was born in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1650: Nagashige was born in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1672年（寛文12年）　公方小姓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1672: Was appointed as kuho-kosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1672: Was appointed as kuho-kosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1672: Was appointed as kubo-kosho.</e>
<cmt>kuhoをkuboに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>1681年（天和 (日本)元年）　書院番頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1681: Was appointed as shoinban-gashira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1681: Was appointed as shoinban-gashira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1681: Was appointed as shoinban-gashira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>1685年（貞享2年）　兄・長祐の養子となる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1685: Was adopted by his elder brother, Nagasuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1685: Was adopted by his elder brother, Nagasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1685: Was adopted by his elder brother, Nagasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>1690年（元禄3年）　6月17日、長祐死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1690: Nagasuke died on June 17.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1690: Nagasuke died on June 17.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1690: Nagasuke died on July 22.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>10月10日に吉田藩を相続。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succeeded to Yoshida Domain on October 10.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagashige Succeeded the Yoshida Domain on October 10th.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagashige Succeeded the Yoshida Domain on November 10th.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>奏者番兼寺社奉行（12月3日 (旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was appointed as soshaban and jisha-bugyo (December 3 in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as soshaban and jisha-bugyo (December 3rd in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as soshaban and jisha-bugyo (December 3rd in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>1691年（元禄4年）　京都所司代（8月26日 (旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1691: Was appointed as Kyoto-shoshidai (August 26 in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1691: Was appointed as Kyoto-shoshidai (August 26th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1691: Was appointed as Kyoto-shoshidai (August 26th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>1697年（元禄10年）　老中も兼務（4月19日 (旧暦)）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1697: Was additionally appointed as roju (on April 19 in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1697: Was additionally appointed as roju (on April 19th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1697: Was additionally appointed as roju (on April 19th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>岩槻に転封</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moved to Iwatsuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved to Iwatsuki.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved to Iwatsuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>1705年（宝永2年）　所司代免、江戸城西丸付（8月27日 (旧暦)）、1万石加増</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1705: Resigned shoshidai and moved to nishinomaru of Edo-jo castle (on August 27 in the old calendar) and 10,000 koku was added to his salary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1705: Resigned as shoshidai and transferred to nishinomaru of Edo-jo castle (on August 27th in the old calendar) and 10,000 koku was added to his salary.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1705: Resigned as shoshidai and transferred to nishinomaru of Edo-jo castle (on August 27th in the old calendar) and 10,000 koku was added to his salary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>1709年（宝永6年）　西丸から本丸老中に転ずる（1月10日 (旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1709: Moved from nishinomaru to honmaru as roju (on January 10 in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1709: Transferred from nishinomaru to honmaru as roju (on January 10th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1709: Transferred from nishinomaru to honmaru as roju (on January 10th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>1710年（宝永7年）　老中免、隠居（5月18日 (旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1710: Resigned roju and retired (on May 18 in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1710: Resigned from the position of roju and retired (on May 18th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1710: Resigned from the position of roju and retired (on May 18th in the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>1732年（享保17年）　死去、享年83</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1732: Died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1732: Died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1732: Died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="52">
<j>官位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official ranks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>1672年（寛文12年）従五位下佐渡守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1672: Jugoinoge and the governor of Sado Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1672: Jugoinoge and the governor of Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1672: Jugoinoge and the governor of Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>1691年（元禄4年） 従四位下武家官位江戸時代の武家官位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1691: Jushiinoge, a rank for a samurai warrior, a rank for a samurai warrior in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1691: Jushiinoge, a rank for a samurai warrior during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1691: Jushiinoge, a rank for a samurai warrior during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), シェーラ(id:17988), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Swordarts(id:54566), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>