<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原季能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 季能（ふじわら の すえよし、仁平3年（1153年） - 建暦元年（1211年））は平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけての公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi (1153 - 1211) was a Kuge (court noble) over the end of Heian Period and the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi (1153 - 1211) was a Kuge (court noble) near the end of Heian Period and the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi (1153 - 1211) was a Kuge (court noble) near the end of Heian Period and the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は太皇太后宮権大夫藤原俊盛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Toshimori, Taikotaigogu Gon no daibu (provisional master of the grand empress dowager&apos;s household.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Toshimori, Taikotaigogu Gon no daibu (provisional master of the grand empress dowager&apos;s household.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Toshimori, Taikotaigogu Gon no daibu (provisional master of the grand Empress dowager&apos;s household.)</e>
<cmt>empressをEmpressに変更しました。単語調査では小文字で登録されていました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は源雅兼の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Masakane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Masakane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Masakane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正三位兵部卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ranked at Shosanmi Hyobukyo (Senior Third Rank, chief of Hyobu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ranked as Shosanmi Hyobukyo (Senior Third Rank, chief of Hyobu.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ranked as Shosanmi Hyobukyo (Senior Third Rank, chief of Hyobu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原顕季を祖とする六条藤家の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He hailed from the Rokujo Toke (the Rokujo Fujiwara family) whose ancestor was FUJIWARA no Akisue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He hailed from the Rokujo Toke (the Rokujo Fujiwara family) whose ancestor was FUJIWARA no Akisue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He hailed from the Rokujo Toke (the Rokujo Fujiwara family) whose ancestor was FUJIWARA no Akisue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後白河法皇の側近として活動し、治承3年（1179年）に平清盛が法皇を鳥羽殿に幽閉しその近臣一派を大量に解任した際には、一旦越後国守の職を解かれている（治承三年の政変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He acted as a close associate of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and in 1179 when TAIRA no Kiyomori confined the Cloistered Emperor to Toba-dono Palace and dismissed a group of many of his kinshin (trusted vassals), Sueyoshi was once relieved of his post as the Echigo no kuni no kami (Governor of Echigo Province) (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a close associate of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and in 1179 when TAIRA no Kiyomori confined the Cloistered Emperor to Toba-dono Palace and dismissed a group of many of his kinshin (trusted vassals), Sueyoshi was relieved of his post as the Echigo no kuni no kami (Governor of Echigo Province) (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a close associate of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and in 1179 when TAIRA no Kiyomori confined the Cloistered Emperor to Toba-dono Palace and dismissed a group of many of his kinshin (trusted vassals), Sueyoshi was relieved of his post as the Echigo no kuni no kami (Governor of Echigo Province) (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかしこの翌年、清盛の意向をもって法皇の身柄を八条坊門の自邸に迎えており、平家側からも一定の信頼を得ていたことが伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, however, according to the wishes of Kiyomori he received the Cloistered Emperor in his home in Hachijo Bomon and it suggests that the part of the Taira family also had a certain degree of confidence in him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, however, according to the wishes of Kiyomori he received the Cloistered Emperor in his home in Hachijo Bomon and this suggests that part of the Taira family also had a certain degree of confidence in him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, however, according to the wishes of Kiyomori he received the Cloistered Emperor in his home in Hachijo Bomon and this suggests that part of the Taira family also had a certain degree of confidence in him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この背景には、季能の妻が平基盛（清盛の次男）の娘であったことが関係しており、対立を深める法皇と平家の両者の狭間において、一種の潤滑油として作用する存在でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this background, it was related to fact that the wife of Sueyoshi was a daughter of TAIRA no Motomori (the second son of Kiyomori), and her presence also served as a kind of lubricant between both sides, the Cloistered Emperor and the Taira family, who were deeply opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this as a background, it was related to fact that the wife of Sueyoshi was the daughter of TAIRA no Motomori (the second son of Kiyomori), and her presence also served as a kind of lubricant between both sides, the Cloistered Emperor and the Taira family, who were deeply opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behind this background, it was related to the fact that the wife of Sueyoshi was the daughter of TAIRA no Motomori (the second son of Kiyomori), and her presence also served as a kind of lubricant between both sides, the Cloistered Emperor and the Taira family, who were deeply opposed to each other.</e>
<cmt>With this as a backgroundをBehind this backgroundに変更しました。factの前にtheを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>治承・寿永の乱を経て平家が没落した後も、法皇の傍に親しく仕えて一定の地位を確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the ruin of the Taira family following the Jisho-Juei War, he served the Cloistered Emperor closely and kept a certain position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the fall of the Taira family following the Jisho-Juei War, he served the Cloistered Emperor closely and kept a certain position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the fall of the Taira family following the Jisho-Juei War, he served the Cloistered Emperor closely and kept a certain position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>文治元年（1185年）に源頼朝の介入によって宮廷内の実権が藤原兼実らの親鎌倉派に移った後も、高階泰経、藤原隆房、藤原実教らとともに法皇側近グループを組織して暗にこれに対抗したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the pro-Shogunate forces including FUJIWARA no Kanezane took the helm of the Imperial court due to the intervention by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in 1185, he was said to organize a group of close associates of the Cloistered Emperor with TAKASHINA no Yasutsune, FUJIWARA no Takafusa, FUJIWARA no Sanenori and others to oppose it implicitly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the pro-Shogunate forces, including FUJIWARA no Kanezane, took the helm of the Imperial court due to the intervention by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in 1185, he was said to have organized a group of close associates of the Cloistered Emperor with TAKASHINA no Yasutsune, FUJIWARA no Takafusa, FUJIWARA no Sanenori and others in opposition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the pro-Shogunate forces, including FUJIWARA no Kanezane, took the helm of the Imperial court due to the intervention by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in 1185, he was said to have organized a group of close associates of the Cloistered Emperor with TAKASHINA no Yasutsune, FUJIWARA no Takafusa, FUJIWARA no Sanenori and others in opposition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>歌人としても活動しており、一女は藤原定家に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also acted as a kajin (waka poet) and his daughter married FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also acted as a kajin (waka poet) and his daughter married FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also acted as a kajin (waka poet) and his daughter married FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 小者(id:172526), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>