<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原三守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadamori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 三守（ふじわら の ただもり、延暦4年（785年） - 承和 (日本)7年7月7日 (旧暦)（840年8月7日））は平安時代初期の政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamori (785 ~ August 7, 840) was a statesman of the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadamori (785 ~ August 7, 840) was a statesman of the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamori (785 ~ August 7, 840) was a statesman of the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原南家の出身で、その祖である藤原武智麻呂の曾孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born of the Southern House of the Fujiwara Clan, and was a great-grandson of the founder of the clan, FUJIWARA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born of the Southern House of the Fujiwara Clan, and was a great-grandson of the founder of the clan, FUJIWARA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born of the Southern House of the Fujiwara Clan, and was a great-grandson of the founder of the clan, FUJIWARA no Muchimaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原真作の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 4th son of FUJIWARA no Matanari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 4th son of FUJIWARA no Matanari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 4th son of FUJIWARA no Matanari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>異名は後山科大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His nickname was Nochi no yamashina daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His nickname was Nochi no yamashina daijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His nickname was Nochi no yamashina daijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Life in Brief</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Life in Brief</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストより</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>彼が生まれた時は南家は既に藤原仲麻呂の乱等でかつての勢いを失い、代わりに藤原式家が桓武天皇の外戚として主流に立っていたことなどから、祖父の藤原巨勢麻呂は参議・父の藤原真作は従五位上阿波守止まりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan where Tadamori was born already lost their former influence as a result of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War and so on while the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara Clan became the mainstream instead, because the latter was maternal relatives of Emperor Kanmu, Tadamori&apos;s grandfather, FUJIWARA no Kosemaro&apos;s rank was Sangi (Councilor) and his father, FUJIWARA no Matanari was Goinojo (Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) at best.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan where Tadamori was born already lost their former influence as a result of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War and so on while the instead the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara Clan became the mainstream, because the latter were maternal relatives of Emperor Kanmu, Tadamori&apos;s grandfather, FUJIWARA no Kosemaro&apos;s rank was Sangi (Councilor) and his father, FUJIWARA no Matanari was Goinojo (Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) at best.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan where Tadamori was born already lost their former influence as a result of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War and so on while instead the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara Clan became the mainstream, because the latter were maternal relatives of Emperor Kanmu, Tadamori&apos;s grandfather, FUJIWARA no Kosemaro&apos;s rank was Sangi (Councilor) and his father, FUJIWARA no Matanari was Goinojo (Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) at best.</e>
<cmt>余分なtheを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、彼自身は嵯峨天皇の側近として重用され、弘仁7年（816）、32才の若さで参議に、同12年権中納言となり、嵯峨天皇が譲位して淳和天皇が即位した後も、同14年中納言へと順調な出世を遂げ、同年11月、嵯峨上皇に近侍するため中納言を辞すものの、天長5年（828年）には大納言に昇進している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was taken into confidence as an close aide of Emperor Saga, and in 816, he was appointed to Sangi at the age of only 32 and in 821, appointed to Gonchunagon (Junior Middle Councilor,) and even after Emperor Saga abdicated the throne and Emperor Junna acceded, he was promoted to Chunagon (Middle Councilor) in 823 and advanced his career, and although he resigned the post temporally to serve closely the Retired Emperor Saga, he was promoted to Dainagon (Major councilor) in 828.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was taken into confidence as a close aide of Emperor Saga, and in 816, he was appointed to Sangi at the age of only 32 and in 821, appointed to Gonchunagon (Junior Middle Councilor,) and even after Emperor Saga abdicated the throne and Emperor Junna acceded, he was promoted to Chunagon (Middle Councilor) in 823 and advanced his career, and although he resigned the post temporally to serve closely the Retired Emperor Saga, he was promoted to Dainagon (Major councilor) in 828.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was taken into confidence as a close aide of Emperor Saga, and in 816, he was appointed to Sangi at the age of only 32 and in 821, appointed to Gonchunagon (,provisional vice-councilor of state) and even after Emperor Saga abdicated the throne and Emperor Junna acceded, he was promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) in 823 and advanced his career, and although he resigned the post temporally to serve closely the Retired Emperor Saga, he was promoted to Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 828.</e>
<cmt>Junior Middle Councilor→provisional vice-councilor of state Major councilorchief →councilor of state</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同7年、嵯峨朝から引き続き修訂が進められていた「弘仁格式」を撰上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 830, he completed Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) for which revision works had been carried out from the age of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 830, he completed Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) for which revisions had been made since the age of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 830, he completed Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) for which revisions had been made since the age of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>承和5年（838年）には右大臣に昇進し、臣下では式家の藤原緒嗣に次いで高い地位に上った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 838, he was promoted to the Minister of Right which was the 2nd highest position as a subject next to FUJIWARA no Otsugu of the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 838, he was promoted to the Minister of Right which was the 2nd highest position as a subject next to FUJIWARA no Otsugu of the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 838, he was promoted to the Minister of Right which was the 2nd highest position as a subject next to FUJIWARA no Otsugu of the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>最終位階は従二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His final rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His final rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His final rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>没後、従一位が追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was raised to Juichii (Junior First Rank) after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was raised to Juichii (Junior First Rank) after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was raised to Juichii (Junior First Rank) after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>また、天台・真言両宗の熱心な後援者であり、僧綱の強硬な反対に遭って難航していた最澄の独立大乗戒壇設立構想が、弘仁13年6月11日、勅許を得るに至ったのは、彼および藤原冬嗣、良峯安世、大伴国道らの尽力によるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a vehement supporter of both Tendai sect and Shingon sect of Buddhism, and that the Imperial sanction was given on June 11, 822 (lunar calendar date) to the project of the building of Daijo-Kaidan (Mahayana ordination center), which was tangling because Sogo (Office of Monastic Affairs) strongly opposed, is said to be due to the efforts of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, OTOMO no Kunimichi and him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a vehement supporter of both Tendai sect and Shingon sect of Buddhism, and that the Imperial sanction was given on June 11, 822 (lunar calendar date) to the project of the building of Daijo-Kaidan (Mahayana ordination center), which was tangling because Sogo (Office of Monastic Affairs) strongly opposed, is said to be due to the efforts of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, OTOMO no Kunimichi and him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a vehement supporter of both Tendai sect and Shingon sect of Buddhism, and that the Imperial sanction was given on June 11, 822 (lunar calendar date) to the project of the building of Daijo-Kaidan (Mahayana ordination center), which was tangling because Sogo (Office of Monastic Affairs) strongly opposed, is said to be due to the efforts of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, OTOMO no Kunimichi and him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>翌14年3月には、大伴国道とともに初代延暦寺俗別当に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of the next year, he was appointed to the 1st Zokubetto (the secular superior post) of Enryaku-ji Temple with OTOMO no Kunimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of the next year, he was appointed to the 1st Zokubetto (the secular superior post) of Enryaku-ji Temple with OTOMO no Kunimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of the next year, he was appointed to the 1st Zokubetto (the secular superior post) of Enryaku-ji Temple with OTOMO no Kunimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天長5年12月15日 (旧暦)には、空海が彼から譲り受けた私邸に綜芸種智院を設置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 15, 828 (lunar calendar date), Kukai established Shugei Shuchiin school at the private residence given from Tadamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 15, 828 (lunar calendar date), Kukai established the Shugei Shuchiin school at the private residence given from Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 15, 828 (lunar calendar date), Kukai established the Shugei Shuchiin school at the private residence given from Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>嵯峨天皇の皇后、橘嘉智子の義兄であり、藤原長良・藤原良房らの伯父でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also a brother-in-law of TACHIBANA no Kachiko, the Empress of Emperor Saga and an uncle of FUJIWARA no Nagara and FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also a brother-in-law of TACHIBANA no Kachiko, the Empress of Emperor Saga and an uncle of FUJIWARA no Nagara and FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also a brother-in-law of TACHIBANA no Kachiko, the Empress of Emperor Saga and an uncle of FUJIWARA no Nagara and FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>三守の死後、藤原南家は直後に起きた承和の変などによる、藤原北家の台頭もあって、政治的にさらに衰退したが、彼の曾孫藤原元真は三十六歌仙の一人とされるほどの歌人となり、玄孫の藤原棟世は清少納言と結婚している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Tadamori, the Southern House of the Fujiwara Clan further declined politically as the rise of the Northern House of Fujiwara Clan mainly due to the Jowa incident broken out soon after his death, however, his great-grandson FUJIWARA no Motozane became a great poet who was counted in one of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets and his great-great-grandson FUJIWARA no Muneyo married Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Tadamori, the Southern House of the Fujiwara Clan further declined politically as the rise of the Northern House of Fujiwara Clan mainly due to the Jowa incident broken out soon after his death, however, his great-grandson FUJIWARA no Motozane became a great poet who was counted in one of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets and his great-great-grandson FUJIWARA no Muneyo married Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Tadamori, the Southern House of the Fujiwara Clan further declined politically as the rise of the Northern House of Fujiwara Clan mainly due to the Jowa incident broken out soon after his death, however, his great-grandson FUJIWARA no Motozane became a great poet who was counted in one of the Thirty-six Immortal Poets and his great-great-grandson FUJIWARA no Muneyo married Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>棟世と清少納言との間の娘である上東門院小馬命婦も、一条天皇の皇后藤原彰子に仕え、平安時代中期の円融朝で女性歌人として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jotomonin Kouma no Myobu who was a daughter of Muneyo and Sei Shonagon also served the Empress of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, and played an active role as a female poet in the period of Emperor Enyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jotomonin Kouma no Myobu who was a daughter of Muneyo and Sei Shonagon also served the Empress of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, and played an active role as a female poet in the period of Emperor Enyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jotomonin Kouma no Myobu who was a daughter of Muneyo and Sei Shonagon also served the Empress of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, and played an active role as a female poet in the period of Emperor Enyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Andee(id:20421), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>