<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今出川実直</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanenao IMADEGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanenao IMADEGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanenao IMADEGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今出川 実直（いまでがわ さねなお、興国3年/康永元年（1342年） - 応永3年5月15日 (旧暦)（1396年6月21日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)・室町時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanenao IMADEGAWA (1342 - June 21, 1396) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanenao IMADEGAWA (1342 - June 21, 1396) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanenao IMADEGAWA (1342 - June 29, 1396) was a kugyo (court noble) who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に後村上天皇（97代）/後光厳天皇（北朝4代）から後小松天皇（100代）にわたって仕え、官位は従一位右大臣まで昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served the dynasties from Emperor Gomurakami (the 97th emperor) to Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th emperor), and advanced up to Udaijin (minister of the right) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served the dynasties from Emperor Gomurakami (the 97th emperor) to Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th emperor), and advanced up to Udaijin (minister of the right) at the rank of Juichii (Junior 1rst Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served the dynasties from Emperor Gomurakami (the 97th) and Emperor Gokogon (the 4th emperor of the Northern Court) to Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th), and advanced up to Udaijin (minister of the right) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は大納言今出川実尹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sanetada IMADEGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sanetada IMADEGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Dainagon (chief councilor of state) Sanetada IMADEGAWA.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄に左大臣今出川公直がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinnao IMADEGAWA was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinnao IMADEGAWA was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinnao IMADEGAWA, Sadaijin (minister of the left), was his older brother.</e>
<cmt>用語統一訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に左大臣今出川公行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinyuki IMADEGAWA, Sadaijin (minister of the left) was his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinyuki IMADEGAWA, Sadaijin (minister of the left) was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinyuki IMADEGAWA, Sadaijin (minister of the left) was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後今出川右大臣と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called later Imadegawa Udaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was later called Imadegawa Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was later called Imadegawa Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>正平 (日本)13年/延文3年（1358年）に従三位となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1358, he was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1358, he was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank), becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1358, he was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、周防権守・参議・中納言・大納言・内教坊別当・近衛府などを歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he assumed Suo no Gon no kami (a provisional governor of Suo Province), Sangi (a councilor), Chunagon (a middle counselor), Dainagon (a major counselor), Naikyobo no Betto (the chief of Naikyobo (a place in Imperial Palace where singing and dancing was taught), and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) in succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he assumed Suo no Gon no kami (provisional governor of Suo Province), Sangi (councilor), Chunagon (middle counselor), Dainagon (major counselor), Naikyobo no Betto (chief of Naikyobo - a place in the Imperial Palace where singing and dancing was taught), and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) in succession.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he assumed Suo no Gon no kami (provisional governor of Suo Province), Sangi (councilor), Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Naikyobo no Betto (chief of Naikyobo - a place in the Imperial Palace where singing and dancing was taught), and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) in succession.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除用語統一－→-</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>応永元年（1394年）に内大臣を経ずして右大臣に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1394, he was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) without assuming Naidaijin (minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1394, he was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) without assuming Naidaijin (minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1394, he was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) without assuming Naidaijin (minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌年官職を辞すも従一位を授与される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned from the post in the next year, but awarded the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from the post during the next year, but awarded the rank of Juichii (Junior 1st Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from the post during the next year, but awarded the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>応永3年（1396年）5月に兄公直が嗣子無く薨去し、実直が今出川家の跡を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brother, Kinnao, died in June - July of 1396 with no heir, and Sanenao inherited the line of Imadegawa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brother, Kinnao, died in June - July of 1396 with no heir, and Sanenao inherited the line of Imadegawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brother, Kinnao, died in June of 1396 with no heir, and Sanenao inherited the line of Imadegawa family.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリ暦表記方法</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしながら、実直も同年同月中に後を追うように薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he also died in the same month of the same year, as chasing his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he also died in the same month of the same year, following his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he also died in the same month of the same year, following his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>結局、実直の子公行が今出川家の名跡を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, Sanenao&apos;s son, Kinyuki, inherited the Imadegawa&apos;s line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, Sanenao&apos;s son, Kinyuki, inherited the Imadegawa line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, Sanenao&apos;s son, Kinyuki, inherited the Imadegawa line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>