<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源隆国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takakuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Takakuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takakuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 隆国（みなもと の たかくに、寛弘元年（1004年） - 承保4年7月9日 (旧暦)（1077年7月31日））は、平安時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takakuni (1004 – Jul. 31, 1077) was a courtier in the later Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Takakuni (1004 – Jul. 31, 1077) was a courtier during the later Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takakuni (1004 – August 6, 1077) was a courtier during the later Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>醍醐源氏、大納言源俊賢の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigo Genji, Dainagon MINAMOTO no Toshikata&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigo Genji, Dainagon MINAMOTO no Toshikata&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigo-Genji (Minamoto clan), Dainagon (chief councilor of state) MINAMOTO no Toshikata&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>「醍醐源氏」、「大納言」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幼名は宗国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Munekuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Munekuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Munekuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正二位・大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>宇治大納言と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called the Uji Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called the Uji Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called the Uji Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>長和4年（1014年）に従五位下となり、以後侍従・伊予国介・右近衛権中将・蔵人頭などを歴任し、長元7年（1034年）、従三位参議に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1014, he becameJugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and later was Jiju, Iyo Province Assistant Governor, Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), and in 1034 reached Jusanmi Sangi (councillor in the Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1014, he became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and later was Jiju, Iyo Province Assistant Governor, Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), and in 1034 reached Jusanmi Sangi (councillor in the Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1014, he became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and later was Jiju (Chamberlain), Assistant Governor of Iyo Province, Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), and in 1034 reached Jusanmi Sangi (councillor in the Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Jijuの補足追加、Iyo Province Assistant Governor→Assistant Governor of Iyo Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1043年（長久4年）権中納言に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1043, he was appointed Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1043, he was appointed Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1043, he was appointed Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>康平4年（1061年）、権中納言を辞し、子の源俊明を加賀国守に申任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1061, he quit Gon chunagon and had his child MINAMOTO no Toshiaki as Kaga Province Governor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1061, he quit Gon chunagon and had his child MINAMOTO no Toshiaki as Kaga Province Governor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1061, he quit Gon Chunagon and had his child MINAMOTO no Toshiaki as Governor of Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagon、Governor of Kaga Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1067年（治暦3年）正二位権大納言に任じられるが、承保元年（1074年）権大納言を辞し、外孫である藤原師兼を申任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1067, he was appointed Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon, but in 1074 he quit Gondainagon and had his grandchild through his daughter, FUJIWARA no Morokane appointed to the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1067, he was appointed Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon, but in 1074 he quit Gondainagon and had his grandchild through his daughter, FUJIWARA no Morokane appointed to the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1067, he was appointed Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon, but in 1074 he quit Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) and had his grandchild through his daughter, FUJIWARA no Morokane appointed to the position.</e>
<cmt>Gondainagon→Gon Dainagonとし、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>井澤長秀（肥後藩士、国学者、関口流抜刀術第三代）によって、『今昔物語』の作者とされたが（『考訂今昔物語』）、現在では否定説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was considered as the author of Konjaku Monogatari (Shu) (The Tale of Times Now Past) by Nagahide IZAWA (Higo hanshi, Japanese study acedemic, Sekiguchi style battojutsu (the technique of drawing a sword) third head) in &quot;Kotei Konjyaku monogatari&quot;, but currently there is strong evidence to negate this theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was considered as the author of Konjaku Monogatari (Shu) (The Tale of Times Now Past) by Nagahide IZAWA (Higo hanshi, Japanese study acedemic, Sekiguchi style battojutsu (the technique of drawing a sword - third head) in &quot;Kotei Konjyaku monogatari,&quot; but currently there is strong evidence to negate this theory.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was considered as the author of &quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu)&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past) by Nagahide IZAWA (clansman of the Higo Domain, scholar of Japanese classical literature, and the third head of Sekiguchi style battojutsu - the technique of drawing a sword) in &quot;Kotei Konjaku Monogatari,&quot; but currently there is strong evidence to negate this theory.</e>
<cmt>(肥後藩士、国学者、関口流抜刀術第三代) の表記を修正、Konjaku Monogatari (Shu)のクォーテーション追加、&quot;Kotei Konjaku Monogatari&quot;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、隆国は『宇治大納言物語』の作者ともされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni is also considered as the author of Ujidainagon monogatari (The Tale of Uji Dainagon chief councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni is also considered as the author of Ujidainagon monogatari (The Tale of Uji Dainagon chief councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni is also considered as the author of &quot;Uji Dainagon Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Uji Dainagon chief councilor).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Uji Dainagon Monogatari&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 デーモン博士(id:99293), Masyu(id:31065), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Bueller 007(id:30970), Y.Sanada(id:36926), 代言人(id:33675), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>