<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原忠通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadamichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 忠通（ふじわら の ただみち、承徳元年1月29日 (旧暦)（1097年3月15日） - 長寛2年2月19日 (旧暦)（1164年3月13日））は、平安時代後期の摂政・関白・太政大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamichi [January 29, 1097 - February 19, 1164 on lunar calendar (March 15, 1097 - March 13, 1164)] was a regent, chief advisor to the Emperor and Grand Minister in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadamichi [January 29, 1097 - February 19, 1164 according to the lunar calendar (March 15, 1097 - March 13, 1164)] served as regent, chief advisor to the Emperor, and Grand Minister in the later part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadamichi (February 19, 1097 - March 20, 1164) served as regent, chief advisor to the Emperor, and Grand Minister in the later part of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>新暦のみの表記にしました。グレゴリオ暦に変換。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原忠実の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Tadazane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Tadazane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Tadazane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は右大臣源顕房の娘・源師子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother MINAMOTO no Moroko was a daughter of Minister of the Right, MINAMOTO no Akifusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother, MINAMOTO no Moroko, was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Akifusa, who had served as Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>grammar, time frame he held the post</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother, MINAMOTO no Moroko, was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Akifusa, who had served as Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>北政所（正室）は権大納言藤原宗通の娘・宗子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kita-no-Mandokoro (legal wife) was Muneko, a daughter of gon-dainagon (provisional major councilor) FUJIWARA no Munemichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal wide (Kita-no-Mandokoro) was named Muneko, and she was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Munemichi, who had served as a gon-dainagon (provisional major councilor).</e>
<cmt>unclear as to meaning of Kita-no-Madokoro, title?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wide (Kita no mandokoro) was named Muneko, and she was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Munemichi, who had served as a Gon Dainagon (provisional major councilor).</e>
<cmt>Kita no mandokoroと訂正しました。Gon Dainagonと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>覚忠・近衛基実（母は権中納言源国信女信子）・松殿基房（母は源国信女俊子）・九条兼実（母は太皇太后宮大進藤原仲光女加賀）・藤原兼房 (太政大臣)（母は兼実に同じ）・信円・慈円（母は兼実に同じ）らの父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons were Kakuchu Motozane KONOE (his mother Nobuko was a daughter of gon-chunagon MINAMOTO no Kunizane), MATSUDONO no Motofusa (his mother Toshiko was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Kunizane), Kanezane KUJO (his mother Kaga was a daughter of Taiko taigo miya taishin FUJIWARA no Nakamitsu), FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (Grand Minister) (his mother was same as Kanezane, and Shinen and Jien (their mother was the same as Kanezane).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons were Kakuchu Motozane KONOE (his mother Nobuko was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Kunizane, who had served as a gon-chunagon), MATSUDONO no Motofusa (his mother Toshiko was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Kunizane), Kanezane KUJO (his mother Kaga was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nakamitsu, who had served as a Taiko taigo miya taishin), FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (who was to become a Grand Minister, and whose mother was same as Kanezane&apos;s, Shinen, and Jien (their mother was also the same as Kanezane&apos;s).</e>
<cmt>titles need English definitions or approximations?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons were Kakuchu Motozane KONOE (his mother Nobuko was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Kunizane, who had served as a Gon Chunagon), MATSUDONO no Motofusa (his mother Toshiko was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Kunizane), Kanezane KUJO (his mother Kaga was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nakamitsu, who had served as a Taiko taigo miya taishin), FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (who was to become a Grand Minister, and whose mother was same as Kanezane&apos;s, Shinen, and Jien (their mother was also the same as Kanezane&apos;s).</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagonと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>娘に崇徳天皇の中宮聖子（皇嘉門院、母は正室藤原宗子）・二条天皇の中宮藤原育子（母は上野守源顕俊女俊子、養女ともいわれる）、養女に近衛天皇の中宮呈子（九条院、北政所宗子の兄太政大臣藤原伊通の娘）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughters were Emperor Sutoku&apos;s wife Chugu Seiko (Koka Moin, her mother was Tadamichi&apos;s legal wife FUJIWARA no Muneko), Emperor Nijo&apos;s wife Chugu FUJIWARA no Ikushi (her mother Toshiko was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Akitoshi, Ueno no kami, might be adopted daughter) and his adopted daughter Emperor Konoe&apos;s wife Chugu Teishi (Kujo-in, his legal wife Muneko&apos;s brother Grand Minister FUJIWARA no Koremichi&apos;s daughter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughters were Emperor Sutoku&apos;s wife Chugu Seiko (Koka Moin, her mother was Tadamichi&apos;s legal wife FUJIWARA no Muneko), Emperor Nijo&apos;s wife Chugu FUJIWARA no Ikushi (her mother, Toshiko, was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Akitoshi, who had served as Ueno no kami, and she may have been adopted), and his adopted daughter Emperor Konoe&apos;s wife Chugu Teishi (Kujo-in, the daughter of the brother, Grand Minister FUJIWARA no Koremichi, of his legal wife, Muneko).</e>
<cmt>confusing where the same person has two names.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughters were Emperor Sutoku&apos;s wife Chugu Seiko (Kokamonin, her mother was Tadamichi&apos;s legal wife FUJIWARA no Muneko), Emperor Nijo&apos;s wife Chugu FUJIWARA no Ikushi (her mother, Toshiko, was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Akitoshi, who had served as Ueno no kami, and she may have been adopted), and his adopted daughter Emperor Konoe&apos;s wife Chugu Teishi (Kujoin, the daughter of the brother, Grand Minister FUJIWARA no Koremichi, of his legal wife, Muneko).</e>
<cmt>Kokamoninと訂正しました。Kujoinと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1121年、父忠実に代わって藤原氏の藤氏長者となり、鳥羽天皇の関白に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1121, he became a head of the Fujiwara clan and acceded to the post of Kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor) of Emperor Toba in place of his father Tadazane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1121, he became a head of the Fujiwara clan and was appointed to the post of Kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor), serving Emperor Toba in place of his father, Tadazane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1121, he became a head of the Fujiwara clan and was appointed to the post of Kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor), serving Emperor Toba in place of his father, Tadazane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後も崇徳天皇・近衛天皇・後白河天皇の3代に渡って摂政・関白を務めることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Sesho (regent) and Kanpaku for three more emperors; Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe and Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as Sesho (regent) and Kanpaku under three more emperors: Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe, and Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as Sesho (regent) and Kanpaku under three more emperors: Emperor Sutoku, Emperor Konoe, and Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>摂関歴37年は高祖父藤原頼通の50年に次ぐ2位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had worked for 37 years as Sesho and Kanpaku, that was the second longest after FUJIWARA no Yorimichi&apos;s 50 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His tenure of 37 years in the posts of Sesho and Kanpaku was the second longest; FUJIWARA no Yorimichi had held the posts for a total of 50 years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His tenure of 37 years in the posts of Sesho and Kanpaku was the second longest; FUJIWARA no Yorimichi had held the posts for a total of 50 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>一般には父忠実が弟の藤原頼長を寵愛する余り、摂政・関白の座を弟に譲るように圧力をかけられたように言われているが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his father Tadazane loved his younger son Yorinaga so much that Tadazane forced Tadamichi to cede the position of Sesho and Kanpaku to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his father, Tadazane, loved his younger son Yorinaga so much that he pressuredTadamichi to cede the positions of Sesho and Kanpaku to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his father, Tadazane, loved his younger son Yorinaga so much that he pressured Tadamichi to cede the positions of Sesho and Kanpaku to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>実際には長い間家を継ぐべき男子に恵まれず、1125年に23歳年下の頼長を一度は養子に迎えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Tadamichi hadn&apos;t had any heirs for years and adopted Yorinaga who was 23 years younger than him as his son in 1125.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, as Tadamichi had not been blessed with an heir for many, he adopted Yorinaga, who was 23 years younger than him, in 1125.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, as Tadamichi had not been blessed with an heir for many, he adopted Yorinaga, who was 23 years younger than him, in 1125.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>だが、40歳を過ぎてから次々と男子に恵まれるようになった忠通が実子に家を譲るために頼長との縁組を破棄したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he had boys after age of 40 years and renounced the adoption of Yorinaga to cede to his real sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when he had passed the age of 40 years he his wives gave birth to sons, whereupon he renounced the adoption of Yorinaga so as to pass the posts along to his real sons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when he had passed the age of 40 years he his wives gave birth to sons, whereupon he renounced the adoption of Yorinaga so as to pass the posts along to his real sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>忠通と忠実・頼長は近衛天皇の後宮政策においても対立し、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamichi conflicted with Tadazane and Yorinaga about inner palace (harem) of Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamichi was at odds with Tadazane and Yorinaga regarding the inner palace (harem) of Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamichi was at odds with Tadazane and Yorinaga regarding the inner palace (harem) of Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>1150年正月に頼長が養女藤原多子を入内させ、皇后に冊立させたのに対し、忠通もその三ヵ月後にやはり養女藤原呈子を入内させて、中宮に冊立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On New Years of 1150, Yorinaga sent his adopted daughter FUJIWARA no Tashi to the inner palace as bride-to-be, then Tadamichi also put his adopted daughter FUJIWARA no Teishi into the inner palace three months later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On New Years of 1150, Yorinaga sent his adopted daughter, FUJIWARA no Tashi, to the inner palace as bride-to-be, three months after which Tadamichi also sent his adopted daughter, FUJIWARA no Teishi, to the inner palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On New Years of 1150, Yorinaga sent his adopted daughter, FUJIWARA no Tashi, to the inner palace as bride-to-be, three months after which Tadamichi also sent his adopted daughter, FUJIWARA no Teishi, to the inner palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この呈子立后にとうとう忠実・頼長は業を煮やし、忠通は同年父から義絶されて弟頼長に氏長者職を譲らされるが、多子と天皇の接触を妨害する事などで対抗し、1155年の後白河天皇の即位により復権。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadazane and Yorinaga got angry at Tadamichi&apos;s inner palace plan, cut off the relationship and made him cede the post of Ujinochoja (head of Fujiwara clan), however, Tadamichi countered them, interrupting Tashi&apos;s meeting the emperor, then finally when Emperor Go-Shirakawa ascended in 1155, Tadamichi revested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamichi&apos;s machinations on the inner palace were the last straw for Tadazane and Yorinaga, and that same year Tadazane severed his relationship with Tadamichi, forcing him to cede the title of Ujinochoja (head of the Fujiwara clan) to Yorinaga; however, Tadamichi countered by interferring in Tashi&apos;s relationship with the emperor, and when Emperor Go-Shirakawa ascended the throne in 1155, Tadamichi was reinstated to his former posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar. somewhat lacking detail</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamichi&apos;s machinations on the inner palace were the last straw for Tadazane and Yorinaga, and that same year Tadazane severed his relationship with Tadamichi, forcing him to cede the title of Ujinochoja (head of the Fujiwara clan) to Yorinaga; however, Tadamichi countered by interfering in Tashi&apos;s relationship with the emperor, and when Emperor Goshirakawa ascended the throne in 1155, Tadamichi was reinstated to his former posts.</e>
<cmt>interferingスペル訂正しました。Goshirakawaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>それら一連の対立が保元の乱一つの原因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These series of conflicts became causes of the Hogen Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This series of incidents were one cause of the Hogen Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This series of incidents were one cause of the Hogen Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>乱後、藤氏長者の地位は回復されたが、その際に前の藤氏長者である頼長が罪人でかつ死亡していることを理由として、宣旨によって任命が行われ、藤原氏による自律性を否認された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Hogen Disturbance, Tadamichi got back the post of the head of Fujiwara clan, however, as the former head Yorinaga died as sinner, the autonomy of Fujiwara clan collapsed and the appointment was proceeded with the senji (imperial letter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Hogen Disturbance, Tadamichi regained the title as head of Fujiwara clan; however, because the former head, Yorinaga, had been disgraced and was now dead, the Fujiwara clan was stripped of its autonomous status, and the appointment was made by senji (Imperial letter).</e>
<cmt>unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Hogen Disturbance, Tadamichi regained the title as head of Fujiwara clan; however, because the former head, Yorinaga, had been disgraced and was now dead, the Fujiwara clan was stripped of its autonomous status, and the appointment was made by senji (Imperial letter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>更に忠実・頼長が所有していた摂関家伝来の荘園及び個人の荘園が全て没官領として剥奪されることになったが、忠通が忠実に摂関家伝来のものと忠実個人の荘園を自分に譲与するように迫り、漸く忠通の所領として認められて没収を回避された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the all manors which Tadazane and Yorinaga owned including line of regents and advisers manors and their private monors were to be forfeited, but as Tadamichi pressed Tadazane to give the line of regents and advisers manors and Tadazane&apos;s private manors to him, Tadamichi owned them without forfeit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the official residences that were in the possession of Tadazane and Yorinaga, including those for the regent and advisors, as well as their privately owned residences were to be forfeited; however, as Tadamichi had imposed upon Tadazane to cede possession of the official and private residences to him, Tadamichi was at length able to avert their confiscation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the official residences that were in the possession of Tadazane and Yorinaga, including those for the regent and advisors, as well as their privately owned residences were to be forfeited; however, as Tadamichi had imposed upon Tadazane to cede possession of the official and private residences to him, Tadamichi was at length able to avert their confiscation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>1158年、関白職を嫡男の近衛基実に譲った後、1162年に出家して円観と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1158, Tadamichi ceded the post of Kanpaku to his son Motonzane KONOE, then became priest named Enkan in 1162.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1158, Tadamichi ceded the post of Kanpaku to his son Motozane KONOE, then became a Buddhist priest, assuming the name Enkan, in 1162.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1158, Tadamichi ceded the post of Kanpaku to his son Motozane KONOE, then became a Buddhist priest, assuming the name Enkan, in 1162.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>忠通が藤氏長者となった時は既に摂関政治は形骸化し、さらに父や弟との対立を抱え、男子を設けるのも遅い方であったが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadamichi became the head of Fujiwara clan, his situation was not so good because Sekkan seiji (regency politics) had lost substance, he had conflicts against his father and brother and also he had late children.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tadamichi had become head of the Fujiwara clan, the situation was somewjhat adverse in that the Sekkan seiji (regency politics) had lost its viability, he was in conflict with his father and brother, and he did not produce a son to be his heir until much later.</e>
<cmt>grammar, time frame</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tadamichi had become head of the Fujiwara clan, the situation was somewhat adverse in that the Sekkan seiji (regency politics) had lost its viability, he was in conflict with his father and brother, and he did not produce a son to be his heir until much later.</e>
<cmt>somewhatスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのような悪い状況の中でも本来対抗勢力である鳥羽法皇や平氏等院政勢力と巧みに結びつき、保元の乱に続く、平治の乱でも実質的な権力者藤原信西とは対称的に生き延び、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he could survive during the Hogen Disturbance and the Heiji Revolt working with Emperor Toba and Taira clan who were his opponents, while FUJIWARA no Shinzei who had real power at that time died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was able to survive under these circumstances by crafting alliances with Emperor Toba and the Taira clan, with whom had originally been foes, and lived through the Hogen Disturbance and the Heiji Revolt, when FUJIWARA no Shinzei had exercised the real power.</e>
<cmt>end is unclear, don&apos;t catch the reference to his death.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was able to survive under these circumstances by crafting alliances with Cloistered Emperor Toba and the Taira clan, with whom had originally been foes, and lived through the Hogen Disturbance and the Heiji Revolt, when FUJIWARA no Shinzei had exercised the real power.</e>
<cmt>鳥羽法皇→Cloistered Emperor Tobaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>彼の直系子孫のみが摂家として原則的に明治時代開幕まで摂政・関白職を独占する事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only his direct descendant could continue as regents and advisers family until Meiji period started.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the end of the Edo bakufu and the beginning of the Meiji period, Tadamichi&apos;s direct descendants, in principle, had a monopoly on the posts of kanpaku (chief advisors to the emperor) and sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>grammar, what is meant by 原則的 is unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the end of the Edo bakufu and the beginning of the Meiji period, Tadamichi&apos;s direct descendants, in principle, had a monopoly on the posts of kanpaku (chief advisors to the emperor) and sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>詩歌にも長じ、書法にも一家をなして法性寺様といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was good at poetry and also a great calligrapher called Mr. Hosho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a good poet and an expert calligrapher, who was sometimes called Mr. Hosho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>What is the significance of &quot;法性寺様&quot; in relation to poetry and calligraphy? Unclear at this juncture.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a good poet and an expert calligrapher, who was sometimes called &quot;Hosshoji sama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>通称であると解釈して、&quot;Hosshoji sama&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>漢詩集に『法性寺関白集』、家集に『田多民治集』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his works, kanshi shu (Chinese poetry collection) &quot;Hosho-ji Kanpaku shu&quot; and a poet&apos;s poetical works &quot;Tadamichi shu&quot;are known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to his works, there is a collection of his Chinese style poetry) entitled, &quot;Hosho-ji Kanpaku shu&quot;, and a collection of his other poetical works entitled, &quot;Tadamichi shu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to his works, there is a collection of his Chinese style poetry) entitled, &quot;Hosshoji Kanpaku shu&quot;, and a collection of his other poetical works entitled, &quot;Tadamichi shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Hosshojiに訂正しました。ピリオド位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>百人一首から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakunin Ishu (100 poems by 100 famous poets)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakunin Ishu (100 poems by 100 famous poets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakunin Ishu (100 poems by 100 famous poets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>「わたの原 こぎいでてみれば 久方の雲いにまがふ 沖つ白波」（法性寺入道前関白太政大臣）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">O&apos;er the wide sea plain, As I row and look around, It appears to me That the white waves, far away, Are the ever shining sky.&apos; (Hoshoji no Nyudomae Kampaku Grand Minister)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As I row out into the wide open sea, the foaming crests of far off waves appear as one with the clouds shining in the sky.&apos; (Hoshoji no Nyudomae Kampaku Grand Minister)</e>
<cmt>Is the original translation a bonafide translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As I row out into the wide open sea, the foaming crests of far off waves appear as one with the clouds shining in the sky.&apos; (Hosshoji no nyudo, the former Kampaku Grand Minister)</e>
<cmt>Hosshoji no nyudo, the former Kampaku Grand Ministerと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>書家としての評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reputation as a Calligrapher</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reputation as a Calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reputation as a Calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>法性寺流を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He opened Hoshoji ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He founded the Hoshoji school of calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He founded the Hoshoji school of calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>肉太で、丸味と力強さを兼ね備えた生々したものであるという定評がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His style has been noted for bold, round and powerful and vital handwriting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This school is noted for its vivacious style, combingin bold, round and powerful strokes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This school is noted for its vivacious style, combining bold, round and powerful strokes.</e>
<cmt>combiningスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="32">
<j>藤原基衡が毛越寺に伽藍を建立した際、金堂円隆寺（のちに兵火で焼失）に掲げる額の揮毫を忠通に依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Motohira built a monastery in Motsu-ji Temple, he asked Tadamichi to write a framed calligraphy for Kondo enryaku-ji Temple (later, it was burnt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When FUJIWARA no Motohira was building a large temple at Motsu-ji Temple, he asked Tadamichi for a sample of his calligraphy to frame and hang at Kondo enryaku-ji Temple (which later burned down).</e>
<cmt>grammar, what is the relationship between the two temples? Is the name of the first temple the name of what (monastery?) was being built, or does that refer to new construction in the precents? I assumed that the second is a sub-temple located in the precincts of the first.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Motohira was building a large temple at Motsu-ji Temple, he asked Tadamichi for a sample of his calligraphy to frame and hang at Kondo Enryaku-ji Temple (which later burned down).</e>
<cmt>Enryakuと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、奥州藤原氏は京都からすれば俘囚の係累であり、身分を明かして依頼しても応じられるはずがないため、実際の依頼は仁和寺を通して行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohira asked writing through Ninna-ji Temple because Oshu-Fujiwara clan looked like frontiersmen from people in Kyoto and he worried that Tadamichi didn&apos;t write for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohira made the request for the calligraphy through the Ninna-ji Temple, as he was concerned that people like him, from the Oshu branch of the Fujiwara clan, would be taken for crude frontiersmen by people in Kyoto, and that Tadamichi mightnot be inclined to grant his request.</e>
<cmt>Where was Oshu?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohira made the request for the calligraphy through the Ninna-ji Temple, as he was concerned that people like him, from the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, would be taken for crude frontiersmen by people in Kyoto, and that Tadamichi might not be inclined to grant his request.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。Oshu-Fujiwaraと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>のちに真の依頼者を知った忠通は額を取り返そうとしたが失敗に終わる（『吾妻鏡』には「円隆寺の額は関白忠通の筆、色紙形は藤原教長」とある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadamichi knew that the real request came from Motohira, he tried to get back his writing but failed. (According to the &quot;Azuma kagami,&quot; the framed calligraphy in Enryaku-ji Temple was written by Kanpaku Tadamichi, and a calligraphy on strips of paper was written by FUJIWARA no Norinaga.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tadamichi found out who the request actually came from, he tried to have his calligraphy returned, but his efforts ended in failure. (According to the &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; the framed calligraphy in Enryaku-ji Temple was written by Kanpaku Tadamichi, and the calligraphy on the paper strips was written by FUJIWARA no Norinaga.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tadamichi found out who the request actually came from, he tried to have his calligraphy returned, but his efforts ended in failure. (According to the &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; the framed calligraphy in Enryaku-ji Temple was written by Kanpaku Tadamichi, and the calligraphy on the paper strips was written by FUJIWARA no Norinaga.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>嘉承2年（1107年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1107</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1107</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1107</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>4月26日 (旧暦)：元服し、正五位下に叙位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 26 (lunar calendar) : After the ceremony of attaining manhood, Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 26 (lunar calendar) : After he celebrated his Genpuku ceremony (first wearing of the hakama), the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was conferred on Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, format?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 26 (lunar calendar): After he celebrated his Genpuku ceremony (first wearing of the hakama), the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was conferred on Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>禁色を許される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was allowed to wear banned colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was permitted to wear prohibited colors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was permitted to wear prohibited colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="39">
<j>6月18日 (旧暦)：侍従に任官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 18 (lunar calendar) : He became chamberlain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 18 (lunar calendar) : He became chamberlain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 18 (lunar calendar): He became chamberlain.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>11月25日 (旧暦)：右近衛権少将に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 25 (lunar calendar) : He was appointed to Ukonoegon shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 25 (lunar calendar) : He was appointed to the post of Ukonoegon shosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar. Why no English translation of &quot;ukonoegon shosho?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 25 (lunar calendar): He was appointed to the post of Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。右近衛権少将→Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>12月8日 (旧暦)：右近衛中将に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 8 (lunar calendar) : He was appointed to Ukonnoe chusho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 8 (lunar calendar) : He was appointed to the post of Ukonnoe chusho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 8 (lunar calendar): He was appointed to the post of Ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>12月29日 (旧暦)：従四位下に昇叙し、右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 29 (lunar calendar) : Upgraded to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Ukonoe chusho, as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 29 (lunar calendar) : Promoted to the court rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), retained post of Ukonoe chusho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 29 (lunar calendar): Promoted to the court rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), retained post of Ukon no chujo.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>嘉承3年のち改元して天仁元年（1108年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1108 (name of era was changed from Kasho to Tennin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1108 (the name of era was changed from Kasho to Tennin)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1108 (the name of era was changed from Kasho to Tennin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>1月：播磨権守を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January : Harima gon no kami (chief of Harima Province), concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January : Appointed as Harima gon no kami (chief of Harima Province), concurrently held with his other post.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January: Appointed as Harima gon no kami (provisional governor of Harima Province), concurrently held with his other post.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。播磨権守→Harima gon no kami (provisional governor of Harima Province)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>12月20日 (旧暦)：正四位下に昇叙し、右近衛中将・播磨権守如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 20 (lunar calendar) : Upgraded to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Ukonoe chusho and Harima gon no kami, as they were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 20 (lunar calendar) : Promoted to the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), retained his posts as Ukonoe chusho and Harima gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 20 (lunar calendar): Promoted to the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), retained his posts as Ukone no chujo and Harima gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>天仁3年（1110年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1110</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1110</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1110</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>2月25日 (旧暦)：従三位に昇叙し、右近衛中将・播磨権守如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 25 (lunar calendar) : Upgraded to Jusani (Junior Third Rank), Ukonoe chusho and Harima gon no kami, as they were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 25 (lunar calendar) : Promoted to the court rand of Jusani (Junior Third Rank), retained his posts of Ukonoe chusho and Harima gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 25 (lunar calendar): Promoted to the court rand of Jusani (Junior Third Rank), retained his posts of Ukone no chujo and Harima gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>5月13日 (旧暦)：正三位に昇叙し、右近衛中将・播磨権守如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 13 (lunar calendar) : Upgraded to Shosani (Senior Third Rank), Ukonoe chusho and Harima gon no kami, as they were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 13 (lunar calendar) : Promoted to Shosani (Senior Third Rank), retained his posts of Ukonoe chusho and Harima gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 13 (lunar calendar): Promoted to Shosani (Senior Third Rank), retained his posts of Ukone no chujo and Harima gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>天永2年（1111年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1111</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1111</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1111</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>1月23日 (旧暦)：権中納言に転任し、右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 23 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Gon-Chunagon and Ukonnoe chusho, as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 23 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the post of Gon-Chunagon, retained the post of Ukonnoe chusho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 23 (lunar calendar): Appointed to the post of Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor), retained the post of Ukone no chujo.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。権中納言→Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor)右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>2月1日 (旧暦)：従二位に昇叙し、権中納言・右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 1 (lunar calendar) : Upgraded to Junii (Junior Second Rank), Gon-Chunagon and Ukonnoe chusho, as they were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 1 (lunar calendar) : Promoted to the court rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank), retained the posts of Gon-Chunagon and Ukonnoe chusho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 1 (lunar calendar): Promoted to the court rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank), retained the posts of Gon Chunagon and Ukone no chujo.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。権中納言→Gon Chunagon右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>天永3年（1112年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1112</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1112</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1112</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>3月18日 (旧暦)：正二位に昇叙し、権中納言・右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 18 (lunar calendar) : Upgraded to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Gon-Chunagon and Ukonnoe chusho, as they were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 18 (lunar calendar) : Promoted to the court rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank), retained the posts of Gon-Chunagon and Ukonnoe chusho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 18 (lunar calendar): Promoted to the court rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank), retained the posts of Gon Chunagon and Ukone no chujo.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。権中納言→Gon Chunagon右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>永久 (元号)3年（1115年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1115</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1115</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1115</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>1月29日 (旧暦)：権大納言に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 29 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Gon-Dainagon (provisional major councilor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 29 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the post of Gon-Dainagon (provisional major councilor).</e>
<cmt>grammar. This post does have an English translation…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 29 (lunar calendar): Appointed to the post of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。権大納言→Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>4月16日 (旧暦)：内大臣に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 16 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 16 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the post of Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 16 (lunar calendar): Appointed to the post of Naidaijin (minister).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。内大臣→Naidaijin (minister)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>元永2年（1119年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1119</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1119</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1119</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>2月6日 (旧暦)：左近衛大将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 6 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Western Commander, concurrently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 6 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the post of Western Commander, concurrently held with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar, unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 6 (lunar calendar): Appointed to the post of Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), concurrently held with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。左近衛大将→Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="59">
<j>保安 (元号)2年（1121年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1121</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1121</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1121</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>3月5日 (旧暦)：関白宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 5 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 5 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the post of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>capitalization in this section for post names inconsitent with earlier sections</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 5 (lunar calendar): Appointed to the post of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。関白→Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>藤原氏長者宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointed to the head of Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointed as head of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appointed as head of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>内大臣如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal, as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the post of Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained the post of Naidaijin (minister).</e>
<cmt>内大臣→Naidaijin (minister)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>従一位行右大臣源雅実の次座のため、一座宣下無し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No upgraded because his rank was next to Juichiigyo Minister of the Right, MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was not promoted, as he was next in rank to the Juichiigyo Minister of the Right, MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was not promoted, as he was next in rank to the Juichii (Junior First Rank) gyo Minister of the Right, MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt>従一位→Juichii (Junior First Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="64">
<j>保安3年（1122年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1122</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1122</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1122</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>12月17日 (旧暦)：従一位に昇叙し、左大臣に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 17 (lunar calendar) : Upgraded to Juichii (Junior First Rank), appointed to Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 17 (lunar calendar) : Promoted to the court rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank), appointed to the post of Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17 (lunar calendar): Promoted to the court rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank), appointed to the post of Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。左大臣→Sadaijin (minister of the left)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>関白・藤原氏長者如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpaku, the head of Fujiwara clan, as they were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the post of Kanpaku and status as head of Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained the post of Kanpaku and status as head of Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>序列は、太政大臣従一位源雅実の次座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was next to Grand Minister Juichii (Junior First Rank), MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was next in rank to Grand Minister Juichii (Junior First Rank), MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His was next in rank to Grand Minister Juichii (Junior First Rank), MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="68">
<j>保安4年（1123年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1123</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1123</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1123</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>1月28日 (旧暦)：関白を止め、摂政宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 28 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Sesho in place of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 28 (lunar calendar) : Resigned as Sesho, appointed to the posit of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 28 (lunar calendar): Resigned as Sesho, appointed to the posit of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>左大臣如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minister of the Left, as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the post of Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the post of Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>序列は、太政大臣従一位源雅実より上座。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was one rank upper than Daijo daijin Juichii, MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one rank above the Daijo daijin Juichii, MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt>grammar, title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one rank above the Daijo daijin Juichii (Junior First Rank), MINAMOTO no Masazane.</e>
<cmt>従一位→Juichii (Junior First Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>一座宣下を得たか?</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He might get upgraded one rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He might have been promoted one court rank, but it is not clear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He might have been promoted one court rank, but it is not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="73">
<j>大治3年（1128年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1128</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1128</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1128</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>12月17日 (旧暦)：太政大臣宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 17 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 17 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the post of Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17 (lunar calendar): Appointed to the post of Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>摂政如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sesho, as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the post of Sesho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the post of Sesho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="76">
<j>大治4年（1129年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1129</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1129</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1129</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>4月10日 (旧暦)：太政大臣を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 10 (lunar calendar) : Resigned Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 10 (lunar calendar) : Resigned the post of Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 10 (lunar calendar): Resigned the post of Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>7月1日 (旧暦)：摂政を止め、関白宣下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 1 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Kanpaku in place of Sesho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 1 (lunar calendar) : Resigned as Sesho, appointed to the post of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 1 (lunar calendar): Resigned as Sesho, appointed to the post of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>永治元年（1141年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1141</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1141</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1141</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>12月7日 (旧暦)：関白を止め、摂政宣下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 7 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Sesho in place of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 7 (lunar calendar) : Resigned as Kanpaku, appointed to the posit of Sesho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 7 (lunar calendar): Resigned as Kanpaku, appointed to the posit of Sesho.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>久安5年（1149年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1149</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1149</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1149</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>10月25日 (旧暦)：太政大臣宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 25 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 25 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the post of Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 25 (lunar calendar): Appointed to the post of Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>摂政如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sesho, as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the post of Sesho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained the post of Sesho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="84">
<j>久安6年（1150年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1150</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1150</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1150</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>3月13日 (旧暦)：太政大臣を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 13 (lunar calendar) : Resigned Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 13 (lunar calendar) : Resigned as Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 13 (lunar calendar): Resigned as Grand Minister.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>9月26日 (旧暦)：藤原氏長者を止む（従一位行左大臣藤原頼長に長者宣下）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 26 (lunar calendar) : Resigned the head of Fujiwara clan (ceded to Junior First Rank, Minister of the left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 26 (lunar calendar) : Relinquiished status as head of Fujiwara clan (ceded to Junior First Rank, Minister of the left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 26 (lunar calendar): Relinquished status as head of Fujiwara clan (ceded to Junior First Rank, Minister of the left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga.)</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。Relinquishedスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>12月8日 (旧暦)：摂政を止め、関白宣下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 8 (lunar calendar) : Resigned Sesho and appointed to Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 8 (lunar calendar) : Resigned as Sesho, and appointed to Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 8 (lunar calendar): Resigned as Sesho, and appointed to Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>久寿3年（1156年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1156</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1156</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1156</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>7月11日 (旧暦)：藤原氏長者宣下（藤原氏長者従一位行左大臣藤原頼長同日、薨去のため）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 11 (lunar calendar) : Appointed to the head of Fujiwara clan (because Junior First Rank, Minister of the left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga died on this day.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 11 (lunar calendar) : Appointed as head of Fujiwara clan (due to the death of Junior First Rank, Minister of the left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, on this day.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 11 (lunar calendar): Appointed as head of Fujiwara clan (due to the death of Junior First Rank, Minister of the left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, on this day.)</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>保元3年（1158年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1158</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1158</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1158</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>8月11日 (旧暦)：関白を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 11 (lunar calendar) : Resigned Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 11 (lunar calendar) : Resigned as Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 11 (lunar calendar): Resigned as Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>応保2年（1162年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1162</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1162</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1162</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>6月8日 (旧暦)：出家　法名は圓観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 8 (lunar calendar) : Entered the priesthood, named Enkan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 8 (lunar calendar) : Took the tonsure and entered the Buddhist priesthood, assuming the name Enkan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 8 (lunar calendar): Took the tonsure and entered the Buddhist priesthood, assuming the name Enkan.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1164</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1164</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1164</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>2月19日 (旧暦)：薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19 (lunar calendar) : died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 19 (lunar calendar) : Died.</e>
<cmt>grammar, phrasing?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19 (lunar calendar): Died.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>享年68</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 68 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 68 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 68 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works in Which FUJIWARA no Tadamichi Appears</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works in which FUJIWARA no Tadamichi is portrayed</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works in which FUJIWARA no Tadamichi is portrayed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>『弓張月』（1955年 監督：丸根賛太郎、演：津村礼司）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yumiharizuki (quarter moon)&quot;(1955, directed by Santaro MARUNE, featuring Reiji TSUMURA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yumiharizuki (quarter moon)&quot;(1955, directed by Santaro MARUNE, featuring Reiji TSUMURA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yumiharizuki&quot; (quarter moon) (1955, directed by Santaro MARUNE, featuring Reiji TSUMURA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>『新・平家物語 (映画)』（1955年 監督：溝口健二、演：十朱久雄）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (Tale of Heike)&quot; movie, 1955, directed by Kenji MIZOGUCHI, featuring Hisao TOAKE)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (Tale of Heike)&quot; movie, 1955, directed by Kenji MIZOGUCHI, featuring Hisao TOAKE)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Heike, movie) (1955, directed by Kenji MIZOGUCHI, featuring Hisao TOAKE)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置訂正しました。()補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>『新・平家物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1972年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：原保美）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (Tale of Heike)&quot; long-running historical drama series on NHK TV, 1972, featuring Yasumi HARA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari (Tale of Heike)&quot; long-running historical drama series on NHK TV, 1972, featuring Yasumi HARA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Heike) (long-running historical drama series on NHK TV, 1972, featuring Yasumi HARA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置訂正しました。()補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Lonicera(id:20638), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Ks8823(id:130146), 瑞雲(id:27410), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), 水野白楓(id:22811), 三浦大輔(id:93377), ふたりはGoki鰤MaxHeart(id:19635), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), さららゆら(id:12274), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 代言人(id:33675), Yume149(id:17504), Point136(id:211299), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Yas(id:739), 伏儀(id:142093), 蔭人(id:80171), 小川尚明(id:93076), Kouko0515(id:100370), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 小太刀(id:18154), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>