<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>滋野貞主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIGENO no Sadanushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIGENO no Sadanushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHIGENO no Sadanushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>滋野 貞主（しげの の さだぬし、延暦4年（785年） - 仁寿2年2月8日 (旧暦)（852年3月2日））は平安時代前期の官僚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIGENO no Sadanushi (785 – March 2, 852) was a bureaucrat in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIGENO no Sadanushi (785 – March 2, 852) was a bureaucrat during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHIGENO no Sadanushi (785–March 6, 852) was a bureaucrat in the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正。スペースを削除。「前期」を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>尾張守・滋野家訳の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The child of Owari no kami (the governor of Owari Province) SHIGENO no Ieosa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Owari no kami (the governor of Owari Province) SHIGENO no Ieosa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Owari no kami (the governor of Owari Province) SHIGENO no Ieosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に滋野善蔭、滋野善根、縄子（仁明天皇女御）、奥子（文徳天皇宮人）、直子（源国紀室）、娘（滋野吉備雄室）らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included SHIGENO no Yoshikage, SHIGENO no Yoshine, Tsunako who was nyogo (a high-ranking lady of the court (a consort of an emperor) Emperor Ninmyo, Okuko (a court lady of Emperor Montoku), 直子 (the lawful wife of MINAMOTO no Kuninori) and another daughter (the lawful wife of SHIGENO no Kibio).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included SHIGENO no Yoshikage, SHIGENO no Yoshine, Tsunako who was nyogo (a high-ranking lady of the court - a consort of an emperor) Emperor Ninmyo, Okuko (a court lady of Emperor Montoku), 直子 (the lawful wife of MINAMOTO no Kuninori) and another daughter (the lawful wife of SHIGENO no Kibio).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included SHIGENO no Yoshikage, SHIGENO no Yoshine, Tsunako (who was nyogo, a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor) of Emperor Ninmyo), Okuko (Kyujin, a court lady of Emperor Montoku), Naoiko (wife of MINAMOTO no Kuninori) and another daughter (wife of SHIGENO no Kibio).</e>
<cmt>「女御、宮人、室」を修正。「直子」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>大同 (日本)2年（807年）に文章生に及第し、弘仁6年（815年）に大内記となり弘仁14年（823年）には父とともに朝臣に改め、姓を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 807, successfully becoming a monjosho (student of Literary Studies in the Imperial University), Sadanushi was appointed as Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs) in 815 whereby, with his father, he received the title of Ason (the second highest of the eight hereditary titles) and was given the surname.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 807, successfully becoming a monjosho (student of Literary Studies in the Imperial University), Sadanushi was appointed as Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs) in 815 whereby, with his father, he received the title of Ason (the second highest of the eight hereditary titles) and was given the surname.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 807, successfully becoming a monjosho (student of Literary Studies in the Imperial University), Sadanushi was appointed as Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs) in 815 whereby, with his father, he received the title of Ason (the second highest of the eight hereditary titles) and was given the surname in 823.</e>
<cmt>年号を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>外従五位下に叙され、図書頭・東宮学士となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadanushi was conferred 外従五位下 and was appointed as Zusho no kami (Director of the Bureau of Drawing and Books) and Togu gakushi (the classic teacher for the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>「外従五位下」読み・意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadanushi was conferred 外従五位下 and was appointed as Zusho no kami (Director of the Bureau of Drawing and Books) and Togu gakushi (the classic teacher for the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadanushi was conferred Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) given to persons outside Kyoto) and was appointed as Zusho no kami (Director of the Bureau of Drawing and Books) and Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>「外従五位下、東宮学士」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天長8年（831年）には従五位下に進み、儒学者たちと古今の文書を分類して『秘府略』1000巻（現存2巻）を撰集し、また『経国集』20巻を撰上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 831, advancing to the court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Sadanushi, in cooperation with Confucian scholars, classified ancient and modern documents compiling 1000 volumes of &quot;Hifuryaku&quot; (2 volumes remain in existence today) and 20 volumes of Keikokushu (The third first anthology of Chinese poems collected by Imperial command or Japan&apos;s first anthology of Chinese miscellany compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>経国集。第三の勅撰漢詩集。また日本初の勅撰漢詩文集。http://d.hatena.ne.jp/keyword/%B7%D0%B9%F1%BD%B8</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 831, advancing to the court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Sadanushi, in cooperation with Confucian scholars, classified ancient and modern documents compiling 1000 volumes of &quot;Hifuryaku&quot; (2 volumes remain in existence today) and 20 volumes of Keikokushu (The third first anthology of Chinese poems collected by Imperial command or Japan&apos;s first anthology of Chinese miscellany compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 831, advancing to the court rank of Jugoinoge, Sadanushi, in cooperation with Confucian scholars, classified ancient and modern documents compiling 1000 volumes of &quot;Hifuryaku&quot; (2 volumes remain in existence today) and 20 volumes of &quot;Keikoku-shu&quot; (an anthology of Chinese poems compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを修正、追加。『経国集』を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>仁明天皇の時に内蔵頭・宮内大輔・兵部大輔・弾正大弼をへて従四位上の大蔵卿に讃岐守を兼ね、式部大輔となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the era of Emperor Ninmyo, after serving as Kura no kami (Chief of Kuraryo, Burau of Palace Storehouses), Kudai-taifu (a post of Imperial Household Ministry), Hyobu taiyu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Hyobusho, Ministry of Military) and Danjo-daihitsu (Senior Assistant President of the Board of Censors), Sadanushi was appointed as Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonies), holding the concurrent posts of Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury) with the court rank being Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and Sanuki no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province), becoming Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the era of Emperor Ninmyo, after serving as Kura no kami (Chief of Kuraryo, Burau of Palace Storehouses), Kudai-taifu (a post of Imperial Household Ministry), Hyobu taiyu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Hyobusho, Ministry of Military) and Danjo-daihitsu (Senior Assistant President of the Board of Censors), Sadanushi was appointed as Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonies), holding the concurrent posts of Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury) with the court rank being Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and Sanuki no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province), becoming Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the era of Emperor Ninmyo, after serving as Kura no kami (Chief of Kuraryo, Bureau of Palace Storehouses), Kudai-taifu (a post of Imperial Household Ministry), Hyobu taiyu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Hyobusho, Ministry of Military) and Danjo-daihitsu (Senior Assistant President of the Board of Censors), Sadanushi was appointed as Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial), holding the concurrent posts of Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury) with the court rank being Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and Sanuki no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正。「～を兼ね、式部大輔となる」を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>承和 (日本)9年（842年）から参議・勘解由使長官などを歴任し、「便宜十四事」を陳述。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 842, Sadanushi successively held various positions including Sangi (the Councilor) and Kageyushi chokan (Secretary of the Office of Investigators of the Records of Outgoing Officials) and issued &apos;Bengi Jushiji.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 842, Sadanushi successively held various positions including Sangi (the Councilor) and Kageyushi chokan (Secretary of the Office of Investigators of the Records of Outgoing Officials) and issued &apos;Bengi Jushiji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 842, Sadanushi successively held various positions including Sangi (the Councilor) and Kageyushi chokan (Secretary of the Office of Investigators of the Records of Outgoing Officials) and issued &apos;Bengi Jushiji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>承和11年（844年）には私宅を寺として慈恩寺を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 844, Sadanushi built made his own residence into a temple setting up Jion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 844, Sadanushi built his own residence into a temple setting up Jion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 844, Sadanushi built his own residence into a temple setting up Jion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>嘉祥年間（848年-851年）の初めに尾張守を兼ね宮内卿に遷る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Kaho era (848 – 851), Sadanushi transferred to the post Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) concurrently serving as Owari no kami (the Governor of Owari Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Kaho era (848 – 851), Sadanushi transferred to the post Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) concurrently serving as Owari no kami (the Governor of Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Kasho era (848–851), Sadanushi transferred to the post Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) concurrently serving as Owari no kami (the governor of Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>「嘉祥」のスペルを訂正。スペースを削除。クォーテーションマークを修正。Governor を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>文徳天皇が即位した直後に、正四位下に相模守を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after Emperor Montoku&apos;s accession to the throne, Sadanushi was conferred Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) with an additional post of Sagami no kami (the Governor of Sagami Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after Emperor Montoku&apos;s accession to the throne, Sadanushi was conferred Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) with an additional post of Sagami no kami (the Governor of Sagami Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after Emperor Montoku&apos;s accession to the throne, Sadanushi was conferred Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) with an additional post of Sagami no kami (the governor of Sagami Province).</e>
<cmt>Governor を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>毒瘡に病み、詔により医薬を賜るが、まもなく慈恩寺西書院で没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadanushi suffered from syphilis and was given medications by the Imperial command but died shortly at Seishoin of Jion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadanushi suffered from syphilis and was given medication by the Imperial command, but died shortly at Seishoin of Jion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadanushi suffered from syphilis and was given medication by the Imperial command, but died shortly at Seishoin of Jion-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その死が伝わると哀惜しない者はなかったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, when it became known, there was not one person who did not mourn over his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, when it became known, there was not one person who did not mourn over his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, when it became known, there was not one person who did not mourn over his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fromm(id:71291), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Hannah(id:15935), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>