<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原道隆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michitaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michitaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michitaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 道隆（ふじわら の みちたか、天暦7年（953年）－長徳元年4月10日 (旧暦)（995年5月16日））は、平安時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michitaka (953 - May 16, 995) was a court noble in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michitaka (953 - May 16, 995) was a court noble in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michitaka (953 - May 17, 995) was a court noble in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原兼家の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>従一位、摂政、関白、内大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and was sessho (regent), kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), and naidaijin (Minister of the Center.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and served as sessho (regent), kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), and naidaijin (Minister of the Center.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and served as sessho (regent), kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), and naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中関白（なかのかんぱく）と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Naka no Kanpaku (literally, middle kanpaku.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Naka no Kanpaku (literally, middle kanpaku.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Naka no Kanpaku (literally, middle kanpaku).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>花山天皇退位事件で父兼家の意を受けて宮中で活動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the plot to dethrone Emperor Kazan, he took an active part in the Imperial Court under his father Kaneie&apos;s instructions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the plot to dethrone Emperor Kazan, Michitaka took an active part in the Imperial Court under his father Kaneie&apos;s instructions.</e>
<cmt>substituted name for &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the plot to dethrone Emperor Kazan, Michitaka took an active part in the Imperial Court under his father Kaneie&apos;s instructions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>甥にあたる一条天皇の即位後は急速に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his nephew, Emperor Ichijo ascended the throne, he was rapidly promoted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his nephew, Emperor Ichijo, ascended the throne, he was rapidly promoted.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his nephew, Emperor Ichijo, ascended the throne, he was rapidly promoted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>娘の定子を女御として入内させ、後に中宮となす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had his daughter Teishi make an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court as nyogo (high rank lady serving at court), and later she became chugu (the second consort of an emperor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had his daughter Teishi make an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court as nyogo (high rank lady serving at court), and she later became chugu (the second consort of an emperor.)</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had his daughter Teishi make an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court as nyogo (high rank lady serving at court), and she later became chugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>父兼家が死ぬと後を継いで関白となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his father Kaneie died, he succeeded to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his father Kaneie died, he succeeded to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his father Kaneie died, he succeeded to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>朝政を主導するが僅か5年ほどで病に倒れ、嫡男の伊周を後任の関白に願うが、天皇から許されず、死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took the initiative in governing the Imperial Court but was struck down by illness in only five years or so, then he intended to be succeeded as kanpaku by his legitimate son Korechika, which was not granted by the Emperor, and he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took the initiative in governing the Imperial Court but was struck down by illness in only five years or so; at that time he intended to be succeeded as kanpaku by his legitimate son Korechika, which was not granted by the Emperor, and he died.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took the initiative in governing the Imperial Court but was struck down by illness in only five years or so; at that time he intended to be succeeded as kanpaku by his legitimate son Korechika, which was not granted by the Emperor, and he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>藤原北家の藤原兼家の長男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the first son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michitaka was born the first son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;, substituted name for &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michitaka was born the first son of FUJIWARA no Kaneie of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>父の兼家は円融天皇に道隆の同母妹の詮子を女御として送り込み、詮子は一条天皇を生んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Kaneie had presented Senshi, his younger sister by the same mother, to Emperor Enyu as nyogo, and Senshi had given birth to Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Kaneie had presented Senshi, his younger sister by the same mother, to Emperor Enyu as nyogo, and Senshi had given birth to Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>formatting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Kaneie had presented Senshi, his younger sister by the same mother, to Emperor Enyu as nyogo, and Senshi had given birth to Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、同じく同母妹の超子は冷泉天皇の女御となり、三条天皇を生んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Choshi, his another younger sister by the same mother, had been presented to Emperor Reizei as nyogo and had given birth to Emperor Sanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Choshi, another younger sister by the same mother, had been presented to Emperor Reizei as nyogo and had given birth to Emperor Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;his&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Choshi, another younger sister by the same mother, had been presented to Emperor Reizei as nyogo and had given birth to Emperor Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>永観2年（984年）8月、円融天皇が花山天皇に譲位すると、道隆は従三位に叙せられ、東宮（皇太子）となった懐仁親王の春宮権大夫に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 984 when Emperor Enyu abdicated the throne to Emperor Kazan, Michitaka was conferred Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed to attend Imperial Prince Yasuhito (also known as Kanehito) who had become togu (the Crown Prince, also referred to as kotaishi) as Togu Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 984, when Emperor Enyu abdicated the throne to Emperor Kazan, Michitaka was conferred Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed to attend Imperial Prince Yasuhito (also known as Kanehito) who had become togu (the Crown Prince, also referred to as kotaishi) as Togu Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 984, when Emperor Enyu abdicated the throne to Emperor Kazan, Michitaka was conferred Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed to attend Imperial Prince Yasuhito (also known as Kanehito) who had become togu (the Crown Prince, also referred to as kotaishi) as Togu Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>花山天皇の外祖父は兼家の亡兄の藤原伊尹で、伊尹の子の中納言藤原義懐が外叔父となり天皇を補佐していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie&apos;s deceased elder brother FUJIWARA no Koretada was the maternal grandfather of Emperor Kazan and Koretada&apos;s son Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, who was accordingly a maternal uncle of Emperor Kazan, assisted the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie&apos;s deceased elder brother FUJIWARA no Koretada was the maternal grandfather of Emperor Kazan, and Koretada&apos;s son Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, who was accordingly a maternal uncle of Emperor Kazan, assisted the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie&apos;s deceased elder brother FUJIWARA no Koretada was the maternal grandfather of Emperor Kazan, and Koretada&apos;s son Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Yoshichika, who was accordingly a maternal uncle of Emperor Kazan, assisted the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>花山天皇と外戚関係を持つ義懐は脅威であり、そのため、兼家は孫の懐仁親王の早期の即位を強く望んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing Yoshichika, a maternal relative of Emperor Kazan, as a threat, Kaneie earnestly desired enthronement of his grandson Imperial Prince Yasuhito as soon as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing Yoshichika, a maternal relative of Emperor Kazan, as a threat, Kaneie earnestly desired enthronement of his grandson, Imperial Prince Yasuhito, as soon as possible.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing Yoshichika, a maternal relative of Emperor Kazan, as a threat, Kaneie earnestly desired enthronement of his grandson, Imperial Prince Yasuhito, as soon as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>寛和2年（986年）、兼家は策を講じ、寵妃を失って落胆していた花山天皇を二男の道兼がそそのかして内裏から寺へ連れ出し、騙すようにして出家させてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 986, Kaneie schemed to have his second son Michikane lead Emperor Kazan who was grief-stricken over his beloved lady&apos;s death out of dairi (the Imperial Palace precincts) into a temple and induce the Emperor to take the tonsure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 986, Kaneie schemed to have his second son, Michikane, lead Emperor Kazan, who was grief-stricken over his beloved lady&apos;s death, out of dairi (the Imperial Palace precincts) into a temple and induce the Emperor to take the tonsure.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 986, Kaneie schemed to have his second son, Michikane, lead Emperor Kazan, who was grief-stricken over his beloved lady&apos;s death, out of dairi (the Imperial Palace precincts) into a temple and induce the Emperor to take the tonsure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天皇が消えて宮中が大騒ぎになっている間に、道隆は弟の道綱とともに八尺瓊勾玉天叢雲剣を東宮御所へ運び込む役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While they frantically searched for the vanished Emperor in the Imperial Court, Michitaka, with his younger brother Michitsuna, brought Yasakani-no-Magatama (comma-shaped jewel pierced for stringing; one of the three imperial regalia) and Ame-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi (the sacred sword, literally, heaven&apos;s cloud-gathering sword; one of the three imperial regalia) into togu gosho (the Crown Prince&apos;s Palace.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While they frantically searched for the vanished Emperor in the Imperial Court, Michitaka, with his younger brother Michitsuna, brought Yasakani-no-Magatama (comma-shaped jewel pierced for stringing; one of the three imperial regalia) and Ame-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi (the sacred sword, literally, heaven&apos;s cloud-gathering sword; another one of the three imperial regalia) into togu gosho (the Crown Prince&apos;s Palace.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While they frantically searched for the vanished Emperor in the Imperial Court, Michitaka, with his younger brother Michitsuna, brought Yasakani no magatama (comma-shaped jewel; one of the three imperial regalia) and Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword (literally, heaven&apos;s cloud-gathering sword; another one of the three imperial regalia) into togu gosho (the Crown Prince&apos;s Palace).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そして、速やかに懐仁親王が即位する（一条天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Imperial Prince Yasuhito promptly ascended the throne (the Emperor Ichijo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Imperial Prince Yasuhito promptly ascended the throne (the Emperor Ichijo.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Imperial Prince Yasuhito promptly ascended the throne (the Emperor Ichijo).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>一条天皇の外祖父の兼家が摂政となり、嫡男の道隆は正三位権中納言から従二位権大納言へ一気に引き上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie, the maternal grandfather of the Emperor Ichijo, became sessho and Kaneie&apos;s legitimate son Michitaka was rapidly raised from Shosanmi Gon Chunagon (Senior Third Rank, Provisional Middle Counselor) to Junii Gon Dainagon (Junior Second Rank Provisional Major Counselor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie, the maternal grandfather of the Emperor Ichijo, became sessho, and Kaneie&apos;s legitimate son Michitaka was rapidly raised from Shosanmi Gon Chunagon (Senior Third Rank, Provisional Middle Counselor) to Junii Gon Dainagon (Junior Second Rank Provisional Major Counselor.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie, the maternal grandfather of the Emperor Ichijo, became sessho, and Kaneie&apos;s legitimate son Michitaka was rapidly raised from shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) to Junii (Junior Second Rank) Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>永祚 (日本)元年（989年）内大臣を拝す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 989, Michitaka was appointed to the office of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 989, Michitaka was appointed to the office of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 989, Michitaka was appointed to the office of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>道隆はこれ以上官位が進むのを望まなかったようで、この間、永延元年（987年）10月、従一位に昇叙されるべき所を、伊周の正五位下叙爵のために譲っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michitaka supposedly did not want to be elevated to a higher rank any more, and in the interim in October 987, he renounced his right to be conferred Juichii (Junior First Rank) in exchange for conferment of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on Korechika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michitaka supposedly did not want to be elevated to a higher rank, and in the interim in October 987, he renounced his right to be conferred Juichii (Junior First Rank) in exchange for conferment of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on Korechika.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michitaka supposedly did not want to be elevated to a higher rank, and in the interim in October 987, he renounced his right to be conferred Juichii (Junior First Rank) in exchange for conferment of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>正暦元年（990年）正月、道隆は長女の定子を一条天皇の女御として入内させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 990, he had his first daughter Teishi make an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court as nyogo of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 990, he had his first daughter, Teishi, make an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court as nyogo of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 990, he had his first daughter, Teishi, make an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court as nyogo of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>同年5月に病のため兼家が関白を辞すると、代わって関白、次いで摂政となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June in the same year when Kaneie resigned his post of kanpaku owing to illness, Michitaka substituted for him as kanpaku, then as sessho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June in the same year when Kaneie resigned his post of kanpaku owing to illness, Michitaka substituted for him as kanpaku, then as sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June in the same year when Kaneie resigned his position of kanpaku owing to illness, Michitaka substituted for him as kanpaku, then as sessho.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>7月、兼家は死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, Kaneie died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, Kaneie died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Kaneie died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>『古事談』などによると、兼家は自分の後継をどの息子にするかを腹心の藤原有国、平惟仲、平国平と諮った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to documents such as &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks on old affairs), Kaneie consulted with his right-hand-men FUJIWARA no Arikuni, TAIRA no Korenaka, and TAIRA no Kunihira about which son should succeed Kaneie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to documents such as &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks on old affairs), Kaneie consulted with his right-hand-men FUJIWARA no Arikuni, TAIRA no Korenaka, and TAIRA no Kunihira about which son should succeed Kaneie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to documents such as &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks on old affairs), Kaneie consulted with his right-hand-men FUJIWARA no Arikuni, TAIRA no Korenaka, and TAIRA no Kunihira about which son should succeed Kaneie.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>有国は胆力のある二男の道兼をふさわしいとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arikuni named the second son, courageous Michikane as suitable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arikuni said that the second son, the courageous Michikane, was suitable.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arikuni said that the second son, the courageous Michikane, was suitable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>一方、惟仲、国平は嫡庶の序によって道隆を推した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Korenaka and Kunihira recommended Michitaka according to the order of legal wife&apos;s child and concubine&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Korenaka and Kunihira recommended Michitaka, according to the order of legal wife&apos;s child and concubine&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Korenaka and Kunihira recommended Michitaka, according to the order of legal wife&apos;s child and concubine&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>結局、後継は道隆となり、この話を知った道隆は有国をはなはだ憎み、関白職に就くと直ちに有国父子の官を奪った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michitaka was decided as the successor in the end -- Having heard the developments, Michitaka bore a grudge against Arikuni and cashiered Arikuni and his son as he assumed the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Michitaka was chosen as the successor -- Having heard of the developments, Michitaka bore a grudge against Arikuni and cashiered Arikuni and his son as he assumed the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Michitaka was chosen as the successor; having heard of the developments, Michitaka bore a grudge against Arikuni and cashiered Arikuni and his son as he assumed the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>10月に定子を中宮とし、帝の外舅そして岳父となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he presented Teishi as chugu and became a maternal father and a father-in-law of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he presented Teishi as chugu and became a maternal father and a father-in-law of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he presented Teishi as chugu and became a father-in-law of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>「外舅」と「岳父」は同じ意味と思われるため統合して訳出しました。(check欄に記載されていたコメントは「trans2」「comment」に続けてコピーしました（太字部分））</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>正暦2年（991年）内大臣の位を道兼に譲り、摂関と大臣が分離する先例を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 991, he handed over the office of naidaijin to Michikane, setting a precedent for having the two posts of sekkan (considering sessho and kanpaku as the same post) and minister fell to different persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 991, he handed over the office of naidaijin to Michikane, setting a precedent for having the two posts of sekkan (considering sessho and kanpaku to be the same post) and minister fall to different persons.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 991, he handed over the office of naidaijin to Michikane, setting a precedent for having the two posts of sekkan (considering sessho and kanpaku to be the same post) and minister fall to different persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>正暦4年（993年）4月22日に再び関白となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 21, 993, he assumed the office of kanpaku again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 21, 993, he assumed the office of kanpaku again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 21, 993, he assumed the office of kanpaku again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>長徳元年（995年）正月、二女原子を皇太子居貞親王（後の三条天皇）の妃とし、後宮政策の強化を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 995, he made his second daughter Genshi the empress of the Crown Prince, the Imperial Prince Okisada (later Emperor Sanjo), and tighten management of kokyu (literally, rear palace; imperial harem.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 995, he made his second daughter, Genshi, the empress of the Crown Prince, the Imperial Prince Okisada (later Emperor Sanjo), and tightened management of kokyu (literally, rear palace; imperial harem.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, verb tenseunclear if Michitaka or Genshi tighteded management; if Genshi did, than change to &quot;...and had her tighten management&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 995, he made his second daughter, Genshi, the empress of the Crown Prince, the Imperial Prince Okisada (later Emperor Sanjo), and tightened management of kokyu (literally, rear palace; imperial harem).</e>
<cmt>道隆が政策の強化を図ったとして訳出しました。(check欄に記載されていたコメントは「trans2」「comment」に続けてコピーしました（太字部分））</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>だが、それから程無く、道隆は病に伏し、3月9日、一条天皇に請うて嫡子の内大臣伊周を内覧とし政務を委任し後継者にしようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironically, Michitaka fell ill in a little while, and on April 16, with an intention of being succeeded by his legitimate son naidaijin Korechika, he appealed Emperor Ichijo to grant him permission to resign nairan (an emperor&apos;s private inspector of all official documents) in favor of Korechika and entrust Korechika the political affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironically, Michitaka fell ill in a little while, and on April 16, with an intention of being succeeded by his legitimate son naidaijin Korechika, he appealed to Emperor Ichijo to grant him permission to resign nairan (an emperor&apos;s private inspector of all official documents) in favor of Korechika and to entrust Korechika with the political affairs.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironically, Michitaka fell ill in a little while, and on April 16, with an intention of being succeeded by his legitimate son naidaijin Korechika, he appealed to Emperor Ichijo to grant him permission to resign nairan (an emperor&apos;s private inspector of all official documents) in favor of Korechika and to entrust Korechika with the political affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、病中の内覧のみ許され、伊周に関白の位を譲る事は許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the Emperor allowed him to entrust Korechika the post of nairan only during his illness and did not allowed him to hand over the post of kanpaku to Korechika.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Emperor allowed him to entrust Korechika the post of nairan only during his illness and did not allow him to hand over the post of kanpaku to Korechika.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Emperor allowed him to entrust Korechika the post of nairan only during his illness and did not allow him to hand over the post of kanpaku to Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>4月3日、関白を辞し、伊周の関白就任を再度奏上したがかなわなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 10, Michitaka resigned the office of kanpaku, and repeatedly reported to the Emperor on Korechika&apos;s succession to the office of kanpaku in vain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 10, Michitaka resigned the office of kanpaku, and repeatedly reported to the Emperor, in vain, on Korechika&apos;s succession to the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 10, Michitaka resigned the office of kanpaku, and repeatedly reported to the Emperor, in vain, on Korechika&apos;s succession to the office of kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>同6日出家し、10日薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 13, he became a priest, and on 17, died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 13, he became a priest, and on May 17, he died.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 13, he became a priest, and on May 17, he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>享年43。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>死因については、当時流行して多数の貴族の命を奪った疫病ではなく、酒の飲みすぎなどからきた飲水病（糖尿病）の悪化が偶々この時期に重なったものと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is supposed to have died not of a plague which had prevailed and killed many court nobles at that time but of aggravation of mizu nomi yami (water-drinking illness) (diabetes) resulting from excessive sake (alcohol) ingestion and so on which he experienced by coincidence at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is supposed to have died not of a plague which had prevailed and killed many court nobles at that time, but of aggravation of mizu nomi yami (water-drinking illness) (diabetes) resulting from excessive ingestion of sake (alcohol), which he coincidentally experienced at the time.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is supposed to have died not of a plague which had prevailed and killed many court nobles at that time, but of aggravation of mizu nomi yami (water-drinking illness) (diabetes) resulting from excessive ingestion of sake (alcohol), which he coincidentally experienced at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="39">
<j>道隆没後、その遺志に反して弟道兼が関白となり、以後、中関白家の急速な衰退が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Michitaka, his younger brother Michikane succeeded as kanpaku against Michitaka&apos;s will, and the Naka no Kanpaku family slipped into a steep decline since then,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Michitaka, his younger brother Michikane succeeded as kanpaku against Michitaka&apos;s will, and the Naka no Kanpaku family slipped into a steep decline from that time.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Michitaka, his younger brother Michikane succeeded as kanpaku against Michitaka&apos;s will, and the Naka no Kanpaku family slipped into a steep decline from that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>『大鏡』や『枕草子』などによれば、道隆は大酒飲みで、軽口を好んだ朗らかな人であったらしく、不羈な一面もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to such documents as &quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, the Great Mirror; a historical tale) and &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (literally, the Pillow Book; collection of essays), Michitaka had a free-hearted side such that he was a cheerful hard-drinking man enjoying witty remarks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to such documents as &quot;Okagami&quot; (literally, the Great Mirror; a historical tale) and &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (literally, the Pillow Book; collection of essays), Michitaka had a free-hearted side such that he was a cheerful hard-drinking man who enjoyed witty remarks.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to such documents as &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror) and &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book), Michitaka had a free-hearted side such that he was a cheerful hard-drinking man who enjoyed witty remarks.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>『大鏡』は、藤原済時、藤原朝光を飲み仲間とし、道隆たちが酔っ払って人前で烏帽子を外した頭を晒した話を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Okagami&quot; described that Michitaka had drinking companions such as FUJIWARA no Naritoki and FUJIWARA no Asateru, and together with them he once got drunk and took off his eboshi (formal headwear for court nobles) and exposed his bare head in public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Okagami&quot; described that Michitaka had drinking companions such as FUJIWARA no Naritoki and FUJIWARA no Asateru, and together with them he once got drunk and took off his eboshi (formal headwear for court nobles) and exposed his bare head in public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Okagami&quot; described that Michitaka had drinking companions such as FUJIWARA no Naritoki and FUJIWARA no Asateru, and together with them he once got drunk and took off his eboshi (formal headwear for court nobles) and exposed his bare head in public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その一方で、容貌が端正だった上に、人への気配りが行き届く気の広さを持ち、薨去直前に宣命を伝えに来た上卿源俊賢は、彼の優れた立ち居振る舞いを後々まで忘れずに口にかけたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he is described as a good-looking man with generosity of showing careful attention to people such that Shokei (a high-ranking court noble) MINAMOTO no Toshikata who visited Michitaka just before his death to pronounce an imperial edict repeatedly mentioned Michitaka&apos;s splendid bearing afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he is described as a good-looking man with generosity of showing careful attention to people such that Shokei (a high-ranking court noble) MINAMOTO no Toshikata, who visited Michitaka just before his death to pronounce an imperial edict, repeatedly mentioned Michitaka&apos;s splendid bearing afterwards.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he is described as a good-looking man with generosity of showing careful attention to people such that Shokei (a high-ranking court noble) MINAMOTO no Toshikata, who visited Michitaka just before his death to pronounce an imperial edict, repeatedly mentioned Michitaka&apos;s splendid bearing afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>山城国守藤原守仁女との間に第一子の権大納言藤原道頼を儲けたが、道隆は高階成忠女高階貴子（高内侍、儀同三位母）との間に生まれた、内大臣藤原伊周・中納言藤原隆家・権大僧都隆円・皇后藤原定子ら諸子女を嫡系として優遇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michitaka had the first child, Gon Dainagon FUJIWARA no Michiyori with a daughter of Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiiro Province) FUJIWARA no Morihito, but he favored the children he had with TAKASHINA no Kishi (Ko no naishi, Gidosanshi no haha (Mother of Gidosanshi)), a daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada, including naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika, chunagon FUJIWARA no Takaie, gondaisozu Ryuen, and Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi as a stem family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michitaka had his first child, Gon Dainagon FUJIWARA no Michiyori, with a daughter of Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiiro Province) FUJIWARA no Morihito, but he favored the children he had with TAKASHINA no Kishi (Ko no naishi, Gidosanshi no haha (Mother of Gidosanshi)), a daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada, including naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika, chunagon FUJIWARA no Takaie, gondaisozu Ryuen, and Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi, as a stem family.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michitaka had his first child, Gon Dainagon FUJIWARA no Michiyori, with a daughter of Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiro Province) FUJIWARA no Morihito, but he favored the children he had with TAKASHINA no Kishi (also known as Ko no naishi, Gidosanshi no haha (Mother of Gidosanshi)), a daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada, including naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika, chunagon FUJIWARA no Takaie, gondaisozu (a provisional highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the second highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) Ryuen, and Empress FUJIWARA no Teishi, as a stem family.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career as an official</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career as an official</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of Office and Rank</e>
<cmt>他ファイルに合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>康保4年（967年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 967</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 967</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">967</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>10月11日 (旧暦)：従五位下に叙位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 20: Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 20: Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 20: Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>11月：昇殿を許される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December: Granted shoden (access to the administration chambers in the Seiryo den Hall in the imperial court.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December: Granted shoden (access to the administration chambers in the Seiryo den Hall in the imperial court.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December: Granted shoden (access to the administration chambers in the Seiryo den Hall in the imperial court).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>康保5年（968年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 968</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 968</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">968</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>1月13日 (旧暦)：侍従に任官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19: Installed as palace staff.</e>
<cmt>後述の蔵人と訳し分けるためにpalace staffとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 19: Installed as member of palace staff.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;member of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19: Installed as member of palace staff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>12月18日 (旧暦)：左兵衛佐に遷任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 13: Transferred to Sahyoue no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 13: Reasigned to post of Sahyoue no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 13: Reassigned to post of Sahyoue no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>天禄2年（971年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 972</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 972</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">972</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>12月15日 (旧暦)：右衛門佐に遷任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 9: Transferred to Uemon no suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 9: Reassigned to post of Uemon no suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 9: Reassigned to post of Uemon no suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>天禄4年改元して天延元年（973年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 973 (the era name was changed from Tenroku to Tenen.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 973 (era name changed from Tenroku to Tenen.)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">973</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>1月7日 (旧暦)：従五位上に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 17: Raised to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 17: Promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 17: Promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>右衛門佐如元か?</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether remained in the office of Uemon no suke or not is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether or not he remained in the office of Uemon no suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether or not he retained his position as Uemon no suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>天延2年（974年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 974</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 974</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">974</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>1月8日 (旧暦)：蔵人に補任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 7: Appointed to the office of kurodo (Chamberlain.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 7: Appointed to the office of kurodo (Chamberlain.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 7: Appointed to the office of kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>2月7日 (旧暦)：伊予権介を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 8: Served concurrently as Iyo no Gon no Suke (provisional vice governor of Iyo Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 8: Assigned additional duty of Iyo no Gon no Suke (provisional vice governor of Iyo Province.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 8: Assigned additional duty of Iyo no Gon no Suke (provisional vice governor of Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>10月11日：左近衛少将に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 2: Transferred to Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 2: Reassigned to post of Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 2: Reassigned to post of Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>蔵人・伊予権介如元か?</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether remained in the office of kurodo and Iyo no Gon no Suke or not is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether or not he remained in the office of kurodo and Iyo no Gon no Suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether or not he retained his position as kurodo and Iyo no Gon no Suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>天延3年（975年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 975</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 975</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">975</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>1月7日：正五位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 25: Raised to Shogoinoge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 25: Promotoed to Shogoinoge.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 25: Promoted to Shogoinoge.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>左近衛少将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the office of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained position of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>蔵人・伊予権介も如元か?</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether also remained in the office of kurodo and Iyo no Gon no Suke or not is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether or not he also remained in the office of kurodo and Iyo no Gon no Suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether or not he also retained his position as kurodo and Iyo no Gon no Suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="64">
<j>天延4年改元して貞元_(日本)元年（976年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 976 (the era name was changed from Tenen to Jogen.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 976 (era name changed from Tenen to Jogen.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">976</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>1月28日 (旧暦)：備後権介に任ず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 6: Appointed to the office of Bingo gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Bingo Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 6: Appointed to the office of Bingo gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Bingo Province.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6: Appointed to the office of Bingo gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Bingo Province).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>伊予権介を去るか?</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether resigned from the office of Iyo no Gon no Suke or not is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether or not he resigned from the office of Iyo no Gon no Suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether or not he resigned from the office of Iyo no Gon no Suke is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="67">
<j>貞元2年（977年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 977</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 977</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">977</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>1月7日：従四位下に昇叙し、左近衛少将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 2: Raised to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) as remained in the office of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 2: Promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained the office of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 2: Promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>1月：備中権守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January: Transferred to Bicchu gon no kami (Provisional governor of Bicchu Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January: Reassigned to post of Bicchu gon no kami (Provisional governor of Bicchu Province.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between January - February (January in old lunar calendar): Reassigned to post of Bitchu gon no kami (Provisional governor of Bitchu Province).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>左近衛少将を去る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned from the office of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resigned from the office of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resigned from the office of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>昇殿を許される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Granted shoden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Granted shoden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Granted shoden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="72">
<j>貞元3年改元して天元 (日本)元年（978年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 978 (the era name was changed from Jogen to Tengen.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 978 (era name changed from Jogen to Tengen.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">978</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>10月17日 (旧暦)：右近衛権中将に任官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5: Appointed to the office of Ukonoe no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5: Appointed to the office of Ukonoe no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 25: Appointed to the office of Ukonoe no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>天元2年（979年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 979</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 979</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">979</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>1月29日 (旧暦)：備中権守を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 5: Served concurrently as Bicchu gon no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 5: Assigned additional post of Bicchu gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 5: Assigned additional post of Bitchu gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>天元4年（981年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 981</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 981</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">981</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>1月7日：従四位上に昇叙し、右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19: Promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) as remained in the position of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 19: Promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained the position of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19: Promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained his position as Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>天元5年（982年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 982</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 982</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">982</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>1月7日：正四位下に昇叙し、右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 8: Raised to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) as remained in the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 8: Promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 8: Promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>永観2年（984年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 984</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 984</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">984</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>1月7日：従三位に昇叙し、右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 16: Raised to Jusanmi as remained in the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 16: Promoted to Jusanmi and retained the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 16: Promoted to Jusanmi and retained his position as Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>8月27日 (旧暦)：春宮（のちの一条天皇こと、懐仁親王）権大夫を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 29: Served concurrently as Togu gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters for Togu (Imperial Prince Yasuhito, later Emperor Ichijo.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 29: Assigned additional post of Togu gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters for Togu (Imperial Prince Yasuhito, later Emperor Ichijo.))</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 29: Assigned additional post of Togu gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters for Togu (Imperial Prince Yasuhito, later Emperor Ichijo)).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>寛和2年（986年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 986</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 986</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">986</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>6月23日 (旧暦)：春宮権大夫を止む</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 6: Resigned from the office of Togu gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 6: Resigned from the office of Togu gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 6: Resigned from the office of Togu gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>7月5日 (旧暦)：権中納言に転任し、皇太后宮（藤原兼家の娘、藤原詮子）大夫を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 17: Transferred to Gon Chunagon and served concurrently as Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household (Empress Dowager was FUJIWARA no Senshi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 17: Reassigned to Gon Chunagon and served concurrently as Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household (the Empress Dowager was FUJIWARA no Senshi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kaneie.))</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 17: Reassigned to Gon Chunagon and served concurrently as Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household (the Empress Dowager was FUJIWARA no Senshi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kaneie)).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="87">
<j>7月9日 (旧暦)：正三位に昇叙し、権中納言・皇太后宮大夫・右近衛中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 21: Raised to Shosanmi as remained in the offices of Gon Chunagon, Kotaigo gu no daibu, and Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 21: Promotoed to Shosanmi and retained the offices of Gon Chunagon, Kotaigo gu no daibu, and Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 21: Promoted to Shosanmi and retained his position as Gon Chunagon, Kotaigo gu no daibu, and Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>7月13日 (旧暦)：右近衛中将を去る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 25: Resigned from the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 25: Resigned from the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 25: Resigned from the office of Ukonoe no chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>7月20日 (旧暦)：権大納言に転任し、皇太后宮大夫如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 1: Transferred to Gon Dainagon as remained in the office of Kotaigo gu no daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 1: Reassigned to Gon Dainagon and retained the office of Kotaigo gu no daibu.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1: Reassigned to Gon Dainagon and retained his position as Kotaigo gu no daibu.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>7月22日 (旧暦)：従二位に昇叙し、権大納言・皇太后宮大夫如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 3: Raised to Junii as remained in the office of Gon Dainagon and Kotaigo gu no daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 3: Promoted to Junii and retained the offices of Gon Dainagon and Kotaigo gu no daibu.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 3: Promoted to Junii and retained his position as Gon Dainagon and Kotaigo gu no daibu.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>永延3年改元して永祚 (日本)元年（989年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 989 (the era name was changed from Einen to Eiso.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 989 (era name changed from Einen to Eiso.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">989</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>2月23日 (旧暦)：内大臣に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 6: Transferred to naidaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 6: Reassigned to position of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 6: Reassigned to position of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>7月13日：左近衛大将を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 21: Served concurrently as Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 21: Assigned additional post of Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 21: Assigned additional post of Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>永祚2年改元して正暦元年（990年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 990 (the era name was changed from Eiso to Shoryaku.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 990 (era name changed from Eiso to Shoryaku.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">990</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>5月8日 (旧暦)：関白宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 8: Raised by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 8: Promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 8: Promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>内大臣・左近衛大将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the office of naidaijin and Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the offices of naidaijin and Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as naidaijin and Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="97">
<j>5月13日 (旧暦)：藤氏長者宣下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 13: Raised by Imperial edict to Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 13: Promotoed by Imperial edict to Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 13: Promoted by Imperial edict to Toshi Choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>5月26日 (旧暦)：関白を止め、摂政宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 26: Resigned from the office of kanpaku and raised by Imperial edict to sessho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 26: Resigned from the office of kanpaku and promoted by Imperial edict to sessho.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 26: Resigned from the office of kanpaku and promoted by Imperial edict to sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>内大臣・左近衛大将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the office of naidaijin and Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the offices of naidaijin and Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as naidaijin and Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="100">
<j>5月30日 (旧暦)：左近衛大将を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 30: Resigned the office of Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>正暦元年5月は小の月で29日までしかないと、暦変換ツールでエラーが出ます（http://can-chan.com/koyomi/qreki-seireki.html）(http://maechan.net/kanreki/)。ご確認下さい。旧暦6月1日として変換し、訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 30: Resigned the office of Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 30: Resigned the office of Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>正暦元年5月30日は実在しないようですが、原文に合わせて訳出しています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="101">
<j>正暦2年（991年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 991</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 991</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">991</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>7月14日 (旧暦)：内大臣を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 31: Resigned from the office of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 31: Resigned from the office of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 31: Resigned from the office of naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>正暦4年（993年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 993</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 993</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">993</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>4月22日 (旧暦)：摂政を止め、関白宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 21: Resigned from the office of sessho and raised by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 21: Resigned from the office of sessho and promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 21: Resigned from the office of sessho and promoted by Imperial edict to kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>藤原氏長者如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the office of Toshi choja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained the office of Toshi choja.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Toshi choja.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="106">
<j>正暦6年改元して長徳元年（995年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 995 (the era name was changed from Shoryaku to Chotoku.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 995 (era name changed from Shoryaku to Chotoku.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">995</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>4月3日 (旧暦)：関白・藤原氏長者を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 10: Resigned from the office of kanpaku and Toshi choja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 10: Resigned from the offices of kanpaku and Toshi choja.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 10: Resigned from the offices of kanpaku and Toshi choja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>4月6日 (旧暦)：出家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 13: Became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 13: Became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 13: Became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>4月10日 (旧暦)：薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 17: Died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 17: Died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 17: Died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>享年43</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Lonicera(id:20638), Nnh(id:474), China(id:10362), Novo(id:87875), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), 水野白楓(id:22811), 三浦大輔(id:93377), 味っ子(id:17086), Snap55(id:89773), 伊集院聖(id:53199), BAKU(id:55205), MDR-SK(id:192066), パの字(id:34188), Masyu(id:31065), YurikBot(id:18605), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), UMBRO(id:100484), Yume149(id:17504), Point136(id:211299), Avxz(id:123412), 伏儀(id:142093), Junger(id:10282), 小川尚明(id:93076), Kouko0515(id:100370), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Saaki(id:43602), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>