<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>永山武四郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro NAGAYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro NAGAYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro NAGAYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>永山 武四郎（ながやま たけしろう、天保8年4月24日 (旧暦)（1837年5月28日） - 明治37年（1904年）5月27日）は、日本の陸軍軍人、華族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro NAGAYAMA (May 28, 1837-May 27, 1904) was a military man of the Japanese Army and belonged to the peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro NAGAYAMA (May 28, 1837 - May 27, 1904) was a military man of the Japanese Army and a nobleman.</e>
<cmt>用語・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro NAGAYAMA (May 28, 1837 - May 27, 1904) was a military man of the Japanese Army and a nobleman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治時代に北海道庁長官、第7師団長、貴族院議員等を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, he served in different positions such as the director general of the Hokkaido government, as a military man in the 7th division of the Japanese Imperial Army and as a parliament member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji Period, he served in a variety of high ranking positions, such as Director General of the Hokkaido government, Chief of the 7th division of the Japanese Imperial Army and a Member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt>原文リンク先表示を修正のうえ再訳出しました。表現・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, he served in a variety of high ranking positions, such as Director General of the Hokkaido government, Chief of the 7th division of the Japanese Imperial Army and a Member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>官位は陸軍中将従二位勲一等男爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was lieutenant general of the Army, and his court rank was baron of Junior Second Rank with the First Order of Merit.</e>
<cmt>「位階」は「従二位」として訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was lieutenant general of the Army, and his court rank was baron of Junior Second Rank with the First Order of Merit.</e>
<cmt>原文リンク先表示を修正のうえ再訳出しました。表現・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was lieutenant general of the Army, and his court rank was baron of Junior Second Rank with the First Order of Merit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>貴族院議員・筑摩県権県令・新潟県令等を務めた永山盛輝男爵は兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baron Moriteru NAGAYAMA, who served as a parliament member of the House of Peers, as the Governor of Chikuma Prefecture and as the Governor of Niigata Prefecture, was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baron Moriteru NAGAYAMA, who served as a Member of the House of Peers, Provisional Governor of Chikuma Prefecture, and Governor of Niigata Prefecture, was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ箇所を加筆修正しました。原文リンク先表示を修正しました。表現・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baron Moriteru NAGAYAMA, who served as a Member of the House of Peers, Provisional Governor of Chikuma Prefecture, and Governor of Niigata Prefecture, was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>天保8年(1837年)、鹿児島藩士、永山盛広の四男として生まれた武四郎は、同じく鹿児島藩士の永山喜八郎の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro, born as the fourth son of Morihiro NAGAYAMA, a feudal retainer for Kagoshima Domain in 1837, was adopted by Kihachiro NAGAYAMA who was also a feudal retainer for Kagoshima Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro, born in 1837, as the fourth son of Morihiro NAGAYAMA who was a retainer of Kagoshima Domain, was adopted by Kihachiro NAGAYAMA who was also a retainer of Kagoshima Domain.</e>
<cmt>表現・文脈・用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro, born in 1837, as the fourth son of Morihiro NAGAYAMA who was a retainer of Kagoshima Domain, was adopted by Kihachiro NAGAYAMA who was also a retainer of Kagoshima Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>戊辰戦争に従軍し、明治維新後の明治4年(1871年)7月陸軍大尉・2番大隊付に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro participated in the Boshin War and in July of 1871 after the Meiji Restoration, he was appointed as taijo (Senior Lieutenant) of the Japanese Army, assigned to the second battalion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro participated in Boshin War, and in July of 1871, after the Meiji Restoration, he was appointed as Taii (Captain) of the Army and assigned to the second battalion.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro participated in Boshin War, and in July of 1871, after the Meiji Restoration, he was appointed as Taii (Captain) of the Army and assigned to the second battalion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>明治5年(1872年)9月から開拓使に移り、北海道開拓使八等出仕となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of 1872, Takeshiro was transferred to the Office of Hokkaido Development Commissioner and served as an officer of the eighth grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1872, Takeshiro was transferred to the Office of Hokkaido Development Commission and served as an officer of the eighth grade.</e>
<cmt>形式・用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1872, Takeshiro was transferred to the Office of Hokkaido Development Commission and served as an officer of the eighth grade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治8年(1875年)3月に陸軍准少佐・開拓使七等出仕、屯田事務局付。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of 1875, he became a deputy Major of the Army, and served in the Office of Hokkaido Development Commissioner an officer of the seventh grade, belonging to the Bureau of Tonden (settlement of ex-legionaries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1875, he became a Deputy Major of the Army, and served as Hokkaido Development Commission Officer of the seventh grade and assigned to the Bureau of Tonden (settlement of ex-legionary).</e>
<cmt>用語・形式・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1875, he became a Deputy Major of the Army, and served as Hokkaido Development Commission Officer of the seventh grade and assigned to the Bureau of Tonden (settlement of ex-legionary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治10年(1877年)4月に屯田兵第1大隊長に就任し堀基大佐の指揮のもと、西南戦争に従軍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of 1877, he assumed the post of chief of the first battalion of Tondenhei (ex-legionaries) and participated in the Seinan War under the command of Colonel Motoi HORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1877, he assumed the post of Chief of the First Battalion of Ex-legionaries and participated in Seinan War under the command of Colonel Motoi HORI.</e>
<cmt>用語・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1877, he assumed the post of Chief of the First Battalion of Ex-legionaries and participated in Seinan War under the command of Colonel Motoi HORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>戦争から帰還した後は開拓少書記官・屯田事務局副長・屯田事務局長と累進し、階級は屯田兵大佐となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning from the war, he was promoted to Deputy Secretary of the Office of Hokkaido Development Commissioner, Deputy Secretary General of the Bureau of Tonden and then to Secretary General of the Bureau of Tonden, and was given the rank of Colonel of Tondenhei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning from the war, he was successively promoted to Deputy Secretary of Hokkaido Development Commission, Deputy Secretary General of the Bureau of Tonden and then to Secretary General of the Bureau of Tonden, and was given the rank of Tondenhei Taisa (literally, Colonel of Ex-legionary).</e>
<cmt>用語・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning from the war, he was successively promoted to Deputy Secretary of Hokkaido Development Commission, Deputy Secretary General of the Bureau of Tonden and then to Secretary General of the Bureau of Tonden, and was given the rank of Tondenhei Taisa (literally, Colonel of Ex-legionary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一時陸軍省出仕を経験し明治18年(1885年)5月には陸軍少将・屯田兵副本部長となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After serving temporarily in the Ministry of Army, he became Army Major General and Deputy Director General of Tondenhei headquarters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving temporarily in the Ministry of Army, he became Army Major General and Deputy Director General of Ex-legionary headquarters.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving temporarily in the Ministry of Army, he became Army Major General and Deputy Director General of Ex-legionary headquarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1年間の欧米出張をへて明治21年(1888年)6月から北海道庁長官を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, he was stationed in Europe and the United States for a year and then since June of 1888, he doubled as the director general of the Hokkaido government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he was stationed in Europe and the United States for a year, and then from June 1888, he doubled as Director General of the Hokkaido government.</e>
<cmt>用語・文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he was stationed in Europe and the United States for a year, and then from June 1888, he doubled as Director General of the Hokkaido government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>北海道庁長官は岩村通俊の後を受けたもので、永山は第2代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAYAMA, who had assumed the post to succeed to Michitoshi IWAMURA, was the second director general of the Hokkaido government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAYAMA, who had assumed the post to succeed to Michitoshi IWAMURA, was the second Director General of the Hokkaido government.</e>
<cmt>形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAYAMA, who had assumed the post to succeed to Michitoshi IWAMURA, was the second Director General of the Hokkaido government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その間明治22年(1889年)8月には屯田兵司令官に就任し、北海道庁長官退任後の明治28年(1895年)2月には臨時第7師団司令官となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, he became Commander in Chief of Tondenhei in August of 1889, and after retiring from the position of the director general of the Hokkaido government, he became Commander of the Ad Hoc Seventh Division of the Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, he became Commander in Chief of Ex-legionary in August 1889, and after retiring as Director General of the Hokkaido government, he became Commander of the Seventh Ad Hoc Division of the Army.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, he became Commander in Chief of Ex-legionary in August 1889, and after retiring as Director General of the Hokkaido government, he became Commander of the Seventh Ad Hoc Division of the Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同年12月4日、男爵に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 4 of the same year, he was given the title of baron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 4 in the same year, he was baronized.</e>
<cmt>用語・文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 4 in the same year, he was baronized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>臨時第7師団は組織改変を経て明治29年(1896年)5月には第7師団となり、武四郎が師団長に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ad Hoc Seventh Division was reorganized and in May of 1896, was established as the Seventh Division, of which Takeshiro became Chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seventh Ad Hoc Division was reorganized, and in May 1896, it was established as the Seventh Division, of which Takeshiro became Chief.</e>
<cmt>用語・文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seventh Ad Hoc Division was reorganized, and in May 1896, it was established as the Seventh Division, of which Takeshiro became Chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>同年10月陸軍中将に進級し明治33年(1900年)4月まで務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October of 1896, NAGAYAMA was promoted to Lieutenant General of the Army and served the Army until April of 1900.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1896, NAGAYAMA was promoted to Lieutenant General of the Army and served until April 1900.</e>
<cmt>形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1896, NAGAYAMA was promoted to Lieutenant General of the Army and served until April 1900.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>軍を退役した後は明治36年(1903年)11月から貴族院議員を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After retiring from the Army, he served as a parliament member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) from November of 1903.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After retiring from the Army, he served as a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) from November 1903.</e>
<cmt>形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After retiring from the Army, he served as a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) from November 1903.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>明治37年(1904年)議会出席の為上京中に倒れ、5月27日薨去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He broke down during his stay in Tokyo to attend the Parliament in 1904, and died on May 27.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He broke down during his stay in Tokyo to attend the Parliament in 1904, and died on May 27.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He broke down during his stay in Tokyo to attend the Parliament in 1904, and died on May 27.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>死を悟った武四郎は親しい者たちに「我が躯は北海道に埋めよ、必ずやかの地をロシアから守らん」と述べたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Takeshiro, who had realized that his number was up, said to those close to him as follows: &quot;Bury my body in Hokkaido, so that I may surely protect the place from Russia.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Takeshiro, who had realized that his number was up, left the following words to those close to him: &quot;Bury my body in Hokkaido, and I will be sure to protect the place from Russia.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。なお、次項原文中のセリフ後半部分を当項へ移動・統合し、次項空欄一行を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Takeshiro, who had realized that his number was up, left the following words to those close to him: &quot;Bury my body in Hokkaido, and I will be sure to protect the place from Russia.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この遺言により北海道札幌市豊平墓地に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to his will, he was entombed at Toyohira Cemetery in Sapporo City, Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this will, he was entombed at Toyohira Cemetery in Sapporo City, Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this will, he was entombed at Toyohira Cemetery in Sapporo City, Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後に里塚霊園に改葬される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, his tomb was moved to Satozuka Cemetery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, his tomb was moved to Satozuka Cemetery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, his tomb was moved to Satozuka Cemetery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>現役時代は屯田兵を掌握し軍部内では一大勢力だったが、本人に政治的野心はなく、中央の政治抗争のためにその力を行使することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his career, although he held a control over Tondenhei to form a clout, he had no political ambition and did not wield the clout for political struggles in the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although during his career he held a control over ex-legionaries and became a force within military, he had no political ambition and did not wield power for political battle in the central government.</e>
<cmt>用語・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although during his career he held a control over ex-legionaries and became a force within military, he had no political ambition and did not wield power for political battle in the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>終生北海道を案じ、その身を捧げた武人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro was a warrior, who was always concerned for Hokkaido and dedicated his life to Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro was a warrior, who was always concerned about Hokkaido all his life and dedicated his life to Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro was a warrior, who was always concerned about Hokkaido all his life and dedicated his life to Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>武四郎の後を長男の永山武敏が継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro&apos;s eldest son Taketoshi NAGAYAMA succeeded to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro&apos;s eldest son Taketoshi NAGAYAMA succeeded to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro&apos;s eldest son Taketoshi NAGAYAMA succeeded to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>武敏は陸軍大佐正二位勲三等功五級（金鵄勲章）・貴族院議員となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taketoshi became Colonel of the Army, was awarded with the court rank of Senior Second Grade and the third Order of the Golden Pheasant, and then became a parliament member of Kizokuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taketoshi became Colonel of the Army, was awarded with the court rank of Senior Second Grade and the third Order of the Golden Pheasant, Fifth Class, and became a member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。なお、原文リンク先表示を修正のうえ再訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taketoshi became Colonel of the Army, was awarded with the court rank of Senior Second Grade and the third Order of the Golden Pheasant, Fifth Class, and became a member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>三男の永山武美は慈恵医科大学第3代学長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro&apos;s third son Takeyoshi NAGAYAMA was the third president of the Jikei University School of Medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro&apos;s third son Takeyoshi NAGAYAMA was the third president of the Jikei University School of Medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro&apos;s third son Takeyoshi NAGAYAMA was the third president of the Jikei University School of Medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>武敏の後を継ぎ永山敏行が襲爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiyuki NAGAYAMA succeeded to Taketoshi and the peerage membership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiyuki NAGAYAMA succeeded to Taketoshi and the peerage membership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiyuki NAGAYAMA succeeded to Taketoshi and the peerage membership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>敏行の弟永山武臣は文化功労者で、松竹会長・日本演劇興行協会長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiyuki&apos;s younger brother, Takeomi NAGAYAMA, who was chairman of SHOCHIKU Co., Ltd. and chairman of the Japan Association of Major Theaters, was chosen as a Bunkakorosha (Person of Cultural Merits).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiyuki&apos;s younger brother, Takeomi NAGAYAMA, was chosen as a Bunkakorosha (Person of Cultural Merits), who was chairman of SHOCHIKU Co., Ltd., and chairman of the Japan Association of Major Theaters.</e>
<cmt>文脈・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiyuki&apos;s younger brother, Takeomi NAGAYAMA, was chosen as a Bunkakorosha (Person of Cultural Merits), who was chairman of SHOCHIKU Co., Ltd., and chairman of the Japan Association of Major Theaters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>武四郎は永山神社・北海道神宮末社開拓神社に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro is enshrined at Nagayama Shrine and Kaitaku Shrine which is a subordinate shrine of Hokkaido Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro is enshrined at Nagayama-jinja Shrine and Kaitaku-jinja Shrine which is a subordinate shrine of Hokkaido-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro is enshrined at Nagayama-jinja Shrine and Kaitaku-jinja Shrine which is a subordinate shrine of Hokkaido-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>永山神社には銅像が建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a bronze statue of Takeshiro built at Nagayama Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a bronze statue of Takeshiro built at Nagayama-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a bronze statue of Takeshiro built at Nagayama-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>武四郎の生誕の地である鹿児島県鹿児島市薬師にはそれを記す説明板が設置され、北海道札幌市中央区には永山武四郎の邸宅である旧永山武四郎邸が保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the birth place of Takeshiro NAGAYAMA, Yakushi of Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture, there is an explanatory board while in Chuo Ward, Sapporo City, Hokkaido, the house he lived is preserved as the former residence of Takeshiro NAGAYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An explanatory board indicating the birth place of Takeshiro NAGAYAMA is set up at Yakushi, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture, while in Chuo Ward, Sapporo City, Hokkaido, the house which he used to live in is preserved as the old residence of Takeshiro NAGAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避のため文章を整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An explanatory board indicating the birth place of Takeshiro NAGAYAMA is set up at Yakushi, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture, while in Chuo Ward, Sapporo City, Hokkaido, the house which he used to live in is preserved as the old residence of Takeshiro NAGAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>上川離宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamikawa Imperial Villa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamikawa-rikyu Detached Palace</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamikawa-rikyu Detached Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>北海道庁長官となった武四郎は北海道でも特に内陸部の開発に着目した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshiro, as the Hokkaido Governor, focused particularly on development of inland areas in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshiro, as Director General of the Hokkaido government, focused particularly on development of inland areas in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshiro, as Director General of the Hokkaido government, focused particularly on development of inland areas in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>就任前には先代長官の岩村通俊と共に上川原野を視察した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before taking office, he inspected the wildland in Kamikawa area together with his predecessor, Governor Michitoshi IWAMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before taking office, he inspected Kamikawa wildland together with his predecessor, Michitoshi IWAMURA.</e>
<cmt>用語・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before taking office, he inspected Kamikawa wildland together with his predecessor, Michitoshi IWAMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>ここに屯田兵村を設置するが、この村は明治23年永山村（旭川市）と名前を変える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He set up a Tondenhei village there and the name of the place was changed to Nagayama (currently Asahikawa City) in 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He set up a Tondenhei mura (literally, ex-legionary village) there and the name of the place was changed to Nagayama-mura Village (currently Asahikawa City) in 1890.</e>
<cmt>原文のリンク先表示を修正のうえ、用語・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He set up a Tondenhei mura (literally, ex-legionary village) there and the name of the place was changed to Nagayama-mura Village (currently Asahikawa City) in 1890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>勿論この名は武四郎に由来するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Needless to say, the name derived from Takeshiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Needless to say, the name derived from Takeshiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Needless to say, the name derived from Takeshiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>さて、本州からの移住を促進する為に上川の地に東京・京都に並ぶ｢北京｣を作る構想を先代岩村から受け継いだ武四郎は、政府に働き掛ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, taking over the vision of establishing in Kamikawa area &quot;northern state capital &quot;comparable to Tokyo and Kyoto to promote immigration from Honshu (the main land of Japan) from his predecessor IWAMURA, NAGAYAMA appealed it to the national government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, taking over his predecessor IWAMURA&apos;s vision of establishing in Kamikawa area &quot;Hokkyo&quot; (literally, northern state capital) comparable to Tokyo and Kyoto so as to promote immigration from Honshu (the main island of Japan), NAGAYAMA appealed it to the central government.</e>
<cmt>用語・文脈・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, taking over his predecessor IWAMURA&apos;s vision of establishing in Kamikawa area &quot;Hokkyo&quot; (literally, northern state capital) comparable to Tokyo and Kyoto so as to promote immigration from Honshu (the main island of Japan), NAGAYAMA appealed it to the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>政府からは好意見も聞こえたが、内閣法制局の反対にあいこの計画は退けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some government officials positively reacted while the Cabinet Legislation Bureau disagreed with him and rejected his plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some government officials positively reacted while the Cabinet Legislation Bureau disagreed with him and rejected his plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some government officials positively reacted while the Cabinet Legislation Bureau disagreed with him and rejected his plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>かわって上川に離宮を設ける案が浮上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, establishment of an imperial villa was proposed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, an idea of building a detached palace in Kamikawa was proposed.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, an idea of building a detached palace in Kamikawa was proposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>予定地は現在の旭川市神楽岡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The planned construction site was Kaguraoka, Asahikawa City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The planned construction site was Kaguraoka, Asahikawa City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The planned construction site was Kaguraoka, Asahikawa City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>明治天皇の裁可を得たこの計画は明治22年(1889年)に宮内省をへて閣議決定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Approved by Emperor Meiji, the plan was endorsed by the Imperial Household Ministry and then by the Cabinet in 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approved by Emperor Meiji, the plan was endorsed by the Imperial Household Ministry and then by the Cabinet in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approved by Emperor Meiji, the plan was endorsed by the Imperial Household Ministry and then by the Cabinet in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>離宮が出来るとなると旭川の評価は高まり、神楽岡の一帯を御料地に指定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With announcement of the plan, Asahikawa received high appreciation and Kaguraoka area was designated as goryochi (an imperial estate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the announcement of the plan, Asahikawa received high appreciation and the Kaguraoka area was designated as goryochi (an imperial estate).</e>
<cmt>形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the announcement of the plan, Asahikawa received high appreciation and the Kaguraoka area was designated as goryochi (an imperial estate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>明治23年には前述の永山村に加え旭川村・神居村が開村、明治25年には永山神社が創建される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1890, in addition to the above-mentioned Nagayama Village, Asahikawa Village and Kamui Village were established and in 1892, Nagayama Shrine was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890, in addition to the above-mentioned Nagayama-mura Village, Asahikawa-mura Village and Kamui-mura Village opened, and in 1892, the Nagayama-jinja Shrine was built.</e>
<cmt>形式・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890, in addition to the above-mentioned Nagayama-mura Village, Asahikawa-mura Village and Kamui-mura Village opened, and in 1892, the Nagayama-jinja Shrine was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>入植者は一気に増え開発が進むが、札幌・小樽方面の反発と日清戦争の始まりによって計画が頓挫してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of immigrants frastically increased and development of Hokkaido proceeded while the plan of the imperial villa was dashed by backlash from the regions of Sapporo City and Otaru City and the outbreak of the Japanese-Sino War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of immigrants drastically increased and development of Hokkaido proceeded, but the plan of the detached palace was aborted due to backlash from Sapporo and Otaru and the outbreak of the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>原文のリンク先表示を修正しました。誤字・用語・スペーシングを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of immigrants drastically increased and development of Hokkaido proceeded, but the plan of the detached palace was aborted due to backlash from Sapporo and Otaru and the outbreak of the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>上川神社境内には武四郎の歌碑と、記念碑が建立され今に伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A monument having an epigraph of Takeshiro&apos;s waka poem engraved thereon and a memorial monument, which were set up in the precincts of Kamikawa Shrine, serve as reminders of him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A monument having an epigraph of Takeshiro&apos;s waka poem engraved thereon and a memorial monument, which were set up in the precincts of Kamikawa Shrine, serve as reminders of him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A monument having an epigraph of Takeshiro&apos;s waka poem engraved thereon and a memorial monument, which were set up in the precincts of Kamikawa Shrine, serve as reminders of him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 海亀(id:48936), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 櫻井(id:225946), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Safkan(id:423), K. Takeda(id:119013), Nopira(id:29335), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>