<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条長成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naganari ICHIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naganari ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naganari ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一条 長成（いちじょう ながなり、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naganari ICHIJO (date of birth and death unknown) was a kuge (court noble) who lived in the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naganari ICHIJO (date of birth and death unknown) was a kuge (court noble) who lived near the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naganari ICHIJO (year of birth and death unknown) was a kuge (court noble) who lived near the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>dateをyearに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原長成とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called FUJIWARA no Naganari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called FUJIWARA no Naganari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called FUJIWARA no Naganari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>源義経の義父として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous as the father in law of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was famous as the father in law of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was famous as the father in law of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原北家道隆流（水無瀬流）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a person of Michitaka line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (Minase line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a person of the Michitaka line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (Minase line).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a person of the Michitaka line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (Minase line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>極官は大蔵卿で、邸が北大路沿いにあったことから一条大蔵卿の呼称で知られるが、後の摂関家一条家とは無関係。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The highest official court rank was Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury) and he was famous for the name of Ichijo Okura-kyo because his residence was located on the Kitaoji street, but he had no relationship with the later Ichijo clan which was Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The highest official court rank was Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury) and he was famous concerning the name of Ichijo Okura-kyo because his residence was located on Kitaoji street, but he had no relationship with the later Ichijo clan which was Sekkan-ke (family that produced regents).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The highest official court rank was Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury) and he was famous concerning the name of Ichijo Okura-kyo because his residence was located on Kitaoji street, but he had no relationship with the later Ichijo clan which was Sekkan-ke (family that produced regents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また同時期の権中納言一条能保（中御門流、源頼朝の妹婿）や、一条忠頼（甲斐源氏）とも関係がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he had no relationship with Yoshiyasu ICHIJO who was Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) (Nakamikado-ryu (the Nakamikado line) and a husband of the sister of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo) and Tadayori ICHIJO (Kai-Genji (Minamoto clan)) in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he had no relationship with Yoshiyasu ICHIJO who was Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) (Nakamikado-ryu - the Nakamikado line) and the husband of the sister of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo) and Tadayori ICHIJO (Kai-Genji (Minamoto clan)) in those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he had no relationship with Yoshiyasu ICHIJO who was Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) (Nakamikado-ryu - the Nakamikado line) and the husband of the sister of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo) and Tadayori ICHIJO (Kai-Genji (Minamoto clan)) in those days.</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor)→Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>父は白河天皇・鳥羽天皇の院近臣として知られる参議藤原忠能で、長成は次男にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Tadayoshi (藤原忠能) who was Sangi (councilor) known as In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) of the Emperor Shirakawa and the Emperor Toba, and Naganori was his second son.</e>
<cmt>藤原忠能の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Tadayoshi (藤原忠能) who was Sangi (councilor) known as In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) of the Emperor Shirakawa and the Emperor Toba, and Naganori was his second son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Tadayoshi (藤原忠能) who was Sangi (councilor) known as In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) of the Emperor Shirakawa and the Emperor Toba, and Naganori was his second son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>母は参議藤原長忠の娘で、その姉妹はやはり鳥羽院近臣の藤原基隆に嫁ぎ、藤原忠隆を生んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nagatada who was Sangi and her sister married with FUJIWARA no Mototaka who was also In no Kinshin of the Emperor Toba and gave birth to FUJIWARA no Tadataka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Nagatada who was Sangi and her sister married FUJIWARA no Mototaka who was also In no Kinshin of Emperor Toba and she gave birth to FUJIWARA no Tadataka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Nagatada who was Sangi and her sister married FUJIWARA no Mototaka who was also In no Kinshin of Emperor Toba and she gave birth to FUJIWARA no Tadataka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>史料では、久安5年（1149年）従五位上兵衛府として美福門院への昇殿を許可されているのが初見である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In historical materials, it was the first appearance that he was admitted to the court of Bifukumonin as an official of Hyoe-fu (Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guards) in Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 1149.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In historical materials, it was the first appearance when he was admitted to the court of Bifukumonin as an official of Hyoe-fu (Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guards) in Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 1149.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In historical materials, it was the first appearance when he was admitted to the court of Bifukumonin as an official of Hyoe-fu (Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guards) in Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 1149.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>仁平2年（1152年）には従四位下加賀国守となっており、同年末には但馬国守に遷任されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1152 he was assigned to Kaga no kuni no kami (Governor of Kaga Province) in Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1152 and transferred to Tajima no kuni no kami (governor of Tajima Province) in the end of that year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1152 he was assigned to Kaga no kuni no kami (Governor of Kaga Province) in Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1152 and transferred to Tajima no kuni no kami (governor of Tajima Province) at the end of that year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1152 he was assigned to Kaga no kuni no kami (Governor of Kaga Province) in Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1152 and transferred to Tajima no kuni no kami (governor of Tajima Province) at the end of that year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>保元2年（1157年）大蔵卿となり、同年正四位下に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1157 he was assigned to Okura-kyo and conferred to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1157 he was assigned to Okura-kyo and conferred to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) during the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1157 he was assigned to Okura-kyo and conferred to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) during the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>長く子がなかったが、源義朝の側室であった常盤御前（阿野全成・義円・源義経の母）を平清盛から下げ渡され、後添えとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had no child before he married with Tokiwa gozen (the mother of Zenjo ANO, Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune) who had been a concubine of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as the second wife, ordered by TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had no child before he married Tokiwa gozen (the mother of Zenjo ANO, Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune) who had been a concubine of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a second wife, ordered by TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had no child before he married Tokiwa gozen (the mother of Zenjo ANO, Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune) who had been a concubine of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a second wife, ordered by TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>2人の間には嫡子・一条能成が生まれ、後に従三位に上り異父兄・義経の側近となっているが、長成自身は正四位下大蔵卿にまで昇進しながらも、公卿にはなれずに終わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their legitimate child Yoshinari ICHIJO was later conferred to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and became a vassal of Yoshitsune who was his half brother, but Naganori himself could not became Kugyo (the top court officials) although he was promoted to Okura-kyo in Shoshiinoge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their legitimate child Yoshinari ICHIJO was later conferred to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and became a vassal of Yoshitsune who was his half brother, but Naganori himself could not became Kugyo (top court official) although he was promoted to Okura-kyo in Shoshiinoge.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their legitimate child Yoshinari ICHIJO was later conferred to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and became a vassal of Yoshitsune who was his maternal half-brother, but Naganori himself could not became Kugyo (top court official) although he was promoted to Okura-kyo in Shoshiinoge.</e>
<cmt>half brotherをmaternal half-brotherに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『尊卑分脈』によれば長成は皇后宮亮となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in thefourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy), Naganari was kogogu no suke (person who is in charge of the things about the empress).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in thefourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy), Naganari was kogogu no suke (person who is in charge of the matters concerning the empress).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in thefourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy), Naganari was kogogu no suke (person who is in charge of the matters concerning the empress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>義経が幼少時、陸奥平泉町の藤原秀衡に庇護されたのは、長成の支援によるものといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yoshitsune was protected by FUJIWARA no Hidehira in Hiraizumi of Mutsu Province in his childhood because of Naganari&apos;s support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yoshitsune was protected by FUJIWARA no Hidehira in Hiraizumi of Mutsu Province in his childhood because of Naganari&apos;s support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yoshitsune was protected by FUJIWARA no Hidehira in Hiraizumi of Mutsu Province in his childhood because of Naganari&apos;s support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>秀衡の舅である藤原基成（義経の父義朝の上司藤原信頼の弟。娘が藤原泰衡を生む）は、長成の母方の従兄弟にあたる藤原忠隆の子であり、親戚関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Motonari (a brother of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, a boss of Yoshitomo, Yoshitsune&apos;s father. His daughter gave birth to FUJIWAWA no Yasuhira), who was Hidehira&apos;s father-in-law, was a son of FUJIWARA no Tadataka, who was a maternal cousin of Naganari so that they were relatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Motonari (a brother of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, a boss of Yoshitomo, Yoshitsune&apos;s father. His daughter gave birth to FUJIWAWA no Yasuhira), who was Hidehira&apos;s father-in-law, was a son of FUJIWARA no Tadataka, who was the maternal cousin of Naganari so that they were relatives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Motonari (a brother of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, a boss of Yoshitomo, Yoshitsune&apos;s father. His daughter gave birth to FUJIWAWA no Yasuhira), who was Hidehira&apos;s father-in-law, was a son of FUJIWARA no Tadataka, who was the maternal cousin of Naganari so that they were relatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 諏訪太郎頼光(id:98476), Im224(id:57113), Point136(id:211299), トホホ川(id:50502), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 小者(id:172526), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>