<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原公通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinmichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinmichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinmichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原公通（ふじわら の きんみち、永久 (元号)5年（1117年） - 承安 (日本)3年9月9日 (旧暦)（1173年10月17日）、または4月9日 (旧暦)（5月22日））は、平安時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinmichi (1117-October 24 or May 29, 1173) was Kugyo in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinmichi (1117-October 24 or May 29, 1173) was Kugyo during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinmichi (1117-October 24 or May 29, 1173) was Kugyo (court noble) during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>西園寺家の第二代に数えられる人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second generation of the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a second generation member of the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a second generation member of the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中納言藤原通季の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the child of FUJIWARA no Michisue, Chunagon (a vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of FUJIWARA no Michisue, Chunagon (a vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of FUJIWARA no Michisue, Chunagon (a vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は閑院按察。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Kanin Azechi.</e>
<cmt>「閑院按察」については読み不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (pen name) was Kanin Azechi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Kanin Azechi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>藤大納言とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Todainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Todainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Todainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>鳥羽天皇（74代）・崇徳天皇（75代）・近衛天皇（76代）・後白河天皇（77代）・二条天皇（78代）・六条天皇（79代）の六朝にわたって朝廷に仕え、官位は正二位大納言まで昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served the Imperial Court in six generations of the Emperor Toba (the seventy-fourth), the Emperor Sutoku (the seventy-fifth), the Emperor Konoe (the seventy-sixth), the Emperor Goshirakawa (the seventy-seventh), the Emperor Nijo (the seventy-eighth) and the Emperor Rokujo (the seventy-ninth), and promoted up to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon (a chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served the Imperial Court for six generations of Emperor Toba (the 74th), Emperor Sutoku (the 75th), Emperor Konoe (the 76th), Emperor Goshirakawa (the 77th), Emperor Nijo (the 78th) and Emperor Rokujo (the 79th), and was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served the Imperial Court for six generations of Emperor Toba (the 74th), Emperor Sutoku (the 75th), Emperor Konoe (the 76th), Emperor Goshirakawa (the 77th), Emperor Nijo (the 78th) and Emperor Rokujo (the 79th), and was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>保安 (元号)3年（1122年）に叙爵してから累進し、丹波守・侍従・因幡守・右近衛少将・右近衛中将などを歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had promoted successively since ennoblement in 1122, he experienced Tanba no kami (the governor of Tanba Province), jiju (a chamberlain), Inaba no kami (the governor of Inaba Province), Ukone no shosho (a minor captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Ukone no chujo (a middle captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>本来の原文は、「丹波国・侍従・因幡国・近衛府・近衛府などを歴任」でしたが、一部意味不明なためウェブを参照したところ「丹波守・侍従・因幡守・右近衛少将・右近衛中将などを歴任」となっていましたので、こちらに変更して訳出しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted successively since ennoblement in 1122, he had experience as Tanba no kami (governor of Tanba Province), jiju (chamberlain), Inaba no kami (governor of Inaba Province), Ukone no shosho (minor captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Ukone no chujo (middle captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted successively since conferring a peerage in 1122, he had experience as Tanba no kami (governor of Tanba Province), jiju (chamberlain), Inaba no kami (governor of Inaba Province), Ukone no shosho (minor captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Ukone no chujo (middle captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>用語統一全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>久安5年（1149年）には蔵人頭に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Kurodo no to (head chamberlain) in 1149.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Kurodo no to (head chamberlain) in 1149.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Kurodo no to (head chamberlain) in 1149.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>久安6年（1150年）には参議となり、公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Sangi (councilor) and was raised to Kugyo in 1150.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Sangi (councilor) and was raised to Kugyo in 1150.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Sangi (councilor) and was raised to Kugyo in 1150.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、備前権守・美作権守・権中納言・中納言を経て、応保元年（1161年）大納言に任じられ、仁安 (日本)2年（1167年）まで務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After experiencing Bizen gon no kami (a provincial governor of Bizen Province), Mimasaka gon no kami (a provincial governor of Mimakasa Province), Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Chunagon later, he had served as Dainagon until 1167 since its appointment in 1161.</e>
<cmt>本来の原文は、「備前国・美作国・権中納言・中納言を経て」でしたが、一部意味不明なためウェブを参照したところ「備前権守・美作権守・権中納言・中納言を経て」となっていましたので、こちらに変更して訳出しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After experience as Bizen gon no kami (provincial governor of Bizen Province), Mimasaka gon no kami (provincial governor of Mimakasa Province), Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state) and Chunagon later, he had served as Dainagon until 1167 since his appointment in 1161.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After experience as Bizen gon no kami (provincial governor of Bizen Province), Mimasaka gon no kami (provincial governor of Mimasaka Province), Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state) and Chunagon later, he had served as Dainagon until 1167 since his appointment in 1161.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>応保2年（1162年）には按察使に就任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Azechi (an inspector of the provincial government) in 1162.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) in 1162.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) in 1162.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まさふゆ(id:232040), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), Namimakura0115(id:292875), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>