<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>広幡豊忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyotada HIROHATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyotada HIROHATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyotada HIROHATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>広幡 豊忠（ひろはた とよただ、寛文6年6月26日 (旧暦)（1666年7月27日） - 元文2年8月1日 (旧暦)（1737年8月26日））は、江戸時代前期から中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyotada HIROHATA (July 27, 1666-August 26, 1737) was Kugyo (the top court official) in the early to mid Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyotada HIROHATA (July 27, 1666-August 26, 1737) was Kugyo (top court official) during the early to mid Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyotada HIROHATA (July 27, 1666 - August 26, 1737) was a Kugyo (top court official) during the early to mid Edo period.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に霊元天皇（112代）・東山天皇（113代）・中御門天皇（114代）の三朝にわたり仕え、官位は従一位内大臣まで昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served the Imperial Court mainly in three generations of the Emperor Reigen (the one hundred and twelfth), the Emperor Higashiyama (the one hundred and thirteenth) and the Emperor Nakamikado (the one hundred and fourteenth) and promoted up to Juichii (Junior First Rank) Naidaijin (minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served the Imperial Court mainly in three generations of Emperor Reigen (the 112th), Emperor Higashiyama (the 113th) and Emperor Nakamikado (the 114th) and promoted to Juichii (Junior 1st Rank) Naidaijin (minister).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served the Imperial Court mainly in three generations of Emperor Reigen (the 112th), Emperor Higashiyama (the 113th) and Emperor Nakamikado (the 114th) and promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) Naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt>1st →First としました。内大臣→Minister of the Center としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は久我通名（従三位中納言）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Michina KOGA (Jusanmi Chunagon (Junior Third Rank, Associate Chief of the Councilor of State)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Michina KOGA (Jusanmi Chunagon - Junior Third Rank, Associate Chief of the Councilor of State).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Michina KOGA (Jusanmi [Junior Third Rank], Chunagon [Associate Chief of the Councilor of State]).</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は西園寺公満（従二位左近衛中将）の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Kinmitsu SAIONJI (Junii (Junior Second Rank) Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Kinmitsu SAIONJI (Junii (Junior 2nd Rank) Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Kinmitsu SAIONJI (Junii [Junior Second Rank], Sakone no chujo [Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards]).</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>養父は広幡忠幸（正三位大納言）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His foster father was Tadayuki HIROHATA (Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank)) Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His foster father was Tadayuki HIROHATA (Shosanmi (Senior 3rd Rank) Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His adoptive father was Tadayuki HIROHATA (Shosanmi [Senior Third Rank], Dainagon [chief councilor of state]).</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄に久我通誠（従一位内大臣）、弟に堀川広益（幕府に仕え、高家旗本となる）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brother was Michitomo KOGA (Juichii (Junior First Rank), Naidaijin (minister)), and his younger brother was Hiromasu HORIKAWA (who served bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and became Koke-Hatamoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brother was Michitomo KOGA (Juichii - Junior First Rank), Naidaijin (minister), and his younger brother was Hiromasu HORIKAWA (who served the bakufu -Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun and became Koke-Hatamoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brother was Michitomo KOGA (Juichii, Naidaijin), and his younger brother was Hiromasu HORIKAWA (who served the bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun] and became Koke-Hatamoto [direct retainers of the bakufu, who were in a privileged family under Tokugawa Shogunate]).</e>
<cmt>高家旗本　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に広幡忠誠、広幡忠章、広幡忠成、広幡長忠がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Tadashige HIROHATA, Tadaaki HIROHATA, Tadanari HIROHATA and Nagatada HIROHATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Tadashige HIROHATA, Tadaaki HIROHATA, Tadanari HIROHATA, and Nagatada HIROHATA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Tadashige HIROHATA, Tadaaki HIROHATA, Tadanari HIROHATA, and Nagatada HIROHATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>娘に小倉宣季（正二位大納言）室、正親町実連（正二位大納言）室がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughters were the wife of 小倉宣季 (Shonii Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Major Counselor)) and the lawful wife of Sanetsura OGIMACHI (Shonii Dainagon).</e>
<cmt>読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughters were the wives of 小倉宣季 (Shonii Dainagon - Senior 2nd Rank, Major Counselor and the lawful wife of Sanetsura OGIMACHI -Shonii Dainagon).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughters were the wives of Nobusue OGURA (小倉宣季) (Shonii [Senior Second Rank], Dainagon) and the lawful wife of Sanetsura OGIMACHI (Shonii, Dainagon).</e>
<cmt>小倉宣季→Nobusue OGURA　と推測し、漢字も追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>寛文9年（1669年）に久我家から広幡家に養子入りした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted into the Hirohata family from the Koga family in 1669.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted into the Hirohata family from the Koga family in 1669.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted into the Hirohata family from the Koga family in 1669.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>先祖の久我晴通は近衛家からの養子であり、豊忠は近衛家の血筋を引いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ancestor, Haremichi KOGA was adopted from the Konoe family and Toyotada was descended from the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His ancestor, Haremichi KOGA was adopted from the Konoe family and Toyotada was descended from the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ancestor, Haremichi KOGA was adopted from the Konoe family and Toyotada was descended from the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>養父の広幡忠幸は八条宮智仁親王を父に持つ旧皇族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His foster father, Tadayuki HIROHATA was from the former Imperial Family, with Imperial Prince Hachijonomiya Toshihito as a father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His foster father, Tadayuki HIROHATA was from the former Imperial Family, with Imperial Prince Hachijonomiya Toshihito as his father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His adoptive father, Tadayuki HIROHATA was from the former Imperial Family, with Imperial Prince Hachijonomiya Toshihito as his father.</e>
<cmt>養父→adoptive father としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため広幡家は新家ながら清華家の格式を与えられている家柄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Hirohata family had the social status of the Seiga family in spite of the newly founded family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Hirohata family had the social status of the Seiga family in spite of the newly founded family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Hirohata family had the social status of the Seiga family (one of the highest court noble families in Japan at that time) in spite of the newly founded family.</e>
<cmt>清華家　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>寛文10年（1670年）に叙爵し、以降清華家の当主として速いスピードで昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ennobled in 1670 and then promoted at a fast pace as the family head of the Seiga family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ennobled in 1670 and then was promoted at a fast pace to the family head of the Seiga family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred peerage in 1670 and then was promoted at a fast pace as the family head of the Seiga family.</e>
<cmt>叙爵→conferred peerage　と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>左近衛少将や左近衛中将を経て、天和 (日本)3年（1683年）には霊元天皇中宮鷹司房子の中宮職に任命されるとともに従三位となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After experiencing Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was appointed to Chugushiki (Office of the Consort&apos;s Household) of Fusako TAKATSUKASA, the second consort of the Emperor Reigen as well as becoming Jusanmi and was raised to Kugyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After experience as Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was appointed to Chugushiki (Office of the Consort&apos;s Household) of Fusako TAKATSUKASA, the second consort of the Emperor Reigen as well as becoming Jusanmi and was raised to Kugyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving as Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Sakone no chujo, he was appointed to Chugushiki (Office of the Consort&apos;s Household) of Fusako TAKATSUKASA, the second consort of the Emperor Reigen as well as becoming Jusanmi in 1683 and was raised to Kugyo.</e>
<cmt>1683 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>さらにその後中納言・踏歌節会外弁をへて、元禄5年（1692年）に大納言に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he became Dainagon in 1692 after experiencing Chunagon and Toka no sechie Geben (a kugyo who supervised many matters outside Jomei Gate at Toka no sechie (Imperial Court Ceremony)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he became Dainagon in 1692 after experience as Chunagon and Toka no sechie Geben (a kugyo who supervised many matters outside Jomei Gate at Toka no sechie - Imperial Court Ceremonies).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he became Dainagon in 1692 after serving as Chunagon and Toka no sechie Geben (a kugyo who supervised many matters outside Jomei Gate at Toka no sechie, an Imperial Court ceremony).</e>
<cmt>experience→ serving としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>宝永元年（1704年）に辞するまでの12年にわたって務めあげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had served for 12 years until he resigned in 1704.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served for twelve years until resigning in 1704.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served for 12 years until resigning in 1704.</e>
<cmt>12 アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後の宝永7年（1710年）にももう一度権大納言に任ぜられ、享保5年（1720年）までの10年にわたって務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Dainagon again in 1710 and had served for 10 years until 1720.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Dainagon again in 1710 and had served for ten years until 1720.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Dainagon again in 1710 and served for ten years until 1720.</e>
<cmt>had を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この間の享保4年（1719年）には右近衛大将、右馬寮御監にも任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1719 during that period, he was also appointed to Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Umaryo gogen (Inspector of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1719 during that period, he was also appointed to Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Umaryo gogen (Inspector of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1719 during that period, he was also appointed to Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Umaryo gogen (Inspector of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>享保8年（1723年）2月4日内大臣に就任したが、同月8日に辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he was appointed to Naidaijin in February 4, 1723, he resigned in February 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he was appointed to Naidaijin on February 4, 1723, he resigned on February 8.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was appointed to Naidaijin on March 10, 1723, he resigned on March 16.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>享保11年（1726年）に従一位に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was conferred to Juichii in 1726.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was conferred to Juichii in 1726.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred to Juichii in 1726.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>