<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利義稙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 義稙（義材）（あしかが よしたね（よしき））は、室町幕府の第10代征夷大将軍（将軍職在位：延徳2年（1490年）-明応3年（1493年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane (or Yoshiki) ASHIKAGA was the tenth Seii-Taishogun (Commander-in-Chief; in office from 1490 to 1493) of the Muromachi Shogunate Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane (or Yoshiki) ASHIKAGA was the tenth Shogun (in office from 1490 to 1493) of the Muromachi Shogunate Government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Seii-Taishogun&quot;→&quot;Shogun&quot;　－I think Shogun is sufficient for most English speakersDeleted &quot;Commander-in-Chief;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane (or Yoshiki) ASHIKAGA was the tenth Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) (in office from 1490 to 1493) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>室町幕府→Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)Shogun→Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>永正5年（1508年） - 大永元年（1521年））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1508-1521</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1508-1521</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1508-1521</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>父は第8代将軍・足利義政の弟で一時は義政の養嗣子となっていた足利義視、母は日野重政の娘（日野富子の妹にあたる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane&apos;s father was Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, a younger brother and one time heir of of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA (the eighth Shogun), and his mother was Shigemasa HINO&apos;s daughter (Tomiko HINO&apos;s younger sister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane&apos;s father was Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, a younger brother of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA (the eighth Shugun), who was also once an adopted heir of Yoshimasa, and his mother was Shigemasa HINO&apos;s daughter (Tomiko HINO&apos;s younger sister).</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;Shogun&quot;&quot;who was also once an adopted heir of Yoshimasa&quot;→&quot;and one time heir&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane&apos;s father was Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, a younger brother of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA (the eighth Shogun), who was also once an adopted heir of Yoshimasa, and his mother was Shigemasa HINO&apos;s daughter (Tomiko HINO&apos;s younger sister).</e>
<cmt>Shugun→Shogun</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>義政の養子となり、義政の死後に第10代将軍に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane was adopted by Yoshimasa and was appointed as the tenth Shugun after the latter&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane was adopted by Yoshimasa and was appointed as the tenth Shogun after the latter&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;Shogun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane was adopted by Yoshimasa and was appointed as the tenth Shogun after the latter&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし管領の細川政元と対立して廃立、幽閉されたが、越中国へ逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he came into conflict with his Chief Adviser (Kanryo) Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and having been deprived of power and confined by Masamoto, he fled to Etchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he came into conflict with the Kanrei (Deputy Shogun) Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and having been deprived of power and placed under house arrest, he fled to Etchu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;his Chief Adviser (Kanryo)&quot;→&quot;the Kanrei (Deputy Shogun)&quot; - I think &quot;Kanrei&quot; is more usual than &quot;Kanryo&quot; and the position was more important than chief adviser&quot;confined by Masamoto&quot;→&quot;placed under house arrest&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he came into conflict with the Kanrei (Deputy Shogun) Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and having been deprived of power and placed under house arrest, he fled to Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>越中国→Ecchu Province[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明応7年（1498年）に義尹（よしただ）と改名、永正10年（1513年）には義稙（よしたね）と改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed his name to Yoshitada in 1498 and again to Yoshitane in 1513.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his name to Yoshitada in 1498 and then to Yoshitane in 1513.</e>
<cmt>&quot;again&quot;→&quot;then&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his name to Yoshitada in 1498 and then to Yoshitane in 1513.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>後に周防国の大内義興を後ろ盾にして室町幕府将軍職に復帰するが、今度は管領の細川高国（政元の養子）と対立して京都を出奔し、阿波で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he later regained his position as the Shogun of the Muromachi Government with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI, he came into conflict with his Chief Adviser (Kanryo) Takakuni HOSOKAWA once again, fled Kyoto and died in Awa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he later regained his position as the Shogun of the Muromachi Government with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI, he came into conflict with the new Kanrei, Takakuni HOSOKAWA, fled Kyoto and died in Awa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;his Chief Adviser (Kanryo)&quot;→&quot;the Kanrei&quot;&quot;once again&quot;→&quot;new&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he later regained his position as the Shogun of the Muromachi Government with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI, he came into conflict with the new Kanrei, Takakuni HOSOKAWA, fled Kyoto and died in Awa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;History&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Life →Biographyに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>文正元年（1466年）7月30日、足利義視の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiki (later Yoshitane) ASHIKAGA was born as a son of Yoshimi ASHIKAGA on July 30, 1466.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiki (later Yoshitane) ASHIKAGA was born as a son of Yoshimi ASHIKAGA on July 30, 1466.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiki (later Yoshitane) ASHIKAGA was born as a son of Yoshimi ASHIKAGA on July 30, 1466.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>延徳元年（1489年）、室町幕府第9代将軍の足利義尚が近江国の六角高頼征伐の在陣中に死去した後、伯父の義政と和睦した父・義視と共に逼塞先の美濃国の土岐成頼のもとから上洛し、足利義政の養子となって延徳2年（1490年）に第10代将軍に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, the ninth Shogun of the Muromachi Government, died in 1489 during his war to conquer Takayori ROKKAKU, Yoshiki left the domain of Shigeyori TOKI, where he was hiding, in order to visit the Imperial Court in Kyoto along with his father Yoshimi, who concluded a truce with his uncle Yoshimasa, as an adopted son of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA and was appointed by the Emperor as the tenth Shogun of the Muromachi Government in 1490.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1489, after Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, the ninth Shogun of the Muromachi Government, died during his war to conquer Takayori ROKKAKU, Yoshiki left the domain of Shigeyori TOKI, where he was hiding, in order to visit the Imperial Court in Kyoto with his father, who had signed a truce with his uncle, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, was adopted by Yoshimasa and appointed by the Emperor as the tenth Shogun of the Muromachi Government in 1490.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;in 1489&quot;&quot;concluded&quot;→&quot;had signed&quot;&quot;as an adopted son of&quot;→&quot;was adopted by&quot;Deleted &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1489, after Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, the ninth Shogun of the Muromachi Government, died during his war to conquer Takayori ROKKAKU, Yoshiki left the domain of Shigeyori TOKI, where he was hiding, in order to visit the Imperial Court in Kyoto with his father, who had signed a truce with his uncle, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, was adopted by Yoshimasa and appointed by the Emperor as the tenth Shogun of the Muromachi Government in 1490.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし政治の実権は父に握られ、父が延徳3年（1491年）に死去した後は、畠山政長の支援を背景に権力の確立を企図するが、管領の細川政元と義政未亡人の日野富子らと対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the real political power was in the hands of his father, and after his father died in 1491, Yoshiki strove to gain full control of the government with the support of Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, but came into conflict with the the group of Kanryo Masamoto HOSOKAWA and Yoshimasa&apos;s widow Tomiko HINO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the real political power was in the hands of his father, and after his father died in 1491, Yoshiki tried to gain full control of the government with the support of Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, but came into conflict with the Kanrei, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and Yoshimasa&apos;s widow, Tomiko HINO.</e>
<cmt>&quot;strove&quot;→&quot;tried&quot;Deleted &quot;group of&quot;&quot;Kanryo&quot;→&quot;Kanrei&quot;Added commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the real political power was in the hands of his father, and after his father died in 1491, Yoshiki tried to gain full control of the government with the support of Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, but came into conflict with the Kanrei, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and Yoshimasa&apos;s widow, Tomiko HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>明応2年（1493年）、畠山義豊を討伐するために河内国に出陣していたが、その間に京都では細川政元と日野富子によって義政・義視の弟に当たる足利政知の子・足利義澄が新将軍として擁立されたため、義材は将軍職を廃されることとなった（明応の政変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1493, while Yoshiki was fighting a battle to conquer Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA, Masamoto HOSOKAWA and Tomiko HINO conspired together to have Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, the son of Masatomo ASHIKAGA (a younger brother of Yoshimasa and Yoshimi), appointed as a new Shogun; as a result, Yoshiki was dethroned as Shogun (Meio no Seihen (Coups of Meio)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1493, while Yoshiki was fighting a battle to conquer Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA, Masamoto HOSOKAWA and Tomiko HINO conspired to have Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, the son of Masatomo ASHIKAGA (a younger brother of Yoshimasa and Yoshimi), appointed as the new Shogun, resulting in Yoshiki&apos;s removal (the Meio Coup).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;together&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;; as a result,&quot;→&quot;resulting in&quot;&quot;was dethroned as Shogun&quot;→&quot;&apos;s removal&quot;&quot;Meio no Seihen (Coups of Meio)&quot;→&quot;the Meio Coup&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1493, while Yoshiki was fighting a battle to conquer Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA, Masamoto HOSOKAWA and Tomiko HINO conspired to have Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, the son of Masatomo ASHIKAGA (a younger brother of Yoshimasa and Yoshimi), appointed as the new Shogun, resulting in Yoshiki&apos;s removal (the Meio Coup).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>義材は幽閉されたが、側近らの手引きで越中国の放生津に下向し、畠山政長の家臣・神保長誠を頼ったため、越中公方（越中御所）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshiki was placed in confinement, he managed to flee to Hojozu in Etchu and visited Naganobu JIMBO, a retainer of Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, for support; accordingly, he was ridiculed as a &quot;puppet Shogun&quot; in Etchu (Etchu Kubo or Etchu Gosho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshiki was placed under house arrest, he managed to flee to Hojozu in Etchu and visited Naganobu JIMBO, a retainer of Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, for support; accordingly, he was ridiculed as a &quot;puppet Shogun&quot; in Etchu (Etchu Kubo or Etchu Gosho).</e>
<cmt>&quot;in confinement&quot;→&quot;under house arrest&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshiki was placed under house arrest, he managed to flee to Hojozu in Etchu and visited Naganobu JINBO, a retainer of Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, for support; accordingly, he was ridiculed as a puppet Shogun in Ecchu (Ecchu Kubo or Ecchu Gosho).</e>
<cmt>神保長誠→Naganobu JINBO[用語集]原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除越中国→Ecchu Province[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>明応8年（1499年）に政元派との和睦交渉が進展したという認識から、義尹（義材より改名）は越前国の朝倉貞景のもとへ移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1499, believing that peace negotiations with Masamoto&apos;s group were being successfully conducted, Yoshitada (Yoshiki&apos;s new name) moved his residence to Sadakage ASAKURA&apos;s domain in Echizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1499, believing that peace negotiations with Masamoto were being successfully conducted, Yoshitada (Yoshiki&apos;s new name) moved his residence to Sadakage ASAKURA&apos;s domain of Echizen.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;&apos;s group&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1499, believing that peace negotiations with Masamoto were being successfully conducted, Yoshitada (Yoshiki&apos;s new name) moved his residence to Sadakage ASAKURA&apos;s domain of Echizen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ところが政元派との和睦は不調となり、朝倉貞景や政長の子である畠山尚順（尚慶）と同調して軍事攻撃による上洛へ方針転換したが敗北し、周防の大内義興を頼って落ち延びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as negotiations with Masamoto&apos;s group resulted in failure, he changed his tactics and launched a military attack in collaboration with Sadakage ASAKURA and Hisanobu (Naoyoshi) HATAKEYAMA in his attempt to visit the Imperial Court in Kyoto; however, he was defeated in the battle and fled to Yoshioki OUCHI&apos;s domain in Suo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as negotiations with Masamoto resulted in failure, he changed his tactics and, in an attempt to return to Kyoto, launched a military attack in collaboration with Sadakage ASAKURA and Hisanobu (Naoyoshi) HATAKEYAMA but was defeated in the battle and fled to Yoshioki OUCHI&apos;s domain in Suo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in his attempt to visit the Imperial Court in Kyoto&quot;→&quot;in an attempt to return to Kyoto&quot; and moved&quot;; however, he&quot;→&quot;but&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as negotiations with Masamoto resulted in failure, he changed his tactics and, in an attempt to return to Kyoto, launched a military attack in collaboration with Sadakage ASAKURA and Hisanobu (Naoyoshi) HATAKEYAMA but was defeated in the battle and fled to Yoshioki OUCHI&apos;s domain in Suo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>永正4年（1507年）に細川政元が暗殺されると、義尹は将軍への復帰をもくろみ、永正5年（1508年）4月に大内義興や細川高国の支援を得て中国地方や九州の諸大名と共に上洛し、義澄を廃して再び将軍になった（永正の錯乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated in 1507, Yoshitada plotted to return to the Shogunate, and with the support of Yoshioki OUCHI and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, he visited the Imperial Court in Kyoto in April 1508 to be reappointed as the Shogun to drive Yoshizumi out of power (Eisho-no-Sakuran (assassination of Masatomo HOSOKAWA)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated in 1507, Yoshitada plotted to return to the Shogunate and, supported by Yoshioki OUCHI, Takakuni HOSOKAWA and several daimyo from western Japan and Kyushu, he returned to Kyoto in April 1508, deposed Yoshizumi and was reappointed as the Shogun (the Eisho Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>Reworded second half of sentenceDeleted &quot;the Imperial Court&quot;Added &quot;and several daimyo from western Japan and Kyushu&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated in 1507, Yoshitada plotted to return to the Shogunate and, supported by Yoshioki OUCHI, Takakuni HOSOKAWA and several daimyo from western Japan and Kyushu, he returned to Kyoto in April 1508, deposed Yoshizumi and was reappointed as the Shogun (the Eisho Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、義澄やその一派と将軍職をめぐって抗争するが、永正8年（1511年）8月の船岡山合戦直前に義澄が病死し、さらにこの戦いにも勝利したため、義尹改め義稙の将軍職が確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He subsequently fought with Yoshizumi and his group for the succession to the Shogunate; however, since Yoshizumi died from disease immediately before the Funaokayama-no-kassen (battle at Mt. Funaoka) in August 1511, which resulted in Yoshitada&apos;s victory, Yoshitane (Yoshitada&apos;s new name) was able to secure his position as the Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He subsequently fought with Yoshizumi and his supporters for the position of Shogun but since Yoshizumi died from disease immediately before the Battle of Mt. Funaokayama in August 1511, resulting in Yoshitada&apos;s victory, Yoshitane (Yoshitada&apos;s new name) was able to secure his position as the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>&quot;group&quot;→&quot;supporters&quot;&quot;succession to the Shogunate; however&quot;→&quot;position of Shogun but&quot;&quot;Funaokayama-no-kassen (battle at Mt. Funaoka)&quot;→&quot;Battle of Mt. Funaokayama&quot;&quot;which resulted in&quot;→&quot;resulting in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He subsequently fought with Yoshizumi and his supporters for the position of Shogun but since Yoshizumi died from disease immediately before the Battle of Mt. Funaokayama in August 1511, resulting in Yoshitada&apos;s victory, Yoshitane (Yoshitada&apos;s new name) was able to secure his position as the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし大永元年（1521年）、管領の細川高国と対立して出奔した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1521, however, he again fled his country as a result of his conflict with Kanryo Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1521, however, he again fled as a result of his conflict with Kanryo Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;his country&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1521, however, he again fled as a result of his conflict with Kanryo Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>the Kanrei (Deputy Shogun)と前出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>高国は新将軍には義澄の子・足利義晴を擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni supported Yoshizumi&apos;s son Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA as the new Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni supported Yoshizumi&apos;s son Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA as the new Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni supported Yoshizumi&apos;s son Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA as the new Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義稙は和泉国から淡路国に逃れ、ここで再挙を図って高国と抗争するが敗れ、大永3年（1523年）4月9日（4月7日 (旧暦)とも）に阿波国撫養（現在の鳴門市）で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Yoshitane fled from Izumi to Awaji and reorganized his army to fight with Takakuni, but lost the battle and died in Muya, Awa (currently, Naruto City) on April 9, 1523.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Yoshitane fled from Izumi to Awaji and reorganized his army to fight with Takakuni, but lost the battle and died in Muya, Awa (currently, Naruto City) on April 9, 1523.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Yoshitane fled from Izumi to Awaji Province and reorganized his army to fight with Takakuni, but lost the battle and died in Muya, Awa Province (currently, Naruto City) on April 9, 1523.</e>
<cmt>Province補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>享年58。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 58.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 58.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 58.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>法名：恵林院殿巌山道舜大禅定門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist name: Keirinin-ten Ganzan-doshun Daizenjomon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist name: Keirinin-ten Ganzan-doshun Daizenjomon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist name: Keirinin-ten Ganzan-doshun Daizenjomon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>墓所：徳島県阿南市の西光寺に五輪塔が立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane&apos;s grave: A Buddhist monument was erected in Saiko-ji Temple in Anan City, Tokushima Prefecture to commemorate Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane&apos;s grave: A Buddhist monument was erected in Saiko-ji Temple in Anan City, Tokushima Prefecture to commemorate Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane&apos;s grave: A Buddhist monument was erected in Saiko-ji Temple in Anan City, Tokushima Prefecture to commemorate Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>没地である徳島県鳴門市の岡崎城跡に将軍塚と呼ばれる場所があり、義材の墓所と伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a mound known as Shogun-zuka (Shogun Mound) on the former site of Okazaki Castle in Naruto City, Tokushima Prefecture, which is believed to be Yoshiki&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a mound known as Shogun-zuka (Shogun Mound) on the former site of Okazaki Castle in Naruto City, Tokushima Prefecture, which is believed to be Yoshiki&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a mound known as Shogun-zuka (Shogun Mound) on the former site of Okazaki Castle in Naruto City, Tokushima Prefecture, which is believed to be Yoshiki&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>肖像：没後まもなく作られた京都市北区 (京都市)の等持院霊光殿安置の木造束帯像が著名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane&apos;s portraits: A wooden statue wearing Sokutai (old ceremonial court dress) enshrined in Reikoden Chapel, Tojiin Temple, which was made soon after his death, is well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane&apos;s portraits: There is a well-known wooden statue, made soon after his death, of Yoshitane wearing Sokutai (old ceremonial court dress) enshrined in Reikoden Chapel, Tojiin Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot;A&quot;→&quot;There is a well-known&quot;Added &quot;of Yoshitane&quot;Moved &quot;made soon after his death&quot;Deleted &quot;which was&quot;Deleted &quot;, is well known&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane&apos;s portraits: There is a well-known wooden statue, made soon after his death, of Yoshitane wearing Sokutai (old ceremonial court dress) enshrined in Reikoden Chapel, Tojiin Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>栃木県足利市の鑁阿寺には、室町幕府１５代の将軍像があり、その１体として義材の木造束帯像がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statues of fifteen Shoguns of the Muromachi Government are enshrined in Banna-ji Temple in Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture, including a wooden statue of Yoshiki wearing Sokutai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statues of fifteen Shoguns of the Muromachi Government are enshrined in Banna-ji Temple in Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture, including a wooden statue of Yoshiki wearing Sokutai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues of fifteen Shoguns of the Muromachi Government are enshrined in Banna-ji Temple in Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture, including a wooden statue of Yoshiki wearing Sokutai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>徳島県阿南市の阿南市立阿波公方・民俗資料館所蔵の義材像は鑁阿寺像の容貌を模している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of Yoshiki at the Anan Municipal Awakubo Minzoku Shiryokan Museum in Anan City, Tokushima Prefecture, was modelled after the statue in Banna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of Yoshiki at the Anan Municipal Awakubo Minzoku Shiryokan Museum in Anan City, Tokushima Prefecture, was modelled after the statue in Banna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue of Yoshiki at the Anan Municipal Awakubo Minzoku Shiryokan Museum in Anan City, Tokushima Prefecture, was modelled after the statue in Banna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>富山県射水市の放生津橋にある義材銅像は狩衣姿１体・甲冑姿１体である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two bronze statues of Yoshiki on the Hojotsu-bashi Bridge in Imizu City, Toyama Prefecture: one wearing hunting clothes and the other wearing armour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two bronze statues of Yoshiki on the Hojotsu-bashi Bridge in Imizu City, Toyama Prefecture: one wearing hunting clothes and the other wearing armour.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two bronze statues of Yoshiki on the Hojotsu-bashi Bridge in Imizu City, Toyama Prefecture: one wearing hunting clothes and the other wearing armor.</e>
<cmt>armour→米国スペルで統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>東京国立博物館にも伝足利義稙（義澄）肖像がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a portrait of a person believed to be Yoshitane (or Yoshizumi) ASHIKAGA at the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a portrait of a person believed to be Yoshitane (or Yoshizumi) ASHIKAGA at the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a portrait of a person believed to be Yoshitane (or Yoshizumi) ASHIKAGA at the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>Character and Anecdotes→Personal Profile and Anecdotesに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>『塵塚物語』の「恵林院殿様御事」項に、義材が流浪時代を回顧したという逸話が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote about Yoshiki&apos;s period of wandering in a &apos;Story about Keirin Lord&apos; in &quot;Chirizuka Monogatari (Tales of Chirizuka).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote about Yoshiki&apos;s period of wandering in the &apos;Story of Lord Keirinin&apos; in the &quot;Chirizuka Monogatari (Tales of Chirizuka).&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;Story about Keirin Lord&quot;→&quot;Story of Lord Keirinin&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote about Yoshiki&apos;s period of wandering in the &apos;Story of Lord Keirinin&apos; in the &quot;Chirizuka Monogatari (Tales of Chirizuka).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この中で、不安に襲われた自身や困窮する人々を目の当たりにした義材が、「政治に携わるものは常に慈悲の心をもって臨まねばならない」という心境に至ったと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this story, Yoshiki, who suffers from anxiety and sees poverty-stricken people with his own eyes, tells the reader that through his own experiences, he has come to feel that those who are engaged in government must always have pity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this story, Yoshiki, filled with anxiety at the sight of poverty-stricken people, tells the reader that through his own experiences, he has come to feel that those who are engaged in government must always have pity.</e>
<cmt>&quot;who suffers from&quot;→&quot;filled with&quot;&quot;and sees&quot;→&quot;at the sight of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this story, Yoshiki, filled with anxiety at the sight of poverty-stricken people, tells the reader that through his own experiences, he has come to feel that those who are engaged in government must always have pity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>将軍職を追われて諸国を流浪した経緯から、「流れ公方」・「島の公方」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to his personal experience of having been deprived of power and wandering from place to place, he was known as a &quot;wandering Shogun&quot; or a &quot;Shogun in exile.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to his personal experience of having been deprived of power and wandering from place to place, he was known as the &quot;wandering Kubo&quot; or the &quot;Kubo in exile.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;Shogun&quot;→&quot;Kubo&quot; - the Japanese has &quot;公方&quot;, though Shogun may be OK for the general reader</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his personal experience of having been deprived of power and wandering from place to place, he was known as the &apos;wandering Kubo&apos; or the &apos;Kubo in exile.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>陰徳太平記には、細川高国と対立して出奔した義稙の乗った船に「たぞやこの鳴門の沖に御所めくは泊り定めぬ流れ公方か」という狂歌が張り出されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Intoku Taiheiki, it is written that when Yoshitane fled his country as a result of his conflict with Takakuni HOSOKAWA, a satirical poem (known as &quot;kyoka&quot;) was posted on the ship that carried Yoshitane, which read: &quot;Oh poor, miserable wandering Shogun, who is on a wandering boat off the shore of Naruto as if it were his own palace!&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Intoku Taiheiki, it is written that when Yoshitane fled as a result of his conflict with Takakuni HOSOKAWA, a satirical poem (known as a &quot;kyoka&quot;) posted on the ship that carried him read: &quot;Oh poor, miserable wandering Kubo on a wandering boat off the shore of Naruto as if it were his own palace!&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;his country&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;Deleted &quot;was&quot;, &quot;,which&quot;&quot;Yoshitane&quot;→&quot;him&quot;&quot;Shogun&quot;→&quot;Kubo&quot; - the Japanese has &quot;公方&quot;, though Shogun may be OK for the general readerDeleted &quot;, who is&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Intoku Taiheiki, it is written that when Yoshitane fled as a result of his conflict with Takakuni HOSOKAWA, a satirical poem (known as a &quot;kyoka&quot;) posted on the ship that carried him read: &apos;Oh poor, miserable wandering Kubo on a wandering boat off the shore of Naruto as if it were his own palace!&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>義稙には息子がなかったが、前将軍で対立者でもあった義澄の子・足利義維を養子として阿波に伴ったため、義稙の死後、義維は将軍職を継いだ兄の足利義晴と対立し、義稙流（義稙・義維・義栄・義助）と義澄流（義澄・義晴・義輝・義昭）に分かれ、新たな戦乱の火種となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshitane did not have his own son, he fled to Awa accompanied by Yoshitsuna, a son of Yoshizumi, the former Shogun and Yoshitane&apos;s opponent, whom he adopted as his son; therefore, after Yoshitane&apos;s death, Yoshitsuna came into conflict with his older brother Yoshiharu, who succeeded to the Shogunate, causing another power struggle between the Yoshitane group (Yoshitane, Yoshitsuna, Yoshihide and Yoshisuke) and Yoshizumi group (Yoshizumi, Yoshiharu, Yoshiteru and Yoshiaki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshitane did not have any sons, he fled to Awa accompanied by Yoshitsuna, a son of Yoshizumi, the former Shogun and Yoshitane&apos;s opponent, whom he adopted as his son and after Yoshitane&apos;s death, Yoshitsuna came into conflict with his older brother Yoshiharu, who had succeeded to the Shogunate, causing another power struggle between the Yoshitane faction (Yoshitane, Yoshitsuna, Yoshihide and Yoshisuke) and the Yoshizumi faction (Yoshizumi, Yoshiharu, Yoshiteru and Yoshiaki).</e>
<cmt>&quot;his own son&quot;→&quot;any sons&quot;&quot;; therefore&quot;→&quot;and&quot;Added &quot;had&quot;&quot;group&quot;→&quot;faction&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshitane did not have any sons, he fled to Awa accompanied by Yoshitsuna, a son of Yoshizumi, the former Shogun and Yoshitane&apos;s opponent, whom he adopted as his son and after Yoshitane&apos;s death, Yoshitsuna came into conflict with his older brother Yoshiharu, who had succeeded to the Shogunate, causing another power struggle between the Yoshitane faction (Yoshitane, Yoshitsuna, Yoshihide and Yoshisuke) and the Yoshizumi faction (Yoshizumi, Yoshiharu, Yoshiteru and Yoshiaki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Offices and Ranks Held</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Offices and Ranks Held</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Offices and Ranks Held</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="34">
<j>1487年（長享元年）8月29日、従五位下に叙し、左馬頭に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29, 1487, Yoshitane was awarded the Jugoinoge rank and was appointed Chief Stabler (Sama-no-kami).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29, 1487, Yoshitane was awarded the Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth, Lower Grade) rank and was appointed as the Chief Stabler (Sama-no-kami).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Junior Fifth, Lower Grade)&quot;Deleted &quot;as the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 29, 1487: Yoshitane was awarded the Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed as the Sama-no-kami (Chief Stabler).</e>
<cmt>従五位下→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)[用語集]rank削除Chief Stabler (Sama-no-kami)→Sama-no-kami (Chief Stabler)On August 29, 1487, →August 29, 1487:に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>時に、義材を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sometimes used his old name Yoshiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sometimes used his old name Yoshiki to call himself.</e>
<cmt>Added commaDeleted &quot;to call himself&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sometimes used his old name Yoshiki to call himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>1490年（延徳2年）7月5日、従四位下に昇叙し、右近衛中将に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 5, 1490, Yoshiki was promoted to the Jushiinoge rank and was appointed as the Vice Minister of the Ukon-e Division (Ukon-e-no-Chujo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 5, 1490, Yoshiki was promoted to the Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth, Lower Grade) rank and was appointed a Middle Captain of the Imperial Guards.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Junior Fourth, Lower Grade)&quot;&quot;as the Vice Minister of the Ukon-e Division (Ukon-e-no-Chujo)&quot;→&quot;a Middle Captain of the Imperial Guards&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 5, 1490: Yoshiki was promoted to the Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed a Middle Captain of the Imperial Guards.</e>
<cmt>従四位下→Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)[用語集]rank削除On July 5, 1490,→July 5, 1490:に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>併せて征夷大将軍宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he was appointed by the Emperor as the Seii-Taishogun (Commander in Chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he was appointed Shogun by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as the Seii-Taishogun (Commander in Chief)&quot;→&quot;Shogun&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he was appointed the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>同日、さらに参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day, he was also appointed a Councilor of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same day, he was also appointed as a Councilor of State.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same day, he was also appointed as a Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt>参議→sangi (councillor)[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>右近衛中将兼任は元の如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued to remain in his position as the Ukon-e-no-Chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to remain in his position as a Middle Captain of the Imperial Guards.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Ukon-e-no-Chujo&quot;→&quot;a Middle Captain of the Imperial Guards&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to remain in his position as a Ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>右近衛中将→Ukone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>1498年（明応7年）　名を義尹と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1498, he changed his name to Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1498, he changed his name to Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1498: He changed his name to Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>In 1498, he→1498: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>1501年（明応10年）　征夷大将軍並びに参議を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1501, he resigned as the Seii-Taishogun and Councilor of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1501, he resigned from the positions of Shogun and Councilor of State.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as the Seii-Taishogun&quot;→&quot;from the positions of Shogun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1501: He resigned from the positions of Sseii taishogun and Sangi.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)[用語集]参議→Sangi (councillor)[用語集]In 1501, he→1501: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>1508年（永正5年）7月1日　従三位に昇叙し、権大納言に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 1, 1508, he was promoted to the Jusammi rank and was appointed as the Vice Chief Councilor of State (Gon-dai-nagon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 1, 1508, he was promoted to the Jusammi (Junior Third) rank and was appointed Vice Chief Councilor of State (Gon-dai-nagon).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Junior Third)deleted &quot;as the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 1, 1508: He was promoted to the Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and was appointed Gon dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>従三位→Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)[用語集]rank削除権大納言→Gon dainagon (provisional major counselor)[用語集]On July 1, 1508, he→July 1, 1508: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>併せて征夷大将軍宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also appointed by the Emperor as the Seii-Taishogun (Commander in Chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also appointed Shogun by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as the Seii-Taishogun (Commander in Chief)&quot;→&quot;Shogun&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also appointed Seii taishogun by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)[用語集]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>12月27日、従二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 27, 1508, he was promoted to the Juni rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 27, 1508, he was promoted to the Juni (Junior Second) rank.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Junior Second)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 27, 1508: He was promoted to the Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>従二位→Junii (Junior Second Rank)[用語集]rank削除On December 27, 1508, he→December 27, 1508: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>1513年（永正10年）11月9日、名を義稙と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 9, 1513, he renamed himself Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 9, 1513, he renamed himself Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 9, 1513: He renamed himself Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>On November 9, 1513, he→November 9, 1513: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>1519年（永正16年）9月27日、源氏長者、淳和奨学両院別当を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 27, 1519, he was appointed as the Master of Genji (Genji Choja) and also as the President of Junnain and Shogakuin Temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 27, 1519, he was appointed Head of the Genji (Genji Choja) and also the head of Junnain and Shogakuin Temples.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as the Master&quot;→&quot;Head&quot;Deleted &quot;as&quot;&quot;President&quot;→&quot;head&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 27, 1519: He was appointed Head of the Genji choja (Head of the Genji) and also the betto (the superior of a temple) of Junnain and Shogakuin Temples.</e>
<cmt>Head of the Genji (Genji Choja)→Genji choja (Head of the Genji)別当→betto (the superior of a temple)On September 27, 1519, he→September 27, 1519: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="47">
<j>1521年（永正18年）12月25日、征夷大将軍を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 25, 1521, he resigned as the Seii-Taishogun (Commander in Chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 25, 1521, he resigned from the position of Shogun.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as the Seii-Taishogun (Commander in Chief)&quot;→&quot;from the position of Shogun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 25, 1521: He resigned from the position of Seii taishogun.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)[用語集]On December 25, 1521, he→December 25, 1521: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="48">
<j>1523年（大永3年）4月9日、薨去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on April 9, 1523.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on April 9, 1523.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 9, 1523: He died.</e>
<cmt>He died on April 9, 1523.→April 9, 1523: He died.に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>1535年（天文 (元号)4年）4月8日、贈従一位・太政大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumously awarded the Juichii rank and the post of Grand Minister of State on April 8, 1535.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumously awarded the Juichii (Junior First) rank and the post of Grand Minister of State on April 8, 1535.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Junior First)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 8, 1535: Posthumously awarded the Juichii (Junior First Rank) and the post of Grand Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>従一位→Juichii (Junior First Rank)[用語集]rank削除 on April 8, 1535→前煮出してApril 8, 1535:としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="50">
<j>偏諱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People granted use of Chinese characters from Yoshitane&apos;s name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese Characters Used in Yoshitane&apos;s Names</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese Characters Used in Yoshitane&apos;s Names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="51">
<j>材の字</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character &apos;zai&apos; (材)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character &apos;zai&apos; (材)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character &apos;zai&apos; (材)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>武将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warlord</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warlords</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warlords</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>北畠材親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kichika KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kichika KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichika KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>京極材宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimune KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimune KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimune KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>尹の字</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character &apos;in&apos; (尹)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character &apos;in&apos; (尹)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character &apos;in&apos; (尹)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>武将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warlord</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warlords</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warlords</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>細川尹賢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakata HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakata HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>稙の字</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character &apos;tane&apos; (稙)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character &apos;tane&apos; (稙)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character &apos;tane&apos; (稙)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>公卿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobles</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Nobles&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>近衛稙家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneie KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneie KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneie KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>武将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warlord</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warlords</e>
<cmt>Made plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warlords</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>葛西稙清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanekiyo KASAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanekiyo KASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanekiyo KASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>葛西稙信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanenobu KASAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanenobu KASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanenobu KASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>朽木稙綱 (戦国武将)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanetsuna KUTSUKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanetsuna KUTSUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanetsuna KUTSUKI (Busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period)</e>
<cmt>戦国武将→busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>波多野稙通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanemichi HATANO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanemichi HATANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanemichi HATANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>畠山稙長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanenaga HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanenaga HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanenaga HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>伊達稙宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanemune DATE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanemune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanemune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>冨樫稙泰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyasu TOGASHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyasu TOGASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyasu TOGASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>細川稙国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanekuni HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanekuni HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanekuni HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 花蝶風月雪月花警部(id:163674), ドルチェット(id:46458), Ittyon(id:1348), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Doskoi 8(id:1070), Rai koku(id:1661), Ash Crow(id:26765), Kamakura(id:472), Ohura(id:5986), Alex K(id:86829), ひろっきー(id:87284), Kurz(id:1601), でここ(id:9565), Tsk(id:1153), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), Goki(id:7107), 秀の介(id:490), Sumaru(id:20609), Kozawa(id:672), Tosiho(id:73924), Izayohi(id:13095), たね(id:10372), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Daranome(id:1429), Yanahan(id:2437), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), 海衛士(id:19229), Louperibot(id:128971), Suisui(id:69), Kwappa(id:85455), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>