<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>脇屋義治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu WAKIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu WAKIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu WAKIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>脇屋義治（わきや よしはる）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu WAKIYA was a warlord during the Nanbokucho Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu WAKIYA was a warlord during the Nanbokucho Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu WAKIYA was a warlord during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>脇屋義助の長男で、新田義貞の甥。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Yoshisuke WAKIYA and a nephew of Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of Yoshisuke WAKIYA and a nephew of Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Yoshisuke WAKIYA and a nephew of Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>妻は児島高徳の娘といわれ、義則・義隆（義陸）らを儲けたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife is said to have been a daughter of Tananori KOJIMA and had children including Yoshinori and Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife is said to have been a daughter of Tananori KOJIMA and had children including Yoshinori and Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife is said to have been a daughter of Takanori KOJIMA and had children including Yoshinori and Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>他に兼治・佐田義久という庶子がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has also children born out of wedlock, Kaneharu and Yoshihisa SADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also has children born out of wedlock, Kaneharu and Yoshihisa SADA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also has children born out of wedlock, Kaneharu and Yoshihisa SADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>元弘3年（1333年）、父・義助は義貞の挙兵に参加し活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshisada raised an army, Yoshiharu&apos;s father Yoshisuke participated in the army and showed great performances in 1333..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshisada raised an army, Yoshiharu&apos;s father Yoshisuke participated in the army and performed greatly during 1333..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshisada raised an army, Yoshiharu&apos;s father Yoshisuke participated in the army and performed greatly during 1333.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>義治はまだ幼く、父の所領である新田荘脇屋郷に残留したと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu, who was still very young at that time, seems to have stayed at his father&apos;s territory, Nitta no sho (manor) in Wakiya-go village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu, who was still very young at that time, seems to have stayed within his father&apos;s territory, Nitta no sho (manor) in Wakiya-go village.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu, who was still very young at that time, seems to have stayed within his father&apos;s territory, Wakiya-go village in Nitta no sho (manor).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、上京したと見られ、建武 (日本)2年（1335年）、伯父新田義貞が建武政権に反旗を翻した足利尊氏への追討令を下されると、父・義助と共にその軍に加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years he seems to have come up to the capital, Kyoto, and in 1335 he participated in the army of his uncle Yoshisada NITTA, who had been ordered to search and kill Takauji ASHIKAGA, a rebel against the Kenmu government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years he seems to have gone to the capital, Kyoto, and in 1335 he participated in the army of his uncle Yoshisada NITTA, who had been ordered to search for and kill Takauji ASHIKAGA, a rebel against the Kenmu government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years he seems to have gone to the capital, Kyoto, and in 1335 he participated with his father Yoshisuke in the army of his uncle Yoshisada NITTA, who had been ordered to search for and kill Takauji ASHIKAGA, a rebel against the Kenmu government.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>箱根・竹ノ下の戦いでは父・義助の大手軍に属し、足柄峠を目指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Hakone and Takenoshita, he belonged to the Ote army led by his father Yoshisuke and headed for Ashigara-toge mountain path.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Hakone and Takenoshita, he belonged to the Ote army led by his father Yoshisuke and headed for the Ashigara-toge mountain path.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Hakone and Takenoshita, he belonged to the Ote army led by his father Yoshisuke and headed for the Ashigara-toge mountain path.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>戦闘では大友貞載、塩冶高貞らの寝返りにより、宮方が敗北し、京へ敗退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the battle, the army standing for the imperial court was defeated after betrayals of Sadatoshi (Sadanori) OTOMO and Takasada ENYA, and he then ran away to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the battle, the standing army for the imperial court was defeated after betrayals by Sadatoshi (Sadanori) OTOMO and Takasada ENYA, and he then ran away to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the battle, the standing army for the imperial court was defeated after betrayals by Sadanori (also known as Sadatoshi) OTOMO and Takasada ENYA, and he then ran away to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、父や伯父と共に京をめぐる戦闘や、播磨国赤松則村攻め、湊川の戦いに参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years he, along with his father and uncle, fought battles over Kyoto, an attack of Norimura AKAMATSU in Harima Province, and the Battle of Minato-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years he, along with his father and uncle, fought in battles over Kyoto, an attack of Norimura AKAMATSU in Harima Province, and the Battle of Minato-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years he, along with his father and uncle, fought in battles over Kyoto, an attack of Norimura AKAMATSU in Harima Province, and the Battle of the Minato-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>建武3年(1336年)後醍醐天皇が足利尊氏と和議を結び、新田義貞が恒良親王と尊良親王を奉じて北陸に下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, Emperor Godaigo agreed on a compromise with Takauji ASHIKAGA, and Yoshisada NITTA was sent to Hokuriku district. In obedience to Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi and Imperial Prince Takanaga.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, Emperor Godaigo agreed on a compromise with Takauji ASHIKAGA, and Yoshisada NITTA was sent to Hokuriku district. In obedience to Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi and Imperial Prince Takanaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, Emperor Godaigo agreed on a compromise with Takauji ASHIKAGA, and Yoshisada NITTA was sent to Hokuriku region, in obedience to Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi and Imperial Prince Takanaga.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>父・義助と共に越前国金ヶ崎城に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and his father accompanied Yoshisada NITTA to enter the Kanegasaki Castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He and his father accompanied Yoshisada NITTA to enter the Kanegasaki Castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He and his father Yoshisuke entered the Kanegasaki-jo Castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>義治は瓜生氏の杣山城に入り、諸氏への働きかけを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu entered Soyama Castle of the Uryu clan and worked on local magnates to make an ally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu entered Soyama Castle of the Uryu clan and worked on local magnates to make an ally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu entered Soyama-jo Castle of the Uryu clan and worked on local magnates to make an ally.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>まもなく金ヶ崎城は高師泰・斯波高経に包囲される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, Moroyasu KONO and Takatsune SHIBA surrounded Kanegasaki Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, Moroyasu KONO and Takatsune SHIBA surrounded Kanegasaki Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, KO no Moroyasu and Takatsune SHIBA surrounded Kanegasaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>瓜生保と義治は援軍を組織し救援に向かうが失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamotsu URYU and Yoshiharu organized reinforcements for relief, but in vain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamotsu URYU and Yoshiharu organized reinforcements for relief, but in vain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamotsu URYU and Yoshiharu organized reinforcements for relief, but in vain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>義貞、義助兄弟は援軍を組織するために金ヶ崎城から抜け出し、瓜生氏の下に身を寄せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The brother Yoshisada and Yoshiharu were successful in getting out of the castle to organize reinforcements, and put under protection of the Uryu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brother Yoshisada and Yoshiharu were successful in getting out of the castle to organize reinforcements, and put under protection of the Uryu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brothers Yoshisada and Yoshiharu were successful in getting out of the Kanegasaki-jo Castle to organize reinforcements, and put under protection of the Uryu clan.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>義貞は援軍を組織し包囲軍に攻撃をかけるが、救援に失敗し、金ヶ崎城は建武4年（1337年）3月6日落城する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu organized reinforcements and attacked the surrounding army, but he was not successful in relief, Kanegasaki Castle fell in 1337.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu organized reinforcements and attacked the surrounding army, but he was not successful in relief, Kanegasaki Castle fell in 1337.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu organized reinforcements and attacked the surrounding army, but he was not successful in relief, the Kanegasaki-jo Castle fell in April 15, 1337.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同年夏頃に、義貞は勢いを盛り返し、斯波高経を越前北部に追い詰める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshisada regained his strength around summer in the same year and got Takatsune SHIBA into cornered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshisada regained his strength around summer in the same year and corneredTakatsune SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshisada regained his strength around summer in the same year and cornered Takatsune SHIBA to the north of Echizen region.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>翌建武5年（1338年）閏7月2日に伯父・新田義貞が不慮の戦死をすると、北陸の宮方の総指揮を脇屋義助が執ることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year (1338), his uncle Yoshisada NITTA died an accidental death and Yoshiharu gained control of the force standing for the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year (1338), his uncle Yoshisada NITTA died an accidental death and Yoshiharu gained control of the force standing for the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 25, the following year 1338, his uncle Yoshisada NITTA died an accidental death and Yoshiharu WAKIYA gained control of the force standing for the imperial court in Hokuriku region.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>義治は義助と共に北陸経営を行うが、徐々に斯波高経が勢いを盛り返し興国2年（1341年）夏には杣山城が陥落し、越前の宮方は駆逐される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Yoshiharau managed Hokuriku district jointly with Hoshisuke managed Hokuriku district, Takatsune SHIBA gradually regained his strength and conquered Soyama Castle in the summer of 1341, ousting the party standing for the imperial court out of Echizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Yoshiharau managed Hokuriku district jointly with Hoshisuke, Takatsune SHIBA gradually regained his strength and conquered Soyama Castle in the summer of 1341, ousting the party standing for the imperial court out of Echizen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Yoshiharu managed Hokuriku region jointly with Yoshisuke, Takatsune SHIBA gradually regained his strength and conquered Soyama-jo Castle in the summer of 1341, ousting the party standing for the imperial court out of Echizen.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>脇屋父子は美濃国、尾張国と落ち延び、吉野に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The father and son of Wakiya family ran away to Mino Province and Owari Province, and finally entered Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The father and son of th eWakiya family ran away to Mino Province and Owari Province, and finally entered Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The father and son of the Wakiya family ran away to Mino Province and Owari Province, and finally entered Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>興国3年（1342年）に父・義助と共に中国、四国の宮方の指揮を取るために伊予国に下向する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1342, Yoshiharu and his father left the capital for Iyo Province to organize and control the party standing for the imperial court in Chugoku and Shokoku districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1342, Yoshiharu and his father left the capital for Iyo Province to organize and control the party standing for the imperial court in Chugoku and Shokoku districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1342, he and his father Yoshisuke left the capital for Iyo Province to organize and control the party standing for the imperial court in Chugoku and Shikoku regions.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、下向直後の5月11日に脇屋義助は突然の発病により没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshisuke WAKIYA died of a sudden disease on May 11, upon leaving the capital..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshisuke WAKIYA died of a sudden disease on May 11, upon leaving the capital..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshisuke WAKIYA died of a sudden disease on June 22, upon leaving the capital.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、余分なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>義治は里見氏の所領がある越後国波多岐荘や妻有荘に向かい、義貞の次男新田義興、三男新田義宗らと合流して東国で活動するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu headed for Hataki no sho (manor), Echigo Province and Tsumari no sho (manor)--where the Satomi clan had their territories, and he joined Yoshisada&apos;s second and third sons, Yoshioki NITTA and Yoshimune NITTA to be active in eastern countries from kinki district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu headed for Hataki no sho (manor), Echigo Province and Tsumari no sho (manor)--where the Satomi clan had their territories, and he joined Yoshisada&apos;s second and third sons, Yoshioki NITTA and Yoshimune NITTA to be active in eastern countries from the kinki district.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu headed for Hataki no sho (manor), Echigo Province and Tsumari no sho (manor), where the Satomi clan had their territories, and he joined Yoshisada&apos;s second and third sons, Yoshioki NITTA and Yoshimune NITTA to be active in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>正平 (日本)7年（1352年）観応の擾乱と正平の一統で混乱する室町幕府に対し、南朝 (日本)が一斉に蜂起した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Court (Japan) rose up arms against the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which had been thrown into confusion after Kanno no Joran (internal conflict of Kanno) and Shohei no Itto (unified for Shohei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Court (Japan) rose up in arms against the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which had been thrown into confusion after Kanno no Joran (internal conflict of Kanno) and Shohei no Itto (unified for Shohei).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court (Japan) rose up in arms against the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which had been thrown into confusion after Kanno Disturbance and Shohei no itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts) in 1352.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>畿内では北畠顕信、千種顕経、楠木正儀が直義派残党も糾合し、足利義詮を破り、京を奪還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinai (countries near Kyoto), Akinobu KITABATAKE, Akitsune CHIKUSA, Masanori KUSUNOKI and remnant army of Naoyoshi faction combined their forces to defeat Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA and took back Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kinai (countries near Kyoto), Akinobu KITABATAKE, Akitsune CHIKUSA, Masanori KUSUNOKI and the remnant army of Naoyoshi faction combined their forces to defeat Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA and took back Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), Akinobu KITABATAKE, Akitsune CHIKUSA, Masanori KUSUNOKI and the remnant army of Naoyoshi faction combined their forces to defeat Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA and took back Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>それに呼応して、新田義宗、義興と脇屋義治は上野国で挙兵、同時に信濃国では征夷大将軍宗良親王も挙兵し、一斉に鎌倉目指して進撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, Yoshimune NITTA, Yoshioki NITTA, and Yoshiharu WAKIYA raised their armies in Ueno Province and headed for Kamakura, so did Imperial Prince Muneyoshi, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) at the same time in Shinano Province; they advanced to Kamakura together..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, Yoshimune NITTA, Yoshioki NITTA, and Yoshiharu WAKIYA raised their armies in Ueno Province and headed for Kamakura, so did Imperial Prince Muneyoshi, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) at the same time in Shinano Province; they advanced to Kamakura together..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, Yoshimune NITTA, Yoshioki, and Yoshiharu WAKIYA raised their armies in Kozuke Province, and so did Imperial Prince Muneyoshi, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) at the same time in Shinano Province then they advanced to Kamakura together.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>宮方には北条時行の他、直義派残党の上杉憲顕も加わり、鎌倉を一時的に占拠するが、結局敗れ、宗良親王は信濃に、義宗、義興、義治らは越後へ逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO and Noriaki UESUGI--remnant army of Naoyoshi faction--joined the army standing for the imperial court and were once successful in occupying Kamakura, but finally were defeated; Imperial Prince Muneyoshi ran away to Shinano, while Yoshimune, Yoshioki, and Yoshiharu to Echigo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiyuki HOJO and Noriaki UESUGI--remnant army of Naoyoshi faction--joined the army standing for the imperial court and were once successful in occupying Kamakura, but finally were defeated; Imperial Prince Muneyoshi ran away to Shinano, while Yoshimune, Yoshioki, and Yoshiharu to Echigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO and Noriaki UESUGI of remnant army of Naoyoshi faction joined the army standing for the imperial court and were once successful in occupying Kamakura, but finally were defeated; Imperial Prince Muneyoshi ran away to Shinano, while Yoshimune, Yoshioki, and Yoshiharu to Echigo.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>北条時行は捕縛され、処刑された（武蔵野合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO was captured and executed. (the Battle of Musashino)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiyuki HOJO was captured and executed. (the Battle of Musashino)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO was captured and executed (the Battle of Musashino).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>正平23年（1368年）に足利義詮、足利基氏が相次いで没すると、新田義宗と脇屋義治は再度上野、越後国境周辺で挙兵するが、上野沼田荘で敗れ、義宗は戦死し、義治は出羽国に逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA and Motouji ASHIKAGA died one after the other, Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshiharu WAKIYA once again raised their armies in Ueno and around the border with Echigo but was defeated at Ueno-Numata no sho (manor); Yoshimune was dead in battle and Yoshiharau ran away to Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA and Motouji ASHIKAGA died one after the other, Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshiharu WAKIYA once again raised their armies in Ueno and around the border with Echigo, but was defeated at Ueno-Numata no sho (manor); Yoshimune was dead in battle and Yoshiharau ran away to Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA and Motouji ASHIKAGA died one after the other in 1368, Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshiharu WAKIYA once again raised their armies around the border of Kozuke and Echigo Provinces, but was defeated at Kozuke Numata no sho (manor); Yoshimune was dead in battle and Yoshiharu ran away to Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>その後の消息については不明であるが、明徳年間（1390～94）丹波国に逃れたとの伝承や、陸奥国の伊達持宗が応永21年（1413年）に挙兵した際、脇屋義治を押し立てて足利満貞・足利満直両御所を襲撃したとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What happened to him after this battle was not known; there is a folk story that he lived in secret in Tanba Province from 1390 to 1394, or he is said to have supported Yoshinori WAKIYA to attack gosho (the palace) of Mitsusada ASHIKAGA and Mitsutada ASHIKAGA in 1431.</e>
<cmt>「脇屋義治を押し立てて」は脇屋義則の間違えではないかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What happened to him after this battle was not known; there is a folk story that he lived in secret in Tanba Province from 1390 to 1394, or he is said to have supported Yoshinori WAKIYA to attack gosho (the palace) of Mitsusada ASHIKAGA and Mitsutada ASHIKAGA in 1431.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What happened to him after this battle was not known; there is a folk story that he lived in secret in Tanba Province during 1390 and 1394, or he is said to have supported Yoshiharu WAKIYA to attack gosho (the palace) of Mitsusada ASHIKAGA and Mitsunao ASHIKAGA in 1431.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、1370年代から義治の長子・脇屋義則が単独で活動をするため、出羽逃走直後に没したと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he may have died upon running away to Dewa, because his eldest son Yoshinori WAKIYA acted independently in and after the 1370&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he may have died upon running away to Dewa, because his eldest son Yoshinori WAKIYA acted independently in and after the 1370&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he may have died upon running away to Dewa, because Yoshiharu&apos;s eldest son Yoshinori WAKIYA acted independently in and after the 1370&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BuxWV(id:169145), Andee(id:20421), カイの迷宮(id:72682), UMBRO(id:100484), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>