<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条経嗣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一条 経嗣（いちじょう つねつぐ、正平_(日本)13年/延文3年（1358年） - 応永25年11月17日 (旧暦)（1418年12月14日））は、室町時代前期の公卿（関白）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO (1358-December 14, 1418) was the Kugyo (the top court official), who held the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), in early Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO (1358-December 14, 1418) was a Kugyo (top court official), who held the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), in the early Muromachi Era.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO (1358 - December 14, 1418) was a court noble, who held the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>era →period　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>関白二条良基の三男で、一条経通の猶子として一条家を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of Yoshimoto NIJO, who held the title of Kanpaku, and inherited the house of Ichijo by being adopted by Tsunemichi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of Yoshimoto NIJO, who held the title of Kanpaku, and inherited the house of Ichijo after being adopted by Tsunemichi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of Yoshimoto NIJO, who held the title of Kanpaku, and inherited the house of Ichijo after being adopted by Tsunemichi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に一条兼良・僧雲章一慶がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Kaneyoshi ICHIJO and Priest Ikkei UNSHO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Kaneyoshi ICHIJO and Priest Ikkei UNSHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Kaneyoshi ICHIJO and Priest Ikkei UNSHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>正平22年/貞治6年（1367年）に元服して正五位下に叙され、翌正平23年/応安元年（1368年）従三位となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went through the Genpuku ceremony (Coming of Age Ceremony) and was given the Jo rank (official court rank) of Shogoi no ge rank (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1367 and entered Jusanmi rank (Junior Third Rank) in 1368.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He underwent the Genpuku ceremony (Coming of Age Ceremony) and was given the Jo rank (official court rank) of Shogoi no ge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1367, followed by the Jusanmi rank (Junior Third Rank) in 1368.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He underwent the Genpuku ceremony (Coming of Age Ceremony) and was given the official court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1367, followed by another rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1368.</e>
<cmt>官位の表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>元中5年/嘉慶 (日本)2年（1388年）内大臣、元中8年/明徳2年（1391年）従一位となり、応永元年（1394年）に関白左大臣に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Naidaijin (Great Minister of the Centre) in 1388, Juichi rank (Junior First Rank) in 1391 and was assigned as Kanpaku and Sadaijin (Great Minister of the Left) in 1394.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Naidaijin (Great Minister of the Centre) in 1388, was promoted Juichi rank (Junior First Rank) in 1391, and was assigned as Kanpaku and Sadaijin (Great Minister of the Left) in 1394.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) in 1388, was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1391, and was assigned as Kanpaku and Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 1394.</e>
<cmt>内大臣→minister of the center左大臣→minister of the leftとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>応永5年（1398年）関白の職を辞したが、同6年（1399年）と17年（1410年）に関白に任じられ、関白職のまま准三宮の宣下を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left Kanpaku position in 1398 but was reassigned as Kanpaku in 1399 and 1410 and received Senge (imperial proclamation) of Ju sangu rank (rank at the same level as the birth mother of an imperial prince) while still holding the Kanpaku position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left Kanpaku position in 1398 but was reassigned as Kanpaku in 1399 and 1410, and received Senge (imperial proclamation) of Ju sangu rank (rank at the same level as the birth mother of an imperial prince) while still holding the Kanpaku position.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left Kanpaku position in 1398 but was reassigned as Kanpaku in 1399 and 1410, and received Senge (imperial proclamation) of Jusangu (one of the highest ranks of court noble, standing on equal ground with members of imperial family) while still holding the Kanpaku position.</e>
<cmt>Jusangu (one of the highest ranks of court noble, standing on equal ground with members of imperial family)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>令を中原章忠に、日本書紀を吉田兼煕に学んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Ryo (law) under Akitada NAKAHARA and Nihonshoki (Japanese history) under Kanehiro YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Ryo (law) under Akitada NAKAHARA and Nihonshoki (Japanese history) under Kanehiro YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Ryo (law) under Akitada NAKAHARA and Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) under Kanehiro YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>日本書紀の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>足利義満と同年でその信任を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was at the same age as Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and was trusted by him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the same age as Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and trusted by him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the same age as Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and trusted by him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>成恩寺殿と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Go (name) was Jonji-dono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Go (name) was Jonji-dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a second name (alias) of Jonji-dono.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>日記『荒暦』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His diary was called &quot;Koryaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His diary was called &quot;Koryaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His diary was called &quot;Koryaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また『相国寺塔供養記』『北山院御入内記』『北山殿行幸記』『応永大嘗会記』などの仮名日記がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had Kana nikki (a diary written under a pen name) such as &quot;Shokoku-ji to kuyoki,&quot; &quot;Kitayama-in gojudaiki,&quot; &quot;Kitayama-dono gyokoki,&quot; and &quot;Oei daijoeki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also wrote Kana nikki (diaries written under a pen name), including &quot;Shokoku-ji to kuyoki,&quot; &quot;Kitayama-in gojudaiki,&quot; &quot;Kitayama-dono gyokoki,&quot; and &quot;Oei daijoeki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also wrote diaries in Kana (the Japanese syllabary), including &quot;Shokoku-ji to kuyoki,&quot; &quot;Kitayama-in gojudaiki,&quot; &quot;Kitayama-dono gyokoki,&quot; and &quot;Oei daijoeki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>仮名日記の補足を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), TakuyaMurata(id:156), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Seibuabina(id:37532), 伏儀(id:142093), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>