<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>細川ガラシャ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Garasha HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Garasha (Gracia) HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Gracia)&quot; - Garasha being a katakana-ized version of Gracia, Ｉ added it here but left it as Garasha elsewhere, except in the titles of books, films, etc at the bottom (except cell 42).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Garasha (Gracia) HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>細川ガラシャ/明智 珠（明智 玉）（ほそかわガラシャ/あけち たま、俄羅奢、永禄6年（1563年） - 慶長5年7月17日 (旧暦)（1600年8月25日））は、明智光秀の三女で細川忠興の正室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Garasha HOSOKAWA/Tama AKECHI (1563-August 25, 1600) was the third daughter of Mitsuhide AKECHI and Tadaoki HOSOKAWA&apos;s legal wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Garasha HOSOKAWA/Tama AKECHI (1563-August 25, 1600) was the third daughter of Mitsuhide AKECHI and the wife of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;&apos;s legal wife&quot;→&quot;the wife of&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Garasha HOSOKAWA/Tama AKECHI (1563 - August 25, 1600) was the third daughter of Mitsuhide AKECHI and the wife of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンの前後にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は「たま」（珠、玉）または玉子（たまこ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imina (name given after death) was Tama or Tamako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her imina (name given after death) was Tama or Tamako.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Her&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her personal name was Tama or Tamako.</e>
<cmt>personal name としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>キリスト教信徒（キリシタン）として有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is known as a Christian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is known for being a Christian.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot;→&quot;for being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is known for being a Christian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に、於長（おちょう：1579年生前野景定室）、細川忠隆（1580年生）、細川興秋（1584年生）、細川忠利（1586年生）、多羅（たら：1588年生稲葉一通室）などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had children such as Ocho(born in 1579, Kagesada MAENO&apos;s wife), Tadataka HOSOKAWA (born in 1580), Okiaki HOSOKAWA (born in 1584) and Tara (born in 1588, Kazumichi INABA&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her children included Ocho(born in 1579, Kagesada MAENO&apos;s wife), Tadataka HOSOKAWA (born in 1580), Okiaki HOSOKAWA (born in 1584) and Tara (born in 1588, Kazumichi INABA&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt>&quot;She had children such as&quot;→&quot;Her children included&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her children included Ocho (born in 1579, Kagesada MAENO&apos;s wife), Tadataka HOSOKAWA (born in 1580), Okiaki HOSOKAWA (born in 1584), Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA (born in 1586), and Tara (born in 1588, Kazumichi INABA&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt>忠利を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>明治期にキリスト教徒らが彼女を讃えて「細川ガラシャ」と呼ぶようになったが、前近代の日本は夫婦別姓であり、北条政子・赤橋登子・日野富子などの例に照らせば「細川」姓で呼ぶのは明らかな間違いで、「明智 珠」と呼ぶのが正しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To honor her, Christians started to call her &quot;Garasha HOSOKAWA&quot;in Meiji Period, however, the dual-surname system was common in feudalistic Japan, thus, it is clearly wrong to call her &quot;Hosokawa&quot;in view of the examples of Masako HOJO, Toko AKAHASHI and Tomiko HINO and it is appropriate to call her &quot;Tama AKECHI&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To honor her, Christians started to call her &quot;Garasha HOSOKAWA&quot;in Meiji Period; however, in feudal Japan, it was common for husbands and wives to have different surnames, and in view of the examples of Masako HOJO, Toko AKAHASHI and Tomiko HINO, it is clearly wrong to use the name &quot;Hosokawa&quot;, her correct name being &quot;Tama AKECHI&quot;.</e>
<cmt>comma→semicolonReworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To honor her, Christians started to call her &apos;Garasha HOSOKAWA&apos; in Meiji period; however, in feudal Japan, it was common for husbands and wives to have different surnames, and in view of the examples of Masako HOJO, Toko AKAHASHI and Tomiko HINO, it is clearly wrong to use the name &apos;Hosokawa,&apos; her correct name being &apos;Tama AKECHI.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>細川忠興に嫁ぐ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She married into Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marriage to Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;She married into&quot;→&quot;Marriage to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marriage to Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>永禄6年（1563年）、明智光秀と妻明智煕子の間に三女（四女説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1563, she was born as the third daughter of Mitsuhide AKECHI and his wife, Hiroko AKECHI (she is also considered to have been the fourth daughter,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1563, she was born as the third daughter of Mitsuhide AKECHI and his wife, Hiroko AKECHI (she is also considered to have been the fourth daughter,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1563, she was born as the third daughter of Mitsuhide AKECHI and his wife, Hiroko AKECHI (she is also considered to have been the fourth daughter,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただしこの場合、長女と次女は養女であり、実質は次女となる）として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in this case, the first and second daughters were adopted ones and substantially she was the second daughter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in this case, the first and second daughters were adopted ones, so essentially she was the second daughter).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;However,&quot;&quot;and substantially&quot;→&quot;, so essentially&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in this case, the first and second daughters were adopted ones, so essentially she was the second daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>天正6年（1578年）、15歳の時に父の主君織田信長のすすめによって細川幽斎の嫡男・細川忠興に嫁いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1578, when she was fifteen, she married into Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Yusai HOSOKAWA, on the advice of her father&apos;s master, Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1578, when she was fifteen, she married Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Yusai HOSOKAWA, on the advice of her father&apos;s master, Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;into&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1578, when she was fifteen, she married Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Yusai HOSOKAWA, on the advice of her father&apos;s master, Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>珠は美女で忠興とは仲のよい夫婦であり、天正7年（1579年）には長女が、同8年（1580年）には長男（細川忠隆後の長岡休無）が二人の間に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tama was beautiful and on good terms with Tadaoki, the first daughter was born in 1579 and the first son (Tadataka HOSOKAWA, latter-day Kyumu NAGAOKA) was born in 1580.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tama was beautiful and on good terms with Tadaoki, their first daughter being born in 1579 and their first son (Tadataka HOSOKAWA, later Kyumu NAGAOKA) being born in 1580.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;their&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;being&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;their&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;being&quot;&quot;latter-day&quot;→&quot;later&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tama was beautiful and on good terms with Tadaoki, their first daughter being born in 1579 and their first son (Tadataka HOSOKAWA, later Kyumu NAGAOKA) being born in 1580.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>本能寺の変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honnoji-Temple Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honnoji-Temple Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt>左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし天正10年（1582年）6月、父の光秀が織田信長を本能寺で討って（本能寺の変）自らも滅んだため、珠は「逆臣の娘」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, her father, Mitsuhide killed Nobunaga ODA at the Honnoji-Temple (the Honnoji-Temple Incident) in June 1582, then he himself also died, thus Tama is called &quot;rebel&apos;s daughter&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, her father, Mitsuhide, killed Nobunaga ODA at Honnoji-Temple (the Honnoji-Temple Incident) in June 1582, then he himself also died, and Tama became known as the &quot;traitor&apos;s daughter&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Added commaDeleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;thus&quot;→&quot;and&quot;&quot;is called &quot;rebel&apos;s daughter&quot;&quot;→&quot;became known as the &quot;traitor&apos;s daughter&quot;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, her father, Mitsuhide, killed Nobunaga ODA at Honnoji-Temple (the Honnoji Incident) in June 1582, then he himself also died, and Tama became known as the &apos;traitor&apos;s daughter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Honnoji としました。&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>忠興は珠を愛していたがために離縁する気になれず、天正12年（1584年）まで彼女を丹後国の味土野（現在の京都府京丹後市弥栄町）に隔離・幽閉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Tadaoki loved Tama and was unwilling to divorce, he confined her in Midono, Tango Province (present-day Yasaka Town, Kyotango City, Kyoto prefecture) until 1584.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Tadaoki loved Tama and was unwilling to divorce, he confined her in Midono, Tango Province (present-day Yasaka Town, Kyotango City, Kyoto prefecture) until 1584.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Tadaoki loved Tama and was unwilling to divorce, he confined her in Midono, Tango Province (present-day Yasaka-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture) until 1584.</e>
<cmt>Prefectureと大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この間の彼女を支えたのは、光秀が玉の結婚する時に付けた小侍従や、細川家の親戚筋にあたる清原家の清原いと（公家清原枝賢の娘）らの侍女達だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that period, Kojijyu whom Mitsuhide made escort Tama when she got married and the waiting maids of Ito KIYOHARA (court noble, Shigekata KIYOHARA&apos;s daughter) of the Kiyohara family which was the Hosokawa family&apos;s relatives.</e>
<cmt>小侍従→Kojijyu[人名と判断しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that period, Tama was waited upon by Kojiyu, whom Mitsuhide had made escort Tama when she got married, and by the maids of Ito KIYOHARA (daughter of aristocrat Shigekata KIYOHARA) of the Kiyohara family, relatives of the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that period, Tama was waited upon by Kojiu (chamberlain), whom Mitsuhide had made escort Tama when she got married, and by the maids of Ito KIYOHARA (daughter of a noble Shigekata KIYOHARA) of the Kiyohara family, who were relatives of the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>一部補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>珠の幽閉先とされる場所であるが、丹後味土野の山中（現京丹後市弥栄町）に天正10年9月以降に幽閉されたことは史実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a historical fact that Tama was confined in the mountains of Midono, Tango Province after September, 1582.</e>
<cmt>（現京丹後市弥栄町）は、既出のため省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a historical fact that Tama was confined in the mountains of Midono, Tango Province after September, 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a historical fact that Tama was confined in the mountains of Midono (Yasaka-cho, Kyotango City, Kyoto Prefecture), Tango Province after September, 1582.</e>
<cmt>弥栄町～　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし一方、「丹波史」には丹波味土野に珠が隠棲していたとの伝承「丹波味土野説」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in &quot;Tanbashi (History of Tanba)&quot;, there is a tradition called &apos;Tanba Midono theory&apos; which explains that Tama was hiding in Midono, Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in &quot;Tanbashi (History of Tanba)&quot;, there is a tradition called &apos;Tanba Midono theory&apos; which explains that Tama was hiding in Midono, Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;explains&quot;→&quot;says&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in &apos;Tambashi&apos; (History of Tamba), there is a tradition called &apos;Tamba Midono theory&apos; which explains that Tama was hiding in Midono, Tamba Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この伝承が事実とすると、本能寺の変直後には、細川忠興は珠をまず明智領の丹波味土野屋敷に送り返し、明智が滅亡したのちに改めて細川領の丹後味土野に屋敷を作って珠を幽閉したとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this tradition is a fact, it is possible that Tadaoki HOSOKAWA sent Tama back to Tanba Midono residence in the Akechi&apos;s domain immediately after the Honnoji-Temple Incident, then he built a residence in Midono, Tango Province in the Hosokawa&apos;s domain and confined Tama there after Akechi went to ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this tradition is a fact, it is possible that Tadaoki HOSOKAWA sent Tama back to the Tanba Midono residence in the Akechi&apos;s domain immediately after the Honnoji-Temple Incident, then built a residence in Midono, Tango Province in the Hosokawa&apos;s domain and confined Tama there after the downfall of the Akechi.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Ddeleted &quot;he&quot;&quot;Akechi went to ruin&quot;→&quot;the downfall of the Akechi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this tradition is a fact, it is possible that Tadaoki HOSOKAWA sent Tama back to the Tanba Midono residence in the Akechi&apos;s domain immediately after the Honnoji-Temple Incident, then built a residence in Midono, Tango Province in the Hosokawa&apos;s domain and confined Tama there after the downfall of the Akechi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>キリスト教徒へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Becoming a Christian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Becoming a Christian</e>
<cmt>Deleted full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Becoming a Christian</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>天正12年（1584年）3月、信長の死後に覇権を握った豊臣秀吉の取り成しもあって、忠興は珠を細川家の大坂屋敷に戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1584, Tadaoki brought Tama back to Osaka residence of the Hosokawa family by mediation of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who gained the hegemony after Nobunaga&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1584, through the mediation of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who had gained hegemony after Nobunaga&apos;s death, Tadaoki brought Tama back to the Hosokawa&apos;s Osaka residence.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Osaka residence of the Hosokawa family&quot;→&quot;the Hosokawa&apos;s Osaka residence&quot;&quot;by&quot;→&quot;through the&quot;Added comma, &quot;had&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1584, through the mediation of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who had gained hegemony after Nobunaga&apos;s death, Tadaoki brought Tama back to the Hosokawa&apos;s Osaka residence.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この年に細川興秋が生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year, Okiaki HOSOKAWA was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this year, Okiaki HOSOKAWA was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this year, Okiaki HOSOKAWA was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これらの人生の変転の中で、珠はカトリック教会の話を聞き、その教えに心を魅かれていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the course of the changing life, Tama heard about Catholic Church and was gradually fascinated by the tenet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the course of her tumultuous life, Tama had heard about the Catholic Church and gradually became fascinated by its tenets.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the changing&quot;→&quot;her tumultuous&quot;Added &quot;had&quot;, &quot;the&quot;&quot;was gradually&quot;→&quot;gradually became&quot;&quot;the tenet&quot;→&quot;its tenets&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the course of her tumultuous life, Tama had heard about the Catholic Church and gradually became fascinated by its tenets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>天正14年（1586年）、細川忠利（幼名・光千代）が生まれたが、病弱のため、珠は日頃から心配していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586, Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA (his childhood name was Mitsuchiyo) was born and Tama always worried about his poor health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1586, Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA (his childhood name was Mitsuchiyo) was born and Tama always worried about his poor health.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1586, Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA (his childhood name was Mitsuchiyo) was born and Tama always worried about his poor health.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天正15年（1587年）2月11日 (旧暦)（3月19日）、夫の忠興が九州へ出陣し、彼女は意を決してカトリックの教えを聞きに行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 19, 1587, when her husband Tadaoki went off to Kyushu, she dared to go to listen to a Catholic sermon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 19, 1587, when her husband Tadaoki went off to Kyushu, she dared to go to listen to a Catholic sermon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 19, 1587, when her husband Tadaoki went off to Kyushu, she dared to go to listen to a Catholic sermon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>教会ではそのとき復活祭の説教を行っているところであり、珠は修道士にいろいろな質問をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When she arrived the church, a sermon of Easter was being given and Tama asked various questions to a monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When she arrived the church, an Easter sermon was being given and Tama asked various questions to a monk.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;at&quot;&quot;a sermon of Easter&quot;→&quot;an Easter sermon&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When she arrived the church, an Easter sermon was being given and Tama asked various questions to a monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのコスメ修道士は後に「これほど明晰かつ果敢な判断ができる日本の女性と話したことはなかった」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the monk, Cosme remarked &quot;I had never spoken with such a brilliant and courageous Japanese woman before&quot;.</e>
<cmt>コスメ→Cosme[正しいスペルが不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the monk, Cosme, remarked &quot;I had never spoken with such a brilliant and courageous Japanese woman before&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the monk, Cosme, remarked &apos;I had never spoken with such a brilliant and courageous Japanese woman before.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>教会から戻った珠は大坂に滞在していたイエズス会士グレゴリオ・デ・セスペデス神父の計らいで密かに洗礼を受け、ガラシャ（Gratia、ラテン語で恩寵・神の恵みの意）という洗礼名を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After coming back from the church, Tama secretly received baptism by an arrangement of Father Gregorio de Sespedes who was a Jesuit and stayed in Osaka and her Christian name was Garasha (Gratia, meaning grace and blessing in Latin).</e>
<cmt>イエズス会士→Jesuit グレゴリオ・デ・セスペデス→Gregorio de Sespedes</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After coming back from the church, Father Gregario de Sespedes, a Jesuit staying in Osaka, arranged a secret baptism for Tama and she received the Christian name &apos;Garasha&apos;, a Japanized form of Gracia (from Gratia, meaning grace and blessing in Latin).</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After coming back from the church, Father Gregorio de Sespedes, a Jesuit staying in Osaka, arranged a secret baptism for Tama and she received the Christian name &apos;Garasha&apos;, a Japanized form of Gracia (from Gratia, meaning grace and blessing in Latin).</e>
<cmt>Gregorioとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、後に秀吉はバテレン追放令を出し、大名が許可無くキリスト教を信仰することを禁じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi prohibited feudal lords from having faith in Christianity without permission by the deportation edict of Christian missionaries.</e>
<cmt>バテレン追放令→the deportation edict of Christian missionaries[定訳不明のため、仮訳をつけました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hideyoshi ordered the deportation of Christian missionaries and prohibited feudal lords from having faith in Christianity without permission.</e>
<cmt>&quot; by the deportation edict of Christian missionaries&quot;→&quot;ordered the deportation of Christian missionaries and&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi ordered the deportation of Christian missionaries and prohibited feudal lords from having faith in Christianity without permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>忠興は家中の侍女らがキリスト教に改宗したことを知って激怒し、改宗した侍女の鼻を削ぎ、追い出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki was furious at the fact that all waiting maids were converted to Catholicism and chipped off their nose and removed them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki, furious at the fact that all the maids in the house had converted to Catholicism, cut off their noses and threw them out.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was&quot;→comma&quot;waiting&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Addeed &quot;in the house&quot;&quot;were&quot;→&quot;had&quot;&quot;and&quot;→comma&quot;chipped&quot;→&quot;cut&quot;Made &quot;nose&quot; plural&quot;removed them&quot;→&quot;threw them out&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki, furious at the fact that all the maids in the house had converted to Catholicism, cut off their noses and threw them out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>幸いにもガラシャは発覚を免れたが、拠り所を失ったガラシャは「夫と別れたい」と宣教師に打ち明けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fortunately, Garasha could avoid a disclosure, but she lost mooring and confessed to a missionary, &quot;I want to leave my husband&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fortunately, Garasha was able to keep her secret, but she felt abandonned and confessed to a missionary, &quot;I want to leave my husband&quot;.</e>
<cmt>&quot;could avoid a disclosure&quot;→&quot;was able to keep her secret&quot;&quot;lost mooring&quot;→&quot;felt abandonned&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fortunately, Garasha was able to keep her secret, but she felt abandoned and confessed to a missionary, &apos;I want to leave my husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>宣教師は「誘惑に負けてはならない」「困難に立ち向かってこそ、徳は磨かれる」と説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The missionary taught her, &quot;Don&apos;t yield to temptation, your virtue would heighten only when you tackle the difficulty.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The missionary taught her, &quot;Don&apos;t yield to temptation, your virtue will increase only when you tackle the difficulty.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;would heighten&quot;→&quot;will increase&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The missionary taught her, &apos;Don&apos;t yield to temptation, your virtue will increase only when you tackle the difficulty.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>それまで、彼女は気位が高く怒りやすかったが、キリストの教えを知ってからは謙虚で忍耐強く穏やかになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had been proud and gotten angry easily until then, but after she learned the teaching of Christ, she became modest, patient and gentle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had been proud and quick-tempered until then, but after she learned the teaching of Christ, she became modest, patient and gentle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;gotten angry easily&quot;→&quot;quick-tempered&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had been proud and quick-tempered until then, but after she learned the teaching of Christ, she became modest, patient and gentle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>壮絶な最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heroic death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heroic death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heroic death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いが勃発する直前の慶長5年（1600年）7月16日 (旧暦)（8月24日）、大坂玉造の細川屋敷にいた彼女を、西軍の石田三成は人質に取ろうとしたが、ガラシャはそれを拒絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 24, 1600, just before the Sekigahara War, Mitsunari ISHIDA of the West army tried to hold Garasha, who was in the Hosokawa residence in Tamatsukuri, Osaka, as a hostage, but she rejected that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 24, 1600, just before the Sekigahara War, Mitsunari ISHIDA of the West army tried to hold Garasha, who was in the Hosokawa residence in Tamatsukuri, Osaka, as a hostage, but she refused.</e>
<cmt>&quot;rejected that&quot;→&quot;refused&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 24, 1600, just before the Sekigahara War, Mitsunari ISHIDA of the West army tried to hold Garasha, who was in the Hosokawa residence in Tamatsukuri, Osaka, as a hostage, but she refused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その翌日、三成が実力行使に出て兵に屋敷を囲ませると、ガラシャは家老の小笠原秀清（少斎）に槍で部屋の外から胸を貫かせて死んだ（キリスト教では自殺は大罪であるため）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next day, when Mitsunari resorted to force by making soldiers surround the residence, Garasha got the chief retainer, Hidekiyo (Shosai) OGASAWARA to pierce her chest with lance from outside the room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next day, when Mitsunari resorted to force by having soldiers surround the residence, Garasha got the chief retainer, Hidekiyo (Shosai) OGASAWARA, to pierce her chest with lance from outside the room.</e>
<cmt>&quot;making&quot;→&quot;having&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next day, when Mitsunari resorted to force by having soldiers surround the residence, Garasha got the chief retainer, Hidekiyo (Shosai) OGASAWARA, to pierce her chest with lance from outside the room (this is because in Christianity, committing suicide is a mortal sin).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>享年38。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her age at death was 38.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was 38 years old.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Her age at death&quot;→&quot;She&quot;Added &quot;years old&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was 38 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>辞世の句として、「ちりぬべき　時知りてこそ　世の中の　花も花なれ　人も人なれ」と詠んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She composed a death haiku (Japanese poem) like &quot;Flower is most beautiful when it knows the timing to fall, people are like flower. I will die without hesitation&quot;.</e>
<cmt>辞世の句→death haiku (Japanese poem)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She composed the following death haiku (Japanese poem): &quot;A flower is most beautiful when it knows the time to fall. People are like flowers, I will die without hesitation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the following&quot;Deleted &quot;like&quot;Added colonAdded &quot;A&quot;Made &apos;F&apos; lower case&quot;timing&quot;→&quot;time&quot;comma→full stopCapitalised &apos;p&apos;Made &quot;flower&quot; pluralfull stop→commaMoved full stop insde quote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She composed the following death haiku (Japanese poem): &apos;A flower is most beautiful when it knows the time to fall. People are like flowers, I will die without hesitation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>この後、小笠原はガラシャの遺体が残らぬように屋敷に爆薬を仕掛け火を点けて自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Ogasawara set off an explosive in the residence to erase Garasha&apos;s dead body and killed himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Ogasawara set off an explosive in the residence to erase Garasha&apos;s dead body and killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Ogasawara set off an explosive in the residence to erase Garasha&apos;s dead body and killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>ガラシャの死の数時間後、グネッキ・ソルディ・オルガンティノは細川屋敷の焼け跡を訪れてガラシャの骨を拾い、堺のキリシタン墓地に葬った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several hours from Garasha&apos;s death, Gnecchi Soldi Organtino visited the ruins of Hosokawa residence and picked up Garasha&apos;s bones and buried them in the Christian cemetery in Sakai.</e>
<cmt>グネッキ・ソルディ・オルガンティノ→Gnecchi Soldi Organtino[正しいスペルが不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several hours after Garasha&apos;s death, Gnecchi Soldi Organtino visited the ruins of Hosokawa residence, picked up Garasha&apos;s bones and buried them in the Christian cemetery in Sakai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;from&quot;→&quot;after&quot;&quot;and&quot;→comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several hours after Garasha&apos;s death, Gnecchi Soldi Organtino visited the ruins of Hosokawa residence, picked up Garasha&apos;s bones and buried them in the Christian cemetery in Sakai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>細川忠興はガラシャの死を悲しみ、慶長6年（1601年）にオルガンティノにガラシャ教会葬を依頼して葬儀にも参列し、後に遺骨を大坂の崇禅寺 (大阪市)へ改葬した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA mourned over Garasha&apos;s death and asked Organtino to perform a funeral service for Garasha at the church and attended it, later, he reburied her cremains in the Sozen-ji Temple in Osaka (present-day Osaka City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA mourned over Garasha&apos;s death and asked Organtino to perform a funeral service for Garasha at the church, which he attended; later, he reburied her remains at Sozen-ji Temple in Osaka (present-day Osaka City).</e>
<cmt>&quot;and attended it,&quot;→&quot;, which he attended;&quot;Deleted &apos;c&apos;&quot;in the&quot;→&quot;at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA mourned over Garasha&apos;s death and in 1601, asked Organtino to perform a funeral service for Garasha at the church, which he attended; later, he reburied her remains at Sozen-ji Temple (Osaka City).</e>
<cmt>(Osaka City)としました。1601年を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>他にも、京都大徳寺塔中高桐院や、肥後熊本の泰勝寺等、何箇所かガラシャの墓所とされるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there are several sites considered to be Garasha&apos;s grave such as Daitoku-ji Temple,-tacchu-kotoin in Kyoto and Taisho-ji Temple in Kumamoto, Higo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several other sites considered to be Garasha&apos;s grave, including Daitoku-ji Temple Tacchu-kotoin in Kyoto and Taisho-ji Temple in Kumamoto, Higo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Also,&quot;→&quot;other&quot; and moved&quot;such as&quot;→&quot;, including&quot;Deleted &quot;,-&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several other sites considered to be Garasha&apos;s grave, including Daitoku-ji Temple Tacchu-kotoin in Kyoto and Taisho-ji Temple in Kumamoto, Higo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>なお細川屋敷を三成の兵に囲まれた際に、ガラシャは世子細川忠隆の正室で前田利家娘の千世に逃げるように勧め、千世は姉・豪姫の住む隣の宇喜多屋敷に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Hosokawa residence was surrounded by Mitsunari&apos;s soldiers, Garasha recommended Chiyo, who was a legal wife of the hair Tadataka HOSOKAWA and daughter of Toshiie MAEDA, to run away and Chiyo evacuated to the next Ukita residence where her older sister, Gohime lived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Hosokawa residence was surrounded by Mitsunari&apos;s soldiers, Garasha advised Chiyo, who was the legal wife of the heir, Tadataka HOSOKAWA, and a daughter of Toshiie MAEDA, to run away and Chiyo evacuated to the neighboring Ukita residence where her older sister, Gohime, lived.</e>
<cmt>&quot;recommended&quot;→&quot;advised&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;hair&quot;→&quot;heir&quot;Added commasAdded &quot;a&quot;&quot;next&quot;→&quot;neighboring&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Hosokawa residence was surrounded by Mitsunari&apos;s soldiers, Garasha advised Chiyo, who was the legal wife of the heir, Tadataka HOSOKAWA, and a daughter of Toshiie MAEDA, to run away and Chiyo evacuated to the neighboring Ukita residence where her older sister, Gohime, lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、これに激怒した忠興は忠隆に千世との離婚を命じ、反発した忠隆を勘当廃嫡してしまった（忠隆子孫はのちに細川一門家臣・長岡内膳家〔別名：細川内膳家〕となり、明治期に細川姓へ復している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki boiled at this and ordered Tadataka to divorce Chiyo, but Tadataka repelled the order, thus Tadaoki renounced and disinherited him (later, Tadataka&apos;s descendants became the Nagaoka-naizen family (or the Hosokawa-naizen family) which was retainer of the Hosokawa family) and regained their family name, Hosokawa in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki was furious at this and ordered Tadataka to divorce Chiyo, but Tadataka refused, leading Tadaoki to renounce and disinherit him (later, Tadataka&apos;s descendants became the Nagaoka-naizen family (also known as the Hosokawa-naizen family), retainers of the Hosokawa family, regaining their family name, Hosokawa, in the Meiji Period).</e>
<cmt>&quot;boiled&quot;→&quot;was furious&quot;&quot;repelled the order&quot;→&quot;refused&quot;&quot;thus&quot;→&quot;leading&quot;&quot;renounced and disinherited&quot;→&quot;to renounce and disinherit&quot;&quot;or&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;Deleted &quot;which was&quot;Made &quot;retainer&quot; pluralMoved closing bracket&quot;and&quot;→comma&quot;regained&quot;→&quot;regaining&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki was furious at this and ordered Tadataka to divorce Chiyo, but Tadataka refused, leading Tadaoki to renounce and disinherit him (later, Tadataka&apos;s descendants became the Nagaoka-naizen family (also known as the Hosokawa-naizen family), retainers of the Hosokawa family, regaining their family name, Hosokawa, in the Meiji period).</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>戯曲「気丈な貴婦人」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A play called &quot;Kijo na kifujin (A brave lady)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A play called &quot;Kijo na kifujin (A brave lady)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A play called &apos;Kijo na kifujin&apos; (A brave lady)</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>ガラシャをモデルにした戯曲「気丈な貴婦人」（グラーシャ）の初演は神聖ローマ帝国のエレオノーレ・マグダレーナ皇后の聖名祝日（7月26日）の祝いとして、1698年7月31日にイエスズ会の劇場でオペラとして発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A play called &quot;Kijo na kifujin (A brave lady)&quot;(Gratia) modeled on Garasha was premiered as an opera on July 31, 1698 in the Jesuit theater to cerebrate the name day of the Holy Roman Empress Eleonor Magdalene (July 26).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A play called &quot;Kijo na kifujin (A brave lady)&quot;(Gratia), modeled on Garasha, was premiered as an opera on July 31, 1698 in the Jesuit theater to celebrate the name day of the Holy Roman Empress Eleonor Magdalene (July 26).</e>
<cmt>Added commasSpelling of &quot;celebrate&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A play called &apos;Kijo na kifujin&apos; (A brave lady) (Gratia), modeled on Garasha, was premiered as an opera on July 31, 1698 in the Jesuit theater to celebrate the name day of the Holy Roman Empress Eleonor Magdalene (July 26).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>ガラシャの死はヨーロッパでは殉教死と考えられた（「武士道」と言う観念、武家社会の礼法が理解されない為）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Garasha&apos;s death was considered as a martyrdom in Europe (it is because the concept of &apos;Bushido (the way of the samurai)&apos; and the manners of samurai society were not understood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Garasha&apos;s death was considered martyrdom in Europe (this was because the concept of &apos;Bushido (the way of the samurai)&apos; and the manners of samurai society were not understood).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;as a&quot;&quot;it is&quot;→&quot;this was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Garasha&apos;s death was considered martyrdom in Europe (this was because the concept of &apos;Bushido&apos; (the way of the samurai) and the manners of samurai society were not understood).</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>その戯曲の中でのガラシャは、夫である野蛮な君主の非道に耐えながらも信仰を貫き、最後は命を落として暴君を改心さるという解釈になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The play describes Garasha as a woman who keep the faith enduring the enormity of her barbarian and dominant husband, and her death reformed the dictator at last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The play depicts Garasha as a woman who kept her faith while enduring the unjustness of her barbarian and dominant husband, with her death reforming the tyrant at last.</e>
<cmt>&quot;describes&quot;→&quot;depicts&quot;&quot;keep the&quot;→&quot;kept her&quot;Added &quot;while&quot;&quot;enormity&quot;→&quot;unjustness&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;with&quot;&quot;reformed&quot;→&quot;reforming&quot;&quot;dictator&quot;→&quot;tyrant&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The play depicts Garasha as a woman who kept her faith while enduring the unjustness of her barbarian and dominant husband, with her death reforming the tyrant at last.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>この戯曲はオーストリア・ハプスブルク家の姫君達に特に好まれたとされ、彼女達は政治的な理由で他国に嫁がされるガラシャを自分達の身の上に重ね、それでも自らの信仰を貫いた気高さに感銘を受けたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this play was particularly favored by the princesses of the Habsburg family of Austria, they empathized Garasha&apos;s life in which she was forced to marry into other country for political reasons and impressed by the nobility of having kept her faith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this play was particularly favored by the princesses of the Habsburg family of Austria, who empathized with Garasha&apos;s life in which she was forced to marry into other country for political reasons, and were impressed by the nobility of her having kept her faith.</e>
<cmt>&quot;they&quot;→&quot;who&quot;Added &quot;with&quot;Added comma, &quot;were&quot;, &quot;her&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this play was particularly favored by the princesses of the Habsburg family of Austria, who empathized with Garasha&apos;s life in which she was forced to marry into other country for political reasons, and were impressed by the nobility of her having kept her faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>エレオノーレ・マグダレーナ、マリア・テレジア、マリー・アントワネット、エリーザベト (オーストリア皇后)などの生き方にも尊敬と感銘を受け深く影響を与えたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that they admired the life of Eleonor Magdalene, Maria Theresia, Marie Antoinette and Elisabeth (Empress of Austria), also they were impressed and affected by those lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the play also left a deep impression of respect and admiration on the lives of Eleonor Magdalene, Maria Theresia, Marie Antoinette and Elisabeth (Empress of Austria).</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the play also left a deep impression of respect and admiration on the lives of Eleonor Magdalene, Maria Theresia, Marie Antoinette and Elisabeth (Empress of Austria).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>ガラシャの登場する作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works featuring Garasha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works featuring Garasha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works featuring Garasha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>小説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>司馬遼太郎「胡桃に酒」（短編集「故郷忘じがたく候」に収録）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kurumi ni Sake (Walnut and Sake)&quot; (contained in the anthology &apos;Kokyo wasuregataki soro (I miss my hometown)&apos;) written by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kurumi ni Sake (Walnut and Sake)&quot; (contained in the anthology &apos;Kokyo wasurejigataku soro (I miss my hometown)&apos;) written by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;wasurejigataku&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurumi ni Sake&apos; (Walnut and Sake) (contained in the anthology &apos;Kokyo wasurejigataku soro&apos; (I miss my hometown)) written by Ryotaro SHIBA</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>三浦綾子「細川ガラシャ夫人」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mrs. Garasha Hosokawa&quot; written by Ayako MIURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Lady Gracia&quot; written by Ayako MIURA</e>
<cmt>&quot;Mrs. Garasha Hosokawa&quot;→&quot;Lady Gracia&quot;- this is the name of the English translation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lady Gracia&apos; written by Ayako MIURA</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>テレビドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TV dramas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TV dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TV dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="48">
<j>大河ドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NHK Taiga drama series</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NHK Taiga drama series</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NHK Taiga drama series</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="49">
<j>国盗り物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)（1973年、司馬遼太郎原作『国盗り物語』、演：今別府ミカ→林寛子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kunitori monogatari (Tale of acquiring countries)&quot; (1973, original novel &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; was written by Ryotaro SHIBA, performed by Mika IMABEPPU, then Hiroko HAYASHI)</e>
<cmt>すでにセル83の項目名で「NHK大河ドラマ」とあるのでこちらでは省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kunitori monogatari (Tale of acquiring countries)&quot; (1973, based on the novel &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA, portrayed by Mika IMABEPPU, then Hiroko HAYASHI)</e>
<cmt>&quot;original novel &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; was written&quot;→&quot;based on the novel &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot;&quot;&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; (Tale of acquiring countries) (1973, based on the novel &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA, portrayed by Mika IMABEPPU, then Hiroko HAYASHI)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="50">
<j>黄金の日々（1978年、演：島田陽子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Golden days&quot; (1978, performed by Yoko SHIMADA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ogon no Hibi (Golden days)&quot; (1978, portrayed by Yoko SHIMADA)</e>
<cmt>- not sure if this is an official English title so added Japanese as wellperformed→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ogon no Hibi&quot; (Golden days) (1978, portrayed by Yoko SHIMADA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="51">
<j>おんな太閤記（1981年、演：岡まゆみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Onna-taikoki (female Imperial adviser)&quot; (1981, performed by Mayumi OKA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Onna-taikoki (Female Imperial Adviser)&quot; (1981, portrayed by Mayumi OKA)</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &apos;f&apos;, &apos;a&apos;performed→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Onna-taikoki&quot; (Female Imperial Adviser) (1981, portrayed by Mayumi OKA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="52">
<j>徳川家康 (NHK大河ドラマ)（1983年、演：丸尾りえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&quot;</e>
<cmt>すでにセル83の項目名で「NHK大河ドラマ」とあるのでこちらでは省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&quot; (1983, portrayed by Mayumi OKA)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot; (1983, portrayed by Mayumi OKA)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&quot; (1983, portrayed by Rie MARUO)</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="53">
<j>信長 KING OF ZIPANGU（1992年、演：今村恵子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nobunaga KING OF ZIPANGU&quot; (1992, performed by Keiko IMAMURA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nobunaga KING OF ZIPANGU&quot; (1992, portrayed by Keiko IMAMURA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nobunaga KING OF ZIPANGU&quot; (1992, portrayed by Keiko IMAMURA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="54">
<j>秀吉 (NHK大河ドラマ)（1996年、演：清水桂那→田村英里子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hideyoshi&quot; (1996, performed by Keina SHIMIZU, then Eriko TAMURA)</e>
<cmt>すでにセル83の項目名で「NHK大河ドラマ」とあるのでこちらでは省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hideyoshi&quot; (1996, portrayed by Keina SHIMIZU, then Eriko TAMURA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hideyoshi&quot; (1996, portrayed by Keina SHIMIZU, then Eriko TAMURA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="55">
<j>葵徳川三代（2000年、演：鈴木京香）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Three generations of Tokugawa&quot; (2000, performed by Kyoka SUZUKI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Aoi Tokugawa Sandai (Three generations of Tokugawa)&quot; (2000, portrayed by Kyoka SUZUKI)</e>
<cmt>- not sure if this is an official English title so added Japanese as wellperformed→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Aoi Tokugawa Sandai&quot; (Three generations of Tokugawa) (2000, portrayed by Kyoka SUZUKI)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="56">
<j>利家とまつ〜加賀百万石物語〜（2002年、演：中西夏奈子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Toshiie and Matsu&quot; (2002, performed by Kanako NAKANISHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Toshie to Matsu (Toshiie and Matsu)&quot; (2002, portrayed by Kanako NAKANISHI)</e>
<cmt>&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Toshiie to Matsu&quot; (Toshiie and Matsu) (2002, portrayed by Kanako NAKANISHI)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="57">
<j>功名が辻 (NHK大河ドラマ)（2006年、演：長谷川京子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Konyogatsuji (Crossroads of a great achievement)&quot; (2006, performed by Kyoko HASEGAWA)</e>
<cmt>すでにセル83の項目名で「NHK大河ドラマ」とあるのでこちらでは省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Konyo ga Tsuji (Crossroads of a great achievement)&quot; (2006, portrayed by Kyoko HASEGAWA)</e>
<cmt>Added spaces&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Konyo ga Tsuji&quot; (Crossroads of a great achievement) (2006, portrayed by Kyoko HASEGAWA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="58">
<j>その他ドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other dramas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="59">
<j>大坂城の女（1970年、フジテレビ、演：八千草薫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Woman in Osaka-jo Castle&quot; (1970, Fuji Television, performed by Kaoru YACHIGUSA)</e>
<cmt>フジテレビ→Fuji Television[フジテレビHPより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Osaka-jo no Onna (Woman in Osaka-jo Castle)&quot; (1970, Fuji Television, portrayed by Kaoru YACHIGUSA)</e>
<cmt>- not sure if this is an official English title so added Japanese as wellperformed→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Osaka-jo no Onna&quot; (Woman in Osaka-jo Castle&quot; (1970, Fuji Television, portrayed by Kaoru YACHIGUSA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="60">
<j>関ヶ原 (テレビドラマ)（1981年、司馬遼太郎原作『関ヶ原』、演：栗原小巻）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sekigahara&quot; (1981, original novel &quot;Sekigahara&quot; was written by Ryotaro SHIBA, performed by Komaki KURIHARA)</e>
<cmt>（テレビドラマ）は不要と考え、省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sekigahara&quot; (1981, based on the novel &quot;Sekigahara&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA, portrayed by Komaki KURIHARA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;original novel &quot;Sekigahara&quot; was written&quot;→&quot;based on the novel &quot;Sekigahara&quot;&quot;&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sekigahara&quot; (1981, based on the novel &quot;Sekigahara&quot; by Ryotaro SHIBA, portrayed by Komaki KURIHARA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="61">
<j>新春ワイド時代劇織田信長 (テレビドラマ 1994年)（1994年、テレビ東京、演：戸田菜穂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Year&apos;s special period drama &quot;Nobunaga ODA&quot; (1994, TV TOKYO, performed by Naho TODA)</e>
<cmt>新春ワイド時代劇→New Year&apos;s special period drama[定訳不明のため仮訳をつけました]テレビ東京→TV TOKYO[テレビ東京HPより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New Year&apos;s special period drama &quot;Nobunaga ODA&quot; (1994, TV TOKYO, portrayed by Naho TODA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New Year&apos;s special period drama &quot;Nobunaga ODA&quot; (1994, TV TOKYO, portrayed by Naho TODA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="62">
<j>新春ワイド時代劇国盗り物語（2005年、テレビ東京、演：田中美悠→石川梨華）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Year&apos;s special period drama &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; (2005, TV TOKYO, performed by Miyu TANAKA, then Rika ISHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New Year&apos;s special period drama &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; (2005, TV TOKYO, portrayed by Miyu TANAKA, then Rika ISHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt>&quot;performed&quot;→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New Year&apos;s special period drama &quot;Kunitori monogatari&quot; (2005, TV TOKYO, portrayed by Miyu TANAKA, then Rika ISHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="63">
<j>明智光秀～神に愛されなかった男～（2007年、フジテレビ、演：佐々木麻緒）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mitsuhide AKECHI, unloved by God&quot; (2007, Fuji TV, performed by Mao SASAKI)</e>
<cmt>明智光秀～神に愛されなかった男～→&quot;Mitsuhide AKECHI, unloved by God&quot;[定訳不明のため仮訳をつけました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mitsuhide Akechi, Kami ni Ai sarenakatta Otoko (Mitsuhide AKECHI, unloved by God)&quot; (2007, Fuji TV, portrayed by Mao SASAKI)</e>
<cmt>- not sure if this is an official English title so added Japanese as wellperformed→&quot;portrayed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mitsuhide Akechi, Kami ni Ai sarenakatta Otoko&quot; (Mitsuhide AKECHI, unloved by God) (2007, Fuji TV, portrayed by Mao SASAKI)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="64">
<j>映画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="65">
<j>敵は本能寺にあり（1960年、松竹、演：岸恵子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;An enemy is in the Honno-ji Temple&quot; (1960, Shochiku, performed by Keiko KISHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Teki ha Honno-ji ni ari (The enemy is in Honno-ji Temple)&quot; (1960, Shochiku, performed by Keiko KISHI)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Teki ha Honno-ji ni ari&quot;&quot; and brackets - not sure of the English title so added Japanese&quot;An&quot;→&quot;The&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Teki ha Honno-ji ni ari&quot; (The enemy is in Honno-ji Temple) (1960, Shochiku, performed by Keiko KISHI)</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="66">
<j>オペラ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Operas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opera</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opera</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="67">
<j>ヴィンチェンツォ・チマッティ「細川ガラシャ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Garasha HOSOKAWA&quot; written by Vincenzo Cimatti</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;HOSOKAWA Grazia&quot; written by Vincenzo Cimatti</e>
<cmt>&quot;Garasha&quot;→&quot;Grazia&quot; and moved - I think this is the English name of the opera</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;HOSOKAWA Grazia&quot; written by Vincenzo Cimatti</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="68">
<j>マンドリンオーケストラ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mandolin Orchestra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mandolin Orchestra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mandolin orchestra</e>
<cmt>orchestraを小文字から始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="69">
<j>鈴木静一「劇的序楽「細川ガラシャ」」（1968年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gekiteki joraku &apos;Garasha HOSOKAWA&apos;&quot; written by Seiichi SUZUKI (1968)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gekiteki joraku &apos;Garasha HOSOKAWA&apos;&quot; written by Seiichi SUZUKI (1968)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gekiteki joraku &apos;Garasha HOSOKAWA&apos;&quot; written by Seiichi SUZUKI (1968)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="70">
<j>ゲーム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Games</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Games</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Games</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="71">
<j>Playstation2 戦国無双</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sengoku muso&quot; (matchless man in the period of warring states) for Playstation2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Samurai Warriors&quot; for Playstation2</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;Sengoku muso&quot; (matchless man in the period of warring states)&quot;→&quot;&quot;Samurai Warriors&quot;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Samurai Warriors&quot; for Playstation2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>Playstation2 無双OROCHI</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Muso OROCHI&quot; for Playstation2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Warriors Orochi&quot; for Playstation2</e>
<cmt>&quot;Muso OROCHI&quot;→&quot;Warriors Orochi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Warriors Orochi&quot; for Playstation2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="73">
<j>映画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="74">
<j>魔界転生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Transmigration of the demon world&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Makai tensho: Samurai Reincarnation&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Transmigration of the demon world&quot;→&quot;Makai tensho: Samurai Reincarnation&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Makai tensho: Samurai Reincarnation&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), T@ka(id:12814), Nnh(id:474), かがみ(id:137074), Suutaroka(id:174573), MIsogi(id:20599), Eskimbot(id:29676), ANTOHER(id:87167), Akechicyaya(id:70862), Kunipoo(id:35872), Harupri(id:133581), Akoyano(id:56905), Kamakura(id:472), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Sgi1962(id:80778), Ohura(id:5986), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), Johncapistrano(id:969), Takeler(id:51437), A6M4(id:14155), Gakuinryou(id:9665), A-Taul(id:41790), Kanoe(id:17203), 寂華(id:83725), こぶまき(id:38278), Avxz(id:123412), Bankokuya(id:91191), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Azirosas(id:143367), Law soma(id:45202), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Hosokawajun(id:72875), マスダ(id:92699), KOGARASI(id:201883), Kagetudo(id:163875), Kamitani(id:30757), Hatsune(id:26654), 樒(id:35770), ちぇるぱぱ(id:146237), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 663highland(id:18755), 今紫(id:9521), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>