<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>治部卿局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>治部卿局（じぶきょうのつぼね、仁平2年（1152年）- 寛喜3年9月11日 (旧暦)（1231年10月8日））は、平安時代末期、鎌倉時代前期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo (1152-October 8, 1231) was a woman from the end of the Heian period through until the first half of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo (1152 - October 8, 1231) was a woman from the late Heian and early Kamakura periods.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo (1152 - October 15, 1231) was a woman from the late Heian and early Kamakura periods.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平知盛の妻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the wife of TAIRA no Tomonori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the wife of TAIRA no Tomonori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the wife of TAIRA no Tomomori.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後高倉院（守貞親王）の乳母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a wet nurse of Gotakakura-in (Imperial Prince Morisada).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a wet nurse of Gotakakura-in (Imperial Prince Morisada).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a wet nurse of Gotakakura-in (Imperial Prince Morisada).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に平知章、平知忠、中納言局（高倉範茂室）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomoakira, TAIRA no Tomotada, and Chunagon no tsubone (wife of Norishige TAKAKURA) were her children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tomoakira, TAIRA no Tomotada, and Chunagon no tsubone (the wife of Norishige TAKAKURA) were her children.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomoakira, TAIRA no Tomotada, and Chunagon no tsubone (the wife of Norishige TAKAKURA) were her children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>はじめ従二位平時子に仕えて南御方（みなみのおんかた）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She originally served Junii (Junior Second Rank), TAIRA no Tokiko, and was called Minami no onkata.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She originally served Junii (Junior Second Rank) TAIRA no Tokiko, and was called Minami no onkata.</e>
<cmt>remove comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She originally served Junii (Junior Second Rank) TAIRA no Tokiko, and was called Minami no onkata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>治承3年（1179年）、守貞親王の乳母となって候名（さぶらいな）を「治部卿」とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1179, she became a wet nurse of Imperial Prince Morisada, and made Saburai na (given name in the court) as`jibukyo&apos; (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1179, she became a wet nurse for Imperial Prince Morisada, and choose &quot;Jibukyo&quot; as her saburai na (given name in the court).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1179, she became a wet nurse for Imperial Prince Morisada, and choose &quot;Jibukyo&quot; as her saburai na (given name in the court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後年は四条局（しじょうのつぼね）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in her life, she was called Shijo no tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the latter part of her life, she was called Shijo no tsubone.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the latter part of her life, she was called Shijo no tsubone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>出自ははっきりしていないが、「御方」と敬称で呼ばれるのは大臣の娘である事から、治部卿局が時子の女房となった時期に内大臣の地位にあり、平清盛と縁の深い内大臣藤原忠雅が父親と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her origin was not clear, but her father was deemed to be FUJIWARA no Tadamasa who was the Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior) when Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo was a nyobo of Tokiko and who had deep ties with TAIRA no Kiyomori given that she was called the `onkata,&apos; which meant she was a daughter of daijin (minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her origin was not clear, but given the fact that she was called &quot;onkata,&quot; which meant she was a daughter of a daijin (minister), her father was believed to be FUJIWARA no Tadamasa, who was the Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior) when Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo was a nyobo of Tokiko, and who had close relations with TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her origin was not clear, but given the fact that she was called &apos;onkata,&apos; which meant she was a daughter of a daijin (minister), her father was believed to be FUJIWARA no Tadamasa, who was the Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior) when Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo was a nyobo of Tokiko, and who had close relations with TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Life</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>仁安 (日本)2年（1167年）頃、平氏全盛期に同年齢の平知盛に見初められて妻となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Taira clan was prosperous around 1167, TAIRA no Tomonori who was her age fell in love with and married her.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1167, during a time when the Taira clan was prosperous, TAIRA no Tomonori fell in love with and married Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo, who was the same age as him.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1167, during a time when the Taira clan was prosperous, TAIRA no Tomomori fell in love with and married Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo, who was the same age as him.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>嘉応元年（1169年）に18歳で長男平知章を生む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gave birth to her eldest son, TAIRA no Tomoakira in 1169 when she was eighteen.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to their eldest son, TAIRA no Tomoakira, in 1169, when she was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gave birth to their eldest son, TAIRA no Tomoakira, in 1169, when she was 18 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>舅の平清盛の指示によって治承3年（1179年）に生まれた高倉天皇の第二皇子守貞親王の乳母となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She became the wet nurse of Imperial Prince Morisada who was born as the second prince of Emperor Takakura in 1179 by the order from her father in law, TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She became the wet nurse of Imperial Prince Morisada, who was born as the second prince of Emperor Takakura in 1179, by an order from her father-in-law, TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She became the wet nurse of Imperial Prince Morisada, who was born as the second prince of Emperor Takakura in 1179, by an order from her father-in-law, TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>夫知盛と共に自邸で親王を養育した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She brought up the imperial prince at home with her husband, Tomonori.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She and her husband, Tomonori, raised the Imperial Prince at their residence.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She and her husband, Tomomori, raised the Imperial Prince at their residence.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>その後治承・寿永の乱が起こり、戦乱の中で長男知章は一ノ谷の戦いで討ち死にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Jisho-Juei Civil War took place, and her eldest son, Tomoakira was killed by the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the Jisho-Juei Civil War took place, and her eldest son, Tomoakira, was killed in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the Jisho-Juei Civil War took place, and her eldest son, Tomoakira, was killed in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）7月、守貞親王を伴って平氏一門の都落ちに同行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, 1183, she followed the Taira clan exiling from the capital; the Imperial Prince Morisada was with her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1183, she was part of the exile of Imperial Prince Morisada and the Taira clan from the capital.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1183, she was part of the exile of Imperial Prince Morisada and the Taira clan from the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>文治元年（1185年）4月、壇ノ浦の戦いで夫知盛は自害し、平氏一門は滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1185, her husband, Tomonori killed himself in the Battle of Dan no ura, thus the Taira clan died out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1185, her husband, Tomonori, killed himself in the Battle of Dan no ura, thereby marking an end to the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1185, her husband, Tomomori, killed himself in the Battle of Dan no ura, thereby marking an end to the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>治部卿局は生き残って守貞親王や建礼門院ら一門の女性たちと共に都へ戻り、縁者である藤原隆房夫妻の四条大宮邸に身を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo went back to Kyoto with the Imperial Prince Morisada and women from the Taira clan including Kenreimonin, lived in the house of FUJIWARA no Takafusa, her relative, in Shijo-Omiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo went back to Kyoto with the Imperial Prince Morisada and the women of the Taira clan, including Kenreimonin, and lived in Shijo-Omiya at the residence of her relative, FUJIWARA no Takafusa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo went back to Kyoto with the Imperial Prince Morisada and the women of the Taira clan, including Kenreimonin, and lived in Shijo-Omiya at the residence of her relative, FUJIWARA no Takafusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>守貞親王は上西門院統子内親王の養子となった事から、治部卿局は親王の乳母として上西門院に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince Morisada was adopted by the Princess Josaimonin Muneko, and Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo served Josaimonin as a wet nurse of the imperial prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Morisada was adopted by Princess Josaimonin Muneko, and Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo served Josaimonin as a wet nurse of the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Morisada was adopted by Princess Josaimonin Muneko, and Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo served Josaimonin as a wet nurse of the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>守貞親王と共に藤原孝道に師事し、琵琶の名手となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She and the Imperial Prince Morisada learned from FUJIWARA no Takamichi, and became excellent players of biwa (Japanese flute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She and Imperial Prince Morisada learned to play the biwa (a type of Japanese flute) from FUJIWARA no Takamichi, and eventually became very skilled at it.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She and Imperial Prince Morisada learned to play the biwa (a type of Japanese flute) from FUJIWARA no Takamichi, and eventually became very skilled at it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>建久7年（1196年）6月、都落ちの際に幼少であったため乳母に預けたまま生き別れになっていた次男平知忠が謀反を起こして梟首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July in 1196, her second son, TAIRA no Tomotada who had been left with his wet nurse ever since the exile of the Taira clan was beheaded for his rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1196, her second son, TAIRA no Tomotada, who had been left with his wet nurse ever since the exile of the Taira clan, was beheaded for his rebellion.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1196, her second son, TAIRA no Tomotada, who had been left with his wet nurse ever since the exile of the Taira clan, was beheaded for his rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>首実検に呼び出された治部卿局は知忠の首に夫の面影を見て泣き伏したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo was called out, and cried to have seen the image of her husband in Tomotada&apos;s head.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo, who was called out for that execution, broke out into tears when she thought she had seen her late husband in the place of her son, Tomotada.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo, who was called out for that execution, broke out into tears when she thought she had seen her late husband in the place of her son, Tomotada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>承久3年（1221年）の承久の乱後、後堀河天皇が即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Jokyu War in 1221, Emperor Gohorikawa ascended to the throne.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Jokyu War in 1221, Emperor Gohorikawa ascended to the throne.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Jokyu War in 1221, Emperor Gohorikawa ascended to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その父守貞親王は後高倉院として院政を執った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Prince Morisada, the father of Emperor Gohorikawa managed Cloister government as Gotakakura-in.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Morisada, the father of Emperor Gohorikawa, managed the Cloistered Government as Gotakakura-in.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Morisada, the father of Emperor Gohorikawa, managed the Cloistered Government as Gotakakura-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>治部卿局は後高倉院、新帝の母北白河院を支えて再び脚光を浴びる存在となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo moved into limelight again by supporting Gotakakura-in and the mother of Emperor Gohorikawa, Kitashirakawa-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo moved into limelight again by supporting Gotakakura-in and the mother of Emperor Gohorikawa, Kitashirakawa-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo moved into limelight again by supporting Gotakakura-in and the mother of Emperor Gohorikawa, Kitashirakawa-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>寛喜3年（1231年）、80歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1231, she passed away at the age of eighty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1231, she passed away at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1231, she passed away at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>娘の中納言局は後堀河天皇に仕えて宮廷の実力者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The daughter of Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo, Chunagon no tsubone served Emperor Gohorikawa, and was recognized as the person of influence in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The daughter of Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo, Chunagon no tsubone, served Emperor Gohorikawa, and was a person of influence within the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The daughter of Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo, Chunagon no tsubone, served Emperor Gohorikawa, and was a person of influence within the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>『明月記』で「権勢の女」と評された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon), she was described as `the woman with power.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (The Chronicle of the Bright Moon), she was described as `the woman with power.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (The Chronicle of the Bright Moon), she was described as `the woman with power.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>『平家物語』が成立したとされる1230年頃、治部卿局は存命であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;was said to be created around 1230, Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo was still alive.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo was still alive in 1230 when &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;is known to have been completed.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsubone Court Lady of Jibukyo was still alive in 1230 when &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; is known to have been completed.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>平氏の血を引く天皇の世となって平家縁の女性たちが権勢を持った時代であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the period of time when the women who was associated with the Taira clan had power.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a time when women who were associated with the Taira clan wielded political power.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a time when women who were associated with the Taira clan wielded political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>『治承物語』が『平家物語』とタイトルを変えていったのは、当時の社会状況が微妙に影響した結果と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason that &quot;Jisho monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Jisho) changed its title into &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; was slightly related to the social situation at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title of the &quot;Jisho monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Jisho) was changed to &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; most likely due to the social circumstances around that time.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of the &quot;Jisho monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Jisho) was changed to &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; most likely due to the social circumstances around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちちぶ(id:184715), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>