<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原善時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 善時（ふじわら の よしとき、生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期頃の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki (dates of birth and death unknown) was a noble in about the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki (dates of birth and death unknown) was a nobleman approximately during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki (year of birth and death unknown) was a nobleman approximately during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>武蔵国介を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He successively held the position of Suke (assistant director) of the Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He successively held the position of Suke (assistant director) of Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He successively held the position of Assistant governor of Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>安和2年（969年）3月の安和の変では左馬助源満仲との協力で、左大臣源高明らを失脚させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Anna Incident in March 969, he worked with Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses) MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka to overthrow Sadaijin (minister of the left) MINAMOTO no Takaaki and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Anna Incident in March 969, he worked with Meryo (the section taking care of the imperial horses) MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka to overthrow Sadaijin (minister of the left) MINAMOTO no Takaaki and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Anna Incident in March 969, he worked with Sama no suke (vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses) MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka to overthrow Sadaijin (minister of the left) MINAMOTO no Takaakira and others.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたので、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>