<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京極高清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakiyo KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakiyo KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakiyo KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京極 高清（きょうごく たかきよ、1460年（寛正元年） - 1538年（天文 (元号)7年））は室町時代末期から戦国時代 (日本)初期の大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakiyo KYOGOKU (1460 – 1538) was a Daimyo (feudal lord) from the late Muromachi Period through to to Japan&apos;s Sengoku (Warring States) Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakiyo KYOGOKU (1460 – 1538) was a Daimyo (feudal lord) from the late Muromachi Period through Japan&apos;s Sengoku (Warring States) Period.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakiyo KYOGOKU (1460 – 1538) was a Daimyo (feudal lord) from the late Muromachi period through Japan&apos;s Sengoku period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。全角の’を半角にしました。(Period of Warring States)説明を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>京極氏の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He hailed from the Kyogoku Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He hailed from the Kyogoku Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He hailed from the Kyogoku Clan.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>応仁の乱の混乱を乗り切り、同族との家督争いを経て当主になったが、自身の子の代の家督争いを防ぐことはできず京極氏の衰退を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Managing to plot a course through the mayhem of the Onin no Ran (Onin Rebellion), and becoming head of the family after battling with his family to inherit the title, he could not however, protect his own child from the family battles which bought about a decline in the Kyogoku family fortunes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Managing to plot a course through the mayhem of the Onin no Ran (Onin Rebellion), and becoming head of the family after battling with his family to inherit the title, he could not protect his own child from the family battles, which bought about a decline in the Kyogoku family fortunes.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Managing to plot a course through the mayhem of the Onin no Ran (Onin Rebellion), and becoming head of the family after battling with his family to inherit the title, he could not protect his own child from the family battles, which bought about a decline in the Kyogoku family fortunes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>守護大名である京極持清の四男とも、持清の嫡子京極勝秀の子ともされ、幼名は乙童子丸と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was either 4th son of Shugo Daimyo (Governor feudal lord) Mochikiyo KYOGOKU, or the child of Katsuhide KYOGOKU who was Mochikiyo&apos;s progeny, going by the childhood name of Otsudojimaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was either the 4th son of Shugo Daimyo (Governor feudal lord) Mochikiyo KYOGOKU, or the child of Katsuhide KYOGOKU, who was Mochikiyo&apos;s progeny, and he went by the childhood name of Otsudojimaru.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was either the 4th son of Shugo Daimyo (Governor feudal lord) Mochikiyo KYOGOKU, or the child of Katsuhide KYOGOKU, who was Mochikiyo&apos;s progeny, and he went by the childhood name of Otsudojimaru.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>六郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>中務少輔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakatsukasa-no-shobu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakatsukasa-no-shobu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakatsukasa no Shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs)</e>
<cmt>Nakatsukasa no Shoyuに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>応仁の乱が起こると、持清は、近江国で西軍に属した六角高頼と戦うが、その戦いの中1470年（文明 (日本)2年）に病死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the outbreak of the Onin no Ran (Onin Rebellion), Mochikiyo fought against Takayori ROKKAKU on attachment to the West forces but, in 1470 during the battles he fell ill and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the outbreak of the Onin no Ran (Onin Rebellion), Mochikiyo fought against Takayori ROKKAKU on attachment to the West forces, but in 1470 he fell ill during battle and died.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the outbreak of the Onin no Ran (Onin Rebellion), Mochikiyo fought against Takayori ROKKAKU on attachment to the West forces, but in 1470 he fell ill during battle and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>持清の長男京極勝秀と次男京極政光は既に亡くなっており、勝秀の嫡子と考えられている京極孫童子丸が家督を継ぐが、1471年（文明3年）に死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochikiyo&apos;s elder brother Katsuhide KYOGOKU and his younger brother Masamitsu ROKKAKU were already dead so Sondojimaru KYOGOKU inherited the role of clan head however, he passed away in 1471.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochikiyo&apos;s elder brother Katsuhide KYOGOKU and his younger brother Masamitsu ROKKAKU were already dead, so Sondojimaru KYOGOKU inherited the role of clan head; however, he passed away in 1471.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochikiyo&apos;s elder brother Katsuhide KYOGOKU and his younger brother Masamitsu ROKKAKU were already dead, so Sondojimaru KYOGOKU inherited the role of clan head; however, he passed away in 1471.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その跡目を巡って持清の三男である京極政経と争い、敗北により越前国の敦賀市へと逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In relation to the family heir, he battled with Mochikiyo&apos;s 3rd son Masatsune KYOGOKU and, after being defeated he escaped to Tsuruga City in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In relation to the family heir, he battled with Mochikiyo&apos;s 3rd son Masatsune KYOGOKU and, after being defeated, he escaped to Tsuruga City in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In relation to the family heir, he battled with Mochikiyo&apos;s 3rd son Masatsune KYOGOKU and, after being defeated, he escaped to Tsuruga City in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後所在を転々とするが、1488年（長享2年）8月に近江松尾での政経との戦いに勝利し、政経を伊勢国へと敗走させ、1492年（明応元年）には征夷大将軍足利義稙から家督を安堵され、翌年には江北に帰還する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards he moved from place to place however, in August 1488 at Matsuo in Omi Province, he was victorious in battle against Masatsune and, Masatsune was forced to retreat to Ise Province. In 1492 he received relief with the inheritance from the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshitame ASHIKAGA and in the following year returned to Kohoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards he moved from place to place; however, in August 1488 at Matsuo in Omi Province, he was victorious in battle against Masatsune and Masatsune was forced to retreat to Ise Province; in 1492 he received relief with the inheritance from the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshitame ASHIKAGA and in the following year returned to Kohoku.</e>
<cmt>combined into 1 sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards he moved from place to place; however, in August 1488 at Matsuo in Omi Province, he was victorious in battle against Masatsune and Masatsune was forced to retreat to Ise Province; in 1492 he received relief with the inheritance from the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshitane ASHIKAGA and in the following year returned to Kohoku.</e>
<cmt>Yoshitane ASHIKAGAに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、1497年（明応5年）に助力を得ていた美濃国守護代斎藤利国が亡くなると、再び政経に追われ、美濃海津に寄留する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1497 with the death of Toshikuni SAITO, the Mino-no-kuni Shugodai (deputy governor of Mino Province) who had provided reinforcements, he was pursued once again by Masatsune took temporary refuge at Umezu (Mino Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1497, with the death of Toshikuni SAITO, the Mino-no-kuni Shugodai (deputy governor of Mino Province) who had provided reinforcements, he was pursued once again by Masatsune and took temporary refuge at Umezu (Mino Province).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1497, with the death of Toshikuni SAITO, the Mino no kuni Shugodai (deputy military governor of Mino domain) who had provided reinforcements, he was pursued once again by Masatsune and took temporary refuge at Umezu (Mino Province).</e>
<cmt>Mino no kuni Shugodai (deputy military governor of Mino domain)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが翌々年には京極氏重臣である上坂家信の助力を得て江北へと帰還し、1505年（永正2年）には政経の子である京極材宗と和解し、ついに家督争いを勝利で終える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, 2 years later, with the support of Ienobu KAMISAKA, a key retainer of the Kyogoku Clan, he managed to return to Omi Province and, in 1505 brokered a reconciliation with Masatsune&apos;s son Kimune KYOGOKU thus bringing a victorious end to the inheritance battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, 2 years later, with the support of Ienobu KAMISAKA, a key retainer of the Kyogoku Clan, he managed to return to Omi Province and in 1505 brokered a reconciliation with Masatsune&apos;s son Kimune KYOGOKU, thus bringing a victorious end to the inheritance battles.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, 2 years later, with the support of Ienobu KAMISAKA, a key retainer of the Kyogoku clan, he managed to return to Omi Province and in 1505 brokered a reconciliation with Masatsune&apos;s son Kimune KYOGOKU, thus bringing a victorious end to the inheritance battles.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>1509年（永正6年）には上平寺城を築いて居城とし、上坂家信の死後は家信の後を継いだ上坂信光を頼っていたが、1523年（大永3年）に、高清の後継を巡って、長男の京極高延を押す浅見貞則、浅井亮政らと、次男の京極高吉（京極高次の父）を推す高清、信光らに家中は分かれ、翌年には戦いへとおよび、敗れた高清らは尾張へと逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1509, he built Johei-ji Castle and became lord of the castle and, after the death of Ienobu KAMISAKA he relied upon Ienobu&apos;s heir Nobumitsu KAMISAKA for support but, in 1523, the individual in line to be Takakiyo&apos;s successor, his eldest son Takanobu KYOGOKU came under pressure by Sadanori ASAMI and Sukemasa AZAI so, Takakiyo promoted the interests of his younger son, Takayoshi KYOGOKU (Takatsugu KYOGOKU&apos;s father), the families became divided regarding Nobumitsu and the following year headed towards conflict and, Takakiyo and his losing counterparts escaped to Owari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1509, he built Johei-ji Castle and became lord of the castle and, after the death of Ienobu KAMISAKA he relied upon Ienobu&apos;s heir Nobumitsu KAMISAKA for support, but in 1523, the individual in line to be Takakiyo&apos;s successor, his eldest son Takanobu KYOGOKU, came under pressure by Sadanori ASAMI and Sukemasa AZAI, so Takakiyo promoted the interests of his younger son, Takayoshi KYOGOKU (Takatsugu KYOGOKU&apos;s father), the families became divided regarding Nobumitsu, and the following year, headed towards conflict, Takakiyo and his losing counterparts escaped to Owari.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1509, he built Johei-ji Castle and became lord of the castle and, after the death of Ienobu KAMISAKA he relied upon Ienobu&apos;s heir Nobumitsu KAMISAKA for support, but in 1523, the individual in line to be Takakiyo&apos;s successor, his eldest son Takanobu KYOGOKU, came under pressure by Sadanori ASAMI and Sukemasa AZAI, so Takakiyo promoted the interests of his younger son, Takayoshi KYOGOKU (Takatsugu KYOGOKU&apos;s father), the families became divided regarding Nobumitsu, and the following year, headed towards conflict, Takakiyo and his losing counterparts escaped to Owari.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしその年内には、貞則を下して江北の覇権を手にした亮政に、その居城である小谷城の京極丸へ、長男の高広と共に招かれ饗応される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, within that year, Sukemasa had overthrown Sadanori, grasped control of the Kohoku region, and then proceeded to invite Takakiyo and his eldest son Takahiro to a banquet at Kyogokumaru within his castle abode at Kotani Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, within that year, Sukemasa had overthrown Sadanori, grasped control of the Kohoku region, and then proceeded to invite Takakiyo and his eldest son Takahiro to a banquet at Kyogokumaru within his castle abode at Kotani Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, within that year, Sukemasa had overthrown Sadanori, grasped control of the Kohoku region, and then proceeded to invite Takakiyo and his eldest son Takahiro to a banquet at Kyogokumaru within his castle abode at Kotani Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この一件により江北の実質的な支配者は京極氏から浅井氏へ移ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this one event, the substantive rule of Kohoku passed from the Kyogoku Clan to the Azai Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this one event, the substantive rule of Kohoku passed from the Kyogoku Clan to the Azai Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this one event, the substantive rule of Kohoku passed from the Kyogoku clan to the Azai clan.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>高清はその後、余生を上平寺城で過ごし亡くなったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, Takakiyo spent the remaining years of his life at Johei-ji Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, Takakiyo spent the remaining years of his life at Johei-ji Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, Takakiyo spent the remaining years of his life at Johei-ji Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 俊(id:14924), Jmho(id:10472), Dream100(id:41924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>