<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>出雲狛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IZUMO no Koma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>出雲狛（いずものこま、生没年不詳）は、日本の飛鳥時代の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma, whose dates of birth and death were unknown, was a historical figure lived in the Asuka Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IZUMO no Koma, whose dates of birth and death were unknown, was a historical figure lived during Japan&apos;s Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルのネイティブチェックを参考に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma, whose dates of birth and death were unknown, was a historical figure lived during Japan&apos;s Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧仮名遣いでの読みは同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to pronounce his name is the same even though the name is written in the old Japanese syllabary characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is pronounced the same in the old Japanese kana syllabary.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルのネイティブチェックを参考に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is pronounced the same in the old Japanese kana syllabary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>姓（カバネ）は臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was Omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kabane (hereditary title) was Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>672年の壬申の乱のとき大海人皇子（天武天皇）につき、玉倉部邑で戦い、さらに三尾城を攻略した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sided Oama no Miko (Prince Oama) and Emperor Tenmu in the Jinshin War in 672, fought at Tamakurabenomura, and took over Sanbi Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sided Oama no Miko (Prince Oama, later Emperor Tenmu) in the Jinshin War of 672, fought at Tamakurabenomura, and took over the Mionoki Castle.</e>
<cmt>「大海人皇子（天武天皇）」は同一人物です。三尾城はMionoki Castleとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sided Oama no Miko (Prince Oama, later Emperor Tenmu) in the Jinshin War of 672, fought at Tamakurabenomura, and took over the Mionoki Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>壬申の乱勃発時に出雲狛がどこにいて、いつ大海人皇子の軍に加わったかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whereabouts of IZUMO no Koma at the break of the Jinshin War and how he became involved in the army of Oama no Miko were unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereabouts of IZUMO no Koma at the outbreak of the Jinshin War and how he became involved in the army of Oama no Miko were unknown.</e>
<cmt>breakを outbreakに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereabouts of IZUMO no Koma at the outbreak of the Jinshin War and how he became involved in the army of Oama no Miko were unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大海人皇子側の軍勢が美濃国の不破郡に集結しつつあった6月末に、近江朝廷の軍は精兵を放って玉倉部邑を急襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When troops of Oama no Miko were gathering force in Fuwa-gun of Mino Province at the end of the June, the special force of Omi Imperial Court launched a surprise attack on Tamakurabenomura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When troops of Oama no Miko were gathering in Fuwa-gun of Mino Province at the end of July, the special force of Omi Imperial Court launched a surprise attack on Tamakurabenomura.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When troops of Oama no Miko were gathering in Fuwa-gun of Mino Province at the end of July, the special force of Omi Imperial Court launched a surprise attack on Tamakurabenomura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>不破の本道を避け、北から迂回して和蹔の大海人皇子か不破の高市皇子の本営を狙ったものと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory is that the special force bypassed main roads in Fuwa, and took the northern route to attack Oama no Miko in Wazami or the headquarters of Takechi no Miko (Prince Takechi) in Fuwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the special force bypassed main roads in Fuwa and took the northern route to attack the headquarters of Oama no Miko in Wazami or of Takechi no Miko (Prince Takechi) in Fuwa.</e>
<cmt>文頭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the special force bypassed main roads in Fuwa and took the northern route to attack the headquarters of Oama no Miko in Wazami or of Takechi no Miko (Prince Takechi) in Fuwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このとき出雲狛が派遣されて敵を撃退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma was sent to fight and defeated the enemy in this battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IZUMO no Koma was sent to fight and defeated the enemy in this battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma was sent to fight and defeated the enemy in this battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『日本書紀』は7月2日の記事に「是より先」としてこの戦いを追記しているので、7月1日以前の数日間のうちにおきたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle most likely took place over few days before July 1 since an account of the battle was added to the entry on July 2 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and described as &quot;it happened earlier.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article of July 2 (old lunar calendar; July 25, 662) in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) describes that this battle occurred &apos;prior to this day,&apos; so it most likely took place over few days before July 24.</e>
<cmt>日本書紀の記事の項目なので日付が旧暦であることを付記しました。文の語順を原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article of July 2 (old lunar calendar; July 25, 662) in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) describes that this battle occurred &apos;prior to this day,&apos; so it most likely took place over few days before July 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>後に出雲狛は、琵琶湖を北回りで進む羽田矢国の軍に加わったらしく、7月22日に共同して三尾城を降した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, IZUMO no Koma likely joined the troop of HATA no Yakuni advancing on the northern route along Lake Biwa; IZUMO no Koma together with HATA no Yakuni took over Sanbi Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, IZUMO no Koma seemed to join the troop of HATA no Yakuni advancing on the northern route along Lake Biwa, and they cooperated in the seizure of the Mionoki Castle on August 14.</e>
<cmt>後半の文を書き換え、日付を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, IZUMO no Koma seemed to join the troop of HATA no Yakuni advancing on the northern route along Lake Biwa, and they cooperated in the seizure of the Mionoki Castle on August 14.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>以上の『日本書紀』の記述は、狛のことを「出雲臣狛」と「臣」をつけて記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the entries of events in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; described above, IZUMO no Koma was written with &apos;Omi&apos; as in IZUMO no Omi Koma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the above descriptions in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; IZUMO no Koma was referred to as IZUMO no Omi Koma with his kabane of Omi.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the above descriptions in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; IZUMO no Koma was referred to as IZUMO no Omi Koma with his kabane of Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>大宝2年（802年）8月1日に、出雲狛は従五位下になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on August 1, 802.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IZUMO no Koma was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on September 1, 702.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変換しました。（原文の「802年」は誤記と思われます）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IZUMO no Koma was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on September 1, 702.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同年9月21日に従五位下出雲狛は臣の姓を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded with kabane, Omi, on September 21 of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded with the kabane of Omi on October 20 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded with the kabane of Omi on October 20 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これら『続日本紀』の記事では、これ以前には狛には姓がなかったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to these entries in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), he didn&apos;t have kabane before 802.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to these entries in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), he did not hold a kabane before 802.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルのネイティブチェックを参考に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to these entries in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), he did not hold a kabane before 802.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kinori(id:443), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>