<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源義清 (左京権大夫)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (Sakyo no gon no daibu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo</e>
<cmt>eliminated content in parenthesis since it is also written below and to be consistent with other articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (Sakyo no gon no daibu)</e>
<cmt>原文wikiを参照しますと、源義清が3人いるようであり、それぞれ異なるタイトルで区別されているようですので、ここでも翻訳者の方の翻訳どおり括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 義清（みなもと の よしきよ、生没年未詳）は源義忠の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (date of birth and death unknown) was the fourth son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (year of birth and death unknown) was the fourth son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;date&quot; to &quot;year&quot; to match the word list</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (year of birth and death unknown) was the fourth son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>従五位下、左京権大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Sakyo no gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) in Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the post of Sakyo no gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) and his official court rank was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>changed to be more consistent with similar articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the post of Sakyo no gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) and his official court rank was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>系図によると母は平忠盛の娘とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the family tree, his mother was a daughter of TAIRA no Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to his family tree, Yoshikiyo&apos;s mother was a daughter of TAIRA no Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;the&quot; to&quot; his&quot;; changed &quot;his&quot; to &quot;Yoshikiyo&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to his family tree, Yoshikiyo&apos;s mother was a daughter of TAIRA no Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>が、年代的に考えてこれは誤りであり、平正盛の娘、即ち忠盛の姉妹が正しいと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the date, however, this is wrong and it seems that she was a daughter of TAIRA no Masamori, that is, a sister of Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is incorrect based on the dates, however, making it more likely that Yoshikiyo&apos;s mother was a daughter of TAIRA no Masamori and a sister of Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is incorrect based on the dates, however, making it more likely that Yoshikiyo&apos;s mother was a daughter of TAIRA no Masamori and a sister of Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>いずれにせよこれは、義忠と伊勢平氏一族の繋がりを暗示する記述であり、後世治承・寿永の乱において、義忠の子孫の一部が平家方に与したことの遠因の一つとして考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, this is a description which indicates the relationship between Yoshitada and the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan), and this relationship is considered to be one of the remote causes why a part of Yoshitada&apos;s descendant took the side of the Taira family in Jisho-Juei War later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, these relationships indicate the connection between Yoshitada and the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan), and it is these relationships that are considered to be one of the remote causes for some of Yoshitada&apos;s descendants to side with the Taira family during the Jisho-Juei War later on.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Anyway&quot; to &quot;In any case&quot;; fixed grammar to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, these relationships indicate the connection between Yoshitada and the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan), and it is these relationships that are considered to be one of the remote causes for some of Yoshitada&apos;s descendants to side with the Taira family during the Jisho-Juei War later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、平清盛の「清」の一字は、彼が烏帽子親となったことに由来するともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is said that the letter of &apos;清&apos; of TAIRA no Kiyomori comes from the fact that Yoshikiyo was his eboshioya (a person who put on an eboshi in the case of genpuku ceremony).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also been inferred that the character &quot;清&quot; representing the &quot;kiyo&quot; in TAIRA no &quot;Kiyomori&quot; as well as in &quot;Yoshikiyo&quot; comes from the fact that Yoshikiyo was eboshioya (the person who wears an eboshi (black-lacquered headgear (made of silk, cloth or paper) originally worn by court nobles in ancient Japan, and afterwards spreading to the common people) at Kiyomori&apos;s genpuku (coming of age ceremony)).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In addition&quot; to &quot;It has also&quot;; added more description for the kanji character used; added description for eboshi found at &lt;http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~jwb/cgi-bin/wwwjdic.cgi?1F&gt;; added description for genpuku</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also been inferred that the character &apos;清&apos; representing the &quot;kiyo&quot; in TAIRA no &quot;Kiyomori&quot; as well as in &quot;Yoshikiyo&quot; comes from the fact that Yoshikiyo was eboshioya (the person who wears an eboshi [black-lacquered headgear, which is made of silk, cloth or paper, originally worn by court nobles in ancient Japan, and afterwards spreading to the common people] at Kiyomori&apos;s coming of age ceremony).</e>
<cmt>烏帽子親の補足内の表現を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>清盛の父、忠盛の「忠」の一字も、彼の父、源義忠が烏帽子親であったことに由来し、忠盛、清盛親子と、義忠、義清親子の親密さを伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letter of &apos;忠&apos; of Tadamori, who was Kiyomori&apos;s father, also came from the fact that his father MINAMOTO no Yoshitada was his eboshioya, which shows their intimate relationship between Tadamori and his son Kiyomori and Yoshitada and his son Yoshikiyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The character &quot;忠&quot; representing the &quot;tada&quot; of &quot;Tadamori,&quot; who was Kiyomori&apos;s father, was also used based on the fact that MINAMOTO no Yoshitada was Tadamori&apos;s eboshiya. This shows the intimate relationship between Tadamori, his son Kiyomori, Yoshitada and his son Yoshikiyo.</e>
<cmt>added description to make the kanji character easier to understand; fixed to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The character &apos;忠&apos; representing the &quot;tada&quot; of &quot;Tadamori,&quot; who was Kiyomori&apos;s father, was also used based on the fact that MINAMOTO no Yoshitada was Tadamori&apos;s eboshioya; this shows the intimate relationship between Tadamori, his son Kiyomori, Yoshitada and his son Yoshikiyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>右衛門尉、兵庫助などを歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikiyo held positions such as Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Hyogo no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikiyo held positions such as Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Hyogo no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikiyo held positions such as Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Hyogo no suke (assistant director of military storehouses).</e>
<cmt>兵庫助→assistant director of military storehouses　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>子に従五位下左衛門尉、因幡介となった源義久がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son was MINAMOTO no Yoshihisa who was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Inaba no suke (assistant governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, MINAMOTO no Yoshihisa, had the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and held the position of Saemon no jo (Third-ranked Officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Inaba no suke (assistant governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt>added commas; added &quot;had the rank of&quot; before &quot;Juoinoge&quot;; added &quot;held the position of&quot; before &quot;Saemon&quot;; fixed grammar; capitalized job title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, MINAMOTO no Yoshihisa, had the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and held the position of Saemon no jo (Third-ranked Officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Inaba no suke (assistant governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>義久には一子があり、従五位下宮内少輔源義高がそれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa had a son, MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka, who was Jugoinoge Kunai shoyu/Kunai no sho (Junior Assistant Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka, had the rank of Jugoinoge and held the position of Kunai shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;kunai no sho&quot; and left only &quot;Kunai shoyu&quot; for &quot;宮内少輔&quot;; added &quot;had the rank of&quot; before &quot;Jugoinoge&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka, had the rank of Jugoinoge and held the position of Kunai shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>現代の源姓の人物は歴史上の源氏と必ずしも関係があるわけではないが、源義清の子孫は現在も源を今日的な意味の姓として名乗っており、江戸時代の資料等にも苗字が源であり、姓も源とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present people whose family name are Minamoto have not necessarily related with the historical Minamoto clan, but for the descendants of MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo, the name of Minamoto is still relevant as their surname and there are descriptions about Minamoto as Myoji or Sei (family name) in historical materials of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People living today with the family name Minamoto are not necessarily related to the historical Minamoto clan, but for the descendants of MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo, the name is still used as a relevant surname. There are also descriptions in historical materials from the Edo period about how Minamoto was used as a Myoji or Sei (family name).</e>
<cmt>split this sentence into two sentences; rearranged sentence structure to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People living today with the family name Minamoto are not necessarily related to the historical Minamoto clan, but for the descendants of MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo, the name is still used as a relevant surname; there are also descriptions in historical materials from the Edo period about how Minamoto was used as a Myoji or Sei (family name).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお義清の兄・源義高 (左兵衛権佐)及び弟・源義雄の子孫も義清の子孫同様、現在も源を苗字としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the descendants of MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (Sahyoe no gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards)) and MINAMOTO no Yoshikatsu who were Yoshikiyo&apos;s brothers also use the name of Minamoto as their surname as well as the descendants of Yoshikiyo at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (Sahyoe no gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards)) and MINAMOTO no Yoshikatsu, who were Yoshikiyo&apos;s brothers, also use the name of Minamoto as their surname in addition to the descendants of Yoshikiyo.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;at present&quot; because it seemed unecessary and I could find a better place to put it; added commas; moved &quot;in addition&quot; from the beginning of the sentence to the end</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (Sahyoe no gon no suke [Provisional Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards]) and MINAMOTO no Yoshikatsu, who were Yoshikiyo&apos;s brothers, also use the name of Minamoto as their surname in addition to the descendants of Yoshikiyo.</e>
<cmt>括弧を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 阿波座行広(id:39667), コバルトブルーとターコイズブルー(id:290948), スクリュードライバー(id:242305), 小者(id:172526), はるひ(id:59079), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>