<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源維義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Koreyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Koreyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Koreyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源維義（みなもと の これよし、生没年不明)は平安時代の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Koreyoshi (the year of his birth and death is not clear) was a bushi (samurai) in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Koreyoshi (the year of his birth and death is not clear) was a bushi (samurai) in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Koreyoshi (the year of his birth and death is not clear) was a bushi (samurai) in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源為義十四男とも云うが、その人物像は資料が乏しく、詳細では不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi Toshio, but the details concerning him is not clear because of the lack of material.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi Toshio, but the details concerning him is not clear because of the lack of material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi Toshio, but the details concerning him is not clear because of the lack of material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>惟義とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name is also written in Chinese characters as 惟義 (Koreyoshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is also written in Chinese characters as 惟義 (Koreyoshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is also written in Chinese characters as 惟義 (Koreyoshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称を松井冠者と称したとされ、子孫にこれを起源とする源為義流松井氏がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Matsui-kaja and the MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi-ryu Matsui clan, his descendent, derives from this name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Matsui-kaja and the MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi-ryu Matsui clan, his descendent, derives from this name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Matsui-kaja and the MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi-ryu Matsui clan, his descendent, derives from this name.</e>
<cmt>from の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この松井氏は山城国出身とされ、同国葛野郡松井庄の出と云う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Matsui clan is believed to have hailed from Matsuisho Kadono-gun in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsui clan is believed to have hailed from Matsuisho Kadono-gun in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsui clan is believed to have hailed from Matsuisho Kadono-gun in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>葛野郡松井庄は現在の京都市右京区西院松井町であると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is contemplated that Matsuisho Kadono-gun coincides with Saiin Matsui-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is contemplated that Matsuisho Kadono-gun coincides with Saiin Matsui-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is contemplated that Matsuisho Kadono-gun coincides with Saiin Matsui-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>為義の子供たちの多くは、保元の乱・平治の乱に巻き込まれて命を落としたが、維義のように生存したものがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although many of Tameyoshi&apos;s children died while being embroiled in Hogen Disturbance and Heiji Disturbance, some of them survived including Koreyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although many of Tameyoshi&apos;s children died while being embroiled in Hogen Disturbance and Heiji Disturbance, some of them survived including Koreyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although many of Tameyoshi&apos;s children died while being embroiled in Hogen War and Heiji War, some of them survived including Koreyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Disturbance→War</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>彼はこれらの戦乱のとき、あるいは幼児のため禍を免れたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that he could escape the ravage of battle because he was still an infant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that he escaped the ravages of battle because he was still an infant.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that he escaped the ravages of battle because he was still an infant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>また、西院松井町の域内にはかつて後院（天皇の隠居所）としての奨学院が存在し、淳和天皇の女院が隠棲の寺をその域内に建立してこれを松院と称したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that goin (a palace for the retired Emperor) called Shogakuin was located in the area of Saiin Matsui-cho and the Emperor Junna&apos;s nyoin (close female relatives of the Emperor) constructed a temple for their secluded life in the same area and named it Matsu-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that goin (a palace for the retired Emperor) called Shogakuin was located in the area of Saiin Matsui-cho and the Emperor Junna&apos;s nyoin (close female relatives of the Emperor) constructed a temple for their secluded life in the same area and named it Matsu-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that goin (a palace for the retired Emperor) called Shogakuin was located in the area of Saiin Matsui-cho and the Emperor Junna&apos;s nyoin (close female relatives of the Emperor) constructed a temple for their secluded life in the same area and named it Matsu-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>松院は後代松井寺と呼ばれ、この地の名称のもととなったとも云う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Matsu-in was called Matsui-ji Temple in later years and became the origin of the name of this place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Matsu-in was called Matsui-ji Temple in later years and became the origin of the name of this place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Matsu-in was called Matsui-ji Temple in later years and became the origin of the name of this place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そして、淳和院は別当職を代々源氏長者（当時は村上源氏が世襲）がつとめ、源氏にゆかりの深い施設であるが維義との関係性は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junnain was a facility which was closely connected with Minamoto clan since its Bettoshoku (a chief of Junnain) was successively assumed by Genji choja (the chief of Minamoto clan) (at that time, it was hereditary post of Murakami Genji), but its relation with Koreyoshi is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junnain was a facility which was closely connected with Minamoto clan since its Bettoshoku (a chief of Junnain) was successively assumed by Genji choja (the chief of Minamoto clan) (at that time, it was hereditary post of Murakami Genji), but its relation with Koreyoshi is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junnain was a facility which was closely connected with Minamoto clan since its Bettoshoku (a chief of Junnain) was successively assumed by Genji choja (the chief of Minamoto clan) (at that time, it was hereditary post of Murakami Genji), but its relation with Koreyoshi is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>松井氏はこの後、山城国を中心に発展分岐し、室町期松井康之(武将)・松井友閑(堺奉行)等を輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, the Matsui clan developed and branched off into some lineages with Yamashiro Province being its base, and Yasuyuki MATSUI (busho (Japanese military commander)) and Yukan MATSUI (Sakai bugyo (Magistrate of around Sakai)) appeared in succession during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, the Matsui clan developed and branched off into some lineages with Yamashiro Province being its base, and Yasuyuki MATSUI (busho (Japanese military commander)) and Yukan MATSUI (Sakai bugyo (Magistrate of around Sakai)) appeared in succession during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, the Matsui clan developed and branched off into some lineages with Yamashiro Province being its base, and Yasuyuki MATSUI (busho (Japanese military commander)) and Yukan MATSUI (Sakai bugyo (Magistrate of around Sakai)) appeared in succession during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>第一の系統は、室町幕府御家人として足利氏に仕え、のち細川氏和泉上守護家の細川幽斎（幽斎）に付属して肥後国八代藩主となった（但し、綴喜郡松井出身説もあり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first lineage is the clan that served for the Ashikaga Clan as Gokenin (vassals) of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and later became the lord of Yatsushiro domain in Higo Province (however, some asserts that this clan hailed from Tsuzuki-gun Matsui) by affiliating itself to Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai), who belonged to the Hosokawa clan that was the military governor of Izumikami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first lineage is the clan that served the Ashikaga Clan as Gokenin (vassals) of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and later became the lord of Yatsushiro domain in Higo Province (however, some asserts that this clan hailed from Tsuzuki-gun Matsui) by affiliating itself to Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai), who belonged to the Hosokawa clan that was the military governor of Izumikami.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first lineage is the clan that served the Ashikaga Clan as Gokenin (vassals) of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and later became the lord of Yatsushiro domain in Higo Province (however, some asserts that this clan hailed from Tsuzuki-gun Matsui) by affiliating itself to Yusai HOSOKAWA, who belonged to the Hosokawa clan that was the military governor of Izumikami.</e>
<cmt>(Yusai) 削除しました。who の前のスペース削除「数字不一致確認済み」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>第二の系統は建武年間足利尊氏に味方し、今川範国に属して遠江国に移住して二俣城主になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second lineage is the clan that sided with Takauji ASHIKAGA during Kenmu era, then moved to Totomi Province and became the castellan of Hutamata Castle by affiliating itself with Norikuni IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second lineage is the clan that sided with Takauji ASHIKAGA during Kenmu era, then moved to Totomi Province and became the castellan of Hutamata Castle by affiliating itself with Norikuni IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second lineage is the clan that sided with Takauji ASHIKAGA during Kenmu era, then moved to Totomi Province and became the castellan of Futamata-jo Castle by affiliating itself with Norikuni IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Hutamata→Futamata-jo「数字不一致確認済み」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>第三の系統は二俣城主の系統から分かれて三河国に移住、吉良氏・松平氏に属して江戸幕府譜代大名や旗本になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third lineage is the clan that branched off from the clan of the castellan of Hutamata Castle, moved to Mikawa Province, affiliated themselves to the Kira clan or the Matsudaira clan and finally became Hudai Daimyo (feudal lord in hereditary vassal of Tokugawa family) or Hatamoto (direct vassals of a shogun) in the era of Edo Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third lineage is the clan that branched off from the clan of the castellan of Hutamata Castle, moved to Mikawa Province, affiliated themselves to the Kira clan or the Matsudaira clan and finally became Hudai Daimyo (feudal lord in hereditary vassal of Tokugawa family) or Hatamoto (direct vassals of a shogun) in the era of Edo Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third lineage is the clan that branched off from the clan of the castellan of Hutamata Castle, moved to Mikawa Province, affiliated themselves to the Kira clan or the Matsudaira clan and finally became fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) or Hatamoto (direct vassals of a shogun) in the era of Edo Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Hutamata→Futamata-jo「数字不一致確認済み」譜代大名の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 故城一片之月(id:109503), Andee(id:20421), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>