<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北条時行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiyuki HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北条 時行（ほうじょう ときゆき）は、鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代 (日本)の武将である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the time from the late Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiyuki HOJO was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the late Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>余分な訳は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiyuki HOJO was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the late Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府第14代執権北条高時の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of Takatoki HOJO, the fourth regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of Takatoki HOJO, the fourteenth regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>「14代」の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Takatoki HOJO, the fourteenth regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>兄である北条邦時が、正中 (日本)2年（1325年）生まれであるため、それ以後の誕生と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his older brother, Kunitoki HOJO was born in 1325, it is assumed that he was born before the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since his older brother Kunitoki HOJO was born in 1325, it is assumed that he was born after that.</e>
<cmt>「それ以後」ですので、&quot;before&quot;ではなく&quot;after&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since his older brother Kunitoki HOJO was born in 1325, it is assumed that he was born after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後醍醐天皇が討幕運動を起こすと、幕府御家人であった足利尊氏や新田義貞らが宮方に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo launched the anti-shogunate movement, shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu including Takauji ASHIKAGA and Yoshisada NITTA sided with the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Godaigo launched the anti-shogunate movement, shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu including Takauji ASHIKAGA and Yoshisada NITTA sided with the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo launched the anti-shogunate movement, shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu including Takauji ASHIKAGA and Yoshisada NITTA sided with the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉は新田義貞に攻められて高時ら北条氏は滅亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshisada NITTA attacked Kamakura, and then the Hojo family including Takatoki was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshisada NITTA attacked Kamakura, and then the Hojo family including Takatoki was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshisada NITTA attacked Kamakura, and then the Hojo family including Takatoki was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幕府滅亡後に後醍醐天皇による建武の新政が開始されるが、時行は鎌倉から脱出し、北条氏の守護国であった信濃国に逃れ、諏訪氏などに迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kenmu Restoration (the new government) by Emperor Godaigo started after the fall of the bakufu, Tokiyuki escaped from Kamakura to Shinano Province governed by the Hojo clan and was received by the Suwa clan amongst others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Emperor Godaigo started the new government by the Kenmu Restoration after the fall of the bakufu, Tokiyuki escaped from Kamakura to Shinano Province governed by the Hojo clan and was sheltered by the Suwa clan.</e>
<cmt>「建武の新政」の訳を自然な流れになるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Emperor Godaigo started the new government by the Kenmu Restoration after the fall of the bakufu, Tokiyuki escaped from Kamakura to Shinano Province governed by the Hojo clan and was sheltered by the Suwa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>北条一族の残党は各地に潜伏して蜂起した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remnants of the Hojo family ware hidden in various places and then rose in revolt.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remnants of the Hojo family hid in various places and then rose in revolt.</e>
<cmt>「潜伏」は能動態にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remnants of the Hojo family hid in various places and then rose in revolt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>高時の弟である北条泰家は京都で西園寺公宗らとともに各地の北条残党と連絡を取り新政の転覆と鎌倉幕府再興を図るが失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with Kinmune SAIONJI in Kyoto, Takatoki&apos;s younger brother Yasuie HOJO communicated with the remnants of the Hojo family in various places to overthrow the new government and restore the Kamakura bakufu but failed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with Kinmune SAIONJI in Kyoto, Takatoki&apos;s younger brother Yasuie HOJO communicated with the remnants of the Hojo family in various places to overthrow the new government and restore the Kamakura bakufu but failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with Kinmune SAIONJI in Kyoto, Takatoki&apos;s younger brother Yasuie HOJO communicated with the remnants of the Hojo family in various places to overthrow the new government and restore the Kamakura bakufu but failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>建武 (日本)2年（1335年）7月 (旧暦)、10歳前後（7歳とも）であったと考えられている時行は信濃の諏訪頼重 (南北朝時代)に擁立されて挙兵し建武政権に不満を持つ武士を糾合しながら武蔵国へ入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiyuki who was presumably around ten (or seven) years old raised an army with the support of Yorishige SUWA (in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts) in Shinano, and entered Musashi Province while rallying commanders who were dissatisfied with the new government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiyuki who was presumably around ten (or seven) years old raised an army with the support of Yorishige SUWA (in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts) in Shinano, and entered Musashi Province while rallying samurai who were dissatisfied with the new government.</e>
<cmt>「武士」は&quot;samurai&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiyuki who was presumably around ten (or seven) years old raised an army with the support of Yorishige SUWA (in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts) in Shinano, and entered Musashi Province while rallying samurai who were dissatisfied with the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>町田市の菅原神社 (町田市)での合戦で尊氏の弟である鎌倉将軍府執権足利直義を破り鎌倉を一時占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He beat the regent of the Kamakura bakufu Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s younger brother in the battle in the Sugawara-jinja Shrine in Machida City and temporarily occupied Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He beat the regent of the Kamakura bakufu Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s younger brother in the battle in the Sugawara-jinja Shrine in Machida City and temporarily occupied Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He beat the regent of the Kamakura bakufu Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s younger brother in the battle in the Sugawara-jinja Shrine in Machida City and temporarily occupied Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>時行軍は逃げる直義を駿河国手越河原で撃破するが、京から直義救援に駆けつけた足利尊氏に、遠江国橋本、小夜の中山、相模国相模川などの戦いで連破され、時行の軍は壊滅し時行は逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Tokiyuki army defeated escaping Tadayoshi in Tegoshigawara, Suruga Province, Tokiyuki ran away because his army was beat and destroyed by Takauji ASHIKAGA who came from Kyoto to assist Tadayoshi in battles in Hashimoto, Totoumi Province, Sayo no Nakayama (Nakayaka pass at Sayo) and Sagamigawa, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Tokiyuki army defeated escaping Tadayoshi in Tegoshigawara, Suruga Province, Tokiyuki ran away because his army was beaten and destroyed by Takauji ASHIKAGA who came from Kyoto to assist Tadayoshi in battles in Hashimoto, Totoumi Province, Sayo no Nakayama (Nakayaka pass at Sayo) and Sagamigawa, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Tokiyuki army defeated escaping Tadayoshi in Tegoshigawara, Suruga Province, Tokiyuki ran away because his army was beaten and destroyed by Takauji ASHIKAGA who came from Kyoto to assist Tadayoshi in battles in Hashimoto, Totoumi Province, Sayo no Nakayama (Nakayaka pass at Sayo) and Sagamigawa, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>時行が鎌倉を占領していたのはわずか20日間であるが、先代（北条氏）と後代（足利氏）の間に立った鎌倉の一時的支配者となったことから、この乱は中先代の乱と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This battle is called Nakasendai War because Tokiyuki became a ruler in Kamakura temporarily bridging between the predecessor (the Hojo clan) and the successor (the Ashikaga clan) although he occupied Kamakura for as short as 20 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle is called Nakasendai (intermediate predecessor) War because Tokiyuki became the ruler of Kamakura temporarily bridging between the predecessor (the Hojo clan) and the successor (the Ashikaga clan) although he occupied Kamakura for as short as 20 days.</e>
<cmt>「中先代」は&quot;(intermediate predecessor)&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle is called Nakasendai (intermediate predecessor) War because Tokiyuki became the ruler of Kamakura temporarily bridging between the predecessor (the Hojo clan) and the successor (the Ashikaga clan) although he occupied Kamakura for as short as 20 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>尊氏は中先代の乱を契機に新政から離反し、宮方を破り京都に武家政権を設立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of the Nakasendai War, Takauji seceded from the new government and established a military government in Kyoto after beating the imperial court forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of the Nakasendai War, Takauji seceded from the new government and established a military government in Kyoto after beating the imperial court forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of the Nakasendai War, Takauji seceded from the new government and established a military government in Kyoto after beating the imperial court forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後醍醐天皇は吉野で南朝 (日本)を開いて南北朝時代 (日本)となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo established the Southern Court (Japan) in Yoshino and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts began.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo established the Southern Court (Japan) in Yoshino and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo established the Southern Court (Japan) in Yoshino and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>延元2年（1337年）時行は吉野の後醍醐と接触し、朝敵恩赦の綸旨を受けて南朝方に属す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1337, Tokiyuki contacted Emperor Godaigo in Yoshino and belonged to the Southern Court after receiving the imperial order to grant amnesty to court enemies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1337, Tokiyuki contacted Emperor Godaigo in Yoshino and joined the Southern Court after receiving the imperial order to grant amnesty to court enemies.</e>
<cmt>新たに加わったので&quot;join&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1337, Tokiyuki contacted Emperor Godaigo in Yoshino and joined the Southern Court after receiving the imperial order to grant amnesty to court enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>時行は北畠顕家の軍に属し、青野原の戦いなどで足利方と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiyuki belonged to the army of the Akiie KITABATAKE and fought against the Ashikaga forces in the battles such as the Battle of Aonogahara.</e>
<cmt>青野原の戦い（あおのがはらのたたかい）&lt;http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%9D%92%E9%87%8E%E5%8E%9F%E3%81%AE%E6%88%A6%E3%81%84&gt;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiyuki belonged to the army of the Akiie KITABATAKE and fought against the Ashikaga forces in the battles such as the Battle of Aonogahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiyuki belonged to the army of the Akiie KITABATAKE and fought against the Ashikaga forces in the battles such as the Battle of Aonogahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>観応の擾乱の直後の1352年（正平7年/文和元年）に、新田義貞の遺児新田義宗・新田義興と共に上野国で挙兵するが、武蔵国で足利尊氏とその子足利基氏に敗れて捕らえられ、翌年5月20日に鎌倉龍ノ口で処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1352 soon after the Kanno Disturbance, he raised an army with bereaved children of Yoshisada NITTA, Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshioki NITTA in Kozuke Province, but he was beat and captured by Takauji ASHIKAGA and his son Motouji ASHIKAGA and then executed in Kamakura tatsu no guchi on May 20 of the following year.</e>
<cmt>龍ノ口（たつのくち）&lt;http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%BE%8D%E5%8F%A3&gt;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1352 soon after the Kanno Disturbance, he raised an army with Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshioki NITTA, the bereaved children of Yoshisada NITTA in Kozuke Province, but he was beaten and captured by Takauji ASHIKAGA and his son Motouji ASHIKAGA and then executed in Kamakura tatsu no guchi on May 20 of the following year.</e>
<cmt>誤解のないように、語順を入れ替えました。文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1352 soon after the Kanno Disturbance, he raised an army with Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshioki NITTA, the bereaved children of Yoshisada NITTA in Kozuke Province, but he was beaten and captured by Takauji ASHIKAGA and his son Motouji ASHIKAGA and then executed in Kamakura tatsu no guchi on May 20 of the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>時行の死により北条得宗家は滅亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokuso family of the Hojo clan was destroyed by the death of Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo Tokuso family (the direct line of the regency Hojo family) was destructed by the death of Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt>得宗家の説明を入れました。「滅亡」は&quot;destructed&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo Tokuso family (the direct line of the regency Hojo family) was destructed by the death of Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし、岡野氏、横井氏（子孫には横井小楠）や平野氏（尾張平野氏、子孫に平野長泰）など時行の子孫を称する家系もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some families, however, such as the Okano clan, the Yokoi clan (whose descendant was Shonan YOKOI), and the Hirano clan (such as the Owari-Hirano clan, whose descendant was Nagayasu HIRANO) claimed descent from Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some families, however, such as the Okano clan, the Yokoi clan (whose descendants include Shonan YOKOI), and the Hirano clan (the Owari-Hirano clan, whose descendants include Nagayasu HIRANO) claimed descent from Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some families, however, such as the Okano clan, the Yokoi clan (whose descendants include Shonan YOKOI), and the Hirano clan (the Owari-Hirano clan, whose descendants include Nagayasu HIRANO) claimed descent from Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Oxhop(id:2551), Nakamanman(id:10339), 水野白楓(id:22811), KurmUmy(id:202680), ちちぶ(id:184715), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kamitani(id:30757), でここ(id:9565), Yoshiichi(id:27210), DNCAL(id:120593), まちっこ(id:240169), 代言人(id:33675), Goki(id:7107), 海衛士(id:19229), Shostakist(id:54214), R28Bot(id:177951), 怪蘇(id:45514), 210.(id:9838), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>