<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近衛信尹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutada KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutada KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutada KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近衛 信尹（このえ のぶただ　永禄8年11月1日 (旧暦)(1565年11月23日) - 慶長19年11月25日 (旧暦)(1614年12月25日)）は、安土桃山時代の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutada KONOE (November 23, 1565-December 25, 1614) was a court noble lived in the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutada KONOE (November 23, 1565-December 25, 1614) was a court noble lived in the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;who&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutada KONOE (November 23, 1565 - December 25, 1614) was a court noble lived in the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近衛前久の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Sakihisa KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Sakihisa KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Sakihisa KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は近衛家女房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a nyobo (female servants who work at noble people&apos;s house) of the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a lady in waiting of the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;nyobo (female servants who work at noble people&apos;s house)&quot;→&quot;lady in waiting&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a lady in waiting of the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初名、信基、信輔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Nobumoto then changed to Nobusuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Nobumoto, later changed to Nobusuke.</e>
<cmt>&quot;then&quot;→&quot;, later&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Nobumoto, later changed to Nobusuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>号は三藐院（さんみゃくいん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go (artist name) was Sanmyakuin.</e>
<cmt>号→go (artist name)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pen name was Sanmyakuin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;go (artist name)&quot;→&quot;pen name&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pen name was Sanmyakuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>天正5年(1577年)元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went through genpuku (a ceremony to celebrate a young man&apos;s coming of age) in 1577.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He celebrated his coming of age in 1577.</e>
<cmt>&quot;went through genpuku (a ceremony to celebrate a young man&apos;s coming of age)&quot;&quot;celebrated his coming of age&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He celebrated his coming of age in 1577.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>加冠の役をつとめたのが織田信長で、信長の一字を貰い信基と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who performed kakan (put a crown on a young man&apos;s head on a genpuku ceremony) was Nobunaga ODA and he got one character of the name of Nobunaga and called himself Nobumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kakan (where a crown is put on the head of the person coming of age) was performed by Nobunaga ODA, who gave him permission to use one character of the name of Nobunaga and he took the name Nobumoto.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kakan (where a crown is put on the head of the person coming of age) was performed by Nobunaga ODA, who gave him permission to use one character of the name of Nobunaga and he took the name Nobumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天正8年(1580年)に内大臣、天正13年(1585年)左大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1580, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (managerial position who supports Emperor), then Sadaijin (minister of the left) in 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1580, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center), then Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 1585.</e>
<cmt>&quot;managerial position who supports Emperor&quot;→&quot;Minister of the Center&quot;Capitalised &apos;m&apos;, &apos;l&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1580, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center), then Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>関白の位をめぐり二条昭実と口論（関白相論）となり、菊亭晴季の蠢動で、豊臣秀吉に関白就任の口実を与えてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got into an argument with Akizane NIJO over the position of Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor) (it is called &quot;Kanpaku Soron&quot;) and provided Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI an excuse for assuming the position of Kanpaku due to the shundo(maneuver) by Harusue KIKUTEI.</e>
<cmt>関白相論→Kanpaku Soron[定訳不明。直前で内容が説明されているので、この語の後に入れる説明は省きました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He got into an argument with Akizane NIJO over the position of Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor), an incident known as the &quot;Kanpaku Soron&quot;, which, following maneuvering by Harusue KIKUTEI, provided Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI with an excuse for assuming the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;(it is called &quot;Kanpaku Soron&quot;)&quot;→&quot;, an incident known as the &quot;Kanpaku Soron&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;,which&quot;&quot;due to the shundo(maneuver) by Harusue KIKUTEI&quot;→&quot;following maneuvering by Harusue KIKUTE&quot; and movedAdded &quot;with&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He got into an argument with Akizane NIJO over the position of Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor), an incident known as the &quot;Kanpaku Soron,&quot; which, following maneuvering by Harusue KIKUTEI, provided Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI with an excuse for assuming the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>カンマを位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>実に藤原氏一門以外の者が関白についたのは、秀吉と甥の豊臣秀次だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, only Hideyoshi and his nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI were the persons who assumed the position of Kanpaku other than the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Hideyoshi and his nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, were the only people to assume the position of Kanpaku not from the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt>Added commaMoved &quot;only&quot;&quot;who assumed&quot;→&quot;to assume&quot;&quot;other than&quot;→&quot;not from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Hideyoshi and his nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, were the only people to assume the position of Kanpaku not from the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>clanを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>秀吉が秀次に関白位を譲ったことに、内心、穏やかではなく、文禄元年(1592年)正月に左大臣を辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was privately upset by the fact that Hideyoshi transferred the position of kanpaku to Hidetsugu and resigned from the position of Sadaijin in January, 1592.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutada was privately upset by the fact that Hideyoshi transferred the position of Kanpaku to Hidetsugu and resigned from the position of Sadaijin in January, 1592.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He&quot;→&quot;Nobutada&quot;Capitalised &apos;k&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutada was privately upset by the fact that Hideyoshi transferred the position of Kanpaku to Hidetsugu and resigned from the position of Sadaijin in February, 1592.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>信尹は、幼い頃から父とともに地方で過ごし、帰京後も公家よりも信長の小姓らと仲良くする機会が多かったために武士に憧れていたという（天正18年（1590年）に書かれた菊亭晴季あての手紙）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Nobutada yearned for samurai since he spent his early life in the provinces with his father and had more opportunities to get along with Nobunaga&apos;s pageboys than with the court nobles after he went back to Kyoto (written in the letter to Harusue KIKUTEI in 1590).</e>
<cmt>小姓→pageboy[英辞郎 on the WEB]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a letter received by Harusue KIKUTEI in 1590, it was said that Nobutada, who spent his early years in the provinces and even after returning to Kyoto had more opportunities to make friends with Nobunaga&apos;s pageboys than with the nobles, admired the samurai.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a letter received by Harusue KIKUTEI in 1590, it was said that Nobutada, who spent his early years in the provinces and even after returning to Kyoto had more opportunities to make friends with Nobunaga&apos;s pageboys than with the nobles, admired the samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>秀吉が朝鮮出兵の兵を起こすや否や、文禄元年12月に自身も朝鮮に渡海するため京都を出奔し肥前名護屋に赴いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as Hideyoshi directed his forces against Korea, he ran away from Kyoto and went off to Hizen Nagoya in order to cross the sea to Korea in December, 1592.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as Hideyoshi directed his forces against Korea, he ran away from Kyoto and went off to Hizen Nagoya in order to cross the sea to Korea in December, 1592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as Hideyoshi directed his forces against Korea, he ran away from Kyoto and went off to Hizen Nagoya in order to cross the sea to Korea in January, 1593 (December, 1592 in lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後陽成天皇は宸襟を悩ましたてまつり、勅書を秀吉に賜って信尹の渡海をくい止めようとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Goyozei puzzled over the event and sent a chokusho (an official document from Emperor) to Hideyoshi to prevent Nobutada from crossing the sea.</e>
<cmt>「宸襟」という名詞を使うと文章が不自然になるため、「頭を悩ませていた」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Goyozei puzzled over the event and sent an imperial rescript to Hideyoshi to prevent Nobutada from crossing the sea.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a chokusho (an official document from Emperor)&quot;→&quot;an imperial rescript&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Goyozei puzzled over the event and sent an imperial rescript to Hideyoshi to prevent Nobutada from crossing the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>廷臣としては余りに奔放な行動であり、更に菊亭晴季らが讒言（前述の手紙には「関白が豊臣氏の世襲になるならばせめて内覧任命を希望したい」という文言が入っていた事が問題になったと言われている）したため、文禄3年(1594年)4月についに後陽成天皇の勅勘を蒙る羽目に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his conduct was too bold for a retainer of the Imperial Court, in addition, Harusue KIKUTEI made zangen (a false charge) (it is said that the foregoing letter included a phrase like &quot;If the position of Kanpaku is transferred by succession, I hope to assign him at least as Nairan (a position of the person who see documents sent for the Emperor in advance)</e>
<cmt>内覧→Nairan (a position of the person who see documents sent for the Emperor in advance)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His conduct, which was too bold for a courtier, and a false accusation by Harusue KIKUTEI (it is said that the sentence, &quot;If the position of Kanpaku is transferred by succession, I hope to be assigned at least as Nairan (the person who checked documents before they were given to the Emperor)&quot; included in the afore-mentioned letter caused the problem) led the Emperor to censure Nobutada, leaving him in a difficult position.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Since&quot;Added &quot;, which&quot;&quot;retainer of the Imperial Court&quot;→&quot;courtier&quot;&quot;in addition, Harusue KIKUTEI made zangen (a false charge)&quot;&quot;and a false accusation by Harusue KIKUTEI&quot;&quot;foregoing&quot;→&quot;afore-mentioned&quot;&quot;a phrase like&quot;→&quot;the sentence&quot;&quot;to assign him&quot;→&quot;to be assigned&quot;Changed explanation of NairanAdded &quot;caused the problem&quot;Added &quot;ed the Emperor to censure Nobutada, leaving him in a difficult position.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His conduct, which was too bold for a courtier, and a false accusation by Harusue KIKUTEI (it is said that the sentence, &apos;If the position of Kanpaku is transferred by succession, I hope to be assigned at least as Nairan (the person who checked documents before they were given to the Emperor)&apos; included in the afore-mentioned letter caused the problem) led the Emperor to censure Nobutada in May 1594, leaving him in a difficult position.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>信尹は、薩摩国坊津に3年間配流となり、その間の事情は、信尹の日記「三藐院記」に詳述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutada had been exiled to Bonotsu, Satsuma Province for 3 years and the things happened during that period are described in detail in Nobutada&apos;s diary, &quot;Sanmyakuinki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「配流」は日本語のローマ字表記不要と判断し、&quot;exile&quot;のみを使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutada was exiled to Bonotsu, Satsuma Province for 3 years and the things that happened during that period are described in detail in Nobutada&apos;s diary, &quot;Sanmyakuinki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>&quot;had been&quot;→&quot;was&quot;Added &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutada was exiled to Bonotsu, Satsuma Province for three years and the things that happened during that period are described in detail in Nobutada&apos;s diary, &apos;Sanmyakuinki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>遠い九州での暮らしは心細くもあったが、一方で島津義久から滞在中、厚遇を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he felt lonely living in distant Kyushu, he was received warmly by Yoshihisa SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he felt lonely living in distant Kyushu, he was made to feel welcome by Yoshihisa SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>&quot;While&quot;→&quot;Although&quot;&quot;received warmly&quot;→&quot;made to feel welcome&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he felt lonely living in distant Kyushu, he was made to feel welcome by Yoshihisa SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>慶長元年(1596年)9月勅許が下り京都に戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 1596, he got chokkyo (permission by Emperor) to go back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, 1596, received permission from the Emperor to go back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;got chokkyo (permission by Emperor)&quot;→&quot;received permission from the Emperor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1596, Nobutada received permission from the Emperor to go back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>慶長6年(1601年)左大臣に復職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601, he returned to the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601, he returned to the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601, he returned to the position of Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>慶長10年(1605年)には念願の関白となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1605, he assumed the long-cherishedposition of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1605, he assumed the long-cherishedposition of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1605, he assumed the long-cherishedposition of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>慶長19年(1614年)11月25日薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on November 25, in 1614.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on November 25, 1614.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on December 25, 1614.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>享年50。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 50.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 50 years old.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;His age at death&quot;Added &quot;He&quot;, &quot;years old&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 50 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>京都東福寺に葬られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried in Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>信尹には嗣子がいなかったので、後陽成天皇第4皇子で信尹の妹中和門院前子の産んだ近衛信尋を名のり継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Nobutada had no shishi (successor), the Emperor Goyozei&apos;s forth son whose mother was Chuwamonin Sakiko, a younger sister of Nobutada, was named Nobuhiro KONOE and succeeded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Nobutada had no successor, Emperor Goyozei&apos;s fourth son, whose mother was Chuwamonin Sakiko, a younger sister of Nobutada, was named Nobuhiro KONOE and made heir.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;shishi&quot;, brackets, &quot;the&quot;Spelling of &quot;fourth&quot;Added comma&quot;succeeded&quot;→&quot;made heir&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Nobutada had no successor, Emperor Goyozei&apos;s fourth son, whose mother was Chuwamonin Sakiko, a younger sister of Nobutada, was named Nobuhiro KONOE and made heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>書、和歌、連歌、絵画の諸道に優れた才能を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He showed exceptional talent in calligraphy, waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem), renga (linked verse) and painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He showed exceptional talent in calligraphy, waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem), renga (linked verse) and painting.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He&quot;→&quot;Nobutada&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He showed exceptional talent in calligraphy, waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem), renga (linked verse) and painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>特に書道は尊円流を学び、更にこれを発展させて一派を形成し、近衛流、または三藐院流と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, for calligraphy, he learned Sonen school (style) and developed a manner of his own called Konoe school(style) or Sanmyakuin school(style).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was particularly known for calligraphy, having learned the Sonen school and developed a manner of his own called the Konoe school or the Sanmyakuin school.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In particular, for calligraphy, he&quot;→&quot;He was particularly known for calligraphy, having&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;(style)&quot;&quot;manner&quot;→&quot;style&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;(style)&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;(style)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was particularly known for calligraphy, having learned the Sonen school and developed a manner of his own called the Konoe school or the Sanmyakuin school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>本阿弥光悦、松花堂昭乗とともに「寛永の三筆」と後世、能書を称えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was praised for his nosho (skillful penmanship) together with Koetsu HONAMI and Shojo SHOKADO and they were called &quot;Three great calligraphers in Kanei (a period from 1624 to 1643 in Japan)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>寛永→Kanei (a period from 1624 to 1643 in Japan)[カッコ書きで説明を入れました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was praised for his skillful brushwork and, together with Koetsu HONAMI and Shojo SHOKADO, was one of the &quot;Three great calligraphers of Kanei period&quot;.</e>
<cmt>&quot;nosho (skillful penmanship)&quot;→&quot;skillful brushwork&quot;- not sure if this a good word but as Japanese calligraphy doesn&apos;t use pens, &quot;penmanship&quot; sounds a bit strangeAdded &quot;and&quot;, commas&quot;and they were called&quot;→&quot;was one of the&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;of the&quot;Added &quot;period&quot;Deleted &quot; (a period from 1624 to 1643 in Japan)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was praised for his skillful brushwork and, together with Koetsu HONAMI and Shojo SHOKADO, was one of the &apos;Three great calligraphers of Kanei era.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Himazin(id:22034), こぶまき(id:38278), 岡部碩道(id:182846), 伏儀(id:142093), 蔭人(id:80171), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), うあち(id:17332), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>