<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉良貞家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaie KIRA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaie KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaie KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉良 貞家（きら さだいえ、生没年不詳）は室町時代初期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaie KIRA (dates of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaie KIRA (dates of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaie KIRA (dates of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三河国幡豆郡吉良荘（愛知県幡豆郡吉良町）の前期東条吉良氏の第三代吉良経家の子で、奥州管領吉良氏の初代となり、陸奥国の南朝 (日本)勢力の鎮撫に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Tsuneie KIRA, the third head of the Oshu (Musashi) Kira clan in Kiranosho, Hazu County, Mikawa Province (Kira-cho, Hazu County, Aichi Prefecture) and became the first head of Kira clan of Oshu Kanrei (governor of Oshu [Mutsu province]), working towards repression of the Southern Court (Japan) force in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>吉良氏奥州（武蔵）吉良氏→意味が重複しているため「奥州（武蔵）吉良氏」と解釈し訳しました。（現在のwikipediaでは当該部分は「前期東条吉良氏」となっていますが、原文に沿い訳しました）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Tsuneie KIRA, the third head of the Oshu (Musashi) Kira clan in Kiranosho, Hazu County, Mikawa Province (Kira-cho, Hazu County, Aichi Prefecture) and became the first head of Kira clan of Oshu Kanrei (governor of Oshu [Mutsu province]), working towards repression of the Southern Court (Japan) force in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Tsuneie KIRA, the third head of the early Tojo-Kira clan in Kiranosho, Hazu County, Mikawa Province (Kira-cho, Hazu County, Aichi Prefecture) and became the first head of Kira clan of Oshu Kanrei (governor of Oshu [Mutsu province]), working towards repression of the Southern Court (Japan) force in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>原文でリンク箇所が抽出されていた箇所を修正し、訳文にも反映しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>官途名は馬寮・修理権大夫・右京大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official title of kanto (government service) was Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses), Shuri gon no daibu (Provisional Master in the Office of Palace Repairs), and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official title of kanto (government service) was Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses), Shuri gon no daibu (Provisional Master in the Office of Palace Repairs), and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official title of kanto (government service) was Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses), Shuri gon no daibu (Provisional Master in the Office of Palace Repairs), and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>前期東条吉良氏の経家の嫡子として三河国幡豆郡の東条城に居城したと考えられるが、この時期の詳細については史料が乏しく不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a legitimate child of Tsuneie of the early Tojo-Kira clan, he is considered to have lived in Tojo-jo Castle in Hazu County, Mikawa Province, but the details about this period is unknown because of lack of historical materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a legitimate child of Tsuneie of the early Tojo-Kira clan, he is considered to have lived in Tojo-jo Castle in Hazu County, Mikawa Province, but the details about this period is unknown because of lack of historical materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a legitimate child of Tsuneie of the early Tojo-Kira clan, he is considered to have lived in Tojo-jo Castle in Hazu County, Mikawa Province, but the details about this period is unknown because of lack of historical materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>元弘の乱では他の吉良一族とともに足利宗家に従ったと考えられ、建武の新政期に足利尊氏の弟・足利直義に従い関東に下向、建武 (日本)元年正月（1334年2月）に関東廂番（かんとうひさしばん）六番衆の第三番の頭人に任ぜられ、成良親王警護の任を負った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Genko War, he is considered to have followed the head family of Ashikaga along with the other Kira family members, at Kenmu Restoration, he went down to Kanto region, following Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, younger brother of Takauji ASHIKAGA, and he was appointed as the third tonin (the director) of the six banshu (guards) of Kanto Hisashi ban (people who keep the night watch staying under the eaves of building) in February 1334, getting the assignment to guard Imperial Prince Nariyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Genko War, he is considered to have followed the head family of Ashikaga along with other Kira family members, at Kenmu Restoration, he went down to Kanto region, following Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, younger brother of Takauji ASHIKAGA, and he was appointed as the third tonin (the director) of the six banshu (guards) of Kanto Hisashi ban (people who keep the night watch staying under the eaves of building) in February 1334, getting the assignment to guard Imperial Prince Nariyoshi.</e>
<cmt>the other Kira family members --&gt; other Kira family members</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Genko War, he is considered to have followed the head family of Ashikaga along with other Kira family members, at Kenmu Restoration, he went down to Kanto region, following Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, younger brother of Takauji ASHIKAGA, and he was appointed as the third tonin (the director) of the six banshu (guards) of Kanto Hisashi ban (people who keep the night watch staying under the eaves of building) in February 1334, getting the assignment to guard Imperial Prince Nariyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同僚には一族の吉良満義（西条吉良氏）がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His colleagues included Mitsuyoshi KIRA (Mikawa-Kira clan) of the same family.</e>
<cmt>吉良満義→http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%90%89%E8%89%AF%E6%BA%80%E7%BE%A9参照しました。吉良氏三河吉良氏→意味が重複しているため「三河吉良氏」と解釈し訳しました。（現在のwikipediaでは当該部分は「西条吉良氏」となっていますが、原文に沿い訳しました）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His colleagues included Mitsuyoshi KIRA (Mikawa-Kira clan) of the same family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His colleagues included Mitsuyoshi KIRA (Saijo-Kira clan) of the same family.</e>
<cmt>原文でリンク箇所が抽出されていた箇所を修正し、訳文にも反映しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>建武2年（1335年）の政変に足利尊氏に従い畿内・西国を転戦、南朝軍に追われ九州に出奔していた尊氏が反攻で京都を回復すると、因幡・但馬両国の守護職に任じられまた、室町幕府評定衆・五番制内談衆の二番頭人をも歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Coup of 1335, He followed Takauji ASHIKAGA and moved from place to place to fight in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Saigoku (western part of Japan [esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki]), when Takauji who had run away from the Southern Court army and hidden out in Kyushu recovered Kyoto by counterattack, he was appointed as shugoshiki (provincial constable) of Inaba Province and Tajima Province, and also held a position of the second tonin of the hyojoshu (a member of the Council of State) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and naidanshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) with five turn system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Coup of 1335, He followed Takauji ASHIKAGA and moved from place to place to fight in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Saigoku (western part of Japan [esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki]); when Takauji, who had run away from the Southern Court army and hidden out in Kyushu, recovered Kyoto by counterattack, he was appointed as shugoshiki (provincial constable) of Inaba Province and Tajima Province, and also held a position of the second tonin of the hyojoshu (a member of the Council of State) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and naidanshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) of five-turn system.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, when Takauji who had run away from the Southern Court army and hidden out in Kyushu&quot; を &quot;; when Takauji, who had run away from the Southern Court army and hidden out in Kyushu,&quot; に変更with five turn systemを　of five-turn systemに変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Coup of 1335, He followed Takauji ASHIKAGA and moved from place to place to fight in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Saigoku (western part of Japan [usually referring to Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki]); when Takauji, who had run away from the Southern Court army and hidden out in Kyushu, recovered Kyoto by counterattack, he was appointed as shugoshiki (provincial constable) of Inaba Province and Tajima Province, and also held a position of the second tonin of the hyojoshu (a member of the Council of State) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and naidanshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) of five-turn system.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>貞和元年（1345年）、畠山国氏 (奥州管領)とともに奥州管領に補任され、奥州国府の多賀城に下向・着任、奥州を拠点に反北朝 (日本)活動を展開する北畠氏等南朝軍と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1345, he was appointed as Oshu Kanrei along with Kuniuji HATAKEYAMA, and went down to Taga-jo Castle, the kokufu (provincial office) of Oshu to assume the post, fighting against the Southern Court army including the Kitabatake clan which had been developing anti-Northern Court activities based in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>畠山国氏 (奥州管領)→()内の部分は意味が重複するため訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1345, he was appointed as Oshu Kanrei along with Kuniuji HATAKEYAMA, and went down to Taga-jo Castle, the kokufu (provincial office) of Oshu to assume the post, where he fought against the Southern Court army including the Kitabatake clan which had been developing anti-Northern Court activities based in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>fighting against を where he fought against に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1345, he was appointed as Oshu Kanrei along with Kuniuji HATAKEYAMA, and went down to Taga-jo Castle, the kokufu (provincial office) of Oshu to assume the post, where he fought against the Southern Court army including the Kitabatake clan which had been developing anti-Northern Court activities based in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>観応の擾乱には直義方として尊氏方の畠山氏と対立、観応2年2月（1351年3月）畠山高国・国氏父子を陸奥岩切城（現宮城県利府町）に攻めて自刃させたが、北朝方の内訌の機に乗じた南朝方北畠顕信に攻められ一時、多賀城を退去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Kanno Disturbance, on Tadayoshi&apos;s side, he confronted the Hatakeyama clan who was on Takauji&apos;s side, in March 1351, he attacked Kuniuji HATAKEYAMA and his father Takakuni HATAKEYAMA at Iwakiri-jo Castle in Mutsu Province (present-day Rifu-cho, Miyagi Prefecture) and made them commit suicide, but he was once forced to leave Taga-jo Castle when he was attacked by Akinobu KITABATAKE of the Southern Court who took advantage of infighting in the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>畠山高国→http://kotobank.jp/word/%E7%95%A0%E5%B1%B1%E9%AB%98%E5%9B%BD参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Kanno Disturbance, on Tadayoshi&apos;s side, he confronted the Hatakeyama clan who was on Takauji&apos;s side, in March 1351, he attacked Kuniuji HATAKEYAMA and his father Takakuni HATAKEYAMA at Iwakiri-jo Castle in Mutsu Province (present-day Rifu-cho, Miyagi Prefecture) and made them commit suicide, but he was temporarily forced to leave Taga-jo Castle when he was attacked by Akinobu KITABATAKE of the Southern Court who took advantage of infighting in the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>he was once forced --&gt; he was temporarily forced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Kanno Disturbance, on Tadayoshi&apos;s side, he confronted the Hatakeyama clan who was on Takauji&apos;s side, in March 1351, he attacked Kuniuji HATAKEYAMA and his father Takakuni HATAKEYAMA at Iwakiri-jo Castle in Mutsu Province (present-day Rifu-cho, Miyagi Prefecture) and made them commit suicide, but he was temporarily forced to leave Taga-jo Castle when he was attacked by Akinobu KITABATAKE of the Southern Court who took advantage of infighting in the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし文和元年3月（1352年4月）に多賀城を奪回、翌年5月（1353年6月）には南朝方の拠点宇津峰城を陥落させて奥州の南朝勢力を崩壊させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in April 1352, he recaptured Taga-jo Castle, and in June 1353, he took control of Uzumine-jo Castle, a stronghold of the Southern Court, wiping out the Southern Court force in Oshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in April 1352, he recaptured Taga-jo Castle, and in June 1353, he took control of Uzumine-jo Castle, a stronghold of the Southern Court, wiping out the Southern Court force in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in April 1352, he recaptured Taga-jo Castle, and in June 1353, he took control of Uzumine-jo Castle, a stronghold of the Southern Court, wiping out the Southern Court force in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後の動向は文和3年（1354年）以降には貞家の現れる史料が存在しなくなるため、この頃に死没したと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for what happened to him after that, there is no historical materials about Sadaie after 1354, so he seems to have died around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for what happened to him after that, there are no historical materials about Sadaie after 1354, so he seems to have died around that time.</e>
<cmt>there is no historical materials --&gt; there are no historical materials</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for what happened to him after that, there are no historical materials about Sadaie after 1354, so he seems to have died around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 故城一片之月(id:109503), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>