<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>右田弘詮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki MIGITA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki MIGITA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki MIGITA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>右田 弘詮（みぎた ひろあき、生年不詳 - 大永3年10月24日 (旧暦)（1523年12月1日））は戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki MIGITA (year of birth unknown - December 1, 1523) was a military commander in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki MIGITA (year of birth unknown - December 1, 1523) was a military commander in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki MIGITA (year of birth unknown - December 1, 1523) was a military commander in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>ウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに（日本）を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大内氏の重臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a senior vassal of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a senior vassal of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a senior vassal of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は多々良氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original surname was the Tatara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was originally of the Tatara clan.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally of the Tatara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家系は百済聖明王を祖とするという渡来人氏族　多々良氏の流れを汲むという大内氏の庶流　右田氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family lineage was the Migita clan, a branch line of the Ouchi clan which was allegedly in the line of the Tatara clan, a clan of the settlers of which ancestor was allegedly King Shomyoo in Baekje.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family lineage was the Migita clan, a branch line of the Ouchi clan which was allegedly in the line of the Tatara clan, a clan of the settlers of which ancestor was allegedly King Shomyoo in Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family lineage was the Migita clan, a branch line of the Ouchi clan which was allegedly in the line of the Tatara clan, a clan of the settlers of which ancestor was allegedly King Shomyoo in Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弘詮は右田氏の庶流　陶氏の出身であるが宗家である右田氏を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki was from the Sue clan, a branch line of the Migita clan, but inherited the Migita clan which was the head family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki was from the Sue clan, a branch line of the Migita clan, but inherited the Migita clan which was the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki was from the Sue clan, a branch line of the Migita clan, but inherited the Migita clan which was the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>陶弘房の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of Hirofusa SUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Hirofusa SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Hirofusa SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>母は仁保盛郷の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Morisato NIHO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Morisato NIHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Morisato NIHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>陶弘護の同母弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki was a younger maternal half-brother of Hiromori SUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki was a younger maternal half-brother of Hiromori SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki was a younger maternal half-brother of Hiromori SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>官位は安房守従五位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court rank was Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>長門国諏訪山城城主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the lord of Suwayama Castle in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the lord of Suwayama Castle in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Suwayama-jo Castle in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同じく長門矢田城城主とも伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was also the lord of Yata Castle in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was also the lord of Yata Castle in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was also the lord of Yata-jo Castle in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>陶（すえ）弘詮・朝倉 弘詮とも称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki was also called himself Hiroaki SUE or Hiroaki ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki was also called himself Hiroaki SUE or Hiroaki ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki was also called himself Hiroaki SUE or Hiroaki ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>子に陶隆康、陶興就。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons were Takayasu SUE and Okinari SUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons were Takayasu SUE and Okinari SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons were Takayasu SUE and Okinari SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>娘は陶興房の妻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter became a wife of Okifusa SUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter became a wife of Okifusa SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter became a wife of Okifusa SUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>Terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>大内政弘・大内義興の二代にわたって仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki served two generations of Masahiro OUCHI and Masahiro OUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki served the two generations of Masahiro OUCHI and Masahiro OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki served the two generations of Masahiro OUCHI and Yoshioki OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>二度目の Masahiro→Yoshioki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>父陶弘房は同族の右田弘篤の跡を継いでいたが、その兄陶弘正が戦死したため、本性の陶氏に戻り、寛正6年（1465年）にその子弘詮に右田家を継がせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirofusa SUE, his father, had inherited Hiroatsu MIGITA of the same clan, but returned to the original family name, SUE, because Hiromasa SUE, his older brother, was killed in the war, and transferred the MIGITA family to Hiroaki, his son, in 1465.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirofusa SUE, his father, had succeeded Hiroatsu MIGITA of the same clan but returned to the original family name of Sue because Hiromasa SUE, his older brother, was killed in battle, and transferred the MIGITA family to his son Hiroaki in 1465.</e>
<cmt>the war &gt; battle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirofusa SUE, his father, had succeeded Hiroatsu MIGITA of the same clan but returned to the original family name of Sue because Hiromasa SUE, his older brother, was killed in battle, and transferred the Migita family to his son Hiroaki in 1465.</e>
<cmt>二度目の MIGITA→Migita</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>文明 (日本)10年（1478年）7月、兄・弘護とともに九州に渡り、少弐氏と戦ってこれを滅ぼす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1478, Hiroaki moved to Kyusyu with Hiromori, his older brother, to fight with the Shoni clan and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1478, Hiroaki moved to Kyusyu with Hiromori, his older brother, to fight with the Shoni clan and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1478, Hiroaki moved to Kyusyu with Hiromori, his older brother, to fight with the Shoni clan and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>翌年兄に代わって筑前国の守護代となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Shugodai (deputy military governor) in Chikuzen Province replacing with his older brother next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, he replaced his older brother as Shugodai (deputy military governor) of Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, he replaced his older brother as Shugodai (deputy military governor) of Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>文明14年（1482年）、兄の陶弘護が28歳の若さで不慮の死を遂げ、その子達が幼なかったため、大内政弘の命により本姓の陶氏に戻り陶兵庫頭を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1482, Hiromori SUE, his older brother, unexpectedly died at the young age of twenty-eight and his children were young, therefore, Hiroaki returned to the original family name, SUE, and used the name of Sue Hyogo no kami (Sue, the head of the armory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1482, his older brother Hiromori SUE, unexpectedly died at the young age of twenty-eight, and as his children were still young, Hiroaki returned to the original family name of Sue and used the name of Sue Hyogo no kami (Sue, the head of the armory).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1482, his older brother Hiromori SUE, unexpectedly died at the young age of 28, and as his children were still young, Hiroaki returned to the original family name of Sue and used the name of Sue Hyogo no kami (Sue, the head of the armory).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>兄・弘護の三男の陶興房が成人するまで番代（当主代行・後見人）を務めて周防国及び筑前両国の守護代職を務め、主君・大内義興の上洛中は留守を守って領内の政務を執り行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki served as Bandai (deputy and guardian of the family head) until Okifusa SUE, the third son of Hiromori, his older brother, attained manhood and also as Shugodai (deputy military governor) in Suo and Chikuzen Provinces, while holding a fort and attending to government affairs in the domain when Yoshioki OUCHI, his lord, went up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki served as Bandai (deputy and guardian of the family head) until Okifusa SUE, the third son of Hiromori, his older brother, attained manhood and also as Shugodai (deputy military governor) in Suo and Chikuzen Provinces, while holding a fort and attending to government affairs in the domain when Yoshioki OUCHI, his lord, visited Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>went up to &gt; visited</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki served as Bandai (deputy and guardian of the family head) until Okifusa SUE, the third son of Hiromori, his older brother, attained manhood and also as Shugodai in Suo and Chikuzen Provinces, while holding a fort and attending to government affairs in the domain when Yoshioki OUCHI, his lord, visited Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>系図類には「暫称陶氏」と書かれ、右田姓に復したとされているが、現存の古文書ではその事実を確認できず、陶姓を通したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written as &apos;Sue clan, the tentative name&apos; in the family tree and others and it is said that he returned to the family name, MIGITA, but it is not possible to confirm that fact in the existing old documents, and thereby it is considered that he kept the family name, SUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name is written as &apos;Sue clan, the tentative name&apos; in family trees and it is said that he returned to the family name of MIGITA, but it is not possible to confirm this using surviving documents, and it is therefore considered that he kept the family name SUE.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name is written as &apos;Sue clan, the tentative name&apos; in family trees and it is said that he returned to the family name of Migita, but it is not possible to confirm this using surviving documents, and it is therefore considered that he kept the family name Sue.</e>
<cmt>MIGITA→MigitaSUE→Sue</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>初め中務大輔を名乗っていたが、永正15年（1518年）には従五位下安房国守に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first Hiroaki called himself Nakatsukasasho (Ministry of Central Affairs), but was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Awa no kuni no kami (Governor of Awa Province) in 1518.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first Hiroaki took the name Nakatsukasasho (Ministry of Central Affairs), but was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Awa no kuni no kami (Governor of Awa Province) in 1518.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first Hiroaki took the name Nakatsukasa no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs), but was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Awa no kuni no kami (Governor of Awa Province) in 1518.</e>
<cmt>中務省→中務大輔　ウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、前年に家督を息子の隆康に譲っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that he transferred the family estate to Takayasu, his son, in the previous year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is said that he transferred the family estate to his son Takayasu in the previous year.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that he transferred the family estate to his son Takayasu in the previous year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>後に（鳳梧真幻）昌瑞と号し、死後の戒名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he called himself (Hogosingen) Shosui and this became his Buddhist name after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later took the name (Hogosingen) Shosui and this became his Buddhist name after his death.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later took the name (Hogosingen) Shosui and this became his Buddhist name after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>大永3年（1523年）10月24日、筑前国筥﨑において病の為没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki died at Hakozaki of Chikuzen Province due to illness in October 24, 1523.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki died at Hakozaki in Chikuzen Province due to illness in October 24, 1523.</e>
<cmt>of &gt; in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki died at Hakozaki in Chikuzen Province due to illness in December 1, 1523.</e>
<cmt>没年を文頭どおりに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>弘詮が後見をした陶興房の妻は弘詮の娘で、その間に生まれた男子が陶晴賢（隆房）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wife of Okifusa SUE, to whom Hiroaki acted as guardian, was his daughter, and a boy born between them was Harukata SUE (Takafusa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wife of Okifusa SUE, to whom Hiroaki acted as guardian was his daughter and her son was Harukata SUE (Takafusa).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wife of Okifusa SUE, to whom Hiroaki acted as guardian was his daughter and her son was Harukata SUE (Takafusa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>弘詮の死から28年後に、この晴賢は主君・大内義隆（義興の子）に対して謀反を起こし、義隆の側近であった弘詮の息子・隆康とその嫡男・隆弘はこれに抵抗するも討死することになる（大寧寺の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-eight years after the death of Hiroaki, this Harutaka rebelled against Yoshitaka OUCHI (the son of Yoshioki), his lord, and Takayasu, the son of Hiroaki who was a close associate of Yoshitaka, and Takahiro, Takayasu&apos;s legitimate son, resisted this, but died on the battle field (Taineiji no hen, the revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twenty-eight years after the death of Hiroaki, this Harutaka rebelled against his lord Yoshitaka OUCHI (the son of Yoshioki) and Takayasu, the son of Hiroaki who was a close associate of Yoshitaka, and Takahiro, Takayasu&apos;s legitimate son, resisted this, but died on the battlefield (Taineiji no hen, the revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twenty-eight years after the death of Hiroaki, this Harutaka rebelled against his lord Yoshitaka OUCHI (the son of Yoshioki) and Takayasu, the son of Hiroaki who was a close associate of Yoshitaka, and Takahiro, Takayasu&apos;s legitimate son, resisted this, but died on the battlefield (the revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt>Taineiji no hen　削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>『吾妻鏡』の収集・校訂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collection and revision of &quot;Azumakagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collection and revision of &quot;Azumakagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collection and revision of &quot;Azumakagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>右田弘詮（陶弘詮）は文人としても知られ、宗祇や猪苗代兼載といった当時一流の文化人と親交があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki MIGITA (Hiroaki SUE) was also known as a man of literature and had a close friendship with the first-class men of culture of that time such as Sogi and Kensai INAWASHIRO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki MIGITA (Hiroaki SUE) was also known as a man of literature and had a close friendship with the leading men of culture of the time such as Sogi and Kensai INAWASHIRO.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki MIGITA (Hiroaki SUE) was also known as a man of literature and had a close friendship with the leading men of culture of the time such as Sogi and Kensai INAWASHIRO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>弘詮はそれら文化人から「吾妻鏡と号す」「関東記録」があり「文武諸道の亀鑑」と聞いていたがなかなか目にすることが出来なかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki had heard that &apos;it was called Azumakagami&apos; and there was &apos;Kanto Record&apos; which was &apos;the paragon of all arts&apos; from those men of culture, but it was very hard to see with his own eyes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki had heard from these men of culture that &apos;there is a record of the Kanto region entitled &quot;Azumakagami&quot;&apos; which was &apos;a paragon of the literary and military arts&apos; but it is said that he was unable to see it for himself.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki had heard from these men of culture that &apos;there is a record of the Kanto region entitled &quot;Azumakagami&quot;&apos; which was &apos;a paragon of the literary and military arts&apos; but it is said that he was unable to see it for himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし文亀元年（1501年）頃、その写本42帖を手に入れることが出来、数人の筆生を雇い書き写させて秘蔵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he could obtain forty-two chapters of its copy around 1501, hired several amanuenses for copying them and stashed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he was able to obtain a 42 volume copy circa 1501 and employed several writers to transcribe the text which he hid.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he was able to obtain a 42 volume copy circa 1501 and employed several writers to transcribe the text and he hid them.</e>
<cmt>which の前にカンマ （カンマがないと、秘蔵していたtextを写本させたことになると思います。）, which he hid.→and he hid them.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>それは治承4年（1180年）から文永3年（1266年）と、現在知られる範囲ではあったが、尚その間に20数年分の欠落があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the currently known range, that is, from 1180 to 1266, and moreover, the portion of twenty years or more was missed between it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The text covered of the currently known period from 1180 to 1266 but there is a period of more than 20 years missing.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The text covered of the currently known period from 1180 to 1266 but there is a period of more than 20 years missing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>このため弘詮は諸国を巡礼する僧徒、または往還の賓客に託して、京はもちろん畿内・東国・北陸に至まで尋ねまわり、ようやくにして欠落分の内5帖を手に入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Hiroaki inquired not only in Kyoto, but also up to Kinai, Togoku, and Hokuriku regions entrusting monks on a pilgrimage to various districts or guests who came and went, and finally obtained five chapters of the missing portion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Hiroaki entrusted monks on pilgrimages throughout the country and guests who came and went as well as personally traveling to not only Kyoto but also as far as the Kinai, Togoku, and Hokuriku regions to finally obtain the five volumes of the missing portion.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Hiroaki entrusted monks on pilgrimages throughout the country and guests who came and went as well as personally traveling to not only Kyoto but also as far as the Kinai, Togoku, and Hokuriku regions to finally obtain the five volumes of the missing portion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これを最初の書写と同じ形式で書き写させて全47帖とし、その目次も兼ねて年譜1帖を書き下ろし全48帖とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroaki had them copy in the same format as that in the first transcription to make it the complete works of forty-seven chapters and newly wrote a chapter of the chronicle, also serving as the table of the contents, to make it those of forty-eight chapters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki had these volumes transcribed in the same format as the previously transcribed volumes to create a complete 47-volume set plus an additional contents and chronology volume to make 48 volumes.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki had these volumes transcribed in the same format as the previously transcribed volumes to create a complete 47-volume set plus an additional contents and chronology volume to make 48 volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>大永2年（1522年）9月5日のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in September 5, 1522.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was in September 5, 1522.</e>
<cmt>It &gt; This</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was in October 4, 1522.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その後書きにはこう記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described in the postscript as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The afterword of this collection is as follows.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The afterword of this collection is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>上記の大寧寺の変の後、難を逃れた隆康の次男・元弘は安芸国の毛利元就を頼った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the above Taineiji no hen, Motohiro, Takayasu&apos;s second son who got out of trouble, took refuge at Motonari MORI in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the above Taineiji no hen, Motohiro, Takayasu&apos;s second son who had escaped trouble took refuge with Motonari MORI in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the above revolt of Taineiji, Motohiro, Takayasu&apos;s second son who had escaped trouble took refuge with Motonari MORI in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>Taineiji no hen→the revolt of Taineiji</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この際に弘詮の『吾妻鏡』も毛利氏に献上され、元就の次男・吉川元春の子孫に伝わることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Azumakagami&quot; of Hiroaki was also presented to the Mori clan at that time, and consequently handed down to the descendants of Motoharu KIKKAWA, the second son of Motonari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroaki&apos;s &quot;Azumakagami&quot; was also presented to the Mori clan at that time, and consequently handed down to the descendants of Motoharu KIKKAWA, the second son of Motonari.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroaki&apos;s &quot;Azumakagami&quot; was also presented to the Mori clan at that time, and consequently handed down to the descendants of Motoharu KIKKAWA, the second son of Motonari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>そのため、弘詮の『吾妻鏡』は今日では“吉川本”と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, &quot;Azumakagami&quot; of Hiroaki is called &quot;Kikkawa bon&quot; (the copy of Azumakagami owned by the Kikkawa family) today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore Hiroaki&apos;s &quot;Azumakagami&quot; is called the &quot;Kikkawa bon&quot; (the copy of Azumakagami owned by the Kikkawa family) today.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore Hiroaki&apos;s &quot;Azumakagami&quot; is called the &quot;Kikkawa bon&quot; (the copy of Azumakagami owned by the Kikkawa family) today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>記事に3年分の欠損はあるが、現在では吾妻鏡の最善本と目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the portion of three years are missing, it is now regarded as the best document of Azumakagami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though a three year section is missing, it is now regarded as the best version Azumakagami.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though a three year section is missing, it is now regarded as the best version Azumakagami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 玄史生(id:43670), Yuanfei(id:105020), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), 水野白楓(id:22811), Ktmchi(id:113301), Im224(id:57113), Kuma83(id:31177), Suisui(id:69), Hatsune(id:26654), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>