<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>多賀高忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada TAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada TAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada TAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>多賀 高忠（たが たかただ、応永32年（1425年）－文明 (日本)18年8月17日 (旧暦)（1486年9月14日））は室町時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada TAGA (1425 – September 14, 1486) was a busho (military commander) in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada TAGA (1425 – September 14, 1486) was a busho (military commander) during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada TAGA (1425–September 23, 1486) was a busho (military commander) during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除。日付を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>多賀豊後守家当主で近江国京極氏の重臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was the head of the Taga Bungo no kami family and a senior vassal of the Kyogoku Clan of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the head of the Taga Bungo no kami family and a senior vassal of the Kyogoku Clan of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the head of the Taga Bungo no kami family and a senior vassal of the Kyogoku Clan of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>多賀高長の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada was the child of Takanaga TAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada was the child of Takanaga TAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada was the child of Takanaga TAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称新左衛門・豊後守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly referred to as Shizaemon or Bungo no kami (governor of Bung Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly referred to as Shizaemon or Bungo no kami (governor of Bung Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly referred to as Shinzaemon or Bungo no kami (governor of Bungo Province).</e>
<cmt>「新左衛門、豊後守」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>法号は宗本。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His hogo (Buddhist name) was Sohon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His hogo (Buddhist name) was Sohon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His hogo (Buddhist name) was Sohon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>号は大源。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada&apos;s mnemonic name was Daigen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada&apos;s mnemonic name was Daigen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada&apos;s mnemonic name was Daigen.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>2度に渡り侍所を務め、名所司代として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada twice served as a member of Samurai dokoro (the Board of Retainers) and was known as a fine shoshidai (representative of the Governor of the Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada twice served as a member of Samurai dokoro (the Board of Retainers) and was known as a fine shoshidai (representative of the Governor of the Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada twice served as a member of Samurai dokoro (the Board of Retainers) and was known as a fine shoshidai (representative of the Governor of the Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストにより修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>主君京極持清は実の従兄でもあり、その片腕として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada had an active career as the right-hand man of his lord and also his biological cousin Mochikiyo KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada had an active career as the right-hand man of his lord and also his biological cousin Mochikiyo KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada had an active career as the right-hand man of his lord and also his biological cousin Mochikiyo KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>寛正3年10月5日 (旧暦)（1462年10月27日）に京都侍所所司代を任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 27, 1462, Takatada was appointed as Samurai dokoro shoshi dai (a local governor of the Board of Retainers) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 27, 1462, Takatada was appointed as Samurai dokoro shoshi dai (a local governor of the Board of Retainers) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 5, 1462, Takatada was appointed as Samurai dokoro shoshi dai in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正。「侍所所司代」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、文正元年（1466年）暮れ、持清の失脚とともに解任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the year-end of 1466, however, with Mochikiyo&apos;s downfall, Takatada was removed from office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the year-end of 1466, however, with Mochikiyo&apos;s downfall, Takatada was removed from office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the year-end of 1466, however, with Mochikiyo&apos;s downfall, Takatada was removed from office.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>翌応仁元年（1467年）、応仁の乱が勃発すると持清と共に一万の兵を率いて細川勝元ら東軍に属し、西軍の六角高頼らを圧倒して、山城国に如意岳城を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1467, the following year, when the Onin War began, Takatada, along with Mochikiyo, led 10,000 soldiers to join the Eastern Camp including Katsumoto HOSOKAWA whereby overpowering the Western Camp including Takayori ROKKAKU and subsequently building Nyoigatake-jo Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1467, the following year, when the Onin War began, Takatada, along with Mochikiyo, led 10,000 soldiers to join the Eastern Camp including Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, overpowering the Western Camp including Takayori ROKKAKU and subsequently building Nyoigatake-jo Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1467, the following year, when the Onin War began, Takatada, along with Mochikiyo, led 10,000 soldiers to join the Eastern Camp including Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, overpowering the Western Camp including Takayori ROKKAKU and subsequently building Nyoigatake-jo Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>文明元年（1469年）には六角氏の本拠である観音寺城を一時制圧して征夷大将軍足利義政から直々に感状を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1469, Takatada temporarily conquered the headquarters of the Rokkaku clan Kannonji-jo Castle and was awarded citation directly from Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1469, Takatada temporarily conquered the headquarters of the Rokkaku clan Kannonji-jo Castle and was awarded a citation directly from Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1469, Takatada temporarily conquered the headquarters of the Rokkaku clan Kannonji-jo Castle and was awarded a citation directly from Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;) Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>「征夷大将軍」を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ところが、翌年に主君・持清が病死、遺児である京極政高を庇護して京極高清、京極政光、六角高頼、多賀宗直らの勢力に一時優勢を保つも文明4年（1472年）敗走、京極政高と共に越前国へ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, however, Takatada&apos;s lord Mochikiyo died from natural causes whereby taking Mochikiyo&apos;s posthumous child Masataka KYOGOKU under his wing and while temporarily having an advantage over the forces including Takakiyo KYOGOKU, Masamitsu KYOGOKU, Takayori ROKKAKU and Munenao TAGA, in 1472, Takatada retreated and fled to Echizen Province with Masataka KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, however, Takatada&apos;s lord Mochikiyo died from natural causes and he took Mochikiyo&apos;s posthumous child Masataka KYOGOKU under his wing and while temporarily having an advantage over the forces including Takakiyo KYOGOKU, Masamitsu KYOGOKU, Takayori ROKKAKU and Munenao TAGA, in 1472, Takatada retreated and fled to Echizen Province with Masataka KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, however, Takatada&apos;s lord Mochikiyo died from disease and he took Mochikiyo&apos;s posthumous child Masataka KYOGOKU under his wing and while temporarily having an advantage over the forces including Takakiyo KYOGOKU, Masamitsu KYOGOKU, Takayori ROKKAKU and Munenao TAGA, in 1472, Takatada retreated and fled to Echizen Province with Masataka KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正。「病死」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>文明7年（1475年）、出雲国の国人を擁して再起して六角高頼らと戦い勝利するが、西軍土岐成頼、斯波義廉が高頼方に付き敗北、三沢氏ら有力国衆を戦死させて敗退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1475, leading by local bushi of Izumo Province, Takatada came back to fight the enemies including Takayori ROKKAKU winning against them but was subsequently defeated with the Western Camp including Shigeyori TOKI and Yoshikado SHIBA joining the Takayori&apos;s side and various influential kunishu (local samurais) including the Misawa clan were killed in action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1475, led by local bushi of Izumo Province, Takatada came back to fight his enemies including Takayori ROKKAKU and won, but was subsequently defeated with the Western Camp, including Shigeyori TOKI and Yoshikado SHIBA joining Takayori&apos;s side and various influential kunishu (local samurais) including the Misawa clan, were killed in action.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1475, led by Kokujin (local samurai) of Izumo Province, Takatada came back to fight his enemies including Takayori ROKKAKU and won, but was subsequently defeated with the Western Camp, including Shigeyori TOKI and Yoshikado SHIBA joining Takayori&apos;s side and various influential kunishu (local samurais) including the Misawa clan, were killed in action.</e>
<cmt>「国人」を修正。アポストロフィを修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>文明9年（1477年）の応仁の乱終結後も本拠である近江国犬上郡に復帰できずに京都での隠棲生活を余儀なくされていたが、文明17年4月15日 (旧暦)（1485年5月28日）に室町幕府に召されて2度目の京都侍所所司代を任ぜられ、幕命を受け山城国内の土一揆を鎮圧して、京都市中の再建に尽力するも翌年没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Onin War ended in 1477, unable to return to his home base Inugami County, Omi Province, Takatada was forced to continue living in seclusion in Kyoto but, on May 28, 1485, was called over by the Muromachi Shogunate to be appointed as Samurai dokoro shoshi dai in Kyoto for the second time and although he performed services to rebuild Kyoto City such as, by order of the shogunate, suppressing a peasants&apos; uprising in Yamashiro Province, Takatada died the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Onin War ended in 1477, unable to return to his home base Inugami County, Omi Province, Takatada was forced to continue living in seclusion in Kyoto but, on May 28, 1485, was called by the Muromachi Shogunate to be appointed as Samurai dokoro shoshi dai in Kyoto for the second time and although he performed services to rebuild Kyoto City such as, by order of the shogunate, suppressing the peasants&apos; uprising in Yamashiro Province, Takatada died the following year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Onin War ended in 1477, unable to return to his home base Inugami County, Omi Province, Takatada was forced to continue living in seclusion in Kyoto but, on June 6, 1485, was called by the Muromachi Shogunate to be appointed as Samurai dokoro shoshi dai in Kyoto for the second time and although he performed services to rebuild Kyoto City such as, by order of the shogunate, suppressing the peasants&apos; uprising in Yamashiro Province, Takatada died the following year.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除。日付を修正。アポストロフィを修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>子孫は室町幕府に仕えて近江国高島郡に拠点を移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants of Takatada served the Muromachi Shogunate and relocated their home to Takashima County in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of Takatada served the Muromachi Shogunate and relocated their home to Takashima County in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of Takatada served the Muromachi Shogunate and relocated their home to Takashima County in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>墓所は京都市下京区堺町の宗仙寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grave site of Takatada is Sosen-ji Temple in Sakai-machi, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grave site of Takatada is Sosen-ji Temple in Sakai-machi, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grave site of Takatada is Sosen-ji Temple in Sakai-machi, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>高忠は武家故実に明るく小笠原持長に弓術を学び、『高忠聞書』を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada was well-versed in Buke-kojitsu (regulations governing the customs of the samurai class) studying archery under Mochinaga OGASAWARA and writing &quot;Takatada kikigaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada was well-versed in Buke-kojitsu (regulations governing the customs of the samurai class) studying archery under Mochinaga OGASAWARA and writing &quot;Takatada kikigaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada was well-versed in Buke-kojitsu (regulations governing the customs of the samurai class) studying archery under Mochinaga OGASAWARA and writing &quot;Takatada kikigaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『高忠聞書』は弓術に於ける研究資料として、また当時の故実を知る史料として現在まで重要な役割を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To date, &quot;Takatada kikigaki&quot; has been making valuable contributions as a research material for archery and also as historical sources shedding light on practices of those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To date, &quot;Takatada kikigaki&quot; has been making valuable contributions as research material for archery and also as historical sources shedding light on practices in those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To date, &quot;Takatada kikigaki&quot; has been making valuable contributions as research material for archery and also as historical sources shedding light on practices in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また隠棲中の文明12年（1480年）、高忠は尾張国守護代の織田敏定へ弓道書の『犬追物記』（『高忠聞書』と同じものか？）を借したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is said that, in 1480 while living in seclusion, Takatada loaned &quot;Inumonono ki,&quot; (the same book as &quot;Tadataka kikigaki?&quot;) the book of archery to Owari no kuni shugodai (provincial governor of Owari Province) Toshisada ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is said that, in 1480 while living in seclusion, Takatada loaned &quot;Inumonono ki,&quot; (the same book as &quot;Tadataka kikigaki?&quot;) the book of archery to Owari no kuni shugodai (provincial governor of Owari Province) Toshisada ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is said that, in 1480 while living in seclusion, Takatada loaned &quot;Inumonono ki,&quot; (the same book as &quot;Tadataka kikigaki&quot;?) the book of archery to Owari no kuni shugodai (provincial governor of Owari Province) Toshisada ODA.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを修正。「また」のみ27に入っていましたが、28の最初に持ってきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>更に和歌・連歌にも通じるなど、当時の知識人の1人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada was one of intellectuals of those days being also acquainted with waka and linked verse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada was one of intellectuals of those days being also acquainted with waka and linked verse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada was one of intellectuals of those days being also acquainted with waka and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt>「連歌」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 福太郎(id:132415), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Kalz(id:92749), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>