<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蕨姫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warabihime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warabihime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warabihime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蕨姫（わらびひめ、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warabihime (year of birth and death unknown) was a woman who lived in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warabihime (year of birth and death unknown) was a woman who lived during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warabihime (year of birth and death unknown) was a woman who lived during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平氏一門の平時忠の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of TAIRA no Tokitada, who was a member of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the daughter of TAIRA no Tokitada, who was a member of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the daughter of TAIRA no Tokitada, who was a member of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本名は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real name is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『尊卑分脈』で源義経の妾とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) states that she was a mistress of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) states that she was a mistress of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Bloodlines of Noble and Base) states that she was a mistress of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>用語補足を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>能登国（現石川県能登半島）の伝承で蕨姫と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tradition of Noto Province (present-day Noto Peninsula in Ishikawa Prefecture) has it that she was called Warabihime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tradition of Noto Province (present-day Noto Peninsula in Ishikawa Prefecture) has it that she was called Warabihime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tradition of Noto Province (present-day Noto Peninsula in Ishikawa Prefecture) has it that she was called Warabihime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>寿永4年（1185年）3月24日の壇ノ浦の戦いで平家一門が滅亡すると、父時忠は源義経の軍勢に捕らえられて捕虜として平安京へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Taira clan was defeated in the Battle of Dan no ura on May 2, 1185, his father Tokitada was captured by the army of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and sent to Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto) as a captive.</e>
<cmt>寿永4年（1185年）3月24日は西暦1185年5月2日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Taira clan was defeated in the Battle of Dan no ura on May 2, 1185, his father Tokitada was captured by the army of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and sent to Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto) as a captive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Taira clan was defeated in the Battle of Dan no ura on May 2, 1185, his father Tokitada was captured by the army of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and sent to Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto) as a captive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>時忠は義経に押収された機密文書を取り戻すために、娘を義経に差し出す事を考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an attempt to retrieve a confidential document seized by Yoshitsune, he planned to offer his daughter to Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an attempt to retrieve a confidential document seized by Yoshitsune, he planned to offer his daughter to Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an attempt to retrieve a confidential document seized by Yoshitsune, he planned to offer his daughter to Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>18歳の現妻の娘は惜しいので先妻の娘である23歳（『源平盛衰記』では28歳）の蕨姫を義経に娶らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of his 18-year-old daughter of the present wife, with whom he was unwilling to part, he made his 23-year-old (28-year-old according to &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans)) daughter called Warabihime, who was a daughter of his former wife, a wife of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of his 18-year-old daughter of the present wife, with whom he was unwilling to part, he made his twenty-three-year-old (twenty-eight-year-old according to &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) daughter called Warabihime, who was a daughter of his former wife, a wife of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of his 18-year-old daughter of the present wife, with whom he was unwilling to part, he made his 23-year-old (28-year-old according to &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans)) daughter called Warabihime, who was a daughter of his former wife, a wife of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>姫に懇願された義経は封も開けずに文書を時忠に送り、時忠はすぐさま焼却処分したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entreated by Warabihime, Yoshitsune returned the document unopened, which Tokitada burned immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entreated by Warabihime, Yoshitsune returned the document unopened, which Tokitada immediately burned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entreated by Warabihime, Yoshitsune returned the document unopened, which Tokitada immediately burned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（『平家物語』「文之沙汰」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike), &apos;Humi no Sata&apos; (Occurrence of the letter))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; - The tale of the Heike), &apos;Humi no Sata&apos; (Occurrence of the letter)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Humi no Sata&apos; (Occurrence of the letter) section of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike))</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>『吾妻鏡』によると、同年5月20日に配流の決定が出されていた時忠が、義経の舅となった縁によって未だ京都に滞在し、義経の兄源頼朝の怒りを買っている記録がある（文治元年9月2日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A record (an article dated October 4, 1185) in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) states that Tokitada, who was to be exiled on June 26, was still staying in Kyoto because he had become the father in law of Yoshitsune, and that this aroused the displeasure of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was an elder brother of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>5月20日は西暦1185年6月26日、文治元年9月2日は西暦1185年10月4日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A record (an article dated October 4, 1185) in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) states that Tokitada, who was to be exiled on June 26, was still living in Kyoto because he had become the father-in law of Yoshitsune, and that this aroused the displeasure of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was an elder brother of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A record (an article dated September 2 in the first year of the Bunji era) in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) states that Tokitada, who was to be exiled on June 26, was still living in Kyoto because he had become the father-in-law of Yoshitsune, and that this aroused the displeasure of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was an older brother of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。an article dated October 4, 1185→an article dated September 2 in the first year of the Bunji era</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>9月23日、時忠は流刑地の能登国へ送られるが、蕨姫のその後の消息は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tokitada was exiled to Noto Province on October 25, 1185, Ibarahime was never heard of again.</e>
<cmt>9月23日は西暦1185年10月25日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tokitada was exiled to Noto Province on October 25, 1185, Ibarahime was never heard of again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tokitada was exiled to Noto Province on October 25, Warabihime was never heard of again.</e>
<cmt>読みなど原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>能登半島には都落ち後の義経一行が、蕨姫の父時忠の配流地を訪れたという伝承が多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many traditional stories saying that Yoshitsune and his followers visited the place of exiled Tokitada, who was the father of Warabihime, on their flight from the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many traditional stories saying that Yoshitsune and his followers visited the place of the exiled Tokitada, who was the father of Warabihime, on their flight from the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many traditional stories saying that Yoshitsune and his followers visited the place of the exiled Tokitada, who was the father of Warabihime, on their flight from the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちちぶ(id:184715), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>