<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近衛前久</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakihisa KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakihisa KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakihisa KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近衞 前久（このえ さきひさ、天文 (元号)5年（1536年） - 慶長17年5月8日 (旧暦)（1612年6月7日））は、戦国時代 (日本)・安土桃山時代の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakihisa KONOE (1536 - June 7, 1612) was a court noble who lived during the Azuchi-Momoyama Period of the Sengoku Period(Period of Warring States),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakihisa KONOE (1536 - June 7, 1612) was a court noble who lived during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) and the Azuchi-Momoyama Period,</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;the Azuchi-Momoyama Period&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;, space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakihisa KONOE (1536 - June 7, 1612) was a court noble who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) and the Azuchi-Momoyama period,</e>
<cmt>periodを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近衛家当主であり、関白左大臣・太政大臣を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the family head of the Konoe family and assumed the position of Kanpaku-Sadaijin (the chief adviser to the Emperor) and Daijodaijin (grand minister of the state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the family head of the Konoe family and assumed the position o f Kanpaku-Sadaijin (the chief adviser to the Emperor and Minister of the Left) and Daijodaijin (Grand Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;and Minister of the LeftDeleted &quot;the&quot;Capitalised &apos;g&apos;, &apos;m&apos;, &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the family head of the Konoe family and assumed the position o f Kanpaku Sadaijin (the chief adviser to the Emperor and Minister of the Left) and Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>Daijo-daijin としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初名は晴嗣、前嗣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Harutsugu, then Sakitsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Harutsugu, which he later changed to Sakitsugu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;then&quot;→&quot;which he later changed to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Harutsugu, which he later changed to Sakitsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>官位を極める</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He reached the top of official ranks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He reached the top of official ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He reached the top of official ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>天文 (元号)5年（1536年）、近衛稙家の長男として京都に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the first son of Taneie KONOE in Kyoto in 1536.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the first son of Taneie KONOE in Kyoto in 1536.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the first son of Taneie KONOE in Kyoto in 1536.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は久我通言の養女久我慶子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Keiko KOGA, the adopted daughter of Michinobu KOGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Keiko KOGA, the adopted daughter of Michinobu KOGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Keiko KOGA, the adopted daughter of Michinobu KOGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>天文9年（1540年）に元服し、室町幕府第12代将軍足利義晴から一字を賜り晴嗣と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1540, he got through genpuku (a ceremony to celebrate a young man&apos;s coming of age) and received one character from the name of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun of the Muromachi bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), then called himself Harutsugu (晴嗣).</e>
<cmt>晴嗣→Harutsugu[正しい読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1540, he had his coming of age ceremony and received one character from the name of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate, taking the name Harutsugu (晴嗣).</e>
<cmt>&quot;got through genpuku (a ceremony to celebrate a young man&apos;s coming of age)&quot;→&quot;had his coming of age ceremony&quot;&quot;bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)&quot;→&quot;Shogunate&quot;&quot;then called himself&quot;→&quot;taking the name&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1540, he had his coming of age ceremony and received one character from the name of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate, taking the name Harutsugu.</e>
<cmt>最後の漢字表記は不要と解釈し、削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>天文10年（1541年）には従三位に叙せられ公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the rank of Jusani (Junior Third Rank) in 1541 and raised to the court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the rank of Jusani (Junior Third Rank) in 1541 and raised to the nobility.</e>
<cmt>&quot;court noble&quot;→&quot;nobility&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1541 and raised to the nobility.</e>
<cmt>Jusanmi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天文16年（1547年）に内大臣、天文22年（1553年）に右大臣、天文23年（1554年）に関白左大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1547, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (managerial position who support Emperor), Udaijin (minister of the right) in 1553, then Kanpaku Sadaijin (the chief adviser to the Emperor and minister of the left) in 1554.</e>
<cmt>関白左大臣→Kanpaku Sadaijin (the chief adviser to the Emperor and minister of the left)[定訳不明。関白と左大臣を兼任していたと解釈して説明を入れました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1547, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center), Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 1553, then Kanpaku Sadaijin (chief adviser to the Emperor and Minister of the Left) in 1554.</e>
<cmt>&quot;managerial position who support Emperor&quot;→&quot;Minister of the Center&quot;Capitalised &apos;m&apos;, &apos;r&apos;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Capitalised &apos;m&apos;, &apos;l&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1547, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center), Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 1553, then Kanpaku Sadaijin in 1554.</e>
<cmt>関白左大臣　既出のため、括弧での補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、藤氏長者に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the Toshichoja (representative of the Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt>藤氏長者→Toshichoja (representative of the Fujiwara family)[近衛信尋のファイルより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the Toshichoja (representative of the Fujiwara Clan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also became the Toshichoja (representative of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>clan 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天文24年（1555年）1月13日、従一位に昇叙し、名を前嗣と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Januafy 13, 1555, he was promoted to the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and changed his name into Sakitsugu (前嗣).</e>
<cmt>前嗣→Sakitsugu[正しい読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13, 1555, he was promoted to the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and changed his name to Sakitsugu (前嗣).</e>
<cmt>Spelliing of &quot;January&quot;&quot;into&quot;→&quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 14, 1555, he was promoted to the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and changed his name to Sakitsugu.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。最後の漢字表記は不要と解釈し、削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>永禄2年（1559年）、越後国の長尾景虎（後の上杉謙信）が上洛したが、前久と景虎は互いに肝胆照らし合い、血書の起請文を交わして盟約を結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1559, when Kagetora NAGAO (latter-day Kenshin UESUGI) of Echigo Province went to Kyoto, Sakihisa and Kagetora got to like each other and they leagued by exchanging kessho-no- kisobun (promissory letter written in one&apos;s own blood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1559, when Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of Echigo Province went to Kyoto, he became close to Sakihisa and they made a pact by exchanging vows written in blood.</e>
<cmt>&quot;latter-day&quot;→&quot;later&quot;&quot;Sakihisa and Kagetora got to like each other&quot;→&quot;he became close to Sakihisa&quot;&quot;leagued&quot;→&quot;made a pact&quot;&quot;kessho-no- kisobun (promissory letter written in one&apos;s own blood)&quot;→&quot;vows written in blood&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1559, when Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of Echigo Province went to Kyoto, he became close to Sakihisa and they made a pact by exchanging vows written in blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>前久は、関白の職にありながら、永禄3年（1560年）に越後に下向し、更に景虎の関東平定を助けるために上野国、下総国の古河御所に赴くなど戦国の公家らしい行動力に溢れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Sakihisa was in the position of Kanpaku, he was a typical court noble in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) who had so much energy that he went down to Echigo in 1560, then Kozuke Province and Koga gosho in Shimousa Province to support Kagetora to rule Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Sakihisa was Kanpaku, like most nobles of the Sengoku Period he moved around a lot, going to Echigo in 1560, then Kozuke Province and Koga Palace in Shimousa Province to help Kagetora control Kanto.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Sakihisa was Kanpaku, like most nobles of the Sengoku period he moved around a lot, going to Echigo in 1560, then Kozuke Province and Koga Palace in Shimosa Province to help Kagetora control Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>Shimosa としました。Periodを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>永禄4年（1561年）、名を前久と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1561, he changed his name to Sakihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1561, he changed his name to Sakihisa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1561, he changed his name to Sakihisa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、永禄5年（1562年）8月に帰洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, in August 1562, he came back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1562, he came back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;But,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1562, he came back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>景虎の関東平定後に上洛を促す計画であったともされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that he planned to encourage Kagetora to come to Kyoto after ruling Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that he planned to encourage Kagetora to come to Kyoto after subjugating Kanto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ruling&quot;→&quot;subjugating&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that he planned to encourage Kagetora to come to Kyoto after subjugating Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>朝廷からの出奔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Runaway from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flight from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Runaway&quot;→&quot;Flight</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flight from the Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>永禄8年（1565年）の永禄の変で将軍足利義輝を殺害した三好三人衆・松永久秀は将軍殺害の罪に問われる事を危惧して揃って前久を頼った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyoshi sanninshu (Three retainers of th Miyoshi clan) and Hisahide MATSUNAGA who killed Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA in the Eiroku incident in 1565 concerned about being accused of killing the Shogun and relied on Sakihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">in 1565, Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was killed by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and three retainers of the Miyoshi Clan who, fearing being charged with the Shogun&apos;s murder, turned to Sakihisa.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1565, Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was killed by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and three retainers of the Miyoshi clan who, fearing being charged with the Shogun&apos;s murder, turned to Sakihisa.</e>
<cmt>clanを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>前久は義輝の従兄弟であったがその正室である自分の姉を保護した事を評価してこれを認め、彼らが推す足利義栄の将軍就任を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Sakihisa was a cousin of Yoshiteru, he decided to make Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, who was reccmmended by them, assume the position of Shogun since he appreciated Yoshihide for protecting his older sister, a legal wife of Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Sakihisa was a cousin of Yoshiteru, he decided to make Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, who was recommended by them, Shogun since he appreciated Yoshihide for protecting his older sister, a legal wife of Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;recommended&quot;Deleted &quot;assume the position of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Sakihisa was a cousin of Yoshiteru, he decided to make Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, who was recommended by them, Shogun since he appreciated Yoshihide for protecting his older sister, a legal wife of Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt>Although としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>だが、永禄11年（1568年）織田信長が足利義昭を奉じ上洛を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1568 Nobunaga ODA successfully went to Kyoto under Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1568 Nobunaga ODA successfully went to Kyoto on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos;s orders.</e>
<cmt>&quot;under&quot;→&quot;on&quot;Added &quot;&apos;s orders&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1568 Nobunaga ODA successfully went to Kyoto on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos;s orders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義昭は永禄の変後の前久の行動から兄の死には前久が関与しているのではと疑い、更に関白を狙う二条晴良も前久を追及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki suspected Sakihisa of involvement in his older brother&apos;s death due to the acts of Sakihisa after the Eiroku Incident, also Haruyoshi NIJO who aspired to the position of Kanpaku blamed Sakihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to Sakihisa&apos;s behavior after the Eiroku Incident, and also because Haruyoshi NIJO, who aspired to the position of Kanpaku, blamed Sakihisa, Yoshiaki suspected him of involvement in his older brother&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;the acts of Sakihisa&quot;→&quot;Sakihisa&apos;s behavior&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;, &quot;because&quot;, commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to Sakihisa&apos;s behavior after the Eiroku Incident, and also because Haruyoshi NIJO, who aspired to the position of Kanpaku, blamed Sakihisa, Yoshiaki suspected him of involvement in his older brother&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これに危機感を抱いた前久は、京都から本願寺11世顕如を頼って大阪石山本願寺に入って関白を解任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakihisa felt the sense of crisis by this and asked Kennyo, the 11th head of the Hongan-ji Temple in Kyoto for help and entered the Ishiyama-hongan-ji Temple in Osaka, then he was dismissed as Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakihisa, sensing danger, asked Kennyo, the 11th head of the Hongan-ji Temple in Kyoto for help and entered the Ishiyama-Hongan-ji Temple in Osaka, then he was dismissed as Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;felt the sense of crisis by this and&quot;→&quot;,sensing danger,&quot;Capitalised &apos;h&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakihisa, sensing danger, asked Kennyo, the 11th head of the Hongan-ji Temple in Kyoto for help and entered the Ishiyama-Hongan-ji Temple in Osaka, then he was dismissed as Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この時、顕如の長男教如を自分の猶子としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he adopted Kyonyo, the first son of Kennyo, as his yushi (a kind of adopted child).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, he adopted Kyonyo, the first son of Kennyo.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;, as his yushi (a kind of adopted child)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he adopted Kyonyo, the first son of Kennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後に「信長包囲網」の動きが出てくると、前久も三好三人衆の依頼を受けてこれに参加して顕如に決起を促したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when &quot;the coalition against Nobunaga&quot;was built, Sakihisa joined that at the request of the Miyoshi sanninshu and encouraged Kennyo to rise in revolt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when &quot;the coalition against Nobunaga&quot;was built, Sakihisa joined at the request of the three Miyoshi retainers and encouraged Kennyo to rise in revolt.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;that&quot;&quot;Miyoshi sanninshu&quot;→&quot;three Miyoshi retainers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when &apos;the coalition against Nobunaga&apos; was built, Sakihisa joined at the request of the three Miyoshi retainers and encouraged Kennyo to rise in revolt.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、前久自身は信長に敵意は無く、信長の下で将軍・関白となった足利義昭と二条晴良の排除が目的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sakihisa felt no hostility toward Nobunaga, thus his purpose was to eliminate Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and Haruyoshi NIJO who became Shogun and Kanpaku under Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sakihisa felt no hostility toward Nobunaga; his purpose was to eliminate Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and Haruyoshi NIJO who had become Shogun and Kanpaku under Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, thus&quot;→semicolon&quot;became&quot;→&quot;had become&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sakihisa felt no hostility toward Nobunaga; his purpose was to eliminate Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and Haruyoshi NIJO who had become Shogun and Kanpaku under Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そのため、天正元年（1573年）に義昭が信長によって京都を追放され、一方晴良も政治能力の無さから信長から疎んじられるようになると、前久は丹波国の赤井直正のもとに移って「信長包囲網」から離脱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, when Nobunaga expelled Yoshiaki from Kyoto in 1573 and gradually disfavored Haruyoshi due to his lack of political capacity, Sakihisa fell under Naomasa AKAI in Tanba Province and left &quot;the coalition against Nobunaga&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, when Nobunaga expelled Yoshiaki from Kyoto in 1573 and Haruyoshi gradually fell out of favor due to his lack of political capacity, Sakihisa switched to Naomasa AKAI in Tanba Province and left &quot;the coalition against Nobunaga&quot;.</e>
<cmt>&quot;gradually disfavored Haruyoshi&quot;→&quot;Haruyoshi gradually fell out of favor&quot;&quot;fell under&quot;→&quot;switched to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, when Nobunaga expelled Yoshiaki from Kyoto in 1573 and Haruyoshi gradually fell out of favor due to his lack of political capacity, Sakihisa switched to Naomasa AKAI in Tamba Province and left &apos;the coalition against Nobunaga.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>天正3年（1575年）、信長の奏上により、帰洛を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1575, he was allowed to return to Kyoto due to a sojo (say to Emperor) of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1575, he was allowed to return to Kyoto following Nobunaga&apos;s report to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;due to a sojo (say to Emperor) of Nobunaga&quot;→&quot;following Nobunaga&apos;s report to the Emperor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1575, he was allowed to return to Kyoto following Nobunaga&apos;s report to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>信長との親交</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Friendship with Nobunaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Friendship with Nobunaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Friendship with Nobunaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>以後は信長との親交を深め、特に鷹狩りという共通の趣味を有していた事から、前久と信長はしばしば互いの成果を自慢しあったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, he deepen a friendship with Nobunaga, particularly, they shared a common interest with falconry and often boasted of the results each other</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, he developed a deep friendship with Nobunaga; in particular, they shared a common interest in falconry and often boasted of the results to each other.</e>
<cmt>&quot;deepen a friendship&quot;→&quot;developed a deep friendship&quot;&quot;, particularly&quot;&quot;; in particular&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;in&quot;Added &quot;to&quot;, full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, he developed a deep friendship with Nobunaga; in particular, they shared a common interest in falconry and often boasted of the results to each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>9月には、信長に要請される形で、九州に下向し、大友氏・伊東氏・相良氏・島津氏の和議を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, at the request of Nobunaga, he went down to Kyushu to settle disputes among the Otomo clan, the Ito clan, the Sagara clan and the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, at the request of Nobunaga, he went down to Kyushu to settle disputes among the Otomo, the Ito, the Sagara and the Shimazu Clans.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;individual &quot;clan&quot;s and changed final &quot;clan&quot;→&quot;Clans&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, at the request of Nobunaga, he went down to Kyushu region to settle disputes among the Otomo, the Ito, the Sagara and the Shimazu clans.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>天正5年（1577年）に京都に戻り、翌天正6年（1578年）准三宮の待遇を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1577, he returned to Kyoto and was given the title of Jusangu (title given to novels and Imperial families).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1577, he returned to Kyoto and was given the title of Jusangu (title given to nobles and Imperial families).</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;nobles&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1577, he returned to Kyoto and was given the title of Jusangu (title given to nobles and Imperial families) in 1578.</e>
<cmt>1578を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>次いで信長と本願寺の調停に乗り出し、天正8年（1580年）顕如は石山本願寺を退去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he began to interfere in the Hongan-ji Temple with Nobunaga, then Kennyo left the Ishiyama-hongan-ji Temple in 1580.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he tried to mediate between Nobunaga and Hongan-ji Temple, and in 1580, Kennyo left Ishiyama-hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot;began to interfere in the Hongan-ji Temple with Nobunaga&quot;→&quot;tried to mediate between Nobunaga and Hongan-ji Temple&quot;&quot;then&quot;→&quot;and in 1580,&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;, &quot;in 1580&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he tried to mediate between Nobunaga and Hongan-ji Temple, and in 1580, Kennyo left Ishiyama-hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>特に10年近くかかっても攻め落とせなかった石山本願寺を開城させた事に対する信長の評価は高く、前久が息子近衛信尹にあてた手紙によれば、信長から「天下平定の暁には近衛家に令制国を献上する」約束を得たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, Nobunaga appreciated Sakihisa for having conquered the Ishiyama-hongan-ji Temple which had not been captured for almost 10 years and according to the Sakihisa&apos;s letter to his son, Nobutada KONOE, Nobunaga promised him to &quot;give a ryoseikoku (province) to the Konoe family after the domination of the whole country.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga particularly appreciated Sakihisa for forcing the surrender of Ishiyama-hongan-ji Temple, which had withstood a 10-year siege, and according to Sakihisa&apos;s letter to his son, Nobutada KONOE, Nobunaga promised to &quot;give a province to the Konoe family after the domination of the whole country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Deleted commaMoved &quot;particularly&quot;&quot;having conquered the&quot;→&quot;forcing the surrender of&quot;Added comma&quot;not been captured for almost 10 years&quot;→&quot;withstood a 10-year siege,&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;, &quot;him&quot;, &quot;ryoseikoku&quot;, brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga particularly appreciated Sakihisa for forcing the surrender of Ishiyama-hongan-ji Temple, which had withstood a 10-year siege, and according to Sakihisa&apos;s letter to his son, Nobutada KONOE, Nobunaga promised to &apos;give a province to the Konoe family after the domination of the whole country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>天正10年（1582年）2月に太政大臣となるが、5月には辞任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed the position of Daijodaijin (grand minister of state),but resigned from that in May.</e>
<cmt>太政大臣→Daijodaijin (grand minister of state)[近衛家熙のファイルより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1582, he assumed the position of Daijodaijin (Grand Minister of State), but resigned in May.</e>
<cmt>Addeed &quot;In February 1582,&quot;Capitalised &apos;g&apos;, &apos;m&apos;, &apos;s&apos;Changed Japanese comma to Western oneDeleted &quot;from that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1582, he assumed the position of Daijo-daijin, but resigned in June.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これは信長の三職推任問題に関連して前久が信長に同職を譲る意向であったからだとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this was because Sakihisa intended to transfer the position to Nobunaga relating to the sanshoku-suininmondai(the interpretational problem over the Honno-ji Temple Incident) of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was because Sakihisa intended to transfer the position to Nobunaga to help solve the problem of Nobunaga&apos;s position.</e>
<cmt>- Not quite sure of the meaning of this sentence. I think the 三職推任問題 is to do with the interpretation of documents discovered in the 1960s and doesn&apos;t directly relate to why Sakihisa resigned.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this was because Sakihisa intended to transfer the position to Nobunaga to help solve the problem of the position of Nobunaga, who at that time did not have any position and had been recommended to assume one of the following three positions; Daijo-daijin, Kanpaku or Shogun.</e>
<cmt>三職推任問題　の簡単な説明を左記のようにいたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>3月の甲州征伐には信長と同行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied Nobunaga on the expedition of Koshu in March.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he accompanied Nobunaga on the Koshu Expedition.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;In March&quot;Added comma&quot;expedition of Koshu&quot;→&quot;Koshu Expedition&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, he accompanied Nobunaga on the Koshu Expedition.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>本能寺の変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honno-ji Temple Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honno-ji Temple Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt>左記のようにいたしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>だが、6月2日の本能寺の変によって、信長が横死したため、前久の運命も変転を余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Nobunaga died an unnatural death in the Honno-ji Temple Incident on June 2, then the destiny of Sakihisa was forced to change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nobunaga died an unnatural death in the Honno-ji Temple Incident on June 2, and Sakihisa&apos;s destiny was out of his own hands.</e>
<cmt>&quot;But&quot;→&quot;However, &quot;Reworded 2nd clause</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nobunaga died an unnatural death in the Honnoji Incident on July 1, and Sakihisa&apos;s destiny was out of his own hands.</e>
<cmt>Honnoji Incident としました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>失意の前久は落飾し龍山と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakihisa felt disappointed and cut his hair to become a priest and called himself Ryuzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disappointed, Sakihisa took the tonsure, calling himself Ryuzan.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disappointed, Sakihisa took the tonsure, calling himself Ryuzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし、「本能寺を攻撃した明智光秀軍が前久邸から本能寺を銃撃した」と讒言に遭い、織田信孝や豊臣秀吉からも詰問される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was grilled by Nobutaka ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI due to a zangen(a false charge) saying &quot;The army of Mitsuhide AKECHI shot the Honno-ji Temple from the residence of Sakihisa.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was grilled by Nobutaka ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI due to the false charge that &quot;the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI fired shots at Honno-ji Temple from the residence of Sakihisa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;a zangen(a false charge) saying&quot;→&quot;the false charge that&quot;Made &apos;T&apos; lower case&quot;shot&quot;→&quot;fired shots at&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was grilled by Nobutaka ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI due to the false charge that &apos;the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI fired shots at Honno-ji Temple from the residence of Sakihisa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>そのため、今度は徳川家康を頼り、遠江国浜松に下向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he relied on Ieyasu TOKUGAWA this time and went down to Hamamatsu, Totoumi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he turned to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA this time and moved to Hamamatsu, Totoumi Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;relied on&quot;→&quot;turned to&quot;&quot;went down&quot;→&quot;moved&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he turned to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA this time and moved to Hamamatsu, Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>Totomi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>一年後、家康の斡旋により秀吉の誤解は解け京都に戻るが、天正12年（1584年）小牧・長久手の戦いで両雄が激突したため、またもや立場が危うくなった前久は奈良に身を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One year later, thanks to the mediation by Ieyasu, misunderstandings by Hideyoshi were cleared up and he could return to Kyoto, but Ieyasu and Hideyoshi fought fiercely each other in the Komaki-Nagakute War in 1584, and Sakihisa&apos;s position became shaky again and hid himself in Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One year later, thanks to mediation by Ieyasu, the misunderstandings with Hideyoshi were cleared up and he could return to Kyoto, but Ieyasu and Hideyoshi fought fiercely each other in the Komaki-Nagakute War in 1584, and Sakihisa&apos;s position became shaky again and hid himself in Nara.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;by&quot;→&quot;with&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One year later, thanks to mediation by Ieyasu, the misunderstandings with Hideyoshi were cleared up and he could return to Kyoto, but Ieyasu and Hideyoshi fought fiercely each other in the Komaki-Nagakute War in 1584, and Sakihisa&apos;s position became shaky again and hid himself in Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>両者の間に和議が成立したことを見届けてから帰洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Kyoto after confirming the settlement of disputes between both parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Kyoto after confirming the settlement of disputes between both parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Kyoto after confirming the settlement of disputes between both parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>晩年は一方的に慈照寺を別荘にして隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his last years, he retired in the Jisho-ji Temple which he used as a villa without asking</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his last years, he retired to the Jisho-ji Temple which he arbitrarily used as a villa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot;→&quot;to&quot;&quot;Added comma&quot;without asking&quot;→&quot;arbitrarily&quot; and movedAdded full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his last years, he retired to the Jisho-ji Temple which he arbitrarily used as a villa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>慶長17年（1612年）5月8日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on May 8, 1612.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on May 8, 1612.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on June 7, 1612.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>享年77。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 77.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was years old 77.</e>
<cmt>&quot;His age at death&quot;→&quot;He&quot;Added &quot;years old&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 77 years old.</e>
<cmt>77 years old としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>京都東福寺に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried in the Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried in Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried in Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>法名は東求院龍山空誉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was 東求院龍山空誉.</e>
<cmt>東求院龍山空誉→[正しい読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was 東求院龍山空誉.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was 東求院龍山空誉 (its pronunciation is unclear).</e>
<cmt>他ファイルにあわせ、(its pronunciation is unclear)を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>人物・評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality/Reputation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality/Reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile and reputation</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>前久は、五摂家の嫡流らしく、和歌・連歌に優れた才能を発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a chakuryu (main descent) of gosekke (five main regent families), Sakihisa showed his excellent ability in waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem) and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an eldest son of one of the gosekke (five main regent families), Sakihisa showed considerable talent in waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem) and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt>&quot;a chakuryu (main descent) of gosekke&quot;→&quot;an eldest son&quot;Added &quot;one of the&quot;Deleted &quot;his&quot;&quot;excellent ability&quot;→&quot;considerable talent&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an eldest son of one of the gosekke (five main regent families), Sakihisa showed considerable talent in waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem) and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>書道は、青蓮院流を学び、有職故実にも詳しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For calligraphy, he learned the Shorenin school (style) and was familiar with yusokukojitsu (ancient rules of the Imperial court and military commander).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned the Shorenin school of calligraphy and was familiar with the ancient customs and manners of the Imperial court and military.</e>
<cmt>&quot;For calligraphy, &quot;→&quot; of calligraphy&quot; and moved&quot;learned&quot;→&quot;studied&quot;Deleted &quot;(style)&quot;&quot;yusokukojitsu (ancient rules of the Imperial court and military commander)&quot;→&quot;the ancient customs and manners of the Imperial court and military&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned the Shorenin school of calligraphy and was familiar with the ancient customs and manners of the Imperial court and military.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>更に馬術や鷹狩りなどにも抜群の力量を示して「龍山公鷹百首」という鷹狩りの専門的な解説書を兼ねた歌集も執筆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he displayed outstanding competence in equitation and falconry and wrote &quot;Ryuzankotakahyakushu (龍山公鷹百首)&quot; which was an anthology of waka and technical guide for falconry.</e>
<cmt>「龍山公鷹百首」→&apos;Ryuzankotakahyakushu&apos;[正しい読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he displayed outstanding competence in horsemanship and falconry, writing &quot;Ryuzankotakahyakushu (龍山公鷹百首)&quot;, which was an anthology of waka and a technical guide for falconry.</e>
<cmt>&quot;equitation&quot;→&quot;horsemanship&quot;&quot; and wrote&quot;→&quot;, writing&quot;Added comma, &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he displayed outstanding competence in horsemanship and falconry, writing &apos;Ryuzankotakahyakushu (龍山公鷹百首),&apos; which was an anthology of waka and a technical guide for falconry.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>京都を離れ、地方を流浪遍歴することを余儀なくされたが、前久にとっては、単に経済的困窮や戦乱を逃れるためのものではなく、むしろ政治への積極参加のための手段の一つであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had to leave Kyoto and roamed about rural areas, but for Sakihisa, it was not just a way to escape economic hardship or war, but one of the ways to actively participate in politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had to leave Kyoto and travel around rural areas, but for Sakihisa, this was not just a way to escape economic hardship or war, but one way to actively participate in politics.</e>
<cmt>&quot;roamed about&quot;→&quot;travel around&quot;&quot;it&quot;→&quot;this&quot;&quot;of the ways&quot;→&quot;way&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had to leave Kyoto and travel around rural areas, but for Sakihisa, this was not just a way to escape economic hardship or war, but one way to actively participate in politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>同時に地方に中央の文化を伝播する上で重要な役割を果たしたと評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, it is considered that he played an important role in introducing the central culture into rural areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, it is considered that he played an important role in introducing the culture of the capital into rural areas.</e>
<cmt>&quot;central culture&quot;→&quot;culture of the capital&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, it is considered that he played an important role in introducing the culture of the capital into rural areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronological Table</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronological Table</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Timeline</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Law soma(id:45202), 二八(id:10408), Cprobot(id:97843), 砂場(id:27896), 水野白楓(id:22811), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), Kamitani(id:30757), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 玄史生(id:43670), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), こぶまき(id:38278), 伏儀(id:142093), けんち(id:5147), 210.(id:9838), 蔭人(id:80171), ５１６(id:45205), Kouko0515(id:100370), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>