<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>田中足麻呂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TANAKA no Tarimaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TANAKA no Tarimaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TANAKA no Tarimaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>田中足麻呂（たなかのたりまろ、生年不明 - 文武天皇2年6月29日 (旧暦)（698年8月10日））は、日本の飛鳥時代の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TANAKA no Tarimaro (Birth date unknown-698 August 10th) is a personality from Japan&apos;s Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TANAKA no Tarimaro (date of birth unknown - August 10, 698) lived during the Asuka period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TANAKA no Tarimaro (date of birth unknown - August 13, 698) lived during the Asuka period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は足摩侶とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name is also written as 足摩侶 (using different Kanji characters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name Tarimaro (足麻呂) was also written as 足摩侶 (the pronunciation was the same).</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name Tarimaro (足麻呂) was also written as 足摩侶 (the pronunciation was the same).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>旧仮名遣いでの読みは「たなかのたりまろ」で同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the old Japanese syllabary characters, his name is read as &quot;TANAKA no Tarimaro&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old Japanese syllabary characters, the pronunciation of his name was the same as &apos;Tanaka no Tarimaro.&apos;</e>
<cmt>今の発音と違って（同じく）昔は…という説明文なので、時制はwasになります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old Japanese syllabary characters, the pronunciation of his name was the same as &apos;Tanaka no Tarimaro.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>姓は臣、後に朝臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His title was Omi, and was later changed to Ason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kabane (hereditary title) was Omi, and was later changed to Asomi (Ason).</e>
<cmt>かばねについて説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was Omi, and was later changed to Asomi (Ason).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>672年の壬申の乱のとき湯沐令で、大海人皇子（天武天皇）の側について倉歴道を守り、夜襲を受けて敗走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Jinshin War he sided with Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) and guarded the Kurareki Road, but fled in defeat after a night attack broke through their ranks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jinshin war, he was Yu-no-unagashi (manager of Yu [imperial territories]) and sided with Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu); he guarded Kurafu-no-michi Road, and was attacked by the enemy in the night and ran away.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ、固有名詞読み間違いがあります。「倉歴」は「くらふ」。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jinshin war, he was Yu-no-unagashi (manager of Yu [imperial territories]) and sided with Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu); he guarded Kurafu-no-michi Road, and was attacked by the enemy in the night and ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>贈直広壱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awarded the rank of Jikikoichi</e>
<cmt>直広壱の読み方が見つかりませんでしたので、これかな、と思ったものを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given posthumously the rank of Jikikoichi.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。「贈」がついているので、死後に贈られたと明記しなければなりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given posthumously the rank of Jikikoichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>壬申の乱の勃発時、田中足麻呂は湯沐令であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the onset of the Jinshin War, Tarimaro TANAKA held the position of Yunonagashi (Governor of royal lands).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the onset of the Jinshin War, TANAKA no Tarimaro was Yu-no-unagashi.</e>
<cmt>名詞読み間違いがあります。「湯沐令」は「ゆのうながし」。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the onset of the Jinshin War, TANAKA no Tarimaro was Yu-no-unagashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>田中が管理した湯沐邑がどこにあったかは、『日本書紀』に記されておらず、伊勢国と美濃国の二説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tomokuyu (royal land) that TANAKA governed isn&apos;t recorded in the &quot;Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot; but it&apos;s believed to be either the Ise province or the Mino province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yu-no-mura (Imperial territories) that Tanaka managed is not recorded in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and at present there are two opinions that it was Ise Province and that it was Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を統一します。名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yu-no-mura (Imperial territories) that Tanaka managed is not recorded in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and at present there are two opinions that it was Ise Province and that it was Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>伊勢国とするのは、後述の大海人皇子との邂逅が伊勢国であり、ともに皇子を出迎えた三宅石床が伊勢の国司と推測されるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ise province theory is based on the speculation that his chance meeting with Prince Oama was in Ise province, and that Iwatoko MIYAKE, the provincial governor that accompanied him to greet the prince, was said to be from Ise province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ise Province theory is based on that he met Prince Oama in Ise Province (explained below), and that MIYAKE no Iwatoko who had received Prince with Tanaka is considered to have been Kuninomikotomochi (provincial governor) of Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ise Province theory is based on that he met Prince Oama in Ise Province (explained below), and that MIYAKE no Iwatoko who had received Prince with Tanaka is considered to have been Kuninomikotomochi (provincial governor) of Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>美濃国とするのは、やはりともに出迎えた高田新家が続日本紀の記事から美濃国の主稲と推測され、かつ主稲は湯沐邑の役人と考えられるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mino theory is likewise based on speculation that the newly founded Takada family, which accompanied him to greet the prince, is recorded as &quot;Inanushi&quot; in the Shokunihongi (Continuation of the Chronicles of Japan), and Inanushi is believed to be a Yunongashi official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mino Province theory is based on that Takata no Niinomi who also received Prince with Tanaka is considered to have been Inamori (manager of rice storehouse) from an article of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan Continued), and Inamori is believed to have been an official of Yu-no-mura.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。誤訳、固有名詞読み間違いがあります。「高田新家」は人名で、「たかたのにいのみ」。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mino Province theory is based on that Takata no Niinomi who also received Prince with Tanaka is considered to have been Inamori (manager of rice storehouse) from an article of &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan Continued), and Inamori is believed to have been an official of Yu-no-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>書紀の記事には高田は肩書きなしで田中の後に記されているので、美濃国説では両人は同じ湯沐からきた上司と部下とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nihon Shoki (historical records), Takada is mentioned after TANAKA without any title so it appears that they were both from the same province and served as superior and subordinate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article of Nihonshoki, Takata is mentioned after Tanaka without any title, and the Mino Province theory explains that they were a superior and a subordinate of the same Imperial territory.</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を統一します。訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article of Nihonshoki, Takata is mentioned after Tanaka without any title, and the Mino Province theory explains that they were a superior and a subordinate of the same Imperial territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>壬申の乱の開始時、大海人皇子はまず美濃国の安八間郡（後の安八郡）で兵を集めさせ、自らは24日に吉野宮を発って東に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the start of the Jinshin war, Prince Oama gathered his troops in Anpachi county, Mino, departing from Yoshino-miya on the 24th and heading east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the start of the Jinshin war, Prince Oama first ordered to gather soldiers in Ahachima County (later became Ahachi County) of Mino Province and Prince himself left Yoshino-no-miya (Yoshino Palace) on the 24th and headed east.</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を統一します。固有名詞読み間違いがあります。「安八間」は「あはちま」。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the start of the Jinshin war, Prince Oama first ordered to gather soldiers in Ahachima County (later became Ahachi County) of Mino Province and Prince himself left Yoshino-no-miya (Yoshino Palace) on the 24th and headed east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>25日に従う者わずかに数十人で伊勢国の鈴鹿郡に入ったところ、三宅石床、三輪子首、湯沐令の田中足麻呂、高田新家に出会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 25th, he entered Suzuka county, of Ise, with an escort of a few dozen men and was met by Iwatoko MIYAKE, MIWA no Kobito, and the Yunongashi (governor), Maro TANAKA, and the newly founded Takada family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 25th, he entered Suzuka County of Ise Province with a few dozen men, and met MIYAKE no Iwatoko, MIWA no Kobito, Yu-no-unagashi TANAKA no Tarimaro and TAKATA no Niinomi.</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を統一します。固有名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 25th, he entered Suzuka County of Ise Province with a few dozen men, and met MIYAKE no Iwatoko, MIWA no Kobito, Yu-no-unagashi TANAKA no Tarimaro and TAKATA no Niinomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>大海人皇子はそこから美濃国に入ったが、足麻呂がそれに従ったかどうかは定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From there Prince Oamu entered Mino, but it&apos;s uncertain whether Maro accompanied him there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From there Prince Oama entered Mino Province; and it is unknown whether Tarimaro followed Prince or not.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。固有名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From there Prince Oama entered Mino Province; and it is unknown whether Tarimaro followed Prince or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>7月2日、倭（後の大和国）で苦戦していた大伴吹負への増援として、美濃から数万の軍が進発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 2nd, an army of ten thousands set out from Mino to reinforce OTOMO no Hukei who was engaged in a heavy battle at Wa (latter day Yamato-no-Kuni).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 2, an army of ten thousands soldiers departed from Mino Province as the reinforcements for OTOMO no Fukei who had been putting up bad fights in Yamato (later changed to Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。訳語選択ミスがあります。「倭」は「やまと」。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 2, an army of ten thousands soldiers departed from Mino Province as the reinforcements for OTOMO no Fukei who had been putting up bad fights in Yamato (later changed to Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この時、足麻呂は倉歴（くらふ）道の守備を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Maro was assigned to guard the Kurafu road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Tarimaro was ordered to guard Kurafu-no-michi Road.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Tarimaro was ordered to guard Kurafu-no-michi Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>倉歴は近江国甲賀郡のあたりで、倉歴道とは伊賀国と倉歴を結ぶ道と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurafu Road was around Koga county, Omi Province, and is believed to have connected Iga Province and Kurafu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurafu was around Koka (Koga) County of Omi Province, and Kurafu-no-michi Road is believed to have connected Iga Province and Kurafu.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。固有名詞「甲賀」は「こうか」の方が正しいようなので先にします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurafu was around Koka (Koga) County of Omi Province, and Kurafu-no-michi Road is believed to have connected Iga Province and Kurafu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>足麻呂の後方では多品治が三千の兵で莿萩野（たらの）に駐屯した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oo no HONJI took up Maro&apos;s rear and was based at Tarano with 3000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Behind the troop of Tarimaro, O no Honji was camped leading three thousands soldiers at Tarano.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behind the troop of Tarimaro, O no Honji was camped leading three thousands soldiers at Tarano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>美濃から伊勢、伊賀、大和に入る経路の側面守備である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They guarded the roads to Ise, Iga and Yamato Province from Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In brief, they were to guard the route from Mino Province to Ise, Iga and Yamato.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In brief, they were to guard the route from Mino Province to Ise, Iga and Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>これに対して弘文天皇側の将、田辺小隅は、鹿深山を越えて5日に倉歴に夜襲をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To counter this move, Emperor Kobun&apos;s general, Tanabe no OSUMI, crossed over the mountains and attacked the Kurafu Road on the night of the 5th.</e>
<cmt>[鹿深山] の読み方が見つからなかったため、名前をいれずにＭｏｕｎｔａｉｎといれました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To counter this move, TANABE no Osumi (Tanae no Osumi), a commander of the Emperor Kobun (Prince Otomo at that time)&apos;s army, went over Mt. Kafuka and attacked the troop on Kurafu in the night of the 5th.</e>
<cmt>「鹿深山」は「かふかのやま」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To counter this move, TANABE no Osumi (Tanae no Osumi), a commander of the Emperor Kobun (Prince Otomo at that time)&apos;s army, went over Mt. Kafuka and attacked the troop on Kurafu in the night of the 5th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>小隅は敵味方の識別のため、「金（かね）」を合言葉とし、刀を交えるとき必ず「金」と言わせ、「金」と答える者を味方とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To differentiate between friend and foe, Kobun ordered his soldiers to shout the password &quot;Kin (gold)&quot; when fighting, and to not attack all those who shouted &quot;Kin (gold)&quot; in reply.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osumi had arranged that their word should be &apos;kane&apos; to tell their side from the enemy&apos;s side, and during the battle, his soldiers had to say the word to each met soldier and they knew their side hearing the response of &apos;kane.&apos;</e>
<cmt>読み間違い、訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osumi had arranged that their word should be &apos;kane&apos; to tell their side from the enemy&apos;s side, and during the battle, his soldiers had to say the word to each met soldier and they knew their side hearing the response of &apos;kane.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>足摩侶の部隊は混乱して敗れたが、足摩侶自身は、敵が合言葉を使っていることを悟り、「金」と言って逃れることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maro&apos;s troops fell into confusion and were defeated, but Maro himself caught onto the enemy&apos;s use of a password, and managed to escape by using the password.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tarimaro&apos;s troop fell into disorder and was defeated, however Tarimaro himself had noticed that the enemy&apos;s soldiers had been using a word, and managed to run away saying &apos;kane&apos; to the enemy.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tarimaro&apos;s troop fell into disorder and was defeated, however Tarimaro himself had noticed that the enemy&apos;s soldiers had been using a word, and managed to run away saying &apos;kane&apos; to the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>田辺小隅の部隊は、翌日多品治によって撃退された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanabe no OSUMI&apos;s troups were pushed back the following day by Oo no HONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following day TANABE no Osumi&apos;s troops were beaten by O no Honji.</e>
<cmt>表記ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following day TANABE no Osumi&apos;s troops were beaten by O no Honji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>田中臣は、天武天皇13年（684年）11月1日に、朝臣の姓を授かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanaka Omi was given the title of Ason on November 1st, 684.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanaka no Omi was given the kabane of Asomi (Ason) on November 1, 684.</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanaka no Omi was given the kabane of Asomi (Ason) on December 15, 684.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>田中朝臣足麻呂は、文武天皇2年（698年）6月29日に死んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TANAKA Ason Maro died on June 29th, 698.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TANAKA no Asomi Tarimaro died on June 29, 698.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞読み間違いがあります。用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TANAKA no Asomi Tarimaro died on August 13, 698.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更して最初の日付に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そのとき直広参の位であったが、壬申の功臣であるため、直広壱の位を贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held the rank of jikikosan at the time of his death, but was given the rank of jikikoichi to honor his outstanding service during the Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt>直広壱の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had held the rank of Jikikosan at that time, and was given the rank of Jikikoichi to honor his outstanding service during the Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had held the rank of Jikikosan at that time, and was given the rank of Jikikoichi to honor his outstanding service during the Jinshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kinori(id:443), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>