<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浅井久政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisamasa AZAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisamasa AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisamasa AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浅井 久政（あざい ひさまさ、淺井 久政、）は日本の戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisamasa AZAI was a Japanese military commander called busho in the Sengoku period (the Warring States period).</e>
<cmt>本文に「日本の」があるため、（日本）は略。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisamasa AZAI was a Japanese military commander called busho during the Sengoku period (the Warring States period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisamasa AZAI was a Japanese military commander called busho during the Sengoku period (the Warring States period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近江国の戦国大名浅井氏2代目当主、下野国守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second head of the Azai clan, the warring lord of Omi Province, and the governor of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second head of the Azai clan, the warring lord of Omi Province, and the governor of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second head of the Azai clan, the warring lord of Omi Province, and the governor of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>浅井長政（賢政）の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of Nagamasa (賢政 Yoshimasa/Takamasa) AZAI.</e>
<cmt>[正しい読み方が不明です]　賢政: 一般に、２通りの読み方があり、この場合はどちらか分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of Nagamasa (賢政 Yoshimasa/Takamasa) AZAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of Nagamasa (賢政 Yoshimasa/Takamasa) AZAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、名字および所領地の「浅井」の読みは「あざい」が正しく、「あさい」という読み方は誤りであると考えられてきたが、最新の研究では、やはり「あさい」が正しいという学説もある（宮島敬一著「浅井氏三代」参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;浅井&quot; has been pronounced as &quot;Azai&quot; not as &quot;Asai&quot; when it represents the family name and the territory, another theory that it was originally &quot;Asai&quot; has now come as a result of the latest research (see &quot;Asai-shi sandai&quot; ([The Three Generations of the Asai Clan] by Kei-ichi Miyajima).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;浅井&quot; has been pronounced as &quot;Azai&quot; not as &quot;Asai&quot; when it represents the family name and the territory, another theory that it was originally &quot;Asai&quot; has now come as a result of the latest research (see &quot;Asai-shi sandai&quot; ([The Three Generations of the Asai Clan] by Kei-ichi Miyajima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;浅井&quot; has been pronounced as &quot;Azai&quot; not as &quot;Asai&quot; when it represents the family name and the territory, one of the theory based on the latest research states that it should be pronounced as &quot;Asai&quot; (see &quot;Asai-shi sandai&quot; [The Three Generations of the Asai Clan] by Kei-ichi Miyajima).</e>
<cmt>another theory that it was originally → one of the theory based on the latest research states that</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>浅井亮政の長子（庶長子の説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eldest child (or the eldest illegitimate child) of Sukemasa AZAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eldest child (or the eldest illegitimate child) of Sukemasa AZAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eldest child (or the eldest illegitimate child) of Sukemasa AZAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>生母は側室尼子氏の娘尼子馨庵（近江国の尼子氏で、出雲国の尼子氏はその庶家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real mother was Kaan AMAGO, a daughter of the Amago clan, who was a concubine (the Amago clan in Omi Province, and the Amago clan in Izumo Province was its branch family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real mother was Kaan AMAGO, a daughter of the Amago clan, who was a concubine (the Amago clan in Omi Province, and the Amago clan in Izumo Province was its branch family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real mother was Kaan AMAGO, a daughter of the Amago clan, who was a concubine (the Amago clan in Omi Province, and the Amago clan in Izumo Province was its branch family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>生母については、諸説があり『六角佐々木氏系図略』・「浅井過去帳」に浅井千代鶴とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for his real mother, there are several theories: &quot;Rokkaku Sasaki-shi keizuryaku&quot; [Rokkaku Sasaki Family Tree Rough] and &quot;the Azai family register of deaths&quot; show it was Chiyozuru AZAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for his real mother, there are several theories: &quot;Rokkaku Sasaki-shi keizuryaku&quot; [Rokkaku Sasaki Family Tree Rough] and &quot;the Azai family register of deaths&quot; show it was Chiyozuru AZAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for his real mother, there are several theories: &quot;Rokkaku Sasaki-shi keizuryaku&quot; [Rokkaku Sasaki Family Tree Rough] and &quot;the Azai family register of deaths&quot; show it was Chiyozuru AZAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この女性は六角宗能（親泰）側室で、久政は養子であり、尼子氏は養母であるとも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This woman was a concubine of Muneyoshi [Chikayasu] ROKKAKU, and Hisamasa was an adopted child, whose adopted mother was the Amago clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This woman was a concubine of Muneyoshi [Chikayasu] ROKKAKU, and Hisamasa was an adopted child, whose adopted mother was from the Amago clan.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This woman was a concubine of Muneyoshi [Chikayasu] ROKKAKU, and Hisamasa was an adopted child, whose adopted mother was from the Amago clan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>妻は近江豪族井口経元の娘小野殿（阿古御料人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was Lady Ono (also called Ago goryonin), a daughter of Tsunemoto IGUCHI, a local ruling family in Omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was Lady Ono (also called Ago goryonin), a daughter of Tsunemoto IGUCHI, a local ruling family in Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was Lady Ono (also called Ago goryonin), a daughter of Tsunemoto IGUCHI, a local ruling family in Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>1542年に父・亮政が没したため後を継いだが、武勇に優れた父とは対照的に武勇に冴えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1542, when his father Sukemasa died, Hisamasa succeeded to his position as head of the family, but unlike his father he was not celebrated for his valor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1542, when his father Sukemasa died, Hisamasa succeeded to his position as head of the family, but unlike his father he was not celebrated for his valor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1542, when his father Sukemasa died, Hisamasa succeeded to his position as head of the family, but unlike his father he was not celebrated for his valor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>亮政は正室との間に生まれた鶴千代（久政の異母姉）の婿として、田屋明政（田屋氏は浅井氏庶家）に家督を譲ることを望んでいたともいわれるが、亮政が若いころに側室との間に生まれた久政が家督を継ぐこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Sukemasa expected Akimasa TAYA (the Taya is a branch family of the Azai) to succeed to the head position as the husband of Tsuruchiyo, a daughter with his lawful wife (an older paternal half-sister of Hisamasa), but Hisamasa, who was born of a concubine when Sukemasa was young, finally took over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Sukemasa expected Akimasa TAYA (the Taya is a branch family of the Azai) to succeed to the head position as the husband of Tsuruchiyo, his daughter with his lawful wife (an older paternal half-sister of Hisamasa), but Hisamasa, who was born of a concubine when Sukemasa was young, finally took over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Sukemasa expected Akimasa TAYA (the Taya is a branch family of the Azai) to succeed to the head position as the husband of Tsuruchiyo, his daughter with his lawful wife (an older paternal half-sister of Hisamasa), but Hisamasa, who was born of a concubine when Sukemasa was young, finally took over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため、義兄・明政は久政の家督相続を承服せず、反乱をおこすなど久政の家督相続は家中に少なからぬ禍根を残す結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, his brother-in-law, Akimasa, did not accept Hisamasa&apos;s succession to the position of family head by raising a rebellion, which resulted in the significant cause of later trouble in his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, his brother-in-law, Akimasa, did not accept Hisamasa&apos;s succession to the position of family head by raising a rebellion, which resulted in the significant cause of later trouble in his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, his brother-in-law, Akimasa, did not accept Hisamasa&apos;s succession to the position of family head by raising a rebellion, which resulted in the significant cause of later trouble in his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>久政が当主となってからの浅井家は次第に六角氏の攻勢に押されてついにその配下となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Azai family headed by Hisamasa was gradually overwhelmed by the power of the Rokkaku clan, and finally the Azai became their subordinate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Azai family headed by Hisamasa was gradually overwhelmed by the power of the Rokkaku clan, and finally the Azai became their subordinate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Azai family headed by Hisamasa was gradually overwhelmed by the power of the Rokkaku clan, and finally the Azai became their subordinate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>嫡男に六角義賢の一字　賢の字を偏諱として受けさせ、「賢政」と名乗らせたりその妻に六角氏家臣平井定武の娘を娶らせるなど、六角氏に対しては徹底した従属的姿勢をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisamasa persistently showed a subordinate posture to the Rokkaku clan by taking in part of Yoshikata ROKKAKU&apos;s name, &quot;taka,&quot; into his heir&apos;s name as &quot;Takamasa,&quot; in addition to his marriage with a daughter of Sadatake HIRAI, a vassal of the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisamasa persistently showed a subordinate posture to the Rokkaku clan by taking in part of Yoshikata ROKKAKU&apos;s name, &quot;taka,&quot; into his heir&apos;s name as &quot;Takamasa,&quot; in addition to his marriage with a daughter of Sadatake HIRAI, a vassal of the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisamasa persistently showed a subordinate posture to the Rokkaku clan by taking in part of Yoshikata ROKKAKU&apos;s name, &quot;taka (賢),&quot; into his heir&apos;s name as &quot;Takamasa (賢政),&quot; in addition to his marriage with a daughter of Sadatake HIRAI, a vassal of the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>漢字を添えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>このような、久政の弱腰外交に家臣たちの多くが不満をもつようになり、1560年に久政の嫡男・浅井長政が野良田の戦いで六角義賢に大勝し六角氏から独立すると、家臣たちから家督を長政に譲ることを強要され、強制的に隠居させられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dissatisfied with Hisamasa&apos;s such weak-kneed diplomacy, many of his vassals forced Hisamasa to retire for transferring his position as head of the family to Nagamasa AZAI, the heir to Hisamasa in 1560, when Nagamasa won a landslide victory over Yoshikata ROKKAKU in the Battle of Norada and became independent from the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dissatisfied with Hisamasa&apos;s weak-kneed diplomacy, many of his vassals forced Hisamasa to retire for transferring his position as head of the family to Nagamasa AZAI, the heir to Hisamasa in 1560, when Nagamasa won a landslide victory over Yoshikata ROKKAKU at the Battle of Norada and became independent from the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dissatisfied with Hisamasa&apos;s weak-kneed diplomacy, many of his vassals forced Hisamasa to retire for transferring his position as head of the family to Nagamasa AZAI, the heir to Hisamasa in 1560, when Nagamasa won a landslide victory over Yoshikata ROKKAKU at the Battle of Norada and became independent from the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一時は竹生島に幽閉されていたほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisamasa was even incarcerated in the Chikubu Island for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisamasa was even incarcerated on Chikubu Island for a while.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisamasa was even incarcerated on Chikubu Island for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしこのクーデター的家督移譲には不明瞭なところが多く、久政は隠居してもなおも発言力を持ちつづけ、父以来の朝倉氏との友好関係に固執し、新興勢力の織田氏との同盟関係の構築には終始反対しつづけたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this coup-like transfer does not make sense overall: it is said that Hisamasa maintained a big voice even after his retirement and continued to oppose the establishment of an alliance with an emerging force, the Oda clan, sticking to the amicable relationship with the Asakura clan, which had been maintained since his father was in power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this coup-like transfer does not make sense overall: it is said that Hisamasa maintained a big voice even after his retirement and continued to oppose the establishment of an alliance with an emerging force, the Oda clan, sticking to the amicable relationship with the Asakura clan, which had been maintained since his father was in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this coup-like transfer of power has some ambiguous aspects: it is said that Hisamasa maintained a big voice even after his retirement and continued to oppose the establishment of an alliance with an emerging force, the Oda clan, sticking to the amicable relationship with the Asakura clan, which had been maintained since his father was in power.</e>
<cmt>transfer does not make sense overall → transfer of power has some ambiguous aspects</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、この久政と長政との曖昧な関係が結果的には浅井家滅亡の遠因となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this vague relationship between Hisamasa and Nagamasa resulted in an underlying cause of the ruin of the Azai family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this vague relationship between Hisamasa and Nagamasa resulted in the underlying cause of the ruin of the Azai family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this vague relationship between Hisamasa and Nagamasa resulted in the underlying cause of the ruin of the Azai family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>織田氏と朝倉氏が対立を深め、両家と同盟関係にあった浅井家はどちらにつくかの決断を迫られた場面で久政は強硬に朝倉方につくべきであると主張し、長政が折れる形で信長に反旗を翻すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Azai family had to make a decision on which side they should take under the serious confrontation between the Oda and the Asakura clans as a partner of both sides, Hisamasa strongly insisted that they should side with the Asakura, and Nagamasa rebelled against Nobunaga, making a compromise with his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Azai family had to make a decision on which side they should take under the serious confrontation between the Oda and the Asakura clans as a partner of both sides, Hisamasa strongly insisted that they should side with the Asakura, and Nagamasa rebelled against Nobunaga, compromising with his father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Azai family had to make a decision on which side they should take under the serious confrontation between the Oda and the Asakura clans as a partner of both sides, Hisamasa strongly insisted that they should side with the Asakura, and Nagamasa rebelled against Nobunaga, compromising with his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>結果的に数年間の抵抗の末、浅井・朝倉連合は織田氏に敗北し、1573年、織田軍の猛攻を受けた久政は、小谷城京極丸にて自害し、長政もやがて自刃し戦国大名浅井氏は三代で終幕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of a struggle over several years, the alliance of the Azai and the Asakura was defeated by the Oda clan, and in 1573, Hisamasa killed himself in the Kyogokumaru section inside Odani-jo Castle due to fierce attacks from the Oda army while Nagamasa soon fell on his sword, which resulted in putting an end to the Azai family as a feudal lord only in three generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of a struggle over several years, the alliance of the Azai and the Asakura was defeated by the Oda clan, and in 1573, Hisamasa killed himself in the Kyogokumaru section inside Odani-jo Castle due to fierce attacks from the Oda army while Nagamasa soon fell on his sword, which resulted in putting an end to the Azai family as a feudal lord in just three generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of a struggle over several years, the alliance of the Azai and the Asakura was defeated by the Oda clan, and in 1573, Hisamasa killed himself in the Kyogokumaru section inside Odani-jo Castle due to fierce attacks from the Oda army while Nagamasa soon fell on his sword, which resulted in putting an end to the Azai family as a feudal lord in just three generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>後世の再評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reappraisal by Later Generations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reappraisal by Later Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reappraisal by Later Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>一般に久政は、時の流れを読めなかった暗愚な当主とされることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, Hisamasa is often regarded as a foolish family head, who was not able to anticipate the current of the times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, Hisamasa is often regarded as a foolish family head, who was not able to anticipate the currents of the times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, Hisamasa is often regarded as a foolish family head, who was not able to anticipate the currents of the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>久政暗愚説の根拠となっている歴史書の多くが学術的には偽書と位置付けられており、後年になって誇大に記述されたり、脚色されたものがほとんどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the history books regarded as the grounds for the theories where Hisamasa was imbecile are considered to be academically apocryphal, and most of them were exaggerated or embroidered in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the history books regarded as grounds for the theories where Hisamasa was an imbecile are considered to be academically apocryphal, and most of them were exaggerated or embroidered in later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the history books regarded as grounds for the theories where Hisamasa was an imbecile are considered to be academically apocryphal, and most of them were exaggerated or embroidered in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>最近の有力説に久政がそれほど無能ではなかったという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the widely accepted theories in recent years is that Hisamasa was not so incompetent as regarded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the widely accepted theories in recent years is that Hisamasa was not so incompetent as regarded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the widely accepted theories in recent years is that Hisamasa was not so incompetent as regarded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>六角氏への従属の再評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reassessment of Subordination to the Rokkaku Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reassessment of Subordination to the Rokkaku Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reassessment of Subordination to the Rokkaku Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>浅井・朝倉同盟は久政の父で長政の祖父である浅井亮政の代には存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The alliance between the Asai and the Asakura had already existed when Sukemasa AZAI, the father of Hisamasa and the grandfather of Nagamasa, was in power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alliance between the Asai and the Asakura had already existed when Sukemasa AZAI, the father of Hisamasa and the grandfather of Nagamasa, was in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alliance between the Asai and the Asakura had already existed when Sukemasa AZAI, the father of Hisamasa and the grandfather of Nagamasa, was in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>亮政は南近江守護であり、かつての主家である北近江守護京極家の本家筋である六角家と対立していた際に、朝倉氏との同盟を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukemasa, who was the provincial constable of Minami Omi, had established an alliance with the Asakura clan when he was conflicting with the Rokkaku family, the head family of the Kyogoku serving as the provincial constable of Kita Omi, who once was the master of Sukemasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukemasa, who was the provincial constable of Minami Omi, had established an alliance with the Asakura clan when he was in conflict with the Rokkaku family, the head family of the Kyogoku serving as the provincial constable of Kita Omi, who once was the master of Sukemasa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukemasa, who was the provincial constable of Minami Omi, had established an alliance with the Asakura clan when he was in conflict with the Rokkaku family, the head family of the Kyogoku serving as the provincial constable of Kita Omi, who once was the master of Sukemasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>当時の六角家は名君六角定頼を筆頭に日の出の勢いであり、その優劣の差は亮政の才をもってしても補うことはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Headed by a wise ruler Sadayori, the Rokkaku family was in the ascendant, and the gap in power between the two families could not be bridged even by Sukemasa, who was a brilliant ruler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Headed by the wise ruler Sadayori, the Rokkaku family was in the ascendant, and the gap in power between the two families could not be bridged even by Sukemasa, who was a brilliant ruler.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Headed by the wise ruler Sadayori, the Rokkaku family was in the ascendant, and the gap in power between the two families could not be bridged even by Sukemasa, who was a brilliant ruler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>事実、亮政は美濃や越前へ幾度も逃亡している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Sukemasa escaped to Mino and Echizen several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Sukemasa escaped to Mino and Echizen several times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Sukemasa escaped to Mino and Echizen several times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>一方、当時の朝倉家も全盛期であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Asakura family was also at the highest of its prosperity at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Asakura family was also at the highest of its prosperity at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Asakura family was also at the highest of its prosperity at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その朝倉家にしても、北に一向一揆という爆弾を抱えており、大勢力である六角家との直接対立は望むことではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the Asakura family had a flash point of Ikko sect&apos;s revolt in the northern area, and they were not willing to directly conflict with the Rokkaku family, a large force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even the Asakura family had a flash point of Ikko sect&apos;s revolt in the northern area, and they were not willing to directly conflict with the Rokkaku family, a large force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even the Asakura family had a flash point of Ikko sect&apos;s revolt in the northern area, and they were not willing to directly conflict with the Rokkaku family, a large force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>緩衝地帯として、北近江を手中に収める浅井氏との同盟は理に適ったものあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The alliance with the Azai clan, who controlled Kita Omi, was reasonable enough to leave it as a buffer zone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alliance with the Azai clan, who controlled Kita Omi, was reasonable enough to leave as a buffer zone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alliance with the Azai clan, who controlled Kita Omi, was reasonable enough to leave as a buffer zone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>両者の利が一致して、朝倉・浅井同盟は築かれたのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sharing a mutual interest, the alliance between the Asakura and the Azai seems to have been established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sharing a mutual interest, the alliance between the Asakura and the Azai seemed to have been established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sharing a mutual interest, the alliance between the Asakura and the Azai seemed to have been established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、朝倉孝景 (10代当主)と朝倉宗滴が世を去った後の朝倉家はかつての勢いを失っており、同盟の意味は薄まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the death of Takakage ASAKURA (the 10th head) and Soteki (宗滴) ASAKURA, the Asakura family was not so powerful as in the past, and the alliance had little significance.</e>
<cmt>宗滴: 「のりかげ」という読み方を併記してあるものもありましたが、景が使ってないので「そうてき」で良いように思いました。朝日日本歴史人物事典の用語解説では、「そうてき」です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the death of Takakage ASAKURA (the tenth head) and Soteki (宗滴) ASAKURA, the Asakura family was not so powerful as in the past, and the alliance had little significance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the death of Takakage ASAKURA (the tenth head) and Soteki (宗滴) ASAKURA, the Asakura family was not so powerful as in the past, and the alliance had little significance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>だからこそ、久政は朝倉家から六角家へと乗り換えたのだろうと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Hisamasa is regarded to have transferred to the Rokkaku family from the Asakaura family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Hisamasa is regarded to have transferred to the Rokkaku family from the Asakaura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Hisamasa is regarded to have transferred to the Rokkaku family from the Asakaura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>六角氏に臣従した頃、浅井家は京極氏や隣国美濃の斎藤道三からたびたび攻撃され、窮地に陥っていた事実がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the Azai family ran into difficulty due to repeated attacks from the Kyogoku clan and Dosan SAITO in the neighboring province, Mino when they subordinated themselves to the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, the Azai family ran into difficulty due to repeated attacks from the Kyogoku clan and Dosan SAITO in the neighboring province, Mino when they subordinated themselves to the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the Azai family ran into difficulty due to repeated attacks from the Kyogoku clan and Dosan SAITO in the neighboring province, Mino when they subordinated themselves to the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>六角氏に臣従して庇護を受ければ、他の勢力を牽制することになって侵攻を食い止められ、領国経営に専念することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the protection from the Rokkaku clan as their subordinate, the Azai family could concentrate on management of their territory while preventing invasion from other powers with restraints put on them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the protection from the Rokkaku clan as their subordinate, the Azai family was able to concentrate on the management of their territory while preventing invasions from other powers with restraints put on them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the protection from the Rokkaku clan as their subordinate, the Azai family was able to concentrate on the management of their territory while preventing invasions from other powers with restraints put on them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>事実、その間に久政は政治の安定化（後述）や先代浅井亮政が武力によって傘下に収めた土豪たちの掌握に努めており、浅井家を戦国大名へと押し上げる基礎を築きあげることに成功していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Hisamasa succeeded in building up the foundation for the Azai family&apos;s rise to a feudal lord while stabilizing political circumstances (mentioned later) and putting effort into taking control of powerful local clans who were forced to be affiliated with the former lord, Sukemasa AZAI, at sword point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Hisamasa succeeded in building up the foundation for the Azai family&apos;s rise to a feudal lord while stabilizing political circumstances (mentioned later) and putting effort into taking control of powerful local clans who were forced to be affiliated with the former lord, Sukemasa AZAI, at sword point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Hisamasa succeeded in building up the foundation for the Azai family&apos;s rise to a feudal lord while stabilizing political circumstances (mentioned later) and putting effort into taking control of powerful local clans who were forced to be affiliated with the former lord, Sukemasa AZAI, at sword point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>さらに、六角氏の勢力内といっても、大名の家名を保ち、領土も削られていないのは、従属大名としては稀な例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Azai family maintained the family name as a feudal lord without reducing the territory even under the control of the Rokkaku clan, which was a rare case to a subordinate lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Azai family maintained the family name as a feudal lord without reducing the territory even under the control of the Rokkaku clan, which was a rare case for a subordinate lord.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Azai family maintained the family name as a feudal lord without reducing the territory even under the control of the Rokkaku clan, which was a rare case for a subordinate lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>松平家は今川義元や織田信長に領土を一部明け渡している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Matsudaira family ceded part of their territory to Yoshimoto IMAGAWA and Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsudaira family ceded part of their territory to Yoshimoto IMAGAWA and Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsudaira family ceded part of their territory to Yoshimoto IMAGAWA and Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>このことからすると、久政は優れた外交能力を持っていたのではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking this into account, Hisamasa seems to have had superior ability in diplomacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking this into account, Hisamasa seems to have had superior ability in diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking this into account, Hisamasa seems to have had superior ability in diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>弱腰と見られがちな従属という形も領国を守る手であり、外交の分野では成功を収めたのではないだろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The subordination, which is often regarded as a sign of weakness, may have been a means to protect his territory, and Hisamasa seems to have succeeded in the field of diplomacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subordination, often regarded as a sign of weakness, may have been a means to protect his territory, and Hisamasa seems to have succeeded in the field of diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subordination, often regarded as a sign of weakness, may have been a means to protect his territory, and Hisamasa seems to have succeeded in the field of diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>内政においての再評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reappraisal in Domestic Administration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reappraisal in Domestic Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reappraisal in Domestic Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>内政面でも久政の業績を挙げることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisamasa made significant achievements also in domestic administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisamasa made significant achievements also in domestic administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisamasa made significant achievements also in domestic administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>まず、治水や灌漑事業がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, he implemented flood control and irrigation projects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, he implemented flood control and irrigation projects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, he implemented flood control and irrigation projects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>湖北の村々の河川用水の使用区域の対立を調停するため、法令や文書を発給し、それを阻害すると思われる豪族に対して圧力をかけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issuing regulations and documents to conciliate the confrontation over where to use river water among the villages in Kohoku, he put pressure upon the local ruling families who seemed to prevent the conciliation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issuing regulations and documents to conciliate the confrontation over where to use river water among the villages in Kohoku, he put pressure upon the local ruling families who seemed to be preventing the conciliation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issuing regulations and documents to conciliate the confrontation over where to use river water among the villages in Kohoku, he put pressure upon the local ruling families who seemed to be preventing the conciliation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>例としてこんな話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here is one of such episodes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here is one of such episodes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here is one of such episodes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>当時小谷麓の村々で深刻な水不足があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those days the villages located at the foot of mountains in Odani suffered serious water deficiency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those days the villages located at the foot of mountains in Odani suffered serious water deficiency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those days the villages located at the foot of mountains in Odani suffered serious water deficiency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その辺りの用水の源である高時川の水流を握るのは、力を持つ豪族の井口氏であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the Iguchi clan, a local ruling family, that controlled the water flow of the Takatoki-gawa River, the water source around there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the Iguchi clan, a local ruling family, that controlled the water flow of the Takatoki-gawa River, the water source around there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the Iguchi clan, a local ruling family, that controlled the water flow of the Takatoki-gawa River, the water source around there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>久政は村民の願いによって井口氏へ圧力をかけたが、井口氏は大量の貢物という難題をふっかけ、あきらめさせようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hisamasa put pressure upon the Iguchi clan at the request of the villagers, the Iguchi clan made an unreasonable demand of an enormous amount of tribute in order to keep them quiet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hisamasa put pressure upon the Iguchi clan at the request of the villagers, the Iguchi clan made an unreasonable demand of an enormous amount of tribute in order to keep them quiet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hisamasa put pressure upon the Iguchi clan at the request of the villagers, the Iguchi clan made an unreasonable demand of an enormous amount of tribute in order to keep them quiet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし中野（現東浅井郡）の土豪がこれを引き受けたため、井口氏も渋々承諾したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a rich clan in Nakano (now Higashiazai County) accepted this demand, so the Iguchi clan reluctantly agreed in the end.</e>
<cmt>「最上流井堰を認める条件を提示し、暗に断ったつもりでいた。ところが、あにはからんや中野の土豪で資産家である長者が資産をなげ出して、この無理難題の品を贈ってきたので、やむを得ずこれを認めざるを得なかったと伝えられている。」を参考に翻訳。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a rich clan in Nakano (now Higashiazai County) accepted this demand, so the Iguchi clan reluctantly agreed in the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a rich clan in Nakano (now Higashiazai County) accepted this demand, so the Iguchi clan reluctantly agreed in the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>（この間に中野の土豪の娘が人柱となって水を得たという逸話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(There is also an anecdote that in the meantime a daughter of that clan in Nakano sacrificed herself to obtain water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(There is also an anecdote that in the meantime a daughter of that clan in Nakano sacrificed herself to obtain water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There is also an anecdote that in the meantime a daughter of that clan in Nakano sacrificed herself to obtain water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また貢物の中に餅千駄とあったため、彼らの業績をたたえて餅ノ井と名づけられた。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The weir was named &quot;Mochinoi&quot; after the rice cake loaded on 1,000 oxen to be delivered part of the tribute, commemorating their deed.)</e>
<cmt>「綾千駄、餅千駄、綿千駄（千駄とは牛千頭こ積んだ荷物分）」「かくしてようやく最上流に井堰を新設し餅千駄から餅ノ井と名ずけれらたという。」を参考に翻訳。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The weir was named &quot;Mochinoi&quot; after the rice cake loaded on 1,000 oxen to be delivered part of the tribute, commemorating their deed.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The weir was named &quot;Mochinoi&quot; after the rice cake loaded on 1,000 oxen to be delivered part of the tribute, commemorating their deed.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>用水路を確保した久政は灌漑事業を拡大したが、用水をめぐって村同士の争いが発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hisamasa secured water and expanded the irrigation project, a conflict was caused over the water among the villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hisamasa secured water and expanded the irrigation project, a conflict was caused over the water among the villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hisamasa secured water and expanded the irrigation project, a conflict was caused over the water among the villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この調停のため、用水口の統一や水量や村による優先順位の指定などをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For mediation, Hisamasa prescribed the size of weirs for unification, the volume of water consumption and the priority among the villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For mediation, Hisamasa prescribed the size of weirs for unification, the volume of water consumption and the priority among the villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For mediation, Hisamasa prescribed the size of weirs for unification, the volume of water consumption and the priority among the villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>（なお、この時の取り決めは江戸から現代にかけてまで守られている。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(These rules have been strictly observed until today since the Edo period.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(These rules have been strictly observed until today since the Edo period.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(These rules have been strictly observed until today since the Edo period.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="54">
<j>また、小谷城山上に六坊（寺の集住）を建設したり、寺社衆に対して所領の安堵や税政策の強化などを打ち出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hisamasa built rokubo (a complex of temples) on the top of the mountain where Odani-jo Castle is located while guaranteeing the ownerships of territory to temples and shrines with reinforced taxation policies.</e>
<cmt>「安堵（あんど）とは、古代末期から近世にかけて日本の土地私有制度において、主君（もしくは支配者）が家臣（もしくは被支配者）に対して所領知行（土地権利）や所職の存在・継続・移転などを保証・承認する行為を指す。」を参考。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hisamasa built rokubo (a complex of temples) on the top of the mountain where Odani-jo Castle is located while guaranteeing the ownerships of territory to temples and shrines with reinforced taxation policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Hisamasa built rokubo (a complex of temples) on the top of the mountain where Odani-jo Castle is located while guaranteeing the ownerships of territory to temples and shrines with reinforced taxation policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="55">
<j>さらには小谷城の増築、土塁の建設も行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hisamasa extended Odani-jo Castle and constructed earthworks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hisamasa extended Odani-jo Castle and constructed earthworks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Hisamasa extended Odani-jo Castle and constructed earthworks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="56">
<j>この他に、後世の悪評にもつながるが、積極的に能などの文化を推進し（久政には森本鶴太夫というお抱えの舞楽師がいた）、鷹狩や連歌を嗜み、文化人としても名を馳せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Hisamasa, who was well known as a man of culture, proactively promoted culture including Noh (he had an exclusive Noh player, Tsurutayu NORIMOTO), and enjoyed falconry and renga (linked verses), which led to a bad reputation in later generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Hisamasa, who was well known as a man of culture, proactively promoted culture including Noh (he had an exclusive Noh player, Tsurutayu NORIMOTO), and enjoyed falconry and renga (linked verses), which led to a bad reputation in later generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Hisamasa, who was well known as a man of culture, proactively promoted culture including Noh (he had an exclusive Noh player, Tsurutayu MORIMOTO), and enjoyed falconry and renga (linked verses), which led to a bad reputation in later generations.</e>
<cmt>NORIMOTO → MORIMOTO</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>長政への家督移譲の再評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reassessment of the Transfer to Nagamasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reassessment of the Transfer to Nagamasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reassessment of the Transfer to Nagamasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>通常、戦の有無にかかわらず、クーデターという実力行使によって家督が移った場合、前代当主の家中における発言力は皆無になることが通例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, the influence of the former head is completely lost in the family when the position is forcibly transferred in a coup regardless of a fight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, the influence of the former head is completely lost in the family when the position is forcibly transferred in a coup regardless of the fight.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, whether or not a fight have taken place, the influence of the former head is completely lost in the family when the position is forcibly transferred in a coup.</e>
<cmt>regardless of a fight では分かりにくいようで regardless of the fight に変更されていますが、特定の戦いではないのでこれもおかしいと思います。whether or not a fight have taken place として位置を前にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、竹生島に幽閉された久政が、長政や長政派の家臣たちと和解したという形で小谷城に帰還していることからすると、この家督移譲劇は、浅井家中にある久政に対する不満を長政に家督を譲ることで沈静化させ、家臣団の結束を高めるための芝居に過ぎなかったとみることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking account of the fact that Hisamasa incarcerated in Chikubu Island returned to Odani-jo Castle under the reconciliation with Nagamasa and his vassals, this transfer incident may be regarded as only a play to closely unite the vassals by releasing dissatisfaction with Hisamasa growing in the Azai family through the transfer of the head position to Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking account of the fact that Hisamasa incarcerated in Chikubu Island returned to Odani-jo Castle under reconciliation with Nagamasa and his vassals, this transfer incident may be regarded as only a play to closely unite the vassals by releasing dissatisfaction with Hisamasa that was growing in the Azai family through the transfer of the head position to Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking account of the fact that Hisamasa incarcerated in Chikubu Island returned to Odani-jo Castle under reconciliation with Nagamasa and his vassals, this transfer incident may be regarded as only a play to closely unite the vassals by releasing dissatisfaction with Hisamasa that was growing in the Azai family through the transfer of the head position to Nagamasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>言い換えれば、久政自身の政治力を剥ぐためのものではなかったということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, this transfer did not aim to deprive Hisamasa of his political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, this transfer did not actually aim to deprive Hisamasa of his political power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, this transfer did not actually aim to deprive Hisamasa of his political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>それに、クーデターを起こされた側が失脚後も権力を維持していた場合、元の権力の奪還のための動きが起こり得るのに、浅井家では起こっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the party against which a coup was launched often tries to regain control of the power when that party has been maintaining the power even after the loss of position, which did not occur in the Azai family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the party against which a coup was launched often tries to regain control of the power when that party has been maintaining the power even after the loss of position, which did not occur in the Azai family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the party against which a coup was launched often tries to regain control of the power when that party has been maintaining the power even after the loss of position, which did not occur in the Azai family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>こうしたことを考えると、この家督移譲は六角家からの独立を意図した芝居であった可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking these into consideration, there is a high possibility that this transfer may have been a play aiming to become independent from the Rokkaku family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking these into consideration, there is a high possibility that this transfer may have been a play aiming to become independent from the Rokkaku family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking these into consideration, there is a high possibility that this transfer may have been a play aiming to become independent from the Rokkaku family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>織田氏との敵対の再評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reassessment of Confrontation with the Oda Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reassessment of the Confrontation with the Oda Clan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reassessment of the Confrontation with the Oda Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>久政が朝倉方につくべきだと主張した理由として、「亮政の代からの同盟関係であること」、「度重なる斎藤氏氏、京極氏、六角氏の攻勢に共闘した大恩」、「久政自身が信長の性格や方針に懐疑的であったこと」などが挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the reasons why Hisamasa insisted that they should side with the Asakura clan were as follows: &quot;the alliance had been maintained since Sukemasa was in power&quot;; &quot;they were deeply indebted to the Asakura clan for joint fights against repeated attacks from the Saito, the Kyogoku and the Rokkaku clans&quot;; and &quot;Hisamasa himself was skeptical about the character and the policy of Nobunaga.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the reasons why Hisamasa insisted that they should side with the Asakura clan were as follows: &quot;the alliance had been maintained since Sukemasa was in power;&quot; &quot;they were deeply indebted to the Asakura clan for joint fights against repeated attacks from the Saito, the Kyogoku, and the Rokkaku clans;&quot; and &quot;Hisamasa himself was skeptical about the character and policy of Nobunaga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the reasons why Hisamasa insisted that they should side with the Asakura clan were as follows: &quot;the alliance had been maintained since Sukemasa was in power;&quot; &quot;they were deeply indebted to the Asakura clan for joint fights against repeated attacks from the Saito, the Kyogoku, and the Rokkaku clans;&quot; and &quot;Hisamasa himself was skeptical about the character and policy of Nobunaga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>しかし、朝倉家との同盟関係があるなら、六角家に服属するようなことはしないはずであり、朝倉・浅井同盟は存在しない可能性も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Azai would not have subordinated themselves to the Rokkaku family if they had built an alliance with the Asakura family, which implies the possibility that the alliance between the Asakura and the Azai may have not existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Azai would not have subordinated themselves to the Rokkaku family if they had built an alliance with the Asakura family, which implies the possibility that the alliance between the Asakura and the Azai may have not existed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Azai would not have subordinated themselves to the Rokkaku family if they had built an alliance with the Asakura family, which implies the possibility that the alliance between the Asakura and the Azai may have not existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>（ただし、朝倉家は冬場の軍事的活動が困難な上、久政が当主を継いだ時期には朝倉家は加賀一向一揆との緊張が再燃する一方、美濃土岐家の内紛に深く関与しており、近江方面への積極的な介入が困難であった事実は考慮されるべきである。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(However, the following facts should be taken into account: it was difficult for the Asakura family to take military action during the wintertime, and it was hard to willingly intervene in Omi Province in association with Hisamasa&apos;s succession to the position of the family head when the tension between the Asakura family and the Ikko sect followers in Kaga was running high again, and the Asakura family was deeply involved in the internal conflict of the Toki family in Mino.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, the following facts should be taken into account: it was difficult for the Asakura family to take military action during the wintertime, and it was hard to willingly intervene in Omi Province in association with Hisamasa&apos;s succession to the position of the family head when the tension between the Asakura family and the Ikko sect followers in Kaga was running high again, and the Asakura family was deeply involved in the internal conflict of the Toki family in Mino.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, the following facts should be taken into account: it was difficult for the Asakura family to take military action during the wintertime, and it was hard to willingly intervene in Omi Province in association with Hisamasa&apos;s succession to the position of the family head when the tension between the Asakura family and the Ikko sect followers in Kaga was running high again, and the Asakura family was deeply involved in the internal conflict of the Toki family in Mino.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>この傍証として、朝倉家が主家である斯波家からその領土を奪うような形で越前を乗っ取った時点で、斯波家配下の守護代であった織田家と朝倉家は仇敵のような間柄であったはずという考え方がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As collateral evidence of this perception, it is said that the Asakura family and the Oda family, the acting military governor under the control of the Shiba family, had been in an enemy-like relationship since the Asakura family occupied Echizen by depriving the Shiba family, their master, of the territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As collateral evidence of this perception, it is said that the Asakura family and the Oda family, the acting military governor under the control of the Shiba family, had been in an enemy-like relationship since the Asakura family occupied Echizen by depriving the Shiba family, their master, of the territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As collateral evidence of this perception, it is said that the Asakura family and the Oda family, the acting military governor under the control of the Shiba family, had been in an enemy-like relationship since the Asakura family occupied Echizen by depriving the Shiba family, their master, of the territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>そうであるなら、朝倉家と対立する織田家の当主である信長の妹を、息子の正室に迎えることは、朝倉・浅井同盟があるのならば、しなかったはずというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If so, Hisamasa would not have accepted a younger sister of Nobunaga, the head of the Oda family in confrontation with the Asakura family, as the lawful wife of his son, under the alliance between the Asakura and the Asai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If so, Hisamasa would not have accepted the younger sister of Nobunaga, the head of the Oda family in confrontation with the Asakura family, as the lawful wife for his son, under the alliance between the Asakura and the Asai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If so, Hisamasa would not have accepted the younger sister of Nobunaga, the head of the Oda family in confrontation with the Asakura family, as the lawful wife for his son, under the alliance between the Asakura and the Azai.</e>
<cmt>Asai → Azai</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="67">
<j>また、三好・朝倉・石山本願寺・武田、そして浅井家による信長包囲網の成立した頃は、信長が最も窮地に立たされた時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, completely surrounded by the Miyoshi clan, the Asakura clan, Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple, the Takeda clan and the Azai clan, Nobunaga was facing the extreme difficulty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, completely surrounded by the Miyoshi clan, the Asakura clan, Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple, the Takeda clan and the Azai clan, Nobunaga was facing extreme difficulty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, completely surrounded by the Miyoshi clan, the Asakura clan, Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple, the Takeda clan and the Azai clan, Nobunaga was facing extreme difficulty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>これだけの強敵に囲まれた信長を、当時は誰もが滅亡すると思っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, everyone thought that Nobunaga, who was surrounded by such tough enemies, would be ruined sooner or later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, everyone thought that Nobunaga, who was surrounded by such tough enemies, would be ruined sooner or later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, everyone thought that Nobunaga, who was surrounded by such tough enemies, would be ruined sooner or later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>だが、幸運と独自の戦略眼によって信長はその窮地を脱し、覇者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to good luck and his unique strategic perspective, Nobunaga got out of the difficulty to be the hegemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to good luck and his unique strategic perspective, Nobunaga escaped the difficulty to become the hegemon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to good luck and his unique strategic perspective, Nobunaga escaped the difficulty to become the hegemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="70">
<j>これらのことからすると、久政が織田氏を見限って朝倉氏との共闘を選択したのは、従来言われてきたような復古的・情緒的理由からではなく、戦国大名としての戦略的な思考によるものではないかと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking these into account, the reason Hisamasa abandoned the Oda clan to choose the coalition with the Asakura clan seems to have been not his reactionary emotion but the result of his strategic perception as a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking this into account, the reason Hisamasa abandoned the Oda clan to choose the coalition with the Asakura clan seems to not have been his reactionary emotion, but the result of his strategic perception as a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking this into account, the reason Hisamasa abandoned the Oda clan to choose the coalition with the Asakura clan seems to not have been his reactionary emotion, but the result of his strategic perception as a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>結果的に戦国大名浅井氏が滅亡に追い込んだことから、久政は時の流れを読むことができなかった暗愚な当主と言われるようになったのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leading to the ruin of a feudal lord, the Asai clan, Hisamasa seems to have been regarded as a foolish leader who could not read the current of the times.</e>
<cmt>「結果的に戦国大名浅井氏が滅亡に追い込んだことから」日本語がおかしいような気がします。「結果的に戦国大名浅井氏[を]滅亡に追い込んだことから」と解釈してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leading to the ruin of a feudal lord, the Asai clan, Hisamasa seems to have been regarded as a foolish leader who could not read the current of the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leading to the ruin of a feudal lord, the Asai clan, Hisamasa seems to have been regarded as a foolish leader who could not read the current of the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>久政の最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Death of Hisamasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Death of Hisamasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Death of Hisamasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>1573年、織田軍は一乗谷陥落後打って返して小谷城を攻撃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, the Oda army attacked Odani-jo Castle soon after returning from Ichijodani Castle they destroyed.</e>
<cmt>「戦国時代に一乗谷城を中心に越前国を支配した戦国大名朝倉氏の遺跡。一乗谷城（山城）と山麓の城下町（朝倉氏および家臣の居館）からなる」を参考に翻訳。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, the Oda army attacked Odani-jo Castle soon after returning from destroying Ichijodani Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, the Oda army attacked Odani-jo Castle soon after returning from destroying Ichijodani Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>京極丸を羽柴隊に落とされ、久政の籠る小丸は長政の本丸と分断された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Kyogokumaru section was broken through by the Hashiba troops, the Komaru section, where Hisamasa entrenched himself, was disconnected from the castle keep, where Nagamasa stayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Kyogokumaru section was broken through by the Hashiba troops, the Komaru section, where Hisamasa entrenched himself, was disconnected from the castle keep, where Nagamasa stayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Kyogokumaru section was broken through by the Hashiba troops, the Komaru section, where Hisamasa entrenched himself, was disconnected from the castle keep, where Nagamasa stayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>羽柴勢はそのまま小丸を攻撃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hashiba troops continued to attack the Komaru section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hashiba troops continued to attack the Komaru section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hashiba troops continued to attack the Komaru section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>最期を悟った久政は井口越前守、赤尾清定らを呼び、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing that he was meeting the end, Hisamasa called Governor Iguchi of Echizen Province, Kiyosada Akao and other vassals, saying,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing that he was meeting his end, Hisamasa called Governor Iguchi of Echizen Province, Kiyosada Akao and other vassals, saying,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing that he was meeting his end, Hisamasa called Governor Iguchi of Echizen Province, Kiyosada Akao and other vassals, saying,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="76">
<j>「今よりわしは腹を切るゆえ、その間敵勢を食い止めてくれ」と言い渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I&apos;m committing hara-kiri, so please hold the enemy in check for the time being.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I&apos;m committing hara-kiri, so please hold the enemy in check for the time being.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I&apos;m committing hara-kiri, so please hold the enemy in check for the time being.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="77">
<j>彼らは羽柴勢より屋敷を死守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They defended the residence from the Hashiba troops to the death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They defended the residence from the Hashiba troops to the death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They defended the residence from the Hashiba troops to the death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>文字通り討ち死にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They literally died in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They literally died in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They literally died in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>久政は一族・浅井惟安、舞楽師の森本鶴松大夫と共に盃を傾けた後に切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After drinking the last sake together with Koreyasu AZAI, his relative, and MATSUMOTO Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫), a Noh dancer, Hisamasa committed hara-kiri.</e>
<cmt>[正しい読み方が不明です] 「鶴松大夫という舞の名手」とありますので、当時、舞とは能の舞のことを指すと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After drinking the last sake together with Koreyasu AZAI, his relative, and MATSUMOTO Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫), a Noh dancer, Hisamasa committed hara-kiri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After drinking the last sake together with Koreyasu AZAI, his relative, and MORIMOTO Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫), a Noh dancer, Hisamasa committed hara-kiri.</e>
<cmt>MATSUMOTO → MORIMOTO</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>これを福寿庵（惟安）が介錯し、次に福寿庵を鶴松大夫が介錯した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukujuan (Koreyasu) assisted Hisamasa in committing hara-kiri by beheading him, and then Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫) assisted Fukujuan.</e>
<cmt>[正しい読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukujuan (Koreyasu) assisted Hisamasa in committing hara-kiri by beheading him, and then Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫) assisted Fukujuan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukujuan (Koreyasu) assisted Hisamasa in committing hara-kiri by beheading him, and then Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫) assisted Fukujuan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>鶴松大夫は、「主君と同じ座敷では恐れ多い」と言って庭へ降り、そこで切腹して果てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saying, &quot;it is terribly rude to die in the same room together with the lord, &quot;Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫) went down into the garden, where he committed hara-kiri to die.</e>
<cmt>[正しい読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saying, &quot;it is terribly rude to die in the same room together with the lord, &quot;Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫) went down into the garden, where he committed hara-kiri to die.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saying, &quot;it is terribly rude to die in the same room together with the lord,&quot; Tsurumatsu Dayu (鶴松大夫) went down into the garden, where he committed hara-kiri to die.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="82">
<j>内政官的な久政ではあったが、この最期は同時期の武田勝頼や織田信長に引けをとらないものであり、湖北武士の名に恥じない最期であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being bureaucratic in domestic administration, Hisamasa died a glorious death like Katsuyori TAKEDA and Nobunaga ODA, who met their end in the same period, showing the spirit of a samurai in Kohoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being bureaucratic in domestic administration, Hisamasa died a glorious death like Katsuyori TAKEDA and Nobunaga ODA, who met their end during the same period, showing the spirit of the samurai in Kohoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being bureaucratic in domestic administration, Hisamasa died a glorious death like Katsuyori TAKEDA and Nobunaga ODA, who met their end during the same period, showing the spirit of the samurai in Kohoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>諸子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>男子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sons</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>浅井長政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa AZAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>浅井政元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto AZAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>浅井政之</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masayuki AZAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masayuki AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masayuki AZAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>岡崎安休</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ankyu OKAZAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ankyu OKAZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ankyu OKAZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>- 本願寺顕如の乳兄、異説 / 諸説あり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-Older foster brother of Kennyo HONGANJI, but there are different and various theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">-Older foster brother of Kennyo HONGANJI, but there are different and various theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">-Older foster brother of Kennyo HONGANJI, but there are different and various theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>大文字屋新十郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjuro DAIMONJIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinjuro DAIMONJIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinjuro DAIMONJIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>- 浅井治政のこと、異説 / 諸説あり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-Another name of Harumasa AZAI, but there are different and various theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">-Another name of Harumasa AZAI, but there are different and various theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">-Another name of Harumasa AZAI, but there are different and various theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="92">
<j>女子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daughters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daughters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daughters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>昌安見久尼（昌庵見久尼）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenkyuni SHOAN (昌庵 is also used instead of 昌安)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenkyuni SHOAN (昌庵 is also used instead of 昌安)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenkyuni SHOAN (昌庵 is also used instead of 昌安)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>京極マリア（京極高吉室）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maria KYOGOKU (the wife of Takayoshi KYOGOKU)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maria KYOGOKU (the wife of Takayoshi KYOGOKU)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maria KYOGOKU (the wife of Takayoshi KYOGOKU)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>大弐局（六角義実室）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daini no tsubone (the wife of Yoshisane ROKKAKU)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daini no tsubone (the wife of Yoshisane ROKKAKU)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daini no tsubone (the wife of Yoshisane ROKKAKU)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>近江の方（久政の妹の説あり、斎藤義龍室、斎藤龍興生母）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi no kata (she is also said to have been a younger sister of Hisamasa; the wife of Yoshitatsu SAITO, and the mother of Tatsuoki SAITO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi no kata (she is also said to have been a younger sister of Hisamasa; the wife of Yoshitatsu SAITO, and the mother of Tatsuoki SAITO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi no kata (she is also said to have been a younger sister of Hisamasa; the wife of Yoshitatsu SAITO, and the mother of Tatsuoki SAITO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="97">
<j>孫に浅井万福丸・淀殿（諸説あり）・常高院・崇源院・京極高次・京極竜子・京極高知ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandchildren include Manpukumaru AZAI, Yodo dono (there are various theories), Joko in, Sugen-in, Takatsugu KYOGOKU, Tatsuko KYOGOKU, and Takatomo KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandchildren included Manpukumaru AZAI, Yodo dono (there are various theories), Joko in, Sugen-in, Takatsugu KYOGOKU, Tatsuko KYOGOKU, and Takatomo KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandchildren included Manpukumaru AZAI, Yodo dono (there are various theories), Joko in, Sugen-in, Takatsugu KYOGOKU, Tatsuko KYOGOKU, and Takatomo KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="98">
<j>曾孫に豊臣鶴松・豊臣秀頼・豊臣完子・千姫・珠姫・勝姫 (天崇院)・初姫・徳川家光（双方とも諸説あり）と徳川忠長・徳川和子・京極忠高・京極高広・京極高三ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His great-grandchildren include Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, Sadako TOYOTOMI, Sen hime, Tama hime, Katsu hime (Tensu-in), Hatsu hime, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA and Tadanaga TOKUGAWA (there are various theories on both of them), Masako TOKUGAWA, Tadataka KYOGOKU, Takahiro KYOGOKU, and Takamitsu KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>ここでの姫は、皇室の姫ではないので、princessの訳を付けてありません。敬称としての姫として、院と同じように～himeとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His great-grandchildren included Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, Sadako TOYOTOMI, Sen hime, Tama hime, Katsu hime (Tensu-in), Hatsu hime, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA and Tadanaga TOKUGAWA (there are various theories about both of them), Masako TOKUGAWA, Tadataka KYOGOKU, Takahiro KYOGOKU, and Takamitsu KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His great-grandchildren included Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, Sadako TOYOTOMI, Sen hime, Tama hime, Katsu hime (Tensu-in), Hatsu hime, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA and Tadanaga TOKUGAWA (there are various theories about both of them), Masako TOKUGAWA, Tadataka KYOGOKU, Takahiro KYOGOKU, and Takamitsu KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="99">
<j>玄孫に九条道房・二条康道・豊臣国松・奈阿姫・前田光高・前田利次・前田利治・松平光長・亀姫 (宝珠院)・千代姫・徳川家綱・徳川綱重・徳川綱吉・京極高国・京極高直・明正天皇ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His great-great-grandchildren include Michifusa KUJO, Yasumichi NIJO, Kunimatsu TOYOTOMI, Naa hime, Mitsutaka MAEDA, Toshitsugu MAEDA, Toshiharu MAEDA, Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA, Kame hime (Hojuin), Chiyo hime, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, Tsunashige TOKUGAWA, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, Takakuni KYOGOKU, Takanao KYOGOKU, and Emperor Meisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His great-great-grandchildren included Michifusa KUJO, Yasumichi NIJO, Kunimatsu TOYOTOMI, Naa hime, Mitsutaka MAEDA, Toshitsugu MAEDA, Toshiharu MAEDA, Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA, Kame hime (Hojuin), Chiyo hime, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, Tsunashige TOKUGAWA, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, Takakuni KYOGOKU, Takanao KYOGOKU, and Emperor Meisho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His great-great-grandchildren included Michifusa KUJO, Yasumichi NIJO, Kunimatsu TOYOTOMI, Naa hime, Mitsutaka MAEDA, Toshitsugu MAEDA, Toshiharu MAEDA, Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA, Kame hime (Hojuin), Chiyo hime, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, Tsunashige TOKUGAWA, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, Takakuni KYOGOKU, Takanao KYOGOKU, and Emperor Meisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Izayohi(id:13095), Ayakey(id:115486), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), 麝香(id:89874), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Sakurako h(id:80733), Yanahan(id:2437), 味っ子(id:17086), Bakira(id:184047), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Giniro(id:39859), GAVVA(id:47103), Kagetudo(id:163875), Kurz(id:1601), Loafer(id:270948), Kazukiokumura(id:142935), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), Loveless(id:129239), こぶまき(id:38278), Yas(id:739), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), NDR(id:5500), Louperibot(id:128971), 浅井久政(id:27407), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>