<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉沢検校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉沢検校（よしざわ けんぎょう、寛政12年（1800年） - 明治5年（1872年）、生年は一説には文化_(元号)5年（1808年））は、幕末に活躍した盲人音楽家（地歌三味線、箏曲、胡弓、平家琵琶演奏家、作曲家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA (1800 or 1808 - 1872) was a visually impaired musician (player of jiuta shamisen [traditional Japanese shamisen music], sokyoku [koto music], kokyu (Chinese fiddle), and Heike biwa [a biwa with four strings and five frets used to play Heike Monogatari], and composer) who was active in the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA (1800 or 1808 - 1872) was a visually impaired musician, playing jiuta shamisen (traditional music for the three-stringed banjo-like shamisen), sokyoku (music for the zither-like koto), the kokyu (Chinese fiddle), and the Heike biwa (a lute-like instrument with four strings and five frets used to play Heike Monogatari), and composer active at the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA (1800 or 1808 - 1872) was a visually impaired musician, playing jiuta shamisen (traditional music for the three-stringed banjo-like shamisen), sokyoku (music for the zither-like koto), the kokyu (Chinese fiddle), and the Heike biwa (a lute-like instrument with four strings and five frets used to play Heike Monogatari), and composer active at the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>初世と二世がおり、ふつう吉沢検校というと二世を指し、初世の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were Kengyo the first and Kengyo the second, and Kengyo YOSHIZAWA usually indicates the second, and this Kengyo the second was the first son of Kengyo the first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were Kengyo the first and Kengyo the second, and Kengyo YOSHIZAWA usually indicates the second, who was the eldest son of Kengyo the first.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were Kengyo the first and Kengyo the second, and Kengyo YOSHIZAWA usually indicates the second, who was the eldest son of Kengyo the first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1800年（寛政12年、一説には1808年（文化5年））に現愛知県愛西市で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA was born in the present Aisai City, Aichi Prefecture, in 1800 (or 1808).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA was born in what is now Aisai City, Aichi Prefecture, in 1800 (or 1808).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA was born in what is now Aisai City, Aichi Prefecture, in 1800 (or 1808).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>九歳で失明し、父である初世吉沢検校、藤田検校に地歌、箏曲、胡弓を、荻野検校に平曲（平家琵琶）を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizawa lost his eyesight when he was nine years old, and then learned jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment), sokyoku, and kokyu under Kengyo the first, his father, and Kengyo FUJITA, and Heikyoku (Heike biwa) under Kengyo OGINO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost his eyesight when he was nine years old, and then studied jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment), sokyoku, and the kokyu under his father, Kengyo the first, and Kengyo FUJITA, and Heikyoku (Heike biwa) under Kengyo OGINO.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost his eyesight when he was nine years old, and then studied jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment), sokyoku, and the kokyu under his father, Kengyo the first, and Kengyo FUJITA, and Heikyoku (Heike biwa) under Kengyo OGINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1837年（天保8年）に検校となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the name of Kengyo in 1837.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took the name Kengyo, which was given to the highest ranking members of the Todo-za, the traditional guild for visually impaired people, in 1837.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took the name Kengyo, which was given to the highest ranking members of the Todo-za, the traditional guild for visually impaired people, in 1837.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>名古屋伊勢町一丁目に居住、都名（いちな・当道座に属する視覚障害者）が名乗る名前は審一（しんのいち）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizawa lived in 1-chome, Ise-cho, Nagoya and his name as Ichina (a visually impaired person who belonged to Todo-za [the traditional guild for visually impaired people]) was Shinichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizawa lived at 1-chome, Ise-cho, Nagoya and his name as an &apos;ichina&apos; (a term for members of the Todo-za) was Shinnoichi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizawa lived at 1-chome, Ise-cho, Nagoya and his name as an &apos;ichina&apos; (a term for visually impaired members of the Todo-za) was Shinnoichi.</e>
<cmt>「視覚障害者」の訳抜けに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また国学者氷室長翁に師事して国学、和歌にも造詣深く、自ら作詞した自作曲もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Yoshizawa studied under ChoO HIMURO, a scholar of Japanese classical literature, had deep knowledge in the study of Japanese classical literature and waka poetry, and also left pieces of which lyrics and music created by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizawa also studied under Cho-o HIMURO, a scholar of Japanese classical literature, gaining for himself a deep knowledge of Japanese classical literature and waka poetry, and also created his own lyrics and music.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizawa also studied under Cho-o HIMURO, a scholar of Japanese classical literature, gaining for himself a deep knowledge of Japanese classical literature and waka poetry, and also created his own lyrics and music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>11歳で地歌「屋島」に箏の手を付けるなど幼少より楽才秀で、1852年（嘉永5年）には藩の命で尾張の盲人支配頭となり、五人扶持を賜り、尾張徳川家の諸行事での演奏、例えば先祖供養の際の平曲演奏や、雛の節句での胡弓の演奏などを勤めたのをはじめ、松坂屋（現松坂屋百貨店）の当主の婚礼祝いの曲を作ったりと、名古屋の名士音楽家として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizawa excelled in music since childhood, such as adding a koto play to jiuta &apos;Yashima&apos; at the age of eleven, and in 1852 he was appointed to the head manager of visually impaired people in Owari (the present Aichi Prefecture) ordered by the domain with a stipend of five people and very successful as a prominent musician in Nagoya by playing at various occasions for the Owari Tokugawa clan, including Heikyoku playing at memorial services for their ancestors and kokyu playing at Dolls&apos; Festival, and making a song for a marriage ceremony of the family head of Matsuzakaya (the present Matsuzakaya department store).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizawa excelled in music from an early age, adding a koto part to the jiuta &apos;Yashima&apos; at the age of eleven; in 1852, he was given responsibility for visually impaired people in Owari (present-day Aichi Prefecture) by the domain, with a stipend five times larger than the average, and became a celebrated musician in Nagoya, performing at various occasions for the Owari Tokugawa family, including playing Heikyoku at memorial services for their ancestors, playing the kokyu at the Dolls&apos; Festival, and composing a song for the marriage ceremony of the head of the family that owned Matsuzakaya (present-day Matsuzakaya Department Stores).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizawa excelled in music from an early age, adding a koto part to the jiuta &apos;Yashima&apos; at the age of eleven; in 1852, he was given responsibility for visually impaired people in Owari (present-day Aichi Prefecture) by the domain, with a stipend for five persons, and became a celebrated musician in Nagoya, performing at various occasions for the Owari Tokugawa family, including playing Heikyoku at memorial services for their ancestors, playing the kokyu at the Dolls&apos; Festival, and composing a song for the marriage ceremony of the head of the family that owned Matsuzakaya (present-day Matsuzakaya Department Stores).</e>
<cmt>「五人扶持」の意味を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>夫人の実家も裕福で経済的にも恵まれており、当道座の高位役職に進んだこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family home of Yoshizawa&apos;s wife was also rich and they were economically blessed as well, he even advanced to the post of high position in Todo-za.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizawa&apos;s wife&apos;s family was also affluent and economically blessed, and Yoshizawa rose to a prominent position within Todo-za.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizawa&apos;s wife&apos;s family was also affluent and economically blessed, and Yoshizawa rose to a prominent position within Todo-za.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>いっぽう彼の才能に対して同僚音楽家たちの妬みを買うことも多く、名古屋を避けて京都で暮らすこともしばしばあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Yoshizawa&apos;s fellow musicians were often jealous of his abilities, and therefore, he stayed in Kyoto many times avoiding living in Nagoya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Yoshizawa&apos;s fellow musicians were often jealous of his abilities, and he frequently stayed in Kyoto to avoid Nagoya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Yoshizawa&apos;s fellow musicians were often jealous of his abilities, and he frequently stayed in Kyoto to avoid Nagoya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>こうして京阪の音楽家たちとも交流が深く、とくに京都の光崎検校からは作曲上で大きな影響を受け、また大阪の厳得からは胡弓曲「鶴の巣籠」を伝授されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizawa deepened exchanges with the musicians in Keihan (Kyoto and Osaka) due to the reason above, and was especially influenced by Kengyo MITSUZAKI in Kyoto on music composition, and moreover, initiated into &apos;Tsuru-no- Sugomori&apos; (a song depicting various aspects of the life cycle of the crane), a kokyu piece, by Gentoku in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizawa became friends with musicians in the Kyoto and Osaka area due to the reason above, his compositions being especially influenced by Kyoto&apos;s Kengyo MITSUZAKI, and he also received instruction on &apos;Tsuru-no-Sugomori&apos;, a kokyu piece, from Gentoku in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizawa became friends with musicians in the Kyoto and Osaka area due to the reason above, his compositions being especially influenced by Kyoto&apos;s Kengyo MITSUZAKI, and he also received instruction on &apos;Tsuru-no-Sugomori,&apos; a kokyu piece, from Gentoku in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>数回名古屋と京都を行き来して作曲活動を行ない、1872年（明治5年）に京都で没したが、生涯多くの門弟を育て、今日でも名古屋を中心にその流れは伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizawa came and went between Nagoya and Kyoto several times for the composition work and died in Kyoto in 1872, during which he raised many disciples and its stream has been handed down even today mainly in Nagoya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizawa often traveled between Nagoya and Kyoto while composing and, although he died in Kyoto in 1872, he taught many students during his lifetime and his influence can still be seen today, especially in Nagoya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizawa often traveled between Nagoya and Kyoto while composing and although he died in Kyoto in 1872, he taught many students during his lifetime and his influence can still be seen today, especially in Nagoya.</e>
<cmt>余分なカンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>音楽上の業績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Achievements on music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musical Achievements</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Musical Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>復古的箏曲様式の確立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the revivalistic sokyoku form</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the revivalist sokyoku form</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the revivalist sokyoku form</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸時代の音楽は中期以降、三味線がリードしてきたが、幕末にはその技巧が発展の極に達してしまい、またそこに複雑に箏が絡み合う「替手」式合奏が発達、楽曲形式としての「手事もの」も完成し、行き着く所まで来たという感があり、それを超える新たな作曲表現が模索されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the mid-Edo period, shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) was leading the music world, but its technique reached the height of development in the end of Edo period, and moreover, an ensemble called &apos;kaede&apos; (accompanying melody) intricately tangling with koto developed and also &apos;Tegoto mono&apos; (Japanese koto) completed as a style of composition, which caused a sense of ending up, and therefore, a new expression of composition beyond these had been sought for.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the latter half of the Edo Period, the shamisen had become the most important instrument in Japanese music, but towards the end of the period there was a feeling that, with technique having been fully developed, the rise of the &apos;kaede&apos; ensemble, which involved intricate interplay with the koto, and the &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; style of composition being perfected, it had nowhere left to go musically and so a new way to express compositions beyond these was sought.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the latter half of the Edo Period, the shamisen had become the most important instrument in Japanese music, but towards the end of the period there was a feeling that, with technique having been fully developed, the rise of the &apos;kaede&apos; ensemble, which involved intricate interplay with the koto, and the &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; style of composition being perfected, it had nowhere left to go musically and so a new way to express compositions beyond these was sought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このような試みは幕末の音楽作品に色々なかたちで垣間見えるが、中でも、元禄の生田検校以来、三味線に対し従属的な立場にあった箏に再注目することによって、作曲に新たな方向性を見いだしたのが京都の光崎検校であり、「五段砧」「秋風の曲」など箏のみの名曲をも残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An attempt like this could be found in various ways in music pieces in the end of Edo Period, and especially Kengyo MITSUZAKI in Kyoto found a new direction in composition by focusing again koto, which had been subordinated to shamisen since Kengyo IKUTA in Genroku era, and left the masterpieces such as &apos;Godanginuda&apos; and &apos;Akikaze no kyoku&apos; (a song for the autumn wind) played by koto only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such attempts can be seen in the many styles of pieces from the end of the Edo Period, especially those of Kengyo MITSUZAKI in Kyoto, who found a new direction in composition by refocusing on the koto, which had been neglected in favor of the shamisen since Kengyo IKUTA at the end of the 17th century and left koto-only masterpieces such as &apos;Godan-ginuta&apos; (Instrumental in Five Sections) and &apos;Akikaze no Kyoku&apos; (Song of the Autumn Wind).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such attempts can be seen in the many styles of pieces from the end of the Edo Period, especially those of Kengyo MITSUZAKI in Kyoto, who found a new direction in composition by refocusing on the koto, which had been neglected in favor of the shamisen since Kengyo IKUTA at the Genroku era (the end of the 17th century) and left koto-only masterpieces such as &apos;Godan-ginuta&apos; (Instrumental in Five Sections) and &apos;Akikaze no Kyoku&apos; (Song of the Autumn Wind).</e>
<cmt>「元禄」の訳抜けに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>吉沢検校もその影響を受け、古い時代の箏曲である「組歌」や、さらには雅楽家羽塚秋楽に雅楽を学んで研究し、楽箏の調弦にヒントを得た新調弦を考案、「古今組」「新古今組」をはじめとして箏本位の曲を多く作曲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA was also influenced by that, learned and studied &apos;kumiuta&apos;, koto suites of songs in the old times, and also gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) under Shuraku HAZUKA, a gagaku musician, devised new tuning by obtaining an idea from that of a Japanese harp, and composed many koto-oriented pieces including &apos;Kokin-gumi&apos; and &apos;Shinkokin-gumi&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These influences led Kengyo YOSHIZAWA to learn and research the oldest koto pieces, known as &apos;kumiuta&apos;, and gagaku (ancient Japanese court music) under Shuraku HAZUKA, a gagaku musician, to devise a new tuning based on that of the Japanese harp, and to compose many koto-oriented pieces including &apos;Kokin-gumi&apos; and &apos;Shinkokin-gumi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These influences led Kengyo YOSHIZAWA to learn and research the oldest koto pieces, known as &apos;kumiuta,&apos; and gagaku (ancient Japanese court music) under Shuraku HAZUKA, a gagaku musician, to devise a new tuning based on that of the Japanese harp, and to compose many koto-oriented pieces including &apos;Kokin-gumi&apos; and &apos;Shinkokin-gumi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマとピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これらは箏曲本来の気品と雅楽的な古雅さを備え、一方で音楽的にはより自由な展開をさせ、近代的ともいえる印象的描写性もみられ、よく独自のスタイルを確立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These pieces had koto-originated class and gagaku-style elegance, while being developed freely in music, also with impressive portrayal which could be stated to be modernistic, and a unique style was well established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These works had the grace of koto pieces and the traditional elegance of gagaku, while musically they allowed freer development, and showed an almost modern impressive portrayal, establishing a distinctive style.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These works had the grace of koto pieces and the traditional elegance of gagaku, while musically they allowed freer development and showed an almost modern impressive portrayal, establishing a distinctive style.</e>
<cmt>カンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>維新後には全国的に広く知られるようになり、特に「千鳥の曲」と同様の様式の曲が大阪を中心に各地で作られることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were becoming known nationwide after the Meiji Restoration, and especially the pieces of the similar form as that of &apos;Chidori (a pipe making the sound like plover&apos;s cry) Music&apos; were created in various places mainly in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They became known nationwide after the Meiji Restoration, especially &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; (Song of the Plover), which inspired similar pieces around the country, particularly in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They became known nationwide after the Meiji Restoration, especially &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; (The Song of the Plover), which inspired similar pieces around the country, particularly in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>「明治新曲」と呼ばれる曲群がそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A group of songs called &apos;Meiji shinkyoku piece&apos; (new song of Meiji) correspond to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One example is the style of songs known as &apos;Meiji shinkyoku&apos; (new song of Meiji).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One example is the style of songs known as &apos;Meiji shinkyoku&apos; (new song of Meiji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、例えば「千鳥の曲」に見られる海辺の描写的表現は、後世の「春の海」を予見させるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, for example, a descriptive expression of the seaside seen in &apos;Chidori Music&apos; has something foreseeable &apos;Haru no umi&apos; (Spring Sea) in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the descriptive expression of the seaside seen in &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; foreshadows the later &apos;Haru no Umi&apos; (Spring Sea).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the descriptive expression of the seaside seen in &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; foreshadows the later &apos;Haru no Umi&apos; (Spring Sea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>つまり吉沢の箏作品(光崎検校の箏作品も含め)は「千鳥の曲」を一つの転換点として、明治以降の日本音楽の流れを方向づけることになったということもできるであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, it is safe to say that koto pieces of Yoshizawa (including those of Mitsuzaki) defined the direction of the stream in the Japanese music after the Meiji period with &apos;Chidori Music&apos; as a turning point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, it is safe to say that Yoshizawa&apos;s koto pieces (as well as those by Mitsuzaki) defined the direction Japanese music would take after the Meiji period, with &apos;Chidori Music&apos; being a turning point.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, it is safe to say that Yoshizawa&apos;s koto pieces (as well as those by Kengyo MITSUZAKI) defined the direction Japanese music would take after the Meiji period, with &apos;Chidori Music&apos; being a turning point.</e>
<cmt>「光崎検校」の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ただし作曲が進むに従い、晩期の作品では簡潔美の追求が進み、流麗さすら排除されて一般受けしづらくなる傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the pieces of his last period, succinct beauty was more pursued as the composition proceeded, and even elegance was excluded, which made difficult for general people to accept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as his song writing progressed, he sought succinct beauty with his final works, even to the exclusion of elegance, which made them difficult for general people to accept.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as his song writing progressed, he sought succinct beauty with his final works, even to the exclusion of elegance, which made them difficult for general people to accept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これは多分に人の世の煩瑣や最幕末の不安定な世相を厭う、芸術家としての孤高の精神の発露ゆえなのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This may be because of appearance of lone spirits as an artist who evaded the troublesome world and the unstable social conditions in the very end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was probably an expression of the isolated soul of an artist who avoided the troublesome world and the unstable social conditions of the last days of Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was probably an expression of the isolated soul of an artist who avoided the troublesome world and the unstable social conditions of the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、やはりこういった吉沢の路線を受け継ぎ、京極流を打ち立てた鈴木鼓村のような明治期の箏曲家もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some koto players inherited such Yoshizawa Line and established the Kyogoku-ryu koto school like Koson SUZUKI in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some Meiji-period koto players, like Koson SUZUKI, continued the Yoshizawa Line and established the Kyogoku-ryu koto school.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some Meiji-period koto players including Koson SUZUKI, who established the Kyogoku-ryu koto school, continued the Yoshizawa Line.</e>
<cmt>原文の解釈ミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このように幕末期の箏曲における吉沢検校の業績には、実に多大なものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like this, the achievements of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA in koto music in the end of Edo period are really tremendous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As such, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA&apos;s achievements in the koto music of the end of the Edo Period are extremely noteworthy.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA&apos;s achievements in the koto music of the end of the Edo Period are extremely noteworthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし次に挙げるように、吉沢検校には従来の京流手事ものの作品や、胡弓のための作品も少なくないことを忘れてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as described below, it should be remembered that the pieces of traditional Kyoto style arrangement and those for kokyu are also included in the masterpieces of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as described below, it should also be remembered that he also produced many Kyoto-style &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; works and as well as pieces for the kokyu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as described below, it should also be remembered that he also produced many Kyoto-style &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; works and as well as pieces for the kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>地歌作品と箏の手付け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masterpieces of jiuta and Arrangement of koto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiuta&apos; Pieces and Koto Arrangements</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiuta&apos; Pieces and Koto Arrangements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>三味線の作品（地歌）は手事ものがほとんどで、その他には端歌ものも作曲している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For shamisen pieces (jiuta), most of them are Tegoto (Japanese Koto), and Yoshizawa also composed hauta (kind of shamisen song).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of Yoshizawa&apos;s shamisen pieces (jiuta) are &apos;tegoto-mono,&apos; though he also composed &apos;hauta&apos; (literally, &apos;short songs&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of Yoshizawa&apos;s shamisen pieces (jiuta) are &apos;tegoto-mono,&apos; although he also composed &apos;hauta&apos; (literally, &apos;short songs&apos;).</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストに従いthoughをalthoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>手事ものは様式的には「京流手事もの」を完全に踏襲しており、さすがに既に三味線の技巧が極められてしまっている時代であるだけに、特別に吉沢が新たに切り開いた感はないが、やはり京都の作曲家のものとは少し違う独自性が感じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tegoto completely took over &apos;Kyoryu tegotomono&apos; in its style and there is no special feeling that Yoshizawa newly founded shamisen technique because it had already reached to the max in those times, still there is the originality a little different from that of the composers in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; were stylistically no different to the Kyoto style &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; and there is no particular sense of Yoshizawa having developed anything new since by that time, shamisen technique was already fully developed, although compared to the Kyoto composers, they possess a slightly different originality.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; were stylistically no different to the Kyoto style &apos;tegoto-mono&apos; and there is no particular sense of Yoshizawa having developed anything new since by that time, shamisen technique was already fully developed, although they possess a slightly different originality compared to the Kyoto composers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>三味線の技巧もかなり高度に追求され、「花の縁（えにし）」は手事を二箇所に持つ堂々とした大曲であり、吉沢検校の作品における器楽面での充実ぶりを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shamisen&apos;s technique was also highly pursued, and &apos;Hana no enishi&apos; is a large majestic piece with Tegoto in two places, which indicates richness of instruments in the masterpieces by Kengyo YOSHIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizawa also sought a high technical level for the shamisen, with &apos;Hana no Enishi,&apos; a large majestic piece with tegoto in two places, indicating the richness of the instrumental side of his works.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizawa also sought a high technical level for the shamisen, with &apos;Hana no Enishi,&apos; a large majestic piece with tegoto in two places, indicating the richness of the instrumental side of his works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>同曲の他「玉くしげ」「夏衣」など、明るい雰囲気の曲が多いのも特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides above, characteristics are that there are many pieces of bright atmosphere, such as &apos;Tamakushige&apos; and &apos;Natsugoromo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another characteristic is the large number of songs with a bright atmosphere, such as &apos;Tamakushige&apos; and &apos;Natsugoromo,&apos; in addition to those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another characteristic is the large number of songs with a bright atmosphere, such as &apos;Tamakushige&apos; and &apos;Natsugoromo,&apos; in addition to those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>箏の手付けも全ての自作曲において自分で行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For arrangement of koto, Yoshizawa did by himself in all of his own pieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For his koto arrangements, Yoshizawa wrote all his own pieces by himself.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For his koto arrangements, Yoshizawa wrote all his own pieces by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>幼少の頃から箏にも長けていたらしく、既に11歳で地歌「屋島」に箏の手を付けているのをはじめ、既存の地歌曲にもいくつか箏の手付けをしているが、これらもやはり八重崎検校など京都の手付けとは雰囲気が異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he was good at playing koto since childhood, and added koto arrangement to &apos;Yashima&apos;, a jiuta song, already at the age of eleven as well as to the existing jiuta songs, and an atmosphere different from the arrangement in Kyoto such as Kengyo YAEZAKI is seen in them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that he was skilled with the koto since childhood, and had already added a koto arrangement to &apos;Yashima&apos;, a jiuta song, at the age of eleven, after which he added arrangements to numerous existing jiuta songs, different in atmosphere to the Kyoto arrangements by composers such as Kengyo YAEZAKI.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that he was skilled with the koto since childhood, and had already added a koto arrangement to &apos;Yashima,&apos; a jiuta song, at the age of eleven, after which he added arrangements to numerous existing jiuta songs, different in atmosphere to the Kyoto arrangements by composers such as Kengyo YAEZAKI.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また作曲上大きな影響を受けた光崎検校の「秋風の曲」にも箏の替手を作っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he also created kaede (accompanying melody) in &apos;Akikaze no kyoku&apos; (a song for the autumn wind) by Kengyo MITSUZAKI, under whom he was greatly influenced on composition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he also created kaede (accompanying melody) for &apos;Akikaze no Kyoku&apos; (Song of the Autumn Wind) by Kengyo MITSUZAKI, who had a significant influence on his compositions.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he also created kaede (accompanying melody) for &apos;Akikaze no Kyoku&apos; (Song of the Autumn Wind) by Kengyo MITSUZAKI, who had a significant influence on his compositions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>後述のように胡弓の手付けも非常に独創的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arrangement for kokyu is also very creative as later mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described below, his arrangements for the kokyu are also very original.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described below, his arrangements for the kokyu are also very original.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>一方、同僚たちの妬みによって、辛い思いをした名古屋を去る時に作った端歌もの曲「捨扇」では、流麗な中に頻繁な転調や非常に凝った節付けの歌など、小品ながら侮りがたい作りで、作曲術の力量のほどが偲ばれるとともに、失意や悲しみがひしひしと感じられ、雅びな「千鳥の曲」や明るく華やかな「花の縁」などとはまた違った、吉沢の心の一面を垣間見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, hauta (a short song) &apos;Suteogi&apos; (a folding fan forgotten in fall), created when leaving Nagoya after spending sad days due to colleagues&apos; jealousy, is a piece which should not be underestimated regardless of its small size, with frequent key changes in elegance and a song of very elaborated fushizuke (musical aspect), by which composition skills can be recalled as well as disappointment and sadness can be fully felt, and thereby, one face of Yoshizawa&apos;s mind, different from that in elegant &apos;Chidori Music&apos; and bright, gorgeous &apos;Hana no enishi&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the hauta &apos;Suteogi&apos; (Discarded Fan), created when leaving Nagoya and its bad memories, is a piece which should not be underestimated regardless of its small size, with frequent flowing key changes and a melody with an extremely elaborate fushizuke (where the melody is fitted to the text), which as well as recalling his compositional skills, also acutely show disappointment and sadness and, thereby, an aspect of Yoshizawa&apos;s mind different from that of the elegant &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; and the bright, gorgeous &apos;Hana no Enishi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the hauta &apos;Suteogi&apos; (Discarded Fan), created when leaving Nagoya and its bad memories, is a piece which should not be underestimated regardless of its small size, with frequent flowing key changes and a melody with an extremely elaborate fushizuke (where the melody is fitted to the text), which as well as recalling his compositional skills, also acutely show disappointment and sadness and, thereby, an aspect of Yoshizawa&apos;s mind different from that of the elegant &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; and the bright, gorgeous &apos;Hana no Enishi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>作曲者個人の生の心情を直接的に表すということも、ある意味近代的といえるかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a way, it may be modernistic to directly express how the composer himself really felt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a way, it could be said to be a modern direct expression of how the composer himself really felt.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a way, it could be said to be a modern direct expression of how the composer himself really felt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>彼の作品全般を見渡してみると、内容としては恋愛的要素が数例しか見られないのが大きな特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering his entire masterpieces, great characteristics are that a love case can be seen only in a few examples as contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A major characteristic of all his pieces is that only a few examples relate to love.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A major characteristic of all his pieces is that only a few examples relate to love.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ことに地歌曲にその傾向が希薄なのは、三味線音楽として見た場合、まことに珍しいことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially its trend is sparse in jiuta, which is unusual when considering as shamisen music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This trend is especially true in his jiuta, which is extremely unusual for shamisen music.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This trend is especially true in his jiuta, which is extremely unusual for shamisen music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>胡弓音楽の開拓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reclamation of kokyu music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reclamation of Kokyu Music</e>
<cmt>Capital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reclamation of Kokyu Music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>吉沢検校は更に胡弓にも注目、これまで合奏においてほとんど三味線にユニゾンで加わっていた胡弓に独自の旋律を与え、胡弓の地位を高めたことも彼の業績として重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA paid attention to kokyu, which was added almost in unison to shamisen in an ensemble, and gave the original melody to kokyu, and consequently raised the position of kokyu high, which is important as one of his achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA also focused on the kokyu, and one of his most important achievements was elevating the status of and writing original melodies for the kokyu, which until then had been used in unison with the shamisen.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA also focused on the kokyu, and one of his most important achievements was elevating the status of and writing original melodies for the kokyu, which until then had been used in unison with the shamisen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この点は従来、吉沢検校の業績を語る上でもっとも留意されてこなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was traditionally the least attended point in the achievements of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was traditionally the most ignored of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was traditionally the most ignored of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし曲によっては胡弓が主役となるほど技巧的、独創的な手を作っており、いくつかの自作曲では一人で三味線，箏、胡弓の全パートを作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, arrangement was very technical and creative enough to make kokyu the main part in some pieces, and also in some of his own compositions he created all parts of shamisen, koto, and kokyu only by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the arrangements were technical and creative enough to make kokyu the main part in some pieces, and in some of his own compositions he wrote all the shamisen, koto, and kokyu parts by himself.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the arrangements were technical and creative enough to make kokyu the main part in some pieces, and in some of his own compositions he wrote all the shamisen, koto, and kokyu parts by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>またいくつかの胡弓の名曲を残してもいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also left several masterpieces of kokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also left several kokyu masterpieces.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also left several kokyu masterpieces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>特に「千鳥の曲」は胡弓の名曲、箏の名曲として広く知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially &apos;Chidori Music&apos; is widely known as a masterpiece of kyoku and koto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chidori no Kyoku&apos; in particular is widely known as a masterpiece of the kyoku and koto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chidori no Kyoku&apos; in particular is widely known as a masterpiece of the kyoku and koto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>現在も吉沢の伝承を守っている国風音楽会では、彼の胡弓作品である「千鳥の曲」「蝉の曲」と、大阪の厳得から伝えられたという「鶴の巣籠」の三曲を同会の胡弓本曲としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokufu Ongaku Kai (the Traditional Japanese Music Association), which keeps the tradition of Yoshizawa even at the present days, has made three music pieces of &apos;Chidori Music&apos; and &apos;Semi no uta&apos; (a song of cicadas) which were his kokyu pieces, and &apos;Tsuru-no- Sugomori&apos; as kokyu honkyoku (music for the kokyu) of their association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokufu Ongaku Kai (the Traditional Japanese Music Association), which continues to preserve Yoshizawa&apos;s tradition, has made three pieces, Yoshizawa&apos;s kokyu pieces &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; and &apos;Semi no Uta&apos; (Song of the Cicadas), and Gentoku&apos;s &apos;Tsuru no Sugomori&apos; their &apos;kokyu honkyoku&apos; (music for the kokyu).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokufu Ongaku Kai (the Traditional Japanese Music Association), which continues to preserve Yoshizawa&apos;s tradition, has made three pieces, Yoshizawa&apos;s kokyu pieces &apos;Chidori no Kyoku&apos; and &apos;Semi no Uta&apos; (Song of the Cicadas), and Gentoku&apos;s &apos;Tsuru no Sugomori&apos; their &apos;kokyu honkyoku&apos; (music for the kokyu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="49">
<j>平曲の伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handing down of Heikyoku to subsequent generations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heritage of Heikyoku</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heritage of Heikyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>平曲（平家琵琶）は古代の日本音楽である雅楽と声明（しょうみょう）から生まれ、能楽と共に中世を代表する日本音楽である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heikyoku (Heike biwa) was born from gagaku and shomyo (chanting of Buddhist hymns), which were the music in the ancient times of Japan, and is the Japanese music typical in the medieval period as well as Nohgaku (the art of Noh).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heikyoku (Heike biwa) developed from the ancient musical forms of gagaku and shomyo (chanting of Buddhist hymns) and, together with Nohgaku (the art of Noh), is typical medieval Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heikyoku (Heike biwa) developed from the ancient musical forms of gagaku and shomyo (chanting of Buddhist hymns), and is typical medieval Japanese music together with Nohgaku (the art of Noh).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>もともと当道座の盲人音楽家たちは、この平曲の演奏こそが正規の本業であり、もっぱらにしていたし、平曲は中世には絶大な人気を保っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally playing of this Heikyoku was an official profession of visually impaired musicians who belonged to the Todo-za, and they mainly played this, by which Heikyoku boasted enormous popularity in the medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, performing heikyoku was an official profession of visually impaired musicians of the Todo-za, who played only this style, by which heikyoku boasted enormous popularity in the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, performing heikyoku was an official profession of visually impaired musicians of the Todo-za, who played only this style, by which heikyoku boasted enormous popularity in the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>しかし近世に至って表現豊かな楽器である三味線が渡来、完成され、更に箏、胡弓が加わり、これらによる新たな音楽が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a music instrument with full of expression called shamisen came from abroad in the early modern times and had been completed, and moreover, koto and kokyu were added to this, and consequently a new kind of music was born by all these.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, by the late 19th century, the shamisen, an instrument full of expression introduced from abroad, had reached its full potential, and moreover, the koto and kokyu were added and consequently a new kind of music developed.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the shamisen, an instrument full of expression, introduced from abroad and reached its full potential by the early Edo period, and moreover, the koto and kokyu were added and consequently a new kind of music developed.</e>
<cmt>「近世」の解釈　三味線が日本に伝わって発展したのは安土桃山から江戸時代にかけてなので「19世紀後半までに」という表現は不適切ですので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これに携わったのもかつての琵琶法師、つまり当道座の盲人音楽家たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former biwa-playing minstrels, that is, visually impaired musicians who belonged to the Todo-za, were also involved with this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former biwa-playing minstrels, that is, the visually impaired musicians of the Todo-za, were also involved with this.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former biwa-playing minstrels, that is, the visually impaired musicians of the Todo-za, were also involved with this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>こうして彼らにより三味線音楽や箏曲が興隆する一方で、本来彼らの表芸であるはずの平曲は完全に停滞、固定化して、ただ伝承されるだけの存在となり、新作もなく、平曲を演奏出来る人は次第に減少して行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Shamisen music and koto music flourished like this by them, Heikyoku, which should have been their original profession, completely fixed at a standstill and existed just as being inherited with no new work, and gradually the number of musicians who could play Heikyoku were getting less and less.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While they contributed to the flourishing of shamisen music and koto music, heikyoku, which should have been their original profession, came to a complete standstill, being handed down with no new work, and gradually the number of musicians who could play heikyoku decreased.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While they contributed to the flourishing of shamisen music and koto music, heikyoku, which should have been their original profession, came to a complete standstill, being handed down with no new work, and gradually the number of musicians who could play heikyoku decreased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>江戸時代にも平曲をもっぱらとする演奏家はいたが、衰退を止めることはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were some musicians who played mainly Heikyoku in the Edo period as well, but they could not stop it from declining.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A few musicians continued to play mainly heikyoku in the Edo Period, but they could not stop it from declining.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A few musicians continued to play mainly heikyoku in the Edo Period, but they could not stop it from declining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="56">
<j>吉沢検校は江戸時代の平曲の大流派の一つである波多野流を荻野検校に学び、門弟たちに伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA learned the Hatano School, one of the great schools of Heikyoku in the Edo period and introduced to his disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA learned the Hatano School, one of the great schools of Heikyoku in the Edo period, introducing it to his disciples.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo YOSHIZAWA learned the style of the Hatano School, one of the great schools of Heikyoku in the Edo period, from Kengyo OGINO, and he introduced it to his disciples.</e>
<cmt>「荻野検校に学び」が抜けているので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>現在では平曲の伝承がほとんど絶えてしまった中で、吉沢検校からの流れが名古屋において今も伝承されており、極めて貴重な存在となっている（他に仙台にも別の伝承がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays the tradition of Heikyoku almost died down, but the stream since Kengyo YOSHIZAWA has been inherited in Nagoya even now as a rare valuable existence (there is another tradition in Sendai as well).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, the tradition of Heikyoku has almost died out, although Kengyo YOSHIZAWA&apos;s influence continues in Nagoya even now in an extremely valuable existence (there is another tradition in Sendai as well).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, the tradition of Heikyoku has almost died out, although Kengyo YOSHIZAWA&apos;s influence continues in Nagoya even now in an extremely valuable existence (there is another tradition in Sendai as well).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また必ずしも吉沢に限ったことではないが、彼の地歌作品の中にも、平曲の節回しの影響、あるいは応用と見られる部分がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, though this is not limited to Yoshizawa, even his jiuta pieces indicate influence or application of Fushimawashi (melody) of Heikyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, his jiuta pieces show the influence or application of the fushimawashi (melody) of Heikyoku, although this is not limited to Yoshizawa.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, his jiuta pieces show the influence or application of the fushimawashi (melody) of Heikyoku, although this is not limited to Yoshizawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="59">
<j>「復古運動提唱」について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Advocating the reversionism&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Advocating reversionism&apos;</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Advocating Reversionism&apos;</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>吉沢検校が古い箏曲や雅楽を取り入れ純箏曲を多く作ったということで、かつては彼が「復古運動を提唱」したとか、「箏曲独立の精神を樹立」したなどと言われることがしばしばあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was often said that Kengyo YOSHIZAWA &apos;advocated the reversionism&apos; or &apos;established the independent spirit of koto music&apos;, etc. because he had taken old koto music and gagaku to create many pure koto music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was often said that Kengyo YOSHIZAWA &apos;advocated reversionism&apos; or &apos;established the independent spirit of koto music&apos;, because he had taken old koto music and gagaku to create many pieces of pure koto music.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was often said that Kengyo YOSHIZAWA &apos;advocated reversionism&apos; or &apos;established the independent spirit of koto music,&apos; because he had taken old koto music and gagaku to create many pieces of pure koto music.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>しかし吉沢本人が実際にそのようなことをとなえたという記録は何もないし、現実として彼の作品には前述のように胡弓曲や三味線曲も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is no record that Yoshizawa himself actually advocated such a thing, and it is the fact that there are many kokyu and shamisen pieces in his works as above-mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is no record that Yoshizawa himself actually advocated such a thing, and it is a fact that his works include many kokyu and shamisen pieces, as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is no record that Yoshizawa himself actually advocated such a thing, and it is a fact that his works include many kokyu and shamisen pieces, as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>確かに彼の箏曲に復古主義的な面は濃厚に見られるが、復古主義は当時の文化全般に見られ、箏曲に限ったことではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surely aspects of the reversionism can be heavily seen in his koto music, but it was not only in them because the reversionism could be generally found in the culture of that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is true that many aspects of reversionism can be seen in his koto music, but reversionism could be generally found in the culture of the time and not only in his koto music.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is true that many aspects of reversionism can be seen in his koto music, but reversionism could be generally found in the culture of the time and not only in his koto music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>むしろ、従来の地歌三味線に加え、さらに箏や胡弓に新たな作曲表現の道を見いだし、切り開いたという方がより正しいと言えるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It would be rather fair to say that he found and founded a new way of expression in koto and kokyu composition in addition to the traditional jiuta shamisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather, it would be fair to say that he discovered and opened up a new way of expression in koto and kokyu composition, adding to the traditional jiuta shamisen.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather, it would be fair to say that he discovered and opened up a new way of expression in koto and kokyu composition, adding to the traditional jiuta shamisen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="64">
<j>主な作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major masterpieces</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Works</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>千鳥の曲（胡弓・箏本手、箏替手）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chidori Music (the melody part of kokyu and koto, accompanying melody of koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chidori no Kyoku (main melody for kokyu and koto, accompanying melody for koto)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chidori no Kyoku (main melody for kokyu and koto, accompanying melody for koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>春の曲（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Spring Music (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haru no Kyoku (Spring Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haru no Kyoku (Spring Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>夏の曲（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Summer Music (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natsu no Kyoku (Summer Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natsu no Kyoku (Summer Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>秋の曲（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Autumn Music (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aki no Kyoku (Autumn Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aki no Kyoku (Autumn Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>冬の曲（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Winter Music (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuyu no Kyoku (Winter Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuyu no Kyoku (Winter Music) (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>以上古今組、「千鳥の曲」は胡弓本曲ともされる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above Kokin-gumi and &apos;Chidori Music&apos; are said to be kokyu honkyoku (Music for the kokyu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above Kokin-gumi and &apos;Chidori Music&apos; are said to be kokyu honkyoku (music for the kokyu).</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above Kokin-gumi and &apos;Chidori Music&apos; are said to be kokyu honkyoku (music for the kokyu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>山桜 (箏曲)（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamazakura (sokyoku) (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamazakura (Mountain Cherry) (sokyoku) (koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamazakura (Mountain Cherry) (sokyoku) (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>新雪月花（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-setsugetuka (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-setsugetuka (New Snow, Moon and Flowers) (koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-setsugetuka (New Snow, Moon and Flowers) (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>初瀬川（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatsusegawa River (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatsusegawa River (koto)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatsusegawa River (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>唐衣（箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaginu [a waist length Chinese style jacket] (koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaginu (Chinese Jacket) (koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaginu (Chinese Jacket) (koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>以上新古今組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above four belong to Shinkokin-gumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above four form the Shinkokin-gumi</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above four form the Shinkokin-gumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>蝉の曲（胡弓・箏）　胡弓本曲ともされる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semi no uta (a song of cicadas) (kokyu and koto) It is also said that this is a kokyu honkyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Semi no Uta (kokyu and koto) - also said to be a kokyu honkyoku.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Semi no Uta (kokyu and koto) - also said to be a kokyu honkyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>花の縁（三絃・箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hana no enishi (sangen [a three-stringed musical instrument] and koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hana no enishi (sangen [a three-stringed musical instrument] and koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hana no enishi (sangen [a three-stringed musical instrument] and koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>玉くしげ（三絃・箏・胡弓）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamakushige (sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamakushige (Jeweled Comb Box) (sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamakushige (Jeweled Comb Box) (sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>夏衣（三絃・箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natsugoromo (sangen and koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natsugoromo (Summer Clothes) (sangen and koto)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natsugoromo (Summer Clothes) (sangen and koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>深山木（三絃・箏・胡弓）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyamagi (sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyamagi (Mountain Forest) (sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt>Added translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyamagi (Mountain Forest) (sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>新山姥（歌詞・三絃・箏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-Yamanba (Mountain Witch) (lyrics, sangen, and koto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-Yamanba (Mountain Witch) (lyrics, sangen, and koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-Yamanba (Mountain Witch) (lyrics, sangen, and koto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>捨扇（歌詞・三絃・箏・胡弓）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suteogi (lyrics, sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suteogi (lyrics, sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suteogi (lyrics, sangen, koto, and kokyu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>その他、胡弓、箏の手付も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, Yoshizawa arranged many pieces of kokyu and koto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, Yoshizawa arranged many pieces for the kokyu and koto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, Yoshizawa arranged many pieces for the kokyu and koto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Point136(id:211299), Hermes(id:21387), Cprobot(id:97843), 詠狸庵(id:41048), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>