<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中岡慎太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaro NAKAOKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintaro NAKAOKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintaro NAKAOKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中岡 慎太郎（なかおか しんたろう、天保9年4月13日 (旧暦)（1838年5月6日） - 慶応3年11月17日 (旧暦)（1867年12月12日））は、日本の志士（活動家）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaro NAKAOKA (May 6, 1838 (April 13, 1838 by the old calendar) - December 12, 1867 (November 17, 1867 by the old calendar)) was a political activist involed in fighting to restore imperial rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintaro NAKAOKA (May 6, 1838 (April 13, 1838 by the old calendar) - December 12, 1867 (November 17, 1867 by the old calendar)) was a political activist involved in the fight to restore imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;involved&quot;&quot;fighting&quot;→&quot;the fight&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintaro NAKAOKA (May 6, 1838 - December 12, 1867) was a political activist involved in the fight to restore imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>新暦のみの表現としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>陸援隊隊長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the leader of the Rikuentai, an army formed during the last days of Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the leader of the Rikuentai, an army formed during the last days of Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the leader of the Rikuentai, an army formed during the last days of Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名は始め光次、後、道正。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Koji, a name that was later changed to Michimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Koji, a name that was later changed to Michimasa.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;original&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Koji, and then later changed to Michimasa.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は遠山・迂山など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had several pen names, including Toyama and Uzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had several pen names, including Toyama and Uzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had several pen names, including Toyama and Uzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>変名は石川清之助（誠之助）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used Seinosuke ISHIKAWA as his assumed name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He used Seinosuke ISHIKAWA as his assumed name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He used Seinosuke ISHIKAWA as his assumed name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>贈正四位（1891年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded the official rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded the official rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded the official rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) in 1891.</e>
<cmt>1891 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>土佐国安芸郡北川郷柏木村（現･高知県安芸郡 (高知県)北川村柏木）に北川郷の大庄屋　中岡小傳次、はつの長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in the Kashiwagi Village, Kitagawa-go, Aki County, Tosa Province (Presently Kashiwagi, Kitagawa Village, Aki County, Tosa Prefecture) as the first son of Kodenji, headman of Kitagawago Village, and Hatsu NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt>小傳次の読みが確認できませんでした。傳次でデンジという名前がありましたので、仮訳でコデンジで入れてます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kashiwagi Village, Kitagawa-go, Aki County, Tosa Province (present-day Kashiwagi, Kitagawa Village, Aki County, Tosa Prefecture) as the first son of Kodenji, headman of Kitagawago Village, and Hatsu NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;Presently&quot;→&quot;present-day&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kashiwagi Village, Kitagawa-go, Aki County, Tosa Province (present-day Kashiwagi, Kitagawa-mura, Aki-gun (Tosa Prefecture), Tosa Prefecture) as the first son of Kodenji NAKAOKA, headman of Kitagawago Village, and Hatsu NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt>括弧の中を、(present-day Kashiwagi, Kitagawa-mura, Aki-gun (Tosa Prefecture), Tosa Prefecture)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>武市瑞山（半平太）の道場に入門する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered a martial arts training school run by Zuizan TAKEICHI (a.k.a. Hanbeita).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered a martial arts training school run by Zuizan TAKEICHI (also known as Hanbeita)</e>
<cmt>&quot;a.k.a&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;Deleted full stop to rejoin to cell F15</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered a martial arts training school run by Zuizan TAKEICHI (also known as Hanbeita).</e>
<cmt>二文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>文久元年（1861年）には武市が結成した土佐勤皇党に加盟して、本格的に志士活動を展開し始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1861, he joined the Tosaginno Party that TAKEICHI had formed and took an active part in its politidal activities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and in 1861, he joined the Tosaginno Party that TAKEICHI had formed, taking an active part in its political activities.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;and&quot;&quot;and took&quot;→&quot;, taking&quot;Spelling of &quot;political&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1861, he joined the Tosaginno Party that TAKEICHI had formed, taking an active part in its political activities.</e>
<cmt>二文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>文久2年（1862年）、長州の俊英久坂玄瑞・宍戸たまきとともに、松代に佐久間象山を訪ね、国防・政治改革について議論し、大いに意識を高める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, he visited Shozan SAKUMA at Matsushiro with Gensui SAKA, a man of outstanding ability from Choshu Province, and Tamaki SHISHIDO, where they discussed national defense and political reform, which heightened their motivation for political activity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862, he visited Shozan SAKUMA at Matsushiro with Gensui SAKA, a man of outstanding ability from Choshu Province, and Tamaki SHISHIDO, where they discussed national defense and political reform, which heightened their motivation for political activity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1862, he visited Shozan SAKUMA at Matsushiro with Gensui KUSAKA and Tamaki SHISHIDO, who were both of outstanding ability from Choshu clan, where they discussed national defense and political reform, which heightened their motivation for political activity.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。久坂玄瑞・宍戸たまき の両方が長州の俊英である、としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>文久3年（1863年）、京都での八月十八日の政変後に土佐藩内でも尊王攘夷活動に対する大弾圧が始まると、速やかに藩を脱藩し、同年9月、長州藩三田尻（現防府市）に亡命する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863, following the August 18 Incident in Kyoto, and the great suppression began against the movement to restore the emperor and expel the barbarians in the domain of Tosa, he quickly escaped and sought refuge in Mitajiri, the domain of Choshu (now Hofu City) in September of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863, with the start of a big crackdown on the Sonnoi Joi (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarians) movement in Tosa Domain that followed the August 18 Incident in Kyoto, he quickly escaped and in September of the same year, he sought refuge in Mitajiri, Choshu Domain (now Hofu City).</e>
<cmt>Reworded first part of sentenceMoved &quot;in September of the same year&quot;Added &quot;&apos;he&quot;&quot;the domain of Choshu&quot;→&quot;Choshu Domain&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863, with the start of a big crackdown on the Sonno Joi (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarians) movement in Tosa domain that followed the August 18 Incident (which falls on September 30 in the Gregorian calendar) in Kyoto, he quickly escaped the domain and in October of the same year, he sought refuge in Mitajiri, Choshu domain (now Hofu City).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>以後、長州藩内で同じ境遇の脱藩志士たちのまとめ役となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he became the leader of samurai who sought refuge in Choshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he became the leader of samurai who sought refuge in Choshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he became the leader of samurai who sought refuge in Choshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、三田尻に七卿落ちしていた三条実美の随臣（「衛士」）となり、長州はじめ各地の志士たちとの重要な連絡役となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the guard in the service of Sanetomi SANJO, who was one of the seven court nobles who was deprted from Kyoto, and acted as an important liaison between restoration activists in Choshu and those spread throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a guard in the service of Sanetomi SANJO, who was one of the seven court nobles who was deported from Kyoto, and acted as an important liaison between restoration activists in Choshu and those spread throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;Deleted &quot;who was&quot;Spelling of &quot;deported&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a guard in the service of Sanetomi SANJO, who was one of the seven court nobles who was deported to Mitajiri from Kyoto, and acted as an important liaison between restoration activists in Choshu and those spread throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>Mitajiri　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>元治元年（1864年）、石川誠之助を名乗り上洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, he went to Kyoto under the name of Seinosuke ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, he went to Kyoto under the name of Seinosuke ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, he went to Kyoto under the name of Seinosuke ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>薩摩藩の島津久光暗殺を画策したが果たせず、また脱藩志士たちを率いて禁門の変、下関戦争を長州側で戦い、負傷する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He schemed to assassinate Hisamitsu SHIMAZU of the domain of Satsuma, which failed, and he also led his followers in the Kinmon Incident and the Shimonoseki War, where he was wounded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He schemed to assassinate Hisamitsu SHIMAZU of Satsuma Domain, which failed, and he also led his followers in the Kinmon Incident and the Shimonoseki War, where he was wounded.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the domain of Satsuma&quot;→&quot;Satsuma Domain&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He schemed to assassinate Hisamitsu SHIMAZU of Satsuma clan, which failed, and he also led his followers in the Kinmon Incident and the Shimonoseki War as the Choshu side, where he was wounded.</e>
<cmt>長州側で　を追加しました。Satsuma clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>長州藩への冤罪・雄藩同士の有害無益な対立・志士たちへの弾圧を目の当たりにして、活動方針を単なる尊皇攘夷論から雄藩連合による武力倒幕論に発展させる（中岡慎太郎自身のこの頃の手紙による）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing that false charges were being brought against the domain of Choshu, witnessing the hostility between the major domains that was causing more harm than good, and seeing the suppression of the restoration activists, Shintaro changed from acting to protect the Emperor and exile barbarians to actively working to overthrow the shogunate by force (according to a letter written by Shintaro NAKAOKA at about this time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing that false charges were being brought against Choshu Domain, witnessing the hostility between the major domains that was causing more harm than good, and seeing the suppression of the restoration activists, Shintaro changed from acting to protect the Emperor and exile barbarians to actively working to overthrow the shogunate by force (according to a letter written by Shintaro NAKAOKA at about this time).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the domain of Choshu&quot;→&quot;Choshu Domain&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing that false charges were being brought against Choshu clan, witnessing the hostility between the major clans that was causing more harm than good, and seeing the suppression of the restoration activists, Shintaro changed from acting to protect the Emperor and exile barbarians to actively working to overthrow the shogunate by force (according to a letter written by Shintaro NAKAOKA at about this time).</e>
<cmt>domain→ clan　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして、長州藩の桂小五郎（木戸孝允）と薩摩藩の西郷隆盛（隆盛）との会合による薩長同盟締結を志士たちの第一の悲願として活動し始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he began working to form an alliance between Satsuma and Choshu as a priority goal and arranged a meeting between Kogoro KATSURA (a.k.a. Takayoshi KIDO) of Choshu and Takamori SAIGO of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, his priority became forming an alliance between Satsuma and Choshu and he arranged a meeting between Kogoro KATSURA (also known as Takayoshi KIDO) of Choshu and Takamori SAIGO of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he began working to form&quot;→&quot;his priority became forming&quot;Deleted &quot;as a priority goal&quot;Added &quot;he&quot;&quot;a.k.a&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, his priority became forming an alliance between Satsuma and Choshu and he arranged a meeting between Kogoro KATSURA (also known as Takayoshi KIDO) of Choshu and Takamori SAIGO of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>三条実美とも連絡を取りつつ脱藩志士たちのまとめ役として、薩摩と長州の志士たちの間を飛び回り、海援隊 (浪士結社)の坂本龍馬や三条の随臣土方楠左衛門（土方久元）をも説き伏せて巻き込んで行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaro maintained contact with Sanetomi SANJO and actively served as a liaison to all the exiles from Satsuma and Choshu, involving Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Kaientai (a group of leaderless warriors) and Kasuzaemon HIJIKATA (a.k.a. Hisamoto HIJIKATA), who served as Sanjo&apos;s guard.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintaro maintained contact with Sanetomi SANJO and actively served as a liaison to all the exiles from Satsuma and Choshu, involving Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Kaientai (a group of leaderless warriors) and Kasuzaemon HIJIKATA (also known as Hisamoto HIJIKATA), who served as Sanjo&apos;s guard.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a.k.a&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintaro maintained contact with Sanetomi SANJO and actively served as a liaison to all the exiles from Satsuma and Choshu, involving Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Kaientai (a group of leaderless warriors) and Kusuzaemon HIJIKATA (also known as Hisamoto HIJIKATA), who served as Sanjo&apos;s guard.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>慶応2年（1866年）1月21日（あるいは22日、旧暦）、京都二本松薩摩藩邸において薩長の和解および薩長同盟を結実させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 21, 1866 (or the 22nd by the old calendar), he was able to lead the two domains to a reconciliation and finalized the alliance between Satsuma and Choshu at the Nihonmatsu Satsuma residence in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21, 1866 (or the 22nd by the old calendar), he was able to lead the two domains to a reconciliation and finalized the alliance between Satsuma and Choshu at the Satsuma residence in Nihonmatsu, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Nihonmatsu&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 7, 1866 (or March 8), he was able to lead the two clans to a reconciliation and finalized the alliance between Satsuma and Choshu at the Satsuma residence in Nihonmatsu, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）2月、同志坂本龍馬ともども土佐藩から脱藩罪を赦免される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February of 1867, the charge of fleeing the domain of Tosa was dropped along with his comrade, Ryoma SAKAMOTO,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of 1867, the charge against him and Ryoma SAKAMOTO of fleeing Tosa Domain was dropped.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the domain of Tosa&quot;→&quot;Tosa Domain&quot;&quot; along with his comrade, Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot;→&quot;against him and Ryoma Sakamoto&quot; and movedDeleted comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of 1867, the charge against him and Ryoma SAKAMOTO of fleeing Tosa domain was dropped.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、薩土同盟についても同様に奔走し、まず、5月21日（旧暦）、土佐の乾退助（板垣退助）と薩摩の小松帯刀・西郷吉之助との間で倒幕のための薩土密約締結に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he engaged in forging an alliance between Satsuma and Tosa, starting with successfully forming a secret pact between Taisuku INUI (a.k.a. Taisuke ITAGAKI) of Tosa and Tatewaki KOMATSU and Kichinosuke SAIGO of Satsuma on May 21 (by the old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he engaged in forging an alliance between Satsuma and Tosa, starting with successfully forming a secret pact between Taisuku INUI (also known as Taisuke ITAGAKI) of Tosa and Tatewaki KOMATSU and Kichinosuke SAIGO of Satsuma on May 21 (by the old calendar).</e>
<cmt>&quot;a.k.a&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he engaged in forging an alliance between Satsuma and Tosa, starting with successfully forming a secret pact between Taisuke INUI (also known as Taisuke ITAGAKI) of Tosa and Tatewaki KOMATSU and Kichinosuke SAIGO of Satsuma on June 23.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>更に土佐藩そのものを本格的に取り込むための運動を展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he worked to stabilize the domain of Tosa, and, on June 22 (by the old calendar), at &apos;Yoshidaya&apos;, a restaurant in Sanbonigi, Kyoto, where a pact was formed to overthrow the shogunate and restore imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he worked to stabilize the domain of Tosa, and, on June 22 (by the old calendar), at &apos;Yoshidaya&apos;, a restaurant in Sanbonigi, Kyoto, a pact was formed to overthrow the shogunate and restore imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;where&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he continued to work to win over Tosa clan in earnest.</e>
<cmt>。で終わるように、和文原文を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>6月22日（旧暦）、京都三本木料亭「吉田屋」において、薩摩の小松帯刀・大久保一蔵（大久保利通）・西郷吉之助、土佐の寺村左膳・後藤象二郎・乾退助・福岡藤次（福岡孝弟）・石川誠之助（中岡）・才谷梅太郎（坂本龍馬）との間で、倒幕・王政復古実現のための薩土盟約が締結される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The parties to the pact were Tatewaki KOMATSU, Ichizo OKUBO (a.k.a. Toshimichi OKUBO), Kichinosuke SAIGO of Satsuma, and Sazen TERAMURA, Shojiro GOTO, Taisuke INUI, Toji FUKUOKA (a.k.a. Tachikawa FUKUOKA), Seinosuke ISHIKAWA (NAKAOKA), Umetaro SAITANI and (a.k.a. Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The parties to the pact were Tatewaki KOMATSU, Ichizo OKUBO (also known as Toshimichi OKUBO), Kichinosuke SAIGO of Satsuma, and Sazen TERAMURA, Shojiro GOTO, Taisuke INUI, Toji FUKUOKA (also known as Tachikawa FUKUOKA), Seinosuke ISHIKAWA (NAKAOKA) and Umetaro SAITANI (also known as Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt>&quot;a.k.a&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;&quot;a.k.a&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;Moved &quot;and&quot;&quot;a.k.a&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, on July 23, at &apos;Yoshidaya,&apos; a restaurant in Sanbongi, Kyoto, a pact was formed to overthrow the shogunate and restore imperial rule; the parties to the pact were Tatewaki KOMATSU, Ichizo OKUBO (also known as Toshimichi OKUBO), Kichinosuke SAIGO of Satsuma, and Sazen TERAMURA, Shojiro GOTO, Taisuke INUI, Toji FUKUOKA (also known as Takachika FUKUOKA), Seinosuke ISHIKAWA (NAKAOKA) and Umetaro SAITANI (also known as Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt>上記セルにつづき、和文原文および英文を修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>この薩土盟約は、更なる雄藩連合推進のため、同年6月26日、長州藩の隣の安芸藩を加えた薩土芸三藩約定書に拡大発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 26 of the same year, the pact between Satsuma and Tosa expanded to include the three domains of Satsuma, Tosa and Aki, to further strengthen ties among major domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 26 of the same year, the pact between Satsuma and Tosa was expanded to include the three domains of Satsuma, Tosa and Aki, further strengthening ties among major domains.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;was&quot;Deleted &quot;to&quot;&quot;strengthen&quot;→&quot;strengthening&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 27 of the same year, the pact between Satsuma and Tosa was expanded to include Aki, which was a neighboring domain of Choshu, further strengthening ties among major clans.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、当時はまだ土佐藩・安芸藩自身による大政奉還建白書や山内容堂の徳川宗家への強い「恩顧」意識があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the alliances between Satsuma and Tosa, and Satsuma, Tosa and Aki, had been formed, not so much for the objectives set forth by Nakaoka, but more so by the Tosa and Aki domains to petition for the return of the Emperor&apos;s power in the Tokugawa shogunate, and Yodo YAMAUCHI&apos;s hope of doing Tokugawa a favor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the alliances between Satsuma and Tosa, and Satsuma, Tosa and Aki, had been formed, not so much for the objectives set forth by Nakaoka, but more so by the Tosa and Aki domains to petition the Tokugawa Shogunate for the return of the Emperor&apos;s power, and Yodo YAMAUCHI&apos;s hope of doing Tokugawa a favor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in the Tokugawa shogunate&quot;→&quot;the Tokugawa Shogunate&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at that time, the Tosa and Aki clans themselves tried to petition the Tokugawa Shogunate for the return of the Emperor&apos;s power; furthermore, Yodo YAMAUCHI still strongly felt indebted to the head of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>原文を。で終わるように修正し、英文もそれに合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そのためこれらの薩土同盟・薩土芸同盟は、翌年1月の鳥羽・伏見の戦いにおいて薩長官軍側の優勢が判明するまで実質的な威力には乏しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the lead of the Satsuma and Choshu forces became apparent in the Toba-Fushimi War that took place in January of the following year, the pact was not able to exercise power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the lead of the Satsuma and Choshu forces became apparent in the Toba-Fushimi War that took place in January of the following year, the pact was not able to exercise power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the;ead pf Satsuma and Choshu forces became apparent in the Toba-Fushimi War that took place in January of the following year, these alliances between Satsuma and Tosa, and Satsuma, Tosa and Aki, were not able to exercise power.</e>
<cmt>原文を。で終わるように修正し、英文もそれに合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>しかしながら、これらの慎太郎・龍馬の労苦の結晶である軍事同盟締結は、土佐藩内においては旧態依然とした兵制を改革させる決定的契機となり、土佐を戊辰戦争において薩摩・長州・肥前と並ぶ倒幕の主要勢力たらしめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These military alliances formed through the efforts of Shintaro and Ryoma led to the opportunity to reform the old military system in the Tosa domain, allowing Tosa to be become a major power, one equivalent to Satsuma, Choshu and Hizen at the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These military alliances, formed through the efforts of Shintaro and Ryoma, led to the opportunity to reform the old military system in Tosa Domain, allowing Tosa to be become a major power, one equivalent to Satsuma, Choshu and Hizen during the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>Added commasDeleted &quot;the&quot;Capitalised &apos;d&apos;&quot;at&quot;→&quot;during&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These military alliances, formed through the efforts of Shintaro and Ryoma, led to the opportunity to reform the old military system in Tosa clan, allowing Tosa to become a major power, one equivalent to Satsuma, Choshu and Hizen during the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>domain →clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また同時に、倒幕後の政治ビジョンを描かざるを得ないことから封建制・幕藩体制をどう変えていかなければならないかという意識改革・藩政改革を他の諸藩よりも早めに進めざるを得なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the alliances accelerated a rise in the awareness of the part that the domain needed to play to change the feudal and shogunate systems, and the need to draw up a government vision for after the overthrow of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the alliances accelerated a rise in the awareness of the part that the domains needed to play to change the feudal and shogunate systems, and the need to draw up a government vision for after the overthrow of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;domain&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the alliances accelerated a rise in the awareness of the part that the domains needed to play to change the feudal and shogunate systems, and the need to draw up a government vision for after the overthrow of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>土佐出身者を薩摩・長州・肥前出身者同様に幕末・明治をリードする主要政治勢力たらしめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To move ahead with the plan, Tosa was placed in a position to lead through the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate and enter the Meiji Era with power equivalent to Satsuma, Choshu and Hisen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To move ahead with the plan, Tosa was placed in a position to lead through the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate and enter the Meiji Era with power equivalent to Satsuma, Choshu and Hisen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To move ahead with the plan, Tosa was placed in a position to lead through the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate and enter the Meiji period with power equivalent to Satsuma, Choshu and Hizen.</e>
<cmt>era →period　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>7月、かねてから長州で見聞させてもらっていた奇兵隊を参考に陸援隊を本格的に組織し始め、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, he began to organize the Rikuentai, learning from the Kiheitai system in Choshu that Shintaro had been closely observing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, he began to organize the Rikuentai, learning from the Kiheitai system in Choshu that he had been closely observing.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shintaro&quot;→&quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, he began to organize the Rikuentai, learning from the Kiheitai system in Choshu that he had been closely observing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>自ら隊長となり、白川土佐藩邸を陸援隊の本拠地と定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the head of the Rikuentai and established headquarters at the Shirajawa Tosa Domain residence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the head of the Rikuentai and established its headquarters at the Shirajawa Tosa Domain residence.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;its&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the head of the Rikuentai and established its headquarters at the Shirakawa Tosa clan residence.</e>
<cmt>Shirakawa Tosa clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この頃、討幕と大攘夷を説いた『時勢論』を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At about this time, he wrote &quot;Jiseiron&quot; an explanation of anti-Shogunate and anti-foreigner theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about this time, he wrote &quot;Jiseiron&quot;, an explanation of anti-Shogunate and anti-foreigner theory.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At about this time, he wrote &quot;Jiseiron,&quot; an explanation of anti-Shogunate and anti-foreigner theory.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>11月15日（旧暦）、京都近江屋に坂本龍馬を訪問中、何者かに襲撃され、瀕死の重傷を負う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 15 (by the old calendar), Shintaro was attacked and received a near-fatal injury when he was visiting Ryoma SAKAMOTO at Omiya in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 15 (by the old calendar), Shintaro was attacked and received a near-fatal injury when he was visiting Ryoma SAKAMOTO at Omiya in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 10, Shintaro was attacked and received a near-fatal injury when he was visiting Ryoma SAKAMOTO at Omiya in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>龍馬は即死ないし翌日未明に息絶えたが、慎太郎は二日間生き延びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma died on that day or the day following the attack, and Shintaro lived for 2 more days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma died early the following day, and Shintaro lived for 2 more days,</e>
<cmt>&quot;that day or the day following the attack&quot;→&quot;early the following day&quot;full stop→comma to rejoin to cell F51</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma died instantly (or early the following day), and Shintaro lived for two more days.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>暗殺犯の襲撃の様子について谷干城などに詳細に語り、11月17日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave Tateki TANI a detailed account of the attack by assassins before succumbing on November 17th.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">giving Tateki TANI a detailed account of the assassins&apos; attack before succumbing on November 17th.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He gave&quot;→&quot;giving&quot;&quot;attack by assassins&quot;→&quot;assassins&apos; attack&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gave Tateki TANI a detailed account of the assassins&apos; attack before succumbing on December 12.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>享年29。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 29 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 29 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 29 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="37">
<j>墓所は、京都市東山区の京都霊山護国神社ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried at the Kyoto-Ryozan-Gokoku-Jinja Shrine in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried at the Kyoto-Ryozan-Gokoku-Jinja Shrine in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried at the Kyoto-Ryozan-Gokoku-Jinja Shrine in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>室戸岬に銅像が立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His bronze statue stands at Muroto Point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bronze statue of him stands at Muroto Point.</e>
<cmt>&quot;His bronze statue&quot;→&quot;A bronze statue of him&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bronze statue of him stands at Muroto-misaki Cape.</e>
<cmt>Muroto-misaki Cape　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この銅像は桂浜にある坂本龍馬の銅像を向いているといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This statue is said to be facing Ryoma Sakamoto&apos;s statue in Katsurahama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This statue is said to be facing Ryoma Sakamoto&apos;s statue in Katsurahama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This statue is said to be facing Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s statue in Katsurahama.</e>
<cmt>SAKAMOTO と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>土佐藩では庄屋は転勤の制度があったため、中岡家のルーツは室戸ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the domain of Tosa, village headsmen were transferred, and so the Nakaoka family&apos;s roots are not in Muroto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the domain of Tosa, village headsmen were transferred around, and so the Nakaoka family&apos;s roots are not in Muroto.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;around&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tosa clan, village headsmen were transferred around, and so the Nakaoka family&apos;s roots are not in Muroto.</e>
<cmt>domain →clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>なお、姓は藤原氏、家紋は丸に綿の花である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nakaoka family ws a part of the Fujiwara clan, and the family crest is a cotton flower in a circle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakaoka family was part of the Fujiwara clan, and the family crest is a cotton flower in a circle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ws a&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakaoka family was part of the Fujiwara clan, and the family crest is a cotton flower in a circle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="43">
<j>生誕の地である高知県安芸郡北川村柏木地区に「中岡慎太郎館」が建てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nakaoka Shintaro Memorial of Museum was established at his birthplace, Kashiwagi, Kitagawa Village, Aki County, Kochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakaoka Shintaro Memorial Museum was established at his birthplace, Kashiwagi, Kitagawa Village, Aki County, Kochi.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakaoka Shintaro Memorial Museum was established at his birthplace, Kashiwagi, Kitagawa-mura, Aki-gun, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>場所の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>土佐くろしお鉄道土佐くろしお鉄道阿佐線奈半利駅より北川村営バスで約20分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The museum is approximately 20 minutes from the Nahari Station of the Tosa-Kuroshio Railway&apos;s Asa Line by Kitagawa Village-operated bus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The museum is approximately 20 minutes from Nahari Station on the Tosa-Kuroshio Railway&apos;s Asa Line by Kitagawa Village-operated bus.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The museum is approximately 20 minutes from Nahari Station on the Tosa-Kuroshio Railway&apos;s Asa Line by Kitagawa Village-operated bus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="45">
<j>近江屋で坂本龍馬と一緒に襲われたが、彼は即死せず二日間生き延びて、刺客が「こなくそ」といいながら襲ってきたと話している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaro and Ryoma Sakamoto were attacked together at Omiya; however Shintaro lived for days after the attack and told about the attack that the assassins shouted &quot;Konakuso&quot; (meaning &quot;Damn you&quot; in Iyo dialect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintaro and Ryoma Sakamoto were attacked together at Omiya; however Shintaro lived for days after the attack and said of the attack that the assassins shouted &quot;Konakuso&quot; (meaning &quot;Damn you&quot; in Iyo dialect).</e>
<cmt>&quot;told about&quot;→&quot;said of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintaro and Ryoma SAKAMOTO were attacked together at Omiya; however Shintaro lived for two days after the attack and said of the attack that the assassins shouted &apos;Konakuso&apos; (meaning &quot;Damn you&quot; in Iyo dialect).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、焼飯を食べたいとも話したらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems he said he wanted to eat fried rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems he said he wanted to eat fried rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems he said he wanted to eat fried rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="47">
<j>「今日賎しいものが、明日には貴いかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last words were; &quot;That which may seem vulgar today may be precious tomorrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last words were; &quot;That which may seem vulgar today may be precious tomorrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His last words were; &apos;That which may seem vulgar today may be precious tomorrow.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>小人か君子かは、人の心の中にある」という言葉を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The potential to be a man of little consequences or to become a man of virtue lies in the mind of each man.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The potential to be a man of little consequences or to become a man of virtue lies in the mind of each man.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The potential to be a man of little consequences or to become a man of virtue lies in the mind of each man.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="49">
<j>薩長連合、薩土密約、大政奉還等は、坂本龍馬が中心に描かれたテレビドラマや小説が多いが、その発想や行動において真の立役者は本当はどちらかであったかは議論が分かれるところである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many novels and TV dramas about the Satsuma-Choshu alliance, the Satsuma-Tosa pact, and the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate with an emphasis on Ryoma SAKAMOTO; however, there is debate as to who the central person in these events was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many novels and TV dramas about the Satsuma-Choshu alliance, the Satsuma-Tosa pact, and the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate with an emphasis on Ryoma SAKAMOTO; however, there is debate as to who the central person in these events was.</e>
<cmt>Deleted space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many novels and TV dramas about the Satsuma-Choshu alliance, the Satsuma-Tosa pact, and the return of political power to the Emperor by the Tokugawa Shogunate with an emphasis on Ryoma SAKAMOTO; however, there is debate as to who the central person in these events was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>実際は、中岡であったという歴史家の意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some historians think it was Nakaoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some historians think it was Nakaoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some historians think it was Nakaoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また、中岡が龍馬の西洋的な議会主義的思想にどの程度まで理解を示したのかも今日まで不明な点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It remains unclear as to how much of Ryoma&apos;s western ideology Nakaoka agreed with.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It remains unclear as to how much of Ryoma&apos;s western ideology Nakaoka agreed with.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It remains unclear as to how much of Ryoma&apos;s western legislative ideology Nakaoka agreed with.</e>
<cmt>legislativeを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="52">
<j>2000年にアメリカで発行された「JAPAN」という日本を紹介する本では、何故か坂本竜馬の銅像として室戸の中岡の銅像が紹介されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a book entitled &quot;JAPAN&quot; that was published in the US in 2000, Nakaoka&apos;s statue in Muroto is mistakenly labeled as Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a book entitled &quot;JAPAN&quot; that was published in the US in 2000, Nakaoka&apos;s statue in Muroto is mistakenly labeled as Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a book entitled &apos;JAPAN&apos; that was published to introduce Japan in the US in 2000, Nakaoka&apos;s statue in Muroto is mistakenly labeled as Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), Lemon pie(id:66842), Bakkai(id:7233), PANYNJ(id:38638), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), ウース(id:31355), Cprobot(id:97843), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kamuin(id:5241), Sgi1962(id:80778), 認定者(id:99098), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 中岡駿馬直道(id:32636), 間久部緑郎(id:22345), SouthTrend(id:184482), Parachutes(id:139813), 轟俊(id:150842), MioUzaki(id:89034), Northface(id:70750), ×(id:36400), Goki(id:7107), 上田隼人(id:23104), Cooldriver(id:88517), ぎぼうし(id:139427), Korokoro(id:42329), トホホ川(id:50502), Maakun(id:16735), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>