<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小関三英</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanei KOSEKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanei KOSEKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanei KOSEKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小関三英（こせき さんえい、天明7年6月11日 (旧暦)（1787年7月25日） - 天保10年5月17日 (旧暦)（1839年6月27日））は、江戸時代後期の医者・蘭学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanei KOSEKI (July 25, 1787 - June 27, 1839) was a doctor and a Dutch scholar during the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanei KOSEKI (July 25, 1787 - June 27, 1839) was a doctor and Dutch scholar during the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Dutch scholarの前のa を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanei KOSEKI (July 25, 1787 - June 27, 1839) was a doctor and Dutch scholar during the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は好義、通称良蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was 好義 and his common name was 良蔵.</e>
<cmt>好義、良蔵：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Kogi and his common name was Ryozo.</e>
<cmt>鶴岡市郷土資料館に問い合わせたところ、はっきりとは特定できないが、音読みするのが一般的とのことですので、そのように処理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Kogi and his common name was Ryozo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は鶴洲、あるいは篤斎（とくさい）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go (pen name) was 鶴洲 or Tokusai.</e>
<cmt>鶴洲：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (pen name) was Kakushu or Tokusai.</e>
<cmt>鶴岡市郷土資料館に問い合わせたところ、はっきりとは特定できないが、音読みするのが一般的とのことですので、そのように処理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Kakushu or Tokusai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>出羽国（山形県）庄内地方・鶴岡市の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanei was born in Tsuruoka City, Shonai Region, Dewa Province (Yamagata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanei was born in Tsuruoka City, Shonai Region, Dewa Province (Yamagata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanei was born in Tsuruoka City, Shonai Region, Dewa Province (Yamagata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>長崎でフィリップ・フランツ・フォン・シーボルトに師事したとされてきたが、最近では長崎遊学、シーボルト門下とする典拠はないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it had been believed that Sanei learned under Philipp Franz von Siebold, it became clear that there are no sources of evidence indicating that Sanei travelled to Nagasaki for learning and became a disciple of Siebold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanei was believed to have studied under Philipp Franz von Siebold in Nagasaki, but it became clear that there is no such evidence.</e>
<cmt>・表現を簡略にしました。・「師事」は定訳を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanei was believed to have studied under Philipp Franz von Siebold in Nagasaki, but it became clear that there is no such evidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸で蘭医吉田長淑・馬場佐十郎に蘭学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanei learned Western studies from Choshuku YOSHIDA and Sajuro BABA, both Dutch doctors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanei studied Western studies under Choshuku YOSHIDA and Sajuro BABA, both of whom were Western doctors.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanei studied Western studies under Choshuku YOSHIDA and Sajuro BABA, both of whom were Western doctors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>コンスブルフの内科書を和訳して「泰西内科集成」を上梓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He translated a book on internal medicine written by コンスブルフ and published it as &apos;Taisei Naika Shusei&apos; (literally, Western Internal Medicine Compilation).</e>
<cmt>コンスブルフ：英語表記は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He translated a book on internal medicine written by Consbruch and published it as &apos;Taisei Naika Shusei&apos; (literally, Western Internal Medicine Compilation).</e>
<cmt>コンスブルフの英語標記判明しました。http://www.wul.waseda.ac.jp/kotenseki/search.php?cndbn=Consbruch,+Georg+Wilhelm+Christoph</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He translated a book on internal medicine written by Consbruch and published it as &apos;Taisei Naika Shusei&apos; (literally, Western Internal Medicine Compilation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天保3年（1832年）、和泉国岸和田医となり、のち幕府の天文方阿蘭陀書籍和解御用、すなわち翻訳係となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1832, Sanei became a doctor of Kishiwada of Izumi Province and was later appointed as a translator belonging to Tenmonkata (Astronomical Institute) of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1832, Sanei became a doctor of Kishiwada in Izumi Province and was later appointed as a translator belonging to Tenmonkata (Astronomical Institute) of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>「和泉国岸和田」は定訳に従いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1832, Sanei became a doctor of Kishiwada in Izumi Province and was later appointed as a translator belonging to Tenmonkata (Astronomical Institute) of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このころ渡辺崋山・高野長英と親交をもち、尚歯会に参加、歴史や地理を講じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, Sanei got acquainted with Kazan WATANABE (a senior vassal of the Hahara Domain) and Choei TAKANO (a doctor and a Dutch scholar) and joined &apos;Shoshikai&apos; to give a lecture on history and geography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, Sanei got acquainted with Kazan WATANABE (a senior vassal of the Tahara Domain) and Choei TAKANO (a doctor and Dutch scholar) and joined Shoshikai to give a lecture on history and geography.</e>
<cmt>崋山と長英の補足説明は原文にはありませんが、残しました。尚、Hahara ではなく、Tahara (田原藩）が正当なので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, Sanei got acquainted with Kazan WATANABE (a senior vassal of the Tahara Domain) and Choei TAKANO (a doctor and Dutch scholar) and joined Shoshikai to give a lecture on history and geography.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>蛮社の獄の際、崋山・長英の入牢を聞き、自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning) occurred, Sanei killed himself after being informed that Kazan and Choei were imprisoned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning) occurred, Sanei, having heard of the imprisonment of Kanan and Choei, killed himself.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning) occurred, Sanei, having heard of the imprisonment of Kanan and Choei, killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>崋山に「耶蘇伝」を口訳したことなどから連坐を恐れたものとされるが、三英には特に処罰される必然性はなく、自害は早計だったのではないか、とする意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Sanei killed himself for fear of the punishment by bakufu jointly with Kazan and Choei for translating &apos;Yasoden&apos; (a book on Jesus Christ) into a colloquial speech, but some observers say that Sanei did not have to commit a suicide as there seems no logical ground for bakufu to punish him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Sanei killed himself for fear of the punishment by bakufu for translating &apos;Yasoden&apos; (a book on Jesus Christ) into colloquial speech, but some argue that Sanei did not have to commit suicide because bakufu had no reason to punish him.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Sanei killed himself for fear of the punishment by bakufu for translating &apos;Yasoden&apos; (a book on Jesus Christ) into colloquial speech, but some argue that Sanei did not have to commit suicide because bakufu had no reason to punish him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>西洋史にも興味を持ち、日本にナポレオン・ボナパルトを紹介する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanei was also interested in history of the Western world and introduced Napoleon BONAPARTE to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanei was also interested in history of the Western world and introduced Napoleon BONAPARTE to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanei was also interested in history of the Western world and introduced Napoleon BONAPARTE to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>著書に「西医原病略」「輿地誌」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the author of &apos;Seii Genbyou ryaku&apos; (literally, Western medicine disease summary) and &apos;Yochi shi&apos; (literally, a record of the earth).</e>
<cmt>「西医原病略」「輿地誌」：詳細がウェブで見当たりませんので、語彙的に訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the author of &apos;Seiigenbyoryaku&apos; (literally, summary of Western medicine diseases) and &apos;Yochi-shi&apos; (literally, a record of the earth).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。前者は句切りどころが不明なので、スペースを設けませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the author of &apos;Seiigenbyoryaku&apos; (literally, summary of Western medicine diseases) and &apos;Yochi-shi&apos; (literally, a record of the earth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), MDR-SK(id:192066), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Rusk(id:9895), Nnh(id:474), Nekomiminarikin(id:199247), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), こいつぅ(id:2105), Akoyano(id:56905), Bow(id:16755), Klesha(id:203751), Inukawa(id:842), 間久部緑郎(id:22345), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>