<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>阿佐太子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Asa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Asa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Asa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>阿佐太子（あさたいし、アジャテサ、557年 - 631年）百済の威徳王 (百済)の息子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Asa (also known as Asa Taishi or Ajatesa, 557-631) was a son of King Widok (Baekje) in Baekje.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Asa (also known as Asa Taishi or Ajatesa, 557-631) was a son of King Widok (Baekje) in Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Asa (also known as Asa Taishi or Ajatesa, 557-631) was a son of King Widok (Baekje) in Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本に来て肖像画を描いたと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He supposedly came to Japan and drew portraits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He supposedly came to Japan and drew portraits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He supposedly came to Japan and drew portraits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀」によれば、597年4月に日本に渡って聖徳太子の肖像を描いたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the oldest chronicles of Japan), he came over Japan and made a portrait of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the oldest chronicles of Japan), he came over Japan in April, 597 and made a portrait of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>597年4月が抜けていたので、追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the oldest chronicles of Japan), he came over Japan in April, 597 and made a portrait of Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現在日本の宮内庁に所庁されている絵は、日本で一番古い肖像画とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting presently stored in the Japanese Imperial Household Agency is believed to be the oldest portrait in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting presently stored in the Japanese Imperial Household Agency is believed to be the oldest portrait in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting presently stored in the Japanese Imperial Household Agency is believed to be the oldest portrait in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その形式は太子を中に置いて左右には2人の王子（伝えられるところによれば、右側が山背大兄王、左側が殖栗王）を少し小さく配置した構成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the form of the portrait, it has a construction that placed Prince Shotoku between another two princes (Prince Yamashiro no oe on the right side, while Eguri-O on the other side, as the story goes), drawn a little smaller than the size of him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the form of the portrait, it has a construct that Prince Shotoku is placed between another two princes (Prince Yamashiro no oe on the right side, while Eguri-O on the other side, as the story goes) drawn a little smaller than Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>constructionをconstructに変更しました。より自然な表現となるように左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the form of the portrait, it has a construct that Prince Shotoku is placed between another two princes (Prince Yamashiro no oe on the right side, while Eguri-O on the other side, as the story goes) drawn a little smaller than Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この配置は、仏教の影響を受けた三尊仏的構成とも考えられ、あるいは閻立本の絵に伝わる『歴代帝王島圏 歴代帝王図巻』に見られる、その頃の構図法に起因したものと解釈されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This layout is also thought to be a construction of Sansonbutsu (three Buddhist deities) affected by Buddhism, or often interpreted as the one arising from a way of composition at that time, which could be found in &quot;歴代帝王島圏 the Rekidai Teio Zumaki&quot; (The Thirteen Emperors Scroll), the painting of the EN Rippon (a Chinese painter and government official of the early Tang Dynasty) handed down to today.</e>
<cmt>三尊仏的構成→a construction of Sansonbutsu (three Buddhist deities)としました。ウェブによりますと、 『歴代帝王図巻』はthe Thirteen Emperors Scroll と訳されていました。歴代帝王島圏の読み方と定訳が見つかりません。閻立本→EN Rippon (a Chinese painter and government official of the early Tang Dynasty)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This layout is also thought to be a construct of Sansonbutsu (three Buddhist deities) affected by Buddhism, or often interpreted as a construct originated from a composition technique of the time, which is found in &quot;歴代帝王島圏 the Rekidai Teio Zumaki&quot; (The Thirteen Emperors Scroll) of Yan Liben (a Chinese painter and government official of the early Tang Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>EN Ripponのスペルを変更しました。より自然な表現となるように左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This layout is also thought to be a construct of Sansonbutsu (three Buddhist deities) affected by Buddhism, or often interpreted as a construct originated from a composition technique of the time, which is found in &quot;歴代帝王島圏 the Rekidai Teio Zumaki&quot; (The Thirteen Emperors Scroll) of Yan Liben (a Chinese painter and government official of the early Tang Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>現在日本学界でも論議が多いこの像は、製作時期においても太子及び脇侍王子の服飾から見て、後の白鳳時代の作品だと見る説と、鎌倉時代の模本と見る説が概して多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many theories about when this image was drawn, now a topic of debate in Japanese academic circles, mostly including the ideas that it is the work in later Hakuho period or a replica in Kamakura period, judged by the clothes that the Prince and kyoji (attendant figures) wore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many theories about when this image was drawn, now a topic of debate in Japanese academic circles, mostly including the ideas that it is the work in later Hakuho period or a replica in Kamakura period, judged by the clothes that the Prince and kyoji (attendant figures) wore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theories abound about when this image--currently the subject of considerable debate in Japan&apos;s academic world--was made; most such theories judge from the clothes worn by the Prince and his attendants to assert either that it is a work dating from the late Hakuho period (645-710 C.E.) or that it is a Kamakura period copy.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>このように現在伝えられる聖徳太子像は、様式上の問題点と同時に、阿佐太子に対する記録が大韓民国側資料にはないという事実によって、未解決の課題だが、三国時代 (朝鮮半島)当時の百済と日本との活発な交流を考慮すれば、その可能性は充分に認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That could be possible, considering the cultural exchanges between Baekje and Japan at that time during the Three Kingdoms period (of Korean history) though Shotoku Taishi zo (Statue of Price Shotoku) come down to today accordingly has remained an unresolved issue because of its formal problem as well as because of the fact that the materials in the Republic of Korea have no record relating to Prince Asa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That could be possible, considering the cultural exchanges between Baekje and Japan at that time during the Three Kingdoms period (of Korean history) though Shotoku Taishi zo (Statue of Price Shotoku) come down to today accordingly has remained an unresolved issue because of its formal problem as well as because of the fact that the materials in the Republic of Korea have no record relating to Prince Asa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is quite possible that Prince Asa did make a portrait of Prince Shotoku, considering the active cultural exchange between Baekje and Japan at that time, during the Three Kingdoms period (of Korean history); however, the matter is still in doubt, due to stylistic problems with such an attribution and the fact that historical records in the Republic of Korea do not mention Prince Asa.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), RTC(id:45114), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Nopira(id:29335), 風魔小太郞(id:149411), Kaznov17(id:68122), Uraios(id:72687), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>