<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原葛野麻呂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 葛野麻呂（ふじわら の かどのまろ、天平勝宝7年（755年） - 弘仁9年11月10日 (旧暦)（818年12月11日））は、奈良時代から平安時代前期にかけての貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro (755 ~ December 11, 818) is a court noble from Nara period to the former half of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro (755 ~ December 11, 818) was a court noble from the Nara period to the former half of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro (755 - December 11, 818) was a court noble from the Nara period to the former half of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>~→- 他ファイルに合わせる</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大納言藤原小黒麻呂の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the eldest son of Dainagon (Major Counselor), FUJIWARA no Oguromaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of Dainagon (Major Counselor), FUJIWARA no Oguromaro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Dainagon (chief councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Oguromaro.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正三位中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), Chunagon (middle counselor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), Chunagon (middle counselor.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>妹が桓武天皇の後宮に入ったために重んじられ、785年（延暦4年）従五位下に叙されると、陸奥介を振り出しに、以後少納言・春宮大夫・右大弁・大宰大弐などを歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his sister entered to kokyu (empress&apos;s residence), he was taken into confidence, and in 785 when he was ranked to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he filled successively the posts from Mutsu no suke (Assistant governor of Mutsu Province) and later to Shonagon (Lesser counselor), Togu no daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters), Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right), Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices.,) etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his sister entered kokyu (empress&apos;s residence), he was taken into confidence, and in 785 when he was ranked to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he successively filled the posts from Mutsu no suke (Assistant governor of Mutsu Province) and later to Shonagon (Lesser counselor), Togu no daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters), Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right), Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices.,) etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his sister became a consort of Emperor Kanmu, he was highly honored and in 785 was conferred the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and made Mutsu no Suke (assistant governor of Mutsu Province) before going on to successively hold positions including Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), Togu no Daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters), Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right), and Dazai no Daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平安京の造宮使にも任ぜられ、793年（延暦12年）には官人に新京の宅地を配分した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also designated to zogushi (palace construction officer) of Heian-kyo, and in 793, he allocated lands of the new capital to residences of government officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also designated to zogushi (palace construction officer) of Heian-kyo, and in 793, he allocated lands of the new capital to residences of government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also appointed Zogushi (palace construction officer) of Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), and in 793, he allocated residential land in the new capital to government officials.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>801年（延暦20年）遣唐使に任命され、804年（延暦23年）に最澄・空海らと共に唐に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 801, he was appointed to Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty, China,) and he crossed the sea to Tang Dynasty with Saicho and Kukai in 804.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 801, he was appointed to Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty, China,) and he crossed the sea to the Tang Dynasty with Saicho and Kukai in 804.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 801, he was appointed Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty, China) and traveled to Tang Dynasty China with Saicho and Kukai in 804.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>徳宗 (唐)に謁見し翌805年（延暦24年）の徳宗崩御と順宗 (唐)即位に遭遇する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had an audience with Emperor Dezong of Tang dynasty and in the next year of 805, he encountered the demise of Emperor Dezong and accession of Emperor Shunzong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had an audience with Emperor Dezong of the Tang dynasty and in the next year of 805, he encountered the demise of Emperor Dezong and accession of Emperor Shunzong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted an audience with Emperor Dezong (Tang Dynasty) and in the following year of 805, he witnessed the death of Emperor Dezong and accession of Emperor Shunzong.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この年7月に帰国、大使の功により従三位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Japan in July of this year and was ranked to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) for the achievement as an Ambassador to Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Japan in July of that year and was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) for his achievements as an Ambassador to Tang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Japan in August of the same year and was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) for his achievements as an ambassador.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。（延暦24年）7月をグレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>806年（延暦25年/大同 (日本)元年）に平城天皇が即位すると、かつて皇太子時代の春宮大夫であった事から直ちに権参議に、続いて参議に昇任し、式部卿を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 806 when Emperor Heizei acceded, he was soon promoted to Gon-sangi (deputy councilor), and Sangi (councilor) the next, and doubled with post of Shikibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial) as he was Togu no daibu when the emperor was Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 806 when Emperor Heizei acceded, he was soon promoted to Gon-sangi (deputy councilor), and Sangi (councilor) the next, and doubled with post of Shikibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonies) as he was Togu no daibu when the emperor was Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Heizei was enthroned in 806, Kadonomaro&apos;s role as Togu no Daibu while the emperor was Crown Prince saw him promoted to the position of Gonsangi (a provisional deputy councilor) and then Sangi (councilor) while he also served as Shikibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonies).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足など修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌807年（大同2年）参議が一時廃止されると東海道観察使に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year of 807 when the post of Sangi was temporally abolished, he was transferred to Tokai-do (road) Kansatsu-shi (inspector).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year of 807 when the post of Sangi was temporally abolished, he was transferred to Tokai-do (road) Kansatsu-shi (inspector).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the post of Sangi was temporally abolished in the following year of 807, he was appointed Tokai-do Kansatsu-shi (Inspector of the Tokai Circuit).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後も天皇の近臣として重用され、808年（大同3年）に中納言に任じられ、翌809年（大同4年）に正三位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was taken into confidence as the emperor&apos;s close aide also in later time, and he was posted to Chunagon in 808, and in the next year of 809, he was ranked to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was taken into confidence as the emperor&apos;s close aide also at a later time, and he was posted to Chunagon in 808, and in the next year of 809, he was given the rank Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was subsequently appointed a trusted vassal of the emperor and the year 808 was made Chunagon before being conferred the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in the following year of 809.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>810年（弘仁元年）薬子の変が起きた際には藤原真雄とともに平城上皇を挙兵を思いとどまるよう諌めたが受け入れられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 810 when the Kusuko Incident broke out, he tried with FUJIWARA no Saneo to persuade the Retired Emperor Heizei not to rise in arms, however, it was not accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 810 when the Kusuko Incident broke out, he tried with FUJIWARA no Saneo to persuade the Retired Emperor Heizei not to rise in arms, however, it was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kusuko Incident broke out in the year 810, both he and FUJIWARA no Saneo warned Retired Emperor Heizei not to raise an army but this was not heeded.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>藤原薬子と縁戚関係であったが、罪を問われずにその後は民部卿を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he was a relative of FUJIWARA no Kusuko, he was acquitted on a charge, and later he doubled with the post of Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he was a relative of FUJIWARA no Kusuko, he was acquitted on the charge, and later he doubled the post of Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kadonomaro was a relative of FUJIWARA no Kusuko, he was found not to be guilty and later also served as Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>嵯峨天皇の元において、藤原冬嗣・秋篠安人らと「弘仁格式」の編纂にも関わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also involved in the compilation of &quot;Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820)&quot; with FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu and AKISHINO no Yasuhito under Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also involved in the compilation of the &quot;Konin&quot; kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) with FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu and AKISHINO no Yasuhito under Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also involved in the compilation of the &quot;Konin&quot; kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820) with FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu and AKISHINO no Yasuhito under Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>死後、834年（承和 (日本)元年）には、息子の常嗣が父に続いて遣唐大使（実際に渡唐した最後の遣唐使）に任命されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death, in 834, his son FUJIWARA no Tsunetsugu was appointed to Kento-shi after his father (it was the last Kento-shi which actually visited Tang dynasty.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death, in 834, his son FUJIWARA no Tsunetsugu was appointed to Kento-shi after his father (it was the last Kento-shi which actually visited the Tang dynasty.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death, his son Tsunetsugu was appointed chief of the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China (the last Kento-shi to have actually visited Tang Dynasty China) in 834.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), UMBRO(id:100484), Shimoxx(id:9332), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>