<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>坂本龍馬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma SAKAMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma SAKAMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma SAKAMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>革命家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revolutionist</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Revolutionist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Revolutionist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>坂本 龍馬（さかもと りょうま、天保6年11月15日 (旧暦)（1836年1月3日） - 慶応3年11月15日 (旧暦)（1867年12月10日）は、幕末の日本の政治家・実業家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma SAKAMOTO (Jan.3, 1836-Dec.10, 1867) is a Japanese statesman and businessperson in the end of Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma SAKAMOTO (Jan.3, 1836-Dec.10, 1867) is a Japanese statesman and businessperson in the end of Edo era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma SAKAMOTO (Jan.3, 1836-Dec.10, 1867) is a Japanese statesman and businessperson in the end of Edo era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>土佐藩脱藩後、貿易会社と政治組織を兼ねた亀山社中・海援隊 (浪士結社)の結成、薩長連合の斡旋、大政奉還の成立に尽力するなど、志士として活動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having fled from Tosa clan he acted as a royalist, exerting himself into establishing Kameyama-shachu, later Kaienntai (a society of masterless samurai), a mixture of a trading company and a political organization, mediating collaboration between Satsuma and Choshu, and realizing Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having fled from Tosa clan he acted as a royalist, exerting himself into establishing Kameyama-shachu, later Kaientai (a society of master less samurai), a mixture of a trading company and a political organization, mediating collaboration between Satsuma and Choshu, and realizing Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule).</e>
<cmt>Kaienntai→Kaientai, masterless→master less</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having fled from Tosa clan he acted as a royalist, exerting himself into establishing Kameyama-shachu, later Kaientai (a society of master less samurai), a mixture of a trading company and a political organization, mediating collaboration between Satsuma and Choshu, and realizing Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>贈官位、正四位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">conferred official title: Senior Fourth Rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">conferred the official title: Senior Fourth Rank</e>
<cmt>conferred official title→conferred the official title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">conferred the official title: Senior Fourth Rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>司馬遼太郎の小説『竜馬がゆく』の主人公とされて以来、国民的人気を誇っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has gained a national reputation as a grand homme since Ryotaro SHIBA have made him the leading character in his novel &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has gained a national reputation as a popular person since Ryotaro SHIBA had made him the leading character in his novel &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>gainedの後にaを挿入, as a grand homme→as a popular person</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has gained a national reputation as a popular person since Ryotaro SHIBA had made him the leading character in his novel &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、その事跡についてはさまざまな論議がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are multilateral arguments on his vestiges.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also multilateral arguments on his vestiges.</e>
<cmt>areの後にalso</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also multilateral arguments on his vestiges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>諱は直陰のち直柔（なおなり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name is Naokage, which was later changed to Naonari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name is Naokage, which was later changed to Naonari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name is Naokage, which was later changed to Naonari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>龍馬は通称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma is a popular name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma is a popular name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma is a popular name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>他に才谷梅太郎などの変名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had some aliases, such as Umetaro SAITANI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had some aliases, such as Umetaro SAITANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had some aliases, such as Umetaro SAITANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「龍馬」は慣用音（『広辞苑』第5版）では「りゅうま」だが、漢音は「りょうま」で、同時代人の日記や書簡に「良馬」の当て字で記されていることもあり、また龍馬自身も書簡の中で「りよふ」と自署していることもあるため、「りょうま」と読まれていたことは間違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no doubt that his first name was pronounced as &quot;Ryoma&quot; considering that the kanji of his first name is pronounced &quot;Ryoma&quot; according to &quot;Kan-on&quot; (the Han reading of a kanji) although pronounced &quot;Ryuma&quot;according to &quot;Kan-yo on&quot; (the special Japanease reading) (see &quot;Kojien&quot; the fifth edition), that his contemporaries wrote down in their diaries and letters the kanji of the phonetic equivalent of &quot;Ryoma&quot; to refer to Ryoma, and that Ryoma himself sometimes added his signature reading &quot;Riyofu&quot; to his letters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no doubt that his first name was pronounced as &quot;Ryoma&quot; considering that the kanji of his first name is pronounced &quot;Ryoma&quot; according to &quot;Kan-on&quot; (the Han reading of a kanji) although pronounced &quot;Ryuma&quot;according to &quot;Kan-yo on&quot; (the special Japanese reading) (see &quot;Kojien&quot; the fifth edition), that his contemporaries wrote down in their diaries and letters the kanji of the phonetic equivalent of &quot;Ryoma&quot; to refer to Ryoma, and that Ryoma himself sometimes added his signature reading &quot;Riyofu&quot; to his letters.</e>
<cmt>Japanease→Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no doubt that his first name was pronounced as &quot;Ryoma&quot; considering that the kanji of his first name is pronounced &quot;Ryoma&quot; according to &quot;Kan-on&quot; (the Han reading of a kanji) although pronounced &quot;Ryuma&quot; according to &quot;Kan-yo on&quot; (the special Japanese reading) (see &quot;Kojien&quot; the fifth edition), that his contemporaries wrote down in their diaries and letters the kanji of the phonetic equivalent of &quot;Ryoma&quot; to refer to Ryoma, and that Ryoma himself sometimes added his signature reading &quot;Riyofu&quot; to his letters.</e>
<cmt>単語の間にスペースを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、「竜」は「龍」の異体字（「竜」は「龍」の古体字）で、龍馬自身は「竜」の字体を使ったことがないが、司馬遼太郎の「竜馬がゆく」で使われたことや、「竜」が常用漢字に採用されたこともあり、慣用化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the kanji character for &quot;Ryo,&quot; the old-style character is also commonly used for Ryoma partly because Ryotaro SHIBA used the old style in his novel &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot; and the old-style character was selected as a &quot;Kanji Designated for Everyday Use&quot; although Ryoma himself never used the old-style charracter.</e>
<cmt>「龍」が「竜」の古体字ではないのかと思いましたが、原文通りの意味で英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the kanji character for &quot;Ryo&quot;, the old-style character is also commonly used for Ryoma partly because Ryotaro SHIBA used the old style in his novel &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot; and the old-style character was selected as a &quot;Kanji Designated for Everyday Use&quot; although Ryoma himself never used the old-style character.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Ryo,&quot;のコンマを二重括弧&quot;の外へ,　charracter→character</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the kanji character for &quot;Ryo,&quot; the old-style character is also commonly used for Ryoma partly because Ryotaro SHIBA used the old style in his novel &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot; and the old-style character was selected as a &quot;Kanji Designated for Everyday Use&quot; although Ryoma himself never used the old-style character.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を戻した</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>むしろ生前より死後に有名になった人物であり、司馬遼太郎の作品を始め、小説やドラマに度々取り上げられる人物ではあるが、それらは実際の龍馬とかけ離れているのではないかという指摘は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became famed after his death rather than in life. Although he appears frequently in various novels and dramas such as Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s, there are many who mention that these images are away from factual Ryoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became famed after his death rather than in life. Although he appears frequently in various novels and dramas such as Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s, there are many who mention that these images are away from factual Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became famed after his death rather than in life. Although he appears frequently in various novels and dramas such as Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s, there are many who mention that these images are away from factual Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>歴史家の中に、特にそのような指摘をする人は多く、松浦玲などが代表格。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly among historians there are many who point out this difference, one of the representatives being Rei MATSUURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly among historians there are many who point out this difference, one of the representatives being Rei MATSUURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly among historians there are many who point out this difference, one of the representatives being Rei MATSUURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>松浦玲『検証・龍馬伝説』（論創社、2001年）・池田敬正「司馬遼太郎「竜馬がゆく」をめぐって」（『歴史評論』317、1976年）・絲屋寿雄「竜馬の虚像・実像-司馬遼太郎「竜馬がゆく」によせて-」（『歴史評論』317、1976年）などが参考になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to &quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (Ronsosha, 2001), &quot;Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot;&quot; by Takamasa IKEDA (&quot;Rekishi Hyoron&quot; (History Review) 317, 1976), and &quot;Ryoma&apos;s Persona and the Real Nature - Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;S &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku- &quot; by Hisao ITOYA (Rekishi Hyoron&quot; (History Review 317, 1976)).</e>
<cmt>「池田敬正」と「糸糸屋寿雄」の読みがわかりませんでしたが、それぞれ、”Takamasa IKEDA”、”Hisao ITOYA”としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to &quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (Ronsosha, 2001), &quot;Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot; by Takamasa IKEDA (&quot;Rekishi Hyoron&quot; (History Review) 317, 1976), and &quot;Ryoma&apos;s Persona and the Real Nature - Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot; - by Hisao ITOYA (Rekishi Hyoron&quot; (History Review 317, 1976)).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot;&quot;の&quot;を一つ削除, - Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;S の&apos;Sを&apos;sへ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to &quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (Ronsosha, 2001), &quot;Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot; by Takamasa IKEDA (&quot;Rekishi Hyoron&quot; (History Review) 317, 1976), and &quot;Ryoma&apos;s Persona and the Real Nature - Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot; - by Hisao ITOYA (Rekishi Hyoron&quot; (History Review 317, 1976)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ちなみに、龍馬の伝記を書いた歴史家としては、平尾道雄・池田敬正・飛鳥井雅道などが代表的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representatives of historians who wrote the biography of Ryoma are Michio HIRAO, Takamasa IKEDA, and Masamichi ASUKAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representatives of historians who wrote the biography of Ryoma are Michio HIRAO, Takamasa IKEDA, and Masamichi ASUKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representatives of historians who wrote the biography of Ryoma are Michio HIRAO, Takamasa IKEDA, and Masamichi ASUKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その他、詳しくは「文献」の項目を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For further details, refer to &quot;Literature&quot; clause.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For further details, refer to &quot;Literature&quot; clause.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For further details, refer to &quot;Literature&quot; clause.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The life of Ryoma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The life of Ryoma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The life of Ryoma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>12歳、小高坂の楠山塾で学ぶが退塾。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 12, Ryoma started studying at Kusuyama-juku private school in Kodakasaka, but left school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 12, Ryoma started studying at Kusuyama-juku private school in Kodakasaka but he left school later.</e>
<cmt>, but left schoolの,を削除し、but he left school later</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of 12, Ryoma started studying at Kusuyama-juku private school in Kodakasaka but he left school later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>14歳になり高知城下の日根野弁治の道場へ入門し、下士の習う小栗流を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 14, he enrolled in Benji HINENO&apos;s dojo, a martial arts school, in Kochi castle town and learned the swordsmanship of the Oguri-ryu style that the lower-rank samurai learns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 14, he enrolled in Benji HINENO&apos;s dojo, a martial arts school, in Kochi castle town and learned the swordsmanship of the Oguri-ryu style that the lower-rank samurai learns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of 14, he enrolled in Benji HINENO&apos;s dojo, a martial arts school, in Kochi castle town and learned the swordsmanship of the Oguri-ryu style that the lower-rank samurai learns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>1846年、母・幸死す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s mother, Sachi, died in 1846.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s mother, Sachi, died in 1846.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s mother, Sachi, died in 1846.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>1853年（嘉永6年）に剣術修行のため江戸（東京都）に出て、桶町の北辰一刀流剣術開祖千葉周作の弟の千葉定吉道場（通称：小千葉道場）（東京都千代田区）に入門した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1853, Ryoma moved to Edo (Tokyo) to master swordsmanship, and joined the dojo of Sadakichi CHIBA (commonly known as Kochiba dojo) (Tokyo, Chiyoda-ku Ward), whose elder brother is Shusaku CHIBA, the founder of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style at Okecho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1853, Ryoma moved to Edo (Tokyo) to master swordsmanship, and joined the dojo of Sadakichi CHIBA (commonly known as Kochiba dojo in Chiyoda-ku Ward, Tokyo), whose elder brother is Shusaku CHIBA, the founder of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style at Oke-cho.</e>
<cmt>(commonly known as Kochiba dojo) (Tokyo, Chiyoda-ku Ward)→(commonly known as Kochiba dojo in Chiyoda-ku Ward, Tokyo), Okecho→Oke-cho</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1853, Ryoma moved to Edo (Tokyo) to master swordsmanship, and joined the dojo of Sadakichi CHIBA (commonly known as Kochiba dojo in Chiyoda-ku Ward, Tokyo), whose elder brother is Shusaku CHIBA, the founder of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style at Oke-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>12月には佐久間象山の私塾にも通っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1853, Ryoma also went to the Shozan SAKUMA&apos;s private school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1853, Ryoma also went to the Shozan SAKUMA&apos;s private school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, 1853, Ryoma also went to the Shozan SAKUMA&apos;s private school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>1854年（安政元年）に土佐に帰郷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IN 1854, Ryoma returned home to Tosa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1854, Ryoma returned to hometown in Tosa.</e>
<cmt>IN→In, returned home to Tosa→returned to hometown in Tosa</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1854, Ryoma returned to hometown in Tosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>画家の川田小龍から西洋事情を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned from a painter, Shoryo KAWADA the Western affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned the Western affairs from a painter, Shoryo KAWADA.</e>
<cmt>語順変化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned the Western affairs from a painter, Shoryo KAWADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>1855年（安政2年）、父・八平が死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s father, Hachihei, died in 1855.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s father, Hachihei, died in 1855.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s father, Hachihei, died in 1855.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>1856年（安政3年）に再び江戸・定吉道場に遊学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma left home to join again the Sadakichi dojo in Edo in 1856.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma left home to join again the Sadakichi&apos;s dojo in Edo in 1856.</e>
<cmt>Sadakichi dojo→Sadakichi&apos;s dojo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma left home to join again the Sadakichi&apos;s dojo in Edo in 1856.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>1857年（安政4年）、盗みを働き切腹沙汰となった仲間の沢辺琢磨を逃がす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1857, Ryoma let one of his peers Takuma SAWABE go, who was forced to commit seppuku (ritual hara-kiri suicide) for stealing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857, Ryoma let one of his peers Takuma SAWABE go, who was forced to commit seppuku (ritual hara-kiri suicide) for stealing.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857, Ryoma let one of his peers Takuma SAWABE go, who was forced to commit seppuku (ritual hara-kiri suicide) for stealing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>1858年（安政5年）に剣術修行を終えて帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1858, Ryoma returned home finishing his swordsmanship training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1858, Ryoma returned home finishing his swordsmanship training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1858, Ryoma returned home finishing his swordsmanship training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>北辰一刀流免許皆伝と言われる事もあるが、実際には「北辰一刀流長刀兵法・目録」を与えられた物であり、一般にいう剣術では無く、正しくは薙刀術兵法であり、免許でもなければ皆伝でもなく、北辰一刀流としては一番低い「初目録」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma is said to have been conferred the full mastership of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style, but in fact he was conferred a &quot;certificate of the art of war using a long-handled sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu style;&quot; what he mastered is not a commonly-termed swordplay but correctly a long-handled sword tactics; and the certificate was not a licence or a diploma certifying full mastership but the &quot;first certificate&quot;, the lowest-ranked certificate for the Hokushin Itto-ryu style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma is said to have been conferred the full mastership of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style, but in fact he was conferred a &quot;certificate of the art of war using a long-handled sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu style&quot;; what he mastered is not a commonly-termed swordplay but correctly a long-handled sword tactics; and the certificate was not a license or a diploma certifying full mastership but the &quot;first certificate&quot;, the lowest-ranked certificate for the Hokushin Itto-ryu style.</e>
<cmt>Itto-ryu style;”の”を半角&quot;に。また、;を&quot;の外へ。licence→license</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma is said to have been conferred the full mastership of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style, but in fact he was conferred a &quot;certificate of the art of war using a long-handled sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu style&quot;; what he mastered is not a commonly-termed swordplay but correctly a long-handled sword tactics; and the certificate was not a license or a diploma certifying full mastership but the &quot;first certificate,&quot; the lowest-ranked certificate for the Hokushin Itto-ryu style.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を戻した、全角のｓを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ただ千葉道場で塾頭を勤めたことや同世代の人物の証言に「免許皆伝を伝授された」という証言も残るため、免許皆伝状は単に現存していないものと思われる（龍馬の遺品は災害や盗難等で幾つか損失している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But considering the fact that Ryoma once became president of the disciples of the Chiba dojo and that his contemporaries testified to the fact that Ryoma was conferred the full mastership, the certificate of the full mastership actually conferred upon him is thought to be no longer exist (some of the personal mementos left by Ryoma have been lost by disaster or theft).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But considering the fact that Ryoma once became president of the disciples of the Chiba dojo and that his contemporaries testified to the fact that Ryoma was conferred the full mastership, the certificate of the full mastership actually conferred upon him is thought to be no longer exist (some of the personal mementos left by Ryoma have been lost by disaster or theft).</e>
<cmt>thought to→thought to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But considering the fact that Ryoma once became president of the disciples of the Chiba dojo and that his contemporaries testified to the fact that Ryoma was conferred the full mastership, the certificate of the full mastership actually conferred upon him is thought to be no longer exist (some of the personal mementos left by Ryoma have been lost by disaster or theft).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ちなみに、「北辰一刀流長刀兵法・目録」が薙刀の目録であることについては、松岡司「初見の坂本龍馬書状と北辰一刀流長刀兵法目録」（『日本歴史』454号、1986年）、土居晴夫「北辰一刀流とその免許皆伝」（『坂本龍馬事典』新人物往来社、1988年）が詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details on the opinion of the &quot;certificate of the art of war using a long-handled sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu style&quot; being a certificate for long-handled sword, refer to &quot;My First Sight of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;S Letter and Certificate of the Art of War Using a Long-handled Sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu Style&quot; by Tsukasa MATSUOKA (&quot;Japanese History&quot; 454, 1986) and &quot;The Hokushin Itto-ryu Style and its Full Mastership&quot; by Haruo DOI (&quot;Encyclopedia of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 1988).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details on the opinion of the &quot;certificate of the art of war using a long-handled sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu style&quot; being a certificate for long-handled sword, refer to &quot;My First Sight of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s Letter and Certificate of the Art of War Using a Long-handled Sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu Style&quot; by Tsukasa MATSUOKA (&quot;Japanese History&quot; 454, 1986) and &quot;The Hokushin Itto-ryu Style and its Full Mastership&quot; by Haruo DOI (&quot;Encyclopedia of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 1988).</e>
<cmt>SAKAMOTO&apos;S→SAKAMOTO&apos;s, MATSUOKA後の全角スペースを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details on the opinion of the &quot;certificate of the art of war using a long-handled sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu style&quot; being a certificate for long-handled sword, refer to &quot;My First Sight of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s Letter and Certificate of the Art of War Using a Long-handled Sword in the Hokushin Itto-ryu Style&quot; by Tsukasa MATSUOKA (&quot;Japanese History&quot; 454, 1986) and &quot;The Hokushin Itto-ryu Style and its Full Mastership&quot; by Haruo DOI (&quot;Encyclopedia of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 1988).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>1861年（文久元年）、3月、土佐で井口村刃傷事件が起り、龍馬の属する下士と上士の間で対立が深まる『維新土佐勤王史』「坂本等、一時池田の宅に集合し、敢て上士に対抗する気勢を示したり」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 1861, Iguchi-mura village sword wound incident occurred in Tosa, which deepened fonflict between the lower-rank samurai to which Ryoma belonged and the upper-rank samurai (refer to &quot;Ishin Tosa Kinnoshi&quot; (History of Support of the Emperor in Tosa during the Restration), which reads &quot;SAKAMOTO and other lower-rank samurai temporarily gathered at IKEDA&apos;s house and showed their enthusiasm to fight against the upper-rank samurai&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, 1861, Iguchi-mura village sword wound incident occurred in Tosa, which deepened conflict between the lower-rank samurai to which Ryoma belonged and the upper-rank samurai (refer to &quot;Ishin Tosa Kinnoshi&quot; (History of Support of the Emperor in Tosa during the Restoration), which reads &quot;SAKAMOTO and other lower-rank samurai temporarily gathered at IKEDA&apos;s house and showed their enthusiasm to fight against the upper-rank samurai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>fonflict→conflict, Tosa duringの間のスペースを半角へ, Restration→Restoration</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, 1861, Iguchi-mura village sword wound incident occurred in Tosa, which deepened conflict between the lower-rank samurai to which Ryoma belonged and the upper-rank samurai (refer to &quot;Ishin Tosa Kinnoshi&quot; (History of Support of the Emperor in Tosa during the Restoration), which reads &quot;SAKAMOTO and other lower-rank samurai temporarily gathered at IKEDA&apos;s house and showed their enthusiasm to fight against the upper-rank samurai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、事件の当事者で切腹した池田虎之進の介錯を龍馬が行って、その血に刀の下緒を浸しながら下士の団結を誓ったという逸話が流布しているが、これは坂崎紫瀾の小説『汗血千里駒』のフィクションである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote that Ryoma assisted Toranoshin IKEDA, who was blamed for the incident and was forced commit seppuku (ritual hara-kiri suicide), in committing seppuku by beheading him and Ryoma pledged solidarity among the lower-rank samurai wetting his sword knot with Toranoshin&apos;s blood, but this anecdote is a fiction appearing in Shiran SAKAZAKI&apos;s novel &quot;Kanketsu Senri no Koma.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote that Ryoma assisted Toranoshin IKEDA, who was blamed for the incident and was forced commit seppuku (ritual hara-kiri suicide), in committing seppuku by beheading him and Ryoma pledged solidarity among the lower-rank samurai wetting his sword knot with Toranoshin&apos;s blood, but this anecdote is a fiction appearing in Shiran SAKAZAKI&apos;s novel &quot;Kanketsu Senri no Koma.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote that Ryoma assisted Toranoshin IKEDA, who was blamed for the incident and was forced commit seppuku (ritual hara-kiri suicide), in committing seppuku by beheading him and Ryoma pledged solidarity among the lower-rank samurai wetting his sword knot with Toranoshin&apos;s blood, but this anecdote is a fiction appearing in Shiran SAKAZAKI&apos;s novel &quot;Kanketsu Senri no Koma.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>半年後、下士は武市瑞山をリーダーに土佐勤王党を結成し、龍馬は9番目に加盟した（土佐では加盟第1号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six months later, the lower-rank samurai formed Tosa Kinnoto making Zuizan TAKECHI the leader, and Ryoma became the nineth member (the first member in Tosa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six months later, the lower-rank samurai formed Tosa Kinnoto making Zuizan TAKECHI the leader, and Ryoma became the nineth member (the first member in Tosa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six months later, the lower-rank samurai formed Tosa Kinnoto making Zuizan TAKECHI the leader, and Ryoma became the ninth member (the first member in Tosa).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>10月、武市の密使として長州へ向かい、翌年2月、久坂玄瑞と面談。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October Ryoma headed to Choshu as a confidential agent for TAKECHI, and in next February Ryoma met Genzui KUSAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, Ryoma headed to Choshu as a confidential agent for TAKECHI, and in next February Ryoma met Genzui KUSAKA.</e>
<cmt>In Octoberのあとにコンマを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, Ryoma headed to Choshu as a confidential agent for TAKECHI, and in next February Ryoma met Genzui KUSAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>1862年（文久2年）3月に沢村惣之丞とともに脱藩した理由は定かではないが、龍馬が吉田東洋暗殺を企てる武市瑞山の方針に反対だったからではないかとの指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known exactly why Ryoma fled from Tosa clan with Sonojo SAWAMURA in March, 1862, but some point out that it is because Ryoma opposed Zuizan TAKECHI&apos;s policy to attempt to assassinate ToyoYOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known exactly why Ryoma fled from Tosa clan with Sonojo SAWAMURA in March, 1862, but some point out that it is because Ryoma opposed Zuizan TAKECHI&apos;s policy to attempt to assassinate Toyo YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>ToyoYOSHIDAの間に半角スペース</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known exactly why Ryoma fled from Tosa clan with Sonojo SAWAMURA in March, 1862, but some point out that it is because Ryoma opposed Zuizan TAKECHI&apos;s policy to attempt to assassinate Toyo YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>飛鳥井雅道『坂本龍馬』（平凡社、1975年）・石尾芳久『大政奉還と討幕の密勅』（三一書房、1979年）などを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to &quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; by Masamichi ASUKAI (Heibonsha, 1975) and &quot;Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule) and Confidential Imperial Order to Overthrow the Tokugawa Shogunate&quot; by Yoshihisa ISHIO (San-ichi Shobo, 1979).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to &quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; by Masamichi ASUKAI (Heibonsha, 1975) and &quot;Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule) and Confidential Imperial Order to Overthrow the Tokugawa Shogunate&quot; by Yoshihisa ISHIO (San-ichi Shobo, 1979).</e>
<cmt>スペースの訂正。 Shogunate&quot; by→Shogunate&quot; by</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to &quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; by Masamichi ASUKAI (Heibonsha, 1975) and &quot;Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule) and Confidential Imperial Order to Overthrow the Tokugawa Shogunate&quot; by Yoshihisa ISHIO (San-ichi Shobo, 1979).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その直後に勤王党による吉田東洋の暗殺事件が起り、当初は龍馬が実行犯として疑われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately thereafter, the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA by Kinnoto occurred, and at the beginning Ryoma was suspected as the assassin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately thereafter, the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA by Kinnoto occurred, and at the beginning Ryoma was suspected as the assassin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately thereafter, the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA by Kinnoto occurred, and at the beginning Ryoma was suspected as the assassin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>龍馬は九州などを放浪した後、江戸へ入り千葉道場に身を寄せる『維新土佐勤王史』「坂本は飄然として江戸に下り、彼の旧識なる鍛冶橋外桶町の千葉重太郎方に草蛙を解きぬ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having wandered in Kyushu, Ryoma went to Edo and stayed at the Chiba dojo. &quot;Ishin Tosa Kinnoshi (History of Support of the Emperor in Tosa during the Restration)&quot;reads &quot;Ryoma traveled to Edo as free as the wind and took off his shoes at the house of Juutaro CHIBA, an old friend of his, located at Okecho outside Kajibashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having wandered in Kyushu, Ryoma went to Edo and stayed at the Chiba dojo. &quot;Ishin Tosa Kinnoshi (History of Support of the Emperor in Tosa during the Restoration)&quot;reads &quot;Ryoma traveled to Edo as free as the wind and took off his shoes at the house of Juutaro CHIBA, an old friend of his, located at Okecho outside Kajibashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>dojo &quot;Ishinの間のスペースを半角に, Restration→Restoration,)と&quot;readsの間に半角スペース</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having wandered in Kyushu, Ryoma went to Edo and stayed at the Chiba dojo; &quot;Ishin Tosa Kinnoshi (History of Support of the Emperor in Tosa during the Restoration)&quot; reads &quot;Ryoma traveled to Edo as free as the wind, and settled down in the place of Jutaro CHIBA, an old friend of his, located at Okecho outside Kajibashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Restoration)&quot;reads間にスペース挿入、草鞋を解くを訳した</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その後、千葉重太郎の紹介で、幕府政事総裁職の松平春嶽に面会。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Ryoma met Directeor of Political Affairs of the Shogunate, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, through Juutaro CHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Ryoma met Director of Political Affairs of the Shogunate, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, through Jutaro CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>Directeor→Director, Juutaro→Jutaro</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Ryoma met Director of Political Affairs of the Shogunate, Shungaku MATSUDAIRA, through Jutaro CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>春嶽の紹介状を携え、12月、勝海舟に面会して弟子となる一説には勝を暗殺するために面会に行ったとされるが、これには色々と異説があり、正確な史実は確定していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the fact that with a referral from Shungaku, Ryoma met Kaishu KATSU and bacame a disciple of KATSU in December, one theory has it that Ryoma met KATSU to kill him but there are lots of different theories and the correct historical evidence has not yet been confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the fact that with a referral from Shungaku, Ryoma met Kaishu KATSU and became a disciple of KATSU in December, one theory has it that Ryoma met KATSU to kill him but there are lots of different theories and the correct historical evidence has not yet been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>文頭のスペースを削除, bacame→became</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the fact that with a referral from Shungaku, Ryoma met Kaishu KATSU and became a disciple of KATSU in December, one theory has it that Ryoma met KATSU to kill him but there are lots of different theories and the correct historical evidence has not yet been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ただし、勝を殺そうとして、逆に諭されて勝の弟子になった人間がたくさんいるのは事実。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is true that many met KATSU to kill him but were admonished instead to end up becoming disciples of KATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is true that many met KATSU to kill him but were admonished instead to end up becoming disciples of KATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is true that many met KATSU to kill him but were admonished instead to end up becoming disciples of KATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、入門時期や、一緒に勝を訪問した人物についても諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories as to when Ryoma became a dicsiple of KATSU and with whom Ryoma went to meet KATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are other various theories as to when Ryoma became a disciple of KATSU and with whom Ryoma went to meet KATSU.</e>
<cmt>otherを挿入, dicsiple→disciple</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are other various theories as to when Ryoma became a disciple of KATSU and with whom Ryoma went to meet KATSU.</e>
<cmt>全角文字ｃを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>諸説を、春名徹「勝海舟」（『坂本龍馬事典』新人物往来社、1988年）が詳しくまとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These various theories are described in detail in &quot;Kaishu KATSU&quot; by Toru HARUNA (&quot;Encyclopedia of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 1988).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These various theories are described in detail in &quot;Kaishu KATSU&quot; by Toru HARUNA (&quot;Encyclopedia of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 1988).</e>
<cmt>スペースの削除　1988)→1988)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These various theories are described in detail in &quot;Kaishu KATSU&quot; by Toru HARUNA (&quot;Encyclopedia of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 1988).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="44">
<j>1863年（文久3年）、勝が進める神戸海軍操練所の設立に尽力し、操練所よりも先に開設された神戸海軍塾の塾頭をつとめるただし、勝海舟の研究者として著名な歴史家の松浦玲をはじめとして何人かの歴史家は、龍馬が塾頭を務めたという説には懐疑的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863 Ryoma exerted himself into establishing Kobe Navy Training Center that KATSU promoted and Ryoma became president of the trainees of Kobe Navy School opened earlier than the Training Center, but some historians includingRei MATSUURA who is eminent as the researcher of Kaishu KATSU are skeptical about the theory of Ryoma being president of the trainees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863, Ryoma exerted himself into establishing Kobe Navy Training Center that KATSU promoted and Ryoma became president of the trainees of Kobe Navy School opened earlier than the Training Center, but some historians including Rei MATSUURA who is eminent as the researcher of Kaishu KATSU are skeptical about the theory of Ryoma being president of the trainees.</e>
<cmt>In 1863の後にコンマ。includingReiの後にスペースを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863, Ryoma exerted himself into establishing Kobe Navy Training Center that KATSU promoted and Ryoma became president of the trainees of Kobe Navy School opened earlier than the Training Center, but some historians including Rei MATSUURA who is eminent as the researcher of Kaishu KATSU are skeptical about the theory of Ryoma being president of the trainees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="45">
<j>詳しくは松浦玲『検証・龍馬伝説』（論創社、2001年）・濱口裕介「師とともに目指したアジア諸国共有海軍への夢」（『新・歴史群像シリーズ(4) 維新創世 坂本龍馬』学習研究社、2006年）を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, refer to &quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (Ronsosha, 2001), and &quot;Dream for the Navy Jointly Owned by Asian-countries, Shared with Mentor&quot; by Yusuke HAMAGUCHI (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, refer to &quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (Ronsosha, 2001), and &quot;Dream for the Navy Jointly Owned by Asian-countries, Shared with Mentor&quot; by Yusuke HAMAGUCHI (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, refer to &quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (Ronsosha, 2001), and &quot;Dream for the Navy Jointly Owned by Asian-countries, Shared with Mentor&quot; by Yusuke HAMAGUCHI (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>勝・松平春嶽の運動で土佐藩主山内容堂から脱藩の罪を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Efforts made by KATSU and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA encouraged the lord of the Tosa clan, Yodo YAMAUCHI, to condone Ryoma&apos;s charge of fleeing from the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Efforts made by KATSU and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA encouraged the lord of the Tosa clan, Yodo YAMAUCHI, to condone Ryoma&apos;s charge of fleeing from the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Efforts made by KATSU and Shungaku MATSUDAIRA encouraged the lord of the Tosa clan, Yodo YAMAUCHI, to condone Ryoma&apos;s charge of fleeing from the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>この頃、龍馬は勝の護衛に勤王党の人斬り・岡田以蔵をつけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At around that time, Ryoma appointed the murderer in Kinnoto, Izo OKADA, to be a bodyguard for KATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At around that time, Ryoma appointed the murderer in Kinnoto, Izo OKADA, to be a bodyguard for KATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At around that time, Ryoma appointed the murderer in Kinnoto, Izo OKADA, to be a bodyguard for KATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>八月十八日の政変で京から尊攘派が駆逐され、土佐勤王党も藩によって壊滅状態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The political change on August 18 expelled Sonno joi (revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians) royalists from Kyoto, which resulted in destruction in Tosa k assassin.innoto by the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The political change on August 18 expelled Sonno joi (revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians) royalists from Kyoto, which resulted in destruction in Tosa Kinnoto by the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>kinnotoの頭文字を大文字に</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The political change on August 18 expelled Sonno joi (revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians) royalists from Kyoto, which resulted in destruction in Tosa Kinnoto by the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>藩の弾圧は江戸の龍馬にも伸び、龍馬は再脱藩する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tosa clan&apos;s oppression extended to Ryoma in Edo, and therefore Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tosa clan&apos;s oppression extended to Ryoma in Edo, and therefore Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan again.</e>
<cmt>oppression extendedの間のスペースを半角に</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tosa clan&apos;s oppression extended to Ryoma in Edo, and therefore Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="50">
<j>1864年（文久4年改元して元治元年）、神戸海軍操練所が創設されたしかし浪人は入所資格を認められなかったこともあり、龍馬は入所できなかったのではないかと指摘している研究者もいる（松浦玲『検証・龍馬伝説』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864 Kobe Navy Training Center was founded, but some researchers point out that Ryoma might not have been able to enroll in the Center partly because masterless samurai was not entitled to enroll (&quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, Kobe Navy Training Center was founded, but some researchers point out that Ryoma might not have been able to enroll in the Center partly because master less samurai was not entitled to enroll (&quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA).</e>
<cmt>年号の後にコンマ。masterless→master less, MATSUURAの後のスペースを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, Kobe Navy Training Center was founded, but some researchers point out that Ryoma might not have been able to enroll in the Center partly because master less samurai was not entitled to enroll (&quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>龍馬はこの頃、弾圧が激しさを増していた京の尊攘過激派を救うべく蝦夷地への移住計画を開始するが、池田屋事件によって頓挫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At around that time, Ryoma started an emigration plan to Ezochi (Hokkaido) to try to save the Sonno joi (revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians) royalists in Kyoto, where the oppression was escalating, but this plan was derailed after the occurrence of Ikedaya incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At around that time, Ryoma started an emigration plan to Ezochi (Hokkaido) to try to save the Sonno joi (revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians) royalists in Kyoto, where the oppression was escalating, but this plan was derailed after the occurrence of Ikedaya incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At around that time, Ryoma started an emigration plan to Ezochi (Hokkaido) to try to save the Sonno joi (revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians) royalists in Kyoto, where the oppression was escalating, but this plan was derailed after the occurrence of Ikedaya incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>池田屋事件への報復である禁門の変で、長州側に多数の海軍塾生が加わっていたため、海軍塾は幕府から弾圧され、勝も解任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since a number of the Navy School trainees fought on the Choshu side in Kinmon no hen incident as reprisal for Ikedaya incident, the Navy School was cracked down on by the Shogunate and KATSU was removed from his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since a number of the Navy School trainees fought on the Choshu side in Kinmon no hen incident as a reprisal for Ikedaya incident, the Navy School was cracked down on by the Shogunate and KATSU was removed from his position.</e>
<cmt>as reprisal→as a reprisal</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since a number of the Navy School trainees fought on the Choshu side in Kinmon no hen incident as a reprisal for Ikedaya incident, the Navy School was cracked down on by the Shogunate and KATSU was removed from his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>勝の庇護を失った龍馬であるが、勝の紹介で西郷吉之助（西郷隆盛）を頼って大阪の薩摩藩邸に保護されるこれには、薩摩藩側が龍馬らの航海技術に利用価値を感じた点も大きいと指摘されている（松浦玲『検証・龍馬伝説』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ryoma lost support from KATSU, Ryoma asked Kichinosuke SAIGO (Takamori SAIGO) for help on referral from KATSU, and Ryoma was harbored at Satsuma clan&apos;s house in Osaka, on which some point out that Satsuma clan helped Ryoma because they thought that Ryoma would be of vital use to navigation skills (&quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ryoma lost support from KATSU, Ryoma asked Kichinosuke SAIGO (Takamori SAIGO) for help on referral from KATSU, and Ryoma was harbored at Satsuma clan&apos;s house in Osaka, on which some point out that Satsuma clan helped Ryoma because they thought that Ryoma would be of vital use to navigation skills (&quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA).</e>
<cmt>skillsの後のスペースを半角に変換</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ryoma lost support from KATSU, Ryoma asked Kichinosuke SAIGO (Takamori SAIGO) for help on referral from KATSU, and Ryoma was harbored at Satsuma clan&apos;s house in Osaka, on which some point out that Satsuma clan helped Ryoma because they thought that Ryoma would be of vital use to navigation skills (&quot;Verification: The Legend of Ryoma&quot; by Rei MATSUURA).</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="54">
<j>1865年（元治2年改元して慶応元年）、京の薩摩藩邸に移った龍馬の元に中岡慎太郎らが訪問。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1865, Shintaro NAKAOKA and other royalists visited Ryoma who moved to Satsuma clan&apos;s house in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1865, Shintaro NAKAOKA and other royalists visited Ryoma who moved to Satsuma clan&apos;s house in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1865, Shintaro NAKAOKA and other royalists visited Ryoma who moved to Satsuma clan&apos;s house in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この頃から中岡と共に薩長同盟への運動を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At around that time Ryoma together with NAKAOKA started working on the achievement for Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At around that time Ryoma together with NAKAOKA started working on the achievement for Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At around that time Ryoma together with NAKAOKA started working on the achievement for Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>薩摩藩の援助により、土佐脱藩の仲間と共に長崎で社中（亀山社中・のちに海援隊_(浪士結社)）を組織し、物産・武器の貿易を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the assistance of Satsuma clan, Ryoma together with his peers who aslo fled from Tosa clan established shachu (Kameyama-shachu, later Kaientai (ronin&apos;s association)) in Nagasaki and carried on trade of goods and arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the assistance of Satsuma clan, Ryoma together with his peers who also fled from Tosa clan established shachu (Kameyama-shachu, later Kaientai (ronin&apos;s association)) in Nagasaki and carried on trade of goods and arms.</e>
<cmt>aslo→also</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the assistance of Satsuma clan, Ryoma together with his peers who also fled from Tosa clan established shachu (Kameyama-shachu, later Kaientai (ronin&apos;s association)) in Nagasaki and carried on trade of goods and arms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この年、「非義勅命は勅命にあらず」という文言で有名な大久保利通の書簡を、長州藩重役に届けるという重大な任務を龍馬が大久保や西郷隆盛に任されている。佐々木克『幕末政治と薩摩藩』（吉川弘文館、2004年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year, Ryoma achieved a crucial mission entrusted by Toshimichi OKUBO and Takamori SAIGO to deliver a OKUBO&apos;s letter, which is famous for its phrase, &quot;Unjustifiable Imperial order is not Imperial order,&quot; to the Choshu clan&apos;s high-ranking official. &quot;Politics in the End of Edo Era and Satsuma Clan&quot; by Suguru SASAKI (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 2004)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this year, Ryoma achieved a crucial mission entrusted by Toshimichi OKUBO and Takamori SAIGO to deliver an OKUBO&apos;s letter, which is famous for its phrase, &quot;Unjustifiable Imperial order is not Imperial order,&quot; to the Choshu clan&apos;s high-ranking official. &quot;Politics in the End of Edo Era and Satsuma Clan&quot; by Suguru SASAKI (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 2004).</e>
<cmt>a OKUBO&apos;s→an OKUBO&apos;s, &quot;Politicsの前のスペースを半角に変換, 2004)のあとにピリオド</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this year, Ryoma achieved a crucial mission entrusted by Toshimichi OKUBO and Takamori SAIGO to deliver an OKUBO&apos;s letter, which is famous for its phrase, &quot;Unjustifiable Imperial order is not Imperial order,&quot; to the Choshu clan&apos;s high-ranking official. &quot;Politics in the End of Edo Era and Satsuma Clan&quot; by Suguru SASAKI (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 2004).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="58">
<j>1866年（慶応2年）、1月、坂本龍馬の斡旋により、京都で長門国の木戸孝允（木戸孝允）と薩摩の西郷隆盛が会見し、薩長同盟（薩長盟約）が結ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, 1866, the meeting between Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO) from Nagatonokuni and Takamori SAIGO from Satsuma was held in Kyoto by Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s mediation to achieve Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt>一つ目の木戸孝允は、桂小五郎の間違いかもしれないと考えたので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, 1866, the meeting between Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO) from Nagatonokuni and Takamori SAIGO from Satsuma was held in Kyoto by Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s mediation to achieve Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, 1866, the meeting between Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO) from Nagatonokuni and Takamori SAIGO from Satsuma was held in Kyoto by Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s mediation to achieve Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>このとき龍馬は桂に求められて盟約書の裏書を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Ryoma endorsed the Alliance upon request by KATSURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Ryoma endorsed the Alliance upon request by KATSURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Ryoma endorsed the Alliance upon request by KATSURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>天下の大藩同士の同盟に一介の素浪人が保証を与えたものであって、彼がいかに信を得ていたかがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means a single ronin provided guarantee to the Allaiance forged between the giant clans, from which we can see how Ryoma gained trust.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means a single ronin provided guarantee to the Allaiance forged between the giant clans, from which we can see how Ryoma gained trust.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means a single ronin provided guarantee to the Alliance forged between the giant clans, from which we can see how Ryoma gained trust.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>なお薩長同盟については龍馬最大の功績と言われるが、実際には、西郷や小松清廉ら薩摩藩の指示を受けて動いていたという説もあり（青山忠正など）、薩長連合に果たした役割の重要性については評価が分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Satuma-Choshu Alliance is considered as the Ryoma&apos;s major achievement, there is also a theory that Ryoma was in fact instructed by Satsuma clan including SAIGO and Kiyotada KOMATSU to work on the achievement for the Alliance (Tadamasa AOYAMA), and therefore there are devided evaluations over what kind of role Ryoma played for Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Satuma-Choshu Alliance is considered as the Ryoma&apos;s major achievement, there is also a theory that Ryoma was in fact instructed by Satsuma clan including SAIGO and Kiyotada KOMATSU to work on the achievement for the Alliance (Tadamasa AOYAMA), and therefore there are devided evaluations over what kind of role Ryoma played for Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Satuma-Choshu Alliance is considered as the Ryoma&apos;s major achievement, there is also a theory that Ryoma was in fact instructed by Satsuma clan including SAIGO and Kiyotada KOMATSU to work on the achievement for the Alliance (Tadamasa AOYAMA), and therefore there are divided evaluations over what kind of role Ryoma played for Satsuma-Choshu Alliance.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>その後、青山忠正を皮切りに、芳即正・三宅紹宣・宮地正人・高橋秀直・佐々木克などの研究者を中心に薩長同盟についての議論が盛んである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting with the Tadamasa AOYAMA&apos;s theory, Satsuma-Choshu Alliance has been a hotly-debated issue among scholars including Norimasa KANBASHI, Tsugunobu MIYAKE, Masato MIYACHI, Hidenao TAKAHASHI, and Suguru SASAKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting with the Tadamasa AOYAMA&apos;s theory, Satsuma-Choshu Alliance has been a hotly-debated issue among scholars including Norimasa KANBASHI, Tsugunobu MIYAKE, Masato MIYACHI, Hidenao TAKAHASHI and Suguru SASAKI.</e>
<cmt>TAKAHASHIの後のコンマを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting with the Tadamasa AOYAMA&apos;s theory, Satsuma-Choshu Alliance has been a hotly-debated issue among scholars including Norimasa KANBASHI, Tsugunobu MIYAKE, Masato MIYACHI, Hidenao TAKAHASHI and Suguru SASAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>薩長同盟研究の動向については、桐野作人「同盟の実相と龍馬の果たした役割とは？」（『新・歴史群像シリーズ(4) 維新創世 坂本龍馬』学習研究社、2006年）が詳しくまとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the trend of study on Satsuma-Choshu Alliance, refer to &quot;Reality of the Alliance and The Role Ryoma Played therein&quot; by Sakujin KIRINO (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the trend of study on Satsuma-Choshu Alliance, refer to &quot;Reality of the Alliance and The Role Ryoma Played therein&quot; by Sakujin KIRINO (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the trend of study on Satsuma-Choshu Alliance, refer to &quot;Reality of the Alliance and The Role Ryoma Played therein&quot; by Sakujin KIRINO (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>直後の2月、寺田屋で幕吏に襲撃されたが一命を取り留める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately thereafter in February, Ryoma was attacked by shogunate officials at Teradaya inn, but escaped death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately thereafter in February, Ryoma was attacked by shogunate officials at Teradaya inn, but escaped death.</e>
<cmt>byの前のスペースを半角スペースに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately thereafter in February, Ryoma was attacked by shogunate officials at Teradaya inn, but escaped death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>その傷を癒すため、妻おりょうと共に鹿児島を旅行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma set out on a journey to Kagoshima together with his wife, Oryo, to heal the wounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma set out on a journey to Kagoshima together with his wife, Oryo, to heal the wounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma set out on a journey to Kagoshima together with his wife, Oryo, to heal the wounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>6月、第二次長州征伐では亀山社中の船・乙丑丸で長州藩海軍を支援。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Ryoma assisted Choshu clan&apos;s navy using Kameyama-shachu&apos;s ship, the Union, in the Second Choshu Punitive Expedition.</e>
<cmt>乙丑丸については、ここでは亀山社中の船とありましたので、ユニオン号として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, Ryoma assisted Choshu clan&apos;s navy using Kameyama-shachu&apos;s ship, the Union, in the Second Choshu Punitive Expedition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, Ryoma assisted Choshu clan&apos;s navy using Kameyama-shachu&apos;s ship, the Union, in the Second Choshu Punitive Expedition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="67">
<j>1867年（慶応3年）、土佐藩との関係を修復して海援隊を創設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1867, Ryoma mended his relationship with Tosa clan and founded Kaientai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1867, Ryoma mended his relationship with Tosa clan and founded Kaientai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1867, Ryoma mended his relationship with Tosa clan and founded Kaientai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>4月、いろは丸展示館いろは丸沈没事件がおこり徳川御三家紀州藩に損害を賠償させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, the Iroha was sunken and Ryoma obtained damages from Kishu clan, one of three top Tokugawa-related families.</e>
<cmt>いろは丸展示館が文脈から考えてどのように訳すべきか不明でしたので訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, the Iroha was sunk and Ryoma obtained damages from Kishu clan, one of the three top Tokugawa-related families.</e>
<cmt>sunken→sunk, one of three top→one of the three top</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, the Iroha was sunk and Ryoma obtained damages from Kishu clan, one of the three top Tokugawa-related families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>後藤象二郎とともに船中八策を策定し、後藤象二郎が山内容堂を説いて土佐藩の進言による大政奉還を実現させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma laid down together with Shojiro GOTO Eight Rules Laid down on a Ship, Shojiro GOTO persuaded Yodo YAMAUCHI, and they realized Taisei-hokan (the Restorationof the Imperial Rule), which was a proposal from Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma laid down together with Shojiro GOTO Eight Rules Laid down on a Ship, Shojiro GOTO persuaded Yodo YAMAUCHI, and they realized Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial Rule), which was a proposal from Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>(the Restorationof→(the Restoration of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma laid down together with Shojiro GOTO Eight Rules Laid down on a Ship, Shojiro GOTO persuaded Yodo YAMAUCHI, and they realized Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial Rule), which was a proposal from Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>ただし、「船中八策」には原文書も写本も存在しないため、本当に龍馬が作成したのか疑問視している研究者も存在する（青山忠正、松浦玲など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But some researchers including Tadamasa AOYAMA and Rei MATSUMOTO raise questions about credibility of the fact that Ryoma actually made the Eight Rules since there exist no original text and copy thereof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But some researchers including Tadamasa AOYAMA and Rei MATSUMOTO raise questions about credibility of the fact that Ryoma actually made the Eight Rules since there exist no original text and copy thereof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But some researchers including Tadamasa AOYAMA and Rei MATSUMOTO raise questions about credibility of the fact that Ryoma actually made the Eight Rules since there exist no original text and copy thereof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>龍馬が「船中八策」を作成したことは通説になっているが、史料的根拠は見当たらないのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is now accepted that Ryoma made the Eight Rules, but there are no grounds according to historical data available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is now accepted that Ryoma made the Eight Rules, but there are no grounds according to historical data available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now accepted that Ryoma made the Eight Rules, but there are no grounds according to historical data available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>詳しくは、青山忠正『明治維新の言語と史料』（清文堂出版、2006年）・松浦玲「『万機公論ニ決スヘシ』は維新後に実現されたか?」（『新・歴史群像シリーズ(4) 維新創世 坂本龍馬』学習研究社、2006年）を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the details, refer to &quot;Language and Historical Data of Meiji Restoration&quot; by Tadamasa AOYAMA (Seibundo shuppan, 2006) and &quot;Was Democracy Realized after the Restoration?&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the details, refer to &quot;Language and Historical Data of Meiji Restoration&quot; by Tadamasa AOYAMA (Seibundo shuppan, 2006) and &quot;Was Democracy Realized after the Restoration?&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the details, refer to &quot;Language and Historical Data of Meiji Restoration&quot; by Tadamasa AOYAMA (Seibundo shuppan, 2006) and &quot;Was Democracy Realized after the Restoration?&quot; by Rei MATSUURA (&quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; GAKKEN, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>12月、京都の旅寓・近江屋（京都市中京区）で何者かに中岡慎太郎と共に暗殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, Ryoma and Shintaro NAKAOKA were assassinated at Ohmiya inn in Kyoto (Kyoto City, Nakagyo-ku Ward).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Ryoma and Shintaro NAKAOKA were assassinated at Omiya inn in Kyoto (Kyoto City, Nakagyo-ku Ward).</e>
<cmt>Ohmiya→Omiya</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Ryoma and Shintaro NAKAOKA were assassinated at Omiya inn in Kyoto (Kyoto City, Nakagyo-ku Ward).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>旧暦の誕生日と命日は同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the lunar calendar, his birthday and the anniversary of his death are the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the lunar calendar, his birthday and the anniversary of his death are the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the lunar calendar, his birthday and the anniversary of his death are the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>暗殺犯は京都見廻組という説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory that the assassin belonged to Kyoto Mimawarigumi is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory that the assassin belonged to Kyoto Mimawarigumi is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory that the assassin belonged to Kyoto Mimawarigumi is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="76">
<j>1871年（明治4年）、8月20日に龍馬の系統が途絶えるのを防ごうと、綸旨により姉千鶴の長男高松太郎が「坂本直」として龍馬の名跡を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 20, 1871, in accordance with imperial rescript, the first son of Ryoma&apos;s elder sister Chizuru, Taro TAKAMATSU, changed his name to Nao SAKAMOTO to inherit Ryoma&apos;s family name, trying to avoid the end of the Ryoma&apos;s ancestry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 20, 1871, in accordance with imperial prescript, the first son of Ryoma&apos;s elder sister Chizuru, Taro TAKAMATSU, changed his name to Nao SAKAMOTO to inherit Ryoma&apos;s family name, trying to avoid the end of the Ryoma&apos;s ancestry.</e>
<cmt>rescript→prescript</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 20, 1871, in accordance with imperial prescript, the first son of Ryoma&apos;s elder sister Chizuru, Taro TAKAMATSU, changed his name to Nao SAKAMOTO to inherit Ryoma&apos;s family name, trying to avoid the end of the Ryoma&apos;s ancestry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="77">
<j>墓所は京都市東山区の京都霊山護國神社参道中腹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s tomb is in the middle of approach of Kyoto Ryozen Gokoku Shrine in Kyoto City, Higashiyama-ku Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s tomb is in the middle of approach of Kyoto Ryozen Gokoku Shrine in Kyoto City, Higashiyama-ku Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s tomb is in the middle of approach of Kyoto Ryozen Gokoku Shrine in Kyoto City, Higashiyama-ku Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>なお、靖国神社に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma is enshrined in Yasukuni Jinja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma is enshrined in Yasukuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Yasukuni Jinja→Yasukuni-jinja Shrine</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma is enshrined in Yasukuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="79">
<j>暗殺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>(写真)坂本龍馬像（高知県の桂浜）:第二次大戦中の金属供出の際もこの銅像だけは供出を免れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Picture) Statue of Ryoma SAKAMOTO (Katsurahama beach in Kochi prefecture): even at metal contribution during the World War II, this bronze statue was exempted from the contribution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Picture) Statue of Ryoma SAKAMOTO (Katsurahama beach in Kochi prefecture): even at metal contribution during the World War II, this bronze statue was exempted from the contribution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Picture) Statue of Ryoma SAKAMOTO (Katsurahama beach in Kochi prefecture): even at metal contribution during the World War II, this bronze statue was exempted from the contribution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="81">
<j>龍馬は慶応3年11月15日（1867年12月10日）の暗殺当日には風邪を引いて河原町の蛸薬師で醤油商を営む近江屋新助宅母屋の二階にいたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the assassination day, December 10, 1867, Ryoma was said to be on the second floor of the main building of the house of Shinsuke Ohmiya who carried on trade of soy sauce at Takoyakushi in Kawaramachi, since Ryoma had a cold on that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the assassination day, December 10, 1867, Ryoma was said to be on the second floor of the main building of the house of Shinsuke OMIYA who carried on trade of soy sauce at Takoyakushi in Kawaramachi, since Ryoma had a cold on that day.</e>
<cmt>Ohmiya→OMIYA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the assassination day, December 10, 1867, Ryoma was said to be on the second floor of the main building of the house of Shinsuke OMIYA who carried on trade of soy sauce at Takoyakushi in Kawaramachi, since Ryoma had a cold on that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>当日は陸援隊の中岡慎太郎や土佐藩士の岡本健三郎、画家の淡海槐堂などに訪問されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that day Kaientai&apos;s Shintaro NAKAOKA, Tosa clan&apos;s Kenzaburo OKAMOTO, painter Kaido OHMI, and others visited Ryoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that day Kaientai&apos;s Shintaro NAKAOKA, Tosa clan&apos;s Kenzaburo OKAMOTO, painter Kaido OMI, and others visited Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>OHMI→OMI</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that day Kaientai&apos;s Shintaro NAKAOKA, Tosa clan&apos;s Kenzaburo OKAMOTO, painter Kaido OMI, and others visited Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>中岡はそのまま龍馬と話していたところ、十津川郷士と名乗る男達数人に切られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAKAOKA stayed there and kept talking with Ryoma, and then several men identifying themselves as Totsukawa goshi slashed NAKAOKA and Ryoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAKAOKA stayed there and kept talking with Ryoma, and then several men identifying themselves as Totsukawa goshi slashed NAKAOKA and Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAKAOKA stayed there and kept talking with Ryoma, and then several men identifying themselves as Totsukawa goshi slashed NAKAOKA and Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>龍馬達は近江屋の人間が入ってきたものと油断しており、帯刀していなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma and NAKAOKA were off guard thinking that somebody from Ohmiya entered, and therefore Ryoma and NAKAOKA took no sword with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma and NAKAOKA were off guard thinking that somebody from Omiya entered, and therefore Ryoma and NAKAOKA took no sword with them.</e>
<cmt>Ohmiya→Omiya</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma and NAKAOKA were off guard thinking that somebody from Omiya entered, and therefore Ryoma and NAKAOKA took no sword with them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>龍馬はまず額を深く斬られ、奮戦するもののそれが原因ですぐに死亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s forehead was first severely slashed, and in spite of his brave fighting he died immediately because of this slash.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s forehead was first severely slashed, and in spite of his brave fighting he died immediately because of this slash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s forehead was first severely slashed, and in spite of his brave fighting he died immediately because of this slash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>中岡も重傷を負うが数日間は意識があり事件の証言を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAKAOKA was also severely injured, but remained conscious for a few days and left testimony of the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAKAOKA was also severely injured, but remained conscious for a few days and left testimony of the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAKAOKA was also severely injured, but remained conscious for a few days and left testimony of the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>慎太郎もまもなく死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaro also died soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintaro also died soon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintaro also died soon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>京都見廻組実行説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory of implementation by Kyoto Mimawarigumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theory of implementation by Kyoto Mimawarigumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory of implementation by Kyoto Mimawarigumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>大正時代になって元京都見廻組隊士だった今井信郎、渡辺篤 (剣客)の口述で、佐々木只三郎らが実行犯であると証言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taisho era, Nobuo IMAI and Atsushi WATANABE (swordman), who were members of Kyoto Mimawarigumi, orally testified that Tadasaburo SASAKI and others killed Ryoma and NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taisho era, Nobuo IMAI and Atsushi WATANABE (swordsman), who were members of Kyoto Mimawarigumi, orally testified that Tadasaburo SASAKI and others killed Ryoma and NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt>(swordman)→(swordsman)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taisho era, Nobuo IMAI and Atsushi WATANABE (swordsman), who were members of Kyoto Mimawarigumi, orally testified that Tadasaburo SASAKI and others killed Ryoma and NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>また、勝海舟は幕府上層部の指示であるとも推測している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU speculated that the assassination was instructed by the high-ranking officials of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaishu KATSU speculated that the assassination was instructed by the high-ranking officials of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU speculated that the assassination was instructed by the high-ranking officials of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>この見廻組実行説がいわば通説となっており、これに疑問を呈する歴史学者は皆無に等しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory that the assassination was carried out by Mimawarigumi is now widely accepted, and almost no historian raises questions about this theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory that the assassination was carried out by Mimawarigumi is now widely accepted, and almost no historian raises questions about this theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory that the assassination was carried out by Mimawarigumi is now widely accepted, and almost no historian raises questions about this theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>ただし、今井や渡辺の口述に食い違う部分があるため、主に作家を中心に色々な異説が唱えられている状況である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since there are some discrepancies in oral testimonies between IMAI and WATANABE, authors mainly propose various theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since there are some discrepancies in oral testimonies between IMAI and WATANABE, authors mainly propose various theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since there are some discrepancies in oral testimonies between IMAI and WATANABE, authors mainly propose various theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>2006年に学習研究社から発売された『新・歴史群像シリーズ(4) 維新創世 坂本龍馬』では、菊地明が「寺田屋事件の際に捕縛方一人を殺害したことで「お尋ね者」になっており、見廻組が逮捕のためにやってきた」という説を出しているが、この説に関しても今後精査が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot;sold by GAKKEN in 2006, Akira KIKUCHI put forward a theory that since Ryoma was wanted for killing one capturing official in the Teradaya incident, Mimawarigumi came to Ryoma for arrest, but this theory also needs to be closely examined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; sold by GAKKEN in 2006, Akira KIKUCHI put forward a theory that since Ryoma was wanted for killing one capturing official in the Teradaya incident, Mimawarigumi came to Ryoma for arrest, but this theory also needs to be closely examined.</e>
<cmt>Inの後の全角スペースを半角スペースに変換, SAKAMOTO&quot;の後に半角スペースを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;New Historical Figures Series (4) Creation of the Restoration Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; sold by GAKKEN in 2006, Akira KIKUCHI put forward a theory that since Ryoma was wanted for killing one capturing official in the Teradaya incident, Mimawarigumi came to Ryoma for arrest, but this theory also needs to be closely examined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>新選組犯行説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory of Shinsengumi&apos;s responsibility</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theory of Shinsengumi&apos;s responsibility</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory of Shinsengumi&apos;s responsibility</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>龍馬暗殺当時の現場に残された鞘などの物証や、３日後に暗殺された伊東甲子太郎の御陵衛士らの証言から新選組の原田左之助によるものと信じられていたが、刀傷は左利きによるものであると言う説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the material evidence such as the scabbard left on the scene at the time of Ryoma&apos;s assassination, and the testimony by Goryo eji including Kashitaro ITOH assassinated three days later than Ryoma&apos;s assassination, Shinsengumi&apos;s Sanosuke HARADA was believed to be the Ryoma&apos;s assassin, but there is a theory that the sword wounds were by left-handed person.</e>
<cmt>伊東甲子太郎と御陵衛士の関係がよくわからなかったので、伊東～を含む御陵衛士と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the material evidence such as the scabbard left on the scene at the time of Ryoma&apos;s assassination, and the testimony by Goryo eji including Kashitaro ITO assassinated three days later than Ryoma&apos;s assassination, Shinsengumi&apos;s Sanosuke HARADA was believed to be the Ryoma&apos;s assassin, but there is a theory that the sword wounds were by left-handed person.</e>
<cmt>ITOH→ITO, HARADAの後を半角スペースに変換</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the material evidence such as the scabbard left on the scene at the time of Ryoma&apos;s assassination, and the testimony by Goryo eji including Kashitaro ITO assassinated three days later than Ryoma&apos;s assassination, Shinsengumi&apos;s Sanosuke HARADA was believed to be the Ryoma&apos;s assassin, but there is a theory that the sword wounds were by left-handed person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>これを採用するなら左利きで、北辰一刀流の達人である龍馬を殺害できるだけの実力のある人物となると、斎藤一という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this theory is to be employed, there is one theory popping up that Hajime SAITO was the assassin considering a person who also mastered swordsmanship well enough to kill Ryoma, a master of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this theory is to be adopted, there is one theory popping up that Hajime SAITO was the assassin considering a person who also mastered swordsmanship well enough to kill Ryoma, a master of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style.</e>
<cmt>employed→adopted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this theory is to be adopted, there is one theory popping up that Hajime SAITO was the assassin considering a person who also mastered swordsmanship well enough to kill Ryoma, a master of the Hokushin Itto-ryu style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>しかし現在では、新選組犯行説を支持する研究者はほとんどいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But currently there are almost no researchers who support the theory of Shinsengumi&apos;s responsibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But currently there are almost no researchers who support the theory of Shinsengumi&apos;s responsibility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But currently there are almost no researchers who support the theory of Shinsengumi&apos;s responsibility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="96">
<j>（斉藤一の新撰組復帰時期は諸説あるが、浅田次郎の壬生義士伝の中では、御陵衛士（高台寺党）としての斉藤説を唱えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Mibu gishidenJiro ASADA put forward a theory of Hajime SAITO&apos;s responsibility as a member of Goryo eji (Kodaiji temple sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In Mibu gishiden, Jiro ASADA put forward a theory of Hajime SAITO&apos;s responsibility as a member of Goryo eji (Kodaiji temple sect).</e>
<cmt>文頭にInとコンマを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In Mibu gishiden, Jiro ASADA put forward a theory of Hajime SAITO&apos;s responsibility as a member of Goryo eji (Kodaiji temple sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>しかしながら、斎藤の左利き説自体が史実である可能性は低い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the possibility that the theory of SAITO being left-handed itself is the historical fact is low.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the possibility that the theory of SAITO being left-handed itself is the historical fact is low.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the possibility that the theory of SAITO being left-handed itself is the historical fact is low.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>薩摩藩陰謀説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satsuma clan&apos;s conspiracy theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satsuma clan&apos;s conspiracy theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satsuma clan&apos;s conspiracy theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>大政奉還以降、龍馬は幕府に対する態度を軟化させ、徳川慶喜を含めた諸侯会議による新政府の設立に傾いていたともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma is said to have softened his attitude toward the Shogunate after Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule) and have started thinking of establishing a new government constituting congress by the lords of clans including Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma is said to have softened his attitude toward the Shogunate after Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule) and have started thinking of establishing a new government constituting congress by the lords of clans including Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma is said to have softened his attitude toward the Shogunate after Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial rule) and have started thinking of establishing a new government constituting congress by the lords of clans including Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>武力倒幕を目指していた西郷隆盛、大久保利通らが、こうした龍馬の動きを看過できなくなり、故意に幕府側に龍馬の所在を漏らしたとする説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Takamori SAIGO, Toshimichi OKUBO, and other activists, who aimed for the violent overthrow of the Shogunate, intentionally leaked Ryoma&apos;s whereabouts to the Shogunate side because they became cautious about such Ryoma&apos;s changed attitudes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Takamori SAIGO, Toshimichi OKUBO and other activists, who aimed for the violent overthrow of the Shogunate, intentionally leaked Ryoma&apos;s whereabouts to the Shogunate side because they became cautious about such Ryoma&apos;s changed attitudes.</e>
<cmt>OKUBOの後のコンマを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Takamori SAIGO, Toshimichi OKUBO and other activists, who aimed for the violent overthrow of the Shogunate, intentionally leaked Ryoma&apos;s whereabouts to the Shogunate side because they became cautious about such Ryoma&apos;s changed attitudes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>維新クーデターによる大政奉還派の暗殺説は、佐々木多門の書状や近江屋の女中たちの証言などの資料をもとにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of assassination by supporters for Taisei-hokan (the Restration of the Imperial Rule) through the restoration coup d&apos;etat is based on Tamon SASAKI&apos;s letter and testimony by housemaids of Ohmiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of assassination by supporters for Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial Rule) through the restoration coup d&apos;etat is based on Tamon SASAKI&apos;s letter and testimony by housemaids of Omiya.</e>
<cmt>Restration→Restoration, testimonyの後のスペースを半角に変換, Ohmiya→Omiya</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of assassination by supporters for Taisei-hokan (the Restoration of the Imperial Rule) through the restoration coup d&apos;etat is based on Tamon SASAKI&apos;s letter and testimony by housemaids of Omiya.</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>また、この説は大政奉還路線と武力倒幕路線の対立を必要以上に強調しすぎたきらいがあり、両者は相容れない路線ではなかったとする学説　家近良樹『幕末政治と倒幕運動』（吉川弘文館、1995年）・高橋秀直「「公議政体派」と薩摩倒幕派-王政復古クーデター再考-」（『京都大学文学部研究紀要』41、2002年）・佐々木克『幕末政治と薩摩藩』（吉川弘文館、2004年）・井上勲「大政奉還運動の形成過程(一)」（『史学雑誌』81-11、1972年）などが参考になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some argues that this theory emphasizes a little bit too much the fonflict between Taisei-hokan policy and violent overthrow of the Shogunate policy, which is also another theory and points out that the both policies are not so much contradicting: &quot;Politics in the end of Edo era and Movement of overthrow of the Shogunate&quot; by Yoshiki IECHIKA (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 1995), &quot;Supporters for Politics by Congress and Supporters for Overthrow of the Shogunate by Satsuma- Review on Imperial Rule Restoration Coup D&apos;etat -&quot; by Hidenao TAKAHASHI (&quot;Kyoto University, Faculty of Letters, Research Report&quot; 41, 2002), &quot;Politics in the End of Edo Era and Satsuma Clan&quot; by Suguru SASAKI (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 2004), and &quot;Formation Process of Taisei-hokan Movement (-)&quot; by Isao INOUE (&quot;Shigaku zasshi&quot; 81-11,1972).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And also there are some argues that this theory emphasizes too much the conflict between Taisei-hokan policy and violent overthrow of the Shogunate policy, which is also another theory and points out that the both policies are not so much contradicting: &quot;Politics in the end of Edo era and Movement of overthrow of the Shogunate&quot; by Yoshiki IECHIKA (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 1995), &quot;Supporters for Politics by Congress and Supporters for Overthrow of the Shogunate by Satsuma - Review on Imperial Rule Restoration Coup d&apos;etat -&quot; by Hidenao TAKAHASHI (&quot;Kyoto University, Faculty of Letters, Research Report&quot; 41, 2002), &quot;Politics in the End of Edo Era and Satsuma Clan&quot; by Suguru SASAKI (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 2004), and &quot;Formation Process of Taisei-hokan Movement (1)&quot; by Isao INOUE (&quot;Shigaku zasshi&quot; 81-11, 1972).</e>
<cmt>文頭を変化, fonflict→conflict, 1995)の後のスペースを半角に変換, a little bitを削除, Satsumaと-の間に半角スペース, Coup D&apos;etat→Coup d&apos;etat, Movement (-)→Movement(1), 1972の前に半角スペースを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And also there are some argues that this theory emphasizes too much the conflict between Taisei-hokan policy and violent overthrow of the Shogunate policy, which is also another theory and points out that the both policies are not so much contradicting: &quot;Politics in the end of Edo era and Movement of overthrow of the Shogunate&quot; by Yoshiki IECHIKA (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 1995), &quot;Supporters for Politics by Congress and Supporters for Overthrow of the Shogunate by Satsuma - Review on Imperial Rule Restoration Coup d&apos;etat -&quot; by Hidenao TAKAHASHI (&quot;Kyoto University, Faculty of Letters, Research Report&quot; 41, 2002), &quot;Politics in the End of Edo Era and Satsuma Clan&quot; by Suguru SASAKI (Yoshikawa kobunkan, 2004), and &quot;Formation Process of Taisei-hokan Movement (1)&quot; by Isao INOUE (&quot;Shigaku zasshi&quot; 81-11, 1972).</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>を全く考慮に入れていないところが最大の問題で、その点で根拠が弱い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major problem is that (something) is not taken into consideration at all, and in this respect the grounds are weak.</e>
<cmt>「を全く考慮に入れていない」から始まっていて、それ以前の部分が不明であるため、それ以前をsomething として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major problem is that (something) is not taken into consideration at all, and in this respect the grounds are weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major problem is that (something) is not taken into consideration at all, and in this respect the grounds are weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>この説には一部で熱狂的な支持者がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some enthusiastic supporters for this theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some enthusiastic supporters for this theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some enthusiastic supporters for this theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>幕藩側に立って書かれた大河ドラマ『新選組!』やテレビ東京新春ワイド時代劇『竜馬がゆく (2004年 テレビドラマ)』ではこの説に則って龍馬の暗殺を描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the NHK&apos;s period drama&quot;Shinsen-gumi!&quot; described from the Shogunate viewpoint and the Television Tokyo&apos;s new year wide period drama &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku (2004, TV drama),&quot; Ryoma&apos;s assassination is depicted based on this theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the NHK&apos;s period drama &quot;Shinsen-gumi!&quot; described from the Shogunate viewpoint and in the Television Tokyo&apos;s new year wide period drama &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku (2004, TV drama),&quot; Ryoma&apos;s assassination is depicted based on this theory.</e>
<cmt>drama&quot;Shinsen-gumi!→drama の後に半角スペース, the Television Tokyo&apos;sの前にinを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the NHK&apos;s period drama &quot;Shinsen-gumi!&quot; described from the Shogunate viewpoint and in the Television Tokyo&apos;s new year wide period drama &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku (2004, TV drama),&quot; Ryoma&apos;s assassination is depicted based on this theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>時空警察PART4でもこの説に基づいて龍馬暗殺犯を解説するなど、テレビ・小説などではこの説を採用することが多く、一般ではこの説を信じている人が多い傾向が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Ryoma&apos;s assassin was commented on based on this theory in Jikuukeisatsu PART 4, many of the TV programmes and novels employ this theory, and therefore generally people tend to believe this theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Ryoma&apos;s assassin was commented on based on this theory in Jikukeisatsu PART 4, many of the TV programs and novels adopt this theory, and therefore generally people tend to believe this theory.</e>
<cmt>Jikuukeisatsu→Jikukeisatsu, programmes→programs, employ→adopt</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Ryoma&apos;s assassin was commented on based on this theory in Jikukeisatsu PART 4, many of the TV programs and novels adopt this theory, and therefore generally people tend to believe this theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>ものの、歴史学界ではほとんど相手にされていないのが実情。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The circle of history study rarely believes this theory though.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The circle of history study rarely believes this theory though.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circle of history study rarely believes this theory though.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>薩摩藩陰謀説が成り立たないことを政治史的な観点から論証したものに、桐野作人「龍馬遭難事件の新視角-海援隊士・佐々木多門書状の再検討- 第1回・第2回・最終回」（『歴史読本』第51巻第10号・第51巻第11号・第51巻第12号、2006年）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a book arguing from the viewpoint of political history that the Satsuma clan&apos;s conspiracy theory does not hold true, refer to &quot;New Angle toward Ryoma&apos;s Distress Incident -Review on Letters by a Kaientai Member, Tamon SASAKI- the First, the Second, and the Last&quot; by Sakujin KIRINO (&quot;Rekishi dokuhon&quot; Vol. 51, No. 10, Vol. 51, No. 11, Vol. 51, No. 12, 2006).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a book arguing from the viewpoint of political history that the Satsuma clan&apos;s conspiracy theory does not hold true, refer to &quot;New Angle toward Ryoma&apos;s Distress Incident -Review on Letters by a Kaientai Member, Tamon SASAKI- the First, the Second, and the Last&quot; by Sakujin KIRINO (&quot;Rekishi dokuhon&quot; Vol. 51, No. 10, Vol. 51, No. 11, Vol. 51, No. 12, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a book arguing from the viewpoint of political history that the Satsuma clan&apos;s conspiracy theory does not hold true, refer to &quot;New Angle toward Ryoma&apos;s Distress Incident -Review on Letters by a Kaientai Member, Tamon SASAKI- the First, the Second, and the Last&quot; by Sakujin KIRINO (&quot;Rekishi dokuhon&quot; Vol. 51, No. 10, Vol. 51, No. 11, Vol. 51, No. 12, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>死後の評判</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous reputation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Posthumous reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Posthumous reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>前述の通り、坂本龍馬はむしろ生前よりも死後に有名になった人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As previously described, Ryoma SAKAMOTO became famed after his death rather than in life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As previously described, Ryoma SAKAMOTO became famed after his death rather than in life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As previously described, Ryoma SAKAMOTO became famed after his death rather than in life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>その最初は明治16年（1883年）、高知の『土陽新聞』に坂崎紫瀾が書いた『汗血千里の駒（かんけつせんりのこま）』が掲載され、大評判となった事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first of the Ryoma craze occurred when Shiran SAKAZAKI&apos;s novel &quot;Kanketsu Senri no Koma&quot; appeared in &quot;Toyo shinbun&quot; published in Kochi in 1883.</e>
<cmt>土陽新聞の読みがわからなかったので「とようしんぶん」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first of the Ryoma craze occurred when Shiran SAKAZAKI&apos;s novel &quot;Kanketsu Senri no Koma&quot; appeared in &quot;Toyo shinbun&quot; published in Kochi in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first of the Ryoma craze occurred when Shiran SAKAZAKI&apos;s novel &quot;Kanketsu Senri no Koma&quot; appeared in &quot;Toyo shinbun&quot; published in Kochi in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="110">
<j>次に龍馬ブームが起きるのは日露戦争時である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next Ryoma craze occurred at the time of Nichiro senso war (Japanese-Russo War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next Ryoma craze occurred at the time of Nichiro senso war (Japanese-Russo War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next Ryoma craze occurred at the time of the Japanese-Russo War.</e>
<cmt>日露戦争のローマ字を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>日本海海戦の直前に、龍馬が昭憲皇太后逸話の夢枕に立ち、「日本海軍は絶対勝てます」と語ったという話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote about Empress Dowager Shoken that Ryoma appeared in her dream and said that the Imperial Japanese Army would definitely win.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote about Empress Dowager Shoken that Ryoma appeared in her dream and said that the Imperial Japanese Army would definitely win.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote about Empress Dowager Shoken that Ryoma appeared in her dream and said that the Imperial Japanese Army would definitely win.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>皇后はこの人物を知らなかったが、宮内大臣の田中光顕が、龍馬の写真を見せたところ、間違いなくこの人物だということになったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then-Empress did not know about the man appeared in her dream, but when Imperial Household Minister Mitsuaki TANAKA showed her a photograph of Ryoma, it turned out to be the man was obviously this person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the Empress did not know about the man appeared in her dream, but when Imperial Household Minister Mitsuaki TANAKA showed her a photograph of Ryoma, it turned out to be the man was obviously this person.</e>
<cmt>文頭を変化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the Empress did not know about the man appeared in her dream, but when Imperial Household Minister Mitsuaki TANAKA showed her a photograph of Ryoma, it turned out to be the man was obviously this person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>真偽のほどは定かではないが、この話が全国紙に掲載されたため、坂本龍馬の評判が全国に広まる事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known whether this is true or not, but Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s reputation spread nationwide since this story appeared in the national press.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known whether this is true or not, but Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s reputation spread nationwide since this story appeared in the national press.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known whether this is true or not, but Ryoma SAKAMOTO&apos;s reputation spread nationwide since this story appeared in the national press.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="114">
<j>坂崎はもちろん、田中も土佐出身の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only SAKAZAKI but also TANAKA are from Tosa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only SAKAZAKI but also TANAKA is from Tosa.</e>
<cmt>are→is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only SAKAZAKI but also TANAKA is from Tosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>当時明治政府を牛耳っていた薩長閥に対し、土佐出身者が挽回を図るべく、土佐出身の維新の功労者として、坂本龍馬を持ち上げたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They praised Tosa-native Ryoma as a person of merit who realized theMeiji Restoration to regain Tosa-native&apos;s power against the Satsuma-Choshu clique who dominated then Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They praised Tosa-native Ryoma as a person of merit who realized the Meiji Restoration to regain Tosa-native&apos;s power against the Satsuma-Choshu clique who dominated then Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>theMeijiの間に半角スペース</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They praised Tosa-native Ryoma as a person of merit who realized the Meiji Restoration to regain Tosa-native&apos;s power against the Satsuma-Choshu clique who dominated then Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>全角のｊを半角に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>勝海舟も坂本龍馬を持ち上げたひとりであるが、旧幕臣という立場で薩長閥に対する反発があったのは、想像に難く無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU also praised Ryoma SAKAMOTO, and it is easy to imagine the KATSU as a former vassal of the Shogun had some resentment against the Satsuma-Choshu clique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaishu KATSU is the one who also praised Ryoma SAKAMOTO, and it is easy to imagine that KATSU as a former vassal of the Shogun had some resentment against the Satsuma-Choshu clique.</e>
<cmt>is the one whoを挿入, the→that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU is the one who also praised Ryoma SAKAMOTO, and it is easy to imagine that KATSU as a former vassal of the Shogun had some resentment against the Satsuma-Choshu clique.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other matters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other matters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other matters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>京都国立博物館には数箇所の血痕が残る掛け軸が所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A hanging scroll with several stains of blood is in the possession of Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A hanging scroll with several stains of blood is in the possession of Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A hanging scroll with several stains of blood is in the possession of Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>それは淡海槐堂が暗殺当日に誕生日祝いとして贈った「梅椿図」という作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scroll, referred to as &quot;Baichin zu&quot; (picture of ume apricot and camellia) was a birthday gift presented by Tankai, Kaido just on that day of the assassination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scroll, referred to as &quot;Baichin zu&quot; (picture of ume apricot and camellia) was a birthday gift presented by Kaido OHMI just on that day of the assassination.</e>
<cmt>Tankai, Kaido→Kaido OHMI</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scroll, referred to as &quot;Baichin zu&quot; (picture of ume apricot and camellia) was a birthday gift presented by Kaido OMI just on that day of the assassination.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>付着した血痕は暗殺された龍馬らのものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stains of the blood adhered to the scroll are believed to be Ryoma and others&apos;, who were assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stains of the blood adhered to the scroll are believed to be Ryoma and others&apos;, who were assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stains of the blood adhered to the scroll are believed to be Ryoma and others&apos;, who were assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>『竜馬がゆく』でも描かれているように、剣術の腕は相当なものだったと暗殺された時の状況から推測できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the situation in which the assassination took place, his skills on swordsmanship is presumed to be substantial as described in &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from the situation in which the assassination took place, his skills on swordsmanship is presumed to be substantial as described in &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>最後のピリオドの位置を変化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from the situation in which the assassination took place, his skills on swordsmanship is presumed to be substantial as described in &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="121">
<j>龍馬は刺客からの「不意」をつかれた「突然」の攻撃から、二の太刀目で身をひねって刀に手を伸ばし、三の太刀目には鞘で受け止めるまで防御の体制を取っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma was caught unprepared, receiving a sudden sward attack from an assassin then at the subsequent second attack he twisted his body and reached his hand to his sword, and received the third sword attack on the sheath of his swore, all these actions being done in defensive posture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma was caught unprepared, receiving a sudden sward attack from an assassin then at the subsequent second attack he twisted his body and reached his hand to his sword, and received the third sword attack on the sheath of his swore, all these actions being done in defensive posture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma was caught unprepared, receiving a sudden sward attack from an assassin then at the subsequent second attack he twisted his body and reached his hand to his sword, and received the third sword attack on the sheath of his swore, all these actions being done in defensive posture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>龍馬の人生・人格形成において多大な影響を与えていったのは、父・八平の後妻である伊興の実家、下田屋（川島家）といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What greatly influenced Ryoma&apos;s life and character formation is said to be Shimodaya (the KAWASHIMA family) that is the parent&apos;s home of Iyo, the second wife of Ryoma&apos;s father Hachihei.</e>
<cmt>下田屋の読みがわかりませんでしたが、「しもだや」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s said that what greatly influenced Ryoma&apos;s life and character formation is Shimodaya (the KAWASHIMA family) that is the parents&apos; home of Iyo, the second wife of Ryoma&apos;s father Hachihei.</e>
<cmt>語順を変化,　parent&apos;s→parents&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s said that what greatly influenced Ryoma&apos;s life and character formation is Shimodaya (the KAWASHIMA family) that is the parents&apos; home of Iyo, the second wife of Ryoma&apos;s father Hachihei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>龍馬は姉である乙女とともに浦戸湾を船で漕ぎ、当時土佐藩御船蔵のあった種崎にある継母伊興の家をたびたび訪れては、長崎や下関からの珍しい土産話などを聞いたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Ryoma togher with his eleder sister Otome rowed a boat in the Urado Bay to visit the stepmother IYO&apos;s house located in Tanezaki, where there was a shipyard of the Tosa clan at that time, and listened to novel stories of travelers from Nagasaki and Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ryoma together with his elder sister Otome rowed a boat in the Urado Bay to visit the stepmother Iyo&apos;s house located in Tanezaki, where there was a shipyard of the Tosa clan at that time, and listened to novel stories of travelers from Nagasaki and Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt>togher→together, eleder→elder, IYO→Iyo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ryoma together with his elder sister Otome rowed a boat in the Urado Bay to visit the stepmother Iyo&apos;s house located in Tanezaki, where there was a shipyard of the Tosa clan at that time, and listened to novel stories of travelers from Nagasaki and Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>また、世界地図や数々の輸入品を見て外の世界への憧れを高めたともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Ryoma conceived his longing for the outer world watching a global map and various imported goods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Ryoma conceived his longing for the outer world watching a global map and various imported goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Ryoma conceived his longing for the outer world watching a global map and various imported goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>詳細は山田一郎『海援隊遺文』（新潮社、1991年）などに、また土佐藩の御船蔵や海事資料については吉永豊実『土佐海事法制史』（山海堂、1983年）に詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the details, refer to &quot;Letters of Kaientai&quot; by Ichiro YAMADA (Shinchosha, 1991); for information about Tosa clan&apos;s shipyard and maritime data, refer to &quot;History of Tosa Maritime Law&quot; by Toyomi YOSHINAGA (Sankaido, 1983).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the details, refer to &quot;Letters of Kaientai&quot; by Ichiro YAMADA (Shinchosha, 1991); for information about Tosa clan&apos;s shipyard and maritime data, refer to &quot;History of Tosa Maritime Law&quot; by Toyomi YOSHINAGA (Sankaido, 1983).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the details, refer to &quot;Letters of Kaientai&quot; by Ichiro YAMADA (Shinchosha, 1991); for information about Tosa clan&apos;s shipyard and maritime data, refer to &quot;History of Tosa Maritime Law&quot; by Toyomi YOSHINAGA (Sankaido, 1983).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>当時土佐藩士の間では長刀をさすことが流行していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, among samurais of Tosa clan wearing long swards was prevalent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, among samurais of Tosa clan wearing long swards was prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, among samurais of Tosa clan wearing long swards was prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>あるとき龍馬の旧友が龍馬と再会したとき、龍馬は短めの刀を差していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, when Ryoma&apos;s old friend met him again, Ryoma wore a rather short sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, when Ryoma&apos;s old friend met him again, Ryoma wore a rather short sword.</e>
<cmt>wore の後に aを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, when Ryoma&apos;s old friend met him again, Ryoma wore a rather short sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>そのことを指摘したところ「実戦では短い刀のほうが取り回しがよい」と言われ、納得した旧友は短い刀を差すようにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma who was questioned about his short swore replied to his friend, saying &quot;The short sword is easy to handle during actual battle.&quot; His friend assented to Ryoma and decided to wear a short sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma who was questioned about his short sword replied to his friend, saying &quot;The short sword is easy to handle during actual battle.&quot; His friend assented to Ryoma and decided to wear a short sword.</e>
<cmt>Ryomaの前の半角スペースを削除, swore→sword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma who was questioned about his short sword replied to his friend, saying &quot;The short sword is easy to handle during actual battle.&quot; His friend assented to Ryoma and decided to wear a short sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>次に再会したとき、旧友が勇んで刀を見せたところ龍馬は懐から拳銃を出し「銃の前には刀なんて役にたたない」と言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they met again next time, the friend proudly showed his sward to Ryoma. Ryoma took a handgun out of his inside pocket, showing it to his friend and said &quot;The sword is useless at all in the presence of the gun.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they met again next time, the friend proudly showed his sword to Ryoma. Ryoma took a handgun out of his inside pocket, showing it to his friend and said &quot;The sword is useless at all in the presence of the gun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>sward→sword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they met again next time, the friend proudly showed his sword to Ryoma. Ryoma took a handgun out of his inside pocket, showing it to his friend and said &quot;The sword is useless at all in the presence of the gun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>納得した旧友はさっそく拳銃を買い求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The friend again consented to him and run for buying a handgun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The friend again consented to him and run for buying a handgun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The friend again consented to him and run for buying a handgun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>三度再会したとき、旧友が購入した拳銃を見せたところ龍馬は万国公法（国際法）の洋書を取り出し「これからは世界を知らなければならない」といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they met with each other third time, the friend showed Ryoma a handgun which he had bought, but this time Ryoma took a foreign book on international public law out of his internal pocket and said to him &quot;From now on, we must know the world.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they met with each other third time, the friend showed Ryoma a handgun which he had bought, but this time Ryoma took a foreign book on international public law out of his internal pocket and said to him &quot;From now on, we must know the world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they met with each other third time, the friend showed Ryoma a handgun which he had bought, but this time Ryoma took a foreign book on international public law out of his internal pocket and said to him &quot;From now on, we must know the world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>もはや旧友はついていけなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said the old friend of Ryoma could not catch up with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said the old friend of Ryoma could not catch up with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said the old friend of Ryoma could not catch up with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>これは龍馬の性格を鮮やかに描写しているものの、あくまで逸話であって史実ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This story vividly depicts Ryoma&apos;s disposition, but it is only an anecdote and not historical fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story vividly depicts Ryoma&apos;s disposition, but it is only an anecdote and not historical fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story vividly depicts Ryoma&apos;s disposition, but it is only an anecdote and not historical fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>逸話の起源は、定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of this story is not certain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of this story is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of this story is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="135">
<j>寺田屋事件直後にお龍と結婚した龍馬は、同事件での傷をいやすことも兼ねてお龍を伴って薩摩に滞在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma, who got married to Oryu right after Teradaya incident, has stayed in Satsuma together with her, one of the purposes of the stay being healing the wounds among others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma, who got married to Oryo right after Teradaya incident, has stayed in Satsuma together with her, one of the purposes of healing the wounds among others.</e>
<cmt>Oryu→Oryo, the stay being を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma, who got married to Oryo right after Teradaya incident, has stayed in Satsuma together with her, one of the purposes of healing the wounds among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>これを指して、日本で初めての新婚旅行とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Referring to this trip to Satsuma, an incipiency of the first honey moon trip in Japan is mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Referring to this trip to Satsuma, an incipiency of the first honey moon trip in Japan is mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Referring to this trip to Satsuma, an incipiency of the first honey moon trip in Japan is mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="137">
<j>龍馬が愛用した拳銃は2丁ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma had two favorite handguns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma had two favorite handguns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma had two favorite handguns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>ひとつは高杉晋作から贈呈されたスミス&amp;ウェッソンモデル2アーミー 33口径で、寺田屋事件の際に火を噴いたのはこの銃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is SMISS &amp; WESSON MODEL 2, ARMY, 33,which presented to Ryoma by Shinsaku TAKASUGI, with which Ryoma opened fire in the Teradaya incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is SMITH &amp; WESSON MODEL 2, ARMY, 33, which presented to Ryoma by Shinsaku TAKASUGI, with which Ryoma opened fire in the Teradaya incident.</e>
<cmt>検索結果、SMISSはSMITHのようです。33の後をコンマに変換</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One is SMITH &amp; WESSON MODEL 2, ARMY, 33, which presented to Ryoma by Shinsaku TAKASUGI, with which Ryoma opened fire in the Teradaya incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>しかし同事件の際に紛失し、後に買い求めたのがS&amp;Wモデル1 22口径で、これは妻・お龍とともに1丁ずつ所持し、薩摩滞在時はこれで狩猟などを楽しんだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the incident Ryoma lost the gun and later bought two of S&amp;W MODEL 1, 22, which were carried by Ryoma and Oryo and with which they enjoyed hunting during the stay in Satsuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the incident Ryoma lost the gun and later bought two of S&amp;W MODEL 1, 22, which were carried by Ryoma and Oryo and with which they enjoyed hunting during the stay in Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>of S&amp;Wの間のスペースを半角に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the incident Ryoma lost the gun and later bought two of S&amp;W MODEL 1, 22, which were carried by Ryoma and Oryo and with which they enjoyed hunting during the stay in Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>当然この銃は暗殺時も携帯していたが発砲することなく殺害されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally Ryoma carried the gun with him at the time of assassination, but was killed without opening fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally Ryoma carried the gun with him at the time of assassination, but was killed without opening fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally Ryoma carried the gun with him at the time of assassination, but was killed without opening fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="141">
<j>幼少の頃、水練（水泳）に出かける途中、友人に「こんな雨で泳ぐのか」と問われたが、「濡れるのに雨も関係あるか」とそのまま川に行ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his childhood, on his way to swimming training he was questioned by a friend, &quot;Do you swim in this heavy rain?&quot;. He replied, &quot;Rain doesn&apos;t matter, anyway I will get wet.&quot; and proceeded to the river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his childhood, on his way to swimming training he was questioned by a friend, &quot;Do you swim in this heavy rain?&quot;. He replied, &quot;Rain doesn&apos;t matter, anyway I will get wet.&quot; and proceeded to the river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his childhood, on his way to swimming training he was questioned by a friend, &quot;Do you swim in this heavy rain?&quot;. He replied, &quot;Rain doesn&apos;t matter, anyway I will get wet.&quot; and proceeded to the river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="142">
<j>身長6尺（約182cm。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was six feet (about 182 cm) high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was six feet (about 182 cm) high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was six feet (about 182 cm) high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>近年の研究では174cmや169cmというものもあり）と江戸時代の当時としてはかなりな大男であったといえるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the recent researches suggest 174 cm or 169 cm, which anyway mean that he was a man of high stature in Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the recent researches suggest 174 cm or 169 cm, which anyway mean that he was a man of high stature in Edo era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the recent researches suggest 174 cm or 169 cm, which anyway mean that he was a man of high stature in Edo era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="144">
<j>背中に黒毛が生えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had black hairs on his back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had black hairs on his back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had black hairs on his back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="145">
<j>少年時はおねしょタレで、泣き虫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a bed-wetter and crybaby, in his boyhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a bed-wetter and crybaby, in his boyhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a bed-wetter and crybaby, in his boyhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>勉強についていけず塾を退塾になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He could not follow study progress and was kicked out of the clan&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He could not follow study progress and was kicked out of the clan&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>could not→could not, progress and→progress and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He could not follow study progress and was kicked out of the clan&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="147">
<j>武市半平太とは「アギ（あご）」「アザ（痣）」とあだ名で呼び合う仲だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanpeita TAKECHI and Ryoma were so close friends each other that they called each other by their nick names, &quot;Agi (chin) and Aza (birthmark).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanpeita TAKECHI and Ryoma were so close friends each other that they called each other by their nick names, &quot;Agi (chin) and Aza (birthmark).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanpeita TAKECHI and Ryoma were so close friends each other that they called each other by their nick names, &quot;Agi (chin) and Aza (birthmark).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="148">
<j>姉・幸の夫の家によく遊びに行き、屋根に上って太平洋を眺めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma frequently visited the house of his elder sister Sachi&apos;s husband, and climbed atop the roof to look at the pacific ocean.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma frequently visited the house of his elder sister Sachi&apos;s husband, and climbed atop the roof to look at the pacific ocean.</e>
<cmt>of hisの間のスペースを半角に変換</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma frequently visited the house of his elder sister Sachi&apos;s husband, and climbed atop the roof to look at the pacific ocean.</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="149">
<j>西郷に対し「わしは世界の海援隊をやります」と語り、その様子を同席していた陸奥宗光がことあるごとに回想して語ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allegedly, Ryoma told Saigo, &quot;I will manage Kaientai, looking toward the world.&quot; Munemitsu MUTSU who shared the table with them, also allegedly remembered this scene and spoke about it in every opportunity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allegedly, Ryoma told Saigo, &quot;I will manage Kaientai, looking toward the world.&quot; Munemitsu MUTSU who shared the table with them, also allegedly remembered this scene and spoke about it in every opportunity.</e>
<cmt>alsoの前のスペースを半角へ変換</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allegedly, Ryoma told Saigo, &quot;I will manage Kaientai, looking toward the world.&quot; Munemitsu MUTSU who shared the table with them, also allegedly remembered this scene and spoke about it in every opportunity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>しかしこれは後世の創作らしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This, however is likely a creation in the later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This, however is likely a creation in the later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This, however is likely a creation in the later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="151">
<j>同時代の龍馬評</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reputation of Ryoma by his comtemporaries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reputation of Ryoma by his contemporaries</e>
<cmt>comtemporaries→contemporaries</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reputation of Ryoma by his contemporaries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="152">
<j>住谷寅之介「龍馬誠実可也の人物、併せて撃剣家、事情迂闊、何も知らずとぞ」（龍馬江戸修行後）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryoma is very honest, a brave swordsman, and little informed.&quot; by Toranosuke SUMIYA (after Ryoma finished dojo training in Edo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryoma is very honest, a brave swordsman, and little informed.&quot; by Toranosuke SUMIYA (after Ryoma finished dojo training in Edo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryoma is very honest, a brave swordsman, and little informed.&quot; by Toranosuke SUMIYA (after Ryoma finished dojo training in Edo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>平井収二郎「元より龍馬は人物なれども、書物を読まぬ故、時として間違ひし事もござ候へば」（龍馬脱藩後）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryoma is definitely some fellow, but he sometimes make a mistake since he does not read books.&quot; by Shujiro HIRAI (after Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryoma is definitely some fellow, but he sometimes make a mistake since he does not read books.&quot; by Shujiro HIRAI (after Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryoma is definitely some fellow, but he sometimes make a mistake since he does not read books.&quot; by Shujiro HIRAI (after Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>武市半平太「土佐一国にはあだたぬ奴」（龍馬脱藩後）、「肝胆もとより雄大、奇機おのずから湧出し、 飛潜だれか識るあらん、ひとえに龍名 に恥じず」（獄中で）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;He is not a type of person who does excellent jobs only within the Tosa clan.&quot; by Hanpeita TAKECHI (ater Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan); &quot;Ryoma is bvave, grand, innovative, and unique, jut true to his name &quot;dragon&quot;.&quot; also by Hanpeita TAKECHI (in prison)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanpeita TAKECHI said that &quot;He is not a type of person who does excellent jobs only within the Tosa clan&quot; (after Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan) and also &quot;Ryoma is brave, grand, innovative, and unique, just true to his name &quot;dragon.&quot; (in prison)</e>
<cmt>語順変化。ater→after, bvave→brave, jut→just, &quot;dragon&quot;.&quot;の後の二重括弧を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanpeita TAKECHI said that &quot;He is not a type of person who does excellent jobs only within the Tosa clan&quot; (after Ryoma fled from the Tosa clan) and also &quot;Ryoma is brave, grand, innovative, and unique, just true to his name &quot;dragon.&quot; (in prison)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>東久世通禧「龍馬面会、偉人なり。奇説家なり」（薩長同盟直前）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I met Ryoma. He is a great man; he has extraordinary ideas.&quot;Toyomichi HIGASHIKUZE (immediately before Satsuma-Choshu Alliance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I met Ryoma. He is a great man; he has extraordinary ideas.&quot; by Toyomichi HIGASHIKUZE (immediately before Satsuma-Choshu Alliance)</e>
<cmt>by を挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I met Ryoma. He is a great man; he has extraordinary ideas.&quot; by Toyomichi HIGASHIKUZE (immediately before Satsuma-Choshu Alliance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="156">
<j>勝海舟「坂本龍馬、彼はおれを殺しに来た奴だが、なかなか人物さ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU &quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO is a person who visited me to kill me, but a some fellow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaishu KATSU said that &quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO is a person who visited me to kill me, but a some fellow.</e>
<cmt>said that を挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU said that &quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO is a person who visited me to kill me, but a some fellow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>その時おれは笑って受けたが、沈着いて、なんとなく冒しがたい威権があってよい男だったよ」（維新後）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time I just laghed and accepted him, but he was discouraged; he had some dignity that nobody could perturb and an atrractive aura.&quot; (After the Restoration)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time I just laughed and accepted him, but he was discouraged; he had some dignity that nobody could perturb and an attractive aura.&quot; (After the Restoration)</e>
<cmt>laghed→laughted, atrractive→attractive,（全角スペース）(After the Restoration)→（半角スペース）(After the Restoration)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time I just laughed and accepted him, but he was discouraged; he had some dignity that nobody could perturb and an attractive aura.&quot; (After the Restoration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="158">
<j>西郷隆盛「天下に有志あり、余多く之と交わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO &quot;There are hopefules under the sun, and I have met lots of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamori SAIGO said that &quot;There are hopefuls under the sun, and I have met lots of them.</e>
<cmt>said that を挿入, hopefules→hopefuls</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO said that &quot;There are hopefuls under the sun, and I have met lots of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>然れども度量の大、龍馬に如くもの、未だかつて之を見ず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But I&apos;ve never met such a large-minded person as Ryoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But I&apos;ve never met such a large-minded person as Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But I&apos;ve never met such a large-minded person as Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>龍馬の度量や到底測るべからず」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No one would see how magnanimous he is.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No one would see how magnanimous he is.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No one would see how magnanimous he is.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="161">
<j>土方久元「その言行すこぶる意表に出で、時としては大いに馬鹿らしき事を演じたれど、また実に非凡の思想を有し、之を断行し得たり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisamoto HIJIKATA &quot;Ryoma&apos;s words and deeds were something extremely unexpected, and he sometimes did very absurd things, but he had extraordinary ideas and achieved what he believes.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisamoto HIJIKATA said that &quot;Ryoma&apos;s words and deeds were something extremely unexpected, and he sometimes did very absurd things, but he had extraordinary ideas and achieved what he believes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>said that を挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisamoto HIJIKATA said that &quot;Ryoma&apos;s words and deeds were something extremely unexpected, and he sometimes did very absurd things, but he had extraordinary ideas and achieved what he believes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>三吉慎蔵「過激なることは豪も無し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzo MIYOSHI &quot;There is nothing radical in Ryoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzo MIYOSHI said that &quot;There is nothing radical in Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>said that を挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzo MIYOSHI said that &quot;There is nothing radical in Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>かつ声高に事を論ずる様のこともなく、至極おとなしき人なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He does not argue in a loud voice and is very quiet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He does not argue in a loud voice and is very quiet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He does not argue in a loud voice and is very quiet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>容貌を一見すれば豪気に見受けらるるも、万事温和に事を処する人なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he is seemingly dynamic, but he deals with everything calmly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he is seemingly dynamic, but he deals with everything calmly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he is seemingly dynamic, but he deals with everything calmly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>但し胆力が極めて大なり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he has got lots of nerves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he has got lots of nerves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he has got lots of nerves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>家系・家族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family history and family member</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family history and family member</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family history and family member</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="166">
<j>清和源氏の一支族美濃源氏土岐氏の庶家、明智氏の末裔を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is claimed to be a descendant of the AKECHI family, a cadet branch of Mino Genji the Doki family which is a tribe of Seiwa Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He claims to be a descendant of the AKECHI family, a cadet branch of Mino Genji the Doki family which is a tribe of Seiwa Genji.</e>
<cmt>is の削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He claims to be a descendant of the AKECHI family, a cadet branch of Mino Genji the Doki family which is a tribe of Seiwa Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>坂本姓の由来は、本能寺の変以前、明智氏所領であった坂本（現滋賀県大津市坂本）に由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the SAKAMOTO family name is a place called SAKAMOTO (Sakamoto, Otsu city, Shiga prefecture at present) tha was a domain of the AKECHI family before the Honnoji no hen incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the family name SAKAMOTO came from a place called SAKAMOTO (Sakamoto, Otsu city, Shiga prefecture at present) that was a domain of the AKECHI family before the Honnoji no hen incident.</e>
<cmt>The origin of the SAKAMOTO family name is a place→The origin of the family name SAKAMOTO came from a place, tha→that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the family name SAKAMOTO came from a place called SAKAMOTO (Sakamoto, Otsu city, Shiga prefecture at present) that was a domain of the AKECHI family before the Honnoji no hen incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>しかしこれは後世の創作だろうとする声も強い土居晴夫『坂本龍馬の系譜』（新人物往来社、2006年）などが詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But many people considers that this is a fiction made up later; refer to &quot;Family History of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; by Haruo DOI (Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 2006).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But many people considers that this is a fiction made up later; refer to &quot;Family History of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; by Haruo DOI (Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 2006).</e>
<cmt>2006の前のスペースを半角に変換</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But many people considers that this is a fiction made up later; refer to &quot;Family History of Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; by Haruo DOI (Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>家紋は組み合わせ角に桔梗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest is combined squares and a bellflower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest is combined squares and a bellflower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest is combined squares and a bellflower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="170">
<j>坂本家が主君に差し出した『先祖書指出控』には、「先祖、坂本太郎五郎、生国山城国、郡村未だ詳らかならず、仕声弓戦之難を避け、長岡郡才谷村に来住す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Copy of Submitted Document about Ancestor&quot; reads &quot;Ancestor, Taro Goro SAKAMOTO was born in Yamashiro no kuni, although the details such as which county and village in Yamashiro no kuni are yet to be known. He escaped a war disaster and arrived at and settled in Saitani-mura village of Nagaoka-gun county.</e>
<cmt>仕声弓戦の意味が分からなかったので、戦いという意味で訳しました。才谷村は「たに」とよむのか「だに」とよむのか分からなかったので、竜馬の変名に合わせて「さいたに」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Copy of Submitted Document about Ancestor&quot; reads &quot;Ancestor, Taro Goro SAKAMOTO was born in Yamashiro no kuni, although the details such as which county and village in Yamashiro no kuni are yet to be known. He escaped a war disaster and arrived at and settled in Saitani-mura village of Nagaoka-gun county.</e>
<cmt>county.→county.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Copy of Submitted Document about Ancestor&quot; reads &quot;Ancestor, Taro Goro SAKAMOTO was born in Yamashiro no kuni, although the details such as which county and village in Yamashiro no kuni are yet to be known. He escaped a war disaster and arrived at and settled in Saitani-mura village of Nagaoka-gun county.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>但し年歴、妻之里、且つ病死之年月等未詳」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But when he settled is not known. Where his wife came from and when he died of a disease are also not known.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But when he settled is not known. Where his wife came from and when he died of a disease are also not known.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Butの前の半角スペースを削除, Whereの前の全角スペースを半角スペースへ変換</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But when he settled is not known. Where his wife came from and when he died of a disease are also not known.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="172">
<j>天正16年（1588年）才谷村の検地で村の3番目の百姓として登録されているにすぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SAKAMOTO family is merely registered as the third-largest peasant in the village in the official land-measurement survey conducted at Saitani-mura in 1588.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SAKAMOTO family was merely registered as the third-largest peasant in the village in the official land-measurement survey conducted at Saitani-mura in 1588.</e>
<cmt>is→was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SAKAMOTO family was merely registered as the third-largest peasant in the village in the official land-measurement survey conducted at Saitani-mura in 1588.</e>
<cmt>全角スペースを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="173">
<j>どうやら3代目太郎左衛門までは公認の名字をもたぬ百姓身分と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the SAKAMOTO family had been in a peasant status that was not entitled to have an accredited family name until the third generation Tarozaemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the SAKAMOTO family had been in a peasant status that was not entitled to have an accredited family name until the third generation Tarozaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the SAKAMOTO family had been in a peasant status that was not entitled to have an accredited family name until the third generation Tarozaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>2代目彦三郎、3代目太郎左衛門まで才谷村で農業を営んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the second generation Hikosaburo and the third generation Tarozaemon, the SAKAMOTO family had been engaged in farming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the second generation Hikosaburo and the third generation Tarozaemon, the SAKAMOTO family had been engaged in farming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the second generation Hikosaburo and the third generation Tarozaemon, the SAKAMOTO family had been engaged in farming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>4代目守之、5代目正禎は才谷村の大字の一つである「大浜」を家名としてなのりはじめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At aroung the fourth generation Moriyuki and the fifth generation Masayoshi, the family started to use&quot;Ohama&quot; as their family name, that is an area in Saitani-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At around the fourth generation Moriyuki and the fifth generation Masayoshi, the family started to use &quot;Ohama&quot; as their family name which standed for an area in Saitani-mura.</e>
<cmt>At aroung→At around, use&quot;Ohama&quot;→use &quot;Ohama&quot;,,that is an area→which standed for an area</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At around the fourth generation Moriyuki and the fifth generation Masayoshi, the family started to use &quot;Ohama&quot; as their family name, which was one of the regional name in Saitani-mura.</e>
<cmt>全角ｔを半角に、スペースの重複を削除、大字の一つ、の訳を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="176">
<j>寛文6年（1666年）3代目太郎左衛門の次男・八兵衛は高知城下にでて質屋を開業（屋号は才谷屋）し、酒屋、呉服等を扱う豪商となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachibei, who is the second son of the third generation Tarozaemon, moved to and opned a pawnshop (shop name: Saitaniya) in the town around Kochi castle, and then became a wealthy merchant running a liquor shop and dealing with kimono fabrics and other goods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachibei, who is the second son of the third generation Tarozaemon, moved to and opened a pawnshop (shop name: Saitaniya) in the town around Kochi castle, and then became a wealthy merchant running a liquor shop and dealing with kimono fabrics and other goods.</e>
<cmt>opned→opened</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachibei, who is the second son of the third generation Tarozaemon, moved to and opened a pawnshop (shop name: Saitaniya) in the town around Kochi castle, and then became a wealthy merchant running a liquor shop and dealing with kimono fabrics and other goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="177">
<j>享保15年（1730年）ころ本町筋の年寄役となり、藩主に拝謁を許されるにいたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At around 1730, the family gained an official position of chief executive of Honmachi-suji and became allowed to meet the lord of the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At around 1730, the family gained an official position of chief executive of Honmachi-suji and became allowed to meet the lord of the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At around 1730, the family gained an official position of chief executive of Honmachi-suji and became allowed to meet the lord of the Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="178">
<j>明和7年（1770年）6代目直益は郷士の株を買い長男・直海を郷士坂本家の初代とし、名字帯刀、すなわち公認の名字を名乗り身分表象として二本差す身分にたどりついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1770, the sixth generation Naomasu boutght a stock for the title of Goshi and appointed his first son Naomi to become the first generation of goshi SAKAMOTO family, at which point the falimy reached the social status of Myoji-taito, i.e., to have an accredited family name and as a representation of this status carry two swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1770, the sixth generation Naomasu bought a stock for the title of Goshi and appointed his first son Naomi to become the first generation of goshi SAKAMOTO family, at which point the family reached the social status of Myoji-taito, i.e., to have an accredited family name and as a representation of this status carry two swords.</e>
<cmt>boutght→bought, falimy→family</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1770, the sixth generation Naomasu bought a stock for the title of Goshi and appointed his first son Naomi to become the first generation of goshi SAKAMOTO family, at which point the family reached the social status of Myoji-taito, i.e., to have an accredited family name and as a representation of this status carry two swords.</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="179">
<j>次男直清には商家才谷屋をつがせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasu ordered his second son Naokiyo to inherit the merchant family SAITANIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasu ordered his second son Naokiyo to inherit the merchant family SAITANIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasu ordered his second son Naokiyo to inherit the merchant family SAITANIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>郷士坂本家3代目直足は白札郷士山本覚右衛門の次男としてうまれ坂本家へ養子としてはいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The goshi SAKAMOTO family&apos;s third generation Naotari was born as the second son of upper level goshi Kakuemon YAMAMOTO and adopted to the SAKAMOTO family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The goshi SAKAMOTO family&apos;s third generation Naotari was born as the second son of upper level goshi Kakuemon YAMAMOTO and adopted to the SAKAMOTO family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The goshi SAKAMOTO family&apos;s third generation Naotari was born as the second son of upper level goshi Kakuemon YAMAMOTO and adopted to the SAKAMOTO family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>直足の次男が直陰（坂本龍馬）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son of Naotari is Naokage (Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son of Naotari is Naokage (Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son of Naotari is Naokage (Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="182">
<j>土佐藩郷士・坂本直足の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma is the second son of Naotari SAKAMOTO, a Tosa clan&apos;s goshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma is the second son of Naotari SAKAMOTO, a Tosa clan&apos;s goshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma is the second son of Naotari SAKAMOTO, a Tosa clan&apos;s goshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="183">
<j>母は坂本幸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s mother is Sachi SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s mother is Sachi SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s mother is Sachi SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="184">
<j>兄は権平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s elder brother is Gonpei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s elder brother is Gonpei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s elder brother is Gonpei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>姉は千鶴、栄、坂本乙女（おとめ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s elder sisters are Chizu, Sakae, and Otome SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s elder sisters are Chizu, Sakae and Otome SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>and前のコンマを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s elder sisters are Chizu, Sakae and Otome SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>妻はおりょう（楢崎龍）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s wife is Oryo (Ryo NARASAKI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma&apos;s wife is Oryo (Ryo NARASAKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma&apos;s wife is Oryo (Ryo NARASAKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>婚約者・千葉さな子もいたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Ryoma also had a fiancee, Sanako CHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ryoma also had a fiance, Sanako CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>fiancee→fiance</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ryoma also had a fiance, Sanako CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), 経済準学士(id:22656), Tast(id:29478), Ring Snowstorm(id:121740), 1234Gorilla(id:127546), Greenland4(id:114494), Michael Friedrich(id:44338), Mois(id:30596), Tk70(id:28827), でここ(id:9565), Parachutes(id:139813), Fxcxt(id:21803), 河雲地蔵(id:115144), リチー(id:116392), らりた(id:1327), MioUzaki(id:89034), Northface(id:70750), モンゴルの白い虎(id:134187), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), A-Taul(id:41790), Kahskydream(id:5116), 今門裕樹(id:107091), Squarepp(id:131094), Yorix2(id:80253), スコットチャックベス(id:58691), Maakun(id:16735), -1g(id:67660), Jkluio(id:139869), DCyokohama(id:26779), 松茸(id:27535), Huemat(id:19503), S kitahashi(id:10307), Himazin(id:22034), Seibuabina(id:37532), 浪士(id:62980), Birdie(id:36320), よもすがら(id:212112), Baldanders(id:81163), Kagetudo(id:163875), MDR-SK(id:192066), Shigechan(id:50958), Rusk(id:9895), Hamichan(id:4829), 轟俊(id:150842), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), 非通知設定(id:6751), Prx(id:60340), おきた(id:18906), ぴかり(id:116821), Bigben(id:1039), Junger(id:10282), Suisui(id:69), 机龍之介(id:61257), Sogiya(id:82968), Zoominshiodome(id:149045), Bluesky07(id:121929), Julius Caesar(id:181760), ノトス(id:42992), 陽一(id:92099), Koba-chan(id:860), 土方　誠(id:3651), 沢田(id:40580), MoonChronicle(id:199514), さららゆら(id:12274), An-chan(id:14590), ぎぼうし(id:139427), Chobot(id:20846), こぶまき(id:38278), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Lonicera(id:20638), Mam1kawa(id:151331), 虎水大輔(id:86189), Race(id:131322), 水野白楓(id:22811), Duke-Sillywalker(id:108015), きゅうり(id:2182), 7777(id:70360), SieBot(id:126695), Nerv4(id:38341), 戊辰龍馬(id:10371), Sapphire95(id:50211), Green3558(id:59508), ZassouTori(id:136771), Nyanya(id:55612), Opponent(id:720), Hypno(id:64354), LEVINO(id:213634), Yas(id:739), ASAMA501(id:91947), Mnd(id:15140), Clay(id:110480), GoGoDoll(id:131511), ZZZ(id:9462), MIO(id:31681), Yaky(id:22711), Cider house(id:74739), タニ公(id:100594), Baioextra(id:164616), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Naganotoshiki(id:113963), KSKS(id:97637), Nikousei(id:20326), NIKE(id:16342), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), ツナマヨ(id:40302), Kwappa(id:85455), Nog(id:53565), Thaw(id:119634), みょうじ(id:124419), E-190(id:74680), Tatsu55(id:44816), Reggaeman(id:6214), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Tuffyrhodes20(id:55171), Toto-tarou(id:16648), April44(id:121522), Rita(id:19950), Kurz(id:1601), Naru-W(id:17852), Ponta2(id:129030), Nevylax(id:38464), Goki(id:7107), Alljal(id:46858), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Dokure(id:40343), Izayohi(id:13095), J-ishikawa(id:74471), クロウ(id:21337), Aphaia(id:3132), Tigerthegreat(id:32546), 間久部緑郎(id:22345), Shinkansen(id:13703), Akaloli(id:141644), Kazutoko(id:84234), まむし(id:40389), 上田隼人(id:23104), Fromm(id:71291), Pacusi(id:70460), 江戸ラー(id:30154), 663highland(id:18755), 芦原温泉(id:125555), 8マン(id:135319), Chatama(id:16156), Louperibot(id:128971), Tomorrow0622(id:26939), Tagmaniaforce(id:197220), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>