<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>九鬼隆一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuichi KUKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuichi KUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuichi KUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>九鬼 隆一（くき りゅういち、嘉永3年8月7日_(旧暦)（1850年9月12日） - 昭和6年（1931年）8月18日）は日本の官僚、男爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuichi KUKI (August 7, 1850 [the old calendar], September 12, 1850 to August 18, 1931) was a Japanese bureaucrat and baron.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は「嘉永3年8月7日」側を指していると解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuichi KUKI (August 7, 1850 [the old calendar], September 12, 1850 to August 18, 1931) was a Japanese bureaucrat and a baron.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuichi KUKI (September 12, 1850 to August 18, 1931) was a Japanese bureaucrat and a baron.</e>
<cmt>dateを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>文部少輔（現在の文部省事務次官）、帝国博物館（現・国立博物館）初代総長、貴族院議員、枢密院 (日本)宮中顧問官などを務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Shoyu (a Junior Assistant Minister) of the Ministry of Education (the present deputy secretary of the Ministry of Education), the first chief of the Imperial Museum (the present National Museum), a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers), as well as an imperial court councilor of Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>「枢密院 (日本)」の「日本」を訳する必要はない気もしましたが、そのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as Shoyu (a Junior Assistant Minister) of the Ministry of Education (the present deputy secretary of the Ministry of Education), the first chief of the Imperial Museum (the present National Museum), a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers), as well as an imperial court councilor of Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as Shoyu (a Junior Assistant Minister) of the Ministry of Education (the present deputy secretary of the Ministry of Education), the first chief of the Imperial Museum (the present National Museum), a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers), as well as an imperial court councilor of Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>特に美術分野に造詣が深く、かつて三田市にあった三田博物館（現在は閉館）の創設者でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He especially had a lot of knowledge of fine art, and is the founder of the Sanda Museum which used to be in Sanda City (but is closed now).</e>
<cmt>「三田博物館」→「Sanda Museum」＜定訳不明＞</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He especially had a lot of knowledge of fine art, and is the founder of the Sanda Museum which used to be in Sanda City (but is closed now).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He especially had a lot of knowledge of fine art, and was the founder of the Sanda Museum which used to be in Sanda City (but is closed now).</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、息子は哲学者の九鬼周造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, Shuzo KUKI, was a philosopher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, Shuzo KUKI, was a philosopher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, Shuzo KUKI, was a philosopher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>三田藩・綾部藩時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time of the Sanda Domain and the Ayabe Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The time of the Sanda Domain and the Ayabe Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The time in the Sanda Domain and the Ayabe Domain</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>嘉永3年（1850年）、三田藩の家臣で180石取りの星崎貞幹の次男として藩内の屋敷町（現・兵庫県三田市）で生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1850, he was born in Yashikimachi, the Sanda Domain (current, Sanda City, Hyogo Prefecture), as a second son of 星崎貞幹 who was a vassal of the Sanda Domain and was granted 180 koku (a volume measure for rice [approximately, 180 liters]).</e>
<cmt>「星崎貞幹（Sadamoto, HOSHIZAKI）」読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1850, he was born in Yashikimachi, the Sanda Domain (current, Sanda City, Hyogo Prefecture), as a second son of 星崎貞幹 who was a vassal of the Sanda Domain and was granted 180 koku (a volume measure for rice [approximately, 180 liters]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1850, he was born in Yashikimachi, the Sanda Domain (current, Sanda City, Hyogo Prefecture), as the second son of 星崎貞幹 who was a vassal of the Sanda Domain and was granted 180 koku (a volume measure for rice [approximately, 180 liters]).</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幼名は貞次郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Jiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Jiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Teijiro (貞次郎).</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1860年（万延元年）に母・龍が亡くなるが、藩主・九鬼隆義の斡旋で、跡継ぎを探していた綾部藩家老・九鬼隆周の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his mother, 龍, died in 1860, he was adopted to 九鬼隆周, a chief retainer of the Ayabe Domain who was looking for a successor, through the intercession of the lord of domain, Takayoshi, KUKI.</e>
<cmt>「龍（Ryu）」読み方不明「九鬼隆周（Takachika, KUKI)」読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his mother, 龍, died in 1860, he was adopted by 九鬼隆周, a chief retainer of the Ayabe Domain who was looking for a successor, through the intercession of the lord of domain, Takayoshi, KUKI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his mother, 龍, died in 1860, he was adopted by 九鬼隆周, a chief retainer of the Ayabe Domain who was looking for a successor, through the intercession of the lord of domain, Takayoshi, KUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>慶応元年（1866年）に家督を継ぎ九鬼家の当主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1866, he took over the family estate and became the head of the Kuki family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1866, he took over the family estate and became the head of the Kuki family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1866, he took over the family estate and became the head of the Kuki family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>三田藩の藩政改革に携わっていた福澤諭吉が大阪江戸堀の藩屋敷で饗応された際に同席し、面識を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yukichi FUKUZAWA, who was involved in the reformation of the duties of the Sada Domain, came to Kyoo (a banquet) in the domain residence in Edobori, Osaka, Kuki attended the same Kyoo and met him there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yukichi FUKUZAWA, who was involved in the reformation of the duties of the Sada Domain, came to Kyoo (a banquet) in the domain residence in Edobori, Osaka, Kuki attended the same Kyoo and met him there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yukichi FUKUZAWA, who was involved in the reformation of the duties of the Sanda Domain, came to Kyoo (a banquet) in the domain residence in Edobori, Osaka, Kuki attended the same Kyoo and met him there.</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>明治2年（1869年）5月19日に九鬼隆義と共に上京した際に福澤を再訪し、藩の推薦もあって学校法人慶應義塾への入塾を許可された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he went to Tokyo with Takayoshi, KUKI on May 19, 1869, he visited Yukichi FUKUZAWA again with the recommendation of the domain and got permission to enter the Gakko Hojin Keio Gijuku (Keio University).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he went to Tokyo with Takayoshi, KUKI on May 19, 1869, he visited Yukichi FUKUZAWA again with the recommendation of the domain and got permission to enter the Gakko Hojin Keio Gijuku (Keio University).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he went to Tokyo with Takayoshi, KUKI on June 28, 1869, he visited Yukichi FUKUZAWA again with the recommendation of the domain and got permission to enter the Gakko Hojin (incorporated educational institution) Keio Gijuku.</e>
<cmt>dateを修正しました。 ()内不要です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同年11月、綾部藩の洋式練兵中隊長、権少参事などの職に就き、山陰鎮撫総督として丹波街道の塚原口を受け持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, he was assigned to be a company commander of the Western style military drill court as well as a Junior Councillor of the Ayabe Domain, and he became in charge of Tukaharaguchi of the Tanba Kaido Road, as Sanin Chinbu-sotoku (the general of placating Sanin).</e>
<cmt>洋式練兵中隊長→company commander of the Western style military drill court「山陰鎮撫総督」→Sanin Chinbu-sotoku (the general of placating Sanin)用語集にある「山陰道鎮撫総督」の訳を参考にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, he was assigned to be a company commander of the Western style military drill court as well as a Junior Councillor of the Ayabe Domain, and he became in charge of Tukaharaguchi of the Tanba Kaido Road, as Sanin Chinbu-sotoku (the general of placating Sanin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of the same year, he was assigned to be a company commander of the Western style military drill court as well as a Junior Councillor of the Ayabe Domain, and he became in charge of Tukaharaguchi of the Tanba Kaido Road, as Sanin Chinbu-sotoku (the general of placating Sanin).</e>
<cmt>dateを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>入塾、文部省出仕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering a private school and serving at the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering a private school and serving at the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering a private school and serving at the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>明治3年（1870年）2月に川本幸民の私塾に入学し、閉校までの数ヶ月間、教えを受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1870, he entered Koumin KAWAMOTO&apos;s private school and studied there for several months until the school closed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870, he entered Koumin KAWAMOTO&apos;s private school and studied there for several months until the school closed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1870, he entered Koumin KAWAMOTO&apos;s private school and studied there for several months until the school closed.</e>
<cmt>dateを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同年11月には権少参事の職を退き、翌年2月に学校法人慶應義塾に入塾して英語などを学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, he retired from a Junior Councillor, and entered Keio Gijuku (Keio University) in February of the following year and studied English and other subjects there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, he retired as Junior Councillor, and entered Keio Gijuku (Keio University) in February of the following year and studied English and other subjects there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of the same year, he retired as Junior Councillor, and entered the Gakko Hojin Keio Gijuku in March of the following year and studied English and other subjects there.</e>
<cmt>dateを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この頃から隆一と名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started calling himself Ryuichi around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started calling himself Ryuichi around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started calling himself Ryuichi around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>明治5年（1872年）4月に文部省に十一等出仕し大学南校の監事、同9月には大学東校事務主任となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1872, he started working for the Ministry of Education as the 11th class, and became the inspector of Daigaku Nanko (the predecessor of the University of Tokyo) and an office manager at Daigaku Toko (the Eastern College of the University).</e>
<cmt>「十一等」がわからず、直訳で「the 11th class」としました。「監事」の訳がわからず、辞書に載っていた「inspector」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1872, he started working for the Ministry of Education as the eleventh class, and became the inspector of Daigaku Nanko (the predecessor of the University of Tokyo) and an office manager at Daigaku Toko (the Eastern College of the University).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1872, he started working for the Ministry of Education as the eleventh class, and became the inspector of Daigaku Nanko (the predecessor of the University of Tokyo) and an office manager at Daigaku Toko (the Eastern College of the University).</e>
<cmt>dateを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>当時、国内の教育予算のうち40％弱が海外に派遣されていた260名の留学費用に充てられており、文部省としては彼らの留学を打ち切ってその費用で外国人教師（お雇い外国人）を招聘することを考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, 40 percent of the national budget for education went into the overseas education expense of 260 people dispatched abroad, and the Ministry of Education was thinking of aborting their overseas education and using the expense to invite foreign teachers (foreign residents in Japan employed to teach new techniques).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, fourty percent of the national budget for education went into the overseas education expense of 260 people dispatched abroad, and the Ministry of Education was thinking of aborting their overseas education and using the expense to invite foreign teachers (foreign residents in Japan employed to teach new techniques).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, fourty percent of the national budget for education went into the overseas education expense of 260 people dispatched abroad, and the Ministry of Education was thinking of aborting their overseas education and using the expense to invite foreign teachers (foreign residents in Japan employed to teach new techniques).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>留学生は薩長土肥の高官や明治維新の功績者の子弟が中心であり、特権的な留学による身分の固定化への危惧や優秀な学生の機会獲得のため、九鬼は文部省の方針に積極的に賛同していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since people studying abroad were mostly the children of high officers from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa and Hizen, or the children of people who made a great contribution to the Meiji Restoration, Kuki strongly agreed to the government policy in order to prevent the social classes from cementing due to the privileged overseas education as well as to provide opportunities to all gifted students.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since people studying abroad were mostly the children of high officers from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa and Hizen, or the children of people who made a great contribution to the Meiji Restoration, Kuki strongly agreed to the government policy in order to prevent the social classes from cementing due to privileged overseas education as well as to provide opportunities to all gifted students.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since people studying abroad were mostly the children of high officers from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa and Hizen, or the children of people who made a great contribution to the Meiji Restoration, Kuki strongly agreed to the government policy in order to prevent the social classes from cementing due to privileged overseas education as well as to provide opportunities to all gifted students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>このため、現地で留学生の実態調査と帰国の説明・説得にあたるため九鬼は明治6年（1873年）に渡欧している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, Kuki went to Europe in 1873 in order to see the actual situation of overseas students as well as to explain and convince them into coming back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Kuki went to Europe in 1873 in order to see the actual situation of overseas students as well as to explain and convince them to come back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Kuki went to Europe in 1873 in order to see the actual situation of overseas students as well as to explain and convince them to come back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>当時の留学生の中には井上毅、井上和郎などもおり当初は強い反発を受けたが、中江篤介（後の中江兆民）の理解などもあって最終的に全員の承諾を得ることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kowashi INOUE and Kazuro INOUE, who were studying abroad at that time, showed strong oppositions at first, however, Tokusuke NAKAE (later, Choumin NAKAE) understood the situation, leading to the consent of everyone in the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kowashi INOUE and Kazuro INOUE, who were studying abroad at that time, showed strong opposition at first, however, Tokusuke NAKAE (later, Choumin NAKAE) understood the situation, leading to the consent of everyone in the end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kowashi INOUE and Kazuro INOUE, who were studying abroad at that time, showed strong opposition at first, however, Tokusuke NAKAE (later, Choumin NAKAE) understood the situation, leading to the consent of everyone in the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、制度変更後の第一回国費留学生には政治家となった鳩山和夫、外交官となった小村寿太郎などの人材がおり、結果的に九鬼の目標は達成されたと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first government-sponsored overseas students after the revision of the system were Kazuo HATOYAMA who became a statesman and Jutaro KOMURA who became a diplomat, which shows that Kuki eventually achieved his goal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first government-sponsored overseas students after the revision of the system were Kazuo HATOYAMA who became a statesman and Jutaro KOMURA who became a diplomat, which shows that Kuki eventually achieved his goal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first government-sponsored overseas students after the revision of the system included Kazuo HATOYAMA who became a statesman and Jutaro KOMURA who became a diplomat, which shows that Kuki eventually achieved his goal.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>文部省での昇進</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promotion in the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promotion in the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Promotion in the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>説得の成功もあり、帰国後の明治7年（1874年）4月には文部少丞となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to his success in convincing the overseas students, he became Shojo (Junior Secretary) of the Ministry of Education in 1874 after he came back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to his success in convincing the overseas students, he became Shojo (Junior Secretary) of the Ministry of Education in 1874 after he came back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his success in convincing the overseas students, he became Shojo (Junior Secretary) of the Ministry of Education in 1874 after he came back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに明治9年（1876年）4月には奏任官である文部大丞・一等法制官に、翌・明治10年（1877年）年1月には文部大書記官・太政官大書記官に昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1876, he was promoted to Soninkan (a senior officer originally selected as a candidate by the Prime Minister), a Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Education as well as the first class legal system officer, and in January 1877, the next year, he was promoted to the Great Secretary of the Ministry of Education as well as the secretary of Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>「法制官」→legal system officer</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1876, he was promoted to Soninkan (a senior officer originally selected as a candidate by the Prime Minister), a Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Education as well as the first class legal system officer, and in January 1877, the next year, he was promoted to the Great Secretary of the Ministry of Education as well as the secretary of Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1876, he was promoted to Soninkan (a senior officer originally selected as a candidate by the Prime Minister), a Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Education as well as the first class legal system officer, and in January 1877, the following year, he was promoted to the Great Secretary of the Ministry of Education as well as the secretary of Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>10月には翌年のパリ万国博覧会 (1878年)のため派遣され、明治12年（1879年）5月に帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he was sent to Paris for the Paris World Exposition which was going to be held in the following year (1878), and came back to Japan in May 1879.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he was sent to Paris for the Paris World Exposition which was going to be held in the following year (1878), and came back to Japan in May 1879.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he was sent to Paris for the Paris World Exposition which was going to be held in the following year (1878), and came back to Japan in May 1879.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この渡仏中に博覧会副総裁の松方正義と出会い、以後交流が深まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his stay in France, he met Masayoshi MATSUKATA, the vice-director of the exhibition, and since then their relationship grew.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his stay in France, he met Masayoshi MATSUKATA, the vice-director of the exhibition, and since then their relationship grew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his stay in France, he met Masayoshi MATSUKATA, the vice-director of the exhibition, and since then their relationship grew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>また、フランスで西洋美術や美術行政に触れたことがきっかけでこの分野への関心を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was exposed to western art and its art administration in France, he became interested in those fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was exposed to western art and its art administration in France, he became interested in those fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was exposed to western art and its art administration in France, he became interested in those fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この後にアーネスト・フェノロサや岡倉天心と面識を持ち、その美術研究の支援者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he met Ernest Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA, and started supporting their art research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he met Ernest Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA, and started supporting their art research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he met Ernest Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA, and started supporting their art research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>後援を受けたフェノロサらは京都や奈良をはじめ全国各地で寺社などにある文化財の調査を効率的に進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fenollosa, with Kuki&apos;s support, effectively conducted the investigation on the cultural properties in the temples or other places in Kyoto, Nara, and all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fenollosa, with Kuki&apos;s support, effectively conducted the investigation on the cultural properties in the temples or other places in Kyoto, Nara, and all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fenollosa, with Kuki&apos;s support, effectively conducted the investigation on the cultural properties in the temples and shrines or other places of all over Japan including Kyoto and Nara.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>明治13年（1880年）に文部少輔（現在の文部省事務次官）となり、同11月には内国勧業博覧会の審査副長および議官に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1880, he became Shoyu (a Junior Assistant Minister) of the Ministry of Education (present Deputy Secretary of the Ministry of Education), and in November of the same year, he became the vice chief of audition and the councilor of the National Industrial Exhibition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1880, he became Shoyu (a Junior Assistant Minister) of the Ministry of Education (present Deputy Secretary of the Ministry of Education), and in November of the same year, he became the vice chief of audition and the councilor of the National Industrial Exhibition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1880, he became Shoyu of the Ministry of Education, and in November of the same year, he became the vice chief of audition and the councilor of the National Industrial Exhibition.</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>藩閥の力が強力な当時では、小藩出身の人物の出世としては珍しいほどの速さである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the domain cliques had strong power at that time, it was rare for a person from a small domain to be promoted that quickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the domain cliques had strong power at that time, it was rare for a person from a small domain to be promoted that quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the domain cliques had strong power at that time, it was rare for a person from a small domain to be promoted that quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>文部卿（現在の文部大臣）の河野敏鎌の行政への関心が薄かったこともあり、「九鬼の文部省」と呼ばれるほどの権勢を振るった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Mombukyo (the chief of Ministry of Education [present, the Minister of Education]), Togama KONO was not very interested in administration, Kuki dominated the Ministry of Education and it was called &apos;Kuki&apos;s Ministry of Education&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Mombukyo (the chief of Ministry of Education [present, the Minister of Education]), Togama KONO was not very interested in administration, Kuki dominated the Ministry of Education and it was called &apos;Kuki&apos;s Ministry of Education.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Monbukyo (the chief of Ministry of Education [present, the Minister of Education]), Togama KONO was not very interested in administration, Kuki dominated the Ministry of Education and it was called &apos;Kuki&apos;s Ministry of Education.&apos;</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>明治十四年の政変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>翌・明治14年（1881年）に自由民権運動に歯止めをかけようとした伊藤博文らにより、いわゆる明治十四年の政変が起き、大隈重信が政府から追放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, 1881, in order to stop the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, Hirobumi ITO and others initiated Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881) and expelled Shigenobu OKUMA from the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, 1881, in order to stop the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, Hirobumi ITO and others initiated Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881) and expelled Shigenobu OKUMA from the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, 1881, in order to stop the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, Hirobumi ITO and others initiated Meiji juyonen no seihen and expelled Shigenobu OKUMA from the government.</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この際に、大隈や福澤諭吉が藩閥政府に代わる内閣を組織しようとしていたとの疑惑から、福澤の影響が強い慶應義塾出身の官僚が多数官を辞することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, due to the suspicion that Okuma and Yukichi FUKUZAWA were trying to set up a new cabinet to replace the han-dominated government, many government officials who graduated from Keio Gijuku and were greatly influenced by Fukuzawa left their positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, due to the suspicion that Okuma and Yukichi FUKUZAWA were trying to set up a new cabinet to replace the han-dominated government, many government officials who graduated from Keio Gijuku and were greatly influenced by Fukuzawa left their positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, due to the suspicion that Okuma and Yukichi FUKUZAWA were trying to set up a new cabinet to replace the han-dominated government, many government officials who graduated from Keio Gijuku and were greatly influenced by Fukuzawa left their positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この中には犬養毅、尾崎行雄などが含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuyoshi INUKAI and Yukio OZAKI were included in those government officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuyoshi INUKAI and Yukio OZAKI were included in those government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuyoshi INUKAI and Yukio OZAKI were included in those government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし九鬼は彼らと一線を画して文部省に残り、福澤の文明開化主義に反対する伝統主義的な教育政策の実施者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kuki, holding the line against them, stayed in the Ministry of Education, and tried to implement the education policy based on the traditionalism which was against the Fukuzawa&apos;s idea of civilization and enlightenment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kuki, holding the line against them, stayed in the Ministry of Education, and tried to implement the education policy based on the traditionalism which was against the Fukuzawa&apos;s idea of civilization and enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kuki, holding the line against them, stayed in the Ministry of Education, and tried to implement the education policy based on the traditionalism which was against the Fukuzawa&apos;s idea of civilization and enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このため九鬼と福澤の関係は極度に緊張し、後に福澤の会合への招待状を誤って九鬼に送った事務担当者に対する注意の中で、『九鬼の存在は座上に犬ころがいるようなものだ』という過激な表現を福澤が用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the relationship between Kuki and Fukuzawa became extremely tense, and when a clerical officer sent the invitation of Fukizawa&apos;s meeting to Kuki by mistake, Fukuzawa warn the officer by using the following rabid expressions: &quot;Having Kuki in the meeting is the same as having a stupid dog in the meeting&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the relationship between Kuki and Fukuzawa became extremely tense, and when a clerical officer sent the invitation of Fukizawa&apos;s meeting to Kuki by mistake, Fukuzawa warn the officer by using the following rabid expressions: &quot;Having Kuki in the meeting is the same as having a stupid dog in the meeting..&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the relationship between Kuki and Fukuzawa became extremely tense, and when a clerical officer sent an invitation of Fukizawa&apos;s meeting to Kuki by mistake, Fukuzawa warn the officer by using the following rabid expressions: &quot;Having Kuki in the meeting is the same as having a stupid dog in the meeting.&quot;</e>
<cmt>spacing, grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>なお、最終的には九鬼が福澤に謝罪する形で両者の間に和解が成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuki, in the end, apologized to Fukuzawa, leading to their reconciliation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuki, in the end, apologized to Fukuzawa, leading to their reconciliation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuki, in the end, apologized to Fukuzawa, leading to their reconciliation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>文部省退官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retirement from the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement from the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retirement from the Ministry of Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>明治15年（1882年）12月に文部卿となった大木喬任は九鬼への信頼が弱く、翌年に強力な支持者であった岩倉具視が亡くなると文部省での九鬼の権勢は弱まった、と三宅雪嶺は語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsurei MIYAKE mentioned that Kuki lost his power in the Ministry of Education since Takato OKI, who became Mombukyo in December 1882, did not trust Kuki very much, and his great supporter Tomomi IWAKURA died the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setsurei MIYAKE mentioned that Kuki lost his power in the Ministry of Education since Takato OKI, who became Mombukyo in December 1882, did not trust Kuki very much, and his great supporter Tomomi IWAKURA died the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsurei MIYAKE mentioned that Kuki lost his power in the Ministry of Education since Takato OKI, who became Monbukyo in December 1882, did not trust Kuki very much, and his great supporter Tomomi IWAKURA died the following year.</e>
<cmt>spelling,grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>さらに明治17年（1884年）、西洋化を進める伊藤博文の方針で森有礼が初代文部大臣に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, due to Hirobumi ITO who was promoting the westernization of Japan, Arinori MORI became the first Minister of Education in 1884.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, due to Hirobumi ITO who was promoting the westernization of Japan, Arinori MORI became the first Minister of Education in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, due to Hirobumi ITO who was promoting the westernization of Japan, Arinori MORI became the first Minister of Education in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>そのため、元田永孚とともに儒学的な指向だった九鬼は同年5月に文部省を去り、特命全権公使としてワシントンD.C.に赴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, Nagazane MOTODA and Kuki, whose ideals were Confucianist, left the Ministry of Education in May of the same year, and Kuki went to Washington, D.C. as the envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, Nagazane MOTODA and Kuki, whose ideals were Confucianist, left the Ministry of Education in May of the same year, and Kuki went to Washington, D.C. as the envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, Nagazane MOTODA and Kuki, whose ideals were Confucianist, left the Ministry of Education in May of the same year, and Kuki went to Washington, D.C. as the envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>ワシントンでは公使館の客間に数百幅の日本画を飾って日本美術を紹介し、また古美術品の海外流出防止の観点から国宝保存を文部省や宮内省に進言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Washington, D.C., he displayed a few hundred Japanese paintings in the guest room to introduce Japanese art, and also proposed the Ministry of Education that the antiquities should be preserved as national treasures in order to prevent them from going to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>「数百幅」を「数百個」と解釈して訳しました。ここでの「幅」が、個数ではなく、「布の幅を計る単位(a unit to measure the width of cloth [approx. 36 cm])」ですと、絵にしては長すぎる気がしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Washington, D.C., he displayed a few hundred Japanese paintings in the guest room to introduce Japanese art, and also proposed the Ministry of Education that the antiquities should be preserved as national treasures in order to prevent them from going to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Washington, D.C., he displayed a few hundreds of Japanese paintings in the guest room in order to introduce Japanese art, and also proposed the Ministry of Education that the antiquities should be preserved as national treasures in order to prevent them from going to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この背景には以前から交流のあったアーネスト・フェノロサの意見があったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ernest Fenollosa, whom Kuki had known for some time, seems to have suggested this to Kuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ernest Fenollosa, whom Kuki had known for some time, seems to have suggested this to Kuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ernest Fenollosa, whom Kuki had known for some time, seems to have suggested this to Kuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>明治20年（1887年）、ヨーロッパでの視察を終えたフェノロサと岡倉天心がアメリカに立ち寄り、数年ぶりに再開している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1887, he met Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA again for the first time in years, when they had completed the inspection in Europe and stopped in America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1887, he met Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA again for the first time in years, when they had completed the inspection in Europe and stopped in America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1887, he met Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA again for the first time in years, when they had completed the inspection in Europe and stopped in America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>九鬼の妻・初子が妊娠していたため天心が付き添いとして一緒に帰国し、10月に横浜港に着いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kuki&apos;s wife, Hatusko was pregnant, Tenshin left with her for Japan and arrived at Yokohama Port in October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kuki&apos;s wife, Hatusko was pregnant, Tenshin left with her for Japan and arrived at Yokohama Port in October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kuki&apos;s wife, Hatsuko was pregnant, Tenshin left with her for Japan and arrived at Yokohama Port in October.</e>
<cmt>spellingを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>帰国後、明治21年（1888年）2月15日に生まれたのが後の九鬼周造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After she came back to Japan, Shuzo KUKI was born on February 15, 1888.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After she came back to Japan, Shuzo KUKI was born on February 15, 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After she came back to Japan, Shuzo KUKI was born on February 15, 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>九鬼自身も同年2月に帰国している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuki came back to Japan in February of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuki came back to Japan in February of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuki came back to Japan in February of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>宮内省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>帰国後、九鬼は宮内省の図書頭に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After coming back to Japan, Kuki became Zusho no kami (the Director of the Bureau of Drawings and Books) at Kunaisho (the Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning to Japan, Kuki became Zusho no kami (the Director of the Bureau of Drawings and Books) at Kunaisho (the Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to Japan, Kuki became Zusho no kami (the Director of the Bureau of Drawings and Books) at Kunaisho (the Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>ここで臨時全国宝物取調掛を設置して自ら委員長となり、旧知のフェノロサや天心が委員を務めて文化財の調査・保護に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, he set up a bureau for provisional national inspection of treasure where he became its chairman and Fenollosa and Tenshin became its members, to inspect and preserve cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, he set up a bureau for provisional national inspection of treasure where he became its chairman and Fenollosa and Tenshin became its members, to inspect and preserve cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, he set up a bureau for provisional national inspection of treasure where he became its chairman and Fenollosa and Tenshin became its members, to inspect and preserve cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>明治21年5月から9月と、10月から翌年2月の2回にわたり、フェノロサを伴って近畿地方の京都府・大阪府・奈良県・滋賀県・和歌山県を訪れ、社寺や美術品の調査を行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From May to September in 1888 and from October in 1888 to February of the next year, he visited Kyoto Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Shiga Prefecture and Wakayama Prefecture in the Kinki area with Fenollosa to investigate the temples and the arts there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From May to September in 1888 and from October in 1888 to February of the next year, he visited Kyoto Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Shiga Prefecture and Wakayama Prefecture in the Kinki area with Fenollosa to investigate the temples and the arts there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From May to September in 1888 and from October in 1888 to February of the next year, he visited Kyoto Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Shiga Prefecture and Wakayama Prefecture in the Kinki area with Fenollosa to investigate the shrines and temples and the arts there.</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>翌・明治22年（1889年）に東京国立博物館・京都国立博物館・奈良国立博物館に帝国博物館（現在の国立博物館）が設立されると、初代総長となり、明治33年（1900年）まで務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Imperial Museum (present, National Museum) was established in the Tokyo National Museum, the Kyoto National Museum and the Nara National Museum in 1889, he became the first chief of the Imperial Museum and served until 1900.</e>
<cmt>「東京国立博物館・京都国立博物館・奈良国立博物館に帝国博物館（現在の国立博物館）が設立されると」の部分は、「東京、京都、奈良に帝国博物館（現在の国立博物館）が設立されると」の間違いではないかと思いましたが、そのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Imperial Museum (present, National Museum) was established in the Tokyo National Museum, the Kyoto National Museum and the Nara National Museum in 1889, he became the first chief of the Imperial Museum and served until 1900.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Imperial Museums (present, National Museum) were established in Tokyo, Kyoto and Nara in 1889, he became the first chief of the Imperial Museum and served until 1900.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>同年には九鬼の支援した東京美術学校（現・東京藝術大学美術学部）も設立され、フェノロサが校長となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, the Tokyo School of Fine Arts, which Kuki supported, was established and Fenollosa became the principal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, the Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Faculty of Fine Arts of Tokyo University of Arts), which Kuki supported, was established and Fenollosa became the principal.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, the Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Faculty of Fine Arts of Tokyo University of Arts), which Kuki supported, was established and Fenollosa became the principal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>明治23年（1890年）に上野で開催された第3回内国勧業博覧会では審査総長を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the 3rd National Industrial Exhibition held in Ueno in 1890, he was the chief of audition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the third National Industrial Exhibition held in Ueno in 1890, he was the chief of audition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the third National Industrial Exhibition held in Ueno in 1890, he was the chief of audition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>同年には帝室技芸員の制定に携わり、また帝国議会の設立に際して貴族院 (日本)議員に任命されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he was involved with the establishment of Teishitsu Gigeiin (Imperial art experts), and he was also appointed to the member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) when the Imperial Diet was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he was involved with the establishment of Teishitsu Gigeiin (Imperial art experts), and he was also appointed to the member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) when the Imperial Diet was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was involved with the establishment of Teishitsu Gigeiin (Imperial art experts), and he was also appointed to the member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) when the Imperial Diet was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>翌・明治24年（1891年）4月、農商務大臣・陸奥宗光の命令で2年後のシカゴ万国博覧会 (1893年)の準備組織作りを行ない、実質的な責任者である副総裁となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1891, he was assigned by the Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, Munemitsu MUTSU, to create an organization for the preparation of the World&apos;s Columbian Exposition which was going to be held two years later, and became the vice-director, who was practically in charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1891, he was assigned by the Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, Munemitsu MUTSU, to create an organization for the preparation of the World&apos;s Columbian Exposition which was going to be held two years later, and became the vice-director, who was practically in charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1891, the following year, he was assigned by the Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, Munemitsu MUTSU, to create an organization for the preparation of the World&apos;s Columbian Exposition (1893) which was going to be held two years later, and became the vice-director, who was practically in charge.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>総選挙支援</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supporting general election</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supporting general election</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supporting general election</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>明治25年（1892年）の第2回衆議院議員総選挙では総理大臣・松方正義の依頼を受けて1月から2月まで近畿地方・瀬戸内地方で政府系候補の支援活動を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the 2nd general election of members of the House of Representatives held in 1892, he was requested by the Prime Minister, Masayoshi MATSUKATA to support the government-affiliated candidates in Kinki area and Setouchi area from January to February.</e>
<cmt>33</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the second general election of members of the House of Representatives held in 1892, he was requested by the Prime Minister, Masayoshi MATSUKATA to support the government-affiliated candidates in Kinki area and Setouchi area from January to February.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the second general election of members of the House of Representatives held in 1892, he was requested by the Prime Minister, Masayoshi MATSUKATA to support the government-affiliated candidates in Kinki area and Setouchi area from January to February.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>この時の身分は渡米時から続いていた特命全権公使で、同年9月にこれを免ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His position at that time was the envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary, which he had since he went to America, but he was excused from it in September of the same year.</e>
<cmt>ここでの「身分」は、「social status」ではなく、「position」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His position at that time was the envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary, and had since he gone to America, but he was excused from it in September of the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His position at that time was the envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary which he had been since going to America, but he was excused from it in September of the same year.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>この選挙では品川弥二郎や白根専一が強力な選挙干渉を行ない、警察官に武力行使を命じて高知県などで死者が出たことが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is well known that Yajiro SHINAGAWA and Senichi SHIRANE strongly interfered this election and ordered police officers to use force, causing death in Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well known that Yajiro SHINAGAWA and Senichi SHIRANE strongly interfered this election and ordered police officers to use force, causing death in Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is well known that Yajiro SHINAGAWA and Senichi SHIRANE strongly interfered this election and ordered police officers to use force, causing death in Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>九鬼も警察官への命令を下しているが、政党系候補の支援をする壮士の取締りなど、相対的に消極的な方針を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Kuki&apos;s plan was relatively moderate, like he ordered police officers to control Soshi (political activists) supporting the government-affiliated candidates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Kuki&apos;s plan was relatively moderate, like he ordered police officers to control Soshi (political activists) supporting government-affiliated candidates.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Kuki&apos;s plan was relatively moderate, like he ordered police officers to control Soshi (political activists) supporting government-affiliated candidates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>むしろ政府系候補者の一本化や、三井家・住友家など財閥、美術調査で面識を得た本願寺への働きかけ、資金の効率的な運用などに力を注いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, he focused his energy to unify the government-affiliated candidates; to ask for support from Zaibatsu (company syndicates) including the Mitsui Family and the Sumitomo Family as well as from Hongan-ji Temple which he had gotten to know during the art investigation; and to manage the budget effectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, he focused his energy to unify the government-affiliated candidates; to ask for support from Zaibatsu (company syndicates) including the Mitsui Family and the Sumitomo Family as well as from Hongan-ji Temple which he had gotten to know during the art investigation; and to manage the budget effectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, he focused his energy to unify the government-affiliated candidates; to ask for support from Zaibatsu (company syndicates) including the Mitsui family and the Sumitomo family as well as from Hongan-ji Temple which he had gotten to know during the art investigation; and to manage the budget effectively.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>法的な根拠を持たない身分での出張だったため、京都府知事の北垣国道が独立に行動するなどした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kuki took a business trip without a legal position, the governor of Kyoto Prefecture, Kunimichi KITAGAKI, went a different way from Kuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処ここでの「身分」は、「social status」ではなく、「position」と訳しました。「京都府知事の北垣国道が独立に行動するなどしたが」の意味がよくわからないため、「京都府知事の北垣国道が九鬼とは別行動した」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kuki took a business trip without a legal position, the governor of Kyoto Prefecture, Kunimichi KITAGAKI, went a different way from Kuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kuki took a business trip without a legal position, the governor of Kyoto Prefecture, Kunimichi KITAGAKI, went a different way from Kuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>結果として九鬼の活動した地方では奈良県の4増をはじめ政府系候補が10議席増加し、自由党 (日本)の大物である大井憲太郎を落選に追い込むなどの成果を収めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, however, the number of seats of government-affiliated candidates increased by 10 seats in the areas where Kuki conducted election campaigns, including 4 seats in Nara, and Kuki also succeeded in making a big-shot politician from the Liberal Party (Japan), Kentaro Oi, lose the election.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, however, the number of seats of government-affiliated candidates increased by ten seats in the areas where Kuki conducted election campaigns, including four seats in Nara, and Kuki also succeeded in making a big-shot politician from the Liberal Party (Japan), Kentaro Oi, lose the election.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the number of seats of government-affiliated candidates increased by ten seats in the areas where Kuki conducted election campaigns, including four seats in Nara, and Kuki also succeeded in making a big-shot politician from the Liberal Party (Japan), Kentaro OI, lose the election.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし選挙後は大臣候補にすら名前が上らなかったため松方と袂を分かち、伊藤博文に接近していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the election, he was not even selected as a candidate for a minister, and thus he left Matsukata and started befriending Hirobumi ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the election, he was not even selected as a candidate for a minister, and thus he left Matsukata and started befriending Hirobumi ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the election, he was not even selected as a candidate for a minister, and thus he left Matsukata and started befriending Hirobumi ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>栄達と晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Advancement in social status and later years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Advancement in social status and later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Advancement in social status and later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>明治26年（1893年）のシカゴ万国博覧会では、九鬼や天心の意向から日本の展示は日本画を中心とした伝統的なものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the World&apos;s Columbian Exposition held in 1893, due to the wishes of Kuki and Tenshin, the exhibition of Japan was traditional and focused on Nihonga (Japanese-style Painting).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the World&apos;s Columbian Exposition held in 1893, due to the wishes of Kuki and Tenshin, the exhibition of Japan was traditional and focused on Nihonga (Japanese-style Painting).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the World&apos;s Columbian Exposition held in 1893, due to the wishes of Kuki and Tenshin, the exhibition of Japan was traditional and focused on Nihonga (Japanese-style Painting).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>日本館として平等院鳳凰堂を模した鳳凰殿を建て、工芸品の輸出を積極的に促進したことが前回までとの大きな違いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was greatly different from the previous one in that a Hoo Palace (Phoenix Palace) copying Hoo-do Hall (Phoenix Hall) of Byodoin Temple was built as a Japanese pavilion, and the exportation of artifacts was promoted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It greatly differed from the previous one in that a Hoo Palace (Phoenix Palace) copy of Hoo-do Hall (Phoenix Hall) of Byodoin Temple was built as a Japanese pavilion, and the exportation of artifacts was promoted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It greatly differed from the previous one in that a Hoo Palace (Phoenix Palace) copy of Hoo-do Hall (Phoenix Hall) of Byodoin Temple was built as a Japanese pavilion, and the exportation of artifacts was promoted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>明治28年（1895年）4月に京都で開かれた第4回内国勧業博覧会では前回に続いて審査総長となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the 4th National Industrial Exhibition held in Kyoto in April 1895, he again became the chief of audition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the 4th National Industrial Exhibition held in Kyoto in April 1895, he again became the chief of audition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the fourth National Industrial Exhibition held in Kyoto in April 1895, he again became the chief of audition.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この際、黒田清輝が出品した裸体画・「朝妝」が問題視されたが、九鬼の判断で展示が許可されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, a nude portrait painted by Seiki KURODA, &apos;Chosho (Le Lever)&apos; became a subject of discussion, but Kuki permitted the exhibition of the portrait.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a nude portrait painted by Seiki KURODA, &apos;Chosho (Le Lever)&apos; became a subject of discussion, but Kuki permitted the exhibition of the portrait.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a nude portrait painted by Seiki KURODA, &apos;Chosho&apos; (Le Lever) became a subject of discussion, but Kuki permitted the exhibition of the portrait.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>同年6月には第2次伊藤内閣の下で枢密院 (日本)宮中顧問官に任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year, under the Second Ito Cabinet, he was appointed to the Imperial Court Councilor of Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>「枢密院 (日本)」の「日本」を訳する必要はない気もしましたが、そのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, under the Second Ito Cabinet, he was appointed to Imperial Court Councilor of Sumitsu-in (Privy Council) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year, under the Second Ito Cabinet, he was appointed to Imperial Court Councilor of Sumitsu-in.</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>明治29年（1896年）、それまでの功績を称えて男爵に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To honor great achievement, he was conferred baron in 1896.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To honor great achievement, he was conferred baron in 1896.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To honor great achievement, he was conferred baron in 1896.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>翌年には古社寺保存法の制定に加わり、同法により日本で初めて文化財が指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, he was involved with the establishment of the law for preserving old temples and shrines, and this law specified the first cultural property in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, he was involved with the establishment of the law for preserving old temples and shrines, and this law specified the first cultural property in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, he was involved with the establishment of the law for preserving old temples and shrines, which specified the first cultural property in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>明治31年（1898年）にいわゆる美術学校騒動が起き、岡倉天心と九鬼の妻・初子の不倫が公になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1898, so-called the Turmoil of the Art School occurred, which disclosed the affair between Tenshin OKAKURA and Hatsuko, Kuki&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>美術学校騒動→the Turmoil of the Art School＜定訳不明＞</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1898, so-called the Turmoil of the Art School occurred, which disclosed the affair between Tenshin OKAKURA and Hatsuko, Kuki&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1898, so-called the Turmoil of the Art School occurred, which disclosed the affair between Tenshin OKAKURA and Hatsuko, Kuki&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>同年、天心は東京美術学校の校長や帝国博物館美術部長を辞任することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Tenshin resigned the principle of Tokyo School of Fine Arts as well as the director of the art department of the Imperial Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Tenshin resigned the principle of Tokyo School of Fine Arts as well as the directorship of the art department of the Imperial Museum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Tenshin resigned the principle of Tokyo School of Fine Arts as well as the directorship of the art department of the Imperial Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="72">
<j>明治33年（1900年）、初子との離婚が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900, he was divorced from Hatusko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1900, he was divorced from Hatusko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1900, he was divorced from Hatusko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>この後は主に美術行政に専念し、大正3年（1914年）に旧・有馬郡の役所を利用して自身の収蔵品を展示する三田博物館を設立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he devoted himself into the art administration, and in 1914, he founded the Sanda Museum by using the administrative institution of the old Arima county to store his own collections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he devoted himself into the art administration, and in 1914, he founded the Sanda Museum by using the administrative institution of the old Arima county to store his own collections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he devoted himself into the art administration, and in 1914, he founded the Sanda Museum by using the administrative institution of the old Arima County to store his own collections.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>大正9年（1920年）に議定官となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1920, he became Gijo-kan (an official post in Decoration Bureau).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1920, he became Gijo-kan (an official post in Decoration Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1920, he became Gijo-kan (an official post in Decoration Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>枢密顧問官と議定官を務めたまま昭和6年（1931年）8月18日に鎌倉で亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in Kamakura in August 1931 when he was serving as Gijo-kan as well as the Imperial Court Councilor of Sumitsu-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in Kamakura in August 1931 when he was serving as Gijo-kan as well as the Imperial Court Councilor of Sumitsu-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in Kamakura on August 18, 1931 while he was serving as Gijo-kan as well as the Imperial Court Councilor of Sumitsu-in.</e>
<cmt>date, grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>人柄など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>人格、趣味</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality and Hobbies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality and Hobbies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality and Hobbies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>性格は尊大で、容易にへりくだらないと評された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His was arrogant and did not condescend easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was arrogant and did not condescend easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was discribed to be arrogant and not to condescend easily.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>また女性との交遊も多く、これが夫人と岡倉天心の不倫の一因になったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also enjoyed sexual relations with many women, which is said to be one of the reasons his wife had an affair with Tenshin OKAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also enjoyed sexual relations with many women, which is said to be one of the reasons his wife had an affair with Tenshin OKAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also enjoyed sexual relations with many women, which is said to be one of the reasons why his wife had an affair with Tenshin OKAKURA.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>先述のように師である福澤諭吉からは酷評を受けるなど、人柄への評価はあまり芳しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His personality was considered not very good, as mentioned above: he received harsh criticism fromhis mentor, Yukichi FUKUZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His personality was considered not very good, as mentioned above: he received harsh criticism fromhis mentor, Yukichi FUKUZAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His personality was considered not to be very good as he received harsh criticism from his master, Yukichi FUKUZAWA as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>晩年は達磨を題材にした絵画を数百点収集し、自らもこれを好んで描いたが、人に所望されても謙遜して承諾することは少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later life, he collected hundreds of paintings about Dharma, and he also drew paintings by himself, but he was too modest to give his paintings to anyone when he was asked.</e>
<cmt>「達磨」の訳が用語集で「Dharma」となっていたので、それを使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later life, he collected hundreds of paintings about Dharma, and he also drew paintings by himself, but he was too modest to give his paintings to anyone when he was asked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later life, he collected hundreds of paintings about Dharma, and he also favored to paint on them by himself, but he was too modest to give his paintings to anyone when he was asked.</e>
<cmt>grammerを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>また、史記の李斯伝から「成海」という雅号を名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used Gago (a pseudonym), &apos;Narumi&apos; from Shiki (a Chinese history book), Rishi-den.</e>
<cmt>「李斯伝」→ Rishi-den＜定訳不明＞</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He used Gago (a pseudonym), &apos;Narumi&apos; from Shiki (a Chinese history book), Rishi-den.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He used Gago (a pseudonym), &apos;Narumi&apos; from Shiki (a Chinese history book), Rishi-den.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>岡倉天心との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship with Tenshin OKAKURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with Tenshin OKAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with Tenshin OKAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>天心も奔放な性格で知られ、人格面での相性は必ずしも良好でなかったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenshin&apos;s personality was also raffish, and it is thought that their personalities did not match.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenshin&apos;s personality was also raffish, and it is thought that their personalities did not match.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenshin&apos;s personality was also raffish, and it is thought that their personalities did not match.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>しかし、藩閥に属せないため得意分野を確立したい九鬼と、寺社などを相手に研究を進めるため権力の支援を必要とする天心の間では利害関係が完全に一致していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, their interests coincided: Kuki, who could not belong to any Zaibutus, wanted to establish his area of specialty and Tenshin needed someone with authority to conduct his research with temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, their interests coincided: Kuki, who could not belong to any Zaibutus, wanted to establish his area of specialty and Tenshin needed someone with authority to conduct his research with temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, their interests coincided: Kuki, who could not belong to any domain clique, wanted to establish his area of specialty and Tenshin needed someone with authority to conduct his research with temples.</e>
<cmt>termを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>さらに両者は共に人並み外れた能力を有しており、これが20年以上に渡る両者の関係を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, they had extraordinary prowess, which maintained their relationship for more than 20 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, they had extraordinary prowess, which maintained their relationship for more than twenty years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, they had extraordinary prowess, which maintained their relationship for more than twenty years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Okapia2(id:98589), 松浸史(id:78240), 0null0(id:582), Rambler(id:59491), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Point136(id:211299), Yuichiokubo(id:88759), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>