<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>熊沢蕃山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banzan KUMAZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banzan KUMAZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banzan KUMAZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>熊沢 蕃山（くまざわ ばんざん、元和 5年（1619年） － 元禄4年8月17日 (旧暦)（1691年9月9日））は江戸時代初期の陽明学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in 1619 and gone in 1691,- in detail, the date he was gone is August 17 by the lunar calendar (by the solar calendar, September 9) - Banzan KUMAZAWA was a neo-Confucianist (a scholar of the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in 1619 and died in 1691,- specifically he died on August 17 by the lunar calendar (by the solar calendar, September 9) - Banzan KUMAZAWA was a neo-Confucianist (a scholar of the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banzan KUMAZAWA (1619 - September 9, 1691) was a scholar of Yomeigaku neo-Confucianism (the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記を原文に合せました。新暦のみ記載しました。陽明学者→scholar of Yomeigaku neo-Confucianismに訂正しました。従って、括弧説明内も訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は伯継（しげつぐ）、字は了介（一説には良介）、通称は次郎八・助右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was &quot;Shigetsugu,&quot; and his Chinese courtesy name was &quot;Ryosuke&quot; (in Chinese characters, &quot;了介,&quot; or - some say - &quot;良介&quot;), and his common name was &quot;Jirohachi,&quot; or &quot;Sukeemon.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was &quot;Shigetsugu,&quot; and his Chinese courtesy name was &quot;Ryosuke&quot; (in Chinese characters, &quot;了介,&quot; or - some say - &quot;良介&quot;), and his common name was &quot;Jirohachi,&quot; or &quot;Sukeemon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Shigetsugu, and his Chinese courtesy name was Ryosuke, and his common name was Jirohachi, or Sukeemon.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記は不要と考え、括弧書き削除しました。原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>生い立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京都稲荷（現・京都府京都市下京区）の浪人であった父・野尻藤兵衛一利と母・亀女の6人兄弟の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the oldest son of the mother &quot;Kamejo&quot; and the father &quot;NOJIRI Tobe Kazutoshi,&quot; who was a &quot;ronin&quot; (a masterless samurai) living in Kyoto Inari (the present Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the oldest son of his mother &quot;Kamejo&quot; and father &quot;NOJIRI Tobe Kazutoshi,&quot; who was a &quot;ronin&quot; (a masterless samurai) living in Kyoto Inari (the present Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the oldest son of his mother Kamejo and father Tobe Kazutoshi NOJIRI, who was a ronin (a masterless samurai) living in Kyoto Inari (the present Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。Tobe Kazutoshi NOJIRIに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幼名は左七郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was &quot;Sashichiro.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was &quot;Sashichiro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Sashichiro.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>8歳の時、母方の祖父、熊沢守久の養子となり熊沢姓を名乗ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When 8 years old, he was adopted by his maternal grandfather &quot;Morihisa KUMAZAWA,&quot; so he began to use his mother&apos;s family name &quot;KUMAZAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When 8 years old, he was adopted by his maternal grandfather &quot;Morihisa KUMAZAWA,&quot; so he began to use his mother&apos;s family name &quot;KUMAZAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When 8 years old, he was adopted by his maternal grandfather Morihisa KUMAZAWA, so he began to use his mother&apos;s family name KUMAZAWA.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>藤樹門下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until becoming a pupil of &quot;Toju NAKAE&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until becoming a pupil of &quot;Toju NAKAE&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until becoming a pupil of Toju NAKAE</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>寛永11年（1634年）池田輝政の女婿であった丹後国宮津藩主京極高広の紹介で、輝政の孫である備前国岡山藩主池田光政の児小姓役として出仕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1634, he was employed as &quot;Kogosho-yaku&quot; (the young samurai waiting for, and doing the chores of, the feudal lord) by Mitsumasa IKEDA (the feudal lord of the Bizen Province Okayama Clan ＆the grandson of Terumasa IKEDA) thanks to the introduction by Takahiro KYOGOKU (the son-in-law of Terumasa IKEDA ＆ the feudal lord of the Tango Province Miyazu Clan).</e>
<cmt>※「児小姓役（こごしょうやく）」の解説部分については「藩主のそばに控え、その雑用をこなした若い侍」（Wiki 「小姓」参照）と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1634, he was employed as &quot;Kogosho-yaku&quot; (a young samurai waiting for, and doing the chores of, the feudal lord) by Mitsumasa IKEDA (the feudal lord of the Bizen Province Okayama Clan ＆the grandson of Terumasa IKEDA) thanks to the introduction by Takahiro KYOGOKU (the son-in-law of Terumasa IKEDA ＆ the feudal lord of the Tango Province Miyazu Clan).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1634, he was employed as Kogoshoyaku (a young samurai waiting for, and doing the chores of, the feudal lord) by Mitsumasa IKEDA (the feudal lord of the Okayama Domain of Bizen Province and the grandson of Terumasa IKEDA) thanks to the introduction by Takahiro KYOGOKU (the son-in-law of Terumasa IKEDA and the feudal lord of the Miyazu Domain of Tango Province).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。ハイフン削除しました。＆→andOkayama Domain of Bizen Province、Miyazu Domain of Tango Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>寛永16年（1639年）島原の乱に参陣することを願い出たが受け入れられず、一旦は池田家を離れ、近江国桐原（現・滋賀県近江八幡市）の祖父の家へ戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He applied for the participation in suppressing the Shimabara Rebellion, only to be rejected, so in 1639, he once left the Ikeda family and returned to his grandfather&apos;s home in Kirihara, Omi Province (the present Omihachiman City, Saga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>※島原の乱は1638年に終わっているので、冒頭の「寛永16年（1639年）」は「池田家を離れ」にかかるものとして訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He applied to participate in suppressing the Shimabara Rebellion, only to be rejected, so in 1639, he once left the Ikeda family and returned to his grandfather&apos;s home in Kirihara, Omi Province (the present Omihachiman City, Saga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He applied to participate in suppressing the Shimabara Rebellion, only to be rejected, so in 1639, he once left the Ikeda family and returned to his grandfather&apos;s home in Kirihara, Omi Province (the present Omihachiman City, Saga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寛永19年（1642年）伊予国大洲藩を致仕し郷里の近江国小川村（現・滋賀県高島市）に帰郷していた中江藤樹の門下に入り陽明学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1642, he began to learn neo-Confucianism (based on the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) as a pupil of Toju NAKAE, who resigned from the Iyo Province Ozu Clan and returned to his home &quot;Ogawa-mura&quot; (Ogawa Village), Omi Province (the present Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1642, he began to learn neo-Confucianism (based on the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) as a pupil of Toju NAKAE, who resigned from Iyo Province Ozu Clan and returned to his home &quot;Ogawa-mura&quot; (Ogawa Village), Omi Province (the present Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1642, he began to learn neo-Confucianism (based on the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) as a pupil of Toju NAKAE, who resigned from Ozu Domain of Iyo Province and returned to his home Ogawa Village, Omi Province (the present Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Ozu Domain of Iyo Provinceとしました。&quot;Ogawa-mura&quot;、（）削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>岡山藩時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Years in the Okayama Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Years in the Okayama Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Years in the Okayama Domain</e>
<cmt>ClanをDomainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>正保2年（1645年）再び京極氏の口添えで岡山藩に出仕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1645, he was employed again by Mitsumasa IKEDA thanks to the recommendation by Takahiro KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>※「出仕する」は「大名に召しかかえられる」の意味なので、「岡山藩に出仕する」の部分は「光政に召しかかえられる」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1645, he was employed again by Mitsumasa IKEDA thanks to a recommendation by Takahiro KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1645, he was employed again by Mitsumasa IKEDA in Okayama Domain thanks to a recommendation by Takahiro KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>in Okayama Domain補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>光政は陽明学に傾倒していたため、藤樹の教えを受けていた蕃山を重用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsumasa was fascinated by neo-Confucianism (based on the teachings of Wang Yngming and his followers), so he gave Banzan, who was a pupil of neo-Confucianist Toju NAKAE, a senior position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsumasa was fascinated by neo-Confucianism (based on the teachings of Wang Yngming and his followers), so he gave Banzan, who was a pupil of neo-Confucianist Toju NAKAE, a senior position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsumasa was fascinated by neo-Confucianism, so he gave Banzan, who was a pupil of Toju NAKAE, a senior position.</e>
<cmt>既出のため括弧説明削除しました。neo-Confucianist 削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>寛永18年（1641年）全国に先駆けて開校した藩校「花畠教場」を中心に活動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banzan worked mainly at &quot;Hanabata Kyojo,&quot; which is the first clan school in Japan they opened in 1641.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banzan worked mainly at &quot;Hanabata Kyojo,&quot; which is the first clan school in Japan opened in 1641.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banzan worked mainly at &apos;Hanabata Kyojo,&apos; which is the first hanko (a domain school) in Japan opened in 1641.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。藩校→hanko (a domain school)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>正保4年（1647年）には側役、知行300石取りとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1647, he became &quot;Sobayaku&quot; (Secretary) of Mitsumasa IKEDA, so he was enfeoffed 300 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1647, he became &quot;Sobayaku&quot; (Secretary) of Mitsumasa IKEDA, and was enfeoffed 300 koku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1647, he became Sobayaku (Secretary) of Mitsumasa IKEDA, and was chigyo (enfeoffment) 300 koku.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。知行→chigyo (enfeoffment)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>慶安2年（1649年）には光政に随行し江戸に出府する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1649, he accompanied Mitsumasa to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1649, he accompanied Mitsumasa to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1649, he accompanied Mitsumasa to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>慶安3年（1650年）鉄砲組番頭、知行3,000石の上士に累進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1650, he was promoted even higher to the general manager of &quot;teppo-gumi&quot; (a group of harquebusiers), which was a &quot;joshi&quot; (a high-ranking samurai in the clan) being enfeoffed 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>※当時の鉄砲は火縄銃だったと解されますので、「鉄砲組」の解説部分にある「銃兵」も&quot;musketeers&quot;（マスケット銃兵）ではなく&quot;harquebusiers&quot;（火縄銃兵）としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1650, he was promoted even higher to the general manager of &quot;teppo-gumi&quot; (a group of harquebusiers), which was a &quot;joshi&quot; (a high-ranking samurai in the clan) being enfeoffed 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1650, he was promoted even higher to general manager of Teppo-gumi (a Group of musketeers), which was a joshi (a high-ranking samurai in the clan) being chigyo 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>知行→chigyo鉄砲組番頭→general manager of Teppo-gumi (a Group of musketeers)原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>慶安4年（1651年）庶民教育の場となる「花園会」の会約を起草し、これが蕃山の致仕後の寛文10年（1670年）日本初の庶民学校として開かれた「閑谷学校」の前身となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1651, he drafted the rules of &quot;Hanazono-kai&quot; (a circle for the education of the ordinary people), and this circle was the predecessor of &quot;Shizutani School,&quot; which was founded in 1670 - when Banzan already left the Okayama Clan - as the first shool in Japan that was open to the ordinary people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1651, he drafted the rules of &quot;Hanazono-kai&quot; (a circle for the education of the ordinary people), and this circle was the predecessor of &quot;Shizutani School,&quot; which was founded in 1670 - when Banzan already left the Okayama Clan - as the first shool in Japan that was open to ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1651, he drafted the rules of &apos;Hanazono-kai&apos; (a circle for the education of the ordinary people), and this circle was the predecessor of &apos;Shizutani School,&apos; which was founded in 1670 - when Banzan already left the Okayama Domain - as the first school in Japan that was open to ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>schoolスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。ClanをDomainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>承応3年（1654年）備前平野を襲った洪水と大飢饉の際、光政を補佐し飢民の救済に尽力する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1654, when a flood and a severe famine struck the the people living in Bizen Plain, Banzan assisted Mitsumasa in making every effort to help the starving.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1654, when a flood and severe famine struck people living in Bizen Plain, Banzan assisted Mitsumasa in making every effort to help those who were starving.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1654, when a flood and severe famine struck people living in Bizen Plain, Banzan assisted Mitsumasa in making every effort to help those who were starving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、津田永忠とともに光政の補佐役として岡山藩初期の藩政確立に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And along with Nagatada TSUDA, Banzan was engaged in establishing the the policy base of the Okayama Clan in the early Edo period as an assistant of Mitsumasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And along with Nagatada TSUDA, Banzan was engaged in establishing the policy base of the Okayama Clan in the early Edo period as an assistant of Mitsumasa.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And along with Nagatada TSUDA, Banzan was engaged in establishing the policy base of the Okayama Domain in the early Edo period as an assistant of Mitsumasa.</e>
<cmt>ClanをDomainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>零細農民の救済、治山治水等の土木事業により農業政策を充実させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banzan promoted the agricultural policy by helping small-scale peasants and by implementing construction work including the forestry and flood cotrol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banzan promoted agricultural policy by helping small-scale peasants and by implementing construction work including forestry and flood cotrol.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banzan promoted agricultural policy by helping small-scale peasants and by implementing construction work including forestry and flood control.</e>
<cmt>controlスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、大胆な藩政の改革は守旧派の家老らとの対立をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But his bold policy reform in the Okayama Clan caused the conflict with the conservative samurai including the &quot;karo&quot; (the chief retainer of the feudal lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But his bold reform policy in the Okayama Clan caused conflict with conservative samurai including the &quot;karo&quot; (the chief retainer of the feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But his bold reform policy in the Okayama Domain caused conflict with conservative samurai including the karo (the chief retainer of the feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>ClanをDomainに訂正しました。原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、江戸幕府が官学とする朱子学と対立する陽明学者である蕃山は、保科正之・林羅山らの批判を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And his thought (neo-Confucianism based on the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) was incompatible with the thought that was authorized by the Edo shogunate (also called neo-Confucianism, but based on the teachings of Zhu Xi and his followers), so Masayuki HOSHINA and Razan HAYASHI, both on the side of the establishment, criticized Banzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And his thought (neo-Confucianism based on the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) was incompatible with that which was authorized by the Edo shogunate (also called neo-Confucianism, but based on the teachings of Zhu Xi and his followers), so Masayuki HOSHINA and Razan HAYASHI, both on the side of the establishment, criticized Banzan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, Robert: &quot;both on the side of the establishment&quot; doesn&apos;t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And his thought (neo-Confucianism based on the teachings of Wang Yangming and his followers) was incompatible with that which was authorized by the Edo shogunate (also called neo-Confucianism, but based on the teachings of Zhu Xi and his followers), so Masayuki HOSHINA and Razan HAYASHI, both on the side of the establishment, criticized Banzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>このため、岡山城下を離れ和気郡蕃山村（しげやまそん　現・岡山県備前市蕃山）に隠棲を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So Banzan had to leave the town around Okayama-jo Castle and live a secluded life in &quot;Shigeyama-son&quot; (Shigeyama Village), &quot;Wake-gun&quot; (Wake County) - the present Shigeyama, Bizen City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So Banzan had to leave the town around Okayama-jo Castle and live a secluded life in &quot;Shigeyama-son&quot; (Shigeyama Village), &quot;Wake-gun&quot; (Wake County) - the present Shigeyama, Bizen City, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So Banzan had to leave the town around Okayama-jo Castle and live a secluded life in Shigeyama Village, Wake County (the present Shigeyama, Bizen City, Okayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。Shigeyama Village, Wake Countyとしました。―削除、()補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>なお彼の号「蕃山」の名はこの地名に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, his title &quot;Banzan&quot;- in Chinese characters, Banzan spells &quot;蕃山&quot;- comes from this place name &quot;Shigeyama,&quot; because in Chinese characters, Shigeyama also spells &quot;蕃山.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, his title &quot;Banzan&quot;- in Chinese characters, Banzan spells &quot;蕃山&quot;- comes from this place name &quot;Shigeyama,&quot; because in Chinese characters, Shigeyama also spells &quot;蕃山.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, his title &apos;Banzan&apos; comes from this place name &apos;Shigeyama,&apos; because these pronunciations use the same Chinese characters, &quot;蕃山.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。― in Chinese characters, Banzan spells &quot;蕃山&quot;―削除しました。because以下訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、岡山城下の屋敷があった場所は、現在、岡山市蕃山町となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the area near Okayama-jo Castle, in which he once had his premises, now becomes &quot;Banzan-cho,&quot; Okayama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area near Okayama-jo Castle, in which he once had his premises, has now become &quot;Banzan-cho,&quot; Okayama City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area near Okayama-jo Castle, in which he once had his premises, has now become Banzan-cho, Okayama City.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>浪々・晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ronin years &amp; his later years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ronin years &amp; his later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ronin years and his later years</e>
<cmt>＆→and</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>明暦3年（1657年）幕府と藩の反対派の圧力に耐えがたく、遂に岡山藩を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1657, the pressure from the opposing force in the Edo shogunate and in the Okayama Clan obliged him to resign from his post in the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1657, the pressure from the opposing force in the Edo shogunate and in the Okayama Clan caused him to resign from his post in the clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1657, the pressure from the opposing force in the Edo shogunate and in the Okayama Domain caused him to resign from his post in the clan.</e>
<cmt>ClanをDomainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>万治元年（1658年）京都に移り私塾を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1658, he moved in Kyoto and opened his private school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1658, he moved to Kyoto and opened his private school.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1658, he moved to Kyoto and opened his private school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>万治3年（1660年）には豊後国岡藩主中川久清の招聘を受け竹田に赴き土木指導などを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1660, at the invitation of Hisakiyo NAKAGAWA, who was the feudal lord of the Bungo Province Oka Clan, Banzan went to Takeda and gave some advice including that about construction work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1660, at the invitation of Hisakiyo NAKAGAWA, who was the feudal lord of the Bungo Province Oka Clan, Banzan went to Takeda and gave advice including that about construction work.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1660, at the invitation of Hisakiyo NAKAGAWA, who was the feudal lord of the Oka Domain of Bungo Province, Banzan went to Takeda and gave advice including that about construction work.</e>
<cmt>Oka Domain of Bungo Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>寛文元年（1661年）その名声が高まるにつれ再び幕府に監視されるところとなり、とうとう時の京都所司代牧野親成により京都から追放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1661, as Banzan gained good reputation, the Tokugawa shogunate became wary of him once again, and in the end Chikasige MAKINO, the then &quot;Kyoto Shoshidai&quot; (the governor of Kyoto apponited by the Tokugawa shogunate), purged him from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1661, as Banzan gained a reputation, the Tokugawa shogunate became wary of him once again, and in the end Chikasige MAKINO, the then &quot;Kyoto Shoshidai&quot; (the governor of Kyoto apponited by the Tokugawa shogunate), purged him from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1661, as Banzan gained a reputation, the Tokugawa shogunate became wary of him once again, and in the end Chikasige MAKINO, the Kyoto Shoshidai (the governor of Kyoto appointed by the Tokugawa shogunate) at that time, purged him from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>appointedスペル訂正しました。原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。Then削除しました、at that time補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>寛文7年（1667年）には大和国吉野山（奈良県吉野郡吉野町）に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1667, he fled to Yoshino-yama Mountain, Yamato Province (the present Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1667, he fled to Yoshino-yama Mountain, Yamato Province (the present Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1667, he fled to Yoshino-yama Mountain, Yamato Province (the present Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>さらに山城国鹿背山（現・京都府木津川市）に隠棲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he secluded himself in Kaseyama, Yamashiro Province (the present Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he secluded himself in Kaseyama, Yamashiro Province (the present Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he secluded himself in Kaseyama, Yamashiro Province (the present Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>寛文9年（1669年）幕命により播磨国明石藩主松平信之の預かりとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1669, Nobuyuki MATSUDAIRA, the feudal lord of the Harima Province Akashi Clan, took him into custody under the direction of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>※「預かり」とは、江戸時代の刑罰の一種で、身柄が大名や寺に預けられ身体の自由が剥奪されるものを言い、左でもそれを踏まえて訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1669, Nobuyuki MATSUDAIRA, the feudal lord of the Harima Province Akashi Clan, took him into custody under the direction of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1669, Nobuyuki MATSUDAIRA, the feudal lord of the Akashi Domain of Harima Province, took him into custody under the direction of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Akashi Domain of Harima Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>このとき太山寺（現神戸市西区）に幽閉される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And at that time, he was imprisoned in Taisan-ji Temple (located in the present Nishi Ward, Kobe City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And at that time, he was imprisoned in Taisan-ji Temple (located in the present Nishi Ward, Kobe City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And at that time, he was imprisoned in Taisan-ji Temple (located in the present Nishi Ward, Kobe City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>延宝7年（1679年）信之の郡山藩転封に伴い、大和国矢田山（現・奈良県大和郡山市）に移住する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1679, with Nobuyuki transferred to the Koriyama Clan, he moved in Yatayama, Yamato Province (the presnt Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1679, with Nobuyuki transferred to the Koriyama Clan, he moved in Yatayama, Yamato Province (the presnt Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1679, with Nobuyuki transferred to the Koriyama Domain, he moved in Yatayama, Yamato Province (the present Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>presentスペル訂正しました。ClanをDomainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>天和3年（1683年）には大老堀田正俊の招聘を受けたが辞退している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1683, Masatoshi HOTTA, the then &quot;Tairo&quot; (the extraordinary highest ranking official in the Tokugawa shogunate), invited him to seek advice, but he declined.</e>
<cmt>※「大老」については「徳川幕府において臨時に設けられた最高位の職」と訳しています（Wiki 「大老」参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1683, Masatoshi HOTTA, the then &quot;Tairo&quot; (the extraordinary highest ranking official in the Tokugawa shogunate), invited him to seek advice, but he declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1683, Masatoshi HOTTA, the then Tairo (chief minister), invited him to seek advice, but he declined.</e>
<cmt>大老→Tairo (chief minister)原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>岡山藩致仕後、浪々の中で執筆活動とともに幕府の政策、特に参勤交代や兵農分離を批判し、また岡山藩の批判をも行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After resignation from the post in the Okayama Clan, he became a &quot;ronin&quot; (a masterless samurai), but he developed his criticism in his writings on the Tokugawa shogunate policies, especially on &quot;sankinkotai&quot; (the system that obliged feudal lords to live in Edo every other year) &amp; &quot;Heino-bunri&quot; (the class system that fixed samurai as the armed class), and he also criticized the policies of the Okayama Clan.</e>
<cmt>①「参勤交代」の解説部分については、「大名に隔年で江戸参勤を義務付けた制度」と訳しています。　②「兵農分離」については、正確には「武士を武力を有する唯一の階級とする一方で、農民の武装を禁じこれを農業に専念させた階級制度」です（Wiki 「兵農分離」参照）が、蕃山の主張の力点は「武士も就農を」という点にあったので、「武士を武装集団として固定した階級制度」と簡略に訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After resignation from the post in the Okayama Clan, he became a &quot;ronin&quot; (a masterless samurai), but he criticized the Tokugawa shogunate policies in his writings, especially on &quot;sankinkotai&quot; (the system that obliged feudal lords to live in Edo every other year) &amp; &quot;Heino-bunri&quot; (the class system that fixed samurai as the armed class), and he also criticized the policies of the Okayama Clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After resignation from the post in the Okayama Domain, he became a ronin (a masterless samurai), but he criticized the Tokugawa shogunate policies in his writings, especially on Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and Heinobunri (a separation of the warrior class in this domain from the soil), and he also criticized the policies of the Okayama Domain.</e>
<cmt>ClanをDomainに訂正しました。原文に『』がないので、&quot; &quot;削除しました。＆→and参勤交代→Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo)兵農分離→Heinobunri (a separation of the warrior class in this domain from the soil)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>貞享4年（1687年）幕府は政権批判を行った蕃山が余程憎かったのか69歳と高齢にもかかわらず、松平信之の嫡子である下総国古河藩主松平忠之に預け古河城内の竜崎頼政廓に蟄居謹慎させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1687, the Tokugawa shogunate directed Tadayuki MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of the Shimousa Province Furukawa Clan &amp; the heir of Nobuyuki MATSUDAIRA) to take Banzan (then aged 69) into custody and to shut him up in a room of Yorimasa RYUZAKI within Koga-jo Castle, and considering the old age of Banzan, this punishment might show how impatient the shogunate became with his criticism.</e>
<cmt>※「蟄居謹慎」とは江戸時代の刑罰の一種で、閉門の上一室に謹慎させられ身体の自由が奪われるものをいい左でもそれを踏まえて訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1687, the Tokugawa shogunate directed Tadayuki MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of the Shimousa Province Furukawa Clan &amp; the heir of Nobuyuki MATSUDAIRA) to take Banzan (then aged 69) into custody and to shut him up in a room of Yorimasa RYUZAKI within Koga-jo Castle, and considering Banzan&apos;s old age, this punishment might show how impatient the shogunate had become with his criticism.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1687, the Tokugawa shogunate directed Tadayuki MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of the Koga Domain of Simousa Province and the heir of Nobuyuki MATSUDAIRA) to take Banzan (then aged 69) into custody and to shut him up in a room of Yorimasa RYUZAKI within Koga-jo Castle, and considering Banzan&apos;s old age, this punishment might show how impatient the shogunate had become with his criticism.</e>
<cmt>下総国古河藩→Koga Domain of Simousa Province＆→and</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>元禄4年（1691年）反骨の儒者は病を得て古河城にてその生涯を閉じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1691, the neo-Confucianist with the rebellious spirit became ill and ended his life in Koga-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1691, the rebellious neo-Confucianist became ill and ended his life in Koga-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1691, the rebellious neo-Confucian became ill and ended his life in Koga-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>neo-Confucianist をneo-Confucianに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>享年74。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>その死後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>蕃山の遺骸は忠之により茨城県古河市大堤にある鮭延寺に手厚く葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayuki buried the corpse of Banzan with the greatest respect on the premises of Sakenobu-dera Temple, whose location is the present Otsutsumi, Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayuki buried the corpse of Banzan with the greatest respect on the premises of Sakenobu-dera Temple, whose location is the present Otsutsumi, Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayuki buried the corpse of Banzan with the greatest respect on the premises of Sakenobu-dera Temple, whose location is the present Otsutsumi, Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>墓碑銘は当初「息游軒墓」とあったが、後に「熊沢息游軒伯継墓」と刻まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, his epitaph was &quot;Sokuyuken no haka&quot; (the grave of Sokuyuken), but later it became &quot;KUMAZAWA Sokuyuken Shigetsugu no haka&quot; (the grave of KUMAZAWA Sokuyuken Shigemitsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, his epitaph was &quot;Sokuyuken no haka&quot; (the grave of Sokuyuken), but later it became &quot;KUMAZAWA Sokuyuken Shigetsugu no haka&quot; (the grave of KUMAZAWA Sokuyuken Shigemitsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, his epitaph was &apos;Sokuyuken no haka&apos; (the grave of Sokuyuken), but later added as &apos;KUMAZAWA Sokuyuken Shigetsugu no haka&apos; (the grave of KUMAZAWA Sokuyuken Shigemitsu).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。it becameをadded as　に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="45">
<j>幕末、蕃山の思想は再び脚光を浴びるところとなり藤田東湖、吉田松陰などが傾倒し、倒幕の原動力となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, the thought of Banzan came under the spotlight once again, and great thinkers, such as Toko FUJITA &amp; Shoin YOSHIDA, admired him, so his thought became a driving force of &quot;tobaku,&quot; the movement to overthrow the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, Banzan came under the spotlight once again, and great thinkers, such as Toko FUJITA &amp; Shoin YOSHIDA, admired him, so his ideas became a driving force of &quot;tobaku,&quot; the movement to overthrow the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, Banzan came under the spotlight once again, and great thinkers, such as Toko FUJITA and Shoin YOSHIDA, admired him, so his ideas became a driving force of the movement to overthrow the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>＆→and&quot;tobaku,&quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、勝海舟は蕃山を評して「儒服を着た英雄」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Kaishu KATSU, another great figure at that time, also admired him with the expression of &quot;a hero in Confucian clothes.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Kaishu KATSU, another great figure at that time, also admired him with the expression of &quot;a hero in Confucian clothes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Kaishu KATSU, another great figure at that time, also admired him with the expression of &apos;a hero in Confucian clothes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="47">
<j>明治43年（1910年）江戸時代の学問を興隆させた功績により正四位が贈呈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1910, Senior Fourth Rank was presented to Banzan for his contribution to the academic development in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1910, Senior Fourth Rank was presented to Banzan for his contribution to the academic development in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1910, the rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) was presented to Banzan for his contribution to the academic development in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>the rank of Shosii、()補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Raff(id:14006), Reggaeman(id:6214), Chinamie(id:213556), 水野白楓(id:22811), Charenji(id:7908), Cprobot(id:97843), Hannah(id:15935), 陽一(id:92099), Himazin(id:22034), Rusk(id:9895), Yonoemon(id:55450), Buckstars(id:8767), 663highland(id:18755), 胆識(id:35749), Knua(id:66861), Sprinkler(id:14399), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>