<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>裴世清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seisei HAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seisei HAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seisei HAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>裴世清（はい せいせい、生没年不明）は、7世紀前半に中国王朝隋の煬帝による命で俀國（倭国）を訪れた使者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seisei HAI (date of birth and death unknown) is an envoy who visited Wakoku (Japan) by the order of Yo-dai (Emperor Yang) of the Sui Dynasty in the first half of the seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seisei HAI (date of birth and death unknown) was an envoy who visited Wakoku (Japan) in accordance with the orders of Yo-dai (Emperor Yang) of the Sui Dynasty in the first half of the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>grammar and wording 正しく修正されていると思いますが、by the order of は修正なしでも意味が通ると考えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seisei HAI (date of birth and death unknown) was an envoy who visited Wakoku (Japan) in accordance with the orders of Yo-dai (Emperor Yang) of the Sui Dynasty in the first half of the seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>隋書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suishu (the Book of the Sui Dynasty)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suishu (the Book of the Sui Dynasty)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suishu (the Book of the Sui Dynasty)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>『隋書』「」によれば、俀王多利思比孤は大業3年（607年）に第2回遣隋使を派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Suishu (the Book of the Sui Dynasty), Taio tarishihiko sent the second Japanese envoy to Sui Dynasity China in 607.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Suishu, Taio Tarishihiko (the ruler of Japan at this time), sent a second Japanese envoy with an official diplomatic letter to Sui Dynasty China in 607.</e>
<cmt>There&apos;s no need to explain Suishu twice so I have deleted &quot;(the Book of the Sui Dynasty)&quot;          </cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Suishu, Tarishihiko, the king of Wa (Japan) at this time, sent a second Japanese envoy with an official diplomatic letter to Sui Dynasty China in 607.</e>
<cmt>「」内が抽出されていませんが、ウェブ上にこの記事はないようですので、そのままにしています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>煬帝はその国書に立腹したが、翌大業2年（608年）、文林郎である裴清（世については太宗（唐朝の二代目皇帝李世民) の諱世民のため避諱された）をその答礼使として派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yo-dai (Emperor Yang) was angry at the letter, but he sent Sei HAI (a part of his name is omitted because of a taboo against using the personal name of Seimin RI, the second emperor of the Tang Dynasty), who was the bunrinrou, as an envoy for return visit in 608.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yo-dai was angry at the letter, but he still sent Sei HAI (One kanji character 世 [pronounced &quot;Sei&quot;], which was also used in Emperor Tang tai zong (the 2nd emperor of the Tang Dynasty)&apos;s real name (李世民), was omitted from his name because it was taboo for people in the ancient China to use any of the kanji characters used in the Emperor&apos;s name), who was a bunrinrou (secretary), as the envoy for a return visit in 608.</e>
<cmt>There&apos;s no need to explain Yo-dai twice so I have deleted &quot;(Emperor Yang)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yo-dai was angry at the letter brought by the envoy, but he still sent Sei HAI (One of his Chinese character &apos;世&apos; [pronounced &quot;Sei&quot;] was also used in the real name [李世民] of the second emperor of the Tang Dynasty, Emperor Tang Taizong; therefore it was omitted from his name because it was taboo for people in the ancient China to use any of the characters used in the Emperor&apos;s name), a secretary, as the envoy for a return visit in 608.</e>
<cmt>括弧内をわかりやすく修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大海の都斯麻國（対馬）、東に一支國（一支国）、竹斯國（筑紫）、東に秦王國（中国人の国）他10余国をへて海岸についたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came to the coast of Japan through Tsushima Island in the ocean, Ikikoku in the east, Chikushi, Shinokoku in the east (the land of Chinese), and ten-odd countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came to the coast of Japan through Tsushima Island in the ocean, Ikikoku in the east, Chikushi, Shinokoku in the east (the land of Chinese), and ten-odd countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came to the coast of Japan through Tsushima Island in the ocean, Ikikoku in the east, Chikushi, Shinokoku in the east (the land of Chinese), and ten-odd countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>竹斯國から東はすべて俀であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that all the countries in the east fromChikushi is part of Tai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that all the countries in the east from Chikushi is part of Tai.</e>
<cmt>fromとChikushiの間にスペース追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that all the countries in the east from Chikushi is part of Tai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>俀王は小徳（冠位十二階の位）阿輩臺が数百人で迎え、10日後に大礼の哥多が200騎で警護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taio welcomed HAI with hundreds of Shotoku (one of the twelve grades of cap rank) Ahaiichi, and ten days later, Dairai (the fifthe grade of the twelve grades of cap rank) Kata gurded him with 200 knights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taio sent Shotoku (one of the twelve grades of cap rank) Ahaiichi with hundreds of attendants to meet the envoy, and ten days later, Dairai (the fifthe grade of the twelve grades of cap rank) Kata escorted him with 200 horse guards.</e>
<cmt>原文が誤りではないでしょうか。「小徳（冠位十二階の位）阿輩臺」（一人）が供の数百人とともに出迎えたのだと考えます。fifthe→fifth gurded→guarded　knights→horse guards他文全体を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taio sent Shotoku (one of the twelve grades of cap rank) Ahaiichi with hundreds of attendants to meet the envoy, and ten days later, Dairai (the fifthe grade of the twelve grades of cap rank) Kata escorted him with 200 horse guards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>王と会った清は王の歓迎のことばに皇帝の命を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meeting the king, HAI informed the order of his emperor after receiving the words of welcome from the king.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meeting the king, HAI told him the words of Emperor Yo-dai after receiving the words of welcome from the king.</e>
<cmt>informed the order of his emperor→ told him the words of Emperor Yo-dai</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meeting the king, HAI told him the words of Emperor Yo-dai after receiving the words of welcome from the king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後清は使者とともに帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, HAI returned home with envoys.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, HAI returned home with envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, HAI returned home with envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>三国史記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samguk Sagi (History of the Three Kingdoms)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samguk Sagi (History of the Three Kingdoms)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samguk Sagi (History of the Three Kingdoms)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>『三国史記』卷第27 百済本紀第5 武王 (百済)9年3月によれば「九年 春三月 遣使入隋朝貢 隋文林郞裴淸奉使倭國 經我國南路」とあり裴清は百済南部を経由したことが記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the 27th book of &quot;Samguk Sagi&quot;(History of the Three Kingdomes), History of Baekje, the Fifth, King Wo of Zhou (Baekje) the ninth year, March, it is stated that &quot;the ninth year, March in the spring, an envoy arrived in Suiy to bring tributes. The bunnrinnrou HaiSEI went to Japan as an envoy through the south route&quot; and described that Hai SEI chose his way via the south part of Baekje.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) describes in the 27th volume, the 5th section of History of Baekje, as an event that occurred in March of the ninth year of King Wu of Zhou&apos;s time (Baekje), that &quot;in March in the spring of the ninth year, bunrinro Hai SEI, an envoy from Sui Dynasty to Wakoku (Japan), passed the south of our country,&quot; which means that he came to Japan via the southern part of Baekje.</e>
<cmt>kingdomes→kingdoms         book→volume          Sagi&quot;の後にスペース挿入。『三国史記』卷第27 百済本紀第5 武王 (百済)9年3月の訳文が単なる訳語の羅列となっており本の構成がわからないので、構成を踏まえた訳文とし,また、2文を1文にまとめ全文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Samguk Sagi&quot; (History of the Three Kingdoms) describes in the 27th volume, the 5th section of History of Baekje, as an event that occurred in March of the ninth year of King Wu of Zhou&apos;s time (Baekje), that &quot;in March in the spring of the ninth year, bunrinro Hai SEI, an envoy from Sui Dynasty to Wakoku (Japan), passed the south of our country,&quot; which means that he came to Japan via the southern part of Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本書紀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>『日本書紀』では次のとおり裴世清と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seisei HAI is described as such in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) refers to him as Seisei HAI, and describes as follows.</e>
<cmt>ニュアンスが違うと考え全文書換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) refers to him as Seisei HAI, and describes as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その12人の一行は小野妹子とともに筑紫に着き、難波吉士雄成が招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group of 12 members arrived at Tsukushi with ONO no Imoko, and they were invited by Nanba Kishino Onari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group of 12 members arrived at Chikushi with ONO no Imoko, and they were invited by Naniwa no Kishino Onari.</e>
<cmt>Tsukushi→Chikushi  Nanba→Naniwa no</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group of 12 members arrived at Chikushi with ONO no Imoko, and they were invited by Naniwa no Kishino Onari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>難波高麗館の上に館を新しく建てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New mansion was built on Nanba koma-no-murotsumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New mansion was built on Naniwa koma-no-murotsumi.</e>
<cmt>館名を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New mansion was built on Naniwa koma-no-murotsumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>6月15日難波津に泊まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They stayed at Nanba-tsu on June 15th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They stayed at Naniwatsu on June 15.</e>
<cmt>Nanba-tsu→Naniwatsu 15th→15</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They stayed at Naniwatsu on June 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>船30艘で歓迎、新館に泊めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were welcomed by 30 ships and stayed at the new mansion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were welcomed by 30 ships and were lodged at the new mansion.</e>
<cmt>「泊めた」とあるので使節団は「泊められた」とするべきと考えstayedをwere lodgedに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were welcomed by 30 ships and were lodged at the new mansion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>8月3日に京に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They entered the capital on Augurst 3rd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They entered the capital on Augurst 3.</e>
<cmt>3rd→3</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They entered the capital on Augurst 3.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「「鴻臚寺の掌客」である裴世清の「皇帝問倭皇」という書を阿部臣が大門の机の上においた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letter of &quot;To Wako from Emperor&quot; which was brought by Hai SEISEI, &quot;the host of Koroji&quot;, is placed on the desk of Daimon-gate by the liege Abe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letter including &apos;questions to Wako from Emperor (of China)&apos; which was brought in by Seisei HAI as &quot;Koroji no shokyaku&quot; (Chinese official in charge of entertaining important guests) was placed on Omikado (Emperor of Japan)&apos;s desk by Abe no omi.</e>
<cmt>原文の最初の「が不要と思われます。   &quot;To Wako from Emperor&quot;を&apos;questions to Wako from Emperor of China&apos; としました。    Hai SEISEI:表記ミス         「鴻臚寺の掌客」は古代中国における外交施設の接待係という官職のようです。説明的な訳文として書き換えました。またthe liege AbeをAbe no omiとしました。          さらにisをwasとしました。          なお,ここでは「大門」は「だいもん」ではなく「おおみかど」とするべきであり、天皇をさすものと考えるほうが筋が通ると思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letter including &apos;questions to Wako from Emperor (of China)&apos; which was brought in by Seisei HAI as &quot;Koroji no shokyaku&quot; (Chinese official in charge of entertaining important guests) was placed on Omikado (Emperor of Japan)&apos;s desk by Abe no omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>9月5日に難波大都に、11日に帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to the great capital of Nanba on September fifth, and returned on 11th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to the great capital of Nanba on September 5, and left for home on September 11.</e>
<cmt>fifth→5 returned on 11th→left for home on September 11</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to the great capital of Nanba on September 5, and left for home on September 11.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), デーモン博士(id:99293), Izayohi(id:13095), Straysheep(id:42448), BJP039(id:47469), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>