<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>姫の前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hime no Mae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hime no Mae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hime no Mae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>姫の前（ひめのまえ、生没年不詳）は鎌倉時代初期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hime no Mae (the dates of her birth and death unknown) was a woman who lived in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hime no Mae (year of birth and death unknown) was a woman who lived in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>生没年不詳の部分を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hime no Mae (year of birth and death unknown) was a woman who lived in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府の御家人、比企朝宗の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daugther of Tomomune HIKI who was a Gokenin (a vassal of the shogunate) of the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daugther of Tomomune HIKI who was a Gokenin (a vassal of the shogunate) of the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daugther of Tomomune HIKI who was a Gokenin (a vassal of the shogunate) of the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉幕府第二代執権・北条義時の正室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the lawful wife of Yoshitoki HOJO, who was the second regent of Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the lawful wife of Yoshitoki HOJO, who was the second regent of Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the lawful wife of Yoshitoki HOJO, who was the second regent of Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に北条朝時（北条氏 (名越流)祖）、北条重時（北条氏 (極楽寺流)祖）、竹殿（大江親広・土御門定通妻）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her children included Tomotoki HOJO (the founder of NAGOE-ryu [Line of HOJO clan]), Shigetoki HOJO (the founder of Gokurakuji-ryu [Line of HOJO clan]), Takedono (a wife of OE no Chikahiro first and then a wife of Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO).</e>
<cmt>名越流-NAGOE-ryu (Line of HOJO clan) 　 極楽流-GOKURAKUJI-ryu (Line of HOJO clan)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her children were Tomotoki HOJO (the founder of NAGOE-ryu [Line of HOJO clan]), Shigetoki HOJO (the founder of Gokurakuji-ryu [Line of HOJO clan]), and Takedono (a wife of OE no Chikahiro first and then a wife of Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO).</e>
<cmt>includedをwereとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her children were Tomotoki HOJO (the founder of NAGOE-ryu [Line of HOJO clan]), Shigetoki HOJO (the founder of Gokurakuji-ryu [Line of HOJO clan]), and Takedono (a wife of OE no Chikahiro first and then a wife of Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>源頼朝の御所に勤める女官であった姫の前は美人で有名で、『吾妻鏡』に｢比企の籐内朝宗が息女、当時権威無双の女房なりて、殊に御意に相叶う、容顔太だ美麗なり｣と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hime no Mae, who was famous for her beauty, worked at MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s Palace as a court lady and, according to &quot;Azumakagami&quot; (a histrical book written in the Kamakura period), she was described as &quot;a daughter of Tomomune TONAI in HIki county and at the time a matchlessly powerfull employee, a favorite of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and a very beautifull woman&quot;.</e>
<cmt>無双-matchlessly</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hime no Mae, who worked at MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s Palace as a court lady was famous for her beauty, and according to &quot;Azumakagami&quot; (a histrical book written in the Kamakura period), she was described as &apos;a daughter of Tomomune TONAI in HIki county and at the time a matchlessly powerfull employee, a favorite of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and a very beautifull woman.&apos;</e>
<cmt>語順を変え、”を’にし、ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hime no Mae, who worked at MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s Palace as a court lady was famous for her beauty, and according to &quot;Azumakagami&quot; (a histrical book written in the Kamakura period), she was described as &apos;a daughter of Tomomune TONAI in HIki county and at the time a matchlessly powerfull employee, a favorite of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and a very beautifull woman.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>義時は一年あまりの間姫の前に恋文を送っていが、姫の前は一向になびかず、それを見かねた頼朝が義時に｢絶対に離縁致しません｣という起請文を書かせて二人の仲を取り持ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitoki kept sending love letters to Hime no Mae for about a year without response from her, so Yoritomo helped Yoshitoki to marry her by making him write a sworn oath describing that he would never divorce her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitoki kept sending love letters to Hime no Mae for about a year without any response, and Yoritomo who could not stand watching this helped Yoshitoki to marry her by making him write a sworn oath, saying &apos;he would never divorce her.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「見かねた」を追加し、「」を’’としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitoki kept sending love letters to Hime no Mae for about a year without any response, and Yoritomo who could not stand watching this helped Yoshitoki to marry her by making him write a sworn oath, saying &apos;he would never divorce her.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>こうして建久3年（1192年）9月25日、姫の前は義時に嫁ぎ、建久4年（1193年）義時の次男･朝時を、建久9年（1198年）三男･重時を産む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Hime no Mae finally married with Yoshitoki on September 25, 1192 and gave a birth to Yoshitoki&apos;s second son, Tomotoki in 1193 and to his third son, Shigetoki in 1198.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Hime no Mae finally married with Yoshitoki on November 8, 1192 and gave birth to Yoshitoki&apos;s second son, Tomotoki in 1193 and to his third son, Shigetoki in 1198.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦に直しました。Gave a birthのaを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Hime no Mae finally married with Yoshitoki on November 8, 1192 and gave birth to Yoshitoki&apos;s second son, Tomotoki in 1193 and to his third son, Shigetoki in 1198.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後の消息はわからず、建仁3年（1203年）に姫の前の実家である比企氏一族が比企能員の変で滅亡していることや、義時の後妻の伊賀の方が元久2年（1205年）北条政村を産んでいることから、その間に死去したか、または何らかの事情により離縁したと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No information is available about what happened to Hime no Mae after she gave the birth to children; however, since the Hiki family perished after Yoshikazu HIKI no Hen (the Conspiracy of Yoshikazu HIKI) and Yoshitoki remarried Iga no Kata who gave birth to his son, Masamura HOJO in 1205, she was presumed to have died or divorced during this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her later life was unknow, however, since Hime no Mae&apos;s family, the Hiki clan was destroyed after Yoshikazu HIKI no Hen (the Conspiracy of Yoshikazu HIKI) in 1203, and Yoshitoki remarried Iga no Kata who gave birth to his son, Masamura HOJO in 1205, she was presumed to have died or to be divorced for any reason during this time.</e>
<cmt>いくつか抜けていた語を補い、書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her later life was unknow, however, since Hime no Mae&apos;s family, the Hiki clan was destroyed after Yoshikazu HIKI no Hen (the Conspiracy of Yoshikazu HIKI) in 1203, and Yoshitoki remarried Iga no Kata who gave birth to his son, Masamura HOJO in 1205, she was presumed to have died or to be divorced for any reason during this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちちぶ(id:184715), Andee(id:20421), ５１６(id:45205), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 小者(id:172526), 電田蒸(id:249216), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>