<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>前野良沢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryotaku MAENO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryotaku MAENO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryotaku MAENO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>前野 良沢（まえの りょうたく、享保8年（1723年） - 享和3年10月17日 (旧暦)（1803年11月30日））は、豊前国中津藩（現在の大分県中津市）の藩医で蘭学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryotaku MAENO (1723 to November 30, 1803) was a clan doctor and Dutch scholar in Nakatsu clan of Buzen Province (Nakatsu City of Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryotaku MAENO (1723 to November 30, 1803) was a domain doctor and Dutch scholar in the Nakatsu Domain of Buzen Province (present Nakatsu City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「～藩」の扱いを用語統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryotaku MAENO (1723 to November 30, 1803) was a domain doctor and Dutch scholar in the Nakatsu Domain of Buzen Province (present Nakatsu City, Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『解体新書』の主幹翻訳者の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of main stem translators of &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (the historic Japanese translation of a Dutch anatomical text).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the main translators of &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (the historic Japanese translation of a Dutch anatomical text).</e>
<cmt>「主幹」はmain１語で十分と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the main translators of &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (the historic Japanese translation of a Dutch anatomical text).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は蘭化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His title was Ranka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (pen name) was Ranka.</e>
<cmt>「号」の説明は定訳に依りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Ranka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>母方の大叔父の宮田全沢に養われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was brought up by Zentaku MIYATA, who was his great-uncle in his mother side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was brought up by Zentaku MIYATA, who was his great-uncle on his mother side.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was brought up by Zentaku MIYATA, who was his great-uncle on his mother side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1769年（明和6年）蘭学を志して、晩年の青木昆陽に師事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1769, he was determined to study western sciences, and he studied under Konyo AOKI in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1769, he was determined to study Western studies under Konyo AOKI in his later years.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1769, he was determined to study Western studies under Konyo AOKI in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、1770年（明和7年）藩主の参勤交代について中津に下向した際、長崎へと留学した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward in 1770, when he was heading downward to Nakatsu for the handing over of feudal lord&apos;s duties, he went to study in Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1770, he went down to Nakatsu by joining the head of the domain on his return home for sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and left for Nagasaki to study.</e>
<cmt>参勤交代の説明が不十分だったので、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1770, he went down to Nakatsu by joining the head of the domain on his return home for sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and left for Nagasaki to study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>留学中に手に入れた西洋の解剖書『ターヘル・アナトミア』を杉田玄白、中川淳庵、桂川甫周ら盟友と3年5ヶ月で翻訳し『解体新書』を編纂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He translated the Western anatomy book &quot;Ontleedkundige Tafelen&quot; which he obtained while going to study abroad, and compiled the translations into &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Book of Anatomy) with Genpaku SUGITA, Junan NAKAGAWA, Hoshu KATSURAGAWA and other sworn friends in three years and five months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He translated the Western anatomy book &quot;Ontleedkundige Tafelen,&quot; which he obtained in Nagasaki, into Japanese with Genpaku SUGITA, Junan NAKAGAWA, Hoshu KATSURAGAWA in three years and five months to issue the translation as &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Book of Anatomy).</e>
<cmt>「～ら盟友と」はこの３人プラスアルファではなく、この３人と解しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He translated the Western anatomy book &quot;Ontleedkundige Tafelen,&quot; which he obtained in Nagasaki, into Japanese with Genpaku SUGITA, Junan NAKAGAWA, Hoshu KATSURAGAWA in three years and five months to issue the translation as &quot;Kaitai Shinsho&quot; (New Book of Anatomy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、解体新書発行当時、その業績は知られておりません。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at the time when &quot;New Book of Anatomy&quot; was published, the achievement was not known.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Kaitai Shinsho was published, the achievement was not recognized.</e>
<cmt>「解体新書」は直前に説明しているので、そのままの表記でいいと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Kaitai Shinsho was published, the achievement was not recognized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>（発行時に名を出したのは杉田玄白他数名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(at the time of publication, only a few names including Genpaku SUGITA)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(the book featured Genpaku SUGITA and some others as the editors and translators)</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(the book featured Genpaku SUGITA and some others as the editors and translators)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その存在が知られるのは解体新書の翻訳作業の困難を記した杉田玄白の『蘭東事始（蘭学事始）』を待たねばならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existence was being known by Genpaku SUGITA who recorded the difficulty of the translation work of &quot;New Book of Anatomy&quot; and had to wait for &quot;Rangaku Kotohajime&quot; (The Beginning of Dutch Studies) by Genpaku SUGITA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book became famous after Genpaku SUGITA issued &quot;Rangaku Kotohajime&quot; (The Beginning of Dutch Studies) that described how difficult it was to put Ontleedkundige Tafelen into Kaitai Shinsho.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book became famous after Genpaku SUGITA issued &quot;Rangaku Kotohajime&quot; (The Beginning of Dutch Studies) that described how difficult it was to put Ontleedkundige Tafelen into Kaitai Shinsho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>良沢が解体新書に自らの名を出さなかったのは、その翻訳の不備（とはいえ、当時の日本の語学水準からすれば、その翻訳は奇跡に近い完成度を誇っていた）を自らがよく解っております。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryotaku&apos;s New Book of Anatomy not having his own name put out was because he himself understood the incompleteness (However, in view of the foreign language proficiency level of Japan at that time, the translation took pride in being miraculously a near perfection) of the translation well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryotaku did not put his name in Kaitai Shinsho as a translator and editor because he recognized that the translation quality was quite low (however, the translation quality was exceptionally high considering the language level in Japan of that time).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryotaku did not put his name in Kaitai Shinsho as a translator and editor because he recognized that the translation quality was quite low (however, the translation quality was exceptionally high considering the language level in Japan of that time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これを恥として許すことができなかったためと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was because he could not forgive the shame of this.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ryotaku took this as an unforgivable shame.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ryotaku took this as an unforgivable shame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また一説としては、蘭学に対する幕府の対応が微妙でもあったため、万が一の際に、最も蘭語に通ずる良沢に咎が及ぶのを避けるためと、前説の訳の不備に対する良沢の気持ちを杉田が酌み取ったためともされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, according to another theory, it was also because the response of the shogunate to the western sciences was slight.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to another theory, Genpaku did not want to see Ryotaku who were the most familiar with Dutch punished by bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) that was frowning on Western studies and took his frustration about the translation into consideration.</e>
<cmt>分割の仕方がよくなかったので結合し、表現も修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to another theory, Genpaku did not want to see Ryotaku who were the most familiar with Dutch punished by bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) that was frowning on Western studies and took his frustration about the translation into consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後、蘭学に対する真摯な姿勢より、藩主奥平昌鹿より「蘭学の化け物」と賞賛され、これを誉とし「蘭化」と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, because of his sincere posture to western sciences, he was praised &quot;Monster in western sciences&quot; by the feudal lord Masashika OKUDAIRA, and he took the title &quot;Ranka&quot; (Dutch Monster).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, because of his sincere posture to Western studies, he was praised as &apos;蘭学の化け物&apos; (literally, wizard of Western studies) by Masashika OKUDAIRA, the lord of the domain, and was so proud of the title that he called himself &apos;蘭化&apos; (ranka).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正。「蘭学の化け物」と「蘭化」の関係は日本語表記でしか説明できないので、日本語表記としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, because of his sincere posture to Western studies, he was praised as &apos;蘭学の化け物&apos; (literally, wizard of Western studies) by Masashika OKUDAIRA, the lord of the domain, and was so proud of the title that he called himself &apos;蘭化&apos; (ranka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>寛政の三奇人のひとり高山彦九郎とは親しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was intimate with Hikokuro TAKAYAMA, who was one of the Three bizzare characters of Kansei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was close to Hikokuro TAKAYAMA, who was one of the Three bizarre characters of Kansei.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was close to Hikokuro TAKAYAMA, who was one of the Three bizarre characters of Kansei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>娘の嫁ぎ先である幕府医師・小島家に於いて没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in the house of shogunate doctor Kojima, where his daughter was married into.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in the household of the Kojima family, a doctor working for the shogunate, family which his daughter married into.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in the household of the Kojima family, a doctor working for the shogunate, family which his daughter married into.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>弟子に司馬江漢、大槻玄沢などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among his students were Kokan SHIBA, Gentaku OTSUKI and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his students were Kokan SHIBA, Gentaku OTSUKI and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his students were Kokan SHIBA, Gentaku OTSUKI and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 パの字(id:34188), S.Kiyama(id:9815), Sat666(id:127263), Immergruen(id:53578), 0null0(id:582), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), UMBRO(id:100484), いたる(id:58536), Himazin(id:22034), Point136(id:211299), 伏儀(id:142093), けんち(id:5147), Zzzz(id:16596), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>