<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>西園寺実晴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saneharu SAIONJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saneharu SAIONJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saneharu SAIONJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>西園寺実晴（さいおんじさねはる、慶長6年（1601年） - 寛文13年1月11日 (旧暦)（1673年2月27日））は江戸時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saneharu SAIONJI (1601 to February 27, 1673) was a kugyo (high court noble) in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saneharu SAIONJI (1601 to February 27, 1673) was a kugyo (high court noble) in Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saneharu SAIONJI (1601 to February 27, 1673) was a kugyo (high court noble) in Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>内大臣西園寺公益の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the child of Kinmasu SAIONJI, Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Kinmasu SAIONJI, Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Kinmasu SAIONJI, Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>礼学・絵画を好み、1667年左大臣まで上った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He liked courtesy science and painting, and in 1667, he was promoted to the position of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He liked courtesy science and painting, and in 1667, he was promoted to the position of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He liked courtesy science and painting, and in 1667, he was promoted to the position of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1619年（元和 (日本)5年）に参議し、内大臣・右大臣・従一位左大臣を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attended meetings in 1619, became Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior), Udaijin (the Minister of the Right), and Junior First Rank Sadaijin (the Minister of the Left) successively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in national administration in 1619, became Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior), Udaijin (the Minister of the Right), and Juichii (Junior First Rank) Sadaijin successively.</e>
<cmt>官位の表記を用語統一リストに従って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in national administration in 1619, became Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior), Udaijin (the Minister of the Right), and Juichii (Junior First Rank) Sadaijin successively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1651年（慶安4年）に朝廷は徳川家光に対して正一位太政大臣の追贈と「大猷院」の諡を決め、内大臣西園寺実晴を勅使として日光に派遣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1651, the court decided to award the position of Senior First Rank Grand Minister of state and a posthumous name &quot;Taiyuin&quot; to Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, and sent the Minister of the Interior Saneharu SAIONJIto Nikko as an envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1651, the court decided to award a position of Shoichii (Senior First Rank) Dajo-daijin (Grand minister of state) and a posthumous name &quot;Taiyuin&quot; to Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, and sent Saneharu SAIONJI, who was the Minister of the Interior, to Nikko as an envoy.</e>
<cmt>官位の表記を用語統一リストおよび用語集に従って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1651, the court decided to award a position of Shoichii (Senior First Rank) Dajo-daijin (Grand minister of state) and a posthumous name &quot;Taiyuin&quot; to Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, and sent Saneharu SAIONJI, who was the Minister of the Interior, to Nikko as an envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1672年（寛文12年）に出家して大忠院入道と号し、法名は性永。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1672, he became a priest, titled Daichuin Nyudo with a posthumous Buddhist name Shoei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1672, he became a priest, titled Daichuin Nyudo with a posthumous Buddhist name Shoei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1672, he became a priest, titled Daichuin Nyudo with a posthumous Buddhist name Shoei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>正室は細川忠興と細川ガラシャの子の細川忠隆（1604年の廃嫡後は長岡休無と号す）の長女・徳姫（1605-1663）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legal wife was Tokuhime (1605 to 1663), the eldest daughter of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Tadataka HOSOKAWA (child of Gracia HOSOKAWA), titled Kyumu NAGAOKA after the disinheritance in 1604.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal wife was Tokuhime (1605 to 1663), the eldest daughter of Tadataka HOSOKAWA (who called himself Kyumu NAGAOKA after being disinherited in 1604), who was a child of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Gracia HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>元の英文では血族関係が混乱していたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wife was Tokuhime (1605 to 1663), the eldest daughter of Tadataka HOSOKAWA (who called himself Kyumu NAGAOKA after being disinherited in 1604), who was a child of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Gracia HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>京都在住の休無から助成金が毎年西園寺家へ贈られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsidy was presented every year from Kyumu who was living in Kyoto to the SAIONJI family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Financial assistance was given to the Saionji family every year by Kyumu, who lived in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>subsidyは政府からの助成金を表すのでここには不適です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Financial assistance was given to the Saionji family every year by Kyumu, who lived in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また休無遺産として500石が徳姫（西園寺家）に相続され、西園寺家の財政の基盤となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, 500 Koku of crop yield was succeeded to Tokuhime (the SAIONJI family) as Kyumu&apos;s inheritance, and it became the financial foundation of the SAIONJI family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Kyumu&apos;s estate, which totaled to 500 Koku of crop yield, was inherited by Tokuhime (the Saionji family) and became the financial foundation of Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>直訳では分かりにくいので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Kyumu&apos;s estate, which totaled to 500 Koku of crop yield, was inherited by Tokuhime (the Saionji family) and became the financial foundation of Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>子は23代目となった西園寺公満のほかに、西園寺公遂、西園寺公宣(別名公義又は随宜)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Kinmitsu SAIONJI who were the 23rd generation, among his children were also Kinsui SAIONJI, and Kinnobu SAIONJI (also called Kimiyoshi or Zuigi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his children was Kinmitsu SAIONJI, who became the 23rd head of the family, as well as Kinsui SAIONJI, and Kinnobu SAIONJI (also called Kimiyoshi or Zuigi).</e>
<cmt>文構造を整理しました。「23代目」は「23代目の家長」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his children was Kinmitsu SAIONJI, who became the 23rd head of the family, as well as Kinsui SAIONJI, and Kinnobu SAIONJI (also called Kimiyoshi or Zuigi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、末子の西園寺公宣は京都の公家生活を嫌って、長岡休無の子の長岡忠春（1622-1704年、細川内膳家祖）を頼って肥後国に移り住み菊池（現熊本県菊陽町）で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His youngest child Kinnobu SAIONJI disliked court noble life of Kyoto, relied all the affairs to Tadaharu NAGAOKA (1622 to 1704, under the Hosokawa-naizen family) who was a child of Kyumu NAGAOKA, moved to Higo province, and died in Kikuchi (present Kumamoto Prefecture Kikuyo-cho Town).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His youngest child Kinnobu SAIONJI disliked the life of court nobles in Kyoto, moved to the Higo province, where he could rely on Tadaharu NAGAOKA (1622 to 1704, an ancestor of the Hosokawa-naizen family) who was a child of Kyumu NAGAOKA, and died in Kikuchi (presently Kikuyo-cho, Kumamoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>元の英文のrely all the affairs toの意味が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His youngest child Kinnobu SAIONJI disliked the life of court nobles in Kyoto, moved to the Higo province, where he could rely on Tadaharu NAGAOKA (1622 to 1704, an ancestor of the Hosokawa-naizen family) who was a child of Kyumu NAGAOKA, and died in Kikuchi (presently Kikuyo-cho, Kumamoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、そこで生まれた娘（也須姫もしくは安姫）が京に戻って鷹司家から婿（西園寺実輔）を取り西園寺家を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his daughter(Princess Yasu or Yasuhime)who was born there returned to the capital, took the bridegroom(Sanesuke SAIONJI)from the TAKATSUKASA family, and inherited with the SAIONJI family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kinnobu&apos;s daughter (Princess Yasu or Yasuhime)who was born there returned to the capital, took a husband (Sanesuke SAIONJI)from the Takatsukasa family, and succeeded the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>公宣の娘であることを明確にしました。また家名は頭文字のみを大文字で表記します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kinnobu&apos;s daughter (Princess Yasu or Yasuhime)who was born there returned to the capital, took a husband (Sanesuke SAIONJI)from the Takatsukasa family, and succeeded the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まさふゆ(id:232040), こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), 寂華(id:83725), Yonoemon(id:55450), 松茸(id:27535), Hosokawajun(id:72875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>