<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>駒姫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komahime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komahime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komahime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>駒姫（こまひめ、天正7年（1581年） - 文禄4年8月2日 (旧暦)（1595年9月5日））は、最上義光と大崎夫人の二女で、豊臣秀次の側室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komahime (1581-September 5, 1595) was the second daughter between Yoshiaki MOGAMI and Osaki fujin and was a concubine of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komahime (1581-September 5, 1595) was the second daughter between Yoshiaki MOGAMI and Osaki fujin and was a concubine of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>If the lettering in red is correct, it should be explained because this word does not exist in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komahime (1581 - September 5, 1595) was the second daughter of Yoshiaki MOGAMI and Osaki Fujin, and was a concubine of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名、伊万（いま）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had another name, Ima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had another name: Ima.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had an alias: Ima.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伊達政宗の従妹に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a cousin to Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a cousin to Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a cousin of Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>彼女の名は御駒山からとられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name 駒 was taken from Mt.Okoma 御駒山.</e>
<cmt>文意を明確にするために全角文字（漢字）を残しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name, Koma (駒), was taken from Mt.Okoma 御駒山.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name Koma (駒) derived from Mt. Okoma (御駒山).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>駒姫は、その類いまれな美しさから父母に溺愛されて育ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komahime was amazingly beautiful, and she was raised with plenty of love from her parents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komahime was amazingly beautiful, and she was raised with plenty of love from her parents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Komahime was amazingly beautiful, her parents doted on her.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>時の関白・豊臣秀次は、東国一の美少女と名高かった駒姫の噂を聞き、側室に差し出すよう義光に迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) at the time heard about Komahime who was famous as the most beautiful girl in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region), and pressed Yoshimitsu to offer Komahime as a concubine to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Kampaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) at the time, heard about Komahime, who was famous as the most beautiful girl in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region), and pressed Yoshimitsu to offer Komahime as a concubine to him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, the chief adviser to the Emperor at the time, heard about Komahime having the reputation of the most beautiful girl in the eastern part of Japan, pressed Yoshimitsu to offer Komahime as a concubine to him.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>義光は断ったが度重なる要求に折れ、十五歳になったら娘を山形から京へと嫁がせると約束する羽目に陥る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshimitsu kept refusing, he ended up promising to have Komahime marry into Kyoto from Yamagata when Komahime turn fifteen years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshimitsu kept refusing, he ended up promising to have Komahime marry into Kyoto from Yamagata when Komahime turned fifteen years old.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshimitsu kept refusing, he was consequently forced into promising to have Komahime marry into Kyoto from Yamagata when Komahime turned fifteen years old.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、九戸政実討伐の帰途、山形城に立ち寄った秀次を、義光が駒姫に接待させたという挿話は後世の創作とみたほうが妥当である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the episode that Yoshimitsu had Komahime entertain Hidetsugu who dropped by Yamagata Castle on the way back from subjugation of Masazane KUNOHE was probably a functional story made up in after ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, the episode where Yoshimitsu had Komahime entertain Hidetsugu, who stopped in Yamagata Castle on the way back from the subjugation of Masazane KUNOHE, was probably a fictitious story made up in subsequent ages.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the episode where Yoshimitsu had Komahime entertain Hidetsugu, who stopped in Yamagata-jo Castle on the way back from the subjugation of Masazane KUNOHE, was probably a fictitious story made up in later ages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）、駒姫は京に到着し、最上屋敷で長旅の疲れを癒していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Komahime arrived at Kyoto in 1595, Komahime was in the Saijo residence relieving the weariness of a long journey.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処定訳不明なため、最上屋敷→Saijo residence と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Komahime arrived in Kyoto in 1595, Komahime was in the Saijo residence relieving the weariness of a long journey.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Komahime arrived in Kyoto in 1595, she was in the Mogami&apos;s residence relieving her weariness of a long journey.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ところが、七月十五日、秀次は豊臣秀吉の命により高野山で切腹させられてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on July 15, Hidetsugi was forced to commit Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) at Koya-san Mountain by the order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on July 15, Hidetsugi was forced to commit Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) on Koya-san Mountain by the order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on July 15, Hidetsugi was forced to commit Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) on Mt. Koya by order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして駒姫も、八月二日に他の秀次の側室達と共に、三条河原に引き立てられ十一番目に処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komahime too was forcibly taken to Sanjo-gawara Riverside with other concubines of Hidetsugu on August 2; she was executed eleventhly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komahime was also forcibly taken to Sanjo-gawara Riverside with the other concubines of Hidetsugu on August 2. She was the eleventh to be executed.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komahime was also forcibly taken to Sanjo-gawara Riverside with the other concubines of Hidetsugu on August 2, and was the eleventh to be executed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>まだ実質的な秀次の側室になる前だったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was before Komahime practically became Hidetsugu&apos;s concubines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was even before Komahime became one of Hidetsugu&apos;s concubines.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was even before Komahime virtually became a Hidetsugu&apos;s concubine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>父の義光が必死で助命嘆願に廻り、各方面からも処刑せぬようにと声があがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komahime&apos;s father, Yoshimitsu desperately pleaded for her life visiting various parties, and outcry for saving her life occurred from various parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komahime&apos;s father, Yoshimitsu desperately pleaded for her life visiting various parties. There was also an outcry to save her life from various people.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komahime&apos;s father Yoshimitsu desperately pleaded for her life visiting various quarters, and there was also an outcry to save her life from various people.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>秀吉もついにこれを無視できなくなり「鎌倉で尼にするように」と早馬を処刑場に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became hard for Hideyoshi to ignore this, Hideyoshi dispatched a post horse to the execution ground to stop to execute her with a order to have her become a priest in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became hard for Hideyoshi to ignore this, Hideyoshi dispatched a post horse to the execution ground to stop the execution of her with an order to have her become a priest in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it became hard for Hideyoshi to ignore this, Hideyoshi dispatched a fast post-horse to the execution ground to stop the execution of her with an order &apos;to have her become a priest in Kamakura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかしあと一町の差で間に合わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, it was just a little late; when Komahime was killed, the post horse was only a town before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was too late; when Komahime was killed, the post horse was only one town away.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was too late; Komahime was killed when the horse was only approximately 109 meters away.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>享年15。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その従容とした死に様は、さすが大名の娘であるといわしめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died so bravely that everybody was impressed with it, saying she was a real daughter of Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died so bravely that everybody was impressed with it, saying she was the real daughter of a Daimyo (a Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died so bravely that everybody was impressed with it, saying she was the real daughter of a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>辞世の句は｢罪をきる弥陀の剣にかかる身のなにか五つの障りあるべき」（慈悲深い弥陀様の剣に斬られる私に、どうして往生できない五つの罪があるのでしょうか）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her death haiku (Japanese poem) was `I will be killed by the sword of merciful Mida (Amitabha) who brings criminals to justice, and I certainly did not commit any of five sins that kept someone from going to heaven.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her death haiku (Japanese poem) was `I will be killed by the sword of merciful Mida (Amitabha) who brings criminals to justice, and I have certainly not commited any of the five sins that prevents someone from ascending to heaven&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her death poem was &apos;I will be killed by the sword of merciful Mida (Amitabha) who brings criminals to justice, and I have certainly not committed any of the five sins that prevents someone from ascending to heaven&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この辞世は彼女愛用の着物で表装され、他の処刑者のものとともに京都国立博物館に保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This death haiku (Japanese poem) was covered by her favorite Kimono, and is kept in Kyoto National Museum with those of other executed concubines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This death haiku (Japanese poem) was covered by her favorite Kimono, and is kept in the Kyoto National Museum with those of other executed concubines.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This death poem, covered by her favorite kimono, is kept in the Kyoto National Museum with those of other executed concubines.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>複製品は京都・瑞泉寺、山形市・最上義光歴史館で見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its replicas are in Kyoto Zuisen-ji Temple and in Mogami Yoshiaki Historical Museum in Yamagata City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its replicas are in Kyoto Zuisen-ji Temple and in Mogami Yoshiaki Historical Museum in Yamagata City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its copies are in Kyoto Zuisen-ji Temple and in Mogami Yoshiaki Historical Museum in Yamagata City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>彼女らの遺体は遺族が引き渡しを願ったが許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The families of concubines asked to take their bodies back, but it was not approved.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The families of the concubines requested to repatiate their bodies, but this was refused.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The families of the concubines requested to hand over their bodies, but it was refused.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その場で掘られた穴に投げ込まれ、さらにその上に「畜生塚」と刻まれた碑が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bodies were thrown into a hole instantly dug, and on which a monument that contained the word of `Chikushozuka&apos; (Mound of Beasts) was placed.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bodies were thrown into a hole dug impromptu, and a monument was placed on it which had inscribed the word of `Chikushozuka&apos; (Mound of Beasts).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bodies were thrown into a hole dug impromptu, and a monument was placed on it which had inscribed threeon the words of &apos;Chikushozuka&apos; (Mound of Beasts).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そのむごたらしさに都人は浅ましいとも何とも言いようがない思いを感じたと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What they did was so brutal that Kyoto citizens felt that they couldn&apos;t express their feelings even using the word of shameless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What they did was so brutal that the Kyoto citizens felt that even the word &apos;shameless&apos; could not express their disgust.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What they did was so brutal that the Kyoto citizens felt that even the word &apos;shameless&apos; could not express their disgust.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>娘の死を聞いた母の大崎夫人も、悲しみのあまり処刑の14日後に亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaki fujin (lady), Komahime&apos;s mother, was filled with sorrow when she heard her daughter&apos;s death, and then she passed away in sadness fourteen days after her daughter died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaki fujin (lady), Komahime&apos;s mother, was filled with sorrow when she heard of her daughter&apos;s death, and then she passed away in mourning fourteen days after her daughter died.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komahime&apos;s mother Lady Osaki was filled with sorrow when she heard of her daughter&apos;s death, and passed away in mourning fourteen days after the execution.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>自殺と推察されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was deemed as a suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was deemed a suicide.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was deemed a suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>義光の憤激と悲嘆も激しく、この悲劇がのちに彼が関ヶ原の戦いで東軍に属すきっかけになったという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu&apos;s fury and grief were very intense, and some people said this tragedy caused Yoshimitsu to join the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu&apos;s fury and grief were very intense, and some people said this tragedy caused Yoshimitsu to join the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu was in quite intensive fury and grief, and some people said this tragedy caused Yoshimitsu to join the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>駒姫の死の翌年、義光は高擶で布教中の真宗僧乗慶に帰依した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year of Komahime&apos;s death, Yoshimitsu became a believer of a monk of Shinshu sect, Jokei who was propagating in Takatama.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year of Komahime&apos;s death, Yoshimitsu became a follower of a monk of the Shinshu sect, Jokei, who was proselytizing in Takatama.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year of Komahime&apos;s death, Yoshimitsu became a follower of a monk of the Shinshu sect, Jokei, who was preaching in Takatama.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>専称寺 (山形市)を山形城下に移し、駒姫と大崎夫人の菩提寺とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He moved Sensho-ji Temple (Yamagata City) to Yamagata-jo Castle town, and made it a family temple for Komahime and Osaki fujin.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved Sensho-ji Temple (Yamagata City) to Yamagata-jo Castle town, and made it a family temple for Komahime and Osaki fujin.</e>
<cmt>If the lettering in red is correct, it should be explained because this word does not exist in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved Sensho-ji Temple (Yamagata City) to the Yamagata-jo Castle town, and made it a family temple for Komahime and Lady Osaki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>さらに慶長3年（1598年）、八町四方の土地と寺領14石を寄進し城下最大の伽藍を建立、敷地に村山地方の真宗寺院十三ケ寺を塔頭として集め、のちに寺町と呼ばれるようになる町を整備した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, in 1598, he donated fourteen koku (a unit of volume) of temple estate, had the biggest Buddhist temple in a castle town built, and gathered thirteen Shinshu sect temples in Muraya area as tatchu (sub-temples in the site of main temple), maintaining the town which would be called as a temple town later.</e>
<cmt>八町四方の土地→定訳・読み共に不明なため訳文には反映していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in 1598, he donated fourteen koku (a unit of volume) of a temple estate, had the biggest Buddhist temple in a castle town built, and gathered thirteen Shinshu sect temples in the Muraya area as tatchu (sub-temples in the site of the main temple), maintaining the town which would be called as a temple town later.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in 1598, he donated approximately eight hectare patch of land and fourteen koku (a unit of volume) of a temple estate, had the biggest Buddhist temple in a castle town built, and gathered thirteen Shinshu sect temples in the Murayama area as tatchu (sub-temples in the site of the main temple), maintaining the town which would be called as a temple town later.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この寺には、山形城より駒姫の居室が移築されており、大崎夫人像とともに彼女の肖像画が保存されている（なお、広く知られている彼女の肖像画は大正期に描かれたものである。もとの画は尼僧姿のもの）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this temple, Komahime&apos;s room in Yamagata Castle was built in, and her portrait was preserved as well as Osaki fujin&apos;s (her well-known portrait was drawn in the Tasho period while the original one was in a priest style).</e>
<cmt>本来一文であると思われるため、セルB41を40に結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this temple was built Komahime&apos;s room in Yamagata Castle and her portrait was preserved along with Osaki fujin&apos;s (her well-known portrait was drawn in the Tasho period while the original one was in a priest style).</e>
<cmt>wording; If the lettering in red is correct, it should be explained because this word does not exist in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this temple, Komahime&apos;s room was relocated from Yamagata-jo Castle and her portrait was preserved along with that of Lady Osaki (her well-known portrait was drawn in the Taisho period while the original one was in a priest style).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>駒姫の悲劇性とその後への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komahime&apos;s tragedy and How it influenced subsequent history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komahime&apos;s tragedy and the way it influenced subsequent history</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komahime&apos;s tragedy and the way it influenced later history</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>当時の武家社会でも男子はともかく女性は助けられるのが慣例であり、秀吉が秀次の妻妾子女ほぼ全員を処刑したのはそれを無視したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Samurai society at that time, women were accustomed to be saved apart from men, Hideyoshi ignored it by executing almost all the family members of Hidetsugu; a wife, concubines, children.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Samurai society at that time, women were accustomed to being treated differently from men, Hideyoshi ignored this by executing almost all the family members of Hidetsugu; a wife, concubines, and children.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the samurai society at that time, women were accustomed to being treated differently from men, but Hideyoshi ignored this by executing almost all the family members of Hidetsugu; a wife, concubines, and children.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>幼い駒姫の死や、遺骸の処理は当時の社会通念からしても明らかに不当かつ残忍極まりないものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Execution of young Komahime and treatment of dead bodies were obviously unjust and brutal, which was not socially accepted even at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Execution of young Komahime and the treatment of the dead bodies were obviously unjust and brutal, which was not socially accepted even at that time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Execution of young Komahime and the treatment of the dead bodies were obviously unjust and brutal, which were not socially accepted even at that time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>最上家はもちろん諸大名、世間一般にもショッキングなものと受け取られたことは想像に難くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not hard to imagine that it shocked many Daimyos and the world as well as the Mogami family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not hard to imagine that it shocked many Daimyo and the Japanese society as well as the Mogami family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not hard to imagine that it shocked many feudal lords and the Japanese society as well as the Mogami family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="36">
<j>ちなみにごく一部ではあるが、秀次の妻子でも助命されたものもいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a few of Hidetsugu&apos;s wives and children, incidentally were saved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a few of Hidetsugu&apos;s wives and children, incidentally, were saved.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, a few of Hidetsugu&apos;s wives and children were saved, however.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>駒姫がまだ実質的な側室ではなかったにも関わらず、助命嘆願を無視して処刑されたことを考えると、当時義光が秀吉から冷遇されていたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was certain that Yoshimitsu was treated unfavorably then given that Komahime was executed, although she was not practically Hidetsugu&apos;s concubine yet and Yoshimitsu pleaded for saving her life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was certain that Yoshimitsu was treated unfavorably, given that Komahime was executed, despite not yet being Hidetsugu&apos;s actual concubine and Yoshimitsu&apos;s pleas to have her life spared.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was certain that Yoshimitsu was treated unfavorably by Hideyoshi, given that Komahime was executed, despite not yet being Hidetsugu&apos;s actual concubine and Yoshimitsu&apos;s pleas to have her life spared.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この事件以降、義光は反豊臣急先鋒となり、慶長出羽合戦では奥羽における東軍の要として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu turned out to be a leading edge of anti-TOYOTOMI after this incident, and he was active as a key part of the East squad in Ou (Mutsu Province and Dewa Province) in the Battle of Dewa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu became the spearhead of the anti-TOYOTOMI faction after this incident, and he was active as a key part of the East squad in Ou (Mutsu Province and Dewa Province) in the Battle of Dewa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu became an active leader of the anti-Toyotomi faction after this incident, and he was active as a key figure of the East squad in Ou (Mutsu Province and Dewa Province) in the Battle of Dewa in the Keicho Era.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この惨劇は豊臣政権の寿命を縮める一要因ともなったわけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, this tragedy turned out to be one of causes that reduced the life of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, this tragedy turned out to be one of the causes that reduced the life of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, this tragedy turned out to be one of the causes that cut short the life of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 立つのかよ(id:111350), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 帝皇(id:112059), Cprobot(id:97843), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>