<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大幾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大幾（だいき）は日本の戦国時代 (日本)、安土桃山時代の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki lived in Sengoku Period (in Japan) and Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiki lived during the Sengoku Period (in Japan) and Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiki lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) and Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→Sengoku period (period of warring states)period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>臨済宗の僧侶である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki was a Buddhism priest of Rinzai-shu faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiki was a Buddhism priest of the Rinzai-shu faction.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiki was a Buddhism priest of the Rinzai sect.</e>
<cmt>臨済宗→Rinzai sect</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>織田信長と豊臣秀吉の信認を得て、そのブレーンとして活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki obtained confidence of Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and played important roles for them as a member of their brains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He obtained the trust of both Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and played important roles as a think tank for both individuals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He obtained the trust of both Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and played important roles as a think tank for both individuals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>備中国下道郡久代村横田（現在の岡山県総社市久代）に生まれ、幼少時に地元・久代村横田の天福寺（天福禅寺）で小僧となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki was born in Yokota in Hisashiro village in Shimomichi county in Bicchu Province (currenly, Hisashiro in Fusashiro City in Okayama Prefecture) and, wihen he was a child, became a young Buddhism monk in Tenpuku-ji temple (Tempukuzen-ji temple) in his home town, Yokota in Hisashiro village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiki was born in Yokota in Hisashiro village in Shimomichi county in Bicchu Province (currenly, Hisashiro in Fusashiro City in Okayama Prefecture) and, when he was a child, became a young Buddhism monk in Tenpuku-ji temple (Tempukuzen-ji temple) in his home town, Yokota in Hisashiro village.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiki was born in Yokota, Hisashiro village, Shimomichi county, Bicchu Province (currently, Hisashiro, Fusashiro City in Okayama Prefecture) and, when he was a child, became a young Buddhism monk in Tenpuku-ji Temple (Tempukuzen-ji Temple) in his home town, Yokota, Hisashiro village.</e>
<cmt>currentlyスペル訂正しました。住所訂正しました、in Yokota, Hisashiro village, Shimomichi county, Bicchu Province (currently, Hisashiro, Fusashiro City in Okayama Prefecture)Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>のち雪舟も出家した井山の宝福寺 (総社市)満足庵で正式に出家し、その後京都の東福寺に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Daiki formally became a priest in Manzoku-an hermitage in Hofuku-ji temple (currently, in Fusashiro City) in Iyama where Sesshu also had become a priest and Daiki later on moved to Tofuku-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Daiki formally became a priest in Manzoku-an hermitage in Hofuku-ji temple (currently, in Fusashiro City) in Iyama where Sesshu also had become a priest and Daiki later on moved to Tofuku-ji temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Daiki formally became a priest in Manzoku-an hermitage in Hofuku-ji Temple in Iyama (currently, Soja City) where Sesshu also had become a priest and Daiki later on moved to Tofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Temple大文字にしました。総社市→Soja Cityin Iyama (currently, Soja City) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>天正9年（1581年）2月に織田信長の使者として備中国経山城主中島元行に使いをし、信長方への加勢を要請。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1581, Daiki brought a message to Motoyuki NAKAJIMA, the lord of Tsuneyama-jo castle in Bicchu Province as a messenger of Nobunaga ODA and demanded reinforcements for Nobunaga&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1581, Daiki brought a message to Motoyuki NAKAJIMA, the lord of Tsuneyama-jo castle in Bicchu Province as a messenger of Nobunaga ODA and demanded reinforcements for Nobunaga&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1581, Daiki brought a message to Motoyuki NAKAJIMA, the lord of Tsuneyama-jo Castle in Bicchu Province as a messenger of Nobunaga ODA and demanded reinforcements for Nobunaga&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>Castle大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>信長の死後は秀吉に仕え活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga died, Daiki served Hideyoshi playing an important role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga died, Daiki played an important role while serving Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga died, Daiki played an important role while serving Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>秀吉の要請によって朝鮮に渡り、当地の人情、風俗などを調査し、文禄・慶長の役に参画する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki went to Korea by request of Hideyoshi, surveyed on the human nature, customs, etc., of Korea, and participated Bunroku War and Keicho War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiki went to Korea at the request of Hideyoshi, in order to survey human nature, customs, etc., of Korea, and participate in the Bunroku and Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiki went to Korea at the request of Hideyoshi, in order to survey human nature, customs, etc., of Korea, and participate in the Bunroku and Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、豊臣秀頼の養育係を依頼され、その任に付くが、しばらくして、建仁寺の文英清韓を代役として推挙して地元に帰郷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Daiki was asked to be the nursing tutor of Hideyori TOYOTOMI and accepted the position, however, after a while, he recommended Seikan BUNEI of Kennin-ji temple as his substitute and returned to his home town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Daiki was asked to be the nursing tutor for Hideyori TOYOTOMI which he accepted, however, after a while, he recommended Seikan BUNEI of Kennin-ji temple as his substitute and returned to his home town.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Daiki was asked to be the nursing tutor for Hideyori TOYOTOMI which he accepted, however, after a while, he recommended Seikan BUNEI of Kennin-ji Temple as his substitute and returned to his home town.</e>
<cmt>Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宝福寺満足庵の住職となり、久代村横田才の鼻にて示寂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki became the chief priest of Manzoku-an hermitage of Hofuku-ji temple and died in front of a wise man in Yokota in Hisashiro village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiki became the chief priest of Manzoku-an hermitage of Hofuku-ji temple and died in front of a wise man in Yokota in Hisashiro village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiki became the chief priest of Manzoku-an hermitage of Hofuku-ji Temple and died in Saigahana, Yokota, Hisashiro village.</e>
<cmt>Temple大文字にしました。才の鼻→才ヶ鼻で、地名です。in Saigahana, Yokota, Hisashiro villageとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天福寺に墓と石碑がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiki&apos;s grave and a stone monument for him were in Tenpulu-ji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiki&apos;s grave and a stone monument are located in Tenpulu-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiki&apos;s grave and a stone monument are located in Tenpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Tenpuku-ji Templeスペル訂正、Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), Cardshw(id:152276), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>