<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>菅原為長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SUGAWARA no Tamenaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SUGAWARA no Tamenaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SUGAWARA no Tamenaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>菅原 為長（すがわら の ためなが、保元3年（1158年） - 寛元4年3月28日 (旧暦)（1246年4月15日））は平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SUGAWARA no Tamenaga (1158 - April 15, 1246) was a Kugyo(the top court officials) who lived from the end of the Heian period to the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SUGAWARA no Tamenaga (1158 - April 15, 1246) was a Kugyo(the top court officials) who lived from the end of the Heian period to the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SUGAWARA no Tamenaga (1158 - April 22, 1246) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) who lived from the end of the Heian period to the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>初名を忠親、別名高辻 為長とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Tadachika, he is also known as TAKATSUJI no Tamenaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Tadachika, he is also known as TAKATSUJI no Tamenaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Tadachika, he is also known as TAKATSUJI no Tamenaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>保元3年（1158年）、菅原長守（高辻長守）（従四位上・大学頭）の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as a son of SUGAWARA no Nagamori (TAKATSUJI no Nagamori) who was at the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and assumed the position of Daigaku no kami (Chief of the Bureau of Education) in 1158.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as a son of SUGAWARA no Nagamori (TAKATSUJI no Nagamori) who was at the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and assumed the position of Daigaku no kami (Chief of the Bureau of Education) in 1158.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as a son of SUGAWARA no Nagamori (TAKATSUJI no Nagamori) who was at the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and assumed the position of Daigaku no kami (Chief of the Bureau of Education) in 1158.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>元暦2年（1185年）に秀才、次いで文治3年（1187年）に献策。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1185, he became a Shusai (government official), then a Kensaku(government adviser) in 1187.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1185, he became a Shusai (government official), then a Kensaku(government adviser) in 1187.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1185, he became a Shusai (government official), then a Kensaku (government adviser) in 1187.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同年位階に叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これ以降、五摂家のひとつ九条家の家司として仕えることとなり、その間、九条家の子弟に対して家業である紀伝道（文章道）の教育にも当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he began to serve as a Keishi (the steward) for the Kujo family, one of the Gosekke (the five Sekke regent family) and during that period, he taught the children of the Kujo family about Kidendo (historical science), also called Monjodo(Chinese classics), which was their family business..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he began to serve as a Keishi (the steward) for the Kujo family, one of the Gosekke (the five Sekke regent family) and during that period, he taught the children of the Kujo family about Kidendo (historical science), also called Monjodo(Chinese classics), which was their family business..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he began to serve as a Keishi (the steward) for the Kujo family, one of the Gosekke (the five Sekke regent family) and during that period, he taught the children of the Kujo family about Kidendo (historical science), also called Monjodo (Chinese classics), which was their family business..</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>以後、官位は兵部省、中務省、式部省等を経て、元久元年（1204年）には歴代菅原氏が叙任される文章博士に昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he worked for Hyobusho (the Ministry of War), Nakatsukasasho (the Ministry of Central Affairs), then Shikibusho (the Ministry of Ceremonial) and he was promoted to the rank of Monjohakase (Doctor of Letters) which was successively assumed by the Sugawara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he worked for Hyobusho (the Ministry of War), Nakatsukasasho (the Ministry of Central Affairs), then Shikibusho (the Ministry of Ceremonial) and he was promoted to the rank of Monjohakase (Doctor of Letters) which was successively assumed by the Sugawara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he worked for Hyobusho (the Ministry of War), Nakatsukasasho (the Ministry of Central Affairs), then Shikibusho (the Ministry of Ceremonial) and, in 1204, he was promoted to the rank of Monjohakase (Doctor of Letters) which was successively assumed by the Sugawara clan.</e>
<cmt>in 1204補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同年土御門天皇の侍読となり、以降順徳天皇・後堀河天皇・四条天皇・後嵯峨天皇の5代の天皇に渡り侍読を務めることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he became a Jidoku (imperial tutor) for Emperor Tsuchimikado and from then on, he had been serving as Jidoku for five generations of the emperors:Emperor Juntoku; Emperor Gohorikawa; Emperor Shojo and Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he became a Jidoku (imperial tutor) for Emperor Tsuchimikado and from then on, he served as Jidoku for five generations of emperors:Emperor Juntoku; Emperor Gohorikawa; Emperor Shojo and Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he became a Jidoku (imperial tutor) for Emperor Tsuchimikado and from then on, he served as Jidoku for five generations of emperors: Emperor Juntoku; Emperor Gohorikawa; Emperor Shijo and Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。Shijoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>建暦元年（1211年）には、従三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1211, he was promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1211, he was promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1211, he was promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>公卿に列せられるが、菅原氏から公卿を輩出するのは、1009年に薨去した菅原輔正以来、200数年ぶりの快挙であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was raised to the Kugyo (the top court officials), and it was the first feat in 200 years since SUGAWARA no Sukemasa who had died in 1009.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was raised to the Kugyo (the top court officials), which was the first time that this had happened in 200 years since SUGAWARA no Sukemasa who had died in 1009.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was raised to the Kugyo (the top court officials), which was the first time that this had happened in 200 years since SUGAWARA no Sukemasa who had died in 1009.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（既に1歳年少の氏長者菅原在高が従三位となっていた事実は措いておくとしても）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(excluding the fact that SUGAWARA no Aritaka who was a Ujichoja (chieftain of the family)and one year younger than him was in the rank of Jusanmi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(excluding the fact that SUGAWARA no Aritaka who was a Ujichoja (chieftain of the family)and one year younger than him was in the rank of Jusanmi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Excluding the fact that SUGAWARA no Aritaka who was a Ujichoja (chieftain of the family) and one year younger than him was in the rank of Jusanmi.)</e>
<cmt>Excluding大文字にしました。ピリオド補足しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>更に建保3年（1215年）には大蔵省に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to Okurasho(the Ministry of the Treasury) in 1215.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred to Okurasho(the Ministry of the Treasury) in 1215.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred to Okurasho (the Ministry of the Treasury) in 1215.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>以後薨去まで同職に留任することなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he had remained in the same position until he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he remained in the same position until he died.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he remained in the same position until he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（参議に任じられていた2年間を除く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(excluding the two years when he had been assigned to serve as Sangi (royal adviser))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(excluding the two years when he had been assigned to serve as Sangi (royal adviser))</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Excluding the two years when he had been assigned to serve as Sangi (royal adviser).)</e>
<cmt>Excluding大文字にしました。ピリオド補足しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>承久3年（1221年）には正三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1221, he was promoted to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1221, he was promoted to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1221, he was promoted to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>次いで同閏10月には文章博士、大学頭と並び歴代の菅原氏が叙任される式部大輔を兼任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he assumed the position of Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial) which was a position successively given to the Sugawara family as well as Monjohakase and Daigaku no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he assumed the position of Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial) which was a position successively given to the Sugawara family as well as Monjohakase and Daigaku no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, on October of the same year, he assumed the position of Shikibu no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial) which was a position successively given to the Sugawara family as well as Monjohakase and Daigaku no kami.</e>
<cmt>on October of the same year, 補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして終に嘉禎元年（1235年）には、悲願である参議に叙任される（同年6月に勘解由使長官を兼任）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, he was given the longed-for position of Sangi in 1235 (he also assumed the position of Kageyushi chokan(Secretary of the Office of Investigators of the Records of Outgoing Officials) in June of the same year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, he was given the much coveted position of Sangi in 1235 (he also assumed the position of Kageyushi chokan(Secretary of the Office of Investigators of the Records of Outgoing Officials) in June of the same year).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, he was given the much coveted position of Sangi in 1235 (he also assumed the position of Kageyushi chokan (Secretary of the Office of Investigators of the Records of Outgoing Officials) in June of the same year).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>為長の参議叙任は菅原氏においては前述の菅原輔正以来、実に226年ぶりの出来事であり、従三位に叙せられたこと以上の大事件であり、彼の参議叙任に関しては、世間から賛否の渦が生ずることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamenaga was the first Sangi in 226 years after the said SUGAWARA no Sukemasa and it was much bigger incident than the fact that he was given the rank of Jusanmi,thus it caused controversy over his assignment for Sangi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamenaga was the first Sangi in 226 years after SUGAWARA no Sukemasa and it was a much bigger incident than the fact that he was given the rank of Jusanmi,thus it caused much controversy.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamenaga was the first Sangi in 226 years after SUGAWARA no Sukemasa and it was a much bigger incident than the fact that he was given the rank of Jusanmi, thus it caused much controversy.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。、を,に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（「吾妻鏡」承久三年閏十月十日より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; bissextile October 10, 1221)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; bissextile October 10, 1221)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; bissextile December 2, 1221)</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>嘉禎3年（1237年）には参議を辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1237, he resigned from the position of Sangi (royal adviser).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1237, he was resigned from the position of Sangi (royal adviser).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1237, he was resigned from the position of Sangi (royal adviser).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>以後没年まで大蔵卿と勘解由使長官を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had been assumed the position of Okurakyo (Minister of the Ministry of the Treasury) and Kageyushi until the year of death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He assumed the position of Okurakyo (Minister of the Ministry of the Treasury) and Kageyushi until he died.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumed the position of Okurakyo (Minister of the Ministry of the Treasury) and Kageyushi chokan until he died.</e>
<cmt>chokan補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>仁治元年（1240年）11月には正二位に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to the rank of Shonii Senior Second Rank) in November, 1240.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to the rank of Shonii Senior Second Rank) in November, 1240.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in November, 1240.</e>
<cmt>(補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そして寛元4年（1246年）3月28日薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on March 28, 1240.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on March 28, 1240.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on April 22, 1240.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>享年89。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 89.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death was 89.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at death was 89.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>為長の事跡と子孫たちへの影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His footprints and effects on his descendents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His effect on his descendents</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His effect on his descendents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>菅原為長が正二位・参議・大蔵卿叙任という栄誉を勝ち得た理由としては、89歳まで生きたその生命力もさることながら次のようなことが挙げられるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why SUGAWARA no Tamenaga won the honor that he was given the rank and position of Shonii, Sangi and Okurakyo was not only his so much vitality that he lived to age 89, but also the following factors.</e>
<cmt>対訳の形式にしやすいよう、元々B46のセルにあった「といった理由が挙げられよう。」という文をこちらにつなげました(元のB46は削除しました)。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why SUGAWARA no Tamenaga was given the honor of being given the rank and position of Shonii, Sangi and Okurakyo was due in part ot his vitality, (he lived to the ripe age of 89), but also the following factors.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why SUGAWARA no Tamenaga was given the honor of being given the rank and position of Shonii, Sangi and Okurakyo was due in part of his vitality, (he lived to the ripe age of 89), but also the following factors.</e>
<cmt>ofスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>30年以上にわたる大蔵卿在任中に蓄積した経済力</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The economic power that he built up over 30-years tenure of the office of Okurakyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The economic power that he built up over his 30-year tenure as Okurakyo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The economic power that he built up over his 30-year tenure as Okurakyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>大江広元が鎌倉幕府政所初代別当に就任するということに代表されるように、家業の文章道におけるライヴァル的存在の大江氏が朝廷の中心から離脱したこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown in the fact that OE no Hiromoto assumed the position of the first Betto (secretary) in Mandokro (government office) of the Kamakura bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the Oe clan who was a rival in his family business, Monjodo defected from the center of the Imperial Court</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown by the fact that OE no Hiromoto assumed the position of the first Betto (secretary) in Mandokoro (government office) of the Kamakura bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the Oe clan who was a rival in his family business, Monjodo defected from the center of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Robert: Doesn&apos;t make much sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown by the fact that OE no Hiromoto assumed the position of the first Betto (secretary) in Mandokoro (government office) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the Oe clan who was a rival in his family business, Monjodo defected from the center of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>彼が家司として務めていた九条家、特に九条道家が鎌倉幕府に対して親幕府的な態度をとっていたことで承久の乱以降も九条道家の政治顧問として朝廷の中枢に留まった事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kujo family for which Tamenaga served as Keisi, particularly Michiie KUJO was pro-Kamakura bakufu, thus he stayed at the center of the Imperial Court as Michiie KUJO&apos;s political adviser after Jokyu no Ran(Rebellion of Jokyu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kujo family for which Tamenaga served as Keisi, particularly Michiie KUJO was pro-Kamakura bakufu, thus he stayed at the center of the Imperial Court as Michiie KUJO&apos;s political adviser after Jokyu no Ran(Rebellion of Jokyu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kujo family for which Tamenaga served as Keisi, particularly Michiie KUJO was pro-Kamakura bakufu, thus he stayed at the center of the Imperial Court as Michiie KUJO&apos;s political adviser after Jokyu no Ran (Rebellion of Jokyu).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>為長と幕府との関係は北条政子から『貞観政要』の和訳を依頼され、その任に応えている点からも伺う事が可能である（「玉蕊」嘉禎元年正月二十三日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between Tamenaga and bakufu can be seen the fact that Masako HOJO asked him to translate &quot;Joganseiyo&quot; into Japanese (&quot;Gyokuzui&quot; January 23, 1235).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between Tamenaga and bakufu can be seen by the fact that Masako HOJO asked him to translate &quot;Joganseiyo&quot; into Japanese (&quot;Gyokuzui&quot; January 23, 1235).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between Tamenaga and bakufu can be seen by the fact that Masako HOJO asked him to translate &quot;Joganseiyo&quot; into Japanese (&quot;Gyokuzui&quot; February 19, 1235).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>九条家のブレーンとしての実力は、天皇五代に渡って侍読を務めていたことからも証明できるものと考えられ、同じ時期に九条家に仕えた藤原定家からも高く評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that his ability as brains for the Kujo family can be proved by the fact that he had been serving as Jidoku for five generations of the Emperors, also FUJIWARA no Sadaie who served the Kujo family during same period highly evaluated his ability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that his ability as the brains behind the Kujo family can be proven by the fact that he served Jidoku for five generations of Emperors, also FUJIWARA no Sadaie who served the Kujo family during the same period regarded his ability very highly.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that his ability as the brains behind the Kujo family can be proven by the fact that he served Jidoku for five generations of Emperors, also FUJIWARA no Sadaie who served the Kujo family during the same period regarded his ability very highly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、世間から「文道棟梁」「今世之宏才」「当代大才」「国之元老」という賛辞が彼に送られたことも彼の子孫にとって大いなる栄誉となり、明治維新まで堂上家（高辻家・五条家・東坊城家等の六家）として存続できたことの大きな要因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the public compliments for him like &quot;the master of Bumdo (literature)&quot;, &quot;brilliant of the day&quot;. &quot;the most clever man of the day&quot; and &quot;elder statesman of the country&quot;were great honor for his descendants and it was a key factor that they could persist as the Tosho family (one of the six court noble families such as the Takatsuji family, the Gojo family and the Higashibojo family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The public compliments, which included &quot;the master of Bumdo (literature)&quot;, &quot;brilliant of the day&quot;. &quot;the most clever man of the day&quot; and &quot;elder statesman of the country&quot;were a great honor for his descendants and were a key factor in allowing them to persist as the Tosho family (one of the six court noble families such as the Takatsuji family, the Gojo family and the Higashibojo family).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The public compliments, which included &apos;the master of Bumdo (literature),&apos; &apos;brilliant of the day,&apos; &apos;the most clever man of the day&apos; and &apos;elder statesman of the country&apos; were a great honor for his descendants and were a key factor in allowing them to persist as the Tosho family (one of the six court noble families such as the Takatsuji family, the Gojo family and the Higashibojo family).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>子供に、高辻長成（正二位・参議）（1205年－1281年）、五条高長（従二位・式部大輔）（1210年－1284年）（五条家の祖）等がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Nagashige TAKATSUJI (Shonii, Sangi) (1205 - 1281), Takanaga GOJO (Junii (Junior Second Rank), Shikibu no taifu) (1210 -1284) (patriarch of the Gojo family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Nagashige TAKATSUJI (Shonii, Sangi) (1205 - 1281), Takanaga GOJO (Junii (Junior Second Rank), Shikibu no taifu) (1210 -1284) (patriarch of the Gojo family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Nagashige TAKATSUJI (Shonii, Sangi) (1205 - 1281), Takanaga GOJO (Junii (Junior Second Rank), Shikibu no taifu) (1210 -1284) (patriarch of the Gojo family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>主な著作には『帝国系図』（現存せず）『文鳳抄』『国史綱要』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His major literary works were such as &quot;Teikoku keizu&quot;(defunct), &quot;Bunposho&quot; and &quot;Kokushi koyo&quot;, also he left numerous Shibun (poems) and Ganmon (prayer) and contributed to conservation of Kanseki (Chinese books).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His major literary works include &quot;Teikoku keizu&quot;(defunct), &quot;Bunposho&quot; and &quot;Kokushi koyo.&quot; He also left numerous Shibun (poems) and Ganmon (prayer) and contributed to the conservation of Kanseki (Chinese books).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His major literary works include &quot;Teikoku keizu&quot;(defunct), &quot;Bunposho&quot; and &quot;Kokushi koyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>あまたの詩文、願文を残すとともに漢籍の保存にも貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also left numerous Shibun (poems) and Ganmon (prayer) and contributed to the conservation of Kanseki (Chinese books).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>更に日記として『菅大府記』（現存せず）『編御記』（『為長卿記』）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he left diaries such as &quot;Kantaifuki&quot; (defunct) and &quot;Hengyoki&quot; (or &quot;Tamenagakyoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he left diaries such as &quot;Kantaifuki&quot; (defunct) and &quot;Hengyoki&quot; (or &quot;Tamenagakyoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he left diaries such as &quot;Kantaifuki&quot; (defunct) and &quot;Hengyoki&quot; (or &quot;Tamenagakyoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>他にも『十訓抄』の著者に擬せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that he was a author of &quot;Jikkinsho&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also considered that he was the author of &quot;Jikkinsho&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also considered that he was the author of &quot;Jikkinsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 湖沼亭(id:126910), Seibuabina(id:37532), 味っ子(id:17086), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), ウラヌス(id:25954), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>