<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源義朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正室：藤原季範娘（由良御前）常盤御前、三浦義明娘、波多野義通妹、遠江国池田宿遊女、青墓長者大炊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official wife: Daughter of FUJIWARA no Suenori (Yura gozen), Tokiwa gozen, daughter of Yoshiaki MIURA, younger sister of Yoshimichi HATANO, Totoumi Province Ikeda-juku asobime (prostitute), Aohaka choja Oi (rich man&apos;s cook in Aohaka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lawful wives: Yura GOZEN (daughter of FUJIWARA no Suenori); Tokiwa GOZEN; a daughter of Yoshiaki MIURA; a younger sister of Yoshimichi HATANO; a prostitute from Ikeda-juku, Totoumi Province; and the daughter of Aohaka Choja</e>
<cmt>「青墓長者大炊」の訳は仮訳です。（参照：「http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E6%BA%90%E7%BE%A9%E6%9C%9D#cite_note-0」の脚注に基づいた）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lawful wives: Yura GOZEN (daughter of FUJIWARA no Suenori); Tokiwa GOZEN; a daughter of Yoshiaki MIURA; a younger sister of Yoshimichi HATANO; a prostitute from Ikeda-juku, Totoumi Province; and the daughter of Aohaka Choja</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>源 義朝（みなもと の よしとも、1123年 - 1160年） は、平安時代末期の河内源氏の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (1123-1160) was a warlord of the Kawachi Minamoto clan in the end of Heian era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (1123-1160) was a warlord of the Kawachi Minamoto clan who lived toward the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (1123 - 1160) was a warlord of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) who lived toward the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンの前後にスペースKawachi Minamoto clan→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>河内源氏の嫡流、源為義の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, who was in the main branch of the Kawachi Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, who was from the main branch of the Kawachi Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, who was from the main branch of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Kawachi Minamoto clan→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は白河天皇近臣である藤原忠清 (白河院近臣)の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tadakiyo who was a kinshin of the Emperor Shirakawa (trusted vassal of the Cloistered Emperor Shiraka.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tadakiyo, who was a kinshin (trusted vassal of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa.)</e>
<cmt>It&apos;s best to place the translation of a term such as &quot;kinshin&quot; immediately after the term itself.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Tadakiyo, who was a kinshin (trusted vassal of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを）の外に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>源義平・源朝長・源頼朝・源義門・源希義・源範頼・阿野全成・義円・源義経らの父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo&apos;s sons were; MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, MINAMOTO no Tomonaga, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, MINAMOTO no Yoshikado, MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, Zenjo ANO, Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo was the father of MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, MINAMOTO no Tomonaga, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, MINAMOTO no Yoshikado, MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, Zenjo ANO, Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>の父…I believe it is more faithful to keep this as &quot;father&quot; as this keeps the focus on Yoshitomo himself.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo was the father of MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, MINAMOTO no Tomonaga, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, MINAMOTO no Yoshikado, MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, Zenjo ANO, Gien and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>左馬頭、下野国守、播磨国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sama no kami (head of the horse caring), kokushu of Shimotsuke Province, kokushu of Harima Province. After his death, he was awarded the title of Inner Minister with the rank Sho ni-i.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sama no kami (head of caring for horses), kokushu of Shimotsuke Province, kokushu of Harima Province. After his death, he was named an Inner Minister with the rank Shonii.</e>
<cmt>According to the Yougo sheet provided, no spaces or hyphens are needed for Shonii I added &quot;was named&quot; because it makes the sentence sound more natural. Changed word order to caring for horses instead of horse-caring.. Consider even something like &quot;horsemaster&quot; which is a well established term in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sama no kami (head of caring for horses), kokushu (governor) of Shimotsuke Province, kokushu of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処(governor)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>薨後、内大臣正二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death, he was named an Inner Minister with the rank Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処(Senior Second Rank)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>生前、下野守の任にあったことから下野守、また平治の乱にて左馬頭に任ぜられたことから、頭ノ殿と尊称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Shimotsuke no kami because of his position as kokushu of Shimotsuke Province, and also called Ko no tono because of the position of the sama no kami in the event of the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Shimotsuke no kami because of his position as kokushu of Shimotsuke Province, and he was also called Ko no tono because of the position of the sama no kami when the Heiji Rebellion occured.</e>
<cmt>to preserve parallel structure in the event --&gt; when.. Occurred. In the event of sounds like a condition contrary to fact (like if or の場合）.. Clearly not correct.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Shimotsuke no kami because of his position as kokushu of Shimotsuke Province, and he was also called Ko no tono because of the position of the sama no kami when the Heiji Rebellion occurred.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>京都生まれで幼少期を京都で過ごすが、少年期に東国（関東地方）に下向し、上総介氏等の庇護を受け同地で成長した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto and had spent his childhood in Kyoto, then moved to Togoku (Kanto region) in his boyhood and had grown up under the aegis of Kazusa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto and spent his childhood there, then moved to Togoku (Kanto region) in his boyhood and grew up under the aegis of Kazusa clan.</e>
<cmt>I am very confused by the use of pluperfect throughout this sentence. Perhaps I am missing a nuance.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto and spent his childhood there, then moved to Togoku (Kanto region) in his boyhood and grew up under the aegis of Kazusa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため父とは別に東国を根拠地に独自に勢力を伸ばし、相馬御厨・大庭御厨などの支配権をめぐって在地豪族間の争いに介入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he extended power based on Togoku independently from his father and intervened in the conflicts about control of Soma and Oba mikuriyas (dedicated area to Ise shrine) between local powerful families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he extended the power that stemmed from his base in Togoku independently from his father, and he intervened in the conflicts for the control of Soma and Oba mikuriyas, etc., (a dedicated area of Ise shrine) between the families powerful in that locality.</e>
<cmt>I am unsure of the preposition that should be used in relation to Ise shrine and the dedicated area. などの is left untranslated. Rephrased the first sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he extended the power that stemmed from his base in Togoku independently from his father, and he intervened in the conflicts for the control of Soma and Oba mikuriyas, etc., (a dedicated area of Ise shrine) between the families powerful in that locality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その結果、三浦義明・大庭景義ら有力な在地豪族を傘下に収める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, he put some powerful families under control such as Yoshiaki MIURA and Kageyoshi OBA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, he subjugated some of the powerful families there, such as those of Yoshiaki MIURA and Kageyoshi OBA.</e>
<cmt>should family be used instead of &quot;clan&quot; or another word here? The yougo seems to reserve &quot;家&quot; for family …but here we have 豪族</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, he subjugated some of the powerful families there, such as those of Yoshiaki MIURA and Kageyoshi OBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>河内源氏の主要基盤が東国（関東）となったのはこの義朝の代であり、特に高祖父の源頼義以来ゆかりのある鎌倉を中心とする相模国一帯に強い基盤を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his time, the main base of Kawachi Minamoto clan became Togoku (Kanto), especially, the Kawachi Minamoto clan had a strong base in Sagami Province centering on Kamakura, where had been associated since his great-great-grandfather MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in his time that the main base of the Kawachi Minamoto clan became Togoku (Kanto), and especially the Kawachi Minamoto clan had a strong base in Sagami Province centering on Kamakura, with which it had been associated since the time of his great-great-grandfather MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi.</e>
<cmt>many additions to smoothen the translation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in his time that the main base of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) became Togoku (Kanto), and especially the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) had a strong base in Sagami Province centering on Kamakura, with which it had been associated since the time of his great-great-grandfather MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Kawachi Minamoto clan→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、義朝の勢力伸張は関東の他の源氏、特に下野国の足利に本拠を置く義朝の大叔父源義国の勢力と武蔵国などで競合することとなり緊張を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his extending power caused conflicts and produced tension between he and other Minamoto clans in Kanto, especially, in Musashi Province, Yoshitomo competed with MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni, who was his granduncle and had the main base in Ashikaga, Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, extending his power caused conflicts and produced tensions between him and other Minamoto clans in Kanto, especially in the Musashi Province, and Yoshitomo competed with MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni, who was his granduncle, and had the main base in Ashikaga, Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>many additions to smoothen the translation; word order, commas added, etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, extending his power caused conflicts and produced tensions between him and other Minamoto clans in Kanto, especially in the Musashi Province, and Yoshitomo competed with MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni, who was his granduncle, and had the main base in Ashikaga, Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その両者の緊張は、義国の指揮下にいた叔父河内経国が仲介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for their tension, Tunekuni KAWACHI, who was Yoshitomo&apos;s uncle and was controlled under Yoshikuni, brokered a peace deal between them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for these tensions, Tunekuni KAWACHI, who was Yoshitomo&apos;s uncle and was under Yoshikuni, brokered a peace deal between them.</e>
<cmt>many additions to smoothen the translationcontrolled --&gt; deletedShould it be Tsunekuni instead of tunekuni?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for these tensions, Tsunekuni KAWACHI, who was Yoshitomo&apos;s uncle and was under Yoshikuni, brokered a peace deal between them.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除Tunekuni→Tsunekuni</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>義国と義朝が同盟を締結し盟友となることで解消され、両者の勢力を保持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikuni and Yoshitomo became allies and kept balance between both powers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikuni and Yoshitomo became allies, and both maintained power.</e>
<cmt>it seems that one of the phrases a the beginning of this clause is omitted, but it is slightly redundant anyway.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikuni and Yoshitomo became allies, and both maintained power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後上洛し、義国の子の源義康（足利義康）と義朝は親しくなり、義国・義康父子と義朝は連携を強めることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yoshitomo went to Kyoto and got along with Yoshikuni&apos;s son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu (Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA), that strengthened alliance with Yoshitomo and father and son pair Yoshikuni and Yoshiyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yoshitomo went to Kyoto and befriended Yoshikuni&apos;s son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu (Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA), and that strengthened the alliance between Yoshitomo and the father and son pair of Yoshikuni and Yoshiyasu.</e>
<cmt>get along with is not strong enough phrasing. Added &quot;the&quot; &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yoshitomo went to Kyoto and befriended Yoshikuni&apos;s son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu (Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA), and that strengthened the alliance between Yoshitomo and the father and son pair of Yoshikuni and Yoshiyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして義康とともに義朝は鳥羽天皇や藤原忠通にも接近、仁平3年（1153年）には下野国守に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo and Yoshiyasu moved to improve the relationship with the Emperor Toba and FUJIWARA no Tadamichi and Yoshitomo was appointed as kokushu of Shimotsuke Province in 1153.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo and Yoshiyasu moved to improve their relationship with the Emperor Toba and FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, and Yoshitomo was appointed as kokushu of Shimotsuke Province in 1153.</e>
<cmt>removed space added comma the --&gt; their</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo and Yoshiyasu moved to improve their relationship with the Emperor Toba and FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, and Yoshitomo was appointed as kokushu of Shimotsuke Province in 1153.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>下野守となった義朝と在地領主である源義国の結縁はこの時期にさらに強固になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between Yoshitomo who became the kokushu of Shimotsuke Province and Yoshikuni who was the local feudal lord of Shimotsuke Province got reinforced in this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between Yoshitomo, who became the kokushu of Shimotsuke Province, and Yoshikuni, who was the local feudal lord of Shimotsuke Province, was reinforced at this time as well.</e>
<cmt>need to set off relative clauses with commas as well is not present in the japanese but it helps it flow with the sentence before.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between Yoshitomo, who became the kokushu of Shimotsuke Province, and Yoshikuni, who was the local feudal lord of Shimotsuke Province, was reinforced at this time as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>一説によれば、義朝が幼少期に河内源氏の本拠地河内国のある畿内を離れ東国に下ったのは、父の為義から廃嫡同然に勘当されたためではないかとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory holds that the reason Yoshitomo moved to Togoku from Kinai (area near Kyoto) which includes Kawachi Province as the base of the Kawachi Minamoto clan, is that he was cut off by his father Tameyoshi as like disinherited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory holds that the reason Yoshitomo moved to Togoku from Kinai (area near Kyoto that includes Kawachi Province as the base of the Kawachi Minamoto clan) is that he was relations were cut by his father Tameyoshi and he was disinherited.</e>
<cmt>was cut off -&gt;relations were cut as like-&gt; was both sound more formal rephrasing this as parenthetical makes it much more easy to read.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory holds that the reason Yoshitomo moved to Togoku from Kinai (area near Kyoto that includes Kawachi Province as the base of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)) is that relations were cut by his father Tameyoshi and he was disinherited.</e>
<cmt>Kawachi Minamoto clan→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)he was削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため、義朝の東国での動きを牽制するために遣わされたのが弟の源義賢であるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, his younger brother MINAMOTO no Yoshikata was said to be sent down to Togoku to keep Yoshitomo in check.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, his younger brother MINAMOTO no Yoshikata was said to be sent down to Togoku to keep Yoshitomo in check.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, his younger brother MINAMOTO no Yoshikata was said to be sent down to Togoku to keep Yoshitomo in check.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）、父の為義の意向を受けて東国に下向し勢力を伸ばしていた義賢を15歳の長男・源義平に討たせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo ordered his 15-year-old first son to kill Yoshikata, who moved to Togoku and had extended influences on behalf of his father Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo ordered his eldest, 15-year-old son to kill Yoshikata, who had moved to Togoku and extended influences on behalf of his father Tameyoshi in the year 1155.</e>
<cmt>first --&gt; eldestadded &quot;in the year 1155). IMPORTANT add a translation for 久寿2年</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo ordered his eldest, 15-year-old son, MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, to kill Yoshikata, who had moved to Togoku and extended influences on behalf of his father Tameyoshi in the year 1155.</e>
<cmt>MINAMOTO no Yoshihira補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このため、もう一人の弟源頼賢が復仇のため信濃国に下り、頼賢と合戦になりかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, his another younger brother MINAMOTO no Yorikata sent down to Shinano Province to avenge Yoshikata and they came close to a war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, another younger brother of his, MINAMOTO no Yorikata, was sent down to Shinano Province to avenge Yoshikata, and war almost broke out.</e>
<cmt>his another --&gt; Xthey came close to a war --&gt; war almost broke out added comma to join 2 independent clauses.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, another younger brother of his, MINAMOTO no Yorikata, was sent down to Shinano Province to avenge Yoshikata, and war almost broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>保元の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogen Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogen Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogen Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱の際に崇徳天皇方の父為義、弟の頼賢・源為朝らと袂を分かち、平清盛と共に後白河天皇方として戦い勝利する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the event of Hogen Rebellion, while his father Tameyoshi, his brothers Yorikata and MINAMOTO no Tametomo were on the side of the Emperor Sutoku, Yoshitomo got on the side of the Emperor Go-Shirakawa with TAIRA no Kiyomori and won the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hogen Rebellion, while his father Tameyoshi, his brothers Yorikata and MINAMOTO no Tametomo were allied with the Emperor Sutoku, Yoshitomoallied with the Emperor Go-Shirakawa with TAIRA no Kiyomori, and won the war.</e>
<cmt>allied with is more formal than &quot;got on the side of&quot; Removed &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hogen Rebellion, in 1156, while his father Tameyoshi, his brothers Yorikata and MINAMOTO no Tametomo were allied with the Emperor Sutoku, Yoshitomo allied with the Emperor Goshirakawa with TAIRA no Kiyomori, and won the war.</e>
<cmt>in 1156,補足Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>乱後、左馬頭に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, he was appointed as sama no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, he was appointed sama no kami.</e>
<cmt>as --&gt; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, he was appointed sama no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、義朝の戦功に代えての助命嘆願にもかかわらず為義・頼賢ら親兄弟の多くが処刑され、更に論功行賞でも清盛より低い官位に甘んじたことから大いに不満を持った、とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was said to complain about bad treatments, for example, most his family such as Tameyoshi and Yorikata were executed in spite of his sparing them in place of his achievement and also, his rewarded post was lower than Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was said to complain about very bad treatment, for example, most his family such as Tameyoshi and Yorikata were executed in spite of his having spared them; moreover, despite his achievements the post with which he was rewarded was lower than that of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;very&quot; substantial rephrasing of the last clause.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was said to complain about very bad treatment, for example, most his family such as Tameyoshi and Yorikata were executed in spite of his having spared them; moreover, despite his achievements the post with which he was rewarded was lower than that of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、清盛は少年の頃より親王にも等しい待遇を受け、11歳で元服と同時に叙爵されて従五位下、17歳にして既に従四位下にまで官位を上げ、保元の乱の10年も前に正四位下となり公卿の地位の一歩手前にまで達しており、対して義朝は保元の乱の直前に叙爵されて従五位下・下野守となりようやく受領レベルとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kiyomori had been treated as like imperial prince since his childhood and his rank was Ju go-i no ge when he was 11 years old at the ceremony of his coming of age, Ju shi-i no ge at age 17, and Sho shi-i no ge at 10 years before the Hogen Rebellion and he was almost kugyo while Yoshitomo was rewarded as Ju go-i no ge and kokushu of Shimotsuke Province as zuryo just before the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kiyomori had been treated as an imperial prince since his childhood, and his rank was Jugoi no ge when he was 11 years old at the ceremony of his coming of age, Jushii no ge at age 17, and Shoshii no ge at 10 years before the Hogen Rebellion, and he was almost named kugyo, while Yoshitomo was rewarded by being named Jugoi no ge and kokushu of Shimotsuke Province as zuryo just before the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>removed spaces and hyphens, added a few words for clarity &quot;being named&quot; etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kiyomori had been treated as an imperial prince since his childhood, and his rank was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) when he was 11 years old at the ceremony of his coming of age, Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) at age 17, and Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) at 10 years before the Hogen Rebellion, and he was almost Kugyo (the top court official), while Yoshitomo was rewarded by being named Jugoinoge and kokushu of Shimotsuke Province as Zuryo (the highest official of province) just before the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Jugoi no ge→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)Jushii no ge→Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)Shoshii no ge→Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)「公卿」と「受領」の説明を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>そのため、清盛と義朝の地位にはもともと大きな開きがあり、恩賞の差に不満を抱いたという説明はあまり妥当とはいえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the reason that he complained about the mdifferences between Yoshitomo and Kiyomori is not appropriate, because there had been big differences between them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the reasons for which he complained about the differences in rewarding the merits of Yoshitomo and Kiyomori were not appropriate, because there had long been large differences between them.</e>
<cmt>several minor changes. Added &quot;long&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the reasons for which he complained about the differences in rewarding the merits of Yoshitomo and Kiyomori were not appropriate, because there had long been large differences between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>また、左馬頭はその位階以上に武門にとってはそれこそ武士の棟梁にも比されるほどの重要な官位であるから、それへの任官は妥当、むしろ破格な恩賞であるという意見も近年では提示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the recent theory, the status of sama no kami was very important post for samurai like a toryo (leader for samurai), therefore, the achievement of sama no kami was a preferential treatment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to recent theory, the status of sama no kami was a very important one for a samurai like a toryo (leader of samurai), therefore, the achievement of sama no kami consitutes preferential treatment.</e>
<cmt>removed &quot;the&quot;was -_&gt; constitutes status is not the same as a post.Removed &quot;post&quot; for that reason.If you write &quot;a toryo&quot; you must put &quot;a&quot; before samurai.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to recent theory, the status of sama no kami was a very important one for a samurai like a toryo (leader of samurai), therefore, the achievement of sama no kami constitutes preferential treatment.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、為義の処刑はあくまでも彼らを謀反人と断じた朝廷の裁決であり、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the imperial court judged and executed Tameyoshi as a rebel, not Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the imperial court judged and executed Tameyoshi as a rebel, not Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the imperial court judged and executed Tameyoshi as a rebel, not Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>平清盛もまた敵側についた同族を朝命により処刑しており、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Kiyomori executed his own families who were on the enemies side by the order of the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Kiyomori executed his own families who were allied with their enemies by order of the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>IMPORTANT, his own families? Should this be clans? Do we need a modifier like &quot;some of his own&quot; consider substantially altering this.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Kiyomori executed his own families who were allied with their enemies by order of the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このことへの義朝の不満が平治の乱につながったという見方にも疑問が呈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the opinion that Yoshitomo&apos;s complaints provoked the Heiji Rebellion has been questioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the idea that Yoshitomo&apos;s complaints provoked the Heiji Rebellion has been questioned.</e>
<cmt>opinion--&gt; idea.. Not strictly necessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the idea that Yoshitomo&apos;s complaints provoked the Heiji Rebellion has been questioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>（元木泰雄「保元･平治の乱を読み直す」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Rereading the Hogen and Heiji Rebellions&quot; by Yasuo MOTOKI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Rereading the Hogen and Heiji Rebellions&quot; by Yasuo MOTOKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;Rereading the Hogen and Heiji Rebellions&apos; by Yasuo MOTOKI)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>平治の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>平治元年（1159年）12月9日、義朝は源頼政、源光保らと共に藤原信頼と組んで、後白河院の信任厚い藤原信西らがいると目された三条殿を襲撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 9, 1159, Yoshitomo, MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and FUJIWARA no Nobuyori attacked FUJIWARA no Shinzei who had confidence of the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa, in the Sanjo-dono where Nobuyori was supposed to be.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 9, 1159, Yoshitomo, MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and FUJIWARA no Nobuyori attacked FUJIWARA no Shinzei, who had the confidence of the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa, in the Sanjo-dono where Nobuyori was supposed to be.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; and a comma. Unable to verify accuracy of the translation…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 9, 1159, Yoshitomo, MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and FUJIWARA no Nobuyori attacked FUJIWARA no Shinzei, who had the confidence of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, in the Sanjo-dono where Shinzei was supposed to be.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→GoshirakawaNobuyori→Shinzei</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>平治の乱の原因として旧来の説では、義朝の動機を中心に説明されることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the old theories, the cause of the Heiji Rebellion is mainly explained on the basis of Yoshitomo&apos;s motives.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the old theories, the cause of the Heiji Rebellion was usually explained on the basis of Yoshitomo&apos;s motives.</e>
<cmt>is--&gt; was mainly--&gt; usually</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many of the old theories, the cause of Heiji Rebellion is usually attributed to Yoshitomo&apos;s motives.</e>
<cmt>“motives” の意味が不明瞭。I can&apos;t really see what is wrong with &quot;motives&quot; here but I have tried to make the translation read a bit more naturally.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>先に触れたような『平治物語』の記述を史料に、保元の乱での平清盛との恩賞の格差に義朝が不満を抱いたという源氏対平家の因縁説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned before, one is that he complained about the merit reward differences between Yoshitomo and Kiyomori, as a fateful confrontation between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan (&quot;Tale of Heiji&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above in descriptive historical data like that of &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; one theory is that his complaining about the differences in how the accomplishments of Yoshitomo and Kiyomori were rewarded was a cause of the fateful confrontation between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan,</e>
<cmt>の記述を史料に is left out of the translation, and I do not know why…I made significant changes to this. PLEASE VERIFY THIS especially closely. Merits_-&gt; accomplishments</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above in descriptive historical data like that of &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; one theory is that his complaining about the differences in how the accomplishments of Yoshitomo and Kiyomori were rewarded was a cause of the fateful confrontation between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>最後の,を.に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また信西に対しては、信西のあからさまな冷遇を受けたことに対して義朝が不満を募らせ、同じく信西を憎む藤原信頼と組んだという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another is that Yoshitomo complained about Shizei&apos;s discrimination against him and allied with FUJIWARA no Nobuyori who also hated Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another is that Yoshitomo complained about Shizei&apos;s discrimination against him and allied with FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, who also hated Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another is that Yoshitomo complained about Shizei&apos;s discrimination against him and allied with FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, who also hated Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>『愚管抄』の記述を史料に、義朝の縁組の申し入れに対して信西が「我が子は学者であるので、武門の家の聟には相応しくない」と拒否しながら、同じ武家である平家と縁組したことが書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzei rejected Yoshitomo&apos;s offer of marriage saying that his son was scholar and a samurai family was not right for him to marry into, but he contracted a marriage with the Taira clan which was also a samurai family (&quot;Gukansho&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzei rejected Yoshitomo&apos;s offer of marriage, saying that his son was scholar and a samurai family was not right for him to marry into, but then he contracted a marriage with the Taira clan, which was also a samurai family (&quot;Gukansho&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>added a comma. added &quot;then&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzei rejected Yoshitomo&apos;s offer of marriage, saying that his son was a scholar and a samurai family was not right for him to marry into, but then he contracted a marriage with the Taira clan, which was also a samurai family (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>“was scholar”=&gt;”was a scholar”.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また藤原信頼も、『平治物語』には「文にもあらず、武にもあらず、能もなく、また芸もなし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tale of Heiji&quot; said about FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, &apos;he was not intellect, nor warrior, he was stupid and didn&apos;t have any skill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover the &quot;Tale of Heiji&quot; says of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori that &apos;he was not intelligent, nor was he a warrior, rather he was unintelligent and did not have any notable skills.&apos;</e>
<cmt>I made the phrasing more urbane and improved the phrasing. Added one quotation mark.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover the &quot;Tale of Heiji&quot; says of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori that &apos;he was not intelligent, nor was he a warrior, rather he was unintelligent and did not have any notable skills.</e>
<cmt>文が次のセルに続いているため、最後の&apos;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>ただ朝恩にのみほこりて」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He just won the great graces of the emperors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He only won the great graces of the emperors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>just --&gt; onlyadded &quot;however&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He only won the great graces of the emperors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>とどうしようもない能無しのように書かれており、『愚管抄』でも同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also written in the same way in &quot;Gukansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also written of in the same way in &quot;Gukansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also written of in the same way in &quot;Gukansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし、そのような通俗的理解は竹内理三・元木泰雄らの研究により見直されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, those vulgar views of understanding have been reviewed by Rizo TAKEUCHI and Yasuo MOTOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, those unrefined understandings have been reviewed by the research of Rizo TAKEUCHI and Yasuo MOTOKI.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the research&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, those unrefined understandings have been reviewed by the research of Rizo TAKEUCHI and Yasuo MOTOKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>平治の乱の原因は、実際には後白河院政派と二条天皇親政派の対立、そしてその両派ともに反信西グループが居たこと、それらを後白河がまとめきれなかったことにあるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The causes of the Heiji Rebellion were said to be 1) the conflict between the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa&apos;s faction and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction, 2) the anti-Shinzei group were included in each faction, and 3) the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa could not subdue them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The causes of the Heiji Rebellion were said to be the following: 1) the conflict between the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa&apos;s faction and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction, 2) the anti-Shinzei group was included in each faction, and 3) the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa could not subdue them.</e>
<cmt>added &quot; the following&quot; were--&gt; was get under control --&gt; subdue VL</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heiji Rebellion is said to have been caused by the conflict between the factions of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and the Emperor Nijo; the presence of members of the anti-Shinzei group in both factions; and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s inability to subdue them.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>義朝と信頼の関係も信西憎しの一点で結びついたという説は物語としては理解しやすいが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the relationship between Yoshitomo and Nobuyori, the theory that the good relationship was based on their hate for Shinzei is easy to understand as a vulgar belief.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the relationship between Yoshitomo and Nobuyori, it is easy to see that the theory that their good relationship was based on their hatred for Shinzei is a simple-minded belief.</e>
<cmt>hate--&gt; hatred vulgar --&gt; simple-minded VL</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the relationship between Yoshitomo and Nobuyori, it is easy to see that the theory that their good relationship was based on their hatred for Shinzei is a simple-minded belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>義朝が信頼に従ったのは信頼は義朝が南関東で勢力を拡大していたときの武蔵守でその後も知行国主であって、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the reason Yoshitomo followed Nobuyori was that Nobuyori was the Musashi no kami and later became chigyo-kokushu while Yoshitomo had been extending the power in southern Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the reason Yoshitomo followed Nobuyori was that Nobuyori was the Musashi no kami and later became chigyo-kokushu while Yoshitomo had been extending the power in southern Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason Yoshitomo followed Nobuyori was that Nobuyori was the Musashi no kami (the feudal lord of Musashi Province) while Yoshitomo was extending his power in the southern Kanto area and later became chigyo-kokushu (a provincial proprietor with the authority to appoint a provincial governor and collect tax).</e>
<cmt>「知行国主」の説明を補足しました。NR: As this term appears to apply to a person, &quot;which&quot; cannot be used. I decided on &quot;provincial proprietor&quot; based on the following:Ref:http://books.google.com/books?ei=xV6KSqWhNJiBkQXoqvQ2&amp;ct=result&amp;q=%22chigyo-kokushu&amp;btnG=Search+BooksI have added an explanation of &quot;Musashi no kami&quot; as, although the word &quot;kami&quot; has come up before, I don&apos;t think it would be immediately apparent to a native speaker of English what this means.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>義朝の武蔵国への勢力拡大も突然の従五位下・下野守への除目も信頼らの支援があってのことと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo&apos;s extending the power toward Musashi Province and sudden award of Ju go-i no ge and kokushu of the Shimotsuke Province might be based on the support from Nobuyori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo&apos;s extension of power toward the Musashi Province and sudden awarding of the title of Jugoi no ge and kokushu of the Shimotsuke Province might be based on the support of Nobuyori.</e>
<cmt>extending --&gt; extension please verify that &quot;title&quot; is appropriate word chioce for jugoi. Ju go-I --&gt;jugoi</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo&apos;s extension of power toward the Musashi Province and sudden awarding of the title of Jugoinoge and kokushu of the Shimotsuke Province might be based on the support of Nobuyori.</e>
<cmt>Jugoi no ge→Jugoinoge</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>信頼はそうした武蔵国を中心とした地盤から、保元の乱により摂関家家政機構の武力が解体した後においては、それに変わって関東の武士達を京の公家社会に供給出来る立場にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Nobuyori had built the Musashi Province centered basis, he could provide the Kanto samurais to the noble society in Kyoto after dismantle of the military power based on the regent family due to the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Nobuyori had built the Musashi Province centered power base, he could provide the Kanto samurais to the nobles in Kyoto after dismantling the military power based on the regent family due to the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>basis --&gt; power base</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Nobuyori had built the Musashi Province centered power base, he could provide the Kanto samurais to the nobles in Kyoto after dismantling the military power based on the regent family due to the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="47">
<j>三条殿を襲撃し逃れた信西を倒して以降、藤原信頼が政局の中心に立つが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After attacking the Sanjo-dono and defeating Shinzei, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori gained real power in politics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After attacking the Sanjo-dono and defeating Shinzei, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori gained real political power.</e>
<cmt>power in politics --&gt; political power</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After attacking the Sanjo-dono and defeating Shinzei who had once escaped, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori gained real political power.</e>
<cmt>who had once escaped補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>信西を倒したことによって元々信西憎しの一点だけで結びついていた後白河院政派と二条天皇親政派は結束する理由も無くなり空中分解を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, as both the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa&apos;s faction and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction cooperated to defeat Shinzei, after defeating Shinzei, there was no reason to cooperate and their solidarity was broken up.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although originally the Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa&apos;s faction and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction cooperated to defeat Shinzei, after defeating Shinzei, there was no reason to cooperate and their solidarity began to deteriorate.</e>
<cmt>broken up --&gt; lost more normal phrasing with a word like solidarity added &quot;began to&quot; because 始める is found in the original.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although originally the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s faction and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction cooperated to defeat Shinzei, after defeating Shinzei, there was no reason to cooperate and their solidarity began to deteriorate.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>そして今度は藤原信頼と二条天皇親政派との反目が発生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction became at odds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction came to be at odds.</e>
<cmt>purely cosmetic.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction came to be at odds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>離京していた平清盛は勝者・藤原信頼に臣従するそぶりを見せて都に戻るが、その後、二条天皇親政派らの謀略によって二条天皇が清盛六波羅邸に脱出し、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Kiyomori, who had been leaving Kyoto, went back to Kyoto pretending that he would follow the winner FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, but after that, the Emperor Nijo escaped to Kiyomori&apos;s Rokuhara residence by plot of the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Kiyomori, who had left Kyoto, went back to Kyoto pretending that he would serve under the victorious FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, but after that, the Emperor Nijo escaped to Kiyomori&apos;s Rokuhara residence by a plot of the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction.</e>
<cmt>&quot;who had been leaving&quot; I don&apos;t know how best to parse this. &quot;had been about to leave&quot;? &quot;had been preparing to leave&quot;? I am not sure. I went with &quot;had left&quot; because only it seemed to make sense in light of the rest of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Kiyomori, who had left Kyoto, went back to Kyoto pretending that he would serve under the victorious FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, but after that, the Emperor Nijo escaped to Kiyomori&apos;s Rokuhara residence by a plot of the Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>形勢不利を察した後白河法皇も仁和寺に脱出する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa felt the disadvantageous circumstances and escaped to Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Emperor Go-Shirakawa sensed the circumstances were disadvantageous and escaped to Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>felt --&gt;sensed; minor rephrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa sensed the circumstances were disadvantageous and escaped to Ninna-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Go-Shirakawa→Goshirakawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この段階で義朝は全ての梯子を外された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this time, Yoshitomo went against and was isolated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, he was up against the wall and he was isolated.</e>
<cmt>「全ての梯子を外される」 は直訳すると &quot;be taken away all ladders&quot;ですが、英語でわかりやすい表現 (up against the wall) に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, he was up against the wall and isolated.</e>
<cmt>“he was up against the wall and he was isolated.” =&gt;”he was up against the wall and isolated.”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>信頼らに当初同意していた源光保は元々二条天皇親政派であるので信頼陣営から離反、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu agreed with Nobuyori&apos;s group, but he was originally on the side of Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction and seceded from Nobuyori&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu agreed with Nobuyori&apos;s group, but he was originally on the side of Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction, and seceded from his alliance with Nobuyori.</e>
<cmt>added comma. Side -- &gt; alliance. Sounds more formal.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu agreed with Nobuyori&apos;s group, but he was originally on the side of Emperor Nijo&apos;s faction, and seceded from his alliance with Nobuyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>源頼政も信頼陣営から距離を置き、廷臣たちも続々と六波羅に出向いたため、清盛は官軍の地位を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorimasa also seceded from Nobuyori, and many others also moved to Rokuhara, therefore, Kiyomori obtained the justified imperial forces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yorimasa also seceded from Nobuyori, and many others also moved to Rokuhara, therefore, Kiyomori obtained the justified imperial forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorimasa also seceded from Nobuyori, and many others also moved to Rokuhara, therefore, Kiyomori obtained the justified imperial forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>こうして一転賊軍となった信頼・義朝らは討伐の対象となり、ついに12月27日京中で戦闘が開始される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, Nobuyori and Yoshitomo became rebels and the battle for putting down them occurred on December 27 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, Nobuyori and Yoshitomo became rebels, and the battle to put them down them occurred on December 27 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>word order, comma.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Nobuyori and Yoshitomo became rebels, and the battle to put them down occurred on December 27 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>them重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>平家らの官軍に兵数で大幅に劣っていた義朝軍は壊滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Yoshitomo&apos;s army was much less than the imperial army including the Taira clan&apos;s army, and the Yositomo&apos;s army was badly defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of soldiers in Yoshitomo&apos;s army was much smaller that of the imperial army including the Taira clan&apos;s army, and the Yositomo&apos;s army was badly defeated.</e>
<cmt>adding soldiers is justified due to the kanji in 兵数 less--&gt; smaller.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of soldiers in Yoshitomo&apos;s army was much smaller than that of the imperial army including the Taira family&apos;s army, and the Yoshitomo&apos;s army was badly defeated.</e>
<cmt>than補足clan→familyYositomo→Yoshitomo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="57">
<j>その後、藤原信頼を見捨て、長男義平・次男朝長・三男頼朝・一族の源義隆（陸奥六郎義隆）・平賀義信（平賀義信）・源重成（佐渡重成）、家臣の鎌田政清・斉藤実盛・渋谷金王丸らを伴い、東国で勢力挽回を図るべく東海道を下るが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yoshitomo abandoned FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and went to Togoku to regain his power with his first son Yoshihira, the second son Asanaga, the third son Yoritomo, the families MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (later Mutsu Rokuro Yoshitaka), Yoshinobu HIRAGA, MINAMOTO no Shigenari (later Shigenari SADO), his followers Masakiyo KAMATA, Sanemori SAITO and Konnomaru SHIBUYA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yoshitomo abandoned FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and went to Togoku to regain his power with his first son Yoshihira, his second son Asanaga, his third son Yoritomo, the families MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (later Mutsu Rokuro Yoshitaka), Yoshinobu HIRAGA, and MINAMOTO no Shigenari (later Shigenari SADO), his followers Masakiyo KAMATA, Sanemori SAITO and Konnomaru SHIBUYA.</e>
<cmt>the --&gt; his (2x) added &quot;and&quot; once to make the list complete.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yoshitomo abandoned FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and went to Togoku to regain his power with his first son Yoshihira, his second son Asanaga, his third son Yoritomo, the families MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (later Mutsu Rokuro Yoshitaka), Yoshinobu HIRAGA, and MINAMOTO no Shigenari (later Shigenari SADO), his followers Masakiyo KAMATA, Sanemori SAITO and Konnomaru SHIBUYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>その途上たび重なる落武者狩りの襲撃を受け、朝長・義隆・重成は深手を負い亡くなってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way of fleeing, they were often attacked and Asanaga, Yoshitaka and Shigenari died from wounds.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While fleeing, they were often attacked, and Asanaga, Yoshitaka and Shigenari died from injuries sustained during this time..</e>
<cmt>Rephrased, and added a comma. Added quite a few words at the end there because I thought it sounded native.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While fleeing, they were often attacked, and Asanaga, Yoshitaka and Shigenari died from injuries sustained during this time.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また頼朝も一行からはぐれて捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo got separated from the group and was caught.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo got separated from the group and was caught.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo became separatedd from the group and was caught.</e>
<cmt>表現スタイル “Yoritomo got separated” =&gt; “Yoritomo became separated”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>義平は北陸道を目指して一旦離脱するが、また京に戻って潜伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihira went toward Hokuriku-do separately, then went back to Kyoto and hid himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihira went toward Hokuriku-do separately, then went back to Kyoto and hid himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihira went toward Hokuriku-do separately, then went back to Kyoto and hid himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>生き残っていた義朝の郎党の志内景澄と共に報復のため平清盛暗殺を試みるが失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and Yoshitomo&apos;s retainer Kagesumi SHINAI plotted to assassinate TAIRA no Kiyomori in retribution, but it was failed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He and Yoshitomo&apos;s retainer Kagesumi SHINAI plotted to assassinate TAIRA no Kiyomori in retribution, but failed.</e>
<cmt>it was --&gt; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He and Yoshitomo&apos;s retainer Kagesumi SHINAI plotted to assassinate TAIRA no Kiyomori in retribution, but failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="62">
<j>義朝は尾張国にたどり着き、宿をとるため家来の長田忠致のもとに身を寄せるが、長田父子に入浴中に襲撃されてあえない最期を遂げた（『平治物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo reached Owari Province and stayed at his retainer Tadamune OSADA&apos;s residence, but he was killed by Tadatsune and his son while bathing (&quot;Tale of Heiji&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo reached Owari Province and stayed at his retainer Tadamune OSADA&apos;s residence, but he was killed by Tadatsune and his son while bathing (&quot;Tale of Heiji&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo reached Owari Province and stayed at his retainer Tadamune OSADA&apos;s residence, but he was killed by Tadatsune and his son while bathing (&quot;Tale of Heiji&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>享年38であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 38 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 38 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 38 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>『平治物語』によれば、鎌倉時代に入り長田一族は、将軍の父に狼藉を働き殺害した罪をとがめられて処刑されたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; Nagata clan was executed in Kamakura era on the charge of killing the father of Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; the Nagata clan was executed in Kamakura era on the charge of killing the father of Shogun.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot;Is &quot;&quot;tale of heiji&quot; with no articles correct??Not &quot;the tale of the heiji?&quot; …I added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; the Nagata clan was executed in the Kamakura era on the charge of killing the father of the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>文法。 “ in Kamakura era on the charge of killing the father of Shogun.”=&gt;” in the Kamakura era on the charge of killing the father of the Shogun.”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>なお『愚管抄』には、長田父子の陰謀を察知した義朝が乳母子・鎌田政清に自らの殺害を命じたと記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Gukansho,&quot; Yoshitomo scented Nagata and his son&apos;s plot and asked his foster mother&apos;s son Masakiyo KAMATA to kill him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the &quot;Gukansho,&quot; Yoshitomo sensed Nagata and his son&apos;s plot and asked his foster mother&apos;s son Masakiyo KAMATA to kill him.</e>
<cmt>scented --&gt; sensed added &quot;the&quot; again.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to the &quot;Gukansho,&quot; Yoshitomo sensed Nagata and his son&apos;s plot and asked his wet mother&apos;s son Masakiyo KAMATA to kill him.</e>
<cmt>foster→wet</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="66">
<j>義朝の墓は、その終焉の地である愛知県美浜町 (愛知県)の野間大坊の境内に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo&apos;s tomb is inside the Nomadaibo in Mihama-cho, Aichi Prefecture, where was a place of his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo&apos;s tomb is inside the Nomadaibo in Mihama-cho, Aichi Prefecture, which was the place of his death.</e>
<cmt>where --&gt; which</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo&apos;s tomb is inside the Nomadaibo in Mihama-cho, Aichi Prefecture, which was the place of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>関連人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related Person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related Person</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related Person</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>源為義 - 父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi: Yoshitomo&apos;s father</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi: Yoshitomo&apos;s father</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi: Yoshitomo&apos;s father</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>義親の六男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the sixth son of Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth son of Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth son of Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>父義親が流罪になったため叔父源義忠の養子となり河内源氏の棟梁を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his father Yoshichika was sentenced to deportation, Yoshitomo was adopted by his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshitada and took over the head of the Kawachi Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his father Yoshichika was sentenced to exile, Yoshitomo was adopted by his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshitada and became the head of the Kawachi Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>took over -- &gt; became deportation--&gt; exile. Deportation has the more specific meaning of being sent back to your home country. I think exile is what is meant here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his father Yoshichika was sentenced to exile, Yoshitomo was adopted by his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshitada and became the head of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Kawachi Minamoto clan→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>保元の乱当時は、義朝に家督を譲っていた（一説に義朝を勘当し、四男の源頼賢に家督を譲っていたともいう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Hogen Rebellion, Tameyoshi transferred responsibility for the family to Yoshitomo (another theory says that Tameyoshi renounced Yoshitomo and transferred as the head of family to the fourth son MINAMOTO no Yorikata.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Hogen Rebellion, Tameyoshi transferred responsibility for the family to Yoshitomo (although another theory states that Tameyoshi renounced Yoshitomo and transferred the position of head of the family to the fourth son MINAMOTO no Yorikata.)</e>
<cmt>phrasing stilted perhaps &quot;proffers&quot; would be better than &quot;states&quot; … but either is better than &quot;says&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Hogen Rebellion, Tameyoshi transferred responsibility for the family to Yoshitomo (although another theory states that Tameyoshi renounced Yoshitomo and transferred the position of head of the family to the fourth son MINAMOTO no Yorikata.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>源義賢 - 次弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikata: Yoshitomo&apos;s second brother</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshikata: Yoshitomo&apos;s second brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikata: Yoshitomo&apos;s second brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>父の為義と対立的な兄の義朝に対して「為義派」として関東に下り、新たな勢力基盤の形成を画る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He put on the side of his father Tameyoshi&apos;s faction and went down to Kanto against his elder brother Yoshitomo and plotted to establish the base of the power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He weighed in on the side of his father Tameyoshi&apos;s faction, and went down to Kanto against his elder brother Yoshitomo, and there he plotted to establish a base of the power.</e>
<cmt>put -&gt; weighed in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He weighed in on the side of his father Tameyoshi&apos;s faction, and went down to Kanto against his elder brother Yoshitomo, and there he plotted to establish a base of the power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>そのため義朝の長男義平に討たれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he was killed by Yoshitomo&apos;s first son Yoshihira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was for this reason he was killed by Yoshitomo&apos;s first son Yoshihira.</e>
<cmt>therefore--&gt; It was for this reason.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was for this reason he was killed by Yoshitomo&apos;s first son Yoshihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>源義仲（木曾義仲）の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was father of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka (later Yoshinaka KISO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was father of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka (later Yoshinaka KISO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was father of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka (later Yoshinaka KISO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>源義憲 -三弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshinori: Yoshitomo&apos;s third brother</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshinori: Yoshitomo&apos;s third brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshinori: Yoshitomo&apos;s third brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>志田三郎義憲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIDA Saburo Yoshinori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIDA Saburo Yoshinori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHIDA Saburo Yoshinori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>兄義賢とともに関東に下向。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went down to Kanto with his brother Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went down to Kanto with his brother Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went down to Kanto with his brother Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>常陸国に本拠を置き、義賢とともに義朝の勢力圏を脅かす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He set up the base in Hitachi Province and intimidated Yoshitomo&apos;s influential area, cooperating with Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He set up a base in the Hitachi Province, and, cooperating with Yoshikata, jeopardized Yoshitomo&apos;s sphere of influence.</e>
<cmt>a sphere of influence cannot be intimidated any more than it can be amused, but it can be jeopardized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He set up a base in Hitachi Province, and, cooperating with Yoshikata, jeopardized Yoshitomo&apos;s sphere of influence.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞不要。“ the Hitachi Province,”=&gt;”Hitachi Province,”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>別名：義広。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other name : Yoshihiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name of his was Yoshihiro</e>
<cmt>phrasing. Not sure about the context here, so please verify that this is accurate.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name of his was Yoshihiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>保元の乱、平治の乱には不参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He did not participate in the Hogen Rebellion and the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not participate in the Hogen Rebellion or in the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>and -&gt; or. Added &quot;in&quot; for parallel structure.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not participate in the Hogen Rebellion or in the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>甥の頼朝挙兵の時は頼朝を格下と見て、頼朝と敵対。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his nephew Yoritomo raised an army, he looked down on Yoritomo and stood against him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his nephew Yoritomo raised an army, he looked down on Yoritomo and stood against him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his nephew Yoritomo raised an army, he looked down on Yoritomo and stood against him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="82">
<j>源頼賢 - 四弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorikata: Yoshitomo&apos;s fourth brother</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yorikata: Yoshitomo&apos;s fourth brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorikata: Yoshitomo&apos;s fourth brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>兄義朝と為義の決別後、父為義に頼りにされ保元の乱で一戦交える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshitomo and Tameyoshi broke away, he was relied on his father Tameyoshi and fought with Yoshitomo in the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshitomo and Tameyoshi broke away, he relied on his father Tameyoshi and fought with Yoshitomo in the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>was --&gt; deletedThere may be a better word for 頼り than relied.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshitomo and Tameyoshi broke away, he was relied on by his father Tameyoshi and fought with Yoshitomo in the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>he relied on his father→he was relied on by his father</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="84">
<j>源為朝 - 八弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tametomo: Yoshitomo&apos;s eighth brother</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Tametomo: Yoshitomo&apos;s eighth brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tametomo: Yoshitomo&apos;s eighth brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>鎮西八郎為朝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinzei Hachiro Tametomo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinzei Hachiro Tametomo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinzei Hachiro Tametomo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>数多い義朝の兄弟の中でも一番の豪傑。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the most courageous person among numbers of Yoshitomo&apos;s brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the most courageous of any of Yoshitomo&apos;s brothers.</e>
<cmt>among numbers --&gt; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the most courageous of all of Yoshitomo&apos;s brothers.</e>
<cmt>“any of” =&gt; “all of”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>九州に勢力を持つが保元の乱に呼び戻され義朝・清盛と一戦交える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had power in Kyushu, but he was called back in the event of the Hogen Rebellion and had a fight with Yoshitomo and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had power in Kyushu, but he was called back at the time of the Hogen Rebellion and fought with Yoshitomo and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>in the event refers to things that have not happened yet. Here we need &quot;at the time of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had power in Kyushu, but he was called back at the time of the Hogen Rebellion and fought with Yoshitomo and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="88">
<j>源行家 - 十弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yukiie: Yoshitomo&apos;s tenth brother</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yukiie: Yoshitomo&apos;s tenth brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yukiie: Yoshitomo&apos;s tenth brother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>初名・義盛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initial name: Yoshimori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initial name: Yoshimori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initial name: Yoshimori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>新宮十郎義盛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHINGU Juro Yoshimori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHINGU Juro Yoshimori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHINGU Juro Yoshimori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>あるいは新宮十郎行家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">or SHINGU Juro Yukiie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">or SHINGU Juro Yukiie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">or SHINGU Juro Yukiie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>平治の乱で兄義朝軍に参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in the Heiji Rebellion on the side of Yoshitomo&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in the Heiji Rebellion and fought alongside Yoshitomo&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>better wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in the Heiji Rebellion and fought alongside Yoshitomo&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>平治の乱の敗戦後は紀州熊野に雌伏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After defeat in the Heiji Rebellion, he bided his time in Kishu Kumano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being defeated in the Heiji Rebellion, he bided his time in Kishu Kumano.</e>
<cmt>being defeated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being defeated in the Heiji Rebellion, he bided his time in Kishu Kumano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="94">
<j>源義平 - 長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshihira: Yoshitomo&apos;s first son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshihira: Yoshitomo&apos;s first son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshihira: Yoshitomo&apos;s first son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>悪源太。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akugenta</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akugenta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akugenta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>平治の乱で活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave a good performance in the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought well in the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>improved the diction by using words specific to combat.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought well in the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>平治の乱の敗戦後、単独京都に潜入し、平清盛暗殺を企てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After defeat in the Heiji Rebellion, he sneaked into Kyoto by himself and plotted to assassin TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being defeated in the Heiji Rebellion, he slipped into Kyoto by himself and plotted to assassinate TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>being defeated sneaked --&gt; slipped.Assasin -- &gt; assassinate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being defeated in the Heiji Rebellion, he slipped into Kyoto by himself and plotted to assassinate TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="98">
<j>源朝長 - 次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tomonaga: Yoshitomo&apos;s second son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Tomonaga: Yoshitomo&apos;s second son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tomonaga: Yoshitomo&apos;s second son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>平治の乱で傷つき、自害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was wounded in the Heiji Rebellion and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was wounded in the Heiji Rebellion and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was wounded in the Heiji Rebellion and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="100">
<j>源頼朝 - 三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoritomo: Yoshitomo&apos;s third son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoritomo: Yoshitomo&apos;s third son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoritomo: Yoshitomo&apos;s third son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>鎌倉幕府を開き武家政治を創始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a founder of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and established a warrior role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a founder of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and established himself as a warrior.</e>
<cmt>established a warrior role sounds odd.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a founder of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and established himself as a warrior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="102">
<j>源範頼 - 六男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Noriyori: Yoshitomo&apos;s sixth son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Noriyori: Yoshitomo&apos;s sixth son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Noriyori: Yoshitomo&apos;s sixth son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>治承・寿永の乱では一方の大将で蒲冠者と呼ばれた手堅い武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an earnest warlord called Kaba no kanja in the Wars of Jisho and Juei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a hard-nosed warlord called Kaba no kanja in the Wars of Jisho and Juei.</e>
<cmt>earnest warlord --&gt; deletedhard-nosed warlord --&gt; OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a hard-nosed warlord called Kaba no kanja in the Wars of Jisho and Juei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="104">
<j>源義経 - 九男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune: Yoshitomo&apos;s ninth son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune: Yoshitomo&apos;s ninth son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune: Yoshitomo&apos;s ninth son</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>治承・寿永の乱における華々しい活躍と悲劇的な最期で、古来より民衆に人気が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was very popular among the people because of brilliant success in the Wars of Jisho and Juei and oftragic death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was very popular among the people because of brilliant success in the Jisho and Juei Wars, and because of his tragic death.</e>
<cmt>of --&gt; deletedword order alterations.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was very popular among the people because of brilliant success in the Jisho and Juei Wars, and because of his tragic death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="106">
<j>鎌田政清 - 乳兄弟で、第一の郎党。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masakiyo KAMATA: Yoshitomo&apos;s foster brother and his best follower</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masakiyo KAMATA: Yoshitomo&apos;s foster brother and his most loyal follower</e>
<cmt>best --&gt; most loyal. Better in the context of being a follower.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masakiyo KAMATA: Yoshitomo&apos;s foster brother and his most loyal follower</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>義朝と共に殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was killed with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was killed with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was killed with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="108">
<j>源義康（足利義康） - 盟友。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu (later Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA): Yoshitomo&apos;s ally</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu (later Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA): Yoshitomo&apos;s ally</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu (later Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA): Yoshitomo&apos;s ally</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>父、源為義の従兄弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a cousin of Yoshitomo&apos;s father MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a cousin of Yoshitomo&apos;s father MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a cousin of Yoshitomo&apos;s father MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>保元の乱では一方の大将として義朝と共闘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought as a warlord in the Hogen Rebellion cooperating with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooperating with Yoshitomo, he fought as a warlord in the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>changed word order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooperating with Yoshitomo, he fought as a warlord in the Hogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>父は源義国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>保元の乱後に若くして死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Hogen Rebellion, he died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the Hogen Rebellion, however, he died at a young age.</e>
<cmt>more natural phrasing. Inserted &quot;however&quot; as a linking phrase.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the Hogen Rebellion, however, he died at an early age.</e>
<cmt>表現スタイル。 “ at a young age.” =&gt; “ at an early age.”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="113">
<j>河内経国（河内経国） - 後見人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunekuni KAWACHI: Yoshitomo&apos;s guardian</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunekuni KAWACHI: Yoshitomo&apos;s guardian</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunekuni KAWACHI: Yoshitomo&apos;s guardian</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>父、源為義の弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was younger brother of Yoshitomo&apos;s father MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a younger brother of Yoshitomo&apos;s father MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;A&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a younger brother of Yoshitomo&apos;s father MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>源義国の下で育ち足利義康と義朝の同盟を仲立ちした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had grown up with MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni and mediated between Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA and Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had grown up with MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni and mediated between Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA and Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had grown up with MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni and mediated between Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA and Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>源義忠の嫡男（兄の為義は義忠の養子）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada (his brother Tameyoshi was Yoshitada&apos;s adopted child).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada (his brother Tameyoshi was Yoshitada&apos;s adopted child).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada (his brother Tameyoshi was Yoshitada&apos;s adopted child).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>保元の乱後は消息不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Hogen Rebellion, he was never to be heard of again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Hogen Rebellion, he was never heard from again.</e>
<cmt>too colloquail (and slightly misphrased idiom).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Hogen Rebellion, he was never heard from again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="118">
<j>源義隆 - 大叔父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka: Yoshitomo&apos;s granduncle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka: Yoshitomo&apos;s granduncle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka: Yoshitomo&apos;s granduncle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>平治の乱後の逃避行中、義朝を庇って矢を受け死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While escaping after the Heiji Rebellion, he covered Yoshitomo with his own body and died from the arrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the escape just after the Heiji Rebellion, he protected Yoshitomo with his own body and died from the arrows fired.</e>
<cmt>covered --&gt; protected.Added &quot;fired&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the escape just after the Heiji Rebellion, he protected Yoshitomo with his own body and died from the arrows fired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>頼朝はその恩に報いるために義隆の子、源頼隆に恩賞を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo gave a reward to MINAMOTO no Yoritaka whose father was Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo gave a reward to MINAMOTO no Yoritaka, whose father was Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt>added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo gave a reward to MINAMOTO no Yoritaka, whose father was Yoshitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sat666(id:127263), 諏訪太郎頼光(id:98476), Nnh(id:474), 松茸(id:27535), 味っ子(id:17086), Yanahan(id:2437), 葉月(id:25674), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Andee(id:20421), 沢田(id:40580), 三郎太(id:172498), Greenland4(id:114494), Vieira(id:122911), 小者(id:172526), Dwy(id:13375), Kurz(id:1601), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), 代言人(id:33675), 海衛士(id:19229), NPD(id:58640), UMBRO(id:100484), Ktmchi(id:113301), Loveless(id:129239), Avxz(id:123412), Kusune(id:110977), Junger(id:10282), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>