<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利義昭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 義昭（あしかが よしあき）は、室町幕府の第15代征夷大将軍で、室町幕府最後の将軍である（在位：永禄11年（1568年）－天正16年（1588年））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA was the 15th Seii Taishogun of Muromachi Shogunate and its last Shogun (Reigned from 1568 (Eiroku 11) to 1588 (Tensho 16)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA was the 15th Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi Shogunate, and its last Shogun (Reigned from 1568 to 1588).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot;; added comma; deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA was the 15th Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi Shogunate, and its last Shogun (Reigned from 1568 to 1588).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Brief History</e>
<cmt>capitalized words in section heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Brief History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>父は室町幕府第12代将軍・足利義晴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は近衛尚通の娘・慶寿院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Hisamichi KONOE (Keijuin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Hisamichi KONOE (Keijuin).</e>
<cmt>removed space after parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Hisamichi KONOE (Keijuin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>第13代将軍・足利義輝は同母兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the 13th Shogun, was his elder brother from the same mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the 13th Shogun, was his elder brother from the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the 13th Shogun, was his elder brother from the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>はじめ僧籍にあったが、義輝が松永久秀らに暗殺されると、細川幽斎ら幕臣の援助を受けて京都から脱出する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was a priest when Yoshiteru was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and others, he escaped from Kyoto, helped by Shogunate men such as Yusai HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was a priest when Yoshiteru was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and others, he escaped from Kyoto, helped by Shogunate men such as Yusai HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was a priest when Yoshiteru was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and others, he escaped from Kyoto, helped by Shogunate men such as Yusai HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして、美濃国の織田信長に擁されて上洛し、第15代将軍に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he returned to Kyoto under protection of Nobunaga ODA of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he returned to Kyoto under protection of Nobunaga ODA of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he returned to Kyoto under protection of Nobunaga ODA of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>やがて信長と対立し、武田信玄や朝倉義景らと呼応して信長包囲網を築き上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he was opposed to Nobunaga and built a siege with Shingen TAKEDA and Yoshikage ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he was opposed to Nobunaga and built made siege with Shingen TAKEDA and Yoshikage ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt>built a -&gt;made</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he was opposed to Nobunaga and built made siege with Shingen TAKEDA and Yoshikage ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一時は信長を追いつめもしたが、やがて信長によって京都から追放され、事実上、室町幕府は滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He could put Nobunaga into a corner once, but later he was exiled from Kyoto by Nobunaga; this was the de facto end of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was able to get Nobunaga into a corner once, but later he was exiled from Kyoto by Nobunaga; this was the de facto end of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>could put -&gt;was able to get</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was able to get Nobunaga into a corner once, but later he was exiled from Kyoto by Nobunaga; this was the de facto end of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>その後は毛利輝元、そして、豊臣秀吉らの援助を受けて余生を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he spent the rest of his life under patronage of Terumoto MORI, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he spent the rest of his life under patronage of Terumoto MORI, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he spent the rest of his life under patronage of Terumoto MORI, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>将軍への道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way to Shogun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Road to Shogun</e>
<cmt>way-&gt;road</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Road to Shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>天文6年（1537年）11月13日、第12代将軍・足利義晴の次男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the second boy of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun, on November 13, 1537 (Tenmon 6).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the second son of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun, on November 13, 1537.</e>
<cmt>boy-&gt;son; deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, the 12th Shogun, on November 13, 1537.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>兄に嗣子である足利義輝がいたため、幼くして外祖父・近衛尚通の猶子となって仏門（興福寺一乗院）に入り、覚慶と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he had an elder brother, who was a heir of Shogun, he became an adopted son of his grandfather (mother&apos;s father), Naomichi KONOE in the childhood and became a Buddhism priest named Kakukei at Kofuku-ji Ichijoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he had an elder brother, who was heir to the Shogun, he became an adopted son of his maternal grandfather, Naomichi KONOE, in childhood and became a Buddhist priest named Kakukei at Kofuku-ji Ichijoin.</e>
<cmt>of-&gt;to; added &quot;maternal&quot; and removed parenthetical notation; Buddhist-&gt;Buddhism</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he had an elder brother, who was heir to the Shogun, he became an adopted son of his maternal grandfather, Naomichi KONOE, in childhood and became a Buddhist priest named Kakukei at Kofuku-ji Ichijoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>のちに興福寺で権少僧都にまで栄進している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he was promoted to Gon no Shozozu of Kohuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he was promoted to Gon no Shozozu of Kohuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he was promoted to Gon no Shozozu of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>永禄8年（1565年）の永禄の変で、第13代将軍であった兄・義輝が松永久秀や三好三人衆らによって暗殺され、弟で鹿苑院院主であった足利周嵩も誘殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Eiroku no Hen of 1565 (Eiroku 8) his elder brother Yoshiteru, the 13th Shogun, was assasinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA, Miyoshi Sanninshu and others, and his younger brother Shuko ASHIKAGA, a head of Rokuon&apos;in was also killed by betray.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Eiroku no Hen of 1565 his elder brother Yoshiteru, the 13th Shogun, was assasinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA, Miyoshi Sanninshu and others, and his younger brother Shuko ASHIKAGA, a head of Rokuon&apos;in was also killed.</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;by betray&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Eiroku Incident of 1565 his elder brother Yoshiteru, the 13th Shogun, was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA, Miyoshi Sanninshu and others, and his younger brother Shuko ASHIKAGA, a head of Rokuon&apos;in was also killed.</e>
<cmt>「永禄の変」の定訳は見付からないが、桜田門外の変や本能寺の変などと同様に「Eiroku Incident」が良いでしょう、assassinateのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このとき、義昭も松永久秀らによって捕縛され、興福寺に幽閉された（久秀らは覚慶が将軍の弟で、なおかつ将来は興福寺別当の職を約束されていたことから、覚慶を殺すことで興福寺を敵に回すことを恐れて、幽閉にとどめたとされる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time Yoshiaki was also arrested by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and confined at Kofuku-ji Temple (it is said that Hisahide did not kill Kakukei because he was afraid of having Kofuku-ji Temple for an enemy; Kakukei was Shogun&apos;s brother and promissed to be Betto(an director) of Kofuku-ji Temple in future).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time Yoshiaki was also arrested by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and confined at Kofuku-ji Temple (it is said that Hisahide did not kill Kakukei because he was afraid of having Kofuku-ji Temple for an enemy; Kakukei was Shogun&apos;s brother and promissed to be Betto (director) of Kofuku-ji Temple in future).</e>
<cmt>removed space after parenthesis; removed &quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time Yoshiaki was also arrested by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and confined at Kofuku-ji Temple (it is said that Hisahide did not kill Kakukei because he was afraid of having Kofuku-ji Temple for an enemy; Kakukei was Shogun&apos;s brother and promised to be Betto (director) of Kofuku-ji Temple in future).</e>
<cmt>promisedのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、幕臣である細川幽斎や和田惟政らに助けられて脱出し、永禄9年（1566年）2月17日、還俗して義秋と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Yoshiaki could escaped from Kyoto, helped by Yusai HOSOKAWA, Koremasa WADA and others, on February 17, 1566 (Eiroku 9), and he returned to secular life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Yoshiaki was able to escape from Kyoto, helped by Yusai HOSOKAWA, Koremasa WADA and others, on February 17, 1566, and returned to secular life.</e>
<cmt>could-&gt;was able to; deleted &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Yoshiaki was able to escape from Kyoto, helped by Yusai HOSOKAWA, Koremasa WADA and others, on February 17, 1566, and returned to secular life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>義昭のことを記した書物には、別称として武家御所などと呼ばれていたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Book which wrote about Yoshiaki describes that he was called Buke Gosho as another name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Book about Yoshiaki records that he was called Buke Gosho as another name.</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;which wrote&quot;; describes-&gt;records</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Book about Yoshiaki records that he was called Buke Gosho as another name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>京を追われた折は夜盗に襲われ、「貧乏公方」とも呼ばれたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he escaped from Kyoto he was attacked by a robbor and was called &apos;a poor Kubo (a court noble)&apos; as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he escaped from Kyoto he was attacked by a robber and was called &apos;a poor Kubo (a court noble)&apos; as well.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he escaped from Kyoto he was attacked by a robber and was called &apos;a poor Kubo (a court noble)&apos; as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>4月21日には密かに従五位下、左馬頭に叙位・任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Aplil 21 he got an official governmental position of Jugoi-ge, Samano kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 21 he got the official governmental position of Jugoi-ge, Samano kami.</e>
<cmt>spelling; an-&gt;the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21 he got the official governmental position of Junior 5th Rank, Samano kami.</e>
<cmt>従五位下→Jugoi-ge/Junior 5th Rank</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、叙任時期については疑問視する意見があるが、山科言継の『言継卿記』によれば永禄11年（1568年）2月に行われた義昭の対抗馬である足利義栄への将軍宣下当日に宣下の使者であった言継の屋敷に義昭の使者が現れて従四位下への昇進推薦の仲介を依頼しに来たために困惑した事が書かれており、この以前に叙任を受けていた事は明らかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a suspicious opinion about the time of getting an governmental position, but it is obvious that he got it at least before February 1568 (Eiroku 11); according to &apos;Tokitsugu kyoki&apos; written by Tokitsugu YAMASHINA, Tokitsugu was confused when a messenger from Yoshiaki asked him to mediate recommendation of promotion to Juyon&apos;i-ge on the same day Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, who was Yoshiaki&apos;s rival, was ordered to become Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is some doubt about when he attaining governmental position, but it is obvious that he got it at least before February 1568; according to &apos;Tokitsugu kyoki&apos; written by Tokitsugu YAMASHINA, Tokitsugu was confused when a messenger from Yoshiaki asked him to mediate recommendation of promotion to Juyon&apos;i-ge on the same day Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, who was Yoshiaki&apos;s rival, was ordered to become Shogun.</e>
<cmt>reworded for grammar, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is some doubt about when he attaining governmental position, but it is obvious that he got it at least before February 1568; according to &apos;Tokitsugu kyoki&apos; written by Tokitsugu YAMASHINA, Tokitsugu was confused when a messenger from Yoshiaki asked him to mediate recommendation of promotion to Juyon&apos;i-ge on the same day Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, who was Yoshiaki&apos;s rival, was ordered to become Shogun.</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>京都から脱出した義秋は、はじめ近江国の六角義賢・六角義治親子を頼ったが、義治が三好三人衆と密かに内通したため、8月には妹の婿である若狭国の武田義統のもとへ亡命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After an escape from Kyoto, Yoshiaki relied on Yoshitaka ROKKAKU and Yoshiharu ROKKAKU of Omi Province, but Yoshiharu&apos;s secret cotact with Miyoshi-Sanninshu made him exile to Yoshizumi TAKEDA of Wakasa Province on August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After an escape from Kyoto, Yoshiaki relied on Yoshitaka ROKKAKU and Yoshiharu ROKKAKU of Omi Province, but Yoshiharu&apos;s secret cotact with Miyoshi-Sanninshu made him flee to Yoshizumi TAKEDA of Wakasa Province on August.</e>
<cmt>exile-&gt;flee</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After an escape from Kyoto, Yoshiaki relied on Yoshitaka ROKKAKU and Yoshiharu ROKKAKU of Omi Province, but Yoshiharu&apos;s secret contact with Miyoshi-Sanninshu made him flee to Yoshizumi TAKEDA of Wakasa Province on August.</e>
<cmt>contactのスペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし若狭武田氏では家督抗争や重臣の権力争いなどから、上洛できるだけの実力は無く、9月には越前国の朝倉義景のもとへ亡命し、将軍家再興の助力を要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Wakasa TAKEDA clan did not have an enough power to go up to Kyoto because of troubles on inheritance, conflicts between elder statesmen and so on, so Yoshiaki exiled to Yoshikage ASAKURA of Echizen Province on September and asked him to help a revival of Shogugate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the Wakasa TAKEDA clan did not have enough power to go up to Kyoto because of troubles over inheritance, conflicts between elder statesmen and so on, so Yoshiaki fled to Yoshikage ASAKURA of Echizen Province in September and asked him to help restore the Shogugate.</e>
<cmt>reworded for grammar, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the Wakasa TAKEDA clan did not have enough power to go up to Kyoto because of troubles over inheritance, conflicts between elder statesmen and so on, so Yoshiaki fled to Yoshikage ASAKURA of Echizen Province in September and asked him to help restore the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>shogunateのスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし朝倉義景は、すでに足利将軍家連枝の「鞍谷御所」足利嗣知もかかえており、還俗したての足利義秋を奉じて積極的な上洛をする意思がなかったため、上洛は実現しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Yoshikage ASAKURA had already patronized &apos;Kuratani gosho&apos; Tugutomo ASHIKAGA, a relative of ASHIKAGA Shogunate, and did not eager to go up to Kyoto with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA who just returned to secular life; so Yoshiaki could not return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Yoshikage ASAKURA had already patronized &apos;Kuratani gosho&apos; Tugutomo ASHIKAGA, a relative of the ASHIKAGA Shogunate, and was not eager to go up to Kyoto with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who had just returned to secular life; so Yoshiaki could not return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>reworded for grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Yoshikage ASAKURA had already patronized &apos;Kuratani gosho&apos; Tsugutomo ASHIKAGA, a relative of the ASHIKAGA Shogunate, and was not eager to go up to Kyoto with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who had just returned to secular life; so Yoshiaki could not return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、朝倉家亡命中の永禄11年（1568年）4月15日、「秋」の字は不吉であるとし、正式に元服して義昭と改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, on April 15, 1568 (Eiroku 11) during his exile at ASAKURA clan, Yoshiaki had a coming-of-age ceremony formally and changed his name&apos;s Chinese character Aki from 秋 to 昭, because he thought the letter 秋 was ominous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, on April 15, 1568, during his exile with the ASAKURA clan, Yoshiaki had a coming-of-age ceremony and formally changed his name&apos;s Chinese character Aki from 秋 to 昭, because he thought the letter 秋 was ominous.</e>
<cmt>to-&gt;with; added &quot;the&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, on April 15, 1568, during his exile with the ASAKURA clan, Yoshiaki had a coming-of-age ceremony and formally changed his name&apos;s Chinese character Aki from 秋 to 昭, because he thought the letter 秋 was ominous.</e>
<cmt>全角スペースを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>加冠役は朝倉義景が務めている（なお、義昭はこの時点まで正式な元服を行ったという文献史料は一切無く、当時としてはあまりに遅すぎる元服だったといえる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who gave him a headgear for a adult court noble was Yoshikage ASAKURA (there is no record which shows Yoshiaki had a coming-of -age ceremony officially until this time; it could be said that it was too late in this era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who performed the ceremony was Yoshikage ASAKURA (there is no record which shows Yoshiaki had a coming-of -age ceremony officially until this time; it could be said that it was too late in this era).</e>
<cmt>reworded for clarity; removed space after parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person who performed the ceremony was Yoshikage ASAKURA (there is no record which shows Yoshiaki had a coming-of -age ceremony officially until this time; it could be said that it was too late in this era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>やがて、朝倉家の重臣であった明智光秀の仲介により、織田信長を頼って美濃国へ移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, by an intermediation of Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was an elder statesman of ASAKURA, Yoshiaki relied on Nobunaga ODA and moved to Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, through Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was an elder statesman of ASAKURA, as an intermediary Yoshiaki relied on Nobunaga ODA and moved to Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>reworded for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, through Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was an elder statesman of ASAKURA, as an intermediary Yoshiaki relied on Nobunaga ODA and moved to Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）9月、織田信長に擁立されて上洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went up to Kyoto, helped by Nobunaga ODA on September, 1568 (Eiroku 11).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went up to Kyoto, helped by Nobunaga ODA on September, 1568.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went up to Kyoto, helped by Nobunaga ODA on September, 1568.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>10月18日、朝廷から将軍宣下を受けて第15代将軍に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 18 he became the 15th Shogun by an order from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 18 he became the 15th Shogun by an order from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 18 he became the 15th Shogun by an order from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>同時に従四位下、参議・左近衛権中将にも昇叙・任官される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time he was promoted toJushii-ge and got governmental positions of Sangi and Sakonoe Gonchujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time he was promoted toJushii-ge and got governmental positions of Sangi and Sakonoe Gonchujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time he was promoted to Junior 4th Rank and got governmental positions of Sangi and Sakonoe Gonchujo.</e>
<cmt>従四位下→Junio 4th Class</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、管領家である細川信良や畠山昭高に偏諱を与え幕府の再興を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition he tried to revive Muromachi Shogunate by giving hen&apos;i (an official name) to Nobuyoshi HOSOKAWA and Akitaka HATAKEYAMA, who were Kanrei(Bakufu&apos;s statesmen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition he tried to revive the Muromachi Shogunate by giving hen&apos;i (an official name) to Nobuyoshi HOSOKAWA and Akitaka HATAKEYAMA, who were Kanrei (Shogunate statesmen).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot;; spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition he tried to revive the Muromachi Shogunate by giving hen&apos;i (an official name) to Nobuyoshi HOSOKAWA and Akitaka HATAKEYAMA, who were Kanrei (Shogunate statesmen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>織田信長との対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conflict with Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conflict with Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conflict with Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>義昭は当初の信長には恩義を感じていたようで、将軍就任直後の10月24日に信長に対して宛てた感状で、「御父織田弾正忠（信長）殿」と宛て名している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki seemed to thank Nobunaga at first; he wrote an addressee as &apos; my father ODA Danjo no Chu (Nobunaga)&apos; in his thank-you letter to Nobunaga on October 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki seemed to thank Nobunaga at first; he addressed him as &apos;my father ODA Danjo no Chu (Nobunaga)&apos; in his thank-you letter to Nobunaga on October 24.</e>
<cmt>wrote…-&gt;addressed him as; spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki seemed to thank Nobunaga at first; he addressed him as &apos;my father ODA Danjo no Chu (Nobunaga)&apos; in his thank-you letter to Nobunaga on October 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、信長に副将軍・管領職の地位を与えようとするなど良好な関係を維持するが、やがて信長が将軍権力を制約しはじめたために両者の関係は悪化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he had kept a good relation with Nobunaga by trying to give him positions of vice Shogun and Kanrei, the relationship between them became worse because Nobunaga began to limit the power of Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he had kept a good relationship with Nobunaga by trying to give him positions of vice Shogun and Kanrei, relations between them became worse because Nobunaga began to limit the power of Shogun.</e>
<cmt>edited relation/relationship for style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he had kept a good relationship with Nobunaga by trying to give him positions of vice Shogun and Kanrei, relations between them became worse because Nobunaga began to limit the power of Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>信長は永禄12年（1569年）1月、『殿中御掟』という9箇条の掟書を、永禄13年（1570年）1月にも殿中御掟追加7箇条を発して義昭に承認させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga made a rule &apos;Denchu on&apos;okite&apos; which had nine articles on January 1569 (Eiroku 12) and Denchu on&apos;okite tuika seven articles on January 1570, and forced Yoshiaki to accept them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga made a rule &apos;Denchu on&apos;okite&apos;, which had nine articles, on January 1569, and an additional seven articles on January 1570, and forced Yoshiaki to accept them.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese dates; simplified for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga made a rule &apos;Denchu on&apos;okite&apos;, which had nine articles, on January 1569, and an additional seven articles on January 1570, and forced Yoshiaki to accept them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>これに不満を持った義昭は信長を排除しようと企み、顕如や武田信玄、朝倉義景らに信長討伐令を下して信長包囲網を形成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki, who was complained to these, tried to get rid of Nobunaga and made a siege against Nobunaga by an order for Kennyo, Shingen ASAKURA, Yoshikage ASAKURA and others to subjugate him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki, who was upset about these, tried to get rid of Nobunaga and made siege against him by an order for Kennyo, Shingen ASAKURA, Yoshikage ASAKURA and others to subjugate him.</e>
<cmt>complained-&gt;upset; deleted &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki, who was upset about these, tried to get rid of Nobunaga and made siege against him by an order for Kennyo, Shingen ASAKURA, Yoshikage ASAKURA and others to subjugate him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この包囲網には、浅井長政や松永久秀、三好三人衆、三好義継らも加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa AZAI, Hisahide MATASUNAGA, Miyoshi sanninshu, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and others joined this siege.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa AZAI, Hisahide MATASUNAGA, Miyoshi sanninshu, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and others joined this siege.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa AZAI, Hisahide MATASUNAGA, Miyoshi sanninshu, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and others joined this siege.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これにより信長は一時的に窮地に陥ったが、元亀4年（1573年）4月の武田信玄の病死を契機として信長包囲網は瓦解する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Nobunaga was put into a corner once, the siege against Nobunaga ended by the death of a disease of Shingen TAKEDA on April, 1573 (Genki 4).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Nobunaga was put into a corner once, the siege against Nobunaga was ended by the death by disease of Shingen TAKEDA in April, 1573.</e>
<cmt>of a-&gt;by; deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Nobunaga was put into a corner once, the siege against Nobunaga was ended by the death by disease of Shingen TAKEDA in April, 1573.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>4月、義昭は三好義継、松永久秀らと同盟を結び、山城填島城において挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April Yoshiaki made an alliance with Hisahide MATSUNAGA and mustered an army at Makishima Castle in Yamashiro Province,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April Yoshiaki made an alliance with Hisahide MATSUNAGA and mustered an army at Makishima Castle in Yamashiro Province,</e>
<cmt>On-&gt;In</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April Yoshiaki made an alliance with Hisahide MATSUNAGA and mustered an army at Makishima Castle in Yamashiro Province,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>このときは正親町天皇の勅命もあって和睦するが、7月に再度挙兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time they made peace influenced by an order of Emperor Ogimachi, but Yoshiaki mustered an army again on July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time they made peace influenced by an order of Emperor Ogimachi, but Yoshiaki mustered an army again in July.</e>
<cmt>on-&gt;in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time they made peace influenced by an order of Emperor Ogimachi, but Yoshiaki mustered an army again in July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>信長は京都を焼き払って義昭を捕らえ、河内国に追放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga put a fire on Kyoto city, arrested Yoshiaki and banished him to Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga set fire to Kyoto, arrested Yoshiaki and banished him to Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>put fire on-&gt;set fire to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga set fire to Kyoto, arrested Yoshiaki and banished him to Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>一般に、これによって室町幕府は滅亡したとされる（ただし朝廷から征夷大将軍職を解任されたわけではなかったので、信長勢力圏以外の大名の間では、その後も権威を保っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally considered that Muromachi Shogunate finished by this event(but Yoshiaki kept a power against daimyos (Japanese feudal lords) other than supporter of Nobunaga, because Yoshiaki was not dismissed by the Imperial Court..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally considered that the Muromachi Shogunate was finished by this event (but Yoshiaki kept power against the daimyo (Japanese feudal lords), other than supporters of Nobunaga, because Yoshiaki was not dismissed by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>articles; spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally considered that the Muromachi Shogunate was finished by this event (but Yoshiaki kept power against the daimyo (Japanese feudal lords), other than supporters of Nobunaga, because Yoshiaki was not dismissed by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、京都五山の住持任命権は五山を定めた足利将軍家にあると考えられていたため、その任命のための献金収入もあったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition he seemed to get a contribution by appointment of Kyoto&apos;s Five Mountains priests because the power to appoint was regarded as belonging to Ashikaga Shogunate, who had established Kyoto&apos;s Five Mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition he got an income by appointment of Kyoto&apos;s Five Mountains priests because the power to appoint was regarded as belonging to Ashikaga Shogunate, who had established Kyoto&apos;s Five Mountains.</e>
<cmt>reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition he got an income by appointment of Kyoto&apos;s Five Mountains priests because the power to appoint was regarded as belonging to Ashikaga Shogunate, who had established Kyoto&apos;s Five Mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>『公卿補任』（朝廷の人事録）では、関白豊臣秀吉に従って御所へ参内し、秀吉への忠誠を誓って、正式に征夷大将軍位を辞官する天正16年1月13日_(旧暦)（1588年2月9日）まで征夷大将軍として扱っている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;Kugyo bu&apos;nin&apos;(a human affair&apos;s record of the Imperial Court) Yoshiaki had been Seii Taishogun until February 9, 1588 (lunar date) (January 13, Tensho 16) when he went up to the Imperial Palace following to Kanpaku Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and resigned it formally after showing loyalty to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;Kugyo bu&apos;nin&apos; (a human affairs record of the Imperial Court) Yoshiaki had been Seii Taishogun until February 9, 1588, when he went up to the Imperial Palace following Kanpaku Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and resigned it formally after swearing loyalty to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>showing-&gt;swearing; spacing; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;Kugyo bu&apos;nin&apos; (a human affairs record of the Imperial Court) Yoshiaki had been Seii Taishogun until February 9, 1588, when he went up to the Imperial Palace following Kanpaku Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and resigned it formally after swearing loyalty to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>備後へ下向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Going down to Bingo province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Going down to Bingo province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Going down to Bingo province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>信長によって京を追われたとき、本願寺顕如らの仲介もあって信長は助命し、妹婿の河内の大名である三好義継（三好家当主）のもとへ亡命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshiaki was exiled from Kyoto by Nobunaga, he did not killed because of the mediation of Kennyo of Honganji-Temple; Yoshiaki exiled to Yoshitugu MIYOSHI (a master of MIYOSHI clan), who was a feudal lord of Kawachi and his sister&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshiaki was exiled from Kyoto by Nobunaga, he was not killed because of the intervention of Kennyo of Honganji-Temple; Yoshiaki fled to Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI (a leader of the MIYOSHI clan), who was a feudal lord of Kawachi and his sister&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>exiled-&gt;fled; did-&gt;was; mediation-&gt;intervention</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshiaki was exiled from Kyoto by Nobunaga, he was not killed because of the intervention of Kennyo of Honganji-Temple; Yoshiaki fled to Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI (a leader of the MIYOSHI clan), who was a feudal lord of Kawachi and his sister&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし天正元年、信長によって義継は滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1573 (Tensho 1) Yoshitugu was ruined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in 1573, Yoshitugu was ruined.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in 1573, Yoshitsugu was ruined by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字を修正、信長によって、の訳を追加。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>天正4年（1576年）、その昔足利尊氏が再起を果たし足利家にとって縁起の良い土地であった備後国鞆の浦（当時は毛利領）に亡命政府（幕府）を樹立（鞆幕府とも呼ばれる）し、そこから信長追放を目指して諸大名に討伐令を下し続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1576 (Tensho 4) Yoshiaki built a refugee government(Tomo Bakufu) at Tomo no Ura in Bingo Province (Mori clan domain at that time), which was a lucky place for ASHIKAGA family because Takauji ASHIKAGA could success to revive, and continued to make an order for various feudal lords to subjugate Nobunaga,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1576, Yoshiaki built a government in exile (Shogunate) at Tomo no Ura in Bingo Province (Mori clan domain at that time), which was a lucky place for the ASHIKAGA family because Takauji ASHIKAGA successfully revcovered, and continued to give orders to various feudal lords to suppress Nobunaga,</e>
<cmt>refugee government-&gt;government in exile; spacing; articles; word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1576, Yoshiaki built a government in exile (Shogunate) at Tomo no Ura in Bingo Province (Mori clan domain at that time), which was a lucky place for the ASHIKAGA family because Takauji ASHIKAGA successfully recovered, and continued to give orders to various feudal lords to suppress Nobunaga,</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>天正6年（1578年）に関東管領の上杉謙信が死去し、天正8年（1580年）には石山本願寺も降伏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1578 (Tensho 6) Kenshin UESUGI, a Kanrei of Kanto area, was died and in 1580 (Tensho 8) Ishiyama Honganji Temple surrendered to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1578, Kenshin UESUGI, a Kanrei of the Kanto area, died and in 1580 Ishiyama Honganji Temple surrendered to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese dates</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1578, Kenshin UESUGI, a Kanrei of the Kanto area, died and in 1580 Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple surrendered to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>寺名にハイフン挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="46">
<j>まだ備後鞆滞在中であった天正10年（1582年）に信長が本能寺の変で家臣に討たれると、毛利輝元の後ろ盾を得て再び上洛を目論む一方、豊臣秀吉や柴田勝家にも同じような働きかけを盛んに行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga was assassinated by his man in &apos;Honno-ji no Hen&apos; in 1582 (Tensho 10) during a stay at Tomo in Bingo, Yoshiaki tried to go up to Kyoto again by Terumoto MORI&apos;s help and asked hard to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Katsuie SIBATA as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga was assassinated by his vassal in &apos;Honno-ji no Hen&apos; in 1582, during a stay at Tomo in Bingo, Yoshiaki tried to go up to Kyoto again with Terumoto MORI&apos;s help and beseached Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Katsuie SIBATA as well.</e>
<cmt>man-&gt;vassall; deleted Japanese date; by-&gt;with; asked-&gt;beseached</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga was assassinated by his vassal in the Incident at Honno-ji in 1582, during a stay at Tomo in Bingo, Yoshiaki tried to go up to Kyoto again with Terumoto MORI&apos;s help and besought Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Katsuie SHIBATA as well.</e>
<cmt>本能寺の変→the Incident at Honno-jiに、スペル修正、ローマ字修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし、親豊臣派であった小早川隆景らが反対したこともあり、また、義昭は勝家を支持したため、秀吉に接近しつつあった毛利氏との関係は冷却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But relatioship with MORI became worse because Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was familiar to TOYOTOMI, opposed to help Yoshiaki and Yoshiaki&apos;s support forKatsuie was against MORI&apos;s approach to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But his relationship with MORI worsened because Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was close to TOYOTOMI, opposed helping Yoshiaki and Yoshiaki&apos;s support forKatsuie was against MORI&apos;s approach to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;his&quot;; familiar-&gt;close</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But his relationship with MORI worsened because Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was close to TOYOTOMI, opposed helping Yoshiaki and Yoshiaki&apos;s support for Katsuie was against MORI&apos;s approach to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除、スペースを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="48">
<j>天正11年、毛利輝元が羽柴秀吉に臣従し、天正14年、羽柴秀吉が関白太政大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1583 (Tensho 11) Terumoto MORI was overcome by Hideyoshi HASHIBA and in 1586 (Tensho 14) Hideyoshi HASHIBA became Kampaku Daijo Daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1583, Terumoto MORI was overcome by Hideyoshi HASHIBA, and in 1586 Hideyoshi HASHIBA became Kampaku Daijo Daijin.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese dates</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1583, Terumoto MORI was overcome by Hideyoshi HASHIBA, and in 1586 Hideyoshi HASHIBA became Kanpaku Daijo Daijin.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>その後、天正16年（1588年）、征夷大将軍は辞し准三宮の称号を朝廷から得、出家し昌山と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in 1588 (Tensho 16) Yoshiaki resigned Seii Taishogun, got a title of Jusangu from the Imperial Court and became a priest named Shozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in 1588, Yoshiaki resigned from the position of Seii Taishogun, received the title of Jusangu from the Imperial Court and became a priest named Shozan.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date; reworded for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in 1588, Yoshiaki resigned from the position of Seii Taishogun, received the title of Jusangu from the Imperial Court and became a priest named Shozan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>秀吉からは山城槇島城において1万石の領地を認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given a feudal land of ichimangoku and became a master of Makishima Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given a fief of 10,000 koku and became the master of Makishima Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>fief; ichiman-&gt;10,000; a-&gt;the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given a fief of 10,000 koku and became the master of Makishima Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="51">
<j>文禄・慶長の役には、秀吉の要請にともない、軍を引き連れ肥前国名護屋まで参陣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Bunroku &amp; Keicho no eki (Hideyoshi&apos;s invasions of Korea) Yoshiaki joined with his army to Nagoya of Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Bunroku &amp; Keicho no eki (Hideyoshi&apos;s invasions of Korea) Yoshiaki joined with his army as far as Nagoya of Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>to-&gt;as far as</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Bunroku &amp; Keicho no eki (Hideyoshi&apos;s invasions of Korea) Yoshiaki joined with his army as far as Nagoya of Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="52">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）、大阪で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki passed away in 1597 (Keicho 2) in Osaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki passed away in 1597 in Osaka</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki passed away in 1597 in Osaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>享年61。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at 61.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at 61.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at 61.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character/Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character/Stories</e>
<cmt>episodes-&gt;stories</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character/Stories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>天下統一を実現した秀吉が幕府の創立を目論み、義昭を大名にする代わりに自分を養子としてくれるようにと望んだが、名族・足利氏としての意地があったのかこれを拒絶した、という逸話が伝わるがこれは後世の作り話とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a following anecdote which is seemed to be a fiction at a later age; Hideyoshi, who succeeded to rule over the whole country, hoped to be Yoshiaki&apos;s adopted son instead of making Yoshiaki a feudal lord in order to build a new Bakufu, but Yoshiaki rejected this propose because of his pride as a ASHIKAGA noble,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote which now seems fictional; Hideyoshi, who succeeded in ruling over the whole country, hoped to be Yoshiaki&apos;s adopted son instead of making Yoshiaki a feudal lord in order to build a new Shogunate, but Yoshiaki rejected this proposal because of his pride as an ASHIKAGA noble,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote which now seems fictional; Hideyoshi, who succeeded in ruling over the whole country, hoped to be Yoshiaki&apos;s adopted son instead of making Yoshiaki a feudal lord in order to build a new Shogunate, but Yoshiaki rejected this proposal because of his pride as an ASHIKAGA noble.</e>
<cmt>カンマとピリオドを入れ替え。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>織田信長やその家臣を主人公とした作品では、暗君の公家として描かれる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the literatures where Nobunaga ODE and his men are the leading characters, Yoshiaki is often described as a stupid noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In literature where Nobunaga ODE and his men are the leading characters, Yoshiaki is often described as a stupid noble.</e>
<cmt>deleted the; literatures-&gt;literature</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In literature where Nobunaga ODE and his men are the leading characters, Yoshiaki is often described as a stupid noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>しかし、前代までの将軍たちと異なり、生き残ること自体が困難であった戦国時代を生き抜いて天寿を全うしたこと、また壮大な信長包囲網を作り上げたことなどから、非凡な才能を持った将軍であったとも思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But contrary to other former Shoguns Yoshiaki seems to be an unusually talented Shogun, considered that he could die a natural death in the age of wars when it was difficult to survive and that he could establish a large siege against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But contrary to others who held the position, Yoshiaki seems to have been an unusually talented Shogun, considering that died a natural death in an age of wars, when it was difficult to survive and that he was able to wage a major siege against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>edited for style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But contrary to others who held the position, Yoshiaki seems to have been an unusually talented Shogun, considering that died a natural death in an age of wars, when it was difficult to survive and that he was able to wage a major siege against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>政権の最後の責任者は古今東西問わず評価が低くなりがちであるし、さらに信長、秀吉という天才たちの引き立て役とならざるを得ない気の毒な面もあると言えよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last person in charge of administration tends to be undervalued in all ages and countries, and it is a pity that he could not help serving as a foil for talented Nobunaga and Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last person in charge of an administration tends to be undervalued in all ages and countries, and it is a pity that he could not help serving as a foil for the talented Nobunaga and Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last person in charge of an administration tends to be undervalued in all ages and countries, and it is a pity that he could not help serving as a foil for the talented Nobunaga and Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>一色昭国、畠山昭清、畠山昭高、細川昭賢、細川昭元、槙島昭光など偏諱を受けた守護等も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Shugos (feudal lords) such as Akikuni ISSHIKI, Akikiyo HATAKEYAMA, Akitaka HATAKEYAMA, Akikata HOSOKAWA, Akimoto HOSOKAWA and Akimitsu MAKISHIMA were given hen&apos;i from Yoshiaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Shugos (feudal lords) such as Akikuni ISSHIKI, Akikiyo HATAKEYAMA, Akitaka HATAKEYAMA, Akikata HOSOKAWA, Akimoto HOSOKAWA and Akimitsu MAKISHIMA were given hen&apos;i from Yoshiaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Shugos (feudal lords) such as Akikuni ISSHIKI, Akikiyo HATAKEYAMA, Akitaka HATAKEYAMA, Akikata HOSOKAWA, Akimoto HOSOKAWA and Akimitsu MAKISHIMA were given hen&apos;i from Yoshiaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>兄・義輝の死後、幕臣に守られながら流浪したり、信長に追放されて諸国を流浪したりしたりして諸大名を頼った経緯から、「貧乏公方」と噂されたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yoshiaki was rumored as &apos;a poor noble&apos; because he wondered with Bakufu statesmen after his elder brother Yoshiteru died and wondered in various provinces after an exile by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yoshiaki was called &apos;a poor noble&apos; because he wandered with Shogunate statesmen after his elder brother Yoshiteru died and wandered in various provinces after being exiled by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>spacing; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yoshiaki was called &apos;a poor noble&apos; because he wandered with Shogunate statesmen after his elder brother Yoshiteru died and wandered in various provinces after being exiled by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="60">
<j>義昭は自らが将軍に就任した際、元号を「元亀」と改元するべく朝廷に奏請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshiaki became the Shogun he proposed the Imperial Court to change an era name to &apos;Genki&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshiaki became the Shogun he proposed that the Imperial Court change the name of the era to &apos;Genki&apos;.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;that&quot;; era name-&gt;name of the era</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshiaki became the Shogun he proposed that the Imperial Court change the name of the era to &apos;Genki&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>しかし信長はそれが将軍権威の復活につながること、正親町天皇の在位が続いているのに必要ないと反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Nobunaga was against to him because it led to a revival of Shogun power and because Emperor Ogimachi still reigned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Nobunaga was opposed to him because he was connected to a revival of the Shogun&apos;s power and because Emperor Ogimachi still reigned.</e>
<cmt>reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Nobunaga was opposed to him because he was connected to a revival of the Shogun&apos;s power and because Emperor Ogimachi still reigned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし義昭は信長が朝倉氏討伐に出陣した4月23日、改元を実行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But on April 23, when Nobunaga left for the battle against ASAKURA, Yoshiaki put his idea into practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But on April 23, when Nobunaga left for the battle against ASAKURA, Yoshiaki put his ideas into practice.</e>
<cmt>idea-&gt;ideas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But on April 23, when Nobunaga left for the battle against ASAKURA, Yoshiaki put his ideas into practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>義昭の嫡男・義尋は、信長の人質となったあと出家して大乗院門跡を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki&apos;s heir Yoshihiro became a priest after being a hostage of Nobunaga, and succeeded Daijoin monseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki&apos;s heir Yoshihiro became a priest after being a hostage of Nobunaga, and succeeded Daijoin monseki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki&apos;s heir Yoshihiro became a priest after being a hostage of Nobunaga, and succeeded Daijoin monseki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>足利を名乗る子孫は江戸時代にいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no descendant who&apos;s family name was ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no descendant who&apos;s family name was ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no descendant who&apos;s family name was ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of governmental position</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Government Posts</e>
<cmt>reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Government Posts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>永禄9年（1566年）、従五位下に叙し、左馬頭に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1566 (Eiroku 9) Yoshiwaki was appointed as Jugoi-ge and Samanokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1566, Yoshiwaki was appointed as Jugoi-ge and Samanokami.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1566, Yoshiwaki was appointed as Jugoi-ge and Samanokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>叙位任官時期については疑問視もある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a doubt about the time of the appointment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are doubts about the time of the appointment.</e>
<cmt>is a doubt-&gt;are doubts</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are doubts about the time of the appointment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）10月18日 (旧暦)、従四位下に昇叙し、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 18, 1568 (Eiroku 11), he was promoted to Juyon&apos;i-ge and Sangi as an additional post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 18, 1568, he was promoted to Juyon&apos;i-ge and Sangi as an additional post.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 18, 1568, he was promoted to Juyon&apos;i-ge and Sangi as an additional post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>左近衛中将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held concurrently the post of Sakonoe Chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held concurrently the post of Sakonoe Chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held concurrently the post of Sakonoe Chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>征夷大将軍宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="70">
<j>永禄12年（1569年）6月22日 (旧暦)、従三位に昇叙し、大納言に栄進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 22, 1569 (Eiroku 12), he was promoted to Jusanmi and Dai&apos;nagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 22, 1569, he was promoted to Jusanmi and Dai&apos;nagon.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 22, 1569, he was promoted to Junito 3rd Rank and Dai&apos;nagon.</e>
<cmt>従三位→Junior 3rd Rank</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>天正2年（1574年）、京都より追放され、備後鞆の浦に亡命政府（幕府）樹立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1574 (Tensho 2) he was exiled from Kyoto and built a refugee government (Bakufu) at Tomo no Ura in Bingo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1574 he was exiled from Kyoto and built a government in exile (Shogunate) at Tomo no Ura in Bingo Province.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date; government in exile; Shogunate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1574 he was exiled from Kyoto and built a government in exile (Shogunate) at Tomo no Ura in Bingo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="72">
<j>天正16年（1588年）1月13日 (旧暦)、出家し征夷大将軍から准三宮に転身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13 (Tensho 16) (lunar date) he resigned Seii Taishogun and became a priest, Jusanguu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13, he resigned Seii Taishogun and became a priest, Jusanguu.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 13, he resigned Seii Taishogun and became a priest, Jusangu.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="73">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）8月28日 (旧暦)、卒去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 28, 1597 (Keicho 2) (lunar date) he passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 28, 159, he passed away.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 28, 159, he passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>法号は霊陽院昌山道休</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Reiyoin Shozan Donkyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name was Reiyoin Shozan Donkyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Reiyoin Shozan Donkyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>伝記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biographies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biographies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biographies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>奥野高広『足利義昭』（吉川弘文館人物叢書、1996年新装版） ISBN 4642051821</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahiro OKUNO &apos; Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Biographies from Yoshikawa Kobunkan Press, refurbished in 1966) ISBN 4642051821</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahiro OKUNO &apos;Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Biographies from Yoshikawa Kobunkan Press, reprinted in 1966) ISBN 4642051821</e>
<cmt>spacing; refurbished-&gt;reprinted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahiro OKUNO &apos;Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Biographies from Yoshikawa Kobunkan Press, reprinted in 1966) ISBN 4642051821</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="76">
<j>桑田忠親『流浪将軍 足利義昭』（講談社、1985年） ISBN 4642051821</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadachika KUWATA &apos; Wondering Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Kodan-sha Press, 1985) ISBN 4642051821</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadachika KUWATA &apos;Wondering Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Kodan-sha Press, 1985) ISBN 4642051821</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadachika KUWATA &apos;Wondering Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Kodan-sha Press, 1985) ISBN 4642051821</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>足利義昭を題材とした文芸作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literature on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literature on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literature on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>松本清張『陰謀将軍』（新潮文庫『佐渡流人行』収録）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seicho MATSUMOTO &apos;Imbo Shogun&apos; (In &apos;Sado ru&apos;ninko&apos; of Shincho Bunko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seicho MATSUMOTO &apos;Imbo Shogun&apos; (In &apos;Sado ru&apos;ninko&apos; of Shincho Bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seicho MATSUMOTO &apos;Inbo Shogun&apos; (In &apos;Sado ru&apos;ninko&apos; of Shincho Bunko)</e>
<cmt>ローマ字修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>岡本好古『御所車 最後の将軍・足利義昭』（文藝春秋 (出版社)、1993年） ISBN 4163140700</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshifuru OKAMOTO &apos;Goshoguruma the last Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Bungei Syunjuu Press, 1933) ISBN 4163140700</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshifuru OKAMOTO &apos;Goshoguruma: The Last Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Bungei Syunjuu Press, 1933) ISBN 4163140700</e>
<cmt>capitalized words in title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshifuru OKAMOTO &apos;Goshoguruma: The Last Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos; (Bungei Syunju Press, 1933) ISBN 4163140700</e>
<cmt>ローマ字修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="79">
<j>水上勉『足利義昭 流れ公方記』（学陽書房人物文庫、1998年） ISBN 4313750339</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsutomu MIZUKAMI &apos;Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA Nagerekuboki&apos; (Gakuyo Shobo Zimbutu Bunko, 1988) ISBN 4313750339</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsutomu MIZUKAMI &apos;Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA Nagarekuboki&apos; (Gakuyo Shobo Zimbutu Bunko, 1988) ISBN 4313750339</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsutomu MIZUKAMI &apos;Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA Nagarekuboki&apos; (Gakuyo Shobo Jinbutsu Bunko, 1988) ISBN 4313750339</e>
<cmt>ローマ字修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>足利義昭が登場する映像作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The audio-visual works where Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA appears</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Films Featuring Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>made more concise</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Films Featuring Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>映画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>『戦国自衛隊映画版』（1979年、俳優：鈴木瑞穂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movie of G.I Samurai&apos; (1979, the leading actor was Mizuho SUZUKI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;G.I Samurai the Movie&quot; (1979, the leading actor was Mizuho SUZUKI)</e>
<cmt>changed to double quotes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;G.I Samurai the Movie&quot; (1979, the leading actor was Mizuho SUZUKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>TVドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TV dramas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TV Dramas</e>
<cmt>capitalized words in section heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TV Dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>『太閤記 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1965年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：市村家橘（現・市村吉五郎））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikoki (NHK Taiga Drama) &apos; (1965, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Kakitsu ICHIMIRA (present Yoshigoro ICHIMURA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Taikoki&quot; (NHK Taiga Drama) 1965, NHK Taiga Drama (the leading actor was Kakitsu ICHIMIRA - now Yoshigoro ICHIMURA)</e>
<cmt>quotes/parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Taikoki&quot; (NHK Taiga Drama) 1965, NHK Taiga Drama (the leading actor was Kakitsu ICHIMIRA - now Yoshigoro ICHIMURA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>『天と地と (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1969年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：大出俊 (俳優)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten to chi to (Heaven and Earth)(NHK Dramatic Saga)&apos; (1969, NHK saga Drama, the leading actor was Shun OIDE)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heaven and Earth&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1969, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Shun OIDE)</e>
<cmt>Roma-ji deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Heaven and Earth&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1969, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Shun OIDE)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>『国盗り物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1973年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：伊丹十三）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunitori monogatari (NHK Taiga Drama)&apos; (1973, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Juzo ITAMI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kunitori Monogatari&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1973, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Juzo ITAMI)</e>
<cmt>quotes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kunitori Monogatari&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1973, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Juzo ITAMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>『黄金の日日』（1978年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：松橋登）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogon no hibi&apos; (1978, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Noboru MATSUHASHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Golden Days&quot; (1978, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Noboru MATSUHASHI)</e>
<cmt>quotes/parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Golden Days&quot; (1978, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Noboru MATSUHASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="85">
<j>『おんな太閤記』（1981年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：津村鷹志）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onna Tikoki&apos; (1981, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Takahashi TSUMURA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Onna Taikoki&quot; (1981, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Takahashi TSUMURA)</e>
<cmt>changed to double quotes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Onna Taikoki&quot; (1981, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Takahashi TSUMURA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="86">
<j>『徳川家康 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1983年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：篠原大作）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (NHK Taiga Drama)&apos; (1983, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Daisuke SHINOHARA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1983, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Daisuke SHINOHARA)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1983, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Daisuke SHINOHARA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="87">
<j>『太閤記 (TBSドラマ)』（1987年、TBS大型時代劇スペシャル、俳優：石橋蓮司）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikoki (TBS drama)&apos; (1987, TBS large historical play special, the leading actor was Renji ISHIBASHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Taikoki&quot; TBS drama (1987, TBS Grand Historical Play Special - the leading actor was Renji ISHIBASHI)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Taikoki&quot; TBS drama (1987, TBS Grand Historical Play Special - the leading actor was Renji ISHIBASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="88">
<j>『武田信玄 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1988年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：市川團蔵 (9代目)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingen Takeda (NHK Taiga Drama)&apos; (1988, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was the 9th Danzo ICHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shingen Takeda&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1988, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was the 9th Danzo ICHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shingen Takeda&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1988, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was the 9th Danzo ICHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="89">
<j>『織田信長 (TBSドラマ)』（1991年、TBS大型時代劇スペシャル、俳優大橋吾郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA (TBS drama)&apos; (1991,TBS large historical play special, the leading actor was Goro OHASHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nobunaga ODA&quot; (1991,TBS Grand Historical Play Special - the leading actor was Goro OHASHI)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nobunaga ODA&quot; (1991, TBS Grand Historical Play Special - the leading actor was Goro OHASHI)</e>
<cmt>スペースを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="90">
<j>『信長 KING OF ZIPANGU』（1992年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：花柳錦之輔 (3代目)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga KING OF ZIPANGU&apos; (1992, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Kinnosuke HANAYAGI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nobunaga KING OF ZIPANGU&quot; (1992, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Kinnosuke HANAYAGI)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nobunaga KING OF ZIPANGU&quot; (1992, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Kinnosuke HANAYAGI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="91">
<j>『織田信長 (テレビドラマ 1994年)』（1994年、テレビ東京・12時間超ワイドドラマ（後の新春ワイド時代劇）、俳優：京本政樹）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA (TV drama 1994)&apos; (1994, TV Tokyo 12 hours special wide drama(later new spring wide historical play), the leading actor was Masaki KYOMOTO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nobunaga ODA&quot; TV drama 1994 (1994, TV Tokyo Special 12 Hour Miniseries (which later became Spring Historical Play) - the leading actor was Masaki KYOMOTO)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nobunaga ODA&quot; TV drama 1994 (1994, TV Tokyo Special 12 Hour Miniseries (which later became Spring Historical Play) - the leading actor was Masaki KYOMOTO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="92">
<j>『豊臣秀吉 天下を獲る!』（1995年、テレビ東京・12時間超ワイドドラマ（後の新春ワイド時代劇）、俳優：石橋蓮司）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI tenka wo toru&apos; (1995, TV Tokyo 12 hours special wide drama(later new spring wide historical play), the leading actor was Renji ISHIBASHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI: Seize the World&quot; (1995, TV Tokyo Special 12 Hour Miniseries (which later became Spring Historical Play) - the leading actor was Renji ISHIBASHI)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI: Seize the World&quot; (1995, TV Tokyo Special 12 Hour Miniseries (which later became Spring Historical Play) - the leading actor was Renji ISHIBASHI)</e>
<cmt>スペースの重複を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="93">
<j>『秀吉 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1996年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：玉置浩二）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi (NHK Taiga Drama)&apos; (1966, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Koji TAMAKI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hideyoshi&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1966, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Koji TAMAKI)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hideyoshi&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (1966, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Koji TAMAKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="94">
<j>『利家とまつ〜加賀百万石物語〜』（2002年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：モロ師岡）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiie to Matsu Kaga hyakumangoku monogatari&apos; (2002, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Moro MOROOKA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Toshiie to Matsu Kaga Hyakumangoku Monogatari&quot; (2002, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Moro MOROOKA)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Toshiie and Matsu; Kaga One Million-koku Story&quot; (2002, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Moro MOROOKA)</e>
<cmt>タイトルのローマ字を一部訳した</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="95">
<j>『国盗り物語』（2005年、テレビ東京・新春ワイド時代劇、俳優：相島一之）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuni tori monogatari&apos; (2005, TV Tokyo new year wide historical play, the leading actor was Kazuyuki AIJIMA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kuni Tori Monogatari&quot; (2005, TV Tokyo New Year Historical Play - the leading actor was Kazuyuki AIJIMA)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kuni Tori Monogatari&quot; (2005, TV Tokyo New Year Historical Play - the leading actor was Kazuyuki AIJIMA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="96">
<j>『功名が辻 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（2006年、NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：三谷幸喜）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komyogatsuji (NHK Taiga Drama)&apos; (2006, NHK Dramatic Saga, the leading actor was Koki MITANI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Komyogatsuji&quot; NHK Taiga Drama (2006, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Koki MITANI)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Komyogatsuji&quot; (Crossroads of the achievement) NHK Taiga Drama (2006, NHK Taiga Drama - the leading actor was Koki MITANI)</e>
<cmt>タイトルに訳を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="97">
<j>『太閤記〜天下を獲った男・秀吉』（2006年、テレビ朝日火曜時代劇、俳優：京本政樹）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikoki tenka wo totta otoko Hideyoshi&apos; (2006, TV Asahi Tuesday historical play, the leading actor was Masaki KYOMOTO)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Taikoki - Hideyoshi: The Man Who Took the World&quot; (2006, TV Asahi Tuesday Historical Play - the leading actor was Masaki KYOMOTO)&apos;</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Taikoki - Hideyoshi: The Man Who Took the World&quot; (2006, TV Asahi Tuesday Historical Play - the leading actor was Masaki KYOMOTO)&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="98">
<j>『明智光秀〜神に愛されなかった男〜』（2007年、フジテレビジョン、俳優：谷原章介）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuhide AKECHI kami ni aisarenakatta otoko&apos; (2007, Fuji TV, the leading actor was Shosuke TANIHARA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mitsuhide AKECHI: A Man Not Loved by the Gods&quot; (2007, Fuji TV - the leading actor was Shosuke TANIHARA)</e>
<cmt>quotes etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mitsuhide AKECHI: A Man Not Loved by the Gods&quot; (2007, Fuji TV - the leading actor was Shosuke TANIHARA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hatabon(id:146971), Flamelai(id:34490), Tangobot(id:47812), ドルチェット(id:46458), Ittyon(id:1348), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Doskoi 8(id:1070), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 森造(id:48119), Ash Crow(id:26765), Kamakura(id:472), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 建長(id:119884), Johncapistrano(id:969), Rikuzen gun(id:107698), Hiruandon(id:427), 玄史生(id:43670), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), Kinori(id:443), Maakun(id:16735), 谷英樹(id:173520), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Tosiho(id:73924), Lonicera(id:20638), やりたこ(id:113528), Carbuncle(id:346), たね(id:10372), Azirosas(id:143367), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Aoiya(id:44787), Daranome(id:1429), Clen(id:100642), Bakira(id:184047), Escarbot(id:59151), Inukawa(id:842), Kagetudo(id:163875), Carkuni(id:79281), Tanuki Z(id:612), VolkovBot(id:105371), Boca samba(id:137526), Kyube(id:9866), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 故城一片之月(id:109503), Kazusanosuke(id:65668), King-wise(id:19033), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>