<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千葉重太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutaro CHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jutaro CHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutaro CHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千葉 重太郎（ちば じゅうたろう、文政7年（1824年） - 明治18年（1885年）5月7日）は、江戸時代の北辰一刀流の剣客。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutaro CHIBA (1824-May 7, 1885) was a swordsman of the Hokushin Itto-ryu Style during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jutaro CHIBA (1824-May 7, 1885) was a swordsman of the Hokushin Itto-ryu Style in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>duringをinに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutaro CHIBA (1824-May 7, 1885) was a swordsman of the Hokushin Itto-ryu Style in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>鳥取藩士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tottori clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a feudal retainer of the Tottori clan.</e>
<cmt>藩士の意味を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a feudal retainer of the Tottori clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>桶町千葉道場（小千葉）の創始者千葉定吉の息子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A son of Okemachi CHIBA-dojo Training Hall (Kochiba) founder, Sadakichi CHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Sadakichi CHIBA who was the founder of Okemachi Chiba-dojo (a training hall, commonly called Kochiba).</e>
<cmt>「小千葉」の説明の追加と文章の語順を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Sadakichi CHIBA who was the founder of Okemachi Chiba-dojo (a training hall, commonly called Kochiba).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>坂本龍馬は門人にして友人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoma SAKAMOTO was a student of dojo as well as Jutaro&apos;s friend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoma SAKAMOTO was a student of dojo as well as Jutaro&apos;s friend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma SAKAMOTO was a student of dojo as well as Jutaro&apos;s friend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また妹の千葉さな子は坂本龍馬の婚約者（妻とも）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And his sister, Sanako, was Ryoma&apos;s fiance (or rumored to be Ryoma&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And his sister, Sanako, was Ryoma&apos;s fiance (or rumored to be his wife).</e>
<cmt>代名詞に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And his sister, Sanako, was Ryoma&apos;s fiance (or rumored to be his wife).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>諱は一胤（かずたね）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known posthumously as Kazutane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known posthumously as Kazutane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known posthumously as Kazutane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>坂本龍馬と勝海舟を結果的に引き合わせることになった人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resulted in bringing Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Kaishu KATSU together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He eventually brought Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Kaishu KATSU together.</e>
<cmt>result の主語は物・事象なので、eventuallyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He eventually brought Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Kaishu KATSU together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>嘉永6年（1853年）に父・定吉が鳥取藩の剣術師範に就任し、鳥取藩江戸屋敷詰となったため道場は重太郎に任されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1853, Jutaro became in charge of Chiba-dojo after his father, Sadakichi, obtained a new assignment as a swordplay instructor at Tottori-han Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1853, Jutaro became in charge of Chiba-dojo after his father, Sadakichi, was appointed as a swordplay instructor for Tottori clan at Edo residence of Tottori Domain.</e>
<cmt>「鳥取藩江戸屋敷詰」の部分が抜けていたので加えて書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1853, Jutaro became in charge of Chiba-dojo after his father, Sadakichi, was appointed as a swordplay instructor for Tottori clan at Edo residence of Tottori Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>このころ、土佐から江戸に出てきた坂本龍馬が千葉道場に入門しているので、龍馬に剣術指南をしたのは主に重太郎であったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, after moving to EDO from Tosa Province, Ryoma SAKAMOTO became a student at Chiba-dojo; therefore, it is believed that Jutaro was the principal instructor who taught swordmanship to Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, Ryoma SAKAMOTO who came to Edo from Tosa Province became a student at Chiba-dojo, therefore, it is believed that Jutaro was the principal instructor who taught swordplay to Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>簡潔に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Ryoma SAKAMOTO who came to Edo from Tosa Province became a student at Chiba-dojo, therefore, it is believed that Jutaro was the principal instructor who taught swordplay to Ryoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>さらに万延元年（1860年）には重太郎自身も鳥取藩に仕官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Jutaro himself joined the Tottori clan in 1860.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Jutaro himself joined the Tottori clan in 1860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Jutaro himself joined the Tottori clan in 1860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>重太郎は鳥取藩士として江戸政界に関わる中で勝海舟の開国論に反感を抱くようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While being involved in the politics of Edo as one of the Tottori clan members, he began to feel opposed to Kaishu KATSU&apos;s idea of opening Japan to foreign trade and diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While being involved in the politics of Edo as one of the Tottori clan members, he began to feel opposed to Kaishu KATSU&apos;s idea of opening Japan to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>「開国論」の部分を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While being involved in the politics of Edo as one of the Tottori clan members, he began to feel opposed to Kaishu KATSU&apos;s idea of opening Japan to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>文久2年1862年、龍馬を伴い勝邸を訪れ、これを暗殺しようとしたが失敗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accompanied by Ryoma, he visited KATSU&apos;s residence to assassinate him; however, the plan failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accompanied by Ryoma, he visited KATSU&apos;s residence to assassinate him, but failed in 1862.</e>
<cmt>年号を加え、書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accompanied by Ryoma, he visited KATSU&apos;s residence to assassinate him, but failed in 1862.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後年の戊辰戦争では鳥取藩の歩兵頭として一隊を率いて出陣、維新後は鳥取県・北海道開拓使・京都府の官吏として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He led a group of foot soldiers in the later period of the Boshin War and played an active role as a government official for Kyoto prefecture in the Hokkaido Development office in Tottori prefecture after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He led a group of foot soldiers in Boshin War in later years, and after the Meiji Restoration, he played an active role as a government official at Tottori prefecture, Hokkaido Development office, and Kyoto prefecture.</e>
<cmt>原文の通り書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He led a group of foot soldiers in Boshin War in later years, and after the Meiji Restoration, he played an active role as a government official at Tottori prefecture, Hokkaido Development office, and Kyoto prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>墓は東京都豊島区池袋の雑司ヶ谷霊園に現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is in Zoshigaya-reien Cemetery in Ikebukuro, Toshima Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is in Zoshigaya-reien Cemetery in Ikebukuro, Toshima Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is in Zoshigaya-reien Cemetery in Ikebukuro, Toshima Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>重太郎の剣士としての力量については説が定まらないようであるが、重太郎が道場を任されるようになった後にも桶町道場の人気は衰えていないようなので、相当の実力を持つ剣客であったことは言を待たない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutaro&apos;s ability as a swordsman is unknown; however, it is certain that he was an expert swordsman with considerable skill since the popularity of dojo did not decline after he took over dojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jutaro&apos;s ability as a swordsman is unknown, however, it is certain that he was an expert swordsman with considerable skills since the popularity of Okemachi dojo did not decline after he took it over.</e>
<cmt>抜けている語を補い、書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutaro&apos;s ability as a swordsman is unknown, however, it is certain that he was an expert swordsman with considerable skills since the popularity of Okemachi dojo did not decline after he took it over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>本家筋にあたる玄武館道場が千葉道三郎の代になって衰退した例もあり、幕末期は師範の実力が道場の盛衰に直結する時代であったと推測さる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is proof that Genbukan-dojo, which was run by the head family of CHIBA, declined after Michisaburo CHIBA took over; thus, it is thought that the grand master&apos;s ability decided the fate of dojo at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an example that Genbukan-dojo which was run by the head family of Chiba declined after Michisaburo CHIBA took it over, thus, it is thought that the grand master&apos;s ability decided the fate of dojo at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「例」をexampleとし、took overに目的語を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an example that Genbukan-dojo which was run by the head family of Chiba declined after Michisaburo CHIBA took it over, thus, it is thought that the grand master&apos;s ability decided the fate of dojo at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この観点からも重太郎の実力の程が分る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, one can infer Jutaro&apos;s ability considering this aspect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering this aspect, one can infer Jutaro&apos;s ability.</e>
<cmt>語順を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering this aspect, one can infer Jutaro&apos;s ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>創作作品では、司馬遼太郎作「竜馬がゆく」から三谷幸喜の「竜馬におまかせ!」まで幅広いところで出現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutaro appears widely in many fiction novels including &apos;Ryoma ga yuku&apos; by Ryotaro SHIBA and &apos;Ryoma ni omakase&apos; by Koki MITANI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jutaro widely appears in many fiction works including &apos;Ryoma ga yuku&apos; (a novel) by Ryotaro SHIBA and &apos;Ryoma ni omakase !&apos; (a TV drama) scripted by Koki MITANI.</e>
<cmt>小説やドラマとの説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutaro widely appears in many fiction works including &apos;Ryoma ga yuku&apos; (a novel) by Ryotaro SHIBA and &apos;Ryoma ni omakase !&apos; (a TV drama) scripted by Koki MITANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>多くの作品において明朗快活な好青年として描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutaro is described as a cheerful, active, and likable youth in many novels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jutaro was described as a cheerful, active, and likable young man in many works.</e>
<cmt>過去形にし、一部書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutaro was described as a cheerful, active, and likable young man in many works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="20">
<j>また、「千葉道場の跡取り」というイメージからか、父共々鳥取藩士であったことは描かれないことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, from the aspect of &quot;Jutaro being a successor&quot; of CHIBA-dojo, it is not often mentioned that he was a member of the Tottori clan, as was his father.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, from the aspect of &apos;a successor of Chiba-dojo&apos;, it is not often mentioned that he and his father were both members of the Tottori clan.</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos; を加え、一部書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, from the aspect of &apos;a successor of Chiba-dojo&apos;, it is not often mentioned that he and his father were both members of the Tottori clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>（海舟暗殺未遂事件の時には既に鳥取藩に仕官していることに注意）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Note that he was already one of the Tottori clans when he attempted to assassinate Kaishu.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Note that he had already served for Tottori Domain when he attempted to assassinate Kaishu.).</e>
<cmt>「仕官している」の部分と藩の訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Note that he had already served for Tottori Domain when he attempted to assassinate Kaishu.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Sat666(id:127263), 前図書頭(id:134750), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>