<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今川義元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今川 義元（いまがわ よしもと）は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto IMAGAWA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto IMAGAWA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto IMAGAWA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), who lived during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) と大文字に修正しました。（用語統一）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>駿河国の守護大名・戦国大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) and a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Shugo daimyo (Japanese provincial military governors that later became daimyo) and a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;, which were Japanese feudal lords&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Shugo daimyo (Japanese provincial military governors that later became daimyo) and a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>本姓は源氏→real family name was Genji (Minamoto clan) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一家系・河内源氏の流れを汲む足利氏の傍流吉良氏の分家にあたる今川氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a member of the Imagawa clan, a branch family of the Kira clan that was a collateral line of the Ashikaga clan originated from the Kawachi-Genji clan (Minamoto clan), which was one of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan originated from Emperor Seiwa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of the Imagawa clan, a branch family of the Kira clan that was in a collateral line with the Ashikaga clan originating from the Kawachi-Genji clan (Minamoto clan), which was one of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan originated from Emperor Seiwa).</e>
<cmt>originated &gt; originating; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of the Imagawa clan, a branch family of the Kira clan that was in a collateral line with the Ashikaga clan originating from the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), which was one of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan originated from the Emperor Seiwa).</e>
<cmt>Kawachi-Genji clan→Kawachi-Genji と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>今川氏第9代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the ninth family head of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the ninth family head of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the ninth family head of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>駿河国（現在の静岡県中部）の守護大名である今川氏の第9代目当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the ninth family head of the Imagawa clan, which was a family that produced shugo daimyo in Suruga Province (present central part of Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>守護大名→shugo daimyo としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto was the ninth family head of the Imagawa clan, a family of Shugo daimyo in Suruga Province (present central part of Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Yoshimito; eliminated &quot;which was&quot;; that produced &gt; of; capitalized &quot;Shugo&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto was the ninth family head of the Imagawa clan, a family of Shugo daimyo in Suruga Province (present central part of Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>第7代当主・今川氏親とその正室である中御門宣胤の娘（寿桂尼）の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of the seventh family head Ujichika IMAGAWA and his lawful wife was the daughter of Nobutane NAKAMIKADO (Jukeini).</e>
<cmt>中御門宣胤→Nobutane NAKAMIKADO (Nobutane NAKANOMIKADOとも言うようです）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of the seventh family head named Ujichika IMAGAWA, and his lawful wife was the daughter of Nobutane NAKAMIKADO (Jukeini).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;named&quot; before &quot;Ujichika&quot;; added period after &quot;IMAGAWA&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of the seventh family head named Ujichika IMAGAWA, and his lawful wife was the daughter of Nobutane NAKAMIKADO (Jukeini).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名は芳菊丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Hogikumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Hogikumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Hogikumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>正室は武田信虎の娘で武田信玄の姉にあたる定恵院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was Joein, who was Nobutora TAKEDA&apos;s daughter and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s older sister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was Joein, Nobutora TAKEDA&apos;s daughter and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s older sister.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;who was&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was Joein, Nobutora TAKEDA&apos;s daughter and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s older sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>子に今川氏真、娘は武田義信の室となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son was Ujizane IMAGAWA, and his daughter became Yoshinobu TAKEDA&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a son named Ujizane IMAGAWA and his daughter became Yoshinobu TAKEDA&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>His son was &gt; He had a son named;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a son named Ujizane IMAGAWA and his daughter became Yoshinobu TAKEDA&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>北条氏康は義弟にあたり、また武田信玄の義兄でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujiyasu HOJO was his younger brother-in-law, and he himself was Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s older brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujiyasu HOJO was his younger brother-in-law, and he himself was Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s older brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujiyasu HOJO was his younger brother-in-law, and he himself was Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s older brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>寄親・寄子制度を設け、軍事組織力の革命的な改革を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He set up Yorioya-Yoriko system (a system of military unit sustained by a pseudo-parental relation of feudal retainers, in which a powerful retainer assumed the role of Yorioya [dependable person, or literally dependable father] and lead an army group formed by small and middle retainers called Yoriko [depending fellows, or literally depending children]), and carried out a revolutionary reform in strengthening the military organizational power.</e>
<cmt>寄親・寄子制度→定訳不明：system of Yorioya-Yoriko (a system of military unit sustained by a pseudo-parental relation of feudal retainers, in which a powerful retainer assumed the role of Yorioya [dependable person, or literally dependable father] and lead an army group formed by small and middle retainers called Yoriko [depending fellows, or literally depending children]) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He set up the Yorioya-Yoriko system (a system of military units sustained by a pseudo-parental relationship between feudal retainers in which a powerful retainer assumed the role of Yorioya [dependable person, or literally dependable father] and lead an army group formed by small and middle retainers called Yoriko [depending fellows, or literally depending children]), and carried out a revolutionary reform in strengthening military organizational power.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Yorioya&quot;; unit &gt; units; relation &gt; relationship; of feudal retainers &gt; between feudal retainers; eliminated comma after &quot;retainers&quot;; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;military&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He set up the Yorioya-Yoriko system (a system of military units sustained by a pseudo-parental relationship between feudal retainers in which a powerful retainer assumed the role of Yorioya [dependable person, or literally dependable father] and lead an army group formed by small and middle retainers called Yoriko [depending fellows, or literally depending children]), and carried out a revolutionary reform in strengthening military organizational power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>領国経営と外征の双方に才能を発揮し、今川氏の戦国大名への転身を成功させ、所領も駿河・遠江国・東三河から、西三河や尾張国の一部にまで拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He demonstrated an outstanding ability in the management of his own territory as well as in the outward military expedition, and he succeeded in transforming the Imagawa clan into one of the Sengoku daimyo, expanding his territory from Suruga Province, Totomi Province and Higashimikawa (eastern part of Mikawa Province) to Nishimikawa (west part of Mikawa Province), even reaching to a part of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He demonstrated an outstanding ability in management of his own territory as well as in outward military expeditions, and he succeeded in transforming the head of the Imagawa clan into a Sengoku daimyo, expanding his territory from Suruga Province, Totomi Province and Higashimikawa (eastern part of Mikawa Province) to Nishimikawa (west part of Mikawa Province), even reaching into a part of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;management&quot;; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;outward&quot;; expedition &gt; expeditions; added &quot;the head of the&quot; after &quot;transforming&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He demonstrated an outstanding ability in management of his own territory as well as in outward military expeditions, and he succeeded in transforming the head of the Imagawa clan into a Sengoku daimyo, expanding his territory from Suruga Province, Totomi Province and Higashimikawa (eastern part of Mikawa Province) to Nishimikawa (west part of Mikawa Province), even reaching into a part of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし尾張に侵攻した際に桶狭間の戦いで織田信長軍の奇襲により戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during the military offensive in Owari Province, he received a surprise attack of Nobunaga Oda&apos;s army in the Battle of Okehazama, and died in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during a military offensive in Owari Province, Nobunaga Oda&apos;s army made a surprise attack on Yoshimoto in the Battle of Okehazama and he died in battle.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during a military offensive in Owari Province, Nobunaga Oda&apos;s army made a surprise attack on Yoshimoto in the Battle of Okehazama and he died in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内乱と家督相続</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Domestic Conflict and Succession to Family Headship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Domestic Conflict and Succession to Family Head</e>
<cmt>Headship &gt; Head;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Domestic Conflict and Succession to Family Head</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>永正16年（1519年）、今川氏親の五男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1519, he was born as the fifth son of Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto was born in 1519 as the fifth son of Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto was born in 1519 as the fifth son of Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>生まれたときはすでに同母兄でのちに第8代当主となる今川氏輝がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was born, the family already had a heir, Ujiteru IMAGAWA, who was Yoshimoto&apos;s older brother by the same mother and later became the eighth family head.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family had already had an heir when he was born named Ujiteru IMAGAWA, Yoshimoto&apos;s older brother by the same mother, who later became the eighth family head.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family had already had an heir when he was born named Ujiteru IMAGAWA, Yoshimoto&apos;s older brother by the same mother, who later became the eighth family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため、4歳で仏門に出されて臨済宗の駿河富士郡瀬古の善徳寺に預けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Yoshimoto was sent to Zentoku-ji Temple of the Rinzai Sect in Seko, Fuji Country, Suruga Province and became a priest at the age of 4.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Yoshimoto was sent to the Zentoku-ji Temple of the Rinzai Sect in Seko, Fuji Country, Suruga Province and became a priest at the age of four.</e>
<cmt>Therefore &gt; As a result; 4 &gt; four;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Yoshimoto was sent to the Zentoku-ji Temple of the Rinzai Sect in Seko, Fuji County, Suruga Province and became a priest at the age of four.</e>
<cmt>Country→County と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>栴岳承芳（せんがくしょうほう（梅岳承芳（ばいがくしょうほう）は誤伝））と称し教育係につけられた今川家重臣出身の禅僧・太原雪斎とともに京都に上って五山に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Shoho SENGAKU (the reading of Shoho BAIGAKU was inaccurate) and in order to study at Kyoto Gozan (five selected temples in Kyoto), he went up to Kyoto accompanied by Zen priest Sessai TAIGEN, who was a chief retainer of the Imagawa family and deliberately assigned to serve Yoshimoto as a tutor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。五山→定訳不明：Kyoto Gozan (five selected temples in Kyoto) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Shoho SENGAKU (the reading of Shoho BAIGAKU was inaccurate), and in order to study at Kyoto Gozan (the five selected temples in Kyoto), he went up to Kyoto accompanied by the Zen priest Sessai TAIGEN, a chief retainer of the Imagawa family and assigned to serve Yoshimoto as a tutor.</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing after &quot;and&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;five&quot;; eliminated &quot;who was&quot; before &quot;a chief&quot;; eliminated &quot;deliberately&quot; since it was awkward and did not help in understanding the meaning of the sentence;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Sengaku Shoho (the reading of Baigaku Shoho was inaccurate), and in order to study at Kyoto Gozan (the five selected temples in Kyoto), he went up to Kyoto accompanied by the Zen priest Sessai TAIGEN, a chief retainer of the Imagawa family and assigned to serve Yoshimoto as a tutor.</e>
<cmt>Shoho BAIGAKU→Baigaku Shoho （調べるとこちらでの表記が主なのでこのように修正しました）Shoho SENGAKU→Sengaku Shoho （僧侶としての名前であるのと、調べてみて表記の順序がはっきりしないのでこちらに修正しました）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>天文 (元号)5年（1536年）、氏輝が急死したために駿河に戻り異母兄で同じく出家していた玄広恵探との間で家督争いとなるが、雪斎の尽力で勝利し、還俗して今川氏第9代当主・駿河守護となり、義元と称した（花倉の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1536 when Ujiteru died suddenly, he was involved in the family&apos;s succession dispute with Etan GENKO, Yoshimoto&apos;s older paternal half-brother who was also in priesthood, and Yoshimoto, who finally wan the dispute thanks to Sessai&apos;s intensive efforts, quitted the priesthood and took over the positions of the ninth family head of Imagawa clan as well as the shugo (provincial military governor) in Suruga Province, and began calling himself Yoshimoto (Hanakura Rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ujiteru suddenly died in 1536, Yoshimoto got involved in the family succession dispute with Etan GENKO, Yoshimoto&apos;s older paternal half-brother who was also in the priesthood, and Yoshimoto, who finally won the dispute thanks to Sessai&apos;s intensive efforts, quit the priesthood and took over the position of the ninth family head of Imagawa clan as well as the shugo in Suruga Province, and began calling himself Yoshimoto (Hanakura Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>wan &gt; won; quitted &gt; quit; eliminated description of &quot;shugo&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ujiteru suddenly died in 1536, Yoshimoto came to be involved in the family succession dispute with Etan GENKO, Yoshimoto&apos;s older paternal half-brother who was also in the priesthood, and Yoshimoto, who finally won the dispute due to Sessai&apos;s intensive efforts, quit the priesthood and took over the position of the ninth family head of Imagawa clan as well as the shugo in Suruga Province, and began calling himself Yoshimoto (Hanakura Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>got→came to be,thanks to→due to と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>北条・織田との戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle between the Hojo clan and the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle between the Hojo clan and the Oda clan</e>
<cmt>eliminated period;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle between the Hojo clan and the Oda clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>天文6年（1537年）2月、氏輝期までの抗争状態にあった甲斐国の守護武田信虎の娘（定恵院）を正室に迎え、武田氏と同盟を結んだ（甲駿同盟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March or April 1537 (表記の変更), he concluded an alliance with the Takeda clan, with which the Imagawa family had been in a long state of war until the Ujiteru&apos;s generation, by taking the daughter (Joein) of Shugo (provincial military governor) in Kai Province Nobutora TAKEDA, as his lawful wife (Kosun Alliance [an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province]).</e>
<cmt>守護→Shugo (provincial military governor) 肩書きなので大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March or April of 1537 (表記の変更), Yoshimoto created an alliance with the Takeda clan, whom with the Imagawa family had been in a long state of war until the Ujiteru&apos;s generation, by taking the daughter (Joein) of the Shugo in the Kai Province named Nobutora TAKEDA, as his lawful wife (Kosun Alliance [an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province]).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot; before &quot;1537&quot;; he &quot;Yoshimoto&quot;; concluded &gt; created; fixed grammar and spacing;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1537, Yoshimoto created an alliance with the Takeda clan, whom with the Imagawa family had been in a long state of war until the Ujiteru&apos;s generation, by taking the daughter (Joein) of the Shugo in the Kai Province named Nobutora TAKEDA, as his lawful wife (Kosun Alliance [an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province]).</e>
<cmt>天文6年2月→西暦1537年3月として修正しました。(表記の変更）を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>甲駿同盟の成立は旧来の縁戚であった伊豆国（静岡県伊豆地方）・相模国（神奈川県西南部）を領する後北条氏との駿相同盟決裂を招き、北条氏綱が駿河河東郡吉原に侵攻する（河東の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the Kosun Alliance lead to the決裂 break of the Sunso Alliance (Suruga-Sagami alliance), an alliance with a long time relative family, the Gohojo clan, which was dominating the territory of Izu Province (Izu region, Shizuoka Prefecture) and Sagami Province (southwest part of Kanagawa Prefecture), and as a result, Ujitsuna HOJO set out military invasion into Yoshihara of Kato Country in Suruga Province (Kato War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Kosun Alliance lead to the break of the Sunso Alliance (Suruga-Sagami alliance), an alliance that had been with a long time relative family, the Gohojo clan, who were dominating the provinces of Izu (Izu region, Shizuoka Prefecture) and Sagami (southwest part of Kanagawa Prefecture), resulting in Ujitsuna HOJO setting out for a military invasion into Yoshihara of Kato Country in Suruga Province (Kato War).</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;決裂 &quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Kosun Alliance lead to the break of the Sunso Alliance (Suruga-Sagami alliance), an alliance that had been with a long time relative family, the Gohojo clan, who were dominating the provinces of Izu (Izu region, Shizuoka Prefecture) and Sagami (southwest part of Kanagawa Prefecture), resulting in Ujitsuna HOJO setting out for a military invasion into Yoshihara of Kato County in Suruga Province (Kato War).</e>
<cmt>Country→County と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>義元もこれに対して交戦するが、氏綱の前に敗れて河東郡を奪われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto counterattacked to the invasion, however, he lost to Ujitsuna and he was deprived of Kato Country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto made a counterattack to the invasion but lost to Ujitsuna and he was deprived of Kato Country.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto made a counterattack to the invasion but lost to Ujitsuna and he was deprived of Kato County.</e>
<cmt>Country→County と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに、尾張国（愛知県西部）の織田信秀が天文9年（1540年）から三河国（愛知県東部）に対して侵攻を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Nobuhide ODA of Owari Province (western part of Aichi Prefecture) began invading Mikawa Province (eastern part of Aichi Prefecture) in 1540.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Nobuhide ODA of Owari Province (western part of Aichi Prefecture) began invading Mikawa Province (eastern part of Aichi Prefecture) in 1540.</e>
<cmt>Moreover &gt; Additionally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Nobuhide ODA of Owari Province (western part of Aichi Prefecture) began invading Mikawa Province (eastern part of Aichi Prefecture) in 1540.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>このため、義元は三河の諸豪族と連合して天文11年（1542年）に信秀と一大決戦に臨むが、その猛攻の前に敗れた（第1次小豆坂の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Yoshimoto challenged a decisive battle against Nobuhide in 1542 counting on an alliance with various local ruling families in Mikawa Province, however, he went down before an intensive attack of the Nobuhide&apos;s side (the First Battle of Azuki-zaka).</e>
<cmt>第1次小豆坂の戦い→the First Battle of Azuki-zaka としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshimoto challenged Nobuhide to a decisive battle in 1542 by counting on an alliance with various local ruling families in Mikawa Province, he was defeated even before Nobuhide made an intensive attack (the First Battle of Azuki-zaka).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshimoto challenged Nobuhide to a decisive battle in 1542 by counting on an alliance with various local ruling families in Mikawa Province, he was defeated by Nobuhide&apos;s intensive attack (the First Battle of Azuki-zaka).</e>
<cmt>even before Nobuhide made an→by Nobuhide&apos;s と修正しました。（ここでの「猛攻の前に」とは「猛攻によって」との意味合いであると理解し、修正しました。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>ただしこの戦いを創作とする説もあり、その場合は第2次小豆坂の戦いのみが存在する事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is an argument that this battle was a fiction, and according to it, there existed only the Second Battle of Azuki-zaka in the real history.</e>
<cmt>第2次小豆坂の戦い→the Second Battle of Azuki-zaka としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is another theory that this battle is fictitious and there was only a Second Battle of Azuki-zaka in real history.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is another theory that this battle is fictitious and there was only a Second Battle of Azuki-zaka in real history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>また天文10年（1541年）には嫡子の武田晴信に追放された信虎を駿河に庇護しているが、この追放劇は義元と晴信が共謀したものではないかとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1541, Yoshimoto offered asylum to Nobutora TAKEDA, who was banished by his own legitimate son Harunobu TAKEDA, and accepted him in Suruga Province, however, it is also suspect that Nobutora&apos;s banishment might have been carried out in collusion by Yoshimoto and Harunobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1541, Yoshimoto offered asylum to Nobutora TAKEDA, who had been banished by his own legitimate son Harunobu TAKEDA, and accepted him in Suruga Province, but it has also been suggested that Nobutora&apos;s banishment might have been carried out in a collusion between Yoshimoto and Harunobu.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1541, Yoshimoto offered asylum to Nobutora TAKEDA, who had been banished by his own legitimate son Harunobu TAKEDA, and accepted him in Suruga Province, but it has also been suggested that Nobutora&apos;s banishment might have been carried out in a collusion between Yoshimoto and Harunobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>勢力拡大</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expansion of power</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expansion of power</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expansion of power</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>北条家では天文10年（1541年）に氏綱が死去し氏康が家督を継いでいたが、義元は氏康と同じく敵対する上杉憲政と天文14年（1545年）に同盟を結んで、連携して氏康を攻めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While in the Hojo family, Ujiyasu succeeded to the reins of the family after the death of Ujitsuna in 1541, Yoshimoto formed an alliance in 1545 with Norimasa UESUGI, who was also in a warring state with Ujiyasu, and they made a joint attack against Ujiyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Ujiyasu succeeded the head of the Hojo family after the death of Ujitsuna in 1541, Yoshimoto formed an alliance in 1545 with Norimasa UESUGI, who was also in a warring state with Ujiyasu, and they made a joint attack against Ujiyasu.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more smoothly;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Ujiyasu succeeded the head of the Hojo family after the death of Ujitsuna in 1541, Yoshimoto formed an alliance in 1545 with Norimasa UESUGI, who was also in a warring state with Ujiyasu, and they made a joint attack against Ujiyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その結果、義元と氏康は武田晴信（信玄）の仲介により、北条家の河東郡を今川家に返還するという義元に有利な条件で和睦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Yoshimoto and Ujiyasu reached to an reconciliation thanks to the mediation of Harunobu TAKEDA (Shingen) with the conditions favorable for Yoshimoto, in which the Kato Country dominated by the Hojo family was settled to be returned to the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Yoshimoto and Ujiyasu reconciled, due to the mediation of Harunobu TAKEDA (Shingen) with conditions favorable for Yoshimoto, in which it was settled to have the Kato Country dominated by the Hojo family returned to the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more smoothly;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Yoshimoto and Ujiyasu reconciled, due to the mediation of Harunobu TAKEDA (Shingen) with conditions favorable for Yoshimoto, in which it was settled to have the Kato County dominated by the Hojo family returned to the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>Country→County と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>天文20年（1551年）、氏康によって興国寺城を奪われたものの、すぐに奪還して黄瀬川を国境としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshimoto was once deprived of Kokuji-jo Castle by Ujiyasu in 1551, he rapidly regained it and defined the border with the Kise River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshimoto was once deprived of Kokuji-jo Castle by Ujiyasu in 1551, he rapidly regained it and defined the border with the Kise River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshimoto was once deprived of Kokuji-jo Castle by Ujiyasu in 1551, he rapidly regained it and defined the border with the Kise-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Kise River→Kise-gawa River と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>三河においても尾張の織田信秀の進出により圧迫を受けた西三河の松平広忠の帰順を受け、広忠の嫡男・竹千代（のちの徳川家康）を人質に迎え入れようとするが、護送を請け負った三河・田原城 (三河国)（愛知県田原市）の国人領主・戸田康光が裏切って護送中の竹千代を敵方の織田氏に送り届けてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto accepted the submission of Hirotada MATSUDAIRA in Mikawa Province, who felt threatened by the Nobuhide ODA of Owari Province, in exchange for the hostage of Hirotada&apos;s legitimate son, Takechiyo (later Ieyasu TOKUGAWA), however, a kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) of Tawara-jo Castle in Mikawa Province (Tahara City, Aichi Prefecture), Yasumitsu TODA, who was in charge of escorting the hostage, betrayed Yoshimoto during his duty and sent Takechiyo to Yoshimoto&apos;s enemy the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshimoto accepted the submission of Hirotada MATSUDAIRA in Mikawa Province, who felt threatened by Nobuhide ODA of Owari Province, in exchange for Hirotada&apos;s legitimate son as a hostage Takechiyo (later Ieyasu TOKUGAWA), a kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) of Tawara-jo Castle in Mikawa Province (Tahara City, Aichi Prefecture) named Yasumitsu TODA, who was in charge of escorting the hostage, betrayed Yoshimoto and sent Takechiyo to the Oda clan, Yoshimoto&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;however&quot; to &quot;although&quot; and used at the beginning of the sentence; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoshimoto accepted the submission of Hirotada MATSUDAIRA in Mikawa Province, who felt threatened by Nobuhide ODA of Owari Province, in exchange for Hirotada&apos;s legitimate son as a hostage Takechiyo (later Ieyasu TOKUGAWA), a kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) of Tawara-jo Castle in Mikawa Province (Tahara City, Aichi Prefecture) named Yasumitsu TODA, who was in charge of escorting the hostage, betrayed Yoshimoto and sent Takechiyo to the Oda clan, Yoshimoto&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これは、前年に義元が戸田氏の一族である戸田宣成、戸田吉光を滅ぼしたため、これに憤った戸田宗家の当主であった康光が反乱を起こしたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasumitsu did it because he was indignant at Yoshimoto because Yoshimoto destroyed a year earlier Norinari TODA and Yoshimitsu TODA, who were members of the Toda clan, and he declared a rebellion against Yoshimoto as the head of Soke (the head family) of the Toda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasumitsu did so because of his indignance for Yoshimoto destroying Toda clan members Norinari TODA and Yoshimitsu TODA a year earlier, and he declared a rebellion against Yoshimoto as the head of Soke (the head family) of the Toda clan.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasumitsu did so because of his indignance for Yoshimoto destroying Toda clan members Norinari TODA and Yoshimitsu TODA a year earlier, and he declared a rebellion against Yoshimoto as the head of Soke (the head family) of the Toda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これに怒った義元は戸田宗家をも滅ぼし、その居城であった田原城に朝比奈氏を入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto, who got angry about it, destroyed Soke of Toda family, and made the Asahina clan to live in Tawara-jo Castle, which was the castle of the Toda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An angered Yoshimoto destroyed Soke of the Toda clan and had the Asahina clan move into the Toda family&apos;s Tawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more understandably;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An angered Yoshimoto destroyed Soke of the Toda clan and had the Asahina clan move into the Toda family&apos;s Tawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>天文17年（1548年）、義元の三河進出に危機感を覚えた織田信秀が三河に侵攻してくるが、義元の重臣である雪斎・朝比奈泰能らを大将とした今川軍は織田軍に大勝し、織田家の勢力を事実上三河から駆逐した（第2次小豆坂の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1548, Nobuhide ODA, who had a sense of danger at Yoshimoto&apos;s invasion into Mikawa Province, set out an attack against Yoshimoto, however, the Imagawa army lead by major captains such as Yoshimoto&apos;s chief retainers Sessai and Yasuyoshi ASAHINA wan a landslide victory against the Oda army, almost eradicating the influence of the Oda family from Mikawa Province (the Second Battle of Azuki-zaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1548, sensing danger at Yoshimoto&apos;s invasion into the Mikawa Province, Nobuhide ODA set out to attack Yoshimoto, but the Imagawa army, lead by major captains such as Yoshimoto&apos;s chief retainers Sessai and Yasuyoshi ASAHINA, made a clean sweep victory against the Oda army, almost eradicating the influence of the Oda family from Mikawa Province (the Second Battle of Azuki-zaka).</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1548, sensing danger at Yoshimoto&apos;s invasion into the Mikawa Province, Nobuhide ODA set out to attack Yoshimoto, but the Imagawa army, lead by major captains such as Yoshimoto&apos;s chief retainers Sessai and Yasuyoshi ASAHINA, made a clean sweep victory against the Oda army, almost eradicating the influence of the Oda family from Mikawa Province (the Second Battle of Azuki-zaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>天文18年（1549年）、松平広忠が死去すると義元は今川軍を岡崎城（愛知県岡崎市）に送り込んで、事実上松平家の所領とその支配下にあった三河の国人領主を直接支配下に取り込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1549, when Hirotada MATSUDAIRA died, Yoshimoto sent the Imagawa army to Okazaki-jo Castle (Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) and practically took over the Matsudaira family&apos;s territory and placed its kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords) under his immediate dominance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hirotada MATSUDAIRA died in 1549, Yoshimoto sent the Imagawa army to Okazaki-jo Castle (Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) and practically took over the Matsudaira family&apos;s territory and placed its kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords) under his immediate authority.</e>
<cmt>moved location of &quot;1549&quot; to later in the sentence; dominanace &gt; authority;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hirotada MATSUDAIRA died in 1549, Yoshimoto sent the Imagawa army to Okazaki-jo Castle (Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) and practically took over the Matsudaira family&apos;s territory and placed its kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords) under his immediate authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、織田方の三河安祥城（愛知県安城市）を攻略し信秀の庶長子にあたる城将・織田信広を捕らえ、人質交換によって竹千代を奪還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also attacked Mikawa Ansho-jo Castle (Anjo City, Aichi Prefecture) owned by the Oda clan and captured Nobuhide&apos;s eldest bastard child and the castle commander Nobuhiro ODA and used him to retrieve Takechiyo in exchange of the hostages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also attacked the Oda clan&apos;s Mikawa Ansho-jo Castle (Anjo City, Aichi Prefecture), captured Nobuhide&apos;s eldest bastard child and the castle commander Nobuhiro ODA and used him to retrieve Takechiyo in exchange for the hostages.</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing of the period; of the hostages &gt; for the hostages; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also attacked the Oda clan&apos;s Mikawa Ansho-jo Castle (Anjo City, Aichi Prefecture), captured Nobuhide&apos;s first bastard child and the castle commander Nobuhiro ODA and used him to retrieve Takechiyo in exchange for the hostages.</e>
<cmt>eldest→first と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>尾張進出の足掛かりを着々と築いていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, he was steadily gaining footholds for advancing into Owari Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto was steadily gaining footholds for advancing into the Owari Province</e>
<cmt>Thus, he &gt; Yoshimoto; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Owari&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto was steadily gaining footholds for advancing into the Owari Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>天文20年（1551年）に織田信秀が死去すると尾張への攻勢を一段と加速させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1551 when Nobuhide ODA died, he further accelerated an offensive movement in Owari Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nobuhide ODA died in 1551, Yoshimoto further accelerated an offensive movement into the Owari Province</e>
<cmt>moved location of &quot;1551&quot; to later in the sentence; he &gt; Yoshimoto; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Owari&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nobuhide ODA died in 1551, Yoshimoto further accelerated an offensive movement into the Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="38">
<j>更に天文22年（1553年）には亡父の定めた今川仮名目録に仮名目録追加を加えたが、ここにおいて室町幕府が定めた守護使不入地の廃止を宣言、守護大名としての今川氏と室町幕府間に残された関係を完全に断ち切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in 1553 he revised Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house law to control the territory) enacted by his deceased father Ujichika and expanded on it by adding the articles collectively called Kana Mokuroku Tsuika (Expanding on house rules left by Ujichika), and in this event, he declared the abolition within his territory of shugoshi funyu chi (the bakufu-owned area within a feudal lord&apos;s territory where the access was restricted even for the feudal lord who was authorized as shugo [the provincial military governor]) instituted by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and definitively cut off the relation between the Imagawa clan as shugo daimyo (feudal lord vested with the authority of shugo by the bakufu) and the Muromachi bakufu, although their relation had been barely persisting until then.</e>
<cmt>今川仮名目録→定訳不明：Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house rules to control the territory) と、（）内の説明は、統一リストの（Kana List of Articles of the Imagawa)の代わりに (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house rules to control the territory)を加えました。仮名目録追加→定訳不明：Kana Mokuroku Tsuika (Expanding on house rules left by Ujichika) としました。守護→shugo (the provincial military governor) としました。守護使不入地→定訳不明：shugoshi funyu chi (the bakufu-owned area designated within a feudal lord&apos;s territory where the access was restricted even for the feudal lord who was authorized as shugo [the provincial military governor]) としました。守護大名→shugo daimyo (feudal lord vested with the authority of shugo by the bakufu) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in 1553 Yoshimoto revised the Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house law to control the territory), enacted by his deceased father Ujichika, and expanded on it by adding articles collectively referred to as the Kana Mokuroku Tsuika (Expanding on the house rules left by Ujichika), in which he declared abolition within his territory of shugoshi funyu chi (the bakufu-owned area within a feudal lord&apos;s territory where access was restricted even for the feudal lord authorized as shugo) instituted by the Muromachi bakufu, and definitively cut off relations between the Imagawa clan as a Shugo daimyo and the Muromachi bakufu, even though this relationship had barely persisted until then.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Yoshimoto; added &quot;the&quot; before&quot; Imagawa&quot;; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;collectively&quot;; eliminated description of Shugo in brackets; eliminated description of &quot;bakufu&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in 1553 Yoshimoto revised the Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house law to control the territory), enacted by his deceased father Ujichika, and expanded on it by adding articles collectively referred to as the Kana Mokuroku Tsuika (Expanding on the house rules left by Ujichika), in which he declared abolition within his territory of shugoshi funyu chi (the bakufu-owned area within a feudal lord&apos;s territory where access was restricted even for the feudal lord authorized as shugo) instituted by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and definitively cut off relations between the Imagawa clan as a Shugo daimyo and the Muromachi bakufu, even though this relationship had barely persisted until then.</e>
<cmt>「室町幕府」のカッコ部分を補いました。（用語統一）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>天文23年（1554年）、嫡子・氏真に北条氏康の娘（早川殿）を縁組し、武田氏・北条氏と互いに婚姻関係を結んで甲相駿三国同盟を結成した（この会談は善徳寺の会盟とも呼ばれている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1554, he arranged the marriage between his legitimate son Ujizane and the daughter of Ujiyasu HOJO (Hayakawadono), and as a result, he became related to the Takeda clan as well as the Hojo clan through his children&apos;s marriages, and formed Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (alliance between three provinces; Kai, Sagami and Suruga) (this negotiation is also called &apos;tripartite alliance of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, Ujiyasu HOJO and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1554, Yoshimoto arranged a marriage between his legitimate son Ujizane and the daughter of Ujiyasu HOJO (Hayakawadono), tying his family to the Takeda clan as well as the Hojo clan, and formed the Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (alliance between three provinces; Kai, Sagami and Suruga) (this negotiation is also called the &apos;Tripartite alliance of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, Ujiyasu HOJO and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;).</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Yoshimoto; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1554, Yoshimoto arranged a marriage between his legitimate son Ujizane and the daughter of Ujiyasu HOJO (Hayakawadono), tying his family to the Takeda clan as well as the Hojo clan, and formed the Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (alliance between three provinces; Kai, Sagami and Suruga) (this negotiation is also called the &apos;Tripartite alliance of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, Ujiyasu HOJO and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これにより後顧の憂いを断った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this, he cut off his anxiety for future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was able to cut of his anxiety of the future through this marriage.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was able to cut of his anxiety of the future through this marriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>また天文24年・弘治元年（1555年）に行われた川中島の戦いでは武田晴信と長尾景虎の仲介を行って両者の和睦を成立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Kawanakajima that broke out in 1555, he mediated between Harunobu TAKEDA and Kagetora NAGAO and achieved their reconciliation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Kawanakajima that broke out in 1555, Yoshimoto mediated between Harunobu TAKEDA and Kagetora NAGAO and achieved reconciliation between the two.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Yoshimoto; achieved their reconciliation &gt; achieved reconcilation between the two;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Kawanakajima that broke out in 1555, Yoshimoto mediated between Harunobu TAKEDA and Kagetora NAGAO and achieved reconciliation between the two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>永禄元年（1558年）からは氏真と政務の分担を図っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1558, he intended to share the provincial government affaires with his son Ujizane</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1558, Yoshimoto made plans to share provincial government affairs with his son Ujizane.</e>
<cmt>added period; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1558, Yoshimoto made plans to share provincial government affairs with his son Ujizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>駿河・遠江・三河で検地も実施している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also carried out land surveys in Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa Provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also carried out land surveys in Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also carried out land surveys in Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto&apos;s final period</e>
<cmt>changed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto&apos;s final period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>弘治 (日本)元年（1555年）に軍師・雪斎、弘治3年（1557年）には朝比奈泰能といった名補佐役が次々と病死し、次第に今川家の全盛期に翳りが見え始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his prominent assistants successively died of illness, such as his strategist Sessai, who died in 1555, and Yasuyoshi ASAHINA, who died in 1557, the Imagawa family, which had been living at the highest of its prosperity, started to be weakening gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshimoto&apos;s prominent assistants successively died of illness, such as his strategist Sessai dying in 1555 and Yasuyoshi ASAHINA in 1557, the Imagawa family gradually began to weaken after living at the height of its prosperity.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshimoto&apos;s prominent assistants successively died of illness, such as his strategist Sessai dying in 1555 and Yasuyoshi ASAHINA in 1557, the Imagawa family gradually began to weaken after living at the height of its prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>永禄3年（1560年）、三河国に遷任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in 1560 he was transferred from Kyoto to Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>遷任→be transferred from Kyoto to～ としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto was transferred from Kyoto to Mikawa Province in 1560.</e>
<cmt>moved year to the end of the sentence; he &gt; Yoshimoto;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto was transferred from Kyoto to Mikawa Province in 1560.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>5月には2万5000の軍を率いて尾張国への侵攻を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1560 (表記の変更), he started the invasion into Owari Province leading 25,000 soldiers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1560 (表記の変更), he began an invasion into Owari Province leading 25,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>started the &gt; began an; added period;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1560, he began an invasion into Owari Province leading 25,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>(表記の変更）を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>織田方に身動きを封じられた同国知多郡大高城（名古屋市緑区 (名古屋市)大高）を救うべく、大高周辺の織田方諸砦を徳川家康などに落とさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to save the Taka-jo Castle in Chita Country of the same province (present Otaka, Midori Ward, Nagoya City), which was trapped by the presence of the Oda side, he ordered Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and other commanders to get control of forts of the Oda side located in the vicinity of Otaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to save the Taka-jo Castle in the Chita Country (present Otaka, Midori Ward, Nagoya City), which had been trapped by the presence of the Oda side, he ordered Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and other commanders to take control of the forts of the Oda side located in the vicinity of Otaka.</e>
<cmt>which was trapped &gt; which had been trapped; eliminated &quot;of the same province&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to save the Otaka-jo Castle in the Chita County (present Otaka, Midori Ward, Nagoya City), which had been trapped by the presence of the Oda side, he ordered Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and other commanders to take control of the forts of the Oda side located in the vicinity of Otaka.</e>
<cmt>Taka-jo Castle→Otaka-jo Castle,Country→County と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>幸先良く前哨戦に勝利した報せを受けて沓掛城で待機していた本隊を大高城に移動させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he received a notice that his army auspiciously wan the preliminary skirmish, he decided to move the main unit, which was stationed at Kutsukake-jo Castle until then, to the Otaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he received notice that his army auspiciously won the preliminary skirmish, he decided to move his main unit that had been stationed at Kutsukake-jo Castle to Otaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>wan &gt; won; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he received notice that his army auspiciously won the preliminary skirmish, he decided to move his main unit that had been stationed at Kutsukake-jo Castle to Otaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>ところがその途上、桶狭間（おけはざま）山で休息中に織田信長の攻撃を受け松井宗信らと共に奮戦するも、織田家家臣・毛利良勝に愛刀・宗三左文字の太刀ともども首級を奪われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when he and his troops took a rest in Mt. Okehazama on the way to the castle, they were attacked by Nobunaga ODA, and although Yoshimoto fought back hard with Soshin MATSUI, he was decapitated by a vassal of the Oda family, Yoshikatsu MORI, and he was deprived of his favorite long sward inscribed Souzasamonji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when he and his troops took a rest at Mt. Okehazama on the way to the castle, they were attacked by Nobunaga ODA, and even though Yoshimoto fought hard with Soshin MATSUI, he was decapitated by a vassal of the Oda family named Yoshikatsu MORI, and his favorite long sword inscribed Souzasamonji was taken.</e>
<cmt>in Mt. &gt; at Mt.; sward &gt; sword; added &quot;named&quot; before &quot;Yoshikatsu&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when he and his troops took a rest at Mt. Okehazama on the way to the castle, they were attacked by Nobunaga ODA, and even though Yoshimoto fought hard with Soshin MATSUI, he was decapitated by a vassal of the Oda family named Yoshikatsu MORI, and his favorite long sword inscribed Sozasamonji was taken.</e>
<cmt>”（通称「桶狭間の戦い」。”の部分が訳文では下のセルに入っていたため、下段のセルに組み入れました。Souzasaminji→Sozasamonji と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>（通称「桶狭間の戦い」、『信長公記（しんちょうこうき）』の記述による）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(commonly called &apos;the Battle of Okehazama,&apos; according to &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; [Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(this battle is commonly referred to as &apos;The Battle of Okehazama,&apos; according to &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; [Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA]).</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing before the parenthesis; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(This battle is commonly referred to as &apos;The Battle of Okehazama,&apos; according to &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; [Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA].)</e>
<cmt>原文、”（通称「桶狭間の戦い」。”の部分をこの段に組み入れました。this→This と修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>享年42。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 42 yeas old</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 42 yeas old</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 42 yeas old.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>その後、残存した今川兵によって駿府（静岡市）まで連れ帰ろうと試みられた首の無い義元の遺体は想像以上に腐敗の進行が早く、三河国宝飯郡に埋葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, surviving soldiers of the Imagawa side tried to bring back Yoshimoto&apos;s body to Sunpu (Shizuoka City), however, his headless corps suffered considerably rapid decomposition, and it was buried in Hoi Country, Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, surviving soldiers of the Imagawa side tried to bring Yoshimoto&apos;s body back to Sunpu (Shizuoka City), but his headless corpse suffered from considerably rapid decomposition and was buried in Hoi Country, Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>however, &gt; but; corps &gt; corpse; eliminated comma after &quot;decomposition&quot;; added &quot;from&quot; before &quot;considerably&quot;; moved &quot;back&quot; to after &quot;body&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, surviving soldiers of the Imagawa side tried to bring Yoshimoto&apos;s body back to Sunpu (Shizuoka City), but his headless corpse suffered from considerably rapid decomposition and was buried in Hoi County, Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>Country→County と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>戒名：天澤寺秀峯哲公。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Posthumous Buddhist name: Tentaku-ji Shuhotetsuko (秀峯哲公).</e>
<cmt>天澤寺秀峯哲公→正式な読み方が不明です：Tentaku-ji Shuhotetsuko (秀峯哲公)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name is Tentaku-ji Shuhotetsuko (秀峯哲公).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;His&quot;; eliminated colon; added &quot;is&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name is Tentaku-ji Shuhotetsuko (秀峯哲公).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="54">
<j>墓所：愛知県豊明市の桶狭間古戦場伝説地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard: legendary historic battlefield of Okehazama in present Toyoake City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard: the legendary historic battlefield of Okehazama in present Toyoake City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;legendary&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard: the legendary historic battlefield of Okehazama in present Toyoake City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>愛知県豊明市の高徳院 (豊明市)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotoku-in Temple in Toyoake City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotoku-in Temple in Toyoake City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotoku-in Temple in Toyoake City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>静岡県静岡市葵区の臨済寺 (静岡市)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinzai-ji Temple in Aoi Ward, Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinzai-ji Temple in Aoi Ward, Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinzai-ji Temple in Aoi Ward, Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>東京都杉並区の観泉寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansen-ji Temple in Suginami Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansen-ji Temple in Suginami Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansen-ji Temple in Suginami Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="58">
<j>塚：愛知県豊川市牛久保町の大聖寺 (豊川市)（胴塚）（一色時家の墓の隣）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tumulus: Daisho-ji Temple in Ushikubo-cho, Toyokawa City, Aichi Prefecture (Do-zuka [trunk tomb]) (next to the grave of Tokiie ISSHIKI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tumulus: Daisho-ji Temple in Ushikubo-cho, Toyokawa City, Aichi Prefecture (Do-zuka [trunk tomb]) (next to the grave of Tokiie ISSHIKI).</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing after &quot;Temple&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burial mound: Daisho-ji Temple in Ushikubo-cho, Toyokawa City, Aichi Prefecture (Do-zuka [trunk tomb]) (next to the grave of Tokiie ISSHIKI).</e>
<cmt>Tumulus→Burial mound と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>愛知県西尾市駒場町の東向寺（首塚）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toko-ji Temple in Komaba-cho, Nishio City, Aichi Prefecture (Kubi-zuka [severed head tomb]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toko-ji Temple in Komaba-cho, Nishio City, Aichi Prefecture (Kubi-zuka [severed head tomb]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toko-ji Temple in Komaba-cho, Nishio City, Aichi Prefecture (Kubi-zuka [severed head tomb]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>愛知県東海市の今川塚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imagawa-zuka (tomb) in Tokai City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imagawa-zuka (tomb) in Tokai City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imagawa-zuka (tomb) in Tokai City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>愛知県清須市正覚寺の今川塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imagawa-zuka (tomb) in Shogaku-ji Temple in Kiyosu City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imagawa-zuka (tomb) in Shogaku-ji Temple in Kiyosu City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imagawa-zuka (tomb) in Shogaku-ji Temple in Kiyosu City, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>死後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death (postmortem affaires)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death (postmortem affairs)</e>
<cmt>affaires &gt; affairs;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death (postmortem affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>織田方に討ち取られた首級は、鳴海城に留まり奮戦する義元の重臣・岡部元信と信長との開城交渉により後に返還され、駿河に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto&apos;s head severed by the Oda side was later returned to Suruga Province along with the negotiations of surrender of the castle held between Yoshimoto&apos;s chief retainer Motonobu OKABE, who continued fighting back bravely staying at Narumi-jo Castle, and Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto&apos;s severed head was later returned to the Suruga Province along with negotiations for surrender of the castle held by Yoshimoto&apos;s chief retainer Motonobu OKABE, who continued to fight bravely at Narumi-jo Castle against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>head severed by the Oda side &gt; severed head; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Suruga&quot;; of surrender &gt; for surrender; between &gt; by; eliminated comma after &quot;Castle&quot;; and Nobunaga &gt; against Nobunaga;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto&apos;s severed head was later returned to the Suruga Province along with negotiations for surrender of the castle held by Yoshimoto&apos;s chief retainer Motonobu OKABE, who continued to fight bravely at Narumi-jo Castle against Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>義元の戦死により家督は嫡男の今川氏真が継いだが、この隙に乗じた松平元康（後の徳川家康）が西三河で自立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshimoto&apos;s death in battle, his eldest legitimate son Ujizane IMAGAWA succeeded to the family reign, however, Motoyasu MATSUDAIRA (later Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) declared independent in Nishimikawa (western part of Mikawa Province), taking advantage of this unguarded moment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshimoto&apos;s death and his eldest legitimate son Ujizane IMAGAWA succeeded the family reign, Motoyasu MATSUDAIRA (later Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) declared independence in Nishimikawa (western part of Mikawa Province), taking advantage of the unguarded moment.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;in battle&quot;; eliminated &quot;to&quot; after &quot;succeeded&quot;; eliminated &quot;however&quot;; indenpedent &gt; independence; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshimoto&apos;s death and his legitimate son Ujizane IMAGAWA succeeded the family reign, Motoyasu MATSUDAIRA (later Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) declared independence in Nishimikawa (western part of Mikawa Province), taking advantage of the unguarded moment.</e>
<cmt>eldest を削除しました。（嫡男としかないため）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>この動きに追従するように東三河でも戸田氏や西郷氏などが離反、松平氏の傘下へ転属していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Higashimikawa (eastern part of Mikawa Province) the Toda clan, the Saigo clan and others seceded from the Imagawa clan, as if they had been following Motoyasu&apos;s move, and they became affiliated with the Matsudaira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Higashimikawa (eastern part of Mikawa Province), the Toda clan, the Saigo clan and others seceded from the Imagawa clan as well following Motoyasu&apos;s move, and became affiliated with the Matsudaira clan.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Higashimikawa (eastern part of Mikawa Province), the Toda clan, the Saigo clan and others seceded from the Imagawa clan as well following Motoyasu&apos;s move, and became affiliated with the Matsudaira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>このような三河の動揺が隣国・遠江へも伝播すると、正・誤の判別がつかない情報が飛び交う遠江領内は敵味方の見極めさえ困難な疑心暗鬼の状態に陥ってしまう（遠州錯乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once such an unrest in Mikawa Province was transmitted to the neighboring province, Totomi Province, the whole territory of Totomi was wrapped up in suspicion, the people became panic wandering who would be friend or foe amid the chaos full of speculations, which were whether they were true or false (Enshu [Totomi Province] Confusion)..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the unrest in Mikawa Province was transmitted to the neighboring Totomi Province, the whole territory became wrapped in suspicion with people in panic wondering who would be friend or foe amid the chaos and whether the news was true or false (Enshu [Totomi Province] Confusion).</e>
<cmt>eliminated second period; fixed grammar to read more understandably;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the unrest in Mikawa Province was transmitted to the neighboring Totomi Province, the whole territory became wrapped in suspicion with people in panic wondering who would be friend or foe amid the chaos and whether the news was true or false (Enshu [Totomi Province] Confusion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>氏真は人心を掌握する才能に乏しく井伊直親や飯尾連竜などの粛清で事態の収拾を期したが、かえって人心の離反を加速させてしまい今川氏は見る見るうちに衰退し始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujizane, whose ability to control the people&apos;s mind was very limited, expected that the state of affaires would be cool down by purging Naochika II and Tsuratatsu (連竜) IIO, however, on the contrary, their purge accelerated the estrangement of the people&apos;s mind and the Imagawa clan began going into a decline drastically.</e>
<cmt>飯尾連竜→Tsuratatsu (連竜) IIO （「つらたつ」と読まれているようですが、正式には読み方が確立されていないようです。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ujizane, who had very limited ablility to control the minds of the people, thought he could cool down the situation by purging Naochika II and Tsuratatsu (連竜) IIO, their purge had the opposite effect and accelerated the estrangement of the people and the Imagawa clan began a drastic decline.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ujizane, who had very limited ability to control the minds of the people, thought he could cool down the situation by purging Naochika II and Tsuratatsu (連竜) IIO, their purge had the opposite effect and accelerated the estrangement of the people and the Imagawa clan began a drastic decline.</e>
<cmt>ablility→ability と修正しました。「飯尾連竜」は「いいおつらたつ」の読みをウェブ上等で認めましたが、英文表記では&quot;Iio Tsuratatsu&quot;が主であり、御判断を仰ぎたくそのままにしてあります。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>義元の死から8年後、信玄によって駿河を追われ、ここに戦国大名としての今川家は滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eight years after Yoshimoto&apos;s death, the family was expelled from Suruga Province, and thus the Imagawa family as a Sengoku daimyo had disappeared</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eight years after Yoshimoto&apos;s death, the family was expelled from the Suruga Province and the Imagawa family as Sengoku daimyo disappeared.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Suruga&quot;; eliminated &quot;a&quot; before &quot;Sengoku&quot;; eliminated &quot;had&quot; before &quot;disappeared&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eight years after Yoshimoto&apos;s death, the family was expelled from the Suruga Province by Shingen, and the Imagawa family as Sengoku daimyo disappeared.</e>
<cmt>「信玄によって」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>駿河追放後、氏真は京都で隠棲していたが、嫡子・今川範以が病没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the banishment from Suruga, Ujizane was living a retired life in Kyoto but his legitimate son Norimochi IMAGAWA died of illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the banishment from Suruga, Ujizane lived a retired life in Kyoto but his legitimate son Norimochi IMAGAWA died of illness.</e>
<cmt>was living a retired life &gt; lived a retired life;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the banishment from Suruga, Ujizane lived a retired life in Kyoto but his legitimate son Norimochi IMAGAWA died of illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その後、徳川家康に召し出されて江戸幕府に出仕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Ujizane was invited by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to serve the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujizane was then invited by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to serve in the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Afterwards &gt; then;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujizane was then invited by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to serve in the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>温情により500石を与えられ、これ以降、今川氏は幕府高家として幕臣に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given 500-koku (139 cubic meters) crop yield as a stipend of mercy, and since then the Imagawa clan became one of the Shogun&apos;s retainers as bakufu koke (honorable family of bakufu).</e>
<cmt>幕府高家→定訳不明：bakufu koke (honorable family of bakufu) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was given a 500-koku (139 cubic meters) crop yield as a stipend of mercy, the Imagawa clan became one of the Shogun&apos;s retainers as bakufu koke (honorable family of bakufu).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;500&quot;; eliminated &quot;since then&quot; and added &quot;after&quot; to the beginning of the sentence; eliminated &quot;and&quot; before &quot;the Imagawa clan&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was given a 500 koku (139 cubic meters) crop yield as a stipend of mercy, the Imagawa clan became one of the Shogun&apos;s retainers as bakufu koke (honorable family of bakufu).</e>
<cmt>500-koku→500 koku と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="71">
<j>勢力圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Area of Influence</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Area of Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>桶狭間合戦当時の最盛期の今川義元の領国は、駿河国、遠江国、三河国の3カ国の69万石（太閤検地）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The territory of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA at the highest of his prosperity during the Battle of Okehazama extended over three provinces, Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa with a total production of 690,000-koku (according to Taiko kenchi [Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the height of his prosperity during the Battle of Okehazama, Yoshimoto&apos;s territory extended over Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa provinces with a total production of 690,000-koku (according to the Taiko Kenchi [Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey]).</e>
<cmt>at the highest &gt; at the height; Yoshimoto IMAGAWA &gt; Yoshimoto; rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the height of his prosperity during the Battle of Okehazama, Yoshimoto&apos;s territory extended over Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa provinces with a total production of 690,000 koku (according to the Taiko Kenchi [Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s nationwide land survey]).</e>
<cmt>690,000-koku→690,000 koku,Toyotomi→TOYOTOMI と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>なお、尾張国は領国化されておらず、尾張国内に、反織田方として、山口氏、服部氏などが、今川に呼応する動きを見せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in Owari Province, which was not registered as his territory though, the anti-Oda feudal lords, such as the Yamaguchi clan and the Hattori clan, were showing movement to act in concert with the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Owari Province on the other hand, which was not registered as his territory, anti-Oda feudal lords such as the Yamaguchi clan and the Hattori clan were showing movement to act in concert with the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>on the other hand &lt;&gt; in Owari province; eliminated &quot;though&quot;; eliminated comma after &quot;territory&quot;, &quot;lords&quot; and &quot;Hattori clan&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Owari Province on the other hand, which was not registered as his territory, anti-Oda feudal lords such as the Yamaguchi clan and the Hattori clan were showing movement to act in concert with the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>大日本帝国参謀本部作成の日本戦史、桶狭間役の分析では、石高の低い駿河、遠江、三河が水増しされ、さらに尾張が領国に組み入れられ、100万石と推定され、1万石につき250人の兵役で、総兵力2万5千とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the analysis of the Okehazama Incident in the Japanese history of warfare, which was made by the Staff Headquarters of the Empire of Japan, it was estimated that Yoshimoto&apos;s territory produced a total of 1,000,000-koku crop yield and his army had 25,000 soldiers based on calculation that the military service available per 10,000-koku was 250, however, these were the figures gained by padding each crop yield of Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa Provinces, although which in reality were less productive, and in addition, by counting Owari Province as a part of his territory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an analysis of the Okehazama Incident in the Japanese history of warfare made by the Staff Headquarters of the Empire of Japan, based on the calculation that for every 10,000-koku the military service of 250 soldiers could be supported, it was estimated that Yoshimoto&apos;s territory produced a total crop yield of 1,000,000-koku and there were 25,000 soldiers in his army, but these were figures gained by padding each crop yield of the Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa provinces, which in reality were less productive, in addition to counting Owari Province as part of his territory.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;which was&quot; after &quot;warfare&quot;; eliminated comma after &quot;warfare&quot;; moved &quot;crop yield&quot; to before &quot;1,000,000&quot;; available &gt; supportable; however &gt; but; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an analysis of the Okehazama Incident in the Japanese history of warfare made by the Staff Headquarters of the Empire of Japan, based on the calculation that for every 10,000 koku the military service of 250 soldiers could be supported, it was estimated that Yoshimoto&apos;s territory produced a total crop yield of 1,000,000 koku and there were 25,000 soldiers in his army, but these were figures gained by padding each crop yield of the Suruga, Totomi and Mikawa provinces, which in reality were less productive, in addition to counting Owari Province as part of his territory.</e>
<cmt>10,000-koku→10,000 koku,1,000,000-koku→1,000,000 koku と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>が、信長公記では4万5千となっており、正確な実数は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, according to Shincho Koki (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA), Yoshimoto&apos;s territory produced only 45,000-koku crop yield, and therefore, the actual number is unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Shincho Koki (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA) on the other hand, Yoshimoto&apos;s territory produced only a 45,000-koku crop yield, therefore the real figures are unknown.</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;on the other hand&quot; to later in the sentence; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;45,000&quot;; the actual number is unknown &gt; the real figures are unknown;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Shincho Koki (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA) on the other hand, Yoshimoto&apos;s territory produced only a 45,000 koku crop yield, therefore the real figures are unknown.</e>
<cmt>45,000-koku→45,000 koku と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public estimation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public Assessment</e>
<cmt>estimation &gt; Assessment;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public Assessment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>一般の認知度では、桶狭間の戦いで織田信長に討たれた敗将として有名であり、合わせて一般に知られている輿に乗っていた、公家文化にかぶれていたなどの人物像から戦国大名としては暗愚と見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is generally well known as a losing warring lord defeated by Nobunaga ODA in the Battle of Okehazama, and he is consider to have been imbecile as a Sengoku daimyo, judging from the anecdotes about his personality that he preferred to be carried on a palanquin and he was influenced by the court noble culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, Yoshimoto is well known as a general defeated by Nobunaga ODA in the Battle of Okehazama, and he is considered to have been an imbecile as a Sengoku daimyo, judging from anecdotes about his personality, who preferred to be carried on a palanquin and was influenced by court noble culture.</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Yoshimoto; changed &quot;generally&quot; to &quot;In general&quot; and used at the beginning of the sentence; eliminated &quot;losing warring lord&quot;; added &quot;who was&quot; before &quot;defeated&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, Yoshimoto is well known as a general defeated by Nobunaga ODA in the Battle of Okehazama, and he is considered to have been an imbecile as a Sengoku daimyo, judging from anecdotes about his personality, who preferred to be carried on a palanquin and was influenced by court noble culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>特に桶狭間の戦いに関しては、通説では圧倒的に有利な情勢から信長を軽んじ、明らかに地の利が無い田楽狭間で安穏と休憩を取ったことが致命的となったなどが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the popular theory points that his fatal error was that depending on his predominant situation, he downplayed Nobunaga in the Battle of Okehazama and he took a break and got rest at Dengakuhazama, where he did not have any commanding advantage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular theory points especially towards the fatal error he made in depending on his predominant situation, where he downplayed Nobunaga in the Battle of Okehazama and took a break to rest at Dengakuhazama where he had no commanding advantage.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular theory points especially towards the fatal error he made in depending on his predominant situation, where he downplayed Nobunaga in the Battle of Okehazama and took a break to rest at Dengakuhazama where he had no commanding advantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>また、輿に乗り移動していたと言う史実から、騎乗することができなかったと見られるようになり、さらにその理由は幼少時に落馬した恐怖、太っていたため、寸胴短足だったなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, based on the fact that he used a palanquin as a transportation, it came to be said that he was not able to go on horseback, and furthermore, to explain the reason, many vulgar beliefs were invented in the later times, for example, that he was afraid of riding since he fell off a horse when he was a child, he was fat, or he was waistless and short-legged.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on his dependency of using a palanquin for transportation, it came to be said that he was unable to ride on horseback, and many vulgar beliefs were invented in later years to explain why, such as him having a fear of riding since he fell off a horse when he was a child, that he was fat, or he was waistless and short-legged.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on his dependency of using a palanquin for transportation, it came to be said that he was unable to ride on horseback, and many vulgar beliefs were invented in later years to explain why, such as him having a fear of riding since he fell off a horse when he was a child, that he was fat, or he was waistless and short-legged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>後世に様々な俗説が創作されたことも評価を低くする結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And all these popular beliefs contributed to establishing a low public estimation of him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of these popular beliefs contributed to the establishment of his low public assessment.</e>
<cmt>estimation &gt; assessment; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of these popular beliefs contributed to the establishment of his low public assessment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>実際には、戦国大名の中でも政治・軍事に卓越した手腕を見せた人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, he was an outstanding personality in warfare and political tactics among the Japanese territorial lords in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, he was an outstanding personality in warfare and political tactics among the Japanese territorial lords during the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>in &gt; during;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, he was an outstanding personality in warfare and political tactics among the Japanese territorial lords during the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>特に内政面において辣腕を振るい、天文22年（1552年）には「今川仮名目録」の追加法を制定し、さらに商業保護や流通統制、寄親寄子制度による家臣団の結束強化を図るなど優れた行政改革を進めた（後にこの政策は江戸幕府を開府した徳川家康によって踏襲されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the domestic policies he displayed his uncommon ability, starting with the enactment of the added articles (Kana Mokuroku Tsuika) to expand on Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house rules to control the territory) in 1552, he carried out excellent administrative reforms, such as commercial protection and distribution control within his territory and consolidation of vassals by introducing the system of Yorioya-Yoriko (later, when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established the feudal government, he applied these policies to the system of Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。今川仮名目録→定訳不明：Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house rules to control the territory) としました。寄親寄子制→system of Yorioya-Yoriko としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In domestic policies especially, Yoshimoto displayed his uncommon abilities, starting with the enactment of the articles (Kana Mokuroku Tsuika) to expand on the Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house rules to control the territory) in 1552, carrying out excellent administrative reforms such as commercial protection and distribution control within his territory, and consolidation of vassals by introducing the system of Yorioya-Yoriko (later, when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established the feudal government, he applied these policies to the system of the Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt>moved location of &quot;especially&quot; to after &quot;policies&quot;; he &gt; Yoshimoto; ability &gt; abilities; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In domestic policies especially, Yoshimoto displayed his uncommon abilities, starting with the enactment of the articles (Kana Mokuroku Tsuika) to expand on the &apos;Imagawa Kana Mokuroku&apos; (the Imagawa clan&apos;s basic house rules to control the territory) in 1552, carrying out excellent administrative reforms such as commercial protection and distribution control within his territory, and consolidation of vassals by introducing the system of Yorioya-Yoriko (Later, when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established the feudal government, he applied these policies to the system of the Edo bakufu.)</e>
<cmt>クォーツを補いました。最期のカッコ部分、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>朝倉宗滴は、『朝倉宗滴話記』のなかで「国持、人つかひの上手。よき手本と申すべく人」として武田信玄・織田信長・三好長慶・長尾氏・毛利氏らと同列に評価している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Asakura Soteki Waki&quot; (a collection of Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s comments), Soteki ASAKURA made a valuation of Yoshimune as &apos;he is good at governing a country and using persons, and he deserves to be referred to as a good example,&apos; and compared him to such eminent figures as Shingen TAKEDA, Nobunaga ODA, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, and the lords of the Nagao clan, the Mori clan and others.</e>
<cmt>下列にあった、『よき手本と申すべく人」として武田信玄・織田信長・三好長慶・長尾氏・毛利氏らと同列に評価している』を本列に入れました。『朝倉宗滴話記』→定訳不明： &quot;Asakura Soteki Waki&quot; (a collection of Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s comments) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Asakura Soteki Waki&quot; (a collection of Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s comments), Soteki ASAKURA evaluated Yoshimoto as &apos;good at governing a country and using persons and deserving to be referred to as a good example,&apos; and compared him to such eminent figures as Shingen TAKEDA, Nobunaga ODA, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, the lords of the Nagao clan, the Mori clan and others.</e>
<cmt>Yoshimune &gt; Yoshimoto; eliminated &quot;he is&quot; before &quot;good at governing&quot;; valuation &gt; evaluated; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Asakura Soteki Waki&quot; (a collection of Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s comments), Soteki ASAKURA evaluated Yoshimoto as &apos;good at governing a county and using persons and deserving to be referred to as a good example,&apos; and compared him to such eminent figures as Shingen TAKEDA, Nobunaga ODA, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, the lords of the Nagao clan, the Mori clan and others.</e>
<cmt>country→county と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>（『続々群書類従』)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Zokuzoku Gunsho Ruiju&quot; (the second sequel of Gunsho Ruiju the anthology of classified old documents]).</e>
<cmt>本列にあった、『よき手本と申すべく人」として武田信玄・織田信長・三好長慶・長尾氏・毛利氏らと同列に評価している』を上列に入れました。『続々群書類従』→定訳不明：&quot;Zokuzoku Gunsho Ruiju&quot; (the second sequel of Gunsho Ruiju the anthology of classified old documents] としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Zokuzoku Gunsho Ruiju&quot; (The Second Sequel of Gunsho Ruiju: The Anthology of Classified Old Documents]).</e>
<cmt>added colon after &quot;Ruiju&quot;; capitalized words in the title;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Zokuzoku Gunsho Ruiju&quot; [The Second Sequel of Gunsho Ruiju: The Anthology of Classified Old Documents])</e>
<cmt>カッコ内のカッコ部分を守勢しました。ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>（また異本の金吾利口書および宗滴夜話には、今川殿となっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In its alternative versions, &quot;Kingo Rikosho&quot; (&quot;Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s hints for military commanders) and &quot;Soteki Yawa&quot; (Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s posthumous advises), Yoshimoto is mentioned as Imagawa-dono (Lord Imagawa).</e>
<cmt>文頭の『また、』の前に　（　を加えました。金吾利口書→定訳不明：&quot;Kingo Rikosho&quot; (a collection of Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s hints for military commanders) としました。 宗滴夜話→定訳不明：&quot;Soteki Yawa&quot; (a collection of Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s posthumous advises) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In its alternative versions, &quot;Kingo Rikosho&quot; (&quot;Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s hints for military commanders) and &quot;Soteki Yawa&quot; (Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s posthumous advice), Yoshimoto is mentioned as Imagawa-dono (Lord Imagawa).</e>
<cmt>advises &gt; advice;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In its alternative versions, Kingo Rikosho [Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s hints for military commanders] and Soteki Yawa [Soteki ASAKURA&apos;s posthumous advice], Yoshimoto is mentioned as Imagawa-dono [Lord Imagawa].)</e>
<cmt>カッコ内のカッコ、括りなどを修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。クォーツを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>騎乗せず、輿に乗っていたことも、義元は足利将軍家との親密な関係（今川家は足利将軍家の分家）から特別に輿に乗る事を認められており、むしろ合戦の際も輿に乗る事はそのアピールと言う面があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be also said that using a palanquin instead of riding on horseback was a kind of demonstration that he was exceptionally permitted to use a palanquin thanks to a close relationship with the Ashikaga Shogun family (the Imagawa family was a branch of the Ashikaga Shogun family) and therefore he moved on palanquin in battle to make an appeal of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also possible that he used a palanquin instead of riding on horseback in order to demonstrate that he was given exception by the Ashikaga Shogun family and permitted to use a palanquin due to their close relationship (the Imagawa family was a branch of the Ashikaga Shogun family), meaning that he road on palanquin in battle in order to make an appeal of it.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also possible that he used a palanquin instead of riding on horseback in order to demonstrate that he was given exception by the Ashikaga Shogun family and permitted to use a palanquin due to their close relationship (the Imagawa family was a branch of the Ashikaga Shogun family), meaning that he rode a palanquin in battle in order to make an appeal of it.</e>
<cmt>road on→rode a と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>また『信長公記』には桶狭間山から退却する義元が馬に乗っていたと記されており、騎乗ができなかったこと、さらにその理由などは、ほぼ後世の創作と考えられる（一般にこれら記述が登場するのは江戸時代中期の物である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA) there is a description that he withdrew on horseback from Mt. Okehazama, and it can be considered that the common theory that he was not able to ride on horseback and its reasons were all invented later (generally these descriptions began appearing in the middle of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Shincho Koki,&quot; (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA) since it is described how he withdrew on horseback from Mt. Okehazama, it is possible to consider the common theory of his inability to ride on horseback, as well as its reasons, as all being invented at a later time (generally these descriptions began appearing in the middle of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Shincho Koki&quot;; added comma after &quot;Koki&quot;; there is a description &gt; it is described; there &gt; since; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA), since it is described how he withdrew on horseback from Mt. Okehazama, it is possible to consider the common theory of his inability to ride on horseback, as well as its reasons, as all being invented at a later time (Generally these descriptions began appearing in the middle of the Edo period.)</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。最後のカッコ内、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>また、公家文化に関しても、それに精通していることは、素養の高さを示すものであり、必ずしも悪いものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, his knowledge of the court noble culture itself demonstrates the level of culture he had and it is not necessarily a negative point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, his knowledge of the court noble culture itself demonstrates the level of culture he had, and is not necessarily a negative point.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;he had&quot;; eliminated &quot;it&quot; after &quot;and&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, his knowledge of the court noble culture itself demonstrates the level of culture he had, and is not necessarily a negative point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>このように一般の評価と違い戦国大名として高い評価を受けていた面もあるが、近年では積極的な領土拡大を理由とした度重なる軍事行動が、家臣や領民の疲弊を招き、死後の今川氏が急速に衰退した原因の一つであるとも指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, unlike the public estimation, the estimation he received as a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) was relatively high, however, recent studies regard that the frequent military actions driven by Yoshimoto&apos;s aggressive territory expansion produced the fatigue of vassals and the people of the domain and point out that this was one of the causes that lead such a rapid decline of the Imagawa clan after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike his public assessment, he was relatively highly evaluated as a Sengoku daimyo, but recent studies regard Yoshimoto&apos;s frequent military actions driven by aggressive territory expansion as the cause of fatigue in his vassals and the people of the domain, and it is has been determined that this was one of the causes leading to such a rapid decline of the Imagawa clan after his death.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Thus&quot; to reduce the feel of a run-on sentence; fixed grammar; eliminated description of &quot;Sengoku daimyo&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike his public assessment, he was relatively highly evaluated as a Sengoku daimyo, but recent studies regard Yoshimoto&apos;s frequent military actions driven by aggressive territory expansion as the cause of fatigue in his vassals and the people of the domain, and it is has been determined that this was one of the causes leading to such a rapid decline of the Imagawa clan after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>幼いころから仏門に入っていた為、武芸を鍛えられず、個人の武勇には優れなかったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that as he entered the Buddhist priesthood very young, he did not receive training in military art, and personally he lacked military prowess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that as Yoshimoto entered the Buddhist priesthood very young, he did not receive training in military art and personally lacked military prowess.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Yoshimoto; eliminated comma after &quot;art&quot;; eliminataed &quot;he&quot; before &quot;lacked&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that as Yoshimoto entered the Buddhist priesthood very young, he did not receive training in military art and personally lacked military prowess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>しかし桶狭間の戦いでは信長の家臣・服部一忠が真っ先に斬りつけようとした時、自ら抜刀して春安の膝を斬りつけて撃退、更に毛利良勝が斬りつけようとした時にも数合ほどやり合った末に首を掻こうとした毛利の指を食い千切って絶命したと伝えられており、必ずしも個人的武勇が無かった訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that in the Battle of Okehazama, when Nobunaga&apos;s vassal Kazutada HATTORI firstly tried to slash at Yoshimoto, Yoshimoto fought back by drawing the sward and cut Hattori on the knee, and when Yoshikatsu MORI tried to slash at Yoshimoto, they had several contacts of strike, and finally when Mori was about to decapitate him, he bit off Mori&apos;s finger before he died, and it is not certain that he completely lacked personal military prowess</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at the Battle of Okehazama when Nobunaga&apos;s vassal Kazutada HATTORI first tried to slash at Yoshimoto, Yoshimoto fought back by drawing his sword and cutting Hattori on the knee, then Yoshikatsu MORI tried to slash at Yoshimoto and they crossed swords several times, and when Mori was finally about to decapitate him, Yoshimoto bit off Mori&apos;s finger before dying, so it cannot be said that he completely lacked personal military prowess.</e>
<cmt>sward &gt; sword; fixed grammar to read more naturally; added period;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at the Battle of Okehazama when Nobunaga&apos;s vassal Kazutada HATTORI first tried to slash at Yoshimoto, Yoshimoto fought back by drawing his sword and cutting Hattori on the knee, then Yoshikatsu MORI tried to slash at Yoshimoto and they crossed swords several times, and when Mori was finally about to decapitate him, Yoshimoto bit off Mori&apos;s finger before dying, so it cannot be said that he completely lacked personal military prowess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>公家文化に精通し、都を逃れた公家達を保護、さらには自らも公家のようにお歯黒をつけ、置眉、薄化粧をしていた事から、貴族趣味に溺れた人物とされる事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is sometimes considered to have been a person who lost himself in aristocratic taste based on the facts that he was familiar with the court culture and protected court nobles exiling from the capital, and in addition, that he had a dyed-black teeth like a court noble and wore light makeup with okimayu (painted-eyebrows on his brow).</e>
<cmt>置眉→定訳不明：okimayu (painted-eyebrows on his brow) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the argument that Yoshimoto lost himself in his aristocratic tastes based on his familiarity with court culture and his protection from exile from the capital by court nobles, his teeth were dyed black like a court noble and he wore light makeup with okimayu (painted eyebrows on his brow).</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Yoshimoto; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the argument that Yoshimoto lost himself in his aristocratic tastes based on his familiarity with court culture and his protection from exile from the capital by court nobles, his teeth were dyed black like a court noble and he wore light makeup with okimayu (painted eyebrows on his brow).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>しかし公家のような化粧をした話は後世の作であるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to one theory, the story that he was warring makeup like a court noble was a fiction created afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is another theory that the story of him wearing the makeup of a court noble was a fiction created later on.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is another theory that the story of him wearing the makeup of a court noble was a fiction created later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>また、たとえ事実であったとしてもそれは家格の高さを示す事こそあれ、軟弱さの象徴とは言い難い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if it is true, it indicates nothing more than his high social standing, and it can not be seen as a symbol of his weakness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if it is true, it indicates nothing more than his high social standing and cannot be seen as a symbol of his weakness.</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma after &quot;standing&quot;; eliminated &quot;it&quot; after &quot;and&quot;; can not &gt; cannot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if it is true, it indicates nothing more than his high social standing and cannot be seen as a symbol of his weakness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>武士が戦場に向かう際に化粧をしていくことは、珍しくないばかりかたしなみの一つであったと言う説すらある（笹間良彦『時代考証　日本合戦図図典』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even there exist a theory that warring makeup was not a queer habit but an established code that a samurai should follow when he was going to battlefield (Yoshihiko SASAMA &quot;Jidaikosho Nihon Kassen-zu Zuten&quot; (Historical scrutiny: Illustrated dictionary of Japanese battle).</e>
<cmt>『時代考証　日本合戦図図典』→定訳不明：&quot;Jidaikosho Nihon Kassen-zu Zuten&quot; (Historical scrutiny: Illustrated dictionary of Japanese battle) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In yet another theory, it is argued that wearing makeup was not a queer habit but an established code that samurai should follow when going in to the battlefield (Yoshihiko SASAMA &quot;Jidaikosho Nihon Kassen-zu Zuten&quot; (Historical scrutiny: Illustrated dictionary of Japanese battle).</e>
<cmt>Even there exist a theory &gt; In yet another theory, it is argued&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In yet another theory, it is argued that wearing makeup was not a queer habit but an established code that samurai should follow when going in to the battlefield (Yoshihiko SASAMA &quot;Jidaikosho Nihon Kassen-zu Zuten&quot; (Historical scrutiny: Illustrated dictionary of Japanese battle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>『信長公記』では義元の桶狭間の戦いの際の出で立ちを「胸白の鎧に金にて八龍を打ちたる五枚兜を被り、赤地の錦の陣羽織を着し、今川家重代の二尺八寸松倉郷の太刀に、壱尺八寸の大左文字の脇差を帯し、青の馬の五寸計（馬高五尺五寸の青毛の馬）なるの金覆輪の鞍置き、紅の鞦かけて乗られける……。」と伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shincho Koki (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA), Yoshitomo&apos;s costume to go to the Battle of Okehazama is described as follows: &apos;Yoshimoto, who was dressed in armor with a white cuirass and a five-pieces combat helmet decorated with a gold embossed pattern of a legendary dragon Hachiryu, and a red brocaded Jinbaori (sleeveless campaign jacket worn over armor), took a long sword of some 85cm with the inscription of Matsukurago (sword made by GO no Yoshihiro), the family treasure handed down for generations in the Imagawa family, and a short sword of some 55cm with the inscription of Dai-samonji (sword made by Samonji SOZA), and sat straddled upon a jet-black horse of some 166.65cm high with a gold-rimmed saddle, which was fixed by a scarlet breeching...&apos;</e>
<cmt>下列にあった　『」と伝えている。』　を本列に加えました。尺→about 30.3cm で計算しました。寸→about 3.03cmで計算しました。二尺八寸→some 85cm (2.8×30.3cmで計算しました。) 松倉郷 →定訳不明：with the inscription of Matsukurago (sword made by GO no Yoshihiro) としました。壱尺八寸→ some 55cm (1.8×30.3cmで計算しました。)大左文字→定訳不明：with the inscription of Dai-samonji (sword made by Samonji SOZA) としました。青の馬の五寸計（馬高五尺五寸の青毛の馬）→ 定訳不明：jet-black horse of some 166.65cm high (5.5×30.3cmで計算しました。) としました。金覆輪の鞍→定訳不明：gold-rimmed saddle としました。鞦→定訳不明：breeching としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shincho Koki (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA), Yoshitomo&apos;s costume during the Battle of Okehazama is described as follows: &apos;Yoshimoto was dressed in armor with a white cuirass and a five-piece combat helmet decorated with a gold embossed pattern of the legendary dragon Hachiryu; he wore a red brocaded Jinbaori (sleeveless campaign jacket worn over armor), wielded a long sword approximately 85cm long with the inscription of Matsukurago (a sword made by GO no Yoshihiro), a family treasure handed down for generations in the Imagawa family, and a short sword with approximately 55cm in length with the inscription of Dai-samonji (a sword made by Samonji SOZA); he sat straddled upon a jet-black horse of about 166.65cm tall with a gold-rimmed saddle, fixed by a scarlet breeching...&apos;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Shincho&quot;; costume to go to &gt; costume during; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (Biography of the Warlord Nobunaga ODA), Yoshimoto&apos;s costume during the Battle of Okehazama is described as follows: &apos;Yoshimoto was dressed in armor with a white cuirass and a five-piece combat helmet decorated with a gold embossed pattern of the legendary dragon Hachiryu; he wore a red brocaded Jinbaori (sleeveless campaign jacket worn over armor), wielded a long sword approximately 85cm long with the inscription of Matsukurago (a sword made by GO no Yoshihiro), a family treasure handed down for generations in the Imagawa family, and a short sword with approximately 55cm in length with the inscription of Dai-samonji (a sword made by Samonji SOZA); he sat straddled upon a jet-black horse of about 166.65cm tall with a gold-rimmed saddle, fixed by a scarlet breeching...&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の下段にあった”」と伝えている。”を組み入れ、元のセルを削除しました。（訳の段階ではコメント欄にその旨が残されていましたが未処理であったため）クォーツを補いました。Yoshitomo→Yoshimoto と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="96">
<j>通説では松平広忠にとって唯一の嫡男である竹千代（徳川家康）を人質に取ったことは、今川家による松平家に対する過酷な処遇と解釈されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the popular theory, his act of taking Hirotada MATSUDAIRA&apos;s only legitimate son Takechiyo (Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) as a hostage has been considered as a the Imagawa family&apos;s cruel treatment to Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to popular theory, Yoshimoto&apos;s act of taking Hirotada MATSUDAIRA&apos;s only legitimate son Takechiyo (Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) as a hostage is considered as cruel treatment to the Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to popular theory, Yoshimoto&apos;s act of taking Hirotada MATSUDAIRA&apos;s only legitimate son Takechiyo (Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) as a hostage has been considered as cruel treatment to the Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>is→has been と修正しました。（「・・・されてきた」ということから）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>しかし、近年の研究では、今川義元側の見地として、西三河最大の今川の与党である岡崎松平家を重視しての（好意的な）政策だったという説も唱えられるようになってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as a result of the recent studies, some theories present a point of view from the Yoshimoto IMAGAWA&apos;s side and argue that it had been a (favorable) policy of the Imagawa family which was attaching great importance to the Okazaki Matsudaira family because it was the largest family on the Imagawa side in Nishimikawa (western part of Mikawa Province).</e>
<cmt>今川の与党→on the Imagawa side としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of recent studies, however, a number of theories arguing from Yoshimoto IMAGAWA&apos;s side claim that it was a (favorable) policy of the Imagawa family to attach great importance to the Okazaki Matsudaira family since it was the largest family on the Imagawa side in Nishimikawa (the western part of Mikawa Province).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar tor read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of recent studies, however, a number of theories arguing from Yoshimoto IMAGAWA&apos;s side claim that it was a (favorable) policy of the Imagawa family to attach great importance to the Okazaki Matsudaira family since it was the largest family on the Imagawa side in Nishimikawa (the western part of Mikawa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>例えば、幼少期の家康を駿河国に留め置いたのは今川家の準一門扱いとして厚遇であり、人質というよりも「政務見習い」として預けられたという物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, there is a theory that the Imagawa family placed little Ieyasu under its custody in Suruga Province and treated him as a member of junichimon (associate family), and Ieyasu was left to Yoshimoto&apos;s care as &apos;an apprentice of the government affaires,&apos; rather than as a hostage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, there is a theory that the Imagawa family placed little Ieyasu under their custody in Suruga Province, treating him as a member of their junichimon (associate family), and Ieyasu was left to Yoshimoto&apos;s care as &apos;an apprentice of the government affaires,&apos; rather than as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>its custody &gt; their custody; treated &gt; treating; added &quot;their&quot; before &quot;junichimon&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, there is a theory that the Imagawa family placed little Ieyasu under their custody in Suruga Province, treating him as a member of their junichimon (associate family), and Ieyasu was left to Yoshimoto&apos;s care as &apos;an apprentice of the government affairs,&apos; rather than as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>affaires→affairs と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>実際に太原雪斎 の英才教育を受けさせたとの説もある（これに反する異論もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, there is also a theory that Yoshimoto gave him a special education for talented students conducted by Sessai TAIGEN (there are objections to this theory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also another theory that Yoshimoto gave Takechiyo a special education for talented students conducted by Sessai TAIGEN (there are objections to this theory as well).</e>
<cmt>In reality &gt; another; added &quot;as well&quot; after &quot;theory&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also another theory that Yoshimoto gave Takechiyo a special education for talented students conducted by Sessai TAIGEN (there are objections to this theory as well).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>姪である築山殿を嫁がせたことも、家康を今川家に縛り付けたという解釈もできるが、順当に考えれば今川家と縁戚関係を結ぶ事であり厚遇と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The marriage that Yoshimoto forced his niece Tsukiyama-dono to contract with Ieyasu can be interpreted as a measure to tie Ieyasu to the Imagawa family, but it can be also straightforwardly understood as a special favor that Ieyasu was given to become a relative of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The marriage Yoshimoto forced on his niece Tsukiyama with Ieyasu can be interpreted as a measure to tie Ieyasu to the Imagawa family, but it can be also understood as an honest special favor to turn Ieyasu into a relative of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>straightforwardly &gt; honest; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The marriage Yoshimoto forced on his niece Tsukiyama with Ieyasu can be interpreted as a measure to tie Ieyasu to the Imagawa family, but it can be also understood as an honest special favor to turn Ieyasu into a relative of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>しかし、松平氏の家臣にとっては嫡男（特に広忠の死後は主君）を人質に取られていると言う事実に変わりは無く、立場上弱い面からの圧力などがあったようである（墓参りのために岡崎城に一時帰参した家康に対し、鳥居忠吉が今川の横暴を訴えている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is true for the vassals of the Matsudaira clan that the eldest legitimate son of their lord (and particularly, after Hirotada&apos;s death, their lord) was taken as a hostage, and it seems that they felt a certain pressure because of their disadvantaged position (to Ieyasu, who temporarily retuned to the Okazaki-ji Castle to pay his ancestors a visit, Tadayoshi TORII complained about the Imagawa family&apos;s autocratic manner).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the vassals of the Matsudaira clan, however, it was a fact that the eldest legitimate son of their lord (and particularly, after Hirotada&apos;s death, their lord) was taken as hostage, and it seems that they felt a certain amount of pressure due to their disadvantaged position (Tadayoshi TORII complained to Ieyasu, who temporarily returned to the Okazaki-ji Castle to pay his ancestors a visit, about the Imagawa family&apos;s autocratic manner).</e>
<cmt>retuned &gt; returned; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To the vassals of the Matsudaira clan, however, it was a fact that the legitimate son of their lord (and particularly, after Hirotada&apos;s death, their lord) was taken as hostage, and it seems that they felt a certain amount of pressure due to their disadvantaged position (Tadayoshi TORII complained to Ieyasu, who temporarily returned to the Okazaki-ji Castle to pay his ancestors a visit, about the Imagawa family&apos;s autocratic manner.)</e>
<cmt>eldest を削除しました。（嫡男としかないため）ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>また、竹千代が義元の家臣（孕石元泰）から個人的な虐めを受けるなど、忍従の日々であったことに違いは無く、後世、徳川家側の主観のみが広がり、従来の通説になったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And there is no doubt that Takechiyo (later Ieyasu) was living a life full of sufferance such as Yoshimoto&apos;s vassal (Tomoyasu HARAMIISHI)&apos;s personal humiliation, and therefore, it is natural to consider that the only Tokugawa family&apos;s subjective vision had extended to become the traditional common view.</e>
<cmt>竹千代→Takechiyo (later Ieyasu) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no doubt that Takechiyo&apos;s life was full of sufferances, such as the personal humiliation he received from one of Yoshimoto&apos;s vassals (Tomoyasu HARAMIISHI), so it is only natural for the subjective standpoint of the Tokugawa family to be extended to the traditional common view.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;And,&quot;; eliminated (later Ieyasu); fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no doubt that Takechiyo&apos;s life was full of sufferances, such as the personal humiliation he received from one of Yoshimoto&apos;s vassals (Tomoyasu HARAMIISHI), so it is only natural for the subjective standpoint of the Tokugawa family to be extended to the traditional common view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>もっとも家康は隠居先に忍従の日々だったはずの駿河を選んでいることも事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For certain, Ieyasu chose Suruga for his place of retirement, although he must have lived the days of patience during his childhood there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One thing for certain, is that Ieyasu chose Suruga as his place for retirement even though he had supposedly been living a submissive life during his days living there as a child.</e>
<cmt>although &gt; even though; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One thing for certain, is that Ieyasu chose Suruga as his place for retirement even though he had supposedly been living a submissive life during his days living there as a child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="104">
<j>永禄3年（1560年）の尾張侵攻は、上洛目的説と織田信長討伐・尾張攻略説とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two theories on the invasion of Owari Province in 1560, one is the theory that Yoshimoto&apos;s objective was proceeding to the capital (Kyoto), and the other is that he was aiming at putting down Nobunaga ODA and capturing Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>上洛目的説→定訳不明：the theory that Yoshimoto&apos;s objective was proceeding to the capital (Kyoto) としました。織田信長討伐・尾張攻略説→定訳不明：(the theory) that he was among at putting down Nobunaga ODA and capturing Owari Province としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two theories on why Yoshimoto made an invasion into the Owari Province in 1560; one is that Yoshimoto had the objective of proceeding to the capital (Kyoto), and the other is that he was aiming at putting down Nobunaga ODA and capturing Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two theories on why Yoshimoto made an invasion into the Owari Province in 1560; one is that Yoshimoto had the objective of proceeding to the capital (Kyoto), and the other is that he was aiming at putting down Nobunaga ODA and capturing Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Arufu(id:733), Aityanlove(id:203908), Nnh(id:474), Lahire(id:75606), T.Saito(id:64009), Cprobot(id:97843), KurmUmy(id:202680), PATMAN(id:145791), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Naigai(id:288953), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), 朝彦(id:9407), A-Taul(id:41790), Deapy(id:191082), 秀の介(id:490), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), ハニーハニー00(id:263775), Kouko0515(id:100370), Chao35(id:34986), Calvero(id:38360), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Shinbad(id:50287), M-sho-gun(id:88956), んどん(id:148105), Carbuncle(id:346), 果心居士(id:248111), 松茸(id:27535), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Tiyoringo(id:70026), わがまま小皇帝(id:39717), Koolonpas(id:199077), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), 雷(id:25583), Rusk(id:9895), Hungugu(id:20858), 海衛士(id:19229), Yumitan(id:199073), 伏儀(id:142093), Gthantr(id:204541), Oplkiuy7654322(id:188089), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), Suisui(id:69), Jmho(id:10472), MD242(id:11277), Bakkai(id:7233), ドルチェット(id:46458), Herr Weißes(id:71029), 麝香(id:89874), Charenji(id:7908), Yen80(id:6146), ConstantinetheGreat(id:62617), Sgi1962(id:80778), 百人(id:16483), EULE(id:74209), 雪解の泉(id:23671), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 玄史生(id:43670), Goki(id:7107), Paotch(id:3039), Sho-gun(id:74168), ふかざわ(id:214744), 越中掾(id:149423), 00114455pp(id:200694), Exocet(id:86658), Showhead999(id:259332), ぶるるるる(id:130462), Izayohi(id:13095), やりたこ(id:113528), Lombroso(id:20212), 水野白楓(id:22811), Gakukann32(id:157717), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Yanahan(id:2437), Aboshi(id:9318), EOM(id:239799), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kuro-hato(id:34041), YurikBot(id:18605), FOREST(id:126717), Twilight2640(id:134273), Safkan(id:423), Kodai99(id:83937), Hadrianvs et antinovs(id:187552), Ionionion(id:202418), 一騎当千(id:56448), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>