<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>川口雪篷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seppo KAWAGUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seppo KAWAGUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seppo KAWAGUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>川口 雪篷（かわぐち せっぽう、文政元年（1818年）- 明治23年（1890年））は、江戸時代後期（幕末）の薩摩藩出身の書家であり、西郷隆盛の知遇を得て、書道と漢詩を教えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seppo KAWAGUCHI (1818 - 1890) was a calligrapher from the Satsuma Domain at the end of the Edo period and being taken under the wing of Takamori SAIGO, he taught calligraphy and Chinese poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seppo KAWAGUCHI (1818 - 1890) was a calligrapher from the Satsuma Domain at the end of the Edo period and being taken under the wing of Takamori SAIGO, he taught calligraphy and Chinese poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seppo KAWAGUCHI (1818 - 1890) was a calligrapher from the Satsuma Domain at the end of the Edo period and being taken under the wing of Takamori SAIGO, he taught calligraphy and Chinese poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後述するように、沖永良部島から帰島後は亡くなるまで西郷家に寄寓して、西郷家の留守居役を果たし、また西郷の子弟の教育にも当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioning below, he was living with the Saigo Family after returning from Oki-no-erabujima island until his death and was a Rusuiyaku (a person representing the master during his absence); he was also responsible in educating young people of the Saigo Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioning below, after returning from Okinoerabu-jima Island, he lived at the residence of the Saigo family until his death and served as superintendent of the residence during the master Takamori&apos;s absence and also educated Takamori&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioning below, after returning from Okinoerabu-jima Island, he lived at the residence of the Saigo family until his death and served as superintendent of the residence during the master Takamori&apos;s absence and also educated Takamori&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place of Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place of Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place of Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸居付馬廻役として代々江戸藩邸に詰める薩摩藩士川口仲左衛門の四男として文政元年（1818年）に種子島西之表市納曾（のうそ）に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Nouso, Nishinoomote City, Tanegashima Island in 1818 as the fourth son of Nakazaemon KAWAGUCHI who was a Satsuma retainer and his family were successively working as an Umamawariyaku (body guard) at the residence of the Satsuma clan in Edo (Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Nouso, Nishinoomote City, Tanegashima Island in 1818 as the fourth son of Nakazaemon KAWAGUCHI who was a retainer of the Satsuma clan and his family had been successively serving as Umamawari-yaku (body guard) of the residence of the Satsuma clan in Edo (Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Nouso, Nishinoomote City, Tanegashima Island in 1818 as the fourth son of Nakazaemon KAWAGUCHI who was a retainer of the Satsuma clan and his family had been successively serving as Umamawari-yaku (body guard) of the residence of the Satsuma clan in Edo (Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本名は初め量次郎、後に明治元年12月25日に俊作と改名し、さらに明治5年9月19日に雪篷と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was initially Ryojiro, and he changed it to Shunsaku on February 6, 1869 and then to Seppo on October 21, 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was initially Ryojiro, and he changed it to Shunsaku on February 6, 1869 and then to Seppo on October 21, 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was initially Ryojiro, and he changed it to Shunsaku on February 6, 1869 and then to Seppo on October 21, 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>書家としての号は香雲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was a calligrapher, his pen name was Koun.</e>
<cmt>「香雲」の読み不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a calligrapher, he called himself Koun.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a calligrapher, he called himself Koun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸で菊池五山に入門して漢詩を習得して、書は唐様を得意とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo, he became a pupil of Gozan KIKUCHI and learned Chinese poetry; and Karayo (Chinese style) was his specialty in calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>「菊地五山」の「菊地」は「菊池」と表記されているものもあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Edo, he became a pupil of Gozan KIKUCHI and learned Chinese poetry; and Karayo (Chinese style) was his specialty in calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Edo, he became a pupil of Gozan KIKUCHI and learned Chinese poetry; and Karayo (Chinese style) was his specialty in calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また陽明学にも通じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an expert at Yomei-gaku (the heterodox neo-Confucian teachings of Yangming WANG).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an expert at Yomei-gaku (Yangming school, a school of Confucian started by Wang Yangming).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。中国のものの場合特に時代によって見方が変わりますのでneoやheterodoxは不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an expert at Yomei-gaku (Yangming school, a school of Confucian started by Wang Yangming).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>沖永良部島配流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>川口家は父の不始末によりお役御免となって鹿児島市に引き揚げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because his father&apos;s misconduct caused him to lose his job, the Kawaguchi Family moved back to Kagoshima City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to his father&apos;s mistake, the members of the Kawaguchi family were fired and moved back to Kagoshima City.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his father&apos;s mistake, the members of the Kawaguchi family were fired and moved back to Kagoshima City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>兄が鹿児島で家を再生したが、罪を犯して名跡を取り上げられたのに連座して量次郎は沖永良島へ遠島になったとされる（鹿児島立図書館の紹介文による）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brother rebuilt the family home but when he committed a crime, his family name was taken; so Ryojiro was implicated and was sent to Oki-no-erabujima Island (according to the description from the Kagoshima Prefectural Library).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kagoshima, his older brother began some work and readjusted the family, however he committed a crime and the family name was taken; and Ryojiro was implicated in that and sent to Okinoerabu-jima Island (according to the description from the Kagoshima Prefectural Library).</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kagoshima, his older brother began some work and readjusted the family, however he committed a crime and the family name was taken; and Ryojiro was implicated in that and sent to Okinoerabu-jima Island (according to the description from the Kagoshima Prefectural Library).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、別の説では島津久光の写字生として勤めていたが、公の書物を質に入れて焼酎を飲んでいたことがばれて、沖永良部島に流されたとされる（これが流布されている通説）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to another story, when he was working as a scriber for Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, he was found drinking Shochu (distilled spirit) after giving public documents to a pawnbroker to receive money and as a result for that, he was sent to the island (and this is the popular theory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to another story, when he was working as copyist for Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, he was found that he had been buying shochu (Japanese distilled grain liquor) by putting the public documents in pledge, and sent to Okinoerabu-jima Island (and this is the popular theory).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。「写字生」について小説などではcopyistという語をよく見ます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to another story, when he was working as copyist for Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, he was found that he had been buying shochu (Japanese distilled grain liquor) by putting the public documents in pledge, and sent to Okinoerabu-jima Island (and this is the popular theory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに、文久2年（1862年）に西郷隆盛も同じ島に流されて和泊町の牢に入れられたときに、川口は罪人ではないけれども、わざわざ沖ノ永良部へ往って西郷の書や詩作の指導をしたとする説もある（重野安繹による）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was also another story which said that in 1862 when Takamori SAIGO was exiled to the same island and was locked in jail in Wadomari-cho town, Kawaguchi moved to the island to teach Saigo&apos;s calligraphy and poetry, although he was not a criminal (by Yasutsugu SHIGENO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also another story which says that in 1862 when Takamori SAIGO was exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island and was locked in jail of Wadomari-cho, Kawaguchi went to the island to teach calligraphy and poetry to Saigo, although he was not a criminal (according to Yasutsugu SHIGENO&apos;s idea).</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also another story which says that in 1862 when Takamori SAIGO was exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island and was locked in jail of Wadomari-cho, Kawaguchi went to the island to teach calligraphy and poetry to Saigo, although he was not a criminal (according to Yasutsugu SHIGENO&apos;s idea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>川口家の子孫の間には、種子島出身のいわゆる「島五郎（しまごろ）」であるのに久光の書生として重用されたことを周囲に嫉まれて罪を着せられたという言い伝えもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the descendants of the Kawaguchi Family, there was a theory that some people were jealous when Ryojiro, who was only a &apos;Shimagoro&apos; (a Tanegashima island native boy), was given an important position of Hisamitsu&apos;s Shosei (a post managing clerical works) and they lay a crime on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the descendants of the Kawaguchi Family remains a story that since Ryojiro was given an important position such as Hisamitsu&apos;s shosei (a post managing clerical works) although he was just a so-called &apos;Shimagoro&apos; (countryman from island) from Tanega-shima Island, some people were jealous of him and put a crime upon him.</e>
<cmt>時制を直し、わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the descendants of the Kawaguchi Family remains a story that since Ryojiro was given an important position such as Hisamitsu&apos;s shosei (a post managing clerical works) although he was just a so-called &apos;Shimagoro&apos; (countryman from island) from Tanega-shima Island, some people were jealous of him and put a crime upon him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>諸説紛々として判然としないが、文久2年つまり西郷の沖永良部遠島の前から何らかの事情で同じ島に流されて西原村に住み、島の子供たちに読み書きを教えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the real reason for his exile was not clear because of the so many different theories, Kawaguchi was exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island before Saigo was sent there in 1862 and he started to live in Nishihara Village and taught children how to read and write.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the real reason for his exile is not clear because of many different theories, it is a fact that Kawaguchi had been exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island for some reason before Saigo was sent there in 1862, and that he lived in Nishihara Village and taught reading and writing to the children of the island.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the real reason for his exile is not clear because of many different theories, it is a fact that Kawaguchi had been exiled to Okinoerabu-jima Island for some reason before Saigo was sent there in 1862, and that he lived in Nishihara Village and taught reading and writing to the children of the island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>通説によれば、西郷とは初対面から大いに意気投合し、西原から1里弱(3.4km)離れた和泊の西郷の座敷牢まで毎日のように通っては、時世を論じ学問を語り、書や詩作を教えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the popular theory, Kawaguchi got on very well with Saigo from the time when they first met; so Kawaguchi visited Saigo&apos;s Zashikiro (room for confining criminals) everyday in Wadomari, 3.4Km away from Nishihara and discussed current issues and talked about learning; and he taught calligraphy and poetry to Saigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the popular theory, Kawaguchi got on very well with Saigo from the first time they met; and everyday Kawaguchi visited Saigo&apos;s cell of the prison of Wadomari which was 3.4 kilometers away from Nishihara and discussed current issues and talked about learning, and he came to teach calligraphy and poetry to Saigo.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the popular theory, Kawaguchi got on very well with Saigo from the first time they met; and everyday Kawaguchi visited Saigo&apos;s cell of the prison of Wadomari which was 3.4 kilometers away from Nishihara and discussed current issues and talked about learning, and he came to teach calligraphy and poetry to Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>間切横目の土持正照は、西郷が迷惑ではないかと案じて面会の制限を問うたところ、「いや。川口どんは和漢の学に通じ、語るに足るお人じゃ。こんままでよか」と西郷が答えたと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masahiro TSUCHIMOCHI, a Magiri-yokome (officer for province) worried that Saigo might be annoyed and asked if Saigo wanted him to reduce Kawaguchi&apos;s visits, Saigo said &quot;No. Kawaguchi knows a lot about both Chinese and Japanese classics and is worth talking to. Leave it like this, please.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Magiri-yokome (officer of prison) Masahiro TSUCHIMOCHI worried that Saigo might have been annoyed and asked if Saigo wanted him to limit visiting, then Saigo answered &quot;no, Mr. Kawaguchi knows a lot about both Chinese and Japanese classics and is worth talking with, leave it like this.&quot;</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Magiri-yokome (officer of prison) Masahiro TSUCHIMOCHI worried that Saigo might have been annoyed and asked if Saigo wanted him to limit visiting, then Saigo answered &quot;no, Mr. Kawaguchi knows a lot about both Chinese and Japanese classics and is worth talking with, leave it like this.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>二人の間には次のような稚気溢れる逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a rather childish anecdote about them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a rather childish anecdote about them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a rather childish anecdote about them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>（以下、井元正流『種子島』より引用）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Below was cited from &quot;Tanegashima&quot; by Masaru INOMOTO.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Below was cited from &quot;Tanegashima&quot; by Masaru INOMOTO.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Below was cited from &quot;Tanegashima&quot; by Masaru INOMOTO.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>ある時などは、李白の詩を示して、「西郷さん、詩はこう作らないといけません、あなたのはまだ四（詩）になりません。三（賛）にもどうですかなあ、ハッハッハ」と笑ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once, pointing at a poem by Li Po (Rihaku), Kawaguchi said &quot;Mr Saigo, a poem should be written like this. Yours are not yet to be Shi (Japanese for four = a [proper] poem), not even San (Japanese for three = a style of Chinese poetry)!&quot; and laughed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, pointing at a poem by Li Po, Kawaguchi laughed and taught Saigo &quot;Mr Saigo, a poem should be written like this, yours cannot form four (&apos;四&apos; [shi] which pronunciation is the same as &apos;詩&apos; [shi] Chinese poetry) yet, and cannot form even three (&apos;三&apos; [san] which pronunciation is the same as &apos;賛&apos; [san] a style of Chinese literature for praising someone or something), hahaha!&quot;</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, pointing at a poem by Li Po, Kawaguchi laughed and taught Saigo &quot;Mr Saigo, a poem should be written like this, yours cannot form four (&apos;四&apos; [shi] which pronunciation is the same as &apos;詩&apos; [shi] Chinese poetry) yet, and cannot form even three (&apos;三&apos; [san] which pronunciation is the same as &apos;賛&apos; [san] a style of Chinese literature for praising someone or something), hahaha!&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なかなかの酒豪で、酔えばそのまま昼間でも庭先に寝込んでしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was quite a heavy drinker and when he was drunk, he fell asleep in the garden even if it was during the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was quite a heavy drinker and when he was drunk, he fell asleep in the garden even if it was during the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was quite a heavy drinker and when he was drunk, he fell asleep in the garden even if it was during the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>それで南州が＜睡眠先生＞と雅号を贈ったところ、同じスイミンなら＜酔眠先生＞がいいですよと改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nanshu (Saigo) gave Kawaguchi a Gago (pseudonym) of &lt;Mr Suimin (Mr Sleepy head)&gt; (using 睡[sui, meaning &apos;sleep&apos;]), then they changed the Chinese character to &apos;酔&apos; (meaning &apos;drunk&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Nanshu (Saigo) gave Kawaguchi a gago (pseudonym) of &apos;Suimin-sensei&apos; (睡眠先生, literally, &apos;Mr. Sleep&apos;), however Kawaguchi changed it to &apos;Suimin-sensei&apos; (酔眠先生, literally, &apos;Mr. Drunk and Sleep&apos;) saying he preferred it although they had the same pronunciation.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Nanshu (Saigo) gave Kawaguchi a gago (pseudonym) of &apos;Suimin-sensei&apos; (睡眠先生, literally, &apos;Mr. Sleep&apos;), however Kawaguchi changed it to &apos;Suimin-sensei&apos; (酔眠先生, literally, &apos;Mr. Drunk and Sleep&apos;) saying he preferred it although they had the same pronunciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>またある時、南州を訪ねるのに一里の道を迷いに迷って、朝出たのにやっと夕方になってから着いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, when Kawaguchi visited Nanshu, he got lost in that 3.4Km; although he left early morning, he got there in the evening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day Kawaguchi lost his way on the way to visit Nanshu; although he left his home early in the morning, he went round and round the way of only 4 kilometers, and arrived at the destination in the evening.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day Kawaguchi lost his way on the way to visit Nanshu; although he left his home early in the morning, he went round and round the way of only 4 kilometers, and arrived at the destination in the evening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>南州が「それは前代未聞のこと、狐にでもだまされたんですかな、これからは＜迂闊先生＞とでも着け替え申そう」と言ったら、雪篷は「どうでもお勝手に、名前はいくらでもあった方が便利です」と答えて、それから次の約束を交わしたという、「われわれ二人はどちらでも先に赦免された者が、おくれた者を扶養すること」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Nanshu said &quot;Oh, that&apos;s unusual. Maybe a fox did some trick. We should then call you &lt;Mr Careless&gt;&quot;, to which Seppo answered &quot;Call me whatever you like. Having many names is convenient&quot; and made plans for another visit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Nanshu said &quot;oh, that&apos;s unheard-of incident, maybe a fox did some trick, we should call you Ukatsu-sensei (Mr. Careless) from now on,&quot; and Seppo answered &quot;call me whatever you like, since it&apos;s convenient to have a lot of names,&quot; and they promised each other, &quot;whoever gets out of here first would support the other.&quot;</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Nanshu said &quot;oh, that&apos;s unheard-of incident, maybe a fox did some trick, we should call you Ukatsu-sensei (Mr. Careless) from now on,&quot; and Seppo answered &quot;call me whatever you like, since it&apos;s convenient to have a lot of names,&quot; and they promised each other, &quot;whoever gets out of here first would support the other.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>西郷家に寄寓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lodging with Saigo Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Living at Saigo&apos;s home</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Living at Saigo&apos;s home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>西郷の本土帰還の後、慶応元年頃に赦免されて鹿児島城下に戻って、当初は親戚の家を転々としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Saigo went back to the mainland, Kawaguchi was discharged around 1865, went back near the Kagoshima Castle and stayed around at his relatives first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Saigo had returned to the mainland, Kawaguchi was discharged around 1865 and went back to Kagoshima City, and at first drifted from one relative&apos;s house to another.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Saigo had returned to the mainland, Kawaguchi was discharged around 1865 and went back to Kagoshima City, and at first drifted from one relative&apos;s house to another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後、前記の約束あってか上之園の西郷邸に飄然と現れてそのまま食客になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then because of the promise above, he showed up at the door of Saigo&apos;s house in Uenosono and became a guest at meal times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, although it is not clear whether they had made such promise or he had another reason, he casually showed up at the door of Saigo&apos;s house in Uenosono and stayed as the family&apos;s guest.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, although it is not clear whether they had made such promise or he had another reason, he casually showed up at the door of Saigo&apos;s house in Uenosono and stayed as the family&apos;s guest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>西郷は国事に奔走して家を空けることが多く男手が乏しい西郷家にあって、来客の応対や能書を生かした信書連絡などもっぱら外回りの役目を果たす家令あるいは留守居役を果たすとともに、西郷の子弟の書や漢学の師ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Saigo was busy with national affairs and was not at home mostly, at their house where a man&apos;s hand was needed, Kawaguchi was working as a butler to do work around the house such as answering to the visitors and sending and receiving correspondence using his good writing skills and/or Rusuiyaku (a person representing the master during his absence) as well as teaching calligraphy and Chinese poetry to Saigo&apos;s young people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Saigo was busy with national affairs and was not at home mostly, his family needed a man who could manage the master&apos;s works, therefore Kawaguchi worked as butler to deal with the outside such as attending visitors and using his calligraphy for writing letters, and worked as rusui-yaku (person representing the master during his absence) as well as teaching calligraphy and Chinese literature to Saigo&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Saigo was busy with national affairs and was not at home mostly, his family needed a man who could manage the master&apos;s works, therefore Kawaguchi worked as butler to deal with the outside such as attending visitors and using his calligraphy for writing letters, and worked as rusui-yaku (person representing the master during his absence) as well as teaching calligraphy and Chinese literature to Saigo&apos;s children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、西南戦争中に成人男子が出征して西郷家は完全に女所帯となり、武村の屋敷が焼亡した後は鹿児島各地を転々としたが、雪篷は常に一家と苦患をともにし、その精神的支柱となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all adult males were out fighting during the Seinan War, Saigo family became a female household; and after the house was burnt down, they were all moving around from place to place in Kagoshima, but Seppo was together with them sharing the sorrows, and gave them emotional support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Seinan War, all the adult males went to the front, and the women had to protect the Saigo family; and after the residence of Takemura had been burnt down, they drifted from one place to another in Kagoshima; during such days Seppo kept following them sharing the pains and sorrows, and gave them emotional support.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Seinan War, all the adult males went to the front, and the women had to protect the Saigo family; and after the residence of Takemura had been burnt down, they drifted from one place to another in Kagoshima; during such days Seppo kept following them sharing the pains and sorrows, and gave them emotional support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>西郷の長子西郷菊次郎が戦場で片足を失う重傷を負ったときは義足の手配に心をくだいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Saigo&apos;s eldest child Kikujiro SAIGO lost his leg at the war, Seppo was said to have taken the most effort in obtaining a false leg for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that when Saigo&apos;s oldest son Kikujiro SAIGO was injured in a battle and lost his leg, Seppo made his best effort in obtaining a false leg for him.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that when Saigo&apos;s oldest son Kikujiro SAIGO was injured in a battle and lost his leg, Seppo made his best effort in obtaining a false leg for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>西南戦争後の逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes after the Seinan War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes after the Seinan War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes after the Seinan War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>西南戦争後の雪篷の姿を伝えるエピソードがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some episodes to tell us about Seppo after the Seinan War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some episodes to tell us about Seppo after the Seinan War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some episodes to tell us about Seppo after the Seinan War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>明治12年（1879年）に来鹿した頭山満の回想では、「西郷家には、当時七十歳ぐらいの川口雪篷という詩書をよくする老人が家令をつとめていた」（実際には、雪篷は当時62歳）とあり、頭山は、開口一番「南州翁に会いたい」と言ったが、雪篷は「西郷が城山で斃れたことも知らないのか」と呆れたように一喝した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the recollection of Mitsuru TOYAMA who visited Kagoshima in 1879, he said, &quot;At Saigo&apos;s house, there was a butler around the age of 70, called Seppo KAWAGUCHI who wrote calligraphy and poems&quot; (althought Seppo was 62 at that time), and that when Toyama asked, &quot;I would like to see Father Nanshu&quot; as soon as he got there, Seppo was appalled and told him off by saying &quot;Didn&apos;t you know Saigo died in Shiroyama?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the reminiscences by Mitsuru TOYAMA who visited Kagoshima in 1879, &quot;in Saigo&apos;s house, there was a butler around the age of 70, called Seppo KAWAGUCHI who wrote calligraphy and poems well&quot; (in fact Seppo was aged 62 at that time), and when Toyama asked first &quot;I would like to see Mr. Nanshu,&quot; Seppo was appalled and yelled in anger &quot;Don&apos;t you know Saigo died in Shiroyama?&quot;</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the reminiscences by Mitsuru TOYAMA who visited Kagoshima in 1879, &quot;in Saigo&apos;s house, there was a butler around the age of 70, called Seppo KAWAGUCHI who wrote calligraphy and poems well&quot; (in fact Seppo was aged 62 at that time), and when Toyama asked first &quot;I would like to see Mr. Nanshu,&quot; Seppo was appalled and yelled in anger &quot;Don&apos;t you know Saigo died in Shiroyama?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>頭山はそれに答えて「西郷の精神ぐらいは残っているだろう」と答え、以下の会話が交わされたという（以下、『西南記伝』から引用）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To answer him, Toyama said &quot;There must be his spirit left&quot; and they exchanged conversations as follows (cited from &quot;Seinan Kiden&quot; book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To answer him, Toyama said &quot;There must remains Saigo&apos;s spirit&quot; and they exchanged conversations as follows (cited from &quot;Seinan Kiden&quot;).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To answer him, Toyama said &quot;There must remains Saigo&apos;s spirit&quot; and they exchanged conversations as follows (cited from &quot;Seinan Kiden&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>雪蓬、悵然之に謂て曰く『十年役前の鹿児島は、有用の人材輩出せしも、今や、禿山と一般、人才一空、復言ふに忍びざるなり。樹を植ゆるは、百年の計なり。想ふに西郷の如き巨人は、百年又は千年にして一たび出づるもの。而して、斯人再び見る可からず』と。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seppo ruefully said &quot;Kagoshima had many great people before the war but now we only have bald hills and ordinary people, 人才一空, no promise for the future. It takes 100 years to see a tree growing. I think, a titan like Saigo only appearing once in every 100 or 1000 years. So, we will never see anyone like him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seppo ruefully said &quot;although Kagoshima had many talented people before the war, such people and talents all vanished like those trees disappeared and only bald hills remain here, I cannot stand even saying this; it takes a hundred years to raise a tree, and I think a titan like Saigo would appear only once in a hundred years or once in a thousand years, so, we can never see anyone like him.&quot;</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seppo ruefully said &quot;although Kagoshima had many talented people before the war, such people and talents all vanished like those trees disappeared and only bald hills remain here, I cannot stand even saying this; it takes a hundred years to raise a tree, and I think a titan like Saigo would appear only once in a hundred years or once in a thousand years, so, we can never see anyone like him.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>満乃ち雪蓬に就て、西郷遺愛の文藉を見んことを求めしに、雪蓬『洗心洞剳記』を出し、満に謂て曰く『是れ、西郷が南島謫居中愛読して措かざりし書なり』と。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuru then asked Seppo to see Saigo&apos;s cherished books and Seppo showed him &quot;Senshin Dosatsuki&quot; and said &quot;Saigo liked reading this important book while he was exiled on the southern island.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuru then asked Seppo to see Saigo&apos;s cherished books, and Seppo showed him &quot;Senshin Dosatsu-ki&quot; and said &quot;Saigo always had this book by his side and read during he was shutting himself up at the southern island.&quot;</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuru then asked Seppo to see Saigo&apos;s cherished books, and Seppo showed him &quot;Senshin Dosatsu-ki&quot; and said &quot;Saigo always had this book by his side and read during he was shutting himself up at the southern island.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>満披て之を読むに、書中往往隆盛の手記に係る註あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuru started reading it and found some of Saigo&apos;s hand written notes on the book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuru got his permit and read it, and found Saigo&apos;s hand-written notes in the book.</e>
<cmt>前置詞を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuru got his permit and read it, and found Saigo&apos;s hand-written notes in the book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>満、垂涎措かず、雪蓬に請ひて之を借り、飄然去て之く所を知らず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Without a second, Mitsuru asked Seppo if he could borrow it and disappeared quickly without telling where he was going.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instantly Mitsuru asked Seppo to borrow it, then Seppo handed the book and left casually without saying goodbye.</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。文中突然主語が入れ換わり、飄然と去ったのはせっぽうさんの方です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instantly Mitsuru asked Seppo to borrow it, then Seppo handed the book and left casually without saying goodbye.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>後、雪蓬、其返却を逼ること甚だ急なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seppo wanted the book to be returned quickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, later Seppo asked him again and again to return the book.</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。「はなはだ急なり」は「うるさくせかす」のような意味です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, later Seppo asked him again and again to return the book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>居ること一年。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A year later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuru ignored it for a year.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuru ignored it for a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>満、再び鹿児島に遊び、雪蓬に見えて、其書を返しゝに、雪蓬大に喜び、更に『王陽明全集』を出して之に贈り、却て其軽忽を謝したりと云ふ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuru came back to Kagoshima and went to see Seppo to return the book; delighted Seppo gave Mitsuru the &quot;Yangming WANG Collection&quot; and Mitsuru apologized for his delay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuru visited Kagoshima again and went to see Seppo to return the book; then Seppo was delighted and took out his &quot;Wang Yangming Collection&quot; to give Mitsuru, besides, Seppo apologized for his irrational behavior.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。「謝した」のは本を返せとうるさく催促したせっぽうさんの方です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuru visited Kagoshima again and went to see Seppo to return the book; then Seppo was delighted and took out his &quot;Wang Yangming Collection&quot; to give Mitsuru, besides, Seppo apologized for his irrational behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>文中の『洗心洞剳記』とは、天保の大飢饉の際に万民の窮状を顧みない大阪奉行所の悪政に敢然と立ち上がった大塩平八郎（中斎）が記した講義録で、西郷に限らず幕末維新の志士の間で愛読されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, &quot;Senshin Dosatsuki&quot; was a collection of lecture notes written by Heihachiro OSHIO (Chusai) who stood up against maladministration of Osaka Magistrate Office not considering people&apos;s distressed conditions during the Tenpo Famine; and the book was widely read not only by Saigo but also by other supporters of the Restoration at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Senshin Dosatsu-ki&quot; mentioned above is a collection of lecture notes written by Heihachiro OSHIO (Chusai) who stood up against the maladministration of Osaka Magistrate Office not considering the people&apos;s distressed conditions during the Tenpo Famine; and the book was widely read not only by Saigo but also by other supporters of the Restoration at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>簡単な文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Senshin Dosatsu-ki&quot; mentioned above is a collection of lecture notes written by Heihachiro OSHIO (Chusai) who stood up against the maladministration of Osaka Magistrate Office not considering the people&apos;s distressed conditions during the Tenpo Famine; and the book was widely read not only by Saigo but also by other supporters of the Restoration at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>陽明学に傾倒した雪篷らしい発言で、身近に在って西郷の真意をどれほど汲んだものかは分からない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These remarks from Seppo showed that he was right into Yomei-gaku but how much of his remarks were reflecting Saigo&apos;s real intentions was unknown although he was very close to Saigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those Seppo&apos;s words shows that he favored Yomei-gaku, however how much of his remarks were reflecting Saigo&apos;s real intentions is unknown although he had been very close to Saigo.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those Seppo&apos;s words shows that he favored Yomei-gaku, however how much of his remarks were reflecting Saigo&apos;s real intentions is unknown although he had been very close to Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>沖永良部島は西郷の「敬天愛人」思想の培養基であり、一説には本土から1,200冊あまりの本を取り寄せていたそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okinoerabu-jima Island was the base of Saigo&apos;s idea of &apos;Revere heaven, Love people&apos;; there was a story saying Saigo had about 1200 books sent from the mainland while he was there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okinoerabu-jima Island was Saigo&apos;s spiritual base let him develop the idea of &apos;Revere heaven, Love people&apos;; and according to a story, Saigo had about 1200 books sent from the mainland while he was there.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okinoerabu-jima Island was Saigo&apos;s spiritual base let him develop the idea of &apos;Revere heaven, Love people&apos;; and according to a story, Saigo had about 1200 books sent from the mainland while he was there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>したがって、上の発言は雪篷の側から見た主観的見解ともいえるが、雪篷は西郷が事の成否を省みずに義挙に出た精神を訴えたかったのだと理解するのも可であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, above remarks could be Seppo&apos;s subjective views, however it could also be understood that Seppo wanted to tell Mitsuru about Saigo&apos;s spirit as he continued his brave fights without thinking of what the result would be.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, above remarks could be Seppo&apos;s subjective views, however it could be considered that Seppo wanted to tell Mitsuru about Saigo&apos;s spirit which had made him take the action for justice without thinking results.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, above remarks could be Seppo&apos;s subjective views, however it could be considered that Seppo wanted to tell Mitsuru about Saigo&apos;s spirit which had made him take the action for justice without thinking results.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>終焉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End of Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End of Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>雪篷は、前年に西郷から賊将の汚名が消され、改めて維新の功臣として名誉回復されたことを見届けて安心したかのごとく、明治23年（1890年）に病没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seppo died peacefully from an illness in 1890 after Saigo&apos;s name was cleared as the leader of the rebels and his honor was recovered as a meritorious retainer of the Restoration the year before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890, Seppo died peacefully from illness as if he was relieved by watching that in the previous year Saigo&apos;s name as the leader of the rebels had been cleared and his honor as a meritorious retainer of the Restoration had been recovered.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890, Seppo died peacefully from illness as if he was relieved by watching that in the previous year Saigo&apos;s name as the leader of the rebels had been cleared and his honor as a meritorious retainer of the Restoration had been recovered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>享年72。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>死後は西郷家の墓地に埋葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried in the Saigo family&apos;s graveyard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried in the Saigo family&apos;s graveyard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried in the Saigo family&apos;s graveyard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>なお、島民子弟の教育に尽くした遺徳を偲ぶ『川口雪篷流謫之地』の碑が沖永良部島西原に建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a monument of &quot;Seppo KAWAGUCHI&apos;s exiled place&quot; in Nishihara, Okinoerabu-jima Island to commemorate his efforts in educating children of the island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a monument of &quot;Seppo KAWAGUCHI&apos;s exiled place&quot; in Nishihara, Okinoerabu-jima Island to commemorate his efforts in educating children of the island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a monument of &quot;Seppo KAWAGUCHI&apos;s exiled place&quot; in Nishihara, Okinoerabu-jima Island to commemorate his efforts in educating children of the island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>書家としての雪篷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seppo as a Calligrapher</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seppo as a Calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seppo as a Calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>その性格を反映して、雪篷の書風は自由奔放で大胆と伝えられており、今でも数点の書が鹿児島県立図書館に所蔵されているので実見できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reflecting his personality, his style of calligraphy is said to be free and bold; there are a few of his works in the possession of Kagoshima Prefectural Library for public displays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reflecting his personality, his style of calligraphy is said to be free and bold; there are a few of his works in the possession of Kagoshima Prefectural Library for public displays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reflecting his personality, his style of calligraphy is said to be free and bold; there are a few of his works in the possession of Kagoshima Prefectural Library for public displays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>西郷の書への影響については、重野安繹によれば、西郷は最初、福島半助という者から御家流を習った後、雪篷から書を学んだので、福島の和様と川口の唐様が混っているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About Saigo&apos;s calligraphy, according to Yasutsugu SHIGENO, because he learned Oie style from Hansuke FUKUSHIMA first, then from Seppo, his style was a mixture of Fukushima&apos;s Japanese style and Kawaguchi&apos;s Karayo.</e>
<cmt>「福島半助」の読みが不明です。「御家流」は崩し字のスタイルのようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for his influence on Saigo&apos;s calligraphy, according to Yasutsugu SHIGENO, at first Saigo learned Oie-ryu style (the Shorenin school which was very popular calligraphy of Japanese style) from Hansuke FUKUSHIMA, then learned calligraphy from Seppo, so Saigo&apos;s calligraphy was a mixture of Japanese style from Fukushima and Chinese style from Kawaguchi.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for his influence on Saigo&apos;s calligraphy, according to Yasutsugu SHIGENO, at first Saigo learned Oie-ryu style (the Shorenin school which was very popular calligraphy of Japanese style) from Hansuke FUKUSHIMA, then learned calligraphy from Seppo, so Saigo&apos;s calligraphy was a mixture of Japanese style from Fukushima and Chinese style from Kawaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), パの字(id:34188), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Cprobot(id:97843), Point136(id:211299), 蔭人(id:80171), オナガドリ(id:15179), Sigeruu(id:24201), AFU(id:42232), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>