<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>白幽子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakuyushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakuyushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakuyushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>白幽子（はくゆうし）は、江戸時代に京都白川の山中の岩窟に住んでいた隠士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakuyushi was an anchorite who lived in a cave in a mountain in Shirakawa in Kyoto in Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakuyushi was an anchorite who lived in a cave in a mountain in Shirakawa in Kyoto during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakuyushi was an anchorite who lived in a cave in a mountain in Shirakawa in Kyoto during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>数百年生きた仙人とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hakuyushi was a hermit who lived for several hundred years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hakuyushi was a hermit who lived for several hundred years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hakuyushi was a hermit who lived for several hundred years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>文禄年間(1592年-1595年)頃には京都の白川の山中に住み、石川丈山は白幽子の弟子であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1592 to 1595, Hakuyushi lived in a mountain in Shirakawa in Kyoto and it is said that Jozan ISHIKAWA was a disciple of Hakuyushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1592 to 1595, Hakuyushi lived in a mountain in Shirakawa in Kyoto and it is said that Jozan ISHIKAWA was a disciple of Hakuyushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1592 to 1595, Hakuyushi lived in a mountain in Shirakawa in Kyoto and it is said that Jozan ISHIKAWA was a disciple of Hakuyushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>1710年(宝永7年)に、禅病に苦しむ白隠が白幽子が住む岩窟を訪れ、白隠に内観の法を伝えたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1710, Hakuin who suffered a religious disease visited the cave where Hakuyushi lived and Hakuyushi taught him the method of introspection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1710, Hakuin who suffered a religious disease visited the cave where Hakuyushi lived and Hakuyushi taught him a method of introspection.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1710, Hakuin who suffered a religious disease visited the cave where Hakuyushi lived and Hakuyushi taught him a method of introspection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>白隠は『夜船閑話』、『遠羅天釜』にその時の顛末と白幽子から伝えられた内観法の内容を記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yofune-kanwa and in Enra-tenkama, Hakuin wrote the details of that visit and the content of the introspecting method taught from Hakuyushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yofune-kanwa and in Enra-tenkama, Hakuin mentioned details of the visit and the contents of the introspection method taught by Hakuyushi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Yofune kanwa&quot; and in &quot;Enra tenkama,&quot; Hakuin mentioned details of the visit and the contents of the introspection method taught by Hakuyushi.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;補足しました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>京都の真如堂に、かつて白幽子の墓と伝えられる石碑があったといい、そこには没年が宝永6年8月9日 (旧暦)と刻まれていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that there was a tomb stone which was said to be the grave of Hakuyushi in Shinjo-do temple in Kyoto and, on the tomb stone, it was engraved that the date of his death was August 9, 1709.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that there was a tomb stone which was said to be the grave of Hakuyushi in Shinjo-do temple in Kyoto and, on the tomb stone, it was engraved that the date of his death was August 9, 1709.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there was a tomb stone which was said to be the grave of Hakuyushi in Shinnyo-do Temple in Kyoto and, on the tomb stone, it was engraved that the date of his death was September 12, 1709.</e>
<cmt>真如堂→Shinnyo-do Temple新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一説には、享年240であったともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to another view, Hakuyushi died at the age of 240.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to another view, Hakuyushi died at the age of 240.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to another view, Hakuyushi died at the age of 240.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Himazin(id:22034), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>