<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>井伊直政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa II</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa II</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa II</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>井伊 直政（いい なおまさ）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期にかけての武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa II was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in Azuchi-Momoyama period and the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa II was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Azuchi-Momoyama and early Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa II was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Azuchi-Momoyama and early Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>井伊氏第24代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth family head of the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth family head of the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth family head of the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>上野国高崎藩の初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first lord of the domain of Takasaki, the Province of Kozuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first lord of the domain of Takasaki, the Province of Kozuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first lord of the domain of Takasaki, the Province of Kozuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に近江国佐和山藩の藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he became the lord of Sawayama Domain, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he became the lord of the Sawayama Domain, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he became the lord of the Sawayama Domain, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>さらにその後に近江国彦根藩の初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he became the first lord of Hikone Domain, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he became the first lord of the Hikone Domain, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he became the first lord of the Hikone Domain, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>徳川氏の家臣（家臣になった当時は外様）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a vassal of Tokugawa Clan (he was tozama [outsider] at the time he became a vassal).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a vassal of the Tokugawa Clan (he was a tozama [outsider] at the time he became a vassal).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a vassal of the Tokugawa Clan (he was a tozama [outsider] at the time he became a vassal).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>徳川四天王の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>自身が組織した赤備えは戦国屈指の精鋭部隊として特に有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Akazonae (red arms), which he organized himself, is especially famous as one of the best elite troops in Sengoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Akazonae (red arms), which he organized himself, are especially famous as some of the best elite troops in Warring States Period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Akazonae (red arms), which he organized himself, are especially famous as some of the best elite troops among Sengoku (warring provinces).</e>
<cmt>戦国はここでは戦国時代ではなく　戦をする国々という扱いと思われますので変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>徳川氏きっての政治家・外交官としても名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was renowned as the best statesman and diplomat in Tokugawa Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was renowned as the best statesman and diplomat in the Tokugawa Clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was renowned as the best statesman and diplomat in the Tokugawa Clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>遠江国井伊谷の出身で若手の武将でありながら、柳営秘鑑では榊原氏や鳥居氏と並び、三河岡崎御普代として記載されている（譜代の最古参は、安城譜代）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was recorded in Ryueihikan as fudai (hereditary daimyos) of Mikawa Okazaki (the oldest fudai was the Anjo fudai) along with Sakakibara Clan and Torii Clan,Even though he was a young busho from Iinoya, Totoumi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though he was a young military commander from Iinoya, Totoumi Province, he was recorded in Ryueihikan as a fudai (hereditary daimyo) of Mikawa Okazaki along with the Sakakibara Clan and the Torii Clan (the oldest fudai was the Anjo fudai).</e>
<cmt>order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though he was a young military commander from Iinoya, Totoumi Province, he was recorded in Ryueihikan as a fudai (hereditary daimyo) of Mikawa Okazaki along with the Sakakibara Clan and the Torii Clan (the oldest fudai was the Anjo fudai).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、江戸時代に譜代大名の筆頭として、江戸幕府を支えた井伊氏の手本となった人物であり、現在の群馬県高崎市と滋賀県彦根市の発展の基礎を築いた人物でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he also became an example of Ii clan, which supported Edo bakufu as a head of fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in Edo period, and founded the base of development of current Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture and Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also became a paragon of the Ii clan, which supported the Edo shoganate as a head fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in the Edo period, and founded modern day Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture and Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>I assume &quot;founded the base of development&quot; just means &quot;founded&quot;.I also think using Shoganate instead of bafuku is better as the former is generally understood by English speakers who are in some way aquainted with Japan, but the latter is not.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also became a paragon of the Ii clan, which supported Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a head fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in the Edo period, and founded the base of modern day Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture and Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Edo bakufu 用語共有に沿って修正しました。The baseを現代の都市の基礎を築いたという意味で補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>大正6年11月17日、贈従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 17, 1915, he was promoted to zo jusanmi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 17, 1915, he was promoted to zo jusanmi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 17, 1915, he was posthumously conferred to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>家康の家臣になるまで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until he became a vassal of Ieyasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before becoming a vassal of Ieyasu</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before becoming a vassal of Ieyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>永禄4年（1561年）2月19日、今川氏の家臣である井伊直親の長男として、遠江国井伊谷（現在の静岡県浜松市北区 (浜松市)引佐町井伊谷）で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 19, 1561, he was born as a first son to Naochika II, who was a vassal of Imagawa clan, in Iinoya, Totoumi Province (current Iinoya Inasa Kita Ward [Hamamatsu City] Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 19, 1561, he was born in Iinoya, Totoumi Province (modern day Iinoya Inasa Kita Ward, Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture), the first son to Naochika II, a vassal of the Imagawa clan,.</e>
<cmt>wording, ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 14, 1561, he was born in Iinoya, Totoumi Province (modern day Iinoya Inasa Kita Ward, Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture), the first son to Naochika II, a vassal of the Imagawa clan,.</e>
<cmt>和暦⇒グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>井伊氏は先祖代々、遠江国井伊谷の国人領主であり、直政の祖父（または一族）井伊直盛は今川義元に仕えて桶狭間の戦いで戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ii clan had been kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lord) of Iinoya, Totoumi Province for generations and Naomasa&apos;s grandfather (of family) Naomori II died in the Battle of Okehazama, serving as a vassal of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ii clan had been kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords) of Iinoya, Totoumi Province for generations and Naomasa&apos;s grandfather Naomori II died at the Battle of Okehazama, serving as a vassal of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand what &quot;of family&quot; means.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ii clan had been kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords) of Iinoya, Totoumi Province for generations and Naomasa&apos;s grandfather (or one of Naomasa&apos;s family members) Naomori II died at the Battle of Okehazama, serving as a vassal of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>（または一族）の表現を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>父の井伊直親は、直政の生まれた翌、永禄5年（1562年）に謀反の嫌疑を受けて今川氏真に誅殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa&apos;s father Naochika II was killed by Ujizane IMAGAWA on suspicion of rebellion in 1562, the following year Naomasa had been born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1562, the year after Naomasa was born, his father Naochika II was killed by Ujizane IMAGAWA on suspicion of rebellion in.</e>
<cmt>ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1562, the year after Naomasa was born, his father Naochika II was killed by Ujizane IMAGAWA on suspicion of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>in 削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>直親の死によって、遺児直政（当時の名は虎松）は僅か2歳であったため、新たに直親の従兄妹に当たる祐圓尼が井伊直虎と名乗り、井伊氏の当主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Naochika died, a bereaved child Naomasa (Toramatsu at the time) was only 2 years old, therefore Yuenni, Naochika&apos;s cousin, became the family head, naming himself Naotora II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Naochika died, the bereaved child Naomasa (Toramatsu at the time) was only 2 years old, and so Yuenni, Naochika&apos;s cousin, became the family head, naming himself Naotora II.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Naochika died, the bereaved child Naomasa (Toramatsu at the time) was only 2 years old, and so Yuenni, Naochika&apos;s cousin, became the family head, naming himself Naotora II.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、直政の生母が今川氏の家臣である松下清景と再婚したため、直政は井伊の姓を失い、松下虎松と名乗るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Naomasa lost his family name Ii, naming himself Toramatsu MATSUSHITA because his real mother had married Kiyokage MATSUSHITA, a vassal of Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that Naomasa lost his family name Ii, and renamed himself Toramatsu MATSUSHITA because his real mother had married Kiyokage MATSUSHITA, a vassal of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that Naomasa lost his family name Ii, and renamed himself Toramatsu MATSUSHITA because his real mother had married Kiyokage MATSUSHITA, a vassal of the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、やがて井伊氏は井伊谷の所領を失い、まだ幼かった直政も今川氏に命を狙われる日々を送っていたが、新野親矩に救出されて、その後は養母である直虎に育てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Ii clan lost the territory of Iinoya and Imagawa clan became trying to kill still young Naomasa, however, he was saved by Chikanori NIINO, adopted by Naotora, his foster mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Ii clan lost the territory of Iinoya and the Imagawa clan tried to kill the still young Naomasa, but he was saved by Chikanori NIINO, and then adopted by Naotora, his foster mother.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Ii clan lost the territory of Iinoya and the Imagawa clan tried to kill the still young Naomasa, but he was saved by Chikanori NIINO, and then adopted by Naotora, his foster mother.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>天正3年（1575年）、徳川家康に見出され、井伊の姓に復帰を命じられるとともに虎松を万千代と改めて、井伊万千代と名乗るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1575, he was found by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and named himself Manchiyo II, changing his name from Toramatsu as he was ordered to change back his family name to Ii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1575, he was found by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and ordered to revert back to his family name Ii, so he changed his name from Toramatsu and renamed himself Manchiyo II.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1575, he was found by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and ordered to revert back to his family name Ii, so he changed his name from Toramatsu and renamed himself Manchiyo II.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらにかつての井伊氏の旧領である井伊谷を与えられ、家康の小姓として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he was adopted as page of Ieyasu, given Iinoya, which was former territory of Ii clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he was adopted as Ieyasu&apos;s page, and given Iinoya, which was a former Ii clan territory.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he was selected as Ieyasu&apos;s page, and given Iinoya, which was a former Ii clan territory.</e>
<cmt>養子と混同される恐れがあるのでadopt ⇒selectに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>同年、家督を代行していた養母の直虎が亡くなったため、正式に当主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he became family head formally as his foster mother Naotora died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he formally became the head of the family, as his foster mother Naotora died.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he formally became the head of the family, as his foster mother Naotora died.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>安土・桃山時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azuchi Momoyama Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azuchi Momoyama Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuchi Momoyama Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>直政は、高天神城の攻略を初めとする武田氏との戦いで数々の戦功（家康の寝所に忍び込んで来た武田軍の忍者の討ち取りなど）を立ててその名を轟かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa gained public reputation through many distinguished war service in battles against Takeda clan such as the conqueror of Takatenjin-jo Castle (killing ninja, who had been sneaking in to the bedroom of Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa gained public reputation through distinguished military service in battles against the Takeda clan, such as the capturing of Takatenjin-jo Castle, and for killing ninja who had been sneaking in to the bedroom of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>I am not sure about the placing of the parenthesis in this sentence. This translation suggests that Naomasa killed ninja sneaking into Ieyasu&apos;s bedroom during the capture of Takaenjin castle. As I understand it, the Japanese says that Naomasa received some sort of military award for various acts including killing the ninja, but does not say when this happensed. I think removing that parenthesis makes this clearer.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa gained public reputation through distinguished military service in battles against the Takeda clan, such as the capturing of Takatenjin-jo Castle, and for killing ninja who had been sneaking in to the bedroom of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>天正10年（1582年）22歳の時にようやく元服を終え、万千代を直政に改めて、井伊直政と名乗るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, he had finally done his genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) and began naming himself Naomasa II, changing Manchiyo to Naomasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, he finally celebrated his coming of age, and began naming himself Naomasa II, changing Manchiyo to Naomasa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, he finally celebrated his coming of age, and began naming himself Naomasa II, changing Manchiyo to Naomasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、この年に家康の養女で松平康親の娘である花（後の唐梅院）と結婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in the same year, he married Hana (later Tobaiin), who was an adopted daughter of Ieyasu and real daughter of Yasuchika MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he married Hana (later Tobaiin), who was an adopted daughter of Ieyasu and the real daughter of Yasuchika MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he married Hana (later Tobaiin), who was an adopted daughter of Ieyasu and the real daughter of Yasuchika MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その後、旗本先手役に任ぜられて、家康子飼いの武将である本多忠勝や榊原康政の同僚となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he was assigned as Hatamoto sakiteyaku (a hatamoto vassal of the shogun, who leads the way), thus became a comrade of Tadakatsu HONDA and Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was assigned as Hatamoto Sakiteyaku (a Hatamoto vassal of the shogun, who leads the way), thus becoming a comrade of Tadakatsu HONDA and Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was assigned as Hatamoto Sakiteyaku (a Hatamoto vassal of the shogun, who leads the way), thus becoming a comrade of Tadakatsu HONDA and Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>同年の本能寺の変では、家康の伊賀越えに従い、無事に滞在先の堺から三河国に帰還する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he returned to Mikawa Province from Sakai, where he had been staying, following Ieyasu&apos;s crossing over Iga in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he returned to Mikawa Province from Sakai, where he had been staying, following Ieyasu&apos;s crossing over Iga in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he returned to Mikawa Province from Sakai, where he had been staying, following Ieyasu&apos;s crossing over Iga in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>さらに武田氏が滅亡した後、後北条氏との交渉で徳川方の使者として政治的手腕としての実力を発揮し、家康が武田氏の旧領である信濃国、甲斐国を併合すると、武田家の旧臣達を多数与力に付属され、山県昌景の朱色の軍装を復活させて赤備え（いいのあかぞなえ）と呼ばれる精鋭部隊の大将となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the fall of Takeda clan, he showed his political ability as an envoy of Tokugawa side in negotiating with Gohojo clan and became the head of an elite troop called Akazonae (red arms) (Ii&apos;s Akazonae), bringing back the Shu-iro (Empire red) military dress of Masakage YAMAGATA, having been given many old retainer of Takeda clan as yoriki (a police sergeant) as Ieyasu merged Shinano Province and Kai Province, which were former territory of Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the fall of the Takeda clan, he showed his political ability as an envoy for Tokugawa by negotiating with the Gohojo clan, and became the head of an elite troop called Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms).</e>
<cmt>The original Japanese may be one sentence, but it is almost impossible to understand in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the fall of the Takeda clan, he showed his political ability as an envoy for Tokugawa by negotiating with the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外適用OK文の分け方を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、同時に井伊谷4万石に加増された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And his income went up to Iinoya 40,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His income went from Iinoya increased to 40,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>Does &quot;koku&quot; need to be explained?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His income went from Iinoya increased to 40,000 koku (koku is an old unit showing volume and 1 koku is about 180 liter) crop yields.</e>
<cmt>石の説明を用語共有を参考に追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>直政は家臣に非常に厳しく、少しでも戦で失敗をした者がいれば容赦せず処罰し、一軍の将となっても自ら先陣に立って戦うことを好むなど激烈な性格で、短所も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was so strict with his vassals that he relentlessly punished those who had made even a slight mistake in the battle, and had many defects with his character such as his love of fighting taking a lead by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was so strict with his vassals that he relentlessly punished those who had made even a slight mistake in battle, and had many other character defects, such as his love of leading battles from the front.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was so strict with his vassals that he relentlessly punished those who had made even a slight mistake in battle as well as being fond of leading battles from the front, and had many other character defects.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って語順を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのため、戦の際に陣に留まって、指揮を執ることはほとんどなく、井伊氏の筆頭家老である木俣守勝がその役目を果たしていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he seldom led a battle staying back in the camp, Morikatsu KIMATA, Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) of Ii clan, took such role instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he seldom stayed back in camp and led a battle, and this role was instead filled by Morikatsu KIMATA, Hitto karo (the head chief retainer) of the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he seldom stayed back in camp and led a battle, and this role was instead filled by Morikatsu KIMATA, Hitto karo (the head chief retainer) of the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、かえってそのような性格をしていたために大きな戦功を立てることができたのだとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said his such tendency made him able to perform distinguished war service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said this tendency made him able to perform distinguished war services.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said this tendency made him able to perform distinguished war services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>こうした性格から、「井伊の赤鬼」と言われ、諸大名から恐れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was terrified by territorial lords, called &apos; red ogre of Ii&apos; due to his such character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of his character, he was called the &quot;Red Ogre of Ii&quot;, and was greatly feared by other local territorial lords.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of his character, he was called the &quot;Red Ogre of Ii&quot;, and was greatly feared by other local territorial lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>天正12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いでは初めて井伊の赤備えを率いて池田恒興を討ち取るなどの武功を挙げ、一躍天下に名を知られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he made military exploits by killing Tsuneoki IKEDA, leading Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) for the first time, which made him renowned around the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he lead Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) for the first time and killed Tsuneoki IKEDA, making him renowned around the country.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he lead Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) for the first time and killed Tsuneoki IKEDA, making him renowned around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>直政の武力・政治的手腕は、豊臣秀吉にも高く評価され、家康と秀吉が和解すると、従五位下侍従・兵部省に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His military and political ability was highly valued by even Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and he was promoted to Jugoinoge; Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) jiju (a chamberlain) of Hyobusho (ministry of military) as Ieyasu came to a settlement with Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His military and political ability was highly valued by even Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and he was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) chamberlain of the ministry of the military, as Ieyasu reached a settlement with Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>too many Japanese terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His military and political ability was highly valued by even Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and he was promoted to Jugoinoge Juji (Chamberlain at Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) of Hyobusho (ministry of the military), as Ieyasu reached a settlement with Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>用語共有にしたがって位表示を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>天正13年（1585年）には、真田攻めにも出陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined also the attack of Sanada in 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also joined the attack on Sanada in 1585.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also joined the attack on Sanada in 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この後、井伊谷6万石に加増される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that his income was raised to 60,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that his income was raised to 60,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that his income was raised to 60,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>直政は新参ながら数々の戦功を評価され、天正18年（1590年）の小田原の役では数ある武将の中で唯一夜襲をかけて小田原城内にまで攻め込んだ武将としてその名を天下に轟かせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nomasa was acclaimed with his distinguished war services, though he was a come-lately, and he made his name as the only busho (Japanese military commander) among many who was attacked at night and invaded Odawara-jo Castle in the Siege of Odawara in 1590.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was acclaimed for his distinguished war services; though he was a newcomer, he made his name in the Siege of Odawara in 1590 by attacking Odawara-jo Castle at night and being the only commander to breach the castle&apos;s defenses.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was acclaimed for his distinguished war services; though he was a newcomer, he made his name in the Siege of Odawara in 1590 by attacking Odawara-jo Castle at night and being the only commander to breach the castle&apos;s defenses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後、後北条氏に代わって家康が江戸に入ると、直政は上野国箕輪12万石（群馬県高崎市）を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa was given Minowa, Kozuke Province 120,000 koku crop yields (Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture) as Ieyasu entered Edo, replacing Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was then given Minowa, Kozuke Province&apos;s 120,000 koku crop yields (Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture) as Ieyasu entered Edo and replaced the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was then given Minowa, Kozuke Province&apos;s 120,000 koku crop yields (Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture) as Ieyasu entered Edo and replaced the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この石高は徳川氏の家臣の中で最も高い石高である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was the highest Kokudaka (a system for determining land value for tribute purposes in the Edo period) among the vassals of Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was the highest Kokudaka (a system for determining land value for tribute purposes in the Edo period) among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was the highest Kokudaka (a system for determining land value for tribute purposes in the Edo period) among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>なお、徳川氏の家臣の中で10万石以上の領土を与えられた者は、直政、本多忠勝、榊原康政の3人だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only 3 vassals of Tokugawa clan were given the territories of 10,000 koku crop yields and more; Nomasa, Tadakatsu HONDA and Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only 3 vassals of the Tokugawa clan were given territories of 10,000 koku crop yields or more: Naomasa, Tadakatsu HONDA and Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only 3 vassals of the Tokugawa clan were given territories of 100,000 koku crop yields or more: Naomasa, Tadakatsu HONDA and Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA.</e>
<cmt>10,000⇒10,000</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）には、家康の命によって、箕輪城を廃し、南の和田城を改築して高崎城とし、和田を高崎と改めて高崎に移る（地名の由来に関しては群馬県高崎市の項目を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1598, he abandoned Minowa-jo Castle, rebuilt Wada-jo Castle in the south into Takasaki-jo Castle and moved into Takasaki, changing its name from Wada to Takasaki, by Ieyasu&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1598, under orders from Ieyasu, he abandoned Minowa-jo Castle, rebuilt Wada-jo Castle in the south into Takasaki-jo Castle and moved into Takasaki, changing its name from Wada to Takasaki.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1598, under orders from Ieyasu, he abandoned Minowa-jo Castle, rebuilt Wada-jo Castle in the south into Takasaki-jo Castle and moved into Takasaki, changing its name from Wada to Takasaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この時、箕輪城下に住んでいた民衆達も高崎に移っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people living in Minowa-jo Castle town moved into Takasaki at that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people living in Minowa-jo Castle town moved into Takasaki at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people living in Minowa-jo Castle town moved into Takasaki at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦いでは家康本軍に随行し、本多忠勝と共に東軍の軍監に任命され、東軍指揮の中心的存在となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he went along with Ieyasu&apos;s main troop and was assigned as Assistant Deputy General of Eastern Camp along with Tadakatsu HONDA, becoming the key player of commanding the Eastern Camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he accompanied Ieyasu&apos;s main force, and was assigned as Assistant Deputy General of the Eastern Camp along with Tadakatsu HONDA, becoming a key player in the command the Eastern Camp.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he accompanied Ieyasu&apos;s main force, and was assigned as Assistant Deputy General of the Eastern Camp along with Tadakatsu HONDA, becoming a key player in the command the Eastern Camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>同時に全国の諸大名を東軍につける工作を行い、また合戦においても家康の四男・松平忠吉（直政の娘婿）をよく補佐して忠吉と共に当初、東軍の先鋒を任されていた福島正則を差し置いて先鋒を務めた（本来ならば、直政も忠吉も軍令違反で処罰の対象になるが、家康は直政の駆け抜けを認めたため、処罰を命じなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He covertly made territorial lords around the country friends of Eastern Camp and assisted Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA (Naomasa&apos;s son-in-law) the 4th son of Ieyasu well, spearheading the Eastern Camp along with Tadayoshi instead of Masanori FUKUSHIMA, who was supposed to spearhead originally, in the battle (normally, Naoyoshi and Tadayoshi would have been punished for violation of a military order, however, Ieyasu didn&apos;t punish them admitting Naoyoshi&apos;s conduct).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He covertly made territorial lords from around the country friends of the Eastern Camp, and assisted Ieyasu&apos;s 4th son Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA (Naomasa&apos;s son-in-law) well in the battle by spearheading the Eastern Camp along with Tadayoshi instead of Masanori FUKUSHIMA, who was originally supposed to lead (normally, Naoyoshi and Tadayoshi would have been punished for violation of a military order, however, Ieyasu accepted Naoyoshi&apos;s conduct and didn&apos;t punish them).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He covertly made territorial lords from around the country friends of the Eastern Camp, and assisted Ieyasu&apos;s 4th son Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA (Naomasa&apos;s son-in-law) well in the battle by spearheading the Eastern Camp along with Tadayoshi instead of Masanori FUKUSHIMA, who was originally supposed to lead (normally, Naoyoshi and Tadayoshi would have been punished for violation of a military order, however, Ieyasu accepted Naoyoshi&apos;s conduct and didn&apos;t punish them).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>その後の直政と忠吉の行動に関しては2つの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two theories about how Nomasa and Tadayoshi acted after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two theories about how Nomasa and Tadayoshi acted after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two theories about how Nomasa and Tadayoshi acted after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>1つは宇喜多秀家の軍と小西行長の軍と戦ったと言う説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory had it that they fought against the army of Hideie UKITA and that of Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory states they fought against the armies of Hideie UKITA and Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory states they fought against the armies of Hideie UKITA and Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>もう1つは島津義弘の軍と戦ったと言う説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other had it they fought against the army of Yoshihiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other states they fought against the army of Yoshihiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other states they fought against the army of Yoshihiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>最近では島津義弘の軍と戦ったという説が有力であるとされている（直政は開戦当初から義弘の軍と戦う決意を固めていたとも言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter is widely accepted in recent days (it is also said Naomasa determined to fight against Yoshihiro&apos;s army in the beginning of the battle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter is widely accepted these days (it is also said Naomasa was determined to fight against Yoshihiro&apos;s army from the beginning of the battle).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter is widely accepted these days (it is also said Naomasa was determined to fight against Yoshihiro&apos;s army from the beginning of the battle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この戦いで義弘の家臣である島津豊久を討ち取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He killed Toyohisa SHIMAZU, a vassal of Yoshihiro, in this battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He killed Toyohisa SHIMAZU, a vassal of Yoshihiro, in this battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He killed Toyohisa SHIMAZU, a vassal of Yoshihiro, in this battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし、義弘の軍を追撃している際に義弘の軍の鉄砲隊が撃った銃弾が右肘関節（記述によっては右肩または左腕）に命中し、落馬してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he fell from the horse, having been shot in the right elbow (right shoulder or left arm depending on the document) by the musket troops of Yoshihiro&apos;s army during he was pursuing it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, whilst in pursuit of Yoshihiro&apos;s army, he was shot in the right elbow (right shoulder or left arm depending on the source document) by Yoshihiro&apos;s musket troops, and fell from his horse.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, whilst in pursuit of Yoshihiro&apos;s army, he was shot in the right elbow (right shoulder or left arm depending on the source document) by Yoshihiro&apos;s musket troops, and fell from his horse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの後は西軍の総大将を務めた毛利輝元との講和、山内一豊の土佐入国の援助、徳川氏と島津氏の和平交渉の仲立ち（直政自身は和平交渉が完全に終了する前に亡くなったので、その後の和平交渉の仲立ちの役目は本多正信に引き継がれた）などと言った戦後処理と江戸幕府の基礎固めに尽力し、これらの功によって、石田三成の旧領である近江国佐和山（滋賀県彦根市）18万石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, he was given Sawayama Omi Province (Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture), which was former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA, 180,000 koku crop yields for his services such as concluding a peace with Terumoto MORI, who was supreme commander of Western Camp, supporting Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI in entering Tosa Province and mediating a peace negotiation between Tokugawa clan and Shimazu clan (Naomasa died before the peace negotiation was completed and Masanobu HONDA took over his task) to heal the wounds of war and for his effort to build a foundation of Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara, he was given the 180,000 koku crop yield territory of Sawayama Omi Province (Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture), a former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA, for services including making peace with Terumoto MORI, supreme commander of the Western Camp, supporting Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI in entering Tosa Province, mediating peace negotiations between the Tokugawa clan and the Shimazu clan to heal the wounds of war (Naomasa died before the peace negotiations were completed and Masanobu HONDA took over his task), and for his efforts in laying the groundwork for the Edo Shoganate.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, he was given the 180,000 koku crop yield territory of Sawayama Omi Province (Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture), a former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA, for services including making peace with Terumoto MORI, supreme commander of the Western Camp, supporting Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI in entering Tosa Province, mediating peace negotiations between the Tokugawa clan and the Shimazu clan to heal the wounds of war (Naomasa died before the peace negotiations were completed and Masanobu HONDA took over his task), and for his efforts in laying the groundwork for the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Shoganate ⇒ Shogunate</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>また、この頃家康が直政・大久保忠隣・本多正信・榊原康政・本多忠勝・平岩親吉ら六人の重臣を呼び集め、自分の世嗣を誰にするか尋ねているが、直政はこの時自分の娘婿である忠吉を推している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, Ieyasu brought together his six chief vassals; Naomasa, Tadachika OKUBO, Masanobu HONDA, Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, Tadakatsu HONDA and Chikayoshi HIRAIWA, to ask who he ought to make his successor, and Naomasa recommended his son-in-law Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, Ieyasu brought together his six chief vassals; Naomasa, Tadachika OKUBO, Masanobu HONDA, Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, Tadakatsu HONDA and Chikayoshi HIRAIWA, to ask who he ought to make his successor, and Naomasa recommended his son-in-law Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Ieyasu brought together his six chief vassals; Naomasa, Tadachika OKUBO, Masanobu HONDA, Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, Tadakatsu HONDA and Chikayoshi HIRAIWA, to ask who he ought to make his successor, and Naomasa recommended his son-in-law Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし結果的には忠隣が推した徳川秀忠が世嗣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, who Tadachika recommended, ended up becoming a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, who Tadachika recommended, ended up becoming a successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, who Tadachika recommended, ended up becoming a successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>慶長7年（1602年）2月1日に、おそらくは長年の家康に対する奉公による過労と島津義弘の軍を追撃していた際に義弘の軍の鉄砲隊が撃った銃弾による鉄砲傷が癒えないまま、破傷風が元で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 1, 1602, he died probably from overwork by serving Ieyasu for many years and tetanus caused by the wound by bullet shot by musket troops of Yoshihiro&apos;s army while Naomasa was chasing it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa died on February 1, 1602, probably from overwork in serving Ieyasu for many years, and tetanus caused by the bullet would he received from Yoshihiro&apos;s musket troops while chasing his army.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa died on March 24, 1602, probably from overwork in serving Ieyasu for many years, and tetanus caused by the bullet wound he received from Yoshihiro&apos;s musket troops while chasing his army.</e>
<cmt>和暦⇒グレゴリオ暦にwould ⇒wound に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>直政が死去した当初、地元の民衆達の間で三成の亡霊が城下を彷徨っているという噂が広まって、このことが家康の耳に入り、家康の命によって、佐和山城を始めとする三成に関係する物の全てを廃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right after Naomasa&apos;s death, there was a rumor among the local people that a ghost of Mitsunari was wandering around the castle town, Ieyasu ordered to get rid of everything related to Mitsunari including Sawayama-jo Castle, having heard that rumor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Naomasa&apos;s death, there was a rumor among the local people that the ghost of Mitsunari was wandering around the castle town, and upon hearing this rumor Ieyasu ordered the disposal of everything related to Mitsunari, including Sawayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Naomasa&apos;s death, there was a rumor among the local people that the ghost of Mitsunari was wandering around the castle town, and upon hearing this rumor Ieyasu ordered the disposal of everything related to Mitsunari, including Sawayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>その後、彦根城の築城が開始されると同時に佐和山藩は廃藩となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Sawayama Domain became Haihan(abolition of feudal domains) as the construction Hikone-ji Castle started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Sawayama Domain became Haihan (an abolished feudal domain) as the construction Hikone-ji Castle started.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Sawayama Domain became Haihan (an abolished feudal domain) as the construction of Hikone-jo Castle started.</e>
<cmt>of　追加し、ji⇒joに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>代わってこの地には新たに彦根藩が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, the new domain Hikone Domain was put on that area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, the area was given the new name of the Hikone Domain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, the area was given the new name of the Hikone Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>それ以来、この地は明治時代になるまで井伊氏の藩として大いに栄えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the area had been thriving as the domain of Ii clan until Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that point onwards, the area thrived as the domain of the Ii clan until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that point onwards, the area thrived as the domain of the Ii clan until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>家康は、非常時に皇室を守るため、京都に近い彦根に代々勤皇の家柄である井伊家を配したと伝えられ、これを見ても徳川家から強い信頼を受けていたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Ieyasu put Ii clan, which had been pro-Imperial family for generations, in Hikone near Kyoto to protect Imperial family in a time of emergency, which suggests that Ii family gained the strong confidence of Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Ieyasu put the Ii clan, which had been a pro-Imperial family for generations, in Hikone near Kyoto to protect the Imperial family in times of emergency, which suggests that the Ii family had gained the strong confidence of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Ieyasu put the Ii clan, which had been a pro-Imperial family for generations, in Hikone near Kyoto to protect the Imperial family in times of emergency, which suggests that the Ii family had gained the strong confidence of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また、強敵である上杉氏の上洛を阻止するべく、家康家臣団中最強の軍勢を誇る直政を北陸と京都を結ぶ経路上に配したのだとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said Naoyasu, who boasted the strongest troop among the vassals of Ieyasu, was placed on the path between Hokuriku and Kyoto to prevent formidable enemy Uesugi clan from coming to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said Naoyasu, who boasted the strongest forces among the vassals of Ieyasu, was placed on the path between Hokuriku and Kyoto to prevent the formidable enemy the Uesugi clan from coming to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said Naoyasu, who boasted the strongest forces among the vassals of Ieyasu, was placed on the path between Hokuriku and Kyoto to prevent the formidable enemy the Uesugi clan from coming to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>なお、井伊氏の跡継ぎ問題に徳川氏が口出しをすることもあったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Tokugawa clan sometimes interfered in the matter of successor in Ii clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa clan sometimes interfered in the matter of succession in the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa clan sometimes interfered in the matter of succession in the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>実際、直政の次男である井伊直孝を彦根藩の第2代藩主（記述によっては第3代藩主）に命じたのは家康である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, it was Ieyasu who assigned Naotaka II, the second son of Naomasa, as the second lord of Hikone Domain (the third, depending on a document).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, it was Ieyasu who assigned Naotaka II, the second son of Naomasa, as the second lord of Hikone Domain (the third lord, depending on the source document).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, it was Ieyasu who assigned Naotaka II, the second son of Naomasa, as the second lord of Hikone Domain (the third lord, depending on the source document).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>家督は長男の井伊直勝が継いだが、病弱であったため、家康の命により、直勝は隠居して直勝の弟・井伊直孝が家督を継ぐこととなり、直孝の子孫が彦根藩主を継承することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Naokatsu II who succeeded as head of the family, however, his little brother Naotaka II took over and his descendants were to succeed the lord of the Hikone domain as Naokatsu retired due to his poor health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Naokatsu II who succeeded as head of the family, however, after Naokatsu retired due to poor health, his little brother Naotaka II took over and his descendants become the lord of the Hikone domain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Naokatsu II who succeeded as head of the family, however, after Naokatsu retired due to poor health, his little brother Naotaka II took over and his descendants became the lord of the Hikone domain.</e>
<cmt>become ⇒ became</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>直勝の子孫は、安中藩主→西尾藩主→掛川藩主→与板藩主として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of Naokatsu continued existing as the lord of Annaka Domain=&gt;the lord of Nishio Domain=&gt;the lord of Kakegawa Domain=&gt;the lord of Yoita Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of Naokatsu endured first as the lords of the Annaka Domain, then as the lords of the Nishio Domain, the lords of the Kakegawa Domain, and finally as the lords of the Yoita Domain.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not sure what the arrow marks mean here, but I assume they represent a time line.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of Naokatsu endured first as the lords of the Annaka Domain, then as the lords of the Nishio Domain, the lords of the Kakegawa Domain, and finally as the lords of the Yoita Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>直政の死後、直政の子孫は、佐和山城を廃して彦根城を築き、彦根藩18万石から大坂の役の後に5万石ずつ加増されて彦根藩35万石の大大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of Naomasa, who built Hikone-ji Castle after abandoned Sawayama-jo Castle and became Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater stipend) with Hikone Domain 350,000 koku crop yields raised from Hikone Domain 180,000 koku crop yields by being added 50,000 koku crop yields each time after Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka), had influence in the politics of Bakufu as heads of fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), producing 5 Tairo (chief minister) such as Naosuke II during 264 years of Edo period (there are arguments for and against whether Naotaka became Tairo or not).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka), the descendants of Naomasa, who built Hikone-ji Caster after abandoning Sawayama-jo Castle, became Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater stipend), with the koku crop yield of Hikone Domain increasing in 50,000 koku increments from 180,000 to 350,000.</e>
<cmt>Another overly complex sentence. I&apos;ve done my best to split it into two sentences while keeping the meaning of the original Japanese.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Naomasa&apos;s death, his descendants abandoned Sawayama-jo Castle and built Hikone-jo Castle, then after the Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka) their koku crop yield was gradually increased from 180,000 to 350,000 including incremental 50,000 koku three times, and they became Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater stipend) of Hikone Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外OKHikone-ji Caster ⇒ Hikone-jo Castle, また、５万石づつの加増だと計算が合いませんが、５万石づつを含む加増のようですのでそのように修正しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%BD%A6%E6%A0%B9%E8%97%A9</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>彼らは、譜代大名の筆頭として幕政に重きをなし、江戸時代264年間を通じて井伊直弼など5名の大老を輩出した（直孝が大老になったかどうかは賛否両論ある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They wielded influence in the politics of the Shoganate as heads of the fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), producing five Tairo (chief ministers), including Naosuke II, during the 264 years of the Edo period (there are arguments for and against whether Naotaka became Tairo or not).</e>
<cmt>Another overly complex sentence. I&apos;ve done my best to split it into two sentences while keeping the meaning of the original Japanese.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They wielded influence in the politics of the Shogunate as heads of the fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), producing five Tairo (chief ministers), including Naosuke II, during the 264 years of the Edo period (there are arguments for and against whether Naotaka became Tairo or not).</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外OKShoganate ⇒ Shogunate</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>しかし、直弼が安政6年（1859年）に安政の大獄を起こし、その後、安政7年（1860年）の桜田門外の変で暗殺された後、10万石の減封を受け、徳川氏から冷遇されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tokugawa clan diminished Ii clan&apos;s territory of 100,000 koku crop yields as punishment and began to give them the cold shoulder after Naosuke carried out Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate) in 1859 and was assassinated in the Sakuradamongai Incident in 1860.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Tokugawa clan reduced the Ii clan&apos;s territory by 100,000 koku crop yields as punishment and began to give them the cold shoulder after Naosuke carried out Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate) in 1859, and was assassinated in the Sakuradamongai Incident in 1860.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Tokugawa clan reduced the Ii clan&apos;s territory by 100,000 koku crop yields as punishment and began to give them the cold shoulder after Naosuke carried out Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate) in 1859, and was assassinated in the Sakuradamongai Incident in 1860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>その後、戊辰戦争では最初は旧幕府軍の先鋒を務めたが、戦いの最中に新政府軍に寝返った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Ii clan spearheaded former army of bakufu in Boshin War and went over to the side of new government army during the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Ii clan spearheaded an army of former bakufu in the Boshin War, and went over to the side of the new government army during the war.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Ii clan spearheaded an army of former bakufu in the Boshin War, and went over to the side of the new government army during the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>この時、井伊隊に属していた兵の全員が井伊氏の象徴とも言える井伊の赤備えの兜や鎧を始めとする全ての装備品を脱ぎ捨てたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said all the soldiers of Ii troop took off every equipment including helmets and armours of Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms), a symbol of Ii clan, at that moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when that happened all Ii&apos;s troops took off every piece of equipment, including helmets and armour, that displayed Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms), the symbol of the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when that happened all Ii&apos;s troops took off every piece of equipment, including helmets and armour, that displayed Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms), the symbol of the Ii clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>明治時代になると、伯爵となり、華族に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ii clan was raised to the peerage becoming a count in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ii clan was raised to the peerage, becoming counts in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ii clan was raised to the peerage, becoming counts in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>家康との衆道による関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homosexual relationship between Ieyasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homosexual relationship with Ieyasu</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homosexual relationship with Ieyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>天正3年（1575年）のある日、家康は鷹狩りに出かけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day in 1575, Ieyasu went to doing falconry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day in 1575, Ieyasu went out hawking.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day in 1575, Ieyasu went out hawking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>すると、家康はそこにいた少年のあまりの美しさに本気で惚れ込んでしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Ieyasu fell for the beauty of a boy who was there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu fell for the beauty of a boy who was there.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu fell for the beauty of a boy who was there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>この少年こそが、後の直政（当時の名前は虎松）だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That boy was none other than later Naomasa (Toramatsu at that time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That boy was none other than Naomasa (Toramatsu at that time).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That boy was none other than Naomasa (Toramatsu at that time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>その後、家康は直政がかつて桶狭間の戦いの後に自分と内通していた疑いで殺害された井伊直親の実子であることを知り、直政を自分の小姓（児小姓）として取り立て、衆道相手として深く寵愛したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Ieyasu took Naomasa as his pageboy (child page) and love him as a partner of homosexuality, having known Naomasa was a real son of Naochika II, who had been killed on suspicion of collaborating with him after the Battle of Okehazama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, knowing that Naomasa was really the son of Naochika II, who had been killed on suspicion of collaborating with him after the Battle of Okehazama, Ieyasu took Naomasa as his pageboy (child page) and loved him as a sexual partner.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, knowing that Naomasa was really the son of Naochika II, who had been killed on suspicion of collaborating with him after the Battle of Okehazama, Ieyasu took Naomasa as his pageboy (child page) and loved him as a sexual partner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>当時の武士階級では衆道は武士の嗜みともいわれるほど一般的であり、主君の寵童出身であることは出世への近道でもあったが（その例として織田信長‐前田利家など、上杉景勝‐清野長範、伊達政宗‐片倉重綱・只野作十郎が挙げられる）、直政は衆道をあまり好まなかった家康が唯一愛した男性だとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Naomasa was the only man Ieyasu, who didn&apos;t much like homosexuality, loved, though homosexuality was so common in samurai society at that time that it was regarded as one of samurai&apos;s accomplishments and being loved by a lord was the fastest way to succeed (for example Nobunaga ODA and Toshiie MAEDA, Kagekatsu UESUGI and Naganori KIYONO, Masamune DATE and Shigetsuna KATAKURA/Sakujuro TADANO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Naomasa was the only man Ieyasu, who didn&apos;t much like homosexuality, loved; though homosexuality was so common in samurai society at that time that it was regarded as one of a samurai&apos;s accomplishments, and being loved by a lord was the fastest way to advance (other examples include Nobunaga ODA and Toshiie MAEDA, Kagekatsu UESUGI and Naganori KIYONO, Masamune DATE and Shigetsuna KATAKURA/Sakujuro TADANO).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Naomasa was the only man Ieyasu, who didn&apos;t much like homosexuality, loved; though homosexuality was so common in samurai society at that time that it was regarded as one of a samurai&apos;s accomplishments, and being loved by a lord was the fastest way to advance (other examples include Nobunaga ODA and Toshiie MAEDA, Kagekatsu UESUGI and Naganori KIYONO, Masamune DATE and Shigetsuna KATAKURA/Sakujuro TADANO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>直政の忠義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Loyalty of Naomasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa&apos;s Loyalty</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa&apos;s Loyalty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>直政は家康に対する忠義心が最も篤かったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Naomasa had the strongest loyalty to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Naomasa had the strongest loyalty to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Naomasa had the strongest loyalty to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>直政は常に家康の片腕として彼の下を離れず、戦だけでなく、政治や私生活の面でも全力で家康のために働き続けたことがその証拠と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nomasa&apos;s serving fully for Ieyasu not only in battles but also in politics and private life, not leaving Ieyasu always as his right hand confirms that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Naomasa served Ieyasu not only in battles, but also in politics and private life, shows that he never left Ieyasu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Naomasa served Ieyasu not only in battles, but also in politics and private life, shows that he never left Ieyasu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>また、家康を裏切り、秀吉の下に寝返って家臣となった石川数正には激しい憎しみを抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he held a deep grudge against Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, who had become a vassal of Hideyoshi, betraying Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held a deep grudge against Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, who betrayed Ieyasu and became a vassal of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held a deep grudge against Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, who betrayed Ieyasu and became a vassal of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>実際に直政は、自分の怒りを数正にぶつけたことがあった（詳細は「人物・逸話」の項目を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa actually released his anger on Kazumasa once (refer to &apos; Personality and anecdotes&apos; for further information).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa actually vented his anger at Kazumasa on one occasion (see &quot;Personality and Anecdotes&quot; for further information).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa actually vented his anger at Kazumasa on one occasion (see &quot;Personality and Anecdotes&quot; for further information).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>なお、家康自身も直政の武力や政治的手腕における才能を高く評価し、直政を我が子または恋人のような扱いをして見守り続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu himself continued watching over and treated Naomasa as if he had been Ieyasu&apos;s son or lover, thinking much of Naomasa&apos;s military power and ability of politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu thought much of Naomasa&apos;s military power and political ability, and continued to watch over and treat Naomasa as if he was his own son or lover.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu thought much of Naomasa&apos;s military power and political ability, and continued to watch over and treat Naomasa as if he was his own son or lover.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これらのようなことから、直政は家康に最も厚く信頼されていた家臣だとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears Naomasa was the vassal trusted by Ieyasu most from those episodes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From examples such as these, we can see that Naomasa was Ieyasu&apos;s most trusted vassal.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From examples such as these, we can see that Naomasa was Ieyasu&apos;s most trusted vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>井伊の赤備え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>天正10年（1582年）の後北条氏との講和によって、武田氏の旧臣達約120人と家康の旗本の一部が配属されたことから始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It began with about 120 former vassals of Takeda clan and part of hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of Ieyasu&apos;s being attached by a peace treaty with Gohojo clan in 1582.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It began in 1582, when a peace treaty with the Gohojo clan led to about 120 former vassals of the Takeda clan and part of Ieyasu&apos;s hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) being combined.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It began in 1582, when a peace treaty with the Gohojo clan led to about 120 former vassals of the Takeda clan and part of Ieyasu&apos;s hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) being combined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>この時、直政は兜や鎧を始めとする戦で使用する全ての装備品を赤色で統一させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Naomasa made every equipment used in battle such as helmets and armours uniformly red in color.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Naomasa had all equipment used in battle, such as helmets and armor, colored uniformly red.</e>
<cmt>I made this sentence passive because I doubt that Naomasa colored all the armor himself.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Naomasa had all equipment used in battle, such as helmets and armor, colored uniformly red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>これはかつて赤備えの将であった山県昌景の意志を継ぐという意味もあったが、その他に赤色だと目立ちやすく、戦の最中にどこに自分の部下達がいるのかが一目で分かるという意味もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That carried the purpose of succeeding the wish of Masakage YAMAGATA, former head of Akazonae, and also meant to make it easy to find his soldiers location at a glance in a battle, being prominent because of red.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for this was to fulfill the wish of Masakage YAMAGATA, former head of the Akazonae, and also because red stands out, making it easy for him to know his soldiers location at a glance during battle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for this was to fulfill the wish of Masakage YAMAGATA, former head of the Akazonae, and also because red stands out, making it easy for him to know his soldiers location at a glance during battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>初陣の小牧・長久手の戦いでは大いに活躍し、徳川・織田連合軍の約10倍近くの兵を有していた羽柴軍の総大将である羽柴秀吉（後の豊臣秀吉）やその配下の武将達もこの井伊の赤備えには、大変手こずったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) made such great success in its uijin (first battle) Battle of Komaki-Nagakute that Hideyoshi HASHIBA, who was supreme commander of Hashiba army, which consisted of nearly 10 times as many soldiers as the allied forces of Tokugawa and Oda, and his busho (Japanese military commander) were said to have trouble with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) had such great success in their first engagement at the Battle of Komaki-Nagakute that Hideyoshi HASHIBA, supreme commander of a Hashiba army that consisted of nearly 10 times as many soldiers as the allied forces of Tokugawa and Oda, and his busho (Japanese military commanders) were said to have trouble with them.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) had such great success in their first engagement at the Battle of Komaki-Nagakute that Hideyoshi HASHIBA, supreme commander of a Hashiba army that consisted of nearly 10 times as many soldiers as the allied forces of Tokugawa and Oda, and his busho (Japanese military commanders) were said to have trouble with them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この頃から井伊の赤備えは、『戦国屈指の精鋭部隊』または、『徳川家臣団最強の部隊』と見なされ、諸大名に恐れられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) had become teryffied by territorial lords regarded as &apos; the elitest troop in Sengoku&apos; or &apos; the strongest troop of Tokugawa vassals&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) became greatly feared by other territorial lords, and came to be called &quot;the most elite force in the Sengoku&quot; or &quot;the strongest of Tokugawa&apos;s vassals&apos; forces&quot;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) became greatly feared by other territorial lords, and came to be called &quot;the most elite force in the Sengoku&quot; or &quot;the strongest of Tokugawa&apos;s vassals&apos; forces&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>以後、井伊氏の軍装は幕末まで赤備えを基本とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Akazonae (red arms) had been the basic military dress of Ii clan until the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that time onwards, Akazonae (red arms) became the basic military dress of the Ii clan until the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that time onwards, Akazonae (red arms) became the basic military dress of the Ii clan until the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>主な家臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main vassals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main Vassals</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Vassals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>木俣守勝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morikatsu KIMATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morikatsu KIMATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morikatsu KIMATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>近藤秀用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidemochi KONDO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidemochi KONDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidemochi KONDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="90">
<j>近藤康用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasumochi KONDO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasumochi KONDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasumochi KONDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="91">
<j>西郷正友</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatomo SAIGO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatomo SAIGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatomo SAIGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="92">
<j>菅沼忠久</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadahisa SUGANUMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadahisa SUGANUMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadahisa SUGANUMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="93">
<j>鈴木重好</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeyoshi SUZUKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeyoshi SUZUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeyoshi SUZUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality and anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>直政がまだ家康の小姓だった頃、大久保忠世の陣中に招かれて他の若手の武将とともに芋汁を振舞われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Naomasa was still Ieyasu&apos;s pageboy, he was invited to camp of Tadayo OKUBO and presented with potato soup along with other young busho (Japanese military commander).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Naomasa was still Ieyasu&apos;s pageboy, he was invited along with other young busho (Japanese military commanders) to Tadayo OKUBO&apos;s camp and presented with potato soup.</e>
<cmt>ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Naomasa was still Ieyasu&apos;s pageboy, he was invited along with other young busho (Japanese military commanders) to Tadayo OKUBO&apos;s camp and presented with potato soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>だが、戦場の事であり味噌は糠味噌、具は芋の葉や茎が混ざったものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The miso (bean paste) was salted rice-bran paste and the leaf or stem of potatoes were used in the soup because it was a battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because it was a battlefield, the miso (bean paste) was salted rice-bran paste and the leaves or stems of potatoes were used in the soup.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because it was a battlefield, the miso (bean paste) was salted rice-bran paste and the leaves or stems of potatoes were used in the soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>だが、他の若い武将は芋汁を食べているのに、直政の食は進まない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa had difficulty eating potato soup, though other young busho (Japanese military commander) were eating it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa had difficulty eating the potato soup, even though the other young busho (Japanese military commanders) were eating it.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa had difficulty eating the potato soup, even though the other young busho (Japanese military commanders) were eating it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>忠世がどうしたのかを尋ねると、直政は「醤油はありませんか」と応じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadayo asked what was wrong with Naomasa, he replied &apos; Do you have soy sauce?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tadayo asked what was wrong with Naomasa, he replied, &quot;Do you have any soy sauce?&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tadayo asked what was wrong with Naomasa, he replied, &quot;Do you have any soy sauce?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>このことを聞いた他の武将達は「ここは戦場だと言うのにそのような物があるわけがないだろう」と口々に直政を非難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other busho (Japanese military commander) criticized Naomasa saying &apos;How could we have soy sauce in battlefield?&apos;, having heard what Naomasa said.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having heard what Naomasa said, the other busho (Japanese military commanders) criticized Naomasa saying &quot;How could we have soy sauce on a battlefield?&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having heard what Naomasa said, the other busho (Japanese military commanders) criticized Naomasa saying &quot;How could we have soy sauce on a battlefield?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>忠世は直政に「同僚の者たちは皆、同じものを食べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayo said to Naomasa &apos;All your comrades eat same food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayo said to Naomasa, &apos;All your comrades eat the same food.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayo said to Naomasa, &apos;All your comrades eat the same food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>兵士達はこのような物でも満足には食べられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are soldiers who cannot eat even such food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are soldiers who cannot eat enough of such food.</e>
<cmt>I think this is a more accurate translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are soldiers who cannot eat enough of such food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>ましてや農民達の中にはもっと苦しい生活をしている者達もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, many peasants live harder life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, many peasants live a harder life.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, many peasants live a harder life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>一軍の将になりたいのであれば、このことを絶対に忘れてはならぬぞ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You should never forget about that, if you want to become a commander of an army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You should never forget about that, if you want to become a commander of an army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You should never forget about that, if you want to become a commander of an army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>そのためにここへ呼んだのだ」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I have invited you to make you learn that.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I have invited you here to make you learn that.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Lines 54 through 58 are all part of the same quote, so I&apos;m not sure if there should be only one set of speech marks, or speech marks for every line.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I have invited you here to make you learn that.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>新参でありながらも若くして選抜され、部下にも厳しかった直政に対する周囲の目は厳しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others treated Naomasa harshly because he was selected young, though he was a newcomer, and was strict with his subordinates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others treated Naomasa harshly though he was a newcomer because he was selected young,, and was strict with his subordinates.</e>
<cmt>ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others treated Naomasa harshly because he was exceptionally selected although he was a newcomer and young, and also he was strict with his subordinates.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>これ以後、直政はよりいっそう自分にも部下にも厳しくなっていくのである（ちなみに、ここで伝えられる醤油は、味噌を作る際の「たまり」であるため、現在の醤油とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he became stricter with himself and his subordinates (and soy sauce used here was different from today&apos;s soy sauce, it was &apos;rich soy sauce&apos; used to make miso paste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he became stricter with himself and his subordinates (Incidentally, the soy sauce referred to here was &apos;rich soy sauce&apos; used to make miso paste, which was different from today&apos;s soy sauce.</e>
<cmt>ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he became stricter with himself and his subordinates.</e>
<cmt>160項と161項の文の区切りかたが変ですので、区切りなおしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>現在のような醤油が作られるようになったのは江戸時代になってからである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce of today&apos;s hadn&apos;t been made until Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern soy sauce didn&apos;t start being made until the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Incidentally, the soy sauce referred to here was &apos;rich soy sauce&apos; used to make miso paste, which was different from today&apos;s soy sauce, and modern soy sauce didn&apos;t start being made until the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>160項と161項の文の区切りかたが変ですので、区切りなおしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="107">
<j>直政は、三傑・徳川四天王・徳川十六神将の一人とされており、家康の天下取りを全力で支えた功臣として、現在も顕彰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa is regarded as one of three outstanding people, Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu), Tokugawa- Juroku Shinsho (sixteen protective deity generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu) and is honored even today as a meritorious vassal supporting fully Ieyasu in taking the reins of government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa is regarded as one of three outstanding people, one of the Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu), one of the Tokugawa-Juroku Shinsho (sixteen protective deity generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu), and is honored even today as a meritorious vassal who fully supported Ieyasu in taking the reins of government.</e>
<cmt>There is nothing in the original Japanese, but I think &quot;three outstanding people&quot; needs explaining. A reader is bound to wonder who these people were, and why they were outstanding.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa is regarded as one of the Tokugawa&apos;s sanketsu (three outstanding people supporting Tokugawa Ieyasu), one of the Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu), one of the Tokugawa-Juroku Shinsho (sixteen protective deity generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu), and is honored even today as a meritorious vassal who fully supported Ieyasu in taking the reins of government.</e>
<cmt>校正者の指摘に応じ、三傑の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>その一例として、滋賀県彦根市では、直政が現在の彦根市の発展の基礎を築いたということを顕彰して、『井伊直政公顕彰式』という祭典が毎年行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the festival called &quot;Naomasa II kensho (honor a person publicly for an unrecognized good deed) ceremony&quot; is held every year in Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture to honor Naomasa&apos;s having built the foundation of development of current Hikone City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the festival called &quot;Naomasa II kensho (honor a person publicly for an unrecognized good deed) ceremony&quot; is held every year in Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture to honor Naomasa for having founded what is now Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the festival called &quot;Naomasa II kensho (honor a person publicly for an unrecognized good deed) ceremony&quot; is held every year in Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture to honor Naomasa for having founded what is now Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="109">
<j>かつて、家康が豊臣秀吉の生母である大政所を人質にとった際に直政は大政所の警護を任されていたことがあった（この時、大政所やそれに従ってきた数多くの女性達も家康のように直政に惚れ込んだと言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once, Naomasa was in charge of guarding Omandokoro (Mother of the chief Adviser to the Emperor), a real mother of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, when Ieyasu held her as a hostage (it is said Omandokoro and many women following her fell for Naomasa like Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, Naomasa was in charge of guarding Omandokoro (Mother of the chief Adviser to the Emperor), the real mother of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, when Ieyasu held her hostage (it is said Omandokoro and many of her female followers fell for Naomasa much like they did Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, Naomasa was in charge of guarding Omandokoro (Mother of the chief Adviser to the Emperor), the real mother of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, when Ieyasu held her hostage (it is said Omandokoro and many of her female followers fell for Naomasa much like they did Ieyasu).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>直政の手厚い保護に秀吉は大変喜び、自ら茶を立てて直政の疲れを癒そうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi was so happy with Naomasa&apos;s careful protection that he himself prepared tea for Naomasa to heal his fatigue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi was so happy with Naomasa&apos;s careful protection that he himself prepared tea for Naomasa to heal his fatigue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi was so happy with Naomasa&apos;s careful protection that he himself prepared tea for Naomasa to heal his fatigue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>そこには、かつては家康の家臣であったが、今は秀吉の下に寝返って家臣となった石川数正も同席していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And there was also Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, who had once a vassal of Ieyasu and went over to Hideyoshi side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, who had once been a vassal of Ieyasu, but went over to Hideyoshi&apos;s side, was also present.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, who had once been a vassal of Ieyasu, but went over to Hideyoshi&apos;s side, was also present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>このことに我慢ができなくなった直政は数正に向かって、「先祖より仕えた主君に背いて殿下に従う臆病者と同席すること、固くお断り申す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;I refuse to sit with that coward who serves you, having betrayed the lord his family had been serving for generations.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa could not stand it, and yelled at Kazumasa, &quot;I refuse to sit with that coward who serves you after betraying the lord his family had been serving for generations.&quot;</e>
<cmt>169 and 170 should be one sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa could not stand it, and yelled at Kazumasa, &quot;I refuse to sit with that coward who serves you after betraying the lord his family had been serving for generations.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>」と怒鳴った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">yelled Naomasa, who couldn&apos;t stand it, at Kazumasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">yelled Naomasa, who couldn&apos;t stand it, at Kazumasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">yelled Naomasa, who couldn&apos;t stand it, at Kazumasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>これはいかに直政が家康に対して忠義を尽くしていたかを伺える何よりの証拠と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It makes it clear that Naomasa had so much faithful loyalty to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This clearly shows how much faithful loyalty Naomasa had to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This clearly shows how much faithful loyalty Naomasa had to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>秀吉自身は直政が数正に対してどのような態度を見せるのかを知りたくて数正を同席させたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi deliberately made Kazumasa present there to know how Naomasa would react.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hideyoshi deliberately made Kazumasa be there to see how Naomasa would react.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi deliberately made Kazumasa be there to see how Naomasa would react.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>なお、数正が秀吉の下に去ったのは天正13年（1585年）で、この事件が起こったのはその1年後の天正14年（1586年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in 1585 when Kazumasa went over to Hideyoshi, and one year later, in 1586, that incident occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident occurred in 1586, one year after Kazumasa went over to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident occurred in 1586, one year after Kazumasa went over to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="117">
<j>先祖代々、徳川氏の家臣ではない直政を家康が重用した理由は、直政が武勇だけではなく、知略や政治にも長けていたことや家康の四男・松平忠吉との姻戚関係のことももちろんだが、最大の理由は、直政があまり衆道を好まなかった家康に本気で惚れ込まれるほどの美男子だったからだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the biggest reason why Ieyasu gave important posts to Naomasa, whose family had not been serving Tokugawa clan, was because Naomasa was such a beautiful man that Ieyasu, who didn&apos;t much like homosexuality, fell for him seriously, as well as because of Naomasa&apos;s great ability in tactical maneuver and politics not only in military prowess and his matrimonial relation with Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA, the fourth son of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the reason why Ieyasu gave important posts to Naomasa, whose family had not been serving the Tokugawa clan, was not only because of Naomasa&apos;s great ability in tactical maneuvers and politics, his military prowess, nor his relation by marriage to Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA, the fourth son of Ieyasu, but was chiefly because Naomasa was such a beautiful man that Ieyasu fell for him seriously, despite his general dislike of homosexuality.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the reason why Ieyasu gave important posts to Naomasa, whose family had not been serving the Tokugawa clan, was not only because of Naomasa&apos;s great ability in tactical maneuvers and politics, his military prowess, nor his relation by his daughter&apos;s marriage to Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA, the fourth son of Ieyasu, but was chiefly because Naomasa was such a beautiful man that Ieyasu fell for him seriously, despite his general dislike of homosexuality.</e>
<cmt>原文にはありませんが、結婚したのは直政ではなく娘なので　his daughter&apos;sを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="118">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの後、直政は石田三成の旧領を家康から賜ったが、三成は善政を敷いていたため、領民の信望が厚かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa was given the former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA from Ieyasu after the Battle of Sekigahara, however, Mitsunari had great prestige among people of the domain because of his good government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was given the former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA from Ieyasu after the Battle of Sekigahara; however, Mitsunari had been held in great regard by the people of the domain because of his good government.</e>
<cmt>I think this should be two sentences with a break where I have put the semi-colon.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was given the former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA from Ieyasu after the Battle of Sekigahara; however, Mitsunari had been held in great regard by the people of the domain because of his good government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>直政はこのことを熟知していたため、佐和山城に入城すると、民政は三成のやり方を踏襲すると触れを出し、領民が三成を弔うことも黙認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa, who knew that well, informed that he would follow the same way as Mitsunari&apos;s in civil government and he gave silent approval of people&apos;s mourning for Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa, who knew that well, announced that he would follow Mitsunari&apos;s style of civil government, and he gave silent approval of people&apos;s mourning for Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa, who knew that well, announced that he would follow Mitsunari&apos;s style of civil government, and he gave silent approval of people&apos;s mourning for Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>そのため、領民の心をつかむことに成功したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that way, he won the hearts and minds of people of the domain successfully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that way, he successfully won the hearts and minds of people of the domain.</e>
<cmt>ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that way, he successfully won the hearts and minds of people of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>また、三成が処刑される前、直政は三成の面倒を任されており、あまり三成に好感を抱いていなかったが、三成を手厚く保護したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa was in charge of taking care of Mitsunari before he was executed and it is said Naomasa gave him careful protection despite his dislike to Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was in charge of taking care of Mitsunari before he was executed, and it is said Naomasa gave him careful protection despite his dislike of Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was in charge of taking care of Mitsunari before he was executed, and it is said Naomasa gave him careful protection despite his dislike of Mitsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="122">
<j>直政は徳川家中の中では外様でありながら、徳川家臣随一の領国を与えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa was given the biggest territory among the vassals of Tokugawa clan, though he was tozama (outsider) in Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was given the biggest territory among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan, even though he was a tozama (outsider) of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was given the biggest territory among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan, even though he was a tozama (outsider) of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>このため、三河譜代からの家臣から嫉妬、反発されたが、直政はそれに対して常に家康に奉公することで退けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, Naomasa was envied and opposed by Mikawa fudai (hereditary vassals), however, he set that aside by always serving Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, Naomasa was envied and opposed by Mikawa fudai (hereditary vassals), but he dismissed this by always serving Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, Naomasa was envied and opposed by Mikawa fudai (hereditary vassals), but he dismissed this by always serving Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>ただし、そのあまりに厳しすぎる奉公ぶり、そして直政自身は気性が激しく、家臣のわずかな失敗も許さずに手討ちにすることも少なくなかったため、「人斬り兵部」とも称されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said he was called also &apos;Hyobu cutting people down&apos; because of his serving Ieyasu too strictly and his often executing his vassals, not forgiving any slight mistake, since Naomasa himself was quick-tempered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said he was also called &apos;Hyobu cutting people down&apos; because he was quick-tempered and served Ieyasu too strictly, often executing his vassals and not forgiving even the slightest mistake.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said he was also called &apos;Hyobu cutting people down&apos; because he was quick-tempered and served Ieyasu too strictly, often executing his vassals and not forgiving even the slightest mistake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>しかし、政治的手腕は非常に優れていたため、箕輪城主の頃は、城下の民衆から慕われていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said he was loved by the people in castle town when he was a lord of Minowa-jo Castle for his great ability in politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said he was loved for his great ability in politics by the people of the castle town when he was lord of Minowa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said he was loved for his great ability in politics by the people of the castle town when he was lord of Minowa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="126">
<j>大身になる前の頃、直政がどうしても強請るので家康が数ある愛馬の中から、特に栗毛の名馬を直政に与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometime before Naomasa became Taishin (big feudal lord), Ieyasu gave him chesnut fine horse especially selected from Ieyasu&apos;s favorite horses because Naomasa was insistently asking for.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometime before Naomasa became Taishin (great feudal lord), Ieyasu gave him a fine chestnut horse specially selected from Ieyasu&apos;s favorite horses because Naomasa had been insistently asking for it.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;great&quot; is better than &quot;big&quot; for Taishin. &quot;Big&quot; suggests he was a large man.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometime before Naomasa became Taishin (great feudal lord), Ieyasu gave him a fine chestnut horse specially selected from Ieyasu&apos;s favorite horses because Naomasa had been insistently asking for it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>これを聞いた本多重次がわざわざ直政のいるところで、「あのような名馬を万千代みたいな子倅にくれてやるとは、殿も目が暗くなったのではないか」といった意味のことを放言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetsugu HONDA, having heard that, made irresponsible remark deliberately in presence of Naomasa &apos;Our lord must have been blinded in judgement to have given such a fine horse to a brat like Manchiyo&apos; or words to that effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having heard that, Shigetsugu HONDA deliberately made the irresponsible remark, &quot;Our lord must have been blinded in judgement to have given such a fine horse to a brat like Manchiyo,&quot; (or words to that effect) in the presence of Naomasa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having heard that, Shigetsugu HONDA deliberately made the irresponsible remark, &quot;Our lord must have been blinded in judgement to have given such a fine horse to a brat like Manchiyo,&quot; (or words to that effect) in the presence of Naomasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>年が下って家康が関東に移ると直政は家中一の大身となったのに対し、重次は3000石しか与えられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Naomasa was promoted to Taishin (big feudal lord) of the family as Ieyasu moved to Kanto while Shigetsugu was given only 3000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Naomasa was promoted to Taishin (great feudal lord) of the family when Ieyasu moved to Kanto, while Shigetsugu was given only 3000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>see line 187 comment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Naomasa was promoted to Taishin (great feudal lord) of the family when Ieyasu moved to Kanto, while Shigetsugu was given only 3000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>そして、大身になった直政は重次と顔を合わせた時、「昔、殿が名馬を下さった時に子倅だの何だのと馬鹿になされましたが、このような大身になれたのは、名馬に違わぬ働きをしたからでございます。目が暗かったのは本多殿の方でありましたな」と言い放った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Naomasa, who had now become Taishin (big feudal lord), blatantly said to Shigetsugu &apos; I managed to become Taishin because I had served as well as a fine horse, though you treated me like a fool calling me brat or something when the lord gave me the fine horse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Naomasa, who had now become Taishin (great feudal lord), blatantly said, &quot;I managed to become Taishin because I served as well as a fine horse, even though you treated me like a fool, calling me brat or something, when the lord gave me that famous horse. It was you who were blind,&quot; when he met Shigetsugu.</e>
<cmt>I have combined lines 190 and 191 because line 191 does not make sense on its own. However, I am not sure if this fits with established style. There are two sentences within the speech marks, but they are quotes functioning as component parts of a larger sentence, so this could be considered as one single sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Naomasa, who had now become Taishin (great feudal lord), blatantly said, &quot;I managed to become Taishin because I served as well as a fine horse, even though you treated me like a fool, calling me brat or something, when the lord gave me that famous horse. It was you who were blind,&quot; when he met Shigetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>このことから、直政は人に言われたことをすぐ根に持つタイプ、すなわち負けず嫌いであったということが分かる（「井伊年譜」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From that episode, it is clear Naomasa held a grudge easily about what he had been said or he was a person who hated to lose (&apos;chronological list of the main events of Ii clan&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that episode, it is clear that Naomasa either held grudges easily about what people said about him, or he was a person who hated to lose (&apos;chronological list of the main events of the Ii clan&apos;).</e>
<cmt>I have no idea what the function of the parenthesis is in this sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that episode, it is clear that Naomasa either held grudges easily about what people said about him, or he was a person who hated to lose (&apos;II Nenpu&apos; (The Chronological List of Main Events of the Ii clan)).</e>
<cmt>文末、出典であることがわかるように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="131">
<j>毛利家の重臣である小早川隆景は直政の武勇・政治的手腕に関して「直政は小身なれど、天下の政道相成るべき器量あり」と評価したことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was a senior vassal of Mori clan, once praised Naomasa&apos;s military prowess and political ability saying &apos; Even though Naomasa is from low status, he has the potential to become a ruler of the world&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was a senior vassal of the Mori clan, once praised Naomasa&apos;s military prowess and political ability by saying, &quot;Even though Naomasa is from a low status family, he has the potential to become the ruler of the world&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, who was a senior vassal of the Mori clan, once praised Naomasa&apos;s military prowess and political ability by saying, &quot;Even though Naomasa is from a low status family, he has the potential to become the ruler of the world&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>これは直政がその気になれば、天下を取ることもできるということを意味している（隆景だけでなく、地方の武将達も同じようなことを噂していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means Naomasa could the reins of government if he would (not only Takakage but also other busho of the provinces whispered the same thing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That meant Naomasa could the take reins of government if he wanted (not only Takakage but also other busho of the provinces whispered the same thing).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That meant Naomasa could the take reins of government if he wanted (not only Takakage but also other busho of the provinces whispered the same thing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>しかし、生涯直政にそのような野心を見せる様子はなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said Nomasa never expressed such ambition in his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said Nomasa never expressed such ambition in his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said Nomasa never expressed such ambition in his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="134">
<j>井伊の赤備えは、戦国屈指の先鋭部隊として安土・桃山時代の初期から末期にかけて天下に名を轟かせていたが、家臣達の中には直政による厳しい軍律に耐えられなくなり、本多忠勝の下に去る者達も多かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) was renowned around the country as the most elite troops in Sengoku during Azuchi Momoyama Period, however, there seems to have been many vassals who couldn&apos;t stand the strict military discipline by Naokatsu and left to serve Tadakatsu HONDA instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) were renowned around the country as the most elite force in the Warring States Period and during the Azuchi Momoyama Period, however, there seem to have been many vassals who couldn&apos;t stand the strict military discipline of Naokatsu and left to serve Tadakatsu HONDA instead.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ii&apos;s Akazonae (red arms) were renowned around the country as the most elite force among Sengoku (warring provinces) during the Azuchi Momoyama Period, however, there seem to have been many vassals who couldn&apos;t stand the strict military discipline of Naomasa and left to serve Tadakatsu HONDA instead.</e>
<cmt>戦国は戦国時代ではなく、安土桃山時代に闘った戦をする国々という意味と思われますので変更しました。Naokatsu⇒Naomasa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>近藤秀用などのように出奔してしまった例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a vassal who left and hid like Hidemochi KONDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were vassals, such as Hidemochi KONDO, who left and hid.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were vassals, such as Hidemochi KONDO, who left and hid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>筆頭家老である木俣守勝ですら、直政の下にいるのが怖くなり、家康に旗本に戻してくれるように頼んだといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even Morikatsu KIMATA, who was Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers), asked Ieyasu to reinstate him in his former position hatamoto (bannermen), becoming terrified of serving Naomasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even Morikatsu KIMATA, who was the Hitto karo (head of the chief retainers), became terrified of serving under Naomasa, and asked Ieyasu to reinstate him in his former position as a hatamoto (bannerman).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even Morikatsu KIMATA, who was the Hitto karo (head of the chief retainers), became terrified of serving under Naomasa, and asked Ieyasu to reinstate him in his former position as a hatamoto (bannerman).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="137">
<j>直政は一時期滅亡していた井伊氏をわずか一代で再興させ、さらに江戸幕府の譜代大名の筆頭にまで成長させた井伊氏の英雄とされているため、井伊氏の名君の一人と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa is regarded as one of a wise ruler of Ii clan for his having revived Ii clan, which had been moribund once, and growing it to the head of fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa is regarded as one of the wise rulers of the Ii clan for reviving the once moribund clan, and developing it into the head of the fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in the Edo Shoganate.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa is regarded as one of the wise rulers of the Ii clan for reviving the once moribund clan, and developing it into the head of the fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Shoganate ⇒ Shogunate</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="138">
<j>直政は徳川氏の家臣の中で秀吉から最も気に入られていた陪臣であったため、秀吉からも厚い信頼を受けていたが、一説では、直政自身は秀吉をあまり快く思っていなかったとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa was the Hideyoshi&apos;s favorite baishin (indirect vassal) among the vassals of Tokugawa clan, winning the confidence of Hideyoshi, however, one theory has it that Naomasa himself didn&apos;t much like Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa won Hideyoshi&apos;s confidence and was his favorite baishin (indirect vassal) among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan, however, one theory has it that Naomasa himself didn&apos;t much like Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa won Hideyoshi&apos;s confidence and was his favorite baishin (indirect vassal) among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan, however, one theory has it that Naomasa himself didn&apos;t much like Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>その理由は、小田原の陣の後、突然、秀吉が家康が何十年間も苦労して手に入れた三河国、遠江国、駿河国、甲斐国、信濃国の5カ国の領地を没収して、その代わりに後北条氏の旧領である武蔵国、伊豆国、相模国、上野国、下野国、上総国、下総国の7カ国に移封したことを不満に思っていたためだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the reason was that, after Odawara no Jin (The Siege of Odawara), Hideyoshi suddenly confiscated Ieyasu&apos;s 5 territories; Mikawa Province, Totomi Province, Suruga Province, Kai Province and Shinano Province, which Ieyasu had gained the hard way for decades, and gave him 7 fomer territories of Gohojo clan; Musashi Province, Izu Province, Sagami Province, Kozuke Province, Shimotsuke Province, Kazusa Province and Shimousa Province instead, which Naomasa regarded as unsatisfactory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said this was because after Odawara no Jin (The Siege of Odawara) Hideyoshi suddenly confiscated the five territories Naomasa had spent decades gaining the hard way (Mikawa, Totomi, Suruga, Kai and Shinano provinces), and gave him seven former Gohojo clan territories (Musashi, Izu, Sagami, Kozuke, Shimotsuke, Kazusa and Shimousa provinces) instead, which Naomasa regarded as unsatisfactory.</e>
<cmt>wordingwrong names</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said this was because after Odawara no Jin (The Siege of Odawara) Hideyoshi suddenly confiscated the five territories Ieyasu had spent decades gaining the hard way (Mikawa, Totomi, Suruga, Kai and Shinano provinces), and gave him seven former Gohojo clan territories (Musashi, Izu, Sagami, Kozuke, Shimotsuke, Kazusa and Shimousa provinces) instead, which Naomasa regarded as unsatisfactory.</e>
<cmt>Naomasa ⇒ Ieyasuに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>また、直政だけでなく、他の家康の家臣も同じようにこのことを不満に思っていたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears that not only Naomasa, but also other vassals of Ieyasu complained about this.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears that not only Naomasa, but also other vassals of Ieyasu complained about this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="141">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの後、直政は近江国佐和山18万石を与えられたが、自分が嫌っていた石田三成の旧領であったため、直政自身はあまり納得しておらず、家康に上野国高崎に戻してもらうように頼んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was given the 180,000 koku crop yield Sawayama, Omi Province after the Battle of Sekigahara, however, this did not satisfy him because Sawayama was a former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA, whom Naomasa disliked, so he asked Ieyasu to allow him to Takasaki, Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was given the 180,000 koku crop yield Sawayama, Omi Province after the Battle of Sekigahara, however, this did not satisfy him because Sawayama was a former territory of Mitsunari ISHIDA, whom Naomasa disliked, so he asked Ieyasu to allow him to Takasaki, Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>この時直政は、生涯で唯一家康に不信感を抱いたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said this was the only time in his life that Naomasa felt a sense of distrust towards Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said this was the only time in his life that Naomasa felt a sense of distrust towards Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="143">
<j>直政は武力と政治的手腕の両方ともにかなりの実力を有していたにもかかわらず、後世にその名があまりしられていない（かと言って、全く無名というわけでもない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa didn&apos;t earn his place in history despite his great ability in both military and politics (not that he is unheard-of).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite his great ability in both military and political matters, Naomasa didn&apos;t earn his place in history (that is not to say he is completely unheard-of).</e>
<cmt>wording, ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite his great ability in both military and political matters, Naomasa didn&apos;t earn his place in history (that is not to say he is completely unheard-of).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>その理由は直政が家康に対して忠義を篤くしすぎて、あまりにも家臣達に厳しくなってしまったことが裏目に出てしまったのではないかと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the reason was that Naoyasu was so loyal to Ieyasu that he became too strict with his vassals, and this worked against him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the reason was that Naoyasu was so loyal to Ieyasu that he became too strict with his vassals, and this worked against him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="145">
<j>武家社会において、主君が亡くなった時に家臣が殉死することは当たり前であったが、直政の死に従う者は一人もいなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though it was normal in samurai society for vassals to follow their master to the grave, no vassals followed Naomasa when he died,</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though it was normal in samurai society for vassals to follow their master to the grave, no vassals followed Naomasa when he died,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>しかし、家臣達は直政の遺言にはきちんと従ったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said the vassals followed the will of Naomasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said the vassals were following Naomasa&apos;s last will and testament.</e>
<cmt>I have changed &quot;will&quot; to &quot;last will and testament&quot; to make it clear the vassals were following what was written in a document rather than Naomasa&apos;s orders.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said the vassals were following Naomasa&apos;s last will and testament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="147">
<j>生涯に参加した57回の戦で軽装備であったにもかかわらず、一度も傷を負わなかった本多忠勝に対して、直政は重装備であったが、戦で常に傷を負っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa was always injured in battles despite his being heavily-armored while Tadakatsu HONDA was never injured with his being light-armored in 57 battles he joined in his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was always injured in battles despite being heavily-armored, while Tadakatsu HONDA, who wore light armor, was never injured in the 57 battles he joined in his life.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was always injured in battles despite being heavily-armored, while Tadakatsu HONDA, who wore light armor, was never injured in the 57 battles he joined in his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>先陣で自ら戦うのを好む直政自身の激しい性癖によるところも大きいが、自分の存在を天下に轟かせるためには、こうするしかなかったとも言われている（直政は自分が若いにもかかわらず家康に重臣として扱われることで周囲からの嫉妬や妬みの対象にならないようにするために、戦で戦傷を負うのを厭わず、それによって自分の苦労を他の重臣達に理解してもらおうとしていたとも言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said he had no other choices to make his name renowned around the country adding to his fierce inclination for loving to fight in front line himself (it is also said he didn&apos;t care being injured to exempt him from being envied by other vassals because he was treated as a senior vassal despite his being young and to make other vassals understand his effort).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to his love of fighting in the front line and his own fierce disposition, it is said he had no other way to make his name renowned around the country (it is also said that he didn&apos;t care about being injured in battle in order to avoid being envied by other vassals on account of him being treated as a senior vassal despite being so young, and to make the other vassals understand his efforts).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to his love of fighting in the front line and his own fierce disposition, it is said he had no other way to make his name renowned around the country (it is also said that he didn&apos;t care about being injured in battle in order to avoid being envied by other vassals on account of him being treated as a senior vassal despite being so young, and to make the other vassals understand his efforts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>一方で生涯に参加した戦は16回であり、いずれの戦でも直政が負けたことは一度もないと言われている（井伊の赤備え自体は大坂冬の陣で真田信繁率いる赤備えと戦って敗北している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nomasa fought 16 battles in his life, and it is said he was never defeated (the Ii Akazonae [red arms] were defeated by the Akazonae of Nobushige SANADA in the Osaka Fuyu no Jin [The Winter Siege of Osaka]).</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa fought 16 battles in his life, and it is said he was never defeated (the Ii Akazonae [red arms] were defeated by the Akazonae of Nobushige SANADA in the Osaka Fuyu no Jin [The Winter Siege of Osaka]).</e>
<cmt>Nomasa ⇒Naomasa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>これが井伊の赤備え唯一の敗北と言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is said to have been the only time Ii&apos;s Akazonae were defeated.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is said to have been the only time Ii&apos;s Akazonae were defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>このため、直政はかなりの強運の持ち主であったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Naomasa is thought to have been a lucky man.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Naomasa is thought to have been a lucky man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>また、上記のように直政と忠勝は度々比較の対象となったりすることがあり、この2人はお互いにライバル同士であったため、あまり仲がよくなかったと言われている（記述によっては忠勝だけが直政をライバル視していたとされることもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Naomasa and Tadakatsu were on bad terms because they were rivals and compared each other often (depending on document, only Tadakatsu saw Naomasa as a rival).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Naomasa and Tadakatsu were on bad terms because they were rivals and were often compared with each (according to some documents, only Tadakatsu saw Naomasa as a rival).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Naomasa and Tadakatsu were on bad terms because they were rivals and were often compared with each (according to some documents, only Tadakatsu saw Naomasa as a rival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>なお、忠勝と同年齢の榊原康政とは、最初はあまり仲がよくなかったと言われているが、家康が関東に入国してから共に行動をすることが多くなり、段々と仲がよくなっていったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it is said Naomasa wasn&apos;t on good terms with Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, who was the same year of Tadakatsu, first, however, it seems they became closer through acting together after Ieyasu entered Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that at first Naomasa was not on good terms with Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, who was the same age as Tadakatsu, however, it seems they became closer through acting together after Ieyasu entered Kanto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that at first Naomasa was not on good terms with Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, who was the same age as Tadakatsu, however, it seems they became closer through acting together after Ieyasu entered Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>家康の筆頭家老である酒井忠次も家康と同じように直政に対して暖かい目で見守っていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Tadatsugu SAKAI, Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) of Ieyasu, watched Naomasa warmly like Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Tadatsugu SAKAI, Ieyasu&apos;s Hitto karo (head of the chief retainers), looked favorable on Naomasa in the same way as Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Tadatsugu SAKAI, Ieyasu&apos;s Hitto karo (head of the chief retainers), looked favorable on Naomasa in the same way as Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>ちなみに忠次は直政がまだ一軍の将になったばかりの頃に康政がそのことを妬んだために叱ったことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu reprimanded Tadatsugu for that out of jealousy when Naomasa had just become the head of an army.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsugu reprimanded Yasumasa for that out of jealousy when Naomasa had just become the head of an army.</e>
<cmt>名前を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="156">
<j>ある時、家康は直政の家臣達を1つの場所に集めて、直政の衣服を脱がせて体に残っていた戦傷の一つ一つを涙ぐみながら説明したという（家康は直政が常に戦で戦傷を負うことをいつも気にしていたという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On one occasion, Ieyasu gathered Naomasa&apos;s vassals in one place and explained each injury left on Naomasa&apos;s body to them with tears in his eyes, making Naomasa take off his clothes (it is said Ieyasu always care about Naomasa&apos;s being injured at the battlefields).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On one occasion, Ieyasu gathered Naomasa&apos;s vassals in one place, made Naomasa take off his clothes, and, with tears in his eyes, explained each injury left on Naomasa&apos;s body to them (it is said Ieyasu always cared about Naomasa&apos;s being injured in battle).</e>
<cmt>wording, ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On one occasion, Ieyasu gathered Naomasa&apos;s vassals in one place, made Naomasa take off his clothes, and, with tears in his eyes, explained each injury left on Naomasa&apos;s body to them (it is said Ieyasu always cared about Naomasa&apos;s being injured in battle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>このことを聞いた直政の家臣達も家康を見てもらい泣きをし、自分達も主君である直政のために全力で武功を挙げようという決意をしたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Naomasa&apos;s vassals hearing that cried in sympathy with Ieyasu and determined to make military exploits for their lord Naomasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said upon hearing this, Naomasa&apos;s vassals cried in sympathy with Ieyasu and determined to do their best in battle for their lord Naomasa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Make military exploits&quot; doesn&apos;t make sense to me.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said upon hearing this, Naomasa&apos;s vassals cried in sympathy with Ieyasu and determined to do their best in battle for their lord Naomasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="158">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの後、直政は西軍の一員であった島津義弘から家康との和平交渉の仲立ちを依頼された（徳川氏の家臣の中に政治を専門とする本多正信がいるにもかかわらず）ことからその政治的手腕は、他家の者達に知れ渡っていたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears that Naomasa&apos;s ability in politics was well known among the vassals of other clans because he was asked by Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who was a member of Western Camp, to serve as a mediation between Ieyasu for peace talks (even though there was Masanobu HONDA, whose specialty was politics, in the vassals of Tokugawa clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears that Naomasa&apos;s ability in politics was well known among the vassals of other clans, because after the Battle of Sekigahara he was asked by Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who was a member of the Western Camp, to serve as mediator with Ieyasu for peace talks (even though Masanobu HONDA, whose specialty was politics, was among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan).</e>
<cmt>wordingFor some reason the original translation didn&apos;t include 関ヶ原の戦いの後.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears that Naomasa&apos;s ability in politics was well known among the vassals of other clans, because after the Battle of Sekigahara he was asked by Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who was a member of the Western Camp, to serve as mediator with Ieyasu for peace talks (even though Masanobu HONDA, whose specialty was politics, was among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="159">
<j>直政は思慮深く、口重であったため、度々家康の内々の相談相手になっていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Ieyasu sometimes consulted Naomasa because he was thoughtful and discreet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said Ieyasu sometimes consulted Naomasa because he was thoughtful and discreet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said Ieyasu sometimes consulted Naomasa because he was thoughtful and discreet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>そのため、他人を評価することがめったにない家康は、直政のことを「余人がいない時に直政が意見を出してくれる」と高く評価している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Ieyasu, who rarely appraise others, thought highly of Naomasa saying &apos;Naomasa gives his opinion when there is nobody&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Ieyasu, who rarely praised others, thought highly of Naomasa saying &apos;Naomasa gives his opinion when nobody else will&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Ieyasu, who rarely praised others, thought highly of Naomasa saying &apos;Naomasa gives his opinion when nobody else will&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>つまり、直政は家康の御意見番であったということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, Naomasa was Ieyasu&apos;s advisor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, Naomasa was Ieyasu&apos;s advisor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, Naomasa was Ieyasu&apos;s advisor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="162">
<j>直政は石川数正と並んで徳川氏の家臣の中でも数少ない外交官として、大いに力を発揮し、また、家康から見て本多正信と並んで天下取りの知恵袋とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa made a significant contribution as diplomat, which was few in the vassals of Tokugawa clan, along with Kazumasa ISHIKAWA and was regarded as a man of wisdom needed to take the reins of government along with Masanobu HONDA by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, Naomasa made a significant contribution as a diplomat, of which there were few among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan, and, along with Masanobu HONDA, was regarded by Ieyasu as a man of wisdom needed to take the reins of government.</e>
<cmt>wording, ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with Kazumasa ISHIKAWA, Naomasa made a significant contribution as a diplomat, of which there were few among the vassals of the Tokugawa clan, and, along with Masanobu HONDA, was regarded by Ieyasu as a man of wisdom needed to take the reins of government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="163">
<j>なお、直政が兵部少輔に叙任されたのは、最初に赤備えを組織した武田氏の家臣である飯富虎昌が兵部少輔に叙任されていたためだとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the reason Naomasa was assigned as Hyobu-shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military) was that Toramasa OBU, a vassal of Takeda clan, who had organized Akazonae (red arms) first, had been assigned as one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the reason Naomasa was assigned as a Hyobu-shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military) was that Toramasa OBU, a vassal of the Takeda clan who had first organized the Akazonae (red arms), had been assigned as one.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the reason Naomasa was assigned as a Hyobu-shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military) was that Toramasa OBU, a vassal of the Takeda clan who had first organized the Akazonae (red arms), had been assigned as one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="164">
<j>あまり知られていないことだが、直政は正室である唐梅院に対してはかなりの恐妻家で、誰よりも負けず嫌いであった直政もこの唐梅院だけには頭があがらなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known widely that Naomasa was such a submissive husband for his lawful wife Tobaiin that he can&apos;t fight with her even though he hated defeat more than anyone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not widely known that Naomasa was such a submissive husband to his lawful wife Tobaiin that he could not fight with her, even though he hated defeat more than anyone.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not widely known that Naomasa was such a submissive husband to his lawful wife Tobaiin that he could not fight with her, even though he hated defeat more than anyone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>直政の次男である直孝は唐梅院の侍女を母に産まれたとされるが、直政は直孝の誕生後、十年近くも対面しようとしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naotaka, the second son of Naomasa, was born to a waiting woman of Tobaiin, however, Naomasa never tried to meet him for about 10 years after he his birth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naotaka, Naomasa&apos;s second son, was born to a waiting woman of Tobaiin, however, Naomasa did not try to meet him for about 10 years after his birth.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naotaka, Naomasa&apos;s second son, was born to a waiting woman of Tobaiin, however, Naomasa did not try to meet him for about 10 years after his birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>唐梅院に対し大いに遠慮していたためと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears that he respected Tobaiin&apos;s feeling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears that he respected Tobaiin&apos;s feeling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears that he respected Tobaiin&apos;s feeling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="167">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの後、江戸から離れた領地に移封されて政治の表舞台からも姿を消している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He disappeared from the front stage of the history, having moved his territory away from Edo after the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle of Sekigahara, he moved his territory away from Edo and disappeared from the main stage of history.</e>
<cmt>wording, ordering</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle of Sekigahara, he moved his territory away from Edo and disappeared from the main stage of history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>かつての功績があまりにも大きいため家康に冷遇されたとも言われるが、直政は関ヶ原の戦いでの戦傷が元で破傷風を起こしているため病気で出仕できなかったとの見方が大勢である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory has it that Naomasa was given cold shoulder by Ieyasu for his great achievements in the past, however, the other theory that he couldn&apos;t have served due to tetanus caused by the battle wound inflicted in the Battle of Sekigahara is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, Naomasa was given cold shoulder by Ieyasu because of his great achievements in the past, however, another theory that he could not have served due to tetanus caused by the wound he received at the Battle of Sekigahara is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, Naomasa was given cold shoulder by Ieyasu because of his great achievements in the past, however, another theory that he could not have served due to tetanus caused by the wound he received at the Battle of Sekigahara is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Flamelai(id:34490), いいすく(id:136753), Bakkai(id:7233), ドルチェット(id:46458), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Ypacaraí(id:11031), T@ka(id:12814), Cprobot(id:97843), Tribot(id:186681), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), HqB774PW0(id:311341), るがこむ(id:181), らりた(id:1327), 宮下太郎(id:184563), Mymelo(id:122034), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Blowback(id:173308), A-Taul(id:41790), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Kanoe(id:17203), こぶまき(id:38278), シソグラフィティ(id:233006), Maakun(id:16735), Volfgang(id:98768), Tinecici(id:192914), PuzzletChung(id:13816), Bankokuya(id:91191), ウィキ豊(id:82961), M-sho-gun(id:88956), J-ta(id:26559), 蒲生直義(id:235164), 石川入婿(id:106304), 時空の旅人(id:120663), Chinamie(id:213556), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 松茸(id:27535), Yanahan(id:2437), Sorrysorry(id:102591), Kagetudo(id:163875), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Carkuni(id:79281), Rapier(id:95662), VolkovBot(id:105371), Safkan(id:423), オナガドリ(id:15179), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), Mameneko(id:785), 中二病の端くれ(id:137185), Jmho(id:10472), 宇和島太郎(id:105130), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>