<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>常高院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jokoin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jokoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jokoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>常高院（じょうこういん、永禄13年（1570年）？ － 寛永10年8月27日 (旧暦)（1633年9月30日））は、戦国時代 (日本)から江戸時代前期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jokoin (1570 ?) - September 30, 1633) was a woman in the Sengoku period (Japan) to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jokoin (1570 ?) - September 30, 1633) was a woman in the Sengoku period (Japan) to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jokoin (1570 ? - September 30, 1633) was a woman in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan) to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代に説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>室町時代に守護大名、四職の一つとして繁栄した近江源氏の流れをくむ京極家当主京極高次の正室である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a legal wife of Takatsugu Kyogoku, the head of Kyogoku family which was descended from Omi-Genji (Minamoto clan) and thrived in the Muromachi period as a military governor and one of Shishiki (Four major feudal lords who worked for Muromachi bakufu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a legal wife of Takatsugu Kyogoku, the head of Kyogoku family which was descended from Omi-Genji (Minamoto clan) and thrived in the Muromachi period as a military governor and one of Shishiki (Four major feudal lords who worked for Muromachi bakufu).</e>
<cmt>Edited for spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a legal wife of Takatsugu KYOGOKU, the head of Kyogoku family which was descended from Omi-Genji (Minamoto clan) and thrived in the Muromachi period as a military governor and one of the Four major feudal lords who worked for Muromachi Shogunate Government.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本名は浅井 初（あざい はつ）で、一般に「初」という呼び名で知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real name was Hatsu AZAI and she was commonly known as &quot;Hatsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name was Hatsu AZAI and she was commonly known as &quot;Hatsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name was Hatsu AZAI and she was commonly known as &quot;Hatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>父は北近江国小谷城主・浅井長政、母は織田信秀の娘・お市の方（織田信長の末妹）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Nagamasa AZAI, the lord of Odani castle in north Omi Province, and her mother was Oichi no kata, a daughter of Nobunaga ODA (Nobunaga&apos;s youngest daughter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Nagamasa AZAI, the lord of Odani castle in north Omi Province, and her mother was Oichi no kata, a daughter of Nobunaga ODA (Nobunaga&apos;s youngest daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Nagamasa AZAI, the lord of Odani-jo castle in the north Omi Province, and her mother was Oichi no kata, a daughter of Nobunaga ODA (Nobunaga&apos;s youngest daughter).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>姉は豊臣秀吉の側室となった淀殿（淀殿）、妹は徳川秀忠・正室（継室）の崇源院（崇源院）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her elder sister was Yodo-dono (Yodo-dono), the concubine of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and her younger sister was Sugenin, the legal wife (second wife) of Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her elder sister was Yodo-dono (Yodo-dono), the concubine of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and her younger sister was Sugenin, the legal wife (second wife) of Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her elder sister was Chacha (Yodo-dono), the concubine of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and her younger sister was Go (Sugenin), the legal wife (second wife) of Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Web の Wikipedia では「茶々（淀殿）」「江（崇源院）」となっていたため、合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄に浅井万福丸、異母弟に万菊丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had a elder brother Manpukumaru AZAI and a younger half brother with the same mother Mangikumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had an elder brother Manpukumaru AZAI and a younger half brother with the same mother Mangikumaru.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had an elder brother Manpukumaru AZAI, and a younger moternal-half brother Mangikumaru.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>三姉妹のなかで一番格下の家に嫁いだと思われがちだが、新興の豊臣家や徳川家に比べ、京極家は室町時代に数ヶ国の守護を兼ね、四職に列した名門の大名家であり、一番格上の家に嫁いだといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though we tend to think that she married into the lowest-ranked family among three sisters, we might say that she married into the highest-ranked family because the Kyogoku family was, compared with newly-risen Toyotomi family and Tokugawa family, the distinguished feudal lord family which governed several provinces and counted as one of Shishiki in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though we tend to think that she married into the lowest-ranked family among three sisters, we might say that she married into the highest-ranked family because the Kyogoku family was, compared with newly-risen Toyotomi family and Tokugawa family, the distinguished feudal lord family which governed several provinces and counted as one of Shishiki in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although we tend to think that she married into the lowest-ranked family among the three sisters, we might say that she married into the highest-ranked family, because the Kyogoku family was, compared with newly-risen Toyotomi family and Tokugawa family, the distinguished feudal lord family which governed several provinces and counted as one of Shishiki in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、京極家は実家の浅井家の直接の主筋に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the Kyogoku family was the direct master of AZAI family, her parents&apos; family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the Kyogoku family was the direct master of AZAI family, her parents&apos; family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the Kyogoku family was the direct master of her parents&apos; family, the Azai family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>高次との間に子は無く、妹・江の娘と2代将軍徳川秀忠の四女・初姫（興安院）や氏家行広の娘・古奈（母は高次の妹）らを養女とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though she had no children between Takatsugu, she adopted Hatsuhime (Koanin), fourth daughter of the couple of a daughter of her younger sister Go and the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and Kona (her mother was Takatsugu&apos;s younger sister), a daughter of Yukihiro UJIIE.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though she had no children between Takatsugu, she adopted Hatsuhime (Koanin), fourth daughter of the couple of a daughter of her younger sister Go and the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and Kona (her mother was Takatsugu&apos;s younger sister), a daughter of Yukihiro UJIIE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though she had no children with Takatsugu, she adopted Hatsuhime (Koanin), the fourth daughter of the couple of a daughter of her younger sister Go and the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and Kona (her mother was Takatsugu&apos;s younger sister), a daughter of Yukihiro UJIIE.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、側室の子で嫡子の京極忠高（母は山田氏）や高政（母は小倉氏）、また詳細不明の養子1名をはじめとした、血縁・家臣らの子女の養育に積極的に関わったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She also actively reared concubines&apos; children Tadataka KYOGOKU (his mother was Yamada clan), the successor of the family head, and Takamasa (his mother was Ogura clan) as well as children of relatives and vassals including one adopted child whose identity is unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She also actively reared concubines&apos; children Tadataka KYOGOKU (his mother was Yamada clan), the successor of the family head, and Takamasa (his mother was Ogura clan) as well as children of relatives and vassals including one adopted child whose identity is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She also actively reared concubines&apos; children Tadataka KYOGOKU (his mother was from the Yamada clan), the successor of the family head, and Takamasa (his mother was from the Ogura clan), as well as children of relatives and vassals including one adopted child whose identity is unknown.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に養女の初姫と忠高を娶わせるがこの両者にも子はできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later she married her adopted daughter Hatsuhime to Tadataka but they had no children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later she married her adopted daughter Hatsuhime to Tadataka but they had no children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, she married her adopted daughter Hatsuhime to Tadataka but they had no children, either.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>初姫を養女とした際、初と同名であったため「藤」と改めたとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that she changed her name to &quot;Fuji&quot; when she adopted Hatsuhime because her name was also Hatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say that she changed her name to &quot;Fuji&quot; when she adopted Hatsuhime because her name was also Hatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that she changed her name to &apos;Fuji&apos; when she adopted Hatsuhime, because her name was also Hatsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このことから初の名前のなかに「藤原 藤子」と伝わる名もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above, some documentary records called her &quot;Fujiko FUJIWARA&quot; instead of Hatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above, some documentary records called her &quot;Fujiko FUJIWARA&quot; instead of Hatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above, some records described her as &apos;Fujiko FUJIWARA&apos; instead of Hatsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>永禄13年（1570年）？、近江国小谷城（現・滋賀県湖北町）に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born in 1570 ? at the Odani castle in Omi Province (Kohoku-cho Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born in 1570 ? at the Odani castle in Omi Province (Kohoku-cho Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born circa 1570 in the Odani-jo castle in Omi Province (present Kohoku-cho, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>天正元年（1573年）、父の長政は叔父・信長と交戦し、小谷城は落城して父・長政と祖父・浅井久政は自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, her father Nagamasa fought with her uncle Nobunaga, but the Odani castle fell and her father Nagamasa and her grandfather Hidemasa committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, her father Nagamasa fought with her uncle Nobunaga, but the Odani castle fell and her father Nagamasa and her grandfather Hidemasa committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, her father Nagamasa fought her uncle Nobunaga, and the Odani-jo castle fell and her father Nagamasa and her grandfather Hidemasa committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>母・市と三姉妹は以降、織田家の下で保護をうける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, her mother Ich and three sisters were in the custody of Oda family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, her mother Ich and three sisters were in the custody of Oda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, her mother Ichi and the three sisters were in the custody of Oda family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、6月2日の本能寺の変で信長が家臣の明智光秀に討たれた為、6月27日に織田家後継者を決める清洲会議が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga was killed by his vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI in the Honno-ji Incident occurred on June 2, 1582, the Kiyosu conference was held on June 27 in order to decide the successor of Oda family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga was killed by his vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI in the Honno-ji Incident occurred on June 2, 1582, the Kiyosu conference was held on June 27 in order to decide the successor of Oda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Nobunaga was killed by his vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI in the Honno-ji Incident occurred on July 1, 1582, the Kiyosu conference was held on July 26 in order to decide the successor of the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その結果、母・市は織田家の家臣・柴田勝家と再婚し、越前国北ノ庄城へ移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the decision made at the above conference, her mother Ichi remarried Katsuie SHIBATA, a vassal of Oda family, and moved to the Kitanosho castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the decision made at the above conference, her mother Ichi remarried Katsuie SHIBATA, a vassal of Oda family, and moved to the Kitanosho castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the decision made at the above-mentioned conference, her mother Ichi remarried Katsuie SHIBATA, a vassal of the Oda family, and moved to the Kitanosho-jo castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>天正11年（1583年）、勝家は清洲会議がきっかけで豊臣秀吉と対立していたが賤ヶ岳の合戦で勝家は秀吉に敗れ、北ノ庄城の落城のさいに市は勝家と共に自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuie, who was in confrontation with Hideyoshi in the wake of Kiyosu conference, was defeated by Hideyoshi in the battle of Shizugatake and Ichi committed suicide together with Katsuie when the Kitanosho castle fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuie, who was in confrontation with Hideyoshi in the wake of Kiyosu conference, was defeated by Hideyoshi in the battle of Shizugatake and Ichi committed suicide together with Katsuie when the Kitanosho castle fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1583, Katsuie, who was in confrontation with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in the wake of the Kiyosu conference, was defeated by Hideyoshi in the battle of Shizugatake and Ichi committed suicide together with Katsuie when the Kitanosho-jo castle fell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>三姉妹は敵側の秀吉の庇護をうける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three sisters were protected by their enemy Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three sisters were protected by their enemy Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three sisters were protected by their enemy Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>天正15年（1587年）、秀吉の計らいにより従兄弟にあたる京極高次と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, she married her cousin Takatsugu KYOGOKU through the good offices of Hidetoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1587, she married her cousin Takatsugu KYOGOKU through the good offices of Hidetoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1587, she married her cousin Takatsugu KYOGOKU through the good offices of Hidetoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）、秀吉の死後に五奉行の一人、石田三成と五大老の筆頭・徳川家康が対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died in 1600, Mitsunari ISHIDA, one of Gobugyo (five major magistrates), was in confrontation with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the head of Gotairo (council of five elders).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi died in 1600, Mitsunari ISHIDA, one of Gobugyo (five major magistrates), was in confrontation with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the head of Gotairo (council of five elders).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died in 1600, Mitsunari ISHIDA, one of the five major magistrates, was in confrontation with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the head of the council of five elders.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>石田三成ら（西軍）が挙兵すると京極家は一時、三成側につくが、関ヶ原の戦いでは大津城に籠城して東軍に属する（大津篭城戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Mitsunari ISHIDA and others (West squad) raised an army, Kyogoku forces once sided with Mitsunari but in the Battle of Sekigahara, they belonged to East squad while being confined in the Otsu castle (the battle at besieged Otsu castle).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Mitsunari ISHIDA and others (West squad) raised an army, Kyogoku forces once sided with Mitsunari but in the Battle of Sekigahara, they belonged to East squad while being confined in the Otsu castle (the battle at besieged Otsu castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Mitsunari ISHIDA and those in the West squad raised an army, Kyogoku forces once sided with Mitsunari, but in the Battle of Sekigahara, they belonged to the East squad while being confined in the Otsu-jo castle (the battle at besieged Otsu-jo castle).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>合戦があと1日伸びれば落城したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Otsu castle might have fallen if the battle had continued for an extra day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Otsu castle might have fallen if the battle had continued for an extra day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Otsu-jo castle might have fallen, if the battle had continued for one more day.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>西軍の足止めしたと功績され京極家は若狭小浜八万五千石を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyogoku family was given 85 thousands Goku crop yields in Wakasa Obama as the award for hindering the advance of West squad.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyogoku family was given 85 thousands Goku crop yields in Wakasa Obama as the award for hindering the advance of West squad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyogoku family was given the land of Wakasa Obama of 85,000 koku crop yields as the award for hindering the advance of the West squad.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>慶長14年（1609年）、夫・高次が亡くなると剃髪・出家して常高院と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1609, she entered the Buddhist priesthood and called herself Jokoin after the death of her husband Takatsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1609, she entered the Buddhist priesthood and called herself Jokoin after the death of her husband Takatsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1609, Hatsu entered the Buddhist priesthood with the Buddhist name Jokoin after the death of her husband Takatsugu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この頃から甥・豊臣秀頼（姉の茶々〔淀殿〕が豊臣家の実権を掌握とも）と徳川家康（妹・江の舅）の対立が露呈するようになり、常高院は豊臣方の使者として仲介に奔走。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around that time, a confrontation between her nephew Hideyori TOYOTOMI (it is said that her elder sister Chacha (Yodo-dono) seized real power in the Toyotomi family) and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA became known and Jokoin strived for mediation as the messenger of Toyotomi side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since around that time, a confrontation between her nephew Hideyori TOYOTOMI (it is said that her elder sister Chacha (Yodo-dono) seized real power in the Toyotomi family) and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA became known and Jokoin strived for mediation as the messenger of Toyotomi side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around that time, a confrontation between her nephew Hideyori TOYOTOMI (it is said that her elder sister Chacha (Yodo-dono) seized real power in the Toyotomi family) and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (her sister GO&apos;s father-in-law) became known and Jokoin strived for mediation as the messenger of the Toyotomi side.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）、大坂冬の陣では徳川側の雲光院とともに和議を取りまとめ両家の和議に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Osaka Fuyu no Jin (Winter Siege of Osaka) occurred in 1614, she, along with Unkoin of TOKUGAWA side, strived for peace negotiations between the two families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Osaka Fuyu no Jin (Winter Siege of Osaka) occurred in 1614, she, along with Unkoin of TOKUGAWA side, strived for peace negotiations between the two families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Winter Siege of Osaka occurred in 1614, she, along with the Tokugawa side messenger Unkoin, strived for peace negotiations between the two families.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>慶長20年（1615年）、大坂夏の陣で豊臣家が滅亡すると、秀頼の娘・奈阿姫（後の天秀尼）の助命を家康に嘆願したとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that she asked Ieyasu to save the life of Nakahime, a daughter of Hideyori (Tenshuni), when Toyotomi family ceased to exist in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer siege of Osaka) occurred in 1615.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that she asked Ieyasu to save the life of Nakahime, a daughter of Hideyori (Tenshuni), when Toyotomi family ceased to exist in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer siege of Osaka) occurred in 1615.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that she asked Ieyasu to save the life of Nakahime, a daughter of Hideyori (later, Tenshuni), when the Toyotomi family fell in the Summer siege of Osaka occurred in 1615.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その後は妹崇源院とよく会っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She often met her younger sister Sugenin since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She often met her younger sister Sugenin since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She often saw her younger sister Sugenin since then.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>妹・崇源院が亡くなる少し前に常高院は江戸で再会し、対談したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She met Sugenin in Edo and had a conversation shortly before the death of Sugenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She met Sugenin in Edo and had a conversation shortly before the death of Sugenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jokoin saw Sugenin in Edo and had a conversation shortly before the death of Sugenin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>寛永10年（1633年）、京極忠高の江戸屋敷で死去、享年64。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1633, she died at the Edo residence of Tadataka KYOGOKU at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1633, she died at the Edo residence of Tadataka KYOGOKU at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1633, she died at the Edo residence of Tadataka KYOGOKU at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>墓所は福井県小浜市の常高寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is located at Joko-ji Temple in Obama City, Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is located at Joko-ji Temple in Obama City, Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is located at Joko-ji Temple in Obama City, Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>墓所は、常高院永昌尼公の石塔を中心に、尼公に仕えていた尼僧達の石塔が会席する形をとって並んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At her grave yard, gravestones of nuns who served for her are situated with the gravestone of Jokoin Eishoniko in the center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At her grave yard, gravestones of nuns who served her are situated with the gravestone of Jokoin Eishoniko in the center.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the graveyard, gravestones of nuns who served her are situated with the gravestone of Jokoin Eishoniko in the center.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>同寺には常高院の肖像画も伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The portrait of Jokoin is aloso existent at the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The portrait of Jokoin is also existent at the temple.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The portrait of Jokoin is also kept in the temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>常高院は遺言で「もし、将来国替えがあっても常高寺だけはこの若狭の地に、留めおいて下さい」と遺言に残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jokoin left her will saying &quot;even if the Kyogoku family is transferred to another place in future, please keep Joko-ji Temple at Wakasa at the worst&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jokoin a will stating &quot;even if the Kyogoku family is transferred to another place in future, please keep Joko-ji Temple at Wakasa at the worst&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jokoin left a will stating &apos;even if the Kyogoku family is transferred to another place in future, please keep at least Joko-ji Temple in Wakasa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>実際、常高院没後の翌寛永11年（1634年）京極家は出雲松江藩に国替えした時も、常高院は若狭に残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, when the Kyogoku family was transferred to Izumo Matsue domain in 1634 after her death, Joko-ji Temple remained in Wakasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, when the Kyogoku family was transferred to Izumo Matsue domain in 1634 after her death, Joko-ji Temple remained in Wakasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, when the Kyogoku family was transferred to the Izumo Matsue domain in 1634 after Jokoin&apos;s death, Joko-ji Temple remained in Wakasa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>また、初は細身の美女であり、三姉妹は母市の美しさを受け継いだ、誉れ高い美女であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatsu was a slim and beautiful woman and all of three sisters had a reputation as beautiful women who inherited the beauty of their mother Ichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatsu was a slim and beautiful woman and all of three sisters had a reputation as beautiful women who inherited the beauty of their mother Ichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatsu was a slim and beautiful woman, and all of three sisters had a reputation as beautiful women who inherited the beauty of their mother Ichi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>姉・茶々（淀殿）、妹・江（崇源院）とは幼少の頃からたいへん仲の良い姉妹であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since childhood, she had a good relationship with both her elder sister Chacha (Yodo-dono) and her younger sister Go (Sugenin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since childhood, she had a good relationship with both her elder sister Chacha (Yodo-dono) and her younger sister Go (Sugenin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since childhood, she had a good relationship with both of her elder sister Chacha (Yodo-dono) and her younger sister Go (Sugenin).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また三人の中で一番長生きした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She lived the longest among three sisters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She lived the longest among three sisters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She lived the longest among the three sisters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Izayohi(id:13095), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), 0null0(id:582), 二八(id:10408), Kone(id:377), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), こぶまき(id:38278), Panachan(id:177162), Kamakura(id:472), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Bmeg(id:118515), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>