<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中原師元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAKAHARA no Moromoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAKAHARA no Moromoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAKAHARA no Moromoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中原 師元（なかはら の もろもと、天仁2年（1109年） - 承安 (日本)5年（1175年）5月20日 (旧暦)）は平安時代後期の廷臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAKAHARA no Moromoto (1109-June 17, 1175) was the of imperial court retainer of the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAKAHARA no Moromoto (1109-June 17, 1175) was an imperial court retainer of the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>a few stray words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAKAHARA no Moromoto (1109 - June 17, 1175) was an Imperial Court retainer of the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。Imperial Courtに訂正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>外記中原師遠の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of NAKAHARA no Moromoto, who had the title of Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of NAKAHARA no Moromoto, who had the title of Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of NAKAHARA no Moromoto, who had the title of Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子息に師尚、平清貞（平清盛養子）、息女に藤原尹明室、二条天皇後宮（よし子内親王生母）、養子に中原祐安（清原頼業実弟）らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Moronao and TAIRA no Kiyosada (the adopted son of TAIRA no Kiyomori) as sons, the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadaaki, consort of Emperor Nijo (the mother of Imperial Princess Yoshiko)as daughters, and adopted NAKAHARA no Sukeyasu (the real younger brother of KIYOHARA no Yorinari).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had Moronao and TAIRA no Kiyosada (the adopted son of TAIRA no Kiyomori) for sons, the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadaaki, consort of Emperor Nijo (the mother of Imperial Princess Yoshiko), as his daughter, and adopted NAKAHARA no Sukeyasu (the real younger brother of KIYOHARA no Yorinari).</e>
<cmt>Double-byte characters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had Moronao and TAIRA no Kiyosada (the adopted son of TAIRA no Kiyomori) for sons, the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadaaki, consort of Emperor Nijo (the mother of Imperial Princess Yoshiko), as his daughter, and adopted NAKAHARA no Sukeyasu (the real younger brother of KIYOHARA no Yorinari).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明経博士、大外記。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had titles of Myogyo hakase (Doctor of Confucian classics) and &quot;Daigeki&quot; (Senior Secretary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had titles of Myogyo hakase (Doctor of Confucian classics) and &quot;Daigeki&quot; (Senior Secretary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had titles of Myogyo hakase (Doctor of Confucian classics) and Daigeki (Senior Secretary).</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また出羽国他の国司を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also served as the governor of Dewa Province and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also served as the governor of Dewa Province and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also served as the governor of Dewa Province and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>代々大外記を勤める家柄に生まれ、遅くとも天治2年（1125年）には自身もその職にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born into the family that served Daigeki and was assigned to that position as late as 1125.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born into the family that served Daigeki and was assigned to that position as late as 1125.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born into the family that served Daigeki and was assigned to that position as late as 1125.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以後、直講、助教などを兼任しながら同職を勤め、保元2年（1157年）に掃部頭に任じた際に一旦辞するが、永暦 (日本)元年（1160年）に再度任じ、永万2年（1166年）まで勤め上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also served additionally as chokko (assistant teacher of Keisho) and assistant professor but quit once he was became Kamon no kami (Director at the Bureau of Palace Upkeep) in 1157, but was reassigned to the position in 1160 and served until 1166.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also served additionally as chokko (assistant teacher of Keisho) and assistant professor but quit once he became Kamon no kami (Director at the Bureau of Palace Upkeep) in 1157, but was reassigned to the position in 1160 and served until 1166.</e>
<cmt>deleted “was”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also served additionally as chokko (assistant teacher of Keisho) and assistant professor but quit once he became Kamon no kami (Director at the Bureau of Palace Upkeep) in 1157, but was reassigned to the position in 1160 and served until 1166.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>こうした大外記としての豊かな経験から先例に明るく、大治3年（1128年）に家司として招かれた摂関家において藤原忠実・藤原頼長父子より厚い信頼を受け、その相談事に数多く与った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a great experience as Daigeki compared to others, and received a deep trust from both FUJIWARA no Tadazane and Yorinaga parent and child of the regent family, who invited him as Keishi (household superintendent) for many consultations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a great experience as Daigeki compared to others, and gained the deep trust of both FUJIWARA no Tadazane and Yorinaga, parent and child of the regent family, who consulted with him as Keishi (household superintendent) on many occasions.</e>
<cmt>invited for many consultations-&gt;consulted on many occasions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a great experience as Daigeki compared to others, and gained the deep trust of both FUJIWARA no Tadazane and Yorinaga, parent and child of the regent family, who consulted with him as Keishi (household superintendent, in 1128) on many occasions.</e>
<cmt>(in 1128)補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>忠実との会話を師元が筆録した『中外抄』は、院政期の公家社会の様子を克明に伝える史料の一つとして名高い（同書の書名は中原の「中」と大外記の「外」から各々一字を取ったもの）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto wrote down the conversation he had with Tadasane in &quot;Chugaisho,&quot; which became famous as a valuable historical manuscript that told of kuge (aristocrat) society during the insei period (the period of the government by the retired Emperor) (the title of the manuscript derived from taking each character from &apos;中&apos; (Naka) from Nakahara and &apos;外&apos; from Daigeki (大外記).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto wrote down the conversation he had with Tadasane in &quot;Chugaisho,&quot; which became famous as a valuable historical manuscript that told of aristocratic society during the the period of the government by the retired Emperor (the title of the manuscript is derived by taking &apos;中&apos; (Naka) from Nakahara and &apos;外&apos; from Daigeki).</e>
<cmt>removed some Japanese words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto wrote down the conversation he had with Tadasane in &quot;Chugaisho,&quot; which became famous as a valuable historical manuscript that told of aristocratic society during the period of the government by the Retired Emperor (the title of the manuscript is derived by taking &apos;中&apos; (Naka) from Nakahara and &apos;外&apos; from Daigeki).</e>
<cmt>不要なtheを削除しました。Retiredに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱によって忠実が奈良の知足院に逼塞して後は、忠実の孫近衛基実の家司となり、大炊頭や出羽守を歴任し、位階は正四位上に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Keishi (servant) of Motozane KONOE, who was the grandson of Tadasane that lived in hiding in Chisoku-in Temple of Nara since the Hogen Disturbance in 1156, and became Oi no kami (Chief of Oi ryo (Palace kitchens)) and Dewa no kami (the governor of Dewa Province) before being promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a servant of Motozane KONOE, who was the grandson of Tadasane, who lived in hiding in Chisoku-in Temple of Nara after the Hogen Disturbance in 1156, and became Chief of and Governor of Dewa Province before being promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>prepositions; shortened by removing some asides</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a servant of Motozane KONOE, who was the grandson of Tadasane, who lived in hiding in Chisoku-in Temple of Nara after the Hogen Disturbance in 1156, and became Chief of and Governor of Dewa Province before being promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『中外抄』以外の著作としては、日記『大外記中原師元記』、年中行事解説書『師元年中行事』、『雑外抄』などを残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left &quot;Daigeki NAKAHARA no Morimoto ki&quot; (Daigeki of NAKAHARA no Morimoto), &quot;Annual Functions of Moromoto&quot; that described the annual events and ceremonies, and &quot;Zogesho&quot; in writing besides &quot;Chugaisho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The written works that he left are &quot;Daigeki NAKAHARA no Morimoto ki,&quot; &quot;Annual Functions of Moromoto&quot; which described annual events and ceremonies, and &quot;Zogesho,&quot; as well as &quot;Chugaisho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The written works that he left are &quot;Daigeki NAKAHARA no Morimoto ki,&quot; &quot;Annual Functions of Moromoto&quot; which described annual events and ceremonies, and &quot;Zogesho,&quot; as well as &quot;Chugaisho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Andee(id:20421), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>