<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉良義真</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizane KIRA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizane KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizane KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉良 義真（きら よしざね、応永29年（1422年）? - 文明 (日本)13年7月21日 (旧暦)（1481年8月16日））は室町時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizane KIRA (b. Unknown, 1422 – d. August 16, 1481) was a busho (military commander) in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizane KIRA (date of birth unknown, 1422 – August 16, 1481) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>表記を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizane KIRA (date of birth unknown, 1422 – August 16, 1481) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real family name was Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original family name was MINAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>この原文は短いため、その意味を考えずそのまま直訳するとこの訳になりますが、訳文は意味をなしていません。源氏を「げんじ」と呼ぶ際、その氏（うじ＝家系）の一般総称として我々は「げんじ」と言うだけで、源氏の家名は「みなもと」であるはずです。よってこの原文は、「吉良の本姓は「みなもと」姓であった」あるいは「吉良」はもともと「源氏」家系だった」の意味です。次の項目では家系の説明がありますので、ここでは「みなもと」姓であった、という訳にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original family name was MINAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一家系　河内源氏の棟梁　鎮守府将軍源義家の子　源義国を祖とする足利氏の一門 吉良氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family Kira clan related to the Ashikaga clan, descendant of MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni, son of the Chinju-fu shogun MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, head of the Kawachi-Genji clan and belonging to Seiwa-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>The relationship is somewhat unclear and requires review.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kira clan is one of the lineages of Ashikaga clan originated from MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni; since Yoshikuni was the son of Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) and the head of Kawachi-Genji clan (a lineage of Seiwa-Genji clan) MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Kira clan traces its roots to Seiwa-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>この原文はどのような意図か、句読点で区切られずスペースのみでの分節になっています。訳文ではそれをそのまま定冠詞なども用いずコンマで区切り、各文節が何を修飾しているのかがわかりづらくなっていたため、まず「吉良氏が足利氏一門であること」と「足利の祖が清和源氏の家系である河内源氏の棟梁源義家の息子、源義国であること」の二文に分ける形で修正しました。河内源氏の説明を括弧に収め、さらに鎮守府将軍の説明がありませんでしたので加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kira clan is one of the lineages of Ashikaga clan originated from MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni; since Yoshikuni was the son of Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) and the head of Kawachi-Genji clan (a lineage of Seiwa-Genji clan) MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Kira clan traces its roots to Seiwa-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>吉良俊氏の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Third son to Toshiuji KIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of Toshiuji KIRA.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドがありますが訳文は文章ではなく分節です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of Toshiuji KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>西条城主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lord of Saiji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the lord of Saijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドがありますが訳文は文章ではなく分節です。修正しました。西条城が「さいじじょう」に誤訳されていましたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Saijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>西条吉良氏（上吉良）4代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourth head of the Saijo-Kira (upper Kira) clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth head of the Saijo-Kira (upper Kira) clan.</e>
<cmt>文章になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth head of the Saijo-Kira (upper Kira) clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>官位は従四位左兵衛佐、治部少輔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official court ranks were Junior Fourth Rank, Sahyoe no suke and Jibushoyu (institution for the management of ceremonial events).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court ranks were jyushii (Junior Fourth Rank) Sahyoe no suke (undersecretary of the left imperial bodyguards) and Jibushoyu (institution for the management of ceremonial events).</e>
<cmt>従四位は「jyushii」と読みで訳出し、その意味を括弧内で説明する形に修正しました。「左兵衛佐」の解説を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court ranks were jyushii (Junior Fourth Rank) Sahyoe no suke (undersecretary of the left imperial bodyguards) and Jibushoyu (institution for the management of ceremonial events).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>兄は吉良義尚、吉良頼氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brothers were Yoshinao KIRA and Yoriuji KIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brothers were Yoshinao KIRA and Yoriuji KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brothers were Yoshinao KIRA and Yoriuji KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>他に本光院に入り禅僧となった弟がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had a younger brother who entered Honko-in Temple and became a Zen priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had a younger brother who entered Honko-in Temple and became a Zen priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had a younger brother who entered Honko-in Temple and became a Zen priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>妻は細川持賢の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was Mochikata HOSOKAWA&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was the daughter of Mochikata HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>口語では間違いではありませんが、この語順の場合「細川持賢」の印象のほうが強くなります。意味の上でより重要なのは「娘」で、それが「細川」で修飾されるのが本意です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was the daughter of Mochikata HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>子は吉良義信。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son was Yoshinobu KIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son was Yoshinobu KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son was Yoshinobu KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>兄である吉良義尚に男児が無く、その娘婿である斯波義健も早世したため、享徳年間（1452年 - 1455年）に兄から家督を譲られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the reigns to the family during the Kyotoku Era (1452-1455) by his elder brother Yoshinao KIRA who had no sons and whose adoped son-in-law Yoshitake SHIBA died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizane was handed over the headship of the family from his elder brother Yoshinao KIRA during the Kyotoku Era (1452-1455) because Yoshinao had no son and his adopted son-in-law Yoshitake SHIBA died young.</e>
<cmt>間違いではありませんが家督の原文に即し修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizane was handed over the headship of the family from his elder brother Yoshinao KIRA during the Kyotoku Era (1452-1455) because Yoshinao had no son and his adopted son-in-law Yoshitake SHIBA died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>足利義政の側にあって主として禅寺の所領問題に関与し一定の発言権を持っていたようである（『蔭凉軒日録』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was on the side of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, and it appears that he had a certain amount of influence mainly over problems regarding ownership of Zen temples (&quot;Inryoken Nichiroku&quot; [Dietary Life of Zen Priests]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was on the side of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, and it appears that he had a certain amount of influence mainly over the ownership issues regarding Zen temples (&quot;Inryoken Nichiroku&quot; [Dietary Life of Zen Priests]).</e>
<cmt>定冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was on the side of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, and it appears that he had a certain amount of influence mainly over the ownership issues regarding Zen temples (&quot;Inryoken Nichiroku&quot; [Dietary Life of Zen Priests]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、義真の頃には西条吉良氏は、石橋氏、渋川氏とともに将軍の「御一類」と呼ばれ、毎年正月5日に行われる将軍対面の式など様々な面で別格扱いを受けていた（『長禄三年以来申次記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, during Yoshizane&apos;s time the Seijo-Kira clan, along with the Ishibashi and Shibukawa clans were considered to belong to the same clan as the shogun, and received special treatment in many ways including at the ceremony held on the fifth day of each new year to meet the shogun (&quot;Records of Court Appearances from Choroku Era Third Year [1459]&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saijo-Kira clan during Yoshizane&apos;s time was called &quot;goichirui&quot; (lineages sharing the same origin) with the Ashikaga clan in the shogunate along with the Ishibashi and Shibukawa clans; they received special treatments in various occasions such as the ceremonial meeting held every year on the fifth day of a new year (&quot;Records of Court Appearances from Choroku Era Third Year [1459]&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「御一類」を意訳せず訳出し、説明を括弧に収めました。その他諸々の手直しをしています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saijo-Kira clan during Yoshizane&apos;s time was called &quot;goichirui&quot; (lineages sharing the same origin) with the Ashikaga clan in the shogunate along with the Ishibashi and Shibukawa clans; they received special treatments in various occasions such as the ceremonial meeting held every year on the fifth day of a new year (&quot;Records of Court Appearances from Choroku Era Third Year [1459]&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>長禄3年（1459年）12月17日、室町幕府が足利義持の33回忌法要を営むため、諸大名に銭の献納を求めた際、義真は10貫文を献上している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 17, 1459 Yoshizane presented 10 kanmon (1,000 kanmon = 10,000 yen) when the Muromachi shogunate appealed to all feudal lords to donate money in order to perform the Buddhist memorial service for Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA&apos;s 33rd death anniversary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 17, 1459 Yoshizane presented a large amount of contribution totaling 10 kanmon in response to the donation request of Muromachi bakufu to feudal lords for performing the 33rd death anniversary Buddhist memorial service of Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>原文では「10貫文」を大金であると暗に示していると思われますが、「1000 kanmon = 10,000 yen」は間違いではないでしょうか。 多少調べてみると江戸時代には1貫文=4石、10貫文で40石で、江戸時代とすると40石は1200-1300万円ほどになるようです。ただここでは正確な価値がわかりませんので、「大金である10貫文もの献納を行った」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 17, 1459 Yoshizane presented a large amount of contribution totaling 10 kanmon in response to the donation request of Muromachi bakufu to feudal lords for performing the 33rd death anniversary Buddhist memorial service of Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この2日前の12月15日、東条吉良氏（下吉良）当主の吉良義藤が同じく10貫文を献上している（『蔭凉軒日録』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two day prior, on December 15, Yoshifuji KIRA, head of the Tojo-Kira clan (lower Kira) had also presented 10 kanmon (&quot;Inryoken Nichiroku&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December, 15, two day prior to Yoshizane&apos;s contribution, the head of the Tojo-Kira clan (lower Kira) Yoshifuji KIRA had also donated 10 kanmon (&quot;Inryoken Nichiroku&quot;).</e>
<cmt>priorを用いる場合、to+で先立つ事柄を示す必要があり、ここでは用法上間違いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December, 15, two day prior to Yoshizane&apos;s contribution, the head of the Tojo-Kira clan (lower Kira) Yoshifuji KIRA had also donated 10 kanmon (&quot;Inryoken Nichiroku&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>寛正6年（1465年）12月20日に足利義尚が誕生した際、義真も将軍御所へ参上、御祝い言上をしているが、翌日、吉良義藤と揃って伊勢貞親邸を訪れ、将軍への取次ぎの礼を述べている（『親元日記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was born on December 20, 1465, Yoshizane presented himself at the shogun&apos;s palace to give his words of congratulations; the following day he appeared at Sadachika ISE&apos;s home with Yoshifuji KIRA in order to express his gratitude for having his message conveyed to the shogun (&quot;Chikamoto Nikki Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was born on December 20, 1465, Yoshizane visited the palace of shogun to give his words of congratulations; Yoshizane also visited the residence of Sadachika ISE with Yoshifuji KIRA on the following day to express his gratitude for having his message conveyed to the shogun (&quot;Chikamoto Nikki Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「参上」を「presented himself」としています。間違いではありませんが、前項目で「献上」をpresentを用いて訳していますので、誤解に繋がる重複を避けるためvisitedとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA was born on December 20, 1465, Yoshizane visited the palace of shogun to give his words of congratulations; Yoshizane also visited the residence of Sadachika ISE with Yoshifuji KIRA on the following day to express his gratitude for having his message conveyed to the shogun (&quot;Chikamoto Nikki Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>応仁の乱が起こると、義真は妻の従兄弟が細川勝元という関係から東軍に属し、西軍についた吉良義藤と対立、義藤が三河国に下向すると、これに対応するため京都を息子の吉良義信に任せ、応仁元年（1467年）5月18日に三河に向けて出立した（『大乗院寺社雑事記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Onin War broke out Yoshizane sided with the Eastern Camp due to the fact that his wife&apos;s cousin was Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, putting himself against Yoshifuji KIRA who sided with the Western Camp; when Yoshifuji left the capital for Mikawa Province, Yoshizane left his son Yoshinobu KIRA in charge in Kyoto and departed for Mikawa on May 18, 1467 (&quot;Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Onin War broke out Yoshizane sided with the Eastern Camp due to the fact that the cousin of his wife was Katsumoto HOSOKAWA of the Eastern Camp, putting himself against Yoshifuji KIRA sided with the Western Camp; when Yoshifuji left Kyoto to Mikawa Province, Yoshizane appointed his son Yoshinobu KIRA in charge of protecting Kyoto, and departed to Mikawa on May 18, 1467 for tracking down Yoshifuji (&quot;Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine&quot;).</e>
<cmt>語順などの変更を行っています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Onin War broke out Yoshizane sided with the Eastern Camp due to the fact that the cousin of his wife was Katsumoto HOSOKAWA of the Eastern Camp, putting himself against Yoshifuji KIRA sided with the Western Camp; when Yoshifuji left Kyoto to Mikawa Province, Yoshizane appointed his son Yoshinobu KIRA in charge of protecting Kyoto, and departed to Mikawa on May 18, 1467 for tracking down Yoshifuji (&quot;Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>三河での東西両吉良氏の戦いの様子は史料が無く判然としない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What happened in the battles between the eastern and western Kira clans at Mikawa Province are unclear, as there is no historical material on the subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What happened in the battles between the eastern and western Kira clans at Mikawa Province is unclear, as there is no historical material on the subject.</e>
<cmt>複数形を単数形に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What happened in the battles between the eastern and western Kira clans at Mikawa Province is unclear, as there is no historical material on the subject.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>僅かに『三河軍記』（嘉永6年（1853年）成立）がその模様を伝えるが、内容は誤謬が多く信頼できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is brief mention in &quot;the Mikawa Military Diary&quot; (published 1853), but there are too many fallacies to make it a credible source.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is a brief description about the event in the &quot;Mikawa Military Diary&quot; (published 1853), it is difficult to consider as a credible source for the fallacies of the content.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマーク位置をtheの後ろに変更しました。「その模様」が訳されていませんでしたので追加しました。thereで始まる文章が重なりますので、片方を削り重複を避けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is a brief description about the event in the &quot;Mikawa Military Diary&quot; (published 1853), it is difficult to consider as a credible source for the fallacies of the content.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>幾度か合戦は行ったものの、当主が没落するといった大規模なものにはならず、京都の東西両軍の和睦（文明9年（1477年））を受けて東西両吉良氏も和睦をしたのではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although several battles were fought there was nothing to bring down either head of the families, and it is thought that the reconciliation between the Eastern and Western Camps at Kyoto (1477) led to reconciliation between the eastern and western Kira clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were several battles between them, the scale of the battle was too small to damage neither families; it is considered that the reconciliation between the Eastern and Western Camps at Kyoto (1477) also led the peace settlement between the eastern and western Kira clans.</e>
<cmt>当主が没落するといった「大規模なものにはならず」の部分が訳文では欠如しています。追加し修正しました。和睦を同一単語を繰り返さない形で訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were several battles between them, the scale of the battle was too small to damage neither families; it is considered that the reconciliation between the Eastern and Western Camps at Kyoto (1477) also led the peace settlement between the eastern and western Kira clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただし、義真は三河奪回のため活発に活動を続ける西軍一色義直を牽制するためか、その後も三河に留まり一色義直が文明10年（1478年）に至り三河を放棄する旨、文書で表明したのを受け、ようやく翌文明11年（1479年）9月頃上洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshizane remained in Mikawa Province, perhaps to contain Yoshinao ISSHIKI of the Western Camp who was actively continuing his attempts to recapture Mikawa Province, and finally returned to the capital in September 1479 after Yoshinao ISSHIKI abandoned Mikawa in 1478 and expressed it in writing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizane remained in Mikawa Province possibly because he had to contain Yoshinao ISSHIKI of the Western Camp who had continued to be active for recapturing Mikawa Province; Yoshizane finally returned to Kyoto in September, 1479 after Yoshinao ISSHIKI expressed in writing to abandon his plan of capturing Mikawa in 1478.</e>
<cmt>フレーズの時制、流れ、意味の論理的な分割を考慮し修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizane remained in Mikawa Province possibly because he had to contain Yoshinao ISSHIKI of the Western Camp who had continued to be active for recapturing Mikawa Province; Yoshizane finally returned to Kyoto in September, 1479 after Yoshinao ISSHIKI expressed in writing to abandon his plan of capturing Mikawa in 1478.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>上洛後、義真は左大臣近衛政家の邸を訪れるなど公家との交際を再開するが、まもなく病気となり文明13年（1481年）7月21日に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning to the capital he resumed his affiliations with noble families, visiting those such as the Minister of the Left Masaie KONOE, but soon fell to illness and died on July 21, 1481.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning to Kyoto, Yoshizane resumed his affiliations with noble families by visiting the Minister of the Left Masaie KONOE and others, but he soon fell to illness and died on July 21, 1481.</e>
<cmt>「上洛」の訳を一般的な「京都へ行く」の意味になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to Kyoto, Yoshizane resumed his affiliations with noble families by visiting the Minister of the Left Masaie KONOE and others, but he soon fell to illness and died on July 21, 1481.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>享年は60か。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was around 60.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age of death was considered to be 60.</e>
<cmt>原文が意味する「不詳」の意味が伝わるような訳に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age of death was considered to be 60.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>葬儀は8月24日に行われ幕府政所執事伊勢貞宗は10貫文を献じている（『親元日記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The funeral was held on August 24, and Sadamune ISE, steward of the Bakufu Mandokoro, presented 10 kanmon (&quot;Chikamoto Nikki Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The funeral was held on August 24, and Sadamune ISE, steward of the Bakufu Mandokoro, presented 10 kanmon (&quot;Chikamoto Nikki Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The funeral was held on August 24, and Sadamune ISE, steward of the Bakufu Mandokoro, presented 10 kanmon (&quot;Chikamoto Nikki Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>法名は拈花院殿道山正弘大禅定門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Nengein-Dendozan-Masahiro-Daizenjomon.</e>
<cmt>Pronunciation of 拈花院殿道山正弘大禅定門 could not be found.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Nengein-Dendozan-Masahiro-Daizenjomon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Nengein-Dendozan-Masahiro-Daizenjomon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Oxhop(id:2551), GAVVA(id:47103), 海衛士(id:19229), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>