<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東郷平八郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heihachiro TOGO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heihachiro TOGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heihachiro TOGO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東郷 平八郎（とうごう へいはちろう、弘化4年12月22日 (旧暦)（1847年1月27日） - 昭和9年（1934年）5月30日は、日本の武士・薩摩藩士、大日本帝国海軍軍人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heihachiro TOGO (January 27, 1847-May 30, 1934) was a samurai, feudal retainer of Satsuma Domain, and a member of the Imperial Japanese Navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heihachiro TOGO (January 27, 1847 - May 30, 1934) was a samurai, a feudal retainer of the Satsuma Domain, and a member of the Imperial Japanese Navy.</e>
<cmt>Added spacesAdded &quot;a&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heihachiro TOGO (January 27, 1847 - May 30, 1934) was a samurai, a feudal retainer of the Satsuma Domain, and a member of the Imperial Japanese Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>軍隊における階級位階勲等爵位は元帥_(日本)海軍大将・従一位・菊花章・金鵄勲章・侯爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His various military class ranks and honors included fleet admiral, junior first rank, Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, Order of the Golden Kite, and marquis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His various military class ranks and honors included fleet admiral, junior first rank, Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, Order of the Golden Kite, and marquis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His various military class ranks and honors included Fleet Admiral, junior first rank, Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, Order of the Golden Kite, and marquis.</e>
<cmt>OK。wikipediaを参考に原文の「呼称一覧」は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治時代の日本海軍の司令官として日清戦争及び日露戦争の勝利に大きく貢献し、日本の国際的地位を「五大国」の一員とするまでに引き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a Navy commanding officer in the Meiji period, he contributed greatly to victories in the Sino-Japanese War and Russo-Japanese War, boosting Japan international standing to be one of the Big Five nations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a naval commanding officer in the Meiji period, he contributed greatly to victories in the Sino-Japanese War and Russo-Japanese War, boosting Japan&apos;s international standing to make it one of the five most powerful countries.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for grammar and fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a naval commanding officer in the Meiji period, he contributed greatly to victories in the Sino-Japanese War and Russo-Japanese War, boosting Japan&apos;s international standing to make it one of &apos;the five most powerful countries.&apos;</e>
<cmt>quotation mark</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日露戦争においては、連合艦隊を率いて日本海海戦で当時屈指の戦力を誇ったロシア海軍を一方的に破って世界の注目を集め、アドミラル・トーゴー（Admiral Togo、東郷提督）としてその名を広く知られることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He comanded the Combined Fleet in the Russo-Japanese War and became widely known around the world as &apos;Admiral Togo&apos;, being praised for his military potential after completely destroying the Russian Navy in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He comanded the Combined Fleet in the Russo-Japanese War and became widely known around the world as &apos;Admiral Togo&apos;, being praised for his military potential after completely destroying the Russian Navy in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He comanded the Combined Fleet in the Russo-Japanese War and became widely known around the world as &apos;Admiral Togo&apos;, being praised for his military potential after winning a lopsided victory over the Russian Navy in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>completely destroying -&gt; winning a lopsided victory over</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当時、日本の日英同盟国であったイギリスのジャーナリストらは東郷を「東洋のホレーショ・ネルソン」と、同国の国民的英雄に比して称えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Britain, which was in alliance with Japan, journalists coined the name &quot;Nelson of the East&quot; after national hero Vice Admiral Horatio Lord Nelson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Britain, which was in alliance with Japan, journalists coined the name &quot;Nelson of the East&quot; after national hero Vice Admiral Horatio Lord Nelson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Britain, which was in alliance with Japan, journalists coined the name &quot;Nelson of the East&quot; after national hero Vice Admiral Horatio Lord NELSON.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本では、大胆な敵前回頭戦法（丁字戦法）により日本を勝利に導いた世界的な名提督として、『陸の乃木　海の東郷』と乃木希典陸軍大将と並び称され、日露戦争の英雄として国民の尊敬を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the saying &quot;Nogi of the land, Togo of the sea&quot; he was classed with General Maresuku NOGI as the world-famous admiral who led Japan to victory by the daring Crossing the T tactic, and was much revered by the people as a hero of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the saying &quot;Nogi of the land, Togo of the sea&quot; he was classed with General Maresuku NOGI as the world-famous admiral who led Japan to victory by the daring Crossing the T tactic, and was much revered by the people as a hero of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the saying &quot;Nogi of the land, Togo of the sea&quot; he was classed with General Maresuku NOGI as the world-famous admiral who led Japan to victory by the daring Crossing the T tactic, and was much revered by the people as a hero of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生い立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>薩摩国鹿児島城下の加冶屋町二本松馬場（下加治屋町方限）に、薩摩藩士・東郷実友と堀与三左衛門の三女・益子の四男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOGO was born in Nihonmatsu Umaba in Kajiyamura near Kagoshima Castle in Satsuma Province (Shimokajiyacho Katagiri), the forth son of Satsuma feudal retainer Sanetomo TOGO and Mashiko, the third daughter of Saemon YOZO.</e>
<cmt>Confirm names</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TOGO was born in Nihonmatsu Umaba in Kajiyamura near Kagoshima Castle in Satsuma Province (Shimokajiyacho Katagiri), the forth son of Satsuma feudal retainer Sanetomo TOGO and Mashiko, the third daughter of Saemon YOZO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TOGO was born in Nihonmatsu Umaba in Kajiyacho near Kagoshima Castle in Satsuma Province (Shimokajiyacho Katagiri), as the forth son of Satsuma feudal retainer Sanetomo TOGO and Mashuko (益子), the third daughter of Yomizaemon HORI (堀与三左衛門).</e>
<cmt>益子、堀与三左衛門の読み方不明なので括弧書きにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名は仲五郎、14歳の時元服して平八郎実良と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Chugoro, and at his 14th birthday coming of age ceremony was named Heihachiro Saneyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Confirm name</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Chugoro, and at his 14th birthday coming of age ceremony was named Heihachiro Saneyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Nakagoro (仲五郎), and at his 14th birthday coming of age ceremony was named Heihachiro Saneyoshi (平八郎実良).</e>
<cmt>名前の読み方不明なので括弧書きで追記しました。※原文が間違っている可能性があります。「名は実良、後に仲五郎、元服して平八郎」参照：http://www.hakaishi.jp/tomb/tomb/04-51.html※Chugoro → Nakagoro 参照：http://www.bookrags.com/biography/heihachiro-togo/</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>慶応3年(1867年) 6月に分家して一家を興す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1867 he founded a branch family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1867 he founded a branch family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1867 he founded a branch family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>薩摩藩士として薩英戦争に従軍し、戊辰戦争では新潟・函館に転戦して阿波沖海戦や箱館戦争、宮古湾海戦で戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a feudal retainer of Satsuma, he served in the Anglo-Satsuma War (the Bombardment of Kagoshima), and in the Boshin War served in Niigata and Hakodate, and fighting in the Naval Battle of Awa, Battle of Hakodate and the Battle of Miyakowan bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a feudal retainer of Satsuma, he served in the Anglo-Satsuma War (the Bombardment of Kagoshima), and in the Boshin War served in Niigata and Hakodate, and fighting in the Naval Battle of Awa, Battle of Hakodate and the Battle of Miyakowan bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a feudal retainer of Satsuma, he served in the Anglo-Satsuma War (the Bombardment of Kagoshima), and in the Boshin War served in Niigata and Hakodate, and fighting in the Naval Battle of Awa, Battle of Hakodate and the Battle of Miyakowan bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>イギリス留学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Studies in Britain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Studies in Britain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Studies in England</e>
<cmt>Britain→England</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>大政奉還、明治の世の中になると海軍士官として明治4年（1871年）から同11年（1878年）まで、イギリスのポーツマス (イングランド)に官費留学する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1871 to 1879, during the Meiji period when imperial rule was restored, Togo studied in Portsmouth, England as a naval officer on a government scholarship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1871 to 1879, during the Meiji period when imperial rule was restored, Togo studied in Portsmouth, England as a naval officer on a government scholarship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1871 to 1878, during the Meiji period when imperial rule was restored, Togo studied in Portsmouth, England as a naval officer on a government scholarship.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>東郷は当初鉄道技師になることを希望していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He originally had wanted to be a railroad engineer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He originally had wanted to be a railroad engineer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He originally had wanted to be a railroad engineer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>イギリスに官費留学する際、最初は大久保利通に「留学をさせてください」と頼み込んだが、大久保は「平八郎はおしゃべりだから駄目だ」と言い断った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before studying on government scholarship in England, he at first pleaded to Toshimichi OKUBO to allow him to study abroad, but OKUBO denied him accusing him of being too much of a &quot;chatterbox&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before studying on government scholarship in England, he at first pleaded to Toshimichi OKUBO to allow him to study abroad, but Okubo denied him accusing him of being too much of a &quot;chatterbox&quot;.</e>
<cmt>OKUBO &gt; Okubo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before studying on government scholarship in England, he at first pleaded to Toshimichi OKUBO to allow him to study abroad, but Okubo denied him accusing him of being too much of a &quot;chatterbox.&quot;</e>
<cmt>quotation mark</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>次いで西郷隆盛に頼み込んだところ、「任せなさい」と快諾、ほどなく東郷のイギリス留学が決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, after begging Takamori SAIGO, SAIGO agreed saying &quot;leave it to me,&quot; and soon after it was decided that Togo would study in England</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, after begging Takamori SAIGO, Saigo agreed saying &quot;leave it to me,&quot; and soon after it was decided that Togo would study in England</e>
<cmt>SAIGO &gt; Saigo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, after begging Takamori SAIGO, Saigo agreed saying &quot;leave it to me,&quot; and soon after it was decided that Togo would study in England.</e>
<cmt>quotation mark</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>東郷の才能を軍人にあると見込んだ西郷の人物眼の確かさをも物語るものであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Something about SAIGO putting confidence in TOGO&apos;s ability to be a soldier.)</e>
<cmt>Not understood</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This demonstrates the accuracy of Saigo&apos;s ability to read people as he deemed that Togo&apos;s talents were better suited to the military</e>
<cmt>Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This demonstrates the accuracy of Saigo&apos;s ability to read people as he deemed that Togo&apos;s talents were better suited to the military.</e>
<cmt>period</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>当初ダートマスの海軍兵学校 (イギリス)への留学を希望したがイギリス側の事情で許されず、商船学校のウースター協会で学ぶことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first he hoped to study at the Britannia Royal Naval College in Dartmouth, but it was not permitted by Britain, and he ended up studying on the HMS Worcester, a marine merchant school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first he hoped to study at the Britannia Royal Naval College in Dartmouth, but it was not permitted by Britain, and he ended up studying on the HMS Worcester, a marine merchant school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first he hoped to study at the Britannia Royal Naval College in Dartmouth, but it was not permitted by Britain, and he ended up studying on the HMS Worcester, a marine merchant school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>留学先では「To go、China（「支那に行け」の意）」とからかわれるなど苦労が多く、おしゃべりだった性格はすっかり無口になってしまったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He faced many troubles during his study abroad, including being called &quot;to go China&quot; (a play of words on his name), and his outgoing personality turned completely silent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He faced many troubles during his study abroad, including being called &quot;to go China&quot; (a play of words on his name), and his outgoing personality turned completely silent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He faced many troubles during his study abroad, including being called &quot;to go China&quot; (a play of words on his name), and his outgoing personality turned completely silent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし宮古湾海戦に参戦していたことを告げると、一躍英雄として扱われることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when he informed them he participated in the Naval Battle of Miyako Bay he was immediately treated as a hero.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when he informed them he participated in the Naval Battle of Miyako Bay he was immediately treated as a hero.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when he informed them he participated in the Naval Battle of Miyako Bay he was immediately treated as a hero.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>この留学の間に国際法を学んだことによって、日清戦争時に防護巡洋艦浪速 (防護巡洋艦)の艦長として、停船の警告に応じないイギリスの商船「高陞号」を撃沈する（高陞号撃沈事件）にあたって、このことは国際法に違反しない行為であると正しく判断できたのだとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to studying international law in his time abroad, when he was captain of the Japanese cruiser Naniwa in the First Sino-Japanese Warhe, he correctly judged the sinking of the British merchant ship Kowshing, which did not respond after being warned to stop, as not a violation of international law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he studied international law during his time abroad, when he was captain of the Japanese cruiser Naniwa in the First Sino-Japanese War, he correctly judged the sinking of the British merchant ship Kowshing, which did not respond after being warned to stop, as not a violation of international law.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for grammar and spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he studied international law during his time abroad, when he was captain of the Japanese cruiser Naniwa in the First Sino-Japanese War, he correctly judged the sinking of the British merchant ship Kowshing, which did not respond after being warned to stop, as not a violation of international law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらに、このときの沈着な判断力が、のちに連合艦隊司令長官に人選される要素となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, his calm sense of judgement from this incident was later a factor in his selection as Commander-in-Chief of the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, his calm sense of judgement from this incident was later a factor in his selection as Commander-in-Chief of the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, his calm sense of judgement from this incident was later a factor in his selection as Commander-in-Chief of the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>帰国途上、西郷隆盛が西南戦争を起こして自害したと現地で知った東郷は、「もし私が日本に残っていたら西郷さんの下に馳せ参じていただろう」と言って、西郷の死を悼んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">En route back to Japan, Togo, who learnt of Takamori SAIGO&apos;s Satsuma Rebellion and subsequent suicide, said &quot;had I been in Japan I would have rushed to join Saigo,&quot; and he grieved over the man&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">En route back to Japan, Togo, who learnt of Takamori SAIGO&apos;s Satsuma Rebellion and subsequent suicide, said &quot;had I been in Japan I would have rushed to join Saigo,&quot; and he grieved over the man&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">En route back to Japan, Togo, who learnt of Takamori SAIGO&apos;s Satsuma Rebellion and subsequent suicide, said &quot;had I been in Japan I would have rushed to join Saigo,&quot; and he grieved over the man&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>quotation mark</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>実際、東郷の実兄である小倉壮九郎は、薩軍三番大隊九番小隊長として西南戦争に従軍し、城山攻防戦の際に自決している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togo&apos;s elder brother Sokuro OGURA actually served in the Satsuma Rebellion as commanding officer of the 3rd batallion 9th platoon, and committed suicide after the Battle of Shiroyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togo&apos;s elder brother Sokuro OGURA actually served in the Satsuma Rebellion as commanding officer of the 3rd batallion 9th platoon, and committed suicide after the Battle of Shiroyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo&apos;s elder brother Sokuro OGURA actually served in the Satsuma Rebellion as commanding officer of the third battalion ninth platoon, and committed suicide after the Battle of Shiroyama.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日清戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sino-Japanese War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sino-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sino-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>明治27年（1894年）の日清戦争では緒戦より「浪速 (防護巡洋艦)」艦長を務め、豊島沖海戦（イギリス船籍の高陞号撃沈事件）、黄海海戦 (日清戦争)、威海衛海戦で活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togo served as captain of the Naniwa protected cruiser from the beginning of hostilities in the Sino-Japanese War of 1894, and had an active role in the Battle of Pungdo (the sinking of the British Kowshing incident), the Battle of Yalu (Sino-Japanese War), and the Battle of Weihaiwei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togo served as captain of the Naniwa protected cruiser from the beginning of hostilities in the Sino-Japanese War of 1894, and had an active role in the Battle of Pungdo (the sinking of the British Kowshing incident), the Battle of Yalu (Sino-Japanese War), and the Battle of Weihaiwei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo served as captain of the &apos;Naniwa (protected cruiser)&apos; from the beginning of hostilities in the Sino-Japanese War of 1894, and had an active role in the Battle of Pungdo (the sinking of the British Kowshing incident), the Battle of Yalu (Sino-Japanese War), and the Battle of Weihaiwei.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション及び括弧追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>威海衛海戦後に少将に進級し同時に常備艦隊司令官となるが、戦時編成のため実際には連合艦隊第一遊撃隊司令官として澎湖島攻略戦に参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Battle of Weihaiwei he was promoted to rear admiral, and also became commanding officer of the Standing Fleet, but wartime organisation meant that he participated in the capture of Penghu as commander of the first attack column of the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Battle of Weihaiwei he was promoted to rear admiral, and also became commanding officer of the Standing Fleet, but wartime organisation meant that he participated in the capture of Penghu as commander of the first attack column of the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Battle of Weihaiwei he was promoted to rear admiral, and also became commanding officer of the Standing Fleet, but wartime organisation meant that he participated in the capture of Penghu as commander of the first attack column of the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>日清戦争後一時病床に伏すも、明治32年に佐世保鎮守府司令長官となり、明治34年（1901年）には新設の舞鶴鎮守府初代司令長官に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Sino-Japanese War he temporarily lay low with sickness, but in 1899 became commander of the Sasebo Naval College, and in 1901 was assigned the first commander of the newly established Maizuru Naval Base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Sino-Japanese War he temporarily lay low with sickness, but in 1899 became commander of the Sasebo Naval College, and in 1901 was assigned the first commander of the newly established Maizuru Naval Base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Sino-Japanese War he temporarily lay low with sickness, but in 1899 became commander of the Sasebo Naval College, and in 1901 was assigned the first commander of the newly established Maizuru Naval Base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは後の対米戦備での位置づけから閑職であったと見なされがちであるが、来る対露戦を想定してロシアのウラジオストク軍港に対峙する形で設置された重要ポストであり、決して閑職ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the position of later preparations for war against America there was a tendency to see this as a leisurely post, but the important point was that it sat opposite Russia&apos;s Vladivostok naval port on the assumption that war with Russia would come.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the position of later preparations for war against America there was a tendency to see this as a leisurely post, but the important point was that it sat opposite Russia&apos;s Vladivostok naval port on the assumption that war with Russia would come.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the position of later preparations for war against America there was a tendency to see this as a leisurely post, but the important point was that it sat opposite Russia&apos;s Vladivostok naval port on the assumption that war with Russia would come.</e>
<cmt>apostrophe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>但し、東郷自身は中央への移動を希望していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Togo himself seemed to want to transfer to a central position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Togo himself seemed to want to transfer to a central position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Togo himself seemed to want to transfer to a central position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>しかしながら日露開戦前の緊迫時期に海軍首脳の山本権兵衛に呼び戻され、明治36年（1903年）12月に第一艦隊 (日本海軍)兼連合艦隊司令長官に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, in the tense lead-up to the Russo-Japan War Navy Minister Gonnohyoe YAMAMOTO called him back and in December 1903 appointed him as Commander-in-Chief of the IJN 1st Fleet and the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, in the tense lead-up to the Russo-Japan War Navy Minister Gonnohyoe YAMAMOTO called him back and in December 1903 appointed him as Commander-in-Chief of the IJN 1st Fleet and the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, in the tense lead-up to the Russo-Japan War Navy Minister Gonnohyoe YAMAMOTO called him back and in December 1903 appointed him as Commander-in-Chief of the IJN first Fleet and the Combined Fleet.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>本来は常備艦隊司令長官である日高壮之丞がそのまま就任するのが筋であったが、山本が我の強い日高を嫌って命令に忠実な東郷を据えたのだといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally the Commander-in-Chief of the Standing Fleet Sonojo HIDAKA would be next in line for this position, but it was thought that YAMAMOTO disliked HIDAKA&apos;s self-assertion, placing the loyal TOGO into the role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally the Commander-in-Chief of the Standing Fleet Sonojo HIDAKA would be next in line for this position, but it was thought that Yamamoto disliked Hidaka&apos;s self-assertion, placing the loyal Togo into the role.</e>
<cmt>HIDAKA &gt; HidakaYAMAMOTO &gt; YamamotoTOGO &gt; Togo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally the Commander-in-Chief of the Standing Fleet Sonojo HIDAKA would be next in line for this position, but it was thought that Yamamoto disliked Hidaka&apos;s self-assertion, placing the loyal Togo into the role.</e>
<cmt>apostrophe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし実際には、日高が健康問題を抱えており指揮が難しい状態であり、当時の将官の中で実戦経験豊富な東郷が至極順当に選ばれたというのが真相であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In actual fact, HIDAKA had health problems which would make it difficult to command, and Togo, with the most experience of all the admirals at the time, was a very reasonable choice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In actual fact, Hidaka had health problems which would make it difficult to command, and Togo, with the most experience of all the admirals at the time, was a very reasonable choice.</e>
<cmt>HIDAKA &gt; Hidaka</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In actual fact, Hidaka had health problems which would make it difficult to command, and Togo, with the most experience of all the admirals at the time, was a very reasonable choice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>またこの時、明治天皇に理由を聞かれた山本は「東郷は運のいい男ですから」と奏したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YAMAMOTO also reportedly told Emperor Meiji that his reason for selecting him was because he was &quot;a man of good fortune&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamamoto also reportedly told Emperor Meiji that his reason for selecting him was because he was &quot;a man of good fortune&quot;.</e>
<cmt>YAMAMOTO &gt; Yamamoto</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamamoto also reportedly told Emperor Meiji that his reason for selecting him was because he was &quot;a man of good fortune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>quotation mark</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>日露戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>明治37年（1904年）2月10日からの日露戦争では、旗艦三笠 (戦艦)に座乗してロシア東洋艦隊（ロシア第一太平洋艦隊）の基地である旅順港の攻撃（旅順港閉塞作戦）や黄海海戦 (日露戦争)をはじめとする海軍の作戦全般を指揮する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Russo-Japanese War from February 10 1904, he was aboard the flagship battleship Mikasa and commanded the Navy&apos;s entire military strategy, including the attack on Port Arthur (Battle of Port Arthur) which was the base of the Russian Far East fleet (the Russian 1st Pacific Squadron).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Russo-Japanese War from February 10 1904, he was aboard the flagship battleship Mikasa and commanded the Navy&apos;s entire military strategy, including the attack on Port Arthur (Battle of Port Arthur) which was the base of the Russian Far East fleet (the Russian 1st Pacific Squadron).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Russo-Japanese War from February 10 1904, he was aboard the flagship battleship Mikasa and commanded the Navy&apos;s entire military strategy, including the attack on Port Arthur (Battle of Port Arthur) which was the base of the Russian Far East fleet (the Russian first Pacific Squadron).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>そして明治38年（1905年）5月27日に、ヨーロッパから極東へ向けて回航してきたジノヴィー・ロジェストヴェンスキー提督率いるロシアのバルチック艦隊（ロシア第二・第三太平洋艦隊、旗艦「クニャージ・スォーロフ」）を迎撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, on May 27 1905 he ambushed the Russian Baltic Fleet (Russian 2nd and 3rd Pacific Squadrons and the flagship Knyaz Suvorov) that were commanded by Admiral Zinovy Rozhestvensky who had sailed from Europe to the Far East.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, on May 27 1905 he ambushed the Russian Baltic Fleet (Russian 2nd and 3rd Pacific Squadrons and the flagship Knyaz Suvorov) that were commanded by Admiral Zinovy Rozhestvensky who had sailed from Europe to the Far East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, on May 27, 1905 he ambushed the Russian Baltic Fleet (Russian second and third Pacific Squadrons and the flagship Knyaz Suvorov) that were commanded by Admiral Zinovy ROZHESTVENSKY who had sailed from Europe to the Far East.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この日本海海戦に際し、「敵艦見ゆとの警報に接し、連合艦隊はただちに出動これを撃滅せんとす。本日天気晴朗なれども波高し」と秋山真之参謀が起草し大本営に一報を打電した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Battle of Tsushima, staff officer Saneyuki AKIYAMA wired a message to the Imperial General Headquarters which read, &quot;I have received report that that the enemy fleet has been sighted and our fleet will proceed forthwith to sea to attack the enemy and destroy him. The weather today is fine but the waves are high.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Battle of Tsushima, staff officer Saneyuki AKIYAMA wired a message to the Imperial General Headquarters which read, &quot;I have received report that that the enemy fleet has been sighted and our fleet will proceed forthwith to sea to attack the enemy and destroy him. The weather today is fine but the waves are high.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Battle of Tsushima, staff officer Saneyuki AKIYAMA sent a report by telegraph to the Imperial General Headquarters which read, &quot;Have received report that that enemy fleet has been sighted and our fleet will proceed forthwith to sea to attack and destroy the enemy. Weather today is fine but waves are high.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Nothing in the original seems to correspond to &quot;wireless&quot; so I deleted it (this does not exclude the possibility). Also reworded it. Also used concise English to reflect telegraph style, deleting unnecessary words.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、艦隊に対し、「皇国の興廃この一戦にあり。各員一層奮励努力せよ」とZ旗を掲げて全軍の士気を鼓舞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, to inspire morale to the entire fleet Togo said, &quot;the Empire&apos;s fate depends on this battle. Let every man do his utmost duty,&quot; and ordered the hoisting of the Z flag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, to inspire morale to the entire fleet Togo said, &quot;the Empire&apos;s fate depends on this battle. Let every man do his utmost duty,&quot; and ordered the hoisting of the Z flag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, to inspire morale to the entire fleet Togo said, &quot;the Empire&apos;s fate depends on this battle. Let every man do his utmost duty,&quot; and ordered the hoisting of the Z flag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>東郷は丁字戦法、その後「トウゴウ・ターン」と呼ばれる戦法を使って海戦に勝利を納めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Employing the Crossing the T tactic, later called the &quot;Togo Turn&quot;, he led the Imperial Navy to victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Employing the Crossing the T tactic, later called the &quot;Togo Turn&quot;, he led the Imperial Navy to victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Employing the Crossing the T tactic, later called the &quot;Togo Turn,&quot; he led the Imperial Navy to victory.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>この海戦における勝利は、当時帝政ロシアの圧力に苦しんでいたトルコにおいても自国の勝利のように喜ばれ、東郷は同国の国民的英雄となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even Turkey, which was suffering pressure from Imperial Russia at the time, celebrated this victory as if it was its own, and Togo became a national hero there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even Turkey, which was suffering pressure from Imperial Russia at the time, celebrated this victory as if it was its own, and Togo became a national hero there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even Turkey, which was suffering pressure from Imperial Russia at the time, celebrated this victory as if it was its own, and Togo became a national hero there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その年に同国で生まれた子供たちの中には、トーゴーと名づけられる者もおり、また「トーゴー通り」と名付けられた通りもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That year in Turkey there were even people that named their children &quot;Togo&quot;, and a street was also named after him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That year in Turkey there were even people that named their children &quot;Togo&quot;, and a street was also named after him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That year in Turkey there were even people that named their children &quot;Togo,&quot; and a street was also named after him.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>日露戦争後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Post Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Post Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Post Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>日本海海戦での勝利により海軍大将に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following victory in the Battle of Tsushima he was promoted to Navy General.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following victory in the Battle of Tsushima he was promoted to Navy General.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following victory in the Battle of Tsushima he was promoted to Navy General.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>日露戦争終了直後、訪問艦にて同盟国のイギリスに渡洋、他の将校や乗組員とともにサッカー（フットボールリーグ、ニューカッスル・ユナイテッドのホームゲーム）を観戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after the close of the Russo-Japanese War he travelled to allied Britain and went to see a football match (at Newcastle United) with other commissioned officers and the crew.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the close of the Russo-Japanese War he travelled to allied Britain and went to see a football match (at Newcastle United) with other commissioned officers and the crew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the close of the Russo-Japanese War he travelled to allied Britain and went to see a football match (at Newcastle United) with other commissioned officers and the crew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>明治38年（1905年）から同42年（1909年）まで海軍軍令部長、東宮御学問所総裁を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1905 to 1909 he worked as the Chief of Naval General Staff and was put in charge of the Togu School (a school to educate the crown prince).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1905 to 1909 he worked as the Chief of Naval General Staff and was put in charge of the Togu School (a school to educate the crown prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1905 to 1909 he worked as the Chief of Naval General Staff and was put in charge of the president of Togu School (a school to educate the crown prince).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>明治39年（1906年）、日露戦争の功により大勲位菊花大綬章と功一級金鵄勲章を授与される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1906 due to his achievements in the Russo-Japanese War he was awarded the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum and the Order of the Golden Kite (1st class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1906 due to his achievements in the Russo-Japanese War he was awarded the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum and the Order of the Golden Kite (1st class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1906 due to his achievements in the Russo-Japanese War he was awarded the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum and the Order of the Golden Kite (first class).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>明治40年（1907年）には伯爵を授爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also granted the title hakushaku (count) in 1907.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also granted the title hakushaku (count) in 1907.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also granted the title hakushaku (count) in 1907.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>大正2年（1913年）4月には元帥_(日本)に列せられ、天皇の御前での杖の使用を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1913 he received the honorary title of gensui (Naval Marshall-General) and was permitted to stand before the Emperor while holding a cane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1913 he received the honorary title of gensui (Naval Marshall-General) and was permitted to stand before the Emperor while holding a cane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1913 he received the honorary title of gensui (Naval Marshall-General) and was permitted to stand before the Emperor while holding a cane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>大正15年（1926年）に大勲位菊花章頸飾を受章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1926 he was awarded the Collar of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1926 he was awarded the Collar of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1926 he was awarded the Collar of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>当時の頸飾受章者は皇太子昭和天皇と閑院宮載仁親王だけだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only recipients of this award at the time were Crown Prince Hirohito and Prince Kanin Kotohito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only recipients of this award at the time were Crown Prince Hirohito and Prince Kanin Kotohito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only recipients of this award at the time were Crown Prince Hirohito and Prince Kanin Kotohito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、タイム (雑誌)の1926年11月8日号において、日本人としては初のカバーパーソンとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he was the first Japanese person to be on the cover of Time magazine (November 8 1926 edition).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he was the first Japanese person to be on the cover of Time magazine (November 8 1926 edition).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he was the first Japanese person to be on the cover of Time magazine (November 8, 1926 edition).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later Years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later Years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>末次信正、加藤寛治らのいわゆる艦隊派の提督が東郷を利用し軍政に干渉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The heads of the so called Kantaiha (Fleet Faction) Nobumasa SUETSUGU, Kanji KATO used Togo to interfere in the military administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The heads of the so called Kantaiha (Fleet Faction) Nobumasa SUETSUGU, Kanji KATO used Togo to interfere in the military administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The heads of the so called Kantaiha (Fleet Faction) Nobumasa SUETSUGU, Kanji KATO used Togo to interfere in the military administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>昭和5年（1930年）のロンドン海軍軍縮会議に際して反対の立場を取ったロンドン軍縮問題はその典型であるが、その他に明治以来の懸案であった、兵科と機関科の処遇格差の是正（一系問題。兵科は機関科に対し処遇・人事・指揮権等全てに優越していた）についても東郷は改革案に反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One example was that when the London Naval Conference was held in 1930, TOGO was opposed to the treaty for the limitation of naval armaments, and another one was that he expressed objection to the draft for correction of the disparities in treatments between the branches of teeth arms and those of supporting arms (the issue about line of command; teeth arms were superior to supporting arms in everything, such as treatments, personnel affairs, and command authorities).</e>
<cmt>Don&apos;t ｕｎｄｅｒｓｔａｎｄ /   セル83と84を一文として訳出しました。/兵科→teeth arms; branches of the armed forces which actually fight (such as armor, artillery, infantry),/機関科→supporting arms; arms which support the teeth arms (eg. engineers, signals, transport)&lt; Military Dictionary.Com より /一系問題→the issue about the line of command と訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One example was that when the London Naval Conference was held in 1930, TOGO was opposed to the treaty for the limitation of naval armaments, and another one was that he expressed objection to the draft for correction of the disparities in treatments between the branches of teeth arms and those of supporting arms (the issue about line of command; teeth arms were superior to supporting arms in everything, such as treatments, personnel affairs, and command authorities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One example was that when the London Naval Conference was held in 1930, TOGO was opposed to the treaty for the limitation of naval armaments, and another one was that he expressed objection to the draft for correction of the disparities in treatments between the branches of teeth arms and those of supporting arms (the issue about line of command; teeth arms were superior to supporting arms in everything, such as treatments, personnel affairs, and command authorities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>結局、この問題は第二次世界大戦の終戦直前に改正されるまで部内対立の火種として残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, the fire of internal opposition was not contained until this issue was altered just before the end of the Second World War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, the fire of internal opposition was not contained until this issue was altered just before the end of the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, the fire of internal opposition was not contained until this issue was altered just before the end of the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>その他にも、第一種軍装を詰襟からイギリス式のダブルに変更する案が出たが、「この服（詰襟を指す）で、日本海海戦に勝ちました」との東郷の一言で、変更の話は立ち消えになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another one was that the idea of changing a stand-up collar of the first official military dress into a double-breast jacket in English style became a dead issue by words of TOGO, who said, &quot;The Imperial Japanese Navy won the victory in the Battle of Tsushima, wearing this military dress.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Don&apos;t understand/第一種軍装→the first official military dressと訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another one was that the idea of changing a stand-up collar of the first official military dress into a double-breast jacket in English style but this was scrapped by the words of TOGO who said &quot;The Imperial Japanese Navy won the victory in the Battle of Tsushima wearing this military dress.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for accuracy.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another one was that the idea of changing a stand-up collar of the first official military dress into a double-breast jacket in English style but this was scrapped by the words of TOGO who said &quot;The Imperial Japanese Navy won the victory in the Battle of Tsushima wearing this military dress.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>壮年時代はよく遊び、料亭に数日間も居続けたり、鉄砲打ちに出かけたりしたが、晩年は質素倹約を旨とし、趣味といえば盆栽と碁を嗜む程度であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the prime of his life he often played, visited restaurants for days at a time, and went out shooting, but in his later years he made it his concern to live a simple, frugal life, with interests such as bonzai and go.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the prime of his life he often played, visited restaurants for days at a time, and went out shooting, but in his later years he made it his concern to live a simple, frugal life, with interests such as bonzai and go.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the prime of his life he often played, visited Ryotei (fancy Japanese-style restaurants) for days at a time, and went out shooting, but in his later years he made it his concern to live a simple, frugal life, with interests such as bonsai (a dwarf miniature potted tree) and a game of Go.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>自ら七輪を用いて、料理をすることもあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also often cooked using a shichirin (earthen charcoal brazier).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also often cooked using a shichirin (earthen charcoal brazier).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also often cooked using a shichirin (earthen charcoal brazier).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>しかし新聞記者に対し妻が、新婚時代内職して家計を支えたエピソードを話すと、家族に経済的心配を掛けたことはないと激怒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An episode about which TOGO&apos;s wife talked to press reporters made TOGO get angry that she had supplemented to the family income with a side job in their newly-married days; he, however, told that he had never given his family members any economical trouble.</e>
<cmt>Don&apos;t understand. Something about being angry at a reporter, the wife doing the family accounts, never being economically worried about the family.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when his wife told press reporters that she had supplemented the family income with a side job in their newly-married days, he angrily responded that he had never given his family any financial worries.</e>
<cmt>Completely retranslated,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when his wife told press reporters that she had supplemented the family income with a side job in their newly-married days, he angrily responded that he had never given his family any financial worries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>死去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>昭和9年（1934年）に88歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togo died in 1934 at age 88.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togo died in 1934 at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the…of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo died in 1934 at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>死去の前日に侯爵に陞爵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day before he died he was given the title marquis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The day before he died he was given the title marquis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The day before he died he was given the title marquis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>死去に際しては全国から膨大な数の見舞い状が届けられたが、ある小学生が書いた「トウゴウゲンスイデモシヌノ？」という文面が新聞に掲載され大きな反響をよんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he died a great number of sympathy letters were sent, but one primary school student wrote, &apos;Even Admiral Togo dies?,&apos; which was published in the newspapers and received a big reaction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he died a great number of sympathy letters were sent, but one primary school student wrote, &apos;Even Admiral Togo dies?,&apos; which was published in the newspapers and received a big reaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he died a great number of sympathy letters were sent, and one primary school student wrote, &apos;Even Admiral Togo dies?,&apos; which was published in the newspapers and received a big reaction.</e>
<cmt>文脈からbutをandに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>6月5日に国葬が執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His state funeral was held on June 5th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His state funeral was held on June 5th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His state funeral was held on June 5.</e>
<cmt>date</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>国葬の際には、イギリス帝国海軍東洋艦隊旗艦の重巡洋艦「ケント」、アメリカ海軍アジア艦隊旗艦の「ヒューストン」をはじめ、フランスとイタリアという当時の「五大国」の艦船をはじめ、オランダや中華民国の艦船が直ちに東京湾を目指して出港。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of his state funeral, fleets of the Five Big Nations at the time including the British Imperial Navy Eastern Fleet heavy cruiser the Kent, American Navy Asian fleet flagship the Houston, the fleets of France, Italy, Holland and China departed immediately for Tokyo Bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of his state funeral, fleets of the five most powerful countries at the time including the British Imperial Navy Eastern Fleet heavy cruiser the Kent, American Navy Asian fleet flagship the Houston, the fleets of France, Italy, Holland and China departed immediately for Tokyo Bay.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Five Big Nations&quot; &gt; &quot;five most powerful countries&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the occasion of his state funeral, fleets of &apos;the five most powerful countries&apos; at the time including the British Imperial Navy Eastern Fleet heavy cruiser &apos;the Kent,&apos; American Navy Asian fleet flagship &apos;the Houston,&apos; the fleets of France, Italy, Holland and China departed immediately for Tokyo Bay.</e>
<cmt>quotation mark</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>儀仗隊を葬列に参加させ、弔砲を定刻に発砲し、偉大な功績を称えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A cortege participated in a funeral procession, and fired an artillery funeral salute at the appropriate time to mark the greatness of his achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A cortege participated in the funeral procession, and fired an artillery funeral salute at the appropriate time to mark the greatness of his achievements.</e>
<cmt>a &gt; the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A cortege participated in the funeral procession, and fired an artillery funeral salute at the appropriate time to mark the greatness of his achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>東郷の遺髪はイギリス海軍のホレーショ・ネルソンの遺髪と共に海上自衛隊幹部候補生学校（江田島基地）に厳重に保管されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hair of Togo together with the hair of Vice Admiral Horatio Lord Nelson of the British Navy is strictly guarded at the Officer Candidate School and JMSDF Officer Candidate School (Etajima base).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hair of Togo together with the hair of Vice Admiral Horatio Lord Nelson of the British Navy is strictly guarded at the Officer Candidate School and JMSDF Officer Candidate School (Etajima base).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hair of Togo together with the hair of Vice Admiral Horatio Lord NELSON of the British Navy is strictly guarded at JMSDF Officer Candidate School (Etajima base).</e>
<cmt>wikipediaを参考に原文と訳文の「幹部候補生学校」を削除しました。Spelling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="62">
<j>子孫には海軍兵学校 (日本)40期生で少将になった息子の東郷実 (海軍軍人)、その子で72期生の東郷良一（少尉で重巡洋艦摩耶に乗組み、比島沖海戦で戦死し2階級特進で大尉になった）、曾孫には防衛大学校卒の幹部海上自衛官がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOGO&apos;s descendants include Minoru TOGO, his son, who was the 40th alumni of the Imperial Japanese Naval Academy to become major general (of the Imperial Japanese Navy), Ryoichi TOGO, his grandson, (who, boarding on the heavy cruiser Maya, was killed in the Battle of Leyte Gulf, and became next two ranks up from lieutenant to captain), and his great grandson, who was a line officer of the Maritime Self Defense Official, who graduated from National Defense Academy.</e>
<cmt>海軍兵学校→the Imperial Jsapanese Naval Academyと訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TOGO&apos;s descendants include Minoru TOGO, his son, who was the 40th alumni of the Imperial Japanese Naval Academy to become major general (of the Imperial Japanese Navy), Ryoichi TOGO, his grandson, (who, boarding on the heavy cruiser Maya, was killed in the Battle of Leyte Gulf, and became next two ranks up from lieutenant to captain), and his great grandson, who was a line officer of the Maritime Self Defense Official, who graduated from National Defense Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TOGO&apos;s descendants include Minoru TOGO, his son, who was the 40th alumni of the Imperial Japanese Naval Academy to become major general (of the Imperial Japanese Navy), Ryoichi TOGO, his grandson, (who, boarding on the heavy cruiser Maya, was killed in the Battle of Leyte Gulf, and became next two ranks up from lieutenant to captain), and his great grandson, who was a line officer of the Maritime Self Defense Official, who graduated from National Defense Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>係累の東郷良尚は日本ユニセフ協会の副会長である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa TOGO, his relative, is a vice-chairman of the Japan Committee for UNISEF.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa TOGO, his relative, is a vice-chairman of the Japan Committee for UNICEF.</e>
<cmt>UNISEF &gt; UNICEF</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa TOGO, his relative, is a vice-chairman of the Japan Committee for UNICEF.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>神格化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deification</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>死後東京都渋谷区と福岡県宗像郡津屋崎町（現福津市）に「東郷神社」が建立され神として祭られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togo Shrine was founded in Shibuya Ward, Tokyo, and in Tsuyazaki-cho, Munakata-gun, Fukuoka Prefecture (now, Fukutsu City) after his death in his memory.</e>
<cmt>「神として祭られた」→in his memory と意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togo Shrine was founded in Shibuya Ward, Tokyo, and in Tsuyazaki-cho, Munakata-gun, Fukuoka Prefecture (now, Fukutsu City) after his death in his memory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo Shrine&apos; was founded in Shibuya Ward, Tokyo, and in Tsuyazaki-cho, Munakata-gun, Fukuoka Prefecture (now, Fukutsu City), and he after his death in his memory.</e>
<cmt>quotation mark</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>但し東郷自身は生前乃木神社建立の時、将来自身を祭る神社の設立計画を聞いて、「止めて欲しい」と強く懇願したが、結局神社は建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing a plan to found a shrine enshrined him in future when Nogi Shrine was built, Togo pleaded to stop the plan before his death, but the shrine was established in the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon hearing a plan to found a shrine enshrining him in the future when Nogi Shrine was built, Togo pleaded to stop the plan before his death, but the shrine was established in the end.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon hearing a plan to found a shrine enshrining him in the future when Nogi Shrine was built, Togo pleaded to stop the plan before his death, but the shrine was established in the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また銅像が長崎県佐世保市の旧海軍墓地東公園 (佐世保市)と鹿児島県鹿児島市の多賀山公園にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His statues were also erected in the East Park, old Imperial Japanese Navy Cemetery, Sasebo City, Nagasaki Prefecture and in Taga Park, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>住所に佐世保市とあるので（佐世保市）は訳出しておりません</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His statues were also erected in the East Park, old Imperial Japanese Navy Cemetery, Sasebo City, Nagasaki Prefecture and in Taga Park, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His statues were also erected in the East Park, old Imperial Japanese Navy Cemetery, Sasebo City, Nagasaki Prefecture and in Tagayama Park, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>東京都府中市 (東京都)には別荘地に建立された東郷寺があり、桜の名所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togo-ji Temple was founded at the site which used to be his villa, in Fuchu City, Tokyo Prefecture, which is famous for beautiful cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt>住所に東京都があるので（東京都）は訳出しておりません</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togo-ji Temple was founded at the site which used to be his villa, in Fuchu City, Tokyo Prefecture, which is famous for its beautiful cherry blossom.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;its&quot;blossoms &gt; blossoms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo-ji Temple was founded at the site which used to be his villa, in Fuchu City, Tokyo Prefecture, which is famous for its beautiful cherry blossom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>晩年において海軍における東郷の権威は絶大で、官制上の権限は無いにもかかわらず軍令・軍政上の大事は東郷にお伺いを立てることが慣例化していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, TOGO&apos;s enormous authority in the Navy made it a custom for the Navy to ask his statements about military orders and martial laws although he had already stepped down from public office.</e>
<cmt>官制上の権限は無い→step down from public officeと訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, Togo&apos;s enormous authority in the Navy made it a custom for the Navy to ask for his statements about military orders and martial laws although he had already stepped down from public office.</e>
<cmt>TOGO &gt; TogoAdded &quot;for&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, Togo&apos;s enormous authority in the Navy made it a custom for the Navy to ask for his statements about military orders and martial laws although he had already stepped down from public office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>海軍省内では伏見宮博恭王軍令部総長とともに「殿下と神様」と呼ばれ、しばしば軍政上の障碍とみなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ministry of the Navy, Prince Fushinomiya Hiroyasu, the President of the Naval General Staff, and TOGO were called &apos;Imperial Highness and God,&apos; regarded as interferences with military government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ministry of the Navy, Prince Fushinomiya Hiroyasu, the President of the Naval General Staff, and TOGO were called &apos;Imperial Highness and God,&apos; regarded as interferences with military government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ministry of the Navy, Prince Fushiminomiya Hiroyasu, the President of the Naval General Staff, and TOGO were called &apos;Imperial Highness and God,&apos; regarded as interferences with military government.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>井上成美は「東郷さんが平時に口出しすると、いつもよくないことが起きた」と述懐したうえで、「人間を神様にしてはいけません。神様は批判できませんからね。」と語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeyoshi INOUE related TOGO&apos;s reminiscences, saying, &quot;TOGO&apos;s interferences in peace time always caused something bad, and we must not make a human beings a god because the god is out of criticism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>セル118と119は一文にして訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeyoshi INOUE related Togo&apos;s reminiscences, saying that &quot;Togo&apos;s interferences in peacetime always caused something bad to happen, and we must not deify human beings gods because gods are beyond criticism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeyoshi INOUE related Togo&apos;s reminiscences, saying that &quot;Togo&apos;s interferences in peacetime always caused something bad to happen, and we must not deify human beings gods because gods are beyond criticism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>また岡田啓介・米内光政・山本五十六なども、東郷の神格化については否定的な態度をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keisuke OKADA, Mitsumasa YONAI, Isoroku YAMAMOTO, and others expressed skepticism about the deification of TOGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keisuke OKADA, Mitsumasa YONAI, Isoroku YAMAMOTO, and others expressed skepticism about the deification of Togo.</e>
<cmt>TOGO &gt; Togo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keisuke OKADA, Mitsumasa YONAI, Isoroku YAMAMOTO, and others also expressed skepticism about the deification of Togo.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>「東郷ビール伝説」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend of TOGO beer</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend of Togo Beer</e>
<cmt>TOGO beer &gt; Togo Beer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend of Togo Beer</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>「長年ロシアの圧迫を受けてきた北欧諸国では人気絶大で、フィンランドでは東郷の肖像をラベルにしたビールが売られていた」といういわゆる「東郷ビール伝説」があるが、これは1970年から1992年まで製造され2003年に復刻版製造された「提督ビールシリーズ」の一つで、山本五十六や、日露戦争で東郷と戦ったロシアのステパン・マカロフ、ジノヴィー・ロジェストヴェンスキー両提督も同じシリーズのラベルになっており、フィンランドで特別に東郷平八郎が人気絶大といった事実はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was so called &apos;a legend of Togo beer&apos; that TOGO was so popular in Scandinavian countries which had been subjected to pressure by Russia for a long time that beer bottles with a label of TOGO&apos;s portrait were sold in Finland; these were ones of &apos;admiral beer series&apos; that were produced from 1970 to 1992 and reproduced in 2003, and then Isoroku YAMAMOTO, and Stepan Makarov, and Zinovi Rozhdestvenski of Russian Admirals, who fought against TOGO in the Russo-Japanese War also became a label of the same series, but the fact is that Heihachiro TOGO is not especially popular in Finland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a so called &apos;a legend of Togo beer&apos; stating that Togo was so popular in Scandinavian countries which had been subjected to pressure by Russia for a long period of time that beer bottles with Togo&apos;s portrait on the label were sold in Finland; but these were part of the &apos;Admiral Beer Series&apos; that was produced from 1970 to 1992 and reproduced in 2003, and also featured Isoroku YAMAMOTO as well as the Russian Admirals Stepan Makarov and Zinovi Rozhdestvenski, who fought against Togo in the Russo-Japanese War, and the fact is that Heihachiro TOGO is not especially popular in Finland.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for grammar, style and fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a so called &apos;a legend of Togo beer&apos; stating that Togo was so popular in Scandinavian countries which had been subjected to pressure by Russia for a long period of time that beer bottles with Togo&apos;s portrait on the label were sold in Finland; but these were part of the &apos;Admiral Beer Series&apos; that was produced from 1970 to 1992 and reproduced in 2003, and also featured Isoroku YAMAMOTO as well as the Russian Admirals Stepan MAKAROV and Zinovi ROZHDESTVENSKI, who fought against Togo in the Russo-Japanese War, and the fact is that Heihachiro TOGO is not especially popular in Finland.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>東郷のラベルのものは1971年製造開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brewery started production of the beer with a label of TOGO&apos;s portrait in 1971.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brewery began producing the beer with a label bearing Togo&apos;s portrait in 1971.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for grammar, style and fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brewery began producing the beer with a label bearing Togo&apos;s portrait in 1971.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>なお現在日本で販売されている「東郷ビール」は、オランダで製造されているプライベートビールに日本の会社がフィンランド「提督ビールシリーズ」で使われた東郷ラベルをつけているものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bottles of &apos;Togo beer&apos; sold in Japan now are the ones that Japanese brewery company put the label used in &apos;admiral beer series&apos; on the bottles of private beer which is produced in Holland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bottles of &apos;Togo Beer&apos; now sold in Japan now are private beer produced in the Netherlands which have had the labels used on the Finnish &apos;Admiral Beer Series&apos; applied by a Japanese company.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bottles of &apos;Togo Beer&apos; now sold in Japan are private beer produced in the Netherlands which have had the labels used on the Finnish &apos;Admiral Beer Series&apos; applied by a Japanese company.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>しかし、実際に東郷の名をつけたものが多く存在するのも事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, there are many other things named TOGO.</e>
<cmt>しかし→文脈上逆説ではないので訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, there are many other things bearing the name &apos;Togo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, there are many other things bearing the name &apos;Togo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>東郷が亡くなった1934年には、ブラジルのカステロエス社が、「東郷へのオマージュ」として『Cigarros Guensui』という銘柄のタバコを販売した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in1934 when TOGO passed away, カステエロスcompany sold tobacco whose brand name was &quot;Cigarros Gensui&quot; for &apos;homage to TOGO.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カステエロス社→スペリング不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in 1934 when TOGO passed away, the Brazilian company Castellos sold cigarettes under the brand name &quot;Cigarros Gensui&quot; in &apos;homage to Togo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in 1934 when TOGO passed away, the Brazilian company Castelloes sold cigarettes under the brand name &quot;Cigarros Gensui&quot; in &apos;homage to Togo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>宣伝には日本語で『聖将東郷元帥永久の思ひ出にシガーロス「元帥」を日本の皆様に捧ぐ』と書かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The advertisement words written in Japanese said, &quot;The cigarros &apos;Gensui&apos; is dedicated to Japanese people for the eternal memory of Fleet Admiral TOGO.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese words used in the advertisement read &quot;Cigarros &apos;Gensui&apos; is dedicated to Japanese people for the eternal memory of Fleet Admiral Togo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese words used in the advertisement read &quot;Cigarros &apos;Gensui&apos; is dedicated to Japanese people for the eternal memory of Fleet Admiral Togo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>また、水生昆虫のカワゲラにはトウゴウカワゲラ属（Togoperla）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another example is that some of Kawagera (stoneflies), aquatic insects, include the genus named after TOGO, (such as Togoperla).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another example is the Togoperla genus of the kawagera (stonefly) order of aquatic insects.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another example is the Togoperla genus of the kawagera (stonefly) order of aquatic insects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>これは、チェコ人昆虫学者のFrant Klapálekが東郷平八郎にちなんで名づけたとされ、他にもオオヤマカワゲラ（大山巌）、ノギカワゲラ（乃木希典）、カミムラカワゲラ（上村彦之丞）と名づけられたカワゲラ属が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this was named by Czech entomologist, Frant Klapalek after Heihachiro TOGO; others are Oyama kawagera (named after Iwao OYAMA; its scientific name is Oyamia gibba), Nogi kawagera (named after Maresuke NOGI; Cryptoperla japonica), and Kamimura kawagera (named after Hikonojo KAMIMURA; Kamimura tibialis), (those persons were prominent figures in the Russo-Japanese War).</e>
<cmt>大山巌、乃木希典、上村彦之丞について（those persons were prominent figures in the Russo-Japanese War）を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was named by Czech entomologist, Frant Klapalek after Heihachiro TOGO; others are Oyama kawagera (named after Iwao OYAMA; its scientific name is Oyamia gibba), Nogi kawagera (named after Maresuke NOGI; Cryptoperla japonica), and Kamimura kawagera (named after Hikonojo KAMIMURA; Kamimura tibialis), (those persons were prominent figures in the Russo-Japanese War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this was named by Czech entomologist, Frant Klapalek after Heihachiro TOGO; others are Oyama kawagera (named after Iwao OYAMA; its scientific name is Oyamia gibba), Nogi kawagera (named after Maresuke NOGI; Cryptoperla japonica), and Kamimura kawagera (named after Hikonojo KAMIMURA; Kamimura tibialis), (those persons were prominent figures in the Russo-Japanese War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>なお生前には、東郷の名を冠した「東郷鋼（はがね）」という鉄鋼製品が作られていた事から、東郷元帥に反発する海軍内の佐官や将官の手で「東郷バカネ」という地口が作られ、流布したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, it is said that before his death, &apos;Togo hagane,&apos; iron and steel procucts named after TOGO, were manufactured, and a pun, &apos;Togo bakane (meaning TOGO is stupid),&apos; was made and spread by some Sakan (majors, lieutenant colonels, and captains) and some Shokan (major generals, lieutenant generals, and admirals) in the Navy who were hostile to TOGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, it is said that before his death, &apos;Togo hagane,&apos; iron and steel products named after Togo, were manufactured, and a pun, &apos;Togo bakane (meaning Togo is stupid),&apos; was created and spread by some sakan (majors, lieutenant colonels, and captains) and some shokan (major generals, lieutenant generals, and admirals) in the Navy who were hostile to Togo.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, it is said that before his death, &apos;Togo hagane,&apos; iron and steel products named after Togo, were manufactured, and a pun, &apos;Togo bakane&apos; (meaning Togo is stupid), was created and spread by some sakan (majors, lieutenant colonels, and captains) and some shokan (major generals, lieutenant generals, and admirals) in the Navy who were hostile to Togo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>ただ実際は海外鋼輸入問屋河合鋼鉄のライバル流通が考え出した洒落という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one belief, the pun was, in fact, made by a rival company to Kawai Steel Company, a wholesale ware house company which imported foreign steel and sold &apos;Togo hagane.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one belief, the pun was, in fact, made up by a rival company to the Kawai Steel Company, a wholesale warehouse company which imported foreign steel and sold &apos;Togo hagane.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one belief, the pun was, in fact, made up by a rival company to the Kawai Steel Company, a wholesale warehouse company which imported foreign steel and sold &apos;Togo hagane.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>日本の産業界が当時、国産第一を標榜していた背景で考察する事も可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The background that Japan industrial community stood for domestic trading policy in those days also might have made the pun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also possible that the pun arose from the background of Japan&apos;s industrial community at the time which championed domestic products.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also possible that the pun arose from the background of Japan&apos;s industrial community at the time which championed domestic products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>死後、私邸が東郷元帥記念公園として使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since TOGO&apos;s death, his private residence has been used for the memorial park of Marshal TOGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Togo&apos;s death, his private residence has been used as the Marshal Togo Memorial Park.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Togo&apos;s death, his private residence has been used as the Marshal Togo Memorial Park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>現在でも私邸に置かれていた獅子像などが残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even now, there remains a statue of lion which belonged to his private house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even now, there remains a statue of lion which belonged to his private house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even now, there remains a statue of lion which belonged to his private house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="85">
<j>一般に寡黙、荘重という印象があるが時として軽忽な一面もみせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, TOGO gave the impression that he was a man of taciturnity and solemnity, but he sometimes showed an indiscretion side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, TOGO gave the impression that he was a man of taciturnity and solemnity, but he sometimes showed an indiscretionate side.</e>
<cmt>indiscretion &gt; indiscretionate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, TOGO gave the impression that he was a man of taciturnity and solemnity, but he sometimes showed an indiscretionate side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>晩年学習院に招かれた際、講演中に生徒に「将来は何になりたいか」と質問し「軍人になりたい」と答えた生徒に「軍人になると死ぬぞ」 「なるなら大日本帝国陸軍ではなく大日本帝国海軍に入れ。海軍ならしなないから」と発言し、陸軍大将であった乃木希典院長を憮然とさせたというエピソードがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an episode telling about his such side; when he was invited to the Gakushuin School Corporation (an educational institution mainly for children of the imperial family and nobility) in his later years, during his lecture, he asked a student what he wanted to be in future, and then told the student who answered &quot; a soldier&quot; to his question that soldiers would die in battle fields, so that he recommended the student to enter the Imperial Japanese Navy, not the Imperial Japanese Army because those in the Navy would not die, and what he said made the Principal of the Gakushuin School, Maresuke NOGI, who used to be the Army General, disconsolate.</e>
<cmt>セル146と147を一文にして訳出しました/学習院→(an educational institution mainly for children of the imperial family and nobility)を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an episode that demonstrated this side of him that occurred when he was invited to the Gakushuin School Corporation (an educational institution mainly for children of the imperial family and nobility) in his later years and, during his lecture, he asked a student what he wanted to be in future, and then told the student who answered &quot;a soldier&quot; that soldiers would die on battlefields, so he recommended the student to enter the Imperial Japanese Navy as opposed to the Imperial Japanese Army because those in the Navy would not die, making the Principal of the Gakushuin School, Maresuke NOGI, who used to be the Army General, somewhat disappointed.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an episode that demonstrated this side of him that occurred when he was invited to the Gakushuin School Corporation (an educational institution mainly for children of the imperial family and nobility) in his later years and, during his lecture, he asked a student what he wanted to be in future, and then told the student who answered &quot;a soldier&quot; that soldiers would die on battlefields, so he recommended the student to enter the Imperial Japanese Navy as opposed to the Imperial Japanese Army because those in the Navy would not die, making the Principal of the Gakushuin School, Maresuke NOGI, who used to be the Army General, somewhat disappointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>昭和天皇は学習院時代、院長であった乃木希典については「印象深く、尊敬もしている」と述べているが、東宮御学問所総裁であった東郷については、後年、記者の質問に「何の印象もない」と答えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor Showa was a student of the Gakushuin School, he told about Maresuke NOGI, the principal of the school, that NOGI left deep impression on him and he did respect NOGI, but when he was asked about TOGO, president of the Togu School (a school to educate the crown prince), by the press reporters later in his life, he answered he had no impression about TOGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Showa said that Maresuke NOGI, the principal of the school, that NOGI left deep impression on him during his time as a student of the Gakushuin School and he did respect Nogi, but when he was asked about Togo, president of the Togu School (a school to educate the crown prince), by press reporters later in his life, he answered he had no impression about Togo.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Showa said that Maresuke NOGI, the principal of the school, that NOGI left deep impression on him during his time as a student of the Gakushuin School and he did respect Nogi, but when he was asked about Togo, president of the Togu School (a school to educate the crown prince), by press reporters later in his life, he answered he had no impression about Togo.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;the&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>錬度を上げることに熱心で聯合艦隊解散之辞に「百発百中の一砲能（よ）く百発一中の敵砲百門に対抗し得る」という言葉を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOGO was so enthusiastic about raising the level of firing proficiency that he left the words at the dismissal ceremony of the Combined Fleet, saying, &quot;One cannon hitting marks one hundred times out of one hundred makes it possible to take countermeasures against enemies&apos; one hundred cannons hitting one time out of one hundred.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togo was so enthusiastic about raising the level of firing proficiency that he left the words at the dismissal ceremony of the Combined Fleet, saying, &quot;One cannon hitting marks one hundred times out of one hundred makes it possible to take countermeasures against enemies&apos; one hundred cannons hitting one time out of one hundred.&quot;</e>
<cmt>TOGO &gt; Togo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo was so enthusiastic about raising the level of firing proficiency that he left the words at the dismissal ceremony of the Combined Fleet, saying, &quot;One cannon hitting marks one hundred times out of one hundred makes it possible to take countermeasures against enemies&apos; one hundred cannons hitting one time out of one hundred.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="89">
<j>ワシントン軍縮条約の結果主力艦の保有比率が対英米6割と希望の7割より低く抑えられたことに憤激する将官達に向かって、「でも訓練には比率も制限もないでしょう」と諭したと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The agreement of the Disarmament Washington Naval Treaty that a 10:6 tonnage ratio of capital ships, being cut down from a 10:7 ratio which Japan contended, between the navies of the United States and Great Britain and Japan drove generals exasperation, but TOGO is said to have urged them by telling that &apos;there was neither ratio nor limit in skill-up training.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The agreement of the Disarmament Washington Naval Treaty that a 10:6 tonnage ratio of capital ships, being cut down from a 10:7 ratio which Japan contended, between the navies of the United States and Great Britain and Japan drove generals exasperation, but Togo is said to have urged them by saying that &apos;there was neither ratio nor limit in skill-up training.&apos;</e>
<cmt>TOGO &gt; Togotelling &gt; saying</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The agreement of the Disarmament Washington Naval Treaty that a 10:6 tonnage ratio of capital ships, being cut down from a 10:7 ratio which Japan contended, between the navies of the United States and Great Britain and Japan drove generals exasperation, but Togo is said to have urged them by saying that &apos;there was neither ratio nor limit in skill-up training.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>（伊藤正徳著「連合艦隊の最後」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;The End of the Combined Fleet&quot; written by Masanori ITO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;The End of the Combined Fleet&quot; written by Masanori ITO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;The End of the Combined Fleet&quot; written by Masanori ITO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="91">
<j>東郷は宮古湾海戦にて奮戦、戦死した甲賀源吾を軍人として尊敬していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOGO respected Gengo KOGA as a military man, who fought in the naval Battle of Miyako-wan Gulf and was killed there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togo respected Gengo Koga as a military man, who fought in the naval Battle of Miyako-wan Gulf and was killed there.</e>
<cmt>TOGO &gt; TogoKOGA &gt; Koga</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo respected Gengo KOGA as a military man, who fought in the naval Battle of Miyako-wan Gulf and was killed there.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>また、明治新政府によって逆賊として斬首に処せられた小栗忠順の名誉を後に回復している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also vindicated the memory of Tadamasa OGURI, who had been executed by guillotine as a rebel by the New Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also vindicated the memory of Tadamasa OGURI, who had been executed by guillotine as a rebel by the New Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also vindicated the memory of Tadamasa OGURI, who had been executed by guillotine as a rebel by the New Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>日本海海戦でバルチック艦隊を破って後、山村で隠棲していた彼の遺族を私邸に招き、「日本海海戦で勝利を得たのは、（小栗上野介が生前に建造した）横須賀造船所で艦隊の十分な補給と整備を受けることができたからである」と故人の功績を称え、感謝の言葉を惜しまなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Destroying the Russian Baltic Fleet in the Battle of Tsushima, TOGO invited OGURI&apos;s bereaved family who lived in an out of the way village to his private residence to praise OGRI&apos;s distinguishing job (OGURI had built the Yokosuka Dockyard for future Japan before his death) and to express his deep gratitude to them, saying, &quot;Because the Yokosuka Dockyard were able to provide enough replenishment and overhaul for the Combined Fleet, which brought us victory in the Battle of Tsushima.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Destroying the Russian Baltic Fleet in the Battle of Tsushima, Togo invited Oguri&apos;s bereaved family who lived in a remote village to his private residence to praise Oguri&apos;s distinguished service (Oguri had built the Yokosuka Dockyard for future Japan before his death) and to express his deep gratitude to them, saying, &quot;The Yokosuka Dockyard was able to provide enough supplies and maintenance for the Combined Fleet, which brought us victory in the Battle of Tsushima.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for guidelines, spelling, grammar and fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Destroying the Russian Baltic Fleet in the Battle of Tsushima, Togo invited Oguri&apos;s bereaved family who lived in a remote village to his private residence to praise Oguri&apos;s distinguished service (Oguri had built the Yokosuka Dockyard for future Japan before his death) and to express his deep gratitude to them, saying, &quot;The Yokosuka Dockyard was able to provide enough supplies and maintenance for the Combined Fleet, which brought us victory in the Battle of Tsushima.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="94">
<j>東郷の国葬に併せて英米両国から日本向けに追悼のメッセージがラジオで放送された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During TOGO&apos;s state funeral, memory messages for him were broadcast on radio from both England and America to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Togo&apos;s state funeral, memorial messages for him were broadcast by radio from both England and America to Japan.</e>
<cmt>TOGO &gt; Togomemory &gt; memorialon &gt; by</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Togo&apos;s state funeral, memorial messages for him were broadcast by radio from both England and America to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>イギリスからはボルトン・イヤーズ＝モンセル海軍省 (イギリス) のメッセージが英国放送協会から、アメリカからはウィリアム・スタンドレイアメリカ海軍作戦部長のメッセージがNBCからそれぞれ放送されたが、アメリカからの放送では予定より早く終了したため、時間調整に日本の曲として『お江戸日本橋』『かっぽれ』という、おおよそ追悼に似つかわしくない音楽が放送されてしまうというハプニングが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The message of Bolton Eyres-Monsel, First Lord of the Admiralty, by BBC from England, and the message of William Standley, Chief of Naval Operation, by NBC from America were broadcast respectively, and the happening happened that the program by NBC was finished earlier than it had planned, so that NBC broadcast Japanese songs, &quot;Oedo Nihon-bashi Bridge,&quot; and &quot;Kappore, &quot; which were completely unsuitable to the funeral memory, to fill the time allowed it.</e>
<cmt>ボルトン・イヤーズ＝モンセル海軍省→ボルトン・イヤーズ＝モンセル海軍大臣→Bolton Eyres-Monsel, First Lord of the Admiralty/ ウィリアム・スタンドレイアメリカ海軍作戦部長→William Standley, Chief of Naval Operation/ (イギリス)はfrom England とあるので省略しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The message of Bolton EYRES-MONSEL, First Lord of the Admiralty, by BBC from England, and the message of William STANDLEY, Chief of Naval Operation, by NBC from America were broadcast respectively, and it happened that the program by NBC finished earlier than planned, so the NBC broadcast the Japanese songs &quot;Oedo Nihon-bashi Bridge&quot; and &quot;Kappore,&quot; which were completely unsuitable to the funeral memory, to fill its allotted time.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The message of Bolton EYRES-MONSEL, First Lord of the Admiralty, by BBC from England, and the message of William STANDLEY, Chief of Naval Operation, by NBC from America were broadcast respectively, and it happened that the program by NBC finished earlier than planned, so the NBC broadcast the Japanese songs &quot;Oedo Nihon-bashi Bridge&quot; and &quot;Kappore,&quot; which were completely unsuitable to the funeral memory, to fill its allotted time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>この模様が全国に生中継されてしまった日本国内では、アメリカ側の選曲を問題視する声が一部で出たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The program was broadcast all over Japan, and then some Japanese perceived the two songs America had chosen as problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The program was broadcast all over Japan, and some Japanese people thought that the two songs chosen by NBC were a technical problem.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The program was broadcast all over Japan, and some Japanese people thought that the two songs chosen by NBC were a technical problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="97">
<j>元国際連合事務総長のブトロス・ガリは、日本に来ると必ず東郷神社に参拝した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whenever Boutros-Ghali, the former Secretary-General of the United Nations, came to Japan, he always visited to the Togo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whenever Boutros-Ghali, the former Secretary-General of the United Nations, came to Japan, he always visited to the Togo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whenever Boutros-Ghali, the former Secretary-General of the United Nations, came to Japan, he always visited to the Togo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>エジプト出身であるガリは「小さい頃、ものすごく励まされた、心を解放された」と言っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ghali, a person from Egypt, says, &quot;TOGO encouraged and released me when I was young.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ghali, a person from Egypt, says, &quot;Togo encouraged and liberated my heart when I was young.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to reflect source text and for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ghali, a person from Egypt, says, &quot;Togo encouraged and liberated my heart when I was young.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="99">
<j>日本海海戦の際、旗艦三笠に掲げられた大将旗は1911年に、イギリス国王のジョージ5世 (イギリス王)の戴冠式に明治天皇の名代、東伏見宮依仁親王に随行して出席した際、かつての留学先だった海員練習船「ウースター」校に寄贈されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The General&apos;s flag hoisted over the flagship Mikasa during the Battle of Tsushima was donated by TOGO to the HMS Worcester possessing the training ship &apos;Worcester,&apos; for cadets, where he used to study, when he attended Imperial Prince Higashihushiminomiya Yorihito, on behalf of the Emperor Meiji, to participate in the coronation ceremony of George V (King of Britain) in 1911.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The General&apos;s flag hoisted over the flagship Mikasa during the Battle of Tsushima was donated by Togo to the HMS Worcester possessing the training ship &apos;Worcester,&apos; for cadets, where he used to study, when he attended Imperial Prince Higashihushiminomiya Yorihito, on behalf of the Emperor Meiji, to participate in the coronation ceremony of George V (King of Britain) in 1911.</e>
<cmt>TOGO &gt; Togo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The General&apos;s flag hoisted over the flagship Mikasa during the Battle of Tsushima was donated by Togo to the HMS Worcester possessing the training ship &apos;Worcester,&apos; for cadets, where he used to study, when he attended Imperial Prince Higashihushiminomiya Yorihito, on behalf of the Emperor Meiji, to participate in the coronation ceremony of George V (King of Britain) in 1911.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>日本側にこうした経緯を記した記録がなかったため、長らく所在不明となっていたが、2004年東郷神社の松橋暉男宮司が著書の執筆にあたり調査したところ、ウースター校の財産を引き継いでいる財団マリン・ソサエティーが、同時に寄贈された銀杯や東郷元帥の胸像とともに所蔵していることがわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With no record about such a background of the flag in Japan, the flag&apos;s whereabouts had been unknown for a long time, but it turned out by researches which Teruo MAYSUHASHI, Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Togo-jinja Shrine, made in order to write TOGO&apos;s biography in 2004 that the Foundation of the Marine Society, succeeding to the property of the HMS Worcester, had preserved a silver cup, and the bust of Fleet Admiral TOGO as well General&apos;s flag TOGO had donated at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With no record about such a background of the flag in Japan, the flag&apos;s whereabouts had been unknown for a long time, but research conducted by Teruo MAYSUHASHI, Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Togo-jinja Shrine, while writing Togo&apos;s biography in 2004 revealed that the Foundation of the Marine Society, succeeding to the property of the HMS Worcester, had preserved a silver cup, and the bust of Fleet Admiral Togo as well General&apos;s flag Togo had donated at that time.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With no record about such a background of the flag in Japan, the flag&apos;s whereabouts had been unknown for a long time, but research conducted by Teruo MAYSUHASHI, Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Togo-jinja Shrine, while writing Togo&apos;s biography in 2004 revealed that the Foundation of the Marine Society, succeeding to the property of the HMS Worcester, had preserved a silver cup, and the bust of Fleet Admiral Togo as well General&apos;s flag Togo had donated at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>神社側が来年の大祭の際に貸してもらうよう申し入れたところ、無償で永久貸与されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine staff requested the Foundation to lend these things TOGO had left for the grand festival the following year, so that it would lend them at no extra charge forever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the shrine staff requested that the foundation lend these things that Togo had left for the grand festival in the following year, it permanently donated them.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the shrine staff requested that the foundation lend these things that Togo had left for the grand festival in the following year, it permanently donated them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="102">
<j>日本海海戦時カール・ツァイスの双眼鏡を敵の沈没状況や降伏確認に使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOGO used a binocular made by Carl Zeiss to check the sinking enemy&apos;s fleets and the surrender in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofo used a pair of binoculars made by Carl Zeiss to check the sinking of the enemy fleet and the surrender in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togo used a pair of binoculars made by Carl Zeiss to check the sinking of the enemy fleet and the surrender in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>この双眼鏡は5倍と10倍兼用で、発売されて間もない1904年（明治37年）小西本店（現コニカミノルタホールディングス）が輸入したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This binocular offered magnification both five times and ten times, and was imported by the Konishi head office (now KONICA MINOLTA HOLDINGS., INC) in1904 just after sold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This binoculars offered both five times and ten times magnification, and were imported by the Konishi head office (now KONICA MINOLTA HOLDINGS., INC) in 1904 just after they went on the market.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This binoculars offered both five times and ten times magnification, and were imported by the Konishi head office (now KONICA MINOLTA HOLDINGS., INC) in 1904 just after they went on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>現在は三笠記念館に収蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been preserved in the Memorial Ship Mikasa now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are now preserved on the Memorial Ship Mikasa now.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are now preserved on the Memorial Ship Mikasa now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="105">
<j>授与された勲章等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honors TOGO was bestowed on</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honors</e>
<cmt>&quot;Honors TOGO was bestowed on&quot; makes no sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>日本 大勲位菊花章頸飾、大勲位菊花大綬章、功一級金鵄勲章、勲一等旭日桐花大綬章、勲一等瑞宝章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan bestowed several honors on him including the Collar of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, the Order of the Golden Kite (1st class), the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower, and the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan bestowed several honors on Togo including the Collar of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, the Order of the Golden Kite (1st class), the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower, and the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure.</e>
<cmt>him &gt; Togo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan bestowed several honors on Togo including the Collar of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, the Grand Cordon of the Supreme Order of the Chrysanthemum, the Order of the Golden Kite (first class), the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower, and the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>大韓帝国 朝鮮皇帝金尺大綬章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean Empire conferred 朝鮮皇帝金尺綬章 on him.</e>
<cmt>朝鮮皇帝金尺綬章→不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean Empire conferred the 朝鮮皇帝金尺綬章 on him.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean Empire conferred the Grand Cordon of the Gold of Korean Emperor (朝鮮皇帝金尺大綬章) on him.</e>
<cmt>朝鮮皇帝金尺大綬章の訳語を推測して追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>イギリス メリット勲章、ヴィクトリア第一等勲章（Royal Victorian Order）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Britain awarded him the Order of Merit, and the Royal Victorian Order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Britain awarded him the Order of Merit, and the Royal Victorian Order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Britain awarded him the Order of Merit, and the Royal Victorian Order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>フランス レジオンドヌール勲章グラン・トフィシエ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">France honored him with the Order of the Legion of Honor (Legion d&apos;Honneur (Grand Officier)) (Grand Officer).</e>
<cmt>レジオンドヌール勲章グラン・トフィシエ→（仏）Legion d&apos;Ｈｏｎｎｅｕｒ (Grand Officier)→（英）Ｌｅｇion of Honor (Grand fficer)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">France honored him with the Order of the Legion of Honor (Legion d&apos;Honneur (Grand Officier)) (Grand Officer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">France honored him with the Order of the Legion of Honor (Legion d&apos;Honneur [Grand Officier]) (Grand Officer).</e>
<cmt>括弧</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>イタリア サンモーリス・エ・ラ・ザル第一等勲章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Italy bestowed the Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus (1st class) (Ordine dei Santi Maurizio e Lazzaro) on him.</e>
<cmt>サンモーリス・エ・ラ・ザル第一勲章→（伊）Oedine dei Santi Maurizio e Lazzaro→（英）Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus, first class</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Italy bestowed the Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus (1st class) (Ordine dei Santi Maurizio e Lazzaro) on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Italy bestowed the Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus (first class) (Ordine dei Santi Maurizio e Lazzaro) on him.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>ポーランド グラン・クロアオドロゼニア・ボルスキー勲章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poland bestowed the Order of Rebirth of Poland (Order Odrodzenenia Poloski, or Order of Polonia Restituta) on him.</e>
<cmt>グラン・クロアオドロゼニア・ボルスキー勲章→（ポ）Ｏｒｄer Odrodzenia Ploski, Oder of Polonia Restituta→（英）Oder of Rebirth of Poland</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poland bestowed the Order of Rebirth of Poland (Order Odrodzenenia Poloski, or Order of Polonia Restituta) on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poland bestowed the Order of Rebirth of Poland (Order Odrodzenenia Poloski, or Order of Polonia Restituta) on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>ロシア 聖アンナ第一等勲章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia honored him with the Order of St. Anna (1st class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia honored him with the Order of St. Anna (1st class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia honored him with the Order of St. Anna (first class).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>スペイン スペイン海軍有功白色第四級勲章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spain bestowed the Order of Naval Merit (4th class) (white ribbon for general sevice with a blue stripe) on him.</e>
<cmt>スペイン海軍有効白色第四級勲章→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spain bestowed the Order of Naval Merit (4th class) (white ribbon for general sevice with a blue stripe) on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spain bestowed the Order of Naval Merit (fourth class) (white ribbon for general sevice with a blue stripe) on him.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Los688(id:12316), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), 川本浅夫(id:188226), Greenleaf(id:126500), Fujikun(id:29054), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), March(id:9468), ПРУСАКИН(id:23195), 0太郎(id:7375), Shalmaneser(id:167217), NKK2005(id:16294), Gombe(id:27), Takeler(id:51437), 新芽(id:50924), 釣本直紀(id:85142), Northface(id:70750), A-Taul(id:41790), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), STB-1(id:8775), Rabbit(id:12621), PCV(id:209910), 七篠権兵衛(id:129041), Chao35(id:34986), 希望(id:25982), Keydaimon(id:17982), GENMEI(id:31879), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Lemon pie(id:66842), 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), Sizuru(id:52926), Mnd(id:15140), MystBot(id:224584), 浩(id:70121), コタルス(id:143135), Bergmann(id:85282), Treue(id:19072), Bletilla(id:38919), Jmacs(id:72704), Moltke(id:17553), 松茸(id:27535), Gen1218(id:281841), Tiyoringo(id:70026), S kitahashi(id:10307), Jud(id:15582), Miita(id:30561), 256(id:11889), Jun777(id:310944), Sanmari(id:1707), Histwr(id:15646), 斎藤勇輝(id:61190), SilvonenBot(id:190970), MOMO(id:17114), Chikumaya(id:26499), 治部少輔(id:79307), SuisuiBot(id:10165), R28Bot(id:177951), ひろくん(id:79638), 海衛士(id:19229), Muro Bot(id:217619), JongGuk(id:26258), Tonbi ko(id:27171), NDR(id:5500), けんち(id:5147), みょうじ(id:124419), MD242(id:11277), JAnDbot(id:66507), Shain2006(id:66860), Kawai(id:5634), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), 陽一(id:92099), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Ttwo(id:82880), Hayabusa future(id:21110), Sloop25(id:35005), Awx2006(id:51092), ShikiH(id:181574), Johncapistrano(id:969), Lcw8110.1.56(id:189464), A6M4(id:14155), 下総大納言(id:43461), 宝塚ファミリーランド(id:161197), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Sonic883(id:36201), Loveless(id:129239), Iittyoutaku(id:1346), 端くれの錬金術師(id:23040), 竹麦魚(id:11012), ５１６(id:45205), KASAGI(id:24405), Jinzuu(id:60495), Bankokuya(id:91191), Mamasaid(id:2903), Poe(id:16973), Izayohi(id:13095), Blizzardbreaker(id:248394), クロウ(id:21337), Rambler(id:59491), Race(id:131322), Kisaragi(id:9198), Daranome(id:1429), VanishingDuck(id:125995), Pieria(id:48925), Aphaia(id:3132), LaaknorBot(id:220851), Cave cattum(id:41235), Ajtnk(id:18368), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), ( ^ω^)(id:71899), 新茶(id:157775), ×(id:36400), 上田隼人(id:23104), Miya(id:1881), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), 663highland(id:18755), Akimoto(id:6951), SieBot(id:126695), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>