<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安富元綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsuna YASUTOMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsuna YASUTOMI</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsuna YASUTOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>安富 元綱（やすとみ もとつな）は、室町時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsuna YASUTOMI was a Japanese military commander who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsuna YASUTOMI was a Japanese military commander who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsuna YASUTOMI was a Japanese military commander who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>細川氏の家宰・執事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a kasai (main retainer) as well as a steward at the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a kasai (main retainer) as well as a steward in the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>at the → in the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a kasai (main retainer) as well as a steward in the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>細川京兆家の重臣として讃岐国東方守護代を世襲していた安富氏の一族、もしくは惣領。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Yasutomi clan, a chief vassal clan of the Hosokawa-Keicho family, and they handed down a position of Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of the eastern region of Sanuki Province for generations; additionally, he was a soryo (heir) of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Yasutomi clan, a chief vassal clan of the Hosokawa-Keicho family, that handed down the position of Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of the eastern region of Sanuki Province for generations; additionally, he was a soryo (heir) of the clan.</e>
<cmt>and they → that. A position → the position</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Yasutomi clan, a chief vassal clan of the Hosokawa-Keicho family, that handed down the position of Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of the eastern region of Sanuki Province for generations; additionally, he was a soryo (heir) of the clan.</e>
<cmt>守護代の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>元綱は細川勝元に仕え、家宰として京都で勝元に近侍していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsuna served Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and attended him as a kasai in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsuna served Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and attended to him as a kasai in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>attend him → attended to him</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsuna served Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and attended to him as a kasai in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>応仁元年（1467年）に応仁の乱が起こると、元綱は香川氏とともに讃岐の軍勢を指揮し京都を転戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the Onin War occurred in 1467, Mototsuna took part in various battles in Kyoto together with the Kagawa clan at the head of an army from Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the Onin War started in 1467, Mototsuna took part in various battles in Kyoto together with the Kagawa clan as the head of an army from Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>occurred → started. At the head → as the head.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the Onin War started in 1467, Mototsuna took part in various battles in Kyoto together with the Kagawa clan as the head of an army from Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、安富氏は山城西岡の野田氏らも被官化していたようで、元綱は彼らも率いて軍事行動をしていたことが諸史料に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is thought that the Yasutomi clan also had the Noda clan, who was from Nishioka, Yamashiro Province, as their vassal, and various materials have it that Mototsuna took military action taking command of them as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is thought that the Yasutomi clan also headed the Noda clan that was from Nishioka, Yamashiro Province, as their vassal, and there are various documents stating that Mototsuna took military action in order to take command over them also.</e>
<cmt>Re-wrote the last part of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is thought that the Yasutomi clan also headed the Noda clan that was from Nishioka, Yamashiro Province, as their vassal, and there are various documents stating that Mototsuna took military action together with the Noda clan.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣ訳で原文と離れてしまったので書き直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>戦局が西軍有利となる中、応仁元年（1467年）10月、西軍は東軍の本陣であった相国寺を一気に攻撃した（相国寺の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the tide of the war turned in favor of the Western Camp, the Western Camp made an all-out attack on Shokoku-ji Temple, which was the headquarters of the Eastern Camp, in November 1467 (this battle is called the Battle of Shokoku-ji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the tide of the war turned in favor of the Western Camp, the Western Camp made an all-out attack on Shokoku-ji Temple, which was the headquarters of the Eastern Camp, in November 1467 (this battle is called the Battle of Shokoku-ji).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the tide of the war turned in favor of the Western Camp, the Western Camp made an all-out attack on Shokoku-ji Temple, which was the headquarters of the Eastern Camp, in November 1467 (this battle is called the Battle of Shokoku-ji.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧内へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>元綱は三千騎を率いて相国寺を守ったが、一部の僧侶が西軍に内応して相国寺内部から火を放ったことから東軍側は動揺し総崩れとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Mototsuna attempted to defend Shokoku-ji Temple with 3,000 horsemen against the attack, part of Buddhist priests who communicated secretly with the Western Camp set fire to the inside of Shokoku-ji Temple, and consequently, the Eastern Camp became upset and they completely collapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Mototsuna attempted to defend the Shokoku-ji Temple with 3,000 horsemen against the attack, part of Buddhist priests who communicated secretly with the Western Camp set fire to the inside of the Temple, and consequently, the Eastern Camp became upset and collapsed completely.</e>
<cmt>Re-wrote parts of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Mototsuna attempted to defend the Shokoku-ji Temple with 3,000 soldiers against the attack, part of Buddhist priests who communicated secretly with the Western Camp set fire to the inside of the Temple, and consequently, the Eastern Camp became upset and collapsed completely.</e>
<cmt>horsemen→soldiers　（騎馬兵はその一部だと思います。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>元綱は敵の猛攻撃を押し返し奮戦したものの、激戦の末、弟の盛継とともに壮絶な戦死を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsuna fought to the last man against the enemy&apos;s fierce attack, but he and his younger brother Moritsugu met a heroic end after this fierce battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsuna fought to the last man against the enemy&apos;s fierce attack, eventually, he and his younger brother Moritsugu, were victorious after this fierce battle.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsuna fought to the last man against the enemy&apos;s fierce attack, however, he and his younger brother Moritsugu, died a fierce death in battle.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣ訳では「戦死を遂げた」ことにはならないので書き直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>相国寺の戦いは応仁の乱でも激戦の一つであり、その一部始終は「応仁記」に詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Shokoku-ji was one of the fiercest battles of the Onin War, and &apos;Oninki&apos; (The Record of the Onin War) gives detailed description of the whole story of this battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Shokoku-ji was one of the fiercest battles of the Onin War, and &apos;Oninki&apos; (the record of the Onin War) gives a detailed description of the entire story of this battle.</e>
<cmt>The Record → the record. The whole → the entire.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Shokoku-ji was one of the fiercest battles of the Onin War, and &apos;Oninki&apos; (the record of the Onin War) gives a detailed description of the entire story of this battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>元綱はことのほか細川勝元の信頼が厚かったようで、元綱の戦死は勝元を大いに落胆させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Mototsuna enjoyed the fullest confidence of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and Katsumoto was very heartbroken over Mototsuna&apos;s death in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Mototsuna enjoyed the fullest confidence of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and Katsumoto was very heartbroken over Mototsuna&apos;s death in the battle.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Mototsuna enjoyed the fullest confidence of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and Katsumoto was very heartbroken over Mototsuna&apos;s death in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、東軍側の諸将もその死を嘆いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, commanders of the Eastern Camp wept over his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, commanders of the Eastern Camp wept over his death.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, commanders of the Eastern Camp wept over his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal profile and anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal profile and anecdotes</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile and anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>山梨県都留郡に元綱の子孫を称する安富家が存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists the Yasutomi family who claims to be descended from Mototsuna in Tsuru County, Yamanashi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The was a Yasutomi family that claimed to have descended from Mototsuna in Tsuru County, Yamanashi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a Yasutomi family that claims to have descended from Mototsuna in Tsuru County, Yamanashi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが過去形に訂正されていますが、これは現在形が正しいので書き直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その家系図には「安富民部丞源元綱」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their family tree has the text &apos;安富民部丞源元綱&apos; (Yasutomi Minbu no Jo [the officer of popular affairs] MINAMOTO no Mototsuna).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their family tree has the text &apos;安富民部丞源元綱&apos; (Yasutomi Minbu no Jo [the officer of popular affairs] MINAMOTO no Mototsuna).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their family tree has the text &apos;安富民部丞源元綱&apos; (Yasutomi Minbu no Jo [the officer of popular affairs] MINAMOTO no Mototsuna).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>元綱自身は応仁の乱で戦死したが、近世に作成された「南海通記」などの史料には16世紀以降においても讃岐での元綱の活動が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsuna was in fact killed in the Onin War, but some historical materials created during early-modern times such as the &apos;Nankai Tsuki&apos; (Records of the Harbors in the Southern Coast) record what Mototsuna did in Sanuki Province from the 16th century onwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsuna was in fact killed in the Onin War, but some historical materials created during early-modern times such as the &apos;Nankai Tsuki&apos; (Records of the Harbors in the Southern Coast) record what Mototsuna died in Sanuki Province sometime from the 16th century onwards.</e>
<cmt>did in → died in. from the 16th century → sometime from the 16th century onwards.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsuna was in fact killed in the Onin War, but some historical materials created during early-modern times such as the &apos;Nankai Tsuki&apos; (Records of the Harbors in the Southern Coast) record that Mototsuna worked in Sanuki Province during the 16th century.</e>
<cmt>「讃岐での元綱の活動が記されている」を忠実に訳しました。（讃岐で死んだかどうかは不明です。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは応仁の乱のために知名度の高かった元綱を、他の安富氏の一族と混同したものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because they probably confused other Yasutomi clans with Mototsuna, who was well known for his achievement in the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because other Yasutomi clans were confused with Mototsuna, who was well known for his achievement in the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>they probably confused → other Yasutomi clans were confused.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because other Yasutomi clans were confused with Mototsuna, who was well known for his achievement in the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>