<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>柏尾馬之助</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umanosuke KASHIO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umanosuke KASHIO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umanosuke KASHIO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>柏尾　馬之助　（かしお　うまのすけ ・ Kashio Umanosuke、天保9年（1838年）-　明治元年4月8日 (旧暦)（1868年4月30日））は幕末の阿波国出身の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umanosuke KASHIO (1838-April 30, 1868) was a person who was from the Awa Province in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umanosuke KASHIO (1838-April 30, 1868) was a person who was from Awa Province in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umanosuke KASHIO (1838-April 30, 1868) was a person who was from Awa Province in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>はじめ新徴組で活躍し、倒幕派志士に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He actively worked first in the Shinchogumi (Tokugawa Shogunate guard organization) and later became a patriot of forces of overthrowing the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明のため、倒幕派志士→a patriot of forces of overthrowing the Shogunate と訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He actively worked first in the Shinchogumi (Tokugawa Shogunate guard organization) and later became a patriot of forces overthrowing the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He actively worked first in the Shinchogumi (Tokugawa Shogunate guard organization) and later became a patriot of forces overthrowing the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>北辰一刀流剣術の剣豪でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also Kengo (great swordsman) of swordplay of the Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also a Kengo (great swordsman) of swordplay of the Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also a Kengo (great swordsman) of swordplay of the Hokushin-Ittoryu school.</e>
<cmt>kobudo→削除（特に必要ないと思います。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>浪士組六番隊、新徴組での役職は、剣術教授方（代稽古）、組頭、肝煎等。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His post in the Shinchogumi (Tokugawa Shogunate guard organization), the Roshigumi (masterless warriors group), the sixth squad was Teacher of swordsmanship (substituted teaching), kumigashira (head of the group), sponsorship, etc.</e>
<cmt>代稽古：定訳不明のため仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His post in the sixth squad of the Roshigumi (masterless warriors group), Shinchogumi (Tokugawa Shogunate guard organization), the Roshigumi (masterless warriors group) was Teacher of swordsmanship (substituted teaching), kumigashira (head of the group), sponsorship, etc.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in the sixth squad of the Roshigumi (masterless warriors group), and his posts in the Shinchogumi were Teacher of swordsmanship (substituted teaching), kumigashira (head of the group), sponsorship, etc.</e>
<cmt>新徴組、説明削除原文と違うと考え全体的に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>新徴組脱隊後は、維新の志士として尊王・倒幕運動を支援し、明治維新に助力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After resigned from the Shinchogumi, he supported the movement of Sonno (Movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and anti-Shogunate to contribute to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After resigning from the Shinchogumi, he supported the movement of Sonno (Movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and anti-Shogunate to contribute to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After resigning from the Shinchogumi, he supported the movement of Sonno (Movement advocating reverence for the Emperor) and anti-Shogunate to contribute to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>and the expulsion of foreigners 削除　（この部分は「攘夷」の説明です。）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生誕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>天保9年（1838年）阿波国美馬郡貞光に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in 1838 in Sadamitsu, Mima County, Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in 1838 in Sadamitsu, Mima County, Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born in 1838 in Sadamitsu, Mima County, Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>現在の徳島県美馬郡つるぎ町にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is present Tsurugi Town, Mima County, Tokushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is present Tsurugi Town, Mima County, Tokushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is present Tsurugi Town, Mima County, Tokushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>蜂須賀家（松平阿波守）の家来、柏尾嘉蔵（賀造）の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A retainer of the Hachisuka family (Matsudaira awa no kami), and the second son of Kazo KASHIO.</e>
<cmt>柏尾嘉蔵：読方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A retainer of the Hachisuka family (Matsudaira awa no kami), and the second son of Kazo KASHIO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Kazo KASHIO, a retainer of the Hachisuka family (Matsudaira awa no kami).</e>
<cmt>父親が「家来」なので変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（兄は柏尾元左エ門）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(His brother is Motozaemon KASHIO.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(His brother was Motozaemon KASHIO.)</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(His brother was Motozaemon KASHIO.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>剣術道場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Swordplay Dojo (training hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Swordplay Dojo (training hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Swordplay Dojo (training hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>下総国佐原（現・千葉県佐原市）で、北辰一刀流の剣術道場を営んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He managed a swordplay dojo of the Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school in Sahara of Shimousa Province (present Sawara City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He managed a swordplay dojo of the Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school in Sahara of Shimousa Province (present Sawara City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He managed a swordplay dojo of the Hokushin-Ittoryu school in Sahara of Shimousa Province (present Sawara City, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Kobudo 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>弟子の一部は、後に新選組に入隊している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of his students later joined the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of his students later joined the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of his students later joined the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>浪士組 六番隊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roshigumi, Sixth Squad</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sixth Squad, Roshigumi</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sixth Squad, Roshigumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>文久3年（1863年）尊皇攘夷急進派団体「虎尾の会」の中心人物、清河八郎・山岡鉄舟・村上俊五郎・石坂周造らと「浪士組」を結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863, he established &quot;Roshigumi&quot; with Hachiro KIYOKAWA, Tesshu YAMAOKA, Shungoro MURAKAMI, and Shuzo ISHIZAKA, who were the key persons of &quot;Torao no kai,&quot; a Sonno Joi kyushinha group (rapid group of Sonno Joi).</e>
<cmt>虎雄の会：読み方不明です。尊王攘夷急進派団体：定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863, he established &quot;Roshigumi&quot; with Hachiro KIYOKAWA, Tesshu YAMAOKA, Shungoro MURAKAMI, and Shuzo ISHIZAKA, who were the key persons of &quot;Torao no kai,&quot; a Sonno Joi kyushinha group (rapid group of Sonno Joi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863, he established &apos;Roshigumi&apos; with Hachiro KIYOKAWA, Tesshu YAMAOKA, Shungoro MURAKAMI, and Shuzo ISHIZAKA, who were the key persons of &apos;Torao no kai,&apos; a Sonno Joi kyushinha group (radical group of Sonno Joi, expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>rapid→radical&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;尊王は既出のため「攘夷」の説明のみ補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>（村上と柏尾は同郷で阿波から昵懇の仲で、共に佐原に居を構え、剣術も北辰一刀流の同門であったが、柏尾が虎尾の会に属していた記録は無い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Although MURAKAMI and KASHIO were both from Awa, were close friends since they were in Awa, both lived in Sahara, and belonged to the same swordship school, the Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school, there is no record indicating that KASHIO belonged to the Torao no kai.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Although MURAKAMI and KASHIO were both from Awa, were close friends since they were in Awa, both lived in Sahara, and belonged to the same swordsmanship school, the Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school, there is no record indicating that KASHIO belonged to the Torao no kai.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Although Murakami and Kashio were both from Awa, were close friends since they were in Awa, both lived in Sahara, and belonged to the same swordsmanship school, the Hokushin-Ittoryu school, there is no record indicating that Kashio belonged to the Torao no kai.)</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正。kobudo 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>浪士組は、清河が前年（文久2年・1962年）山岡を通じて江戸幕府に建言した建白書「急務三策」によって、攘夷団体として幕府の御墨付を得ていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Roshigumi had an endorsement as a Joi group from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a result of the submission of the petition &quot;three plans of urgent business&quot; by KIYOKAWA through YAMAOKA in 1962.</e>
<cmt>急務三策：定訳不明です。また、原文中の「1962年」は誤記のように思われるため「1862年」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Roshigumi had an endorsement as a Joi group from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a result of the submission of the petition &quot;three plans of urgent business&quot; by KIYOKAWA through YAMAOKA in 1962.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Roshigumi had an endorsement as a Joi group from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a result of the submission of the petition &apos;three plans of urgent business&apos; by Kiyokawa through Yamaoka in 1862.</e>
<cmt>1962年→1862年全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正。&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>幕府としては「治安を脅かす尊皇攘夷・勤皇派浪士を一括りに管理出来る、都合の良い団体」を作る心算であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu&apos;s intention was to establish &quot;a convenient group that could collectively manage Sonno Joi and pro-Imperialist masterless warriors who threatened the public order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu&apos;s intention was to establish &quot;a convenient group that could collectively manage Sonno Joi and pro-Imperialist masterless warriors who threatened the public order.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu&apos;s intention was to establish &apos;a convenient group with which they could collectively manage Sonno Joi and pro-Imperialist masterless warriors who threatened the public order.&apos;</e>
<cmt>that→with which they</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしそれは、清河の「幕府公認の先鋭的な尊皇攘夷団体」を作る為の、幕府の裏を書いた策略だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This, however, was KIYOKAWA&apos;s trick to outsmart the bakufu to establish &quot;a radical Sonno Joi group certified by the bakufu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This, however, was KIYOKAWA&apos;s trick to outsmart the bakufu to establish &quot;a radical Sonno Joi group certified by the bakufu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This, however, was Kiyokawa&apos;s trick to outsmart the bakufu to establish &apos;a radical Sonno Joi group certified by the bakufu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>文久3年（1863年）2月、柏尾は村上（組頭）と、浪士組六番隊で江戸を出立し、中山道を上洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1863, KASHIO left Edo, together with MURAKAMI (kumigashira) and the six squad of the Roshigumi, and went to Kyoto via the Nakasen-do Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1863, KASHIO left Edo, together with MURAKAMI (kumigashira) and the sixth squad of the Roshigumi, and went to Kyoto via the Nakasen-do Road.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1863, Kashio left Edo, together with Murakami (kumigashira) and the sixth squad of the Roshigumi, and went to Kyoto via the Nakasen-do Road.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>京都壬生村（現、京都府京都市中京区壬生）到着までには、芹沢鴨ら水戸の攘夷過激派や近藤勇・土方歳三・沖田総司・永倉新八ら天然理心流試衛館一派も合流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A radical Joi party from Mito including Kamo SERIZAWA and a Shieikan group of the Tennenrishin school including Isami KONDO, Toshizo HIJIKATA, Soji OKITA, and Shinpachi NAGAKURA joined them before their arrival at the Mibu village, Kyoto (present Mibu, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A radical Joi party from Mito including Kamo SERIZAWA and a Shieikan group of the Tennenrishin school including Isami KONDO, Toshizo HIJIKATA, Soji OKITA, and Shinpachi NAGAKURA joined them before their arrival at Mibu village, Kyoto (present Mibu, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A radical Joi party from Mito including Kamo SERIZAWA and a Shieikan group of the Tennenrishin school including Isami KONDO, Toshizo HIJIKATA, Soji OKITA, and Shinpachi NAGAKURA joined them before their arrival at Mibu village, Kyoto (present Mibu, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>浪士組六番隊は、後に幕末を賑す錚々たる人物が集まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eminent people who later worked actively at the end of the Edo period joined the six squad of the Roshigumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eminent people who later worked actively at the end of the Edo period joined the sixth squad of the Roshigumi.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eminent people who later worked actively at the end of the Edo period joined the sixth squad of the Roshigumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>壬生村宿割では、柏尾・村上らは壬生村会所、芹沢・近藤らは八木家と分れて宿を採っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Mibu village, KASHIO, MURAKAMI, and some others stayed at the Mibu village assembly office, and SERIZAWA, KONDO, and some others stayed at the Yagi Residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Mibu village, KASHIO, MURAKAMI, and some others stayed at the Mibu village assembly office, and SERIZAWA, KONDO, and some others stayed at the Yagi Residence.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Mibu village, Kashio, Murakami, and some others stayed at the Mibu village assembly office, and Serizawa, Kondo, and some others stayed at the Yagi Residence.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>この宿割りは、直後の浪士組分裂時に大きな影響を及ぼす事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This accommodation assignment had a significant impact at the split of the Roshigumi immediately thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This accommodation assignment had a significant impact on the split of the Roshigumi immediately thereafter.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This accommodation assignment had a significant impact on the split of the Roshigumi immediately thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>幕府の意表を突く、清河の尊皇攘夷の上書が朝廷に受理され、朝廷の勅諚を受けた浪士組は、同年3月京都を出立して江戸へ向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIYOKAWA&apos;s official document of Sonno Joi, which surprised the bakufu, was accepted by the imperial court, and having received an imperial decree, the Roshigumi left Kyoto in March of that year and to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIYOKAWA&apos;s official document of Sonno Joi, which surprised the bakufu, was accepted by the imperial court, and having received an imperial decree, the Roshigumi left Kyoto in March of that year and went to Edo.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;went&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyokawa&apos;s official document of Sonno Joi, which surprised the bakufu, was accepted by the imperial court, and having received an imperial decree, the Roshigumi left Kyoto in March of that year and went to Edo.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、柏尾や村上と同じ六番隊ではあるが、清河の幕府への裏切りとも取れる行動に反発した隊員、近藤・芹沢ら主に八木家宿泊組と、根岸友山一派らは壬生村に残る事となり袂を別かつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, those who were a member of the Roshigumi like KASHIO and MURAKAMI but protested against KIYOKAWA&apos;s action, which appeared to be betrayal of the bakufu, KONDO, SERIZAWA, and others, mainly those staying at the Yagi Residence, and the Yuzan NEGISHI&apos;s group decided to remain at the Mibu Village to be divorced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, those who were members of the Roshigumi like KASHIO and MURAKAMI but protested against KIYOKAWA&apos;s action, which appeared to be betrayal of the bakufu, including KONDO, SERIZAWA, and others, mainly those staying at the Yagi Residence, and the Yuzan NEGISHI&apos;s group decided to remain at Mibu Village to split from the Roshigumi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, those who were members of the Roshigumi like Kashio and Murakami but protested against Kiyokawa&apos;s action, which appeared to be betrayal of the bakufu, including Kondo, Serizawa, and others, mainly those staying at the Yagi Residence, and the Yuzan NEGISHI&apos;s group decided to remain at Mibu Village to split from the Roshigumi.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="25">
<j>壬生村に残った浪士組隊員は壬生浪士組を名乗り、後に新撰組となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members of the Roshigumi who remained at the Mibu village called themselves Mibu-Roshigumi, and later formed the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members of the Roshigumi who remained at the Mibu village called themselves Mibu-Roshigumi, and later formed the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members of the Roshigumi who remained at the Mibu village called themselves Mibu-Roshigumi, and later formed the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>（根岸友山は、新選組近藤一派に因る粛清が始まると、壬生浪士組を離脱し新徴組に合流）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Yuzan NEGISHI left the Mibu-Roshigumi to join the Shinchogumi when the KONDO group of the Shinsengumi started purging.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Yuzan NEGISHI left the Mibu-Roshigumi to join the Shinchogumi when the KONDO group of the Shinsengumi started purging.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Yuzan NEGISHI left the Mibu-Roshigumi to join the Shinchogumi when the Kondo group of the Shinsengumi started purging.)</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="27">
<j>同年4月、清河が、浪士組を尊王・倒幕運動の切札に使うと危惧した幕府は、佐々木只三郎ら刺客を差向け麻布一ノ橋にて清河を暗殺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu was concerned that KIYOKAWA would use the Roshigumi as a card for the Sonno and anti-shogunate movement, and sent assassins including Tadasaburo SASAKI in April of that year to murder KIYOKAWA at Ichinohashi, Azabu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu was concerned that KIYOKAWA would use the Roshigumi as a card for the Sonno and anti-shogunate movement, and sent assassins, including Tadasaburo SASAKI, in April of that year to murder KIYOKAWA at Ichinohashi, Azabu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu was concerned that Kiyokawa would use the Roshigumi as a card for the Sonno and anti-shogunate movement, and sent assassins, including Tadasaburo SASAKI, in April of that year to murder Kiyokawa at Ichinohashi, Azabu.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="28">
<j>前後して虎尾の会出身者は村上・石坂ら多くが捕縛され、浪士組は解体される事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before and after the murder, many of the members of the Torao no kai, including MURAKAMI and ISHIZAKA, were arrested, and the Roshigumi was dissolved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before and after the murder, many of the members of the Torao no kai, including MURAKAMI and ISHIZAKA, were arrested, and the Roshigumi was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before and after the murder, many of the members of the Torao no kai, including Murakami and Ishizaka, were arrested, and the Roshigumi was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>新徴組 剣術教授方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinchogumi, Teacher of Swordsmanship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinchogumi, Teacher of Swordsmanship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinchogumi, Teacher of Swordsmanship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>清河殺害から間を置かず、浪士組は幕府により再組織され、江戸市中の治安機関『新徴組』として、大きく方向性を変える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after the murder of KIYOKAWA, the Roshigumi was reorganized by the bakufu as &quot;Shinchogumi,&quot; security guards of the Edo City, changing its direction dynamically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the murder of KIYOKAWA, the Roshigumi was reorganized by the bakufu as &quot;Shinchogumi,&quot; security guards of Edo City, changing its direction dynamically.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the murder of Kiyokawa, the Roshigumi was reorganized by the bakufu as &quot;Shinchogumi,&quot; security guards of Edo City, changing its direction dynamically.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>屯所は江戸本所 (墨田区)（現・東京都墨田区本所 (墨田区)）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The headquater was at Edo honjo (Sumida Ward) (present Honjo, Sumida Ward, Tokyo (Sumida Ward)).</e>
<cmt>江戸本所：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headquaters was at Edo honjo (Sumida Ward) (present Honjo, Sumida Ward, Tokyo (Sumida Ward)).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headquaters was at Edo honjo (Sumida Ward) (present Honjo, Sumida Ward, Tokyo (Sumida Ward)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>元治元年（1864年）には庄内藩御預かりとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, it went into the custody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, it was taken into custody.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, it was placed under the custody of Shonai clan.</e>
<cmt>「庄内藩」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>柏尾は撃剣試合で才能を認められ、新徴組剣術教授方の一人に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KASHIO&apos;s talent was recognized in a geki-ken (swordsmanship) match, and was appointed as a teacher of swordsmanship of the Shinchogumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KASHIO&apos;s talent was recognized in a geki-ken (swordsmanship) match, and he was appointed a teacher of swordsmanship of the Shinchogumi.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashio&apos;s talent was recognized in a geki-ken (swordsmanship) match, and he was appointed a teacher of swordsmanship of the Shinchogumi.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>山田官司（新徴組取締・剣術教授方、北辰一刀流の兄弟子）に代わり、隊員に稽古を付ける傍ら、隊の組頭としても先頭に立ち、江戸市中の警戒業務も担っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He trained the members as a substitute for Kanji YAMADA, who was a head teacher of swordsmanship of the Shinchogumi and a senior apprentice, and also led the members as kumigashira and worked to guard the Edo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He trained the members as a substitute for Kanji YAMADA, who was a head teacher of swordsmanship of the Shinchogumi and a senior apprentice, and also led the members as kumigashira and worked to guard Edo City.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He trained the members as a substitute for Kanji YAMADA, who was a head teacher of swordsmanship of the Shinchogumi and a senior apprentice of Hokushin-Ittoryu school, and also led the members as kumigashira and worked to guard Edo City.</e>
<cmt>「北辰一刀流の」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし労咳（結核）を患い、度々喀血することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he suffered Rogai (tuberculosis), and sometimes coughed up blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he suffered Rogai (tuberculosis), and sometimes coughed up blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he suffered Rogai (tuberculosis), and sometimes coughed up blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>新徴組脱退－維新の志士として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resignation from the Shinchogumi - as a patriot of the restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resignation from the Shinchogumi - as a patriot of the restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resignation from the Shinchogumi - as a patriot of the restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>庄内藩から新徴組への影響が大きくなり、佐幕団体への傾向を強めると新徴組を脱隊する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the influence of the Shonai domain on the Shinchogumi increased and the characteristics of the Shinchogumi as a sabaku group (supportive group for the bakufu) became stronger, he left the Shinchogumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the influence of the Shonai domain on the Shinchogumi increased and the characteristics of the Shinchogumi as a sabaku group (supportive group for the bakufu) became stronger, he left the Shinchogumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the influence of the Shonai clan on the Shinchogumi increased and the characteristics of the Shinchogumi as a sabaku group (supportive group for the bakufu) became stronger, he left the Shinchogumi.</e>
<cmt>domain→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>それと前後し、公武合体派は基より尊皇・倒幕派も柏尾に接近、志士として広く維新に力を注ぐようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before and after his leaving, not only kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) groups but also Sonno and anti-shogunate groups contacted KASHIO, and he became more widely devoted as a patriot to the restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before and after his leaving, not only kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) groups but also Sonno and anti-shogunate groups contacted KASHIO, and as a patriot he became more widely devoted to the restoration.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before and after his leaving, not only kobu-gattai (integration of the imperial court and the shogunate) groups but also Sonno and anti-shogunate groups contacted Kashio, and as a patriot he became more widely devoted to the restoration.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正he の後のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>幕府の勝海舟や、海援隊 (浪士結社)の坂本龍馬らとも懇意であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was intimate with Kaishu KATSU of the bakufu and Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Kaientai (an association of roshi organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) (Roshi association).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was intimate with Kaishu KATSU of the bakufu and Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Kaientai (an association of roshi organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) (Roshi association).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was intimate with Kaishu KATSU of the bakufu and Ryoma SAKAMOTO of Kaientai (an association of roshi organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) (Roshi association).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>帰郷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Returning Home</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Returning Home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Returning Home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>晩年、養生のため阿波（美馬郡貞光）へ帰郷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned Awa (Sadamitsu, Mima County) in his later years for curing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Awa (Sadamitsu, Mima County) in his later years for curing.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Awa (Sadamitsu, Mima County) in his later years for curing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>それでもなお、尊皇倒幕、勤皇派武士を屋敷に匿うなど、最後まで維新に助力する姿勢に変わりは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after returning home, he harbored Sonno, anti-shogunate, pro-Imperialist samurai in his residence, and his attitude to contribute to the restoration did not change until the last minute of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after returning home, he harbored Sonno, anti-shogunate, pro-Imperialist samurai in his residence, and his attitude to contribute to the restoration did not change until the last minute of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after returning home, he harbored Sonno, anti-shogunate, pro-Imperialist samurai in his residence, and his attitude to contribute to the restoration did not change until the last minute of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>明治元年4月8日（1868年4月30日）没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died on April 30, 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died on April 30, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died on April 30, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>近代の幕開けと共に、人生の幕を下ろす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life ended when the modern days started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His life ended when the modern days started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His life ended when the modern days started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>戒名　武堅院 義秀勝遠日行居士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name): 武堅院 義秀勝遠日行居士.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name): 武堅院 義秀勝遠日行居士.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name): 武堅院 義秀勝遠日行居士.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>墓所は故郷、徳島県美馬郡つるぎ町貞光の柏尾家墓地内であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyard was in the Kashio family&apos;s cemetery in his hometown, Sadamitsu, Mima County, Tokushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyard was in the Kashio family&apos;s cemetery in his hometown, Sadamitsu, Mima County, Tokushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyard was in the Kashio family&apos;s cemetery in his hometown, Sadamitsu, Tsurugi-machi, Mima County, Tokushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「つるぎ町」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>（現在は徳島市内に移されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The graveyard is now in Tokushima City.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The graveyard is now in Tokushima City.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The graveyard is now in Tokushima City.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>没後、父の嘉蔵は、馬之助の妻（千葉周作の近親。北辰一刀流の小太刀術の使い手）に、千葉の実家に帰る事を勧めた。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death, his father Kazo recommended Umanosuke&apos;s wife, who was a close blood relative of Shusaku CHIBA, to return to her family&apos;s home in Chiba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death, his father Kazo recommended Umanosuke&apos;s wife, who was a close blood relative of Shusaku CHIBA, to return to her family&apos;s home in Chiba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death, his father Kazo recommended Umanosuke&apos;s wife, who was a close blood relative of Shusaku CHIBA, a swordsman of Kodachijutsu (swordmanship of kodachi, a small sword) of Hokushin-Ittoryu school, to return to her family&apos;s home in Chiba.</e>
<cmt>「北辰一刀流の小太刀術の使い手」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>彼女は帰郷の際、千葉家より持参していた短刀を一振り、柏尾家に残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When leaving to return home, she left in the Kashio family a short sword that she had brought from the Chiba family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When leaving to return home, she left in the Kashio family a short sword that she had brought from the Chiba family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When leaving to return home, she left in the Kashio family a short sword that she had brought from the Chiba family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="47">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>家紋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family Crest</e>
<cmt>用語集の family crestのほう を用いております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family Crest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family Crest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>家紋は丸に三柏紋（まるにみつがしわもん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family crest was maru ni mitsukashiwa (Three oak leaves in a circle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family crest was maru ni mitsukashiwa (Three oak leaves in a circle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family crest was maru ni mitsukashiwa (Three oak leaves in a circle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>「柏尾右馬之助」「柏尾右馬助」等の名を使っている場合もあるが、墓碑、系図では「柏尾馬之助」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sometimes used &quot;柏尾右馬之助&quot; and &quot;柏尾右馬助,&quot; but &quot;柏尾馬之助&quot; is written on his tombstone and in the family trees.</e>
<cmt>英語にすると全て同じとなるため、漢字をそのまま残しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sometimes used &quot;柏尾右馬之助&quot; and &quot;柏尾右馬助,&quot; but &quot;柏尾馬之助&quot; is written on his tombstone and in the family trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sometimes used &apos;柏尾右馬之助&apos; and &apos;柏尾右馬助,&apos; but &apos;柏尾馬之助&apos; is written on his tombstone and in the family trees.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>新撰組後期の平隊士 柏尾一郎 は別人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichiro KASHIO, who was a member of the late Shinsengumi, is a different person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichiro KASHIO, who was a member of the late Shinsengumi, is a different person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiro KASHIO, who was a member of the late Shinsengumi, is a different person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>写真</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Photograph</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Photograph</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Photograph</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>写真が柏尾家末裔に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His photograph is maintained by the descendant of the KASHIO family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His photograph is maintained by the descendants of the KASHIO family.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His photograph is maintained by the descendants of the Kashio family.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>痩せ型、右利き。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Skinny, right-handed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Skinny, right-handed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Skinny, right-handed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>東と西（新徴組と新選組）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East and West (Shinchogumi and Shinsengumi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East and West (Shinchogumi and Shinsengumi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East and West (Shinchogumi and Shinsengumi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>新徴組剣術教授方の柏尾馬之助、新撰組撃剣師範の沖田総司。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umanosuke KASHIO, who was a teacher of swordsmanship in the Shinchogumi, and Soji OKITA, who was a grand master of Gekken martial art in the Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umanosuke KASHIO, who was a teacher of swordsmanship in the Shinchogumi, and Soji OKITA, who was a grand master of Gekken martial art in the Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umanosuke KASHIO, who was a teacher of swordsmanship in the Shinchogumi, and Soji OKITA, who was a grand master of Gekken martial art in the Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>晩年の思想は、維新（柏尾）、佐幕（沖田）と正反対ではあるが、共に若くして天才肌の剣客、教授方師範。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although their late-life beliefs were completely different, restoration (KASHIO) and supporting bakufu (OKITA), they were both a genius expert swordsman and a teacher or a master at their young age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although their late-life beliefs were completely different, restoration (KASHIO) and supporting bakufu (OKITA), they were both genius expert swordsmen and teachers or masters at young ages.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although their late-life beliefs were completely different, restoration (Kashio) and supporting bakufu (Okita), they were both genius expert swordsmen and teachers or masters at young ages.</e>
<cmt>全大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>労咳（結核）を患い夭折。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suffered Rogai (tuberculosis) and died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suffered Rogai (tuberculosis) and died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suffered Rogai (tuberculosis) and died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>没年も同じ1868年と共通点も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They both died in 1868, having many similarities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They both died in 1868, having many similarities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They both died in 1868, having many similarities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 おかやまりゅうせい(id:122657), Jun Kashiwao(id:156444), Hidehiko Kashio(id:171866), IwaimBot(id:190695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>