<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ヨハニス・デ・レーケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Johannis de Rijke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Johannis de Rijke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Johannis de Rijke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ヨハニス・デ・レーケ（Johannis de Rijke、1842年12月5日 - 1913年1月20日）は、オランダ人で、日本の砂防や治山の工事を体系づけ、「砂防の父」とも言われるお雇い外国人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Johannis de Rijke (December 5, 1842 - January 20, 1913) was a Dutchman who systemized erosion and torrent control, and designed afforestation construction projects, known in Japan as &quot;the father of erosion and torrent control.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Johannis de Rijke (December 5, 1842 - January 20, 1913) was a Dutchman who systemized erosion and torrent control, and designed afforestation construction projects, and is known in Japan as &quot;the father of erosion and torrent control.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Johannis de Rijke (December 5, 1842 - January 20, 1913) was a Dutchman who systemized erosion and torrent control, and designed afforestation construction projects, and is known in Japan as &quot;the father of erosion and torrent control.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>彼の名前は、日本語では、ヨハネ（ニ）ス・デ・レイ（ー）ケなどと表記されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name is sometimes written as ヨハネ(ニ)ス・デ・レイ(ー)ケ in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is sometimes written as ヨハネ(ニ)ス・デ・レイ(ー)ケ in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is sometimes written as ヨハネ(ニ)ス・デ・レイ(ー)ケ in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本の土木事業（河川改修や砂防）における功績を評価すると、「お雇い外国人」ではなく「内務省技術顧問」や「河川技術者」などといった呼び名の方が相応しいとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering his achievements in engineering, including river improvement, and erosion and torrent control, it might have been better to refer to him as the &quot;Technical Adviser of the Interior&quot; or the &quot;River Improvement Engineer&quot; rather than &quot;Employed Foreigner,&quot; as he was often referred to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering his achievements in engineering, including river improvement, and erosion and torrent control, it might have been better to refer to him as the &quot;Technical Adviser of the Interior&quot; or the &quot;River Improvement Engineer&quot; rather than &quot;Employed Foreigner,&quot; as he was often called.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering his achievements in engineering, including river improvement, and erosion and torrent control, it might have been better to refer to him as the &apos;Technical Adviser of the Interior&apos; or the &apos;River Improvement Engineer&apos; rather than &apos;Employed Foreigner,&apos; as he was often called.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Biographyに変更</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>幼少時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Childhood years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Childhood years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Childhood years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>オランダに生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Holland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Holland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Holland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>兼業農家である築堤職人の息子として育った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of an embankment workman who also worked as a part-time farmer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of an embankment workman who also worked as a part-time farmer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of an embankment workman who also worked as a part-time farmer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>オランダ内務省技官出の水理学者であるJ・レブレットに出会うことから土木の技術者としての道を歩み始めることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After meeting J. Lebret, a hydraulic engineer and an engineering official with the Netherlands Ministry of the Interior, he decided to become a civil engineer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After meeting J. Lebret, a hydraulic engineer and an engineering official with the Netherlands Ministry of the Interior, he decided to become a civil engineer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After meeting J. Lebret, a hydraulic engineer and an engineering official with the Netherlands Ministry of the Interior, he decided to become a civil engineer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子供のいなかったレブレットは数学や力学や水理学など、土木工学に関する学問をデ・レーケに教えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">J. Lebret, who had no son, taught Johannis de Rijke civil engineering, including mathematics, dynamics and hydraulic, as his own child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">J. Lebret, who had no son, taught Johannis de Rijke civil engineering, including mathematics, dynamics, and hydraulics, as his own child.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">J. Lebret, who had no children, taught Johannis de Rijke civil engineering, including mathematics, dynamics, and hydraulics, as his own child.</e>
<cmt>son→children</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>デ・レーケの勤勉な姿勢に、大変、可愛がったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">J. Lebret was impressed with Johannis de Rijke&apos;s industriousness, and devoted a lot of attention to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">J. Lebret was impressed with Johannis de Rijke&apos;s industriousness, and devoted a lot of attention to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">J. Lebret was impressed with Johannis de Rijke&apos;s industriousness, and devoted a lot of attention to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>レブレットにとってデ・レーケは最初の教え子でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Johannis de Rijke was his first student.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Johannis de Rijke was his first student.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Johannis de Rijke was his first student.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内務省お雇い技師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Employed Engineer at the Ministry of the Interior</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Employed Engineer at the Ministry of the Interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Employed Engineer at the Ministry of the Interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>1873年に明治政府による海外の学問や技術の国内導入制度において、内務省土木局に招かれ、ジョージ・アーノルド・エッセル（エッセルは大学でもエリート）らと共に来日した。（エッセルは1等工師でデ・レーケは4等工師）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873, as a part of the project to introduce overseas learning and technologies in Japan, Johannis de Rijke, George Arnold Escher (G. A. Escher was among the elite at university) and others were invited to Japan by the Meiji government. G. A. Escher was a grade-one engineer and Johannis de Rijke was a grade-four engineer.</e>
<cmt>カッコに入っている（エッセルは1等工師でデ・レーケは4等工師）はカッコを外して、一文章として入れるほうが読みやすいと判断し、カッコを外しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1873, as a part of a project to introduce overseas learning and technologies in Japan, Johannis de Rijke, George Arnold Escher (G. A. Escher was among the university elite), and others were invited to Japan by the Meiji government. G. A. Escher was a grade-one engineer and Johannis de Rijke was a grade-four engineer.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873, as a part of a project to introduce overseas learning and technologies in Japan, Johannis de Rijke, George Arnold Escher (G. A. Escher was among the university elite), and others were invited to Japan by the Meiji government. (G. A. Escher was a grade-one engineer and Johannis de Rijke was a grade-four engineer.)</e>
<cmt>「し、」→「した。」括弧をはずすと、これも二文になってしまい、またセルを分けなくてはならないので、原文どおり括弧に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>淀川の改修や三国港の改修などに関わり、エッセルは主に設計を、デ・レーケは施工や監理を中心に担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were involved in improvement work for the Yodo-gawa river and Mikuni Port, Escher in design and de Rijke in construction and supervision.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were involved in improvement work for the Yodo-gawa river and Mikuni Port, Escher in design and de Rijke in construction and supervision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were involved in improvement work for the Yodo-gawa river and Mikuni Port, Escher in design and de Rijke in construction and supervision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後に、ファン・ドールンやエッセルの後任として、内務省の土木技術の助言者や技術指導者として現場を指揮することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he took over the job of Cornelis Johannes Van Doorn and Escher and become a civil engineering advisor and technical director at the Department of the Interior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he took over the job of Cornelis Johannes Van Doorn and Escher, and become a civil engineering advisor and technical director at the Department of the Interior.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he took over the job of Cornelis Johannes Van Doorn and Escher, and become a civil engineering advisor and technical director at the Department of the Interior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>水害を繰り返す河川を治めるため、放水路や分流の工事を行うだけでなく、根本的に重要であった水源の山地における砂防や治山の工事を体系づけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked to control concurrent flooding, not stopping at construction work on discharge channels and diversion rivers, but systemizing erosion and torrent control and affrostation, the origin the problem of flooding at river heads in mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked to control concurrent flooding, not stopping at construction work on discharge channels and diversion rivers, but systemizing erosion and torrent control and affrostation, the origin the problem of flooding at river heads in mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked to control concurrent flooding, not stopping at construction work on discharge channels and diversion rivers, but systemizing erosion and torrent control and affrostation, the origin of the problem of flooding at river heads in mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt>「け、」→「けた。」the origin the problem→the origin of the problem</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また全国の港湾の建築計画を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also made plans for seaport construction throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also made plans for seaport construction throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also made plans for seaport construction throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>特に木曽川の下流三川分流計画には10年にわたり心血を注ぎ成功させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He devoted his heart and soul to the split-flow treatment of three downstream sections of the Kiso-gawa River, a project that extended over 10 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He devoted his heart and soul to the split-flow treatment of three downstream sections of the Kiso-gawa River, a project that extended over 10 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He devoted his heart and soul to the split-flow treatment of three downstream sections of the Kiso-gawa River, a project that extended over 10 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>日本中の現場にも広く足を伸ばし技術指導や助言を行ってもいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He traveled throughout Japan to provide technical training and advice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He traveled throughout Japan to provide technical training and advice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He traveled throughout Japan to provide technical training and advice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これらの業績は高く評価され、1891年、内務省勅任官技術顧問（内務省事務次官に相当する）の扱いになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His achievements were highly acclaimed and he was appointed technical adviser to the Department of the Interior (equivalent in rank to a permanent under-secretary of the Interior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His achievements were highly acclaimed and he was appointed technical adviser to the Department of the Interior (equivalent in rank to a permanent under-secretary of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His achievements were highly acclaimed and in 1891, he was appointed technical adviser to the Department of the Interior (equivalent in rank to a permanent under-secretary of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>1891年、追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ちなみに、奏任官は本省の局長級までの扱いとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His position was one of the offices for which candidates were selected by the Prime Minister and classified as equivalent to chief of the bureau</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His position was an office for which candidates were selected by the Prime Minister and classified as equivalent to chief of the bureau.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His position was an office for which candidates were selected by the Prime Minister and classified as equivalent to chief of the bureau.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>建設事業の竣工時において、事業関係者は招待されたり記念碑に連名されるのが慣例とされているが、デ・レーケが関連した全土木工事おいて、一度も招待を受けたことがなく、また彼の名も記されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was customary for individuals involved in projects to be invited a completion ceremony and to have their names inscribed on a monument; however, de Rijke was never invited nor was his name ever inscribed on any of the monuments that marked his work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was customary for individuals involved in projects to be invited a completion ceremony and to have their names inscribed on a monument; however, de Rijke was never invited nor was his name ever inscribed on any of the monuments that marked his work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was customary for individuals involved in projects to be invited a completion ceremony and to have their names inscribed on a monument; however, de Rijke was never invited nor was his name ever inscribed on any of the monuments that marked his work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>あくまで内務省にとって彼はお雇い外国人（＝裏方）であり、彼の任務は調査と報告書提出のみであってそれを決定し遂行するのは日本側である、という事情が根本的な背景にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was considered an employed foreigner (a behind-the-scenes player) at the Department of the Interior, and his official role was to conduct research and submit reports, and the authority to decide and execute projects remained with the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was considered an employed foreigner (a behind-the-scenes player) at the Department of the Interior, and his official role was to conduct research and submit reports, and the authority to decide and execute projects remained with the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was considered an employed foreigner (a behind-the-scenes player) at the Department of the Interior, and his official role was to conduct research and submit reports, and the authority to decide and execute projects remained with the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>技術者としての誇りは相当に高かったはずだが、デ・レーケはそれを割り切っていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems he was very proud of his work as an engineer, but he appears that he accepted his role as a behind-the-scenes player.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems he was very proud of his work as an engineer, but he appears to have accepted his role as a behind-the-scenes player.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems he was very proud of his work as an engineer, but he appears to have accepted his role as a behind-the-scenes player.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>勅任官技術顧問～内務省退官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Appointment as Technical Adviser - Retirement from the Department of the Interior</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Appointment as Technical Adviser - Retirement from the Department of the Interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Appointment as Technical Adviser - Retirement from the Department of the Interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>後に、工科大学校（現・東京大学工学部）を始め、欧米諸国の大学で水文学をはじめとする高等教育を受けた内務省土木局の日本人技術者が台頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese engineers began to developed through higher education in hydrology at schools such as a Koka Daigakko College (Currently the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Engineering) and in universities in the US and Europe.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese engineers began to be developed through higher education in hydrology at schools such as Koka Daigakko College (Currently the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Engineering) and in universities in the US and Europe.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese engineers began to be developed through higher education in hydrology at schools such as Koka Daigakko College (Currently the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Engineering) and in universities in the US and Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>徐々に活躍の場を失うも、内務省勅任官技術顧問としての責務を全うした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">De Rijke gradually lost his place to exhibit his skills; however, he fulfilled his responsibilities after the imperial appointment as technical adviser of the Department of the Interior</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">De Rijke gradually lost his place to exhibit his skills; however, he fulfilled his responsibilities after the imperial appointment as technical adviser of the Department of the Interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">De Rijke gradually lost his place to exhibit his skills; however, he fulfilled his responsibilities after the imperial appointment as technical adviser of the Department of the Interior</e>
<cmt>imperial の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>都合30年以上日本に滞在し、1903年、離日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lived in Japan for over 30 years before returning to his home country in 1903.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lived in Japan for over 30 years before returning to his home country in 1903.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lived in Japan for over 30 years before returning to his home country in 1903.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>在日中に提出した報告書は57編に上り、2度受勲され、帰国に当たって日本の土木の基礎を築いたとして勲二等瑞宝章を授与される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his stay in Japan, he submitted 57 reports, received decorations twice, and was awarded the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold and Silver Star as a person establishing foundation for civil engineering in Japan upon his departure from Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his stay in Japan, he submitted 57 reports, received decorations twice, and upon his departure from Japan he was awarded the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold and Silver Star as a person establishing the foundation for civil engineering in Japan.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his stay in Japan, he submitted 57 reports, received decorations twice, and upon his departure from Japan he was awarded the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold and Silver Star as a person establishing the foundation for civil engineering in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>退職金は、現在の価格にして4億円に相当したとされ、当時の上官で内務省土木局長だった古市公威ら高級官僚らの労いもあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded a retirement bonus equivalent to 400 million yen at today&apos;s rate, as an expression of appreciation from such high government officials as Koi FURUICHI, the chief of the Engineering Bureau at the Department of Interior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded a retirement bonus equivalent to 400 million yen at today&apos;s rate, as an expression of appreciation from such high government officials as Koi FURUICHI, the chief of the Engineering Bureau at the Department of Interior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded a retirement bonus equivalent to 400 million yen at today&apos;s rate, as an expression of appreciation from such high government officials as Koi FURUICHI, the chief of the Engineering Bureau at the Department of Interior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>中国河川改修技師長以後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Chief Engineer on a river improvement project in China and thereafter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Chief Engineer on a river improvement project in China and thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Chief Engineer on a river improvement project in China and thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>内務省退官後、数年間はオランダに帰郷し英気を養った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After retiring from the Department of the Interior, he returned to his homeland, where he remained for several years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After retiring from the Department of the Interior, he returned to his homeland, where he remained for several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After retiring from the Department of the Interior, he returned to his homeland, where he remained for several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>まもなく、オランダ政府代表として、中国の上海市の黄浦江の改修事業の技師長として現地に赴く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after he was appointed as the representative of the Dutch government to serve as chief engineer for restoration operations on the Huangpu River in the city of Shanghai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after he was appointed as a representative of the Dutch government to serve as chief engineer for restoration operations on the Huangpu River in the city of Shanghai.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after he was appointed as a representative of the Dutch government to serve as chief engineer for restoration operations on the Huangpu River in the city of Shanghai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>辣腕を振るうことになるが、建設系事業者（建設コンサルタントと称していたが実際は浚渫系専門業者などの詐称）の、いい加減さ・中国政府の未曾有の混迷による事業費問題・ドイツやイギリスの政府および報道機関への対応の苦慮…などによる心労が重なり、命を縮めることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was hired for his uncommon ability; however, dealing with problems such as the irresponsibility construction organizations (Venders falsely claimed to be construction consultants but who was in reality dredgers), problems with operating expenses due to confusion within the Chinese government, and difficulty dealing with the German and English governments and the mass media, led to the shortening of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was hired for his uncommon ability; however, dealing with problems such as the irresponsibility of construction organizations (Venders falsely claimed to be construction consultants but were in reality dredgers), problems with operating expenses due to confusion within the Chinese government, and difficulty dealing with the German and English governments and the mass media, led to the shortening of his life.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was hired for his uncommon ability; however, dealing with problems such as the irresponsibility of construction organizations (Venders falsely claimed to be construction consultants but were in reality dredgers), problems with operating expenses due to confusion within the Chinese government, and difficulty dealing with the German and English governments and the mass media, led to the shortening of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>1911年、技師長職を辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911, he resigned his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911, he resigned his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911, he resigned his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>同年1月17日に勲爵位（ライデル）が送られ名実ともに、貴族の仲間入りを果たすことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 17 of the same year, he was awarded the rank and order of merit (Ridder) and he joined the nobles in both name and in reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 17 of the same year, he was awarded the rank and order of merit (Ridder) and he joined the nobility in both name and in reality.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 17 of the same year, he was awarded the rank and order of merit (Ridder) and he joined the nobility in both name and in reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>オランダ政府代表として黄浦江改修事業の技師長としての功績によるものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The award was given for his achievements on the Huangpu River restoration project as the representative of the Dutch government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The award was given for his achievements on the Huangpu River restoration project as the representative of the Dutch government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The award was given for his achievements on the Huangpu River restoration project as the representative of the Dutch government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>2年後の1913年、母国オランダのアムステルダムにて死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two years later in 1913, he died in his home, Amsterdam, Holland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two years later, in 1913, he died in his home, Amsterdam, Holland.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two years later, in 1913, he died in his home, Amsterdam, Holland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>デ・レーケが指導や建設した砂防ダムや防波堤は、100年以上経過した現在でも日本各所に現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Erosion-control dams and breakwaters that were built construction under de Rijke&apos;s supervision still exist throughout Japan, after more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Erosion-control dams and breakwaters that were built under de Rijke&apos;s supervision still exist throughout Japan, after more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Erosion-control dams and breakwaters that were built under de Rijke&apos;s supervision still exist throughout Japan, after more than 100 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1998年にはデ・レーケの孫が来日し、木曽川などを視察し、話題になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1998, de Rijke&apos;s grandchild visited Japan and went to visit the Kiso-gawa River, an event which hit the news.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1998, de Rijke&apos;s grandchild visited Japan and went to visit the Kiso-gawa River, an event which hit the news.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1998, de Rijke&apos;s grandchild visited Japan and went to visit the Kiso-gawa River, an event which hit the news.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), Tawashi(id:72005), 浩(id:70121), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), G.miyanomori(id:9984), Tokumiki0(id:12043), Hide-sp(id:145562), Robotje(id:11192), Hatsune(id:26654), Arpeggio(id:9385), Rusk(id:9895), IwaimBot(id:190695), Birdman(id:1040), Cotton5(id:127398), ぴかり(id:116821), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 河川一等兵(id:41231), Qurren(id:20140), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>