<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>色部長実</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagazane IROBE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagazane IROBE</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagazane IROBE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>色部 長実（いろべ ながざね）は、戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagazane IROBE was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the Sengoku period to the Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagazane IROBE was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the Sengoku period to the Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagazane IROBE was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the Sengoku period (period of warring states) to the Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>越後国上杉氏の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a vassal of the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the vassal of the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>a → the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the vassal of the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>越後岩船郡小泉荘を支配した平林城主である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the lord of Hirabayashi Castle and governed the fiefdom of Koizumi, Iwafune County, Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the lord of Hirabayashi Castle and governed the chiefdom of Koizumi, Iwafune County, Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>fiefdom→chiefdom</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Hirabayashi-jo Castle and governed the fiefdom of Koizumi, Iwafune County, Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが「fiefdom→chiefdom」と訂正されてますが、再び「fiefdom」としました。城名に -jo 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に長真と改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed his first name to &apos;Nagamasa&apos; afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later changed his first name to &apos;Nagamasa&apos;.</e>
<cmt>afterwards → later</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later changed his first name to &apos;Nagamasa&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正妻は新発田重家の妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legal wife was the younger sister of Shigeie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal wife was the younger sister of Shigeie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wife was the younger sister of Shigeie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天文22年（1553年）、越後長尾氏（上杉氏）の重臣・色部勝長の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1553, Nagazane was born the son of Katsunaga IROBE, the senior vassal of the Echigo Nagao clan (Uesugi clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1553, Nagazane was born the son of Katsunaga IROBE, the senior vassal of the Echigo Nagao clan (Uesugi clan).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1553, Nagazane was born the son of Katsunaga IROBE, the senior vassal of the Echigo Nagao clan (Uesugi clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>兄に嗣子である色部顕長がいたため、父の死後は兄が家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he had older brother, Akinaga IROBE, who was a heir, the family head was succeeded by his brother after the death of his father.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he had an older brother, Akinaga IROBE, who was a heir, the family head was succeeded by his brother after the death of his father.</e>
<cmt>added an. 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he had an older brother, Akinaga IROBE, who was a heir, the family head was succeeded by his brother after the death of his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、その顕長が病弱だったため、天正4年（1576年）に兄が隠居し、代わって家督を譲られて色部氏の当主となり、上杉謙信に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1576, however, Akinaga went into retirement because of his delicate health and transferred family responsibilities to Nagazane, who became the head of the Irobe clan and served Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1576, however, Akinaga went into retirement because of his delicate health and transferred the family responsibilities to Nagazane, who became the head of the Irobe clan and served Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>added the to family. 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1576, however, Akinaga went into retirement because of his delicate health and transferred the family responsibilities to Nagazane, who became the head of the Irobe clan and served Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>天正6年（1578年）の謙信没後に起こった御館の乱では上杉景勝を支持して、上杉景虎方と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Otate Infighting, which occurred after the death of Shingen in 1578, he supported Kagekatsu UESUGI and fought against the army of Kagetora UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Otate infighting, which occurred after the death of Shingen in 1578, he supported Kagekatsu UESUGI and fought against the army of Kagetora UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>Infighting → infighting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Otate War, which occurred after the death of Shingen in 1578, he supported Kagekatsu UESUGI and fought against the army of Kagetora UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>「御館の乱」を用語集の訳に変更。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後は景勝の家臣として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he became the vassal of Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, he became the vassal of Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, he became the vassal of Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天正9年（1581年）に勃発した新発田重家の乱では正室が重家の妹であった関係もあり重家対策を任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Shigeie SHIBATA staged a revolt in 1581, Nagazane was instructed to counter Shigeie because his wife was the younger sister of Shigeie.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shigeie SHIBATA staged a revolt in 1581, Nagazane was instructed to encounter Shigeie because his wife was the younger sister of Shigeie.</e>
<cmt>counter→encounter. 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shigeie SHIBATA staged a revolt in 1581, Nagazane was instructed to encounter Shigeie because his wife was the younger sister of Shigeie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>天正18年（1590年）の仙北一揆においては豊臣秀吉の命令を受けて平鹿郡大森城に在城し、大谷吉継と共にその鎮圧に功績を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When an uprising took place in Senboku in 1590, he was stationed to Omori Castle in Hiraka County by order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, whereby together with Yoshitsugu Otani, he contributed to the suppression of the uprising.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When an uprising took place in Senboku in 1590, he was stationed at Omori Castle in Hiraka County by order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, whereby together with Yoshitsugu Otani, he contributed to the suppression of the uprising.</e>
<cmt>to→at</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When an uprising took place in Senboku in 1590, he was stationed at Omori-jo Castle in Hiraka County by order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, whereby together with Yoshitsugu OTANI, he contributed to the suppression of the uprising.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記Otani→OTANI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天正20年（1592年）、秀吉の命令により朝鮮出兵が始まると、景勝に従って肥前国名護屋城に赴いたが、その途上に発病し、京都で病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When invasions of Korea started under the order of Hideyoshi in 1592, he accompanied Kagekatsu to Nagoya Castle in Hizen Province, but suffered illness on its way and died in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the invasions of Korea started under the order of Hideyoshi in 1592, he accompanied Kagekatsu to Nagoya Castle in Hizen Province, but suffered illness on the way and died in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>invastions → to invasions. Its way → the way</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the invasions of Korea started under the order of Hideyoshi in 1592, he accompanied Kagekatsu to Nagoya-jo Castle in Hizen Province, but suffered illness on the way and died in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記Otani→OTANI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>享年40。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 40.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 40.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 40.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、物語としての忠臣蔵に家老として登場する色部又四郎（安長）や戊辰戦争時に家老を勤め新潟で戦死した色部長門は長実の子孫である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, Matajiro (Yasunaga) IROBE, who appears as a vassal in the story Chushingura (The treasury of Loyal Retainers), and Nagato IROBE, who served as a Karo (chief retainer) during the Boshin Civil War and died in battle in Nigata, were the descendants of Nagazane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, Matajiro (Yasunaga) IROBE, who appears as a vassal in the story Chushingura (The treasury of Loyal Retainers), and Nagato IROBE, who served as a Karo (chief retainer) during the Boshin Civil War and died in battle in Nigata, were the descendants of Nagazane.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, Matajiro (Yasunaga) IROBE, who appears as a vassal in the story Chushingura (The treasury of Loyal Retainers), and Nagato IROBE, who served as a Karo (chief retainer) during the Boshin Civil War and died in battle in Niigata, were the descendants of Nagazane.</e>
<cmt>Nigata→Niigata</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>（養子等による家督相続も挟まれている為、直接の血縁では無い）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(They were not direct descendants because the clan had been succeeded also by adopted heirs, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(They were not direct descendants because the clan had also been succeeded by adopted heirs etc.)</e>
<cmt>changed the position of also and heirs, → heirs</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(They were not direct descendants because the clan had also been succeeded by adopted heirs etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), ドルチェット(id:46458), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Symplux(id:122801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>