<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原邦綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 邦綱（ふじわら の くにつな、保安 (元号)3年（1122年） - 治承5年閏2月23日 (旧暦)（1181年4月8日））は平安時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna (1122 - April 8, 1181) was a court noble in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna (1122 - April 8, 1181) was a court noble during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna (1122 - April 8, 1181) was a court noble during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は右馬権助・藤原盛国、母は散位・藤原公長の女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Morikuni, Uma no gon no suke (Asst. Provisional Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses), while his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinnaga, Sani (courtier without post).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Morikuni, Uma no gon no suke (Asst. Provisional Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses), while his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinnaga, Sani (courtier without a post).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Morikuni, Uma no gon no suke (Asst. Provisional Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses), while his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinnaga, Sani (courtier without a post).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に泰季（実父・高階仲親）、重邦、基能、清邦（平清盛の養子）、藤原成子（六条天皇乳母）、邦子（高倉天皇乳母・藤原成頼室）、藤原輔子（安徳天皇乳母・平重衡室）、藤原綱子（平徳子乳母）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Yasusue (a real son of TAKASHINA no Nakachika), Shigekuni, Motoyoshi, Kiyokuni (adopted into a son of TAIRA no Kiyomori), FUJIWARA no Nariko (Emperor Rokujo&apos;s menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby)), FUJIWARA no Kuniko (Emperor Takakura&apos;s menoto and FUJIWARA no Nariyori&apos;s wife), FUJIWARA no Hoshi (Emperor Antoku&apos;s menoto and TAIRA no Shigehira&apos;s wife), and FUJIWARA no Tsunako (TAIRA no Tokuko&apos;s menoto).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処（実父・高階仲親）のカッコ内を文章にせずつなげるため、高階仲親の実子と訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Yasusue (a real son of TAKASHINA no Nakachika), Shigekuni, Motoyoshi, Kiyokuni (adopted as the son of TAIRA no Kiyomori), FUJIWARA no Nariko (Emperor Rokujo&apos;s menoto - a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby), FUJIWARA no Kuniko (Emperor Takakura&apos;s menoto and FUJIWARA no Nariyori&apos;s wife), FUJIWARA no Hoshi (Emperor Antoku&apos;s menoto and TAIRA no Shigehira&apos;s wife), and FUJIWARA no Tsunako (TAIRA no Tokuko&apos;s menoto).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Yasusue (a real son of TAKASHINA no Nakachika), Shigekuni, Motoyoshi, Kiyokuni (adopted as the son of TAIRA no Kiyomori), FUJIWARA no Nariko (Emperor Rokujo&apos;s menoto - a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby), FUJIWARA no Kuniko (Emperor Takakura&apos;s menoto and FUJIWARA no Nariyori&apos;s wife), FUJIWARA no Hoshi (Emperor Antoku&apos;s menoto and TAIRA no Shigehira&apos;s wife), and FUJIWARA no Tsunako (TAIRA no Tokuko&apos;s menoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原良門流藤原氏の系統に属する下級官人だったが、大学寮から蔵人になる一方で藤原忠通の家司として頭角を現わす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Belonging to the family line of FUJIWARA no Yoshikado in the FUJIWARA clan, a lower-ranking government official class, he served as Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) and Kurodo (Chamberlain) but distinguished himself as a Keishi (household superintendent) of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Belonging to the family line of FUJIWARA no Yoshikado in the FUJIWARA clan, a lower-ranking government official class, he served as Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) and Kurodo (Chamberlain) but distinguished himself as a Keishi (household superintendent) of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Belonging to the FUJIWARA no Yoshikado line of the FUJIWARA clan, a lower-ranking government official class, he served as Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) and Kurodo (Chamberlain) but distinguished himself as a Keishi (household superintendent) of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi.</e>
<cmt>「family line of FUJIWARA no Yoshikado in the FUJIWARA clan」→「FUJIWARA no Yoshikado line of the FUJIWARA clan」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>和泉国・越後国・伊予国・播磨国の受領を歴任して財力を蓄え、永万元年（1165年）破格ともいえる蔵人頭に補される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was serving as Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) of the Provinces of Izum, Echigo, Iyo, and Harima, he made a fortune and got an exceptional promotion to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1165.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was serving as Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) of the Provinces of Izum, Echigo, Iyo, and Harima, he made a fortune and received an exceptional promotion to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1165.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was serving as Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) of the Provinces of Izumi, Echigo, Iyo, and Harima, he made a fortune and received an exceptional promotion to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1165.</e>
<cmt>Izum→Izumi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>4人の娘を六条・高倉・安徳三天皇及び高倉中宮・徳子の乳母として、その豊かな財力で養育に力を尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had his four daughters become the menoto of three Emperors--Rokujo, Takakura, and Antoku--and the Empress Takakura, Tokuko and contribute to their upbringing using his great wealth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had his four daughters become the menoto of three Emperors--Rokujo, Takakura, and Antoku--and the Empress Takakura, Tokuko and contributed to their upbringing using his great wealth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had his four daughters become the menoto of three Emperors--Rokujo, Takakura, and Antoku--and the Empress Takakura, Tokuko and contributed to their upbringing using his great wealth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平氏と親密な関係を深め白河殿盛子（関白・近衛基実室）の後見をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He strengthened a tie with the Taira clan and acted as a guardian for Shirakawa dono (TAIRA no) Seishi (the wife of Motozane KONOE, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He strengthened ties with the Taira clan and acted as a guardian for Shirakawa dono (TAIRA no) Seishi (the wife of Motozane KONOE, Kanpaku - chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He strengthened ties with the Taira clan and acted as a guardian for Shirakawa dono (TAIRA no) Seishi (the wife of Motozane KONOE, Kanpaku - chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）基実が没すると多くの摂関家領を盛子に相続させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Motozane died in 1166, he was successful in having many territories of the Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers) inherited to Seishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Motozane died in 1166, he was successful in having many territories of the Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers) inherited to Seishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Motozane died in 1166, he was successful in having many territories of the Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers) inherited to Seishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これについて九条兼実は「平禅門の藤氏を滅亡する、此の人頗る其の事に与る」（『玉葉』治承5年閏2月23日条）と非難している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanezane KUJO criticized this by saying &quot;平禅門の藤氏を滅亡する、此の人頗る其の事に与る&quot; in Gyokuyo (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary), February 23, 1179).</e>
<cmt>「平禅門の藤氏を滅亡する、此の人頗る其の事に与る」は訳し出しできませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanezane KUJO criticized this by saying &quot;平禅門の藤氏を滅亡する、此の人頗る其の事に与る&quot; in Gyokuyo (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary), February 23, 1179).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanezane KUJO criticized this in an entry in Gyokuyo (the name given to his diary) that he made on February 23, 1179, in which he said: &quot;He is willingly trying to extinguish the line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>権大納言まで昇進し公卿に列したが、邦綱の系統では平安前期の藤原兼輔以来だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor), a member of the court nobles; it was the first time for his family line to get advanced to such a high position since FUJIWARA no Kanesuke had taken it in the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor), a member of the court nobles; it was the first time for his family line to be advanced to such a high position since FUJIWARA no Kanesuke had been promoted during the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state), a member of the court nobles; it was the first time for his family line to be advanced to such a high position since FUJIWARA no Kanesuke had been promoted during the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>子を清盛の養子にするなど、清盛から信頼され「平大相国とさしも契深う、心ざし浅からざりし人なり」（『平家物語』）といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori adopted his son, which shows his trust in Kunitsuna was great, and Heike Monogatari (the tale of the Heike) describes: &quot;平大相国とさしも契深う、心ざし浅からざりし人なり.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「平大相国とさしも契深う、心ざし浅からざりし人なり」は訳し出しできませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori adopted his son, which shows his trust in Kunitsuna was great, and Heike Monogatari (the tale of the Heike) describes: &quot;平大相国とさしも契深う、心ざし浅からざりし人なり.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s adoption of Kunitsuna&apos;s son showed how greatly he trusted Kunitsuna, and Heike Monogatari (the tale of the Heike) described Kunitsuna as follows: &quot;He is deeply involved with TAIRA Dajo-daijin (Grand minister of state) and he has great ambition.&quot;</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>第宅も数多く有し、土御門東洞院第は後白河天皇の御所及び六条・高倉両天皇の里内裏として、五条第は高倉天皇の里内裏に用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among many Teitaku (residences) he owned, the Tsuchimikado Higashinotoin-tei (residence) was used for a Gosho (Palace) of the Emperor Goshirakawa and for a Satodairi (a temporary palace) of the Emperors of Rokujo and Takakura, while the Gojo-tei (residence) was used for a Satodairi of the Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among many Teitaku (residences) he owned, the Tsuchimikado Higashinotoin-tei (residence) that was used for a Gosho (Palace) of the Emperor Goshirakawa and for a Satodairi (a temporary palace) of the Emperors of Rokujo and Takakura, while the Gojo-tei (residence) was used for a Satodairi for Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among many Teitaku (residences) he owned, the Tsuchimikado Higashinotoin-tei (residence) that was used for a Gosho (Palace) of the Emperor Goshirakawa and for a Satodairi (a temporary palace) of the Emperors of Rokujo and Takakura, while the Gojo-tei (residence) was used for a Satodairi for Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>高倉上皇の第一の側近として厳島御幸や、遷都が計画された福原京福原行幸に供奉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied the retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s visit to Itsukushima and Fukuhara-kyo (Capital of Fukuhara), the planned capital relocation site, as the closest aide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accompanied the retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s visit to Itsukushima and Fukuhara-kyo (Capital of Fukuhara), the planned capital relocation site, as the closest aide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accompanied the retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s visit to Itsukushima and Fukuhara-kyo (Capital of Fukuhara), the planned capital relocation site, as the closest aide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>高倉崩御に際しては素服を賜わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor Takakura died,. he was given sofuku (white clothes) for mourning.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Takakura died,. he was given sofuku (white clothes) for mourning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Takakura died,. he was given sofuku (white clothes) for mourning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>公卿でこの恩遇にあずかったのは、邦綱の他には平宗盛・平時忠・藤原隆季・土御門通親の4人だけだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among court nobles, given such a treatment were only Kunitsuna and other four nobles--TAIRA no Munemori, TAIRA no Tokitada, FUJIWARA no Takasue, and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among court nobles, treated in such a way, were only Kunitsuna and four other nobles--TAIRA no Munemori, TAIRA no Tokitada, FUJIWARA no Takasue, and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among court nobles, treated in such a way, were only Kunitsuna and four other nobles--TAIRA no Munemori, TAIRA no Tokitada, FUJIWARA no Takasue, and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>やがて清盛も没し、後を追うように治承5年（1181年）閏2月23日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long Kiyomori died, and FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna died on February 23, 1181 as if following Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long Kiyomori died, and FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna died on February 23, 1181 as if following Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long Kiyomori died, and FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna died on February 23, 1181 as if following Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>訃報を聞いた兼実は下記（『玉葉』治承5年閏2月23日条）のように評した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing of his death, Kanezane wrote in Gyokuyo (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary), February 23, 1179) as below:</e>
<cmt>語順を変更しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing of his death, Kanezane wrote in Gyokuyo (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary), February 23, 1179) as below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing of his death, Kanezane wrote in Gyokuyo (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary), February 23, 1179) as below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「邦綱卿は卑賤より出ずと雖も其の心広大なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>「邦綱卿は卑賤より出ずと雖も其の心広大なり。」訳出できませんでした。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunitsuna was from a humble background but he was generous of heart.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「天下の諸人貴賎を論ぜず、其の経営を以て偏に身の大事となす。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>「天下の諸人貴賎を論ぜず、其の経営を以て偏に身の大事となす。」訳し出しできませんでした。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not judge people based on their occupation, only on their progress.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「ここに因りて衆人惜しまざるはなし」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>「ここに因りて衆人惜しまざるはなし」訳し出しできませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is certain that he will be missed by many.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Record of office and rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Record of offices held and rank</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of office and rank</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date:the Gregorian calendar</e>
<cmt>実際英文は旧暦ではなく西暦なので「西暦」と訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date: according to the Gregorian calendar</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date: according to the Gregorian calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>長承4年のち改元して保延元年（1135年）（14歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1135 (14 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1135 (14 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1135 (age 14)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>2月8日文章生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 8: Monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 8: Monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 8: Monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>蔵人所雑色</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoshiki (low-level functionary) in Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoshiki (low-level functionary) in Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoshiki (low-level functionary) in Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>久安4年（1148年）（27歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1149 (27 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1149 (27 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1149 (age 27)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>正月7日六位蔵人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 7: Rokui-Kurodo (kurodo with the Sixth Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7: Rokui-Kurodo (kurodo with the Sixth Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 7: Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank)</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>久安5年（1149年）（28歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1149 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1149 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1149 (age 28)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>4月9日修理権亮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 9: Shuri gon no suke (Provisional assistant master in the Office of Palace Repairs)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 9: Shuri gon no suke (Provisional assistant master in the Office of Palace Repairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 9: Shuri gon no suke (Provisional assistant master in the Office of Palace Repairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>12月25日右衛門少尉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 25: Uemon no shojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 25: Uemon no shojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 25: Uemon no shojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>久安6年（1150年）（29歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1150 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1150 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1150 (age 29)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>正月29日検非違使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 29: kebiishi (a police and judicial chief)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 29: kebiishi (police and judicial chief)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 29: kebiishi (police and judicial chief)</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>久安7年のち改元して仁平元年（1151年）（30歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1151 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1151 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1151 (age 30)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>正月6日従五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 6: Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6: Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 6: Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>2月2日遠江権守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 2: Totoumi-gon-no-kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 2: Totoumi-gon-no-kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 2: Totoumi-gon-no-kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>12月4日中宮少進</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 4: Chugu shojo (Junior Secretary in the Office of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 4: Chugu shojo (Junior Secretary in the Office of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 4: Chugu shojo (Junior Secretary in the Office of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>仁平4年のち改元して久寿元年（1154年）（33歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1154 (33 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1154 (33 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1154 (age 33)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>正月23日壱岐守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 23: Iki no kami (governor of Iki Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 23: Iki no kami (governor of Iki Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 23: Iki no kami (governor of Iki Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）（34歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1155 (34 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1155 (34 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1155 (age 34)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>12月25日中宮権大進</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 25: Chugu Gon no taijo (Provisional Senior Secretary in the Office of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 25: Chugu Gon no taijo (Provisional Senior Secretary in the Office of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 25: Chugu Gon no taijo (Provisional Senior Secretary in the Office of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="40">
<j>久寿3年のち改元して保元元年（1156年）（35歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1156 (35 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1156 (35 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1156 (age 35)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>9月17日和泉守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 17: Izuminokami Guard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 17: Izuminokami Guard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 17: Izuminokami Guard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>保元2年（1157年）（36歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1157 (36 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1157 (36 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1157 (age 36)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>8月9日従五位上（東三条殿から高松殿に還御）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 9: Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) (Return from Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace to Takamatsu-dono Palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 9: Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) (Return from Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace to Takamatsu-dono Palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 9: Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) (Return from Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace to Takamatsu-dono Palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>10月22日正五位下（襲芳舎の造営）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 22: Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building of Shuhosha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 22: Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building of Shuhosha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 22: Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building of Shuhosha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>10月29日従四位下（待賢門の造営）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 29: Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building of Taikenmon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 29: Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building of Taikenmon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 29: Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building of Taikenmon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="46">
<j>保元3年（1158年）（37歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1158 (37 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1158 (37 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1158 (age 37)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>10月21日従四位上（宇治御幸）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 21: Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) (gyoko (royal visit) to Uji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 21: Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) (gyoko - royal visit to Uji)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 21: Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) (gyoko (royal visit) to Uji)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="48">
<j>保元4年のち改元して平治元年（1159年）（38歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1159 (38 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1159 (38 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1159 (age 38)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>正月6日正四位下（八省廊の造営）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 6: Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building Hasshoro (corridor))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6: Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building Hasshoro - corridor)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 6: Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) (Building Hasshoro - corridor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="50">
<j>平治2年のち改元して永暦元年（1160年）（39歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1160 (39 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1160 (39 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1160 (age 39)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>正月21日木工頭兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 21: concurrently served as Moku no kami (chief of Bureau of Carpentry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21: concurrently served as Moku no kami (chief of the Bureau of Carpentry)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 21: concurrently served as Moku no kami (chief of the Bureau of Carpentry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>2月28日越後守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 28: Echigo no kami (Provincial Governor of Echigo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 28: Echigo no kami (Provincial Governor of Echigo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 28: Echigo no kami (Governor of Echigo Province)</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="53">
<j>永暦2年のち改元して応保元年（1161年）（40歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1161 (40 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1161 (40 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1161 (age 40)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>4月3日伊予守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 3: Iyo no Kami (Governor of Iyo Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 3: Iyo no Kami (Governor of Iyo Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 3: Iyo no Kami (Governor of Iyo Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>8月12日右京大夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 12: Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 12: Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 12: Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="56">
<j>応保2年（1162年）（41歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1162 (41 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1162 (41 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1162 (age 41)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>正月27日播磨守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 27: Harima no kami (the governor of Harima Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 27: Harima no kami (governor of Harima Province)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 27: Harima no kami (governor of Harima Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>右京大夫如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="59">
<j>2月19日中宮亮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 19: Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 19: Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 19: Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>右京大夫・播磨守如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu and Harima no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu and Harima no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu and Harima no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="61">
<j>長寛3年のち改元して永万元年（1165年）（44歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1165 (44 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1165 (44 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1165 (age 44)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>7月18日播磨守を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 18: Resigned from Harima no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 18: Resigned from Harima no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 18: Resigned from Harima no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>7月25日蔵人頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 25: Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 25: Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 25: Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="64">
<j>永万2年のち改元して仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）（45歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1166 (45 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1166 (45 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1166 (age 45)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>正月12日参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 12: Appointed to Sangi, Councilor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 12: Appointed to Sangi, Councilor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 12: Appointed to Sangi, Councilor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>右京大夫如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remained in the position of Ukyo no daibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="67">
<j>6月6日従三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 6: Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 6: Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 6: Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>8月27日参議を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 27: Resigned from Sangi, Councilor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 27: Resigned from Sangi, Councilor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 27: Resigned from Sangi, Councilor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>10月6日本座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 6: Received the treatment as Sangi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 6: Received treatment as Sangi</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 6: Received the treatment as Sangi (even though he had resigned from Sangi previously)</e>
<cmt>本座の説明を追加 (even though he had resigned from Sangi previously)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>10月10日春宮権大夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 10: Togu Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10: Togu Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 10: Togu Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>11月3日正三位（春宮行啓）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 3: Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) (Togu (the Crown Prince) gyokei (visit of imperial person))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 3: Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) (Togu (the Crown Prince) gyokei - visit of imperial person)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 3: Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) (Togu (the Crown Prince) gyokei - visit of imperial person)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="72">
<j>仁安2年（1167年）（46歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1167 (46 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1167 (46 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1167 (age 46)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>正月30日周防権守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 30: Director of Suo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 30: Director of Suo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 30: Suo no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Suo Province)</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="74">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）（47歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1168 (47 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1168 (47 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1168 (age 47)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>2月19日春宮権大夫を辞任（高倉天皇践祚）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 19: Resigned from Togu Gon no daibu (Emperor Takakura&apos;s accession (to the throne))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 19: Resigned from Togu Gon no daibu (Emperor Takakura&apos;s accession to the throne)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 19: Resigned from Togu Gon no daibu (Emperor Takakura&apos;s accession to the throne)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>12月23日権中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 23: Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 23: Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 23: Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="77">
<j>仁安4年のち改元して嘉応元年（1169年）（48歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1169 (48 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1169 (48 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1169 (age 48)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>正月6日従二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 6: Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6: Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 6: Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="79">
<j>嘉応3年のち改元して承安 (日本)元年（1171年）（50歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1171 (50 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1171 (50 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1171 (age 50)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>4月21日正二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 21: Shonii (Senior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 21: Shonii (Senior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21: Shonii (Senior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="81">
<j>承安5年のち改元して安元元年（1175年）（54歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1175 (54 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1175 (54 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1175 (age 54)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>11月28日中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 28: Chunagon (middle counselor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 28: Chunagon (middle counselor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 28: Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="83">
<j>安元3年のち改元して治承元年（1177年）（56歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1177 (56 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1177 (56 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1177 (age 56)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>4月24日権大納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 24: Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 24: Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 24: Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state)</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="85">
<j>治承3年（1179年）（58歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1179 (58 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1179 (58 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1179 (age 58)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>7月12日権大納言を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 12: Resigned from Gon Dainagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 12: Resigned from Gon Dainagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 12: Resigned from Gon Dainagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="87">
<j>治承5年のち改元して養和元年（1181年）（60歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1181 (60 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1181 (60 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1181 (age 60)</e>
<cmt>「years old」→「age」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>閏2月3日出家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 3: Entered into priesthood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 3: Entered into priesthood</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 3: Entered into priesthood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), レッドバロン(id:173220), Andee(id:20421), Ganman(id:96316), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Uraios(id:72687), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>