<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大内持世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiyo OUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyo OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyo OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大内 持世（おおうち もちよ、1394年3月23日（明徳5年2月21日 (旧暦)） - 1441年8月14日（嘉吉元年7月28日 (旧暦)））は、室町時代中期の守護大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiyo OUCHI (March 23, 1394 - August 14, 1441) was the Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) in the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyo OUCHI (March 23, 1394 - August 14, 1441) was a Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) in the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;the&quot; to &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyo OUCHI (March 23, 1394 - August 14, 1441) was a Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) in the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大内氏の第12代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the twelfth family head of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the twelfth head of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;family&quot; is not required.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the twelfth head of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は応永の乱を起こしたことで有名な第10代当主・大内義弘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was the tenth family head, Yoshihiro OUCHI, who was famous for causing the Oei War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was the tenth head, Yoshihiro OUCHI, who was famous for starting the Oei War.</e>
<cmt>&quot;starting a war&quot; is a more commonly used expression.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was the 10th head, Yoshihiro OUCHI, who was famous for instigating the Oei War.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は刑部少輔、修理大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Gyobu no sho (Junior Assistant Minister of Justice) and Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyo&apos;s official rank was Gyobu no sho (Junior Assistant Minister of Justice) and Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>It is not clear who &quot;he&quot; is referring to - father or son?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyo&apos;s official rank was Junior Assistant Minister of Justice and Master of the Office of Palace Repairs.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1431年、第11代当主・大内盛見が大友氏・少弐氏と戦って筑前国で敗死した後、大内氏内部では後継ぎをめぐっての争いが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1431, after the eleventh family head, Morimi OUCHI, was killed during the battle against the Otomo clan and the Shoni clan in Chikuzen Province, a conflict over the heir occurred within the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1431, after the eleventh head, Morimi OUCHI, was killed in a battle against the Otomo clan and the Shoni clan in Chikuzen Province, a conflict over the succession arose within the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;succession&quot; works better than &quot;heir&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1431, after the 11th head, Morimi OUCHI, was killed in a battle against the Otomo clan and the Shoni clan in Chikuzen Province, a conflict over the succession arose within the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>生前、盛見は持世に家督と長門国を除く所領を、大内持盛に長門を継ぐように遺言していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his lifetime, Morimi left a will to take over the shoryo (territory) excluding reigns of the family and Nagato Province for Mochiyo, and Nagato Province for Mochimori OUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morimi had made a will leaving all territory except for Nagaoto Province to Mochiyo and leaving the position at the head of the family and Nagato Provice to Mochimori OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>It is obvious that Morimi was still alive when he made the will.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morimi had made a will leaving the position at the head of the family and all territory except for Nagato Province to Mochiyo and leaving Nagato Province to Mochimori OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幕命もあって持世は当初、これに従ったが、やがて国人衆の支持を背景にして持盛を滅ぼし、家督と大内氏の領土全てを相続するに至ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the order of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), he followed the will at first, but he defeated Mochimori over time with the support from Kokujin-shu (local samurais) and inherited reigns of the family and all territories of the Ouchi clan eventually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyo initially respected the contents of the will due to the orders from the bakufu, but soon deposed Mochimori with the support of the Kokujin-shu (local samurai) and took over the postion at the head of the family and all territories of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyo initially respected the contents of the will due to the orders from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), but soon deposed Mochimori with the support of the local samurai) and took over the position at the head of the family and all territories of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足し、スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後は少弐満貞、大友持直と戦ってこれに勝利して勢力を拡大。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he won the battle against Mitsusada SHONI and Mochinao OTOMO and grew his influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he won battles against Mitsusada SHONI and Mochinao OTOMO and extended his influence.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he won battles against Mitsusada SHONI and Mochinao OTOMO and cemented his influence.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>少弐氏を滅亡寸前までに追い込んだが、1440年には持世なりの寛大さがあったのか、幕府の将軍・足利義教に少弐氏との和睦を取り持ってもらうことで少弐氏を存続させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He almost defeated the Shoni clan, but he had generosity perhaps to save the Shoni clan by asking the shogun of the bakufu, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, to mediate reconciliation with the Shoni clan in 1440.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyo came close eliminating the the Shoni clan, but in 1440, he found it within himself to ask the shogun of the bakufu, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, to mediate a reconciliation which allowed the Shoni clan lineage to survive.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyo came close eliminating the Shoni clan, but in 1440, he found it within himself to ask the shogun of the bakufu, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, to mediate a reconciliation which allowed the Shoni clan lineage to survive.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>少弐氏と同盟関係にある対馬国の宗氏との関係悪化を恐れたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that he was afraid to worsen relations with the So family of Tsushima Province who had alliance with the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His motive may have been a fear of worsening relations with the So family of Tsushima Province who had an alliance with the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His motive may have been a fear of worsening relations with the So clan of Tsushima Province who had an alliance with the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1441年、赤松満祐が結城合戦の戦勝祝いにと祝宴を開いたとき、持世も義教に従って臨席していたが、このときの嘉吉の乱で重傷を負い、それがもとで7月28日に死去してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1441, when Mitsusuke AKAMATSU organized a feast celebrating the victory of the Yuki War, Mochiyo also attended it with Yoshinori, but he was gravely-injured during the Kakitsu War at this time and die on July 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1441, when Mitsusuke AKAMATSU organized a feast celebrating the victory in the Yuki War, Mochiyo attended with Yoshinori, but was gravely injured in the Kakitsu war which took place at this time and died of his wounds on July 28.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1441, when Mitsusuke AKAMATSU organized a feast celebrating the victory in the Yuki War, Mochiyo attended with Yoshinori, but was gravely injured in the Kakitsu War which took place at this time and died of his wounds on July 28.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>享年48。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was forty eight years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was forty eight years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was forty eight years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後を、養嗣子の大内教弘が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His adopted heir, Norihiro OUCHI., succeeded him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His adopted heir, Norihiro OUCHI., succeeded him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His adopted heir, Norihiro OUCHI., succeeded him.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>当主として有能なだけではなく、和歌にも優れた教養人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was not only capable as the family head, but also an educated person excellent in waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyo was not only a capable head of the family head, but also an educated man with a talent for waka (traditional Japanese poetry of thirty-one syllables).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyo was not only a capable head of the family head, but also an educated man with a talent for waka (traditional Japanese poetry of thirty-one syllables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>『新続古今和歌集』には多くの作品が遺されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of his works remained on Shinshoku Kokin Wakashu (NEW Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry Continued)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of his works can be found in Shinshoku Kokin Wakashu (NEW Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry Continued)</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of his works can be found in &quot;Shinshoku Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry Continued).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 トホホ川(id:50502), ５１６(id:45205), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>