<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>尋尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinson</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinson</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinson</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>尋尊（じんそん、永享2年8月7日 (旧暦)（1430年8月25日）- 永正5年5月2日 (旧暦)（1508年5月31日））は、室町時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)にかけての奈良興福寺の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinson (August 25, 1430-May 31, 1508) was a Japanese priest of Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara in the mid Muromachi Period to the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinson (August 25, 1430-May 31, 1508) was a Japanese priest of Nara Kofuku-ji Temple lived over the middle of the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>「戦国時代 (日本)」と「奈良興福寺」を単語調査に従い訂正し，「室町時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)にかけての」の表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinson (August 25, 1430-May 31, 1508) was a Japanese priest of Nara Kofuku-ji Temple lived over the middle of the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は一条兼良。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kaneyoshi (or Kanera) ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kaneyoshi (also called Kanera) ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>Kaneraが別読みであることを明確にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kaneyoshi (also called Kanera) ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は中御門宣俊の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Nobutoshi NAKANOMIKADO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Nobutoshi NAKANOMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>娘の数が明確でないので冠詞をtheに換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Nobutoshi NAKANOMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>興福寺180世別当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 180th betto (administrator) of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 180th Kofuku-ji betto (the head priest of Kofuku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>別当の説明を単語調査に従い訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 180th Kofuku-ji betto (the head priest of Kofuku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大乗院第20代門跡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the twentieth monzeki (successor) of Daijo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 20th monzeki (the priest in charge of a temple where the doctrines of the founder of the sect have been handed down) of Daijo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>門跡の説明を単語調査に従い訂正しました。20th を数字に換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 20th monzeki (the priest in charge of a temple where the doctrines of the founder of the sect have been handed down) of Daijo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1438年（永享10年）室町幕府から罪を得て去った経覚のあとを受けて大乗院に入り、以後70年間在院した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinson joined Daijo-in Temple in 1438 to replace priest Kyogaku who had been incriminated by the Muromachi shogunate and forced to leave the temple, and thereafter he served there for 70 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering Daijo-in Temple in 1438 to replace a priest Kyogaku who left the temple after being punished by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Jinson served following 70 years in the temple.</e>
<cmt>「大乗院に入り」の動詞を換え，多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering Daijo-in Temple in 1438 to replace a priest Kyogaku who left the temple after being punished by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Jinson served following 70 years in the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1440年（永享12年）に得度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1440, he was officially allowed to enter the priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the priesthood in 1440.</e>
<cmt>「（得度を）許可される」と訳す必要はないのではと考え，「得度した」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the priesthood in 1440.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>維摩会研学竪義（ゆいまえけんがくりゅうぎ）を遂げ、少僧都・大僧都を経て僧正に任じられ、1456年（康正2年）興福寺別当に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed Kengaku Ryugi (oral examination for learned priests) at Yuimae (a Buddhist service for the Yuima Sutra held at Kofuku-ji Temple) and was appointed as Shosozu (junior secondary prelate), Daisozu (upper Buddhist priest in the second highest position) and then sojo (priest ranked in the highest managerial position), and took the position of betto at Kofuku-ji Temple in 1456.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After passing the Kengaku Ryugi (oral examination for learned priests) at Yuimae (a Buddhist service for the Yuima Sutra held at Kofuku-ji Temple), he was appointed to Shosozu (junior secondary prelate), Daisozu (upper Buddhist priest in the second highest position) and Sojo (priest ranked in the highest managerial position) in that order, and then assumed the post of Kofuku-ji betto in 1456.</e>
<cmt>多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After passing the Kengaku Ryugi (oral examination for learned priests) at Yuimae (a Buddhist service for the Yuima Sutra held at Kofuku-ji Temple), he was appointed to Shosozu (junior secondary prelate), Daisozu (upper Buddhist priest in the second highest position) and Sojo (priest ranked in the highest managerial position) in that order, and then assumed the post of Kofuku-ji betto in 1456.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>のち法務に任じられ、奈良長谷寺・橘寺・薬師寺の別当をも兼任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was appointed as homu (director of temple affairs) and concurrently served as betto of Hase-dera Temple, Tachibana-dera Temple and Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was appointed as homu (director of temple affairs) and concurrently served as betto of Hase-dera Temple, Tachibana-dera Temple and Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was appointed as homu (director of temple affairs) and concurrently served as betto of Hase-dera Temple, Tachibana-dera Temple and Yakushi-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>応仁の乱（1467年－1477年）では父兼良の日記を兵火から守った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of the Onin War (1467-1477), he protected diaries of his father, Kaneyoshi, from the fires of war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Onin War (1467-1477) broke out, he protected diaries of his father, Kaneyoshi, from fires caused by the war.</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペースを訂正，少々書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Onin War (1467-1477) broke out, he protected diaries of his father, Kaneyoshi, from fires caused by the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また見聞したことを多くの記録に書き記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinson recorded many of what he saw and heard, and his diaries &quot;Jinson Daisojo Ki&quot; (Diaries of Daisojo Jinson) are now used as materials indispensable to learn not only about Kofuku-ji Temple but also about the time he lived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinson wrote his experiences down in many documents.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文と訳文の意味がやや異なるので書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinson wrote his experiences down in many documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その日記「尋尊大僧正記」は興福寺に関することだけではなく、この時代を知る上での必須の資料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the diary &apos;Jinson Daisojo Ki&apos; (Diary of Daisojo Jinson) is an indispensable material to understand not only Kofuku-ji Temple but also the period he lived.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。原文と訳文の意味がやや異なると考え書き直しました。「」なので&apos;&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the diary &apos;Jinson Daisojo Ki&apos; (Diary of Daisojo Jinson) is an indispensable material to understand not only Kofuku-ji Temple but also the period he lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1931年（昭和6年）「大乗院寺社雑事記」として刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1931, his diaries were published as &quot;Daijoin jisha zojiki&quot; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijoin Temple and Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diary was published in 1931 by being titled &apos;Daijoin jisha zojiki&apos; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo-in Temple and Shrine).</e>
<cmt>多少わかりづらいので言葉を補いました。「」なので&apos;&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diary was published in 1931 by being titled &apos;Daijoin jisha zojiki&apos; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo-in Temple and Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Nevylax(id:38464), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>