<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原実兼 (太皇太后宮亮)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanekane (Taikodaigogu no suke (assistant master of the grand empress dowager&apos;s household))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanekane, Taikodaigogu no suke (Assistant Master of the Grand Empress Dowager&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanekane, Taikodaigogu no suke (Assistant Master of the Grand Empress Dowager&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 実兼（ふじわら の さねかね、生年不詳 - 大治 (日本)5年9月9日 (旧暦)（1130年10月12日））は、平安時代末期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanekane (date of birth unknown - October 12, 1130) was a nobleman in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanekane (date of birth unknown - October 12, 1130) was a nobleman who lived at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanekane (year of birth unknown - October 19, 1130) was a nobleman who lived at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>(year of birth unknown 用語統一リストより訂正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は藤原公実、母は散位藤原永業女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Kinzane and his mother was the daughter of 藤原永業, Sani (courtier without post)</e>
<cmt>「藤原永業」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Kinzane and his mother was the daughter of 藤原永業, Sani (courtier without post)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Kinzane and his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Naganari, Sani (courtier without post)</e>
<cmt>藤原永業→FUJIWARA no Naganari としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原璋子の異母兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a half brother of FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a half brother of FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a half brother of FUJIWARA no Shoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>妻は藤原知綱女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Tomotsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Tomotsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Tomotsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正四位・刑部省。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and he served Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and he served at the Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and he served at the Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>太皇太后宮亮のほか天仁元年（1108年）から永久 (元号)3年（1115年）まで少納言、ついで備後国国司に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as being Taikodaigogu no suke, he was assigned to shonagon (Lesser counselor) from 1108 to 1115, and Kokushi of Bingo Province after that.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well as being Taikodaigogu no suke, he was made Shonagon (Lesser Counselor) from 1108 to 1115, and Kokushi of Bingo Province after that.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well as being Taikodaigogu no suke, he was made Shonagon (lesser councilor of state) from 1108 to 1115, and Kokushi of Bingo Province after that.</e>
<cmt>Lesser Counselor→lesser councilor of state</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その任期終了後出家したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is reported that he became a priest when he finished his term.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is reported that he became a priest when he finished his term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is reported that he became a priest when he finished his term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>待賢門院の兄として他の兄弟が出世する中、公卿に昇進できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While his brothers advanced in the world as elder brothers of Taikenmonin, he could not be promoted to Kugyo (the top court officials).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While his brothers advanced in the world as elder brothers of Taikenmonin, he could not get promoted to the level of Kugyo (top court officials).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While his brothers advanced in the world as elder brothers of Taikenmonin, he could not get promoted to the level of Kugyo (top court officials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>角田文衛の説では、待賢門院の女房であった実兼の娘に鳥羽天皇が密通し、それを知った白河法皇が怒って女房を追放したことが原因ではないか、としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Bunei TSUNODA, it was because Emperor Toba committed adultery with Sanekane&apos;s daughter, who was the wife of Taikenmonin, and the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa became angry when he came to know it and banished the wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Bunei TSUNODA, this was because Emperor Toba committed adultery with Sanekane&apos;s daughter, who was the wife of Taikenmonin, and the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa became angry when he came to know it and banished the wife.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Bunei TSUNODA, this was because Emperor Toba committed adultery with Sanekane&apos;s daughter, who was the wife of Taikenmonin, and the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa became angry when he came to know it and banished the wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>