<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>重森三玲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mirei SHIGEMORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mirei SHIGEMORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mirei SHIGEMORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>重森 三玲 (しげもり みれい、1896年（明治29年） - 1975年（昭和50年）、本名は重森計夫) は昭和期の日本の庭師・日本庭園史の研究家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mirei SHIGEMORI (1896-1975) (the real name was Kazuo SHIGEMORI) was the Japanese gardener of Showa Period and a researcher of the history of Japanese gardens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mirei SHIGEMORI (1896-1975) (his real name was Kazuo SHIGEMORI) was aJapanese gardener during the Showa Period and a researcher into the history of Japanese gardens.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mirei SHIGEMORI (1896-1975) (his real name was Kazuo SHIGEMORI) was aJapanese gardener during the Showa period and a researcher into the history of Japanese gardens.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴・人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career and Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career and Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography and Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>岡山県上房郡賀陽町吉川（現・加賀郡吉備中央町吉川）の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Yoshikawa, Kayo town, Jobo District, Okayama Prefecture. (It is currently Yoshikawa, Kibi Chuo-cho, Kaga District).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Yoshikawa, Kayo town, Jobo District, Okayama Prefecture. (It is currently Yoshikawa, Kibi Chuo-cho, Kaga District).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Yoshikawa, Kayo-cho, Jobo-gun, Okayama Prefecture (currently Yoshikawa, Kibi Chuo-cho, Kaga-gun).</e>
<cmt>It is、余分なピリオド削除、住所表記のため、town→cho、District→gunに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当地には豪渓(ごうけい)と呼ばれる水墨山水画の世界を思わせる渓谷地帯がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the area with canyons that seemed to resemble the world of Chinese-style landscape calligraphy painting known as &quot;Gokei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area with canyons resembled the world of Chinese-style landscape calligraphy painting known as &quot;Gokei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area with canyons resembled the world of Chinese-style landscape calligraphy painting known as &quot;Gokei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本美術学校で日本画を学び、いけばなと茶道を習い稽古に励む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Japanese Art in Nippon Art College and took ikebana (Japanese art of Flower Arrangement) and Sado (tea ceremony) lessons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Japanese Art in Nippon Art College and took ikebana (Japanese art of Flower Arrangement) and Sado (tea ceremony) lessons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Japanese Art in Nippon Art College and took ikebana (Japanese art of Flower Arrangement) and sado (tea ceremony) lessons.</e>
<cmt>ikebanaにあわせ、Sado→sadoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本美術学校卒業後には東洋大学文学部に学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he graduated from Nippon Art College, he went to study at the Faculty of Literature in Toyo University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he graduated from Nippon Art College, he went to study at the Faculty of Literature in Toyo University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he graduated from Nippon Art College, he went to study at the Faculty of Literature in Toyo University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>大正6年 (1917年) に画家の道を志し上京するが、全国から集まる才能に意気消沈する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Tokyo in 1917 to lead the path of an artist, but became dismayed from seeing many talented artists from across Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Tokyo in 1917 to life as an artist, but became dismayed at seeing many talented artists from across Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Tokyo in 1917 to life as an artist, but became dismayed at seeing many talented artists from across Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>昭和4年 (1929年)京都へ移り住むと、翌年には勅使河原蒼風らと「新興いけばな宣言」を発表、いけばなの革新を世に提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he moved to Kyoto in 1929, he presented &quot;New Ikebana Declaration&quot; with Sofu TESHIGAHARA and advocated the revolution of ikebana to the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he moved to Kyoto in 1929, he presented &quot;New Ikebana Declaration&quot; with Sofu TESHIGAHARA and advocated the revolution of ikebana to the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he moved to Kyoto in 1929, he presented &apos;New Ikebana Declaration&apos; with Sofu TESHIGAHARA and advocated the revolution of ikebana to the world.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後は日本庭園を独学で学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later learned about the Japanese gardens on his own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later learned about Japanese gardens on his own.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later learned about Japanese gardens on his own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1936年より全国の庭園を実測調査し、全国500箇所にさまざまな時代の名庭実測、古庭園の調査などにより、研究家として日本庭園史のさきがけとなっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1936, he surveyed gardens all over Japan, famous gardens of different periods in five hundred places around Japan, researched on ancient gardens, and became a pioneer as a researcher of history of Japanese gardens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1936, he surveyed gardens all over Japan, famous gardens of different periods in five hundred places around Japan, researched on ancient gardens, and became a pioneer as a researcher on the history of Japanese gardens.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1936, he surveyed gardens all over Japan, famous gardens of different periods in five hundred places around Japan, researched on ancient gardens, and became a pioneer as a researcher on the history of Japanese gardens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>昭和14年 (1939年) 『日本庭園史図鑑』26巻を上梓して庭園史研究の基礎を築き、また昭和51年 (1976年) には息子の重森完途と共に『日本庭園史大系』全33巻 (別巻2巻) を完成させるなど庭園史研究家としても多大な功績を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He published twenty-six volumes of &quot;Nihon Teienshi zukan&quot; in 1939, built the basic foundation of research of history of gardens, and completed the thirty-three volumes (two extra volumes) of &quot;Nihon Teienshi Taikei&quot; (A historical overview of Japanese Gardens) along with his son, Kanto SHIGEMORI, and made huge achievements as the researcher of history of gardens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He published twenty-six volumes of &quot;Nihon Teienshi zukan&quot; in 1939, and built the foundation of his research on the history of gardens, and completed the thirty-three volumes (two extra volumes) of &quot;Nihon Teienshi Taikei&quot; (A historical overview of Japanese Gardens) along with his son, Kanto SHIGEMORI, and made huge achievements as a researcher into the history of gardens.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He published twenty-six volumes of &quot;Nihon Teienshi Zukan&quot; (Illustrated guide to the history of Japanese gardens) in 1939, and built the foundation of his research on the history of gardens, and completed the thirty-three volumes (two extra volumes) of &quot;Nihon Teienshi Taikei&quot; (A historical overview of Japanese Gardens) along with his son, Kanto SHIGEMORI in 1976, and made huge achievements as a researcher into the history of gardens.</e>
<cmt>「1976年」を訳出、&quot;Nihon Teienshi Zukan&quot;とし、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>昭和24年 (1949年) には前衛いけばなの創作研究グループ「白東社」を主宰、後に前衛いけばな誌「いけばな藝術」を創刊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the leader for the research group for Zenei ikebana (forefront ikebana), &quot;Hakutosha,&quot; and later published the &quot;Ikebana Geijutsu&quot; (Fine Art of the art of Ikebana), which was the Zenei Ikebana magazine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the leader for the research group for Zenei ikebana (forefront ikebana), &quot;Hakutosha,&quot; and later published the &quot;Ikebana Geijutsu&quot; (Fine Art of the art of Ikebana), which was a Zenei Ikebana magazine.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1949, he became the leader for the research group for Zenei ikebana (forefront ikebana), &apos;Hakutosha,&apos; and later published the &apos;Ikebana Geijutsu&apos; (Fine Art of the art of Ikebana), which was a Zenei Ikebana magazine.</e>
<cmt>「1949年」を訳出、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>三玲が作庭した庭は、力強い石組みとモダンな苔の地割りで構成される枯山水庭園が特徴的であるとされ、代表作に、東福寺方丈庭園、光明院庭園、大徳寺山内瑞奉院庭園、松尾大社庭園などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gardens Mirei did landscape architecture on was the Karesansui Garden (dry landscape garden) with strong stone foundation and modern-style allotment of land by moss, and his representative works were the Garden of the Hojo (Hall of an Abbot) in Tofuku-ji Temple, gardens of Komyo-in Temple, Zuiho-in Temple within the mountain of Daitoku-ji Temple, and the garden of the Matsuo-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gardens Mirei performedlandscape architecture on was the Karesansui Garden (dry landscape garden) with strong stone foundation and modern-style allotment of land by moss, and his representative works include the Garden of the Hojo (Hall of an Abbot) in Tofuku-ji Temple, gardens of Komyo-in Temple, Zuiho-in Temple within the mountain of Daitoku-ji Temple, and the garden of the Matsuo-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gardens Mirei performedlandscape architecture on was the Karesansui Garden (dry landscape garden) with strong stone foundation and modern-style allotment of land by moss, and his representative works include the Garden of the Hojo (Hall of an Abbot) in Tofuku-ji Temple, the garden of Komyo-in Temple, the garden of Zuiho-in Temple within the grounds of Daitoku-ji Temple, and the garden of the Matsuo-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>「大徳寺山内」にあるのは「瑞奉院」だけであることを明確にするため、the garden of Komyo-in Temple, the garden of Zuiho-in Templeとし、within the mountain of Daitoku-ji Temple→within the grounds of Daitoku-ji Temple に修正 (参照: http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/sightdb/sight-raku/view_sight.php?InforKindCode=1&amp;ManageCode=1000131&amp;lang=en)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>代表作 (見学が可能なもの)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works (those that could be visited)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works (those that could be visited)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Representative Works (those that could be visited)</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>東福寺方丈庭園　1939年、京都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Garden of the Hojo in Tofuku-ji Temple built in 1939 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Garden of the Hojo in Tofuku-ji Temple built in 1939 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Garden of the Hojo in Tofuku-ji Temple built in 1939 in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>光明院波心庭　1939年、京都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashintei (Dry pond garden) of Komyo-in Temple built in 1939 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashintei (Dry pond garden) of Komyo-in Temple built in 1939 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashintei (Dry pond garden) of Komyo-in Temple built in 1939 in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>岸和田城八陣の庭　1953年、大阪府岸和田市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of the Hachijin no Niwa (Garden of Eight Battle Formations) of the Kishiwada Castle created in 1953 in Kishiwada city, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of the Hachijin no Niwa (Garden of Eight Battle Formations) of the Kishiwada Castle created in 1953 in Kishiwada city, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of the Hachijin no Niwa (Garden of Eight Battle Formations) of the Kishiwada-jo Castle created in 1953 in Kishiwada City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Kishiwada-jo Castleとし、cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>光明禅寺庭園　1957年、福岡県太宰府市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of Komyozen-ji Temple created in 1957 in Dazaifu city, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of Komyozen-ji Temple created in 1957 in Dazaifu city, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of Komyozen-ji Temple created in 1957 in Dazaifu City, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>以楽公園　1961年、大阪府枚方市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iraku Park created in 1961 in Hirakata city, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iraku Park created in 1961 in Hirakata city, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iraku Park created in 1961 in Hirakata City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>瑞峯院独座の庭　1961年、京都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dokuza no Niwa (Garden of Solitary Meditation) of Zuiho-in created in 1961 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dokuza no Niwa (Garden of Solitary Meditation) of Zuiho-in created in 1961 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dokuza no Niwa (Garden of Solitary Meditation) of Zuiho-in Temple created in 1961 in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Zuiho-in Templeとし、cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>志度寺庭園　1962年、香川県さぬき市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of Shido-ji Temple created in 1962 in Sanuki city, Kagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of Shido-ji Temple created in 1962 in Sanuki city, Kagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of Shido-ji Temple created in 1962 in Sanuki City, Kagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>興禅寺看雲庭　1963年、長野県木曽福島町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanutei (Kanun no niwa) (Garden of Appreciating Clouds) created in 1963 in Fukushima, Kiso town, Kiso District, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanutei (Kanun no niwa) (Garden of Appreciating Clouds) created in 1963 in Fukushima, Kiso town, Kiso District, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanuntei (Kanun no niwa) (Garden of Appreciating Clouds) created in 1963 in Fukushima, Kiso-machi, Kiso-gun, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Kanutei→Kanuntei に修正、住所のためKiso town, Kiso District→Kiso-machi, Kiso-gunとしました。(※「木曽福島町」→合併後の「木曽郡木曽町福島」で訳されています)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>龍吟庵庭園　1964年、京都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of Ryogin-an Temple created in 1964 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of Ryogin-an Temple created in 1964 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of Ryogin-an Temple created in 1964 in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>財団法人北野美術館庭園　1965年、長野県長野市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of the Kitano Museum of Art created in 1965 in Nagano city, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of the Kitano Museum of Art created in 1965 in Nagano city, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of the Kitano Museum of Art created in 1965 in Nagano City, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="23">
<j>住吉神社住之江の庭　1966年、兵庫県篠山市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suminoe no Niwa (Suminoe Garden) of Sumiyoshi jinja Shrine created in 1966 in Sasayama city, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suminoe no Niwa (Suminoe Garden) of Sumiyoshi jinja Shrine created in 1966 in Sasayama city, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suminoe no Niwa (Suminoe Garden) of Sumiyoshi-jinja Shrine created in 1966 in Sasayama City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Sumiyoshi-jinja Shrineとし、cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>天籟庵茶室茶庭　1969年、岡山県吉備中央町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenraian tea garden created in 1969 in Kibichuo town, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenraian tea garden created in 1969 in Kibichuo town, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenraian tea garden created in 1969 in Kibi Chuo-cho, Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>前出の表記に合わせ、Kibi Chuo-choとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="25">
<j>友琳会館友琳庭　1969年、2002年岡山県吉備中央町に移築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yurintei (Yurin no Niwa) (Garden of Yurin) created in 1969 and transferred to Kibichuo town, Okayama Prefecture in 2002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yurintei (Yurin no Niwa) (Garden of Yurin) created in 1969 and transferred to Kibichuo town, Okayama Prefecture in 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yurintei (Yurin no Niwa) (Garden of Yurin) created in 1969 and transferred to Kibi Chuo-cho, Okayama Prefecture in 2002.</e>
<cmt>Kibi Chuo-choとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="26">
<j>漢陽寺庭園　1969年〜73年、山口県周南市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of Kanyo-ji Temple created between 1969 and 1973 in Shunan city, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of Kanyo-ji Temple created between 1969 and 1973 in Shunan city, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of Kanyo-ji Temple created between 1969 and 1973 in Shunan City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="27">
<j>1970年、京都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1970 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1970 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1970 in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="28">
<j>石像寺四神相応の庭　1972年、兵庫県丹波市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Shijin soo no niwa&quot; (Garden of the Proper Arrangement of the Four Guardian Gods) created in 1972 in Tanba city, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Shijin soo no niwa&quot; (Garden of the Proper Arrangement of the Four Guardian Gods) created in 1972 in Tanba city, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shijin soo no niwa (Garden of the Proper Arrangement of the Four Guardian Gods) created in 1972 in Tanba City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除、cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="29">
<j>豐國神社 (大阪市)秀石庭　1972年、大阪府大阪市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shuseki tei (Graceful Stone Garden) of Hokoku jinja Shrine (Osaka city) created in 1972 in Osaka city, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shuseki tei (Graceful Stone Garden) of Hokoku jinja Shrine (Osaka city) created in 1972 in Osaka city, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shuseki tei (Graceful Stone Garden) of Hokoku-jinja Shrine created in 1972 in Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Hokoku-jinja Shrineとし、重複するため(Osaka city)を削除、cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="30">
<j>福智院庭園　1973年、和歌山県高野町 (高野山)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of Fukuchi-in Temple in 1973 in Takano town (Mount Koya), Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of Fukuchi-in Temple in 1973 in Takano town (Mount Koya), Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of Fukuchi-in Temple in 1973 in Koya-cho (Mt. Koya), Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Takano town→Koya-choに修正 (参照: http://www.post.japanpost.jp/cgi-zip/zipcode.php?pref=30&amp;city=1303440)、およびMt. Koyaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="31">
<j>松尾大社庭園　1975年、京都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The garden of Matsuo-taisha Shrine created in 1975 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The garden of Matsuo-taisha Shrine created in 1975 in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The garden of Matsuo-taisha Shrine created in 1975 in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>主な著作 (ほぼ絶版)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His main written works (most are currently out of print)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His main written works (most are currently out of print)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Main Written Works (most are currently out of print)</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>『日本庭園史図鑑　全26巻』 1936〜39年、有光社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon teienshi zukan, Complete Twenty-six volumes&quot; published in 1936 to 1939 by Yukosha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon teienshi zukan, Complete Twenty-six volumes&quot; published in 1936 to 1939 by Yukosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Teienshi Zukan, Complete Twenty-six Volumes&quot; published in 1936 to 1939 by Yukosha.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の単語の頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>『庭の美』 1942年、第一藝文社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Niwa no bi&quot; (The beauty of gardens) published in 1942 by Daiichigeibun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Niwa no bi&quot; (The beauty of gardens) published in 1942 by Daiichigeibun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Niwa no Bi&quot; (The beauty of gardens) published in 1942 by Daiichigeibunsha.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の単語の頭文字を大文字に変更、Daiichigeibun→Daiichigeibunshaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>『枯山水』 1965年、河原書店刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Karesansui&quot; published in 1965 by Kawachi shoten (publisher).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Karesansui&quot; published in 1965 by Kawachi shoten (publisher).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Karesansui&quot; published in 1965 by Kawachi shoten (publisher).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>『庭 こころとかたち』 1968年、社会思想社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Niwa Kokoro to Katachi&quot; (Garden Heart and Shape) published in 1968 by Shakai Shinsosha (the mind of a society).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Niwa Kokoro to Katachi&quot; (Garden Heart and Shape) published in 1968 by Shakai Shinsosha (the mind of a society).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Niwa Kokoro to Katachi&quot; (Garden Heart and Shape) published in 1968 by Shakai Shinsosha (the mind of a society).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>『日本の名園』 1969年、誠文堂新光社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon no Meien&quot; (Famous Gardens of Japan) published in 1969 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon no Meien&quot; (Famous Gardens of Japan) published in 1969 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon no Meien&quot; (Famous Gardens of Japan) published in 1969 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>『実測図日本の名園』 1971年、誠文堂新光社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jissokuzu Nihon no Meien&quot; (The map of surveyed famous gardens of Japan) published in 1971 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jissokuzu Nihon no Meien&quot; (The map of surveyed famous gardens of Japan) published in 1971 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jissokuzu Nihon no Meien&quot; (The map of surveyed famous gardens of Japan) published in 1971 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>『茶室茶庭辞典』 1973年、誠文堂新光社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chashitsu Chatei Jiten&quot; (Dictionary of Tea Rooms and Tea Gardens) published in 1973 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chashitsu Chatei Jiten&quot; (Dictionary of Tea Rooms and Tea Gardens) published in 1973 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chashitsu Chatei Jiten&quot; (Dictionary of Tea Rooms and Tea Gardens) published in 1973 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>『日本庭園史大系　全35巻』 1971〜76年、社会思想社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon teienshi taikei Complete Thirty-five volumes&quot; published between 1971 to 1976 by Shakai Shisosha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon teienshi taikei Complete Thirty-five volumes&quot; published between 1971 to 1976 by Shakai Shisosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Teienshi Taikei Complete Thirty-five Volumes&quot; published between 1971 to 1976 by Shakai Shisosha.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の単語の頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>『日本の庭 (名園・作庭・素材編)』 1975年、毎日新聞社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon no niwa (Meien, Sakutei, Sozaihen)&quot; (Garden of Japan (Famous Gardens, Landscape Architecture, and Texture Volume) published in 1975 by Mainichi Shinbun (Mainichi Newspaper).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon no niwa (Meien, Sakutei, Sozaihen)&quot; (Garden of Japan (Famous Gardens, Landscape Architecture, and Texture Volume) published in 1975 by Mainichi Shinbun (Mainichi Newspaper).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon no Niwa (Meien, Sakutei, Sozaihen)&quot; (Garden of Japan (Famous Gardens, Landscape Architecture, and Texture Volume) published in 1975 by Mainichi Shinbunsha (The Mainichi Newspapers).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の単語の頭文字を大文字に変更、Mainichi Shinbunsha (The Mainichi Newspapers)としました。(参照: http://www.mainichi.co.jp/corporate/co-about.html)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="41">
<j>『重森三玲作品集　庭・神々へのアプローチ』 1975年、誠文堂新光社刊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Collection of Works of Mirei SHIGEMORI, the approach to gardens and gods&quot; published in 1975 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Collection of Works of Mirei SHIGEMORI, the approach to gardens and gods&quot; published in 1975 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Collection of Works of Mirei SHIGEMORI, the Approach to Gardens and Gods&quot; published in 1975 by Seibundo Shinkosha.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の単語の頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>「三玲」の名は、フランスの画家ジャン＝フランソワ・ミレーにちなみ本人が改名したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name, &quot;Mirei&quot; is what he named himself after deriving it from the French artist, Jean-Francois MILLET.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name, &quot;Mirei&quot; is what he named himself after deriving it from the French artist, Jean-Francois MILLET.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name, &apos;Mirei&apos; is what he named himself after deriving it from the French artist, Jean-Francois MILLET.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>白東社は重森邸で月一度の集まりを持ったが、そこには土門拳や小原豊雲、中川幸夫などの前衛いけばな作家も参加していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakutosha gathered in the residence of Shigemori once a month, and Zenei Ikebana artists from Ken DOMON, Houn OHARA, and Yukio NAKAGAWA also participated in the event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakutosha gathered in the residence of Shigemori once a month, and Zenei Ikebana artists from Ken DOMON, Houn OHARA, and Yukio NAKAGAWA also participated in the event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakutosha gathered in the residence of Shigemori once a month, and Zenei Ikebana artists from Ken DOMON, Houn OHARA, and Yukio NAKAGAWA also participated in the event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>重森邸を度々訪れたアメリカの彫刻家・イサム・ノグチとの交友など、庭園を通じた三玲の交友関係は広かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mirei had a large circle of friends through gardens for he was friends with Isamu NOGUCHI, the sculptor in the United States, who visited the residence of Mirei SHIGEMORI several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mirei had a large circle of friends that he established through his work with gardens, and made friends with Isamu NOGUCHI, the sculptor in the United States, who visited the residence of Mirei SHIGEMORI several times.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mirei had a large circle of friends that he established through his work with gardens, and made friends with Isamu NOGUCHI, the sculptor in the United States, who visited the residence of Mirei SHIGEMORI several times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 浩(id:70121), PANYNJ(id:38638), Art Keyword(id:142131), Reggaeman(id:6214), パピヨン星人(id:131851), Charenji(id:7908), Gribeco(id:176878), D.h(id:79056), Im224(id:57113), Mishika(id:276), Petty(id:43013), A192837465a(id:160310), Jugger90(id:17088), Kouchiumi(id:19253), R28Bot(id:177951), Knua(id:66861), NDR(id:5500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>