<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原千古</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Chifuru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Chifuru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Chifuru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 千古（ふじわら の ちふる/ちこ、生没年不詳）は、平安時代の右大臣藤原実資の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Chifuru (also Chiko, years of birth and death unknown) was a daughter of Udaijin (Minister of Right) FUJIWARA no Sanesuke in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Chifuru (also known as Chiko, years of birth and death unknown) was a daughter of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) FUJIWARA no Sanesuke from the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Chifuru (also known as Chiko, years of birth and death unknown) was a daughter of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) FUJIWARA no Sanesuke from the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母親は不明であるが、義弟である源頼定の乳母の娘と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother is no known, but it is said that it was daughter of menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) of his younger half-brother, MINAMOTO no Yorisada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is not known who her mother was, it is said that she was the daughter of the wet-nurse of her younger half-brother, MINAMOTO no Yorisada.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is not known who her mother was, it is said that she was the daughter of the wet-nurse of her younger half-brother, MINAMOTO no Yorisada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>生年は不詳であるが、万寿元年12月13日 (旧暦)（1025年1月15日）に当時の貴族女性の成人の儀式に相当する着裳が行われており、当時の着裳が14歳前後数年のうちに行われていたことから、寛弘8年（1011年）頃の出生と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her year of birth is not known for sure, but since chakumo, a ceremony among female nobilities at that time corresponding to Coming of Age ceremony, was held on January 21, 1025, and chakumo at that time was held in between several years before or after the age of 14, it is estimated that she was born around 1011.</e>
<cmt>暦変換ツールでは１月２１日となりました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her year of birth is not known for sure, but since her chakumo, or Coming of Age ceremony, which took place around the age of 14, was held on January 21, 1025, and chakumo at that time was held in between several, it is estimated that she was born around 1011.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her year of birth is not known for sure, but since her chakumo, or Coming of Age ceremony for female nobilities which took place around the age of 14 at that time, was held on January 21, 1025, it is estimated that she was born around 1011.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>父親の実資は天徳 (日本)元年（957年）生まれであることから、50歳過ぎにして漸く出来た娘 ということになり、非常にこれを溺愛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father Sanesuke was born in 957, meaning that she was long waited daughter born after he became to be more than 50 year old, and he doted her very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father, Sanesuke, was born in 957, meaning he was over 50 when his long awaited daughter was born, and as such he doted on her enormously.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father, Sanesuke, was born in 957, meaning he was over 50 when his long awaited daughter was born, and as such he doted on her enormously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『大鏡』によれば、彼女に「かぐや姫」と愛称を付けたされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Okagami,&quot; he is said to have put the nickname &apos;Kaguya Hime&apos; (Lady Kaguya) on her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Okagami,&quot; he is said to have given her the nickname &apos;Kaguya Hime&apos; (Lady Kaguya).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror), he is said to have given her the nickname &apos;Kaguya Hime&apos; (Lady Kaguya).</e>
<cmt>大鏡　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、寛仁3年12月9日 (旧暦)（1020年1月6日）には処分状を作成して、小野宮家に伝わる荘園などの財産の殆どを千古に継承させ、「道俗子等一切不可口入」と宣言して、養嗣子の藤原資平（甥）や僧侶にしていた庶子良円 (天台宗)には殆ど財産を残さなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also on January 12, 1020, he made papers for inheritance of his properties and made Chifuru inherit most of the properties handed down in Ononomiya family, such as shoen (manor in medieval Japan) and so on, and proclaimed that &apos;no child, whether he is a priest or a common person, can put a word in this,&apos; leaving almost no properties for his adopted heir FUJIWARA no Sukehira (nephew), and his child born out of wedlock, Ryoen (Tendai sect), who was made to be a priest.</e>
<cmt>暦変換ツールでは１月１２日となりました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, on January 12, 1020, he drew up a will, leaving almost all his property, including the manor that had been passed down in the Ononomiya family, to Chifuru and proclaimed that &apos;no child, whether he is a priest or a common person, can change this&apos;, leaving almost nothing to his adopted heir and nephew, FUJIWARA no Sukehira, or his illegitimate son, Ryoen, a monk of the buddhist Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, on January 12, 1020, he drew up a will, leaving almost all his property, including the manor that had been passed down in the Ononomiya family, to Chifuru and proclaimed that &apos;no child, whether he is a priest or a common person, can change this,&apos; leaving almost nothing to his adopted heir and nephew, FUJIWARA no Sukehira, or his illegitimate son, Ryoen, a priest of the Buddhist Tendai sect.</e>
<cmt>Buddhist と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>実資は千古を天皇の妃にすることを望んだが、表面上は実資に敬意を払いつつもその政治力の拡大を恐れる藤原道長・藤原頼通父子の前に入内を阻まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke wished Chifuru to become wife of the Emperor, but FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, father and son, who were paying respect to Sanesuke on the surface but fearing Sanesuke&apos;s political power to be expanded, blocked the judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) of Chifuru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke hoped Chifuru would become the Emperor&apos;s wife, but FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his son, Yorimichi, while outwardly respectful to Sanesuke, feared an increase in Sanesuke&apos;s political power and so blocked Chifuru&apos;s entry into court.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke hoped Chifuru would become the Emperor&apos;s wife, but FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his son, Yorimichi, while outwardly respectful to Sanesuke, feared an increase in Sanesuke&apos;s political power and so blocked Chifuru&apos;s entry into court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、実資は正妻を亡くしていた道長の子・藤原長家の後妻にしようと図り、道長の了承を得るが長家がこれを拒絶したため、縁談は破談となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Sanesuke made effort to make Chifuru as second wife of FUJIWARA no Nagaie, Michinaga&apos;s son, who had lost his wife, and earned Michinaga&apos;s acceptance, but this marriage offer was broke off because Nagaie refused it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Sanesuke tried to have Michinaga&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Nagaie, whose wife had died, take Chifuru as his second wife and although Michinaga accepted, the engagement was broken off because Nagaie was against it.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Sanesuke tried to have Michinaga&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Nagaie, whose wife had died, take Chifuru as his second wife and although Michinaga accepted, the engagement was broken off because Nagaie was against it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、道長の孫である藤原兼頼（藤原頼宗の子）の妻になったと伝えられている（『栄花物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Chifuru is said to have become as wife of FUJIWARA no Kaneyori (FUJIWARA no Yorimune&apos;s son), who was a grandson of Michinaga (&quot;Eiga monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, according to the &quot;Eiga monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes), Chifuru is said to have married FUJIWARA no Kaneyori, FUJIWARA no Yorimune&apos;s son and a grandson of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, according to the &quot;Eiga monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes), Chifuru is said to have married FUJIWARA no Kaneyori, FUJIWARA no Yorimune&apos;s son and a grandson of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、兼頼との間に小野宮尼公を儲けたが、長暦2年（1038年）頃に父・実資よりも先に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, with Kaneyori, she gave birth to Niko ONONOMIYA, but died before her father Sanesuke did in around 1038.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to Kaneyori&apos;s child, Niko ONONOMIYA, but died before her father Sanesuke in around 1038.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gave birth to Kaneyori&apos;s child, ONONOMIYA no Niko, but died before her father Sanesuke in around 1038.</e>
<cmt>小野宮尼公→ONONOMIYA no Niko　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>結果的には、道長ら九条流の最大の競争相手であった小野宮流の財産の殆どが九条流（正確には道長の御堂流）に入ることとなり、経済的基盤を失った小野宮流は院政期には没落して事実上消滅することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, most of the properties of Ononomiya line, who were the biggest competitor of Michinaga and other&apos;s Kujo line, were made to be inherited into Kujo line (Michinaga&apos;s Mido line, to be precise), and Ononomiya line, losing their economical basis, were ruined by the time of Insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor), and virtually disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, most of the property of the Ononomiya line, which was the biggest competitor to Michinaga&apos;s Kujo line, passed to the Kujo line (or to be precise, Michinaga&apos;s Mido line), and the Ononomiya line, having lost their financial foundation, fell into ruin and had almost disappeared by the period of cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, most of the property of the Ononomiya line, which was the biggest competitor to Michinaga&apos;s Kujo line, passed to the Kujo line (or to be precise, Michinaga&apos;s Mido line), and the Ononomiya line, having lost their financial foundation, fell into ruin and had almost disappeared by the period of cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>