<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>村井貞勝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakatsu MURAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu MURAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu MURAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>村井 貞勝（むらい さだかつ）は、織田政権下の京都所司代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakatsu MURAI was the Kyoto shoshidai (the Bakufu-appointed governor of Kyoto) under the government of Oda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu MURAI was the Kyoto shoshidai (the Bakufu-appointed governor of Kyoto) under the government of Oda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu MURAI was the Kyoto Shoshidai (the Kyoto deputy) under the Oda administration.</e>
<cmt>織田政権→Oda administration としました。京都所司代→Kyoto Shoshidai (the Kyoto deputy) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仮名 (通称)は吉兵衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His assumed name (alias) was Kichibe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His assumed name (alias) was Kichibe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His assumed name (alias) was Kichibei.</e>
<cmt>Kichibei としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>出家して春長軒と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gained go (byname) of Shunchoken after shukke (become a Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gained the go (byname) of Shunchoken after shukke (becoming a Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gained the go (byname) of Shunchoken after becoming a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt>shukke を削除し、英語のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は民部省、長門国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Kani (official rank) was Minbu-no-sho (Ministry of Popular Affairs) of Nagato-no-kuni (Nagato Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Kani (official rank) was Minbu-no-sho (Ministry of Popular Affairs) of Nagato-no-kuni (Nagato Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs) of Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Birth Place</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Birth Place</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His birth place</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>太閤記に拠れば、出身は近江国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Taiko ki,&quot; he originated from Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Taiko ki,&quot; Sadakatsu originated from Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province).</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Taikoki (Chronicle of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), Sadakatsu originated from Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>太閤記の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>行政手腕に長けていたため、織田信長から厚い信任を受けて、早期より重用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he excelled in administration, he was given a strong trust from Nobunaga ODA and was assigned with important positions from an early stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he excelled in administration, he won strong trust from Nobunaga ODA and was assigned important positions from an early stage.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he excelled in administration, he won strong trust from Nobunaga ODA and was assigned important positions from an early stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>弘治 (日本)2年（1556年）に織田信行が兄の信長に叛旗を翻した時には既に信長に仕えており、島田秀満（秀順）と共に土田御前の依頼を受けて、信勝や柴田勝家らとの和平交渉を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He already served Nobunaga when Nobuyuki ODA raised a flag of rebellion against his older brother Nobunaga in 1556, and tried to make a peace negotion between Nobukatsu and Katsuie SHIBATA together with Hidemitsu SHIMADA (Hideyori) from the orders of Dota-gozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu already served Nobunaga when Nobuyuki ODA raised a flag of rebellion against his older brother Nobunaga in 1556, and tried to make a peace negotiation between Nobukatsu and Katsuie SHIBATA together with Hidemitsu SHIMADA (Hideyori) from the orders of Dota-gozen.</e>
<cmt>name, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu already served Nobunaga when Nobuyuki ODA raised a flag of rebellion against his older brother Nobunaga in 1556, and tried to make a peace negotiation between Nobukatsu and Katsuie SHIBATA together with Hidemitsu (Hideyori) SHIMADA from the orders of Dota-gozen.</e>
<cmt>(Hideyori)の場所をHidemitsu の後に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>信長が足利義昭と共に上洛した際も同行し、明院良政、佐久間信盛、豊臣秀吉、丹羽長秀らの諸将と共に京都に残留し、諸政務に当たっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied Nobunaga when he performed Joraku (go to Kyoto from a district side) with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, and stayed in Kyoto with Ryosei MYOIN, Nobumori SAKUMA, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and Nagahide NIWA to manage the politics of warlords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accompanied Nobunaga when he performed Joraku (going to Kyoto from a district side) with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, and stayed in Kyoto with Ryosei MYOIN, Nobumori SAKUMA, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and Nagahide NIWA to manage the politics of warlords.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accompanied Nobunaga when he went to Kyoto with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, and stayed in Kyoto with Ryosei MYOIN, Nobumori SAKUMA, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and Nagahide NIWA to manage the politics of warlords.</e>
<cmt>jorakuを削除し、英語のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>上京まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Jokyo (go to the capital)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To Jokyo (going to the capital)</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To Jokyo (going to the capital)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>美濃三人衆降誘の際の人質受け取りや足利義昭の庇護、上洛後の二条城の造営、その他社寺との折衝など、織田氏の政務を担う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took care of the affairs of state of Oda clan, such as the acceptance of hostages during the fall of Mino Sannin-shu (three elite retainers of Mino), protection of weakened Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the construction of Nijo Castle, and made negotiations with temples and shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took care of the affairs of state of the Oda clan, such as the acceptance of hostages during the fall of Mino Sannin-shu (three elite retainers of Mino), protection of the weakened Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, and the construction of Nijo Castle, and conducted negotiations with temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>article. Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took care of the affairs of state of the Oda clan, such as the acceptance of hostages during the fall of Mino Sannin-shu (three elite retainers of Mino), protection of the weakened Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, and the construction of Nijo-jo Castle, and conducted negotiations with temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>Nijo-jo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>朝山日乗と共に京都御所の修築も担当している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also managed the repairment of Kyoto gosho (Imperial Palace) with Nichijo ASAYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also managed the repairment of Kyoto gosho (the Imperial Palace) with Nichijo ASAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also managed the repairment of Kyoto gosho (the Imperial Palace) with Nichijo ASAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>京都所司代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Shoshidai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Shoshidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Shoshidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>足利義昭を追放した信長が京都を完全支配下に置いた後、天正元年（1573年）7月、信長より京都所司代（天下所司代）に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to be the Kyoto Shoshidai (Tenka Shoshidai (the Bakufu-appointed governor of the country)) in July 1573 after Nobunaga outcasted Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and took a full control of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu was assigned to be the Kyoto Shoshidai (Tenka Shoshidai (the Bakufu-appointed governor of the country)) in July 1573 after Nobunaga outcasted Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and assumed full control of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu was assigned to be the Kyoto Shoshidai (Tenka Shoshidai (the Bakufu-appointed governor of the country)) in September 1573 after Nobunaga outcasted Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and assumed full control of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>松井友閑や武井夕庵、明智光秀、塙直政らの信長の行政官僚側近らと共に、京都の治安維持や朝廷・貴族・各寺社との交渉、御所の修復、使者の接待、信長の京都馬揃えの準備など、およそ“織田政権下における、京都に関する行政の全て”を任されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned along with Nobunaga&apos;s administrative officers and close associates, Yukan MATSUI, Sekian TAKEI, Mitsuhide AKECHI, and Naomasa BAN, with &quot;all the official affairs concerning Kyoto under the Oda&apos;s government,&quot;including the maintenance of the security of Kyoto, negotiation with the imperial court, lords, temples, and shrines, repairment of gosho (palace), entertaining of envoys, and preparation of Oda&apos;s Kyoto Umazoroe (military parade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned along with Nobunaga&apos;s administrative officers and close associates, Yukan MATSUI, Sekian TAKEI, Mitsuhide AKECHI, and Naomasa BAN, &quot;all the official affairs concerning Kyoto under the Oda government,&quot; including maintenance of the security of Kyoto; negotiation with the imperial court, lords, temples, and shrines; repairment of the gosho (palace); entertainment of envoys; and preparation of Oda&apos;s Kyoto Umazoroe (military parade).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned along with Nobunaga&apos;s administrative officers and close associates, Yukan MATSUI, Sekian TAKEI, Mitsuhide AKECHI, and Naomasa BAN, &quot;all the official affairs concerning Kyoto under the Oda administration,&quot; including maintenance of the security of Kyoto; negotiation with the Imperial Court, lords, temples, and shrines; repairment of the gosho (palace); entertainment of envoys; and preparation of Oda&apos;s Kyoto Umazoroe (military parade).</e>
<cmt>織田政権→Oda administration としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>天正3年（1575年）、京都の町人に御所の築地塀の修復を命じた貞勝は、人数をいくつかの班に分けて作業を競わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakatsu ordered the repairment of tsuijibei (mud-filled fence or moat) of gosho to civilians in 1575 and divided them into groups to compete the repairment progress with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu ordered civilians to complete the repairment of tsuijibei (mud-filled fence or moat) of gosho in 1575, and divided them into groups to compete with each other in the progress of repairment.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu ordered civilians to complete the repairment of tsuijibei (mud-filled fence or moat) of gosho in 1575, and divided them into groups to compete with each other in the progress of repairment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>築地塀の上では町人たちの歌や踊りが披露され、見物客が殺到し、周辺は大変な賑わいを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were singing and dancing performances of civilians above tsujibei, which created a huge crowd in the surrounding area as many on-lookers came.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were singing and dancing performances of civilians above tsujibei, which created a huge crowd in the surrounding area as many on-lookers came.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were singing and dancing performances of civilians above tsujibei, which created a huge crowd in the surrounding area as many on-lookers came.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>あまりの賑わいに正親町天皇や貴族らも見物に訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there was so much crowd, Emperor Ogimachi and lords also came to watch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attracted by such a large crowd, Emperor Ogimachi and lords also came to watch.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attracted by such a large crowd, Emperor Ogimachi and nobles also came to watch.</e>
<cmt>貴族→nobles　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その賑わいの中で競い合わせて進めた修復工事は、瞬く間に完成したという（信長公記）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The repairment made with competition among that crowd supposedly finished very quickly (&quot;Shincho Kouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With competition among the crowd, the repairment supposedly finished very quickly (&quot;Shincho Kouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With competition among the crowd, the repairment supposedly finished very quickly (according to &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (Biography of Nobunaga ODA)).</e>
<cmt>信長公記　を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>同年7月、信長に官位昇進の勅諚が出されるが、信長はこれを固辞、代わりに家臣団への叙任を願い出て勅許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July of same year, there was an imperial decree given to Nobunaga to promote his official rank, but he firmly declined to ask for Jonin (investiture) of his group of servants, which was accepted by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July of that same year, an imperial decree was given to promote Nobunag in official rank, but he firmly declined to ask for Jonin (investiture) of his group of servants, which was accepted by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August of that same year, an imperial decree was given to promote Nobunaga in official rank, but he firmly declined, and instead, asked for investiture of his group of servants, which was accepted by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。Declined, and instead としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>貞勝は長門国に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakatsu went through Jonin for Nagato-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu went through Jonin for Nagato-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu was appointed to Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>apppinted to としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>天正9年（1581年）、出家して村井春長軒と号し、家督を子の村井貞成に譲っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went through shukke in 1581 and gained Go of Shunchoken MURAI and passed his family estate to his son, Sadanari MURAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went through shukke in 1581, gaining the Go of Shunchoken MURAI and passing his family estate to his son, Sadanari MURAI.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered priesthood in 1581, gaining the Buddhist name of Shunchoken MURAI and passing his family estate to his son, Sadanari MURAI.</e>
<cmt>出家、号する、など表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ルイス・フロイスは貞勝を「京都の総督」と呼び、「尊敬できる異教徒の老人であり、甚だ権勢あり」と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Luis Frois called Sadanari MURAI as &quot;the governor general of Kyoto&quot; and praised him as &quot;the respectable old man of paganism and holding the much reins of power.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Luis Frois called Sadanari MURAI &quot;the governor general of Kyoto&quot; and praised him as &quot;the respectable old man of paganism and holding many of the reins of power.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Luis Frois called Sadanari MURAI &apos;the governor general of Kyoto&apos; and praised him as &apos;the respectable old man of paganism and holding many of the reins of power.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His death</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>天正10年（1582年）の本能寺の変では本能寺向かいの自邸にいたが、信長の嫡男・織田信忠の宿所の妙覚寺に駆け込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was at his own residence, on the opposite side of Honnoji Temple during Honnoji no Hen (Conspiracy of Honno-ji Temple) in 1582, but he rushed to Myokaku-ji Temple, the resident of Nobunaga&apos;s legal son, Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">during Honnoji no Hen (Conspiracy of Honno-ji Temple) in 1582, Sadakatsu was at his own residence, on the opposite side of Honnoji Temple, but he rushed to Myokaku-ji Temple, the residence of Nobunaga&apos;s legal son, Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Honnoji Incident in 1582, Sadakatsu was at his own residence, on the opposite side of Honno-ji Temple, but he rushed to Myokaku-ji Temple, the residence of Nobunaga&apos;s legal son, Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt>Honnoji Incident としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>信忠に二条城への移動を提言し、同じく駆けつけた他の織田家臣らとともに、二条新御所に立て籠もって明智軍に抗戦したが、信忠とともに討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made the proposal to Nobutada to move to Nijo Castle, confined himself within Nijo shingosho with other servants of Oda to resist army of Akechi, but was killed in battle along with Nobutada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made a proposal to Nobutada to move to Nijo Castle, and confined himself within Nijo shingosho with other servants of Oda to resist the army of Akechi, but was killed in battle along with Nobutada.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made a proposal to Nobutada to move to Nijo-jo Castle, and confined himself within Nijo shingosho (Nijo New Imperial Palace) with other servants of Oda to resist the army of Akechi, but was killed in battle along with Nobutada.</e>
<cmt>二条新御所　を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、子の貞成・村井清次も同所で討死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons, Sadanari and Seiji MURAI, were also killed in battle at the same castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons, Sadanari and Seiji MURAI, were also killed in battle at the same castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons, Sadanari and Seiji MURAI, were also killed in battle at the same castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>京都市の大雲院には、“頭を丸めた老人”という体の貞勝の肖像が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a statue of Sadakatsu shaped like &quot;the old man of tonsured head&quot;preserved in Daiun-in, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Daiun-in, Kyoto City, there is a preserved statue of Sadakatsu shaped like &quot;the old man of tonsured head.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Daiun-in Temple, Kyoto City, there is a preserved statue of Sadakatsu shaped like &quot;the old man of tonsured head.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Templeを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>娘は佐々成政、前田玄以、福島高晴に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughters married to Narimasa SASA, Geni MAEDA, and Takaharu FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughters married Narimasa SASA, Geni MAEDA, and Takaharu FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughters married Narimasa SASA, Geni MAEDA, and Takaharu FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Su-no-G(id:52744), 寒(id:53831), Maakun(id:16735), ５１６(id:45205), KASAGI(id:24405), Kouko0515(id:100370), Jmho(id:10472), 相模守信久(id:189309), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>