<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中山忠光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamitsu NAKAYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamitsu NAKAYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamitsu NAKAYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中山 忠光（なかやま ただみつ、弘化2年4月13日 (旧暦)（1845年5月18日）- 元治元年11月15日 (旧暦)（1864年12月13日））は、江戸時代末期の公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamitsu NAKAYAMA (1845 May 18 - 1864 December 13) is a court noble from the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamitsu NAKAYAMA (1845 May 18 - December 13, 1864) is a court noble in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>年と月の順序を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamitsu NAKAYAMA (1845 May 18 - December 13, 1864) is a court noble in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>権大納言中山忠能の七男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seventh son of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor), Tadayasu NAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventh son of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor), Tadayasu NAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventh son of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor), Tadayasu NAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は平戸藩主・松浦清の娘中山愛子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is Aiko NAKAYAMA, the daughter of Hirado Domain, Kiyoshi MATSURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother is Aiko NAKAYAMA, the daughter of Hirado Domain, Kiyoshi MATSUURA.</e>
<cmt>松浦のスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother is Aiko NAKAYAMA, the daughter of Hirado Domain, Kiyoshi MATSUURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明治天皇の生母中山慶子は同母姉にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The real mother of Emperor Meiji, Yoshiko NAKAYAMA is the older sister of his mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The real mother of the Emperor Meiji, Yoshiko NAKAYAMA, is the older sister of his mother.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The real mother of the Emperor Meiji, Yoshiko NAKAYAMA, is the older sister of his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正室は平戸藩主・松浦熈（祖父・松浦清の息子）と正室・筆子（島津重豪の娘）の娘富子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lawful wife is the daughter Tomiko, of Kiyoshi MATSURA, Hirado Domain, and his lawful wife Fudeko (daughter of Shigehide SHIMAZU).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lawful wife is the daughter Tomiko, of Kiyoshi MATSUURA, Hirado Domain, and his lawful wife Fudeko (daughter of Shigehide SHIMAZU).</e>
<cmt>松浦のスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lawful wife is the daughter Tomiko, of Kiyoshi MATSUURA, Hirado Domain, and his lawful wife Fudeko (daughter of Shigehide SHIMAZU).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>富子との間には子女はいないが、長州藩の支藩である長府藩潜伏中、現地女性の恩地トミを妾とし、仲子（南加、嵯峨公勝夫人）をもうけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no daughter between him and Tomiko, but while he was hiding in Chofu which was the branch domain of the Choshu clan, he meets his concubine, Tomi ONCHI, the local female, and have a daughter Nakako (Nanka, Kinto SAGA consort of the emperor).</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no daughter between him and Tomiko, but while he was hiding in Chofu which was the branch domain of the Choshu clan, he met his concubine, Tomi ONCHI, the local female, and had a daughter Nakako (Nanka, Kinto SAGA consort of the emperor).</e>
<cmt>時制を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no daughter between him and Tomiko, but while he was hiding in Chofu which was the branch domain of the Choshu clan, he met his concubine, Tomi ONCHI, the local female, and had a daughter Nakako (Nanka, Kinto SAGA consort of the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>早くより真木和泉、吉村寅太郎ら尊王攘夷派の志士と交わって公武合体派の排斥運動では急先鋒となって画策した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the early times, he joined with the patriot of the Sonnojoi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians), such as Torataro YOSHIMURA, and Izumi MAKI, and in the boycott of the kobu-gattai (party of advocating Kobu-Gattai which unites the court and the shogunate) he was the vanguard of conduct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the early times, he joined with the patriot of the Sonnojoi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians), such as Torataro YOSHIMURA, and Izumi MAKI, and in the boycott of the kobu-gattai (party of advocating Kobu-Gattai which unites the court and the shogunate) he was the vanguard of conduct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the early times, he joined with the patriot of the Sonnojoi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians), such as Torataro YOSHIMURA, and Izumi MAKI, and in the boycott of the kobu-gattai (party of advocating Kobu-Gattai which unites the court and the shogunate) he was the vanguard of conduct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>文久3年（1863年）2月、朝廷に国事寄人が新設されると19歳でこれに加えられたが、ひそかに京都を脱して長州藩に身を投じ、官位を返上して森俊斎（秀斎）と改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1863, when Kokuji yoriudo was newly established in the court, he was added to this group at the age of 19, but he secretly escaped Kyoto, and joined the Choshu clan, turned down his official court rank and changed his name to Shunsai MORI (Shusai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1863, when Kokuji yoriudo was newly established in the court, he was added to this group at the age of 19, but he secretly escaped Kyoto, and joined the Choshu clan, turned down his official court rank and changed his name to Shunsai (Shusai) MORI.</e>
<cmt>かっこの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1863, when Kokuji yoriudo was newly established in the court, he was added to this group at the age of 19, but he secretly escaped Kyoto, and joined the Choshu clan, turned down his official court rank and changed his name to Shunsai (Shusai) MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>久坂玄瑞が率いる光明寺党の党首として下関における外国船砲撃に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in the attack of the foreign ship in Shimonoseki as the head of Komyo-ji Party lead by Genzui KUSAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in the attack of the foreign ship in Shimonoseki as the head of Komyo-ji Party lead by Genzui KUSAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in the attack of the foreign ship in Shimonoseki as the head of Komyo-ji Party lead by Genzui KUSAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>8月13日に大和国行幸の詔が出されると攘夷論先鋒の勅命を奉じると称して退京し、吉村らと共に大和五條の代官所を襲撃して挙兵した（天誅組の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 13, when edict of imperial visit from Yamato Province was given out, he stated that he would obey the orders of the vanguard for the principle of excluding foreigners, and left Kyo, and together with YOSHIMURA he attacked the magistrate&apos;s office in Yamato Gojo, and raised an army (Tenchu-gumi incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 13, when the edict of imperial visit from Yamato Province was given out, he stated that he would obey the orders of the vanguard for the principle of excluding foreigners, and left Kyo, and together with YOSHIMURA he attacked the magistrate&apos;s office in Yamato Gojo, and raised an army (Tenchu-gumi incident).</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 13, when the edict of imperial visit from Yamato Province was given out, he stated that he would obey the orders of the vanguard for the principle of excluding foreigners, and left Kyo, and together with YOSHIMURA he attacked the magistrate&apos;s office in Yamato Gojo, and raised an army (Tenchu-gumi incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし八月十八日の政変によって京都の尊攘過激派が一掃されると朝廷からも見放され、江戸幕府により追討を命じられた彦根藩や紀伊藩兵などにより鎮圧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However due to the coup in August 18, when the radical party revering the Emperor in Kyoto were wiped out, he was abandoned by the imperial court, and was suppressed by Hikone Domain, and Kishu Domain warriors who were ordered by Edo government to track down and kill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However due to the coup on September 18, when the radical party advocating reverence for the Emperor in Kyoto were wiped out, he was abandoned by the imperial court, and was suppressed by Hikone Domain, and Kishu Domain warriors who were ordered by Edo government to track down and kill.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。In→onに変更しました。尊攘過激派の訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However due to the coup on September 18, when the radical party advocating reverence for the Emperor in Kyoto were wiped out, he was abandoned by the imperial court, and was suppressed by Hikone Domain, and Kishu Domain warriors who were ordered by Edo government to track down and kill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>忠光は大阪へ脱出し長州に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamitsu escaped to Osaka, then to Choshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamitsu escaped to Osaka, then to Choshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamitsu escaped to Osaka, then to Choshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>長州藩は忠光の身柄を支藩の長府藩に預けて保護したが、元治元年（1864年）の禁門の変、下関戦争、第一次長州征伐によって藩内俗論派が台頭すると、潜居中の同年11月に長府藩の豊浦郡田耕村で暗殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choshu Domain had their branch, Chofu clan take care and protect Tadamitsu, but during the Kinmon incident in 1864, in Shimonoseki War, when the conventional party within the domain gained power due to the First Conquest of Choshu, he was assassinated in Tako Village, Toyoura District of Chofu Domain in the November of the same year he was kept as a refuge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choshu Domain had their branch, Chofu clan take care and protect Tadamitsu, but during the Kinmon incident in 1864, in Shimonoseki War, when the conventional party within the domain gained power due to the First Conquest of Choshu, he was assassinated in Tako Village, Toyoura District of Chofu Domain in the December of the same year he was kept as a refuge.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choshu Domain had their branch, Chofu clan take care and protect Tadamitsu, but during the Kinmon incident in 1864, in Shimonoseki War, when the conventional party within the domain gained power due to the First Conquest of Choshu, he was assassinated in Tako Village, Toyoura District of Chofu Domain in the December of the same year he was kept as a refuge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>長府藩潜伏中に寵愛した侍妾恩地トミは、忠光が暗殺された後に遺児仲子を産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concubine Tomi ONCHI, who was loved by Tadamitsu while he was hiding under the Chofu Domain, had the bereaved child Nakako after Tadamitsu was murdered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concubine Tomi ONCHI, who was loved by Tadamitsu while he was hiding under the Chofu Domain, had the bereaved child Nakako after Tadamitsu was murdered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concubine Tomi ONCHI, who was loved by Tadamitsu while he was hiding under the Chofu Domain, had the bereaved child Nakako after Tadamitsu was murdered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>忠光の正室・富子が仲子を引き取り養育する事になり、公家の姫として育てるために、忠光が暗殺された長府藩の藩主家・毛利氏の養女となり公家・中山家に引き取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomiko, the lawful wife of Tadamitsu adopted and raised Nakako, and in order to raise her as the princess of the court noble, she became an adopted daughter of Mori clan, the family lord of Chofu Domain, and was taken in by the court noble. Nakayama clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomiko, the lawful wife of Tadamitsu adopted and raised Nakako, and in order to raise her as the princess of the court noble, she became an adopted daughter of Mori clan, the family lord of Chofu Domain, and was taken in by the court noble, Nakayama clan.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドをカンマに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomiko, the lawful wife of Tadamitsu adopted and raised Nakako, and in order to raise her as the princess of the court noble, she became an adopted daughter of Mori clan, the family lord of Chofu Domain, and was taken in by the court noble, Nakayama clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>富子は亡き夫の忘れ形見の仲子を大事に育て上げ、維新後に仲子は嵯峨公勝夫人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomiko raised Nakako with great care, as a remembrance of her deceased husband, and Nakako became Kinto SAGA consort of the emperor after the restoration.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomiko raised Nakako with great care, as a remembrance of her deceased husband, and Nakako became Kinto SAGA consort of the emperor after the restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomiko raised Nakako with great care, as a remembrance of her deceased husband, and Nakako became Kinto SAGA consort of the emperor after the restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、清最後の皇帝で後に満州国皇帝となった愛新覚羅溥儀の弟である愛新覚羅溥傑に嫁いだ正親町三条家（嵯峨家）出身の嵯峨浩は、忠光の一人娘仲子の孫にあたり、夫妻（富子にとっては義理であるが）の曾孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Hiro SAGA from Ogimachisanjo clan (Saga clan) who was married to Fuketsu AISHINKAKURA, the younger brother of Fugi AISHINKAKURA, the last emperor of Shin, the later emperor of Manchukuo, is the grandchild of Tadamitsu&apos;s only daughter, and was the great grandchild for the couple (although for Tomiko she was the daughter-in-law).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Hiro SAGA from Ogimachisanjo clan (Saga clan) who was married to Fuketsu AISHINKAKURA, the younger brother of Fugi AISHINKAKURA, the last emperor of Shin, the later emperor of Manchukuo, is the grandchild of Tadamitsu&apos;s only daughter, and was the great grandchild for the couple (although for Tomiko she was the great grandchild of her adopted daughter).</e>
<cmt>「富子にとっては義理であるが」の訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Hiro SAGA from Ogimachisanjo clan (Saga clan) who was married to Fuketsu AISHINKAKURA, the younger brother of Fugi AISHINKAKURA, the last emperor of Shin, the later emperor of Manchukuo, is the grandchild of Tadamitsu&apos;s only daughter, and was the great grandchild for the couple (although for Tomiko she was the great grandchild of her adopted daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>墓所は山口県下関市の中山神社 (下関市)境内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The graveyard is located in the premises of Nakayama-jinja Shirine, Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The graveyard is located in the premises of Nakayama-jinja Shirine, Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The graveyard is located in the premises of Nakayama-jinja Shirine, Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 キヨンネ(id:56097), Si-take.(id:91094), Boa(id:20845), 貘(id:106080), Reggaeman(id:6214), 上田隼人(id:23104), Cprobot(id:97843), Web.dweller(id:153933), Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), Qazzx(id:8772), Greenland4(id:114494), Atsasebo(id:95407), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>