<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原信頼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 信頼（ふじわら の のぶより、長元6年（1133年）- 平治元年12月27日 (旧暦)（1160年2月6日））は、平安時代末期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori (1133 – February 6, 1160) was a lord in the latter Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori (1133 – February 6, 1160) was a lord in the latter Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori (1133 – February 13, 1160) was a lord in the latter Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鳥羽天皇の近臣大蔵卿藤原忠隆の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Tadataka, Emperor Toba&apos;s personal attendant and Okurakyo (Minister of the Treasury).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Tadataka, Emperor Toba&apos;s personal attendant and Okurakyo (Minister of the Treasury).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Tadataka, Emperor Toba&apos;s personal attendant and Okurakyo (Minister of the Treasury).</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原顕頼の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was daughter of FUJIWARA no Akiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Akiyori.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Akiyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄弟には奥州藤原氏の藤原秀衡の舅として知られた藤原基成をはじめ、藤原隆教、藤原家頼、藤原信説らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To his brothers and sisters he was known as father in law of FUJIWARA no Hidehira of the Oshu-Fujwara Clan which includes FUJIWARA no Motonari, FUJIWARA no Takanori, FUJIWARA no Ieyori and FUJIWARA no Nobutoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To his brothers and sisters he was known as the father-in-law of FUJIWARA no Hidehira of the Oshu-Fujwara Clan; his siblings included FUJIWARA no Motonari, FUJIWARA no Takanori, FUJIWARA no Ieyori, and FUJIWARA no Nobutoki.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To his brothers and sisters he was known as the father-in-law of FUJIWARA no Hidehira of the Oshu-Fujwara clan; his siblings included FUJIWARA no Motonari, FUJIWARA no Takanori, FUJIWARA no Ieyori, and FUJIWARA no Nobutoki.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifetime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>天養元年（1144年）、正六位に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1144 was conferred the court rank of Shorokui (Senior Sixth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1144 was conferred the court rank of Shorokui (Senior Sixth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1144 was conferred the court rank of Shorokui (Senior Sixth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>久安2年（1146年）、従五位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1146 became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1146 achieved Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1146 achieved Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同年、従五位上に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year he was promoted to Jugoijo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year he was promoted to Jugoijo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year he was promoted to Jugoijo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>久安4年（1148年）に土佐国守、久安6年（1150年）に武蔵国守と父の知行国であった国の受領を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Took successive posts of Tosa Province Governor (1148), Musashi Province Governor (1150) and held the title of juryo in his father&apos;s fief of Chigyo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Took successive posts of Tosa Province Governor (1148) and Musashi Province Governor (1150), and held the title of juryo in his father&apos;s fief of Chigyo Province.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Took successive posts of Tosa no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Tosa) (1148) and Musashi no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Musashi) (1150), and held the title of juryo (the head of the provincial governors) in his father&apos;s chigyo koku (provincial fiefdom).</e>
<cmt>土佐国守→Tosa no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Tosa)訂正しました。武蔵国守→Musashi no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Musashi)受領→Juryo (the head of the provincial governors)説明補足しました。全角の’を半角にしました。知行国→chigyo koku (provincial fiefdom)訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>仁平元年（1151年）には正五位下に進み、翌仁平2年（1152年）には右兵衛佐、久寿2年（1155年）には従四位下・武蔵守に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1155 achieved the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), in the following year (1152) was made Uhyoe-no-suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Watch), in 1155 was given the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was made Governor of Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1155 achieved the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), in the following year (1152) was made Uhyoe-no-suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Watch), and in 1155 was given the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was made Governor of Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1151 achieved the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), in the following year (1152) was made Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), and in 1155 was given the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was made Musashi no kami (Provincial Governor of Musashi).</e>
<cmt>In 1151に訂正しました。右兵衛佐→Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards)武蔵守→Musashi no kami (Provincial Governor of Musashi)訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後白河天皇に近侍するや、周囲から「あさましき程の寵愛あり」といわれるまでの寵臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as a valet to Emperor Goshirakawa and those around him said as a favorite retainer he received &quot;a shameful degree of favoritism&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as a valet to Emperor Goshirakawa and those around him said that as a favorite retainer he received &quot;a shameful degree of favoritism&quot;.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as a valet to Emperor Goshirakawa and those around him said that as a favorite retainer he received &apos;a shameful degree of favoritism.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>保元2年（1157年）、右近衛権中将より蔵人頭・左近衛権中将に任ぜられ従四位上から正四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1157 he served as Ukonoe-gonno-chujo (lieutenant general of the inner palace guards, right division), Kurodo-no-to (chief of the palace officer) and Sakonoe-gonno-chujo (lieutenant general of the inner palace guards, left division) and was promoted from court rank of Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade). The following year (1158), as a Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and Kogonomiya-gonno-suke (Assistant Master of the office of empress&apos;s palace) he was promoted from Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) to in the same year and at a youthful 26 years old, the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Sangi (royal adviser) thus joining the ranks of the nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1157 he served as Ukonoe-gonno-chujo (lieutenant general of the inner palace guards, right division), Kurodo-no-to (chief palace officer), and Sakonoe-gonno-chujo (lieutenant general of the inner palace guards, left division) and was promoted from court rank of Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade). The following year (1158), as a Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and Kogonomiya-gonno-suke (Assistant Master of the office of empress&apos;s palace) he was promoted from Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), and at a youthful 26 years old, he was promotoed to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Sangi (royal adviser), thus joining the ranks of the nobility.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1157 he served as Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), and Sakone gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and was promoted from court rank of Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理promotedスペル訂正しました。以下訂正しました、右近衛権中将→Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)蔵人頭→Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)左近衛権中将→Sakone gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>翌・保元3年（1158年）に正四位上・皇后宮権亮を経て従三位より同年2月に26歳の若さで正三位・参議になり公卿に列せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year (1158), as a Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and Kogo no miya gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Empress&apos;s Household) he was promoted from Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), and at a youthful 26 years old, he was promoted to the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Sangi (royal adviser), thus joining the ranks of the nobility.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理以下訂正しました、皇后宮権亮→Kogo no miya gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Empress&apos;s Household)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同年には権中納言に任ぜられ、検非違使別当・右衛門督を兼ねるに至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year he was given the duty of Gonno-chunagon (provisional middle councilor) and concurrently held the roles of Kebiishi Betto (Secretary in the Office of Police and Judicial Chief) and Uemon-no-kami (Captain of the Right Gate Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year he was given the duty of Gonno-chunagon (provisional middle councilor) and concurrently held the roles of Kebiishi Betto (Secretary in the Office of Police and Judicial Chief) and Uemon-no-kami (Captain of the Right Gate Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year he was given the duty of Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and concurrently held the roles of Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>権中納言 = Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)検非違使別当→Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police)右衛門督→Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天皇の譲位後は院別当となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the Emperor&apos;s abdication, he became In Betto (Secretary of the office of the Retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the Emperor&apos;s abdication, he became In Betto (Secretary of the office of the Retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the Emperor&apos;s abdication, he became In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office).</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。院別当→In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>そのころの信頼の権勢は大変なもので、信頼といざこざを起こした前摂政藤原忠通は院から叱責をうけ閉門の憂き目にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, Nobuyori held tremendous power therefore, quarrels arose with Nobuyori. The former sessho (regent) FUJIWARA no Tadamichi was rebuked by the retired Emperor and suffered under house arrest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, Nobuyori held tremendous power; therefore, quarrels arose with Nobuyori. The former sessho (regent) FUJIWARA no Tadamichi was rebuked by the retired Emperor and he suffered under house arrest.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Nobuyori held tremendous power; the former sessho (regent) FUJIWARA no Tadamichi who had quarreled with Nobuyori, was rebuked by the Retired Emperor and he suffered under house arrest.</e>
<cmt>文脈が違うように思います。翻訳者にご確認ください。Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>その後忠通は嫡子摂政近衛基実の妻に信頼の姉妹を迎えることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Tadamichi took the child of the regent Motozane KONOE and Nobuyori`s sister as his wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, Tadamichi took the child of the regent Motozane KONOE and Nobuyori`s sister as his wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, Tadamichi took the child of the regent Motozane KONOE and Nobuyori&apos;s sister as his wife.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その腹から基実嫡子近衛基通が生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From her womb Motozane&apos;s progeny Motomochi KONOE was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From her womb Motozane&apos;s progeny Motomochi KONOE was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From her womb Motozane&apos;s progeny Motomochi KONOE was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>信頼の権勢を見て忠通が判断してのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing the influence of trust, Tadamichi makes up his mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing the influence of trust, Tadamichi made up his mind.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing the influence of trust, Tadamichi made up his mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>また、信頼は一族を陸奥守に送り込み、自らや弟信説が武蔵守に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Again, Nobuyori and family are dispatched to govern Mutsu Province. Personally and his younger brother Nobutoki are commissioned to govern Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Again, Nobuyori and family were dispatched to govern Mutsu Province. Nobuyori and his younger brother Nobutoki were commissioned to govern Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Nobuyori and family were dispatched to govern Mutsu Province, and Nobuyori and his younger brother Nobutoki were commissioned to govern Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>一文に訂正しました。AgainをAlsoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>坂東武士支配の生命線である武蔵の国衙支配の権限と武士にとっては必要不可欠な馬や武器を調達する陸奥を押さえることによって、坂東支配を進めていた源義朝への影響力を強めていくこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bando samurai have a lifeline of support in the exercise of authority of the Musashi provincial government who supply horses and weapons both indispensable to samurai warriors and, with the seizure of Mutsu, the influence of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (who promoted Bando control) is enhanced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bando samurai have a lifeline of support in the exercise of authority of the Musashi provincial government, who supplied horses and weapons, both indispensable to samurai warriors, and, with the seizure of Mutsu, the influence of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (who promoted Bando control) was enhanced.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bando samurai have a lifeline of support in the exercise of authority of the Musashi provincial government, who supplied horses and weapons, both indispensable to samurai warriors, and, with the seizure of Mutsu, the influence of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (who promoted Bando control) was enhanced.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、当時の最大軍事貴族であった平清盛の娘と信頼の嫡男信親との婚姻も成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time the most powerful military aristocrats, TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s daughter and Nobuyori&apos;s eldest son Nobuchika were also joined in wedlock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time the most powerful military aristocrats, TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s daughter and Nobuyori&apos;s eldest son Nobuchika were also joined in wedlock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time the most powerful military aristocrats, TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s daughter and Nobuyori&apos;s eldest son Nobuchika were also joined in wedlock.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>信頼は朝廷における実力者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori was the person holding actual powering the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori was the person holding actual power in the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori was the person holding actual power in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>体格は肥満で色白、男色（衆道）も好んだ後白河天皇に愛され、宮廷では人目も憚らぬ程の寵愛ぶりであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was loved by the corpulent and fair skinned Emperor Goshirakawa who had homosexual (pederast) inclinations and is said not to have also not hesitated showing his affections in the public gaze of the royal court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was loved by the corpulent and fair skinned Emperor Goshirakawa, who had homosexual (pederast) inclinations and is said not to have hesitated in showing his affections in the public gaze of the royal court.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was loved by the corpulent and fair skinned Emperor Goshirakawa, who had homosexual (pederast) inclinations and is said not to have hesitated in showing his affections in the public gaze of the royal court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>幼い頃から気性が激しく、晩年には悪右衛門督と評せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From a young age he had a difficult temperament and, in his latter years he was described as the &quot;evil&quot; Uemon-no-kami (Captain of the Right Gate Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From a young age he had a difficult temperament, and in his latter years he was described as the &quot;evil&quot; Uemon-no-kami (Captain of the Right Gate Guards).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From a young age he had a difficult temperament, and in his latter years he was described as the &apos;evil&apos; Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Gate Guards).</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、そのころ急速に力を伸ばしていた人物にもう一人後白河院近臣藤原信西がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, around that time one other individuals power grew quickly as well: FUJIWARA no SHINZEI a vassal of retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, around that time one other individual&apos;s power grew quickly as well: FUJIWARA no SHINZEI, a vassal of retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, around that time one other individual&apos;s power grew quickly as well: FUJIWARA no Shinzei, a vassal of Retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Shinzeiに訂正しました。Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>いつしか信西と信頼は反目するようになり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, Shinzei and Nobuyori were at loggerheads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, Shinzei and Nobuyori were at loggerheads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, Shinzei and Nobuyori were at loggerheads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="27">
<j>また、後白河院の院政を好まず二条天皇の親政を望む勢力もあって、朝廷内は政治的派閥の対立が目立つようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being ruled by retired Emperor Goshirakawa was not liked, influence was brought to bear in favor of direct Imperial rule by Emperor Nijo and, within the court, battles between the political cliques gained prominence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rule by retired Emperor Goshirakawa was not liked; influence was brought to bear in favor of direct Imperial rule by Emperor Nijo and, within the court, battles between the political cliques gained prominence.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rule by retired Emperor Goshirakawa was not liked; influence was brought to bear in favor of direct Imperial rule by Emperor Nijo and, within the court, battles between the political cliques gained prominence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>平治元年（1159年）12月9日 (旧暦)、都において他を圧倒する軍事力を有する平清盛が熊野詣に出かけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 9, 1159 in Kyoto, TAIRA no Kiyomori who had the military power to overwhelm others was on a pilgrimage to the Shrines of Kumano. In his absence, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and MINAMOTO no Yorimasa were drawn into a trap by Nobuyori who raised an army in Kyoto then, captured and beheaded Shinzei. (Heiji no Ran (Heiji Rebellion))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 9, 1159 in Kyoto, TAIRA no Kiyomori, who had the military power to overwhelm others, was on a pilgrimage to the Shrines of Kumano. In his absence, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu, and MINAMOTO no Yorimasa were drawn into a trap by Nobuyori who had raised an army in Kyoto and then captured and beheaded Shinzei. (Heiji no Ran (Heiji Rebellion))</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 26, 1160 in Kyoto, TAIRA no Kiyomori, who had the military power to overwhelm others, was on a pilgrimage to the Shrines of Kumano.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>留守に信頼は源義朝、源光保、源頼政を誘引しては京で挙兵、信西を捕らえて斬首する（平治の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his absence, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu, and MINAMOTO no Yorimasa were drawn into a trap by Nobuyori who had raised an army in Kyoto and then captured and beheaded Shinzei. (Heiji no Ran (Heiji Rebellion))</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>その功により信頼は朝廷の最大の実力者に成り上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For his success, Nobuyori rapidly rose to be the most powerful individual at court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For his success, Nobuyori rapidly rose to be the most powerful individual at court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For his success, Nobuyori rapidly rose to be the most powerful individual at court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、二条天皇親政を支持する勢力と信頼、その他軍事貴族の連合であるこの政権はすぐに瓦解した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, political administration in the form of Emperor Nijo exercising influence with Nobuyori and, the alliance of other military nobles soon collapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, political administration in the form of Emperor Nijo exercising influence with Nobuyori and the alliance of other military nobles soon collapsed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, political administration in the form of Emperor Nijo exercising influence with Nobuyori and the alliance of other military nobles soon collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="32">
<j>それまで中立的立場を保っていた平清盛が帰京すると二条天皇派は清盛と手を結び二条天皇を六波羅へと御幸させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon returning to Kyoto, TAIRA no Kiyomori who had up until then remained neutral, joined with factions loyal to Emperor Nijo and paid a visit on Emperor Nijo at the Rokuhara estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon returning to Kyoto, TAIRA no Kiyomori, who had up until then remained neutral, joined with factions loyal to Emperor Nijo and paid a visit to Emperor Nijo at the Rokuhara estate.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon returning to Kyoto, TAIRA no Kiyomori, who had up until then remained neutral, joined with factions loyal to Emperor Nijo and paid a visit to Emperor Nijo at the Rokuhara estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>信頼に反乱者の烙印を押した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori branded them as rebels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori branded them rebels.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori branded them rebels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="34">
<j>もともと二条天皇側近であった源光保らの軍事貴族は賊軍となった信頼方から離脱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, military nobles of the likes of MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu who were close associates of Emperor Nijo found themselves withdrawing from Nobuyori&apos;s side, which had become rebel forces. Only Minamoto No Yoshitomo (who Nobuyori depended upon heavily) remained loyal to Nobuyori&apos;s camp</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, military nobles of the likes of MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu, who were close associates of Emperor Nijo, found themselves withdrawing from Nobuyori&apos;s side, who had become rebel forces. Only Minamoto No Yoshitomo (who Nobuyori depended upon heavily) remained loyal to Nobuyori&apos;s camp</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, military nobles of the likes of MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu, who were close associates of Emperor Nijo, found themselves withdrawing from Nobuyori&apos;s side, who had become rebel forces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理原文の文末を訂正しました。全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>信頼に対する依存度が高い源義朝のみが信頼の陣営に残ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (who Nobuyori depended upon heavily) remained loyal to Nobuyori&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理MINAMOTO noに訂正しました。全角の’を半角にしました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="36">
<j>また、清盛の婿となっていた信頼の嫡子は二条天皇の御幸の直後父信頼の元に戻され平家との婚姻関係も解消された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Nobuyori&apos;s son (who had become Kiyomori&apos;s son-in-law) returned back to his father (Nobuyori) immediately after the call on Emperor Nijo and the marital ties with the Taira family were dissolved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Nobuyori&apos;s son (who had become Kiyomori&apos;s son-in-law) returned back to his father (Nobuyori) immediately after the call on Emperor Nijo, and the marital ties with the Taira family were dissolved.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Nobuyori&apos;s son (who had become Kiyomori&apos;s son-in-law) returned back to his father (Nobuyori) immediately after the call on Emperor Nijo, and the marital ties with the Taira family were dissolved.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="37">
<j>12月28日天皇の宣旨を得て攻めかかってきた官軍との戦闘においては、官軍指揮者である都最大の軍事貴族平清盛の大軍の前に信頼・義朝はあっけなく敗北する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the December 28 the Emperor made a proclamation and in the battle with the attacking imperial forces, in front of TAIRA no Kiyomori, the commander of imperial force and capital`s greatest military noble, Nobuyori and Yoshitomo were easily defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 28 the Emperor made a proclamation, and in the battle with the attacking imperial forces, in front of TAIRA no Kiyomori, the commander of imperial forces and the capital`s greatest military noble, Nobuyori and Yoshitomo were easily defeated.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 14, the Emperor made a proclamation, and in the battle with the attacking imperial forces, in front of TAIRA no Kiyomori, the commander of imperial forces and the capital&apos;s greatest military noble, Nobuyori and Yoshitomo were easily defeated.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="38">
<j>平治物語では戦での信頼の臆病ぶりが描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tale of Heiji paints a picture of Nobuyori&apos;s apparent cowardice in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tale of Heiji paints a picture of Nobuyori&apos;s apparent cowardice in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tale of Heiji paints a picture of Nobuyori&apos;s apparent cowardice in battle.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="39">
<j>逃れた信頼は義朝と東国へ落ちようとするが、義朝から「日本一の不覚人」と罵られ拒絶される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Escaping Nobuyori intended to flee with Yoshitomo to the Eastern Provinces however, Yoshitomo had only harsh words &quot;Japan&apos;s greatest loser&quot; and refused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Escaping, Nobuyori intended to flee with Yoshitomo to the Eastern Provinces; however, Yoshitomo had only harsh words, &quot;Japan&apos;s greatest loser,&quot; and refused.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Escaping, Nobuyori intended to flee with Yoshitomo to the Eastern Provinces; however, Yoshitomo had only harsh words, &apos;Japan&apos;s greatest loser,&apos; and refused.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>仁和寺にいた後白河院にすがり助命を嘆願するが、朝廷は信頼を謀反の張本人として許さず、六条河原で斬首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Ninna-ji Temple where Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa had gone, he pleaded for clemency but, the Imperial Court did not pardon Nobuyori as ringleader of insurrection and he was beheaded at the Rokujo-gawara execution grounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Ninna-ji Temple, where Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa had gone, he pleaded for clemency, but the Imperial Court did not pardon Nobuyori as ringleader of insurrection and he was beheaded at the Rokujo-gawara execution grounds.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Ninna-ji Temple, where Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa had gone, he pleaded for clemency, but the Imperial Court did not pardon Nobuyori as ringleader of insurrection and he was beheaded at the Rokujo-gawara execution grounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>首の座になおってももがきもだえ、おさえつけてようやく首を掻き切ったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his neck having been placed on the executioner`s block, he writhed in anguish, calmed down then his head was duly chopped-off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that with his neck having been placed on the executioner`s block, he writhed in anguish, then calmed down, after which his head was duly chopped-off.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that with his neck having been placed on the executioner&apos;s block, he writhed in anguish, then calmed down, after which his head was duly chopped-off.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 諏訪太郎頼光(id:98476), 代言人(id:33675), 俊(id:14924), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Yas(id:739), Ponsaku(id:31417), Klesha(id:203751), FlaBot(id:30804), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>