<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新田義興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yositoki NITTA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshioki NITTA</e>
<cmt>Yositoki --&gt; Yoshioki</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshioki NITTA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新田 義興（にった よしおき）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitoki NITTA was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the period of Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshioki NITTA was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the period of Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>Yoshitoki --&gt; Yoshioki</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshioki NITTA was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the period of Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>新田義貞の次男、生母は上野国一宮貫前神社神主の天野時宣（禰宜時宣とも）の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of Yoshisada NITTA and his birth mother was a daughter of Tokinobu AMANO (also referred as Negi (Shinto priest) Tokinobu), who was the Shinshu (Shinto priest) of Ichinomiya (shrine with the highest ranking in the area) Nukisaki Jinja Shrine of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of Yoshisada NITTA and his birth mother was a daughter of Tokinobu AMANO (also referred to as Negi (Shinto priest) Tokinobu), who was the Shinshu (Shinto priest) of Ichinomiya (shrine with the highest ranking in the area) Nukisaki Jinja Shrine of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>referredの次にtoを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Yoshisada NITTA and his birth mother was a daughter of Tokinobu AMANO (also referred to as Negi (Shinto priest) Tokinobu), who was the Shinshu (Shinto priest) of Ichinomiya (shrine with the highest ranking in the area) Nukisaki Jinja Shrine of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>異母兄は新田義顕、異母弟は新田義宗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His older paternal half-brother was Yoshiaki NITTA and younger paternal half-brother was Yoshimune NITTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older paternal half-brother was Yoshiaki NITTA and younger paternal half-brother was Yoshimune NITTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older paternal half-brother was Yoshiaki NITTA and younger paternal half-brother was Yoshimune NITTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は徳寿丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Tokujumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Tokujumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Tokujumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>1337年（建武 (日本)4年/延元2年）、奥州の北畠顕家が西上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiie KITABATAKE of Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa Provinces) travelled west in 1337.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiie KITABATAKE of Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa Provinces) travelled west in 1337.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiie KITABATAKE of Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa Provinces) travelled west in 1337.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これに呼応して上野で挙兵し、北畠顕家の奥州軍に加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He responded by mobilizing an army in Kozuke Province and joined the Oshu army of Akiie KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He responded by mobilizing an army in Kozuke Province and joined the Oshu army of Akiie KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He responded by mobilizing an army in Kozuke Province and joined the Oshu army of Akiie KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>吉野で後醍醐天皇に謁見し、元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was granted with an audience of Emperor Godaiba and underwent genpuku (coming of age ceremony) at Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He underwent genpuku (coming of age ceremony) in audience by Emperor Godaiba at Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He underwent genpuku (coming of age ceremony) in audience by Emperor Godaiba at Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>父義貞の戦死後、越後に潜伏したと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he hid in Echigo Province after his father Yoshisada died in a battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he hid in Echigo Province after his father Yoshisada died in a battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he hid in Echigo Province after his father Yoshisada died in a battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>観応の擾乱が起こると、鎌倉の奪還を目指して上野国で北条時行らとともに挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kanno Disturbance occurred, he mobilized an army with Tokiyuki HOJO in Kozuke Province in order to retrieve back Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kanno Disturbance occurred, he mobilized an army with Tokiyuki HOJO in Kozuke Province in order to retrieve Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>retrieve back --&gt; retrieve</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kanno Disturbance occurred, he mobilized an army with Tokiyuki HOJO in Kozuke Province in order to retrieve Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>正平一統が破綻すると、1352年（正平 (日本)7年/観応3年）に宗良親王を奉じて弟義宗、従兄弟脇屋義治と挙兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Shoei Itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern courts) became abolished, he mobilized an army with his younger brother Yoshimune and his male cousin, Yoshiharu WAKIYA, under the order of Imperial Prince Muneyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Shoei Itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern courts) became abolished, he mobilized an army with his younger brother Yoshimune and his male cousin, Yoshiharu WAKIYA, under the order of Imperial Prince Muneyoshi in 1352.</e>
<cmt>in 1352を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Shoei Itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern courts) became abolished, he mobilized an army with his younger brother Yoshimune and his male cousin, Yoshiharu WAKIYA, under the order of Imperial Prince Muneyoshi in 1352.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉を一時占拠するが、尊氏の反撃にあって鎌倉を追われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They temporarily occupied Kamakura, but was chased away from Kamakura after a counter attack by Takauji (ASHIKAGA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They temporarily occupied Kamakura, but were chased away from Kamakura after a counter attack by Takauji (ASHIKAGA).</e>
<cmt>was --&gt; were</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They temporarily occupied Kamakura, but were chased away from Kamakura after a counter attack by Takauji (ASHIKAGA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>尊氏が没した半年後の1358年（正平 (日本)13年/延文3年）、尊氏の子で鎌倉公方の足利基氏と関東管領の畠山国清によって送りこまれた竹沢右京亮と江戸氏により、義興と主従13人は、多摩川の矢口渡で謀殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A half a year after Takauji passed away in 1358, Yoshitoki and his 13 servants were murdered premeditatedly on Yaguchi no Watashi (Yaguchi Ferry) of Tama-gawa River by Takesawa, who was the Ukyo no Suke (Assistant Master of the Western Capital Offices), and Edo clan member sent by Motouji ASHIKAGA, who was the child of Takauji and Kamakura kubo (Governor general of the Kanto region), and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, who was the Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A half year after Takauji passed away, in 1358, Yoshitoki and his 13 servants were murdered premeditatedly at Yaguchi no Watashi (Yaguchi Ferry) of Tama-gawa River by Takesawa, who was the Ukyo no Suke (Assistant Master of the Western Capital Offices), and Edo clan members sent by Motouji ASHIKAGA, who was a child of Takauji and was the Kamakura kubo (Governor general of the Kanto region), and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, who was the Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し（冠詞、単数複数）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A half year after Takauji passed away, in 1358, Yoshitoki and his 13 servants were murdered premeditatedly at Yaguchi no Watashi (Yaguchi Ferry) of Tama-gawa River by Takesawa, who was the Ukyo no Suke (Assistant Master of the Western Capital Offices), and Edo clan members sent by Motouji ASHIKAGA, who was a child of Takauji and was the Kamakura kubo (Governor general of the Kanto region), and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, who was the Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>齢28。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His dying age was 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His dying age was 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His dying age was 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>義興の死後、謀殺の下手人であった江戸某が義興の怨霊により狂死したため、現地の住民が義興の霊を慰めるために神として祭ったという記述が、古典「太平記」にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a reference in the classics &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace) that murderer 某 EDO (江戸某) died with madness by the vengeful spirit of Yoshitoki after his death that local residents worshipped Yoshitoki as a god in order to calm the spirit.</e>
<cmt>某[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description in the classics &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace) that a murderer 某 EDO (江戸某) had died in madness by the vengeful spirit of Yoshioki after his death so that local residents worshipped Yoshitoki as a god in order to calm his spirit.</e>
<cmt>Yoshitoki をYoshioki に変更する等、表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description in the classics &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace) that a murderer 某 EDO (江戸某) had died in madness by the vengeful spirit of Yoshioki after his death so that local residents worshipped Yoshitoki as a god in order to calm his spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>後に新田大明神として尊崇される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was later worshipped as Nitta Daimyo-jin (great god).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was later worshipped as Nitta Daimyo-jin (great god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was later worshipped as Nitta Daimyo-jin (great god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>歌舞伎の「神霊矢口渡」は、この事件を扱ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;Shinrei Yaguchi no Watashi&apos; (The Yaguchi Ferry and the Magic Arrows) of kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) dealt with this incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Shinrei Yaguchi no Watashi&apos; (The Yaguchi Ferry and the Magic Arrows) of kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) deals with this incident.</e>
<cmt>dealt with --&gt; deals with</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Shinrei Yaguchi no Watashi&apos; (The Yaguchi Ferry and the Magic Arrows) of kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) deals with this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>東急多摩川線の武蔵新田駅の&quot;新田&quot;は、新田大明神を祭った新田神社に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nitta&apos; of Musashi Nitta Station on Tokyu Tamagawa Line was derived from Nitta jinja Shrine that worshipped Nitta Daimyo-jin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nitta&apos; in the name of Musashi Nitta Station on the Tokyu Tamagawa Line is derived from Nitta-jinja Shrine that worships Nitta Daimyo-jin (the Great God).</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nitta&apos; in the name of Musashi Nitta Station on the Tokyu Tamagawa Line is derived from Nitta-jinja Shrine that worships Nitta Daimyo-jin (the Great God).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Oxhop(id:2551), Okt(id:18107), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), R463(id:150079), Hykw-a4(id:14184), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>