<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原光家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mitsuie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 光家（ふじわら の みついえ、元暦元年（1184年）－？）は、鎌倉時代初期の公家・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuie (1184 - date of death unknown) was a court noble and waka poet in the early part of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mitsuie (1184 - date of death unknown) was a court noble and waka poet in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>「鎌倉時代初期」の英訳を、用語集の表記にあわせるため、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mitsuie (1184 - date of death unknown) was a court noble and waka poet during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>in→during</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原定家の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eldest son of FUJIWARA no Teika</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Teika.</e>
<cmt>主語・動詞を補うことで文として成立させ、「長男」を&quot;first son&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Teika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原季能の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に僧・兼宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children include Kenho, a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his children was Kenho, a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt>&quot;include&quot;ではなく、&quot;one of his children&quot;とすることにより、自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his children was Kenho, a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>初名、定継、後に清家（正治元年改名）、光家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Sadatsugu; he then changed his name to Kiyoie (in 1199) and further to Mitsuie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was first named Sadatsugu, and changed the name to Kiyoie (in 1199) and then to Mitsuie.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he&quot;を主語にすることにより、セミコロンを使わない文としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was first named Sadatsugu, and changed the name to Kiyoie (in 1199) and then to Mitsuie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>法号は浄照房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name is Joshobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His hogo (Buddhist name) was Joshobo.</e>
<cmt>時制を過去形に訂正し、レビュー結果を参照し、「法号」の表記を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His hogo (Buddhist name) was Joshobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>従五位・侍従。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His final rank and service was Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and was appointed as Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>レビュー結果を参照し、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and was appointed as Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>母は御子左家と競合関係にあった六条藤家の出身であったが、公事や和歌の才能に恵まれず、建保3年（1215年）8月15日の内裏歌合では評者であった父・定家から「太尾籠、赧面無極（和歌のルールに適っていないことはなはだしく、恥ずかしいことこの上ない）」と酷評される有様であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born to the Rokujo Toke (Rokujo Fujiwara Family), which was a competitor family of the Mikohidari Family, his mother was not blessed with the capabilities of political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court or waka poetry, and when she participated in a Dairi Utaawase (poet contest in the Palace) on August 15, 1215, her father Teika severely criticized her performance saying she was awfully out of line with the waka poetry rules and should be seriously ashamed.</e>
<cmt>「太尾籠、赧面無極」は訳していません。それに続く説明文を訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although she was from the Rokujo Toke (Rokujo Fujiwara family), which competed with the Mikohidari family, his mother was not gifted with the capabilities of political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court or waka poetry, and when she participated in Dairi Utaawase (Poem contest in the Palace) on September 17, 1215, her father, Teika, severely criticized her waka with saying that &apos;her waka was awfully out of line with the waka poetry rules and was terribly ashamed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「競合関係にあった」を簡潔に&quot;compete with&quot;に変更し、「8月15日」を、こよみのページを参照し、新暦に変更しました。また、「　」で括られた部分にシングル・クォーテーションを付記し、「（母の）和歌がルールに沿っていない」という意味なので、&quot;her performance&quot;及び&quot;she&quot;を&quot;her waka&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although she was from the Rokujo Toke (Rokujo Fujiwara family), which competed with the Mikohidari family, his mother was not gifted with the capabilities of political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court or waka poetry, and when she participated in Dairi Utaawase (Poem contest in the Palace) on September 17, 1215, her father, Teika, severely criticized her waka with saying that &apos;her waka was awfully out of line with the waka poetry rules and was terribly ashamed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>加えて建久年間に父が光家の生母と離婚して西園寺実宗の娘と再婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father had a divorce from his real mother in the Kenkyu era (1190 to 1199) and remarried a daughter of Sanemune SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, his father divorced his real mother in the Kenkyu era (1190 to 1199) and remarried a daughter of Sanemune SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>「加えて」の訳を補い、簡潔にするため、「離婚した」を &quot;divorce&quot;の動詞形としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, his father divorced his real mother in the Kenkyu era (1190 to 1199) and remarried a daughter of Sanemune SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>加えて後妻の兄弟であった西園寺公経が九条道家を娘婿として朝廷にて重きをなし、定家と後妻の間の子である藤原為家を猶子としていたことから、嫡男として扱われるようになると、光家の立場は微妙なものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kintsune SAIONJI, a brother of Teika&apos;s second wife, began to play an important role in the Imperial Palace as the father-in-law of Michiie KUJO, and FUJIWARA no Tameie, child of Teika and his second wife, became an adopted son of Kintsune and was treated as the heir to Kintsune; because of those circumstances, the position of Mitsuie became unstable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, by reason that Kintsune SAIONJI, a brother of Teika&apos;s second wife, began to play an important role in the Imperial Palace as the father-in-law of Michiie KUJO, and adopted FUJIWARA no Tameie, son of Teika and his second wife, Tameie came to be treated as a legitimate son of Kintsune, which put Mitsuie in a delicate position.</e>
<cmt>「為家が嫡男」として扱われるようになり、それにより「光家」が微妙な立場に置かれる様になったので、訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, by reason that Kintsune SAIONJI, a brother of Teika&apos;s second wife, began to play an important role in the Imperial Palace as the father-in-law of Michiie KUJO, and adopted FUJIWARA no Tameie, son of Teika and his second wife, Tameie came to be treated as a legitimate son of Kintsune, which put Mitsuie in a delicate position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、建仁2年（1202年）、加賀権守となった後にあき子内親王及びその保護下にあった九条良輔、更にその養嗣子となった九条教家に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1202, Mitsuie was appointed as Kaga no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Kaga Province) and then served Imperial Princess Akiko, Yoshisuke KUJO, who was under the protection of Princess Akiko, and Noriie KUJO, who became an adopted heir of Yoshisuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, after being appointed as Provisional Governor of Kaga Province in 1202, Mitsuie served Imperial Princess Akiko, Yoshisuke KUJO, who was under the protection of Princess Akiko, and Noriie KUJO, who became an adopted heir of Yoshisuke.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, after being appointed as Provisional Governor of Kaga Province in 1202, Mitsuie served Imperial Princess Akiko, Yoshisuke KUJO, who was under the protection of Princess Akiko, and Noriie KUJO, who became an adopted heir of Yoshisuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ところが、九条良通・九条良経の相次ぐ死で八条院庇護下にあった九条良輔が九条家の中心的な存在となったことで光家の立場にも変化が生じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshimichi KUJO and Yoshitsune KUJO consecutively died, Yoshisuke KUJO, who was under the patronage of Hachijo-in, came to occupy a central position in the Kujo Family, which caused changes to the position of Mitsuie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Yoshimichi KUJO and Yoshitsune KUJO consecutively died, Yoshisuke KUJO, who was under the patronage of Hachijoin, came to occupy a central position in the Kujo family, which caused changes to the position of Mitsuie.</e>
<cmt>「ところが」の訳を補い、また、上記「御子左家」「六条藤家」の表記にあわせ、「九条家」の表記を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Yoshimichi KUJO and Yoshitsune KUJO consecutively died, Yoshisuke KUJO, who was under the patronage of Hachijoin, came to occupy a central position in the Kujo family, which caused changes to the position of Mitsuie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>建暦元年（1211年）に昇殿が許されると、建保元年（1213年）には宇佐使に任じられるなど良輔側近としての地位を得て、為家との差を縮めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Mitsuie was allowed to enter the Imperial Court in 1211, he won a decent position as the close adviser of Yoshisuke, such as Usa-zukai (Imperial messenger to Usa Jingu Shrine), thereby reducing the gap with Tameie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Mitsuie was allowed to access the Imperial Court in 1211, he obtained a position as close adviser to Yoshisuke, like appointment of Usazukai (Imperial messenger to Usa-jingu Shrine), and reduced the gap with Tameie.</e>
<cmt>用語集を参照し、「昇殿」及び「宇佐使」（宇佐神宮を含め）の英訳をへんこうしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Mitsuie was allowed to access the Imperial Court in 1211, he obtained a position as close adviser to Yoshisuke, like appointment of Usazukai (Imperial messenger to Usa-jingu Shrine), and reduced the gap with Tameie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>ところが、建保6年（1218年）に九条良輔が没すると、九条家は良輔の甥で教家の実兄である九条道家（正室は光家の異母弟為家の従兄弟）が率いることになり、九条教家やこれに仕える光家を圧迫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But when Yoshisuke KUJO died in 1218, it was decided that the Kujo Family be led by Michiie KUJO, elder brother of Noriie and a nephew of Yoshisuke, (whose official wife was a cousin of Tameie, half-brother of Mitsuie), and this situation suppressed the positions of Noriie KUJO and Mitsuie who served him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, when Yoshisuke KUJO died in 1218, the Kujo family came to be led by Michiie KUJO, nephew of Yoshisuke and older brother of Noriie, (whose lawful wife was a cousin of Tameie, young parternal half-brother of Mitsuie), and this situation suppressed the positions of Noriie KUJO and Mitsuie who served him.</e>
<cmt>用語リストを参照し、「兄」及び「異母弟」を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, when Yoshisuke KUJO died in 1218, the Kujo family came to be led by Michiie KUJO, nephew of Yoshisuke and older brother of Noriie, (whose lawful wife was a cousin of Tameie, young parternal half-brother of Mitsuie), and this situation suppressed the positions of Noriie KUJO and Mitsuie who served him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>八条院は既に無く、もう1人の後見人であった慈円も嘉禄元年（1225年）に失った教家は9月に慈円の死に先立って出家を遂げ、良輔の没後出家の意向を持っていた光家も9月6日に同じく出家を遂げて浄照房と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Hachijo-in already deceased and Jien, the other guardian of Noriie, having passed away in 1225, Noriie entered into priesthood in September 1225 prior to the death of Jien, and Mitsuie, who had an intention to enter into priesthood after the death of Yoshisuke, also became a priest on September 6 and had the Buddhist name Joshobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By reason that Hachijoin had already died and Jien, another guardian of Noriie, also died in 1225, Noriie entered into priesthood in October 1225 prior to the death of Jien, and Mitsuie, who intended to enter into priesthood after the death of Yoshisuke, also became a priest on October 16, 1225 and called himself Joshobo.</e>
<cmt>こよみのページを参照し、「9月」をOctober （9月1日が10月11日となるので）に変更し、「9月6日」も変更しました。また、簡潔にするため、理由を示す&quot;by reason that&quot;を使用し、&quot;had an intention&quot;を&quot;intended&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By reason that Hachijoin had already died and Jien, another guardian of Noriie, also died in 1225, Noriie entered into priesthood in October 1225 prior to the death of Jien, and Mitsuie, who intended to enter into priesthood after the death of Yoshisuke, also became a priest on October 16, 1225 and called himself Joshobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このことを教家からの報告で知った定家は『明月記』に「此遁世尤可謂穏便」と記して八条系九条家の消滅によって行くあてを失った光家には遁世しか選択の余地は無いとする態度を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having been informed of this in a report from Noriie, Teika understood that Mitsuie, who lost the person to serve following the disappearance of the Kujo Family of the Hachijo line, had no choice but to seclude himself from the world, as described by Teika&apos;s comment in &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having been informed of this in a report from Noriie, Teika took a stance that Mitsuie, who lost a person to serve due to extinction of the Kujo family of the Hachijo line, had no choice but to seclude himself from the world, as he described in &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) that &apos;this seclusion from the world must have been most reasonable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「此遁世尤可謂穏便」の訳出し、「九条家の消滅」は、「九条家の断絶」の意味となるので、&quot;extinction&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having been informed of this in a report from Noriie, Teika took a stance that Mitsuie, who lost a person to serve due to extinction of the Kujo family of the Hachijo line, had no choice but to seclude himself from the world, as he described in &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) that &apos;this seclusion from the world must have been most reasonable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>皮肉にもこの年の12月に為家は蔵人頭に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironically, Tameie was assigned to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironically, Tameie was assigned to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in December (old calendar) of the same year).</e>
<cmt>「12月（１日）」は、新暦に変換すると、「翌年の１月７日」となり、原文の「皮肉にも」と「この年」の持つニュアンスが失われてしまうと判断し、&quot;old calendar&quot;を付記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironically, Tameie was assigned to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in December (old calendar) of the same year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>『明月記』天福 (日本)元年（1233年）4月17日条に定家と浄照房（光家）が出家前に設けた娘の行く末について相談したことが記されているものの、その後は九州方面に下ったとされている以外は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The April 17, 1233, article of &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; mentioned Teika and Joshobo (Mitsuie) talked about a daughter of Joshobo born prior to his entry to priesthood, but no clear record remained about Mitsuie after his documented relocation to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The article dated June 3, 1233 in &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; mentioned that Teika and Joshobo (Mitsuie) talked about a future of Joshobo&apos;s daughter who was born prior to his entry to priesthood, but anything about Mitsuie is unknown except that he wend down to Kyushu thereafter.</e>
<cmt>「行く末」及び「下る」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The article dated June 3, 1233 in &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; mentioned that Teika and Joshobo (Mitsuie) talked about a future of Joshobo&apos;s daughter who was born prior to his entry to priesthood, but anything about Mitsuie is unknown except that he wend down to Kyushu thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>勅撰和歌集に採録された和歌は無く、『浄照房集』と呼ばれる私家集が伝えられているのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No poems created by Mitsuie are found in any anthologies of waka poems compiled by the Imperial command, and a private collection of poems of Mitsuie, called &quot;Joshobo-shu,&quot; alone has been handed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No poems created by Mitsuie are found in any imperial anthologies of poetry in Japanese, but only the private collection of Mitsuie&apos;s poems, called &quot;Joshobo-shu,&quot; has been handed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>用語集を参照し、「勅撰和歌集」の表記を変更しました。また、「勅撰和歌集には和歌がないが、私家集のみ伝えられている」となるので、&quot;and&quot;を&quot;but&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No poems created by Mitsuie are found in any imperial anthologies of poetry in Japanese, but only the private collection of Mitsuie&apos;s poems, called &quot;Joshobo-shu,&quot; has been handed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>