<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源師俊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Morotoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Morotoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Morotoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 師俊（みなもと の もろとし、承暦4年（1080年） - 永治元年12月7日 (旧暦)（1142年1月5日））は、平安時代後期の公卿・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Morotoshi (1080-January 5, 1142) was the kuge (court noble) and kajin (waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) poet) of the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Morotoshi (1080-January 5, 1142) was a kuge (court noble) and kajin (waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) poet) of the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Morotoshi (1080-January 5, 1142) was a court noble and poet at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>1080-January 5, 1142 を1080 - January 12, 1142 に修正しました。a kuge (court noble) を court noble に修正しました。kajin (waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) poet) of をpoet in に修正しました。in the end of the Heian Period→at the end of the Heian period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>村上源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was of the Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan of Murakami).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was of the Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan of Murakami).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was of the Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Minamoto clan of Murakami の of Murakami を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>堀河左大臣源俊房の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of MINAMOTO no Toshifusa, who had the title of Horikawa Sadaijin (Minister of the Left for Emperor Horikawa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of MINAMOTO no Toshifusa, who had the title of Horikawa Sadaijin (Minister of the Left for Emperor Horikawa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of MINAMOTO no Toshifusa, who had the title of Horikawa Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>Minister of the Left for Emperor Horikawa のfor Emperor Horikawa を削除しました（※）。※「堀河」は俊房の邸宅所在地名であって、天皇の名前ではありません。参考：http://ci.nii.ac.jp/Detail/detail.do?LOCALID=ART0001824812&amp;lang=ja</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>叔父の壬生大納言源師忠の養子になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by his uncle, Minamoto no Morotada, who had the title of Mibu Dainagon (major councilor of Mibu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by his uncle, Minamoto no Morotada, who had the title of Mibu Dainagon (major councilor of Mibu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by his uncle, MINAMOTO no Morotada, who had the title of Mibu Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Minamoto を MINAMOTO に修正しました。major councilor を chief councilor of state に修正し、of Mibu を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従三位・権中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the title of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the rank and title of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;rank&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the rank and title of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Provisional Middle Counselor をprovisional vice councilor of state に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>初め俊仲と名乗るが、後に師俊と改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He first called himself as Toshinaka but later changed his name to Morotoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He first called himself Toshinaka but later changed his name to Morotoshi.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He first called himself Toshinaka but later changed his name to Morotoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>弾正台、兵部省、民部省などを経て、長承2年（1133年）参議に任ぜられ、長承3年（1134年）4月従三位に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held positions of Danjodai (Board of Censors), Hyobusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of War), Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs), and Sangi (advisor) in 1133 before receiving the Jusanmi Rank in April 1134.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held positions of Danjodai (Board of Censors), Hyobusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of War), Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs), and Sangi (advisor) in 1133 before receiving the Jusanmi Rank in April 1134.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held positions of Danjodai (Board of Censors), Hyobusho (Ministry of War), Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs), and Sangi (Royal Advisor) in 1133 before receiving the Jusanmi Rank in April 1134.</e>
<cmt>Hyobusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the をHyobusho (に修正しました。advisor を Royal Advisor に修正しました（※）。※出典：http://www.albany.edu/eas/205/rank%20chart.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>保延元年（1135年）権中納言に任ぜられるが、翌年5月13日病のため出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to be Gon Chunagon in 1135 but underwent shukke (become a Buddhist priest) on June 14 of the following year due to illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to be Gon Chunagon in 1135 but underwent shukke (become a Buddhist priest) on June 14 of the following year due to illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to be Gon Chunagon in 1135 but entered priesthood on June 21 of the following year due to illness.</e>
<cmt>underwent shukke (become a Buddhist priest) をentered priesthood に修正しました。June 14 を June 21 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>永治元年（1141年）12月7日、62歳で薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away at the age of sixty-two on January 5, 1142.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away at the age of sixty-two on January 5, 1142.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away at the age of sixty-two on January 12, 1142.</e>
<cmt>January 5 をJanuary 12 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>元永元年（1118年）10月2日の「内大臣忠通歌合」などに参加するなど歌人として活発に活動していたらしく、『金葉和歌集』以下の勅撰和歌集に11首入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He actively participated as a poet in &apos;Naidaijin Tadamichi Uta-awase&apos; (Inner minister Tadamichi, poetry contest) on November 16, 1118 and had eleven poems in &quot;Kinyowakashu&quot; (Kinyo (Golden Leaves) Collection of Japanese poems), which was the Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He actively participated as a poet in &apos;Naidaijin Tadamichi Uta-awase&apos; (Inner minister Tadamichi, poetry contest) on November 16, 1118 and had eleven poems in &quot;Kinyowakashu&quot; (Kinyo (Golden Leaves) Collection of Japanese poems), which was the Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He actively participated as a poet in &apos;Naidaijin Tadamichi Uta-awase&apos; (poetry contest hosted by Minister of the Center, FUJIWARA no Tadamichi) on November 23, 1118 and had eleven poems in imperial anthologies of poetry in Japanese after &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot; (Kinyo (Golden Leaves) Collection of Japanese poems).</e>
<cmt>Inner minister Tadamichi, poetry contest をpoetry contest hosted by Minister of the Center, FUJIWARA no Tadamichi に修正しました。参考：http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=97Oe004BFvEC&amp;pg=PA249&amp;dq=utaawase+Tadamichi&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=utaawase%20Tadamichi&amp;f=false参考（ふじわらのただみち）：http://kotobank.jp/word/%E8%97%A4%E5%8E%9F%E5%BF%A0%E9%80%9ANovember 16 を November 23 に修正しました。『金葉和歌集』以下の「以下の」訳漏れによる誤訳のため、in &quot;Kinyowakashu&quot; (Kinyo (Golden Leaves) Collection of Japanese poems), which was the Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) をimperial anthologies of poetry in Japanese after &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot; (Kinyo (Golden Leaves) Collection of Japanese poems) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>漢詩にも優れていたとされるが、現在伝わっているのは『和漢兼作集』の2篇のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He supposedly excelled in Chinese-style poem as well, but there were only two sections in &quot;Wakankensakushu&quot; (Japanese and Chinese Poetry Collection) that remains until today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He supposedly excelled in Chinese-style poetry as well, but only two sections in &quot;Wakankensakushu&quot; (Japanese and Chinese Poetry Collection) remain until today.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He supposedly excelled in Chinese poetry as well, but there were only two sections in &quot;Wakankensakushu&quot; (Japanese and Chinese Poetry Collection) that remains until today.</e>
<cmt>Chinese-style poem をChinese poetry に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), Snap55(id:89773), Ks8823(id:130146), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>