<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>隆尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuson</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuson</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuson</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>隆尊（りゅうそん、慶雲3年（706年） - 天平宝字4年4月18日 (旧暦)（760年6月9日）は、奈良時代の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuson (706 - June 9, 760) was a priest in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuson (706-June 9, 760) was a priest in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン前後のスペース削除前後のスペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuson (706-June 9, 760) was a priest in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>義淵に師事して法相・華厳の教学を学び、はじめ元興寺に住し、のちに興福寺に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuson learned the doctrines of Hosso (Faxiang) and Kegon (Avatamsaka; Flower Garland) under Gien and he first lived in Gango-ji Temple, then moved to Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuson learned the doctrines of Hosso (Faxiang) and Kegon (Avatamsaka; Flower Garland) under Gien, and he first lived in Gango-ji Temple, then moved to Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>コンマ挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuson learned the doctrines of Hosso (Faxiang) and Kegon (Avatamsaka; Flower Garland) under Gien, and he first lived in Gango-ji Temple, then moved to Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正しく授戒できる師の日本への招聘を舎人親王に建議し、733年（天平5年）栄叡・普照を中国の唐に派遣して道セン・鑑真らの来日のきっかけをつくったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He proposed Imperial Prince Toneri to invite some Chinese priests who could formally hand down the precepts, sending Yoei and Fusho to Tang in 733, which presumably lead to the coming of Dosen and Jianzhen to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He proposed Imperial Prince Toneri to invite some Chinese priests who could formally hand down the precepts and sent Yoei and Fusho to Tang in 733, which presumably led to the coming of Dosen and Jianzhen to Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文から判断し、sentに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He proposed Imperial Prince Toneri to invite some Chinese priests who could formally hand down the precepts and sent Yoei and Fusho to Tang in 733, which presumably led to the coming of Dosen and Jianzhen to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>751年（天平勝宝3年）律師に任じられ、翌752年（天平勝宝4年）の東大寺大仏開眼供養では華厳講師をつとめたが、755年（天平勝宝7年）律師を辞任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuson was appointed Risshi (the second highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the third highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 751, and in the next year (752), on the occasion of the ceremony to consecrate the Great Buddha at Todai-ji Temple he acted as a Kegon Lecturer, but he resigned the position of Risshi in 755.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuson was appointed Risshi (the second highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the third highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 751, and on the occasion of the ceremony to consecrate the Great Buddha at Todai-ji Temple in 752, he acted as Kegon Lecturer, but he resigned the position of Risshi in 755.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、語順変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuson was appointed Risshi (the second highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the third highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 751, and on the occasion of the ceremony to consecrate the Great Buddha at Todai-ji Temple in 752, he acted as Kegon Lecturer, but he resigned the position of Risshi in 755.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>