<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原安子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Anshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Anshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Anshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 安子（ふじわら の あんし（やすいこ）、延長 (日本)5年（927年） - 応和4年4月29日_(旧暦)（964年6月11日））は、右大臣藤原師輔の長女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Anshi (Yasuiko) (927-June 11, 964) was the eldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who had the title of Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Anshi (Yasuiko) (927-June 11, 964) was the eldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who held the title of Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Anshi (Yasuiko) (927-June 16, 964) was the eldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who held the title of Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>新暦を採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>母は藤原経邦女盛子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Moriko, who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Tsunekuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Moriko, who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Tsunekuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was FUJIWARA no Moriko, who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Tsunekuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第62代村上天皇中宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the Chugu (the Empress) of the Sixty-Second Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the Chugu (the Empress) of the Sixty-Second Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the Chugu (the Empress) of the Sixty-Second Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>第63代冷泉天皇・第64代円融天皇、為平親王、選子内親王生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the birth mother of the Sixty-Third Emperor Reizei, Sixty-Fourth Emperor Enyu, Imperial Prince Tamehira, and Imperial Princess Senshi (Nobuko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the birth mother of the Sixty-Third Emperor Reizei, Sixty-Fourth Emperor Enyu, Imperial Prince Tamehira, and Imperial Princess Senshi (Nobuko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the birth mother of the Sixty-Third Emperor Reizei, Sixty-Fourth Emperor Enyu, Imperial Prince Tamehira, and Imperial Princess Senshi (Nobuko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同母兄弟に藤原伊尹・藤原兼通・藤原兼家、藤原登子（重明親王妃）・藤原ふ子（冷泉天皇女御）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her maternal siblings included, FUJIWARA no Koretada (Koremasa), FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, FUJIWARA no Kaneie, FUJIWARA no TOSHI (Nariko) (imperial princess to Imperial Prince Shigeakira), and FUJIWARA no Fushi (Nyogo (imperial consort) of Emperor Reizei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her maternal siblings included, FUJIWARA no Koretada (Koremasa), FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, FUJIWARA no Kaneie, FUJIWARA no TOSHI (Nariko) (imperial princess to Imperial Prince Shigeakira), and FUJIWARA no Fushi (Nyogo (imperial consort) of Emperor Reizei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her maternal siblings included, FUJIWARA no Koretada (Koremasa), FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, FUJIWARA no Kaneie, FUJIWARA no Toshi (Nariko) (imperial princess to Imperial Prince Shigeakira), and FUJIWARA no Fushi (Nyogo (imperial consort) of Emperor Reizei).</e>
<cmt>T以下の大文字を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>天慶3年（940年）、成明親王（村上天皇）に入内。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She underwent Judai (marriage to the imperial court) to the Imperial Prince Nariakira (Emperor Murakami) in 940.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She underwent Judai (marriage to the imperial court) to the Imperial Prince Nariakira (Emperor Murakami) in 940.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She underwent Judai (marriage to the imperial court) to the Imperial Prince Nariakira (Emperor Murakami) in 940.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>内裏の飛香舎で婚儀を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She held her wedding ceremony in Higyosha of the Dairi (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She held her wedding ceremony in Higyosha of the Dairi (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She held her wedding ceremony in Higyosha of the Dairi (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同7年（944年）成明親王が立坊、皇太子妃となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Nariakira underwent Ritsubo (investiture of the Crown Prince), and she became the crown princess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Nariakira underwent Ritsubo (investiture of the Crown Prince), and she became the crown princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Nariakira underwent Ritsubo (investiture of the Crown Prince), and she became the crown princess in 944.</e>
<cmt>年号を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同8年（945年）、従五位上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She received the Jo rank (imperial court rank) of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She received the Jo rank (imperial court rank) of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She received the Jo rank (imperial court rank) of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同9年（946年）従四位下に進み、村上天皇即位で従三位・女御となり昭陽舎に局を賜る。（のち飛香舎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was promoted to the Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) rank in 946 and received the residence at Shoyosha (later at Higyosha) when she became the Nyogo with the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) when Emperor Murakami succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was promoted to the Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) rank in 946 and received the residence at Shoyosha (later at Higyosha) when she became the Nyogo with the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) when Emperor Murakami succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was promoted to the Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) rank in 946 and received the residence at Shoyosha (later at Higyosha) when she became the Nyogo with the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) when Emperor Murakami succeeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天暦4年（950年）第二皇子憲平親王（冷泉天皇）を出産、生後二ヶ月で皇太子に立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gave birth to the second crown prince, Imperial Prince Norihira (Emperor Reizei) in 950, and he was promoted as imperial prince at the age of two months (in later Higyosha).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to the second crown prince, Imperial Prince Norihira (Emperor Reizei) in 950, and he was promoted as imperial prince at the age of two months (in later Higyosha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gave birth to the second crown prince, Imperial Prince Norihira (Emperor Reizei) in 950, and he was promoted as imperial prince at the age of two months.</e>
<cmt>(in later Higyosha) を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同10年（956年）従二位に進み、天徳 (日本)2年（958年）中宮に冊立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was promoted to Junii Rank (Junior Second Rank) in 956 and Chugu in 958.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was promoted to Junii Rank (Junior Second Rank) in 956 and Chugu in 958.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was promoted to Junii Rank (Junior Second Rank) in 956 and Chugu in 958.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>応和4年（964年）、選子内親王を出産後間もなく主殿寮にて崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just after she gave birth to Imperial Princess Senshi, she passed away in Tonomoryo (Shudenryo) (Bureau of Palace Equipment) in 964.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just after she gave birth to Imperial Princess Senshi, she passed away in Tonomoryo (Shudenryo) (Bureau of Palace Equipment) in 964.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just after she gave birth to Imperial Princess Senshi, she passed away in Tonomoryo (Shudenryo) (Bureau of Palace Equipment) in 964.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>享年38。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died at the age of thirty-eight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died at the age of thirty-eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of thirty-eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>のち康保4年（967年）冷泉天皇即位で皇太后を、さらに安和2年（969年）円融天皇即位で太皇太后を追贈される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor Reizei succeeded to the throne, she was given the posthumous title of Empress Dowager in 967 and the Grand Empress Dowager title with the accession of Emperor Enyu in 969.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Emperor Reizei succeeded the throne, she was given the posthumous title of Empress Dowager in 967 and the Grand Empress Dowager title with the accession of Emperor Enyu in 969.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Emperor Reizei succeeded the throne, she was given the posthumous title of Empress Dowager in 967 and the Grand Empress Dowager title with the accession of Emperor Enyu in 969.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>村上天皇即位前に入内した最初の妃であり、また皇太子憲平親王を始めとして妃のうちで最も多い三男四女をもうけたことから、天皇に非常に重んじられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since she was the first wife that underwent Judai before Emperor Murakami ascended to the throne and gave birth to the most number of children among imperial princesses, with three sons and four daughters starting with Imperial prince Norihira that she was greatly valued by the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since she was the first wife that underwent Judai before Emperor Murakami ascended the throne and gave birth to the most number of children among imperial princesses, with three sons and four daughters starting with Imperial prince Norihira, she was greatly valued by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since she was the first wife that underwent Judai before Emperor Murakami ascended the throne and gave birth to the most number of children among imperial princesses, with three sons and four daughters starting with Imperial prince Norihira, she was greatly valued by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし『大鏡』によれば非常に嫉妬深い性格で、後に天皇の寵愛を受けた宣耀殿女御藤原芳子（安子の従姉妹）の姿を垣間見した時にはあまりの美しさに妬心やみがたく、壁の穴から土器（かわらけ）の欠片を投げつけるという暴挙に出たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she had a personality of a person who became deeply jealous, and had a grudge over the beauty of FUJIWARA no Hoshi (Yoshiko) (the cousin of Anshi), who had the title of Senyoden no nyogo and later received the affection of the emperor, when she peeked that she used violence of throwing the piece of pottery through the hole in a wall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she had a deeply jealous personality, and held a grudgee over the beauty of FUJIWARA no Hoshi (Yoshiko) (the cousin of Anshi), who had the title of Senyoden no nyogo and later received the affection of the emperor. Such was her jealously that when she spied the emperor giving his affection to FUJIWARA no Hoshi, she threw a piece of pottery through a hole in the wall in a fit of violence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she had a deeply jealous personality, and held a grudge over the beauty of FUJIWARA no Hoshi (Yoshiko) (the cousin of Anshi), who had the title of Senyoden no nyogo and later received the affection of the emperor. Such was her jealously that when she spied the emperor giving his affection to FUJIWARA no Hoshi, she threw a piece of pottery through a hole in the wall in a fit of violence.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかもそれに立腹した天皇が安子の兄弟らに謹慎を命じると、天皇に詰めよってついに撤回させてしまったというから、話半分としても気性の激しい女性だったようであり、また皇太子の生母としての彼女の影響力の大きさが伺える。（なお、この土器投げの逸話は岡野玲子の漫画『陰陽師』に登場する）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, when she was ordered to go under penitence to the siblings of Anshi by emperor angered by it, she went up to the emperor and made him take down that order that it could be seen that she was a person with a big temper and also showed her influential power as the birth mother of the imperial prince (This pottery throwing anecdote made appearance in manga of Reiko OKANO, &quot;Onmyoji&quot; (diviner and shaman)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, when she was ordered to go under penitence to the siblings of Anshi by emperor angered by it, she went up to the emperor and made him take down that order that it could be seen that she was a person with a big temper and also showed her influential power as the birth mother of the imperial prince (This pottery throwing anecdote made appearance in manga of Reiko OKANO, &quot;Onmyoji&quot; [diviner and shaman]).</e>
<cmt>Robert: Doesn&apos;t make sense (when she was ordered to go under penitence to the sibilings of Anshi by emperor..)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, when she found out that the angry emperor asked her brothers to make her behave, she went up to the emperor and made him take down that order that it could be seen that she was a person with a big temper and also showed her influential power as the birth mother of the imperial prince (This pottery throwing anecdote made appearance in manga of Reiko OKANO, &quot;Onmyoji&quot; [diviner and shaman]).</e>
<cmt>内容修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>安子自身は若くして亡くなったが、安子所生の冷泉天皇・円融天皇の即位は九条流摂関家発展の元となり、やがて安子の甥藤原道長を頂点とする全盛期へ至ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anshi herself died early, but the accession of Emperors Reizei and Enyu, who were born from Anshi became the foundation for the development of the line of regents and advisors of the Kujo School and led to the prosperous period with the niece of Anshi, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, as the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anshi herself died early, but the accession of Emperors Reizei and Enyu, who were born from Anshi became the foundation for the development of the line of regents and advisors of the Kujo School and led to the prosperous period with the niece of Anshi, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, as head.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anshi herself died early, but the accession of Emperors Reizei and Enyu, who were born from Anshi became the foundation for the development of the line of regents and advisors of the Kujo School and led to the prosperous period with the niece of Anshi, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, as head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>陵墓は宇治陵（京都府宇治市木幡中村）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mausoleum is located in Uji no misasagi (Kobata Nakamura, Uji city, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mausoleum is located in Uji no misasagi (Kobata Nakamura, Uji city, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mausoleum is located in Uji no misasagi (Kobata Nakamura, Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>city を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Yukichi99(id:29402), Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 栗花落(id:96208), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>