<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原通基 (侍従)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michimoto (Jiju (a chamberlain))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michimoto (Jiju (a chamberlain))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michimoto (Jiju (a chamberlain))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 通基（ふじわら の みちもと、治安_(元号)元年（1021年） - 長久元年12月8日_(旧暦)（1041年1月13日））は、平安時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michimoto (1021-January 13, 1041) was a Court noble in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michimoto (1021-January 13, 1041) was a Court noble in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michimoto (1021-January 13, 1041) was a Court noble in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原教通の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child of FUJIWARA no Norimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a child of FUJIWARA no Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a child of FUJIWARA no Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原公任の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>教通の父・藤原道長の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted as a son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, father of Norimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted as a son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, father of Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted as a son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, father of Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>初名は信基（のぶもと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Nobumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Nobumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Nobumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>『小右記』長元5年11月26日_(旧暦)（1032年12月31日）条に実弟の藤原信長とともに元服し、藤原頼宗が加冠務めた事が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 31, 1032 entry of &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) described that he celebrated his attainment of manhood with his own younger brother FUJIWARA no Nobunaga and FUJIWARA no Yorimune played the role of Kakan (to place a crown on the head of boys).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 31, 1032 entry of &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) described that he celebrated his attainment of manhood with his own younger brother FUJIWARA no Nobunaga, and FUJIWARA no Yorimune played the role of Kakan (one to place a crown on the head of boys).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 31, 1032 entry of &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (The Diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) described that he celebrated his attainment of manhood with his own younger brother FUJIWARA no Nobunaga, and FUJIWARA no Yorimune played the role of Kakan (one to place a crown on the head of boys).</e>
<cmt>the diary→The Diary</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この際、信長は従五位下に叙せられたのに対して、信基は故入道相府の戸に入っている（4年前に死去した道長の戸籍に入っている。つまり養子関係にある）ために従五位上に叙せられた事が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, while Nobunaga was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Nobumoto was, as described, promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, while Nobunaga was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Nobumoto was, as described, promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, while Nobunaga was promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Nobumoto was, as described, promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) because Nobumoto was in the family register of late Nyudosofu (He was in the family register of Michinaga, who had died four years before; that is, they were united by adoptive ties).</e>
<cmt>次のセルと統合しました。ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌年1月の除目で侍従に任ぜられ、途中で伊予国国司・春宮権亮を兼務するも死ぬまでこの職にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed Jiju at the time of Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) in January next year and kept this position until his death although he was appointed, at some period as additional posts, Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Iyo Province and Togu gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed Jiju at the time of Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) in January of the next year and kept this position until his death, although he was appointed, at some period to additional posts, Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Iyo Province and Togu gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed Jiju at the time of Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) in February of the next year and kept this position until his death, although he was appointed, at some period to additional posts, Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Iyo Province and Togu gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters).</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>長元8年（1035年）に通基と改名し、長暦3年（1039年）には従三位、同年中に正三位には叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed his name to Michimoto in 1035 and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1039 and within the same year to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his name to Michimoto in 1035 and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1039 and within the same year to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his name to Michimoto in 1035 and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1039 and within the same year to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、病弱で血を吐く病にかかっていたとされ、長久元年にわずか20歳の若さで病没してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he is understood to have been in delicate health and affected by a disease of vomiting blood, and died young at the age of 20 in 1040.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he is understood to have been in delicate health and affected by a disease of vomiting blood, and died young at the age of 20 in 1040.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he is understood to have been in delicate health and affected by a disease of vomiting blood, and died young at the age of 20 in 1041.</e>
<cmt>1040→1041</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>