<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源光経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mitsutsune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Mitsutsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mitsutsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 光経（みなもと の みつつね、生年不詳 - 寿永2年11月19日 (旧暦)（1184年1月3日））は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mitsutsune (unknown date of birth - January 3, 1184) is a samurai in the closing years of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Mitsutsune (year of birth unknown - January 10, 1184) is a samurai in the closing years of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>生年不詳 　 year of birth unknown 用語統一リストより訂正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mitsutsune (year of birth unknown - January 10, 1184) is a samurai in the closing years of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伯耆国守源光長の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A second son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaga, Hoki no kuni no kami (Governor of Hoki Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A second son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaga, Hoki no kuni no kami (Governor of Hoki Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A second son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaga, Hoki no kuni no kami (Governor of Hoki Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄弟に源国長、源光衡があり、子に光房（八条院蔵人）、長沢光助（出羽国守）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brothers include MINAMOTO no Kuninaga and MINAMOTO no Mitsuhira, and his children include Mitsufusa (Hachijoin Kurodo) and Mitsusuke NAGASAWA (Dewa no kuni no kami (Governor of Dewa Province)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older brothers include MINAMOTO no Kuninaga and MINAMOTO no Mitsuhira, and his children include Mitsufusa (Hachijoin Kurodo) and Mitsusuke NAGASAWA (Dewa no kuni no kami [Governor of Dewa Province]).</e>
<cmt>olderに訂正しました。括弧内括弧を[]に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brothers include MINAMOTO no Kuninaga and MINAMOTO no Mitsuhira, and his children include Mitsufusa (Hachijoin Kurodo) and Mitsusuke NAGASAWA (Dewa no kuni no kami [Governor of Dewa Province]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>美濃源氏土岐氏の棟梁であった父光長と共に在京し、検非違使、左衛門尉を務めたとされる（『尊卑分脈』）が、寿永2年（1184年）の法住寺合戦で父が後白河院方に加わったため光経もこれに従い、死闘の末に父と共に討ち取られ梟首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is recorded in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) that he resided in Kyoto together with his father Mitsunaga, who was the family head of the Toki clan of Mino Genji, and assumed such titles as Kebiishi Saemon no Jo (third-ranked officer with judicial and police powers in the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), and when his father sided with the army of Goshirakawain in the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple in 1184, he also accompanied his father and fought together in a fierce battle, but he and his father were killed in action and their heads were exposed to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recorded in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) that he resided in Kyoto together with his father Mitsunaga, who was the family head of the Toki clan of Mino-Genji (Minamoto clan), and assumed such titles as Kebiishi Saemon no Jo (third-ranked officer with judicial and police powers in the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), and when his father sided with the army of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa in the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple in 1184, he also accompanied his father and fought together in a fierce battle, but he and his father were killed in action and their heads were exposed to the public.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足しました。(Minamoto clan)補足しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。the Retired Emperor Goshirakawaに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recorded in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) that he resided in Kyoto together with his father Mitsunaga, who was the family head of the Toki clan of Mino-Genji (Minamoto clan), and assumed such titles as Kebiishi Saemon no Jo (third-ranked officer with judicial and police powers in the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), and when his father sided with the army of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa in the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple in 1184, he also accompanied his father and fought together in a fierce battle, but he and his father were killed in action and their heads were exposed to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>後代、次男光助が越中国長沢に居住したことからその子孫が長沢氏として存続し、戦国時代 (日本)には長沢光国などを輩出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsutsune&apos;s second son Mitsusuke later resided in Nagasawa, Ecchu Province, and continued his family line by the name of Nagasawa, and Mitsukuni NAGASAWA was one of the known descendants who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsutsune&apos;s second son Mitsusuke later resided in Nagasawa, Ecchu Province, and continued his family line by the name of Nagasawa, and Mitsukuni NAGASAWA was one of the known descendants who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsutsune&apos;s second son Mitsusuke later resided in Nagasawa, Ecchu Province, and continued his family line by the name of Nagasawa, and Mitsukuni NAGASAWA was one of the known descendants who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 花梨0921(id:214821), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>