<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豊原国周</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunichika TOYOHARA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunichika TOYOHARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunichika TOYOHARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豊原 国周（とよはら くにちか、天保6年（1835年） - 明治33年（1900年））は幕末から明治にかけての浮世絵師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunichika TOYOHARA (1835-1900) was an ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints) artist who lived from the end of Edo period to Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunichika TOYOHARA (1835 - 1900) was an ukiyo-e (Japanese woodblock prints) artist who lived from the end of Edo period to Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>浮世絵はwikipediaでも「ukiyo-e」としていますので、そのように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunichika TOYOHARA (1835 - 1900) was an ukiyo-e (Japanese woodblock prints) artist who lived from the end of Edo period to Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は荒川氏、俗称は八十八。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His main name was Arakawa, and he went by the familiar name of Yasoya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His main name was Arakawa, and he went by the familiar name of Yasoya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His main name was Arakawa, and he went by the familiar name of Yasoya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸京橋五郎兵衛町の湯屋（一説には江戸京橋三十間堀七丁目の家主）大島屋九十の二人兄弟の次男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the second son of one of the two brothers who operated a bathhouse called Tsuku Oshimaya in Gorocho of the Kyobashi district in Edo (in one theory, it is said that the brothers were the landlords of a building located at 7-chome in Sanjikkenbori of the same district).</e>
<cmt>「大島屋九十」の読みが確認できませんでした。「八十八」で「やそや」と読むことを考えれば、「つく」と読む可能性が高いと思います。また、「二人兄弟」とあるように、どちらの子供か確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as one of the two brothers, and as the second son of Tsuku Oshimaya who operated a bathhouse called Tsuku Oshimaya in Gorocho of the Kyobashi district in Edo (some mentions that the family was the landlord of a building located at 7-chome in Sanjikkenbori of the same district).</e>
<cmt>コメントにもあるように、「大島屋九十の二人兄弟の次男として生まれる」の意味がはっきりとはわかりません。「大島屋九十には二人兄弟の息子がおり、その次男が国周である、という意味と考えました。そうすると訳は間違っていることになります。括弧内の説明について簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as one of the two brothers, and as the second son of Tsuku Oshimaya who operated a bathhouse called Tsuku Oshimaya in Gorocho of the Kyobashi district in Edo (some mentions that the family was the landlord of a building located at 7-chome in Sanjikkenbori of the same district).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は同心荒川三之丞娘、八重。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Yae, the daughter of doshin police constable Sannojo ARAKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Yae, the daughter of doshin police constable Sannojo ARAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Yae, the daughter of doshin police constable Sannojo ARAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>画号は国周の他、一鶯斎、豊春楼、花(華)蝶楼、一桃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Kunichika, his artist&apos;s appellation included Ichiosai, Hoshunro, Kachoro and Itto.</e>
<cmt>「一鶯斎、豊春楼、花(華)蝶楼」、「一桃」については信頼に足るソースが確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Kunichika, his artist&apos;s appellation included Ichiosai, Hoshunro, Kachoro and Itto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Kunichika, his artist&apos;s appellation included Ichiosai, Hoshunro, Kachoro and Itto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>画姓を豊原とした経緯は豊原周信への恩を忘れぬためだといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he came to choose TOYOHARA for his main name as an artist so he could always remember the debt of gratitude he owed to Chikanobu TOYOHARA.</e>
<cmt>「豊原周信」は富山市のHPを参考にしています。 http://www.city.toyama.toyama.jp/shisetu/bunka/html/tayori/tayori16/tayori16.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he came to choose TOYOHARA for his main artist name in order to always remember the debt of gratitude he owed to Chikanobu TOYOHARA.</e>
<cmt>「It is believed」は強すぎます。修正しました。冗長な部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he came to choose TOYOHARA for his main artist name in order to always remember the debt of gratitude he owed to Chikanobu TOYOHARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>幼い頃はかなりやんちゃで近所から苦情が来ていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was small, he was so mischievous that he drew complaints from his neighbors.</e>
<cmt>「やんちゃ」の度合いが不明ですが、mischievousを使用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was small, he was so mischievous that he drew complaints from his neighbors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was small, he was so mischievous that he drew complaints from his neighbors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、びら屋で祭礼の際に用いられる地口行灯（もとの言葉を別のものに仕立てて楽しむ言語遊戯、つまりは語呂合わせである地口を、絵で行灯に描いてある。祭礼時に町の辻に飾ることが流行し、その絵の多くが浮世絵師によって描かれた）制作の手伝いをするなど、画才を示していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he already showed his promising talent in painting by helping a biraya flyer shop to make andon oil lampstands for ceremonial occasions known as &quot;jiguchi andon,&quot; which were decorated with pun-motif illustrations (illustrations inspired by puns, a form of word play in which one finds different meanings in word pairs that sound alike [jiguchi puns], were featured on andon lampstands. Installing these andons at crossroads during festivals became widespread, and many of these illustrations were drawn by ukiyoe artists).</e>
<cmt>「びら屋」の定訳が見つからなかったため、「びらを作る店」という理解で&quot;bira flyer shop&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he already showed his promising talent in painting by helping a flyer shop to make andon oil lamp stands for ceremonial occasions known as &quot;jiguchi andon,&quot; which were decorated with pun-motif illustrations (illustrations inspired by puns, a form of word play in which one finds different meanings in word pairs that sound alike [jiguchi puns], were featured on andon lamp stands. Installing these andons at crossroads during festivals became widespread, and many of these illustrations were drawn by ukiyo-e artists).</e>
<cmt>びら屋の訳は二重訳だと思いますので、びらは削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he already showed his promising talent in painting by helping a flyer shop to make andon oil lamp stands for ceremonial occasions known as &quot;jiguchi andon,&quot; which were decorated with pun-motif illustrations (illustrations inspired by puns, a form of word play in which one finds different meanings in word pairs that sound alike [jiguchi puns], were featured on andon lamp stands. Installing these andons at crossroads during festivals became widespread, and many of these illustrations were drawn by ukiyo-e artists).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>兄の長吉が南伝馬町に押絵屋を開業したことがきっかけで、長谷川派の豊原周信に師事し役者似顔を学び、羽子板押絵の原図を制作した（一説には羽子板師・に就いたとも言われる)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his older brother, Nagoyoshi, opened an oshi-e raised cloth picture shop in the Minamidenmacho district, he studied under Chikanobu TOYOHARA, an artist of the Hasegawa school, to learn how to draw portraits of kabuki actors and went on to draw original paintings for hagoita battledores (one theory says that he took on a job at hagoita maker Rinshun&apos;s studio).</e>
<cmt>「押絵」は&quot;raised&quot;となっていますが、&quot;raised cloth picture&quot;としています。また、隣春の読みが確認できず、「りんしゅん」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his older brother, Nagoyoshi, opened an osier (raised cloth picture) shop in the Minamidenmacho district, Kunichika studied under the artist of the Hasegawa school Chikanobu TOYOHARA to learn how to draw portraits of kabuki actors; he went on to draw original paintings for hagoita battledores (some says that he took on a job at hagoita maker Rinshun&apos;s studio).</e>
<cmt>押絵の解説は括弧に含めました。国周の兄の名前が出た直後の「he」は誰を指すか混乱しますので、国周の名を記述しました。羽子板ーの原画製作の部分は分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his older brother, Nagoyoshi, opened an osier (raised cloth picture) shop in the Minamidenmacho district, Kunichika studied under the artist of the Hasegawa school Chikanobu TOYOHARA to learn how to draw portraits of kabuki actors; he went on to draw original paintings for hagoita battledores (some says that he took on a job at hagoita maker Rinshun&apos;s studio).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>数奇屋河岸にあった羽子板問屋明林堂の仕事を引き受け、その役者絵は評判が良かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took on a job at hagoita warehouse merchant Meirindo near Sukiya kashi riverbank area, and was believed to have enjoyed a reputation for his portraits of kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took on a job at hagoita warehouse merchant Meirindo near Sukiya kashi riverbank area; it is said that his portraits of kabuki actors were highly appreciated.</e>
<cmt>「評判が良かったという」の訳は意訳されています。間違いではないでしょうが原文にあわせ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took on a job at hagoita warehouse merchant Meirindo near Sukiya kashi riverbank area; it is said that his portraits of kabuki actors were highly appreciated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>国周の墓所である本龍寺には、現存してはいないが、押絵師湯川周丸を発起人とした国周の辞世句「よの中の人の似かおもあきたれば　ゑむまや鬼の生きうつしせむ」を刻んだ碑があったといわれるので、終生、羽子板絵とのかかわりが保たれたのだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he had been connected with hagoita illustrations all through his life because there used to be a stone monument inscribed with Kunichika&apos;s death poem at Honryu-ji Temple that read &quot;Now that I am tired of drawing portraits of every day people, I could try drawing portrayals of Enma lord of death and oni ogres,&quot;which was founded at the initiative of oshie painter Kanemaru YUKAWA.</e>
<cmt>「本龍寺」は「ほんりゅうじ」、「ゑむま」は&quot;Enma lord of death&quot;、また「鬼」は&quot;oni ogres&quot;としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His connection with hagoita illustration appeared to be maintained throughout his life, because it is assumed there used to be a stone monument inscribed with Kunichika&apos;s death poem at Honryu-ji Temple that read &quot;Now that I am tired of drawing portraits of every day people, I could try drawing portrayals of Enma lord of death and oni ogres,&quot; which was founded at the initiative of oshi-e painter Kanemaru YUKAWA.</e>
<cmt>英文としての言い回しが一般的でないものを修正しています。なお、この原文で意味内容が伝わるかどうか疑問です。この辞世句が彫られた石碑があったら何故羽子板絵との関わりが保たれたと言えるのでしょうか？その説明がこれではわからないため、直訳せざるを得ず、訳文も意味が伝わらないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His connection with hagoita illustration appeared to be maintained throughout his life, because it is assumed there used to be a stone monument inscribed with Kunichika&apos;s death poem at Honryu-ji Temple that read &quot;Now that I am tired of drawing portraits of every day people, I could try drawing portrayals of Enma lord of death and oni ogres,&quot; which was founded at the initiative of oshi-e painter Kanemaru YUKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>嘉永元年(1848)に歌川国貞(三代豊国)に入門する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1848, he became a disciple of Kunisada UTAGAWA (who also referred to himself as Toyo-no-kuni III).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1848, he became a disciple of Kunisada UTAGAWA (who also referred to himself as Toyo-no-kuni III).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1848, he became a disciple of Kunisada UTAGAWA (who also referred to himself as Toyo-no-kuni III).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>嘉永5年(1852)に豊国の役者絵の一部を描き、門人八十八と署名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was helping Toyo-no-kuni to draw a portrait of kabuki actor in 1852, he signed his name as &quot;disciple Yasoya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「役者絵の一部」は単数、つまり１枚の絵だとして訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was helping Toyo-no-kuni to draw a portrait of kabuki actor in 1852, he signed his name as &quot;disciple Yasoya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was helping Toyo-no-kuni to draw a portrait of kabuki actor in 1852, he signed his name as &quot;disciple Yasoya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>安政2年(1855)頃より、最初の師である豊原周信と豊国の名前を合わせた画名である豊原国周と署名するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In or around 1855, he started using his artist appellation of Kunichika TOYOHARA for his signature, which combined the name of his first mentor, Chikanobu TOYOHARA, and Toyo-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In or around 1855, he started using his artist appellation of Kunichika TOYOHARA for his signature, which combined the name of his first mentor, Chikanobu TOYOHARA, and Toyo-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In or around 1855, he started using his artist appellation of Kunichika TOYOHARA for his signature, which combined the name of his first mentor, Chikanobu TOYOHARA, and Toyo-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明治2年(1869)、人形町具足屋嘉兵衛を版元にし、彫工太田升吉による役者似顔大首絵を多数制作し、力量を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, he demonstrated his skills by producing a large series of okubie &quot;large-head&quot; pictures of Kabuki actors using woodprints prepared by woodcrafter Shokichi OTA, with armor maker Kahei GUSOKUYA in Ningyocho district publishing his works.</e>
<cmt>「升吉」の読みが確認できなかったため、「しょうきち」としています。また、「具足屋嘉兵衛」は「具足屋」を屋号ならびに名字として使用していると考えて処理いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, he demonstrated his skills by producing a large series of okubi-e (large-head pictures) of Kabuki actors with woodcrafter Shokichi OTA, and armor maker Kahei GUSOKUYA in Ningyocho district as publisher.</e>
<cmt>大首絵の解説は括弧内に移しました。冗長になっていた部分を省略、簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, he demonstrated his skills by producing a large series of okubi-e (large-head pictures) of Kabuki actors with woodcrafter Shokichi OTA, and armor maker Kahei GUSOKUYA in Ningyocho district as publisher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このシリーズにより「役者絵の国周」として知られるようになり、後世、小島烏水によって「明治の写楽」と称せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became known as &quot;Kunichika of Kabuki actor prints&quot; with the series, which later earned him the moniker of &quot;Sharaku in Meiji period&quot; from Usui KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>「小島烏水」は「こじま・うすい」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became known as &quot;Kunichika of Kabuki actor prints&quot; with the series, which later earned him the moniker of &quot;Sharaku in Meiji period&quot; from Usui KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became known as &quot;Kunichika of Kabuki actor prints&quot; with the series, which later earned him the moniker of &quot;Sharaku in Meiji period&quot; from Usui KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>翌二年には大橋屋弥七から似顔大首絵を2枚、3枚続にした作品を出版した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, he released a series of okubie pictures, each of which came in a set of two or three panels from publisher Yashichi OHASHIYA.</e>
<cmt>「翌二年」とありますが、前々列でも「明治2年」とあり、「翌年」なのか「明治2年」なのか判別がつきません。ここでは「翌年」としています。また、「大橋屋弥七」の読みは「おおはしや・やしち」とし、版元だとしています。また、「枚続」の定訳が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, he released a series of okubi-e pictures from publisher Yashichi OHASHIYA, each of which came in a set of two or three panels.</e>
<cmt>青字部分の語順を内容に合う形に変えています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, he released a series of okubi-e pictures from publisher Yashichi OHASHIYA, each of which came in a set of two or three panels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>後年は伝統的な役者似顔絵の七分身像を多く描き、3枚続の画面に一人立ちの半身役者絵を描く大胆な構図の作品なども描いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years, he produced many prints of Kabuki actors in the traditional style showing 70 percent of their bodies, and he also painted half-length Kabuki actor portraits in the set of three panels, taking to the daring composition featuring a single actor standing alone.</e>
<cmt>「七分身像」「半身役者絵」の定訳が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, he produced many prints of Kabuki actors depicted in the traditional three-quarter view style, while he also painted Kabuki actor portraits in a daring composition, featuring a single actor standing alone in waist and up view within the set of three panels.</e>
<cmt>七分身像は「three-quarter image」で、斜めから見たの意味です。また、半身の部分の訳の修正を行いました。その他語順の変更など（青字）を行い読みやすい文章にしています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, he produced many prints of Kabuki actors depicted in the traditional three-quarter view style, while he also painted Kabuki actor portraits in a daring composition, featuring a single actor standing alone in waist and up view within the set of three panels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>顔貌描写に羽子板絵式の装飾味を持たせ、美人画にも独特のはれやかさを示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He demonstrated his unique style of gorgeousness in his bijinga pictures of beautiful women by adding decorative elements found in hagoita battledores on top of detailed portrayal of facial expressions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He demonstrated a unique flamboyant quality in his bijin-ga (pictures of beautiful women) by adding decorative elements found in hagoita battledores on top of the detailed portrayal of facial expressions.</e>
<cmt>はれやかさの訳を、「gorgeousness」から「flamboyant」としました。美人画の説明を括弧に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He demonstrated a unique flamboyant quality in his bijin-ga (pictures of beautiful women) by adding decorative elements found in hagoita battledores on top of the detailed portrayal of facial expressions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>写真の流行する時代の影響を受け、明治3年（1870）に「写真所」と題した役者のブロマイドがあり、陰影法を用いた木版画を制作したが成功しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influenced by the popularity of photography in his time, there were commercial photographic portraits of Kabuki actors known as &quot;shashinjo&quot; photo studio in 1870, upon which he produced woodblock prints using the shadow method, only to be proven unsuccessful.</e>
<cmt>ブロマイドは一般的に流通していたという理解で訳しています。また、「写真所」はフォトスタジオと補足しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influenced by the popularity of photography in his time, there were commercial photographic portraits publisher of Kabuki actors known as &quot;shashinjo&quot; photo studio in 1870, upon which he produced woodblock prints using the shadow method, only to be proven unsuccessful.</e>
<cmt>写真所の訳に関してですが、「photographic portraits of Kabuki actors know as〜」ですと写真そのものを指し、写真所につながりません。Photographic portraits publisherとしました。原文がまずい文章で、「この写真所と題された訳者のブロマイドが彼の制作した木版画なのか、この時代に既に人気のあったブロマイドなのか、判別できません。訳文で良いとの判断でそのままにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influenced by the popularity of photography in his time, there were commercial photographic portraits publisher of Kabuki actors known as &quot;shashinjo&quot; photo studio in 1870, upon which he produced woodblock prints using the shadow method, only to be proven unsuccessful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>国周の役者絵は、戊辰戦争を受けて不況となった歌舞伎界を盛り上げたともといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that Kunichika&apos;s portraits of Kabuki actors boosted the popularity of the Kabuki community which had been suffered a slump caused by the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that Kunichika&apos;s portraits of Kabuki actors helped boosting the popularity of the Kabuki community, which had suffered a slump because of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>「歌舞伎界を盛り上げた」の訳を修正しました。「had been suffered」は「had suffered」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that Kunichika&apos;s portraits of Kabuki actors helped boosting the popularity of the Kabuki community, which had suffered a slump because of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>国周の門人は多く存在したらしいが、活躍したのは周重と楊洲周延の二人のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Kunichika had many disciples, however, only Chikashige MORIKAWA and and Chikanobu YOSHU flourished as artists.</e>
<cmt>「周重」は「もりかわ・ちかしげ」出典：石川県立美術館http://www.ishibi.pref.ishikawa.jp/syozou/ukiyoehanga/sakka/sakuhin_list_sakka.php?Id=ko0080 「楊洲周延」は「ようしゅう・ちかのぶ」出典：太田記念美術館http://www.ukiyoe-ota-muse.jp/H2103%20chikanobu.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kunichika seemed to have many disciples, only Chikashige MORIKAWA and Chikanobu YOSHU flourished as well-known artists.</e>
<cmt>文中にhoweverを置くのを避け、文頭に同様の意味を持つalthoughを用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kunichika seemed to have many disciples, only Chikashige MORIKAWA and Chikanobu YOSHU flourished as well-known artists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>国周は自らも認めているほどの変わった性格をしていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Kunichika had such a peculiar personality that even he was aware of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kunichika had such a peculiar personality that even he was aware of it.</e>
<cmt>「〜という」の訳を訳者は「it is believed」としていますが、強すぎると思います。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kunichika had such a peculiar personality that even he was aware of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>住まいと妻を変えることが癖で、本人によると転居は117回であり、同じく転居の多かった北斎と比べ「絵は北斎には及ばないが、転居数では勝っている」と誇っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a habit of changing addresses and remarrying, and he once said he moved 117 times and reportedly took pride in comparing himself to Hokusai, who was also known for moving many times, saying &quot;I may not beat Hokusai in painting skills, but I beat him in the number of house-moving.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made a habit of changing addresses and remarrying, and he moved 117 times according to himself; he bragged about his moving comparing to Hokusai who was also known for moving many times by saying, &quot;I may not beat Hokusai in painting skills, but I beat him in the number of moving.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「he once said」と「reportedly took pride in comparing himself」は重複説明に近いと思います。一方を削除し簡略化しました。内容的に「誇る」というより冗談交じりですので、「brag about」を用いました。転居の「house-moving」を「moving」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made a habit of changing addresses and remarrying, and he moved 117 times according to himself; he bragged about his moving comparing to Hokusai who was also known for moving many times by saying, &quot;I may not beat Hokusai in painting skills, but I beat him in the number of moving.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>近所の空気が気に入らないといっては移転し、版元が絵を依頼しようとしても居所がわからず困ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that on several occasions he moved out of one place to another just because he did not like the air in the neighborhood, putting publishers who wanted to offer him a painting job into trouble because they couldn&apos;t find him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that on several occasions some publishers who wanted to commission a painting job had trouble finding his location because he constantly moved from one place to another just because he did not like the air in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>「〜という」の訳を訳者は「it is believed」としていますが、強すぎると思います。修正しました。冗長な訳文を簡略化しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that on several occasions some publishers who wanted to commission a painting job had trouble finding his location because he constantly moved from one place to another just because he did not like the air in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>「今日転居して来て、明日厭気がさすと直ぐ引越し、甚しい時は一日に三度転じたが、その三度目の家も気に入らなかったが、日が暮れて草臥れたので、是非なく思い止まった」という話まである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In one episode, he was quoted as saying: &quot;I once moved in to a place one day and move out of there the next day because I got sick of the place, and in an extreme case, even though I moved three times in a day I didn&apos;t like the third place, but I had no choice but to stay there because it was getting dark and I was too exhausted.&quot;</e>
<cmt>引用文は国周本人の言葉と理解して訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In one episode, he was quoted as saying, &quot;one day I moved into a place but move out of there the next day because I got sick of the place--in an extreme case, I moved three times in a day, and I simply had no choice but to stay at the third house even though I did not like it, because it was getting dark and I was too exhausted.&quot;</e>
<cmt>口語文の中にbutが繰り返されたり、ぎこちない訳になっています。読みやすい形に修正しました。語順がかなり変わっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In one episode, he was quoted as saying, &quot;one day I moved into a place but move out of there the next day because I got sick of the place--in an extreme case, I moved three times in a day, and I simply had no choice but to stay at the third house even though I did not like it, because it was getting dark and I was too exhausted.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>妻も40人余り変え、長続きすることは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed his spouse more than 40 times, but each of the marriages did not last long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his spouse more than 40 times, but each of the marriages did not last long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his spouse more than 40 times, but each of the marriages did not last long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>酒と遊びが大好きで、画料が入っても宵越しの金は持たないとばかりにすぐ使ってしまい、晩年は着物一枚で過ごし舞台に出る役者をスケッチする「中見」の際には版元から着物を貸してもらうほどだったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A drinker and pleasure-seeker, he spent money as soon as he earned, as if saying &quot;money is not something you keep overnight,&quot; and in his later years he only had one kimono to wear, and he reportedly had to ask publishers to lend him kimono when he was in the process of &quot;chuken,&quot; during which he sketched Kabuki actors performing on stage.</e>
<cmt>「中見」の読み方と定訳が確認できず、「ちゅうけん」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A drinker and pleasure-seeker, he spent money as soon as he earned, as if saying &quot;money is not something you keep overnight&quot;; in his later years he seems to have had only one kimono to wear, thus he had to ask publishers to lend him a kimono for doing &quot;nakami&quot; to sketch Kabuki actors appeared on stage.</e>
<cmt>中見はちゅうけんではなく「なかみ」ではないかと思います。文章が長く続くので、「；」で分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A drinker and pleasure-seeker, he spent money as soon as he earned, as if saying &quot;money is not something you keep overnight&quot;; in his later years he seems to have had only one kimono to wear, thus he had to ask publishers to lend him a kimono for doing &quot;nakami&quot; to sketch Kabuki actors appeared on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし、困っている人を見ると助けずにはいられず、時には来客のものまで与えてしまうという非常識ぶりを発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he couldn&apos;t help but helping people in need, and on several occasions he nonsensically gave them items that belonged to his visitors.</e>
<cmt>「時には」という状況が数回あったという理解で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still, he couldn&apos;t help but supporting people in need, and on several occasions he nonsensically gave them items that belonged to his visitors.</e>
<cmt>Butによる文章開始を避けました。内容は異なるにせよhelpが重なりますので、supportを用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still, he couldn&apos;t help but supporting people in need, and on several occasions he nonsensically gave them items that belonged to his visitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>このため、錦絵問屋の主人などは国周を訪問する際には高価なものを携帯することを避けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, operators of nishikie color woodblock print business and others reportedly decided not to bring anything valuable when they visited Kunichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, it is said that those dealers of Nishiki-e color woodblock print business did not bring any valuable when they visited Kunichika.</e>
<cmt>主人の訳を「operators」としていますが、不自然ですので「dealers」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, it is said that those dealers of Nishiki-e color woodblock print business did not bring any valuable when they visited Kunichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>国周の仕事ぶりをうかがわせるエピソードがあるのであわせて紹介する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is an episode that indicates how Kunichika worked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is an episode that indicates how Kunichika worked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is an episode that indicates how Kunichika worked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>福田という版元は芝居が好きで役者絵を多く出版していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A publisher called FUKUDA loved theater, and published many Kabuki actor portraits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A publisher called FUKUDA favored theatrical plays, and published many Kabuki actor portraits.</e>
<cmt>「好きで」をlovedとするのは間違いではないですが文章では避けました。また、芝居の訳は「theatrical plays」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A publisher called FUKUDA favored theatrical plays, and published many Kabuki actor portraits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>あるとき、国周が団十郎(九代目)の姿を描いた版画の本になる下絵が、団十郎に検査してもらったときに無くなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One time, a preliminary sketch of Danjuro the ninth drawn by Kunichika, which was to be used for printing woodcuts, was lost when he had Danjuro check the sketch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One time, a preliminary sketch of Danjuro the ninth drawn by Kunichika, which was to be used for printing woodcuts, was lost when he had Danjuro check the sketch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One time, a preliminary sketch of Danjuro the ninth drawn by Kunichika, which was to be used for printing woodcuts, was lost when he had Danjuro check the sketch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>とても良くできていたのでもう一度下絵を描いてくれと頼んだが、国周は同じものは二度と描かない、と断ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danjuro asked Kunichika to draw the same sketch again because the actor liked it very much, but Kunichika reportedly refused, saying that he would never draw the same thing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danjuro asked Kunichika to draw the same sketch again because the actor liked it very much, but Kunichika refused by saying he would never draw the same thing.</e>
<cmt>reportedlyを避けました。「ーという」の訳出はエピソードの紹介ということで既にわかっていることで、必要ないとしてカットしています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danjuro asked Kunichika to draw the same sketch again because the actor liked it very much, but Kunichika refused by saying he would never draw the same thing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>国周の絵師としての誇りがこのような態度をとったのだろうが、いかにも江戸っ子というような印象を与える挿話でもあると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunichika might have acted that way because of his pride as a painter, but the episode is believed to be one that gives the impression of him as being a native of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunichika might have acted from his pride as a painter, while the episode also reflects the character of him as a native of Edo.</e>
<cmt>冗長さを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunichika might have acted from his pride as a painter, while the episode also reflects the character of him as a native of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>国周の画稿料は3枚続一組が6，7円を普通とし、彫師で版元を兼ねた彫長は平均4円50銭ないし5円で描かせていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunichika usually received 6 or 7 yen for a drawing that came in a set of three panels, but HORICHO, a carver and publisher, apparently paid him the average of 4.50 or 5 yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunichika usually received 6 or 7 yen for a drawing that came in a set of three panels, but HORICHO, a carver and publisher, apparently paid him the average of 4.50 or 5 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunichika usually received 6 or 7 yen for a drawing that came in a set of three panels, but HORICHO, a carver and publisher, apparently paid him the average of 4.50 or 5 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nagaike(id:296891), Maya Tukioka(id:277118), Championship2006(id:38664), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>