<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>細川晴元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>細川 晴元（ほそかわ はるもと）は室町時代末期から戦国時代 (日本)にかけての戦国武将・戦国大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto HOSOKAWA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period and a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period who survived from the late Muromachi era through the Sengoku Period (Period of warrning States) (Japan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto HOSOKAWA was both a busho (Japanese military commander) and a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Sengoku Period. He lived from the late Muromachi era through to the the Sengoku Period (Warring States Period) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>wording; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto HOSOKAWA was both a busho (Japanese military commander) and a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), who lived from the late Muromachi era through to the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則のため、一文に訂正しました。余分なthe削除しました。period小文字にしました。説明を用語集より(period of warring states)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family name was Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family name was Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family name was the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて、Seiwa-Genji及び括弧書き削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家系は清和源氏のひとつ・河内源氏の流れを汲む足利氏の庶流・細川氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family came from a line of Hosokawa clan, a branch family of the Ashikaga clan which belonged to the Kawachi-Genji as a branch of Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family came from a line of the Hosokawa clan, a branch family of the Ashikaga clan, which belonged to the Kawachi-Genji as a branch of Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family came from a line of the Hosokawa clan, a branch family of the Ashikaga clan, which belonged to the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) as a branch of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>(Minamoto clan)補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は右京大夫・従四位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His government rank was Ukyo-no-daibu (chief of Ukyoshiki government agency) Jushi rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His government position was Ukyo-no-daibu (chief of Ukyoshiki government agency) with the rank of Jushi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His government position was Ukyo no daibu (mayor of the right capital district) with the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語集より、右京大夫→Ukyo no daibu (mayor of the right capital district)従四位→Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正室は三条公頼の長女であり、その縁から武田信玄・本願寺顕如の義兄に当たる人物でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Kinyori SANJO&apos;s eldest daughter as his legal wife, and because of it, was a brother-in-law for Shingen TAKEDA and Kennyo HONGANJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had Kinyori SANJO&apos;s eldest daughter as his legal wife, thereby becoming the brother-in-law of Shingen TAKEDA and Kennyo HONGANJI.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had Kinyori SANJO&apos;s eldest daughter as his legal wife, thereby becoming the brother-in-law of Shingen TAKEDA and Kennyo HONGANJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「晴元」という名は12代将軍足利義晴の一字を貰いうけたものであるが、当初は義晴と敵対関係であったため、「細川六郎」という通称を長く用いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Harumoto&apos; was named after the 12nd Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA receiving a Chinese character of his name, but since he and Yoshiharu at first were hostile to each other, he identified himself by &apos;Rokuro HOSOKAWA&apos; for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Harumoto&apos; was received the characters in his name after the 12th Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA. However, since he and Yoshiharu were at first hostile to each other, he identified himself as &apos;Rokuro HOSOKAWA&apos; for a long time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Harumoto&apos; was received the characters in his name after the 12th Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, however, since he and Yoshiharu were at first hostile to each other, he identified himself as &apos;Rokuro HOSOKAWA&apos; for a long time.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。一原文一訳文の原則のため、一文に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この項目での呼称は晴元で統一する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He will be referred to as Harumoto in the all following sections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He will be referred to as Harumoto in the following.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He will be referred to as Harumoto in the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>生涯→Biography</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>永正11年（1514年）、細川澄元の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as a son of Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in 1514.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born a son of Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in 1514.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born a son of Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in 1514.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>永正17年（1520年）、澄元が阿波国で死去したため、晴元は7歳で家督を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the death of Sumimoto in Awa-no-kuni in 1514, he took over the family estate at the age of seven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the death of Sumimoto in Awa-no-kuni in 1514, he took over the family estate at the age of seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the death of Sumimoto in Awa Province in 1520, he took over the family estate at the age of seven.</e>
<cmt>Awa Provinceに訂正しました。1520に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>大永6年（1526年）、三好元長らと共に挙兵して細川高国を攻め、大永7年（1527年）に高国が第12代将軍・足利義晴らとともに近江へ落ち延びると、晴元は足利義維と共に和泉国堺を本拠とし、義維を将軍と成した（堺公方）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attacked Takakuni HOSOKAWA in 1526 together with Motonaga MIYOSHI rising up in arms, and after Takakuni escaped to Omi with the 12nd Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA in 1527, he and Yoshitsune ASHIKAGA determined Izumi-no-kuni Sakai to be their base and appointed Yoshitsune as a shogun (Sakaikubo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined forces with Motonaga MIYOSHI to attack Takakuni HOSOKAWA in 1526. After Takakuni escaped to Omi with the 12th Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA in 1527, he and Yoshitsune ASHIKAGA made Izumi-no-kuni Sakai their base and appointed Yoshitsune as Shogun (Sakaikubo).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined forces with Motonaga MIYOSHI to attack Takakuni HOSOKAWA in 1526, then, in 1527, he and Yoshitsune ASHIKAGA made Sakai, Izumi Province their base and appointed Yoshitsuna as Shogun (Sakai kubo) after Takakuni escaped to Omi with the 12th Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則のため、一文に訂正しました。Sakai, Izumi Provinceに訂正しました。足利義維→Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGAスペル訂正しました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>享禄4年（1531年）三好元長に命じて高国を摂津国の広徳寺 (尼崎市)で自害させた（大物崩れ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He directed Motonaga MIYOSHI to arrange for Takakuni to commit a suicide at Kotoku-ji Temple (Amagasaki City) in Settsu-no-kuni in 1531 (the Battle of Daimotsu-kuzure.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He directed Motonaga MIYOSHI to arrange for Takakuni to commit suicide at Kotoku-ji Temple (Amagasaki City) in Settsu-no-kuni in 1531 (the Battle of Daimotsu-kuzure).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He directed Motonaga MIYOSHI to arrange for Takakuni to commit suicide at Kotoku-ji Temple (Amagasaki City) in Settsu Province in 1531 (the Battle of Daimotsu-kuzure).</e>
<cmt>Settsu Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしやがて元長と対立し、天文 (元号)元年（1532年）に晴元は本願寺証如や木沢長政らと手を結び、一向一揆を扇動して元長を堺で殺害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, soon, he became opposed to Motonaga, and killed him in Sakai in 1532 by inciting Ikko-Ikki riots in cooperation with Shonyo HONGANJI and Nagamasa KIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, soon he conflicted with Motonaga and killed him in Sakai in 1532 by inciting the Ikko-Ikki Riots in cooperation with Sho&apos;nyo HONGANJI and Nagamasa KIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, soon he conflicted with Motonaga and killed him in Sakai in 1532 by inciting the Ikko-Ikki Riots in cooperation with Sho&apos;nyo HONGANJI and Nagamasa KIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに足利義維とも不和になったために追放し、将軍・足利義晴と和睦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the murder of Motonaga, he ousted Yoshitsune ASHIKAGA because their relations worsened, and was reconciled with Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the murder of Motonaga, his worsening relations with Yoshitsune ASHIKAGA led to Yoshitsune&apos;s ouster, and he reconciled with the Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the murder of Motonaga, his worsening relations with Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA led to Yoshitsuna&apos;s ouster, and he reconciled with the Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Yoshitsunaスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後、一向宗は堺公方を襲撃するなど対立し、対立宗派の法華宗と協力して法華一揆を誘発させ、領内で一向宗の活動が活発であった近江の六角氏とも協力して山科本願寺を攻めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Ikko-shu attacked Sakaikubo due to hostility, and he (?) provoked Hokke-Ikki riots in cooperation of an opposing religious sect, Hokke-shu and attacked Yamashina Hongwan-ji Temple in cooperation with the Rokkaku clan in Omi in the territory where Ikko-shu was acting vigorously.</e>
<cmt>原文は省略され過ぎた感じを受けます。原文”対立宗派の法華宗と....攻めた」の主語が定かではなかったので調べました。「細川晴元に将軍（堺公方）職を追放された足利義維（あしかがよしつな）は一向宗と対立した状態が続き、一向宗は堺公方を襲撃するなどしたが、一向一揆が大和国に侵入するに及んでも対立宗派の法華宗と協力して法華一揆を誘発させ、領内で一向宗の活動に苦慮していた近江の六角氏とも協力して山科本願寺門跡八世の顕如（れんにょ）を攻め、一向宗の本拠地山科本願寺を焼き討ちにした。」http://jiyodan.exblog.jp/9623462/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Ikko-shu conflicted with Sakaikubo leading to attacks. He (?) received the cooperation of an opposing religious sect, Hokke-shu, tp provoke the Hokke-Ikki Riots. He also attacked Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple allied with the Rokkaku clan in Omi in the territory where Ikko-shu was most active.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Ikko-shu conflicted with Sakai kubo leading to attacks, Harumoto received the cooperation of an opposing religious sect, the Hokke sect, to provoke the Hokke-Ikki Riots, and also attacked Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple allied with the Rokkaku clan in Omi in the territory where the Ikko sect was most active.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則のため、一文に訂正しました。スペース補足。He(?)→晴元を意味すると解釈しました。一向宗→the Ikko sect法華宗→the Hokke secttoスペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>天文5年（1536年）には京都で勢力を伸ばした法華衆に対し、比叡山延暦寺・六角氏と連合して壊滅させた（天文法華の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He killed all believers of Hokke-shu who were growing their power of influence in Kyoto in cooperation with the Rokkaku clan, Hieizan mountain Enryaku-ji Temple (Tenmon-Hokke no ran (Rebellion of Tenmon-Hokke)) in 1536.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1536, he killed all the believers of the Hokke-shu, which was growing in influence in Kyoto allied with the Rokkaku clan of Enryaku-ji Temple on Mount Hiei (Tenmon-Hokke no ran (Rebellion of Tenmon-Hokke)).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1536, he killed all the believers of the Hokke sect, which was growing in influence in Kyoto allied with the Rokkaku clan of Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei (Tenmon-Hokke Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>Hokke sectに訂正しました。Mt. に訂正しました。天文法華の乱→Tenmon-Hokke Rebellionとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天文6年（1537年）、右京大夫に任官し、幕政を支配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as Ukyo-no-daibu (chief of Ukyoshiki government agency) in 1537 to control the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Ukyo-no-daibu (chief of Ukyoshiki government agency) in 1537 to control the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Ukyo no daibu (mayor of the right capital district) in 1537 to control the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>右京大夫→Ukyo no daibu (mayor of the right capital district)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>天文12年（1543年）、細川高国の養子・細川氏綱が晴元打倒を掲げて挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1543, Takakuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s adopted son Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA raised up in arms to defeat Harumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1543, Takakuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s adopted son Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA raised up in arms to defeat Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1543, Takakuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s adopted son Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA raised up in arms to defeat Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>氏綱は畠山政国や遊佐長教らと手を結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitsuna was in partnership with Masakuni HATAYAMA and Naganori YUSA, and meanwhile, Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA passed the shogunate position on to his natural son Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA in 1546 to support Ujitsuna and got to be against Harumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitsuna was in partnership with Masakuni HATAYAMA and Naganori YUSA. At the same time, Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA passed the shogunate position on to his natural son Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA in 1546 to support Ujitsuna and oppose Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitsuna was in partnership with Masakuni HATAYAMA and Naganori YUSA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>将軍・足利義晴も天文15年（1546年）、将軍職を実子の足利義輝に譲った上で氏綱を支持し、晴元と敵対する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA passed the shogunate position on to his natural son Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA in 1546 to support Ujitsuna and oppose Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これに対して晴元は義晴らを近江坂本へ追放し、氏綱らと戦い続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given the above, Harumoto expelled Yoshiharu and his men to Omi-Sakamoto and continued fighting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, Harumoto expelled Yoshiharu and his men to Omi-Sakamoto and continued fighting.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, Harumoto expelled Yoshiharu and his men to Omi-Sakamoto and continued fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし天文17年（1548年）、元長の嫡男で三好宗家の家督を相続していた三好長慶が、晴元に一族の三好政長の討伐を要請し、これを拒否されたため、天文18年（1549年）に氏綱側に寝返った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, although Motonaga&apos;s progeny Nagayoshi MIYOSHI who was taking over the family estate as a head of Miyoshi family requested Harumoto to kill his kin Masanaga MIYOSHI in 1548, his request was rejected by Harumoto and Nagayoshi switched to the Ujitsuna side in 1549.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Motonaga&apos;s progeny Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who was taking over the family estate as the head of the Miyoshi family, requested Harumoto to kill his kin Masanaga MIYOSHI in 1548. This request was rejected by Harumoto and Nagayoshi switched to the Ujitsuna side in 1549.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Motonaga&apos;s progeny Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who was taking over the family estate as the head of the Miyoshi family, requested Harumoto to kill his kin Masanaga MIYOSHI in 1548, however, this request was rejected by Harumoto and Nagayoshi switched to the Ujitsuna side in 1549.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このため、晴元は摂津江口において長慶らと戦って敗北する（江口の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, Harumoto lost the war (the Battle of Eguchi) in fighting with Nagayoshi in Settsu-eguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Harumoto lost the war (the Battle of Eguchi) in battle with Nagayoshi in Settsu-eguchi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Harumoto lost the war (the Battle of Eguchi) in battle with Nagayoshi in Settsu-Eguchi.</e>
<cmt>Eguchi大文字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この戦いで三好政長・高畠長直ら多くの配下を失った晴元は、将軍・義輝や義晴と共に近江へ逃れ、こうして細川政権は終焉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto lost many followers including Masanaga MIYOSHI and NaganaoTAKABATAKE in this war, and escaped to Omi together with Shogun Yoshiteru and Yoshiharu, resulting in the ending of the Hosokawa&apos;s government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto lost many followers, including Masanaga MIYOSHI and Naganao TAKABATAKE, in this war. He escaped to Omi together with Shogun Yoshiteru and Yoshiharu, resulting in the demise of the Hosokawa government.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto lost many followers, including Masanaga MIYOSHI and Naganao TAKABATAKE, in this war, so he escaped to Omi together with Shogun Yoshiteru and Yoshiharu, resulting in the demise of the Hosokawa government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>その後、晴元は将軍・足利義輝を擁し、香西元成や三好政勝などの晴元党の残党や六角義賢や畠山高政など畿内の反三好勢力の支持を受け三好長慶と争うが、敗北し続け、永禄4年（1561年）に義賢の仲介を受けて長慶と和睦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, under Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, Harumoto continued fighting with Nagayoshi MIYOSHI with the support of Harumoto remnants including Motonari KOZAI and Masakatsu MIYOSHI and Anti-Miyoshi power in the Kinai (countries near Kyoto) including Yoshikata ROKKAKU and Takamasa HATAKEYAMA, but lost wars one after another, and was reconciled with Nagayoshi in 1561through the intervention of Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, under Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, Harumoto continued fighting with Nagayoshi MIYOSHI with the support of Harumoto remnants including Motonari KOZAI and Masakatsu MIYOSHI and the anti-Miyoshi forces in the Kinai (countries near Kyoto) including Yoshikata ROKKAKU and Takamasa HATAKEYAMA. However, he suffered a series of defeats, and reconciled with Nagayoshi in 1561through the intervention of Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, under Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, Harumoto continued fighting with Nagayoshi MIYOSHI with the support of Harumoto remnants including Motonari KOZAI and Masakatsu MIYOSHI and the anti-Miyoshi forces in the Kinai (countries near Kyoto) including Yoshikata ROKKAKU and Takamasa HATAKEYAMA, however, he suffered a series of defeats, and reconciled with Nagayoshi in 1561 through the intervention of Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そして剃髪し、摂津富田の普門寺 (高槻市)に隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Teihatsu (tonsure) and retired to stay at Fumon-ji Temple (Takatsuki City) in Settsu-Tonda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received Teihatsu (a tonsure) and retired to Fumon-ji Temple (Takatsuki City) in Settsu-Tonda.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received Teihatsu (a tonsure) and retired to Fumon-ji Temple (Takatsuki City) in Settsu-Tonda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>永禄6年（1563年）3月1日に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on March 1, 1563.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on March 1, 1563.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on April 3, 1563.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>享年50。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was fifty years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was fifty years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was fifty years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Flamelai(id:34490), 阿波座行広(id:39667), ドルチェット(id:46458), 与左衛門(id:159462), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 小者(id:172526), Kamitani(id:30757), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), Azusayumi7(id:21082), YurikBot(id:18605), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), 小川尚明(id:93076), Jmho(id:10472), 常陸介(id:176100), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>