<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高杉晋作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsaku TAKASUGI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsaku TAKASUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsaku TAKASUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高杉 晋作（たかすぎ しんさく、天保10年8月20日 (旧暦)（1839年9月27日） - 慶応3年4月14日 (旧暦)（1867年5月17日））は、日本の武士（長州藩士）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsaku TAKASUGI (September 27, 1839 - May 17, 1867) was a Japanese samurai (feudal retainer of the Choshu clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsaku TAKASUGI (September 27, 1839 - May 17, 1867) was a Japanese samurai of the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>Ambiguous. The parentheses in the Japanese original indicate explanation, but they may imply equivalency in English. &quot;A Japanese samurai&quot; != &quot;feudal retainer of the Choshu clan.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsaku TAKASUGI (September 27, 1839 - May 17, 1867) was a Japanese samurai of the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>幕末の長州藩の尊王倒幕志士として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an anti-shogunate royalist of the Choshu clan in the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an anti-shogunate royalist who lived at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Wording; also, repeating &quot;of the Choshu clan&quot; sounds stilted and unnatural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an anti-shogunate royalist who lived at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>奇兵隊など諸隊を創設し、幕末長州藩を倒幕に方向付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He formed various corps including Kiheitai and led the Choshu clan to campaign against the shogunate in the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He formed various military corps including the Kiheitai (irregular militia) and led the Choshu clan to campaign against the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Kiheitai is a term currently en vogue due to Prime Minister Naoto Kan&apos;s dubbing of his cabinet as the 奇兵隊内閣 &quot;irregular militia cabinet.&quot; Removed repetitive &quot;in the end of the Edo period.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He formed various military corps including the Kiheitai (irregular militia) and led the Choshu clan to campaign against the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>諱は春風。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (personal name that was generally used posthumously or by one&apos;s parents or lord) was Harukaze.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (personal name generally used posthumously or by one&apos;s parents or lord) was Harukaze.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name generally used posthumously or by one&apos;s parents or lord) was Harukaze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>通称は晋作､東一､和助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common names were Shinsaku, Toichi and Wasuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common names were Shinsaku, Toichi and Wasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common names were Shinsaku, Toichi and Wasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>字は暢夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His courtesy name was Chofu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His courtesy name was Chofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His courtesy name was Chofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>号は東行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pseudonym was Togyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pseudonym was Togyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pseudonym was Togyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>変名を谷 潜蔵、谷 梅之助、備後屋助一郎、三谷和助、祝部太郎、宍戸刑馬、西浦松助など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used some false names including Senzo TANI, Umenosuke TANI, Sukeichiro BINGOYA, Wasuke MITANI, Taro HORI, Gyoma SHISHIDO and Matsusuke NISHIURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He used various aliases including Senzo TANI, Umenosuke TANI, Sukeichiro BINGOYA, Wasuke MITANI, Taro HORI, Gyoma SHISHIDO and Matsusuke NISHIURA.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He used various aliases including Senzo TANI, Umenosuke TANI, Sukeichiro BINGOYA, Wasuke MITANI, Taro HORI, Gyoma SHISHIDO and Matsusuke NISHIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>のち、谷 潜蔵と改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later changed his name to Senzo TANI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later officially changed his name to Senzo TANI.</e>
<cmt>Clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later officially changed his name to Senzo TANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>贈位正四位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded the court rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously awarded the court rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously awarded the court rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>長門国萩城菊屋横丁（現・山口県萩市）に萩藩・高杉小忠太（大組・200石）・みちの長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kukuya Yokocho Street, Hagi-jo Castle Town, Nagato Province (now Hagi City, Yamaguchi Prefecture) as the first son of Kochuta TAKASUGI of the Choshu clan (upper-class samurai with a stipend of 200 koku) and Michi.</e>
<cmt>「萩城菊屋横丁」→「萩城下町の菊屋横丁」と補足して訳しました。「萩藩」→長州藩の別名。統一するため&quot;the Choshu clan&quot;と訳しました。「大組」→定訳不明。萩藩では寄組に次ぐ上級武士のようです。（http://www.geocities.jp/furi_316/kkk.htmなど参照）。&quot;upper-class samurai&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on Kukuya Yokocho Street in Hagi-jo Castle Town, Nagato Province (now Hagi City, Yamaguchi Prefecture) as the first son of Kochuta TAKASUGI (an upper-class samurai with a stipend of 200 koku) and Michi.</e>
<cmt>Wording; I don&apos;t think it&apos;s necessary to repeat &quot;of the Choshu clan&quot; again, as it is clear from context (same surname, father-son) that they must be of the same clan. Repetition of obvious facts makes the text both difficult to read and unenjoyable.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on Kikuya Yokocho Street in Hagi-jo Castle Town, Nagato Province (now Hagi City, Yamaguchi Prefecture) as the first son of Kochuta TAKASUGI (an upper-class samurai with a stipend of 200 koku) and Michi.</e>
<cmt>KukuyaをKikuyaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>10歳の頃に疱瘡を患う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He suffered from smallpox at the age of 10.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He suffered from smallpox at the age of 10.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He suffered from smallpox at the age of 10.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>漢学塾を経て、嘉永5年（1852年）に藩校の明倫館に入学、剣術も学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After studying at a private school of Chinese classics, he entered the domain school, Meirinkan, in 1852 and learned swordplay as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After studying at a private school of Chinese classics, he entered a hanko (public school for the children of samurai), Meirinkan, in 1852 and learned swordplay as well.</e>
<cmt>General readers will not understand &quot;domain school&quot;; Ref. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Han_school</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After studying at a private school of Chinese classics, he entered a hanko (public school for the children of samurai), Meirinkan, in 1852 and learned swordplay as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>安政4年（1857年）には吉田松陰が主宰していた松下村塾に入り、安政5年（1858年）には藩命で江戸へ遊学した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1857, he entered Shoka Sonjuku, private school held by Shoin YOSHIDA, and then went to Edo in 1858 on the order of the clan to study there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857, he entered Shoka Sonjuku, a private school headed by Shoin YOSHIDA, and in 1858 was sent by the clan to study in Edo.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857, he entered Shoka Sonjuku, a private school headed by Shoin YOSHIDA, and in 1858 was sent by the clan to study in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>昌平坂学問所などで学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied at Shoheizaka Gakumonjo (a shogunate school) and other places.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied at Shoheizaka Gakumonjo (a shogunate school) and other places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied at Shoheizaka Gakumonjo (a shogunate school) and other places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>安政6年（1859年）には師の松陰が安政の大獄で捕らえられるとその獄を見舞う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his teacher Shoin was arrested during the Ansei Purge in 1859, he visited Shoin in jail, who was then executed in October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his teacher Shoin was arrested during the Ansei Purge in 1859, Takasugi visited him in jail. Shoin was executed in October.</e>
<cmt>Wording; grammar; &quot;then&quot; may imply causation. 2 sentences.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his teacher Shoin was arrested during the Ansei Purge in 1859, Takasugi visited him in jail.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>松陰は10月に処刑される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoin was executed in October.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>万延元年（1860年）11月に帰郷、防長一の美人と言われた山口町奉行井上平右衛門の次女、まさと結婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned home in November 1860 and married Masa, who was the second daughter of Heiemon INOUE, Yamaguchi town magistrate, and said to be the most beautiful lady in Suo and Nagato Provinces.</e>
<cmt>「防長」→周防と長門国（goo辞書）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi returned home in November 1860 and married the second daughter of Yamaguchi town magistrate Heiemon INOUE, Masa, who was said to be the most beautiful lady in Suo and Nagato Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Ambiguous; wording. Ref. &quot;The Elements of Style&quot;, Strunk and White, p.30</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi returned home in December 1860 and married the second daughter of Yamaguchi town magistrate Heiemon INOUE, Masa, who was said to be the most beautiful lady in Suo and Nagato Provinces.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>文久元年（1861年）3月には海軍修練のため、藩の所蔵する軍艦丙辰丸に乗船、江戸へ渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1861, he went to Edo, by boarding the clan&apos;s warship Heishinmaru for the purpose of naval training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1861, he undertook naval training on the clan&apos;s warship Heishinmaru, and travelled to Edo.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1861, he undertook naval training on the clan&apos;s warship Heishinmaru, and travelled to Edo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>8月には東北遊学を行い、佐久間象山や横井小楠とも交友する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August he went to Tohoku region to study there, and acquainted himself with Shozan SAKUMA and Shonan YOKOI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August he went to the Tohoku region to study, and there associated with Shozan SAKUMA and Shonan YOKOI..</e>
<cmt>Wording. NOTE: It seems to me that &quot;交友&quot; would be better translated as &quot;associated with&quot; or even &quot;befriended&quot; rather than &quot;acquainted himself with&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September he went to the Tohoku region to study, and there associated with Shozan SAKUMA and Shonan YOKOI..</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>文久2年（1862年）5月には藩命で、五代友厚らとともに、幕府使節随行員として長崎から中国の上海市へ渡航した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1862, he departed Nagasaki for Shanghai City, China, with Tomoatsu GODAI and others, accompanying the shogunate envoys on the order of the clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1862, by order of the clan, he departed Nagasaki for Shanghai City, China, with Tomoatsu GODAI and others, accompanying the shogunate envoys.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1862, by order of the clan, he departed Nagasaki for Shanghai City, China, with Tomoatsu GODAI and others, accompanying the shogunate envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>清が欧米の植民地となりつつある実情や、1854年からの民衆反乱である太平天国の乱を見聞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He obtained information there, about the Qing dynasty&apos;s situation of being colonized by the West and the Taiping Rebellion, which was the people&apos;s rebellion continuing from 1854.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There he learned about the state of the Qing dynasty&apos;s colonization by the West and of the Taiping Rebellion, a popular uprising that had continued since 1854.</e>
<cmt>Wording; grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There he learned about the state of the Qing dynasty&apos;s colonization by the West and of the Taiping Rebellion, a popular uprising that had continued since 1854.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そして7月に帰国、日記の『遊清五録』によれば大きな影響を受けたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then returned home in July, having received a great influence according to his diary &quot;Yu-shin Goroku&quot; (Five Accounts of a Voyage to China).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then returned home in July, having been greatly influenced by the journey, according to his diary &quot;Yu-shin Goroku&quot; (Five Accounts of a Voyage to China).</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then returned home in July, having been greatly influenced by the journey, according to his diary &quot;Yu-shin Goroku&quot; (Five Accounts of a Voyage to China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>長州藩では、高杉の渡航中に守旧派の長井雅楽らが失脚、尊王攘夷(尊攘)派が台頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Choshu clan, during the absence of Takasugi, Uta NAGAI and others of old guard faction were ousted and Sonno Joi faction (those who advocated reverence for the Emperor and expulsion of foreigners) became dominant.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Choshu clan, during the absence of Takasugi, Uta NAGAI and others of the old guard faction were ousted and the Sonno Joi faction (those who advocated reverence for the Emperor and expulsion of foreigners) became dominant.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Choshu clan, during the absence of Takasugi, Uta NAGAI and others of the old guard faction were ousted and the Sonno Joi faction (those who advocated reverence for the Emperor and expulsion of foreigners) became dominant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>高杉も桂小五郎（木戸孝允）や久坂義助（久坂玄瑞）たちと共にともに尊攘運動に加わり、江戸・京師（京都市）において勤皇・破約攘夷の宣伝活動を展開し、各藩の志士たちと交流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasugi also joined the Sonno Joi movement with Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO) and Yoshisuke KUSAKA (Genzui KUSAKA) and launched a campaign in Kyoto, for being loyal to the Emperor, nullifying the treaties and expelling foreigners, in cooperation with royalists from other clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi also joined the Sonno Joi movement with Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO) and Yoshisuke KUSAKA (Genzui KUSAKA) and launched a campaign in Kyoto espousing loyalty to the Emperor, nullification of treaties and the expelling of foreigners, in cooperation with royalists from other clans.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi also joined the Sonno Joi movement with Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO) and Yoshisuke KUSAKA (Genzui KUSAKA) and launched a campaign in Kyoto espousing loyalty to the Emperor, nullification of treaties and the expelling of foreigners, in cooperation with royalists from other clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>文久2年（1862年）、高杉は「薩藩はすでに生麦に於いて夷人を斬殺して攘夷の実を挙げたのに、我が藩はなお、公武合体を説いている。何とか攘夷の実を挙げねばならぬ。藩政府でこれを断行できぬならば......」と論じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, Takasugi argued, &quot;the Satsuma clan has already achieved a result for expelling foreigners by killing them in Namamugi, and yet our clan is still advocating for reconciliation between the imperial court and shogunate. We should by any means achieve a result for expelling foreigners. If the clan government cannot take a decisive action to do it...&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862, Takasugi argued, &quot;The Satsuma clan has already seen results in expelling foreigners by killing them in Namamugi, and yet our clan is still advocating for reconciliation between the imperial court and the shogunate. We must find some way to get results in expelling foreigners. If the clan government cannot take a decisive action to do it...&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording. &quot;achieve a result&quot; sounds unnatural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1862, Takasugi argued, &apos;The Satsuma clan has already seen results in expelling foreigners by killing them in Namamugi, and yet our clan is still advocating for reconciliation between the imperial court and the shogunate. We must find some way to get results in expelling foreigners. If the clan government cannot take a decisive action to do it...&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>折りしも、外国公使がしばしば武州金澤（金澤八景)で遊ぶからそこで刺殺しようと同志（高杉晋作、久坂玄瑞、大和弥八郎、長嶺内蔵太、志道聞多、松島剛蔵、寺島忠三郎、有吉熊次郎、赤禰幹之丞、山尾庸三、品川弥二郎）が相談した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just at that time, Takasugi and his comrades (Shinsaku TAKASUGI, Genzui KUSAKA, Yahachiro YAMATO, Kurata NAGAMINE, Monta SHIJI, Gozo MATSUSHIMA, Chuzaburo TERAJIMA, Kumajiro ARIYOSHI, Mikinojo AKANE, Yozo YAMAO and Yajiro SHINAGAWA) conspired to kill foreign ministers who often visited Kanazawa in Musashi Province (Kanazawa Hakkei) for holidays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just at that time, Takasugi and his comrades (Genzui KUSAKA, Yahachiro YAMATO, Kurata NAGAMINE, Monta SHIJI, Gozo MATSUSHIMA, Chuzaburo TERAJIMA, Kumajiro ARIYOSHI, Mikinojo AKANE, Yozo YAMAO and Yajiro SHINAGAWA) conspired to kill the foreign ministers who often holidayed in Kanazawa in Musashi Province (Kanazawa Hakkei).</e>
<cmt>Deleted Shinsaku from list; he is not his own comrade; wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just at that time, Takasugi and his comrades (Genzui KUSAKA, Yahachiro YAMATO, Kurata NAGAMINE, Monta SHIJI, Gozo MATSUSHIMA, Chuzaburo TERAJIMA, Kumajiro ARIYOSHI, Mikinojo AKANE, Yozo YAMAO and Yajiro SHINAGAWA) conspired to kill the foreign ministers who often holidayed in Kanazawa in Musashi Province (Kanazawa Hakkei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし久坂が土佐の武市半平太に話したことから、これが土佐藩主山内容堂を通して長州藩主毛利定広に伝わり、無謀であると制止され実行に到らず、櫻田邸内に謹慎を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kusaka told it to Hanpeita TAKECHI of the Tosa clan, and then it became known to the head of the Tosa clan Yodo YAMAUCHI, and then to the head of the Choshu clan Sadahiro MORI, who stopped them from carrying it out recklessly, and ordered them to confine themselves at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kusaka told the plan to Hanpeita TAKECHI of the Tosa clan, who made it known to the head of the Tosa clan Yodo YAMAUCHI, and from him the news reached the head of the Choshu clan Sadahiro MORI, who stopped them from carrying it out recklessly, and ordered them to confine themselves at home.</e>
<cmt>Wording, clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kusaka told the plan to Hanpeita TAKECHI of the Tosa clan, who made it known to the head of the Tosa clan Yodo YAMAUCHI, and from him the news reached the head of the Choshu clan Sadahiro MORI, who stopped them from carrying it out recklessly, and ordered them to confine themselves at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>謹慎中の同志は御楯組結成の血盟書を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The comrades, during their refinement, signed a covenant to form Mitategumi squad and sealed it with their blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The comrades, during their confinement, signed a covenant to form the Mitategumi group and sealed it with their blood.</e>
<cmt>&quot;squad&quot; seems strange</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The comrades, during their confinement, signed a covenant to form the Mitategumi group and sealed it with their blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>この過程で、高杉は頼りになるのは長州の志士だけだとする長州ナショナリズムを形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this process, Takasugi formed the idea of Choshu nationalism, thinking that only the royalists from the Choshu clan were trustworthy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this process, Takasugi formed the idea of Choshu nationalism, thinking that only the royalists from the Choshu clan were trustworthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this process, Takasugi formed the idea of Choshu nationalism, thinking that only the royalists from the Choshu clan were trustworthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>長州藩と朝廷や他藩との提携交渉は、専ら桂や久坂が担当することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Choshu clan&apos;s cooperation and negotiation with the imperial court or other clans came to be dealt exclusively by Katsura and Kusaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Choshu clan&apos;s cooperation and negotiation with the imperial court and other clans came to be handled by Katsura and Kusaka exclusively.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Choshu clan&apos;s cooperation and negotiation with the imperial court and other clans came to be handled by Katsura and Kusaka exclusively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>文久2年12月12日には、幕府の異勅に抗議するため、同志とともに品川御殿山に建設中の英国公使館焼き討ち事件を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 31, 1863, he attacked and burned the British legation that was under construction in Gotenyama, Shinagawa, with his comrades in order to protest the shogunate&apos;s acting against the intention of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>「文久2年12月12日」→西暦1863年1月31日「異勅」→定訳不明。天皇の意思に背くこと、と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 31, 1863, Takasugi and his comrades attacked and burned the British legation building under construction in Gotenyama, Shinagawa, in order to protest the shogunate&apos;s acting against the intentions of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Wording; clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 31, 1863, Takasugi and his comrades attacked and burned the British legation building under construction in Gotenyama, Shinagawa, in order to protest the shogunate&apos;s acting against the intentions of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、幕府の罪人として処刑された松陰の遺骨を白昼堂々小塚原から世田谷に移して会葬する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also transferred, in broad daylight, the cremains of Shoin who had been executed as a rebel against the shogunate, from Odawara to Setagaya where he held a funeral service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi also transferred the remains of Shoin, who had been executed as a rebel against the shogunate, from Odawara to Setagaya in broad daylight, and held a funeral service.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi also transferred the remains of Shoin, who had been executed as a rebel against the shogunate, from Odawara to Setagaya in broad daylight, and held a funeral service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これらの過激な行いが幕府を刺激する事を恐れた藩では高杉を江戸から召還する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being afraid that such radical actions might irritate the shogunate, the clan recalled Takasugi from Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being afraid that such radical actions might irritate the shogunate, the clan recalled Takasugi from Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being afraid that such radical actions might irritate the shogunate, the clan recalled Takasugi from Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>文久3年（1863年）5月10日、幕府が朝廷から要請されて制定した攘夷期限が過ぎると、長州藩は関門海峡において外国船砲撃を行うが、逆に米仏の報復に逢い惨敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 10, 1863, after the deadline for the expulsion of foreigners that had been set by the shogunate upon the demand of the imperial court, the Choshu clan fired cannons at foreign ships in Kanmon-kaikyo Strait, but was severely defeated in return by the United States of America and France.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 10, 1863, after the deadline for the expulsion of foreigners that had been set by the shogunate upon the demand of the imperial court, the Choshu clan fired cannons at foreign ships in the Kanmon-Kaikyo Strait, but was overwhelmingly defeated by the American and French counter-attack.</e>
<cmt>&quot;severely defeated&quot; sounds slightly strange,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 25, 1863, after the deadline for the expulsion of foreigners that had been set by the shogunate upon the demand of the imperial court, the Choshu clan fired cannons at foreign ships in the Kanmon-Kaikyo Strait, but was overwhelmingly defeated by the American and French counter-attack.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>高杉は下関の防衛を任せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasugi was in charge of defense in Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi was in put charge of the defense of Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt>Wording, clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi was in put charge of the defense of Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>6月には廻船問屋の白石正一郎邸において身分に因らない志願兵による奇兵隊を結成し、阿弥陀寺（赤間神宮の隣）を本拠とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, at the residence of Shoichiro SHIRAISHI who was a wholesaler in the port, he formed Kiheitai corps consisting of voluntary soldiers regardless of social rank, with its headquarters at Amida-ji Temple (next to Akama-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, at the residence of Shoichiro SHIRAISHI who was a wholesaler in the port, Takasugi formed the Kiheitai militia, consisting of voluntary soldiers of any social rank, with its headquarters at Amida-ji Temple (next to Akama-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, at the residence of Shoichiro SHIRAISHI who was a wholesaler in the port, Takasugi formed the Kiheitai militia, consisting of voluntary soldiers of any social rank, with its headquarters at Amida-ji Temple (next to Akama-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、9月には教法寺事件の責任を問われ総監を罷免された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was dismissed from the post of commandant in September, for being responsible for the Incident at Kyoho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was dismissed from the post of commandant in September, for being responsible for the Incident at Kyoho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was dismissed from the post of commandant in October, for being responsible for the Incident at Kyoho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>京都では薩摩藩と会津藩が結託した宮廷クーデターである8月18日の政変で長州藩が追放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, the Choshu clan was ousted in Coup of August 18, by a coalition between the Satsuma clan and Aizu clan in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, the Choshu clan was ousted in the Coup of August 18, by a coalition of the Satsuma and Aizu clans in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Wording; again, what is &quot;the Coup of August 18&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, the Choshu clan was ousted in the Coup of August 18, by a coalition of the Satsuma and Aizu clans in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>文久4年（1864年）1月、高杉は京都進発を主張する急進派の来島又兵衛を説得するが容れられず、脱藩して京都へ潜伏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1864, Takasugi tried to persuade Matabe KIJIMA, who radically insisted on fighting in Kyoto, but failed and then left the domain to hide in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1864, Takasugi tried to dissuade the radical Matabei KIJIMA from his plan to fight the Satsuma and Aizu in Kyoto, but failed and then left the domain to hide in Kyoto himself.</e>
<cmt>The word &quot;persuade&quot; alone doesn&apos;t tell us what Takasugi was trying to persuade Matabei to do or not do. Historically, Matabei led the attack on Kyoto in revenge for the Shinsengumi&apos;s killing of 20 Choshu samurai. Takasugi failed to dissuade him from his plan, and Matabei was ambushed on his way to the Palace. Seems like the name is typically romanized as &quot;Matabei&quot; rather than &quot;Matabe&quot;, despite the kanji. Ref. Wikipedia, 534 Google results.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1864, Takasugi tried to dissuade the radical Matabei KIJIMA from his plan to fight the Satsuma and Aizu in Kyoto, but failed and then left the domain to hide in Kyoto himself.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>桂小五郎の説得で2月には帰郷するが、脱藩の罪で野山獄に投獄された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned home in February, having been persuaded by Kogoro KATSURA, and then was put into Noyamagoku jail for the charge of leaving the domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned home in February, having been persuaded to do so by Kogoro KATSURA, and then was put into Noyamagoku jail for the charge of leaving the domain.</e>
<cmt>Again, &quot;persuade&quot; is vague.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned home in February, having been persuaded to do so by Kogoro KATSURA, and then was put into Noyamagoku jail for the charge of leaving the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>6月には出所して謹慎処分となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was released from jail in June and ordered to confine himself at home.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was released from jail in June and ordered to confine himself at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was released from jail in July and ordered to confine himself at home.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>7月、長州藩は禁門の変で敗北して朝敵となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, the Choshu clan lost a battle in the Kinmon Incident and became an enemy of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, the Choshu clan lost a battle in the Kinmon Incident and became an enemy of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, the Choshu clan lost a battle in the Kinmon Incident and became an enemy of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>来島は戦死、久坂玄瑞は自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kijima died in the battle and Genzui KUSAKA killed himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kijima died in the battle and Genzui KUSAKA killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kijima died in the battle and Genzui KUSAKA killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>8月には、イギリス、フランス、アメリカ、オランダの4カ国連合艦隊が下関を砲撃、砲台が占拠されるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, a combined fleet of the warships of four countries, England, France, the United States of America and Netherlands, attacked Shimonoseki and occupied the gun battery.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, a combined fleet of warships from four nations — England, France, the United States of America and the Netherlands — attacked Shimonoseki and occupied the gun battery there.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, a combined fleet of warships from four nations — England, France, the United States of America and the Netherlands — attacked Shimonoseki and occupied the gun battery there.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>すると、晋作は赦免されて和議交渉を任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsaku was then forgiven and put in charge of peace negotiations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsaku was then forgiven and put in charge of peace negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsaku was then forgiven and put in charge of peace negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>この講和会議において、連合国は数多の条件とともに『彦島の租借』を要求してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the peace conference, the coalition countries demanded &quot;lease of Hiko-shima Island&quot; as well as various other terms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the peace conference, the coalition countries demanded &quot;lease of Hiko-shima Island&quot; as well as various other terms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the peace conference, the coalition countries demanded &quot;lease of Hiko-shima Island&quot; as well as various other terms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>高杉はほぼ全ての提示条件を受け入れたが、この『領土の租借』についてのみ頑として受け入れようとせず、結局は取り下げさせることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasugi accepted almost all terms proposed, but persistently refused this &quot;lease of territory&quot; and finally succeeded in eliminating it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi accepted almost all terms proposed, but persistently refused this &quot;lease of territory&quot; and finally succeeded in eliminating it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi accepted almost all terms proposed, but persistently refused this &quot;lease of territory&quot; and finally succeeded in eliminating it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これは清国の見聞を経た高杉が『領土の期限付租借』の植民地化を深く見抜いていたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was because Takasugi, having seen the situation of the Qing dynasty, understood that the &quot;fixed-term lease of territory&quot; was a method of colonization.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi, having seen the situation of the Qing dynasty, understood that the &quot;fixed-term lease of territory&quot; was a method of colonization.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It was because&quot; unnecessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi, having seen the situation of the Qing dynasty, understood that the &quot;fixed-term lease of territory&quot; was a method of colonization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>もしこの要求を受け入れていれば日本の歴史は大きく変わっていたであろうと後世に分析されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later generations have analyzed that if this demand was accepted, Japanese history would have been very different.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later generations have concluded that if this demand had been accepted, Japanese history would have turned out very differently.</e>
<cmt>&quot;analyzed&quot; can&apos;t be used this way</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later generations have concluded that if this demand had been accepted, Japanese history would have turned out very differently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>時に高杉晋作、24歳であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsaku TAKASUGI was then 24 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsaku TAKASUGI was then 24 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsaku TAKASUGI was then 24 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>幕府による第一次長州征伐が迫る中、長州藩では俗論派が台頭し、10月には福岡へ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the shogunate planned the first conquest of Choshu, a moderate faction advocating reconciliation with the shogunate became dominant in the Choshu clan and he escaped to Fukuoka in October.</e>
<cmt>「俗論派」→「幕府に敵対するのはやめようとする穏健派」と解釈して訳しました。（http://www.nextone.jp/no051208/va/va12.htmlなど参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the shogunate planned the first conquest of Choshu, a moderate faction advocating reconciliation with the shogunate became dominant in the Choshu clan and Takasugi escaped to Fukuoka in October.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the shogunate planned the first conquest of Choshu, a moderate faction advocating reconciliation with the shogunate became dominant in the Choshu clan and Takasugi escaped to Fukuoka in October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>平尾山荘に匿われるが、俗論派による正義派家老の処刑を聞き、再び下関へ帰還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was sheltered in Hirao Sanso Mountain Villa, but returned to Shimonoseki on hearing that the moderate faction had executed a chief retainer of reformist faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was sheltered in the Hirao Sanso Mountain Villa, but returned to Shimonoseki on hearing that the moderate faction had executed a chief retainer of the reformist faction.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was sheltered in the Hirao Sanso Mountain Villa, but returned to Shimonoseki on hearing that the moderate faction had executed a chief retainer of the reformist faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>12月15日夜半、伊藤博文（伊藤博文）率いる力士隊、石川小五郎率いる遊撃隊ら長州藩諸隊を率いて功山寺挙兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the night of December 15, at Kozan-ji Temple, he raised an army consisting of various corps of the Choshu clan, including Rikishitai led by Hirobumi ITO and Yugekitai led by Kojiro ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the night of December 15, at Kozan-ji Temple, Takasugi raised an army made up of various corps of the Choshu clan, including the Rikishitai led by Hirobumi ITO and the Yugekitai led by Kojiro ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>Wording. These corps might need explaining, too.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the night of January 12, at Kozan-ji Temple, Takasugi raised an army made up of various corps of the Choshu clan, including the Rikishitai led by Hirobumi ITO and the Yugekitai led by Kojiro ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>後に奇兵隊ら諸隊も加わり、元治2年（1865年）3月には俗論派の首魁椋梨藤太らを排斥して藩の実権を握る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other corps later joined as well, including Kiheitai, and in March 1865 they ousted the leader of the moderate faction, Tota MUKUNASHI, and seized power in the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other corps later joined as well, including Kiheitai, and in March 1865 they ousted the leader of the moderate faction, Tota MUKUNASHI, and seized power in the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other corps later joined as well, including Kiheitai, and in March 1865 they ousted the leader of the moderate faction, Tota MUKUNASHI, and seized power in the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>同月、海外渡航を試みて長崎でイギリス商人グラバーと接触するが、反対される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he contacted English merchant Glover in Nagasaki in an attempt to go abroad, but Glover opposed it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Takasugi contacted an English merchant named Glover in Nagasaki, in an attempt to go abroad, but Glover rejected the proposal.</e>
<cmt>&quot;opposed it&quot; sounds strange</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Takasugi contacted an English merchant named Glover in Nagasaki, in an attempt to go abroad, but Glover rejected the proposal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>4月には、下関開港を推し進めたことにより、攘夷派・俗論派に命を狙われたため、愛妾・おうの（後の梅処尼）とともに四国へ逃れ、日柳燕石を頼る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He promoted to open the port of Shimonoseki to foreigners, which fact led both the reformist and moderate factions to try to kill him, and in April he escaped to Shikoku region with his mistress Ono (later called Baishoni), trying to rely on Enseki KUSANAGI there.</e>
<cmt>「攘夷派」→既出の「正義派」のことなので、同様に&quot;reformist faction&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi then pressed for the opening of Shimonoseki Port to foreigners, which led both the reformist and moderate factions to try to kill him, and in April he escaped to the Shikoku region with his mistress Ono (later called Baishoni), relying on the support of Enseki KUSANAGI there.</e>
<cmt>wording; also, not sure about the accuracy of &quot;reformist and moderate factions&quot;. Sentence perhaps too long.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi then pressed for the opening of Shimonoseki Port to foreigners, which led both the reformist and moderate factions to try to kill him, and in April he escaped to the Shikoku region with his mistress Ono (later called Baishoni), relying on the support of Enseki KUSANAGI there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>6月に桂小五郎の斡旋により帰郷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Kogoro KATSURA arranged for him to return home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, Kogoro KATSURA arranged for him to return home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Kogoro KATSURA arranged for him to return home.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="59">
<j>慶応元年（1865年）1月11日付で晋作は高杉家を廃嫡されて「育（はぐくみ）」扱いとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 11, 1865, Shinsaku was disinherited by the Takasugi family and treated as &apos;Hagukumi&apos; (peasant who became a samurai through the unique system of the Choshu clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「育（はぐくみ）」扱い→定訳不明。長州藩の育制度（百姓が武士になれる制度）のことで、「育扱い」とは「百姓出身の武士扱い」を指すと思われます。（http://eigaku.cocolog-nifty.com/jyosetu/2005/10/__7492.html参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 11, 1865, Shinsaku was disinherited by the Takasugi family and treated as &apos;Hagukumi&apos; (peasant who became a samurai through a system unique to the Choshu clan).</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 6, 1865, Shinsaku was disinherited by the Takasugi family and treated as &apos;Hagukumi&apos; (peasant who became a samurai through a system unique to the Choshu clan).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>そして同年9月29日、藩命により谷 潜蔵と改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 29 of the same year, he changed his name to Senzo TANI on the order of the clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 29 of the same year, he changed his name to Senzo TANI on the order of the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 17 of the same year, he changed his name to Senzo TANI on the order of the clan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）3月29日には新知100石が与えられ、谷家を創設して初代当主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 29, 1867, he was awarded a stipend of 100 koku and became the first head of the Tani family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 29, 1867, he was awarded a stipend of 100 koku and became the first head of the Tani family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 3, 1867, he was awarded a stipend of 100 koku and became the first head of the Tani family.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="62">
<j>さらに慶応2年（1866年）1月21日（一説には1月22日）、土佐藩の坂本龍馬・中岡慎太郎・土方久元を仲介として、晋作も桂小五郎・井上馨・伊藤俊輔たちと共に進めていた薩長同盟が京都薩摩藩邸で結ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 21, 1866 (January 22 according to another theory), an alliance between the Satsuma and Choshu clan, which Shinsaku had been promoting with Kogoro KATSURA, Kaoru INOUE and Shunsuke ITO, was concluded at the residence of the Satsuma clan in Kyoto, with Ryoma SAKAMOTO, Shintaro NAKAOKA and Hisamoto HIJIKATA from the Tosa clan acting as intermediaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21, 1866 (January 22 according to another theory), an alliance between the Satsuma and Choshu clans, which Shinsaku had been promoting with Kogoro KATSURA, Kaoru INOUE and Shunsuke ITO, was concluded at the residence of the Satsuma clan in Kyoto, with Ryoma SAKAMOTO, Shintaro NAKAOKA and Hisamoto HIJIKATA from the Tosa clan acting as intermediaries.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 7, 1866 (March 8 according to another theory), an alliance between the Satsuma and Choshu clans, which Shinsaku had been promoting with Kogoro KATSURA, Kaoru INOUE and Shunsuke ITO, was concluded at the residence of the Satsuma clan in Kyoto, with Ryoma SAKAMOTO, Shintaro NAKAOKA and Hisamoto HIJIKATA from the Tosa clan acting as intermediaries.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="63">
<j>5月には伊藤俊輔とともに薩摩行きを命じられ、長崎で丙寅丸（オテントサマ丸）を単独購入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he was ordered to go to Satsuma with Shunsuke ITO, and in Nagasaki purchased a warship called Otentosamamaru on his own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, he was ordered to go to Satsuma with Shunsuke ITO, and in Nagasaki independently purchased a warship called the Otentosamamaru.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he was ordered to go to Satsuma with Shunsuke ITO, and in Nagasaki independently purchased a warship called the Otentosamamaru.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="64">
<j>6月の第二次長州征伐（四境戦争）では海軍総督として丙寅丸に乗り込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, at the time of the second conquest of Choshu by the shogunate (Shikyo War), he boarded Otentosamamaru as chief commander of the Navy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, at the time of the second conquest of Choshu by the shogunate (the Shikyo War), he boarded the Otentosamamaru as chief commander of the Navy.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, at the time of the second conquest of Choshu by the shogunate (the Shikyo War), he boarded the Otentosamamaru as chief commander of the Navy.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>周防大島沖に停泊する幕府艦隊を夜襲してこれを退け、林半七率いる第二奇兵隊等と連絡して周防大島を奪還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attacked at night and defeated a shogunate fleet moored in the sea near Suo-oshima Island, and recaptured the island in cooperation with other corps such as the second Kiheitai unit led by Hanshichi HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attacked at night and defeated a shogunate fleet moored in the sea near Suo-oshima Island, and recaptured the island in cooperation with other corps, such as the second Kiheitai unit led by Hanshichi HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>Too long with no comma.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attacked at night and defeated a shogunate fleet moored in the sea near Suo-oshima Island, and recaptured the island in cooperation with other corps, such as the second Kiheitai unit led by Hanshichi HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>小倉市方面の戦闘指揮では、まず軍艦で門司・田ノ浦の沿岸を砲撃させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the area of Kokura City, he firstly commanded warships to fire cannons at the coast of Moji and Tanoura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the area of Kokura City, he began the attack by commanding his warships to fire cannons at the coast of Moji and Tanoura.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the area of Kokura City, he began the attack by commanding his warships to fire cannons at the coast of Moji and Tanoura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>その援護のもと奇兵隊・報国隊を上陸させ、幕軍の砲台、火薬庫を破壊し幕府軍を敗走させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this support, he landed Kiheitai and Hokokutai corps to destroy the gun battery and magazine of the shogunate, whose army then took flight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this support, he landed Kiheitai and Hokokutai troops and destroyed the gun battery and magazine of the shogunate, whose army then took flight.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this support, he landed Kiheitai and Hokokutai troops and destroyed the gun battery and magazine of the shogunate, whose army then took flight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>その後さらに攻勢に出るも小倉城手前で肥後藩の猛反撃に合い、一時小康状態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then tried to attack further, but met a furious counter-attack by the Higo clan before Kokura-jo Castle and temporarily ceased the attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then tried to attack further, but meeting a furious counter-attack by the Higo clan in front of Kokura-jo Castle, he temporarily ceased the assault.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then tried to attack further, but meeting a furious counter-attack by the Higo clan in front of Kokura-jo Castle, he temporarily ceased the assault.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="69">
<j>しかし、幕府軍総督小笠原長行の臆病な日和見ぶりに激怒した幕府軍諸藩が随時撤兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, various clans supporting the shogunate withdrew from time to time, being furious about the timidity and indecisiveness of the shogunate chief commander Nagamichi OGASAWARA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, various clans supporting the shogunate withdrew from time to time, being furious about the timidity and indecisiveness of the shogunate chief commander Nagamichi OGASAWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, various clans supporting the shogunate withdrew from time to time, being furious about the timidity and indecisiveness of the shogunate chief commander Nagamichi OGASAWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>7月には将軍徳川家茂の死去の報を受けた小笠原がこれ幸いと戦線を離脱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, Ogasawara was informed that the Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA had died, and taking this opportunity left the battle, which fact determined the defeat of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, Ogasawara was informed that the Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA had died, and taking this opportunity, he withdrew from the battle. The defeat of the shogunate was decided.</e>
<cmt>Wording. 2 sentences.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, Ogasawara was informed that the Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA had died, and taking this opportunity, he withdrew from the battle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>そのため幕府敗北は決定的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The defeat of the shogunate was decided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>この敗北によって幕府の権威は大きく失墜し、翌慶応3年（1867年）11月の大政奉還への大きな転換点となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This defeat dramatically deprived the shogunate of its authority and marked a turning point towards the restoration of imperial rule in November 1867.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This defeat eroded the authority of the shogunate in a dramatic fashion and marked a turning point towards the restoration of Imperial rule in November 1867.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This defeat eroded the authority of the shogunate in a dramatic fashion and marked a turning point towards the restoration of Imperial rule in November 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>しかし、晋作自身は、肺結核のため桜山で療養生活を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shinsaku himself was forced to cure his disease, pulmonary tuberculosis, in Sakurayama, and died on May 17, 1867 without witnessing the restoration of imperial rule, while he was sure that the Edo shogunate would end (died at the age of 27).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shinsaku himself, suffering from pulmonary tuberculosis, was forced to recuperate in Sakurayama. He died at the age of 27, on May 17, 1867, assured that the Edo shogunate would end, but without witnessing the restoration of Imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>Wording. 2 sentences.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shinsaku himself, suffering from pulmonary tuberculosis, was forced to recuperate in Sakurayama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）5月17日（太陽暦）、江戸幕府の終了を確信しながらも大政奉還を見ずしてこの世を去る（享年27）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 27, on May 17, 1867, assured that the Edo shogunate would end, but without witnessing the restoration of Imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>臨終には、父・母・妻と倅がかけつけ、野村望東尼と山縣有朋、田中顕助が立ち会ったとされるが、田中の残した日記によれば、彼はその日京におり、詳細は定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story says that his father, mother, wife and son came to see him, and Motoni NOMURA, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kensuke TANAKA also witnessed his death, although its details are unclear, as Tanaka&apos;s diary says that he was in Kyoto on that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A story says that his father, mother, wife and son came to see him, and Motoni NOMURA, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kensuke TANAKA also witnessed his death, although its details are unclear, as Tanaka&apos;s diary says that he was in Kyoto on that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A story says that his father, mother, wife and son came to see him, and Motoni NOMURA, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kensuke TANAKA also witnessed his death, although its details are unclear, as Tanaka&apos;s diary says that he was in Kyoto on that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>墓所は山口県下関市。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His tomb is in Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasugi&apos;s tomb is in Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasugi&apos;s tomb is in Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="77">
<j>なお、木戸孝允・大村益次郎らによって、現在の靖国神社に、東京招魂社時代の始めから吉田松陰・久坂玄瑞・坂本龍馬・中岡慎太郎たちと共に表彰・鎮魂され、祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also enshrined and honored at Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine, which is currently Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, by Takayoshi KIDO and Matsujiro OMURA, together with Shoin YOSHIDA, Genzui KUSAKA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Shintaro NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also enshrined and honored at Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine, which is currently Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, by Takayoshi KIDO and Matsujiro OMURA, together with Shoin YOSHIDA, Genzui KUSAKA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Shintaro NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also enshrined and honored at Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine, which is currently Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, by Takayoshi KIDO and Matsujiro OMURA, together with Shoin YOSHIDA, Genzui KUSAKA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO and Shintaro NAKAOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>辞世の句：「おもしろき　こともなき世を　おもしろく」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His death poem is &quot;living an exciting life in the not-exciting world.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His death poem reads &quot;Living an exciting life in the not-exciting world.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His death poem reads &apos;Living an exciting life in the not-exciting world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>下の句は看病していた野村望東尼が「すみなすものは心なりけり」とつけたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last part of the poem, &quot;it depends on what a heart sees&quot; is said to have added by Motoni NOMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last part of the poem, &quot;It depends on what the heart sees&quot; is said to have added by Motoni NOMURA.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last part of the poem, &apos;It depends on what the heart sees&apos; is said to have added by Motoni NOMURA.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>しかし、この句は前年にすでに読んでいたという記録も残っており、正確ではないという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a theory says that it is not correct, since there is a record that this poem was created in the previous year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, another theory claims that this is not true, since there is a record indicating that the poem was created one year previously.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, another theory claims that this is not true, since there is a record indicating that the poem was created one year previously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>都々逸（どどいつ）の「三千世界の烏を殺し、主と朝寝がしてみたい」は一般に晋作の作であると言われている（木戸孝允作の説も有り）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A song of dodoitsu (Japanese popular love song in the 7-7-7-5 syllable pattern), &quot;killing all crows in the whole world, I want to sleep with you in the morning&quot; is widely considered to have made by Sinsaku (or Takayoshi KIDO according to another theory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A dodoitsu song (Japanese popular love song in the 7-7-7-5 syllable pattern), &quot;I want to kill the crow of the Three Thousand Worlds, and sleep with you in the morning&quot; is widely considered to have been penned by Shinsaku (or Takayoshi KIDO according to another theory).</e>
<cmt>This poem refers to the Buddhist universe and the Yatagarasu (八咫烏）; &quot;you&quot; is believed to refer to the aforementioned lover &quot;おうの&quot; or &quot;うの&quot;. Ref. http://detail.chiebukuro.yahoo.co.jp/qa/question_detail/q1410459569</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A dodoitsu song (Japanese popular love song in the 7-7-7-5 syllable pattern), &apos;I want to kill the crow of the Three Thousand Worlds, and sleep with you in the morning&apos; is widely considered to have been penned by Shinsaku (or Takayoshi KIDO according to another theory).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>この都々逸は、現在でも萩の民謡である「男なら」や「ヨイショコショ節」の歌詞として唄われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This dodoitsu song is still sung at the present day as lyrics of folk songs in Hagi, such as &quot;Otoko nara&quot; and &quot;Yoishokosho bushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This dodoitsu song is still sung today as the lyrics of folk songs in Hagi City, such as &quot;Otoko nara&quot; and &quot;Yoishokosho bushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording, clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This dodoitsu song is still sung today as the lyrics of folk songs in Hagi City, such as &apos;Otoko nara&apos; and &apos;Yoishokosho bushi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="83">
<j>顕彰碑には｢動けば雷電の如く発すれば風雨の如し､衆目駭然､敢て正視する者なし｡これ我が東行高杉君に非ずや...｣ とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monument of honer says, &quot;moving like lightning, speaking like a storm, astonishing everone and no one dares to face him. This is our Togyo Takasugi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His monument of honor says, &quot;Moving like the lightning, speaking like the storm, all are astonished and none dare face him. This is our Togyo Takasugi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His monument of honor says, &apos;Moving like the lightning, speaking like the storm, all are astonished and none dare face him. This is our Togyo Takasugi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>これは伊藤博文が高杉晋作を評した言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a comment of Hirobumi ITO on Shinsaku TAKASUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a comment by Hirobumi ITO on Shinsaku TAKASUGI.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a comment by Hirobumi ITO on Shinsaku TAKASUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family Lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family Lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family Lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>高杉氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takasugi clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takasugi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takasugi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>高杉氏のルーツは諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories about the origin of the Takasugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about the origin of the Takasugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about the origin of the Takasugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>小説家の司馬遼太郎は現在の広島県三次市高杉の｢高杉城｣を晋作のルーツであると指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Novelist Ryotaro SHIBA has pointed out that Shinsaku had his origin in &quot;Takasugi-jo Castle&quot; now in Takasugi, Miyoshi City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Novelist Ryotaro SHIBA has pointed out that Shinsaku had his origin in &quot;Takasugi-jo Castle&quot; now in Takasugi, Miyoshi City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Novelist Ryotaro SHIBA has pointed out that Shinsaku had his origin in &apos;Takasugi-jo Castle&apos; in present Takasugi, Miyoshi City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。now inをin presentに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>この高杉城は江田氏の配下にあった祝（はふりし）という神事に関わっていた人々の城跡という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Takasugi-jo Castle is said to be the castle ruins of hafurishi, people involved in Shinto rituals under the control of the Eda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Takasugi-jo Castle is said to be the castle ruins of hafurishi, people involved in Shinto rituals under the control of the Eda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Takasugi-jo Castle is said to be the castle ruins of hafurishi, people involved in Shinto rituals under the control of the Eda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>また、広島県安芸高田市に所在する｢高杉山城｣を指摘する説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory points out that it was &quot;Takasugi-yama-jo Castle&quot; in Akitakata City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory asserts that the castle was &quot;Takasugi-yama-jo Castle&quot; in Akitakata City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Although translated literally, 指摘 may be &quot;point out&quot;, but the passages here are talking about competing theories of origin.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory asserts that the castle was &apos;Takasugi-yama-jo Castle&apos; in Akitakata City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>こちらの城跡には高杉晋作が高杉氏の13代目の子孫であることを示す碑が晋作の子孫により昭和10年(1935年)に建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this former castle site, descendants of Shinsaku established a monument in 1935, indicating that Shinsaku was the thirteenth descendant of the Takasugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this former castle site, descendants of Shinsaku established a monument in 1935, indicating that Shinsaku was the thirteenth descendant of the Takasugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this former castle site, descendants of Shinsaku established a monument in 1935, indicating that Shinsaku was the thirteenth descendant of the Takasugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>どちらの高杉城も晋作とかかわりあるとおもわれるがはっきりしたことはわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both castles of Takasugi seem to be associated with Shinsaku, but it is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both castles of Takasugi seem to be associated with Shinsaku, but it is not clear which theory is correct.</e>
<cmt>Clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both castles of Takasugi seem to be associated with Shinsaku, but it is not clear which theory is correct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>高杉氏は安芸の守護職武田氏の配下でなんらかの神事に関わっていた一族だろうと推測する説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory presuming that the Takasugi clan was a vassal of the Takeda clan, military governor of Aki Province, and involved in some Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory presuming that the Takasugi clan was a vassal of the Takeda clan, military governors of Aki Province, and involved in some Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a theory presuming that the Takasugi clan was a vassal of the Takeda clan, military governors of Aki Province, and involved in some Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>家紋は丸に四つ割菱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest is the design of a diamond divided into four parts in a circle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest is a diamond divided into four parts inside a circle.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest is a diamond divided into four parts inside a circle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 雪村(id:75006), Nnh(id:474), Isuka(id:1126), 宗純(id:232846), 22010515528(id:43149), Cprobot(id:97843), Tast(id:29478), Tribot(id:186681), Jazzy(id:3202), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), Michey.M(id:906), Northface(id:70750), IwaimBot(id:190695), Stitts(id:161422), Koshoku(id:15691), Point136(id:211299), R.Sakamoro(id:149509), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), Pipimaru(id:24707), Maakun(id:16735), FlaBot(id:30804), 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Woyzzeck(id:8923), Moltke(id:17553), GoGoDoll(id:131511), Wiki708(id:85953), ＫｏＺ(id:48584), よもすがら(id:212112), 樒(id:35770), Itten(id:163884), Tietew(id:4054), Tetumusi(id:19527), Trashwriter(id:79181), Alexbot(id:157199), けんち(id:5147), 机龍之介(id:61257), Broad-Sky(id:68334), みょうじ(id:124419), ドルチェット(id:46458), 松岡龍獅(id:143549), Reggaeman(id:6214), Polyester(id:9559), Torajiro(id:169171), Tan-kam(id:213071), 丸山高弘(id:115038), Jinnsg(id:43599), Ponta2(id:129030), 竹麦魚(id:11012), BBBeaver(id:101597), 梅の里(id:15035), Bankokuya(id:91191), Bsx(id:38434), Poe(id:16973), Airship(id:51549), Etopirica(id:32491), しるふぃ(id:11247), Race(id:131322), 怪盗蓬月(id:132496), Hrowtr(id:280079), Carbucketty(id:253794), 貘(id:106080), きゅうり(id:2182), 上田隼人(id:23104), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>