<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中村春続</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harutsugu NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harutsugu NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harutsugu NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中村春続（なかむらはるつぐ、生年不詳 - 天正9年10月24日（1581年11月19日）は戦国時代 (日本)、安土桃山時代の人物、初め大炊助、後に対馬守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harutsugu NAKAMURA (year of birth unknown - November 30, 1581) was a person who lived in Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) and Azuchi Momoyama Period, and he served as Oinosuke (vice-minister of Bureau of Palace Kitchens under the Ministry of the Imperial Household) in early times, and later, he served as Tsushima no kami (Governor of Tsushima Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harutsugu NAKAMURA (year of birth unknown - November 30, 1581) was a person who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) and the Azuchi Momoyama period, and he served as Oinosuke (vice-minister of Bureau of Palace Kitchens under the Ministry of the Imperial Household) in early times, and later, he served as the Governor of Tsushima Province.</e>
<cmt>the Sengoku period, the Azuchi-Momoyama periodに修正、Tsushima no kami (Governor of Tsushima Province)→the Governor of Tsushima Provinceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harutsugu NAKAMURA (year of birth unknown - November 30, 1581) was a person who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) and the Azuchi Momoyama period, and he served as Oinosuke (vice-minister of Bureau of Palace Kitchens under the Ministry of the Imperial Household) in early times, and later, he served as the Governor of Tsushima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>春続は山名豊国の家臣として知られ、山名氏に仕えた中村氏の一族といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harutsugu was known as a vassal of Toyokukni YAMANA, and it is said that he was a member of the Nakamura clan who served the Yamana clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harutsugu was known as a vassal of Toyokuni YAMANA, and it is said that he was a member of the Nakamura clan who served the Yamana clan.</e>
<cmt>Toyokukni→Toyokuniに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harutsugu was known as a vassal of Toyokuni YAMANA, and it is said that he was a member of the Nakamura clan who served the Yamana clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>史料上には永禄7から8年頃と推定される「山名豊儀書状写」に山名豊儀の被官・「中村大炊助」として登場するのが初見である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He first appeared in the historical document, &quot;Yamana Toyoyoshi no Shojo Utsushi&quot; which is thought to be written in about 1564 to 1565, as a hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Yoyoyoshi YAMANA &quot;NAKAMURA Oinosuke&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He first appeared in the historical document, &apos;Yamana Toyoyoshi no Shojo Utsushi&apos; which is thought to have been written in about 1564 to 1565, as a hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Toyoyoshi YAMANA &apos;Nakamura Oinosuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオドの位置を移動、to be written→have been written、Yoyoyoshi→Toyoyoshiに修正、 &apos;Nakamura Oinosuke&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He first appeared in the historical document, &apos;Yamana Toyoyoshi no Shojo Utsushi&apos; which is thought to have been written in about 1564 to 1565, as a hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of Toyoyoshi YAMANA &apos;Nakamura Oinosuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天正2年（1575年）には山名豊国の被官として吉川元春の許へ派遣されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1574, he was dispatched to Motoharu KIKKAWA`s as a hikan of Toyokuni YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>サイトで調べたところ天正２年は、1574年でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1574, he was dispatched to Motoharu KIKKAWA as a hikan of Toyokuni YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Motoharu KIKKAWA`s&quot; の&quot;`s&quot;削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1574, he was dispatched to Motoharu KIKKAWA as a hikan of Toyokuni YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天正8年（1580年）の豊臣秀吉の鳥取城攻撃の際、織田方に降伏した主君の山名豊国を森下道誉らと共に鳥取城より追放、新城主として吉川経家を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s Siege of Tottori-jo Castle in 1580, he expelled his lord, Toyokuni YAMANA, who surrendered to the ODA clan, from Tottori-jo Castle with Doyo MORISHITA, and welcomed Tsuneie KIKKAWA as a new castellan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s Siege of Tottori-jo Castle in 1580, he expelled his lord, Toyokuni YAMANA, who surrendered to the Oda clan, from Tottori-jo Castle with Doyo MORISHITA, and welcomed Tsuneie KIKKAWA as a new castellan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;、 &quot;→&quot;,&quot;に修正、the ODA clan→the Oda clanに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s Siege of Tottori-jo Castle in 1580, he expelled his lord, Toyokuni YAMANA, who surrendered to the Oda clan, from Tottori-jo Castle with Doyo MORISHITA, and welcomed Tsuneie KIKKAWA as a new castellan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>翌天正9年の第二次鳥取城攻撃では吉川経家らと鳥取城に籠り、秀吉軍と抗戦したが、歴史的にも名高い秀吉の兵糧攻めに遭い多くの餓死者を出すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, in 1581, he holed up in Tottori-jo Castle with Tsuneie KIKKAWA and other members during the second Siege of Tottori-jo Castle and resisted Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI army, however, many died of historic renowned Hideyoshi&apos;s starvation policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, in 1581, he holed up in Tottori-jo Castle with Tsuneie KIKKAWA and other members during the second Siege of Tottori-jo Castle and resisted Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI army, however, many died of historic renowned Hideyoshi&apos;s starvation policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, in 1581, he holed up in Tottori-jo Castle with Tsuneie KIKKAWA and other members during the second Siege of Tottori-jo Castle and resisted Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI army, however, many died of historic renowned Hideyoshi&apos;s starvation policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鳥取城は同年10月に吉川経家の切腹により開城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October in the same year, he surrendered Tottori-jo Castle to the enemy because of Tuneie KIKKAWA&apos;s seppuku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November in the same year, he surrendered Tottori-jo Castle to the enemy because of Tuneie KIKKAWA&apos;s seppuku.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November in the same year, he surrendered Tottori-jo Castle to the enemy because of Tuneie KIKKAWA&apos;s seppuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>生前の経家が春続と森下道誉の助命を嘆願するも聞き入れられず、「因幡一国に戦乱を招いた罪」と「主君への裏切りの罪」で切腹を命じられ、10月24日の晩、吉川経家が自刃した同じ陣所にて自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tuneie begged for Harutsugu and Doyo MORISHITA&apos;s lives before his death, his plead was refused and they were commanded to commit seppuku on charges that &quot;bringing the war in Indaba province &quot; and &quot;betrayal of their lord&quot;, then they committed suicide with their swords on the evening of October 24, at the same jinsho (camp) where Tsuneie YOSHIKAWA died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tuneie begged for Harutsugu and Doyo MORISHITA&apos;s lives before his death, his plead was refused and they were commanded to commit seppuku on charges that &apos;bringing the war in Inaba Province&apos; and &apos;betrayal of their lord,&apos; then they committed suicide with their swords on the evening of November 30, at the same jinsho (camp) where Tsuneie YOSHIKAWA died.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、余分なスペース消去、Indaba province→Inaba Provinceに修正、カンマの位置を移動、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tuneie begged for Harutsugu and Doyo MORISHITA&apos;s lives before his death, his plead was refused and they were commanded to commit seppuku on charges that &apos;bringing the war in Inaba Province&apos; and &apos;betrayal of their lord,&apos; then they committed suicide with their swords on the evening of November 30, at the same jinsho (camp) where Tsuneie YOSHIKAWA died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>享年などは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Year of his death is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death is unknown.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容と異なるため訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at death is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、鳥取城内にいた春続の子供は父・春続の切腹後、保護されて吉川氏の家臣となったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Harutsugu&apos;s children who stayed inside of Tottori-jo Castle were given protection after their father&apos;s seppuku, and became vassals of the Kikkawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Harutsugu&apos;s children who stayed inside of Tottori-jo Castle were given protection after their father&apos;s seppuku, and became vassals of the Kikkawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Harutsugu&apos;s children who stayed inside of Tottori-jo Castle were given protection after their father&apos;s seppuku, and became vassals of the Kikkawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>出自に関する異説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different opinion concerning Harutsugu NAKAMURA&apos;s origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different opinion concerning Harutsugu NAKAMURA&apos;s origin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Different opinion concerning Harutsugu NAKAMURA&apos;s origin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>通説では因幡中村氏の一族と言われるが、これには異説が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a common view, Harutsugu Nakamura was a member of the Nakamura clan in Inaba, however, different view existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a common view, Harutsugu NAKAMURA was a member of the Nakamura clan in Inaba, however, different view existed.</e>
<cmt>Harutsugu NAKAMURAに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a common view, Harutsugu NAKAMURA was a member of the Nakamura clan in Inaba, however, different view existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一説によれば春続は同国智頭郡の草刈氏の出身とも言われ、近年発見された播磨国の中村氏系図内にも春続の名が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a theory, it is also said that Harutsugu was from the Kusakari clan in Chizu no kori, Inaba no kuni, and his name was recorded in a family tree of the Nakamura clan in Harima Province, which was found in recent years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory, it is also said that Harutsugu was from the Kusakari clan in Chizu County, Inaba Province, and his name was recorded in a family tree of the Nakamura clan in Harima Province, which was found in recent years.</e>
<cmt>Chizu no kori→Chizu County、Inaba no kuni→Inaba Provinceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a theory, it is also said that Harutsugu was from the Kusakari clan in Chizu County, Inaba Province, and his name was recorded in a family tree of the Nakamura clan in Harima Province, which was found in recent years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>参考までにだが『中村家譜』（内題・因州中村家由来）には中村家を継承したのは春続の弟・春国と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just for your information, in &quot;the Nakamura family genealogy&quot; (the title inside the book: the origins of the Nakamura clan in Inshu domain) it is recorded that Harutsugu and his younger brother 春国 succeeded to the Nakamura clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just for your information, in &quot;The Nakamura Family Genealogy&quot; (the title inside the book: the origins of the Nakamura clan in Inshu [Inaba Province]) it is recorded that Harutsugu and his younger brother Harukuni (春国) succeeded to the Nakamura clan.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、半角カッコに修正、&quot;The Nakamura Family Genealogy&quot;、春国→Harukuni (春国)とし、因州=因幡国のため、Inshu domain→Inshu [Inaba Province]としました。(参考: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%9B%A0%E5%B7%9E)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just for your information, in &quot;The Nakamura Family Genealogy&quot; (the title inside the book: the origins of the Nakamura clan in Inshu [Inaba Province]) it is recorded that Harutsugu and his younger brother Harukuni (春国) succeeded to the Nakamura clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>春国は医術を学んだ後に吉川氏に仕え、50石で召抱えられたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also recorded that after 春国 studied medical science, he served the Yoshikawa clan and employed by 50 koku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also recorded that after Harukuni (春国) studied medical science, he served the Yoshikawa clan and employed by 50 koku.</e>
<cmt>春国→Harukuni (春国)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also recorded that after Harukuni (春国) studied medical science, he served the Yoshikawa clan and employed by 50 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>