<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原俊成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA-no-Toshinari (aka Shunzei)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA-no-Toshinari (aka Shunzei)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshinari</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース補足しました。他の読みは削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原俊成（ふじわら の としなり、永久 (元号)2年（1114年）-元久元年11月30日 (旧暦)（1204年12月29日）は平安時代後期から鎌倉時代初期の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA-no-Toshinari (born 1114, died December 29, 1204) was a poet who lived from the latter part of the Heian period through to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA-no-Toshinari (born 1114, died December 29, 1204) was a poet who lived from the latter part of the Heian period through the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshinari (born 1114, died December 29, 1204) was a poet who lived from the latter part of the Heian period through the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>有職読みで「しゅんぜい」とも読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pen-name was read as &quot;Shunzei&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pen-name was read as &quot;Shunzei&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His yusoku-yomi (expression of respect) was read as &apos;Shunzei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>pen-nameを有職読み→yusoku-yomi (expression of respect)に訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>はじめ葉室家に養子に入り葉室顕広（あきひろ）を名乗ったが後に実家の御子左家に戻り改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially he was adopted by the Hamuro family and took the name Akihiro HAMURO however, subsequently he returned to his parents&apos; Mikohidari family home and changed his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially he was adopted by the Hamuro family and took the name Akihiro HAMURO; however, he subsequently returned to his parents&apos; Mikohidari family home and changed his name.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially he was adopted by the Hamuro family and took the name Akihiro HAMURO; however, he subsequently returned to his parents&apos; Mikohidari family home and changed his name.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法名は釈阿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name as a Buddhist priest was Shakua.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name as a Buddhist priest was Shakua.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name as a Buddhist priest was Shakua.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『千載和歌集』の編者として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Is known as the compiler of the &quot;Senzai wakashu&quot; (Millennium Anthology of Waka Poetry&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Is known as the compiler of the &quot;Senzai wakashu&quot; (Millennium Anthology of Waka Poetry).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Is known as the compiler of the &quot;Senzai wakashu&quot; (Millennium Anthology of Waka Poetry).</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifetime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lifetime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>早くから歌人としての活動を始め、藤原基俊に師事する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started his activities as a poet early on and, studied under FUJIWARA-no-Mototoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started his activities as a poet from an early age and studied under FUJIWARA-no-Mototoshi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started his activities as a poet from an early age and studied under FUJIWARA no Mototoshi.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>西行（西行）の出家に影響され、自身も一時その願望を持つ事となったが、平安末期の無常観を反映しつつ、万葉集や古今和歌集の伝統を踏まえた抒情性の豊かな歌風を確立し、当世風の新奇性を重視した六条流の歌風と当時の歌壇を二分した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influenced by the poet Saigyo becoming a priest, FUJIWARA-no-Toshinari himself held similar aspirations for a time but, reflecting the fluid nature of the late Heian period, he straddled two schools of contemporary poetry: the rich lyrical poetic styles established in the traditions of the Man&apos;yoshu and Kokin Wakashu (First Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry) and, avant-garde literary fashions of the day given prominence amongst Rokujo-school literati.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influenced by the poet Saigyo becoming a priest, FUJIWARA-no-Toshinari himself held similar aspirations for a time, but, reflecting the fluid nature of the late Heian period, he straddled two schools of contemporary poetry: the rich lyrical poetic styles established in the traditions of the Man&apos;yoshu and Kokin Wakashu (First Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry), and avant-garde literary fashions of the day given prominence amongst Rokujo-school literati.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influenced by the poet Saigyo becoming a priest, FUJIWARA no Toshinari himself held similar aspirations for a time, but, reflecting the fluid nature of the late Heian period, he straddled two schools of contemporary poetry: the rich lyrical poetic styles established in the traditions of the Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) and Kokin Wakashu (First Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry), and avant-garde literary fashions of the day given prominence amongst Rokujo-school literati.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース補足しました。Man’yoshuをManyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>和歌所寄人をつとめ、後白河天皇の院宣で単独で『千載和歌集』を編んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a key member of a Waka poetry group, Emperor Goshirakawa independently decreed the compilation of &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a key member of a Waka poetry group, Emperor Goshirakawa independently decreed the compilation of &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a key member of a Waka poetry group, Emperor Goshirakawa independently decreed the compilation of &quot;Senzai Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>歌学書には、『古来風躰抄』（後白河院の皇女である式子内親王に奉ったもの）のほか、『俊成卿和字奏状』『古今問答』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Books of poetry produced include &quot;&quot;Korai Futeisho&quot; (&quot;Poetic Styles from the Past&quot;) a tome presented to Imperial Princess Noriko (one of retired Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s ladies) as well as &quot;Shunzei Kyo Waji Sojo&quot; (&quot;Japanese Poetry of Shunzei&quot;) and &quot;Kokin Mondo&quot; (Ancient and Modern Questions and Answers&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Books of poetry produced include &quot;&quot;Korai Futeisho&quot; (&quot;Poetic Styles from the Past&quot;) a tome presented to Imperial Princess Noriko (one of retired Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s ladies) as well as &quot;Shunzei Kyo Waji Sojo&quot; (&quot;Japanese Poetry of Shunzei&quot;) and &quot;Kokin Mondo&quot; (Ancient and Modern Questions and Answers&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Books of poetry produced include &quot;Korai Futeisho&quot; (Poetic Styles from the Past) a tome presented to Imperial Princess Noriko (one of Retired Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s ladies) as well as &quot;Shunzei Kyo Waji Sojo&quot; (Japanese Poetry of Shunzei) and &quot;Kokin Mondo&quot; (Ancient and Modern Questions and Answers).</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。全角の’を半角にしました。不要、括弧内の&quot;を削除しました。Retired 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>選歌集に『俊成三十六人歌合』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A selection of his poetry is in &quot;Shunzei Thirty-Six Poetry Immortals&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A selection of his poetry appears in &quot;Shunzei Thirty-Six Poetry Immortals&quot;.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A selection of his poetry appears in &quot;Shunzei Thirty-Six Poetry Immortals.&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>家集に『長秋詠藻』『俊成家集』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collections of his poetic works are: &quot;Choushu Eiso&quot; (Choushu Palace Anthology&quot;) and &quot;Shunzei Kashu&quot; (&quot;Shunzei Poetry Anthology&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Ref: 吉原敏雄「俊成歌集について」　『国語と国文学』14（8）1937.8　pp.85-89【YA5-17】 in 国立国会図書館 http://crd.ndl.go.jp/GENERAL/servlet/detail.reference?id=1000040160However also lots of other www references to 家集. Either way &quot;Anthology&quot; makes sense I think. If you wish to change this please do so yourself.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collections of his poetic works are: &quot;Choushu Eiso&quot; (Choushu Palace Anthology&quot;) and &quot;Shunzei Kashu&quot; (&quot;Shunzei Poetry Anthology&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collections of his poetic works are: &quot;Choushu Eiso&quot; (Choushu Palace Anthology) and &quot;Shunzei Kashu&quot; (Shunzei Poetry Anthology).</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。括弧内の&quot;は不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『長秋詠藻』は六家集の一つに数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Choushu Eiso&quot; is six collections of poetry counted as one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Choushu Eiso&quot; is six collections of poetry counted as one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Choushu Eiso&quot; is six collections of poetry counted as one.</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また九条家の九条良経が催した六百番歌合の判者をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Yoshitsune KUJO of the Kujo family acted as a judge of the Six Hundred Round Poetry Contest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune KUJO of the Kujo family acted as a judge of the Six Hundred Round Poetry Contest.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;also&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsune KUJO of the Kujo family acted as a judge of the Six Hundred Round Poetry Contest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>指導者としても定評があり、九条家の歌の指導をおこなうほか、息子定家をはじめとして、門下に寂蓮、藤原家隆など優秀な歌人を多数輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As leader of the group he had a reputation and, besides directing the Kujo family in poetry matters, he produced a number of outstanding poets: commencing with his son Teika, his students included Jakuren and FUJIWARA no Ietaka etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As leader of the group he had a reputation and, besides directing the Kujo family in poetry matters, he produced a number of outstanding poets: commencing with his son Teika, his students included Jakuren and FUJIWARA no Ietaka etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As leader of the group he had a reputation and, besides directing the Kujo family in poetry matters, he produced a number of outstanding poets: commencing with his son Teika, his students included Jakuren and FUJIWARA no Ietaka etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『平家物語』「忠度都落」にも門下のひとり平忠度とのエピソードが描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;) he even paints a word picture of an episode involving one of his students TAIRA no Tadanori in: &apos;Tadanori miyako ochi` (&apos;Tadanori&apos;s Flight from the Capital`).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;) he even paints a word picture of an episode involving one of his students, TAIRA no Tadanori, in: &apos;Tadanori miyako ochi` (&apos;Tadanori&apos;s Flight from the Capital`).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike) he even paints a word picture of an episode involving one of his students, TAIRA no Tadanori, in: &apos;Tadanori miyako ochi&apos; (Tadanori&apos;s Flight from the Capital).</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。括弧内の&quot;は不要と考え削除しました。全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>（詳細は後述）また桐火桶を抱えながら歌を作る癖をからかわれていた事も有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details mentioned later) Also, he was also famous for the curious habit of holding onto a brazier made of Paulownia wood when composing poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Details mentioned later) Also, he was also famous for the curious habit of holding onto a brazier made of Paulownia wood when composing poems.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Details mentioned later) Also, he was also famous for the curious habit of holding onto a brazier made of Paulownia wood when composing poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>北家でも、権大納言を極官とした傍系の藤原長家流で、父と早く死別した事もあって出世は大きく遅れたが、当時としては異例の長寿を保ち、皇太后宮大夫正三位にまで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the Northern House, the most senior court rank of Gondainagon (Senior Major Counselor) was held by collateral family line FUJIWARA no Nagaie school and, his father died early which greatly delayed his promotion but, for those times he lived an extraordinary long life and advanced as far as Kotaigogu-Daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s palace) with a court rank of Shosan&apos;i (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the Northern House, the most senior court rank of Gondainagon (Senior Major Counselor) was held by the collateral family line FUJIWARA no Nagaie school, and his father died early, which greatly delayed his promotion, but for those times he lived an extraordinary long life and advanced as far as Kotaigogu-Daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s palace) with a court rank of Shosan&apos;i (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the Northern House, the most senior court rank of Gon Dainagon (a provisional councilor of state) was held by the collateral family line FUJIWARA no Nagaie school, and his father died early, which greatly delayed his promotion, but for those times he lived an extraordinary long life and advanced as far as Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household) with a court rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>権大納言→Gon Dainagon (a provisional councilor of state)皇太后宮大夫→Kotaigo gu no daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s Household)全角の’を半角に訂正しました。Shosan’iをShosanmiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>息子藤原定家の『小倉百人一首』には皇太后宮大夫俊成として採られるが、彼とともに社会が政治・経済的矛盾が深まる中、武家が政権を奪取する中世へ移行する、時代の激動期を生き抜き、歌の家としての御子左家の名を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his son FUJIWARA no Teika&apos;s &quot;Ogura Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (&quot;Ogura&apos;s Sequence of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets&quot;), Toshinari is engaged as Kotaigogu-Daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s palace) but, with him there was an intensification of political/economic contradictions in society, a shift to the middle ages where the warrior families took back political control, the period was marked by upheaval and the Mikohidari family cemented its name as poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his son FUJIWARA no Teika&apos;s &quot;Ogura Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (&quot;Ogura&apos;s Sequence of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets&quot;), Toshinari is engaged as Kotaigogu-Daibu (Master of the Empress Dowager&apos;s palace), but with him there was an intensification of political/economic contradictions in society, a shift to the middle ages where the warrior families took back political control; the period was marked by upheaval and the Mikohidari family cemented its name as poets.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his son FUJIWARA no Teika&apos;s &quot;Ogura Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (Ogura&apos;s Sequence of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets), Toshinari is engaged as Kotaigo gu no daibu, but with him there was an intensification of political/economic contradictions in society, a shift to the middle ages where the warrior families took back political control; the period was marked by upheaval and the Mikohidari family cemented its name as poets.</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。括弧内の&quot;は不要と考え削除しました。全角の’を半角にしました。皇太后宮大夫→Kotaigo gu no daibu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>俊成と平忠度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshinari &amp; TAIRA no Tadanori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshinari &amp; TAIRA no Tadanori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshinari and TAIRA no Tadanori</e>
<cmt>&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>俊成に関するエピソードで第一に思い浮かぶのが源平合戦（治承・寿永の乱）の最中の平忠度との再会であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first episode involving Toshinari that comes to mind occurs during the Genpei-gassen (Battle of the Minamoto and Taira clans) also known as the Jisho Juei no ran (Jisho/Juei era War) when TAIRA no Tadanori reunite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first episode involving Toshinari that comes to mind occurred during the Genpei-gassen (Battle of the Minamoto and Taira clans), also known as the Jisho Juei no ran (Jisho/Juei era War), when Toshinari and TAIRA no Tadanori reunited.</e>
<cmt>added missing words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first episode involving Toshinari that comes to mind occurred during the Genpei-gassen (Battle of the Minamoto and Taira clans), also known as the Jisho Juei no ran (Jisho/Juei era War), when Toshinari and TAIRA no Tadanori reunited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>『平家物語』巻7『忠度都落』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a record in folio 7 &apos;Tadanori miyako ochi` (&apos;Tadanori&apos;s Flight from the Capital`) of the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;) but,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a record in folio 7 &apos;Tadanori miyako ochi` (&apos;Tadanori&apos;s Flight from the Capital`) of the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;) but,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a record in folio 7 &quot;Tadanori miyako ochi&quot; (Tadanori&apos;s Flight from the Capital) of the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処原文の『』に合せて&apos;を&quot;に訂正しました。括弧説明の&apos;は不要と考え削除しました。but,削除し、ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>武勇も優れていたが、歌人としても俊成に師事し、才能に優れていた平清盛末弟の平忠度は1183年（寿永2）7月 (旧暦)の平氏一門都落ちの際、都に引き返し、俊成の邸を訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">whilst his martial prowess was outstanding, even as a poet he looked up to Toshinari, in July 1183 when the entire Taira clan fled Kyoto, TAIRA no Tadanori (the outstanding genius Kiyomori&apos;s youngest brother) handed over the capital and visited Toshinari&apos;s estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">whilst his martial prowess was outstanding, even as a poet he looked up to Toshinari; in July 1183, when the entire Taira clan fled Kyoto, TAIRA no Tadanori (the outstanding genius Kiyomori&apos;s youngest brother) handed over the capital and visited Toshinari&apos;s estate.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst his martial prowess was outstanding, even as a poet he looked up to Toshinari; in July 1183, when the entire Taira clan fled Kyoto, TAIRA no Tadanori (the outstanding genius Kiyomori&apos;s youngest brother) handed over the capital and visited Toshinari&apos;s estate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処文頭を大文字にしました。全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>動揺する家人達にかまわず会った俊成に忠度が頼んだのはもし勅撰和歌集が作られるのなら、自分の歌を一首入れてほしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Careful not to upset his already agitated family members, Tadanori met with Toshinari and Tadanori requested that if an Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poems was compiled that he wanted on of his poems included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Careful not to upset his already agitated family members, Tadanori met with Toshinari and requested that if an Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poems was compiled that he wanted on of his poems included.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Careful not to upset his already agitated family members, Tadanori met with Toshinari and requested that if an Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poems was compiled that he wanted on of his poems included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>さすれば草葉の陰からお守りするとの頼みだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If that was to be the case Toshinari also asked to be taken good care of in his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If that was to be the case, Toshinari also asked to be taken good care of in his life.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If that was to be the case, Toshinari also asked to be taken good care of in his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>まもなく忠度は一ノ谷の戦いで戦死したが、俊成は朝廷への配慮から詠み人知らずとして『千載集』に載せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently Tadanori died in the Battle of Ichinotani but, Toshinari had insights from the Imperial court and had the &quot;Senzai shu&quot; (&quot;Millennium&quot;) Anthology author noted as anonymous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently Tadanori died in the Battle of Ichinotani, but Toshinari had insights from the Imperial court and had the &quot;Senzai shu&quot; (&quot;Millennium&quot;) Anthology author noted as anonymous.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently Tadanori died in the Battle of Ichinotani, but Toshinari had insights from the Imperial Court and had the &quot;Senzai shu&quot; (Millennium) Anthology author noted as anonymous.</e>
<cmt>Courtを大文字にしました。括弧説明内の&quot;は不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その加護があったのか、既に70近かった俊成は更に20年余り生きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether it was divine intervention or not, Toshinari went on to live to around 70: a further 20 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether it was divine intervention or not, Toshinari went on to live to around 70: a further 20 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether it was divine intervention or not, Toshinari went on to live to around 70: a further 20 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>なお、薨去の4ヶ月前には平氏に代わって政権を握り、鎌倉幕府を建てた源氏も前将軍源頼家が御家人の勢力争いの中命を落とし、それを見ていた専制的君主後鳥羽上皇が政治の主導権を朝廷に取り戻そうとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, 4 months before he passed away, political power was grasped and shifted to the Taira clan, the Genji clan who had built the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the previous Shogun Minamoto No Yoriie lost their lives in power struggles with gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogun in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods) and, seeing this the autocratic monarch retired Emperor Gotoba took back the reigns of government from the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, 4 months before he passed away, political power was grasped and shifted to the Taira clan; the Genji clan, who had built the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and the previous Shogun Minamoto No Yoriie lost their lives in power struggles with gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogun in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods) and, seeing this, the autocratic monarch retired Emperor Gotoba took back the reigns of government from the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, 4 months before he passed away, political power was grasped and shifted to the Taira clan; the Genji clan, who had built the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and the previous Shogun MINAMOTO no Yoriie lost their lives in power struggles with gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogun in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods) and, seeing this, the autocratic monarch Retired Emperor Gotoba took back the reigns of government from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Minamoto No YoriieをMINAMOTO no Yoriieに訂正しました。Retired大文字にしました。imperial courtをImperial Courtに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>早くから出家願望があった俊成だったが、改めて世の無常をかみ締めていたのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since early on, Toshinari had aspirations to join the Buddhist priesthood but, it is possible he considered the shifting uncertainties of the world at large.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since early on, Toshinari had aspirations to join the Buddhist priesthood, but it is possible he considered the shifting uncertainties of the world at large.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since early on, Toshinari had aspirations to join the Buddhist priesthood, but it is possible he considered the shifting uncertainties of the world at large.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="30">
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*Dates=Lunar calendar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*Dates=Lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dates: Lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>記号削除しました。＝は：に訂正しました。また。下記の日付は新暦に訂正します。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>1123年（保安 (元号)4）、父俊忠薨去により、藤原顕頼の養子となり、顕広と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the death of his father Toshitada in 1123, becomes the adopted son of FUJIWARA no Akiyori and takes the name Akihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the death of his father Toshitada in 1123, becomes the adopted son of FUJIWARA no Akiyori and takes the name Akihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the death of his father Toshitada in 1123, becomes the adopted son of FUJIWARA no Akiyori and takes the name Akihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>1127年（大治2）1月19日、従五位下に叙せられ、美作守に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1127 is conferred the court rank of Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade and is appointed as governor of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1127 is conferred the court rank of Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade and is appointed governor of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 10, 1127: conferred the court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and is appointed Mimasaka no kami (Governor of Mimasaka Province).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。日付補足。表記を訂正しました。Jugoinoge、Mimasaka no kami 補足、説明を括弧書きに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>1132年（天承2）閏4月4日、加賀守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 4, 1132 takes up the post of Governor of Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 4, 1132 takes up the post of Governor of Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 27, 1132: took up the post of Kaga no kami (Governor of Kaga Province).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。Kaga no kami 補足、説明を括弧書きに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>1137年（保延3）12月16日、遠江守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 16, 1137 takes up the post of Governor of Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 16, 1137 takes up the post of Governor of Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 4, 1138, took up the post of Totomi no kami (Governor of Totomi Province).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。Totomi no kami 補足、説明を括弧書きに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>1142年（永治2）1月23日、遠江守を重任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 23, 1142 reappointed as Governor of Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 23, 1142 reappointed Governor of Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 27, 1142: reappointed Totomi no kami.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。Totomi no kami 補足、説明は前出のため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="37">
<j>1145年（久安元）11月23日、従五位上に昇叙し、遠江守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 23 1145 promoted to the court rank of Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade and, Governor of Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 23 1145 promoted to the court rank of Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade and Governor of Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 14, 1146: promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained his position as Totomi no kami.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。 Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)に訂正しました。Totomi no kami 補足、説明は前出のため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>12月30日、三河守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 30 takes up the post of Governor of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 30 takes up the post of Governor of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 19, 1146: took up the post of Mikawa no kami (Governor of Mikawa Province).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。Mikawa no kami 補足、説明を括弧書きに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="39">
<j>1149年（久安5）4月9日、丹後守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 9, 1149 takes up the post of Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 9, 1149 takes up the post of Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 34, 1149: took up the post of Tango no kami (Governor of Tango Province).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。Tango no kami 補足、説明を括弧書きに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="40">
<j>1150年（久安6）1月6日、正五位下に昇叙し、丹後守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 6, 1150 promoted to the court rank of Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade and, Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6, 1150 promoted to the court rank of Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade and Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 12, 1150: promoted to the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Tango no kami.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)に訂正しました。Tango no kami 補足、説明は前出のため削除しました。retained his position as 補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="41">
<j>1151年（久安7）1月6日、従四位下に昇叙し、丹後守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 6, 1151 promoted to the court rank of Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade and, Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6, 1151 promoted to the court rank of Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade and Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 1, 1151: promoted to the court rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Tango no kami.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表記を訂正しました。Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)に訂正しました。Tango no kami 補足、説明は前出のため削除しました。retained his position as 補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="42">
<j>1152年（仁平2）12月30日、左京権大夫に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 30 December, 1152 transferred to role of Sakyogondaibu (acting master of the office of the left side of the Capital).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On 30 December, 1152 transferred to role of Sakyogondaibu (acting master of the office of the left side of the Capital).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 2, 1153: transferred to role of Sakyo no gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。左京権大夫→Sakyo no gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Eastern Capital Offices)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="43">
<j>1155年（久寿2）10月23日、従四位上に昇叙し、左京権大夫如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 23, 1155 promoted to the court rank of Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade and Sakyogondaibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 23, 1155 promoted to the court rank of Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade and Sakyogondaibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 26, 1155: promoted to the court rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained his position as Sakyo no gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。左京権大夫→Sakyo no gon no daibuJushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)に訂正しました。retained his position as 補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="44">
<j>1157年（保元2）10月22日、正四位下に昇叙し、左京権大夫如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 22, 1157 promoted to court rank of Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade and, Sakyogondaibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 22, 1157 promoted to court rank of Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade and Sakyogondaibu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 2, 1157: promoted to court rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Sakyo no gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。左京権大夫→Sakyo no gon no daibuShoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)に訂正しました。retained his position as 補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="45">
<j>1161年（応保元）9月19日、左京大夫に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 19, 1161 takes up the position of Sakyodaibu (master of the office of the left side of the Capital).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 19, 1161 takes up the position of Sakyodaibu (master of the office of the left side of the Capital).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 19, 1161 takes up the position of Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。左京大夫→Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="46">
<j>1166年（永万2）1月12日、左京大夫を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 12, 1166 resigns as Sakyodaibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 12, 1166 resigns as Sakyodaibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 21, 1166: resigns as Sakyo no daibu.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。左京大夫→Sakyo no daibu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>改元して仁安元年8月27日、従三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 27, 1166 promoted to court rank of Junior Third Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 27, 1166 promoted to court rank of Junior Third Rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 30, 1166: promoted to court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)に訂正しました、</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="48">
<j>1167年（仁安 (日本)2）1月28日、正三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 28, 1167 promoted to court rank of Senior Third Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 28, 1167 promoted to court rank of Senior Third Rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 26, 1167: promoted to court rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank)に訂正しました、</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>12月24日、諱を俊成と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 24, his real name altered to Toshinari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 24, his real name was altered to Toshinari.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 11, 1168: his real name was altered to Toshinari.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="50">
<j>1168年（仁安3）12月12日、右京大夫に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 12, 1168 is appointed as Ukyodaibu (master of the office of the right side of the Capital).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 12, 1168 is appointed Ukyodaibu (master of the office of the right side of the Capital).</e>
<cmt>omitted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 1169: appointed Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。右京大夫→Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="51">
<j>1170年（嘉暦2）7月26日、皇后宮大夫（後白河の皇后藤原忻子）を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 26, 1170 concurrently holds the role of kogogu-daibu (master of the palace of the Empress (Goshirakawa&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Kinshi)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 26, 1170 concurrently holds the role of kogogu-daibu (master of the palace of the Empress (Goshirakawa&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Kinshi)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 15, 1170: concurrently holds the role of Kogogu daibu (Master of the Empress&apos;s Household) (Goshirakawa&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Kinshi).</e>
<cmt>原文の年号は「嘉応」の誤りと考えられます。新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。全角の’を半角にしました。皇后宮大夫→Kogogu daibu (Master of the Empress&apos;s Household)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="52">
<j>1171年（嘉暦3）1月18日、備前権守を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 18, 1171 concurrently holds the role of acting governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 18, 1171 concurrently holds the role of acting governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 3, 1171: concurrently holds the role of Bizen gon no kami (provisional governor of Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。備前権守→Bizen gon no kami (provisional governor of Bizen Province)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="53">
<j>1172年（承安 (日本)2）2月10日、皇后が皇太后となったため、皇后宮大夫から皇太后宮大夫に異動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the Empress became Dowager Empress on February 10, 1172, his position changed from kogogu-daibu to kotaigogu-daibu (master of the palace of Empress Dowager).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Empress became Dowager Empress on February 10, 1172, his position changed from kogogu-daibu to kotaigogu-daibu (master of the palace of Empress Dowager).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 13, 1172: because the Empress became Dowager Empress, his position changed from Kogogu daibu to Kotaigo gu no daibu.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。皇后宮大夫→Kogogu daibu皇太后宮大夫→Kotaigo gu no daibu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="54">
<j>1175年（承安5）12月8日、右京大夫を止む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 8, 1175 he ceased being Ukyodaibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 8, 1175 he ceased being Ukyodaibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 28, 1176: ceased being Ukyo no daibu.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。右京大夫→Ukyo no daibu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="55">
<j>1176年（安元2）9月28日、出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 28, 1176 he became a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 28, 1176 he became a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 8, 1176: became a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>法名：釈阿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist priest name: &quot;Shakua&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist priest name: &quot;Shakua&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist priest name: &quot;Shakua.&quot;</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="57">
<j>1204年（元久元）11月30日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dies on November 30, 1204.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dies on November 30, 1204.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dies on December 29, 1204.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>享年91</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age at death: 91.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age at death: 91.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age at death: 91.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), ととりん(id:31982), Ks8823(id:130146), 遊翔(id:153881), DOERAX(id:25212), MIsogi(id:20599), Cprobot(id:97843), Urania(id:7213), 春野秋葉(id:36725), 味っ子(id:17086), Aphaia(id:3132), 前図書頭(id:134750), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Kamitani(id:30757), Masyu(id:31065), Rusk(id:9895), さららゆら(id:12274), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), UMBRO(id:100484), Point136(id:211299), 平惣衛門(id:99387), 岡部碩道(id:182846), 麦塚ほとり(id:54917), Kzhr(id:131), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>