<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原朝光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Asateru (or Asamitsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Asateru</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Asateru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 朝光 （ふじわら の あさてる　または　あさみつ、天暦5年（951年） - 長徳元年3月20日 (旧暦)（995年4月22日））は平安時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Asateru (or Asamitsu) (951 - April 22, 995) was a court noble in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Asateru (or Asamitsu) (951 - April 22, 995) was a court noble who lived during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Asateru (or Asamitsu) (951 - April 22, 995) was a court noble who lived during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>太政大臣藤原兼通の次男（三男、四男とも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, the then Daijo Daijin (Chancellor of State) (or was said to be the third or fourth son).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have been the second son of FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, the then Daijo Daijin (Chancellor of State), although he might have been the third or fourth son.</e>
<cmt>edited to improve clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have been the second son of FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, the then Daijo Daijin (Chancellor of State), although he might have been the third or fourth son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は有明親王（醍醐天皇皇子）の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Imperial Prince Ariakira (son of Emperor Daigo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Imperial Prince Ariakira (son of Emperor Daigo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Imperial Prince Ariakira (son of Emperor Daigo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄に左大臣藤原顕光、妹に円融天皇中宮藤原こう子などがあり、子に藤原朝経、花山天皇女御藤原姚子などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brother was FUJIWARA no Akimitsu, Minister of the Left, his younger sister FUJIWARA no Koko, Empress, or the wife of Emperor Enyu, his son FUJIWARA no Asatsune, and his daughter FUJIWARA no Choshi, court lady serving Emperor Kazan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brother was FUJIWARA no Akimitsu (who served as Minister of the Left), his younger sister was FUJIWARA no Koko (Empress of Emperor Enyu), his son was FUJIWARA no Asatsune, and his daughter was FUJIWARA no Choshi (a court lady who served Emperor Kazan).</e>
<cmt>removed “or the wife of”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brother was FUJIWARA no Akimitsu (who served as Sadaijin (minister of the left), his younger sister was FUJIWARA no Koko (Empress of Emperor Enyu), his son was FUJIWARA no Asatsune, and his daughter was FUJIWARA no Choshi (a court lady who served Emperor Kazan).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従二位、大納言、左大将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junii (Junior Second Rank), Dainagon (Chief Councillor of State), and Sakon&apos;e-no Daisho (General of the Left Imperial Guard).</e>
<cmt>左大将は、左近衛大将の略とのことですので、左記下の左近衛大将の略を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank), and served as Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) and Sakonoe-no Taisho (Western Commander).</e>
<cmt>edited to match terms column</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank), and served as Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) and Sadaisho/Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>閑院左大将と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Kanin Sadaisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Kanin Sadaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Kanin Sadaisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>若くしてその才覚を認められ、天延3年（975年）に25歳で中納言、貞元_(日本)2年（977年）には27歳で左近衛大将と順調に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With his intelligence recognized while he was still young, he was smoothly promoted to Chunagon in 975 at the age of 25 and Sakon&apos;e-no Daisho (General of the Left Imperial Guard) in 977 at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With his intelligence recognized while he was still young, he was smoothly promoted to Chunagon in 975 at the age of 25 and Sakon&apos;e-no Daisho (General of the Left Imperial Guard) in 977 at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With his intelligence recognized while he was still young, he was smoothly promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) in 975 at the age of 25 and Sakone no daisho in 977 at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>社交家で華美を好み、矢筈（はず）を石英で製することを考案し流行させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was sociable, liked gaiety and invented the idea of producing the notch of arrows with quartz and made it popular.</e>
<cmt>「矢筈（はず）を石英で製することを考案し」というのが、よくわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was sociable, liked gaiety and invented the idea of producing the notch of arrows with quartz and made it popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was sociable, liked gaiety and invented the idea of producing the nock of arrows with quartz and made it popular.</e>
<cmt>notch→nock</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>歌才にも定評があり、『拾遺和歌集』を初めとする勅撰和歌集に28首が入選。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known for his excellence in poet making; he had 28 of his poems included in &quot;chokusen wakashu,&quot; or anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command, including Shui wakashu (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known for his excellent poems, he had 28 of his poems included in &quot;chokusen wakashu,&quot; anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command, including Shui wakashu (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt>edited to improve clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known for his excellent poems, he had 28 of his poems included in &quot;chokusen wakashu,&quot; anthologies of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command, including Shui wakashu (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>小大君や馬内侍といった同時代の女流歌人達と恋愛関係を持ったことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known for his casual liaisons with his contemporary woman poets such as Kodai no Kimi and Uma no Naishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known for his casual liaisons with contemporary female poets, such as Kodai no Kimi and Uma no Naishi.</e>
<cmt>woman-&gt;female</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known for his casual liaisons with contemporary female poets, such as Kodai no Kimi (also known as Kookimi) and Uma no Naishi.</e>
<cmt>一般的な呼び名が2つあるので併記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>家集としては『朝光集』を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compilation of his own poems was &quot;Asateru shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compilation of his own poems was &quot;Asateru shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compilation of his own poems was &quot;Asateru shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>酒を通じては藤原道隆、藤原済時と格別に親しく交わり、道隆執政下の宮廷に自由な気風をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was in friendly terms particularly with FUJIWARA no Michitaka and FUJIWARA no Naritoki as drinking companions and brought a free atmosphere to the Imperial Court under the reign of Michitaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was on especially friendly terms with FUJIWARA no Michitaka and FUJIWARA no Naritoki as drinking companions and brought a free atmosphere to the Imperial Court under the reign of Michitaka.</e>
<cmt>in-&gt;on, particularly-&gt;especially</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was on especially friendly terms with FUJIWARA no Michitaka and FUJIWARA no Naritoki as drinking companions and brought a free atmosphere to the Imperial Court under the reign of Michitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>永延元年（987年）に大納言昇任、なおも前途を期待されたが、長徳元年（995年）の天然痘の大流行により、道隆、済時らと相前後して世を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 987, he was promoted to Dainagon but died of smallpox that became a pandemic at that time almost simultaneously with his drinking friends Michitaka and Naritoki although he was still expected to have a brighter future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 987, he was promoted to Dainagon, and though he had a bright future ahead of him, he died in a smallpox epidemic at almost the same time as his drinking buddies Michitaka and Naritoki.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 987, he was promoted to Dainagon (chief councilor of state), and though he had a bright future ahead of him, he died in a smallpox epidemic at almost the same time as Michitaka and Naritoki.</e>
<cmt>原文に「his drinking buddies」はありません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), Lonicera(id:20638), Cprobot(id:97843), 怪蘇(id:45514), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), YOSHI438(id:174755), BAKU(id:55205), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>