<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中臣鎌子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAKATOMI no Kamako</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAKATOMI no Kamako</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAKATOMI no Kamako</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>中臣 鎌子（なかとみのかまこ、生没年不詳）は飛鳥時代、欽明天皇の時代の連。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAKATOMI no Kamako (dates of birth and death unknown) was an official who was ranked &apos;Muraji&apos; during the era of Emperor Kinmei in the Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAKATOMI no Kamako (dates of birth and death unknown) was a muraji clan (one of ancient hereditary titles denoting rank and political standing) during the era of Emperor Kinmei in the Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正。「連」は補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAKATOMI no Kamako (dates of birth and death unknown) was a muraji clan (one of ancient hereditary titles denoting rank and political standing) during the era of Emperor Kinmei in the Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仏教公伝に際して、これに強く反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He strongly protested against the official introduction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He strongly protested against the official introduction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He strongly protested against the official introduction of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>欽明天皇13年（552年）百済の聖明王の使者が仏像と経論数巻を献じ、上表して仏教の功徳をたたえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 552, an envoy of Shomyoo (the 26th King) of Paekche (Kingdom in early Korea) offered a Buddha statue and several volumes of &quot;Kyoron&quot; (Dharma teachings of Buddha and its commentaries) to Emperor Kinmei and praised the virtue of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 552, envoys of Shomyoo (the 26th King) of Paekche (Kingdom in early Korea) offered a Buddha statue and several volumes of &quot;Kyoron&quot; (Dharma teachings of Buddha and its commentaries) to Emperor Kinmei with a personal letter from Shomyoo to praise the virtue of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>・使者が1人とは考えにくいので、複数にしました。・「上表して」が抜けていたので補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 552, envoys of Shomyoo (the 26th King) of Paekche (Kingdom in early Korea) offered a Buddha statue and several volumes of &quot;Kyoron&quot; (Dharma teachings of Buddha and its commentaries) to Emperor Kinmei with a personal letter from Shomyoo to praise the virtue of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天皇は仏像を礼拝する可否を群臣に求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor asked his retainers whether or not Japan should worship the Buddha statue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor asked his retainers whether or not Japan should worship the Buddha statue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor asked his retainers whether or not Japan should worship the Buddha statue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大臣の蘇我稲目は礼拝に賛成したが、大連の物部尾輿と鎌子は反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SOGA no Iname, a minister, agreed to the warship, while MONONOBE no Okoshi, Omuraji (the highest ranking officials) and Kamako opposed to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SOGA no Iname, an oomi clan (one of ancient hereditary titles denoting rank and political standing and the most powerful version of omi), agreed to the worship of Buddha, while MONONOBE no Okoshi, an omuraji clan (the most powerful version of muraji) and Kamako opposed it.</e>
<cmt>「大臣」の解釈が間違っていたので修正しました。一応定訳はありましたが、結局は「連」と同じなので、「連」の定義を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SOGA no Iname, an oomi clan (one of ancient hereditary titles denoting rank and political standing and the most powerful version of omi), agreed to the worship of Buddha, while MONONOBE no Okoshi, an omuraji clan (the most powerful version of muraji) and Kamako opposed it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天皇は稲目に仏像を授けて礼拝させたが、間もなく疫病が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kinmei gave the statue to Iname and let him pray to it tentatively, but a plague started after a short while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kinmei gave the statue to Iname and assigned him to Buddhist services, but a plague broke out after a short while.</e>
<cmt>「礼拝させた」は「稲目の指導の下で行わせた」ということだと思うのでそのように処理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kinmei gave the statue to Iname and assigned him to Buddhist services, but a plague broke out after a short while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>尾輿と鎌子は蕃神を礼拝したために国神が怒ったのだとして仏像の廃棄を奏上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okoshi and Kamako blamed the worship of the foreign God for the catastrophe and proposed to the Emperor the disposal of the Buddha statue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okoshi and Kamako pointed out that our worship of banshin (god believed by foreigners) angered our own god and suggested to the Emperor that the statue should be disposed of.</e>
<cmt>より正確に翻訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okoshi and Kamako pointed out that our worship of banshin (god believed by foreigners) angered our own god and suggested to the Emperor that the statue should be disposed of.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天皇はこれを許して、仏像は難波の堀江に流され、寺は焼かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the approval for the disposal from the Emperor, the Buddha statue was discarded in the Horie canal, Nanba and the Palace was set on fire.</e>
<cmt>http://www.asuka-tobira.com/syotokutaishi/bukkyodenrai.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the approval for the disposal from the Emperor, the Buddha statue was discarded in Naniwa no Horie (a canal in Osaka) and the temples were set on fire.</e>
<cmt>・「寺」にPalaceが使われていましたが、templeとしました。・「難波の堀江」は固有名詞なので、そのように処理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the approval for the disposal from the Emperor, the Buddha statue was discarded in Naniwa no Horie (a canal in Osaka) and the temples were set on fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Jihi(id:261170), こぶまき(id:38278), 味っ子(id:17086), トホホ川(id:50502), Nnh(id:474), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>