<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北条氏政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北条 氏政（ほうじょう うじまさ）は、戦国時代 (日本)の相模国の武将・戦国大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa HOJO is a Japanese military commander and a daimyo in the Sengoku Period based in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa HOJO was a busho (Japanese military commander) and a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Sagami Province who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>「戦国大名」を修正しました。（用語統一）in the Sengoku→who lived during the Sengoku</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa HOJO was a busho (Japanese military commander) and a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Sagami Province who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後北条氏の第4代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth family head of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth family head of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth family head of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>personal history→Personal Historyと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>父・北条氏康の後を継いで北条氏の勢力拡大に務め最大版図を築くも、豊臣秀吉の台頭により小田原征伐を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa succeeded a territory expansion policy from his father, Ujiyasu HOJO, and achieved the biggest territory in the clan&apos;s history, but the rise of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI triggered the Siege of Odawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa succeeded the territory expansion policy from his father, Ujiyasu HOJO, and achieved the biggest territory in the clan&apos;s history, but the rise of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI led to the Siege of Odawara.</e>
<cmt>a→thetriggered→led toと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa succeeded the territory expansion policy from his father, Ujiyasu HOJO, and achieved the biggest territory in the clan&apos;s history, but the rise of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI led to the Siege of Odawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>数ヶ月の籠城の末に降伏し、弟の氏照とともに自害して、戦国大名北条氏による関東支配は終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After months of the Siege, Ujimasa surrendered and committed suicide with his brother, Ujiaki, which brought an end to the rule over the Kanto region by the warring lord, the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After months of the Siege, Ujimasa surrendered and committed suicide with his younger brother, Ujiteru, which brought an end to the rule over the Kanto region by the Sengoku daimyo, the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>brother→younger brotherUjiaki→Ujiteru（「北条氏照＝ほうじょううじてる」で確認しました。）warring lord→Sengoku daimyoと修正しました。（用語統一）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After months of the Siege, Ujimasa surrendered and committed suicide with his younger brother, Ujiteru, which brought an end to the rule over the Kanto region by the Sengoku daimyo, the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>家督相続</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>天文 (元号)7年（1538年）、第3代当主・北条氏康の次男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1538, Ujimasa was born the second son to the third family head, Ujiyasu HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1538, Ujimasa was born as the second son to the third family head, Ujiyasu HOJO.</e>
<cmt>asを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1538, Ujimasa was born as the second son to the third family head, Ujiyasu HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>氏康の長男・新九郎が夭折したために世子となり、新九郎のちに氏政と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Ujiyasu&apos;s first son, Shinkuro, died young, Ujimasa was appointed as the heir of Ujiyasu and renamed Shinkuro and later Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Ujiyasu&apos;s first son, Shinkuro, died young, Ujimasa became the heir of Ujiyasu and renamed Shinkuro and later Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>was appointed to as→becameと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Ujiyasu&apos;s first son, Shinkuro, died young, Ujimasa became the heir of Ujiyasu and renamed Shinkuro and later Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>天文23年（1554年）、父・氏康が武田信玄、今川義元との間で甲相駿三国同盟を成立させると、武田信玄の娘・黄梅院 (北条氏政正室)を正室に迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1554, when the father of Ujimasa, Ujiyasu, established an alliance with Shingen TAKEDA and Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, Ujimasa took a daughter of Shingen TAKEDA, Obai-in, for his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1554, when the father of Ujimasa, Ujiyasu, established an alliance Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (tripartite of Kai-Sagami-Suruga alliance) with Shingen TAKEDA and Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, Ujimasa took a daughter of Shingen TAKEDA, Obai-in, for his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>「甲相駿三国同盟」を補いました。Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (tripartite of Kai-Sagami-Suruga alliance)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1554, when the father of Ujimasa, Ujiyasu, established an alliance Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (tripartite of Kai-Sagami-Suruga alliance) with Shingen TAKEDA and Yoshimoto IMAGAWA, Ujimasa took a daughter of Shingen TAKEDA, Obai-in, for his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>夫婦仲は極めて良好であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were happily married.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were happily married.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were happily married.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>永禄2年（1559年）に父・氏康が隠居して家督を譲られ、北条家の第4代当主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After retiring in 1559, Ujiyasu transferred the reigns of the family to Ujimasa, and Ujimasa became the fourth family head of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1559, Ujiyasu retired and transferred the reigns of the family to Ujimasa, and Ujimasa became the fourth family head of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1559, Ujiyasu retired and transferred the reigns of the family to Ujimasa, and Ujimasa became the fourth family head of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>父・氏康存命中は氏康・氏政の両頭体制が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, diarchy by Ujiyasu and Ujimasa continued until Ujiyasu died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, diarchy by Ujiyasu and Ujimasa continued until Ujiyasu died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, diarchy by Ujiyasu and Ujimasa continued until Ujiyasu died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>氏康存命中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Ujiyasu was alive</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Ujiyasu was alive</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Ujiyasu was alive</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>家督相続後、氏政が最初に行なった仕事が北条家所領役帳の作成（代替わりの検地）とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the transfer of the reigns, Ujimasa was first assigned to create a tax ledger (a list of territories and the amount of rice yield) of vassals of the Hojo clan (a land survey was conducted every change of a family head).</e>
<cmt>●代替わり：当主の代替わりの意味で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the transfer of the headship, Ujimasa was first assigned to create a tax ledger (a list of territories and the amount of rice yield) of vassals of the Hojo clan (A land survey was conducted every change of a family head).</e>
<cmt>reigns→headshipと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the transfer of the headship, Ujimasa was first assigned to create a tax ledger (a list of territories and the amount of rice yield) of vassals of the Hojo clan (A land survey was conducted every change of a family head).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>民意を重視し、検地や徳政を行うための内政事情によって代替わりすることが北条氏の常套であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Hojo clan put an importance on the people&apos;s opinion, it was common for the clan to change a family head for domestic reasons such as to conduct a land survey or political reforms.</e>
<cmt>●徳政：政治改革の意で訳しています。●代替わり：当主の代替わりの意味で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Hojo clan valued the people&apos;s opinion, it was common for the clan to change a family head for domestic reasons such as to conduct a land survey or political reforms.</e>
<cmt>put an importance on→valuedと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Hojo clan valued the people&apos;s opinion, it was common for the clan to change a family head for domestic reasons such as to conduct a land survey or political reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>永禄4年（1561年）、越後国の上杉謙信（謙信）が関東・南陸奥の諸大名を糾合した大軍で小田原城を包囲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1561, Kenshin UESUGI of Echigo Province rallied other daimyos of the Kanto and southern Mutsu regions and besieged Odawara Castle by the huge army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1561, Kenshin UESUGI of Echigo Province rallied other daimyo of the Kanto and southern Mutsu regions and besieged Odawara-jo Castle by the huge army.</e>
<cmt>daimyos→daimyoOdawara Castle→Odawara-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1561, Kenshin UESUGI of Echigo Province rallied other daimyo of the Kanto and southern Mutsu regions and besieged Odawara-jo Castle by the huge army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>氏政は父・氏康主導のもとで籠城戦で対抗し、上杉軍を撃退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa followed Ujiyasu&apos;s lead to beat back the attack from the Uesugi army by the rojo-sen fighting method (fighting a battle in a castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa followed Ujiyasu&apos;s lead to beat back the attack from the Uesugi army and defeated them by holding the castle.</e>
<cmt>defeated themを補いました。the rojo-sen fighting method (fighting a battle in a castle)→holding the castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa followed Ujiyasu&apos;s lead to beat back the attack from the Uesugi army and defeated them by holding the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>越後に撤退した謙信が第4次川中島の戦いで武田信玄と戦って甚大な被害を受けると、信玄と呼応して北関東方面に侵攻、上杉方に奪われた領土の大半を奪い返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing that Kenshin, who withdrew to Echigo Province, suffered huge damage in the Fourth Battle of Kawanakajima against Shingen TAKEDA, Ujimasa coordinated with Shingen to invade the northern Kanto region and took back most of the territory seized by the Uesugi army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing that Kenshin, who withdrew to Echigo Province, suffered huge damage in the Fourth Battle of Kawanakajima against Shingen TAKEDA, Ujimasa coordinated with Shingen to invade the northern Kanto region and took back most of the territory seized by the Uesugi army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing that Kenshin, who withdrew to Echigo Province, suffered huge damage in the Fourth Battle of Kawanakajima against Shingen TAKEDA, Ujimasa coordinated with Shingen to invade the northern Kanto region and took back most of the territory seized by the Uesugi army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>永禄7年（1564年）の第2次国府台合戦では、緒戦こそ里見義弘の前に苦戦したが、氏政は北条綱成と共に里見軍の背後を攻撃して勝利を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1564, Ujimasa won the Second Kondai Battle by attacking the Satomi army from behind in coordination with Tsunashige HOJO, although Ujimasa struggled and suffered a setback in the first battle against Yoshihiro SATOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1564, Ujimasa won the Second Konodai Battle by attacking the Satomi army from behind in coordination with Tsunashige HOJO, although Ujimasa struggled and suffered a setback in the beginning of the battle against Yoshihiro SATOMI.</e>
<cmt>Kondai→Konodaifirst battle→beginning of the battleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1564, Ujimasa won the Second Konodai Battle by attacking the Satomi army from behind in coordination with Tsunashige HOJO, although Ujimasa struggled and suffered a setback in the beginning of the battle against Yoshihiro SATOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これによって、上総国に勢力を拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This victory cleared a way for Ujimasa to extend its power to Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This victory cleared a way for Ujimasa to extend its power to Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This victory cleared a way for Ujimasa to extend its power to Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>さらにこの勝利で上総土気城主・酒井胤治らが一時的ながら氏政に帰順している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also brought Taneharu SAKAI, the lord of Toke Castle of Kazusa Province, to swear allegiance to Ujimasa temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also brought Taneharu SAKAI, the lord of Toke-jo Castle of Kazusa Province, to swear allegiance to Ujimasa temporarily.</e>
<cmt>Toke Castle→Toke-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also brought Taneharu SAKAI, the lord of Toke-jo Castle of Kazusa Province, to swear allegiance to Ujimasa temporarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同年には武蔵国岩槻城主・太田資正の長男・太田氏資を調略して、資正を武蔵から追い武蔵全域の支配権を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Ujimasa removed Sukemasa OTA (the lord of Iwatsuki Castle of Musashi Province) from Musashi Province by maneuvering Ujisuke OTA, the eldest son of Sukemasa, and established the hegemony of the Hojo clan over the entire Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Ujimasa removed Sukemasa OTA (the lord of Iwatsuki Castle of Musashi Province) from Musashi Province by maneuvering Ujisuke OTA, the oldest son of Sukemasa, and established the hegemony of the Hojo clan over the entire Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>eldest→oldestと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Ujimasa removed Sukemasa OTA (the lord of Iwatsuki Castle of Musashi Province) from Musashi Province by maneuvering Ujisuke OTA, the oldest son of Sukemasa, and established the hegemony of the Hojo clan over the entire Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>永禄9年（1566年）、謙信を盟主としていた上野国の由良成繁が氏政に帰順した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1566, Narishige YURA of Kazuke Province, an ally of Kenshin, swore allegiance to Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1566, Narishige YURA of Kozuke Province, an ally of Kenshin, swore allegiance to Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>Kazuke→Kozukeと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1566, Narishige YURA of Kozuke Province, an ally of Kenshin, swore allegiance to Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これに連動して、佐野昌綱、北条高広らも氏政に帰順し、上野にも勢力を拡大する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In conjunction with the move, Masatsuna SANO and Takahiro KITAJO also swore allegiance to Ujimasa, which helped Ujimasa to expand his territory to Kazuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In conjunction with the move, Masatsuna SANO and Takahiro KITAJO also swore allegiance to Ujimasa, which helped Ujimasa to expand his territory to Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>Kazuke→Kozukeと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In conjunction with the move, Masatsuna SANO and Takahiro KITAJO also swore allegiance to Ujimasa, which helped Ujimasa to expand his territory to Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに下総国の簗田晴助（真里谷（武田）の一族にして足利晴氏の臣）も一時的に氏政に和したため、謙信と同盟している佐竹義重 (十八代当主)との直接対立が顕在化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as Harusuke YANADA (a family of the Mariya-Takeda clan and a vassal of Haruuji ASHIKAGA) of Shimousa Province was temporarily reconciled with Ujimasa, a confrontation between the Hojo clan and Yoshishige SATAKE (the eighteenth family head), an ally of Kenshin, came to the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as Harusuke YANADA (a family of the Mariya [Takeda] clan and a vassal of Haruuji ASHIKAGA) of Shimousa Province was temporarily reconciled with Ujimasa, a confrontation between the Hojo clan and Yoshishige SATAKE (the 18th family head), an ally of Kenshin, came to be actualized.</e>
<cmt>Takedaをカッコ内に入れ、修正しました。eighteenth→18ththe surface→be actualizedと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as Harusuke YANADA (a family of the Mariya [Takeda] clan and a vassal of Haruuji ASHIKAGA) of Shimousa Province was temporarily reconciled with Ujimasa, a confrontation between the Hojo clan and Yoshishige SATAKE (the 18th family head), an ally of Kenshin, came to be actualized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>佐竹に協調する里見、佐竹の客将となった資正などと臨戦状況となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Ujimasa prepared his army for a war against Yoshihiro SATOMI, who cooperated with the Satake clan, and also Sukemasa OTA, a guest shogun of the Satake army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Ujimasa prepared his army for a war against Satomi, who cooperated with the Satake clan, and also Sukemasa, a guest commander of the Satake army.</e>
<cmt>Yoshihiro SATOMI→SatomiSukemasa OTAと修正しました。guest shogun→guest commanderと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Ujimasa prepared his army for a war against Satomi, who cooperated with the Satake clan, and also Sukemasa, a guest commander of the Satake army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>永禄10年（1567年）、里見義堯・義弘父子が上総奪還を目指して侵攻する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1567, Yoshitaka and Yoshihiro SATOMI (a father and son) moved forces with an aim to regain the land of Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1567, Yoshitaka and Yoshihiro SATOMI (a father and son) moved forces with an aim to regain the land of Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1567, Yoshitaka and Yoshihiro SATOMI (a father and son) moved forces with an aim to regain the land of Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>氏政はこれを撃退しようと上総東部の低山である三舟山（君津市）に着陣し、水軍もこの砦と向かい合う佐貫城を窺った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the Hojo side, Ujimasa arrived at a fort in Mt. Mifune-yama (Kimitsu City), a low mountain in eastern Kazusa Province, to counterattack the Satomi army, while a navy of the Hojo clan was carefully watching Sanuki Castle located in the opposite side of the fort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Hojo side, Ujimasa arrived at a fort in Mt. Mifune (Kimitsu City), a low mountain in eastern Kazusa Province, to counterattack the Satomi army, while a navy of the Hojo clan was carefully watching Sanuki-jo Castle located in the opposite side of the fort.</e>
<cmt>Mt. Mifune-yama→Mt. MifuneSanuki Castle→Sanuki-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the Hojo side, Ujimasa arrived at a fort in Mt. Mifune (Kimitsu City), a low mountain in eastern Kazusa Province, to counterattack the Satomi army, while a navy of the Hojo clan was carefully watching Sanuki-jo Castle located in the opposite side of the fort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、旧里見配下の国人が侵攻軍に内通し、三崎水軍の侵攻も遅滞した状況で、三舟山砦は義堯に大敗して上総の支配権を失った（三船山の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, under the circumstances that a local lord, who was a former vassal of the Satomi clan, let out the information of the Hojo clan to the Satomi army and an invasion by Misaki Navy was delayed for some reasons, the Mifune-yama fort fell to Yoshitaka and Ujimasa lost the control over Kazusa Province (Battle of Mifune-yama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, under the circumstances that a local lord, who was a former vassal of the Satomi clan, let out the information of the Hojo clan to the invading army, and the invasion by Misaki Navy was delayed for some reasons, the Mifune-yama fort fell to Yoshitaka and Ujimasa lost the control over Kazusa Province (Battle of Mifune-yama).</e>
<cmt>Satomi army→invading armyan→theと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, under the circumstances that a local lord, who was a former vassal of the Satomi clan, let out the information of the Hojo clan to the invading army, and the invasion by Misaki Navy was delayed for some reasons, the Mifune-yama fort fell to Yoshitaka and Ujimasa lost the control over Kazusa Province (Battle of Mifune-yama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>この頃、駿河国の今川氏は、今川義元が織田信長に討たれて衰退の一途をたどっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the same time, the Imagawa clan of Suruga Province was on the verge of falling, as Yoshimoto IMAGAWA was killed by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the same time, the Imagawa clan of Suruga Province was on the verge of falling, as Yoshimoto IMAGAWA was killed by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the same time, the Imagawa clan of Suruga Province was on the verge of falling, as Yoshimoto IMAGAWA was killed by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これを好機と見た甲斐の武田信玄が三国同盟を覆し、永禄11年（1568年）12月に駿河に侵攻し、今川氏真（義元の嫡男）は没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shingen TAKEDA of Kai Province, who saw it as a good opportunity, reversed the tripartite alliance with the Imagawa clan and invaded Suruga Province in December 1568, causing a comlete fall of Ujizane IMAGAWA (heir of Yoshimoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Shingen TAKEDA of Kai Province, who saw it as a good opportunity, reversed the tripartite alliance with the Imagawa clan and invaded Suruga Province in December 1568, causing a complete fall of Ujizane IMAGAWA (heir of Yoshimoto).</e>
<cmt>comlete→completeと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shingen TAKEDA of Kai Province, who saw it as a good opportunity, reversed the tripartite alliance with the Imagawa clan and invaded Suruga Province in December 1568, causing a complete fall of Ujizane IMAGAWA (heir of Yoshimoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この信玄の駿河制圧に対抗するため、氏政は出陣し駿河薩埵峠まで進出して武田軍に対抗し、一旦は信玄の勢力を駿河から追放して駿河の一部を勢力圏に治めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To counteract the conquest of Suruga Province by Shingen, Ujimasa moved his forces up to Satta-toge Pass of Suruga Province and expelled the Shingen army from the Province once and gained a control over a part of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To counteract the conquest of Suruga Province by Shingen, Ujimasa moved his forces up to Satta-toge Pass of Suruga Province and expelled the Shingen army from the Province once and gained a control over a part of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To counteract the conquest of Suruga Province by Shingen, Ujimasa moved his forces up to Satta-toge Pass of Suruga Province and expelled the Shingen army from the Province once and gained a control over a part of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>さらに掛川城に籠城していた今川氏真を救出するため、三河国の徳川家康と和議を結び、氏政は氏真（氏真の正室は、氏政の妹の早川殿）を保護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, to save Ujizane IMAGAWA who held up fighting in Kakegawa Castle, Ujimasa had a peace negotiation with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA of Mikawa Province and succeeded in putting Ujizane under Ujimasa&apos;s protection (Ujizane&apos;s lawful wife was Ujimasa&apos;s younger sister, Hayakawa-dono).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, to save Ujizane IMAGAWA who held up fighting in Kakegawa-jo Castle, Ujimasa had a peace negotiation with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA of Mikawa Province, and succeeded in putting Ujizane (Ujizane&apos;s lawful wife was Ujimasa&apos;s younger sister, Hayakawa-dono) under Ujimasa&apos;s protection.</e>
<cmt>Kakegawa Castle→Kakegawa-jo Castleと修正しました。カッコ部分を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, to save Ujizane IMAGAWA who held up fighting in Kakegawa-jo Castle, Ujimasa had a peace negotiation with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA of Mikawa Province, and succeeded in putting Ujizane (Ujizane&apos;s lawful wife was Ujimasa&apos;s younger sister, Hayakawa-dono) under Ujimasa&apos;s protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そして氏政の次男である氏直を氏真の養子として今川の家督を継承し、駿河領有の正当化を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Ujimasa presented his second son, Ujinao HOJO, to Ujizane IMAGAWA for adoption, and let Ujinao succeed the reigns of the Imagawa family in order to justify the Ujimasa&apos;s rule over Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Ujimasa presented his second son, Ujinao, to Ujizane for adoption, and let Ujinao succeed the headship of the Imagawa family in order to justify the Ujimasa&apos;s rule over the Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>Ujinao HOJO→UjinaoUjizane IMAGAWA→Ujizanereign→headshipと修正しました。theを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Ujimasa presented his second son, Ujinao, to Ujizane for adoption, and let Ujinao succeed the headship of the Imagawa family in order to justify the Ujimasa&apos;s rule over the Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、信玄に対抗するために宿敵であった上杉謙信に、弟の三郎（後の上杉景虎）を謙信の養子（人質）として差し出し、さらに上野の支配領域を割譲して同盟を結んでいる（越相同盟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in an effort to vie with Shingen, Ujimasa offered his younger brother, Saburo (later, Kagetora UESUGI), to Kenshin UESUGI, an archenemy of Ujimasa, for adoption (a sort of hostage), and established an alliance by also ceding a portion of Kozuke Province to Kenshin (the Etsu-So Alliance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in an effort to vie with Shingen, Ujimasa offered his younger brother, Saburo (later, Kagetora UESUGI), to Kenshin UESUGI, an archenemy of Ujimasa, for adoption (hostage), and established an alliance by also ceding a portion of Kozuke Province to Kenshin (the Etsu-So Alliance).</e>
<cmt>a sort ofを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in an effort to vie with Shingen, Ujimasa offered his younger brother, Saburo (later, Kagetora UESUGI), to Kenshin UESUGI, an archenemy of Ujimasa, for adoption (hostage), and established an alliance by also ceding a portion of Kozuke Province to Kenshin (the Etsu-So Alliance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この武田との手切れによって愛妻黄梅院と離縁するという悲劇を味わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Alliance meant the severance of a relation with the Takeda clan, and Ujimasa had to divorce with his loved lawful wife, Obai-in, a tragedy for Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This alliance meant the severance of a relation with the Takeda clan, and Ujimasa faced a tragedy of divorcing his loved lawful wife, Obai-in.</e>
<cmt>Alliance→allianceと修正しました。後半部分をわかりやすくなるよう表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This alliance meant the severance of a relation with the Takeda clan, and Ujimasa faced a tragedy of divorcing his loved lawful wife, Obai-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>永禄12年（1569年）9月、碓氷峠から侵攻した武田信玄は小仏峠の別働隊を併せて小田原城を攻撃するが、氏政は父・氏康と共に籠城して武田軍を撃退している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1569, although Shingen TAKEDA invaded Odawara Castle from Usui-toge Pass along with a detached force stationed in Kobotoke-toge Pass, Ujimasa countered the attack by the rojo-sen fighting method with his father, Ujiyasu, and successfully repelled the Takeda army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1569, although Shingen TAKEDA invaded Odawara-jo Castle from Usui-toge Pass along with a detached force stationed in Kobotoke-toge Pass, Ujimasa countered the attack by holding the castle with his father, Ujiyasu, and successfully repelled the Takeda army.</e>
<cmt>永禄12年9月→西暦1569年10月と修正しました。Odawara Castle→Odawara-jo Castlethe rojo-sen fighting method→holding the castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1569, although Shingen TAKEDA invaded Odawara-jo Castle from Usui-toge Pass along with a detached force stationed in Kobotoke-toge Pass, Ujimasa countered the attack by holding the castle with his father, Ujiyasu, and successfully repelled the Takeda army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし武田軍を追撃して会戦した三増峠の戦いでは、氏康の替わりに本隊を率いた氏政が氏照・氏邦等が待ち伏せる三増峠（現愛川町）より数里南方の荻野（現厚木市）まで進出したが、小荷駄を切り落として迅速に進軍した信玄は、三増峠の氏照・氏邦等を打ち破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Mimasetoge, which Ujimasa started by chasing the Takeda army, while Ujimasa led the main army in place of Ujiyasu and moved the force up to Ogino (present-day, Atsugi City), about 10 kilometers south of Mimase-toge Pass (present-day, Aikawa Town) where Ujiteru and Ujikuni HOJO were stationed to ambush Shingen, Shingen moved his forces quickly as killing provision transporters of the Hojo army and beat Ujiteru and Ujikuni in Mimase-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Mimasetoge, which Ujimasa started by chasing the Takeda army, while Ujimasa led the main army in place of Ujiyasu and moved the force up to Ogino (present-day, Atsugi City), about 10 kilometers south of Mimase-toge Pass (present-day, Aikawa Town) where Ujiteru and Ujikuni were stationed to ambush Shingen, Shingen moved his forces quickly to kill provision transporters of the Hojo army and beat Ujiteru and Ujikuni in Mimase-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>HOJOを削除しました。as killing→to killと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Mimasetoge, which Ujimasa started by chasing the Takeda army, while Ujimasa led the main army in place of Ujiyasu and moved the force up to Ogino (present-day, Atsugi City), about 10 kilometers south of Mimase-toge Pass (present-day, Aikawa Town) where Ujiteru and Ujikuni were stationed to ambush Shingen, Shingen moved his forces quickly to kill provision transporters of the Hojo army and beat Ujiteru and Ujikuni in Mimase-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これにより、北条軍は損害を出したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Hojo army suffered big damage in the battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Hojo army suffered big damage in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Hojo army suffered big damage in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>（北条の大敗とも言われているが、近年の研究によって実際には武田方にも多くの死傷者が出ており、双方痛みわけであった可能性が指摘されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It has been said that the Hojo clan suffered a crushing defeat in the battle, but a recent study shows that the Takeda army also had a number of casualties, and hence it is likely that the battle ended in a draw.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It has been said that the Hojo clan suffered a crushing defeat in the battle, but a recent study shows that the Takeda army also had a number of casualties, hence it is likely that the battle ended in a draw.)</e>
<cmt>and hence→henceと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It has been said that the Hojo clan suffered a crushing defeat in the battle, but a recent study shows that the Takeda army also had a number of casualties, hence it is likely that the battle ended in a draw.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後も信玄が伊豆・駿河方面に進出するとこれに対抗するが、蒲原城、深沢城等の駿河諸城が陥落し、後見役であった氏康が病がちになり戦線を後退、元亀元年（1570年）には北条方の駿河支配地域は興国寺城及び駿東南部一帯だけとなり、事実上駿河は信玄によって併合された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Mimasetoge Battle, although Ujimasa resisted Shingen&apos;s invasion of Izu and Suruga Provinces, castles in Suruga Province including Kanbara and Fukazawa Castles fell one after another, and also, Ujiyasu, a guardian of Ujimasa, became too sick to stay in the battlefront, and finally in 1570, Suruga Province were seized and virtually owned by Shingen except Kokuji Castle and a part of southern Sunto County which remained in the hands of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Mimasetoge Battle, although Ujimasa resisted Shingen&apos;s invasion of Izu and Suruga Provinces, castles in Suruga Province including Kanbara-jo and Fukazawa-jo Castles fell one after another, and also, Ujiyasu, a guardian of Ujimasa, became too sick to stay in the battlefront, and finally in 1570, Suruga Province was merged and virtually owned by Shingen except Kokokuji-jo Castle and a part of southern Sunto County which remained in the hands of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>Kanbara→Kanbara-jo Fukazawa→Fukazawa-jowere→wasseized→mergedKokuji Castle→Kokokuji-jo Castle （&quot;こうこくじじょう&quot;）と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Mimasetoge Battle, although Ujimasa resisted Shingen&apos;s invasion of Izu and Suruga Provinces, castles in Suruga Province including Kanbara-jo and Fukazawa-jo Castles fell one after another, and also, Ujiyasu, a guardian of Ujimasa, became too sick to stay in the battlefront, and finally in 1570, Suruga Province was merged and virtually owned by Shingen except Kokokuji-jo Castle and a part of southern Sunto County which remained in the hands of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>元亀2年（1571年）10月、父・氏康が病死したため、その遺言に従って氏政は12月に信玄との同盟を復活させ（甲相同盟）、謙信との同盟を破棄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1571, Ujiyasu died of disease with a will left for Ujimasa who followed the will to restore the alliance with Shingen TAKEDA (the Koso Alliance) in December and abandoned the alliance with Kenshin UESUGI instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1571, Ujiyasu died of disease with a will left for Ujimasa who followed the will to restore the alliance with Shingen TAKEDA (the Koso Alliance) in December, and abandoned the alliance with Kenshin instead.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。Kenshin UESUGI→Kenshinと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1571, Ujiyasu died of disease with a will left for Ujimasa who followed the will to restore the alliance with Shingen TAKEDA (the Koso Alliance) in December, and abandoned the alliance with Kenshin instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>元亀3年（1572年）の信玄の上洛（三方ヶ原の戦い）の際には、諸足軽衆の大藤政信や伊豆衆筆頭で怪力の持ち主とされる清水太郎左衛門など2000余を援軍として武田軍に参加させ、織田・徳川連合軍に勝利している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1572, when Shingen TAKEDA went up to Kyoto, Ujimasa mobilized about 2,000 soldiers including Masanobu DAITO, ashigaru (common foot soldier), and Tarozaemon SHIMIZU, the head of Izusyu (the vassals of the Hojo clan who helped in the suppression of Izu Province) with herculean power, to reinforce the Takeda army, contributing to the winning of the Takeda army in a battle against the Oda and Tokugawa allied forces (Battle of Mikatagahara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1572, when Shingen TAKEDA went up to Kyoto, Ujimasa mobilized about 2,000 soldiers including Masanobu DAITO, ashigaru (common foot soldier), and Tarozaemon SHIMIZU, the head of Izusyu (the vassals of the Hojo clan who helped in the suppression of Izu Province) with herculean power, to reinforce the Takeda army, contributing to the winning of the Takeda army in a battle against the Oda and Tokugawa allied forces (Battle of Mikatagahara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1572, when Shingen TAKEDA went up to Kyoto, Ujimasa mobilized about 2,000 soldiers including Masanobu DAITO, ashigaru (common foot soldier), and Tarozaemon SHIMIZU, the head of Izusyu (the vassals of the Hojo clan who helped in the suppression of Izu Province) with herculean power, to reinforce the Takeda army, contributing to the winning of the Takeda army in a battle against the Oda and Tokugawa allied forces (Battle of Mikatagahara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="41">
<j>なお、この戦いで大藤政信が戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanobu DAITO died in the battle of Mikatagahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanobu DAITO died in the battle of Mikatagahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanobu DAITO died in the battle of Mikatagahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>上杉・武田との戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battles against UESUGI and TAKEDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battles against Uesugi and Takeda</e>
<cmt>UESUGI→UesugiTAKEDA→Takedaと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battles against Uesugi and Takeda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>甲相同盟復活後、氏政と謙信の戦いが再び始まり、天正2年（1574年）に謙信が上野に進出すると、氏政も上野に出陣し、利根川で対陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After restoring the Koso Alliance, Ujimasa resumed a fight against Kenshin UESUGI, and in 1574, when Kenshin moved his forces to Kozuke Province, Ujimasa also headed to the Province, and the two army confronted in Tone-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After restoring the Koso Alliance, Ujimasa resumed a fight against Kenshin, and in 1574, when Kenshin moved his forces to Kozuke Province, Ujimasa also headed to the Province, and the two armies confronted at Tone-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Kenshin UESUGI→Kenshinarmy→armiesin→atと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After restoring the Koso Alliance, Ujimasa resumed a fight against Kenshin, and in 1574, when Kenshin moved his forces to Kozuke Province, Ujimasa also headed to the Province, and the two armies confronted at Tone-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>謙信は越中国方面などの一向衆の動きによって決戦を回避する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kenshin evaded confrontation in coordination with a move of the Ikko sect in Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kenshin evaded the battle in coordination with a move of the Ikko sect in Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>confrontation→the battleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kenshin evaded the battle in coordination with a move of the Ikko sect in Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この隙に、同年閏11月には簗田晴助の下総国関宿城を攻め落とし、翌年には小山秀綱の下野国祇園城を攻め落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ujimasa forced Sekishuku Castle of Shimousa Province ruled by Harusuke YANADA to surrender in leap November 1574, followed by another surrender of Gion Castle of Shimotsuke Province ruled by Hidetsuna OYAMA in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Ujimasa forced Sekiyado-jo Castle of Shimousa Province ruled by Harusuke YANADA to surrender in December 1574, followed by another surrender of Gion-jo Castle of Shimotsuke Province ruled by Hidetsuna OYAMA in the following year.</e>
<cmt>（天正2年）閏11月→西暦1574年12月と修正しました。Sekishuku Castle→Sekiyado-jo Castle （&quot;せきやどじょう&quot;）Gion Castle→Gion-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ujimasa forced Sekiyado-jo Castle of Shimousa Province ruled by Harusuke YANADA to surrender in December 1574, followed by another surrender of Gion-jo Castle of Shimotsuke Province ruled by Hidetsuna OYAMA in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>さらに、下総の結城晴朝が恭順するなど、氏政の勢力は拡大してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Harutomi YUKI of Shimousa Province swore allegiance to Ujimasa, which increased the power of Ujimasa even more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Harutomi YUKI of Shimousa Province swore allegiance to Ujimasa, which increased the power of Ujimasa even more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Harutomi YUKI of Shimousa Province swore allegiance to Ujimasa, which increased the power of Ujimasa even more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>天正5年（1577年）には上総に侵攻し、宿敵・里見義弘との和睦を実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1577, Ujimasa invaded Kazusa Province and realized reconciliation with his old enemy, Yoshihiro SATOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1577, Ujimasa invaded Kazusa Province and realized the reconciliation with his old enemy, Yoshihiro SATOMI.</e>
<cmt>theを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1577, Ujimasa invaded Kazusa Province and realized the reconciliation with his old enemy, Yoshihiro SATOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>なおこの戦いにおいて嫡男氏直が初陣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This battle marked the first battle for his heir, Ujinao HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle marked the first battle for his heir, Ujinao.</e>
<cmt>Ujinao HOJO→Ujinaoと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle marked the first battle for his heir, Ujinao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>天正6年（1578年）、上杉謙信が死去すると、その後継者をめぐって謙信の甥・上杉景勝と氏政の弟で謙信の養子・上杉景虎（北条三郎、名は氏秀と伝わる。しかし氏秀は北条氏繁の弟で江戸城主であり景虎とは別人との説がある）の後継者争いである御館の乱がおこった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1578, when Kenshin UESUGI died, Kagekatsu UESUGI, his nephew, and Kagetora UESUGI (Saburo HOJO), his adopted child and the younger brother of Ujimasa, started fighting over the succession of the reigns (the Otate War) (Although Ujihide HOJO had been identified as Kagetora, a new theory suggests that Ujihide is not Kagetora but the younger brother of Ujishige HOJO who served as the lord of the Edo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1578, when Kenshin UESUGI died, Kagekatsu UESUGI, his nephew, and Kagetora UESUGI (Saburo HOJO, legendary Ujihide, as his name), his adopted child and the younger brother of Ujimasa, started fighting over the succession of the reigns (the Otate War) (Although Ujihide HOJO had been identified as Kagetora, a new theory suggests that Ujihide is not Kagetora but the younger brother of Ujishige HOJO who served as the lord of the Edo Castle).</e>
<cmt>legendary Ujihide, as his nameを補い、補強しました。 ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1578, when Kenshin UESUGI died, Kagekatsu UESUGI, his nephew, and Kagetora UESUGI (Saburo HOJO, legendary Ujihide, as his name), his adopted child and the younger brother of Ujimasa, started fighting over the succession of the reigns (the Otate War) (Although Ujihide HOJO had been identified as Kagetora, a new theory suggests that Ujihide is not Kagetora but the younger brother of Ujishige HOJO who served as the lord of the Edo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>氏政はこのとき下野において佐竹・宇都宮と対陣中であったため、5月に実弟の景虎の援助のために氏照、氏邦らを越後に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the internal conflict, Ujimasa was engaged in a battle against the Satake and Utsunomiya clans in Shimotsuke Province, and therefore, he sent Ujiaki and Ujikuni HOJO to Echigo Province in May for helping his biological younger brother, Kagetora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the internal conflict, Ujimasa was engaged in a battle against the Satake and Utsunomiya clans in Shimotsuke Province, and therefore, he sent Ujiteru and Ujikuni to Echigo Province in June for helping his biological younger brother, Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>Ujiaki→UjiteruUjikuni HOJO→Ujikuniと修正しました。（天正6年）5月→（西暦1578年）6月として修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the internal conflict, Ujimasa was engaged in a battle against the Satake and Utsunomiya clans in Shimotsuke Province, and therefore, he sent Ujiteru and Ujikuni to Echigo Province in June for helping his biological younger brother, Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>8月下旬には氏政自身も景虎援助のため、上野の前橋城まで出陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late August, Ujimasa headed for Maebashi Castle of Kozuke Province to assist Kagetora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In late September, Ujimasa headed for Maebashi-jo Castle of Kozuke Province to assist Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>（天正6年）8月→（西暦1578年）9月として修正しました。Maebashi Castle→Maebashi-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In late September, Ujimasa headed for Maebashi-jo Castle of Kozuke Province to assist Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし、すぐに小田原へ引き返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ujimasa returned to Odawara immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ujimasa returned to Odawara immediately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ujimasa returned to Odawara immediately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>また、これと同時に同盟者で妹婿の武田勝頼にも援軍を依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Ujimasa asked Katsuyori TAKEDA, the husband of his younger sister and his ally, to send reinforcements to Kagetora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Ujimasa asked Katsuyori TAKEDA, the husband of his younger sister and his ally, to send reinforcements to Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Ujimasa asked Katsuyori TAKEDA, the husband of his younger sister and his ally, to send reinforcements to Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>当初、勝頼は景虎を支援して自らも出陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, Katsuyori himself joined the force to support Kagetora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, Katsuyori himself joined the force to support Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, Katsuyori himself joined the force to support Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>しかし、隙をついた徳川家に攻め込まれた東海方面の諸城から援軍を求められる状況に佐渡産の金を押さえた景勝から黄金を贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a situation for Katsuyori changed; his castles in the Tokai region were caught off guard and attacked by the Tokugawa clan and asked for reinforcements, while Kagekatsu UESUGI, who seized the Sado gold mine, offered gold to Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Katsuyori faced a situation that his castles in the Tokai region were caught off guard and attacked by the Tokugawa clan and asked for reinforcements, and Kagekatsu UESUGI, who seized the Sado gold mine, offered gold to Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Katsuyori faced a situation that his castles in the Tokai region were caught off guard and attacked by the Tokugawa clan and asked for reinforcements, and Kagekatsu UESUGI, who seized the Sado gold mine, offered gold to Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>勝頼は、上野沼田の割譲を条件にした同盟を受け入れて景勝支持に転じた（甲越同盟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuyori TAKEDA finally switched to Kagekatsu UESUGI on the condition that he was given the land of Numata, Kozuke Province (the Koetsu Alliance).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuyori finally switched to Kagekatsu side on the condition of the cession of Numata, Kozuke Province (the Koetsu Alliance).</e>
<cmt>TAKEDA, UESUGIを削除しました。sideを補いました。that he was given the land→of the cessionと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuyori finally switched to Kagekatsu side on the condition of the cession of Numata, Kozuke Province (the Koetsu Alliance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>その結果、御館の乱は景勝の勝利に終わり、景虎は自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the Otate War ended with a victory for Kagekatsu UESUGI, and Kagetora UESUGI suicided himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the Otate War ended with a victory for Kagekatsu, and Kagetora killed himself.</e>
<cmt>UESUGIを削除しました。sucided→killedと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the Otate War ended with a victory for Kagekatsu, and Kagetora killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>甲越同盟に対して氏政は第2次甲相同盟を破棄し、織田信長・徳川家康と同盟を結び駿河の武田領国を挟撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rivalry with the Koetsu Alliance, Ujimasa built a new alliance with Nobunaga ODA and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA by reversing the Second Koso Alliance, and invaded the territory of the Takeda clan from the both sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rivalry with the Koetsu Alliance, Ujimasa built a new alliance with Nobunaga ODA and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA by reversing the Second Koso Alliance, and invaded the territory of the Takeda clan in Suruga from both sides.</e>
<cmt>「駿河の」=in Surugaを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rivalry with the Koetsu Alliance, Ujimasa built a new alliance with Nobunaga ODA and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA by reversing the Second Koso Alliance, and invaded the territory of the Takeda clan in Suruga from both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>天正8年（1580年）に勝頼を攻めて重須の合戦が起きたが、勝負はつかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1580, Ujimasa attacked Katsuyori TAKEDA, which triggered the Battle of Omosu, but the battle ended in a draw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1580, Ujimasa attacked Katsuyori, which triggered the Battle of Omosu, but the battle ended in a draw.</e>
<cmt>TAKEDAを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1580, Ujimasa attacked Katsuyori, which triggered the Battle of Omosu, but the battle ended in a draw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>更に上野では勝頼の攻勢が続き、上野下野国衆も武田方に転じたため、劣勢に陥っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Katsuyori continued his offense in Kozuke Province and local samurais of Kozuke and Shimotsuke Provinces switched to the Takeda clan, Ujimasa was pushed into an inferior position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Katsuyori continued his offense in Kozuke Province and the local samurai of Kozuke and Shimotsuke Provinces switched to the Takeda clan side, Ujimasa was pushed into the inferior position.</e>
<cmt>local samurais→the local samuraian→the と修正しました。side を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Katsuyori continued his offense in Kozuke Province and the local samurai of Kozuke and Shimotsuke Provinces switched to the Takeda clan side, Ujimasa was pushed into the inferior position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>このため、この頃、石山本願寺を降伏させて勢いづく織田信長に臣従を申し出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To turn the tide, Ujimasa offered a vassalage to Nobunaga ODA who was building up momentum by forcing Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple to surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To turn the tide, Ujimasa offered a vassalage to Nobunaga ODA who was building up the momentum by forcing Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple to surrender.</e>
<cmt>theを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To turn the tide, Ujimasa offered a vassalage to Nobunaga ODA who was building up the momentum by forcing Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple to surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>敵対した武田勝頼も織田家との和睦・同盟を画策したため、先手を打って同盟を成立した高度な外交と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Katsuyori TAKEDA also aimed at making peace and an alliance with the Oda clan, the move by Ujimasa to forestall his enemy and formed an alliance before Katsuyori was a sophisticated diplomacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Katsuyori TAKEDA, his opposition also aimed at making peace and an alliance with the Oda clan, the move by Ujimasa to forestall his enemy and formed an alliance before Katsuyori was a sophisticated diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>his oppositionを補い補強しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Katsuyori TAKEDA, his opposition also aimed at making peace and an alliance with the Oda clan, the move by Ujimasa to forestall his enemy and formed an alliance before Katsuyori was a sophisticated diplomacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>同年、嫡男の北条氏直に家督を譲って隠居するが、父氏康に倣い、なおも北条家の政治・軍事の実権は掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Ujimasa retired by transferring the reigns of the family to his heir, Ujinao HOJO, but followed the footstep of his father, Ujiyasu, to continue controlling the Hojo clan both politically and militarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Ujimasa retired by transferring the reigns of the family to his heir, Ujinao HOJO, but followed the footstep of his father, Ujiyasu, to continue controlling the Hojo clan both politically and militarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Ujimasa retired by transferring the reigns of the family to his heir, Ujinao HOJO, but followed the footstep of his father, Ujiyasu, to continue controlling the Hojo clan both politically and militarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>勢力拡大</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extension of its influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extension of its influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extension of its influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>天正10年（1582年）2月、織田信長の嫡子の信忠が武田征伐に乗り出すと、駿豆国境間の情報が途絶していたため当初情報の少なかった氏政は氏邦に上野方面から情報収集させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1582, when Nobutada ODA, a legitimate child of Nobunaga ODA, launched conquering efforts of the Takeda clan, Ujimasa ordered Ujikuni to gather information from Kozuke Province to compensate the information shortage in Suruga and Izu Provinces, as the information network in those two provinces were shut down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1582, when Nobutada, a legitimate child of Nobunaga ODA, launched the campaign of conquering the Takeda clan, Ujimasa ordered Ujikuni to gather information from Kozuke Province to compensate the information shortage in Suruga and Izu Provinces, as the information network in those two provinces had been shut down.</e>
<cmt>天正10年（1582年）2月→西暦1582年3月として修正しました。 Nobutada ODA→Nobutada,conquering efforts of→the campaign of conquering,were→had beenと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1582, when Nobutada, a legitimate child of Nobunaga ODA, launched the campaign of conquering the Takeda clan, Ujimasa ordered Ujikuni to gather information from Kozuke Province to compensate the information shortage in Suruga and Izu Provinces, as the information network in those two provinces had been shut down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>その後、伊勢からの船による情報により、織田の武田領国侵攻を確認すると、これに呼応し駿河の武田領に侵攻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a short while, information was transmitted from a ship on Ise that the Oda clan invaded the territory of the Takeda clan, Ujimasa responded to the move and invaded Takeda&apos;s territory in Suruga Province in an concerted action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a short while, the information was transmitted by a ship from Ise that the Oda clan invaded the territory of the Takeda clan, Ujimasa responded to the move and invaded Takeda&apos;s territory in Suruga Province in concerted action.</e>
<cmt>theを補いました。from a ship on Ise→by a ship from Iseと修正しました。anを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a short while, the information was transmitted by a ship from Ise that the Oda clan invaded the territory of the Takeda clan, Ujimasa responded to the move and invaded Takeda&apos;s territory in Suruga Province in concerted action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>3月11日に勝頼は天目山の戦いで正室・桂林院（氏政の妹）と共に自刃し、甲斐武田氏は滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 11, Katsuyori TAKEDA committed suicide with his lawful wife, Keirin-in (a younger sister of Ujimasa), which ended the Kai-Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 13, Katsuyori committed suicide with his lawful wife, Keirin-in (a younger sister of Ujimasa) at the Battle of Tenmokuzan, which ended the Kai-Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>（天正10年）3月11日→（西暦1582年）4月13日と修正しました。TAKEDAを削除しました。「天目山の戦いで」を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 13, Katsuyori committed suicide with his lawful wife, Keirin-in (a younger sister of Ujimasa) at the Battle of Tenmokuzan, which ended the Kai-Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>信長は家臣の滝川一益を上野厩橋城に派遣して関東管領とし、上野西部と信濃国の一部を与え、関東の統治を目論んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA send his vassal, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, to Mayabashi Castle of Kozuke Province as Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), and gave him western Kozuke Province and a part of Shinano Province to govern the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga sent his vassal, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, to Mayabashi-jo Castle of Kozuke Province as Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), and gave him western Kozuke Province and a part of Shinano Province to govern the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>ODAを削除しました。send→sentMayabashi Castle→Mayabashi-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga sent his vassal, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, to Mayabashi-jo Castle of Kozuke Province as Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), and gave him western Kozuke Province and a part of Shinano Province to govern the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>すでに北条は氏直に織田家から姫を迎えて婚姻することを条件にして、織田の分国として関東一括統治を願い出ていたが、これについて織田信長から明確な回答がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan had already asked the Oda clan to unite and govern the Kanto region by offering the Hojo clan&apos;s domain to Oda&apos;s territory on one condition that Ujinao HOJO would have taken a princess of the Oda clan for his wife, but Nobunaga ODA did not give any clear response to it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan had already asked the Oda clan to unite and govern the Kanto region by offering the Hojo clan&apos;s domain to Oda&apos;s territory on one condition that Ujinao HOJO would have taken a princess of the Oda clan for his wife, but Nobunaga ODA did not give any clear response to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan had already asked the Oda clan to unite and govern the Kanto region by offering the Hojo clan&apos;s domain to Oda&apos;s territory on one condition that Ujinao HOJO would have taken a princess of the Oda clan for his wife, but Nobunaga ODA did not give any clear response to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>そのため、氏政は三島大社に氏直の関東支配と織田家との婚姻祈願の願文を捧げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Ujimasa presented a written prayer to the Mishima-taisha Shrine instead to the effect that Ujinao would rule the Kanto region and have a marital relationship with the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Ujimasa presented a written prayer to the Mishima-taisha Shrine as the effect that Ujinao would rule the Kanto region and have a marital relationship with the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>instead to→asと修正しました。スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Ujimasa presented a written prayer to the Mishima-taisha Shrine as the effect that Ujinao would rule the Kanto region and have a marital relationship with the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また滝川一益の仲介により、下野祇園城を元城主の小山秀綱に返還する等、織田氏の関東支配に協力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Ujimasa returned Gion Castle of Shimotsuke Province to the former castle lord, Hidetsuna OYAMA, with the mediation by Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, to realize the unification of the Kanto region by the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Ujimasa returned Gion-jo Castle of Shimotsuke Province to the former castle lord, Hidetsuna OYAMA, with the mediation by Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, to realize the controlling of the Kanto region by the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>Gion Castle→Gion-jo Castleunification→controllingと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Ujimasa returned Gion-jo Castle of Shimotsuke Province to the former castle lord, Hidetsuna OYAMA, with the mediation by Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, to realize the controlling of the Kanto region by the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>氏政はこの時点での信長の勢威を恐れており、織田－北条の友好関係は保たれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa was afraid of an increasing power of Nobunaga at the time, which helped to maintain the favorable relationship between Oda and Hojo clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa was afraid of an increasing power of Nobunaga at the time, which helped to maintain the favorable relationship between the Oda and Hojo clans.</e>
<cmt>theを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa was afraid of an increasing power of Nobunaga at the time, which helped to maintain the favorable relationship between the Oda and Hojo clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>関東の北条領は一益の文書では南方と呼ばれ、重視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a document kept by Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, the territory of the Hojo clan in the Kanto region was called &apos;Minamikata&apos; and highly valued.</e>
<cmt>南方：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a document kept by Kazumasu, the territory of the Hojo clan in the Kanto region was called &apos;Minamikata&apos; and highly valued.</e>
<cmt>TAKIGAWAを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a document kept by Kazumasu, the territory of the Hojo clan in the Kanto region was called &apos;Minamikata&apos; and highly valued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="72">
<j>6月2日、京都本能寺において織田信長が明智光秀の裏切りにより死去した（本能寺の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 2, Nobunaga ODA died due to the betrayal of Mitsuhide AKECHI at Honno-ji Shrine of Kyoto (the Honno-ji Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 1, Nobunaga ODA died due to the betrayal of Mitsuhide AKECHI at Honno-ji Temple of Kyoto (the Honno-ji Incident).</e>
<cmt>（天正10年）6月2日→（西暦1582年）7月1日と修正しました。Shirine→Templeと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 1, Nobunaga ODA died due to the betrayal of Mitsuhide AKECHI at Honno-ji Temple of Kyoto (the Honno-ji Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>信長の死を知った氏政は、当初は滝川一益に引き続き協調関係を継続する旨を通知しているが、その後、氏直と氏邦に上野奪取を命じ、4万3千と称する大軍を上野に侵攻させ、神流川の戦いで大勝し、厩橋城の滝川一益を上野から追放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa, knowing of the death of Nobunaga, informed Kazumasu TAKIGAWA of its continued cooperation, but later invaded Kozoke Province with an army of 43,000 soldiers after ordering Ujinao and Ujikuni to occupy the Province, and in the following battle of Kanna-gawa River, the Ujimasa&apos;s army won a sweeping victory and expelled Kazumasu in Mayabashi Castle from Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa, knowing of the death of Nobunaga, informed Kazumasu TAKIGAWA of its continued cooperation, but later invaded Kozoke Province with an army of 43,000 soldiers after ordering Ujinao and Ujikuni to occupy the Province, and in the following battle of Kanna-gawa River, the Ujimasa&apos;s army won a sweeping victory and expelled Kazumasu TAKIGAWA in Mayabashi-jo Castle from Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>TAKIGAWAを補いました。Mayabashi Castle→Mayabashi-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa, knowing of the death of Nobunaga, informed Kazumasu TAKIGAWA of its continued cooperation, but later invaded Kozoke Province with an army of 43,000 soldiers after ordering Ujinao and Ujikuni to occupy the Province, and in the following battle of Kanna-gawa River, the Ujimasa&apos;s army won a sweeping victory and expelled Kazumasu TAKIGAWA in Mayabashi-jo Castle from Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>この後、北条軍は碓氷峠から信濃に進出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Hojo army also invaded Shinano Province from Usui-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Hojo army also invaded Shinano Province from Usui-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Hojo army also invaded Shinano Province from Usui-toge Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>真田昌幸・木曾義昌・諏訪頼忠などを取り込み、徳川傘下として旧武田兵を集めて決起した依田信蕃等を討った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After putting Masayuki SANADA, Yoshimasa KISO and Yoritada SUWA under its control, the Hojo army also beat Nobushige YODA, who rose against the Hojo clan with former Takeda soldiers now on the Tokugawa side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After coaxing Masayuki SANADA, Yoshimasa KISO and Yoritada SUWA and others, the Hojo army also beat Nobushige YODA and others, who raised an army with former Takeda soldiers as the Tokugawa side.</e>
<cmt>putting...under its control→coaxingnow on→asrose→raisedと修正しました。and others, an armyを補いました。against the Hojo clanを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After coaxing Masayuki SANADA, Yoshimasa KISO and Yoritada SUWA and others, the Hojo army also beat Nobushige YODA and others, who raised an army with former Takeda soldiers as the Tokugawa side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>その後、小諸城に駐屯し、信濃東部から中部にかけて占領下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, It was stationed in Komoro Castle and also brought the eastern and central areas of Shinano Province under its control.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was stationed in Komoro-jo Castle, and also brought the eastern and central areas of Shinano Province under its control.</e>
<cmt>It→heKomoro Castle→Komoro-jo Castleと修正しました。カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was stationed in Komoro-jo Castle, and also brought the eastern and central areas of Shinano Province under its control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>一方、甲斐に侵攻した家康は依田信蕃を通して真田昌幸を調略し、さらに徳川方の小笠原貞慶への肩入れなどにより、北条軍と対立した（天正壬午の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, Ieyasu, who invaded Kai Province, skillfully persuaded Masayuki SANADA into the Tokugawa side with the help of Nobushige YODA, and also supported Sadayoshi OGASAWARA, which caused a confrontation between him and the Hojo army (Tenshojingo Rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, Ieyasu, who invaded Kai Province, skillfully persuaded Masayuki SANADA into the Tokugawa side with the help of Nobushige YODA, and also supported Sadayoshi OGASAWARA of Tokugawa side, which caused a confrontation between him and the Hojo army (Tenshojingo Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>「徳川方の」=of Tokugawa sideを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, Ieyasu, who invaded Kai Province, skillfully persuaded Masayuki SANADA into the Tokugawa side with the help of Nobushige YODA, and also supported Sadayoshi OGASAWARA of Tokugawa side, which caused a confrontation between him and the Hojo army (Tenshojingo Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>その後、甲斐の若神子において氏直と家康は対陣したが（若神子の戦い）、信濃では真田昌幸が離反し、甲斐においても別働隊の北条氏忠が、黒駒において徳川方に敗北し、甲斐の北条領は郡内地方の領有に留まる等、対陣は不利となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ujinao HOJO and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA confronted each other once in Wakamiko of the Kai Province (the Battle of Wakamiko), the Hojo clan reduced its power to fight against the Tokugawa clan, because in Shinano, Masayuki SANADA defected from the Hojo clan, and in Kurokoma of Kai Province, Ujitada HOJO, who led detached forces, lost to the Tokugawa army and only the limited area of the Gunnai region remained in the hands of the Hojo clan in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ujinao and Ieyasu confronted each other once in Wakamiko of the Kai Province (the Battle of Wakamiko), the Hojo clan reduced its power to fight against the Tokugawa clan, since in Shinano, Masayuki SANADA defected from the Hojo clan, and in Kurokoma of Kai Province, Ujitada HOJO, who led detached forces, lost to the Tokugawa army, and only the limited area of the Gunnai region remained in the hands of the Hojo clan in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>Ujinao HOJO→UjinaoIeyasu TOKUGAWA→Ieyasubecause→sinceと修正しました。カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ujinao and Ieyasu confronted each other once in Wakamiko of the Kai Province (the Battle of Wakamiko), the Hojo clan reduced its power to fight against the Tokugawa clan, since in Shinano, Masayuki SANADA defected from the Hojo clan, and in Kurokoma of Kai Province, Ujitada HOJO, who led detached forces, lost to the Tokugawa army, and only the limited area of the Gunnai region remained in the hands of the Hojo clan in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>このため氏直と家康の娘・督姫を結婚させることで和睦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Hojo clan was reconciled with the Tokugasa clan by taking a daughter of Ieyasu, Tokuhime for Ujinao&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Hojo clan was reconciled with the Tokugasa clan by taking a daughter of Ieyasu, Tokuhime for Ujinao&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Hojo clan was reconciled with the Tokugasa clan by taking a daughter of Ieyasu, Tokuhime for Ujinao&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>領土問題は甲斐・信濃を徳川領、上野を北条領とすることで合意したが、信濃佐久・小県両郡と甲斐郡内地方の放棄は不利な講和条件だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo and Tokugawa clans settled a territorial dispute by giving the Tokugawa clan Kai and Shinano Provinces and the Hojo clan Kozuke Province, but the peace terms were unfavorable for the Hojo clan, because it had to waver the territorial rights of Saku and Oagata Counties of Shinano Province and the Gunnai region of Kai County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo and Tokugawa clans settled a territorial dispute by giving the Tokugawa clan Kai and Shinano Provinces and the Hojo clan Kozuke Province, but the peace terms were unfavorable for the Hojo clan, because it had to waver the territorial rights of Saku and Oagata Counties of Shinano Province and the Gunnai region of Kai County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo and Tokugawa clans settled a territorial dispute by giving the Tokugawa clan Kai and Shinano Provinces and the Hojo clan Kozuke Province, but the peace terms were unfavorable for the Hojo clan, because it had to waver the territorial rights of Saku and Oagata Counties of Shinano Province and the Gunnai region of Kai County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>しかも徳川についた真田昌幸が、後に上野の沼田を北条に明け渡す事を拒んで上杉氏に寝返り、上田・沼田城にて徳川・北条と抗戦することとなり、これが後の沼田問題さらに名胡桃事件の伏線となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Masayuki SANADA of the Tokugawa side refused to surrender the Numata area of Kozuke Province to the Hojo clan and switched sides to the Uesugi clan, which brought a confrontation between the Sanada clan and the Tokugawa-Hojo alliance and also triggered the Numata Mondai and the Nagurumi Incident in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Masayuki SANADA of the Tokugawa side refused to surrender the Numata area of Kozuke Province to the Hojo clan and switched sides to the Uesugi clan, which brought a battle between the Sanada clan and the Tokugawa-Hojo alliance at Numata-jo Castle, Ueda, and also triggered the Numata Mondai and the Nagurumi Incident in later years.</e>
<cmt>confrontation→battleと修正しました。「上田・沼田城にて」=at Numata-jo Castle, Uedaを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Masayuki SANADA of the Tokugawa side refused to surrender the Numata area of Kozuke Province to the Hojo clan and switched sides to the Uesugi clan, which brought a battle between the Sanada clan and the Tokugawa-Hojo alliance at Numata-jo Castle, Ueda, and also triggered the Numata Mondai and the Nagurumi Incident in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="82">
<j>天正11年（1583年）に古河公方・足利義氏 (古河公方)が死去すると、官途補任により権力を掌握し、これにより関東の身分秩序の頂点に立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the death of Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, Koga kubo (the Kanto district administrator), in 1583, the Hojo clan assumed a power by holding government posts, which let the clan to preside over the Kanto region as a top commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the death of Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, Koga kubo (the Kanto district administrator), in 1583, the Hojo clan assumed a power by holding government posts, which let the clan to preside over the Kanto region as a top commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the death of Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, Koga kubo (the Kanto district administrator), in 1583, the Hojo clan assumed a power by holding government posts, which let the clan to preside over the Kanto region as a top commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また武蔵の江戸地域、岩付領の支配を掌握し、利根川水系と常陸川水系の支配を確保、これによって流通・交通体系を支配したため、関東の反北条連合は従属か徹底抗戦の二択を迫られるまでに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Musashi Province, the Edo region and Iwatsuki-ryo of Musashi Province were seized by the Hojo clan and both the Tone-gawa River and Hitachi-gawa River Systems were put under its command, which gave the clan the control of the distribution and traffic systems in the region, and the anti-Hojo alliance in the Kanto region was forced to choose either to obey or confront the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Musashi Province, the Edo region and Iwatsuki-ryo of Musashi Province were seized by the Hojo clan and both the Tone-gawa River and Hitachi-gawa River Systems were put under its control, which gave the clan the control of the distribution and traffic systems in the region, and the anti-Hojo alliance in the Kanto region was forced to choose either to obey or confront the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>command→controlと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Musashi Province, the Edo region and Iwatsuki-ryo of Musashi Province were seized by the Hojo clan and both the Tone-gawa River and Hitachi-gawa River Systems were put under its control, which gave the clan the control of the distribution and traffic systems in the region, and the anti-Hojo alliance in the Kanto region was forced to choose either to obey or confront the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>なお、この時期に同地域の支配を確固たるものにするために江戸城を隠居城として政務を執る構想があったとも言われているが、実際には氏政は以後も小田原に居住しており、具体化には至らなかったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is said that the clan had an idea to use the Edo Castle as a &apos;castle in retirement&apos; to administer political affairs there to ensure the rule over the region, but considering Ujimasa continued residing in Odawara, the plan seemed to have failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is said that the clan had an idea to use the Edo-jo Castle as a &apos;castle in retirement&apos; to administer the political affairs there to ensure the rule over the region, but considering Ujimasa continued residing in Odawara, the plan seemed to have failed.</e>
<cmt>Edo Castle→Edo-jo Castleと修正しました。theを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is said that the clan had an idea to use the Edo-jo Castle as a &apos;castle in retirement&apos; to administer the political affairs there to ensure the rule over the region, but considering Ujimasa continued residing in Odawara, the plan seemed to have failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="85">
<j>天正13年（1585年）、佐竹義重 (十八代当主)・宇都宮国綱らが那須資晴・壬生義雄らを攻めると、氏政は那須氏らと手を結んで本格的に下野侵攻を開始し、下野の南半分を支配下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, when Yoshishige SATAKE (the eighteenth family head) and Kunitsuna UTSUNOMIYA attacked Sukeharu NASU and Yoshitake MIBU, Ujimasa began a full-blown invasion of Shimotsuke Province by building an alliance with the Nasu clan and put the southern half of the Province under its control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, when Yoshishige SATAKE (the 18th family head) and Kunitsuna UTSUNOMIYA attacked Sukeharu NASU and Yoshitake MIBU, Ujimasa began a full-blown invasion of Shimotsuke Province by building an alliance with the Nasu clan and put the southern half of the Province under its control.</e>
<cmt>eighteenth→18thと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, when Yoshishige SATAKE (the 18th family head) and Kunitsuna UTSUNOMIYA attacked Sukeharu NASU and Yoshitake MIBU, Ujimasa began a full-blown invasion of Shimotsuke Province by building an alliance with the Nasu clan and put the southern half of the Province under its control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>また常陸南部の江戸崎城の土岐氏及び牛久城の岡見氏を支援し、常陸南部にも勢力を及ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in southern Hitachi Province, Ujimasa supported the Toki clan, the lord of Edosaki Castle, and the Okami clan, the lord of Ushiku Castle, and extended its influence to the region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in southern Hitachi Province, Ujimasa supported the Toki clan, the lord of Edosaki-jo Castle, and the Okami clan, the lord of Ushiku-jo Castle, and extended its influence to the region.</e>
<cmt>Edosaki Castle→Edosaki-jo CastleUshiku Castle→Ushiku-jo Castleと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in southern Hitachi Province, Ujimasa supported the Toki clan, the lord of Edosaki-jo Castle, and the Okami clan, the lord of Ushiku-jo Castle, and extended its influence to the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="87">
<j>こうして、北条氏の領国は相模・伊豆・武蔵・下総・上総・上野から常陸国・下野国・駿河国の一部に及ぶ240万石に達し、最大版図を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the Hojo clan achieved the largest territory of 2.4 million goku (667,200 cubic meters) including Sagami, Izu, Musashi, Shimousa, Kazusa, Kozuke Provinces and parts of Hitachi, Shimotsuke and Suruga Provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the Hojo clan achieved the largest territory of 2.4 million koku (667,200 cubic meters) including Sagami, Izu, Musashi, Shimousa, Kazusa, Kozuke Provinces and parts of Hitachi, Shimotsuke and Suruga Provinces.</e>
<cmt>goku→kokuと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the Hojo clan achieved the largest territory of 2.4 million koku (667,200 cubic meters) including Sagami, Izu, Musashi, Shimousa, Kazusa, Kozuke Provinces and parts of Hitachi, Shimotsuke and Suruga Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>小田原征伐から最期へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the siege of Odawara to the end of the Hojo clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the subjugation of Odawara to the end of the Hojo clan</e>
<cmt>siege→subjugationと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the subjugation of Odawara to the end of the Hojo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>しかし、明智光秀を討ち、織田信長の天下一統事業を継承した豊臣秀吉との対立が待っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After beating Mitsuhide AKECHI, the Hojo clan faced against Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who succeeded the project of unifying the whole nation from Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After beating Mitsuhide AKECHI, the Hojo clan faced against Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who succeeded the project of unifying the whole nation from Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After beating Mitsuhide AKECHI, the Hojo clan faced against Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who succeeded the project of unifying the whole nation from Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>天正16年（1588年）、秀吉から氏政・氏直親子の聚楽第行幸への列席を求められたが、氏政はこれを拒否する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1588, Hideyoshi asked Ujimasa and Ujinao, a parent and son, to attend the Imperial visit to Jurakudai (Hideyoshi&apos;s residence and office in Kyoto), but Ujimasa refused it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1588, Hideyoshi asked Ujimasa and Ujinao, the father and son, to attend the imperial visit to Jurakudai (Hideyoshi&apos;s residence and office in Kyoto), but Ujimasa refused it.</e>
<cmt>a parent→the fatherImperial→imperialと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1588, Hideyoshi asked Ujimasa and Ujinao, the father and son, to attend the imperial visit to Jurakudai (Hideyoshi&apos;s residence and office in Kyoto), but Ujimasa refused it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>京では北条討伐の風聞が立ったが、徳川家康の起請文により以下のような説得を受け、氏政の弟・北条氏規が名代として上洛したことで、北条－豊臣間の関係は一時的にではあるが安定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the capital, there was a rumor that the Hojo clan would be subjugated, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA persuaded Ujimasa by the following written oath to send the younger brother of Ujimasa, Ujinori HOJO, to the capital as a representative of the clan, which helped to temporarily stabilize the relationship between the Hojo clan and the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the capital, there was a rumor that the Hojo clan would be subjugated, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA persuaded Ujimasa by the following written oath to send the younger brother of Ujimasa, Ujinori HOJO, to the capital as a representative of the clan, which helped to temporarily stabilize the relationship between the Hojo clan and the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the capital, there was a rumor that the Hojo clan would be subjugated, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA persuaded Ujimasa by the following written oath to send the younger brother of Ujimasa, Ujinori HOJO, to the capital as a representative of the clan, which helped to temporarily stabilize the relationship between the Hojo clan and the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="91">
<j>家康が北条親子の事を讒言せず、北条氏の領国を一切望まない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu will not make a false charge against the Hojo clan or aim to acquire any territory of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu will not make a false charge against the Hojo clan or aim to acquire any territory of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu will not make a false charge against the Hojo clan or aim to acquire any territory of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>今月中に兄弟衆を派遣する</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan will send siblings to the capital within this month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan will send siblings to the capital within this month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan will send siblings to the capital within this month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>豊臣家への出仕を拒否する場合督姫を離別させる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the Hojo clan refuses to serve the Toyotomi clan, Tokuhime will be separated from her husband (Ujinao HOJO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the Hojo clan refuses to serve the Toyotomi clan, Tokuhime will be separated from her husband (Ujinao HOJO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the Hojo clan refuses to serve the Toyotomi clan, Tokuhime will be separated from her husband (Ujinao HOJO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>なお武州文書によると、この頃、氏政は実質的にも隠居をすると宣言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Bushu Bunsho (Bushu documents), sometime during this period, Ujimasa declared his complete retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Bushu Bunsho (Bushu documents), sometime during this period, Ujimasa declared his complete retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Bushu Bunsho (Bushu documents), sometime during this period, Ujimasa declared his complete retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>（氏政は秀吉への全面従属には反対であったため、親徳川の氏直をたてたとされるが、のちに氏政自身が上洛することを家臣・国衆に通知しており、氏政が主戦派との見解については疑問がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It had been believed that Ujinao, his pro-Tokugawa son, was put up, as Ujimasa was a war advocate and opposed to the total subordination to Hideyoshi, but this theory yields some questions because Ujimasa later informed his vassals and influential domain people that he would go up to the capital himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It had been believed that Ujinao, his pro-Tokugawa son, was put up, as Ujimasa was a war advocate and opposed to the total subordination to Hideyoshi, but this theory yields some questions since Ujimasa later informed his vassals and influential domain people that he would go up to the capital himself.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分を補いました。because→sinceと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It had been believed that Ujinao, his pro-Tokugawa son, was put up, as Ujimasa was a war advocate and opposed to the total subordination to Hideyoshi, but this theory yields some questions since Ujimasa later informed his vassals and influential domain people that he would go up to the capital himself.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="96">
<j>天正17年（1589年）2月、評定衆である板部岡融成が上洛し、沼田問題の解決を秀吉に要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1589, Toonari ITABEOKA, a member of hyojoshu (state council), went up to the capital and requested Hideyoshi to settle the Numata Mondai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1589, Tonari ITABEOKA, a member of hyojoshu (state council), went up to the capital and requested Hideyoshi to settle the Numata Mondai.</e>
<cmt>天正17年2月→西暦1589年3月と修正しました。Toonari→Tonariと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1589, Tonari ITABEOKA, a member of hyojoshu (state council), went up to the capital and requested Hideyoshi to settle the Numata Mondai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>秀吉は沼田領の3分の2を北条側に還付する沼田裁定をおこない、6月には12月氏政上洛の一札を受け取り、沼田領は7月に北条方に引き渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi ruled that two thirds of the Numata area should be returned to the Hojo clan, and Ujimasa sent a letter in July to Hideyoshi promising his visit to the capital in December in return, and handover of the Numata area was carried out in July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi ruled that two thirds of the Numata area should be returned to the Hojo clan, and Ujimasa sent a letter in July to Hideyoshi promising his visit to the capital in December in return, and handover of the Numata area was carried out in August.</e>
<cmt>(天正17年)7月→（西暦1589年）8月と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi ruled that two thirds of the Numata area should be returned to the Hojo clan, and Ujimasa sent a letter in July to Hideyoshi promising his visit to the capital in December in return, and handover of the Numata area was carried out in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>しかし上洛について、氏政は新たに天正18年（1590年）の春夏頃の上洛を申し入れたが、それを秀吉が拒否したことにより、再び関係が悪化し始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ujimasa proposed to reschedule the visit to spring or summer of 1590, but Hideyoshi refused the proposal, which worsened the relationship of the two again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ujimasa proposed to reschedule the visit to spring or summer of 1590, but Hideyoshi refused the proposal, which worsened the relationship of the two again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ujimasa proposed to reschedule the visit to spring or summer of 1590, but Hideyoshi refused the proposal, which worsened the relationship of the two again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>こうした状況の中の10月、氏邦の家臣・猪俣邦憲による名胡桃城奪取事件が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the tense situation, the seizure of Nagurumi Castle (the Nagurumi Incident) by Kuninori INOMATA, a vassal of Ujikuni HOJO, occurred in October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the tense situation, the seizure of Nagurumi-jo Castle (the Nagurumi Incident) by Kuninori INOMATA, a vassal of Ujikuni, occurred in November.</e>
<cmt>Nagurumi Castle→Nagurumi-jo Castleと修正しました。HOJOを削除しました。（天正17年）10月→（西暦1589年）11月と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the tense situation, the seizure of Nagurumi-jo Castle (the Nagurumi Incident) by Kuninori INOMATA, a vassal of Ujikuni, occurred in November.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>秀吉は家康、景勝らを上洛させ、諸大名に対して天正18年（1590年）春の北条氏追討の出陣用意を促した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi ordered Ieyasu and Kagekatsu UESUGI to visit the capital and urged other daimyos to prepare forces for subjugation of the Hojo clan in coming spring of 1590.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi ordered Ieyasu and Kagekatsu to visit the capital, and urged other daimyo to prepare their forces for the subjugation of the Hojo clan in coming spring of 1590.</e>
<cmt>UESUGIを削除しました。 daimyos→daimyoと修正しました。カンマ、their, theを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi ordered Ieyasu and Kagekatsu to visit the capital, and urged other daimyo to prepare their forces for the subjugation of the Hojo clan in coming spring of 1590.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>また、秀吉は津田盛月・富田一白を上使として北条氏に派遣し、名胡桃事件の首謀者を処罰して即刻上洛するよう要求している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Hideyoshi sent Moritsuki TSUDA and Ippaku TOMITA to the Hojo clan as an envoy of the shogun, and demanded that the clan punish the ringleader of the Nagurumi Incident and immediately visit Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Hideyoshi sent Moritsuki TSUDA and Ippaku TOMITA to the Hojo clan as an envoy of the shogun, and demanded that the clan punish the ringleader of the Nagurumi Incident and immediately visit the capital.</e>
<cmt>Hideyoshi→the capitalと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Hideyoshi sent Moritsuki TSUDA and Ippaku TOMITA to the Hojo clan as an envoy of the shogun, and demanded that the clan punish the ringleader of the Nagurumi Incident and immediately visit the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="102">
<j>これに対して氏直は、氏政抑留か国替えの惑説があるため上洛できないことと、徳川家康が臣従時に秀吉が朝日姫と婚姻し大政所を人質とした上で上洛した厚遇を受けたことに対して、名胡桃事件における北条氏に対する秀吉の態度との差を挙げ、抑留・国替がなく心安く上洛を遂げられるよう要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To these demands, Ujinao explained his inability to visit the capital that there were rumors that Ujimasa would be detained or his ruling domain would be changed, and urged Hideyoshi to remove these worries before going up to the capital, and also claimed the difference in treatment between him in the Nagurumi Incident and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who received good treatment from Hideyoshi when offering his vassalage; Ieyasu was allowed to take Hideyoshi&apos;s younger sister, Asahihime, for his wife, i.e. Ieyasu had Omandokoro (the mother of Hideyoshi) as a sort of his hostage before visiting the capital.</e>
<cmt>惑説：意味不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To these demands, Ujinao explained his inability to visit the capital that there were rumors that Ujimasa would be detained or his ruling domain would be changed, and urged Hideyoshi to remove these worries before going up to the capital, claiming that the difference in treatment between him in the Nagurumi Incident and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who received good treatment from Hideyoshi when offering his vassalage; Ieyasu was allowed to take Hideyoshi&apos;s younger sister, Asahihime, for his wife, i.e. Ieyasu had Omandokoro (the mother of Hideyoshi) as a sort of his hostage before visiting the capital.</e>
<cmt>and also claimed→claiming thatと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To these demands, Ujinao explained his inability to visit the capital that there were rumors that Ujimasa would be detained or his ruling domain would be changed, and urged Hideyoshi to remove these worries before going up to the capital, claiming that the difference in treatment between him in the Nagurumi Incident and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who received good treatment from Hideyoshi when offering his vassalage; Ieyasu was allowed to take Hideyoshi&apos;s younger sister, Asahihime, for his wife, i.e. Ieyasu had Omandokoro (the mother of Hideyoshi) as a sort of his hostage before visiting the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="103">
<j>また名胡桃城奪取事件について、氏政や氏直の命令があったわけではなく、真田方の名胡桃城主が北条方に寝返ったことによるもので、すでに名胡桃城は真田方に返還したと弁明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the Nagurumi Incident, Ujinao made an excuse that the lord of the Nagurumi Castle (the Sanada clan) volunteered to switch to the Hojo clan and there was no such an order from Ujimasa or Ujinao to seize the castle, and the castle was already returned to the Sanada clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About the Nagurumi Incident, Ujinao made an excuse that the lord of the Nagurumi-jo Castle (the Sanada side) volunteered to switch to the Hojo clan, and there was no such an order from Ujimasa or Ujinao to seize the castle, and the castle was already returned to the Sanada side.</e>
<cmt>Nagurumi Castle→Nagurumi-jo CastleSanada clan→Sanada sideと修正しました。カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About the Nagurumi Incident, Ujinao made an excuse that the lord of the Nagurumi-jo Castle (the Sanada side) volunteered to switch to the Hojo clan, and there was no such an order from Ujimasa or Ujinao to seize the castle, and the castle was already returned to the Sanada side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="104">
<j>これが真に猪俣の独断であるならば、氏直・氏政の監督不行き届きが招いた結果であり、穏健派の氏規と中間派の氏直、主戦派の氏政・氏照・氏邦の対立が表面化したと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this incident was indeed caused only by INOMATA, it was a result of a lack of supervision by Ujinao and Ujimasa, and it can be said that the confrontation among moderate Ujinori, center Ujinao and pro-war Ujimasa, Ujiaki and Ujikuni surfaced through this incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this incident was indeed caused only by Inomata, it was a result of a lack of supervision by Ujinao and Ujimasa, and it can be said that the confrontation among moderate Ujinori, center Ujinao and pro-war Ujimasa, Ujiaki and Ujikuni surfaced through this incident.</e>
<cmt>INOMATA→Inomataと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this incident was indeed caused only by Inomata, it was a result of a lack of supervision by Ujinao and Ujimasa, and it can be said that the confrontation among moderate Ujinori, center Ujinao and pro-war Ujimasa, Ujiaki and Ujikuni surfaced through this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="105">
<j>しかし現存している各種書状において、沼田城受領後の氏政は自らの上洛時期が当初の12月から翌春夏にずれたものの、上洛に積極的であり、また氏政・氏直が再三にわたり名胡桃城を北条が奪取したわけでないと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ujimasa and Ujinao repeatedly insisted in several (extant) letters that although the capital visit by Ujimasa was delayed, upon the acquisition of Numata Castle, from December to spring or summer of the following year, Ujimasa was willing to visit Hideyoshi, and that the Hojo clan was not responsible for the seizure of Nagurumi Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ujimasa and Ujinao repeatedly insisted in several (extant) letters that although the capital visit by Ujimasa was delayed, upon the acquisition of Numata-jo Castle, from December (old calendar) to spring or summer of the following year, Ujimasa was willing to visit Hideyoshi, and that the Hojo clan was not responsible for the seizure of Nagurumi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Numata Castle→Numata-jo CastleNagurumi Castle→Nagurumi-jo Castleと修正しました。(old calendar)を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ujimasa and Ujinao repeatedly insisted in several (extant) letters that although the capital visit by Ujimasa was delayed, upon the acquisition of Numata-jo Castle, from December (old calendar) to spring or summer of the following year, Ujimasa was willing to visit Hideyoshi, and that the Hojo clan was not responsible for the seizure of Nagurumi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>これらを考慮すると、名胡桃城奪取と言われる真の状況は今をもっても不明といわざるを得ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on these circumstantial evidence, it seems the truth about the so-called seizure of Nagurumi Castle remains to be seen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on these circumstantial evidence, it seems the truth about the so-called seizure of Nagurumi-jo Castle remains to be unknown.</e>
<cmt>Nagurumi Castle→Nagurumi-jo Castleseen→unknownと修正しました。 スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on these circumstantial evidence, it seems the truth about the so-called seizure of Nagurumi-jo Castle remains to be unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="107">
<j>未だに上洛を引き延ばす氏政の姿勢に業を煮やした秀吉は、氏政の上洛・出仕の拒否を豊臣家への従属拒否であるとみなし、12月23日、諸大名に正式に追討の陣触れを発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Hideyoshi, who was frustrated with the delayed visit by Ujimasa, regarded Ujimasa&apos;s attitude not to visit and serve Hideyoshi as the rejection to the subordination to the Toyotomi family, and issued a formal order to daimyos to hunt and kill Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Hideyoshi, who was frustrated with the delayed visit by Ujimasa, regarded Ujimasa&apos;s attitude not to visit and serve Hideyoshi as the rejection of the subordination to the Toyotomi family; issued a formal order to those daimyo to search out and destroy Ujimasa on December 23 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt>to→ofhunt and kill→search out and destroy（用語統一）daimyos→those daimyoと修正しました。パンクチュエーションを修正しました。「12月23日」を補い、加えて(old calendar)を補いました。（変換すると年をまたいでしまうため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Hideyoshi, who was frustrated with the delayed visit by Ujimasa, regarded Ujimasa&apos;s attitude not to visit and serve Hideyoshi as the rejection of the subordination to the Toyotomi family; issued a formal order to those daimyo to search out and destroy Ujimasa on December 23 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>これに先立って駿豆国境間が手切れに及んだことを知った氏政・氏直は、17日には北条領国内の家臣・他国衆に対して小田原への1月15日参陣を命じて迎撃の態勢を整えるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the order, Ujimasa and Ujinao, who were informed of the 手切れ in the border of Suruga and Izu Provinces, organized their army to ambush the Hideyoshi army by ordering the vassals of the Hojo clan and other local samurais on December 17 to join the upcoming battle against Hideyoshi in Odawara on January 15.</e>
<cmt>手切れ：意味不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the order, Ujimasa and Ujinao, who were informed of the 手切れ in the border of Suruga and Izu Provinces, organized their army to attack the Hideyoshi army by ordering the vassals of the Hojo clan and other local samurais on December 17 to join the upcoming battle against Hideyoshi in Odawara on February 19.</e>
<cmt>(old calendar)を補いました。ambush→attackと修正しました。(天正18年)1月15日→（西暦1590年）2月19日と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the order, Ujimasa and Ujinao, who were informed of the 手切れ in the border of Suruga and Izu Provinces, organized their army to attack the Hideyoshi army by ordering the vassals of the Hojo clan and other local samurais on December 17 to join the upcoming battle against Hideyoshi in Odawara on February 19.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>そして3月から、各方面から侵攻してくる豊臣軍を迎え撃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, a war began and the Hojo army counterattacked the Toyotomi army invading from all the directions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, a war began and the Hojo army counterattacked the Toyotomi army invading from all the directions.</e>
<cmt>（天正18年）3月→（西暦1590年）4月と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, a war began and the Hojo army counterattacked the Toyotomi army invading from all the directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>当初は碓井峠を越えてきた真田・依田に対して勝利し、駿豆国境方面でも布陣する豊臣方諸将に威力偵察するなど戦意は旺盛であったが、秀吉の沼津着陣後には、緒戦で山中城が落城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the Hojo clan was highly motivated in fighting a war, winning a battle against the Sanada and Ida clans invading from Usui-toge Pass and surveilling the force levels of warlords on the Toyotomi side in the Suruga-Izu border, but after Hideyoshi arrived at Numazu, the Hojo clan lost a following battle and was forced to surrender Yamanaka Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the Hojo clan was highly motivated in fighting the war, beating the Sanada and Ida clans invading from Usui-toge Pass, and scouting to discover the force levels of warlords on the Toyotomi side in the Suruga-Izu border, and so so on, but after Hideyoshi arrived at Numazu, the Hojo clan lost the following battle and was forced to surrender Yamanaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>a→thewinning a battle against→beatingsurveilling→scouting to discoverYamanaka Castle→Yamanaka-jo Castleと修正しました。カンマ、and so onを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the Hojo clan was highly motivated in fighting the war, beating the Sanada and Ida clans invading from Usui-toge Pass, and scouting to discover the force levels of warlords on the Toyotomi side in the Suruga-Izu border, and so so on, but after Hideyoshi arrived at Numazu, the Hojo clan lost the following battle and was forced to surrender Yamanaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>天正18年（1590年）4月から約3ヶ月に渡って小田原城に籠城する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After losing Yamanaka Castle, the Hojo clan took the rojo-sen fighting method and held up fighting in Odawara Castle for about three months starting in April 1590.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After losing the Yamanaka-jo Castle, the Hojo clan held the Odawara-jo Castle for about three months starting in May 1590.</e>
<cmt>theを補いました。Yamanaka Castle→Yamanaka-jo Castletook the rojo-sen fighting method and held up fighting in→heldOdawara Castle→Odawara-jo Castleと修正しました。 天正18年4月→西暦1590年5月と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After losing the Yamanaka-jo Castle, the Hojo clan held the Odawara-jo Castle for about three months starting in May 1590.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>その後領国内の下田城、松井田城、玉縄城、岩槻城、鉢形城、八王子城、津久井城等の諸城が次々と落城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle continued, and many castles in the Hojo territory, such as Shimoda Castle, Matsuida Castle, Tamanawa Castle, Iwatsuki Castle, Hachigata Castle, Hachioji Castle and Tsukui Castle, fell one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle continued, and many castles in the Hojo territory, such as Shimoda-jo Castle, Matsuida-jo Castle, Tamanawa-jo Castle, Iwatsuki-jo Castle, Hachigata-jo Castle, Hachioji-jo Castle and Tsukui-jo Castle, fell one after another.</e>
<cmt>それぞれに&quot;-jo&quot;を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle continued, and many castles in the Hojo territory, such as Shimoda-jo Castle, Matsuida-jo Castle, Tamanawa-jo Castle, Iwatsuki-jo Castle, Hachigata-jo Castle, Hachioji-jo Castle and Tsukui-jo Castle, fell one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>22万を数える豊臣軍の前には衆寡敵せず、北条氏は降伏した｡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hopelessly outnumbered by the Toyotomi army of 220,000 soldiers, the Hojo army finally surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hopelessly outnumbered by the Toyotomi army of 220,000 soldiers, the Hojo army finally surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hopelessly outnumbered by the Toyotomi army of 220,000 soldiers, the Hojo army finally surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="114">
<j>俗にこの際、一月以上に渡り、北条家家臣団の抗戦派と降伏派によって繰り広げられた議論が小田原評定の語源になったと言われているが、本来は北条家臣団が定期的（概ねの期間において毎月）に行っていた評定を呼ぶものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, vassals of the Hojo clan held a discussion for more than a month whether to continue the war (a pro-war party) or to surrender (a pro-surrender party), but did not reach a conclusion, and this situation is believed to be the origin of a proverb, &apos;Odawara Hyojo&apos; (Odawara conference, meaning &apos;an inconclusive discussion&apos;), but originally, the phrase indicated a regular conference (Hyojo) held monthly by Hojo vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, vassals of the Hojo clan held a discussion for more than a month whether to continue the war (a pro-war party) or to surrender (a pro-surrender party), but did not reach a conclusion, and this situation is believed to be the origin of a proverb, &apos;Odawara Hyojo&apos; (Odawara conference, meaning &apos;an inconclusive discussion&apos;), but originally, the phrase indicated a regular conference (Hyojo) held monthly by Hojo vassals.</e>
<cmt>During this period→On this occasionと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, vassals of the Hojo clan held a discussion for more than a month whether to continue the war (a pro-war party) or to surrender (a pro-surrender party), but did not reach a conclusion, and this situation is believed to be the origin of a proverb, &apos;Odawara Hyojo&apos; (Odawara conference, meaning &apos;an inconclusive discussion&apos;), but originally, the phrase indicated a regular conference (Hyojo) held monthly by Hojo vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="115">
<j>7月5日、氏直が自分の命と引き換えに全ての将兵の助命を乞い、降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 5, Ujinao surrendered to Hideyoshi on the condition that all the officers and soldiers of the Hojo clan were spared their life in exchange for his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 4, Ujinao surrendered to Hideyoshi on the condition that all the officers and soldiers of the Hojo clan were spared their life in exchange for his life.</e>
<cmt>（天正18年）7月5日→（西暦1590年）8月4日 と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 4, Ujinao surrendered to Hideyoshi on the condition that all the officers and soldiers of the Hojo clan were spared their life in exchange for his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>舅・家康も氏政の助命を乞うが、北条氏の討伐を招いた責任者として秀吉は氏政・氏照及び宿老の松田憲秀・大道寺政繁に切腹を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ujimasa&apos;s father-in-law, Ieyasu, asked for a pardon for Ujimasa, Hideyoshi ordered Seppuku to Ujimasa and Ujiteru HOJO, and Norihide MATSUDA and Masashige DAIDOJI, chief vassals, for their responsibility to cause the subjugation of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ujimasa&apos;s father-in-law, Ieyasu, asked for a pardon for Ujimasa, Hideyoshi ordered Seppuku to Ujimasa and Ujiteru, and the chief vassals of Norihide MATSUDA and Masashige DAIDOJI, for their responsibility to cause the subjugation of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>HOJOを削除しました。the chief vassals ofとして移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ujimasa&apos;s father-in-law, Ieyasu, asked for a pardon for Ujimasa, Hideyoshi ordered Seppuku to Ujimasa and Ujiteru, and the chief vassals of Norihide MATSUDA and Masashige DAIDOJI, for their responsibility to cause the subjugation of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="117">
<j>井伊直政の情報では一時は助命されるという見通しもあったが、7月11日に氏政と弟・氏照が切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the information of Naomasa Ii, there was a prospect that they might be given a pardon, but Ujimasa and his younger brother, Ujiaki, commit Seppuku on July 11.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the information of Naomasa Ii, there was a prospect that they might be given a pardon, but Ujimasa and his younger brother, Ujiaki, committed Seppuku on August 10.</e>
<cmt>commit→committedと修正しました。 （天正18年）7月11日→（西暦1590年）8月10日と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the information of Naomasa Ii, there was a prospect that they might be given a pardon, but Ujimasa and his younger brother, Ujiaki, committed Seppuku on August 10.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>享年53。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa&apos;s age of death was 53.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa&apos;s age of death was 53.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa&apos;s age of death was 53.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="119">
<j>静岡県富士市の源立寺に首塚がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kubizuka (tomb of the head) of Ujimasa is now found in Genryu-ji Temple of Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kubizuka (tomb of the head) of Ujimasa is now found in Genryu-ji Temple of Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kubizuka (tomb of the head) of Ujimasa is now found in Genryu-ji Temple of Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="120">
<j>辞世の句は、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the death haiku (Japanese poem) written by Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the death haiku (Japanese poem) written by Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the death haiku (Japanese poem) written by Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="121">
<j>「雨雲の　おほえる月も　胸の霧も　はらいにけりな　秋の夕風」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Autumn wind of eve, blow away the clouds that mass over the moon&apos;s pure light and the mists that cloud our mind, do thou sweep away as well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>http://www.asphodelshaven.com/translations/glossary/series/mirage_05</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Autumn wind of eve, blow away the clouds that mass over the moon&apos;s pure light and the mists that cloud our mind, do thou sweep away as well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Autumn wind of eve, blow away the clouds that mass over the moon&apos;s pure light and the mists that cloud our mind, do thou sweep away as well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="122">
<j>「我身今　消ゆとやいかに　おもふへき　空よりきたり　空に帰れば」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now we disappear, well, what must we think of it? From the sky we came. Now we may go back again. That&apos;s at least one point of view.&apos;</e>
<cmt>http://www.asphodelshaven.com/translations/glossary/series/mirage_05</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now we disappear, well, what must we think of it? From the sky we came. Now we may go back again. That&apos;s at least one point of view.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now we disappear, well, what must we think of it? From the sky we came. Now we may go back again. That&apos;s at least one point of view.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="123">
<j>豊臣家に対して徹底抗戦したことが、家康や長宗我部氏、島津氏征伐の時と異なる一線を画す処置を招いたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possible that the strategy that the Hojo clan took to thoroughly resist the conquest effort by the Toyotomi clan brought about the outcome (Seppuku order), different from the one for Ieyasu, the Chosokabe clan and the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible that the strategy that the Hojo clan took to thoroughly resist the conquest effort by the Toyotomi clan brought about the outcome, different from the one for Ieyasu, the Chosokabe clan and the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>(Seppuku order)を削除しました。（ここで明らかにそうだとは触れられていないので）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible that the strategy that the Hojo clan took to thoroughly resist the conquest effort by the Toyotomi clan brought about the outcome, different from the one for Ieyasu, the Chosokabe clan and the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>ここに戦国大名としての小田原北条氏は滅んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the Odawara-Hojo clan as a warring lord in the Sengoku Period came to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the Odawara-Hojo clan as a Sengoku daimyo came to the end.</e>
<cmt>warring lord in the Sengoku Period→Sengoku daimyoan→theと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the Odawara-Hojo clan as a Sengoku daimyo came to the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>personality→Personal Profileと修正しました。（用語統一）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>氏政は家を滅ぼした武将として評価が低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a military commander, Ujimasa is not highly evaluated because he ruined his own clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a military commander, Ujimasa is not highly evaluated because he ruined his own clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a military commander, Ujimasa is not highly evaluated because he ruined his own clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>北条記においては「四世の氏政は愚か者で、老臣の松田憲秀の悪いたくらみにまどわされ、国政を乱したけれども、まだ父氏康君の武徳のおかげがあって、どうやら無事であった」と評されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Hojo-ki&quot; (a record of the Hojo family), Ujimasa is referred to that &apos;the fourth family head, Ujimasa, is such a fool that he was deceived by Norihide MATSUDA, a roshin (main retainer) and disturbed the affairs of the state, but thanks to the virtue of his father, Ujiyasu, he was spared his life&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hojo-ki (a record of the Hojo family), Ujimasa is referred to that &apos;the fourth family head, Ujimasa, is such a fool that he was deceived by Norihide MATSUDA, a roshin (main retainer) and disturbed the affairs of the state, but due to the virtue of his father, Ujiyasu, he was spared his life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。thanks to→due toと修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hojo-ki (a record of the Hojo family), Ujimasa is referred to that &apos;the fourth family head, Ujimasa, is such a fool that he was deceived by Norihide MATSUDA, a roshin (main retainer) and disturbed the affairs of the state, but due to the virtue of his father, Ujiyasu, he was spared his life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>ちなみに同資料において、北条5代の当主の中でここまで見下ろされ「君」も付けられていない当主は、氏政だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this document, among the five family heads of the Hojo clan, Ujimasa is the only one who is disrespected this much and called without &apos;kun&apos; (a suffix to refer to a ruler).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this document, among the five family heads of the Hojo clan, Ujimasa is the only one who is disrespected this much and called without &apos;kun&apos; (a suffix to refer to a ruler).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this document, among the five family heads of the Hojo clan, Ujimasa is the only one who is disrespected this much and called without &apos;kun&apos; (a suffix to refer to a ruler).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="128">
<j>個人的には家族思いの人物であったらしく、有能な弟達と常に良好な関係を維持していたのみならず、愛妻家としても知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personally, Ujimasa is known as a person who cared for his family, always kept a good relationship with his younger capable brothers and loved his wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personally, Ujimasa is known as a person who cared for his family, always kept a good relationship with his capable younger brothers and loved his wife.</e>
<cmt>younger capable brothers→capable younger brothersと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personally, Ujimasa is known as a person who cared for his family, always kept a good relationship with his capable younger brothers and loved his wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>正妻の黄梅院とは武田の駿河侵攻を機に離婚させられているが、氏政本人は最後まで離婚を渋っており、氏康の死の直後に武田と和睦した際には真っ先に妻の遺骨を貰い受け手厚く葬っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he divorced with his lawful wife, Obai-in, upon the invasion of Suruga Province where the Takeda clan ruled, Ujimasa hesitated to do so until the last minute, and when Ujimasa was reconciled with the Takeda clan after the death of Ujiyasu, he immediately asked to have the cremains of his ex-wife and buried them in a cordial manner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he divorced his lawful wife, Obai-in, upon the invasion of Suruga Province by the Takeda clan, Ujimasa hesitated to do so until the last moment, and when Ujimasa was reconciled with the Takeda clan after the death of Ujiyasu, he immediately asked to have the remains of his ex-wife and buried them in a cordial manner.</e>
<cmt>divorced with→divorcedwhere the Takeda clan ruled→by the Takeda clanminute→momentcremains→remainsと修正しました。スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he divorced his lawful wife, Obai-in, upon the invasion of Suruga Province by the Takeda clan, Ujimasa hesitated to do so until the last moment, and when Ujimasa was reconciled with the Takeda clan after the death of Ujiyasu, he immediately asked to have the remains of his ex-wife and buried them in a cordial manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>北条氏政には逸話が多く、一般に知られているものの多くは否定的な印象を与えるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are many anecdotes on Ujimasa HOJO, most of them are not favorable to Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are many anecdotes on Ujimasa HOJO, most of them are not favorable to Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are many anecdotes on Ujimasa HOJO, most of them are not favorable to Ujimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="131">
<j>汁かけ飯の話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story of soup and rice</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A story of soup and rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A story of soup and rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="132">
<j>氏政の有名な逸話として2度汁かけの逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A famous anecdote about Ujimasa features soup and rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A famous anecdote about Ujimasa features soup and rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A famous anecdote about Ujimasa features soup and rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>食事の際に氏政が汁を一度、飯にかけたが、汁が少なかったのでもう一度汁をかけ足した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a mealtime, Ujimasa poured a soup on rice once, but poured it again as the soup was not enough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a mealtime, Ujimasa poured a soup on rice once, but poured it again as the soup was not enough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At a mealtime, Ujimasa poured a soup on rice once, but poured it again as the soup was not enough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>これを見た父の氏康が次のように嘆息したという逸話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Ujiyasu, who saw it and said &apos;you have a meal every day, but you still do not know how much soup you need for your rice.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Ujiyasu, saw it and sighed as follows;</e>
<cmt>文章単位で分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Ujiyasu, saw it and sighed as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>「毎日食事をしておきながら、飯にかける汁の量も量れんとは。北条家もわしの代で終わりか。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You have a meal every day, but you still do not know how much soup you need for your rice. The Hojo clan may end in my era.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文章単位で分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You have a meal every day, but you still do not know how much soup you need for your rice. The Hojo clan may end in my era.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>（汁かけ飯の量も量れぬ者に、領国や家臣を推し量ることなど出来る訳がない、の意）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan may end in my era.&apos; Ujiyasu lamented (meaning, &apos;someone who cannot measure the amount of soup suitable for his rice cannot assess the situation of his territory or vassals right&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Meaning, someone who cannot measure the amount of soup suitable for his rice cannot assess the situation of his territory or vassals right.)</e>
<cmt>文章単位で分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Meaning, someone who cannot measure the amount of soup suitable for his rice cannot assess the situation of his territory or vassals right.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>氏政が結果的に北条家の滅亡を回避できなかったことが、この逸話を有名なものにし、氏政の評価を一般的に低いものにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that Ujimasa could not evade the fall of the Hojo clan made this anecdote famous and also the evaluation of Ujimasa very low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Ujimasa could not evade the fall of the Hojo clan made this anecdote famous and also the reputation of Ujimasa very low.</e>
<cmt>evaluation→reputationと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Ujimasa could not evade the fall of the Hojo clan made this anecdote famous and also the reputation of Ujimasa very low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>この逸話は後世の創作だが、氏政が佐竹氏との対立などで同じ戦線に何度も陣を重ねたことへの揶揄がもとにされていると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this anecdote is a fiction written in later years, it seems that the story mock the real story that Ujimasa sent his army to the same battle line over and over again in the confrontation against the Satake clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this anecdote is a fiction written in later years, it seems that the story mock the real story that Ujimasa sent his army to the same battle line over and over again in the confrontation against the Satake clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this anecdote is a fiction written in later years, it seems that the story mock the real story that Ujimasa sent his army to the same battle line over and over again in the confrontation against the Satake clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="139">
<j>麦の話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story of wheat</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story of wheat</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story of wheat</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="140">
<j>農民が麦刈りをする様子を氏政が見て、「あの取れたての麦で昼飯にしよう」と言ったという話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujimasa saw peasants harvesting wheat and said, &apos;we should have a lunch with that fresh wheat&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa saw peasants harvesting wheat and said: &apos;we should have a lunch with that fresh wheat.&apos;</e>
<cmt>パンクチュエーションを修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa saw peasants harvesting wheat and said: &apos;we should have a lunch with that fresh wheat.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>刈った麦がそのまますぐ食べられる訳でなく、干し、脱穀し、精白するなどして、ようやく調理できるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wheat after harvest cannot be cooked and eaten immediately, but requires a process of drying, threshing and pearling before eating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wheat after harvest cannot be eaten immediately, but requires a process of drying, threshing and pearling before cooking.</e>
<cmt>cooked and eaten→eaten、eating→cookingと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wheat after harvest cannot be eaten immediately, but requires a process of drying, threshing and pearling before cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>その話を伝え聞いた武田信玄はその無知ぶりを大いに笑ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Shingen TAKEDA, who heard the story, laughed a lot at how ignorant Ujimasa was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Shingen TAKEDA, who heard the story, laughed a lot at how ignorant Ujimasa was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Shingen TAKEDA, who heard the story, laughed a lot at how ignorant Ujimasa was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>これは甲陽軍鑑に載っている逸話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the anecdote recorded in the &quot;Koyo Gunkan&quot; (records of the military exploits of the Takeda family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the anecdote recorded in the Koyo Gunkan (records of the military exploits of the Takeda family).</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the anecdote recorded in the Koyo Gunkan (records of the military exploits of the Takeda family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), MD242(id:11277), Horlicks(id:62133), ドルチェット(id:46458), Nnh(id:474), Htks(id:24185), Cprobot(id:97843), PATMAN(id:145791), ジール(id:222755), 百人(id:16483), Synthebot(id:123032), でここ(id:9565), Natunohi(id:6550), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 玄史生(id:43670), Goki(id:7107), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Kanoe(id:17203), Loveless(id:129239), Sabkakusikaku(id:277058), Avxz(id:123412), Kouko0515(id:100370), Rinohno(id:252340), Orihakat(id:99279), M-sho-gun(id:88956), ぶるるるる(id:130462), Carbuncle(id:346), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 水野白楓(id:22811), 古聞(id:110289), Law soma(id:45202), 松茸(id:27535), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Clen(id:100642), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), Kagetudo(id:163875), Kamitani(id:30757), Geso(id:101555), VolkovBot(id:105371), 風魔忍者(id:237688), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), KSKS(id:97637), 博物学博士(id:33603), こいつぅ(id:2105), Kuma83(id:31177), けんち(id:5147), Richknight(id:141069), Monboco(id:223218), Impromptu(id:39137), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>