<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>金春禅鳳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenpo KONPARU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenpo KONPARU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenpo KONPARU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>金春 禅鳳（こんぱる ぜんぽう、1454年（享徳3年） - 1532年（天文 (日本)元年）？）は、室町時代後期の能楽師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenpo KONPARU (1454-1532) was Nohgakushi (Noh actor) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenpo KONPARU (1454-1532) was a Nohgakushi (Noh actor) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenpo KONPARU (1454 - 1532?) was a Nohgakushi (Noh actor) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>実名・八郎元安、法名・桐林禅鳳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Motoyasu HACHIRO (八郎元安) and his Homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Zenpo TORIN (桐林禅鳳.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Motoyasu HACHIRO (八郎元安) and his Homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Zenpo TORIN (桐林禅鳳.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Motoyasu HACHIRO (八郎元安) and his Homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Zenpo TORIN (桐林禅鳳).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当時を代表する能役者であったとともに、能作者、能楽論の著者としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a representative Noh actor in that period and also famous for writing Noh plays and books of theories of Nogaku (theories of Noh drama.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a representative Noh actor in that period and was also famous for writing Noh plays, as well as books of theories of Nogaku (theories of Noh drama.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a representative Noh actor in that period and was also famous for writing Noh plays, as well as books of theories of Nohgaku (theories of Noh drama).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>現在の能の源流である大和四座の一つ、秦河勝の子孫を称する金春座（円満井座）の大夫・金春宗筠（七郎元氏）の子として生を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of 金春宗筠 (七郎元氏) as Daibu (a master) of Konparu-za (Enmai-za) which was one of Yamato-yoza (four sarugaku performance groups in the Yamato Province) that is an origin of the current Noh and identified themselves as the descendants of HATA no Kawakatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of 金春宗筠 (七郎元氏), who served as Daibu (master) of Konparu-za (Enmai-za), which was one of the Yamato-yoza (four sarugaku performance groups in the Yamato Province) that is the origin of the current Noh, who identified themselves as the descendants of HATA no Kawakatsu.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Soin KONPARU (also known as Shichiro Motouji), who served as Daibu (master) of Konparu-za troupe (also known as Enmai-za troupe), which was one of the Yamato-yoza (four sarugaku (form of theater popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) performance groups in the Yamato Province) that is the origin of the current Noh, who identified themselves as the descendants of HATA no Kawakatsu.</e>
<cmt>読みを確認した漢字をローマ字にし、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>祖父の金春禅竹はやはり謡曲の作者・能楽論の著者として知られた能楽師で、その妻は能楽の大成者・世阿弥の娘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather Zenchiku KONPARU was a Noh actor and also a well-known writer of Yokyoku (Noh song) and books of the theories of Nogaku, and his wife was a daughter of Zeami who made a career of Nogaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather Zenchiku KONPARU was a Noh actor and also a well-known writer of Yokyoku (Noh songs) and books of the theories of Nogaku, and his wife was a daughter of Zeami, who made a career of Nogaku.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather Zenchiku KONPARU was a Noh actor and also a well-known writer of Yokyoku (Noh songs) and books of the theories of Nohgaku, and his wife was a daughter of Zeami, who made a career of Nohgaku.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>禅竹、宗筠ともに一条兼良などとも交際のある優れた能楽師であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a great Noh actor and had relationships with Zenchiku, 宗筠 and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a great Noh actor and had relationships with Zenchiku, 宗筠 and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a great Noh actor and had relationships with Zenchiku, Soin and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>長禄4年（1460年）、7歳の禅鳳は禅竹に付き添われ、大乗院門跡尋尊の元に参上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1460 when Zenpo was seven years old, he visited Jinson DAIJO-in Monzeki Temple accompanied by Zenchiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1460, when Zenpo was seven years old, he visited Jinson DAIJO-in Monzeki Temple accompanied by Zenchiku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1460, when Zenpo was seven years old, he visited Jinson Daijoin Monzeki Temple accompanied by Zenchiku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>禅竹は禅鳳15歳の年まで健在であり、禅鳳がこの祖父から有形無形の影響を受けたことは想像に難くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenchiku died when Zenpo was fifteen years old and it is easily assumed that Zenchiku had a tangible and intangible effect on Zenpo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenchiku died when Zenpo was fifteen years old, and it is easily assumed that Zenchiku had a tangible and intangible effect on Zenpo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenchiku died when Zenpo was 15 years old, and it is easily assumed that Zenchiku had a tangible and intangible effect on Zenpo.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>19歳の文明 (日本)4年（1472年）8月には、奈良古市の祭礼で父の代演を務めるなど、金春座の後継者として順調に成長を遂げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He achieved a stable growth to take over Konparu-za such as acting as a substitute for his father in a festival in Narafuruichi in August 1472 when he was nineteen years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He achieved stable growth and took over Konparu-za, such as acting as a substitute for his father in a festival in Narafuruichi in August 1472 when he was nineteen years old.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He achieved stable growth and took over Konparu-za, such as acting as a substitute for his father in a festival in Furuichi, Nara in September 1472 when he was 19 years old.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、表現を変えアラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>文明12年（1480年）11月、父・宗筠が49歳で急逝し、27歳で禅鳳は大夫に就く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father 宗筠 had a sudden death at the age of forty nine in November 1480 and Zenpo took the place of Daibu (master) of Konparu-za at the age of twenty seven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father 宗筠 suddenly died at the age of forty nine in November 1480, after which Zenpo took the place of Daibu (master) of Konparu-za at the age of twenty seven.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Soin suddenly died at the age of 49 in November 1480, after which Zenpo took the place of Daibu (master) of Konparu-za at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>当時能楽界で隆盛を誇っていたのは、観阿弥・世阿弥・音阿弥と傑才を輩出した観世座であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Nogaku group which was enjoying great success was Kanze-za which had produced Kanami, Zeami and Onami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Kanze-za was the Nogaku group that was enjoying great success, having produced Kanami, Zeami and Onami.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Kanze-za was the Nohgaku group that was enjoying great success, having produced Kanami, Zeami and Onami.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>音阿弥の死後もその第七子・観世小次郎信光が座を支えており、その地位は磐石であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Onami, Kanze-za was supported by his seventh son Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO and maintained its solid and stable position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Onami, Kanze-za was supported by his seventh son, Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO, and maintained its solid and stable position.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Onami, Kanze-za was supported by his seventh son, Kojiro Nobumitsu KANZE, and maintained its solid and stable position.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>加えて時の将軍・足利義政は音阿弥以来観世贔屓であり、金春座は遅れを取っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Luckily, Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA had been a Kanze fan since Onami took over the group, and Konparu-za lagged behind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Luckily, Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA had been a Kanze fan since Onami took over the group, and Konparu-za lagged behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Luckily, Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA had been a Kanze fan since Onami took over the group, and Konparu-za lagged behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>文明15年（1483年）、義政の意向で、従兄弟で大夫を支える有能な脇師の日吉源四郎を、観世座に奪われてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1483, Konparu-za lost Genshiro HIYOSHI who was the Daibu&apos;s cousin and a competent supporting performer by Kanze-za at Yoshimasa&apos;s direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1483, Konparu-za lost Genshiro HIYOSHI, who was the Daibu&apos;s cousin and a competent supporting performer, to Kanze-za at Yoshimasa&apos;s direction.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1483, Konparu-za lost Genshiro HIYOSHI, who was the Dayu&apos;s cousin and a competent supporting performer, to Kanze-za at Yoshimasa&apos;s direction.</e>
<cmt>読みを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>それ以前にもやはりワキ方の守菊（弥）七郎を引き抜かれており、大夫を継いだばかりの禅鳳と金春座は大きな打撃を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, (Ya)shichiro MORIGIKU as a supporting performer had been headhunt, too and both Zenpo as the brand-new Daibu and Konparu-za were deeply shocked and damaged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, (Ya)shichiro MORIGIKU, a supporting performer, had also been headhunted, and both Zenpo as the brand-new Daibu and Konparu-za were deeply shocked and damaged.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, Shichiro (or Yashichiro) MORIGIKU, a supporting performer, had also been headhunted, and both Zenpo as the brand-new Daibu and Konparu-za were deeply shocked and damaged.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし禅鳳は興福寺衆徒の古市澄胤、河内の畠山氏などの後援を受けて何とかこの危機を乗り越える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Zenpo could manage to overcome the crisis with supports of Choin FURUICHI, a priest of Kofuku-ji Temple, the Hatakeyama clan in Kawachi, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Zenpo managed to overcome the crisis with the support of Choin FURUICHI, a priest of Kofuku-ji Temple, the Hatakeyama clan in Kawachi, and others.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Zenpo managed to overcome the crisis with the support of Choin FURUICHI, a priest of Kofuku-ji Temple, the Hatakeyama clan in Kawachi, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明応2年（1493年）6月、40歳で禅鳳は初となる室町御所での演能を果たし、以後中央でもその実力を認められることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1493 when he was forty years old, Zenpo performed the first demonstration of a Noh play in Muromachi Imperial palace and after that, he was also recognized as a well-qualified actor in the center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1493, when he was forty years old, Zenpo performed the first demonstration of a Noh play in Muromachi Imperial palace and after that, he was recognized as a well-qualified actor in the center.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1493, when he was 40 years old, Zenpo performed the first demonstration of a Noh play in Muromachi Imperial palace and after that, he was recognized as a well-qualified actor in the center.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、アラビア数字に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>結果、当時の有力者であった細川政元、大内義興を彼の後援者として、根拠地であった奈良、さらに京でもしばしば勧進能を催すようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, he had a chance to often perform Kanjin-noh play (performances held to raise subscriptions for the construction of shrines or temples) in Nara where they were based and furthermore, in Kyo, with sponsorship of Masamoto HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI who were influential persons at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, he often had a chance to perform Kanjin-noh plays (performances held to raise subscriptions for the construction of shrines or temples) in Nara where they were based and furthermore in Kyo, with the sponsorship of Masamoto HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI, who were influential persons at that time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, he often had a chance to perform Kanjin-noh plays (performances held to raise subscriptions for the construction of shrines or temples) in Nara where they were based and furthermore in Kyo (capital), with the sponsorship of Masamoto HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI, who were influential persons at that time.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>主なものに文亀元年（1501年）京今熊野、永正2年（1505年）粟田口での勧進能がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Principal Kanjin noh plays performed were the ones held in Imakumano region, Kyoto in 1501 and in Awataguchi in 1505.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal Kanjin noh plays performed were those held in the Imakumano region, Kyoto in 1501 and in Awataguchi in 1505.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal Kanjin noh plays performed were those held in the Imakumano region, Kyoto in 1501 and in Awataguchi in 1505.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>文亀元年の際には公卿・女官がこぞって見物に訪れ、また永正2年の勧進能は当時52歳の禅鳳の活動の頂点を示すものとして、よく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjin noh play in 1501 had a big audience of Kugyo (the top court officials) and court ladies, and the one in 1505 is well known to represent the peak of Zenpo&apos;s activities at the age of fifty two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanjin noh play in 1501 had a large audience of Kugyo (top court officials) and court ladies, and the one in 1505 is well known as representing the peak of Zenpo&apos;s activities at the age of fifty two.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanjin noh play in 1501 had a large audience of Kugyo (top court officials) and court ladies, and the one in 1505 is well known as representing the peak of Zenpo&apos;s activities at the age of 52.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>大永8年（1528年）3月までに出家して禅鳳を名乗り、この頃嫡男の金春氏昭に大夫職を譲ったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had entered into priesthood by March 1528 and identified himself Zenpo, and seemed to let his legitimate son Ujiaki KONPARU take over the position of Daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By March 1528 he had entered the priesthood and identified himself as Zenpo, and seemed to let his legitimate son Ujiaki KONPARU take over the position of Daibu.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By March 1528 he had entered the priesthood and identified himself as Zenpo, and seemed to let his legitimate son Ujiaki KONPARU take over the position of Daibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>隠居後は豊後などに下ったというが、その没年についてははっきりとは分からない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that he left for Bingo for his retired life, and his year of death is not certain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that he left for Bingo for his retired life, and his year of death is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that he left for Bingo for his retired life, and his year of death is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>京の戦乱を避けて、後援者でもあった大内氏を頼り西国で晩年を過ごしたとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed that far from wars and confusions in Kyo, he spent the last years of his life in Saigoku with the support of the Ouchi clan as one of his sponsors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others believe that far from wars and chaos in Kyo, he spent the last years of his life in Saigoku with the support of the Ouchi clan as one of his sponsors.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others believe that far from wars and chaos in Kyo, he spent the last years of his life in Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki) with the support of the Ouchi clan as one of his sponsors.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>能作者として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh writers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh writers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh writers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>『能本作者註文』は、禅鳳の作として5番を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on &quot;Sakushazuke Nohon Sakusha Chumon,&quot; the following five are Zenpo&apos;s products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on &quot;Sakushazuke Nohon Sakusha Chumon,&quot; the following five are Zenpo&apos;s works.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on &quot;Nohon Sakusha Chumon&quot; (list of Noh numbers&apos; composers of Kanze lineage compiled by Kanemasa YOSHIDA on the basis of conversations with Yajiro Nagatoshi KANZE), the following five are Zenpo&apos;s works.</e>
<cmt>原文・訳文からリンクテキストを削除し修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>嵐山 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arashiyama (Noh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arashiyama (Noh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arashiyama (Noh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>一角仙人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikkaku sennin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikkaku sennin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkaku sennin (One horned hermit)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>生田敦盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsumori IKUTA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsumori IKUTA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsumori IKUTA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>東方朔 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tobosaku (Noh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tobosaku (Noh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tobosaku (Noh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>初雪 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatsuyuki (Noh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatsuyuki (Noh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatsuyuki (Virgin Snow; Noh)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>他にもまた現在演じられない「黒川（黒川延年）」が禅鳳作と判明しており、廃絶・散逸してしまった壮年期までの曲もまだ複数あると見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is confirmed that &apos;Kurokawa (黒川延年)&apos; which nowadays is not performed was written by Zenpo, and there seems to be many music pieces made until his late middle age, which were removed, disposed of or scattered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is confirmed that &apos;Kurokawa (黒川延年),&apos; which is not performed nowadays, was written by Zenpo, and there seem to be many music pieces made until his late middle age, which were removed, disposed of, or scattered.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is confirmed that &apos;Kurokawa&apos; (also known as Kurokawa Ennen (singing and dancing performed by priests and pages after Buddhist services in temples, which started from the middle of the Heian era)), which is not performed nowadays, was written by Zenpo, and there seem to be many music pieces made until his late middle age, which were removed, disposed of, or scattered.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また「富士の能」などを改作している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He renewed Noh of Fuji (富士の能.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He renewed Noh of Fuji (富士の能.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He renewed &apos;Noh of Fuji&apos; (Mt. Fuji of Noh).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>『自家伝抄』では上の5曲とは全く異なる18番を禅鳳作とするが、従来の説との差から顧みられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Sakushazuke Jika Densho,&quot; eighteen products, that are completely different from the five above, were the ones made by Zenpo, but this idea has not been paid attention because of the discrepancy with the former selection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Sakushazuke Jika Densho,&quot; eighteen works, which are completely different from the five above, were also made by Zenpo, but this idea has not been paid much attention, because of the discrepancy with the former selection.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Jika Densho&quot; (Noh books handed down from Konparu lineage compiled in 16th century), 18 works, which are completely different from the five above, were also made by Zenpo, but this idea has not been paid much attention, because of the discrepancy with the former selection.</e>
<cmt>原文・訳文からリンクテキストを削除し修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ただしその中の「武文（秦武文）」（廃曲）を、その特徴から禅鳳作とする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is partly believed that based on the characteristics,&apos; Takefumi (HATA no Takefumi)&apos; (discontinued) was a product made by Zenpo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some believe that, based on the characteristics,&apos; Takefumi (HATA no Takefumi)&apos; (discontinued) was a work of Zenpo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some believe that, based on the characteristics, &apos;Takebun&apos; (HADA no Takebun) (discontinued) was a work of Zenpo.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>作風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Writing style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Writing style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Writing style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>禅鳳の能は「素材・構想・演出形態などに新しい趣向を持った意欲作」であり、「異色の能」とも評される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenpo&apos;s Noh products are appreciated to &apos;be ambitious products with new features about subject matter, concept and performance style&apos; and &apos;exceptional Noh.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenpo&apos;s Noh works are appreciated to &apos;be ambitious works with new features about subject matter, concept, and performance style&apos; and &apos;exceptional Noh.&apos;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenpo&apos;s Noh works are appreciated to &apos;be ambitious works with new features about subject matter, concept, and performance style&apos; and &apos;exceptional Noh.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その作品には「嵐山」「一角仙人」など、曽祖父・世阿弥や祖父・禅竹が追求した幽玄な味わいよりも、ショー的な動きの華やかさやスペクタクル性を追求した風流能が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the subtle and profound beauty pursued by his great-grandfather Zeami and his grandfather Zenchiku, most of his products are more elegant Noh plays focused on gorgeous actions and spectacle features like a pageant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the subtle and profound beauty pursued by his great-grandfather Zeami and his grandfather Zenchiku, most of Zenpo&apos;s works are more elegant Noh plays focused on gorgeous actions and spectacles such as a pageant.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the subtle and profound beauty pursued by his great-grandfather Zeami and his grandfather Zenchiku, most of Zenpo&apos;s works are more elegant Noh plays focused on gorgeous actions and spectacles such as a pageant, &apos;Arashiyama,&apos; &apos;Ikkaku sennin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>禅鳳の作品としばしば比較されるのが、4歳年上の観世小次郎信光の作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A person who is often compared to Zenpo in terms of products is Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO four years older than him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A person who is often compared to Zenpo in terms of works is Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO, who was four years older than him.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A person who is often compared to Zenpo in terms of works is Kojiro Nobumitsu KANZE, who was four years older than him.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>両者の作品には、上に挙げたようなビジュアル的な絢爛さ、エンターテイメント性などの共通点が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The products of both have some features in common such as visual gorgeousness and the nature of entertainment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their works have some features in common, such as visual gorgeousness and the nature of entertainment.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their works have some features in common, such as visual gorgeousness and the nature of entertainment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>禅鳳は先行する観世座への対抗上、信光の作品を強く意識していたらしく、例えば「一角仙人」には信光の「紅葉狩」からの影響が指摘され、前述の「武文」にも「船弁慶」への対抗意識を見る説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenpo wanted to become more competitive than Kanze-za ahead of their group and seemed to feel extremely conscious about Nobumitsu&apos;s products, and taking for example, &apos;Ikkaku sennin&apos; is found to have been influenced from &apos;Momijigari (Noh)&apos; of Nobumitsu and there is a view that rivalries toward &apos;Funa Benkei&apos; also exist in &apos;Takefumi&apos; above stated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenpo wanted to become more competitive than Kanze-za ahead of their group and seemed to feel extremely conscious about Nobumitsu&apos;s works; for example, &apos;Ikkaku sennin&apos; is found to have been influenced from &apos;Momijigari (Noh)&apos; of Nobumitsu and there is a view that rivalries toward &apos;Funa Benkei&apos; also exist in &apos;Takefumi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenpo wanted to become more competitive than Kanze-za ahead of their group and seemed to feel extremely conscious about Nobumitsu&apos;s works; for example, &apos;Ikkaku sennin&apos; is found to have been influenced from &apos;Momijigari&apos; (viewing autumnal leaves) (Noh) of Nobumitsu and there is a view that rivalries toward &apos;Funa Benkei&apos; (Benkei in the Boat) also exist in &apos;Takebun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし禅鳳の作品には、信光作品に時に見られる凄絶さなどがなく、あくまで楽しさ、愉快さを重視している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenpo&apos;s products only focus on amusement, pleasantness and fun, rather than horrific or fierce aspects which are occasionally seen in Nobumitsu&apos;s products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenpo&apos;s works focus only on amusement, pleasantness, and fun, rather than horrific or fierce aspects, which are occasionally seen in Nobumitsu&apos;s works.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenpo&apos;s works focus only on amusement, pleasantness, and fun, rather than horrific or fierce aspects, which are occasionally seen in Nobumitsu&apos;s works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また特色ある素材を生かした比較的短い作品が多いこと、子方の積極的な使用なども相まって、「空想的な異国趣味」に満ちているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, his products are thought to be full of &apos;fantastic and exotic taste&apos; because of characteristic subject matters included in many relatively short stories and proactive use of Kokata (a child performer.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, his works are thought to be full of &apos;fantastic and exotic taste,&apos; because of characteristic subject matters included in many relatively short stories and proactive use of Kokata (child performers.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, his works are thought to be full of &apos;fantastic and exotic taste,&apos; because of characteristic subject matters included in many relatively short stories and proactive use of Kokata (child performers).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>能楽論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory of Nohgaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theory of Nohgaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory of Nohgaku</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>禅鳳能楽論の特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics of Zenpo&apos;s theory of Nohgaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of Zenpo&apos;s theory of Nohgaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of Zenpo&apos;s theory of Nohgaku</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>能楽論は世阿弥『風姿花伝』に創まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of Nohgaku was for the first time discussed in Zeami&apos;s &quot;Fushikaden.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of Nohgaku was discussed for the first time in Zeami&apos;s &quot;Fushikaden.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of Nohgaku was discussed for the first time in Zeami&apos;s &quot;Fushikaden&quot; (The Flowering Spirit).</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせ、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>世阿弥の死後は娘婿・禅竹が特色ある著作を残し、禅鳳もまた、この二人の先達を引き継ぐ形で多くの能楽論を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Zeami&apos;s death, his son-in-law Zenchiku authored unique books, and also, Zenpo left many theories of Nohgaku, succeeding the achievements of these two seniors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Zeami&apos;s death, his son-in-law Zenchiku authored unique books, and Zenpo also left many theories of Nohgaku, succeeding the achievements of these two seniors.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Zeami&apos;s death, his son-in-law Zenchiku authored unique books, and Zenpo also left many theories of Nohgaku, succeeding the achievements of these two seniors.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし近代以降世阿弥の研究が多岐に渡って行われ、多くの人々に広く読まれているのに対し、禅竹は「観念的」「難解」と一段低く見られる傾向が強く、禅鳳以降にもなるとほとんど顧みられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern times, while Zeami&apos;s Nohgaku theories were extensively studied and read by many people, Zenchiku&apos;s theories tended to be thought less for the reason of being &apos;ideological&apos; and &apos;difficult&apos; and drew little attention after Zenpo appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern times, while Zeami&apos;s Nohgaku theories have been extensively studied and read by many people, Zenchiku&apos;s theories have tended to be thought of less for the reason of being &apos;ideological&apos; and &apos;difficult&apos; and drew little attention after Zenpo appeared.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern times, while Zeami&apos;s Nohgaku theories have been extensively studied and read by many people, Zenchiku&apos;s theories have tended to be thought of less for the reason of being &apos;ideological&apos; and &apos;difficult&apos; and drew little attention after Zenpo appeared.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>事実禅鳳以後、室町後期から江戸初期にかけての能伝書は即物的・実用的な教科書・技術指導書としての色彩が強く、「能とは何か」を問う世阿弥などの芸術論的著作とはかけ離れたものとなっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, after Zenpo, Nodensho books (能伝書) written over the period between the late Muromachi period and the early Edo period had the clear features of a textbook or technical guidance book of fleeting and practical nature and were very different from Zeami&apos;s and other people&apos;s theories of art seeking &apos;What Noh is.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, after Zenpo, Nodensho books (能伝書) written between the late Muromachi period and the early Edo period had the clear features of a textbook or technical guidance book of fleeting and practical nature and were very different from Zeami&apos;s and other people&apos;s theories of art seeking &apos;What Noh is.&apos;</e>
<cmt>omitted unnecessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, after Zenpo, Nodensho books (secret treatises for Noh theater) written between the late Muromachi period and the early Edo period had the clear features of a textbook or technical guidance book of fleeting and practical nature and were very different from Zeami&apos;s and other people&apos;s theories of art seeking &apos;What Noh is.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>禅鳳の著作にもそうした種類のものが多い一方で、『元安本五音之次第』などの重厚な著作もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of Zenpo&apos;s books are classified as those types of books, but he also authored books of grave character such as &quot;元安本五音之次第.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of Zenpo&apos;s books are classified as those types of books, but he also authored books of grave character, such as &quot;元安本五音之次第.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of Zenpo&apos;s books are classified as those types of books, but he also authored books of grave character, such as &quot;Motoyasubon Goon no shidai&quot; (a Noh book handed down from Konparu lineage compiled by Zenpo).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>禅鳳の活躍した時代には「能」というものは既にほぼ確立されており、禅鳳に出来たのは、それをより技術的に洗練することだけであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh&apos; had been completed and established until the period Zenpo did great jobs, so all what Zenpo could do was to refine and polish Noh technically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh&apos; had been completed and established by the the period when Zenpo wrote great works, so all what Zenpo could do was refine and polish Noh technically.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh&apos; had been completed and established by the period when Zenpo wrote great works, so all what Zenpo could do was refine and polish Noh technically.</e>
<cmt>theを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>いわば禅鳳は、世阿弥・禅竹の芸論と、近世の芸論を繋ぐ過渡期の著述家であったと評価することが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, Zenpo can be evaluated to be a transitional author who served as a bridge between Zeami&apos;s and Zenchiku&apos;s theories and the modern theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, Zenpo can be evaluated to be a transitional author who served as a bridge between Zeami&apos;s and Zenchiku&apos;s theories and the modern theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, Zenpo can be evaluated to be a transitional author who served as a bridge between Zeami&apos;s and Zenchiku&apos;s theories and the modern theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>それ故に、世阿弥・禅竹期の能がいかに継承されいかに変わっていったかを知るかには、まさにその著作は第一級の資料であるし、また逆に後世の能伝書に与えた影響は極めて大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given the above, his books are the best and primary materials to know how Noh was continued and was changed in the era of Zeami and Zenchiku and also had significant influence on Nodensho of later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the above, his books are the best and primary materials to know how Noh was continued and was changed in the era of Zeami and Zenchiku and also had significant influence on Nodensho of later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the above, his books are the best and primary materials to know how Noh was continued and was changed in the era of Zeami and Zenchiku and also had significant influence on Nodensho of later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="49">
<j>また『禅鳳雑談』で見られる、茶道の村田珠光、連歌の宗砌、華道の池坊専順、尺八の聞阿弥など当時の他の諸芸の名人たちの言葉への言及も、禅鳳能楽論の特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Zenpo Zatsudan,&quot; references to the words or statements made by masters in other categories of art including Juko MURATA in Japanese tea ceremony, Sozei in Renga (linked verse,) Senjun IKENOBO in flower arrangement and 聞阿弥 as a musician of Shakuhachi bamboo flute are special aspects in Zenpo&apos;s theory of Nohgaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Zenpo Zatsudan,&quot; special aspects of Zenpo&apos;s theory of Nohgaku include references to the words or statements made by masters in other categories of art, including Juko MURATA in Japanese tea ceremony, Sozei in Renga (linked verse,) Senjun IKENOBO in flower arrangement, and 聞阿弥 as a musician of Shakuhachi bamboo flute.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Zenpo Zatsudan,&quot; special aspects of Zenpo&apos;s theory of Nohgaku include references to the words or statements made by masters in other categories of art, including Juko MURATA in Japanese tea ceremony, Sozei in Renga (linked verse), Senjun IKENOBO in flower arrangement, and Monami (聞阿弥) as a musician of Shakuhachi bamboo flute.</e>
<cmt>推測した読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>禅鳳の伝書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenpo&apos;s Densho (books handed down from ancestors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenpo&apos;s Densho (books handed down from ancestors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenpo&apos;s Densho (books handed down from ancestors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>禅鳳の著作は、1915年刊行の吉田東伍校注『禅竹集』に『毛端私珍抄』『反故裏の書』が収録されるなど、比較的早くから出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Motanshichinsho (毛端私珍抄)&quot; and &quot;Hogoura no sho (反故裏の書)&quot; were included in &quot;Zenchiku-shu&quot; which was published in 1915 and revised and annotated by YOSHIDA, and Zenpo&apos;s authored books were published relatively early.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Motanshichinsho (毛端私珍抄)&quot; and &quot;Hogoura no sho (反故裏の書)&quot; were included in &quot;Zenchiku-shu&quot; which was published in 1915 and revised and annotated by YOSHIDA, and Zenpo&apos;s authored books were published relatively early.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Motanshichinsho&quot; (The Motan Collection) and &quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; (Notes on the Back of Used Papers) were included in &quot;Zenchikushu&quot; (Collection of Zenchiku works) which was published in 1915 and revised and annotated by Togo YOSHIDA, and Zenpo&apos;s authored books were published relatively early.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし『禅竹集』では特に『反故裏の書』（三）に関して改変が多く、現在研究には用いられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Speaking of &quot;Zenchikushu,&quot; however, particularly &quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; (Third) are not available for research purposes at present because of lots of corruptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Speaking of &quot;Zenchikushu,&quot; however, particularly &quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; (Third), is not available for research purposes at present because of lots of corruptions.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Speaking of &quot;Zenchikushu,&quot; however, particularly &quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; (third volume), is not available for research purposes at present because of lots of corruptions.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>以下、『禅鳳書物写し』を除き表章・伊藤正義『金春古伝書集成』（わんや書店、1969年）に収録されるほか、『禅鳳雑談』が日本思想大系『古代中世芸術論集』（岩波書店）に収録されている（北川忠彦校訂）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for &quot;Zenpo Shomotsu Utsushi&quot; (copy of Zenpo&apos;s books,) Zenpo&apos;s authored books were included in &quot;Konparu kodensho shusei&quot; by Akira OMOTE and Masayoshi ITO (published by Wanya Shoten in 1969) and also &quot;Zenpo Zatsudan&quot; was included in &quot;Collection of theories of art in the ancient and the medieval period,&quot; a collection of philosophical thoughts in Japan (Iwanami Shoten, publishers) (revised by Tadahiko KITAGAWA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for &quot;Zenpo Shomotsu Utsushi&quot; (copy of Zenpo&apos;s books), Zenpo&apos;s authored books were included in &quot;Konparu kodensho shusei&quot; by Akira OMOTE and Masayoshi ITO (published by Wanya Shoten in 1969) and also &quot;Zenpo Zatsudan&quot; was included in &quot;Collection of theories of art in the ancient and the medieval period,&quot; a collection of philosophical thoughts in Japan (Iwanami Shoten, publishers) (revised by Tadahiko KITAGAWA.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for &quot;Zenpo Shomotsu Utsushi&quot; (copy of Zenpo&apos;s books), Zenpo&apos;s authored books were included in &quot;Konparu Kodensho shusei&quot; (Collection of the Ancient Treatises of Konparu) by Akira OMOTE and Masayoshi ITO (published by Wanya Shoten in 1969) and also &quot;Zenpo Zodan&quot; (Miscellaneous conversations with Zenpo) was included in &quot;Collection of theories of art in the ancient and the medieval period,&quot; a collection of philosophical thoughts in Japan (Iwanami Shoten, publishers) (revised by Tadahiko KITAGAWA).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>『毛端私珍抄』（現存本毛端私珍抄）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Motanshichinsho&quot; (currently existing Motanshichinsho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Motanshichinsho&quot; (currently existing Motanshichinsho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Motanshichinsho&quot; (currently existing Motanshichinsho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>『反故裏の書』（一） - （三）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; (1) - (3)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; (1) - (3)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; (volume 1 to 3)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="55">
<j>いずれも未完の著作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of them are unfinished books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of these are unfinished books.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both of these are unfinished books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>総合的伝書『毛端私珍抄』として執筆を進めていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He seemed to continue writing for a comprehensive Densho &quot;Motanshichinsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He seemed to continue writing for a comprehensive Densho &quot;Motanshichinsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He seemed to continue writing for a comprehensive Densho &quot;Motanshichinsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>『反故裏の書』三部がその執筆用メモであるが、現存する「毛端私珍抄」自体はその完成稿ではなく、あくまで第一稿を書き写したものらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; trilogy was a memorandum for his writing, and the existing &apos;Motanshichinsho&apos; is not a complete version and is thought to be the transcript of the first draft.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; trilogy was a memorandum for his writing, and the existing &apos;Motanshichinsho&apos; is not a complete version and is thought to be the transcript of the first draft.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Hogoura no sho&quot; trilogy was a memorandum for his writing, and the existing &apos;Motanshichinsho&apos; is not a complete version and is thought to be the transcript of the first draft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>相互に内容の重複が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many overlapping areas in those books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many overlapping areas in those books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many overlapping areas in those books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="59">
<j>『元安本五音之次第』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;元安本五音之次第&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;元安本五音之次第&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;元安本五音之次第&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="60">
<j>本来は無題の書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, this book was untitled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, this book was untitled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, this book was untitled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>永正8年（1511年）8月の奥書がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has Okugaki (postscript) dated August 1511.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has an Okugaki (postscript) dated August 1511.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has an Okugaki (postscript) dated September 1511.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>前半は世阿弥『五音曲条々』、禅竹『五音之次第』『五音十体』『五音三曲集』の所説とほぼ同内容、後半は『毛端私珍抄』などと関連する禅鳳独自の説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first half of the book presents his idea which is almost the same as the theories described in Zeami&apos;s &quot;Goongyokujojo&quot; and Zenchiku&apos;s &quot;Goon no shidai,&quot; &quot;Goon-juttai (五音十体)&quot; and &quot;Goon-sangyoku-shu,&quot; and the latter half of the book shows Zenpo&apos;s unique theories related to &quot;Motanshichinsho,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first half of the book presents his idea, which is almost the same as the theories described in Zeami&apos;s &quot;Goongyokujojo&quot; and Zenchiku&apos;s &quot;Goon no shidai,&quot; &quot;Goon-juttai (五音十体),&quot; and &quot;Goon-sangyoku-shu,&quot; and the latter half of the book shows Zenpo&apos;s unique theories related to &quot;Motanshichinsho,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first half of the book presents his idea, which is almost the same as the theories described in Zeami&apos;s &quot;Goongyokujojo&quot; (Various Matters Concerning the Five Modes of Musical Expression) and Zenchiku&apos;s &quot;Goon no shidai,&quot; &quot;Goon Jittei&quot; (Five sounds and ten styles), and &quot;Goon sankyoku shu&quot; (An account on the five modes and the three styles) and the latter half of the book shows Zenpo&apos;s unique theories related to &quot;Motanshichinsho,&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>読み確認済み漢字を削除し、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>当時の謡の流行が窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popular Utai (the chanting of a Noh text) of that time is known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular Utai (the chanting of a Noh text) of that time is known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular Utai (the chanting of a Noh text) of that time is known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>嫡男氏昭に相伝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handed down to his legitimate son Ujiaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handed down to his legitimate son Ujiaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handed down to his legitimate son Ujiaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="65">
<j>『音曲五音』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Onkyoku goon (音曲五音)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Onkyoku goon (音曲五音)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ongyoku Goon&quot; (Songs with Shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) accompaniment and Five sounds)</e>
<cmt>用語補足、読みを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="66">
<j>やはり本来は無題の書と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, this book seems to have been originally untitled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book also seems to have been originally untitled.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book also seems to have been originally untitled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>二種の伝書を合写したもので、前半は永正13年（1516年）12月奥書、後半は大永8年（1528年）3月奥書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book contains the transcripts of two Densho, and the first half of the book was Okugaki dated December 1516 and the latter half was Okugaki dated March 1528.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book contains the transcripts of two Densho, and the first half of the book was Okugaki dated December 1516 and the latter half was Okugaki dated March 1528.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book contains the transcripts of two Densho, and the first half of the book was Okugaki dated January 1517 and the latter half was Okugaki dated March 1528.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>ともに奈良在住の素人弟子であったらしい新屋左衛門五郎という人物に当てて書かれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both were addressed to Shinyazaemongoro who was probably an amateur pupil in Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both were addressed to Shinyazaemongoro, who was probably an amateur pupil in Nara.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both were addressed to Saemon Goro ARAYA (新屋左衛門五郎), who was probably an amateur pupil in Nara.</e>
<cmt>読み未確認の漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="69">
<j>『囃之事』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;囃之事&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;囃之事&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hayashi no koto&quot; (Musical Accompaniment)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="70">
<j>永正2年（1505年）、後に観世座に移籍する鼓の名人・宮増弥左衛門に相伝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1505, it was handed down to 宮増弥左衛門 who was a Tsuzumi (hand drum) master and moved to Kanze-za later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1505, it was handed down to 宮増弥左衛門, who was a Tsuzumi (hand drum) master and later moved to Kanze-za.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1505, it was handed down to Yazaemon MIYAMASU, who was a Tsuzumi (hand drum) master and later moved to Kanze-za.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>書状形式で、鼓役者の心得を記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a letter style and talks about how a Tsuzumi player should be.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is in a letter style and talks about how a Tsuzumi player should be.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is in a letter style and talks about how a Tsuzumi player should be.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="72">
<j>『禅鳳雑談』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zenpo Zatsudan&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zenpo Zatsudan&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Zenpo Zatsudan&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="73">
<j>『禅鳳申楽談儀』とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be called &quot;Zenpo Shinraku Dangi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be called &quot;Zenpo Shinraku Dangi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be called &quot;Zenpo Sarugaku Dangi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>永正9年（1512年）から13年にかけての禅鳳の芸談の聞書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is Kikigaki (account of what one hears) of what Zenpo talked about art over thirteen years from 1512.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a Kikigaki (account of what one hears) of what Zenpo talked about art over thirteen years from 1512.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a Kikigaki (account of what one hears) of what Zenpo talked about art over 13 years from 1512.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>話題は多岐に及び、当時の能の実態を知る上で貴重な史料とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It covers a wide variety of topics and is considered valuable historical materials to know the actual status of Noh at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It covers a wide variety of topics and is considered valuable historical material for knowing the actual status of Noh at that time.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It covers a wide variety of topics and is considered valuable historical material for knowing the actual status of Noh at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>著者は禅鳳の弟子と思われる藤右衛門という人物で、天文22年（1553年）76歳で没したらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author was Touemon who was probably Zenpo&apos;s pupil and is believed to have died at the age of seventy six in 1553.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author was Touemon, who was probably Zenpo&apos;s pupil and is believed to have died at the age of seventy six in 1553.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author was Touemon, who was probably Zenpo&apos;s pupil and is believed to have died at the age of 76 in 1553.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="77">
<j>『禅鳳書物写し』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zenpo shomotsu utsushi&quot; (transcript of Zenpo&apos;s books)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zenpo shomotsu utsushi&quot; (transcript of Zenpo&apos;s books)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Zenpo shomotsu utsushi&quot;</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="78">
<j>無題の一枚の書付。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A piece of paper without title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A piece of paper without title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A piece of paper without title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>娘婿の観世大夫道見に相伝し、禅鳳の孫である観世宗節が書写したものか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It might have been handed down to his daughter&apos;s husband Kanze-daibu Doken (道見) and transcribed by Zenpo&apos;s grandchild Sosetsu KANZE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It might have been handed down to his daughter&apos;s husband Kanze-daibu Doken (道見) and transcribed by Zenpo&apos;s grandchild Sosetsu KANZE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It might have been handed down to his daughter&apos;s husband Kanze-dayu (the chairman of Kanze) Doken (道見) and transcribed by Zenpo&apos;s grandchild Sosetsu KANZE.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>子に金春大夫を継いだ金春氏昭（氏照）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his children was Ujiaki (氏照) KONPARU who took over the position of Konparu Daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his children was Ujiaki (氏照) KONPARU, who took over the position of Konparu Daibu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his children was Ujiaki (also called as Ujiteru) KONPARU, who took over the position of Konparu Dayu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>孫の金春喜勝（岌蓮）は下間少進の師として名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandchild Yoshikatsu KONPARU was well known as the master of Shojin SHIMOTSUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandchild Yoshikatsu KONPARU was well known as the master of Shojin SHIMOTSUMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandchild Yoshikatsu KONPARU was well known as the master of Shojin SHIMOTSUMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>曾孫の金春安照は禅鳳の所説を受け継いだ著作を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His great-grandchild Yasuteru KONPARU succeeded Zenpo&apos;s theories and left his authored books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His great-grandchild Yasuteru KONPARU succeeded Zenpo&apos;s theories and left his authored books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His great-grandchild Yasuteru KONPARU succeeded Zenpo&apos;s theories and left his authored books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>七世観世宗節は娘の子で、さらにその弟宝生重勝が養子として宝生流を継ぎ、三人の孫が大和四座の内三座までの大夫を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seventh Sosetsu KANZE (七世観世宗節) was his daughter&apos;s son, and his younger brother Shigekatsu HOSHO (宝生重勝) was adopted to take over the Hosho school and his three grandchildren each served as Daibu of the three groups of Yamato-yoza (four sarugaku performance groups in the Yamato Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seventh Sosetsu KANZE (七世観世宗節) was his daughter&apos;s son; his younger brother Shigekatsu HOSHO (宝生重勝) was adopted to take over the Hosho school, and his three grandchildren each served as Daibu of three groups of Yamato-yoza (four sarugaku performance groups in the Yamato Province.)</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seventh Sosetsu KANZE was his daughter&apos;s son; his younger brother Shigekatsu HOSHO (宝生重勝) was adopted to take over the Hosho school, and his three grandchildren each served as Dayu of three groups of Yamato-yoza (four Sarugaku performance groups in the Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt>読み確認済み漢字を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sat666(id:127263), Miya(id:1881), 垂耳犬(id:202697), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>