<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳川家宣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienobu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienobu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienobu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳川 家宣（とくがわ いえのぶ）は江戸幕府第6代征夷大将軍である（在職：宝永6年5月1日 (旧暦)（1709年6月8日） - 正徳 (日本)2年10月14日 (旧暦)（1712年11月12日））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienobu TOKUGAWA was the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) who took office from June 8, 1709 to November 12, 1712.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienobu TOKUGAWA was the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and took office from June 8, 1709 to November 12, 1712.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;who&quot; to &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienobu TOKUGAWA was the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and took office from June 8, 1709 to November 12, 1712.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>甲府藩主・徳川綱重（甲府宰相）の長男で、母はお保良の方（長昌院）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA (the prime minister of Kofu), the lord of Kofu Domain, and his mother was Ohora no kata (Choshoin).</e>
<cmt>「長昌院」は「ちょうしょういん」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA (the prime minister of Kofu), the lord of the Kofu Domain, and his mother was Ohora no kata (Choshoin).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA (the prime minister of Kofu), the lord of the Kofu Domain, and his mother was Ohora no kata (Choshoin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正室は近衛基熙の娘・天英院熙子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was Hiroko TENEI-IN, the daughter of Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was Hiroko TENEI-IN, the daughter of Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was Hiroko TENEI-IN, the daughter of Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に徳川家継ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included Ietsugu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Ietsugu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Ietsugu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>第3代将軍・徳川家光の孫に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the grandson of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the grandson of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the grandson of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼名は虎松。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Toramatsu.</e>
<cmt>「虎松」の読みが確認できなかったので、「とらまつ」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Toramatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Toramatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>初名は綱豊（つなとよ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Tsunatoyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Tsunatoyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Tsunatoyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>近年の研究では、甲府時代は松平を名乗っていた（宗家、御三家の当主、世嗣以外は徳川を名乗れなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent researches show that he went by the family name of MATSUDAIRA while he was in Kofu (because TOKUGAWA was only allowed to those from the head family, the three privileged branches of the family and the heir).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent research shows that he went by the family name of MATSUDAIRA while he was in Kofu (because use of TOKUGAWA was only allowed for those from the head family, the three privileged branches of the family, and the heir).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent research shows that he went by the family name of Matsudaira while he was in Kofu (because use of Tokugawa was only allowed for those from the head family, the three privileged branches of the family, and the heir).</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>石高は25万石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had 2.5 million kokudaka (a system for determining land value for tribute purposes) in yield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had 2.5 million kokudaka (a system for determining land value for tribute purposes) in yield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had 250,000 kokudaka (a system for determining land value for tribute purposes) in yield.</e>
<cmt>数字修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>寛文2年4月25日（1662年6月11日）、徳川綱重の長男として江戸根津邸にて生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the first son of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA on June 11, 1662, at the Nezu house in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the first son of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA on June 11, 1662, at the Nezu house in Edo.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the first son of Tsunashige TOKUGAWA on June 11, 1662, at the Nezu house in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>父が正室を娶る直前の19歳の時に身分の低い26歳の女中に生ませた子であったため、世間をはばかって家臣の新見正信に預けられ、養子として新見左近を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he was born to a 26-year-old low-rank maid when his father, who was about to marry the lawful wife, was 19 years old, he was adopted by Masanobu SHINMI, one of the vassals of the family, and went by the name of Sakon SHINMI.</e>
<cmt>「新見正信」は「しんみまさのぶ」、「左近」は「さこん」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he was born to a 26-year-old low-rank maid when his father, who was about to marry his lawful wife, was 19 years old, he was adopted by Masanobu SHINMI, one of the vassals of the family, and went by the name of Sakon SHINMI.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he was born to a 26-year-old low-rank maid when his father, who was about to marry his lawful wife, was 19 years old, he was adopted by Masanobu SHINMI, one of the vassals of the family, and went by the name of Sakon SHINMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>生母は寛永4年（1664年）に死去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His biological mother died in 1664.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His biological mother died in 1664.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His biological mother died in 1664.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>9歳のとき、他の男子に恵まれなかった綱重の世嗣として呼び戻され、元服して伯父である4代将軍・徳川家綱の偏諱を受けて「綱豊」と名乗り、延宝6年（1678年）の父の死後、17歳で家督を継承し祖母・順性院に育てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was brought back to the TOKUGAWA family by Tsunashige who had no male children as heir when he was nine years old, and when he reached adulthood he went by the name of Tsunatoyo after being granted to use a portion of the real name of uncle Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the fourth shogun, and after his father died in 1678, he took over as head of the family at age 17 and was raised by his grandmother JUNSEI-IN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was brought back to the TOKUGAWA family by Tsunashige, who had no male children as heir, when he was nine years old, and when he reached adulthood he went by the name of Tsunatoyo after being granted use of a portion of the real name of uncle Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the fourth shogun, and after his father died in 1678, he took over as head of the family at age 17 and was raised by his grandmother JUNSEI-IN.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was brought back to the Tokugawa family by Tsunashige, who had no male children as heir, when he was nine years old, and when he reached adulthood he went by the name of Tsunatoyo after being granted use of a portion of the real name of uncle Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the fourth shogun, and after his father died in 1678, he took over as head of the family at age 17 and was raised by his grandmother JUNSEI-IN.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>延宝8年（1680年）、家綱が重態となった際には、家綱に男子がなかったことから綱重の弟に当たる上野国館林藩主・徳川綱吉とともに第5代将軍の有力候補であったが、堀田正俊が家光に血が近い綱吉を強力に将軍に推したため、綱豊の将軍就任はならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of leading candidates as the fifth shogun along with Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, Tsunashige&apos;s younger brother and the lord of Tatebayashi Domain in Kozuke Province, when Ietsuna became critically ill in 1680 because Ietsuna had no male child, but because Masatoshi HOTTA strongly recommended Tsunayoshi, who was more closely related to Iemitsu by blood, for the shogun, Tsunatoyo did not took office as shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of leading candidates as the fifth shogun along with Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, Tsunashige&apos;s younger brother and the lord of the Tatebayashi Domain in Kozuke Province, when Ietsuna became critically ill in 1680 because Ietsuna had no male child, but because Masatoshi HOTTA strongly recommended Tsunayoshi, who was more closely related to Iemitsu by blood, for the shogun, Tsunatoyo did not take office as shogun.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of leading candidates as the fifth shogun along with Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, Tsunashige&apos;s younger brother and the lord of the Tatebayashi Domain in Kozuke Province, when Ietsuna became critically ill in 1680 because Ietsuna had no male child, but because Masatoshi HOTTA strongly recommended Tsunayoshi, who was more closely related to Iemitsu by blood, for the shogun, Tsunatoyo did not take office as shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>綱吉にも世嗣がいなかったが、綱吉娘婿の徳川綱教も後継候補だったため、綱教の死後、将軍世嗣として「家宣」と改名して江戸城西の丸に入ったのは宝永元年12月5日 (旧暦)（1704年12月31日）、家宣が43歳の時だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi had no male child, too, but because Tsunayoshi&apos;s son-in-law Tsunanori TOKUGAWA was among the leading candidates as heir, he changed his name to Ienobu as heir to the shogun after Tsunanori&apos;s death and resided in the western citadel of Edo-jo Castle in December 31, 1704, at age 43.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi had no male child either, but because Tsunayoshi&apos;s son-in-law Tsunanori TOKUGAWA was among the leading candidates as heir, he changed his name to Ienobu as heir to the shogun after Tsunanori&apos;s death and took residence in the western citadel of Edo-jo Castle in December 31, 1704, at age 43.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi had no male child either, but because Tsunayoshi&apos;s son-in-law Tsunanori TOKUGAWA was among the leading candidates as heir, he changed his name to Ienobu as heir to the shogun after Tsunanori&apos;s death and took residence in the western citadel of Edo-jo Castle in December 31, 1704, at age 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>宝永6年（1709年）、綱吉が亡くなり、48歳で第6代将軍に就任すると、悪評の高かった生類憐れみの令や酒税を廃止するなど気概を示したため、庶民からの人気と期待は高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tsunayoshi died in 1709 and he assumed the position of the sixth shogun at age 48, Ienobu showed backbone by abolishing notorious ordinances such as Shorui-Awaremi-no-rei (ordinances of animal protection) and liquor tax, winning widespread popularity and raising expectations from the common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tsunayoshi died in 1709 and he assumed the position of the sixth shogun at age 48, Ienobu showed backbone by abolishing notorious ordinances such as Shorui-Awaremi-no-rei (ordinances of animal protection) and liquor tax, winning widespread popularity and raising expectations from the common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tsunayoshi died in 1709 and he assumed the position of the sixth shogun at age 48, Ienobu showed backbone by abolishing notorious ordinances such as Shorui-Awaremi-no-rei (ordinances of animal protection) and liquor tax, winning widespread popularity and raising expectations from the common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>柳沢吉保を免職し、間部詮房・新井白石を登用して文治政治を推進し、荻原重秀に命じて財政改革を試みたが、在職3年後の正徳2年10月14日（1712年11月12日）に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an effort to promote the transformation of the feudal government from a military to civilian institution, he dismissed Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA and appointed Hakuseki ARAI, and also ordered Shigehide OGIWARA in an attempt to reform the government&apos;s financial practices, but Ienobu died on November 12, 1712, three years after he took office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an effort to promote the transformation of the feudal government from a military to civilian institution, he dismissed Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA and appointed Hakuseki ARAI, and also gave orders to Shigehide OGIWARA in an attempt to reform the government&apos;s financial practices, but Ienobu died on November 12, 1712, three years after he took office.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an effort to promote the transformation of the feudal government from a military to civilian institution, he dismissed Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA and appointed Hakuseki ARAI, and also gave orders to Shigehide OGIWARA in an attempt to reform the government&apos;s financial practices, but Ienobu died on November 12, 1712, three years after he took office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>享年51。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 51 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 51 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 51.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>後を子の徳川家継が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son Ietsugu TOKUGAWA took over his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son Ietsugu TOKUGAWA took over his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son Ietsugu TOKUGAWA took over his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>家宣と次代将軍・徳川家継の治世を、併せて正徳の治（正徳の政治）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The periods ruled by Ienobu and his successor Ietsugu TOKUGAWA are known collectively as &quot;Shotoku no chi&quot; (the peaceful era of Shotoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The periods ruled by Ienobu and his successor Ietsugu TOKUGAWA are known collectively as &quot;Shotoku no chi&quot; (the peaceful era of Shotoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The periods ruled by Ienobu and his successor Ietsugu TOKUGAWA are known collectively as &quot;Shotoku no chi&quot; (the peaceful era of Shotoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>戒名：文昭院殿順蓮社清譽廓然大居士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) is Bunshoinden Junrensha Seiyokakunen Dai Koshi.</e>
<cmt>「文昭院殿順蓮社清譽廓然大居士」の読み方が確認できなかったので、仮に「ぶんしょういんでん・じゅんれんしゃ・せいよかくねん・だい・こし」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) is Bunshoinden Junrensha Seiyokakunen Dai Koshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) is Bunshoinden Junrensha Seiyokakunen Dai Koshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>墓所：東京都港区 (東京都)の三縁山広度院増上寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried at Sanenzan Kodoin Zojo-ji Temple in Tokyo&apos;s Minato Ward.</e>
<cmt>「三縁山広度院増上寺」 http://www.zojoji.or.jp/info/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried at Sanenzan Kodoin Zojo-ji Temple in Tokyo&apos;s Minato Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried at Sanenzan Kodoin Zojo-ji Temple in Tokyo&apos;s Minato Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal profile and anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal profile and anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile and anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>心優しい人物だったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed to be a gentle person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have been a gentle person.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have been a gentle person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>父・綱重に世子として呼び戻された際、家宣付の家臣として新見正信、太田正成、島田時之らを付された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his father Tsunashige brought him back to name him as heir, Masanobu SHINMI, Masashige OTA and Tokiyuki SHIMADA were ordered to work under Ienobu.</e>
<cmt>「太田正成」は「おおた・まさしげ」、「島田時之」は「しまだ・ときゆき」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his father Tsunashige brought him back to name him heir, Masanobu SHINMI, Masashige OTA, and Tokiyuki SHIMADA were ordered to work under Ienobu.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his father Tsunashige brought him back to name him heir, Masanobu SHINMI, Masashige OTA, and Tokiyuki SHIMADA were ordered to work under Ienobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>新見は家宣の育ての父であり、さらに養父であったことから家宣の信任が厚く、それを嫉妬した太田・島田らが幕府に対して「左近は早世しており、新見が自らの子を左近として擁立した」と讒訴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienobu had absolute confidence in SHINMI because he was adopted and raised by him, but OTA and SHIMADA became jealous of SHINMI and brought a false charge against him, telling the bakufu that Sakon had died young and SHINMI replaced his own child with Sakon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienobu had absolute confidence in SHINMI because he was adopted and raised by him, but OTA and SHIMADA became jealous of SHINMI and brought a false charge against him, telling the bakufu that Sakon had died young and SHINMI replaced his own child with Sakon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienobu had absolute confidence in Shinmi because he was adopted and raised by him, but Ota and Shimada became jealous of Shinmi and brought a false charge against him, telling the bakufu that Sakon had died young and Shinmi replaced his own child with Sakon.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これがと知れると、両名は幕府から切腹を命じられたが、家宣は「一時とはいえ、自分のために仕えてくれた家臣を助けてほしい」と助命を嘆願し、流罪に減刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the accusation was proved groundless, the bakufu ordered the two to commit harakiri, but Ienobu pleaded the bakufu to save their lives, saying that he would like to have them spared because they served for him even though temporarily, and the sentence was reduced to banishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the accusation was proved groundless, the bakufu ordered the two to commit harakiri, but Ienobu pleaded with the bakufu to save their lives, saying that he would like to have them spared because they had served for him, although temporarily, and the sentence was reduced to banishment.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the accusation was proved groundless, the bakufu ordered the two to commit harakiri, but Ienobu pleaded with the bakufu to save their lives, saying that he would like to have them spared because they had served for him, although temporarily, and the sentence was reduced to banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>綱吉の実子・徳川徳松が早世すると、水戸藩主・徳川光圀から強く次期将軍に推挙されたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he was strongly recommended by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, the lord of Mito Domain, to become the next shogun when Tsunayoshi&apos;s biological child Tokumatsu TOKUGAWA died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he was strongly recommended by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, to become the next shogun when Tsunayoshi&apos;s biological child Tokumatsu TOKUGAWA died young.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he was strongly recommended by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, the lord of the Mito Domain, to become the next shogun when Tsunayoshi&apos;s biological child Tokumatsu TOKUGAWA died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>綱吉との関係は良好なものではなかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed that he had not been on good terms with Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also believed that he had not been on good terms with Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also believed that he had not been on good terms with Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>無類の学問好きで、新井白石から初代将軍・徳川家康、曽祖父の2代将軍・徳川秀忠、祖父の3代将軍・徳川家光の事跡など、歴史について熱心に学んだといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally understood that he was extremely dedicated for learning, and enthusiastically studied history under the tutelage of Hakuseki ARAI on matters including achievements gained by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the first shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the second shogun and his great-grandfather, and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally understood that he was extremely dedicated to learning, and enthusiastically studied history under the tutelage of Hakuseki ARAI on matters including achievements gained by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the first shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the second shogun and his great-grandfather, and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third shogun.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally understood that he was extremely dedicated to learning, and enthusiastically studied history under the tutelage of Hakuseki ARAI on matters including achievements gained by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the first shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the second shogun and his great-grandfather, and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また慶長5年（1600年）から延宝8年（1680年）に至る80年間の諸大名家の家系図と略伝を10ヶ月でまとめさせ、『藩翰譜』と題して常に手元に置いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he ordered his vassals to compile a book in 10 months to cover the family lineage and the brief biography of all the territorial lords existed in the 80 years from 1600 through 1680, and always kept the book, titled &quot;Hankanpu,&quot; on hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he ordered his vassals to compile a book in 10 months to cover the family lineage and the brief biography of all the territorial lords existed in the 80 years from 1600 through 1680, and he always kept the book, titled &quot;Hankanpu,&quot; on hand.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he ordered his vassals to compile a book in 10 months to cover the family lineage and the brief biography of all the territorial lords existed in the 80 years from 1600 through 1680, and he always kept the book, titled &quot;Hankanpu,&quot; on hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>綱吉から養子として迎えられて江戸城西の丸に入ったとき、また下心を持つ諸大名や旗本が賄賂に近い祝い品を持ってきたとき、家宣はこれらを全く受け取らなかったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienobu never received any gifts which could work as bribes from territorial lords and hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) who had an axe to grind when he first came to the western citadel of Edo-jo Castle after he was adopted by Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienobu never received any gifts which could work as bribes from territorial lords and hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) who had an axe to grind when he first came to the western citadel of Edo-jo Castle after he was adopted by Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienobu never received any gifts which could work as bribes from territorial lords and hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) who had an axe to grind when he first came to the western citadel of Edo-jo Castle after he was adopted by Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>後に将軍になると、人事を一新して、不正を厳しく取り締まったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed that he reshuffled bakufu personnel and strictly cracked down on wrongdoings after he took over the position of the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also believed that he reshuffled bakufu personnel and strictly cracked down on wrongdoings after he took over the position of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also believed that he reshuffled bakufu personnel and strictly cracked down on wrongdoings after he took over the position of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>将軍になると、新井のほかに室鳩巣ら多くの学者を招聘し、人材の登用に尽力したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he made tremendous efforts in appointing useful staff members when he became the shogun, bringing ARAI, Kyuso MURO and many other scholars into the administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he made tremendous efforts in appointing useful staff members when he became the shogun, bringing ARAI, Kyuso MURO and many other scholars into the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he made tremendous efforts in appointing useful staff members when he became the shogun, bringing Arai, Kyuso MURO and many other scholars into the administration.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>人気のなかった「生類憐みの令」を廃止するなどして、幕政改革に熱心だったことから、歴代将軍の中でも名君と評されていて、在位3年で死去したのを惜しむ声が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is described as the wise ruler among the successive shoguns, as he came up with various measures to reform the bakufu, including discontinuing the unpopular law prohibiting cruelty to animals, and there are many voices that say it was such a loss that he died only three years after taking office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is described as the wise ruler among the successive shoguns, as he came up with various measures to reform the bakufu, including discontinuing the unpopular law prohibiting cruelty to animals, and there are many voices that say it was such a loss that he died only three years after taking office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is described as the wise ruler among the successive shoguns, as he came up with various measures to reform the bakufu, including discontinuing the unpopular law prohibiting cruelty to animals, and there are many voices that say it was such a loss that he died only three years after taking office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>『徳川実紀』では、「仁慈の心あり」と評されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Tokugawa jikki&quot; (the True TOKUGAWA Records), he is described as having &quot;the heart of mercy and compassion.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Tokugawa jikki&quot; (the True TOKUGAWA Records), he is described as having &quot;a heart of mercy and compassion.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Tokugawa jikki&quot; (the True Tokugawa Records), he is described as having &apos;a heart of mercy and compassion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>5代将軍・綱吉は「生類憐みの令」を厳守することを遺言したが、家宣は葬儀の2日前に綱吉の柩の前で、側用人の柳沢吉保に対し次のように言ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi, the fifth shogun, said in his last testament to strictly observe the law prohibiting cruelty to animals, but Ienobu, two days before the funeral of Tsunayoshi, apparently told lord chamberlain Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA in front of the coffin of Tsunayoshi as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi, the fifth shogun, said in his last testament to strictly observe the law prohibiting cruelty to animals, but Ienobu, two days before the funeral of Tsunayoshi, apparently said the following to lord chamberlain Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA in front of the coffin of Tsunayoshi:</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi, the fifth shogun, said in his last testament to strictly observe the law prohibiting cruelty to animals, but Ienobu, two days before the funeral of Tsunayoshi, apparently said the following to lord chamberlain Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA in front of the coffin of Tsunayoshi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「生類憐みの禁令に触れ、罪に落ちた者は数知れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;There are so many people who violated the law prohibiting cruelty to animals and were accused of the crime.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;There are so many people who violated the law prohibiting cruelty to animals and were accused of the crime.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are so many people who violated the law prohibiting cruelty to animals and were accused of the crime.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>私は天下万民のために、あえて遺命に背くこととする」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I dare to disobey his will for the common people.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I dare to disobey his will for the common people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I dare to disobey his will for the common people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この時、罪を許された者は八千数百人にも上ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, there were apparently more than 8,000 people whose accusations were dropped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, there were apparently more than 8,000 people whose accusations were dropped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, there were apparently more than 8,000 people whose accusations were dropped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>家宣が死の床についたとき、側用人の間部詮房を通じ、新井に将軍継嗣について家宣は以下のように相談したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that when Ienobu was on his deathbed, he consulted ARAI through lord chamberlain Akifusa MANABE about the next shogun as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that when Ienobu was on his deathbed, he consulted ARAI through lord chamberlain Akifusa MANABE about the next shogun as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that when Ienobu was on his deathbed, he consulted Arai through lord chamberlain Akifusa MANABE about the next shogun as follows:</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>鍋松（家継）は幼く、古来幼主の時に世が平穏であったためしが少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nabematsu (Ietsugu) is still young, and from ancient times, the world was hardly at peace when a young leader reigned.&quot;</e>
<cmt>家宣の言葉として、引用句にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nabematsu (Ietsugu) is still young, and from ancient times, the world has hardly been at peace when a young leader reigned.&quot;</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nabematsu (Ietsugu) is still young, and from ancient times, the world has hardly been at peace when a young leader reigned.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、天下の事は私すべきものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;And one should not dominate politics as he wishes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;And one should not dominate politics as he wishes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;And one should not dominate politics as he wishes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>東照宮（家康）が御三家を立てられたのはこのような時のためであるから、自分の後は尾張殿に譲り、鍋松が成人した折には尾張殿の心に任せた方が良いか、あるいは鍋松が成人するまで尾張殿には西丸にいて政治を執ってもらい、不幸にして鍋松が死んだ場合に尾張殿に将軍家を継いでもらった方が良いか、この2案のうちどちらが良いか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Which one of the two plans do you think is better: I should relinquish the shogun&apos;s post for Owari dono and let him decide what to do when Nabematsu reaches adulthood because Tosho-gu (Ieyasu) established the three privileged branches specifically for this kind of situation, or; I should ask Owari dono to stay in the western citadel until Nabematsu reaches adulthood to administer the bakufu and ask him to take over the shogun family in case Nabematsu dies by misfortune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「尾張殿」が誰を指しているのか原文で指定していないため、そのまま「Owari dono」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Which one of the two plans do you think is better: I should relinquish the shogun&apos;s post for Owari dono and let him decide what to do when Nabematsu reaches adulthood because Tosho-gu (Ieyasu) established the three privileged branches specifically for this kind of situation, or; I should ask Owari dono to stay in the western citadel until Nabematsu reaches adulthood to administer the bakufu and ask him to take over the shogun family in case Nabematsu dies by misfortune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Which one of the two plans do you think is better: I should relinquish the shogun&apos;s post for Owari dono and let him decide what to do when Nabematsu reaches adulthood because Tosho-gu (Ieyasu) established the three privileged branches specifically for this kind of situation, or; I should ask Owari dono to stay in the western citadel until Nabematsu reaches adulthood to administer the bakufu and ask him to take over the shogun family in case Nabematsu dies by misfortune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これに対して、白石は2案とも反対し、鍋松を継嗣として譜代の者がこれを補佐することを進言したので、家宣もその案を受け入れ、間もなく息を引き取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Hakuseki was opposed to both plans and advised him to name Nabematsu as heir and order fudai (hereditary vassals) to support him, and Ienobu acknowledged the plan and soon breathed his last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Hakuseki was opposed to both plans and advised him to name Nabematsu the heir and order fudai (hereditary vassals) to support him, and Ienobu acknowledged the plan and soon after breathed his last.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Hakuseki was opposed to both plans and advised him to name Nabematsu the heir and order fudai (hereditary vassals) to support him, and Ienobu acknowledged the plan and soon after breathed his last.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>寛文10年7月9日 (旧暦)（1670年8月24日）、松平虎松を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called himself Toramatsu MATSUDAIRA on August 24, 1670.</e>
<cmt>「虎松」の読みが確認できなかったので、「とらまつ」としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Toramatsu MATSUDAIRA on August 24, 1670.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Toramatsu MATSUDAIRA on August 24, 1670.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>それ以前は、新見左近と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that, he was known as Sakon SHINMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that, he was known as Sakon SHINMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that, he was known as Sakon SHINMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>延宝4年12月12日 (旧暦)（1677年1月15日）、従三位に叙し、左近衛権中将に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 15, he was commissioned with the jusani (junior third rank) and appointed as Sakone gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 15, he was commissioned with the jusani (junior third rank) and appointed Sakone gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>omited &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 15, 1677, he was commissioned with the Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed Sakone gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>左近衛将監を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He concurrently held the position of Sakone no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He concurrently held the position of Sakone no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He concurrently held the position of Sakone no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>同日元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was celebrated his attainment of adulthood the same day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was celebrated his attainment of adulthood the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was celebrated his attainment of adulthood the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>伯父である将軍・家綱の1字を賜り、綱豊と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went by the name of Tsunatoyo after being granted to use a portion of the real name of his uncle Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went by the name of Tsunatoyo after being granted permission to use a portion of the real name of his uncle Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;permission&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went by the name of Tsunatoyo after being granted permission to use a portion of the real name of his uncle Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="51">
<j>延宝6年10月25日 (旧暦)（1678年12月8日）、甲斐国府中城主襲封</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 8, 1678, he was appointed as castellan of Fuchu, Kai Province, and was granted to inherit the territory.</e>
<cmt>「甲斐国府中城主襲封」の意味が確認できなかったので、甲斐の国の城主に任命され、領地を相続した、という理解で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 8, 1678, he was appointed castellan of Fuchu, Kai Province, and was granted inheritance the territory.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 8, 1678, he was appointed castellan of Fuchu, Kai Province, and was granted inheritance the territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>延宝8年8月18日 (旧暦)（1680年9月10日）、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 10, 1680, he was appointed to sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 10, 1680, he was appointed sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 10, 1680, he was appointed sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>9月6日 (旧暦)（10月28日）、正三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 28 the same year, he was promoted to shosanmi (senior third rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 28 the same year, he was promoted to shosanmi (senior third rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 28 the same year, he was promoted to shosanmi (senior third rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>参議如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He remained in the position of sangi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He remained in the position of sangi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He remained in the position of sangi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="55">
<j>元禄3年12月15日 (旧暦)（1691年1月13日）、権中納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13, 1691, he was transferred as gon chunagon (provisional middle councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13, 1691, he was transferred as gon chunagon (provisional middle councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 13, 1691, he was transferred as gon chunagon (provisional middle councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="56">
<j>宝永元年12月5日 (旧暦)（1704年12月31日）、将軍後継者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 31, 1704, he was named as heir to succeed the position of shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 31, 1704, he was named heir to succeed the position of shogun.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 31, 1704, he was named heir to succeed the position of shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="57">
<j>宝永2年3月5日 (旧暦)（1705年3月29日）、従二位に昇叙し、権大納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 29, 1705, he was promoted to the position of junii (junior second rank) and was transferred to the position of go dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 29, 1705, he was promoted to the position of junii (junior second rank) and was transferred to the position of go dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 29, 1705, he was promoted to the position of junii (junior second rank) and was transferred to the position of go dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>家宣と名を改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then changed his name to Ienobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then changed his name to Ienobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then changed his name to Ienobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="59">
<j>宝永6年5月1日 (旧暦)（1709年6月8日）、正二位に昇叙し、内大臣に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 8, 1709, he was promoted to the position of shonii (senior second rank) and was transferred to the position of naidaijin (minister of the interior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 8, 1709, he was promoted to the position of shonii (senior second rank) and was transferred to the position of naidaijin (minister of the interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 8, 1709, he was promoted to the position of shonii (senior second rank) and was transferred to the position of naidaijin (minister of the interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>右近衛大将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He concurrently held the position of Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He concurrently held the position of Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He concurrently held the position of Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>併せて征夷大将軍・源氏長者宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he was named seii taishogun and GENJI no choja (chief of the MINAMOTO clan) under the imperial proclamation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he was named seii taishogun and GENJI no choja (chief of the MINAMOTO clan) under an imperial proclamation.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he was named seii taishogun and Genji no choja (chief of the Minamoto clan) under an imperial proclamation.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="62">
<j>正徳 (日本)2年10月14日 (旧暦)（1712年1月15日）、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on January 15, 1712.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on January 15, 1712.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on January 15, 1712.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>11月3日 (旧暦)（12月1日）、贈正一位太政大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 1 the same year, he was posthumously conferred the title of zo shoichii dajo daijin (senior first rank-grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>死去したのと同じ年という理解で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 1 the same year, he was posthumously conferred the title of zo shoichii dajo daijin (senior first rank-grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 1 the same year, he was posthumously conferred the title of zo shoichii dajo daijin (senior first rank-grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="64">
<j>※近衛府の次官たる中将と同府の判官たる将監を兼任するのは珍しい様相である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rare for someone to concurrently hold the position of chujo (middle captain), who served as suke (assistant director) of the Konoefu (the headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), and shogen, (lieutenant), who also served as hangan (inspector) of the Konoefu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is rare for someone to concurrently hold the position of chujo (middle captain), who served as suke (assistant director) of the Konoefu (the headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), and shogen, (lieutenant), who also served as hangan (inspector) of the Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is rare for someone to concurrently hold the position of chujo (middle captain), who served as suke (assistant director) of the Konoefu (the headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), and shogen, (lieutenant), who also served as hangan (inspector) of the Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>家宣の容姿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appearance of Ienobu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appearance of Ienobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appearance of Ienobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>家宣の埋葬された増上寺で徳川将軍家の墓地が改葬された際に、これに立ち会い被葬者の遺骨の調査を担当した鈴木尚の著書『骨は語る 徳川将軍・大名家の人びと』によると、家宣は細面で鼻筋が通っていて穏やかな顔立ちをした美男であったといい、父・綱重とは猫背であったこと以外に似ている部分は非常に少なかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hone ha kataru: TOKUGAWA Shogun Daimyoke no hitobito&quot; (Bones talk: the people of TOKUGAWA shogun and daimyo families) by Hisashi SUZUKI, who observed the refurbishment of TOKUGAWA shogun family&apos;s grave site at Zojo-ji Temple where Ienobu was also buried and who was also in charge of inspecting the remains, Ienobu was apparently a soft-looking, lean-faced handsome man with a shapely nose and he shared very few resemblances with his father Tsunashige except for the fact that he was round-shouldered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hone ha kataru: TOKUGAWA Shogun Daimyoke no hitobito&quot; (Bones talk: the people of TOKUGAWA shogun and daimyo families) by Hisashi SUZUKI, who observed the refurbishment of the TOKUGAWA shogun family&apos;s grave site at Zojo-ji Temple where Ienobu was also buried and who was also in charge of inspecting the remains, Ienobu was apparently a soft-looking, lean-faced handsome man with a shapely nose and he shared very little resemblance with his father Tsunashige except for the fact that he was round-shouldered.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hone ha kataru: Tokugawa Shogun Daimyoke no hitobito&quot; (Bones talk: the people of Tokugawa shogun and daimyo families) by Hisashi SUZUKI, who observed the refurbishment of the Tokugawa shogun family&apos;s grave site at Zojo-ji Temple where Ienobu was also buried and who was also in charge of inspecting the remains, Ienobu was apparently a soft-looking, lean-faced handsome man with a shapely nose and he shared very little resemblance with his father Tsunashige except for the fact that he was round-shouldered.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また、鈴木が中心となって編纂した『増上寺徳川将軍墓とその遺品・遺体』によれば、家宣のABO式血液型は曽祖父の第2代将軍・秀忠、及び父・綱重と同じくABO式血液型であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And according to &quot;Zojo-ji TOKUGAWA Shogunbo to sono Ishin Itai&quot; (The TOKUGAWA shogun family&apos;s graveyard at Zojo-ji Temple and the mementos and remains), which was mainly compiled by SUZUKI, Ienobu&apos;s blood type was ABO, same as his great-grandfather Hidetada, who served as the second shogun, and Tsunashige.</e>
<cmt>「ABO式血液型」では意味がよく分かりません。ウィキペディアの元記事によればO型ですが、ここではあくまで原文に沿って「ABO」のままにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And according to &quot;Zojo-ji TOKUGAWA Shogunbo to sono Ishin Itai&quot; (The TOKUGAWA shogun family&apos;s graveyard at Zojo-ji Temple and the mementos and remains), which was mainly compiled by SUZUKI, Ienobu&apos;s blood type was ABO, the same as his great-grandfather Hidetada, who served as the second shogun, and Tsunashige.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And according to &quot;Zojo-ji Tokugawa Shogunbo to sono Ihin Itai&quot; (The Tokugawa shogun family&apos;s graveyard at Zojo-ji Temple and the mementos and remains), which was mainly compiled by Suzuki, Ienobu&apos;s blood type was ABO, the same as his great-grandfather Hidetada, who served as the second shogun, and his father Tsunashige.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>遺骨によると、家宣の身長は当時の日本人としては平均よりやや高い160.0センチメートルである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His remains shows that Ienobu was 160 cm tall, meaning that he was slightly taller than average Japanese male at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His remains show that Ienobu was 160 cm tall, meaning that he was slightly taller than the average Japanese male at the time.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His remains show that Ienobu was 160 cm tall, meaning that he was slightly taller than the average Japanese male at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>現在までに判明しているところでは、歴代将軍の中で最も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From what is known to date, he was the tallest man among the successive shoguns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From what is known to date, he was the tallest man among the successive shoguns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From what is known to date, he was the tallest man among the successive shoguns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), BOTarate(id:185620), ドルチェット(id:46458), Nnh(id:474), Reggaeman(id:6214), Lupinoid(id:68), Doskoi 8(id:1070), Rai koku(id:1661), Kamakura(id:472), Tribot(id:186681), Roga246(id:53246), Yogy(id:36183), Alex K(id:86829), Hhst(id:13720), DNCAL(id:120593), でここ(id:9565), Tsk(id:1153), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Goki(id:7107), Loveless(id:129239), Chobot(id:20846), Point136(id:211299), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Yas(id:739), FlaBot(id:30804), Kzhr(id:131), YOUJI(id:172173), LERK(id:4460), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Sorrysorry(id:102591), 前図書頭(id:134750), Sanmari(id:1707), MDR-SK(id:192066), トホホ川(id:50502), Suisui(id:69), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>