<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小堀政一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masakazu KOBORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masakazu KOBORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masakazu KOBORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小堀 政一（こぼり まさかず）は、江戸時代前期の近江小室藩藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masakazu KOBORI was the lord of the Komuro Domain in Omi who lived in the beginning of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masakazu KOBORI was the lord of the Komuro Domain in Omi at the beginning of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masakazu KOBORI was the lord of the Komuro Domain in Omi at the beginning of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>茶道、建築家、作庭家としても有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous for sado (tea ceremony) and as an architect and a landscape gardener.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was famous for sado (tea ceremony) and as an architect and a landscape gardener.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also famous as an expert on sado (Japanese tea ceremony), an architect and a landscape gardener.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>遠江国守に任じられた事から、一般には小堀遠州（こぼりえんしゅう）の名称で知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of beiing appointed to the position of Governer of Totomi-nokuni (Totomi Province), he is generally known by the name Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of beiing appointed to the position of Governer of Totomi-nokuni (Totomi Province), he is generally known by the name Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of being appointed to the position as Governor of Totoumi Province (current day Shizuoka Prefecture), he is generally known by the name, Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたProvince(current→Province (current</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名を作助、元服後、初めは正一、後に政一と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Sakusuke and, after his genpuku (celebrating one&apos;s coming of age), he used the name Masakazu (正一) at first, and later Masakazu (政一).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Sakusuke and, after his genpuku (coming of age), he intitally used the name Masakazu (正一), and later Masakazu (政一).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Sakusuke and after genpuku (coming of age), he initially used the name Masakazu (正一) and later, Masakazu (政一).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>道号は大有宗甫、庵号は孤篷庵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His dogo (a pseudonym as a priest) was Daiyu Soho [大有宗甫 正しい読み不明], and ango (a name (temple name, pen name) ending with the character an) was Kohoan [孤篷庵 正しい読み不明].</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His dogo (priest name) was Daiyu Soho [大有宗甫 正しい読み不明], and ango (temple name/pen name ending with the character an) was Kohoan [孤篷庵 正しい読み不明].</e>
<cmt>A pseudonym is a &quot;false name&quot;, not what is meant here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His dogo (priest name) was Taiyu Soho, and ango (temple name or pen name ending with the character an) was Kohoan.</e>
<cmt>大有宗甫→Taiyu Soho[http://med.honnet.co.jp/metro/oumi/oumi_26.htm]孤篷庵→Kohoan [http://www.kyototsuu.jp/Temple/KohouAn.html]/→or</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>正室は藤堂高虎の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legitimate wife was a daughter of Takatora TODO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was a daughter of Takatora TODO.</e>
<cmt>His &quot;wife&quot; is by definition &quot;legitimate&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wife was the daughter of Takatora TODO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に小堀正之、娘（池田重政室）らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had children including Masayuki KOBORI and a daughter (Shigemasa IKEDA&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Masayuki KOBORI and a daughter (Shigemasa IKEDA&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children include Masayuki KOBORI and a daughter (Shigemasa IKEDA&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt>FBでは△になっているが、どこが修正されたのか不明。文字化け＃部分の修正のみと思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>天正7年（1579年）、小堀正次の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1579, he was born as a child of Masatsugu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1579, he was born as a child of Masatsugu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1579 and his father was Masatsugu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幼名は作助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Sakusuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Sakusuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Sakusuke during his childhood.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>父・正次はもともと近江国坂田郡小堀村（現・滋賀県長浜市）の土豪で、浅井長政の家臣であり縁戚でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Masatsugu, was originally a powerful local clan in Kobori-mura, Sakata-gori in Omi Province (present, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture) and he was a retainer and a relative of Nagamasa ASAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Masatsugu came from a powerful local clan in Kobori-mura, Sakata-gori in Omi Province (present-day, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture) and was a retainer and relative of Nagamasa ASAI.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Masatsugu, came from a powerful local clan in Kobori-mura, Sakata-gori in Omi Province (present-day Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture) and was a retainer and relative of Nagamasa ASAI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし政一が生まれたのは、浅井氏が織田信長により滅亡し、正次が長浜城 (近江国)主豊臣秀吉に取り立てられ、秀吉の弟豊臣秀長に仕えていた頃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Masakazu was born, after the Asai clan was annihilated by Nobunaga ODA, when Masatsugu was given patronage of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was the lord of the Nagahama-jo Castle (Omi Province) and he was serving Hideyoshi&apos;s younger brother, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Masakazu was born after the Asai clan had been annihilated by Nobunaga ODA and Masatsugu, under the patronage of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was the lord of the Nagahama-jo Castle (Omi Province), was serving Hideyoshi&apos;s younger brother, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Masakazu was born after the Asai clan had been annihilated by Nobunaga ODA and Masatsugu was serving Hideyoshi&apos;s younger brother, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI after being recognized by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was the lord of Nagahama-jo Castle (Omi Province).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天正13年（1585年）、秀長は郡山城 (大和国)に移封され、正次は秀長の家老となり、政一もともに郡山に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, Hidenaga was transferred to the Koriyama-jo Castle (Yamato Province) and Masatsugu became Hidenaga&apos;s karo (chief retainer) and moved to Koriyama together with Masakazu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, when Hidenaga was transferred to Koriyama-jo Castle (Yamato Province), Masatsugu became Hidenaga&apos;s karo (chief retainer) and moved to Koriyama taking Masakazu with him.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, when Hidenaga was transferred to Koriyama-jo Castle (Yamato Province, present-day Nara Prefecture), Masatsugu became Hidenaga&apos;s karo (chief retainer) and moved to Koriyama, taking Masakazu with him.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>この頃秀長は山上宗二を招き千利休にも師事しており、郡山は京・堺・奈良と並んで茶の湯の盛んな土地となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, Hidenaga invited Soji YAMANOUE and studied under SEN no Rikyu, and therefore, Koriyama had become a place where chanoyu (tea ceremony) was popular same as in Kyo, Sakai and Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, Hidenaga invited Soji YAMANOUE to Yamato and studied under SEN no Rikyu, with the result that chanoyu (tea ceremony) became popular in Koriyama in same way as in Kyo, Sakai and Nara.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, Hidenaga invited Soji YAMANOUE and also studied under SEN no Rikyu.As a result, chanoyu (Japanese tea ceremony) in Koriyama became as poplar as it was in Kyoto, Sakai and Nara.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>小姓だった政一は、秀吉への給仕を務め利休とも出会っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masakazu, who was a page, waited on Hideyoshi and met Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masakazu, who was a page, waited on Hideyoshi and met Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masakazu, who was a page, waited on Hideyoshi and met Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、父の勧めもあって大徳寺の春屋宗園に参禅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Partly because of his father&apos;s recommendation, he practiced Zen meditation under Shunoku Soen of the Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Partly because of his father&apos;s recommendation, he practiced Zen meditation under Shunoku Soen of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;the&quot; from before the temple name.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following his father&apos;s recommendation, he practiced Zen meditation under Shunoku Soen of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>秀長の死後を嗣いだ豊臣秀保もまもなく没したため、文禄4年（1595年）に秀吉直参となって伏見に移ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hidenaga&apos;s death, as Hidenaga&apos;s successor, Hideyasu TOYOTOMI, also died soon, he became a immediate retainer of Hideyoshi in 1595 and moved to Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Hidenaga&apos;s death, his heir Hideyasu TOYOTOMI also died, and so Masatsugu and Masakazu became a immediate retainer of Hideyoshi in 1595 and moved to Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>Natural English. Also later sentences suggest that both Masatsugu and Masakazu became immediate retainers.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Hidenaga&apos;s death, his heir Hideyasu TOYOTOMI also died and Masatsugu became a direct retainer of Hideyoshi in 1595 and moved to Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>ここで政一は古田重然に茶道を学ぶことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this place, Masakazu learned sado under Shigenari FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, Masakazu learned sado under Shigenari FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, Masakazu learned sado under Shigenari FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>FBでは△になっているが、どこが修正されたのか不明。文字化け＃部分の修正のみと思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）秀吉が没すると、正次・政一は徳川家康に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died in 1598, Masatsugu and Masakazu served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi died in 1598, Masatsugu and Masakazu served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died in 1598, Masatsugu and Masakazu served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBでは△になっているが、どこが修正されたのか不明。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>正次は関ヶ原の戦いでの功により松山城 (備中国)を賜り、備中国代官として松山（現・岡山県高梁市）に赴く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of his exploits in the Battle of Sekigahara, Masatsugu was given the Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province) and moved to Matsuyama (present Takahari City, Okayama Prefecture) as the local governor of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of his exploits in the Battle of Sekigahara, Masatsugu was given Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province) and moved to Matsuyama (present Takahari City, Okayama Prefecture) as the local governor of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;the&quot; from before castle name.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsugu was recognized for his exploits in the Battle of Sekigahara and given Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province), after which he moved to Matsuyama (present-day Takahari City, Okayama Prefecture) as the local governor of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>慶長9年（1604年）の父の死後、政一はその遺領1万2,460石を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death in 1604, Masakazu inherited his father&apos;s former territory for 12,460 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his father&apos;s death in 1604, Masakazu inherited his father&apos;s former territory which had a yield of 12,460 koku.</e>
<cmt>I think 領1万2,460石 means &quot;territory with a yield of 12460 koku.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon his father&apos;s death in 1604, Masakazu inherited his father&apos;s territory of 12,460 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>慶長13年（1608年）には駿府城普請奉行となり、修築の功により従五位遠江国に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1608, he assumed the position of the fushinbugyo (shogunate administrator for civil engineering and construction) for the Sunpu-jo Castle and for his exploits in completing the work, he was conferred Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed to Totomi no kami (governor of Totomi Province).</e>
<cmt>「遠江国」は「遠江守」の誤りであり、そのままでは文章が意味をなさないため、そのように訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1608, he assumed the position of fushinbugyo (shogunate administrator for civil engineering and construction) for Sunpu-jo Castle and, on successfully completing the work, was promoted to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed as governer of Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>Removed unnecessary &quot;the&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1608, he assumed the position of Fushinbugyo (shogunate administrator for civil engineering and construction) for Sunpu-jo Castle (present-day Shizuoka).When he successfully completed the work, he was promoted to the position of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed as governor of Totoumi Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>以後この官名により通称・小堀遠州と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, because of this official post, he was called with a popular name, Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of holding this official post, he came to be known as Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of holding this official post, he was called Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>居所としては、正次の頃から伏見六地蔵の屋敷があったが、六角越後町（三条）にも後陽成天皇御所造営に際して藤堂高虎から譲られた屋敷があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to their residence, there was a residence in Fushimi Rokujizo already in Masatsugu&apos;s time, and there was also a residence in Rokkaku Echigomachi (Sanjo) that was transferred from Takatora TODO on the occasion of building the Imperial Palace for the Emperor Goyozei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The KOBARI familty had a residence in Fushimi Rokujizo from the time of Masatsugu, and received a further residence in Rokkaku Echigomachi (Sanjo) from Takatora TODO around the time that the Imperial Palace was built for the Emperor Goyozei.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobori family had a residence in Fushimi Rokujizo from the time of Masatsugu and also had one in Rokkaku Echigomachi (Sanjo) that was gifted from Takatora TODO when an imperial residence was built for Emperor Goyozei.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また元和 (日本)3年（1617年）に河内国奉行を兼任となり、大坂天満南木幡町に役宅を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1617, he also assumed the position of bugyo (magistrate) of Kawachi Province and an official residence was given to him in Temma Minamikobata-machi in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1617, Masakazu also assumed the position of bugyo (magistrate) of Kawachi Province and was given an official residence in Temma Minamikobata-machi in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1617, Masakazu also assumed the position of Bugyo (magistrate) of Kawachi Province (present-day Osaka Prefecture) and was given an official residence in Temma Minamikobata-machi in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>元和5年（1619年）9月、近江小室藩に移封され、さらに元和8年（1622年）8月に近江国奉行に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1619, he was transferred to Komuro Domain in Omi and, in August 1622, he was appointed to bugyo of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1619, he was transferred to Komuro Domain in Omi Province and, in August 1622, was appointed as bugyo of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>Used &quot;Omi Province&quot; throughout for consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1619, he transferred to Komuro Domain in Omi Province (present-day Shiga Prefecture) and was appointed as Bugyo of Omi Province in August 1622.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ここに陣屋を整備し茶室も設けたが、政一はほとんど使わなかったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he fitted out jinya (regional government office) and provided a tea house also, it is considered that Masakazu hardly used them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Komuro, he fitted out the jinya (regional government office) and built a tea house, but it is considered likely that he hardly used them.</e>
<cmt>It is clear from the context that &quot;he&quot; is &quot;Masakazu&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Komuro, he fitted out a Jinya (regional government office) and built a tea house, but it is considered that he rarely used them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>元和9年（1623年）12月にさらに遠国奉行に任ぜられ、豊後橋（現：観月橋）北詰にあたる新たに奉行屋敷を設け、その後ほとんどここを役宅として暮らしたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was because that, in December 1623, he was also appointed to an ongoku-bugyo (the collective name of the magistrates placed at important areas directly controlled by the government in the Edo period) and he prepared a new residence for bugyo in Bungo-bashi (present Kangetsukyo) Kitazume and, since then, he lived almost fully in this residence using it as the official residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because, when in 1623 he was further appointed as an ongoku-bugyo (name for magistrates placed in important areas directly controlled by the government in the Edo period), he prepared a new official residence in Bungo-bashi (present-day Kangetsukyo) Kitazume and subsequently spent most of his time there.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because he was further appointed as Ongoku-bugyo (name for magistrates placed in important areas directly controlled by the government in the Edo period) in 1623 and subsequently spent most of his time at the new official residence he established in Bungo-bashi bridge (present-day Kangetsukyo) Kitazume (north side).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>晩年になり、真偽は不明であるが、公金一万両を流用したとする嫌疑がかかったが、酒井忠勝 (若狭国小浜藩主)・井伊直孝・細川忠興らの口添えにより不問とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, he was suspected of diversion of public funds of ten thousand ryo although authenticity is uncertain, but it was withdrawing from consideration thanks to good offices by Tadakatsu SAKAI (lord of Obama Domain in Wakasa Province), Naotaka II and Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years Masakazu, with or without foundation, came under suspicion of misusing ten thousand ryo of public funds, but the matter was dropped after the helpful intervention of Tadakatsu SAKAI (lord of Obama Domain in Wakasa Province), Naotaka II and Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although not confirmed whether true or not, Masakazu came under suspicion of misusing ten thousand ryo of public funds in his later years, but the matter was dropped after the helpful intervention of Tadakatsu SAKAI (lord of Obama Domain in Wakasa Province), Naotaka II and Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その後も伏見奉行を務めながら茶道三昧に過ごし、正保4年（1647年）2月6日、伏見奉行屋敷で69歳の生涯を閉じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, while he worked as Fushimi bugyo, he spent days absorbed in sado, and died in the residence of Fushimi bugyo on February 6, 1647 at the age of sixty-nine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he continued to work as in the role of bugyo, devoting himself to sado before dying in the Fushimi residence on February 6, 1647 at the age of sixty-nine.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he continued to work as in the role of Bugyo, devoting himself to sado before dying at the Fushimi residence on February 6, 1647 at the age of sixty-nine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>子孫は松平定信により、天明8年（1788年）改易の憂き目に逢っているが、旗本としては家名は存続された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendant was punished by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, but the family name as hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun) remained to exist.</e>
<cmt>旗本としての家名が存続すれば「改易 (士分剥奪および所領の没収)」には該当せず、「改易」を本来の意味に応じて訳した場合、意味不明の文章になってしますため、「改易= punishment」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masakazu&apos;s descendant suffered in the reforms of 1788 by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, but the family name continued to exist as hatamoto (direct vassals of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>I think it is the reforms of 1788 which are being referred here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masakazu&apos;s descendant suffered in the reforms of 1788 by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, but the family name continued to exist as a Hatamoto (direct vassals of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>公儀作事に関する主な業績としては、松山城 (備中国)の再建、駿府城修築、名古屋城天守、後陽成天皇御所造営等の作業奉行をはじめ、宮中や幕府関係の作事奉行があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His main achievements with respect to construction for the shogunate were management of works for reconstruction of the Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province), repair work for the Sunpu-jo Castle, construction of the tenshu (main keep or tower of a castle) of the Nagoya-jo Castle, construction of the Imperial Palace for the Emperor Goyozei, etc and management of other works for the imperial court and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His achievements in the field of construction for the shogunate included reconstruction of Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province), repairs to Sunpu-jo Castle, construction of the tenshu (main keep or tower) of Nagoya-jo Castle, construction of the Imperial Palace for the Emperor Goyozei, etc and management of other works for the imperial court and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His achievements in the field of construction for the shogunate include the reconstruction of Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province), repairs to Sunpu-jo Castle, construction of the Tenshu (main keep or tower) of Nagoya-jo Castle, construction of an imperial residence for Emperor Goyozei and other construction work for the imperial court and the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>宮中造営の業績のほかに、江戸城内や品川東海寺 (品川区)（徳川氏の菩提寺兼別荘）、征夷大将軍上洛の際の休泊所である水口城（滋賀県甲賀市水口町）、伊庭御茶屋（滋賀県東近江市能登川町）、大坂城内御茶屋などが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than work for the Imperial Court, his known achievements include the interior of Edo-jo Castle and the construction of Tokai-ji Temple in Shinagawa (a family temple and villa for the Tokugawa family in Shinagawa Ward), Minakuchi-jo Castle to accommodate the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) on his way to Kyoto (Minakuchimachi, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture), Iba Ochaya (Notogawacho, Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture), and ochaya in Osaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than work for the Imperial Court, his known achievements include the interior of Edo-jo Castle and the construction of Tokai-ji Temple in Shinagawa (a family temple and villa for the Tokugawa family in Shinagawa Ward), Minakuchi-jo Castle to accommodate the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) on his way to Kyoto (Minakuchimachi, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture), Iba Ochaya (Notogawacho, Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture), and ochaya in Osaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>Explanation of &quot;ochaya&quot; is required.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the work for the Imperial Court, he is known to have worked on the interior of Edo-jo Castle and the construction of Tokai-ji Temple in Shinagawa (a family temple and villa for the Tokugawa family in Shinagawa Ward), Minakuchi-jo Castle to accommodate the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) on his way to Kyoto (Minakuchimachi, Koga City, Shiga Prefecture), Iba Ochaya (rest house) (Notogawa-cho, Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture), and the ochaya within Osaka-jo Castle grounds.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また京都の寺では、将軍の側近者崇伝長老の住坊である南禅寺金地院内東照宮や御祈祷殿（方丈）側の富貴の間、茶室および庭園、同寺本坊の方丈庭園など、準公儀の作事に参画している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to temples in Kyoto, he was involved in construction works related to some extent to the shogunate such as Toshogu in Konchi-in subtemple of the Nanzen-ji Temple, which was the priests lodge for Suden Choro, who was a close advisor of the shogun, fukinoma, tea house and garden on the Gokito-den (Hall for prayer) (hojo (an abbot&apos;s chamber)) side, and hojo teien (garden) of the honbo (a priest&apos;s main living quarter) of the temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, he was involved in construction work that related in some way to the shogunate, such as Toshogu (in Konchi-in subtemple of the Nanzen-ji Temple), a lodge for Suden Choro, a priest who was a close advisor of the shogun, and in the same temple, a hall, tea house and garden on the hojo (abbot&apos;s chamber) side of Gokito-den (Hall for prayer) and the hojo teien (garden) of the honbo (priests&apos; main living quarters).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the temples in Kyoto, he participated in semi-official construction work such as Toshogu, located at Konchi-in of the Nanzen-ji Temple, which was a lodge for Suden Choro, a priest who was a close advisor of the shogun.He also worked on the Hall of Huki (rich and noble), located on the hojo (abbot&apos;s chamber side) of the Gokito-den (Hall for Prayer), the tea house and garden and the Hojo garden of the honbo (priests&apos; main living quarters) of this temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>彼の書状の文面から推察できる様に、彼は江戸にある幕府からの愛顧を気にしていた関係から、公儀の作事（幕府の対皇室政策）以外は公家への出入りは極力避けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As we can surmise from the text of this letter, because he avoided to have relationship with nobles as much as possible other than sakuji (construction work) of the shogunate (policy of the bakufu toward the imperial family, because he was nervous about patronage by the bakufu in Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As we can surmise from his letters, he was nervous about his patronage from the shogunate in Edo, and went to great lengths to avoid getting involved with noble familes in any capacity other than in his role in shoguate construction.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As we can surmise from his letters, he was nervous about his patronage from the shogunate in Edo, and went to great lengths to avoid getting involved with noble families in any capacity other than in his role in shoguate construction.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>師古田重然のような非業の死を避けるためとも思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is surmised that it was for the purpose of avoiding unnatural death similar to that for his teacher, Shigenari FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible that he was being careful in order to avoid the unnatural death which had befallen his teacher, Shigenari FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible that he was being careful in order to avoid the unnatural death which had befallen his teacher, Shigenari FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>彼が奉行として参画したと思われる遺構は、建築としては妙心寺麟祥院の春日のつぼね霊屋（慶長年間、うち溜りを移建）、氷室神社拝殿（慶長年間、内裏池亭を移建）、大覚寺宸殿（慶長年間の内裏の元和期増造の際に中宮宸殿となる）、金地院東照宮、同茶室、同方丈南庭（鶴亀庭）、南禅寺本坊方丈南庭、大徳寺竜光院密庵席（みったんせき）、孤篷庵表門前の石橋、同前庭、同忘筌席露地（建築は寛政年間に焼失後、旧様式を踏襲して復元された）、仙洞御所南池庭のいで島およびその東護岸の石積み部分などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structural remnants which we believe he was involved in are, as construction, are the tamaya (a mausoleum) for Kasuga no Tsubone (in Keicho era (1596 - 1615, partly, the waiting room was relocated.), haiden (a hall of worship) of the Himuro-jinja Shrine (in Keicho era (1596 - 1615), dairi chitei [内裏池亭 読み,英語表記とも不明] was relocated.), Shinden of the Daikaku-ji Temple (changed to Chugu Shinden on the occasion of expansion in Genna era (1615 - 1617) of the dairi (Imperial Palace) constructed in Keicho era), Tosho-gu of the Konchi-in, tea house of the same, south garden of the hojo (an abbot&apos;s chamber) of the same (Tsuru-Kame garden (literally, crane- turtle garden)), south garden of hojo of the honbo of the Nanzen-ji Temple, Mittanseki of Ryukoin of the Daitoku-ji Temple, stone bridge in front of the front gate of Kohoan, a front garden of the same, Bosenseki Roji of the same (the building was lost by fire in the Kansei era (1789 - 1800), and restored after the original style), island [いで島 定訳不明] of the south pond garden [仙洞御所南池庭 定訳不明] and the stone-lined part of the eastern bank protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Work to which he is believed to have contributed includes: the tamaya (mausoleum) for Kasuga no Tsubone (in Keicho era (1596 - 1615, specifically relocation of waiting room); the haiden (hall of worship) of the Himuro-jinja Shrine (Keicho era (1596 - 1615), relocation of Dairi Chitei [内裏池亭 読み,英語表記とも不明]); Shinden of the Daikaku-ji Temple (became Chugu Shinden in the Genna era (1615 - 1617) upon the expansion of the dairi (Imperial Palace) first constructed in the Keicho era); Toshogu (Priest house), tea house and south garden (Tsuru-Kame garden (literally, crane- turtle garden)) of hojo (abbot&apos;s chamber) of Konchi-in; south garden of hojo of the honbo (priests main living quarters) of the Nanzen-ji Temple; Mittanseki (tea house) of Ryukoin of Daitoku-ji Temple; stone bridge in front of the front gate of Kohoan, a front garden and Bosenseki Roji of the same (building was lost to fire in the Kansei era (1789 - 1800) and restored in the original style); and the islands and stone-lined eastern shore of the south garden of Sento Gosho.</e>
<cmt>Added semi-colons for more clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Work to which he is believed to have contributed include: the tamaya (mausoleum) for Kasuga no Tsubone (during the Keicho era (1596 - 1615), relocation of the waiting room); the haiden (hall of worship) of the Himuro-jinja Shrine (Keicho era (1596 - 1615), relocation of Dairi Chitei (an arbor by a pond of the Imperial Palace)); Shinden of the Daikaku-ji Temple (became Chugu Shinden in the Genna era (1615 - 1617) upon the expansion of the dairi (Imperial Palace) first constructed in the Keicho era); Toshogu (Priest house), tea house and south garden (Tsuru-Kame garden (literally, crane-turtle garden)) of hojo (abbot&apos;s chamber) of Konchi-in; south garden of hojo of the honbo (priests main living quarters) of the Nanzen-ji Temple; Mittanseki (tea house) of Ryukoin of Daitoku-ji Temple; stone bridge in front of the front gate of Kohoan, a front garden and Bosenseki Roji of the same (building was lost to fire in the Kansei era (1789 - 1800) and restored in the original style); and the islands and stone-lined eastern shore of the south garden of Sento Gosho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、加賀国大聖寺藩長流亭も手がけていると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that he also built Choryutei in Daishoji Domain in Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also said to have built Choryutei in Daishoji Domain in Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also said to have built Choryutei in Daishoji Domain in Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>幼年期から時折のぞかせた天才的素質を先輩たちは嘱望し、自らも精進することにより、その晩年にいたってますます冴えを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His seniors put their hopes on gifted genius which he showed sometimes since his childhood, and, by trying hard by himself, he sophisticated his genius in his later days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His seniors had high hopes based on the flashes of genius he showed as a youth, and, thanks to his efforts to improve himself, he was to show even great brilliance in later life..</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His seniors had high hopes based on the flashes of genius he showed as a youth and together with his efforts to improve himself, he was to show even greater brilliance in later life.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>庭園の作風については、遠州は師である古田織部の作風を受け継ぎ発展させたとされるが、遠州の著しい特徴は庭園に直線を導入したことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the style of gardens, it is told that Enshu succeeded the style of his teacher, Oribe FUKUTA and further developed it, but remarkable feature of Enshu is introduction of direct line in the garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his gardens Enshu carried on and developed the style of his teacher, Oribe FUKATA, but what marks him out is the introduction of the straight line to his gardens.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his gardens, Enshu carried on and developed the style of his teacher, Oribe FURUTA, but Enshu&apos;s significant contribution to gardening is the introduction of straight lines.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>屏風画に残る御所で実施した築地の庭（後には改修される）や桂離宮の輿寄の「真の飛石」が小堀好みと伝えられた所以とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told to be the reason why Tsuiji no niwa (garden with a roofed mud-wall) implemented in the gosho (Imperial Palace)(improved later) recorded in a folding screen painting and &quot;Shin no tobiishi (stepping-stone)&quot; in okoshiyose [定訳不明] of Katsura Imperial Villa are said to be Kobori-style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is for their inclusion or straight lines that the Tsuiji no niwa (garden with a roofed mud-wall) in Gosho (Imperial Palace)(altered later) shown in a folding screen painting the the &quot;Shin no tobiishi (stepping-stones)&quot; in Okoshiyose (Rest house) [定訳不明] in Katsura Imperial Villa are are said to be in the Kobori style.</e>
<cmt>It is not clear what &quot;it&quot; refers to in trans1</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukiji no niwa (garden with a roofed mud-wall) in Gosho (Imperial Palace) (altered later) that can be still seen in an existing folding screen painting and the &apos;Shin no tobiishi (stepping-stones)&apos; of the Koshiyose (palanquin porch) at Katsura Imperial Villa are said to be favorites of Kobori.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>種々な形の切石を組み合わせた大きな畳石と正方形の切石を配置した空間構成は、以前には見られないものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The space composition in which large tatamiishi [畳石 定訳不明] of combined hewn stones in different shapes and square hewn stones are arranged is not seen before.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A spatial arrangement having different-shaped stones grouped to form large &quot;tatami ishi&quot; (paving stones) and square-hewn stones had never beeen seen before.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;tatami ishi&quot; can be translated as &quot;paving stones&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spatial arrangement of combining different-shaped stones of large paving stones and square-hewn stones had never been seen before.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>直線に使った長い畳石は桂離宮内の諸所にも見られるが、特に松琴亭前の反りのない石橋は圧巻である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Long tatamiishi used in a direct line can be seen in various places in Katsura Imperial Villa, but, in particular, a stone bridge without warpage in front of Shokintei (a building for tea ceremony) is a masterpiece.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Long paving stones arranged in straight lines can be seen in various places in Katsura Imperial Villa, but the finest example is the archless stone bridge in front of Shokintei (building for tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Long paving stones arranged in straight lines can be seen in various places in Katsura Imperial Villa, but the archless stone bridge in front of Shokintei (building for tea ceremony) is especially magnificient.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、樹木を大胆に刈り込み、花壇を多く用い、芝生の庭園を作るなどの工夫は、西洋の影響が指摘される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of the Western technique is pointed out for arrangement to prune trees without hesitation, using many flowerbeds and creating a garden with lawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, techniques such as the adventurous pruning of the trees, the frequent use of flowerbeds and the creation of lawns point to Western influence.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, techniques such as adventurous pruning of the trees, frequent use of flowerbeds and creation of grass lawns point to a western influence.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>茶の湯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chanoyu (tea ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chanoyu (tea ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chanoyu (tea ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>遠州の茶の湯は現在ではきれいさびと称され、遠州流・小堀遠州流として続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshu&apos;s chanoyu is currently called kirei sabi [定訳不明] and it has been inherited as Enshuryu or Kobori Enshuryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshu tea ceromony is currently called Kirei sabi [定訳不明] and continues to be passed down in the Enshu/Kobori Enshu tradition.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshu&apos;s style of tea ceremony is currently now called Kirei sabi [定訳不明] and continues to be passed down as the Enshu/Kobori Enshu school.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>遠州は和歌や藤原定家の書を学び、王朝文化の美意識を茶の湯に取り入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshu learned waka poems and handwriting of FUJIWARA no Sadaie and adopted the sense of beauty (an aesthetic sense) of cultures of the dynasty age into chanoyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshu studied the waka poems and handwriting of FUJIWARA no Sadaie and introduced the aesthetics of the Heian period into tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>According to http://dic.yahoo.co.jp, 王朝　is 武家時代に対して、天皇親政の時代。奈良・平安時代をさし、特に平安時代をいうこともある。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshu studied the waka poems and handwriting of FUJIWARA no Sadaie and introduced the aesthetics of the Heian period into the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>FBでは△になっているが、どこが修正されたのか不明。文字化け＃部分の修正のみと思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>彼の選定した茶道具は和歌から取った銘がつけられ、後世中興名物と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tea utensils selected by him are given names taken from waka poets and later called chuko meibutsu [定訳不明].</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tea utensils he selected were taken from waka poems and later came to be known as chuko meibutsu [定訳不明].</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tea utensils he selected were given names from waka poems and later became known as chuko meibutsu [定訳不明].</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>茶室は織部のものより窓を増やし明るくした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He increased the number of windows in the tea house compared with those of ORIBE, and made the inside lighter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In tea houses, he increased the number of windows compared with the designs of ORIBE and made the inside lighter.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tea houses he designed had more windows and were brighter inside than those of Oribe.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>彼の門下としては松花堂昭乗、沢庵宗彭が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his pupils, Shojo SHOKADO and Takuan Soho are famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his pupils, Shojo SHOKADO and Takuan Soho are famous.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shojo SHOKADO and Takuan Soho are famous among his pupils.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>華道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flower arrangement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flower arrangement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flower arrangement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>遠州がもたらした美意識を華道世界に反映させた流儀として江戸後期に特に栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It flourished in the latter half of the Edo Period as a school that reflect the sense of beauty brought by Enshu to the world of flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flower arrangement flourished in the latter part of the Edo Period in a style that that reflected the aethestics introduced to the field by Enshu.</e>
<cmt>It is not clear what &quot;it&quot; is referring to in trans1.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A style of flower arrangement that reflected the aesthetics introduced to the field by Enshu was especially popular during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>遠州の茶の流れを汲む春秋軒一葉が挿花として天地人の三才を確立し、茶の花から独自の花形へと展開していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunjuken Ichiyo, who was affiliated with Enshu&apos;s tea ceremony, established the three powers of &quot;heaven, earth and human&quot; in flower arrangement and developed cha no hana (flower arrangement for tea ceremony into a unique form of flowers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunjuken Ichiyo, who was affiliated with the Enshu style of tea ceremony, established the idea of the three powers of &quot;heaven, earth and human&quot; in flower arrangement and developed cha no hana (flower arrangement for tea ceremony) into an independent style.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunjuken Ichiyo, who was affiliated with the Enshu style of the tea ceremony, established the idea of the three powers of heaven, earth and human in flower arrangement and developed an independent style from cha no hana (flower arrangement for tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>正風、日本橋、浅草の三大流派でほぼ規矩が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The majority of standard practices in flower arrangment were established in three schools of Shofu, Nihonbashi and Asakusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The majority of standard practices in flower arrangment were established in three schools of Shofu, Nihonbashi and Asakusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The majority of standard practices in flower arrangement were established by the three main schools, Shofu, Nihonbashi and Asakusa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>やがて江戸末期から昭和初期にかけて、既存の流派から独立する家元・宗家が多数生まれ、遠州の名がつく流派が明治期をピークにかなり増える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of the Edo Period to the beginning of the Showa era, many iemoto (the head family of a school) and soke (the head family or house) were born gaining independence from existing schools, and the number of schools having Enshu in its name increased having its peak in the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the Edo Period to the beginning of the Showa era, many iemoto (the head family of a school) and soke (the head family or house) independent from existing schools came into existence, and the number of schools having Enshu in their name increased, reaching a peak in the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the Edo Period to early Showa Period, many iemoto (head of a school) and soke (head of a house) gained independence from existing schools and the number of schools having Enshu in their name increased, reaching a peak during the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>総じて花枝に曲をかなり大げさにつける手法がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, these schools use techniques to introduce exaggerated curves to branches and stems of flowers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, these schools use techniques to introduce exaggerated curves to branches and stems of flowers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, these schools use techniques that introduce exaggerated curves to branches and flower stems.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>華道のなかでも曲生けは技術的に習得するのが難しいとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that kyokuike (a style of flower arrangement which uses curve) is technically difficult to learn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In flower arrangment, kyokuike (the introduction of curves) is said to be a difficult technique to learn.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokuike (the introduction of curves) is said to be a difficult technique to learn in flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notes</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>八条宮智仁親王、近衛信尋、木下勝俊など当代一流の文化人たちとの交際が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His friendship with the top men of culture at that time such as Imperial Prince Hachijonomiya Toshihito, Nobuhiro KONOE and Katsutoshi KINOSHITA is known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshu is known to have had friendships some of the most cultured men of his gneration, including Imperial Prince Hachijonomiya Toshihito, Nobuhiro KONOE and Katsutoshi KINOSHITA.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshu is known to have had friendships with some of the most cultured men of his generation, including the Imperial Prince Hachijonomiya Toshihito, Nobuhiro KONOE and Katsutoshi KINOSHITA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>元和7年（1621年）と寛永19年（1642年）の江戸から上洛途次の歌入日記にもその文学趣味がよく現れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His taste for literature is well shown in his diaries with poems for his trips from Edo to Kyoto in 1621 and 1642.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His interest in literature is clearly shown in his diaries which contain poems for his trips from Edo to Kyoto in 1621 and 1642.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His interest in literature is clearly shown in his diary which contains poems written during his trips from Edo to Kyoto in 1621 and 1642.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>遠州が着用したと伝えられる当世具足が東京国立博物館に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tosei-gusoku (a type of armor) which is told Enshu wore is possessed by the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tosei-gusoku (a type of armor) said to have been worn by Enshu is in the collection of Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tosei-gusoku (a type of armor) said to have been worn by Enshu is owned by the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Foldingfan(id:234775), Julius Caesar(id:181760), Nnh(id:474), カテゴリ整理専用(id:146185), Aotake(id:34929), Reggaeman(id:6214), パピヨン星人(id:131851), D.h(id:79056), Yukke123(id:178302), Sutou(id:32), Roga246(id:53246), ルク(id:180305), Goki(id:7107), 怪蘇(id:45514), Mzaki(id:61977), Point136(id:211299), Kouko0515(id:100370), Mnd(id:15140), Avensisblue(id:159163), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), GoGoDoll(id:131511), Swordarts(id:54566), Himazin(id:22034), Yanahan(id:2437), Aboshi(id:9318), Ikezuki(id:240184), ナツメグ(id:112775), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 663highland(id:18755), Kuma83(id:31177), Jmho(id:10472), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>