<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小山朝政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomasa OYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomasa OYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomasa OYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小山 朝政（おやま ともまさ）は平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期の武将である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomasa OYAMA was a Japanese military commander (busho) from the end of the Heian period (794-1185) to the beginning of the Kamakura period (1185-1333).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomasa OYAMA was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the end of the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomasa OYAMA was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the end of the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>源頼朝に挙兵の頃から仕え、播磨国守護に補されたほか、下野守にも任ぜられたとされるが、朝政の晩年の職位は「左衛門尉」や「判官」でありこれらは従六位か従七位の官位であること、また父・政光の官位も正七位下であったことなどから、卒年に従五位下下野守であったという『吾妻鏡』の記載は誤記の疑いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he had served for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (the founder of the Kamakura Shogunate) since Yoritomo raised an army, and was appointed as Shimotsuke no kami (Governor of Shimotsuke Province) in addition to Shugo (a provincial constable) of Harima Province, and the record in &quot;Azuma Kagami (The Mirror of the East)&quot; (a historical account of the Kamakura Shogunate) that the job position in the year of his death was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Shimotsuke no kami might be a writing error because the job position in his later year was &apos;Saemon no jo (third ranked office of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards)&apos; or &apos;hangan (judge),&apos; whose court rank was Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank) or Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank), and the court rank of his father, Masamitsu, was Shoshichii (Senior Seventh Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he had served for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo since Yoritomo raised an army, and was appointed as Shimotsuke no kami (Governor of Shimotsuke Province) in addition to Shugo (a provincial constable) of Harima Province, and the record in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) (a historical account of the Kamakura Shogunate) that the job position in the year of his death was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Shimotsuke no kami might be a writing error because he was &apos;Saemon no jo&apos; (third ranked office of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) or &apos;hangan&apos; (judge) in his late years, whose court ranks were Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank) or Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank), and the court rank of his father, Masamitsu, was Shoshichii (Senior Seventh Rank).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he had served for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo since Yoritomo raised an army, and was appointed as Shimotsuke no kami (Governor of Shimotsuke Province) in addition to Shugo (a provincial constable) of Harima Province, and the record in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) (a historical account of the Kamakura Shogunate) that the job position in the year of his death was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Shimotsuke no kami might be a writing error because he was &apos;Saemon no jo&apos; (third ranked office of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) or &apos;hangan&apos; (judge) in his late years, whose court ranks were Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank) or Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank), and the court rank of his father, Masamitsu, was Shoshichii (Senior Seventh Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>仁平4年（1154年）頃に小山政光（父で小山氏の祖）の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around in 1154, he was born as a child of Masamitsu KOYAMA (a founder of the Koyama clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around in 1154, he was born as a child of Masamitsu KOYAMA (a founder of the Koyama clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around in 1154, he was born as a child of Masamitsu KOYAMA (a founder of the Koyama clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は武蔵国の太田氏の出であり、下野国小山市に移住して小山氏を名乗り、後妻に八田宗綱の息女で源頼朝の乳母である寒河尼を娶っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was originally from the Ota clan in Musashi Province, and moved to Oyama, Shimotsuke Province, taking a new surname, Koyama, and got married to SAMUKAWA no Ama, a second wife, who was a daughter of Munetsuna Hatta, and a wet nurse of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was originally from the Ota clan in Musashi Province, and moved to Oyama, Shimotsuke Province, taking a new surname, Koyama, and got married to SAMUKAWA no Ama, a second wife, who was a daughter of Munetsuna Hatta, and a wet nurse of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was originally from the Ota clan in Musashi Province, and moved to Oyama, Shimotsuke Province, taking a new surname, Koyama, and got married to SAMUKAWA no Ama, a second wife, who was a daughter of Munetsuna Hatta, and a wet nurse of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>源平合戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Genpei War (Conflict from 1180 to 1185 between two warrior leagues, one under the Taira family (Heishi or Heike), and the other under the Minamoto family (Genji))</e>
<cmt>源平合戦→conflict from 1180 to 1185 ～Minamoto Family (Genji) を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Genpei War (Conflict from 1180 to 1185 between two warrior leagues, one under the Taira family [Heishi or Heike], and the other under the Minamoto family [Genji])</e>
<cmt>カッコ内のカッコを [] に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Genpei War (Conflict from 1180 to 1185 between two warrior leagues, one under the Taira family [Heishi or Heike], and the other under the Minamoto family [Genji])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>治承4年（1180年）、源頼朝は平氏打倒の兵を挙げ、9月3日、朝政はそれへの参向を求める書状を送られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1180, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo took up arms to overthrow the Taira rule, and on September 3, sent a letter to Tomomasa, urging him to participate in Yoritomo&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1180, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo took up arms to defeat the Taira clan, and on September 30, sent a letter to Tomomasa, urging him to participate in Yoritomo&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt>overthrow the Taira rule を defeat the Taira clan に修正しました。日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1180, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo took up arms to defeat the Taira clan, and on September 30, sent a letter to Tomomasa, urging him to participate in Yoritomo&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>10月2日、寒河尼は実子の結城朝光を伴って頼朝の下に参じ、朝政もその後の早い時期に従ったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 2, SAMUKAWA no Ama joined Yoritomo with Tomomitsu YUKI, her biological child, and Tomomasa is thought to have followed Yoritomo soon after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 29, SAMUKAWA no Ama joined Yoritomo with Tomomitsu YUKI, her biological child, and Tomomasa is thought to have followed Yoritomo soon after that.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 29, SAMUKAWA no Ama joined Yoritomo with Tomomitsu YUKI, her biological child, and Tomomasa is thought to have followed Yoritomo soon after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）2月、頼朝の御家人らは鎌倉に襲来すると風聞された平氏のため駿河国に在った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1183, Yoritomo&apos;s gokenin (direct vassals of the Shogunate in the Kamakura through the Edo period) were in Suruga Province (now part of Shizuoka Prefecture) to defense against Taira family&apos;s troops which was said to attack Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, 1183, Yoritomo&apos;s shogunal retainers (of the Kamakura bakufu) were in Suruga Province (now part of Shizuoka Prefecture) to defense against the Taira clan which was said to attack Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>御家人の訳を修正しました。Taira family&apos;s troops を the Taira clan に修正しました。February を March に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, 1183, Yoritomo&apos;s shogunal retainers (of the Kamakura bakufu) were in Suruga Province (now part of Shizuoka Prefecture) to defense against the Taira clan which was said to attack Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>20日、常陸国志田に住む源義広 (志田三郎先生)は鎌倉を攻める兵を挙げ、三万余騎を率い下野国へと到る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, on February 20, MINAMOTO no Yoshihiro (SHIDA Saburo Senjo), who resided in Shida, Hitachi Province, raised arms to attack Kamakura, marching Shimotsuke Province with about 30,000 troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, on March 22, MINAMOTO no Yoshihiro (SHIDA Saburo Senjo), who resided in Shida, Hitachi Province, raised arms to attack Kamakura, marching Shimotsuke Province with about 30,000 troops.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, on March 22, MINAMOTO no Yoshihiro (SHIDA Saburo Senjo), who resided in Shida, Hitachi Province, raised arms to attack Kamakura, marching Shimotsuke Province with about 30,000 troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>頼朝は下野に在った朝政にその対応を託し、それを助けるため弟の長沼宗政らは鎌倉を発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo pinned responsibility on Tomomasa in Shimotsuke Province to fight against Yoshihiro, and delivered reinforcements of Munemasa NAGANUMA, Tomomasa&apos;s brother from Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo pinned responsibility on Tomomasa in Shimotsuke Province to fight against Yoshihiro, and Tomomasa&apos;s brother Munemasa NAGANUMA departed Kamakura to support it.</e>
<cmt>後半部を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo pinned responsibility on Tomomasa in Shimotsuke Province to fight against Yoshihiro, and Tomomasa&apos;s brother Munemasa NAGANUMA departed Kamakura to support it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>23日、義広は鎌倉へ向けて軍を発し、それに加わるよう朝政を誘う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 23, the Yoshihiro marched his army to Kamakura, and told Tomomasa to join his troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 25, Yoshihiro marched his army to Kamakura, and invited Tomomasa to join his troops.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 25, Yoshihiro marched his army to Kamakura, and invited Tomomasa to join his troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>朝政は父が京で大番役を勤めており兵が少なく、加わると偽りの答えを返す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomasa answered Yoshihiro, dutifully lying that Tomomasa had fewer soldier then because his father served as Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto) in Kyoto with their soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomasa answered Yoshihiro, dutifully lying that Tomomasa had fewer soldier then because his father served as Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto) in Kyoto with their soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomasa answered Yoshihiro, dutifully lying that Tomomasa had fewer soldier then because his father served as Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto) in Kyoto with their soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>喜んだ義広は朝政の館に向かい、その途中の野木町に至ると、潜んでいた朝政らは声をあげ狼狽させ攻める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yoshihiro, glad to know that, made for Tomomasa&apos;s residence, Tomomasa and his warriors ambushed and attacked his troops on the way at Nogi-cho, shouting at the top of their voice to make them in panic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yoshihiro, glad to know that, made for Tomomasa&apos;s residence, Tomomasa and his warriors ambushed and attacked his troops on the way at Nogi-cho, shouting at the top of their voice to make them in panic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yoshihiro, glad to know that, made for Tomomasa&apos;s residence, Tomomasa and his warriors ambushed and attacked his troops on the way at Nogi-cho, shouting at the top of their voice to make them in panic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この時の朝政は25歳で力に優れ、火威の鎧を着け鹿毛の馬に跨り、四方に駆け多くの敵を亡ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Tomomasa was 25 years old with young power, riding on horseback all around with his scarlet armor, and destroying many enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Tomomasa was 25 years old with young power, riding on horseback all around with his scarlet armor, and destroying many enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Tomomasa was 25 years old with young power, riding on horseback all around with his scarlet armor, and destroying many enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>義広の放った矢を受け落馬するが死には至らず、野木宮の西南に陣を引いた義広を、朝政と宗政は東から攻め破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hit by an arrow released by Yoshihiro, Tomomasa fell off his horse, non-lethal wound, and Tomomasa and Munemasa met and routed the Yoshihiro&apos;s troop in the east-south of Nogimiya, where Yoshihiro withdrew to take up Yoshihiro&apos;s position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hit by an arrow released by Yoshihiro, Tomomasa fell off his horse, non-lethal wound, and Tomomasa and Munemasa met and routed the Yoshihiro&apos;s troop in the east-south of Nogimiya, where Yoshihiro withdrew to take up Yoshihiro&apos;s position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hit by an arrow released by Yoshihiro, Tomomasa fell off his horse, non-lethal wound, and Tomomasa and Munemasa met and routed the Yoshihiro&apos;s troop in the east-south of Nogimiya, where Yoshihiro withdrew to take up Yoshihiro&apos;s position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>野木宮合戦と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called the Battle of Nogimiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called the Battle of Nogimiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called the Battle of Nogimiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>28日、使者を発し頼朝に戦勝を告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 28, Tomomasa sent a messenger to tell his victory to Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 28, Tomomasa sent a messenger to tell his victory to Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 28, Tomomasa sent a messenger to tell his victory to Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>頼朝は義広に与した常陸国、下野国、上野国の武士を所領を収公し、朝政らは恩賞を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo dispossessed territory of warriors in Hitachi Province, Shimotsuke Province and Kozuke Province, who had sided with Yoshihiro, and then awarded these territories to Tomomasa and his warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo dispossessed territory of warriors in Hitachi Province, Shimotsuke Province and Kozuke Province, who had sided with Yoshihiro, and then awarded these territories to Tomomasa and his warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo dispossessed territory of warriors in Hitachi Province, Shimotsuke Province and Kozuke Province, who had sided with Yoshihiro, and then awarded these territories to Tomomasa and his warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>元暦元年（1184年）8月8日、源範頼は平氏追討の為に京へ向い、9月2日、朝政はそれに属せよとの命を受け鎌倉を発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 8, 1184, Yoritomo sent MINAMOTO no Noriyori, one of his brothers, to Kyoto in order to pursue the Taira family, and also demanded Tomomasa to participate in the Noriyori&apos;s troops, so that Tomomasa left Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 21, 1184, MINAMOTO no Noriyori left for Kyoto in order to pursue the Taira clan, and Tomomasa left Kamakura by an order to join Noriyori.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 21, 1184, MINAMOTO no Noriyori left for Kyoto in order to pursue the Taira clan, and Tomomasa left Kamakura by an order to join Noriyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その際に朝政は兵衛尉を望み、京でその任官を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomasa was appointed as Hyoe no jo (Lieutenant of the Middle Palace Guards) in Kyoto, which he had requested at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomasa was appointed as Hyoe no jo (Lieutenant of the Middle Palace Guards) in Kyoto, which he had requested at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomasa was appointed as Hyoe no jo (Lieutenant of the Middle Palace Guards) in Kyoto, which he had requested at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>元暦2年（1185年）1月26日、範頼らと共に周防国から船で豊後国に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 26, 1185 (old calendar), Tomomasa departed from Suo Province (now part of Yamaguchi Prefecture) to Bungo Province (now part of Oita Prefecture) with Noriyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 6, 1185, Tomomasa departed from Suo Province to Bungo Province with Noriyori by ship.</e>
<cmt>「船で」訳漏れのため、by ship を追記し、全文修正して対応しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 6, 1185, Tomomasa departed from Suo Province to Bungo Province with Noriyori by ship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>3月11日、兵糧の不足に苦しむ範頼の軍の中で、他の御家人らと共に頼朝より慇懃の書を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suffering from the deficiency of army provisions under the army of Noriyori, Tomomasa received a letter of thanks to him and other gokenin expressing gratitude for their efforts from Yoritomo on March 11.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 19, while suffering from the deficiency of army provisions in Noriyori&apos;s troops, Tomomasa and other gokenin received a letter from Yoritomo expressing his gratitude for their efforts.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 19, while suffering from the deficiency of army provisions in Noriyori&apos;s troops, Tomomasa and other gokenin received a letter from Yoritomo expressing his gratitude for their efforts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>3月24日、壇ノ浦の戦いで平家一門は滅びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 24, the Minamoto family destroyed the Taira family completely in the Battle of Dannoura (off the southern tip of Honshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 2, the Taira family was completely destroyed in the Battle of Dan no ura.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 2, the Taira family was completely destroyed in the Battle of Dan no ura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>4月15日、頼朝は内挙を得ず任官を受けた御家人らの帰国を禁じる書状を発し、朝政もそれに入れられ次の様に記された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 15, Yoritomo issued a decree that any gokenin, including Tomomasa, who were appointed without permission should be prohibited to come back to their home land, and it said as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 23, Yoritomo issued a decree that any gokenin, including Tomomasa, who were appointed without permission should be prohibited to come back to their home land, and it said as follows.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 23, Yoritomo issued a decree that any gokenin, including Tomomasa, who were appointed without permission should be prohibited to come back to their home land, and it said as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>「鎮西に下向するの時、京に於いて拝任せしむ事、駘馬の道草を喰らうが如し」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was like a lazy horse loitering away its time to have been appointed as any commission in Kyoto on the way to Chinzei (now Kyusu).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was like a lazy horse loitering away its time to have been appointed as any commission in Kyoto on the way to Chinzei (nickname of Kyushu).&apos;</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was like a lazy horse loitering away its time to have been appointed as any commission in Kyoto on the way to Chinzei (nickname of Kyushu).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>10月24日、朝政は許されており、鎌倉で行われた源義朝の法要に参列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 24, being permitted, Tomomasa participated in the Buddhist memorial service of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo held in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 24, being permitted, Tomomasa participated in the Buddhist memorial service of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo held in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 24, being permitted, Tomomasa participated in the Buddhist memorial service of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo held in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この法要は鎌倉の頼朝と京の源義経が対立する中で、三千人弱の主要な御家人を集めて営まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ceremony, which almost 3,000 gokenin attended, was held with the relationship between Yoritomo in Kamakura and Yoshitsune (another of Yoritomo&apos;s brothers) in Kyoto deteriorated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ceremony, which almost 3,000 gokenin attended, was held with the relationship between Yoritomo in Kamakura and Yoshitsune (another of Yoritomo&apos;s brothers) in Kyoto deteriorated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ceremony, which almost 3,000 gokenin attended, was held with the relationship between Yoritomo in Kamakura and Yoshitsune (another of Yoritomo&apos;s brothers) in Kyoto deteriorated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>法要が終わると頼朝は明日上洛との意を述べ御家人を集める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the memorial ceremony, Yoritomo consolidated his gokenin and told them that he went up to Kyoto the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the memorial ceremony, Yoritomo consolidated his gokenin and told them that he went up to Kyoto the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the memorial ceremony, Yoritomo consolidated his gokenin and told them that he went up to Kyoto the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その中でも明暁に進発する者を募り、朝政はそれに応えた58人中の筆頭であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo recruited volunteers among them who started at dawn, and Tmomasa was the first of those 58 volunteers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo recruited volunteers among them who started at dawn, and Tomomasa was the first of those 58 volunteers.</e>
<cmt>Tmomasa を Tomomasa に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo recruited volunteers among them who started at dawn, and Tomomasa was the first of those 58 volunteers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>11月1日、頼朝の軍は駿河国黄瀬川に達し、義経は戦わずして京を落ちた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 1, the Yoritomo&apos;s troops reached the Kise-gawa River in Suruga Province, so that Yoshitsune fled from Kyoto without fighting against Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 1, the Yoritomo&apos;s troops reached the Kise-gawa River in Suruga Province, so that Yoshitsune fled from Kyoto without fighting against Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 1, the Yoritomo&apos;s troops reached the Kise-gawa River in Suruga Province, so that Yoshitsune fled from Kyoto without fighting against Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>以降、朝政は鎌倉で行われる儀式に多く名を連ねる事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From then on, Tomomasa often participated in the ceremonies held in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then on, Tomomasa often participated in the ceremonies held in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on, Tomomasa often participated in the ceremonies held in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>奥州合戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Oshu (northeastern region of Honshu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Oshu</e>
<cmt>(northeastern region of Honshu) を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Oshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>文治5年（1189年）7月19日、頼朝は藤原泰衡を討つ為に鎌倉を発し、朝政はそれに従う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 19, 1189, Yoritomo, whom Tomomasa followed, led troops from Kamakura to defeat FUJIWARA no Yasuhira in Oshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 8, 1189, Yoritomo led troops from Kamakura to defeat FUJIWARA no Yasuhira in Oshu, and Tomomasa followed Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 8, 1189, Yoritomo led troops from Kamakura to defeat FUJIWARA no Yasuhira in Oshu, and Tomomasa followed Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>7月25日、下野国古多橋駅（現・宇都宮市）において願を立て宇都宮二荒山神社を奉幣した折、その宿所にて父の政光が頼朝に食事を献じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoritomo stayed in Furutabashieki, Shimotsuke Province (now Utsunomiya City), where he prayed for victory at Utsunomiya Futaarayama-jinja Shrine on July 25, Tomomasa&apos;s father served meals for Yoritomo at his camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoritomo stayed in Furutabashieki, Shimotsuke Province (now Utsunomiya City), where he prayed for victory at Utsunomiya Futaarayama-jinja Shrine on September 14, Tomomasa&apos;s father served meals for Yoritomo at his camp.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoritomo stayed in Furutabashieki, Shimotsuke Province (now Utsunomiya City), where he prayed for victory at Utsunomiya Futaarayama-jinja Shrine on September 14, Tomomasa&apos;s father served meals for Yoritomo at his camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その場には熊谷直家が在り、政光が直家は何者かを質問すると、頼朝は直家を無双の勇士と評し、それが直家には郎従が少く源平合戦では自ら戦った事によると応えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoie KUMAGAI was there with Yoritomo, so that Masamitsu asked Yoritomo who he was, and Yoritomo answered that he was one of the bravest warriors in this country because he himself fought in the Genpei War with a few roju (vassals) of his.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoie KUMAGAI was there with Yoritomo, so that Masamitsu asked Yoritomo who he was, and Yoritomo answered that he was one of the bravest warriors in this country because he himself fought in the Genpei War as he had few vassals.</e>
<cmt>with a few roju (vassals) of his を as he had few vassals に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoie KUMAGAI was there with Yoritomo, so that Masamitsu asked Yoritomo who he was, and Yoritomo answered that he was one of the bravest warriors in this country because he himself fought in the Genpei War as he had few vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>政光は朝政、長沼宗政、結城朝光、宇都宮頼綱ら兄弟に対し、今度は自ら合戦を遂げ無双の御旨を蒙るよう命ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing that, Masamitsu raised the moral by telling Tomomasa, Munemasa NAGANUMA, Tomomitsu YUKI, Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA and his brothers to fight enough to be praised as the bravest warriors by Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing that, Masamitsu raised the moral by telling Tomomasa, Munemasa NAGANUMA, Tomomitsu YUKI, Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA and his brothers to fight enough to be praised as the bravest warriors by Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing that, Masamitsu raised the moral by telling Tomomasa, Munemasa NAGANUMA, Tomomitsu YUKI, Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA and his brothers to fight enough to be praised as the bravest warriors by Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>頼朝はこれを聞き入興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo was amused to hear that.</e>
<cmt>quite satisfied を amused に修正しました。※「入興する」は「興に入る、面白がる」の意味です。http://kotobank.jp/word/%E8%88%88%E3%81%AB%E5%85%A5%E3%82%8B</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo was amused to hear that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>8月10日、阿津賀志山の戦いに加わり、守る藤原国衡を破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 10, taking part in the Battle of Atsukashiyama, Tomomasa defeated Fujiwara no Kunihira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 28, taking part in the Battle of Atsukashiyama, Tomomasa defeated FUJIWARA no Kunihira.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。Fujiwara を FUJIWARA に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 28, taking part in the Battle of Atsukashiyama, Tomomasa defeated FUJIWARA no Kunihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>8月14日、玉造郡物見岡に泰衡を追い岡を囲む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 14, Tomomasa pursued Yasuhira into Monomioka, Tamatsukuri-gun, and surrounded the hill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 2, Tomomasa pursued Yasuhira into Monomioka, Tamatsukuri County, and surrounded the hill.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。-gun を County に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 2, Tomomasa pursued Yasuhira into Monomioka, Tamatsukuri County, and surrounded the hill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>泰衡は既に逃亡しており、岡には五十人弱の郎従が残っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuhira had already fled away, and a fewer than 50 vassals remained there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuhira had already fled away, and a fewer than 50 vassals remained there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuhira had already fled away, and a fewer than 50 vassals remained there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>それらは朝政らの武勇により、討たれまたは捕らえられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them were killed and some were captured by Tomomasa and his warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them were killed and some were captured by Tomomasa and his warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them were killed and some were captured by Tomomasa and his warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>9月、合戦は泰衡が自らの郎党に討たれ、頼朝らの勝利に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, the Battle of Oshu resulted in victory of Yoritomo and the death of Yasuhira, who had been killed by his own vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, Yasuhira was killed by his own vassals, and the Battle of Oshu resulted in Yoritomo&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, Yasuhira was killed by his own vassals, and the Battle of Oshu resulted in Yoritomo&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>幕府宿老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shukuro (members of Hyojoshu, a highest office of the Kamakura and Muromachi shogunates, where administrative matters and legal disputes were discussed in council) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>宿老→鎌倉幕府の評定衆・引付衆＜広辞苑→members of Hyoujoshu,～in ｃｏｕｎｃｉｌを補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shukuro (members of Hyojoshu, a highest office of the Kamakura and Muromachi shogunates, where administrative matters and legal disputes were discussed in council) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shukuro (members of Hyojoshu, a highest office of the Kamakura and Muromachi shogunates, where administrative matters and legal disputes were discussed in council) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>建久元年（1190年）冬、頼朝の上洛に随行し、11月11日、石清水八幡宮への参拝では行列の先頭を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In winter, 1190, Tomomasa accompanied Yoritomo to Kyoto, and on November 11, he headed a procession when Yoritomo visited Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In winter, 1190, Tomomasa accompanied Yoritomo to Kyoto, and on December 10, he headed a procession when Yoritomo visited Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In winter, 1190, Tomomasa accompanied Yoritomo to Kyoto, and on December 10, he headed a procession when Yoritomo visited Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>12月11日、頼朝は勲功の有る御家人ら十人を挙任し、朝政はその中の一人として右兵衛尉から右衛門尉に転じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 11, Yoritomo recommended ten gokenin, including Tomomasa, for their military exploits and appointed them as governmental officers, so that Tomomasa was promoted to Uemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) from Uhyoue no jo (officer of the Right division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 15, 1191, Yoritomo recommended 10 gokenin, including Tomomasa, for their military exploits and appointed them as governmental officers, so that Tomomasa was promoted to Uemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) from Uhyoue no jo (officer of the Right division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。ten を 10 に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 15, 1191, Yoritomo recommended 10 gokenin, including Tomomasa, for their military exploits and appointed them as governmental officers, so that Tomomasa was promoted to Uemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) from Uhyoue no jo (officer of the Right division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>建久3年（1192年）9月12日、野木宮合戦の功により常陸国村田下庄の地頭に補任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 12, 1192, he was appointed as Jito (local land stewards) of Muratashimosho, Hitachi Province due to the exploit of the Battle of Nogimiya.</e>
<cmt>村田下庄→むらたしもしょう→Ｍｕｒatashimosho</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 26, 1192, he was appointed as Jito (local land stewards) of Muratashimosho, Hitachi Province due to the exploit of the Battle of Nogimiya.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 26, 1192, he was appointed as Jito (local land stewards) of Muratashimosho, Hitachi Province due to the exploit of the Battle of Nogimiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この時には左衛門尉に転じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Saemon no jo at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) at this time.</e>
<cmt>Saemon no jo に説明文を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>正治元年（1199年）10月28日、梶原景時を訴える連署状に名を連ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October, 1199, he signed a letter appealing against Kagetoki FUJIWARA under joint signatures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 25, 1199, he signed a letter appealing against Kagetoki FUJIWARA under joint signatures.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 25, 1199, he signed a letter appealing against Kagetoki FUJIWARA under joint signatures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>12月19日、播磨守護に補される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 19, he was appointed as Shugo (the Governor of Harima Province) of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 14, 1200, he was appointed as Shugo (the Governor of Harima Province) of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 14, 1200, he was appointed as Shugo (the Governor of Harima Province) of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>建仁元年（1201年）2月3日、大番役で在京しており、関東追討の勅許を求める城長茂に三条東洞院の宿舎を襲われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he served as Obanyaku in Kyoto, Nagamochi JO, who called for being granted decree from the Imperial Court to attack Yoritomo in the Kanto region, made an assault on Sanjo Higashinotoin, Tomomasa&apos;s camp, on February, 1201.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 16, 1201, while Tomomasa was serving as Obanyaku in Kyoto, his Sanjo Higashinotoin camp was attacked by Nagamochi JO, who called for a decree from the Imperial Court to attack the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 16, 1201, while Tomomasa was serving as Obanyaku in Kyoto, his Sanjo Higashinotoin camp was attacked by Nagamochi JO, who called for a decree from the Imperial Court to attack the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>朝政は行幸に随行し不在で、残っていた郎従らが応戦し長茂は兵を引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomasa happened to be absent there because he guarded Emperor&apos;s procession, so that the fight of his vassals&apos; staying in the shrine against Nagamochi forced him to retreat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomasa happened to be absent there because he guarded Emperor&apos;s procession, so his vassals staying in the shrine fought against Nagamochi and Nagamochi was retreated.</e>
<cmt>後半部を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomasa happened to be absent there because he guarded Emperor&apos;s procession, so his vassals staying in the shrine fought against Nagamochi and Nagamochi was retreated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>戻った朝政は長茂が在るという清水坂に向うが行方は知れず、長茂は後に吉野で討たれ首を晒された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomasa, returning back, missed him in spite of leading troops into Kiyomizuzaka, where Nagamochi was said to hide, and Nagamochi was killed in Yoshino with his head exposed in the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomasa, returning back, missed him in spite of leading troops into Kiyomizu-zaka Slope, where Nagamochi was said to hide, and Nagamochi was killed in Yoshino with his head exposed in the end.</e>
<cmt>Kiyomizuzaka を Kiyomizu-zaka Slope に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomasa, returning back, missed him in spite of leading troops into Kiyomizu-zaka Slope, where Nagamochi was said to hide, and Nagamochi was killed in Yoshino with his head exposed in the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="50">
<j>元久2年（1205年）8月7日、幕府から義理の兄弟である宇都宮頼綱の謀反が疑われ、北条政子邸における評議の席で大江広元は朝政が頼綱を追討すべきと主張するが、朝政は反逆には賛同しないが防戦の際には全力を尽くすと述べ、追討を辞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 7, 1205, the Kamakura bakufu, suspicious of a rebellion of Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, who was a Tomomasa&apos;s brother-in-law, discussed this matter in council at the residence of Masako HOJO; OE no Hiromoto insisted that Tomomasa should defeat Yoritsuna, but Tomomsa refused to defeat Yoritsuna, although in the case of the battle, he promised to fight against Yoritsuna by main force, not admitting Yoritsuna&apos;s rebel against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 28, 1205, the Kamakura bakufu, suspicious of a rebellion of Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, who was a Tomomasa&apos;s brother-in-law, discussed this matter in council at the residence of Masako HOJO; OE no Hiromoto insisted that Tomomasa should defeat Yoritsuna, but Tomomsa refused it, although in the case of the battle, he promised to fight against Yoritsuna by main force, not admitting Yoritsuna&apos;s rebel against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。Tomomsa refused to defeat Yoritsuna を Tomomasa refused it に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 28, 1205, the Kamakura bakufu, suspicious of a rebellion of Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, who was a Tomomasa&apos;s brother-in-law, discussed this matter in council at the residence of Masako HOJO; OE no Hiromoto insisted that Tomomasa should defeat Yoritsuna, but Tomomsa refused it, although in the case of the battle, he promised to fight against Yoritsuna by main force, not admitting Yoritsuna&apos;s rebel against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>11日、頼綱と朝政は書状を北条義時に届け、謀計は無き旨を述べるが許されず、この結果、頼綱は遁俗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 11, Yoritsuna and Tomomasa sent a letter saying that Yoritsuna had no conspiracy against the bakufu to Yoshitoki HOJO, but Yoritsuna was not forgiven, so that he renounced the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 2, Yoritsuna and Tomomasa sent a letter to Yoshitoki HOJO saying that Yoritsuna had no conspiracy against the bakufu, but Yoritsuna was not forgiven, so that he renounced the world.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。to Yoshitoki HOJO の位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 2, Yoritsuna and Tomomasa sent a letter to Yoshitoki HOJO saying that Yoritsuna had no conspiracy against the bakufu, but Yoritsuna was not forgiven, so that he renounced the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="52">
<j>承久3年（1221年）、承久の乱では宿老として上洛せず関東に在った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1221, Tomomasa remained in the Kanto region, but not went up to Kyoto as shukuro in the Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1221, Tomomasa remained in the Kanto region, but not went up to Kyoto as shukuro in the Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1221, Tomomasa remained in the Kanto region, but not went up to Kyoto as shukuro in the Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="53">
<j>貞応2年（1223年）10月25日、検非違使を兼ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 25, 1223, he also served as kebiishi (officials with judicial and police power).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 26, 1223, he also served as kebiishi (officials with judicial and police power).</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 26, 1223, he also served as kebiishi (officials with judicial and police power).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="54">
<j>嘉禎4年（1238年）3月30日、84歳で卒する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 30, 1238, he passed away at the age of 84.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 22, 1238, he passed away at the age of 84.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 22, 1238, he passed away at the age of 84.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>病を患うと幾日も経なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died soon after he fell ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died soon after he had fallen ill.</e>
<cmt>fell を had fallen に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died soon after he had fallen ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>（以上、吾妻鏡より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(These mentioned above originate from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(These mentioned above originate from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(These mentioned above originate from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="57">
<j>墓は埼玉県加須市にあり、1959年6月16日、市の史跡に指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His tomb is in Kazo City, Saitama Prefecture, and on June 16, 1959, the Kazo City designated it as a historical site.</e>
<cmt>加須市→かぞ市→Ｋａｚo City</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His tomb is in Kazo City, Saitama Prefecture, and on June 16, 1959, it was designated as a historical site.</e>
<cmt>the Kazo City designated it を it was designated に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His tomb is in Kazo City, Saitama Prefecture, and on June 16, 1959, it was designated as a historical site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>吾妻鏡には卒去時の官位として下野守従五位下とあるが、同書に見られる朝政の晩年の職位は「左衛門尉」や「判官」であり、これらは従六位か従七位の官位であることから、従五位下下野守は誤りの可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; recorded that the job position of Tomomasa was Shimotsuke no kami and court rank was Jugoinoge in the year of his death, but it also recorded that in his later years, his job position was &apos;Saemon no jo&apos; or &apos;hangan&apos;, whose court rank was Jurokui or Jushichii, so that such record about his court rank in the year of his death might be wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Azuka Kagami, his official court rank when he passed away was Jugoinoge, Shimotsuke no kami, however, his job rank described in the same book was &apos;Saemon no jo&apos; or &apos;hangan&apos;, whose court rank was Jurokui or Jushichii, so that his official court rank Jugoinoge, Shimotsuke no kami might be wrong.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Azuka Kagami, his official court rank when he passed away was Jugoinoge, Shimotsuke no kami, however, his job rank described in the same book was &apos;Saemon no jo&apos; or &apos;hangan&apos;, whose court rank was Jurokui or Jushichii, so that his official court rank Jugoinoge, Shimotsuke no kami might be wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Timeline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>全部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>年月日は出典が用いる暦であり、西暦は元日をそれに変更している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The date-month-year of the historical events mentioned above is adopted from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (old Japanese lunar calendar), and a New Year&apos;s Day of the Japanese Imperial Era is converted to a year of the Christian Era.</e>
<cmt>「西暦は元日をそれに変更している」→意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The date-month-year of the historical events mentioned above is adopted from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (old Japanese lunar calendar), and a New Year&apos;s Day of the Japanese Imperial era is converted to a year of the Christian era.</e>
<cmt>above を below に修正しました。※ウィキペディアの原文を確認したところ、この文章の「前」ではなく「後」に、表形式の年表が記載されていたため、このように修正しました。old Japanese lunar calendar の Japanese を削除しました。Era を era に修正しました。※ 指示書では類義語 period の文頭を小文字で表記しているため、これを参考に修正しました。※原文後半部が意味不明のため、訳文に関する正誤の判断がつきかねます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The date-month-year of the historical events mentioned above is adopted from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (old Japanese lunar calendar), and a New Year&apos;s Day of the Japanese Imperial era is converted to a year of the Christian era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 氷鷺(id:73707), FCTR2(id:213046), Nevylax(id:38464), 俊(id:14924), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>