<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>加藤清正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa KATO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>加藤 清正（かとう きよまさ）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期にかけての武将・大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO was a Busho (Japanese military commander) and Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa KATO was a Busho (Japanese military commander) and Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO was a Busho (Japanese military commander) and Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>肥後国熊本藩初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first lord of the Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first lord of the Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first lord of the Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>豊臣秀吉の家臣として仕え、各地を転戦し武功を挙げ肥後北部を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as a retainer, distinguished himself in various battles and was given the northern part of Higo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as a retainer, distinguished himself in various battles and was given the northern part of Higo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as a retainer, distinguished himself in various battles and was given the northern part of Higo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>秀吉没後は徳川氏の家臣となり、関ヶ原の戦いの働きによって肥後熊本藩主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi, he became a retainer of the Tokugawa Clan and, due to his distinguished military service in the Battle of Sekigahara, became the lord of the Kumamoto Domain in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Hideyoshi, he became a retainer of the Tokugawa Clan and, due to his distinguished military service in the Battle of Sekigahara, became the lord of the Kumamoto Domain in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi, he became a retainer of the Tokugawa Clan and, due to his distinguished military service in the Battle of Sekigahara, became the lord of the Kumamoto Domain in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「賤ヶ岳七本槍」の一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the &apos;Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari&apos; (the seven excellent military commanders in Hideyoshi&apos;s army at the battle of Shizugatake).</e>
<cmt>「賤ヶ岳の戦い賤ヶ岳の七本槍」は、広辞苑、各サイトに従い、「賤ヶ岳の七本槍」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the &apos;Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari&apos; (the seven excellent military commanders in Hideyoshi&apos;s army at the battle of Shizugatake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the &apos;Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari&apos; (the seven excellent military commanders in Hideyoshi&apos;s army at the battle of Shizugatake).</e>
<cmt>ウェブで確認し、原文からも「賤ヶ岳の戦い」を削除しました。（原文では「賤ヶ岳七本槍」となっているため、「の」は入れてません。）余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>主君秀吉の死後も豊臣家に忠義を尽くしたことが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous for being devoted to the Toyotomi family even after the death of his lord Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was famous for being devoted to the Toyotomi family even after the death of his lord Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was famous for being devoted to the Toyotomi family even after the death of his lord Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治43年（1910年）に従三位を追贈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1910, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) was posthumously conferred on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1910, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) was posthumously conferred on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1910, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) was posthumously conferred on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>秀吉の子飼い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a retainer trained from boyhood by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a retainer trained from boyhood by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a retainer trained from boyhood by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>永禄5年（1562年）6月24日、尾張国の鍛冶屋加藤五郎助（清忠）の子として、尾張国愛知郡 (愛知県)中村（現在の名古屋市中村区）に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on August 4, 1562 as a child of Gorosuke (Kiyotada) KATO, a blacksmith of Owari Province in Nakamura, Aichi-gun County (Aichi Prefecture) in Owari Province (present Nakamura Ward, Nagoya City).</e>
<cmt>「永禄5年6月24日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1562年8月4日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on August 4, 1562 as the child of Gorosuke (Kiyotada) KATO, a blacksmith from Owari Province in Nakamura, Aichi-gun County (Aichi Prefecture) in Owari Province (present Nakamura Ward, Nagoya City).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on August 4, 1562 as the child of Gorosuke (Kiyotada) KATO, a blacksmith from Owari Province in Nakamura, Aichi County (Aichi Prefecture) in Owari Province (present Nakamura Ward, Nagoya City).</e>
<cmt>Aichi-gun→Aichi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>父は清正が幼いときに死去したが、母・伊都が豊臣秀吉の生母である大政所の従姉妹（あるいは遠縁の親戚）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While his father died in Kiyomasa&apos;s childhood, his mother Ito was one of the female cousins (or a distant relative) of Omandokoro (the mother of a Kanpaku), real mother of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While his father died in Kiyomasa&apos;s childhood, his mother Ito was one of the female cousins (or a distant relative) of Omandokoro (the mother of a Kanpaku), real mother of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>This is correctly translated but should probably be two sentences, and &quot;mother of a Kanpaku&quot; needs to be explained.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While his father died in Kiyomasa&apos;s childhood, his mother Ito was one of the female cousins (or a distant relative) of Omandokoro (Mother of the chief Adviser to the Emperor), biological mother of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>real→biologicalＮＣコメントに従い、大政所の説明を変更しました。用語集から別の表現を用いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのことから血縁関係にあった秀吉に仕え、天正4年（1576年）に170石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi, his blood kin for that reason and in 1576, given a stipend of 70 koku in crop yields.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason he served Hideyoshi as his blood kin and in 1576, was given a stipend of 70 koku in crop yields.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason he served Hideyoshi as his blood kin and in 1576, was given a stipend of 70 koku in crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>清正は秀吉の遠戚として将来を期待され、秀吉に可愛がられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa was expected as a promising relative of Hideyoshi and was treated kindly by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a promising relative, Kiyomasa&apos;s growth was anticipated by Hideyoshi, who treated him kindly.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a promising relative, Kiyomasa&apos;s growth was anticipated by Hideyoshi, who treated him kindly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>清正もこれに応え、生涯忠義を尽くし続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa continued to show loyalty to Hideyoshi throughout his life to reciprocate Hideyoshi&apos;s mentorship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa continued to show loyalty to Hideyoshi throughout his life to reciprocate Hideyoshi&apos;s mentorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa continued to show loyalty to Hideyoshi throughout his life to reciprocate Hideyoshi&apos;s mentorship.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>豊臣家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His days as a retainer of the Toyotomi family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His days as a retainer of the Toyotomi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His days as a retainer of the Toyotomi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>天正10年（1582年）に織田信長が死去すると、清正は秀吉に従って同年の山崎の戦いに参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga ODA died in 1582, Kiyomasa followed Hideyoshi and participated in the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga ODA died in 1582, Kiyomasa followed Hideyoshi and participated in the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga ODA died in 1582, Kiyomasa followed Hideyoshi and participated in the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天正11年（1583年）の賤ヶ岳の戦いでは敵将・山路正国を討ち取るという武功を挙げ、秀吉より「賤ヶ岳の七本槍」の一人として3,000石の所領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, he distinguished himself by defeating Masakuni YAMAJI, the enemy general, for which he was given by Hideyoshi a territory of 2,000 koku in crop yields as one of the Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, he distinguished himself by defeating Masakuni YAMAJI, the enemy general, for which Hideyoshi gave him a territory of 2,000 koku in crop yields as one of the Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, he distinguished himself by defeating Masakuni YAMAJI, the enemy general, for which Hideyoshi gave him a territory of 3,000 koku in crop yields as one of the Shizugatake-no-shichihon-yari.</e>
<cmt>ウェブで確認し、「賤ヶ岳の戦い」を「賤ヶ岳の七本槍」部分から削除しました。2,000→3,000</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>天正13年（1585年）7月、秀吉が関白に就任すると同時に従五位、主計頭に叙任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Hideyoshi having filled the position of Kanpaku in July 1585, Kiyomasa was raised to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed Shukeiryo (Account Office).</e>
<cmt>「天正13年7月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1585年7月27日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Hideyoshi having taken the position of Kanpaku in July 1585, Kiyomasa was raised to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed Shukeiryo (Accounts Office).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Hideyoshi having taken the position of Kanpaku in July 1585, Kiyomasa was raised to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed Kazue no kami (the head of budget bureau).</e>
<cmt>「主計寮」をウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに「主計頭」と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天正14年（1586年）からは秀吉の九州征伐に従い、肥後国に入った佐々成政が失政により改易されると肥後の半国のおよそ19万5,000石を与えられ、熊本城を居城とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1586, Kiyomasa followed Hideyoshi in an expedition against Kyushu and when Narimasa SASSA who entered into Higo Province was punished by being deprived of his fief due to his misgovernment, Kiyomasa was given about 195,000 koku, half of Higo Province and made the Kumamoto-jo Castle his castle where he usually resided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1586, Kiyomasa followed Hideyoshi in an expedition against Kyushu and when Narimasa SASSA, who entered Higo Province, was punished by being deprived of his fief due to his misgovernment, Kiyomasa was given about 195,000 koku, half of Higo Province, and made Kumamoto-jo Castle his castle where he usually resided.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1586, Kiyomasa followed Hideyoshi in an expedition against Kyushu and when Narimasa SASSA, who entered Higo Province, was punished by being deprived of his fief due to his misgovernment, Kiyomasa was given about 195,000 koku, half of Higo Province, and made Kumamoto-jo Castle his castle where he usually resided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このとき、肥後半国と讃岐国とどちらかを選べと言われ、肥後を選んだという逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an anecdote that when he was ordered to choose between half of Higo Province and Sanuki Province, he chose Higo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote which relates that when he was ordered to choose between half of Higo Province and Sanuki Province, he chose Higo.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote which relates that when he was ordered to choose between half of Higo Province and Sanuki Province, he chose Higo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>肥後における治績は良好で、田麦を特産品化し南蛮貿易の決済に当てるなど、世に知られた治水以外に商業政策でも優れた手腕を発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His administration in Higo was a great success, more especially, he exhibited his remarkable ability, other than the well-known flood control, in such commercial policy as making wheat a local specialty and using it for settlement of the trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>「田麦」は、広辞苑、サイトでも見つからず、新和英大辞典第５版　「〔小麦〕 wheat」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His administration in Higo was a great success, and in particular he exhibited his remarkable ability, beyond the well-known flood control, in commercial policies such as making wheat a local specialty and using it to settle trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His administration in Higo was a great success, and in particular he exhibited his remarkable ability, beyond the well-known flood control, in commercial policies such as making wheat a local specialty and using it to settle trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>文禄元年（1592年）からの文禄・慶長の役では、李氏朝鮮へ出兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Bunroku-Keicho War which started in 1592, he sent troops to the Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Bunroku-Keicho War which started in 1592, he sent troops to Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Bunroku-Keicho War which started in 1592, he sent troops to Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>文禄の役では二番隊主将となり鍋島直茂、相良頼房を傘下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Shusho (commander-in-chief) of the second squad in the Bunroku War and placed under his umbrella Naoshige NABESHIMA and Yorifusa SAGARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Shusho (commander-in-chief) of the second squad in the Bunroku War and placed Naoshige NABESHIMA and Yorifusa SAGARA under him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Shusho (commander-in-chief) of the second squad in the Bunroku War and placed Naoshige NABESHIMA and Yorifusa SAGARA under him.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>二番隊は一番隊の小西行長とは別路の先鋒であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second squad led the van on the different route from that of the first squad of Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second squad led the advance guard on a different route from that of Yukinaga KONISHI&apos;s first squad.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second squad led the advance guard on a different route from that of Yukinaga KONISHI&apos;s first squad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>4月17日の釜山上陸後は小西行長と漢城の攻略を競い、5月3日南大門から漢城に入城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After landing at Busan Metropolitan City on May 28, he competed with Yukinaga KONISHI for the capture of the capital, Seoul Special City and on June 12, entered into Hanseong from the Sung-Rye-Mun.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」「文禄元年4月17日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1592年5月28日」、「文禄元年5月3日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1592年6月12日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After landing at Busan Metropolitan City on May 28, he competed with Yukinaga KONISHI for the capture of the capital, Seoul Special City, and on June 12, he entered Hanseong via the Sung-Rye-Mun.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Seoul Special City is strange but I&apos;m not sure of the historical meaning here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After landing at Busan on May 28, he competed with Yukinaga KONISHI for the capture of the capital, Hanseong, and on June 12, he entered Hanseong via Nandai-mon gate (great south gate).</e>
<cmt>ソウル特別市→漢城釜山広域市→釜山崇礼門→南大門以上すべてウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>漢城攻略後は小西行長の一番隊や黒田長政の三番隊と共に北上し臨津江の戦いで金命元等の朝鮮軍を破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the capture of Hanseong, he went on northward with the first squad of Yukinaga KONISHI and the third squad of Nagamasa KURODA, and defeated the Korean troops of Kim Myeong-won in the Battle of Imjin River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the capture of Hanseong, he went on northward with the first squad of Yukinaga KONISHI and the third squad of Nagamasa KURODA, defeating the Korean troops of Kim Myeong-won in the Battle of Imjin River.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the capture of Hanseong, he went on northward with the first squad of Yukinaga KONISHI and the third squad of Nagamasa KURODA, defeating the Korean troops of Kim Myeong-won in the Battle of Imjin River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後黄海道金郊駅からは一番隊、三番隊とは別れ東北方向の咸鏡道に向かい海汀倉の戦いで韓克誠の朝鮮軍を破り、咸鏡道を平定、朝鮮二王子（臨海君・順和君）を生捕りにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After then his troops separated itself from the first squad and the third squad from Kinkoeki in Hwanghae Province, went in the northeastern direction to Hangyong Province, defeated the Korean troops of Kan Katsusei, subjugated Hangyong Province and captured two Korean princes (Prince Imhaegun and Prince Sunhwagun) alive.</e>
<cmt>「金郊駅」「韓克誠」は読みがサイトでも見つからず、日本語読みをローマ字化しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, his troops separated at Kinkoeki in Hwanghae Province into the first squad and the third squad, went in a northeastern direction to Hangyong Province, defeating the Korean troops of Kan Katsusei, subjugating Hangyong Province and capturing two Korean princes (Prince Imhaegun and Prince Sunhwagun) alive.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Not sure if translation is correct.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, his troops separated at Kinkoeki in Hwanghae Province from the first squad and the third squad, went in a northeastern direction to Hangyong Province, defeating the Korean troops of Kan Katsusei, subjugating Hangyong Province and capturing two Korean princes (Prince Imhaegun and Prince Sunhwagun) alive.</e>
<cmt>into→from</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>更には朝鮮の国境豆満江を越えてオランカイ（兀良哈・現在の中国東北部）へ進攻するなど数々の武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Kiyomasa distinguished himself in many actions including his advance to Orangkai (present Northeastern region of China) crossing the Korean border, the Tomanko River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Kiyomasa distinguished himself in many actions including his advance to Orangkai (present Northeastern region of China) crossing the Korean border, the Tomanko River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Kiyomasa distinguished himself in many actions including his advance to Orangkai (present northeastern region of China) crossing the Korean border, the Tomanko River.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除Northeastern→northeastern</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>文禄2年（1593年）6月の第二次晋州城の戦いで加藤軍は北面からの攻城を担当し、亀甲車を作り、配下の森本儀太夫、飯田覚兵衛が、黒田長政配下の後藤基次と一番乗りを競い城を陥落させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Second battle of the Jinju Castle in June 1593, the Kato troops took charge of attacking the castle from the north side and his followers, Gidayu MORIMOTO and Kakubei IIDA assembled a Kikkosha (an armored vehicle), on which they scrambled to be first in the van competing with Mototsugu GOTO, a follower of Nagamasa KURODA.</e>
<cmt>「文禄2年6月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1593年6月29日　」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the second battle of Jinju Castle in June 1593, the Kato troops took charge of attacking the castle from the north side, while his followers, Gidayu MORIMOTO and Kakubei IIDA, assembled a Kikkosha (an armored vehicle), on which they scrambled to be first in the advance guard, competing with Mototsugu GOTO, a follower of Nagamasa KURODA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the second battle of Jinju Castle in June 1593, the Kato troops took charge of attacking the castle from the north side, while his followers, Gidayu MORIMOTO and Kakubei IIDA, assembled a Kikkosha (an armored vehicle), on which they scrambled to be first in the advance guard, competing with Mototsugu GOTO, a follower of Nagamasa KURODA, and made the castle fall.</e>
<cmt>「城を陥落させた」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし交渉材料に朝鮮二王子を返還してしまうなど、慶長元年（1596年）、石田三成と明との和睦をめぐって意見の対立が生じ、それが元で秀吉の勘気を受けて一時は京都に戻される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, including the fact that he returned the two Korean princes as a bargaining chip during negotiations, he became confronted in 1596 with Mitsunari ISHIDAover a peace settlement with Ming, for which he incurred the displeasure of Hideyoshi and was returned to Kyoto at one time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in addition to the fact that he returned the two Korean princes as a bargaining chip during negotiations, he had a confrontation in 1596 with Mitsunari ISHIDA over a peace settlement with Ming, for which he incurred the displeasure of Hideyoshi and was temporarily brought back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in addition to the fact that he returned the two Korean princes as a bargaining chip during negotiations, he had a confrontation in 1596 with Mitsunari ISHIDA over a peace settlement with Ming, for which he incurred the displeasure of Hideyoshi and was temporarily brought back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>小西行長との対立も深刻化していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The confrontation between Kiyomasa and Yukinaga KONISHI had become intensified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The confrontation between Kiyomasa and Yukinaga KONISHI had become intensified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The confrontation between Kiyomasa and Yukinaga KONISHI had become intensified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>京から再び朝鮮に渡海する際、小西行長は明・朝鮮軍側に清正の上陸予想地点をに密かに知らせ、清正を討たせようとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they went from Kyoto to Korea crossing the sea, Yukinaga KONISHI secretly informed the Korean troops of the possible landing point of Kiyomasa for the Koreans to kill Kiyomasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they crossed the sea from Kyoto to Korea, Yukinaga KONISHI secretly informed the Korean troops of Kiyomasa&apos;s possible landing point so that they could kill him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they crossed the sea from Kyoto to Korea, Yukinaga KONISHI secretly informed the Korean troops of Kiyomasa&apos;s possible landing point so that they could kill him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>小西行長はこの件で明・朝鮮側から一定の信頼を得たが、行長はこれを逆手に取り、後に明・朝鮮軍をおびき出しだし打撃を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yukinaga KONISHI consequently earned some trust of the Ming and Korean sides, he took advantage of the situation and later lured the Ming and Korean troops out into the open and attacked them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yukinaga KONISHI earned some trust from the Ming and Korean sides due to this, he took advantage of the situation and later lured the Ming and Korean troops out into the open and attacked them.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yukinaga KONISHI earned some trust from the Ming and Korean sides due to this, he took advantage of the situation and later lured the Ming and Korean troops out into the open and attacked them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）からの慶長の役でも再び小西行長とは別路の先鋒となり、朝鮮軍の守る黄石山城を陥落させると、全羅道の道都全州を占領。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Keicho War from 1597, Kiyomasa again led the van on the different route from that of Yukinaga KONISHI. and after attacked the Hwangsoksan Castle into surrender, he occupied Chonju, the capital of Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Keicho War of 1597, Kiyomasa again led the advance guard on a different route from that of Yukinaga KONISHI and after he attacked the Hwangsoksan Castle and forced it to surrender, he occupied Chonju, the capital of Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Keicho War of 1597, Kiyomasa again led the advance guard on a different route from that of Yukinaga KONISHI and after he attacked the Hwangsoksan Castle and forced it to surrender, he occupied Chonju, the capital of Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>次に忠清道鎮川まで進出後に西生浦倭城‎に駐屯した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, after he advanced to Jincheon, Chungcheong Province, he stationed his troops in the Sosenpo Wajo (Japanese-style castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, after he advanced to Jincheon, Chungcheong Province, he stationed his troops in the Sosenpo Wajo (Japanese-style castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, after he advanced to Jincheon, Chungcheong Province, he stationed his troops in the Sosenpo Wajo (Japanese-style castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>日本側では西生浦倭城の東方に新たに浅野幸長や毛利家家臣・宍戸元続によって清正が縄張りをした蔚山倭城‎を築城し、完成後清正を守備につける予定（西生浦倭城‎には黒田長政を駐屯予定）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese side planned to newly construct by Yoshinaga ASANO and Mototsugu SHISHIDO, a retainer of the Mori family the Ulsan Japanese Castle at the place to the east of the Sosenpo Wajo where Kiyomasa set up Nawabari (castle plan; general term for the layout of a castle and its component structures) and assign Kiyomasa to defend the castle after completion (Nagamasa KURODA was planned to be stationed in the Sosenpo Wajo).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese side planned for Yoshinaga ASANO and Mototsugu SHISHIDO, a retainer of the Mori family, to newly construct the Ulsan Japanese Castle at a place to the east of the Sosenpo Wajo where Kiyomasa set up Nawabari (castle plan; general term for the layout of a castle and its component structures) and assign Kiyomasa to defend the castle after its completion (Nagamasa KURODA was planned to be stationed in the Sosenpo Wajo).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese side planned for Yoshinaga ASANO and Mototsugu SHISHIDO, a retainer of the Mori family, to newly construct the Ulsan Japanese Castle at a place to the east of the Sosenpo Wajo where Kiyomasa set up Nawabari (castle plan; general term for the layout of a castle and its component structures) and assign Kiyomasa to defend the castle after its completion (Nagamasa KURODA was planned to be stationed in the Sosenpo Wajo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、慶長2年（1597年）12月に完成間近の蔚山倭城への明の大軍が攻め寄せて蔚山城の戦いが始まると清正は急遽側近のみ500人ほどを率いて蔚山倭城に入城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in January 1598 when a large force of Ming attacked the Ulsan Japanese Castle approaching completion and the Battle of Ulsan started, Kiyomasa hastily entered the castle leading about 500 close followers.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」「慶長2年12月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1598年1月8日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in January 1598 when a large Ming force attacked the Ulsan Japanese Castle, which was approaching completion, and the Battle of Ulsan started, Kiyomasa hastily entered the castle, leading about 500 close followers.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in January 1598 when a large Ming force attacked the Ulsan Japanese Castle, which was approaching completion, and the Battle of Ulsan started, Kiyomasa hastily entered the castle, leading about 500 close followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>未完成で水も食糧も乏しい状況で明・朝鮮の大軍を防ぎきり、毛利秀元や黒田長政の援軍の到着まで城を守り抜いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa put out all the effort he could muster to defend the castle which was incomplete and short of water and food supply against the large force of Ming and Korea, and kept the castle defended until the arrival of reinforcements of Hidemoto MORI and Nagamasa KURODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa put out all the effort he could muster to defend the castle which was incomplete and short of water and food supply against large forces of Ming and Korean troops, and kept the castle defended until the arrival of reinforcements with Hidemoto MORI and Nagamasa KURODA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa put out all the effort he could muster to defend the castle which was incomplete and short of water and food supply against large forces of Ming and Korean troops, and kept the castle defended until the arrival of reinforcements with Hidemoto MORI and Nagamasa KURODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）9月にも再び蔚山倭城は攻撃を受けるがこれも撃退に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1598, the Ulsan Japanese Castle was attacked again, but the attack was successfully repelled.</e>
<cmt>「慶長3年9月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1598年10月1日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1598, the Ulsan Japanese Castle was attacked again, but the attack was successfully repelled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1598, the Ulsan Japanese Castle was attacked again, but the attack was successfully repelled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="37">
<j>清正は朝鮮の民衆から「犬、鬼（幽霊）上官」と恐れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa was feared by the Korean people as &apos;Dog, Oni (intrepid) (Yurei (ghost)) Jokan (superior officer).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa was feared by the Korean people as &apos;Dog, Oni (Yurei (ghost)) Jokan (superior officer).&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording. Not sure if these are two nicknames or if this is supposed to be one phrase… translation needs to be checked.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa was feared by the Korean people as &apos;Dog, Oni (Yurei (ghost)) Jokan (superior officer).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>なお、朝鮮出兵中にトラ退治をしたという伝承が残り、そこから虎拳という遊びの元になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is a tradition that Kiyomasa subjugated a tiger during his military service in Korea, from which a game called Toraken derived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is a traditional story which states that Kiyomasa subjugated a tiger during his military service in Korea, from which a game called Toraken was derived.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is a traditional story which states that Kiyomasa subjugated a tiger (tora) during his military service in Korea, from which a game called Toraken was derived.</e>
<cmt>虎が tiger であることを伝えないと虎拳がわからないので、括弧で加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>セロリを日本に持ち込んだとされており、セロリの異名の一つが「清正人参」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is understood to have brought celery into Japan and one of the Imyo (Nickname) of celery is &apos;Kiyomasa Ninjin&apos; (carrot).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is understood to have brought celery into Japan and one of the Imyo (nicknames) of celery is &apos;Kiyomasa Ninjin&apos; (Kiyomasa carrot).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is understood to have brought celery into Japan and one of the Imyo (nicknames) of celery is &apos;Kiyomasa Ninjin&apos; (Kiyomasa carrot).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原の戦いから江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Battle of Sekigahara to the Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Battle of Sekigahara to the Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Battle of Sekigahara to the Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）に秀吉が死去すると、五大老の徳川家康に接近し、家康の養女を継室として娶った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died in 1598, Kiyomasa approached Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, one of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) and he married an adopted daughter of Ieyasu as Keishitsu (second wife).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi died in 1598, Kiyomasa approached Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, one of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) and he married an adopted daughter of Ieyasu as Keishitsu (second wife).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died in 1598, Kiyomasa approached Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, one of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) and he married an adopted daughter of Ieyasu as the second wife.</e>
<cmt>Keishitsu は second wife のみで良いと考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>そして慶長4年（1599年）3月に前田利家が死去すると、福島正則や浅野幸長ら6将と共に石田三成暗殺未遂事件を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, after Toshiie MAEDA died in March 1599, Kiyomasa was involved in an attempted assassination of Mitsunari ISHIDA together with the six generals including Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Yoshinaga ASANO.</e>
<cmt>「慶長4年3月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1599年3月27日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, after Toshiie MAEDA died in March 1599, Kiyomasa was involved in an attempted assassination of Mitsunari ISHIDA along with six generals including Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Yoshinaga ASANO.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, after Toshiie MAEDA died in March 1599, Kiyomasa was involved in an attempted assassination of Mitsunari ISHIDA along with six generals including Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Yoshinaga ASANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この計画が失敗すると、さらに家康への接近を強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he failed in the plan, he further approached Ieyasu more closely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this scheme failed, he put even more effort into getting close to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this scheme failed, he put even more effort into getting close to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）に三成が家康に対して挙兵した関ヶ原の戦いでは九州に留まり、黒田孝高と共に家康ら東軍に協力して行長の宇土城、立花宗茂の柳川城などを開城、調略し、九州の西軍勢力を次々と破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Battle of Sekigahara in which Mitsunari raised armies against Ieyasu, Kiyomasa stayed in Kyushu and defeated the powers of the Western Camp in Kyushu one after another giving the Eastern Camp of Ieyasu supports together with Yoshitaka KURODA including the realization of surrender of the Uto-jo Castle of Yukinaga and the Yanagawa-jo Castle of Muneshige TACHIBANA with artifice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Battle of Sekigahara in which Mitsunari raised armies against Ieyasu, Kiyomasa stayed in Kyushu and defeated the powers of the Western Camp in Kyushu one after another, together with Yoshitaka KURODA giving the Eastern Camp of Ieyasu support, including the schemed surrenders of Uto-jo Castle of Yukinaga and Yanagawa-jo Castle of Muneshige TACHIBANA.</e>
<cmt>Wording; translation needs to be checked again for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Battle of Sekigahara in which Mitsunari raised armies against Ieyasu, Kiyomasa stayed in Kyushu and defeated the powers of the Western Camp in Kyushu one after another, together with Yoshitaka KURODA giving the Eastern Camp of Ieyasu support, including the schemed surrenders of Uto-jo Castle of Yukinaga and Yanagawa-jo Castle of Muneshige TACHIBANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>戦後の論功行賞で、肥後の行長旧領を与えられ52万石の大名となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the grant of honors after the war, Kiyomasa was given the former territory of Yukinaga in Higo Province and became a Daimyo of 520,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the granting of honors after the war, Kiyomasa was given the former territory of Yukinaga in Higo Province and became a Daimyo with 520,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Needs to be explained.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the granting of honors after the war, Kiyomasa was given the former territory of Yukinaga in Higo Province and became a Daimyo with 520,000 koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>なお、行長が居城とした宇土城は慶長17年（1612年）に破却されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Uto-jo Castle of Yukinaga was demolished in 1612.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Yukinaga&apos;s Uto-jo Castle was demolished in 1612.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Assuming that Yukinaga is a person</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Yukinaga&apos;s Uto-jo Castle was demolished in 1612.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="46">
<j>慶長10年（1605年）、従五位、侍従・肥後守に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1605, Kiyomasa was promoted to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed Jiju (a chamberlain) in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1605, Kiyomasa was promoted to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed Jiju (a chamberlain) in Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1605, Kiyomasa was promoted to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed Jiju (a chamberlain) and the governor of Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>ウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに　肥後国→肥後守　と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>慶長15年（1610年）、徳川氏による尾張国・名古屋城の普請に協力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1610, he cooperated in construction of the Nagoya-jo Castle by the Tokugawa clan in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1610, he cooperated in the Tokugawa clan&apos;s construction of Nagoya-jo Castle in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1610, he cooperated in the Tokugawa clan&apos;s construction of Nagoya-jo Castle in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>慶長16年（1611年）3月には二条城における家康と豊臣秀頼との会見を取り持つなど和解を斡旋したが、帰国途中の船内で発病し、6月24日に熊本で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1611, he exercised his good offices by mediating a meeting between Ieyasu and Hideyori TOYOTOMI in the Nijo-jo Castle, however, he became ill on the ship on his way back home and died on August 2, 1611 in Kumamoto.</e>
<cmt>「慶長16年3月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1611年4月13日」、「慶長16年6月24日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1611年8月2日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1611, he exercised his good offices by mediating a meeting between Ieyasu and Hideyori TOYOTOMI in Nijo-jo Castle, however, he became ill on the ship on his way back home and died on August 2, 1611 in Kumamoto.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1611, he exercised his good offices by mediating a meeting between Ieyasu and Hideyori TOYOTOMI in Nijo-jo Castle, however, he became ill on the ship on his way back home and died on August 2, 1611 in Kumamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>享年50（満49歳没）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 50 (49 if calculated in completed years)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 50 (49 if calculated in years completed).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 50 (49 if calculated in years completed).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="50">
<j>墓所は熊本市花園の発星山本妙寺の浄池廟、また山形県鶴岡市丸岡の金峰山天澤寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyards are Jochibyo at Hasseizan Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) in Hanazono, Kumamoto City and one at Kinposan Tentaku-ji Temple in Maruoka, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyards are Jochibyo at Hasseizan Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) in Hanazono, Kumamoto City, and one at Kinposan Tentaku-ji Temple in Maruoka, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyards are Jochibyo at Hasseizan Honmyo-ji Temple in Hanazono, Kumamoto City, and one at Kinposan Tentaku-ji Temple in Maruoka, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>（熊本市）はウェブで確認し、原文訳文から削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>さらに東京都港区白金台の最正山覚林寺（清正公）に位牌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, his Ihai (Ancestral tablet) is at Saishozan Kakurin-ji Temple (Seishoko) in Shiroganedai, Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>「最正山覚林寺（清正公）」の読みは下記サイトから引用しました。http://kkubota.cool.ne.jp/kakurinji.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, his Ihai (Ancestral tablet) is at Saishozan Kakurin-ji Temple (Seishoko) in Shiroganedai, Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, his Ihai (Ancestral tablet) is at Saishozan Kakurin-ji Temple (Seishoko) in Shiroganedai, Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>なおまた、東京都大田区の長栄山大国院本門寺（池上本門寺）に供養塔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, his memorial tower is located at Choeizan Daikokuin Honmon-ji Temple (Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple) in Ota Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>「長栄山大国院本門寺」の読みは、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://www.k-daihonzan.jp/html/02_01.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, his memorial tower is located at Choeizan Daikokuin Honmon-ji Temple (Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple) in Ota Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, his memorial tower is located at Choeizan Daikokuin Honmon-ji Temple (Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple) in Ota Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>奉斎神社は熊本市本丸鎮座の加藤神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosai-jinja Shrine dedicated to Kiyomasa is the Kato Shrine located in Honmaru, Kumamoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosai-jinja Shrine, dedicated to Kiyomasa, is the Kato Shrine located in Honmaru, Kumamoto City.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosai-jinja Shrine, dedicated to Kiyomasa, is the Kato-jinja Shrine located in Honmaru, Kumamoto City.</e>
<cmt>kato→Kato-jinja</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="54">
<j>清正の死後、家督は子の加藤忠広が継いだが、寛永9年（1632年）、忠広は幕府の命により改易になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Kiyomasa, his son Tadahiro KATO succeeded him. However, Tadahiro was deprived of his status by order of the Bakufu in 1632.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Kiyomasa, his son Tadahiro KATO succeeded him. However, Tadahiro was deprived of his status by order of the Bakufu in 1632.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Kiyomasa, his son Tadahiro KATO succeeded him; however, Tadahiro was deprived of his status by order of the Bakufu in 1632.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれていたため、一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>理由は諸説あるが、加藤家が豊臣氏恩顧の最有力大名だったためと警戒されたとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason is, though opinion is widely divided, said to have been the fact that the Kato family was one of the most influential Daimyo who received kind favors of the Toyotomi clan and so aroused the wariness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason, though opinion is widely divided, is said to have been the fact that the Kato family was one of the most influential Daimyo who received kind favors of the Toyotomi clan and so aroused suspicion.</e>
<cmt>Wording. (Suspicion among whom?)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason, though opinion is widely divided, is said to have been the fact that the Kato family was one of the most influential Daimyo who received kind favors of the Toyotomi clan and so aroused suspicion.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣコメントにありますが、なぜ「豊臣氏恩顧の有力大名だと警戒された」のか説明すると長くなるため追記していません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>清正は一般に智勇兼備の名将として知られているが、同時に藤堂高虎と並ぶ築城の名手としても知られ熊本城や名護屋城、蔚山倭城、江戸城、名古屋城など数々の城の築城に携わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kiyomasa is generally known as a great commander having both wisdom and courage, he is known as a master of castle construction to rank with Takatora TODO, and Kiyomasa was engaged in construction of many castles including Kumamoto Castle, Nagoya-jo Castle (Hizen Province), Ulsan Japanese Castle, Edo-jo Castle and Nagoya-jo Castle (Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>「名護屋城」 「名古屋城」を区別するため、原文にはありませんが、当時の国名をカッコ内に記入いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kiyomasa is generally known as a great commander having both wisdom and courage, he is also known as a master of castle construction to rank with Takatora TODO, and was engaged in the construction of many castles including Kumamoto Castle, Nagoya-jo Castle (Hizen Province), Ulsan Japanese Castle, Edo-jo Castle and Nagoya-jo Castle (Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kiyomasa is generally known as a great commander having both wisdom and courage, he is also known as a master of castle construction to rank with Takatora TODO, and was engaged in the construction of many castles including Kumamoto-jo Castle, Nagoya-jo Castle (Hizen Province), Ulsan Japanese Castle, Edo-jo Castle and Nagoya-jo Castle (Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>Kumamoto→Kumamoto-jo余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また飯田覚兵衛、大木土佐らと穴太衆を用いて領内の治水事業にも意欲的に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He actively worked on the flood-control in his territory together with Kakubei IIDA and Tosa OKI using Anoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He actively worked on flood-control in his territory along with Kakubei IIDA and Tosa OKI using Anoshu.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Anoshu needs to be explained.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He actively worked on flood-control in his territory along with Kakubei IIDA and Tosa OKI using Anoshu Guild.</e>
<cmt>Anoshu→Anoshu Guild</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>この結果、熊本県内には現在も清正による遺構が多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the fact, there are even today many Kiyomasa-involving ancient structural remnants in Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, there are many remains in Kumamoto Prefecture that Kiyomasa was involved with even today.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, there are many remains in Kumamoto Prefecture that Kiyomasa was involved with even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その土木技術は非常に優れており400年後の現在も実用として使われている遺構も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The civil engineering technology was so superb that there are many ancient structural remnants which have been in actual use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The civil engineering technology was so superb that there are many remains which are still being used in the present day, 400 years later.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Some parts of the translation were removed?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The civil engineering technology was so superb that there are many remains which are still being used in the present day, 400 years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>このとき清正は莫大な人手をまかなうため男女の別なく動員した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Kiyomasa mobilized workers irrespective of gender to secure enormous labor.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Kiyomasa mobilized workers irrespective of gender to secure an enormous labor force.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Kiyomasa mobilized workers irrespective of gender to secure an enormous labor force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>しかし、給金を払い必要以上の労役を課すことなく、事業の多くを農閑期に行う事によって農事に割く時間を確保したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he paid wages, did not assign more labor than needed to them and secured time for agricultural affairs by carrying out many of those projects in the farmers&apos; slack season.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he paid wages, did not assign more labor to them than needed, and secured time for agricultural affairs by carrying out many of his projects in the farmers&apos; slack season.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he paid wages, did not assign more labor to them than needed, and secured time for agricultural affairs by carrying out many of his projects in the farmers&apos; slack season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>清正は熱心な日蓮宗の信徒でもあり、領内に本妙寺をはじめとする日蓮宗の寺を数多く創設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa himself was a devout Nichiren Buddhist, who established in his territory many temples of the Nichiren sect of Buddhism including Honmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa himself was a devout Nichiren Buddhist, who established in his territory many temples of the Nichiren sect of Buddhism including Honmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa himself was a devout Nichiren Buddhist, who established in his territory many temples of the Nichiren sect of Buddhism including Honmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>そのほか、いわゆる「三振法（清正当時の呼称ではない）」を取り入れたことで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he is known by introducing so called &apos;Three strikes and you are out Law (That naming was not one at the time of Kiyomasa).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he is known for introducing the so-called &apos;Three strikes and you are out&apos; law (this naming was not used at the time of Kiyomasa).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he is known for introducing the so-called &apos;Three strikes and you are out&apos; law (this naming was not used at the time of Kiyomasa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これは武士のみが対象であったが、軽微な罪や式典で粗相を3回起こすと切腹を申し付けられるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That law applied only to Samurai (warriors), which provided that a Samurai be ordered to perform hara-kiri if he commit minor offenses or make blunders in ceremonies three times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That law applied only to Samurai (warriors) and required that a Samurai be ordered to perform hara-kiri if he commited minor offenses or made blunders in ceremonies three times.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That law applied only to Samurai (warriors) and required that a Samurai be ordered to perform Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) if he commited minor offenses or made blunders in ceremonies three times.</e>
<cmt>切腹を定訳に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>武将としては福島正則とともに豊臣氏配下の最有力の武将の一人で、正則とは親しかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a Busho, he was one of the most influential Busho to rank with Masanori FUKUSHIMA under the Toyotomi clan and is regarded to have been close to Masanori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That law applied only to Samurai (warriors) and required that a Samurai be ordered to perform hara-kiri if he commited minor offenses or made blunders in ceremonies three times.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That law applied only to Samurai (warriors) and required that a Samurai be ordered to perform hara-kiri if he commited minor offenses or made blunders in ceremonies three times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>石田三成とは豊臣政権下で文治派、武断派が形成されるにつれて関係が悪化し、小西行長とは朝鮮出兵の際に先鋒をめぐって争ったことや互いの領地が隣り合わせであったため常に境界線をめぐって争ったとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his relationship with Mitsunari ISHIDA became worse as the civilian government group and the military government group were gradually formed under the Toyotomi&apos;s government and his relationship with Yukinaga KONISHI was characterized by a scramble to be first in the van in the dispatch of troops to Korea and frequent conflicts over the borderline of their territories which were adjoining each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his relationship with Mitsunari ISHIDA became worse as the civilian government group and the military government group were gradually formed under the Toyotomi government, and his relationship with Yukinaga KONISHI was characterized by a scramble to be first in the advance guard in the dispatching of troops to Korea and by frequent conflicts over the borderline of their adjoining territories.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his relationship with Mitsunari ISHIDA became worse as the civilian government group and the military government group were gradually formed under the Toyotomi government, and his relationship with Yukinaga KONISHI was characterized by a scramble to be first in the advance guard in the dispatching of troops to Korea and by frequent conflicts over the borderline of their adjoining territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="67">
<j>体格は非常に大きく、6尺3寸（約191センチメートル）の大男だったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have been big in body build and about 191centimeters tall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have had a large body build and stood about 191centimeters tall.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have had a large body build and stood about 191centimeters tall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>だが実は5尺3寸（約161cm）にも満たない身長であったが、かぶる兜を長くして全体像を高く見せる事によって相手に威圧感を与えようとしていたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is a theory that he was in reality less than about 161 centimeters tall and he tried to intimidate others by showing his body taller wearing a longer warrior&apos;s helmet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is a theory that he was in reality less than 161centimeters tall and he tried to intimidate others with a show of a taller body by wearing an elongated warrior&apos;s helmet.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is a theory that he was in reality less than 161centimeters tall and he tried to intimidate others with a show of a taller body by wearing an elongated warrior&apos;s helmet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="69">
<j>熊本県（旧熊本藩）においては、「清正公（せいしょこ）さん」として現在も種々の史跡や祭りなどにも取りあげられているが、当時の肥後人の清正への崇敬も強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While there are various historic sites and festivals related to Kiyomasa as &apos;Seishoko-san&apos; in Kumamoto Prefecture (the former Kumamoto Domain) even today, Higo people at that time strongly revered Kiyomasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While there are various historic sites and festivals related to Kiyomasa as &apos;Seishoko-san&apos; in Kumamoto Prefecture (the former Kumamoto Domain) even today, Higo people at that time strongly revered Kiyomasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While there are various historic sites and festivals related to Kiyomasa as &apos;Seishoko-san&apos; in Kumamoto Prefecture (the former Kumamoto Domain) even today, Higo people at that time strongly revered Kiyomasa.</e>
<cmt>today の後で改行されていたようでしたので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>これはほとんどの大名が単に統治しただけとは対照的に、清正の熊本での事業ことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was due to Kiyomasa&apos;s undertakings in Kumamoto in contrast to the most of the daimyo who just ruled their territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was due to Kiyomasa&apos;s undertakings in Kumamoto in contrast to most of the daimyo, who just ruled their territories.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was due to Kiyomasa&apos;s undertakings in Kumamoto in contrast to most of the daimyo, who just ruled their territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>清正没後にほどなく加藤氏清正系加藤氏は改易されるが、肥後人の清正崇拝は細川氏肥後細川家（豊前小倉藩、肥後熊本藩主家）が豊前国小倉藩から転封してくる際にも衰えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Kiyomasa-line Kato clan was deprived of its fief, the reverence of Kiyomasa by the Higo people did not decline even at the time of the Higo Hosokawa family (the lord&apos;s family of the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province and the Kumamoto Domain in Higo Province) of the Hosokawa clan was transferred from the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Kiyomasa-line Kato clan was deprived of its fief, the reverence of Kiyomasa by the Higo people did not decline even at the time that the Higo Hosokawa family (the lord&apos;s family of the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province and the Kumamoto Domain in Higo Province) of the Hosokawa clan was transferred from Kokura Domain, Buzen Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording. A little hard to understand.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Kiyomasa-line Kato clan was deprived of its fief, the reverence of Kiyomasa by the Higo people did not decline even at the time that the Higo Hosokawa family (the lord&apos;s family of the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province and the Kumamoto Domain in Higo Province) of the Hosokawa clan was transferred from Kokura Domain, Buzen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>その人気を慮って、細川氏は清正の霊位を先頭にかざして入部し、藩主細川忠利は熊本城本丸に登り、清正の祀る廟所がある本妙寺 (熊本市)へ拝跪して「あなたのお城を預からせていただきます」と異例の所作をしたと云われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Hosokawa clan considered carefully the popularity of Kiyomasa and entered into the territory with a memorial tablet of Kiyomasa at the head of the procession, then the lord of the domain, Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA went up to the Honmaru of the Kumamoto-jo Castle, knelt down toward the Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) where the mausoleum dedicated to Kiyomasa was located and said &apos;Please let me look after your castle,&apos; which was an exceptional conduct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Hosokawa clan considered the popularity of Kiyomasa carefully and entered the territory with a memorial tablet of Kiyomasa at the head of the procession, after which the lord of the domain, Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, went up to the Honmaru of the Kumamoto-jo Castle, knelt down toward Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) where the mausoleum dedicated to Kiyomasa was located, and said &apos;Please let me look after your castle,&apos; which was exceptional conduct.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Hosokawa clan considered the popularity of Kiyomasa carefully and entered the territory with a memorial tablet of Kiyomasa at the head of the procession, after which the lord of the domain, Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, went up to the Honmaru of the Kumamoto-jo Castle, knelt down toward Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) where the mausoleum dedicated to Kiyomasa was located, and said &apos;Please let me look after your castle,&apos; which was exceptional conduct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>清正の熊本での事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Undertakings of Kiyomasa in Kumamoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Undertakings of Kiyomasa in Kumamoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Undertakings of Kiyomasa in Kumamoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>清正が肥後国を治めていたのは、天正15年（1587年）から慶長16年（1611年）の期間だが、朝鮮出兵等もあって実際に熊本に腰を据えていた期間は、実質延べ15年程である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kiyomasa ruled Higo Province from 1587 to 1611, he really settled down in Kumamoto substantially for a total of about 15 years due to the dispatch of troops to Korea and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kiyomasa ruled Higo Province from 1587 to 1611, he was really substantially settled in Kumamoto for a total of about 15 years due to the dispatch of troops to Korea and so on.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kiyomasa ruled Higo Province from 1587 to 1611, he was really substantially settled in Kumamoto for a total of about 15 years due to the dispatch of troops to Korea and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>清正以前の肥後は有力大名が現われず国人が割拠する時代が続き、佐々成政でさえも収拾できず荒廃していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Higo Province before Kiyomasa, no influential Daimyo appeared and the age of rival Kokujin (Local lord) continued, and even Narimasa SASSA was unable to get the situation under control leaving the province devastated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Higo Province before Kiyomasa, no influential Daimyo had appeared and the age of rival Kokujin (local lords) continued, and even Narimasa SASSA was unable to get the situation under control, leaving the province devastated.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Higo Province before Kiyomasa, no influential Daimyo had appeared and the age of rival Kokujin (local lords) continued, and even Narimasa SASSA was unable to get the situation under control, leaving the province devastated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>そんな中、清正は得意とする治水等の土木技術による生産量の増強を推し進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such a situation, Kiyomasa went ahead with a plan to increase production by civil engineering technology including the flood control which was Kiyomasa&apos;s strong point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a situation, Kiyomasa went ahead with a plan to increase production by civil engineering technology including flood control, which was his strong point.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a situation, Kiyomasa went ahead with a plan to increase production by civil engineering technology including flood control, which was his strong point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これらは主に農閑期に進められ、男女を問わず徴用されたが、これは一種の公共工事であり、給金も支払われた為みな喜んで協力したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although those engineering works were conducted mainly in the farmers&apos; slack season and workers were mobilized irrespective of gender, those were a kind of public works and wages were paid, therefore people were reportedly pleased to cooperate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although those engineering works were conducted mainly in the farmers&apos; slack season and workers were mobilized irrespective of gender, these were a type of public works and wages were paid, and therefore people were reportedly pleased to cooperate.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although those engineering works were conducted mainly in the farmers&apos; slack season and workers were mobilized irrespective of gender, these were a type of public works and wages were paid, and therefore people were reportedly pleased to cooperate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="77">
<j>「隈本（隅本とも）」という地名を｢熊本｣と改名した人は清正である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Kiyomasa who changed the place-name of &apos;Kumamoto&apos; (隈本(隅本)) to &apos;Kumamoto&apos; (熊本).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Kiyomasa who changed the place-name of &apos;Kumamoto&apos; (隈本(隅本)) to &apos;Kumamoto&apos; (熊本).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Kiyomasa who changed the place-name of &apos;Kumamoto&apos; (隈本[隅本]) to &apos;Kumamoto&apos; (熊本).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>「白川・坪井川大改修」以前は白川 (熊本県)と坪井川 (熊本県)は現在の熊本市役所付近で合流していたが、石塘を造り現在の流路に変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the &apos;Major improvement work for Shirakawa and Tsuboigawa,&apos; Shirakawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) and Tsuboigawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) used to merge at the area around the current City Hall of Kumamoto City, however, Kiyomasa changed the course of the rivers to the current one by building stone embankments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the &apos;Major improvement work for Shirakawa and Tsuboigawa,&apos; Shirakawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) and Tsuboigawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) used to merge at the area around the current City Hall of Kumamoto City; however, Kiyomasa changed the course of the rivers to the current one by building stone embankments.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the &apos;Major improvement work for Shirakawa and Tsuboigawa,&apos; Shira-kawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) and Tsuboi-gawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) used to merge at the area around the current City Hall of Kumamoto City; however, Kiyomasa changed the course of the rivers to the current one by building stone embankments.</e>
<cmt>川名を　-kawa に訂正余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>熊本4大河川改修。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He conducted Improvement works for the four major rivers in Kumamoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He conducted improvement works for the four major rivers in Kumamoto.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He conducted improvement works for the four major rivers in Kumamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>菊池川の付替、緑川の鵜の瀬堰、球磨川の遥拝堰、白川に於ける各種改修等。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They included replacement of Kikuchigawa River, a dam for cormorant fishing on Midorikawa River, a dam for worshipping from a distance on Kumagawa River and several improvement works on Shirakawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They included the replacement of Kikuchigawa River, a dam for cormorant fishing on Midorikawa River, a dam for worshipping from a distance on Kumagawa River and several improvement works on Shirakawa River.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They included the replacement of Kikuchi-gawa River, a dam for cormorant fishing on Midori-kawa River, a dam for worshipping from a distance on Kuma-gawa River and several improvement works on Shira-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>川名を　-kawa に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="81">
<j>熊本平野・八代平野の干拓と堤防の整備。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He conducted reclamation and improvement of banks in the Kumamoto Plain and the Yatsushiro Plain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He conducted reclamation and improvement of banks in the Kumamoto Plain and the Yatsushiro Plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He conducted reclamation and improvement of banks in the Kumamoto Plain and the Yatsushiro Plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="82">
<j>白川水系の主に熊本平野への灌漑事業に於ける、非常に実験的な用水技術（馬場楠井手）等。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He adopted a remarkably experimental technology for irrigation channels (Babakusu no Ide) in the irrigation works for the Shirakawa River system, mainly to the Kumamoto Plain.</e>
<cmt>「馬場楠井手」については、下記サイトを参照しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%A6%AC%E5%A0%B4%E6%A5%A0%E4%BA%95%E6%89%8B</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He adopted a remarkably experimental technology for irrigation channels (Babakusu no Ide) in the irrigation works for the Shirakawa River system, mainly to the Kumamoto Plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He adopted a remarkably experimental technology for irrigation channels (Babakusu no Ide) in the irrigation works for the Shira-kawa River system, mainly to the Kumamoto Plain.</e>
<cmt>川名を　-kawa に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="83">
<j>なお、現在の堀川 (熊本県)は加藤忠広が着工し、細川忠利で完了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the current Horikawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) for which a canal-cutting work was started by Tadahiro KATO and completed by Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>「堀川」については、下記サイトを参照しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%A0%80%E5%B7%9D_(%E7%86%8A%E6%9C%AC%E7%9C%8C)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the current Horikawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) had canal-cutting work started by Tadahiro KATO and completed by Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the current Hori-kawa River (Kumamoto Prefecture) had canal-cutting work started by Tadahiro KATO and completed by Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>川名を　-kawa に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>白川と坪井川を結ぶ農業用水路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an irrigation channel connecting Shirakawa River with Tsuboigawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an irrigation channel connecting Shirakawa River with Tsuboigawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an irrigation channel connecting Shira-kawa River with Tsuboi-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>川名を　-kawa に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>清正の亡き後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kiyomasa&apos;s death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kiyomasa&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kiyomasa&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>細川家による統治が始まるも、人民の人気は遂に｢せいしょこさん｣＝清正公を超える事はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Hosokawa family started to rule the province, the popularity of the family among people never surpassed that of &apos;Seishoko.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Hosokawa family started to rule the province, the popularity of the family among the people never surpassed that of &apos;Seishoko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Hosokawa family started to rule the province, the popularity of the family among the people never surpassed that of &apos;Seishoko-san.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Seishoko→Seishoko-san「＝清正」は訳出不要と考えられたと解釈しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>それは今の、官と民との逆転現象と言えよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation can be said to have been a reversal phenomenon of the present order of the bureaucracy and the private sector.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This could be described in modern terms as a reversal phenomenon of the private and public sectors.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This could be described in modern terms as a reversal phenomenon of the private and public sectors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>豪農は開拓し富を蓄え新規開拓に励む一方、細川氏は｢肥後の貧乏な殿様」と蔑まれ、踏み倒した証文も少なくないという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the wealthy farmers developed lands, accumulated wealth and strove for new developments, the Hosokawa clan is said to have been held in contempt as &apos;Poor Tonosama (feudal lord) in Higo&apos; and to have left many of its debts unpaid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the wealthy farmers developed lands, accumulated wealth and strove for new developments, the Hosokawa clan is said to have been held in contempt as &apos;Poor Tonosama (feudal lord) in Higo&apos; and to have left many of its debts unpaid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the wealthy farmers developed lands, accumulated wealth and strove for new developments, the Hosokawa clan is said to have been held in contempt as &apos;Poor Tonosama (feudal lord) in Higo&apos; and to have left many of its debts unpaid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>名門細川氏は遂に肥後に於いて、強権を振るう事無く、前任者の亡霊におびやかし続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A distinguished family, the Hosokawa clan, after all, continued to be made uneasy about the ghost of the predecessor, without asserting ultimate authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a distinguished family, the Hosokawa clan continued to be made uneasy after all by the ghost of their predecessor, without asserting any ultimate authority.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a distinguished family, the Hosokawa clan continued to be made uneasy after all by the ghost of their predecessor, without asserting any ultimate authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>一方で、通潤橋のような農民発議での開発が着々と進行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, developments progressed steadily under such proposal by peasants as Tsujunkyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, developments progressed steadily through the proposals by peasants as Tsujunkyo.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, developments progressed steadily through the proposals by peasants as Tsujun-kyo Blridge.</e>
<cmt>Tsujunkyo→Tsujun-kyo Bridge</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>子供のころからの竹馬の友として森本儀太夫と飯田覚兵衛がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He knew Gidayu MORIMOTO and Kakubei IIDA since they were boys together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He knew Gidayu MORIMOTO and Kakubei IIDA since they were boys together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He knew Gidayu MORIMOTO and Kakubei IIDA since they were boys together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>ある日、剣の試合をして勝ったものが主君になり、負けたものが家来になるという約束をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, they agreed that a winner became a lord and a loser became a retainer in a Kendo (swordsmanship) match.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, they agreed that the winner in a Kendo (swordsmanship) match would become a lord and the loser a retainer.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, they agreed that the winner in a Kendo (swordsmanship) match would become a lord and the loser a retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>清正が勝ち、その約束は守られ、二人は清正の両腕として信頼される主従関係を結び続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa won and the agreement was kept, and the two friends of his continued to have a trustworthy master-servant relationship with Kiyomasa as trusted assistants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa won and the agreement was kept, and his two friends continued to have a trustworthy master-servant relationship with Kiyomasa as his trusted assistants.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa won and the agreement was kept, and his two friends continued to have a trustworthy master-servant relationship with Kiyomasa as his trusted assistants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>口の中に拳を入れる事ができたという逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote that he was able to put his fist into his mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote which relates that he was able to put his fist into his mouth.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote which relates that he was able to put his fist into his mouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>その話を聞いた新選組局長・近藤勇も憧れていた清正にあやかり、真似をして拳を口に入れていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Isami KONDO, the leader of the Shinsengumi (literally, the newly selected corps, referring to a special police force for the Tokugawa regime) came to know the anecdote, he is said to have put his fist into his mouth after the manner of Kiyomasa whom Isami KONDO admired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Isami KONDO, the leader of the Shinsengumi (literally, the newly selected corps, referring to a special police force for the Tokugawa regime) came to know of this anecdote, he is said to have put his fist into his mouth after the manner of Kiyomasa, whom he admired.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Isami KONDO, the leader of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) came to know of this anecdote, he is said to have put his fist into his mouth after the manner of Kiyomasa, whom he admired.</e>
<cmt>新撰組を定訳に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>平時でも常に腰に米3升と味噌、銀銭300文を入れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He always carried even in peacetime three Sho of rice, Miso (Bean paste) and 300 Mon of silver coins at his side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in peacetime, he always carried three Sho of rice, Miso (Bean paste) and 300 Mon of silver coins with him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in peacetime, he always carried three sho (about 5.4 liters) of rice, Miso (Bean paste) and 300 mon of silver coins with him.</e>
<cmt>Sho→sho (about 5.4 liters)Mon→mon</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>ある時親友の福島正則が「それでは腰が重いだろうが」と述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one time, when his close friend, Masanori FUKUSHIMA said to him, &apos;They are heavy on your side, aren&apos;t they?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one time, his close friend, Masanori FUKUSHIMA, said to him, &apos;They are heavy on your side, aren&apos;t they?&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one time, his close friend, Masanori FUKUSHIMA, said to him, &apos;They are heavy on your side, aren&apos;t they?&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除原文を訳文に合わせて、「わたしだってかくるしたい。　を次の文に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>「わしだって軽くしたい。だが、わしがこうしていれば家臣も見習い、常に戦時の備えを怠らないだろう」と答えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To that remarks, Kiyomasa is said to have replied, &apos;I myself want it light, but if I wear these like this, my retainers follow suit and never fail to be always prepared for a battle.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To that remark, Kiyomasa is said to have replied, &apos;I myself want it light, but if I wear these like this, my retainers follow suit and never fail to be prepared for a battle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To that remark, Kiyomasa is said to have replied, &apos;I myself want it light, but if I wear these like this, my retainers follow suit and never fail to be prepared for a battle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>また、平時に腰兵糧をつけるのを忘れた小姓を怠慢であるとして免職にしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he said to have dismissed a page who forgot to carry army provisions on his side in peacetime accusing him of negligence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he said to have dismissed a page who forgot to carry army provisions on his side in peacetime, accusing him of negligence.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he is said to have dismissed a page who forgot to carry army provisions on his side in peacetime, accusing him of negligence.</e>
<cmt>said→is said</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="99">
<j>清正は朝鮮出兵で三成と対立し、それが原因で秀吉から京に召還された後、伏見に蟄居させられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa conflicted with Mitsunari over the dispatch of troops to Korea, as a result of which he was summoned home to Kyoto by Hideyoshi and placed under house arrest in Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa conflicted with Mitsunari over the dispatch of troops to Korea, as a result of which he was summoned home to Kyoto by Hideyoshi and placed under house arrest in Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa conflicted with Mitsunari over the dispatch of troops to Korea, as a result of which he was summoned home to Kyoto by Hideyoshi and placed under house arrest in Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>しかし慶長元年（1596年）、伏見大地震が起こって秀吉がいた伏見城が倒壊したとき、清正は300人の手勢を率いていち早く秀吉のもとに駆けつけ、警護を務めたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the Fushimi Great Earthquake occurred in 1596 and the Fushimi-jo Castle where Hideyoshi lived was collapsed, Kiyomasa is said to have quickly hurried to Hideyoshi with a party of 300 soldiers under his command and acted as escort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the Great Fushimi Earthquake occurred in 1596 and Fushimi-jo Castle where Hideyoshi lived collapsed, Kiyomasa is said to have quickly hurried to Hideyoshi with a party of 300 soldiers under his command and acted as escort.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the Great Fushimi Earthquake occurred in 1596 and Fushimi-jo Castle where Hideyoshi lived collapsed, Kiyomasa is said to have quickly hurried to Hideyoshi with a party of 300 soldiers under his command and acted as escort.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>蟄居身分でありながら、これは秀吉の許しもなく駆けつけたものであり一つ間違えれば切腹となるところだったが、秀吉は清正の忠義を賞賛して朝鮮での罪を許したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regardless of his status of being confined to his house, Kiyomasa hurried to Hideyoshi without the latter&apos;s permission, which could have made him ordered to commit hara-kiri if there was the slightest mistake, however, Hideyoshi is said to have forgiven Kiyomasa for his fault in Korea praising his loyalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regardless of his status of being confined to his house, Kiyomasa hurried to Hideyoshi without the latter&apos;s permission, which could have had him ordered to commit hara-kiri if there was the slightest mistake,; however, Hideyoshi is said to have forgiven Kiyomasa for his fault in Korea, praising his loyalty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regardless of his status of being confined to his house, Kiyomasa hurried to Hideyoshi without the latter&apos;s permission, which could have had him ordered to commit seppuku if there was the slightest mistake; however, Hideyoshi is said to have forgiven Kiyomasa for his fault in Korea, praising his loyalty.</e>
<cmt>,;→;hara-kiri→seppuku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>これにより、清正は「地震加藤」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the fact, Kiyomasa was called &apos;Earthquake Kato.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, Kiyomasa was called &apos;Earthquake Kato.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, Kiyomasa was called &apos;Earthquake Kato.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="103">
<j>清正は豊臣氏への忠義を終生忘れなかったが、家康を恐れその天下も認めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kiyomasa never forgot his loyalty to the Toyotomi clan for life, he admitted the ruling power of Ieyasu who frightened him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kiyomasa never forgot his lifelong loyalty to the Toyotomi clan, he recognized the ruling power of Ieyasu, who frightened him.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Not sure if this is the best translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kiyomasa never forgot his lifelong loyalty to the Toyotomi clan, he recognized the ruling power of Ieyasu, who frightened him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>朋友の正則が家康の子・徳川義直が入る尾張名古屋城の普請を命じられたとき、「大御所の息子の城普請まで手伝わなければならないのか」と愚痴をこぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his friend Masanori was ordered to construct the Nagoya-jo Castle in Owari Province for Yoshinao TOKUGAWA, a child of Ieyasu, he grumbled, &apos;Why should I give help even to construct a castle for a son of Ogosho?&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his friend Masanori was ordered to construct Nagoya-jo Castle in Owari Province for Yoshinao TOKUGAWA, a child of Ieyasu, he grumbled, &apos;Why should I give my help to even construct a castle for a son of Ogosho?&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his friend Masanori was ordered to construct Nagoya-jo Castle in Owari Province for Yoshinao TOKUGAWA, a child of Ieyasu, he grumbled, &apos;Why should I give my help to even construct a castle for a son of Ogosho (Ieyasu)?&apos;</e>
<cmt>Ogosho だけではわからないと思い、Ogosho (Ieyasu) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>これに対して清正は「嫌なら領国に帰って戦準備をしろ」と告げたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To that, Kiyomasa is said to have advised, &apos;If you don&apos;t like it, then go back to your province and prepare for battles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To that, Kiyomasa is said to have advised, &apos;If you don&apos;t like it, then go back to your province and prepare for battles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To that, Kiyomasa is said to have advised, &apos;If you don&apos;t like it, then go back to your province and prepare for battles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="106">
<j>徳川時代になって戦国の気風が謀反の心として警戒されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Tokugawa period started, the militaristic spiritcame to be suspected as intention of a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Tokugawa period started, the militaristic spirit came to be suspected as intention of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Tokugawa period started, the militaristic spirit came to be suspected as intention of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>そして、大名たちに髭を剃ることが流行りだしたとき家康は家臣に命じて清正に聞きに行かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, when it became trendy to shave off their whiskers among Daimyo, Ieyasu ordered a retainer to visit Kiyomasa and to hear his intention.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And then, when it became trendy among Daimyo to shave off their whiskers, Ieyasu ordered a retainer to visit Kiyomasa and to hear his intention.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And then, when it became trendy among Daimyo to shave off their whiskers, Ieyasu ordered a retainer to visit Kiyomasa and to hear his intention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>貴殿も剃られてはいかがかと勧められたのに対して「鎧の頬あてに髭があたる感覚が心地よいので」と断ったことから、骨のある武将との評判がたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To an advice for him to shave off his whiskers, Kiyomasa declined it saying, &apos;I feel comfortable when my whiskers touch the cheek protector of my armor&apos;, by which he came to be seen as a staunch Busho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the recommendation for him to shave off his whiskers, Kiyomasa declined, saying, &apos;I feel comfortable when my whiskers touch the cheek protector of my armor&apos;, by which he came to be seen as a staunch Busho.</e>
<cmt>Wording. I think &quot;beard&quot; might be better than &quot;whiskers&quot; in these passages.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To the recommendation for him to shave off his whiskers, Kiyomasa declined, saying, &apos;I feel comfortable when my beard touch the cheek protector of my armor&apos;, by which he came to be seen as a staunch Busho.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除ＮＣコメントどおり、&quot;beard&quot; と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="109">
<j>晩年は豊臣家への恩義と自家の徳川政権での存続に心を悩ませた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, he was deeply troubled over his moral obligation toward the Toyotomi family and his survival in the Tokugawa government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, he was deeply troubled over his moral obligation toward the Toyotomi family and his survival in the Tokugawa government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, he was deeply troubled over his moral obligation toward the Toyotomi family and his survival in the Tokugawa government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>そのためか、論語に朱で書き込みをして読み込むほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due probably to that, he read deeply the Rongo (Analects of Confucius) even writing in cinnabar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Probably due to this, he deeply studied the Rongo (Analects of Confucius), even writing in cinnabar.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Probably due to this, he deeply studied the Rongo (Analects of Confucius), even writing in cinnabar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>徳川と豊臣の雲行きが怪しいなか、大坂からの船旅の中、清正の飼っていた猿が真似をして彼の論語の本に朱筆で落書きをしたのを見て「お前も聖人の教えが知りたいか」と嘆じたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While things didn&apos;t look too good in the relationship between Tokugawa and Toyotomi, he is said to have lamented saying to his pet monkey, &apos;Would you like to learn the teachings of Confucius, too?&apos; when he saw the monkey scribbled in his Rongo book in red imitating him during a boat trip from Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While things didn&apos;t look too good in the relationship between Tokugawa and Toyotomi, he is said to have lamented by saying to his pet monkey, &apos;Would you like to learn the teachings of Confucius, too?&apos; when he saw the monkey scribbling in his Rongo book in red imitating him during a boat trip from Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While things didn&apos;t look too good in the relationship between Tokugawa and Toyotomi, he is said to have lamented by saying to his pet monkey, &apos;Would you like to learn the teachings of Confucius, too?&apos; when he saw the monkey scribbling in his Rongo book in red imitating him during a boat trip from Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="112">
<j>清正が肥後北部24万石を治めていた頃、小西行長の領地・天草で豪族の反乱が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kiyomasa ruled a territory of 240,000 koku crop yields in the northern part of Higo Province, a rebellion led by the local powerful families occurred in Amakusa, the territory of Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kiyomasa ruled a territory of 240,000 koku crop yields in the northern part of Higo Province, a rebellion led by powerful local families occurred in Amakusa, the territory of Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kiyomasa ruled a territory of 240,000 koku crop yields in the northern part of Higo Province, a rebellion led by powerful local families occurred in Amakusa, the territory of Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>その援軍に向かった時、反乱軍でも武勇知られた木山弾正という豪傑と一騎打ちになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his troops participated in the battle to lend a hand, he engaged in single combat with a well-known heroic figure, Danjo KIYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his troops participated in the battle to lend a hand, he engaged in single combat with a well-known heroic figure, Danjo KIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his troops participated in the battle to lend a hand, he engaged in single combat with a well-known heroic figure, Danjo KIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>相手は弓の使い手で、矢を射ようとしたために清正は「一騎打ちなれば、正々堂々打ち物（太刀）で勝負」と声を掛けて、手にしていた槍をその場で投げ捨てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Danjo, an expert archer was going to shoot an arrow, Kiyomasa said, &apos;This is a one-on-one combat, so let us fight openly and squarely by swords&apos; and instantly threw away the spear he held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Danjo, an expert archer, was going to shoot an arrow, Kiyomasa said, &apos;This is one-on-one combat, so let us fight openly and fairly with swords&apos; and instantly threw away the spear he held.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Danjo, an expert archer, was going to shoot an arrow, Kiyomasa said, &apos;This is one-on-one combat, so let us fight openly and fairly with swords&apos; and instantly threw away the spear he held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>これを見た弾正も弓を捨てたところ、清正はすかさず槍を拾いあげて突きかかり、討ち取ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danjo saw it and also threw away his bow, then Kiyomasa immediately picked up his spear, attacked and defeated his opponent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danjo saw it and also threw away his bow, then Kiyomasa immediately picked up his spear, attacked and defeated his opponent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danjo saw it and also threw away his bow, then Kiyomasa immediately picked up his spear, attacked and defeated his opponent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="116">
<j>同じくこの反乱の際、反乱勢の籠もる志岐城に和平の使者を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in that rebellion, Kiyomasa sent a messenger to the rebels holding the Shiki-jo Castle for a peace talk</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that same rebellion, Kiyomasa sent a messenger to the rebels holding Shiki-jo Castle for a peace talk.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that same rebellion, Kiyomasa sent a messenger to the rebels holding Shiki-jo Castle for a peace talk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>志岐城側が出迎えの衆を寄越すと、これに突然襲い掛かって皆殺しにし、してやったりとして陣を敷いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Shiki-jo Castle side sent a group of soldiers to receive the Kiyomasa&apos;s representatives, Kiyomasa&apos;s troops suddenly attacked and massacred them, and took up a position giving a gleeful chuckle.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Shiki-jo Castle side sent a group of soldiers to receive Kiyomasa&apos;s representatives, Kiyomasa&apos;s troops suddenly attacked and massacred them, and took up a position giving a gleeful chuckle.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Shiki-jo Castle side sent a group of soldiers to receive Kiyomasa&apos;s representatives, Kiyomasa&apos;s troops suddenly attacked and massacred them, and took up a position giving a gleeful chuckle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="118">
<j>木山弾正の遺児は横手五郎と名乗り怪力が自慢であったが、熊本城築城の人夫となり敵討ちの機会をねらっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A bereaved child of Danjo KIYAMA called himself Goro YOKOTE and was proud of his phenomenal strength, and was watching for an opportunity to take revenge for his father&apos;s death working as a laborer in the construction site of the Kumamoto-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bereaved child of Danjo KIYAMA who called himself Goro YOKOTE and was proud of his phenomenal strength, was watching for an opportunity to take revenge for his father&apos;s death working as a laborer in the construction site of Kumamoto-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bereaved child of Danjo KIYAMA who called himself Goro YOKOTE and was proud of his phenomenal strength, was watching for an opportunity to take revenge for his father&apos;s death working as a laborer in the construction site of Kumamoto-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>しかし、これに気付いた清正によって城内の井戸の中の作業をしているときに石・砂を投げ込まれ生き埋めにされたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Goro is said to have been buried alive by throwing stones and sands into a well in the castle in which he was working, by Kiyomasa who came to know his intention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Goro is said to have been buried alive by Kiyomasa, who came to know his plan, throwing stones and sand into a well in the castle in which he was working.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Goro is said to have been buried alive by Kiyomasa, who came to know his plan, throwing stones and sand into a well in the castle in which he was working.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>しかしこの逸話には諸説あり、清正に認められ、忠実な家臣になったと言う逸話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are various theories, one of which is an anecdote that Goro was accepted by Kiyomasa and became his loyal retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are various theories, one of which is an anecdote that Goro was accepted by Kiyomasa and became his loyal retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are various theories, one of which is an anecdote that Goro was accepted by Kiyomasa and became his loyal retainer.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>彼が運んだと伝わる「首掛け石」という凹型の巨石が城内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a huge concave-shaped stone called &apos;Kubikakeishi&apos; in the castle which is said to have been carried by him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a huge concave-shaped stone called &apos;Kubikakeishi&apos; in the castle which is said to have been carried by him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a huge concave-shaped stone called &apos;Kubikakeishi&apos; in the castle which is said to have been carried by him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>死因</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cause of death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cause of death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cause of death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>清正の死因は『当代記』によれば腎虚（花柳病）とされているが、唐瘡（梅毒）説や家康またはその一派による毒殺説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the cause of Kiyomasa&apos;s death is understood to have been emaciation due to sexual overindulgence (venereal disease) according to &quot;Todaiki&quot; (a famous chronicle describing the Early Modern age), some say it was Togasa (syphilis) and some say it was murder by poisoning by Ieyasu or his followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the cause of Kiyomasa&apos;s death is understood to have been emaciation due to sexual overindulgence (venereal disease) according to &quot;Todaiki&quot; (a famous chronicle describing the Early Modern age), some say it was Togasa (syphilis) and some say it was murder by poisoning by Ieyasu or his followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the cause of Kiyomasa&apos;s death is understood to have been emaciation due to sexual overindulgence (venereal disease) according to &quot;Todaiki&quot; (a famous chronicle describing the Early Modern age), some say it was Togasa (syphilis) and some say it was murder by poisoning by Ieyasu or his followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>また清正の死から2年後の慶長18年（1613年）、豊臣氏恩顧の最有力大名であった浅野幸長も同じく花柳病で死去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1613, two years after the death of Kiyomasa, Yoshinaga ASANO, one of the most influential Daimyo under the patronage of the Toyotomi clan also died of venereal disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1613, two years after the death of Kiyomasa, Yoshinaga ASANO, one of the most influential Daimyo under the patronage of the Toyotomi clan, also died of venereal disease.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1613, two years after the death of Kiyomasa, Yoshinaga ASANO, one of the most influential Daimyo under the patronage of the Toyotomi clan, also died of venereal disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>清正・幸長の両名は豊臣氏恩顧の有力大名として家康から警戒されていたのは事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was true that Ieyasu was wary of both Kiyomasa and Yukinaga as influential Daimyo under the patronage of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was true that Ieyasu was wary of both Kiyomasa and Yukinaga as influential Daimyo under the patronage of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was true that Ieyasu was wary of both Kiyomasa and Yukinaga as influential Daimyo under the patronage of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>その両名が同じ病気でしかも急死したため、家康による毒殺ではないかとの憶測も流れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the two Daimyo died of the same disease and suddenly as well, it touched off speculation of murder by poisoning by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the two Daimyo died of the same disease and suddenly as well, it touched off speculation of murder by poisoning by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the two Daimyo died of the same disease and suddenly as well, it touched off speculation of murder by poisoning by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>暗殺説の中でも二条城会見での料理による毒殺、毒饅頭による毒殺など様々にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several theories for the murder of poisoning including that by dishes served in the meeting at the Nijo-jo Castle and that by a poisonous bun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several theories for murder by poisoning including that of poisoning by dishes served in the meeting at Nijo-jo Castle and by a poisonous bun.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several theories for murder by poisoning including that of poisoning by dishes served in the meeting at Nijo-jo Castle and by a poisonous bun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>根強い毒殺説を題材としたのが池波正太郎の『火の国の城』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shotaro IKENAMI made the deeply entrenched murder by poisoning theory the subject matter of his novel &quot;Castle in the fire country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>『火の国の城』は、訳者の直訳で、公式の訳ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shotaro IKENAMI made the deeply entrenched murder by poisoning theory the subject matter of his novel &quot;Castle in the fire country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shotaro IKENAMI made the deeply entrenched murder by poisoning theory the subject matter of his novel &quot;Castle in the fire country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="128">
<j>また死因はハンセン病（癩病、ハンセン病）であったとする説もあり、罹患者の多かった時代には清正を祀る加藤神社に平癒を願う参詣者が多かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that the cause of his death was Hansen&apos;s disease and it is said that many visited Kato Shrine dedicated to Kiyomasa to pray for their recoveryfrom illness in the ages when there were many patients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that the cause of his death was Hansen&apos;s disease and it is said that many visited Kato Shrine dedicated to Kiyomasa to pray for their recoveryfrom illness in the ages when there were many patients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that the cause of his death was Hansen&apos;s disease and it is said that many visited Kato-jinja Shrine dedicated to Kiyomasa to pray for their recovery from illness in the ages when there were many patients.</e>
<cmt>Kato→Kato-jinja</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>ちなみに熊本市の本妙寺 (熊本市)は明治20年代まで梅毒やハンセン病で不具になってしまった患者達で混雑する事が珍しくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, it was not uncommon that the Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) got crowded with patients disabled by syphilis or Hansen&apos;s disease until the 20s of the Meiji period (around the end of 19th century).</e>
<cmt>「明治20年代」のカッコ内 (around the end of 19th century).は以下の根拠に基づきます。明治20年＝1887年、明治29年＝1896年。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, it was not uncommon that the Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) got crowded with patients disabled by syphilis or Hansen&apos;s disease until the 20s of the Meiji period (around the end of 19th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, it was not uncommon that the Honmyo-ji Temple (Kumamoto City) got crowded with patients disabled by syphilis or Hansen&apos;s disease until the 20s of the Meiji period (around the end of 19th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>参拝客達に哀れみを乞い、この寺に墓がある清正を一種の神と崇め、病を治して貰おうという信仰があったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was due to the fact that visitors to the temple as believers treated Kiyomasa whose tomb was located there as a kind of god, begged for mercy of curing their diseases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was due to the fact that visitors to the temple as believers treated Kiyomasa whose tomb was located there as a kind of god, begging for mercy and curing them of their diseases.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was due to the fact that visitors to the temple as believers treated Kiyomasa whose tomb was located there as a kind of god, begging for mercy and curing them of their diseases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>しかしこの現象は全国の寺社で起こっていたことであり、信憑性は薄い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, that phenomenon occurred in the temples and shrines throughout the country, accordingly, the above description on the belief is not so reliable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, that phenomenon occurred in the temples and shrines throughout the country, and therefore the above description of the belief is not so reliable.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, that phenomenon occurred in the temples and shrines throughout the country, and therefore the above description of the belief is not so reliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>日本のハンセン病の歴史において大きな足跡を残した一人、イギリス国教会の婦人伝道師だったハンナ・リデルはこの寺で見た患者達の群を見て甚大なショックを受け、その生涯を彼らの救済に傾けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hannah Riddell, a female missionary of the Church of England, one of the persons who left behind a great achievement in the history of the Hansen&apos;s disease in Japan was greatly shocked to see a crowd of patients at the temple and came to devote her life to give aid to patients of the Hansen&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt>「ハンナ・リデル」は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%83%8F%E3%83%B3%E3%83%8A%E3%83%BB%E3%83%AA%E3%83%87%E3%83%AB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hannah Riddell, a female missionary of the Church of England, one of the persons who left behind a great achievement in the history of the Hansen&apos;s disease in Japan, was greatly shocked to see a crowd of patients at the temple and came to devote her life to give aid to patients suffering from Hansen&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hannah Riddell, a female missionary of the Church of England, one of the persons who left behind a great achievement in the history of the Hansen&apos;s disease in Japan, was greatly shocked to see a crowd of patients at the temple and came to devote her life to give aid to patients suffering from Hansen&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>手話単語のモチーフとして</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a motif of sign language</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sign Language Motifs</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sign Language Motifs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="133">
<j>日本手話における「加藤」の手話単語の一つに「両手で槍を持って前に突き出す」動作を真似たものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For describing &apos;Kato&apos; in Japanese sign language, there is a sign imitating an action of &apos;hold a spear by both hands and thrust it out.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To say &apos;Kato&apos; in Japanese sign language, there is a sign imitating the action of &apos;holding a spear in both hands and thrusting it out.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To say &apos;Kato&apos; in Japanese sign language, there is a sign imitating the action of &apos;holding a spear in both hands and thrusting it out.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>これは加藤清正の虎退治の古事にちなんだものと言われる（他に指文字「か」＋植物の藤を表す手話単語を用いる場合や、タレントの加藤茶にちなんでつけ髭を指で真似る手話単語など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That sign is said to have to do with the fable of subjugation of a tiger by Kiyomasa KATO (There are others to describe it including a sign by &apos;Ka&apos; of the finger alphabet use with a sign to show Japanese wisteria, a plant and a sign imitating a mustache by a finger which have to do with Cha KATO).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That sign is said to have to do with the fable of Kiyomasa KATO subjugating a tiger (there are other ways to say it including a sign for &apos;Ka&apos; of the finger alphabet used with a sign to show Japanese wisteria, a plant, and a sign imitating a mustache with one finger, which has to do with Cha KATO).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That sign is said to have to do with the fable of Kiyomasa KATO subjugating a tiger (there are other ways to say it including a sign for &apos;Ka&apos; of the finger alphabet used with a sign to show &apos;to&apos; [Japanese wisteria], a plant, and a sign imitating a mustache with one finger, which has to do with Cha KATO.)</e>
<cmt>籐が「とう」と発音されることを記述しないと「かとう」と伝わらないため、&apos;to&apos; (Japanese wisteria) としました。余分なスペース削除ピリオドを括弧内へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Yasumi(id:44933), DragonBot(id:161936), Cprobot(id:97843), Hannah(id:15935), HI(id:72996), ＤＦ．Ｋｉｎｇ(id:48817), Lupinoid(id:68), Kamakura(id:472), Mishika(id:276), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Moss(id:46638), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), A-Taul(id:41790), KAMUI(id:9330), Koshoku(id:15691), Kanoe(id:17203), Point136(id:211299), Kouko0515(id:100370), Tinecici(id:192914), シェーラ(id:17988), YukkeBot2(id:251491), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), M-sho-gun(id:88956), 浩(id:70121), ニコタマ二子多摩川(id:228848), たね(id:10372), Moltke(id:17553), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 松茸(id:27535), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Kagetudo(id:163875), 彩華1226(id:64711), MDR-SK(id:192066), N quaker(id:71025), Alecs.bot(id:194707), Arutoki(id:132405), Kishitak(id:9134), Jmho(id:10472), Wybot(id:81801), ドルチェット(id:46458), ましまる(id:99950), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kawai(id:5634), Cureless(id:85558), 陽一(id:92099), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kogane(id:28186), Sutou(id:32), FC Dinamo Bucuresti(id:82343), Gnsin(id:12351), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 玄史生(id:43670), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Chobot(id:20846), こぶまき(id:38278), 寂華(id:83725), Hukidera(id:87796), 宮川将一朗(id:264279), Yosemite(id:5808), Mark-zero(id:48822), KASAGI(id:24405), Lonicera(id:20638), Kalz(id:92749), Hosokawajun(id:72875), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Aoiya(id:44787), Peachkiller(id:99202), Aboshi(id:9318), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), 高槻(id:98635), Jondel(id:6467), VolkovBot(id:105371), もむのふ(id:256963), Pentacube(id:150631), Kenshinw(id:194278), Muyo(id:14948), Snowchild-152(id:265254), 光秀(id:255419), Miya.m(id:4662), Hadrianvs et antinovs(id:187552), 歴史研究家(id:108842), Tokugawa(id:61656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>