<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原秀澄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hidezumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Hidezumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hidezumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 秀澄（ふじわら の ひでずみ、生年不詳 - 承久3年（1221年）10月）は鎌倉時代の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hidezumi (year of birth unknown-October 1221) was a samurai in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Hidezumi (year of birth unknown - October, 1221) was a samurai in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hidezumi (year of birth unknown - October, 1221) was a samurai in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原秀宗の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third son of FUJIWARA no Hidemune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Hidemune.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Hidemune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄に藤原秀康、藤原秀能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His older brothers were FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older brothers were FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brothers were FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原北家流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fujiwara north family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was in the line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in the line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>承久の乱での後鳥羽天皇側の大将軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Daishogun (command in chief) on the side of the Emperor Gotoba at the Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the Daishogun (command in chief) on the side of the Emperor Gotoba at the Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the Daishogun (command in chief) on the side of the Emperor Gotoba at the Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>院政に仕える畿内近国の武士で北面の武士、西面の武士、帯刀、左衛門尉、右衛門尉、河内判官を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidezumi, a samurai in the Kinai-Kingoku area who served cloister government, held various posts including Hokumen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side), Saimen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the west side), Tachihaki (the Prince Imperial&apos;s bodyguard), Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Kawachi hangan (judge, magistrate).</e>
<cmt>「帯刀」の訳不明。ここではTachihaki (the Prince Imperial&apos;s bodyguard)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidezumi, a samurai in the Kinai-Kingoku (provinces in and close to Kyoto) who served the cloister government, held various posts including Hokumen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side), Saimen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the west side), Tachihaki (the Prince Imperial&apos;s bodyguard), Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Kawachi no jo (judge, magistrate of Kawachi Province).</e>
<cmt>用語補足を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidezumi, a samurai in the Kinai-Kingoku (provinces in and close to Kyoto) who served the cloister government, held various posts including Hokumen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side), Saimen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the west side), Tachihaki (the Prince Imperial&apos;s bodyguard), Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Kawachi no jo (judge, magistrate of Kawachi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>兄の秀康は後鳥羽上皇の討幕計画の首謀者のひとりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His older brother Hideyasu was one of the ringleaders who conspired the Emperor Gotoba&apos;s plan for anti-Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older brother Hideyasu was one of the ringleaders of the Retired Emperor Gotoba&apos;s plan for anti-Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brother Hideyasu was one of the ringleaders of the Retired Emperor Gotoba&apos;s plan for anti-Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>承久3年（1221年）5月に後鳥羽上皇は討幕の挙兵をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1221, The Emperor Gotoba raised an army of anti-Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1221, the Retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army of anti-Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1221, the Retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army of anti-Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>6月に京方は幕府軍を迎え撃つべく美濃国と尾張国の国境の尾張川に布陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, kyogata (the Kyoto side or supporters of the Imperial court in Kyoto) lined up at the border between Mino and Owari Provinces to be ready for the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, kyogata (the Kyoto side or supporters of the Imperial court in Kyoto) lined up at the Owari-gawa River, the border between Mino and Owari Provinces, to be ready for the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「尾張川」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, kyogata (the Kyoto side or supporters of the Imperial court in Kyoto) lined up at the Owari-gawa River, the border between Mino and Owari Provinces, to be ready for the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>秀澄は大将軍として出陣して墨俣町に陣をしいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidezumi led an army as a Daishogun at Sunomata-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidezumi led an army as a Daishogun at Sunomata Town.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidezumi led an army as a Daishogun at Sunomata Town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>京方は少ない兵力を分散させる愚策を犯しており、尾張の住人山田重忠は兵力を集中し機制を制して尾張国府を襲う積極策を進言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyogata had a stupid stunt of dispersing their army with a small number of soldiers, and Shigetada YAMADA who lived in Owari advised an aggressive strategy to gather the force, control the situation and attack the provincial capital of Owari province.</e>
<cmt>「機制を制して」の意味が不明です。Control the situationと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyogata had a stupid stunt of dispersing their army with a small number of soldiers, and Shigetada YAMADA who lived in Owari advised an aggressive strategy to gather the force, control the situation and attack the provincial capital of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyogata had a stupid stunt of dispersing their army with a small number of soldiers, and Shigetada YAMADA who lived in Owari advised an aggressive strategy to gather the force, control the situation and attack the provincial capital of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>怯えた秀澄はこれを取り上げず、結局、京方は大敗を喫し、秀澄は京都へ逃げ帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidezumi felt scared and did not adopt this idea; as a result, kyotogata lost big and Hidezumi ran away to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidezumi felt scared and did not adopt this idea; as a result, kyogata lost big and Hidezumi ran away to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidezumi felt scared and did not adopt this idea; as a result, kyogata lost big and Hidezumi ran away to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『承久記』は秀澄を「天性臆病武者なり」「心のたるんだ武者」と酷評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jokyu Ki&quot; (a record of Jokyu) criticized Hidezumi by describing him as &apos;a natural-born coward warrior&apos; and &apos;slacking warrior.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jokyuki&quot; (A Chronicle of the Jokyu War) criticized Hidezumi by describing him as &apos;a natural-born coward warrior&apos; and &apos;slacking warrior.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jokyuki&quot; (A Chronicle of the Jokyu War) criticized Hidezumi by describing him as &apos;a natural-born coward warrior&apos; and &apos;slacking warrior.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>京方は宇治・勢多の戦いでも敗れ、幕府軍は京に乱入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyogata also lost at the battles in Uji and Seta, and the army of bakufu intruded to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyogata also lost at the battles of Uji and Seta, and the army of bakufu intruded to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyogata also lost at the battles of Uji and Seta, and the army of bakufu intruded to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>後鳥羽上皇は秀康、三浦胤義らを乱を引き起こした謀臣として逮捕を命じる院宣を出し、京方武士を見捨てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Gotoba issued a command from a retired emperor to arrest Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA as tacticians of the rebellion and abandoned the samurai of Kyogata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Retired Emperor Gotoba issued a command to arrest Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA as tacticians of the rebellion and abandoned the samurai of kyogata.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Retired Emperor Gotoba issued a command to arrest Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA as tacticians of the rebellion and abandoned the samurai of kyogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>秀澄は奈良に潜伏するが、河内国で捕らえられ、京で斬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidezumi hid in Nara, but was arrested in the Kawachi Province and killed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidezumi hid in Nara, but was arrested in the Kawachi Province and killed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidezumi hid in Nara, but was arrested in the Kawachi Province and killed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Carkuni(id:79281), 味っ子(id:17086), ５１６(id:45205), 花いちもんめ(id:39081), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>