<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>横山大観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikan YOKOYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan YOKOYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan YOKOYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>横山 大観（よこやま たいかん、正字体：大觀、明治元年9月18日 (旧暦)（1868年11月2日） - 昭和33年（1958年）2月26日）は、日本の美術家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikan YOKOYAMA (Orthographic style :Taikan, November 2, 1868 - February 26, 1958) was a Japanese artist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan YOKOYAMA (orthographic style: Taikan, November 2, 1868 - February 26, 1958) was a Japanese artist.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan YOKOYAMA (orthographic style: Taikan, November 2, 1868 - February 26, 1958) was a Japanese artist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本画家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Japanese-style painter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a painter in the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a painter in the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>茨城県水戸市出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came from Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came from Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>近代日本画壇の巨匠であり、今日「朦朧体」と呼ばれる、線描を抑えた独特の没線描法を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a great master of the Japanese art world, who established, what is called today, &apos;Moro-tai&apos; (painting technique), a unique Bossen gaho (painting technique) with vague line drawing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a great master of the Japanese art world who established, what is today called &apos;Moro-tai (painting technique),&apos; a unique Bossen gaho (painting technique) with vague line drawing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a great master of the Japanese art world and established, what is today called &apos;Moro-tai&apos; (painting technique), a unique Bossen gaho (painting technique) with vague line drawing.</e>
<cmt>whoをandに変更しました。()を&apos; &apos;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本芸術院会員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>第一回文化勲章受章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was presented with the first Bunka Kunsho (Order of Culture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was presented with the first Bunka Kunsho (Order of Culture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was presented with the first Bunka Kunsho (Order of Culture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>死後、正三位勲一等旭日大綬章を贈位された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was posthumously presented with Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously presented with theShosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously presented with the Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun.</e>
<cmt>theとShosanmiの間にスペースを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>茨城県名誉県民。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an honorary Ibaraki Prefecture resident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an honorary resident of Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an honorary resident of Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>東京都台東区名誉区民。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Taito Ward resident in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a resident of Taito Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a resident of Taito Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>本名、横山秀麿（-ひでまろ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Hidemaro YOKOYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Hidemaro YOKOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Hidemaro YOKOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治元年（1868年）、旧水戸藩藩士・酒井捨彦の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the eldest son of Sutehiko SAKAI, a former clansman of the Mito Domain in 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1868 as the first son of Sutehiko SAKAI, a former clansman of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1868 as the first son of Sutehiko SAKAI, a former clansman of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>府立一中卒業後、私立の日本学園中学校・高等学校在学中に絵画に興味を抱き、洋画家・渡辺文三郎に鉛筆画を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He graduated from Furitsu Icchu (abbreviation of Tokyo Prefectural No.1 Junior High School), and during his school days in Nihon Gakuen Junior High School and Senior High School, he became interested in the pictorial arts and learned pencil drawing from Bunzaburo WATANABE, a Western-style painter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from Furitsu Icchu (abbreviation for Tokyo Prefectural No. 1 Junior High School), and during his school days in Nihon Gakuen Junior High School and Senior High School he became interested in the pictorial arts and learned pencil drawing from Bunzaburo WATANABE, a Western-style painter.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from Furitsu Icchu (abbreviation for Tokyo Prefectural No. 1 Junior High School), and during his school days in Nihon Gakuen Junior High School and Senior High School he became interested in the pictorial arts and learned pencil drawing from Bunzaburo WATANABE, a Western-style painter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>明治21年（1888年）、母方の縁戚である横山家の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted as a son of Yokohama family, a maternal relative in 1888.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted as a son of the Yokohama family, a maternal relative, in 1888.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted as a son of the Yokoyama family, a maternal relative, in 1888.</e>
<cmt>YokohamaをYokoyamaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同時期、狩野派の巨匠狩野芳崖などに教えを受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the same time, he took lessons from Hogai KANO, a great master of the Kano School and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the same time, he took lessons from Hogai KANO, a great master of the Kano School, and others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the same time, he took lessons from Hogai KANO, a great master of the Kano School, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>翌明治22年（1889年）、東京芸術大学に第一期生として入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Tokyo University of the Arts as a member of the inaugural class in 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Tokyo University of the Arts in 1889 as a member of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered Tokyo University of the Arts in 1889 as a member of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>岡倉天心、橋本雅邦らに学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned under the guidance of Tenshin OKAKURA, Gaho HASHIMOTO and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He progressed under the guidance of Tenshin OKAKURA, Gaho HASHIMOTO and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He progressed under the guidance of Tenshin OKAKURA, Gaho HASHIMOTO and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>同期生には菱田春草、下村観山、西郷孤月などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His classmates included Shunso HISHIDA, Kanzan SHIMOMURA and Kogetsu SAIGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His classmates included Shunso HISHIDA, Kanzan SHIMOMURA and Kogetsu SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His classmates included Shunso HISHIDA, Kanzan SHIMOMURA and Kogetsu SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>美術学校卒業後、京都に移り仏画の研究を始め、同時に京都市立芸術大学予備科教員となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his graduation from Tokyo School of Fine Arts, he moved to Kyoto, where he started studying the Buddhist painting and at the same time became a teacher of the preparatory school of the Kyoto City University of Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his graduation from the Tokyo School of Fine Arts, he moved to Kyoto, where he started studying Buddhist painting and at the same time became a teacher of the preparatory school of the Kyoto City University of Arts.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his graduation from the Tokyo School of Fine Arts, he moved to Kyoto, where he started studying Buddhist painting and at the same time became a teacher of the preparatory school of the Kyoto City University of Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>またこの頃より雅号「大観」を使い始めるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he started using his Gago (pseudonym) &apos;Taikan&apos; around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he started using his Gago (pseudonym) &apos;Taikan&apos; around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he started using his Gago (pseudonym) &apos;Taikan&apos; around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>明治29年（1896年）、同職を辞すと、母校・東京美術学校の助教授に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned the above post and took a position of Assistant Professor of his alma mater, the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned the above post and took a position as assistant professor of his alma mater, the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned the above post and took a position as assistant professor of his alma mater, the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし2年後に校長・岡倉天心への排斥運動が起こり、岡倉が失脚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two years later, however, a movement started to drive out the principal, Tenshin OKAKURA, who lost his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, two years later a movement started to drive out the principal, Tenshin OKAKURA, who then lost his position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, two years later a movement started to drive out the principal, Tenshin OKAKURA, who then lost his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>岡倉を師と仰ぐ大観はこれに従って助教授職を辞し、同年日本美術院創設に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikan who looked up to Okakura as his mentor resigned his position of Assistant Professor to follow suit and in the same year participated in the establishment of The Nihon Bijitsuin (The Japan Art Institute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan, who looked up to Okakura as his mentor, resigned from his position as assistant professor to follow suit, and in the same year he participated in the establishment of the Nihon Bijitsuin (The Japan Art Institute).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan, who looked up to Okakura as his mentor, resigned from his position as assistant professor to follow suit, and in the same year he participated in the establishment of the Nihon Bijitsuin (The Japan Art Institute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>美術院の活動の中で、大観は菱田春草と共に西洋画の画法を取り入れた新たな画風の研究を重ね、やがて線描を大胆に抑えた没線描法の絵画を次々に発表する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his activities in the Institute, he, with Shunso HISHIDA, continued unremitting study of a new style adopting the painting technique of the Western painting and, before long, kept turning out Bossen gaho paintings with courageously vague line drawing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his activities in the Institute he, together with Shunso HISHIDA, continued the unremitting study of a new style adopting the painting technique of Western painting, and before long he was turning out Bossen gaho paintings with courageously vague line drawings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his activities in the Institute he, together with Shunso HISHIDA, continued the unremitting study of a new style adopting the painting technique of Western painting, and before long he was turning out Bossen gaho paintings with courageously vague line drawings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかしその先進的な画風は当時の画壇の守旧派から猛烈な批判を浴びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His forward-thinking style was, however, criticized severely by the old-guard crony of the then art world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His forward-thinking style was, however, severely criticized by the old-guard crony of the art world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His forward-thinking style was, however, severely criticized by the old-guard crony of the art world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>現在ではその画風を的確に表す言葉とされる『朦朧体』という呼称も、当初は「勢いに欠ける、曖昧でぼんやりとした画風」という意味で、批判的に使用された言葉であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the name, &quot;Moro-tai&quot; is regarded as a term which appropriately indicates his style at the present time, it was critically used at the beginning meaning &apos;Lifeless, vague and dim style.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the name &quot;Moro-tai&quot; is regarded as a term that appropriately indicates his style at the time, it was initially used as a criticism to mean a &apos;lifeless, vague and dim style.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the name &quot;Moro-tai&quot; is regarded as a term that appropriately indicates his style at the time, it was initially used as a criticism to mean a &apos;lifeless, vague and dim style.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>保守的風潮の強い国内での活動が行き詰まりを見せはじめたため、大観は菱田と共に海外に渡り、カルカッタ、ニューヨーク、ボストンで相次いで展覧会を開き、高い評価を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his domestic activities began to show signs of a standstill due to a strong conservative trend in the art world in this country, Taikan went abroad with Hishida, held exhibitions one after another in Calcutta, New York and Boston and was highly rated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his domestic activities began to show signs of a standstill due to a strong conservative trend in the country&apos;s art world, Taikan went abroad with Hishida, held exhibitions one after another in Calcutta, New York and Boston, and was well received.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his domestic activities began to show signs of a standstill due to a strong conservative trend in the country&apos;s art world, Taikan went abroad with Hishida, held exhibitions one after another in Calcutta, New York and Boston, and was well received.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後ヨーロッパに渡り、ロンドン、ベルリン、パリでも展覧会を開き、ここでも高い評価を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After then, he went to Europe, where he held exhibitions in London, Berlin and Paris and received a high evaluation also over there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he went to Europe, where he held exhibitions in London, Berlin and Paris, where he was also well received.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he went to Europe, where he held exhibitions in London, Berlin and Paris, where he was also well received.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この欧米での高評価を受けて日本国内でもその画風が評価され始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to that high reputation in Western countries, his type started to be highly rated also in Japan.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the artist&apos;s high reputation in Western countries, his type of work started to be highly rated in Japan as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the artist&apos;s high reputation in Western countries, his type of work started to be highly rated in Japan as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1907年にはこの年より始まった文部省美術展覧会（文展）の審査員を務め、大正2年（1913年）には守旧派に押されて活動が途絶えていた日本美術院の再興に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1907, he was a judge in the annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education (Bunten) which started in that year, and in 1913, restored The Nihon Bijitsuin of which activities had been kept interrupted due to the pressure of the old-guard crony.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1907, he was a judge in a new annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education (Bunten), which started that year, and in 1913 restored the Nihon Bijitsuin, whose activities had been continually interrupted due to the pressures of old-guard cronyism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1907, he was a judge in a new annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education (Bunten), which started that year, and in 1913 restored the Nihon Bijitsuin, whose activities had been continually interrupted due to the pressures of old-guard cronyism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>以後、日本画壇の重鎮として確固たる地位を築き、1934年朝日文化賞受賞、昭和10年（1935年）には帝国美術院会員となり、昭和12年（1937年）にはこの年制定された第一回文化勲章の受章者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he built up a solid position as a leading figure in the Japanese art world, received Asahi Shinbun Cultural Award in 1934, became a member of the Imperial Fine Arts Academy in 1935 and received in 1937 the first Bunka Kunsho (Order of Culture) which was enacted in that year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he built a solid position as a leading figure in the Japanese art world, received the Asahi Shinbun Cultural Award in 1934, became a member of the Imperial Fine Arts Academy in 1935, and in 1937 received the first Bunka Kunsho (Order of Culture), which was enacted that year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he built a solid position as a leading figure in the Japanese art world, received the Asahi Shinbun Cultural Award in 1934, became a member of the Imperial Fine Arts Academy in 1935, and in 1937 received the first Bunka Kunsho (Order of Culture), which was enacted that year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>同年帝国芸術院会員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he became a member of Imperial Art Academy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he became a member of the Imperial Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he became a member of the Imperial Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>1951年日本美術院会員を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951, he resigned his membership in The Nihon Bijitsuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951, he resigned from his membership in the Nihon Bijitsuin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, he resigned from his membership in the Nihon Bijitsuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>51年文化功労者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951, he was selected as Bunkakorosha (Person of Cultural Merits).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951, he was selected as Bunkakorosha (Person of Cultural Merit).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, he was selected as Bunkakorosha (Person of Cultural Merit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>昭和32年（1957年）、89歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 89 in 1957.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1957 at 89 years of age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1957 at 89 years of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>永年に渡る日本美術発展への貢献により正三位に叙せられ、勲一等旭日大綬章を贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was raised to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and presented with Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun for his long services in development of Japanese art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was raised to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and presented with the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun for his many years of service in the development of Japanese art.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was raised to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and presented with the Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun for his many years of service in the development of Japanese art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>脳は、現在もアルコール漬けにされた状態で東京大学医学部に保管されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brain is still preserved in alcohol in Faculty of Medicine, University of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His brain is kept preserved in alcohol at the Faculty of Medicine, University of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His brain is kept preserved in alcohol at the Faculty of Medicine, University of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>代表作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>『無我』1897年　東京国立博物館蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Muga&quot; (selflessness) dated 1897 in the possession of Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Muga (Selflessness),&quot; dated 1897, in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Muga&quot; (Selflessness), dated 1897, in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>『屈原』1898年　厳島神社蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kutsugen&quot; (a Chinese scholar-official) dated 1898 in the possession of Itsukushima-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kutsugen&quot; (a Chinese scholar-official), dated 1898, in the possession of Itsukushima-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kutsugen&quot; (a Chinese scholar-official), dated 1898, in the possession of Itsukushima-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>『流燈』1909年　茨城県近代美術館蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryuto&quot; dated 1909 in the possession of Museum of Modern Art, Ibaraki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryuto,&quot; dated 1909, in the possession of the Museum of Modern Art, Ibaraki</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryuto,&quot; dated 1909, in the possession of the Museum of Modern Art, Ibaraki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>『蕭湘八景』1912年　東京国立博物館蔵　※重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shosho Hakkei&quot; dated 1912 in the possession of Tokyo National Museum, Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shosho Hakkei,&quot; dated 1912, an Important Cultural Property in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shosho Hakkei,&quot; dated 1912, an Important Cultural Property in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>『生々流転』1923年　東京国立近代美術館蔵　※重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Seisei Ruten&quot; (the eternal cycle of birth) dated 1923 in the possession of The National Museum of Modern Art, Tokyo, Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Seisei Ruten (Eternal Cycle of Birth),&quot; dated 1923, an Important Cultural Property in the possession of The National Museum of Modern Art</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Seisei Ruten&quot; (Eternal Cycle of Birth), dated 1923, an Important Cultural Property in the possession of The National Museum of Modern Art</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>『夜桜』1929年　大倉集古館蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yozakura&quot; dated 1929 in the possession of The Okura Shukokan Museum of Fine Arts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yozakura,&quot; dated 1929, in the possession of the Okura Shukokan Museum of Fine Arts</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yozakura,&quot; dated 1929, in the possession of the Okura Shukokan Museum of Fine Arts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>『楠木正成』1938年　湊川神社蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Masashige KUSUNOKI&quot; dated 1938 in the possession of Minatogawa-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Masashige KUSUNOKI,&quot; dated 1938, in the possession of Minatogawa-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Masashige KUSUNOKI,&quot; dated 1938, in the possession of Minatogawa-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>『或る日の太平洋』1952年　東京国立近代美術館蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Aruhino Taiheiyo&quot; (Pacific Ocean of one day) dated 1952 in the possession of The National Museum of Modern Art, Tokyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Aruhino Taiheiyo (Pacific Ocean of One Day),&quot; dated 1952, in the possession of the National Museum of Modern Art, Tokyo</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Aruhino Taiheiyo&quot; (Pacific Ocean of One Day), dated 1952, in the possession of the National Museum of Modern Art, Tokyo</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>大変な酒好きとして知られ、人生後半の50年は飯をほとんど口にせず（たまに食べる時も一粒二粒と数えるほど）、酒と肴だけで済ませていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being known as a heavy drinker, he is considered to have had almost no rice (Even when he occasionally had rice, he ate only a grain or two) but had meals only with Sake (rice wine) and side dishes for 50 years or the latter half of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being known as a heavy drinker, he is considered to have had almost no rice (even when he occasionally had rice, he ate only a grain or two) but had meals only with sake (rice wine) and side dishes for 50 years or the latter half of his life.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being known as a heavy drinker, he is considered to have had almost no rice (even when he occasionally had rice, he ate only a grain or two) but had meals only with sake (rice wine) and side dishes for 50 years or the latter half of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>飲んでいた酒は広島の『醉心』で、これは昭和初期に醉心酒造の社長・山根薫と知り合った大観が互いに意気投合し、「一生の飲み分を約束」した山根より無償で大観に送られていたものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sake he used to drink was &quot;Suishin&quot; of Hiroshima which Kaoru YAMANE, the then President of Suishin Brewery kept sending to him free of charge under the Yamane&apos;s promise to present Sake to Taikan for life,&apos; made when Taikan and Yamane came to know each other and found themselves on the same wavelength in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sake he used to drink was &quot;Suishin&quot; of Hiroshima, which Kaoru YAMANE, then the president of Suishin Brewery, kept sending to him free of charge under the Yamane&apos;s promise to present sake to Taikan for life,&apos; a promise made when Taikan and Yamane came to know each other and found themselves to be on the same wavelength in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sake he used to drink was &quot;Suishin&quot; of Hiroshima, which Kaoru YAMANE, then the president of Suishin Brewery, kept sending to him free of charge under the Yamane&apos;s promise to present sake to Taikan for life,&apos; a promise made when Taikan and Yamane came to know each other and found themselves to be on the same wavelength in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし山根は年に四斗樽で何本も注文が来るので驚いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamane was, however, reportedly surprised to receive several orders of Shitodaru (72-liter barrel) per year.</e>
<cmt>1斗は1升しょうの10倍で、18.039ﾘｯﾄﾙ （広辞苑）。これに４を掛けますと72L　になります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamane was, however, reportedly surprised to receive several orders of Shitodaru (72-liter barrel) per year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamane was, however, reportedly surprised to receive several orders of Shitodaru (72-liter barrel) per year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>代金のかわりとして大観は毎年1枚ずつ自分の絵を無償で送り、結果、醉心酒造に大観の記念館ができることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikan kept sending one painting of his every year free of charge in place of payment for Sake resulting in the establishment of Taikan memorial museum in Suishin Brewery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan kept sending one painting of his every year free of charge in place of payment for the sake, resulting in the establishment of the Taikan Memorial Museum at Suishin Brewery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan kept sending one painting of his every year free of charge in place of payment for the sake, resulting in the establishment of the Taikan Memorial Museum at Suishin Brewery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>もっとも、最初から酒好きだったわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indeed, it wasn&apos;t as if he liked Sake all along.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indeed, it wasn&apos;t as if he liked sake all along.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed, it wasn&apos;t as if he liked sake all along.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>若い頃は猪口2～3杯で真っ赤になってしまう下戸だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his youth, he was a nondrinker who was made deeply flushed with a Choko (small cup) of sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his youth, he was a nondrinker whom even a choko (small cup) of sake could make feel deeply flushed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his youth, he was a nondrinker whom even a choko (small cup) of sake could make feel deeply flushed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし師の岡倉天心は日に2升ともいわれる酒豪であり、「酒の一升くらい飲めずにどうする」と大観を叱咤した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenshin OKAKURA, his teacher was, however, a heavy drinker, who reportedly drank two Sho (approx. 3.6 liters) a day and strongly encouraged Taikan to drink Sake saying, &apos;If you cannot drink such a small quantity of Sake as one Sho, how can you take care of yourself.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his teacher, Tenshin OKAKURA, was a heavy drinker who reportedly drank two sho (approximately 3.6 liters) a day and strongly encouraged Taikan to drink sake, saying, &apos;If you cannot drink such a small quantity of sake as one sho, how can you take care of yourself?&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his teacher, Tenshin OKAKURA, was a heavy drinker who reportedly drank two sho (approximately 3.6 liters) a day and strongly encouraged Taikan to drink sake, saying, &apos;If you cannot drink such a small quantity of sake as one sho, how can you take care of yourself?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>飲んでは吐きながら訓練した結果であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a heavy drinker as the result of his training by repeating drinking and vomiting.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a heavy drinker as the result of his training, in which he would repeatedly drink and vomit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a heavy drinker as the result of his training, in which he would repeatedly drink and vomit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>東京美術学校の同期生である菱田春草とは無二の親友で常に行動を共にし、『春の朝・秋の夕』、『帰路、入船』などを合作している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He always acted together with his best friend and his classmate in the Tokyo School of Fine Arts, Shunso HISHIDA and produced in collaboration with Hishida works including &quot;Morning in spring/Evening in fall&quot; and &quot;On the way home/Arrival in port.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He always acted together with Shunso HISHIDA, his best friend and classmate at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts, and in collaboration with Hishida he produced works such as &quot;Morning in Spring/Evening in Fall&quot; and &quot;On the Way Home/Arrival in Port.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He always acted together with Shunso HISHIDA, his best friend and classmate at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts, and in collaboration with Hishida he produced works such as &quot;Morning in Spring/Evening in Fall&quot; and &quot;On the Way Home/Arrival in Port.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>1911年に菱田が36歳で夭折すると大観は大いに嘆き、菱田春草追悼展の開催を主導し自らも『五柳先生』（東京国立博物館蔵）を出品した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hishida died young at the age of 36 in 1911, Taikan deeply lamented and took the initiative in holding an exhibition in memory of Shunso HISHIDA sending his own work, &quot;Goryu Sensei&quot; (in the possession of Tokyo National Museum) to the exhibition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Taikan&apos;s friend died young in 1911 at the age of 36, he deeply lamented it and took the initiative in holding an exhibition in memory of Shunso HISHIDA, sending his own work, &quot;Goryu Sensei&quot; (now in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum) to the exhibition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Taikan&apos;s friend died young in 1911 at the age of 36, he deeply lamented it and took the initiative in holding an exhibition in memory of Shunso HISHIDA, sending his own work, &quot;Goryu Sensei&quot; (now in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum) to the exhibition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>晩年に至るまで、自らが日本画の巨匠と称されるたびに「あいつ（菱田）が生きていたら俺なんかよりずっと巧い」と口にしていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until his later years, whenever he was called a great master of the Japanese painting, he reportedly said that &apos;If that guy (Hishida) were alive, he would be better than I am.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until his later years, whenever he was called a great master of Japanese painting, he reportedly said, &apos;If that guy [Hishida] were alive, he would be better than I am.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until his later years, whenever he was called a great master of Japanese painting, he reportedly said, &apos;If that guy [Hishida] were alive, he would be better than I am.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>大観は、熱烈な勤王派であった父・捨彦、思想家としても著名であり国粋主義者とも称された師・岡倉天心の影響を色濃く受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikan was strongly affected by Sutehiko, his father and an ardent loyalist and his teacher, Tenshin OKAKURA who was well-known also as a thinker and called as an ultranationalist.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan was strongly affected by Sutehiko, his father and an ardent loyalist, and his teacher, Tenshin OKAKURA, who was well known as a thinker and was characterized as an ultranationalist.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan was strongly affected by Sutehiko, his father and an ardent loyalist, and his teacher, Tenshin OKAKURA, who was well known as a thinker and was characterized as an ultranationalist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>自身も国粋主義的な面を持ち、日本の象徴である勇美な富士山を好んで題材とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He himself had an ultranationalistic aspect and preferably sought subject matter in heroic and beautiful Mt. Fuji which symbolizes Japan.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He himself had an ultranationalistic aspect and preferably sought subject matter in the heroic and beautiful Mt. Fuji, which symbolizes Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He himself had an ultranationalistic aspect and preferably sought subject matter in the heroic and beautiful Mt. Fuji, which symbolizes Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>皇室にもたびたび絵を献上し、太平洋戦争中には自らが売却した絵の代金を戦闘機の制作費用として軍に寄付するなどしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He frequently presented his paintings to the Imperial family and during the Pacific War contributed the proceeds from the sale of his own paintings to the military for manufacturing fighter planes.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He frequently presented his paintings to the Imperial Family, and during the Pacific War he contributed the proceeds from the sale of his own paintings to the military for the manufacture of fighter planes.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He frequently presented his paintings to the Imperial Family, and during the Pacific War he contributed the proceeds from the sale of his own paintings to the military for the manufacture of fighter planes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>そのため、終戦後には連合国軍最高司令官総司令部より戦犯容疑者として取り調べを受けた事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above facts, he was once questioned as a war criminal suspect by the General Headquarters (GHQ) after the War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above facts, afte the war he was once questioned as a suspected war criminal by the General Headquarters (GHQ).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above facts, after the war he was once questioned as a suspected war criminal by the General Headquarters (GHQ).</e>
<cmt>afteをafterに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>大観のタッチは独特ながら一見、模倣しやすいと考えられ、戦前の一時期、横山大観を騙り地方の素封家の食客となって渡り歩く無名画家が多数あらわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Taikan&apos;s touch was considered at a glance to be easy to imitate even though unique, many nameless painters appeared during a certain period of time before the War, falsely representing themselves as a Taikan YOKOYAMA and going from one local wealthy person to another as a guest freeloader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Taikan&apos;s touch was considered at a glance to be easy to imitate despite its uniqueness, many nameless painters appeared during a certain period of time before the war, falsely representing themselves as Taikan YOKOYAMA and going from one local wealthy person to another as freeloading guests.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Taikan&apos;s touch was considered at a glance to be easy to imitate despite its uniqueness, many nameless painters appeared during a certain period of time before the war, falsely representing themselves as Taikan YOKOYAMA and going from one local wealthy person to another as freeloading guests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>この時、彼らによって描かれた作品が数多く現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the paintings they produced during that period are still in existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the paintings they produced during that period are still in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the paintings they produced during that period are still in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>地方名士の子孫には、真筆と信じて所蔵している者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many descendants of local celebrities who possess those Taikan fakes believing they are genuine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many descendants of local celebrities who possess those Taikan fakes, believing they&apos;re genuine.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many descendants of local celebrities who possess those Taikan fakes, believing they&apos;re genuine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>これらの模倣作ないし贋作をさして揶揄的に「田舎大観」と呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These imitations and fakes are sometimes sarcastically called &apos;Inaka Taikan&apos; (Country Taikan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These imitations are sometimes sarcastically called &apos;Inaka Taikan (Country Taikan).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These imitations are sometimes sarcastically called &apos;Inaka Taikan&apos; (Country Taikan).</e>
<cmt>()を&apos; &apos;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これらも含め、贋作が非常に多い事でも知られ、鑑定の結果、真筆と判定された作品には「大観番号」という番号をつけて保護されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Taikan&apos;s works, it is well-know that there are enormous numbers of its fakes including the above, and so Taikan&apos;s paintings are protected by assigning a number called &apos;Taikan number&apos; to his paintings decided as genuine by an appraisal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Taikan&apos;s works, it is well known that there are enormous numbers of fakes including the above, and so Taikan&apos;s paintings are protected by assigning a number called &apos;Taikan number&apos; to paintings that have been appraised by experts as being genuine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Taikan&apos;s works, it is well known that there are enormous numbers of fakes including the above, and so Taikan&apos;s paintings are protected by assigning a number called &apos;Taikan number&apos; to paintings that have been appraised by experts as being genuine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="65">
<j>歌手笠置シヅ子が好きだったと言われ、「東京ブギウギ」や「買物ブギ」のレコードを愛聴していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was a fan of a singer, Shizuko KASAGI and loved listening to &apos;Tokyo Boogie-Woogie&apos; (song title) and &apos;Kaimono Boogie-Woogie&apos; (song title) by playing records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was a fan of the singer Shizuko KASAGI and that he loved listening to the phonograph recordings of &apos;Tokyo Boogie-Woogie&apos; and &apos;Kaimono Boogie-Woogie.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was a fan of the singer Shizuko KASAGI and that he loved listening to the phonograph recordings of &apos;Tokyo Boogie-Woogie&apos; and &apos;Kaimono Boogie-Woogie.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>大観の80代の頃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was when Taikan was in his eighties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan was in his eighties by that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan was in his eighties by that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>明治元年（1868年）9月18日：誕生（異説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 18, 1868 : His birth (There are different views)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 18, 1868: His birth (contested)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 18, 1868: His birth (contested)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>父は、水戸藩士として「水戸学」の尊皇攘夷思想により志士として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, a clansman of the Mito Domain worked actively as a royalist on the basis of the thought of Sonno Joi (reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) of &apos;Mitogaku&apos; (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, a clansman of the Mito Domain, worked actively as a royalist on the basis of the thought of Sonno Joi (reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) of &apos;Mitogaku&apos; (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, a clansman of the Mito Domain, worked actively as a royalist on the basis of the thought of Sonno Joi (reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) of &apos;Mitogaku&apos; (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>大観の天皇への忠誠はここに発するものとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Taikan&apos;s loyalty to Emperor derived from the above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Taikan&apos;s loyalty to the Emperor derived from the above.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Taikan&apos;s loyalty to the Emperor derived from the above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>初名は、酒井秀麿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Hidemaro SAKAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Hidemaro SAKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Hidemaro SAKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>明治11年（1878年）：一家で上京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1878 : His family moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1878: His family moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1878: His family moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="72">
<j>明治14年（1881年）：東京都立日比谷高等学校（現在の東京都立日比谷高等学校）に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1881 : He entered Hibiya High School, Tokyo (the current Hibiya High School, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1881: He entered Hibiya High School, Tokyo (the current Hibiya High School, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1881: He entered Hibiya High School, Tokyo (the current Hibiya High School, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>優秀な成績で卒業するが諸事情により「東大予備門試験」では入学資格を消失。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he graduated with honors, he lost qualification for admission in the examination of Preparatory School of the University of Tokyo (Tokyo Yobimon) due to circumstances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he graduated with honors, due to circumstances he lost the qualification for admission in the examination of the Preparatory School of the University of Tokyo (Tokyo Yobimon).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he graduated with honors, due to circumstances he lost the qualification for admission in the examination of the &apos;Preparatory School of the University of Tokyo&apos; (Tokyo Yobimon).</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>致し方なく、当時は進学予備校として知られていた私立の東京英語学校（現在の日本学園中学校・高等学校）に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against his will, he entered a private school, Tokyo Eigo Gakko (Tokyo English School) (Currently Nihon Gakuen Junior High School/Senior High School) known as a preparatory school at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against his will, he entered a private school, Tokyo Eigo Gakko (Tokyo English School) (currently Nihon Gakuen Junior High School/Senior High School), which was then known as a preparatory school.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against his will, he entered a private school, Tokyo Eigo Gakko (Tokyo English School) (currently Nihon Gakuen Junior High School/Senior High School), which was then known as a preparatory school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>受験英語に勤しみ、その後の大観の海外生活で大きな力を発揮する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked on exam-oriented English, which later displayed its great effects in Taikan&apos;s living overseas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked on exam-oriented English, which later proved instrumental in Taikan&apos;s living overseas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked on exam-oriented English, which later proved instrumental in Taikan&apos;s living overseas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>明治16年（1883年）：絵画に興味をいだいた大観は、渡辺文三郎という画家に師事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1883 : Taikan who became interested in the pictorial arts studied under Bunzaburo WATANABE, a painter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1883: Taikan, who became interested in the pictorial arts, studied under the painter Bunzaburo WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1883: Taikan, who became interested in the pictorial arts, studied under the painter Bunzaburo WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その後、狩野派の指導をえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, he received training from the Kano School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, he received training from the Kano School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, he received training from the Kano School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>狩野芳崖にも影響される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was influenced also by Hogai KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also influenced by Hogai KANO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also influenced by Hogai KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>当時の日本画家は貧乏であり副業を得て生活していたことから父は画家よりは、東京帝国大学進学を切望。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father eagerly wanted him to go on to Tokyo Imperial University rather than to become a painter due to the fact that a Japanese-style painter at that time was poor and made a living with sideline work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father eagerly wanted him to go on to Tokyo Imperial University rather than become a painter, given the fact that a Japanese-style painter at that time was poor and would have to earn a living with sideline work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father eagerly wanted him to go on to Tokyo Imperial University rather than become a painter, given the fact that a Japanese-style painter at that time was poor and would have to earn a living with sideline work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>明治21年（1888年）：東京美術学校を受験。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1888 : He took an entrance examination at Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1888: He took an entrance examination at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1888: He took an entrance examination at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>横山家との養子縁組により、酒井秀麿から横山秀麿となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed from Hidemaro SAKAI to Hidemaro YOKOYAMA under an adoption arrangement with the Yokoyama family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his name from Hidemaro SAKAI to Hidemaro YOKOYAMA under an adoption arrangement with the Yokoyama family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his name from Hidemaro SAKAI to Hidemaro YOKOYAMA under an adoption arrangement with the Yokoyama family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="82">
<j>明治22年（1889年）：東京美術学校一期生として入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1889 : He entered Tokyo School of Fine Arts as a member of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1889: He entered the Tokyo School of Fine Arts as a member of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1889: He entered the Tokyo School of Fine Arts as a member of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>父は画家になることに大反対。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father totally disagreed with his becoming a painter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father totally disagreed with his becoming a painter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father totally disagreed with his becoming a painter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>卒業するまで書籍の図版を模写するアルバイトで生計と学費を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made his living and earned his school expenses by reproducing illustrations on books as a part-time job until his graduation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made his living and earned his school expenses by reproducing illustrations on books as a part-time job until his graduation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made his living and earned his school expenses by reproducing illustrations on books as a part-time job until his graduation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="85">
<j>明治26年（1893年）：東京美術学校卒業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1993 : He graduated from Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1993: He graduated from the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1993: He graduated from the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>その後は、京都で修養。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, he improved himself in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, he improved himself in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, he improved himself in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>古画の模写の仕事に励む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He devoted himself to work of reproducing ancient paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He devoted himself to the work of reproducing ancient paintings.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He devoted himself to the work of reproducing ancient paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="88">
<j>明治28年（1895年）：京都市立美術工芸学校（現：京都市立芸術大学）教諭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1895 : He became an instructor of Kyoto Prefectural School of Art and Crafts (the current Kyoto City University of Arts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1895: He became an instructor at the Kyoto Prefectural School of Art and Crafts (the current Kyoto City University of Arts).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1895: He became an instructor at the Kyoto Prefectural School of Art and Crafts (the current Kyoto City University of Arts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>この京都修行時代と推定されるが、雅号を「大観」とす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Estimated to be in this period of his training in Kyoto, he started using &apos;Taikan&apos; as his Gago (pseudonym).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Estimated to be in this period of his training in Kyoto, he started using &apos;Taikan&apos; as his gago (pseudonym).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Estimated to be in this period of his training in Kyoto, he started using &apos;Taikan&apos; as his gago (pseudonym).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>大観とはあらゆる大局的な観点から世界を見るという意味の法華経の経文からとったという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say this Gago derived from the text of Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra) in which Taikan is explained to mean to take every broad view of the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say this gago derived from the text of Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra), in which &quot;Taikan&quot; is explained to mean to take a very broad view of the world.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say this gago derived from the text of Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra), in which &quot;Taikan&quot; is explained to mean to take a very broad view of the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="91">
<j>明治29年（1896年）：東京美術学校助教授に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1896 : He took a position of Assistant Professor of the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1896: He accepted the position of assistant professor at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1896: He accepted the position of assistant professor at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="92">
<j>明治30年（1897年）：滝沢文子と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1897 : He married Fumiko TAKIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1897: He married Fumiko TAKIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1897: He married Fumiko TAKIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="93">
<j>明治31年（1898年）：岡倉天心が東京美術学校々長を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1898 : Tenshin OKAKURA resigned his position of the principal of the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1898: Tenshin OKAKURA resigned from his position as principal of the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1898: Tenshin OKAKURA resigned from his position as principal of the Tokyo School of Fine Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>大観、橋本雅邦ら14人も続いて辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then the 14 followers including Taikan and Gaho HASHIMOTO did, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, 14 followers--including Taikan and Gaho HASHIMOTO--did too.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, 14 followers--including Taikan and Gaho HASHIMOTO--did too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>その後、天心は日本美術院を設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After then, Tenshin established The Nihon Bijitsuin (The Japan Art Institute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Tenshin established the Nihon Bijitsuin (Japan Art Institute).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Tenshin established the Nihon Bijutsuin (Japan Art Institute).</e>
<cmt>BijitsuinをBijutsuinに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>そして観山、広業、春草、武山、等々がこれに従って、私財を投入して設立運営に奔走する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, Kanzan, Hironari, Shunso, Buzan and others followed Tenshin and were busily involved in the establishment and management putting in their own funds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanzan, Hironari, Shunso, Buzan and others then followed Tenshin and were busily involved in the establishment and management, investing their own funds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanzan, Hironari, Shunso, Buzan and others then followed Tenshin and were busily involved in the establishment and management, investing their own funds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="97">
<j>明治32年（1899年）：長女誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1899 : His first daughter was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1899: His first daughter was born.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1899: His first daughter was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="98">
<j>明治36年（1903年）：妻・文子死亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1903 : His wife, Fumiko died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1903: His wife Fumiko died.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1903: His wife Fumiko died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>インドを訪問。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He visited India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He visited India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He visited India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>釈迦の実像を描こうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried to draw a real image of Shakyamuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He tried to draw a real image of Shakyamuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He tried to draw a real image of Shakyamuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>岡倉天心の勧めるものであったが、天心は日本画の原点をインドと考えたのではないかという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was on the advice of Tenshin OKAKURA, and some say Tenshin regarded India as the starting point of Nihonga (Japanese painting).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was on the advice of Tenshin OKAKURA, and some say that Tenshin regarded India as the starting point of Nihonga (Japanese painting).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was on the advice of Tenshin OKAKURA, and some say that Tenshin regarded India as the starting point of Nihonga (Japanese painting).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="102">
<j>明治37年（1904年）：岡倉天心の勧めでニューヨークへ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1904 : He went to New York on the advice of Tenshin OKAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1904: He went to New York on the advice of Tenshin OKAKURA.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1904: He went to New York on the advice of Tenshin OKAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="103">
<j>明治38年（1905年）：イギリスのロンドンへ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1905 : He went to London, England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1905: He went to London, England.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1905: He went to London, England.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>長女死亡のため帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came back to Japan due to his first daughter&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Japan due to the death of his first daughter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Japan due to the death of his first daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="105">
<j>明治39年（1906年）：遠藤直子と再婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1906 : He remarried Naoko ENDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1906: He remarried Naoko ENDO.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1906: He remarried Naoko ENDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>岡倉天心が住んでいた茨城県の五浦へ転居。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He moved to Itsuura, Ibaraki Prefecture where Tenshin OKAKURA lived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved to Itsuura, Ibaraki Prefecture, where Tenshin OKAKURA lived.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved to Itsuura, Ibaraki Prefecture, where Tenshin OKAKURA lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>五浦での活動、つまり「日本美術院絵画部」は、天心、大観、春草、観山、武山の五名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His activities in Itsuura was based on &apos;Painting section of The Nihon Bijitsuin&apos; (The Japan Art Institute) which consisted of the five members, Tenshin, Taikan, Shunso, Kanzan and Buzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His activities in Itsuura were based on &apos;the Painting section of the Nihon Bijitsuin&apos; (Japan Art Institute), which consisted of the five members, Tenshin, Taikan, Shunso, Kanzan and Buzan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His activities in Itsuura were based on &apos;the Painting section of the Nihon Bijitsuin&apos; (Japan Art Institute), which consisted of the five members, Tenshin, Taikan, Shunso, Kanzan and Buzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="108">
<j>明治40年（1907年）：父死亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1907 : His father died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1907: His father died.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1907: His father died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>国が主催となって、官営の「文展」（文部省美術展覧会）が開催。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bunten exhibition (Annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education) was held under government management.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bunten exhibition (an annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education) was held under government management.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Bunten exhibition&apos; (an annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education) was held under government management.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>大観、観山は文展の審査員を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikan and kanzan were judges in the Bunten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan and kanzan were judges in the Bunten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan and Kanzan were judges in the Bunten.</e>
<cmt>kanzanをKanzanに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="111">
<j>明治43年（1910年）：中国へ出発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1910 : He left for China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1910: He left for China.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1910: He left for China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>ロバを買って帰る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He brought a donkey home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He brought a donkey home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He brought a donkey home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>第四回文展。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>審査員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a judge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a judge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a judge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>作品「楚水の巻」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made public his work, &apos;Sosui no maki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made public his work, &apos;Sosui no maki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made public his work, &apos;Sosui no maki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="116">
<j>明治45年（1912年）：明治天皇崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1912 : Emperor Meiji died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1912: Emperor Meiji died.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1912: Emperor Meiji died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>第六回文展。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixth Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixth Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="118">
<j>大正2年（1913年）：妻、直子が死す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1913 : His wife, Naoko died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1913: His wife Naoko died.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1913: His wife Naoko died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>第七回文展。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seventh Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventh Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventh Bunten was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>最後の審査員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a judge of the last occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a judge of the last occasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a judge of the last occasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>作品「松並木」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made public his work, &apos;Matsunamiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made public his work, &apos;Matsunamiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made public his work, &apos;Matsunamiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>9月、岡倉天心逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, Tenshin OKAKURA died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, Tenshin OKAKURA died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, Tenshin OKAKURA died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>門人代表の弔辞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a memorial address representing the followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made a memorial address representing the followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made a memorial address representing the followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="124">
<j>昭和3年（1928年）：ベニート・ムッソリーニに「立葵」が献呈される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1928 : &apos;Tachiaoi&apos; (hollyhock) was presented to Benito MUSSOLINI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1928: &apos;Tachiaoi (Hollyhock)&apos; was presented to Benito MUSSOLINI.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1928: &apos;Tachiaoi&apos; (Hollyhock) was presented to Benito MUSSOLINI.</e>
<cmt>()を&apos; &apos;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="125">
<j>昭和13年（1938年）：アドルフ・ヒトラーに献呈するため作品「旭日霊峰」を完成させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1938 : He finished his work, &apos;Kyokujitu Reiho&apos; to present it to Adolf Hitler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1938: He finished his work, &apos;Kyokujitu Reiho,&apos; to present it to Adolf Hitler.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1938: He finished his work, &apos;Kyokujitu Reiho,&apos; to present it to Adolf Hitler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="126">
<j>昭和33年（1958年）：死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1958 : He died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1958: He died.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1958: He died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="127">
<j>平成21年（2009年） 1月1日から、著作権が消滅し作品がパブリック・ドメインに。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 1, 2009, his works whose copyright expired came into the public domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1, 2009, his works whose copyrights had expired came into the public domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 2009, his works whose copyrights had expired came into the public domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 霧木諒二(id:9795), Nnh(id:474), Modeha(id:1276), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), Love-art(id:266624), 丸和太郎(id:169090), Unmaokur(id:120715), 堀田俊彦(id:154481), 端くれの錬金術師(id:23040), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Mnd(id:15140), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Gryphon(id:82594), PANYNJ(id:38638), いちごミルク(id:62955), 松茸(id:27535), AKIT(id:52404), Zzzz(id:16596), BodhisattvaBot(id:185411), MDR-SK(id:192066), Rusk(id:9895), 轍(id:290270), らっかさん(id:94610), 海衛士(id:19229), 663highland(id:18755), Dodon(id:187283), Khaosan Lover(id:161770), Poh(id:35479), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>