<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山内一豊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山内 一豊（やまうち かつとよ）は戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代、江戸時代の武将・大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI was a busho/daimyo(feudal lord) during the Sengoku (warring) Period (Japan), through the Azuchi-Momoyama Period to the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI was a busho/daimyo (feudal lord) during the Sengoku (Warring States) period (Japan), through the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI was a warrior and feudal lord from the Warring States period to the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>土佐山内氏の当主であり織田信長、豊臣秀吉、徳川家康らに仕え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the head of the Tosa Yamauchi clan and worked for Nobunaga ODA, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the head of the Tosa Yamauchi clan and worked for Nobunaga ODA, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the head of the Tosa Yamauchi clan and worked for Nobunaga ODA, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いにおいて家康方について功績を認められたため、土佐国20万石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His efforts on the Tokugawa side during the Battle of Sekigahara was recognized and he was given Tosa Province, 200,000-koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His efforts on the Tokugawa side during the Battle of Sekigahara were recognized, and he was given Tosa Province, equaling 200,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought for the Tokugawa side during the Battle of Sekigahara and his services were recognized; therefore, he was given Tosa Province, equaling 200,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>土佐藩初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first lord of the Tosa Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first lord of the Tosa domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first lord of the Tosa Domain.</e>
<cmt>domain語頭大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>岩倉織田氏の重臣・山内盛豊の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of Moritoyo YAMAUCHI, a chief vassal of the Iwakura Oda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of Moritoyo YAMAUCHI, a chief vassal of the Iwakura Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of Moritoyo YAMAUCHI, a chief vassal of the Iwakura Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は法秀尼（法秀院とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Hoshuni (some say Hoshuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Hoshuni (some say Hoshuin).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Hoshuni (or Hoshuin according to some opinions).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>尾張の土豪・梶原氏の娘か）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May be a daughter of the local clan, Kajiwara clan in Owari)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She might have been a daughter of the local clan, the Kajiwara clan of Owari.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She might have been a daughter from the Kajiwara clan, a local clan of Owari.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>祖父は山内久豊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather was Hisatoyo YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather was Hisatoyo YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather was Hisatoyo YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>兄に山内十郎、弟に山内康豊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brother was Juro YAMAUCHI, and younger brother was Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brother was Juro YAMAUCHI, and younger brother was Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brother was Juro YAMAUCHI, and his younger brother was Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>妻は内助の功で知られる見性院 (山内一豊室)（「千代」の名で有名だが、実名かどうかは定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife, Kenshoin (wife of Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI), is known as being a faithful and supportive partner(she is famous as &quot;Chiyo&quot;, but it is unknown whether this was her actual name).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife, Kenshoin (wife of Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI), is known as a faithful, supportive partner (she is famous as &quot;Chiyo,&quot; but it isn&apos;t known whether this was her actual name).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife, Kenshoin was known as a faithful, supportive partner (she is famous as &apos;Chiyo,&apos; but it isn&apos;t known whether this was her actual name).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>若宮友興の娘とも遠藤盛数の娘とも言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is said to be the daughter of Tomooki WAKAMIYA or alternatively, the daughter of Morikazu ENDO.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is said to have been the daughter of Tomooki WAKAMIYA, or alternatively the daughter of Morikazu ENDO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was also said to have been the daughter of Tomooki WAKAMIYA, or alternatively the daughter of Morikazu ENDO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>通称は伊右衛門もしくは猪右衛門（いえもん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was usually called Iemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was usually called Iemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went by the name of Iemon.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>のちに康豊の嫡男・山内忠義（第2代藩主）を養子とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later took Yasutoyo&apos;s legitimate son, Tadayoshi YAMAUCHI (second lord) as his foster son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later took Yasutoyo&apos;s legitimate son, Tadayoshi YAMAUCHI (second lord), as his foster son.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later took Yasutoyo&apos;s legitimate son, Tadayoshi YAMAUCHI (second lord), as his foster son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自と「山内一豊」の読み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin and reading of &quot;Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin and reading of &quot;Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin and reading of &apos;Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>一豊の生まれた土佐山内氏の出自については、江戸時代後半に作成された『寛政重修諸家譜』に土佐藩が提出した内容によれば藤原秀郷の子孫である首藤山内氏の末裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the origin of Tosa Yamauchi clan which Katsutoyo was born to, the content submitted by the Tosa domain for the &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (A record of family trees of samurai warriors of Edo bakufu) produced in the latter half of the Edo Period states that they are the descendants of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan, who are the descendants of FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the origin of the Tosa Yamauchi clan into which Katsutoyo was born, the content submitted by the Tosa domain for the &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (a record of family trees of samurai warriors of the Edo bakufu) produced in the latter half of the Edo period stated that they were the descendants of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan, who were the descendants of FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the origin of the Tosa Yamauchi clan into which Katsutoyo was born, the content submitted by the Tosa Domain for the &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (a record of family trees of samurai warriors of the Edo bakufu) produced in the latter half of the Edo period stated that they were the descendants of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan, who were the descendants of FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>domain語頭大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただし首藤山内氏の明らかな末裔は戦国時代当時には別に備後国に存在し（この山内氏はその後毛利氏に帰属し、江戸時代まで続いている）ている一方、一豊の山内氏は曽祖父以前から八代分について名前すら伝わっておらず本当に首藤山内氏の末裔であるかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is unknown whether they were actually the descendants of the Sudo Yamanouchi because the apparent descendants of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan existed separately in Bigo Province during the Sengoku Period (this Yamauchi clan later became part of the Mori clan and continued into the Edo Period) and even the names for eight generations of Yamauchi clan preceding Katsutoyo&apos;s great grandfather are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it isn&apos;t known whether they were actually the descendants of the Sudo Yamanouchi because the apparent descendants of that clan existed separately in Bigo Province during the Sengoku period (this Yamauchi clan later became part of the Mori clan and continued into the Edo period) and even the names for eight generations of the Yamauchi clan preceding Katsutoyo&apos;s great grandfather are unknown.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it isn&apos;t known whether they were actually the descendants of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan because the apparent descendants of that clan existed separately in Bigo Province during the Warring States period (this Yamauchi clan later became part of the Mori clan and continued into the Edo period) and a record of even the name of the ascendants of Kazutoyo has not been found for eight generations preceding Katsutoyo&apos;s great grandfather.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また会津地方では葦名氏に仕えた山内氏（首藤山内氏の庶流）の子が流浪して信長に仕えたのが一豊であるとする伝承もあるが、これは尾張時代の一豊の事績と合致しないために否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is folklore in the Aizu region saying that Katsutoyo was part of the Yamauchi clan which worked for Ashina clan who became Nobunaga&apos;s vassal when he wandered, but this does not fit Katsutoyo&apos;s accomplishments during the Owari period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folklore of the Aizu region says that Katsutoyo was part of the Yamauchi clan, which worked for the Ashina clan, which in turn became Nobunaga&apos;s vassal when he wandered, but this doesn&apos;t fit Katsutoyo&apos;s accomplishments during the Owari period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folklore of the Aizu region says that Katsutoyo was part of the Yamauchi clan (a branch family of Sudo Ymanouchi clan), which worked for the Ashina clan, which in turn became Nobunaga&apos;s vassal when he wandered, but this doesn&apos;t fit Katsutoyo&apos;s accomplishments during the Owari period.</e>
<cmt>(a branch family of Sudo Ymanouchi clan)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>一豊の山内氏が尾張国（愛知県西部）に名を表すようになったのは一豊の祖父・久豊からであると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsutoyo&apos;s Yamauchi clan begins to appear in the history of Owari Province (west Aichi Prefecture) from the time of Katsutoyo&apos;s grandfather, Hisatoyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsutoyo&apos;s Yamauchi clan begins to appear in the history of Owari Province (western Aichi Prefecture) from the time of Katsutoyo&apos;s grandfather, Hisatoyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Katsutoyo&apos;s Yamauchi clan began to appear in the history of the Owari Province (western Aichi Prefecture) from the time of Katsutoyo&apos;s grandfather, Hisatoyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>それ以前については丹波国三宮城（京都府船井郡京丹波町三ノ宮）あたりを拠点としていた小豪族がそれに当たるとも考えられるが、定かではない（その可能性をにおわせる史料は残っている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the family history before this, there are theories saying that it could have been a small local clan based in Sanomiyajo, Tanba Province (Sannomiya, Kyotanba-cho, Funai-gun, Kyoto Prefecture), but this is unclear (there are historical documents that hint this possibility).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the family history before this, some theories assert that it could have been a small local clan based in Sanomiyajo, Tanba Province (Sannomiya, Kyotanba-cho, Funai-gun, Kyoto Prefecture), but this is unclear (certain historical documents hint at this possibility).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the family history before this, some theories assert that it could have been a small local clan based in Sanomiyajo, Tanba Province (Sannomiya, Kyotanba-cho, Funai-gun, Kyoto Prefecture), but this is unclear (certain historical documents hint at this possibility).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし一豊の父・盛豊については尾張上四郡を支配する守護代・岩倉織田氏に重臣として仕えていたことは間違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Katsutoyo&apos;s father, Moritoyo was definitely a chief vassal of Iwakura Oda clan, who ruled the four upper districts of Owari as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Katsutoyo&apos;s father Moritoyo was definitely a chief vassal of the Iwakura Oda clan, which ruled the four upper districts of Owari as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Katsutoyo&apos;s father Moritoyo was definitely a chief vassal of the Iwakura Oda clan, which ruled the four upper districts of Owari as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>「山内」「一豊」の読み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reading of &quot;Yamauchi&quot;&quot;Katsutoyo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reading of &quot;Yamauchi&quot; and &quot;Katsutoyo&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reading of &apos;Yamauchi&apos; and &apos;Katsutoyo&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>「山内」の読みについて、多くの歴史参考書や辞典などでは「やまのうち」と訓むとされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reading of &quot;Yamauchi&quot; was considered to be read as &quot;Yamanouchi&quot; in many historical reference books and dictionaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reading of &quot;Yamauchi&quot; was considered to be &quot;Yamanouchi&quot; in many historical reference books and dictionaries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reading of &apos;Yamauchi&apos; was considered to be &apos;Yamanouchi&apos; in many historical reference books and dictionaries.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これは、先に書いたとおり土佐山内氏が祖先であるとする首藤山内氏が「やまのうち」と訓むことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is following the reading of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan, read as &quot;Yamanouchi&quot;, who are thought to be the ancestors of the Tosa Yamauchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This follows the reading of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan, read as &quot;Yamanouchi,&quot; who are thought to be the ancestors of the Tosa Yamauchi clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This follows the reading of the Sudo Yamanouchi clan, read as &apos;Yamanouchi,&apos; who are thought to be the ancestors of the Tosa Yamauchi clan.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>現に首藤山内氏が苗字の元とした鎌倉・山内庄（神奈川県鎌倉市山ノ内）の地名は「やまのうち」と訓む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In deed, the place name of Yamanouchisho, Kamakura (Yamanouchi, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) which became the basis for reading the family name of Sudo Yamanouchi clan as &quot;Yamanouchi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indeed, the place name of Yamanouchisho, Kamakura (Yamanouchi, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) became the basis for reading the family name of Sudo Yamanouchi clan as &quot;Yamanouchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed, the toponym of Yamanouchisho, Kamakura (Yamanouchi, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) became the basis for reading the family name of Sudo Yamanouchi clan as &apos;Yamanouchi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>一方、一豊の山内氏は既出の『寛政重修諸家譜』には「やまうち」とひらがなでルビがふってある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the aforementioned &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot;has hiragana readings of Katsutoyo&apos;s Yamauchi clan as &quot;Yamauchi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the aforementioned &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; has hiragana readings of Katsutoyo&apos;s Yamauchi clan as &quot;Yamauchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the aforementioned &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; has hiragana readings of Katsutoyo&apos;s Yamauchi clan as &apos;Yamauchi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また淀殿の侍女であった大蔵卿局が一豊に向けて送った書簡が現在も山内家に残っているがそのあて先はひらがなで「やまうちつしまどの」となっており、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a letter addressed to Katsutoyo from Okurakyo-no-tsubone, a lady-in-waiting for Yododono that still exists as part of the Yamauchi family possessions writes the address in hiragana as &quot;Yamauchitsushima dono&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, a letter addressed to Katsutoyo from Okurakyo-no-tsubone, a lady-in-waiting for Yododono, which still exists as part of the Yamauchi family possessions, writes the address in hiragana as &quot;Yamauchitsushima dono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a letter addressed to Katsutoyo from Okurakyo-no-tsubone, a lady-in-waiting for Yododono, still exists in the present Yamauchi family and writes the address in hiragana as &apos;Yamauchitsushima dono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これらの点から最近では「やまうち」と訓むのが正しいのではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the above evidence, it has been recently considered that the correct reading of the name is &quot;Yamauchi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the above evidence, it has been recently considered that the correct reading of the name is &quot;Yamauchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the above evidence, it has been recently considered that the correct reading of the name is &apos;Yamauchi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>次に「一豊」の読みについては一般的には「かずとよ」と訓まれてきたが、一豊が偏諱を家臣に与えた際の訓みから「かつとよ」であると実際には考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, regarding the reading of his given name, it is conventionally read as &quot;Kazutoyo&quot;, but it is actually thought to be read &quot;Katsutoyo&quot; judging from the reading of subordinates who received the use of a character from his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, regarding the reading of his given name, it is conventionally read as &quot;Kazutoyo&quot; but is actually thought to be read &quot;Katsutoyo,&quot; judging from the reading of subordinates who received the use of a character from his name.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, regarding the pronunciation of his given name, it is conventionally read as &apos;Kazutoyo&apos; but is actually thought to be read &apos;Katsutoyo,&apos; judging from the pronunciation of subordinates who received the use of a character from his name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>2006年に放送された大河ドラマ『功名が辻 (NHK大河ドラマ)』では、「かつとよ」「かずとよ」いずれの読みとするか製作サイドでも最後まで問題となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The production team of the 2006 NHK Historical drama series, &quot;Komyogatsuji (Crossroads of a great achievement)&quot; deliberated until the last moment about which reading, &quot;Katsutoyo&quot; or &quot;Kazutoyo&quot;, to use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The production team of the 2006 NHK Historical drama series, &quot;Komyogatsuji (Crossroads of a Great Achievement)&quot; deliberated until the last moment about which reading, &quot;Katsutoyo&quot; or &quot;Kazutoyo,&quot; should be used.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The production team of the 2006 NHK Historical drama series, &quot;Komyogatsuji&quot; (Crossroads of a Great Achievement) deliberated until the last moment about which pronunciation, &apos;Katsutoyo&apos; or &apos;Kazutoyo,&apos; should be used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これについて、現在の山内家より「親しまれている名前で呼んでやってください」とのメッセージがあり「やまうちかずとよ」と読むことになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current Yamauchi family sent a message saying &quot;Please use the name that is familiar to most people&quot;, and the team settled on &quot;Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current Yamauchi family sent a message saying, &quot;Please use the name that is familiar to most people,&quot; and the team settled on &quot;Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The team settled on &apos;Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI.&apos; according to the message fom the current Yamauchi family, &apos;Please use the name that is familiar to most people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>立身</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>尾張国葉栗郡黒田（現在の愛知県一宮市木曽川町黒田）にある山内家の居城であった黒田城 (尾張国)に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born at Kuroda Castle (Owari Province), the residential castle of the Yamauchi family located in Kuroda, Haguri District, Owari Province(currently, Kuroda, Kisogawa-cho, Ichinomiya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born at Kuroda Castle (Owari Province), the residential castle of the Yamauchi family located in Kuroda, Haguri District, Owari Province (currently Kuroda, Kisogawa-cho, Ichinomiya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kurodajo Castle (Owari Province), the residential castle of the Yamauchi family located in Kuroda, Haguri District, Owari Province (currently Kuroda, Kisogawa-cho, Ichinomiya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>当時山内家は岩倉城 (尾張国)織田氏（当主は織田信安、のち織田信賢）の配下であり、父・盛豊は家老として仕えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the Yamauchi family was under the protection of Iwakura-jo Castle (Owari Province) Oda clan (the head was Nobuyasu ODA, subsequently Obukata ODA) and his father, Moritoyo was a chief vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamauchi family was then under the protection of Iwakura-jo Castle (Owari Province) and the Oda clan (the head was Nobuyasu ODA, subsequently Obukata ODA) and his father, Moritoyo, was a chief vassal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamauchi family was then under the protection of the Oda clan (the head was Nobuyasu ODA, subsequently Nobukata ODA) of Iwakurajo Castle (Owari Province), and his father, Moritoyo, was a chief vassal.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>ところが岩倉織田氏は同族の有力者・織田信長と対立し、家老である山内家もこれに巻き込まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Iwakura Oda clan opposed the powerful Nobunaga ODA who was kin, and Yamauchi family was drawn into this conflict as a chief vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Iwakura Oda clan opposed the powerful Nobunaga ODA, who was kin, and the Yamauchi family was drawn into this conflict as a chief vassal.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Iwakura Oda clan opposed its kin, powerful Nobunaga ODA, and the Yamauchi family was drawn into this conflict as a chief vassal.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>まず弘治_(日本)3年（1557年）に兄十郎が盗賊（織田信長の手勢であるといわれる）に黒田城を襲撃された際に討死、さらに永禄2年（1559年）に主家の居城・岩倉城が落城、この際に父・盛豊が討死ないし自刃した可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, in 1557, his elder brother Juro was killed by pirates (thought to be in league with Nobunaga ODA) when Kuroda-jo Castle was attacked, and in 1559, their lord&apos;s residential castle, Iwakura-jo Castle fell and it is highly probable that his father, Moritoyo was killed or committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, in 1557 his elder brother Juro was killed by pirates (thought to be in league with Nobunaga ODA) when Kuroda-jo Castle was attacked, and in 1559 their lord&apos;s residential castle, Iwakura-jo, fell; it is very likely that his father Moritoyo was killed or committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, in 1557, Kuroda-jo Castle was attacked by pirates (thought to be in league with Nobunaga ODA) and his elder brother Juro was killed, and in 1559, their lord&apos;s residential castle Iwakurajo Castle fell; it is very likely that his father Moritoyo was killed or committed suicide here.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>こうして主家と当主を失った山内一族は離散し流浪することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence the Yamauchi family fell into pieces and wandered after losing their lord and head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence the Yamauchi family fell to pieces and wandered after losing its lord and head.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence the Yamauchi family was broken up and wandered as they lost their lord and head.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>一豊自身は当初は苅安賀城（一宮市）主・浅井政貞、松倉城 (尾張国)（岐阜県各務原市）主・前野長康、その後尾張を出て美濃国牧村城（岐阜県安八郡安八町）主・牧村政倫や近江国勢多城（滋賀県大津市）主・山岡景隆に仕えるなどした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsutoyo himself initially worked for Kariyasuka-jo Castle (Ichinomiya City) lord Masasada AZAI, Matsukura-jo Castle (Owari Province)(Kakamigahara City, Gifu Prefecture) lord Nagayasu MAENO, and later left Owari and worked for Makimura-jo Castle in Mino Province (Anpachi-cho, Anpachi-gun, Gifu Prefecture) lord Masatomo MAKIMURA and Omi Province Seta-jo Castle (Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) lord Kagetaka YAMAOKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsutoyo himself initially worked for the Kariyasuka-jo Castle (Ichinomiya City) lord Masasada AZAI, the Matsukura-jo Castle (Owari Province) (Kakamigahara City, Gifu Prefecture) lord Nagayasu MAENO, but later left Owari and worked for Makimura-jo Castle in Mino Province (Anpachi-cho, Anpachi-gun, Gifu Prefecture) lord Masatomo MAKIMURA and Omi Province Seta-jo Castle (Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) lord Kagetaka YAMAOKA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsutoyo himself initially worked for the lord of Kariyasukajo Castle (Ichinomiya City) Masasada AZAI, and the lord of Matsukurajo Castle (Owari Province) (Kakamigahara City, Gifu Prefecture) Nagayasu MAENO, then left Owari and worked for the lord of Makimurajo Castle in Mino Province (Anpachi-cho, Anpachi-gun, Gifu Prefecture) Masatomo MAKIMURA, and the lord of Omi Province Seta-jo Castle (Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) Kagetaka YAMAOKA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし永禄11年（1568年）頃には織田信長に仕え、木下秀吉（のちの豊臣秀吉）の与力となったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1568, he worked for Nobunaga ODA and became Hideyoshi KINOSHITA (later known as Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)&apos;s yoriki (a police sergeant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In about 1568, he worked for Nobunaga ODA and became Hideyoshi KINOSHITA (later known as Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)&apos;s yoriki (police sergeant).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1568, he worked for Nobunaga ODA and became yoriki (police sergeant) of Hideyoshi KINOSHITA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>その後、元亀元年（1570年）9月の姉川の戦いで初陣し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in Sept. 1570, the Battle of Anegawa was his first battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in September 1570, the Battle of Anegawa was his first military engagement.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he had his first military engagement in the Battle of Anegawa in October and November 1570.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>天正元年（1573年）8月の朝倉氏との刀禰坂の戦いにも参加し顔に重傷を負いながらも敵将三段崎為之を討ち取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Aug. 1573, he participated in the Battle of Tonezaka against the Asakura clan and even though his face was seriously injured, he killed the enemy warrior, Tameyuki MITAZAKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1573, he participated in the Battle of Tonezaka against the Asakura clan, and even though his face was seriously injured he killed the enemy warrior, Tameyuki MITAZAKI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September and October 1573, he fought in the Battle of Tonezaka against the Asakura clan, and even though his face was seriously injured, he killed the enemy warrior Tameyuki MITAZAKI..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>このとき一豊の頬に刺さったと伝えられる矢はこのとき矢を抜いた郎党の五藤為浄の子孫が家宝とし、現在高知県安芸市の歴史民俗資料館に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The arrow that pierced Katsutoyo&apos;s cheek became the family treasure of the descendants of the retainer, Tamekiyo GOTO, who pulled the arrow out and this is currently owned by the Folk Heritage Museum in Aki City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The arrow that pierced Katsutoyo&apos;s cheek became the family treasure of the descendants of the retainer, Tamekiyo GOTO, who pulled the arrow out and this is currently owned by the Folk Heritage Museum in Aki City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The arrow that pierced Katsutoyo&apos;s cheek became the family treasure of the descendants of his retainer Tamekiyo GOTO, who pulled the arrow out, and is currently owned by the Folk Heritage Museum in Aki City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>「山内一豊の妻」こと見性院 (山内一豊室)との結婚は、元亀年間から天正元年（1573年）の間であったと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The marriage to &quot;Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s wife&quot; otherwise known as Kenshoin (wife of Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI) was probably sometime between the Genki period to 1573.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The marriage to &quot;Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s wife,&quot; otherwise known as Kenshoin (wife of Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI) probably occurred sometime between the Genki period and 1573.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The marriage to his wife, who was known as Kenshoin, probably occurred sometime between the Genki era (1570) and Tensho era (1573).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="40">
<j>これらの功績により、近江国浅井郡唐国（現在の東浅井郡虎姫町域）で400石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to these achievements, he was given 400 koku in Karakuni, Asai District, Omi Province(currently, Torahime-cho, Higashiazai District).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to these achievements, he was given 400 koku in Karakuni, Asai District, Omi Province (currently Torahime-cho, Higashiazai District).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to these achievements, he was given 400 koku (a quantity of rice to feed one person for one year) in Karakuni, Asai District, Omi Province (currently Torahime-cho, Higashiazai-gun).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この際に秀吉自身が自身の郎党をほとんど持たないことから彼の直臣に立場を変えたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Hideyoshi himself hardly had any retainers himself and he changed his position to become his direct vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Hideyoshi himself hardly had any retainers, so he changed his position to become his own direct vassal.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Hideyoshi hardly had any retainers for himself, so Katsutoyo changed his position to become Hideyoshi&apos;s own direct vassal.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>なお、400石という禄は同僚であった浅野長政・堀尾吉晴・中村一氏らが同じ時期に100石台であったことから、彼らより一歩先に出るものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the fact that his colleagues, Nagamasa ASANO, Yoshiharu HORIO, Kazuuji NAKAMURA were about 100 koku at the same time, he was one step ahead with 400 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the fact that his colleagues Nagamasa ASANO, Yoshiharu HORIO and Kazuuji NAKAMURA were about 100 koku at the same time, he was one step ahead with 400 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the fact that his colleagues Nagamasa ASANO, Yoshiharu HORIO and Kazuuji NAKAMURA received about 100 koku level at the same time, he was one step ahead with 400 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="43">
<j>この後天正5年（1577年）には播磨国有年（兵庫県赤穂市内）を中心に2000石を領している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in 1577, he was given 2000 koku in Une, Harima Province (within Akaho City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, in 1577 he was given 2000 koku in Une, Harima Province (within Akaho City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in 1577 he was given 2000 koku in Une, Harima Province (within Akaho City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>その後も秀吉の中国地方経略に加わり、播磨の三木城を巡る戦い（三木合戦）や因幡国の鳥取城包囲などに参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he joined in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Chugoku region and participated in the battle regarding Miki-jo Castle of Harima (Battle of Miki-jo Castle) and the siege of Totori-jo Castle in Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he joined in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of the Chugoku region and participated in the battle regarding Miki-jo Castle at Harima (the Battle of Miki-jo Castle) and the siege of Totori-jo Castle in Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he joined Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of the Chugoku region and fought in the battle over Mikijo Castle at Harima (the Battle of Mikijo Castle) and the siege of Tottori-jo Castle in Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>豊臣幕下の小大名として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period as one of the minor daimyo in the Toyotomi government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period as a minor daimyo in the Toyotomi government</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period as a minor feudal lord in the Toyotomi government</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>信長の死後もそのまま秀吉の家臣として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga&apos;s death,he continued to be active as Hideyoshi&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga&apos;s death, Katsutoyo continued to be active as Hideyoshi&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga died, Katsutoyo continued to be active as Hideyoshi&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>天正11年（1583年）の賤ケ岳の戦いでは、その前哨である亀山城 (伊勢国)（三重県亀山市）攻めで一番乗りの手柄をあげている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1583, the Battle of Shizukatake, he had the honor of being the first one to reach the enemy at the attack on Kameyama-jo Castle(Ise Province)(Kameyama City, Mie Prefecture) which was a preliminary battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1583, at the Battle of Shizukatake, he had the honor of being the first one to reach the enemy at the attack on Kameyama-jo Castle (Ise Province) (Kameyama City, Mie Prefecture), which was a preliminary battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the preliminary battle of the Battle of Shizukatake in 1583, he had the honor of being the first one to reach the enemy at the attack on Kameyamajo Castle (Ise Province) (Kameyama City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、翌12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いの参加の際には秀吉から命じられて家康を包囲するための付城（前線基地）構築に当たっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year in 1584, he participated in the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute and was ordered by Hideyoshi to construct the tsukejiro (front line base) to surround Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year (1584) he participated in the battles of Komaki and Nagakute and was instructed by Hideyoshi to construct the tsukejiro (front line base) in order to surround Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year (1584) he participated in the battles of Komaki and Nagakute and was instructed by Hideyoshi to construct the tsukejiro (front line base) in order to surround Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この後秀吉の甥・豊臣秀次の宿老となり天正13年（1585年）には若狭国高浜城主、まもなく近江長浜城 (近江国)主となり2万石を領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in 1585, he became Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;s chief vassal and became the lord of Takahama-jo Castle, Wakasa Province and soon after lord of Omi Nagahama-jo Castle (Omi Province) and became the lord of 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in 1585, he became the chief vassal of Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and later became the lord of Takahama-jo Castle, Wakasa Province; soon after that, he became the lord of Omi Nagahama-jo Castle (Omi Province) and the recipient of 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in 1585, he became the chief vassal of Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and later became the lord of Takahama-jo Castle, Wakasa Province; before long, he became the lord of Omi Nagahama-jo Castle (Omi Province) and received 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この時期に同じく秀次の宿老に列した中に田中吉政・堀尾吉晴・中村一氏・一柳直末らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Yoshimasa TANAKA, Yoshiharu HORIO, Kazuuji NAKAMURA and Naosue HITOTSUYAMANGI were chief vassals of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Yoshimasa TANAKA, Yoshiharu HORIO, Kazuuji NAKAMURA and Naosue HITOTSUYAMANGI were chief vassals of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Yoshimasa TANAKA, Yoshiharu HORIO, Kazuuji NAKAMURA and Naosue HITOTSUYANAGI were chief vassals of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>名前スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>なお、同年に起こった天正大地震によって一人娘の与祢姫を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, he lost his only daughter, Yonehime, during the Tensho Great Earthquake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, he lost his only daughter, Yonehime, during the Tensho Great Earthquake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, he lost his only daughter, Yonehime, during the Great Tensho Earthquake.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>このころ従五位対馬守に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed Junior Fifth Low Court Rank and Chief of the Province of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed Junior Fifth Low Court Rank and Chief of the Province of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed Junior Fifth Low Court Rank and Chief of the Province of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>天正18年（1590年）の小田原の陣にも参戦し、山中城攻めに参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1590, he participated in the Battle of Odawara and the attack on Yamanaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1590, he participated in the Battle of Odawara and the attack on Yamanaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1590, he participated in the Battle of Odawara, and attacked Yamanaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>まもなく遠江国掛川城に5万1000石の所領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after, he was given the 51,000 koku Kakegawa Castle in the Totomi province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon afterward, he was given the 51,000 koku Kakegawa Castle in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon afterward, he was given the land yeilding 51,000 koku of rice a year (1 koku is 5 bushels) in Kakegawa-jo Castle in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>掛川では城の修築と城下町づくりを行い、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kakegawa, he restored the castle and constructed the castle town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kakegawa, he restored the castle and constructed the castle town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kakegawa, he restored the castle and constructed the castle-town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>更に洪水の多かった大井川の堤防の建設や流路の変更を川向いを領する駿府城主・中村一氏とともに行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with Sunpu-jo Castle head Kazuuji NAKAMURA who was across the river, he constructed dikes and changed the flow of Oi River which frequently caused floods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with the Sunpu-jo Castle head Kazuuji NAKAMURA, who was across the river, he constructed dikes and changed the flow of the Oi River, which frequently caused floods.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with the Sunpu-jo Castle lord Kazuuji NAKAMURA, who ruled the land across the river, Katsutoyo constructed dikes and changed the flow of the Oi River, which frequently caused floods.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>また文禄・慶長の役には他の秀次の宿老格であった諸大名と同じく出兵を免れたが、軍船の建造や伏見城の普請などを担当して人夫を供出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Bunroku-Keicho War, he was exempt from war duty like other daimyo of chief vassal class of Hidetsugu, but he provided manpower for building war ships and constructing Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Bunroku-Keicho War, he was exempt from war duty like other daimyo of the chief-vassal class of Hidetsugu, but he provided manpower for building war ships and constructing Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Bunroku-Keicho War, he was exempt from war duty like other feudal lord of the chief-vassal class of Hidetsugu, but he provided manpower for building war ships and constructing Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）には秀次が謀反の疑いで処刑され、一豊と同じく秀次付き重臣であった渡瀬繁詮はこの事件に関わって秀次を弁護したために切腹させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1595, Hidetsugu was executed under suspicion of treason, and Shigeaki WATARASE, who was an advisor of Hidetsugu, was forced to commit ritual suicide when he became involved in this incident and tried to defend Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1595, Hidetsugu was executed under suspicion of treason, and Shigeaki WATARASE, who was an advisor of Hidetsugu, was forced to commit ritual suicide when he became involved in this incident and tried to defend Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1595, Hidetsugu was executed under suspicion of treason, while Shigeaki WATARASE, an advisor to Hidetsugu along with Katsutoyo, being forced to commit ritual suicide when he became involved in this incident and tried to defend Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし一豊は他の宿老の田中・中村・堀尾らとともに無関係の立場を貫き、連座を免れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Katsutoyo and the other chief vassals, Tanaka, Nakamura and Horio continued to take the position of having nothing to do with the incident and managed to evade punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Katsutoyo and the other chief vassals Tanaka, Nakamura and Horio continued to take the position of having nothing to do with the incident and managed to avoid punishment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Katsutoyo and the other chief vassals (Tanaka, Nakamura and Horio) continued taking the position of having nothing to do with the incident and managed to avoid punishment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>このときに秀次の所領から8000石を加増されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">8,000 koku of Hidetsugu&apos;s territory became Katsutoyo&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus 8,000 koku of Hidetsugu&apos;s territory became Katsutoyo&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, 8,000 koku of Hidetsugu&apos;s territory became Katsutoyo&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>秀吉の死後の慶長5年（1600年）には五大老の徳川家康に従って会津の上杉景勝の討伐に参加し、家康の留守中に五奉行の石田三成らが挙兵すると東軍に与している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death in 1600, he followed one of the Gotairo(Council of Five Elders) Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and participated in subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI, and when Gobugyo (five major magistrates) Mitsunari ISHIDA raised his forces while Ieyasu was away, Katsutoyo joined the east forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death in 1600, he followed one of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and participated in the subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI, and when Gobugyo (of the five major magistrates) Mitsunari ISHIDA raised his forces while Ieyasu was away, Katsutoyo joined the eastern forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death in 1600, he participated in the subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI following one of the Council of Five Elders, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and when one of the five major magistrates, Mitsunari ISHIDA raised his forces while Ieyasu was away, Katsutoyo joined the eastern forces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>この最中、一豊は下野国小山城における軍議（いわゆる「小山評定」）で諸将が東軍西軍への去就に迷う中、真っ先に自分の居城である掛川城を家康に提供する旨を発言しその歓心を買っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, when many of the warriors were determining whether to join the west forces or the east forces during the war council at Shimotsuke Province, Koyama-jo Castle (the so called &quot;Koyama Council&quot;), Katsutoyo immediately offered his residential castle, Kakegawa-jo Castle, to Ieyasu and gained his favor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, when many of the warriors were determining whether to join the western forces or the eastern forces during the war council at Shimotsuke Province, Koyama-jo Castle (the so-called &quot;Koyama Council&quot;), Katsutoyo immediately offered his residential castle, Kakegawa-jo Castle, to Ieyasu and gained his favor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, when many of the warriors were determining whether to join the western forces or the eastern forces during the war council called the Koyama Counci at Shimotsuke Province, Koyama-jo Castle, Katsutoyo immediately offered his residential castle, Kakegawa-jo Castle, to Ieyasu and gained his favor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>この居城を提供する案は堀尾忠氏と事前に協議した際に堀尾が提案したものを盗んだといわれる（新井白石『藩翰譜』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This plan to provide his castle was originally proposed by Takauji HORIO when they were discussing events in advance but Katsutoyo took credit for it (Hakuseki ARAI &quot;Hankanpu (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan to provide his castle was originally proposed by Takauji HORIO when they were discussing events in advance, but Katsutoyo took credit for it (Hakuseki ARAI, &quot;Hankanpu (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan to provide his castle was originally proposed by Takauji HORIO when they were discussing in advance, but Katsutoyo borrowed it (Hakuseki ARAI, &quot;Hankanpu&quot; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ただし東海道筋の他の大名である中村一氏が死の床にあり、同じく忠氏の父堀尾吉晴も刺客に襲われて重傷を負うなど老練な世代が行動力を失っているなかで周辺の勢力が東軍につくよう一豊が積極的にとりまとめていたことは事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is true that Katsutoyo was being actively wooed by the people around him to join the east forces because other Tokaido daimyo, especially the older generation were losing power since Kazuuji NAKAMURA was near death and Takauji&apos;s father Yoshiharu HORIO was seriously injured after an attack by an assassin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is true that Katsutoyo was being actively wooed by the people around him to join the eastern forces because other Tokaido daimyo, particularly the older generation, were losing power since Kazuuji NAKAMURA was near death and Takauji&apos;s father, Yoshiharu HORIO, was seriously injured after an attack by a would-be assassin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is true that Katsutoyo was actively wooing the people around him to join the eastern forces because other Tokaido feudal lords, particularly the older generation, were losing power since Kazuuji NAKAMURA was near death and Takauji&apos;s father, Yoshiharu HORIO, was seriously injured after an attack by a would-be assassin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>三河国吉田城 (三河国)主の池田輝政などもこの時期、一豊とたびたび接触しており、なんらかの打ち合わせをしていると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terumasa IKEDA of Mikawa Province Yoshida-jo Castle (Mikawa Province) also had frequent contact with Katsutoyo and it is assumed they discussed issues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terumasa IKEDA of Mikawa Province Yoshida-jo Castle (Mikawa Province) also had frequent contact with Katsutoyo, and it is assumed that they discussed the issues at hand.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terumasa IKEDA, the lord of Yoshida-jo Castle in Mikawa Province also had frequent contact with Katsutoyo, and it is assumed that they discussed the issues at hand.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い本戦では毛利・長宗我部軍などの押さえを担当し、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the main battle of the Battle of Sekigahara, he was in charge of opposing Mori and Chosokabe troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the main conflict of the Battle of Sekigahara, he was in charge of opposing the Mori and Chosokabe troops.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the main conflict of the Battle of Sekigahara, Katsutoyo was in charge of opposing the Mori and Chosokabe troops.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>さしたる手柄はなかったものの戦前の功績を高く評価され土佐国一国・9万8000石（太閤検地時に長宗我部氏が提出した石高、のちに山内氏自身の検地で20万2,600石余の石高を申告）を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he did make any prominent contributions during the battle, his achievements before the battle were highly recognized and he received the whole of Tosa Province, 98,000 koku (koku number submitted by the Chosokabe clan at the Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) but later accounted as 202,600 koku from a land survey by the Yamauchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he didn&apos;t make a prominent contribution during the battle, his achievements prior to the fight were highly recognized and he received the whole of Tosa Province, being 98,000 koku (a koku number submitted by the Chosokabe clan at the Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), which was later accounted as 202,600 koku from a land survey by the Yamauchi clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he didn&apos;t make a prominent contribution during the battle, his achievements prior to the fight were highly recognized and he received the Tosa Province worth 98,000 koku (a koku number submitted by the Chosokabe clan at the Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), which was later accounted as 202,600 koku from a land survey by the Yamauchi clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>土佐一国の領主として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As lord of the whole of Tosa Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As lord of all Tosa Province</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lord of Tosa Province</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>慶長6年（1601年）に領地を掛川から土佐に移封となり浦戸城に入城する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601, his land was transferred from Kakegawa to Tosa and he entered Urato-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601, his land was transferred from Kakegawa to Tosa and he entered Urato-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601, his land was transferred from Kakegawa to Tosa and he made a triumphal entry into Urato-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>大幅な加増があり余所から入部してきた大名はただでさえ人手も足りなくなるので地元の元家臣を大量に雇用するのが常であったが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo who received much larger land and came from a different place had problems filling the ranks and usually hired many of the former local vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo who had received much larger amounts of land and came from a different place had problems filling the ranks, so they usually hired many of the former local vassals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The feudal lords who had received much larger amounts of land and came from a different place usually hired many of the former local vassals because they had problems filling the ranks.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>一領具足を中心とした旧長宗我部氏の武士の多くは新領主に反発し土佐国内で多くの紛争（旧主長宗我部盛親の復帰を求めるなど）を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Chosokabe clan bushi were mainly ichiryo gusoku (cultivators who were allowed to arm themselves) and rebelled against the new lord and caused many battles within Tosa Province (demanding the return of the former lord Morichika CHOSOKABE).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Chosokabe clan bushi were mainly ichiryo gusoku (cultivators who were allowed to arm themselves) who rebelled against the new lord and caused many battles within Tosa Province (such as in demanding the return of the former lord, Morichika CHOSOKABE).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Chosokabe clan warriors were mainly the cultivators who were allowed to arm themselves who rebelled against the new lord and caused many battles within Tosa Province (such as in demanding the return of the former lord, Morichika CHOSOKABE).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>これに対し一豊は重要なポストを外部からの人材で固め、種崎浜での討伐などあくまで武断措置を取ってこれに対応した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In return, Katsutoyo used people from other places for important positions and used military force such as the attack at Tanezaki Beach.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In return, Katsutoyo used people from other places for important positions and used military force such as the attack at Tanezaki Beach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, Katsutoyo used people from other places for important positions and dared to use military force such as the attack at Tanezaki Beach.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この為に命を狙われる危険性があり、築城の際などには5人の影武者と共に現地を視察した（影武者の存在などは機密事項であったため通常記録には残らないが、一豊の場合には明記されている稀有な事例）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there was the danger of assassination and he took 5 kagemusha (body double) with him when he inspected sites such as castle construction (the existence of kagemusha is confidential and normally is not recorded, but in Katsutoyo&apos;s case is a rare case that it is clearly recorded).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus there was the danger of assassination, and he took five kagemusha (body doubles) with him when he inspected sites such as castle construction (the existence of kagemusha is confidential and normally is not recorded, but Katsutoyo&apos;s case is a rarity in that it is clearly recorded).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus there was the danger of assassination, and he took five body doubles with him when he inspected sites such as castle construction (the existence of body doubles was confidential and usually not recorded, but Katsutoyo&apos;s case is a rarity in that it is clearly recorded).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>各地にくすぶりを残しこの課題（以前からの山内家家臣を上士、旧長宗我部氏の家臣を郷士とした差別的扱い）は次代から幕末になるまで引き継がれ坂本龍馬などの人物が生まれることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This left problems throughout the province and this issue (former Yamauchi family vassals being in higher position and former Chosakabe clan vassals being discriminated as goshi (country samurai)) continued until the end of the Edo Period and led to the birth of people such as Ryoma SAKAMATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This left problems throughout the province, and this issue (former Yamauchi family vassals being in higher positions and former Chosakabe clan vassals being discriminated against as goshi (country samurai)) continued until the end of the Edo period, ultimately leading to the birth of people such as Ryoma SAKAMATO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This left problems throughout the province, and this issue of former Yamauchi family vassals being in higher positions and former Chosokabe clan vassals being discriminated against as country samurai continued until the end of the Edo period, ultimately leading to the birth of people such as Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また高知平野内の大高坂山に統治の中心拠点として高知城を築城し（奉行は関ヶ原の戦いの後浪人となった百々綱家を7000石で招聘、慶長8年（1603年）完成）、城下町の整備を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He built Kochi-jo Castle on Odakasa-yama in the Kochi plains as the center of administration (he invited Tsunaie DODO, who was a ronin(master-less samurai) after the Battle of Sekigahara, as magistrate with 7,000 koku, completed in 1603) and built the castle town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He built Kochi-jo Castle on Odakasa-yama in the plain of Kochi as the center of administration (he invited Tsunaie DODO, who was a ronin (master-less samurai) after the Battle of Sekigahara, to serve as magistrate with 7,000 koku) and completed the castle town in 1603.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He built Kochi-jo Castle on Mt. Odakasa on the plain of Kochi as the center of administration by inviting Tsunaie DODO, who was a master-less samurai after the Battle of Sekigahara, to serve as magistrate with 7,000 koku, and completed the castle town in 1603.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また、このころに官位が従四位下土佐守に進んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Jushiinoge Tosa no kami (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade of the governor of Tosa Province) around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Jushiinoge Tosa no kami (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade of the Governor of Tosa Province) around this time.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He advanced to Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade of the Governor of Tosa Province around this time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="75">
<j>また、領民に対して食中毒を気にしカツオを刺身で食べることを禁じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He prohibited his people from eating raw bonito because of the danger of food poisoning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He prohibited his people from eating raw bonito because of the danger of food poisoning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He prohibited his people from eating raw bonito because of the danger of food poisoning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>それに対し、領民がかつおの表面のみをあぶって刺身ではないと言い食すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His people roasted the surface and claimed that it was not raw in order to eat bonito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His people roasted the surface and claimed that it was not raw in order to eat bonito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His people roasted the surface, and claimed that it was not raw in order to eat bonito.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これが鰹のタタキの起源だとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is said to be the beginnings of bonito tataki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is said to be the origin of bonito tataki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is said to be the origin of bonito tataki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>慶長10年（1605年）、高知城にて病死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1605, he died of disease at Kochi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1605, he died of disease at Kochi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1605, he died of disease at Kochi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>享年60。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 60.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 60.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 60.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="80">
<j>法名：大通院殿心峯宗伝大居士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homyo(posthumous Buddhist name): Daitsuindonoshinposhudendaikoji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homyo (posthumous Buddhist name): Daitsuindonoshinposhudendaikoji</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homyo (posthumous Buddhist name): Daitsuindonoshinposhudendaikoji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>墓所：高知県高知市天神町の日輪山真如寺の山内家墓所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place of grave: grave of Yamauchi family at Nichirinzan Shinnyo-ji Temple in Tenjin-cho, Kochi City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave location: The Yamauchi family graves are at Nichirinzan Shinnyo-ji Temple in Tenjin-cho, Kochi City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard: The Yamauchi family graves are at Nichirinzan Shinnyo-ji Temple in Tenjin-cho, Kochi City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>京都市右京区花園妙心寺町の正法山妙心寺大通院（遺骨があるのは日輪山真如寺の墓所、妙心寺大通院には位牌のみ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shobozan Myoshin-ji temple Daitsu-in in Hanazono Myoshinji-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City (his remains are in the grave at Nichirinzan Shinnyo-ji Temple, only his ihai(mortuary tablet) is located at Myoshin-ji Temple Daitsu-in).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shobozan Myoshin-ji temple Daitsu-in in Hanazono Myoshinji-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City (his remains are in the grave at Nichirinzan Shinnyo-ji Temple, so only his ihai (mortuary tablet) is located at Myoshin-ji Temple Daitsu-in).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shobozan Myoshin-ji Temple Daitsu-in in Hanazono Myoshinji-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City (his remains are in the grave at Nichirinzan Shinnyo-ji Temple, so only his ihai (mortuary tablet) is located at Myoshin-ji Temple Daitsu-in).</e>
<cmt>temple語頭大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="83">
<j>高知城には、騎馬姿で槍を持った銅像が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a bronze statue of Katsutoyo on a horse, holding a spear at Kochi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a bronze statue of Katsutoyo on a horse, holding a spear at Kochi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>OR At Kochi-jo Castle there is a bronze statue of Katsutoyo astride a horse, holding a spear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a bronze statue of Katsutoyo riding a horse, holding a spear at Kochi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>官歴と所領推移</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of office and rank and transition of territory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of office and rank, and the transition of territory</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of office and rank, and the transition of territory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>天正元年（1573年）、近江国唐国（滋賀県東浅井郡虎姫町唐国）に400石を領す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1573: He receives 400 koku in Karakuni, Omi Province(Karakuni, Torahime-cho, Higashiazai District, Shiga Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1573: He received 400 koku in Karakuni, Omi Province (Karakuni, Torahime-cho, Higashiazai District, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1573: He received 400 koku in Karakuni, Omi Province (Karakuni, Torahime-cho, Higashiazai-gun, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="85">
<j>天正3年（1577年）、播磨国有年（兵庫県赤穂市有年）に700石を加増。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1577: Addition of 700 koku in Une, Harima Province (Une, Akaho City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1577: Addition of 700 koku in Une, Harima Province (Une, Akaho City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1577: 700 koku was addded in Une, Harima Province (Une, Akaho City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>時に、合計2,700石を領す（石高総計については異説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he owned a total of 2,700 koku (there are alternate theories regarding the total koku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, he owned a total of 2,700 koku (there are alternate theories regarding the total koku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he owned a total of 2,700 koku (there are alternate theories regarding the sum of koku).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>天正10年9月25日 (旧暦)（1582年10月21日）、播磨国印南郡（兵庫県南部地域）に500石を加増。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oct. 21, 1582: Addition of 500 koku in Innami District, Harima Province (Southern Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oct. 21, 1582: Addition of 500 koku in Innami District, Harima Province (Southern Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 21, 1582: 500 koku was added in Innami District, Harima Province (Southern Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>天正11年8月1日 (旧暦)（1583年9月16日）、河内国禁野（大阪府枚方市禁野本町あたり）に361石を加増。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sept. 16, 1583: Addition of 361 koku in Shimeno, Kawachi Province (Kinyahonmachi, Hirakata City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sept. 16, 1583: Addition of 361 koku in Shimeno, Kawachi Province (Kinyahonmachi, Hirakata City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 16, 1583: 361 koku was added in Shimeno, Kawachi Province (Kinyahonmachi, Hirakata City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="89">
<j>天正12年（1584年）9月、近江国長浜城主となって、5,000石を領す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sept. 1584: Becomes lord of Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province and owns 5,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sept. 1584: He became the lord of Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province and owned 5,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1584: He became the lord of Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province and owned 5,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>月表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="90">
<j>天正13年6月2日 (旧暦)（1585年6月29日）、若狭国高浜城主となって1万9,870石を領す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 29, 1585: Becomes lord of Takahama-jo Castle in Wakasa Province and owns 19,870 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 29, 1585: He became the lord of Takahama-jo Castle in Wakasa Province and owned 19,870 koku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 29, 1585: He became the lord of Takahama-jo Castle in Wakasa Province and owned 19,870 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>8月、豊臣秀次の宿老となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aug. 1585: He becomes Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;s chief vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aug. 1585: He becomes Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;s chief vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August or September 1585: He becomes Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;s chief vassal.</e>
<cmt>月表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>8月21日 (旧暦)（10月21日）、近江国長浜城主となって2万石を領す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oct. 21, 1585: Owns 20,000 koku as lord of Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oct. 21, 1585: Owns 20,000 koku as lord of Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 21, 1585: Owned 20,000 koku as lord of Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="93">
<j>天正13年（1585年）9月～天正14年（1586年）4月　正五位下対馬守に叙任（『一豊公記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sept. 1585 – April 1586: Appointed Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chief of the Province of Tsushima (Kazutoyo Koki (Biography of Kazutoyo YAMANOUCHI)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sept. 1585 – April 1586: He was appointed Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chief of the Province of Tsushima (Kazutoyo Koki (Biography of Kazutoyo YAMANOUCHI)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October or November 1585 – May or June 1586: He was appointed Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chief of the Province of Tsushima (&quot;Kazutoyo Koki&quot; (Biography of Kazutoyo YAMANOUCHI)).</e>
<cmt>月表記グレゴリ歴に&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>なお豊臣家臣で一豊と同格の人物の多くは当時従五位下に叙せられているため、正五位下ではなく従五位下の誤記ではないかとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of his peers who were vassals of Toyotomi were appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at this time, there is a theory that this might be a misspelling of Jugoinoge rather than Shogoinoge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of his peers who were vassals of Toyotomi were appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at this time, but there is a theory that this might be a misspelling of Jugoinoge rather than Shogoinoge.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An opinion has it that since most of his peers who were vassals of Toyotomi were appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at this time, this might be a written error of Jugoinoge rather than Shogoinoge.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="95">
<j>天正18年9月20日 (旧暦)（1590年10月21日）、遠江国掛川城主として5万石を領す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oct. 21, 1590: Becomes lord of Kakegawa-jo Castle, Totoumi Province and owns 50,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oct. 21, 1590: He became the lord of Kakegawa-jo Castle, Totoumi Province and owned 50,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 21, 1590: He became the lord of Kakegawa-jo Castle, Totoumi Province and owned 50,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>月表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>さらに10月25日 (旧暦)（11月22日）、遠江国周智郡一宮（静岡県周智郡森町一宮）1万9980石の代官にもなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oct 25, 1590: Becomes daikan (governor) of Ichimiya, Shuchi District, Totoumi Province(Ichimiya, Shuchi-gun Mori-machi, Shizuoka Prefecture) for 19,980 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oct 25, 1590: He became the daikan (governor) of Ichimiya, Shuchi District, Totoumi Province (Ichimiya, Shuchi-gun Mori-machi, Shizuoka Prefecture) and owner of 19,980 koku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 22, 1590: He became the daikan (governor) of Ichimiya, Shuchi District, Totoumi Province (Ichimiya, Shuchi-gun Mori-machi, Shizuoka Prefecture) and owner of 19,980 koku.</e>
<cmt>月表記、日付修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="97">
<j>文禄3年9月21日 (旧暦)（1594年11月2日）、伊勢国鈴鹿郡（三重県鈴鹿市）で1,000石加増。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nov.2, 1594: Addition of 1,000 koku in Suzuka District, Ise Province (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nov.2, 1594: Addition of 1,000 koku in Suzuka District, Ise Province (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 2, 1594: 1,000 koku was added in Suzuka District, Ise Province (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="98">
<j>文禄4年7月15日 (旧暦)（1595年8月26日）、遠江国内の豊臣秀次所有の蔵入地より8,000石を加増。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aug. 26, 1595: Addition of 8,000 koku that was from Hidetsugu TOTOMI&apos;s territory in Totoumi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aug. 26, 1595: Addition of 8,000 koku from Hidetsugu TOTOMI&apos;s territory in Totoumi Province</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 26, 1595: 8,000 koku was added from Hidetsugu TOTOMI&apos;s territory in Totoumi Province</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="99">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）11月、土佐国内9万8,000石（後の検地で20万2,600石）を領有する大名となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nov. 1600: Becomes daimyo of Tosa Province, 98,000 koku (later surveyed as 202,600 koku_).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nov. 1600: He became the daimyo of Tosa Province, with 98,000 koku (later surveyed as 202,600 koku).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1600 or January 1601: He became the feudal lord of Tosa Province, with 98,000 koku (later surveyed as 202,600 koku).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="100">
<j>慶長8年3月25日 (旧暦)（1603年5月6日）、従四位下に昇叙し、土佐守に転任する（『徳川実紀』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to ushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) on May 6, 1603 and transferred as Tosa no kami (the governor of Tosa Province)(.Tokugawa jikki&quot; (The True Tokugawa Records)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to ushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) on May 6, 1603 and transferred as Tosa no kami (the governor of Tosa Province) (&quot;Tokugawa jikki (The True Tokugawa Records&quot;)).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) on May 6, 1603 and transferred to Tosa no kami (the governor of Tosa Province) (&quot;Tokugawa jikki&quot; (The True Tokugawa Records)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="101">
<j>慶長10年9月20日 (旧暦)（1605年11月1日）、卒去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on Nov. 1, 1605.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on Nov. 1, 1605.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on November 1, 1605.</e>
<cmt>月表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="102">
<j>大正8年（1919年）11月15日、贈従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, he was awarded Zo Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank, posthumously conferred).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, he was awarded Zo Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank, posthumously conferred).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 15, 1919, he was awarded Zo Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank, posthumously conferred).</e>
<cmt>On November 1補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>見性院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshoin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>（岐阜市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Gifu City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Gifu City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Gifu City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>一豊の妻である見性院（千代、まつ）は夫を「内助の功」で助けた賢妻とされており、嫁入りの持参金（貧しいながらも貯めたへそくりとの説もある）で名馬（名馬一覧鏡栗毛）を買った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshoin (Chiyo, Matsu) was Katsutoyo&apos;s wife who was considered to be a clever wife who supported her husband and used her dowry (some say savings that she put away even though they were poor) and bought a fine horse(Meibaichiran Kagami Kurige).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshoin (Chiyo, Matsu) was Katsutoyo&apos;s wife who was considered to be a clever woman who supported her husband and used her dowry (some say savings she had put away, even though they were poor) and bought a fine horse (Meibaichiran Kagami Kurige).</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshoin or Chiyo, Matsu was Katsutoyo&apos;s wife who was considered to be a clever woman who supported her husband and used her dowry (some say savings she had put away, even though they were poor) and bought a fine horse (Meibaichiran Kagami Kurige).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>この逸話は特に戦前日本において教科書に採りあげられ、女性のあるべき姿として学校教育に用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This story was commonly used in textbooks during the pre-war period and used in school education to exemplify the ideal woman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story was commonly used in textbooks during the prewar period and used in school education to exemplify the ideal woman.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story was commonly used in textbooks during the pre-World War II period and used in school education to exemplify the ideal woman.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>真偽の程は定かではないが、千代紙の由来になった人物としても知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown if this is true, but she is known as the person who Chiyogami(Japanese paper with colored figures) is named after.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It isn&apos;t known if this is true, but she is known as the person after whom Chiyogami (Japanese paper with colored figures) is named.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It isn&apos;t known if this is true, but she is known as the person after whom &apos;Chiyogami&apos; or Japanese paper with colored figures is named.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 いいすく(id:136753), T@ka(id:12814), Nnh(id:474), LucienBOT(id:290117), KurmUmy(id:202680), Tuny(id:90002), Hide-sp(id:145562), Kamakura(id:472), Tribot(id:186681), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), A-Taul(id:41790), Kanoe(id:17203), Point136(id:211299), シェーラ(id:17988), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Kurayamizaka(id:7150), Woyzzeck(id:8923), DOERAX(id:25212), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 松茸(id:27535), S kitahashi(id:10307), Huemat(id:19503), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), Pote sb88(id:35766), D5(id:60352), 吉閥(id:24594), Ghost(id:8115), Wabisabix(id:16770), けんち(id:5147), King-wise(id:19033), Jmho(id:10472), Flamelai(id:34490), TT(id:46431), 月桂樹(id:62799), ドルチェット(id:46458), Hary(id:95990), Reggaeman(id:6214), Yen80(id:6146), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kotoito(id:21045), 歴史人(id:177710), Johncapistrano(id:969), ひろっきー(id:87284), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Goki(id:7107), 松平蔵人(id:229480), Sho-gun(id:74168), Kone(id:377), Loveless(id:129239), 寂華(id:83725), Chacmool(id:202970), Maruchanmax(id:40219), 越中掾(id:149423), Chev(id:35857), ぶるるるる(id:130462), Izayohi(id:13095), 水野白楓(id:22811), 三浦大輔(id:93377), Taisyo(id:6896), Yanahan(id:2437), 雲居雁乃(id:15842), Shinkansen(id:13703), Aboshi(id:9318), Kamitani(id:30757), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Carkuni(id:79281), White star(id:39779), Mototika(id:184500), Miya(id:1881), 663highland(id:18755), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>