<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大久保利通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimichi OKUBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大久保 利通（おおくぼ としみち、文政13年8月10日 (旧暦)(1830年9月26日) - 明治11年(1878年)5月14日）は、日本の武士（薩摩藩士）、政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO (1830~1878):Japanese warrior, feudal retainer of Satsuma, a statesman</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimichi OKUBO (1830~1878):Japanese warrior, feudal retainer of Satsuma, a statesman</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO (1830~1878):Japanese warrior, feudal retainer of Satsuma, a statesman</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>位階勲等は従一位勲一等。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranks and orders: Junior First Rank and the First Order of Merit</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranks and orders: Junior First Rank and the First Order of Merit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranks and orders: Junior First Rank and the First Order of Merit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治維新の元勲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Statesman Who Contributed in Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Statesman Who Contributed to the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Statesman Who Contributed to the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>西郷隆盛、木戸孝允と並んで「維新の三傑」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is called one of &quot;three contributors of Meiji Restoration&quot; along with Takamori SAIGO and Takayoshi KIDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is called one of &quot;the three contributors to the Meiji Restoration&quot; along with Takamori SAIGO and Takayoshi KIDO.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is called one of &quot;the three contributors to the Meiji Restoration&quot; along with Takamori SAIGO and Takayoshi KIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出生・幼少期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His birth and childhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birth and childhood</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birth and childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>文政13年8月10日（1830年9月26日）、薩摩国鹿児島城下高麗町（現・鹿児島県鹿児島市高麗町）に、琉球館附役の薩摩藩士・大久保利世と皆吉鳳徳の次女・福の長男として生まれる（幼名は正袈裟：しょうけさ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on September 26th, 1830, in Goryeo Town near Kagoshima Castle, Satsuma Province (present: Goryeo Town, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture) as the eldest son between Toshiyo OKUBO, feudal retainer of Satsuma, attatched to Ryukyu palace and his wife Fuku, the second daughter of Hotoku MINAYOSHI (His childhood name: Shokesa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on September 26th, 1830, in Goryeo Town near Kagoshima Castle, Satsuma Province (present: Goryeo Town, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture) as the eldest son of Toshiyo OKUBO, feudal retainer of Satsuma, attatched to the Ryukyu palace, and his wife Fuku, the second daughter of Hotoku MINAYOSHI (his childhood name was Shokesa).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on September 26th, 1830, in Korai Town near Kagoshima Castle, Satsuma Province (present: Korai Town, Kagoshima City, Kagoshima Prefecture) as the eldest son of Toshiyo OKUBO, feudal retainer of Satsuma, attatched to the Ryukyu palace, and his wife Fuku, the second daughter of Hotoku MINAYOSHI (his childhood name was Shokesa).</e>
<cmt>GoryeoをKoraiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大久保家の家格は御小姓与と呼ばれる身分である下級藩士であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Social standing of OKUBO family was a lower ranked feudal retainer that was called Okoshogumi family rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The social standing of the OKUBO family was that of a lower-ranked feudal retainer referred to as the Okoshogumi family rank.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The social standing of the OKUBO family was that of a lower-ranked feudal retainer referred to as the Okoshogumi (escort of the lord) family rank.</e>
<cmt>Okoshogumiの訳を括弧書きで入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>本姓は藤原氏を称するが明確ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">.The main name was referred to the Fujiwara clan, but it is uncertain whether it is true or false.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original name refers to the Fujiwara clan, but it is uncertain as to whether or not this is true.</e>
<cmt>Wording. This is a little unclear; what is the 本姓 referred to? Okoshogumi?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original name refers to the Fujiwara clan, but it is uncertain as to whether or not this is true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼少期に加治屋町（下加治屋町方限）に移住する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his childhood, his family moved to Kjiya Town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his childhood, his family moved to Kajiya Town.</e>
<cmt>**Is &quot;Kjiya&quot; a typo? I changed it to Kajiya</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his childhood, his family moved to Kajiya Town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>親友の西郷隆盛や税所篤、吉井友実、海江田信義らと共に学問を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied learning with Takamori SAIGO, Tomozane YOSHII and Nobuyoshi KAIEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He pursued his studies with Takamori SAIGO, Tomozane YOSHII and Nobuyoshi KAIEDA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Study learning&quot; is redundant. One part is untranslated?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He pursued his studies with Takamori SAIGO, Tomozane YOSHII and Nobuyoshi KAIEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>15歳の時元服し、仮名 (通称)を正助、諱は利済（としさだ）と名乗るが、後に改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was 15 years old, he was celebrated his coming of age and he assumed the first name as Shosuke and common name as Toshisada, but afterwards he changed his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was 15 years old, he celebrated his coming of age and assumed the first name Shosuke and common name Toshisada, though he changed his name afterwards.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was 15 years old, he celebrated his coming of age and assumed the first name Shosuke and common name Toshisada, though he changed his name afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>幕末</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End of Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End of Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>弘化3年（1846年）から藩の記録所書役助として出仕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1846, he presented himself as assistant writer at Land Record Office of Satauma Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1846, he served as an assistant writer at the Land Record Office of Satauma Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1846, he served as an assistant writer at the Land Record Office of Satsuma Province.</e>
<cmt>SataumaをSatsumaに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>嘉永3年（1850年）のお由羅騒動（嘉永朋党事件）では連座して罷免され謹慎処分となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1850, he was implicated in Oyura-sodo (family feud over Narioki SHIMAZU&apos;s heir), suspended.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1850, he was implicated in the Oyura-sodo (family feud over Narioki SHIMAZU&apos;s heir) and was dismissed and put under house arrest.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1850, he was implicated in the Oyura-sodo (the Kaei Hoto incident; family feud over Narioki SHIMAZU&apos;s heir) and was dismissed and put under house arrest.</e>
<cmt>嘉永朋党事件 (the Kaei Hoto incident;を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし島津斉彬が藩主となると、嘉永6年（1853年）に藩記録所御蔵役として復職する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But when Nariakira SHIMAZU became the lord of domain, he was rehabilitated as officer for okura (the rice store of the Edo shogunate), Land Record Office of domain in 1853.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But when Nariakira SHIMAZU became the lord of the domain in 1853, OKUBO was reinstated as an officer for okura (the rice store of the Edo shogunate) at the Land Record Office of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But when Nariakira SHIMAZU became the lord of the domain in 1853, OKUBO was reinstated as an officer for okura (the rice store of the Edo shogunate) at the Land Record Office of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>安政4年（1857年）には徒目付になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1857 he was appointed the superintendent officer of foot soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857 he was appointed the superintendent officer of foot soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857 he was appointed the superintendent officer of foot soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>精忠組の領袖として活動し、安政5年（1858年）の斉彬の死後は、失脚した西郷に代わり新藩主・島津忠義の実父・島津久光（久光）に税所篤の助力で接近する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took a lively part as the the leader of Seichugumi Organization and after the death of Nariakira in 1858 he approached Hisamitsu SHIMADU, father of Tadayoshi SHIMADU (new lord of domain) with the assistance of Atsushi SAISHO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as the leader of Seichugumi Organization and after the death of Nariakira in 1858, he approached Hisamitsu SHIMADU, father of Tadayoshi SHIMADU (new lord of the domain) with the assistance of Atsushi SAISHO.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the leader of Seichugumi Organization and after the death of Nariakira in 1858, he approached Hisamitsu SHIMADU, father of Tadayoshi SHIMADU (new lord of the domain) with the assistance of Atsushi SAISHO, instead of Saigo who lost his position.</e>
<cmt>「失脚した西郷に代わりに」の訳、instead of Saigo who lost his positionを後に付け加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>篤の兄・吉祥院乗願が久光の囲碁相手であったことから、乗願経由で手紙を渡したのが始まりといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the beginning of his approach to Hisamitsu was placing his letter in Hisamitsu&apos;s hands through Jogan Kissho-in, brother of Atsushi, since Jogan, was the Igo partner of Hisamitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the beginning of his approach to Hisamitsu was placing his letter in Hisamitsu&apos;s hands through Jogan Kissho-in, brother of Atsushi, since Jogan, was the Igo partner of Hisamitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the beginning of his approach to Hisamitsu was placing his letter in Hisamitsu&apos;s hands through Jogan Kissho-in, brother of Atsushi, since Jogan, was the Igo partner of Hisamitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>万延元年（1860年）3月11日に久光と初めて面会する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He met Hisamitsu for the first time on March 11th, 1860.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He met Hisamitsu for the first time on March 11th, 1860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He met Hisamitsu for the first time on March 11th, 1860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>文久元年（1861年）に御小納戸役に抜擢、家格も一代新番となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1861 he was selected to the post of assistant to the lord of domain and his family status rose to one&apos;s liftime New Guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1861 he was elected to the post of assistant to the lord of the domain, whereby his family status rose to the next position within one generation.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Not sure about &quot;一代新番&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1861 he was elected to okonanndo yaku (the post of assistant to the lord of the domain), whereby his family status rose to ichidai shimban (the new escort of the lord of the domain within one generation).</e>
<cmt>御小納戸役と一代新番の読みを挿入し、一代新番の訳を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>文久元年12月15日 (旧暦)（1862年1月14日）から文久2年（1862年）3月上旬までの間に久光から一蔵の名を賜り改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period between 1861 and1862 he was given the first name of &quot;Ichizo&quot; by Hisamitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period between 1861 and1862 he was given the first name of &quot;Ichizo&quot; by Hisamitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period between 1861 and1862 he was given the first name of &quot;Ichizo&quot; by Hisamitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>文久2年（1862年)に御小納戸頭取に昇進となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862 he was promoted to the post of chief of assistants to the lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862 he was promoted to the post of chief of assistants to the lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1862 he was promoted to the post of chief of assistants to the lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>文久3年（1863年)には、御側役（御小納戸頭取兼任）に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863 he was promoted to the personal attendant to the lord (serving concurrently as chief of attendants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863 he was promoted to the personal attendant to the lord (serving concurrently as chief of attendants).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863 he was promoted to osoba yaku (the personal attendant to the lord) serving concurrently as chief of attendants.</e>
<cmt>御側役の読みを加えました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>慶応元年（1865年）、利通と改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1865 he changed his first name as &quot;Toshimichi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1865 he changed his first name to &quot;Toshimichi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1865 he changed his first name to &quot;Toshimichi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>久光を擁立して京都の政局に関わり、公家の岩倉具視らと公武合体政策を画策し、徳川慶喜の将軍後見職、福井藩主松平慶永の政事総裁職就任などを進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He backed up Hisamitsu, got involved in the politics in Kyoto, planned reconciliation between imperial court and the Shogunate with Tomomi IWAKURA, and promoted the assumption of Shogun-guardian post by Keiki TOKUGAWA and the post of office for the president of political affairs by Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Fukui Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supporting Hisamitsu, he got involved in politics in Kyoto, planning the reconciliation between the imperial court and the Shogunate with Tomomi IWAKURA, and promoting the assumption of Shogun-guardian post by Keiki TOKUGAWA and the post of office of the president of political affairs by Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Fukui Domain).</e>
<cmt>Wording. This is still hard to read.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supporting Hisamitsu, he got involved in politics in Kyoto, planning the reconciliation between the imperial court and the Shogunate with Tomomi IWAKURA, and promoting the assumption of Shogun-guardian post by Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA and the post of office of the president of political affairs by Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Fukui Domain).</e>
<cmt>徳川慶喜のKeikiをYoshinobuに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>西郷や小松清廉と共に政治の中枢として活動する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played an active part as a central person for politics with SAIGO and Kiyokado KOMATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a pivotal person in politics along with SAIGO and Kiyokado KOMATSU.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a pivotal person in politics along with SAIGO and Kiyokado KOMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）に江戸幕府将軍・徳川慶喜が大政奉還を行うと、岩倉ら倒幕派公家と共に、王政復古 (日本)のクーデターを計画して実行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1867 when Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, shogun of Edo shogunate transferred political power back to the Emperor, he planned and carried out a coup d&apos;tat for Restoration of Imperial rule with anti-shogunate forces of court nobles including IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, shogun of the Edo shogunate, transferred political power back to the Emperor in 1867, he planned and carried out a coup d&apos;etat for the restoration of Imperial rule with anti-shogunate forces of court nobles including IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, shogun of the Edo shogunate, transferred political power back to the Emperor in 1867, he planned and carried out a coup d&apos;etat for the restoration of Imperial rule with anti-shogunate forces of court nobles including IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>王政復古の後、参与に任命され、小御所会議にで慶喜の辞官納地を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Restoration of Imperial Rule, he was assigned to the post of Political Consultant and demanded at an imperial palace meeting to Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA surrendering both the post of Shogunate and parts of his territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Restoration of Imperial Rule, he was assigned to the post of Political Consultant and insisted on an imperial palace meeting with Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA surrendering both the post of Shogunate and parts of his territories.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Restoration of Imperial Rule, he was assigned to the post of Political Consultant and insisted on an imperial palace meeting with Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA surrendering both the post of Shogunate and parts of his territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>明治維新後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>慶応4年（1868年）に大阪遷都論を主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868 he insisted the transfer of the capital to Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1868 he requested the transfer of the capital to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1868 he requested the transfer of the capital to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>明治2年7月22日 (旧暦)（1869年8月29日）に参議に就任し、版籍奉還、廃藩置県などの明治政府の中央集権体制確立を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29th, 1869, he assumed the office of State Councilor and executed the establishment of centralization of administrative power by the Meiji Government including return of lands and people to the Emperor and the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29th, 1869, he assumed the office of State Councilor and executed the establishment of the centralization of administrative power by the Meiji Government, including the return of lands and people to the Emperor, the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 29th, 1869, he assumed the office of State Councilor and executed the establishment of the centralization of administrative power by the Meiji Government, including the return of lands and people to the Emperor, the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>明治4年（1871年）には大蔵卿に就任し、岩倉使節団の副使として外遊する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871 he took the office of Finance Secretary and made a trip abroad as the Vice Commander of Mission headed by IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871 he took the office of Finance Secretary and made a trip abroad as the Vice Commander of a mission headed by IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871 he took the office of Finance Secretary and made a trip abroad as the Vice Commander of a mission headed by IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>外遊中に留守政府では朝鮮出兵を巡る征韓論論争が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While heads of government including Okubo were away for official travel abroad, Japan&apos;s dispatch of troops to Korea became a dispute within the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While heads of government including Okubo were away for official travel abroad, Japan&apos;s dispatch of troops to Korea became a dispute within the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While heads of government including Okubo were away for official travel abroad, Japan&apos;s dispatch of troops to Korea became a dispute within the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この論争では、西郷隆盛や板垣退助ら征韓派と対立し、明治六年政変にて失脚させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the dispute he was opposed to Takamori SAIGO and Taisuke ITAGAKI and broght down SAIGO and ITAGAKI in a coup d&apos;etat in 1873.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the dispute he was opposed by Takamori SAIGO and Taisuke ITAGAKI, and he brought down SAIGO and ITAGAKI in a coup d&apos;etat in 1873.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the dispute he was opposed by Takamori SAIGO and Taisuke ITAGAKI, and he brought down SAIGO and ITAGAKI in a coup d&apos;etat in 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>内務卿就任後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Assumption of Secretary of Interior</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Assumption of Secretary of Interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Assumption of Secretary of Interior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>明治6年（1873年）、内務省 (日本)を設置し、自ら初代内務卿として実権を握ると地租改正や徴兵令などを実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873 he established Ministory of Home Affairs, took the real power by assuming the post of Secretary of Interior for himself and executed land-tax reform and conscription ordinance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1873 he established the Ministry of Home Affairs, took charge by assuming the post of Secretary of Interior for himself and executed land-tax reform and a conscription ordinance.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873 he established the Ministry of Home Affairs, took charge by assuming the post of Secretary of Interior for himself and executed land-tax reform and a conscription ordinance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そして、「富国」をスローガンとして殖産興業政策を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He promoted new industry encouragement encouragement policy under the slogan &quot;rich country&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He promoted a policy of encouraging new industry with the slogan &quot;rich country&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He promoted a policy of encouraging new industry with the slogan &quot;rich country&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また明治7年には台湾出兵を行い、9月14日に戦後処理のため、全権弁理大使として、清に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1874 He also carried out the Taiwan expedition and on September 14th went to Qing (China) as the general commander-in-chief to solve problems after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1874 he also carried out an expedition to Taiwan and on September 14th went to Qing (China) as the general commander-in-chief to solve problems after the war.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1874 he also carried out an expedition to Taiwan and on September 14th went to Qing (China) as the general commander-in-chief to solve problems after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>交渉の末、10月31日、清が台湾出兵を義挙と認め、50万両の償金を支払うことを定めた日清両国間互換条款・互換憑単に調印する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of negotiation on October 31th, Qing recognized the Taiwan expedition as a noble undertaking and signed the treaty between Japan and Qing in which Qing provided to pay 500,000 ryo to Japan for indemnities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result of negotiations on October 31st, Qing recognized the Taiwan expedition as a noble undertaking and signed a treaty between Japan and Qing in which Qing was prescribed to pay 500,000 ryo to Japan for indemnities.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Perhaps &quot;ryo&quot; should be explained</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result of negotiations on October 31st, Qing recognized the Taiwan expedition as a noble undertaking and signed a treaty between Japan and Qing in which Qing was prescribed to pay 500,000 ryo (the old Chinese currency) to Japan for indemnities.</e>
<cmt>ryo(両)の説明を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>また、大久保はドイツ（プロイセン）を目標とした国家を目指していたのではないかといわれるが、実際はイギリスを目標とした立憲君主制の国家を構想していたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period between 1873 and 1878 was called &quot;OKUBO government&quot;, because political powers concentrated in OKUBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period between 1873 and 1878 was called the &quot;OKUBO government&quot;, because the political administration centered around OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally said that OKUBO was aiming for a state such as Germany, but others say that in reality he was aiming for a state of constitutional monarchy like England.</e>
<cmt>この列と後列の説明が入れ違いになっていますので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>明治6年頃から明治11年まで、大久保を中心とした政権だったため、一般に「大久保政権」と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally said that OKUBO was aiming the state such as Germany, but they say that he was outlining the state of constitutional monarchy such as England in reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally said that OKUBO was aiming for a state such as Germany, but others say that in reality he was aiming for a state of constitutional monarchy like England.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period between 1873 and 1878 was called the &quot;OKUBO government&quot;, because the political administration centered around OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>この列と前列の説明が入れ違いになっていますので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>当時、大久保への権力の集中は「有司専制」として批判された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, the concentration of powers in OKUBO was criticized as &quot;despotism by domain-dominated government&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, OKUBO&apos;s domination of political authority was criticized as &quot;despotism by a domain-dominated government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, OKUBO&apos;s domination of political authority was criticized as &quot;despotism by a domain-dominated government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、現在に至るまでの日本の官僚機構（霞ヶ関官界）は、内務省を設置した大久保によって築かれたとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition it is also said that the bureaucratic organization (Kasumigaseki bureaucracy) in Japan until today was established by OKUBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the bureaucratic organization (Kasumigaseki bureaucracy) which exists in Japan up to the present day is also said to have been established by OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the bureaucratic organization (Kasumigaseki bureaucracy) which exists in Japan up to the present day is also said to have been established by OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>明治10年（1877年）には、西南戦争で京都にて政府軍を指揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Seinan War in 1877, he commanded the government army in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Seinan War of 1877, he commanded the government army in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Seinan War of 1877, he commanded the government army in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その後、侍補からの要請に乗る形で自らが宮内卿に就任することで明治政府と天皇の一体化を行う構想を抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he assumed the post of Secretary of Imperial Household according to the demand of an aide and had the plan to integrate Meiji government and Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he assumed the post of Secretary of the Imperial Household by the request of an aide and had a plan to integrate the Meiji government and the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he assumed the post of Secretary of the Imperial Household by the request of an aide and had a plan to integrate the Meiji government and the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし明治11年(1878年)5月14日、石川県士族島田一郎らにより紀尾井坂（東京都千代田区紀尾井町）にて暗殺された（紀尾井坂の変）（享年49〈数え年〉、満47歳没）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But on May 14 th, 1878 he was assassinated at the Kioi-zaka Slope (Kioi-cho Town, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) by Ichiro SHIMADA (a descendant of samurai in Ishikawa Prefecture) and others (Kioizaka Incident) (at the age of full 47).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But on May 14 th, 1878 he was assassinated at the Kioi-zaka Slope (Kioi-cho Town, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) by Ichiro SHIMADA (a descendant of samurai in Ishikawa Prefecture) and others in the Kioizaka Incident (he was 47).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But on May 14 th, 1878 he was assassinated at the Kioi-zaka Slope (Kioi-cho Town, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) by Ichiro SHIMADA (a descendant of samurai in Ishikawa Prefecture) and others in the Kioizaka Incident (he was 47).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>墓所は東京都の港区 (東京都)の青山霊園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyard is in Aoyama Cemetery in Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyard is in Aoyama Cemetery in Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyard is in Aoyama Cemetery in Minato Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>趣味は囲碁。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His hobby was Igo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His hobby was Igo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His hobby was Igo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>島津久光に接近するために碁を学んだとの話も伝えられるが誤りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is reported that he learned Igo in order to approach Hisamitsu SHIMADU, but it was false..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is reported that he learned Igo in order to approach Hisamitsu SHIMADU, but this is false.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is reported that he learned Igo in order to approach Hisamitsu SHIMADU, but this is false.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>嘉永元年（1848年）の日記に碁を三番打って負けたとの記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordint to his diary in 1848 it was written that he had a three-game match of Igo and defeated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a diary entry he wrote in 1848, he had a three-game match of Igo and was defeated.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a diary entry he wrote in 1848, he had a three-game match of Igo and was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>大変なヘビースモーカーで、濃厚な指宿煙草（日本で初めて栽培されたたばこ）を愛用しており、子供達が朝晩パイプ (タバコ)を掃除しなければすぐに目詰まりするほどだった（また、朝用のパイプと夜用のパイプを分けて使っていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a heavy smoker, fond of smoking heavy Ibusuki tobacco (cultivated for the first time in Japan) and his pipe was easily choked unless his children cleaned it in the morning and in the evening (He also had pipes for morning and evening uses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a heavy smoker, fond of smoking rich Ibusuki tobacco (cultivated for the first time in Japan) and his pipe was easily clogged unless his children cleaned it in the morning and in the evening (he also had separate pipes for morning and evening use).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a heavy smoker, fond of smoking rich Ibusuki tobacco (cultivated for the first time in Japan) and his pipe was easily clogged unless his children cleaned it in the morning and in the evening (he also had separate pipes for morning and evening use).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>茶は京都宇治市の玉露を濃く淹れたものを好んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among tea he was fond of thick Gyokuro (refined green tea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for tea, he was fond of dark Gyokuro (refined green tea).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for tea, he was fond of dark Gyokuro (refined green tea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>漬物も好きで、何種類か並んでいないと機嫌が悪かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also fond of pickles and was in an ill humor at meal if several kinds of pickles were not served at the table.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also fond of pickles and would be in a bad mood at mealtimes if several kinds of pickles were not served at the table.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also fond of pickles and would be in a bad mood at mealtimes if several kinds of pickles were not served at the table.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>明治8年から1年かけて、麹町三年町に木造洋館を建てた（建築費用は恩賜金と盟友税所篤からの借金で賄ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took one year from 1875 to build a wooden Western-style residence in Sannen-cho in Koji-machi Town (It is said that expenses for architecture were covered by Imperial money and the debt from Atsushi SAISHO, his intimate friend)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took one year starting in 1875 to build a wooden Western-style residence in Sannen-cho, Koji-machi Town (it is said that expenses for architecture were covered by Imperial money and a debt from Atsushi SAISHO, his intimate friend)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took one year starting in 1875 to build a wooden Western-style residence in Sannen-cho, Koji-machi Town (it is said that expenses for architecture were covered by Imperial money and a debt from Atsushi SAISHO, his intimate friend)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>後にこの邸はベルギー公使館となった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later this residence was used as the Belgium legation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later this residence was used as the Belgium legation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later this residence was used as the Belgium legation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>当時は個人の家としては珍しい洋館であったが、金をかけたものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The residence was a Western-style house, rare as a personal house in those days, but it did not take a lot of expenses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The residence was a Western-style house, rare as a personal house in those days, but it was not expensive to maintain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The residence was a Western-style house, rare as a personal house in those days, but it was not expensive to maintain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、金銭には潔白で私財をなすことをせず、逆に国の借金を個人で埋めるような有様だったため、死後は8,000円もの借金が残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition he was upright and clean about money, did not save up his funds and even tried to cover a loss of the country with his own money, therefore he left the debt of 8,000 yen after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he was very upright about money, not accumulating any personal fortune; instead, he even tried to cover a national debt with his own money, thereby leaving behind a debt of 8,000 yen after his death.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he was very upright about money, not accumulating any personal fortune; instead, he even tried to cover a national debt with his own money, thereby leaving behind a debt of 8,000 yen after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>政府は協議の結果、大久保が生前に鹿児島県庁に学校費として寄付した8,000円を回収し、さらに8,000円の募金を集めてこの1万6,000円で遺族を養うことにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result of conference, the government recovered 8,000yen which he contributed to Kagoshima prefectural government when he was alive and raised 8,000yen, and decided to support his bereaved family with this 16,000 yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result of a conference, the government recovered 8,000 yen which he had contributed to the Kagoshima prefectural government when he was alive and raised another 8,000 yen, deciding to support his bereaved family with this 16,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result of a conference, the government recovered 8,000 yen which he had contributed to the Kagoshima prefectural government when he was alive and raised another 8,000 yen, deciding to support his bereaved family with this 16,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>五代友厚に浜寺公園へ案内された大久保は、堺県県令税所篤が、園内の松を伐採して住宅地として開発しようとするのを知り、「音に聞く 高師の浜のはま松も 世のあだ波は のがれざりけり」と反対する歌を詠んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When OKUBO was guided to Hamadera park by Tomoatsu GODAI, he knew that Atsushi SAISHO, Sakai prefectural governor planned to cut pine trees and use the park for residential area, then he composed a haiku (Japanese poem) saying &quot;Even pine trees on the famous Takasu sands are not able to escape noisy ripples in the world, opposing the residence plan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When OKUBO was guided to Hamadera park by Tomoatsu GODAI, he knew that Atsushi SAISHO, Sakai prefectural governor planned to cut pine trees and use the park for a residential area, so he composed a haiku (Japanese poem) saying &quot;Even the pine trees on the famous Takasu sands are not able to escape noisy ripples in the world, opposing the residence plan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When OKUBO was guided to Hamadera park by Tomoatsu GODAI, he knew that Atsushi SAISHO, Sakai prefectural governor planned to cut pine trees and use the park for a residential area, so he composed a haiku (Japanese poem) saying &quot;Even the pine trees on the famous Takasi sands are not able to escape noisy ripples in the world, opposing the residence plan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>TakasuをTakashiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この歌を知った税所は、開発計画を撤回した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When SAISHO knew this haiku, he withdrew his development plan of Hamadera park.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When SAISHO learned about this haiku, he withdrew his development plans for Hamadera park.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When SAISHO learned about this haiku, he withdrew his development plans for Hamadera park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>なお、浜寺公園の入り口付近にこの時に詠んだ歌が、「惜松碑（せきしょうひ）」として顕彰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, at the entrance of Hamadera park, the monument with the inscription of the haiku composed by OKUBO is standing now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, a monument inscribed with this haiku composed by OKUBO stands at the entrance of Hamadera park now.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the monument named &quot;Sekisho-hi&quot; inscribed with this haiku composed by OKUBO stands at the entrance of Hamadera park now.</e>
<cmt>「惜松碑として」の訳が抜けていますので、追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>寡黙であり、他を圧倒する威厳を持ち、かつ冷静な理論家でもあったため、面と向かって大久保に意見できる人間は少なかったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was reciturn, possessed an air of dignity, and calm theorist, therefore few people could warn him to his face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was taciturn, possessed an air of dignity, and was a calm theorist, therefore few people could put forth their own opinions to his face.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was taciturn, possessed an air of dignity, and was a calm theorist, therefore few people could put forth their own opinions to his face.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>桐野利秋も、大久保に対してまともに話ができなかったので、大酒を飲んで酔っ払った上で意見しようとしたが、大久保に一喝されてすぐに引き下がったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Toshiaki KIRINO could not have a talk face to face with him, therefore KIRINO drank sake heavily and tried to warn him, but he was yelled at by OKUBO and drew back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Toshiaki KIRINO could not normally have a talk face to face with him, therefore KIRINO drank sake heavily first and then tried to reprove him, but he was yelled at by OKUBO and drew back.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Toshiaki KIRINO could not normally have a talk face to face with him, therefore KIRINO drank sake heavily first and then tried to reprove him, but he was yelled at by OKUBO and drew back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>また、若い頃から勇猛で鳴らした山本権兵衛も、大久保の前ではほとんど意見できなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, It is said that Gombei YAMAMOTO who were famous for his dauntless courage, could not express his opinion freely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is said that even Gombei YAMAMOTO, who was famous for his dauntless courage, could not express his opinion to him freely.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that even Gombei YAMAMOTO, who was famous for his dauntless courage, could not express his opinion to him freely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>大久保が内務省に登庁しその靴音が廊下に響くと職員たちは私語を止め、それまでざわついていた庁舎内が水を打ったように静まり返った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When OKUBO came to the Ministry of Interior, the staff hearing the sounds of his footsteps stopped their private talks, and the inside of the Ministry building became very quiet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When OKUBO came to the Ministry of Interior, the staff who heard the sound of his footsteps stopped their private conversations, and the inside of the Ministry building became very quiet.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When OKUBO came to the Ministry of Interior, the staff who heard the sound of his footsteps stopped their private conversations, and the inside of the Ministry building became very quiet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>内務省で勧商局長などを務めて大久保の部下であった河瀬秀治は、大久保の没後の内務省では、伊藤博文内務卿の部屋で西郷従道や中井弘が盛んに夕べの話をしたり、仲居が出入りするようになるなど、すべてが奢侈に流れ堕落したと嘆いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of OKUBO, Hideji KAWASE who were the head of business promotion bureau and the subordinate of OKUBO, sighed over luxury and corruption within the Ministry, like in the cases in the room of Hirofumi ITO, Secretary of Interior, where Tsugumichi SAIGO and Hiroshi NAKAI, influential persons, were talking about the night before and waitresses of traditional restraints were going in and out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of OKUBO, Hideji KAWASE, who was the head of the business promotion bureau and a subordinate of OKUBO, bemoaned the luxury and corruption within the Ministry, such as in the room of Hirofumi ITO, Secretary of Interior, where Tsugumichi SAIGO and Hiroshi NAKAI, influential persons, were talking about the night before while waitresses from traditional restaurants were going in and out.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of OKUBO, Hideji KAWASE, who was the head of the business promotion bureau and a subordinate of OKUBO, bemoaned the luxury and corruption within the Ministry, such as in the room of Hirofumi ITO, Secretary of Interior, where Tsugumichi SAIGO and Hiroshi NAKAI, influential persons, were talking about the night before while waitresses from traditional restaurants were going in and out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="64">
<j>家庭内では子煩悩で優しい父親だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that OKUBO was a very gentle and devoted father to his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that OKUBO was a very gentle and devoted father to his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that OKUBO was a very gentle and devoted father to his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>出勤前のわずか10分か15分の間を唯一の娘である芳子を抱き上げて慈しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the short time of 10 to 15 minutes before starting to the ministry, he loved his only daughter, Yoshiko, by lifting her in his arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the short time of 10 to 15 minutes before heading off to the Ministry, he showed affection to his only daughter, Yoshiko, by lifting her in his arms.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the short time of 10 to 15 minutes before heading off to the Ministry, he showed affection to his only daughter, Yoshiko, by lifting her in his arms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また大久保が馬車で自宅に帰ってくると、三男の大久保利武ら子ども達が争って、玄関に出迎え靴を脱がせようとして、勢いあまって後ろに転がるのを見て笑って喜んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When OKUBO returned to the home, he was delighted to see that his children including his third son, Toshitake, were rushing to the entrance hall to see him and strived to take off his shoes, falling down on their backs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When OKUBO returned home, he was delighted to see that his children, including his third son, Toshitake, would rush to the entrance hall to see him and tried to take off his shoes for him, falling over on their backs.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When OKUBO returned home, he was delighted to see that his children, including his third son, Toshitake, would rush to the entrance hall to see him and tried to take off his shoes for him, falling over on their backs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="67">
<j>青いガラス製の洗面器具を使い、家庭内においても洋間に滞在しながら洋服を着用する、当時としては非常に洋風な生活をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He led a western-style life, rare in those days, using a wash basin made of blue glass, wearing western clothes and living in western room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He led a western-style life, rare in those days, using a wash basin made of blue glass, wearing western clothes and living in a western room.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He led a western-style life, rare in those days, using a wash basin made of blue glass, wearing western clothes and living in a western room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また頭髪をポマードでセットしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he set his heir with pomade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also set his hair with pomade.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also set his hair with pomade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="69">
<j>江藤新平と島義勇が佐賀の乱で挙兵した際に、直ちに自ら鎮台兵を率いて遠征、瓦解させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Shinpei ETO and Yoshitake SHIMA raised an army in Saga War, he made an expedition, leading soldiers in garrisons and suppressed the riot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shinpei ETO and Yoshitake SHIMA raised an army in the Saga War, he made an expedition, leading soldiers in garrisons and suppressed the riot.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shinpei ETO and Yoshitake SHIMA raised an army in the Saga War, he made an expedition, leading soldiers in garrisons and suppressed the riot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>この時大久保の日記には、「江東、陳弁曖昧、実に笑止千万、人物推て知られたり」など書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his diary in those days, he wrote that ETO was obscure, ludicrous and trivial person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his diary in those days, he wrote that ETO was an irrelevant, ludicrous and trivial person.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his diary in those days, he wrote that ETO was an irrelevant, ludicrous and trivial person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="71">
<j>鹿児島が暴発したときには、伊藤博文に対して「朝廷不幸の幸と、ひそかに心中には笑いを生じ候ぐらいにこれあり候」と鹿児島の暴徒を一掃できるとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the rebellion occurred in Kagoshima, he wrote a letter to Hirofumi ITO and expressed his opinion to be able to easily wipe out the rioters, saying &quot;I think that this rebellion is a good fortune aspect of an unfortunate event and I am laughing at this rebellion in my sleeves&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the rebellion occurred in Kagoshima, he wrote a letter to Hirofumi ITO and expressed his opinion that they would be able to easily wipe out the rioters, saying &quot;I think that this rebellion has the aspect of good fortune in an unfortunate event and I am laughing at this rebellion in my sleeves&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the rebellion occurred in Kagoshima, he wrote a letter to Hirofumi ITO and expressed his opinion that they would be able to easily wipe out the rioters, saying &quot;I think that this rebellion has the aspect of good fortune in an unfortunate event and I am laughing at this rebellion in my sleeves&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また西郷については、これでは私学校党に同意せず、「無名の軽挙」をやらかさないだろうと書き送った（明治10年2月7日付書簡）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, concerning SAIGO, he wrote to ITO that OKUBO did not think SAIGO conformed the Shigakko (school mainly for warriors) party and would not act rushly and blindly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, concerning SAIGO, he wrote to ITO that he did not think SAIGO conformed to the Shigakko (school mainly for warriors) party and would not act rashly and blindly.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, concerning SAIGO, he wrote to ITO that he did not think SAIGO conformed to the Shigakko (school mainly for warriors) party and would not act rashly and blindly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>そして、西南戦争が始まる前に西郷が参加していることが分かると、西郷に会って話し合うために、鹿児島へ行くことを希望したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, before Seinan War, when he knew that SAIGO participated in the rebellion, he wanted to go to Kagoshima to have a talk with SAIGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, before the Seinan War, when he knew that SAIGO participated in the rebellion, he wanted to go to Kagoshima to have a talk with SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, before the Seinan War, when he knew that SAIGO participated in the rebellion, he wanted to go to Kagoshima to have a talk with SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>しかし、大久保が殺されることを危惧した伊藤博文らに朝議で反対され、希望は叶わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Hirofumi ITO and others opposed him to go because they were afraid that OKUBO might be killed, and his wish was not realized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Hirofumi ITO and others opposed his going because they were afraid that OKUBO might be killed, and his wish was not realized.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Hirofumi ITO and others opposed his going because they were afraid that OKUBO might be killed, and his wish was not realized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="75">
<j>西郷死亡の報せを聞くと号泣し、時々鴨居に頭をぶつけながらも家の中をグルグル歩き回っていた（この際、「おはんの死と共に、新しか日本がうまれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When OKUBO was informed of SAIGO&apos;s death, he wept bitterly, walking around inside of his house and hitting his head to top slots of rooms (at that time it was reported that he said &quot;New Japan will be born with your death; strong Japan will be born&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When OKUBO was informed of SAIGO&apos;s death, he wept bitterly, walking around inside of his house and hitting his head on the lintels of the rooms (at that time it was reported that he said &quot;a new Japan will be born with your death; a strong Japan will be born&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When OKUBO was informed of SAIGO&apos;s death, he wept bitterly, walking around inside of his house and hitting his head on the lintels of the rooms (at that time it was reported that he said &quot;a new Japan will be born with your death; a strong Japan will be born&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>強か日本が......」と言ったようだ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">strong Japan will be born&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">strong Japan will be born&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">strong Japan will be born&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="77">
<j>西南戦争終了後に「自分ほど西郷を知っている者はいない」と言って、西郷の伝記の執筆を重野安譯に頼んでいたりしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the end of Seinan War, he said there were nobody who knew SAIGO better than him, and he asked SHIGENO to write the biography of SAIGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the end of the Seinan War, he said there was nobody who knew SAIGO better than him, and he asked SHIGENO to write SAIGO&apos;s biography.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the end of the Seinan War, he said there was nobody who knew SAIGO better than him, and he asked Yasutsugu SHIGENO to write SAIGO&apos;s biography.</e>
<cmt>重野安譯（しげのやすつぐ）のYasutsuguをSHIGENOの前に挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>また、暗殺された時に生前の西郷から送られた手紙を持っていたと高島鞆之助が語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Tomonosuke TAKASHIMA told that OKUBO had the letter from SAIGO when OKUBO was assashinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Tomonosuke TAKASHIMA reported that OKUBO had a letter from SAIGO with him when OKUBO was assasinated.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, Tomonosuke TAKASHIMA reported that OKUBO had a letter from SAIGO with him when OKUBO was assasinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="79">
<j>暗殺される日の朝、福島県令山吉盛典に対し、「ようやく戦乱も収まって平和になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the morning of the day of assassination, he told YAMAYOSHI, governor of Fukushima Prefecture about his future plan &quot; rebellions of many years have been suppressed and peace retuned to Japan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the morning of the day of the assassination, he told YAMAYOSHI, governor of Fukushima Prefecture, about his future plan, in which &quot;the rebellions of many years will have been suppressed and peace will be returned to Japan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the morning of the day of the assassination, he told Morisuke YAMAYOSHI, governor of Fukushima Prefecture, about his future plan, in which &quot;the rebellions of many years will have been suppressed and peace will be returned to Japan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>山吉盛典（やまよしもりすけ）のMorisukeを加入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>よって維新の精神を貫徹することにするが、それには30年の時期が要る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Therefore I plan to accomplish the spirit of Meiji Restoration, but it requires the period of 30 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Therefore I plan to carry out the spirit of the Meiji Restoration, but it will require a period of 30 years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Therefore I plan to carry out the spirit of the Meiji Restoration, but it will require a period of 30 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>それを仮に三分割すると、明治元年から10年までの第一期は戦乱が多く創業の時期であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it is diveided in 3 periods, the first period was from 1868 to 1877; this was the period for foundation with a lot of wars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If divided in 3 periods, the first period was from 1868 to 1877; this was the foundation period with many battles.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If divided in 3 periods, the first period was from 1868 to 1877; this was the foundation period with many battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>明治11年から20年までの第二期は内治を整え、民産を興す時期で、私はこの時まで内務の職に尽くしたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second period is from 1878 to 1887 for putting domestic politics in order and promote private industries, until the beginning of this period I have served for domestic affaires.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second period would be from 1878 to 1887 for putting domestic politics in order and promoting private industry; I would like to do my utmost in domestic affairs until the beginning of this period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second period would be from 1878 to 1887 for putting domestic politics in order and promoting private industry; I would like to do my utmost in domestic affairs until the beginning of this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>明治21年から30年までの第三期は後進に譲り、発展を待つ時期だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third period is from 1888 to 1897 for making way for younger people and waiting for their development&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third period would be from 1888 to 1897 in which there will be making way for the next generation and awaiting their development&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third period would be from 1888 to 1897 in which there will be making way for the next generation and awaiting their development&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>」と将来の構想を語ったという（『済世遺言』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus he told the governor about his future plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus he told the governor about his future plans.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus he told the governor about his future plans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="85">
<j>大久保利通を水神として祀る「大久保神社」が、福島県郡山市にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a &quot;OKUBO Shinto shrine&quot; which deifies OKUBO as the God of Water and Rain in Koriyama City, Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an OKUBO Shinto shrine which deifies OKUBO as a God of Water and Rain in Koriyama City, Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an OKUBO Shinto shrine which deifies OKUBO as a God of Water and Rain in Koriyama City, Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="86">
<j>身長：178cm、体重：65kg。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Height: 178 cm, Weight: 65 kg</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Height: 178 cm, Weight: 65 kg</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Height: 178 cm, Weight: 65 kg</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>ABO式血液型はO型。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Blood type: O</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blood type: O</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blood type: O</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="88">
<j>雅号：甲東</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pen name: Koto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pen name: Koto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pen name: Koto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>座右の銘：「為政清明」、「堅忍不抜」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motto: &quot;clean and bright politics&quot;, &quot;indomitable perseverance&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mottos: &quot;clean and bright politics&quot;, &quot;indomitable perseverance.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mottos: &quot;clean and bright politics&quot;, &quot;indomitable perseverance.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>家族・子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family and Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family and Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family and Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>安政4年（1857年）に薩摩藩士早崎七郎右衛門の次女・満寿子と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got married with Masuko, the second daughter of Shichiroemon HAYASAKI, the feudal retainer of Satsuma in 1857.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married Masuko, the second daughter of Shichiroemon HAYASAKI, the feudal retainer of Satsuma, in 1857.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married Masuko, the second daughter of Shichiroemon HAYASAKI, the feudal retainer of Satsuma, in 1857.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>満寿子との間には、長男大久保利和・次男牧野伸顕・三男大久保利武・五男石原雄熊・長女芳子が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Masuko, he had Toshikazu OKUBO, the first son; Nobuaki MAKINO, the second son; Toshitake OKUBO,the third son; Okuma ISHIHARA, the fifth son; Yoshiko, the eldest daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Masuko, he had Toshikazu OKUBO, the first son; Nobuaki MAKINO, the second son; Toshitake OKUBO, the third son; Okuma ISHIHARA, the fifth son; and Yoshiko, the eldest daughter.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Masuko, he had Toshikazu OKUBO, the first son; Nobuaki MAKINO, the second son; Toshitake OKUBO, the third son; Okuma ISHIHARA, the fifth son; and Yoshiko, the eldest daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>芳子は後の外務大臣 (日本)伊集院彦吉に嫁いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiko got married with Hikokichi IJUIN, later foreign minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiko married Hikokichi IJUIN, later a foreign minister.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiko married Hikokichi IJUIN, later a foreign minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>大久保には妻の外におゆう（杉浦勇）という愛妾が居り、おゆうとの間に四男大久保利夫・六男大久保駿熊・七男大久保七熊・八男大久保利賢をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides his wife, he had a favorite concubine named Oyuu (Yuu SUGIURA) and with her, he had Toshio OKUBO, the fourth son; Sukuma OKUBO, the sixth son; Shichikuma OKUBO; seventh son; Toshikata OKUBO, the eighth son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides his wife, he had a favorite concubine named Oyuu (Yuu SUGIURA) and with her, he had Toshio OKUBO, the fourth son; Sukuma OKUBO, the sixth son; Shichikuma OKUBO; the seventh son; and Toshikata OKUBO, the eighth son.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides his wife, he had a favorite concubine named Oyuu (Yuu SUGIURA) and with her, he had Toshio OKUBO, the fourth son; Sukuma OKUBO, the sixth son; Shichikuma OKUBO; the seventh son; and Toshikata OKUBO, the eighth son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>孫の大久保利謙は日本近代史家で東大名誉教授。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshikane OKUBO, one of his grandsons was the scholar of Japan modern times history and honorary professor of Tokyo University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshikane OKUBO, one of his grandsons, was a scholar of Japanese modern history and an honorary professor of Tokyo University.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshikane OKUBO, one of his grandsons, was a scholar of Japanese modern history and an honorary professor of Tokyo University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>もう一人の孫大久保利春は丸紅専務で、ロッキード事件に際しては賄賂の一人として逮捕・起訴され有罪判決を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another grandson, Toshiharu OKUBO was a senior managing director of big trading company, Marubeni, but he was arrested and prosecuted for bribery case in Lockheed scandal, and was found guilty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another grandson, Toshiharu OKUBO, was a senior managing director of a big trading company, Marubeni, but he was arrested and prosecuted for a bribery case in the Lockheed scandal, and was found guilty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another grandson, Toshiharu OKUBO, was a senior managing director of a big trading company, Marubeni, but he was arrested and prosecuted for a bribery case in the Lockheed scandal, and was found guilty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>「じいさんにあわせる顔がない」が口癖だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They say that he used to say &quot;I am too ashamed to see my grandfather&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They say that he used to say &quot;I am too ashamed to see my grandfather&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They say that he used to say &quot;I am too ashamed to see my grandfather&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="97">
<j>曾孫に吉田健一 (英文学者)（作家）、大久保利晃（放射線影響研究所理事長、前産業医科大学長）、玄孫に寛仁親王妃信子、牧野力（通産省事務次官）、麻生太郎（内閣総理大臣）、武見敬三（元参議院議員）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As great-grandchildren, Kenichi YOSHIDA (scholar of American and English literature)(writer), Toshiaki OKUBO (administrative director of radiation influence research institute, former president of industry medical university), as great-great-grand children, Princess Nobuko, the wife of Imperial Prince Tomohito; Tsutomu MAKINO (deputy secretary of the Ministry of International Trade and Industry), Taro ASO (prime minister), Keizo TAKEMI (former Member of the House of Councilors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Great-grandchildren include Kenichi YOSHIDA (scholar of American and English literature; writer), Toshiaki OKUBO (administrative director of a radiation influence research institute, former president of an industrial medical university), great-great-grandchildren include Princess Nobuko, the wife of Imperial Prince Tomohito; Tsutomu MAKINO (deputy secretary of the Ministry of International Trade and Industry), Taro ASO (prime minister) and Keizo TAKEMI (former member of the House of Councilors).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Great-grandchildren include Kenichi YOSHIDA (scholar of American and English literature; writer), Toshiaki OKUBO (administrative director of a radiation influence research institute, former president of an industrial medical university), great-great-grandchildren include Princess Nobuko, the wife of Imperial Prince Tomohito; Tsutomu MAKINO (deputy secretary of the Ministry of International Trade and Industry), Taro ASO (prime minister) and Keizo TAKEMI (former member of the House of Councilors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>大久保氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okubo clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okubo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okubo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>明確ではないが藤原氏末流を称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not clear, they call themselves descendents of Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the connection is not clear, they call themselves descendents of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the connection is not clear, they call themselves descendents of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>家紋は三つ藤巴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family crest: three wisteria tomoe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family crest: three wisteria tomoe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family crest: three wisteria tomoe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)末に京都から薩摩に移るというが、系図は貞享年間に市来郷川上に中宿（城下に籍を残したまま他郷へ移住すること）した仲兵衛より始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they say that their ancestors moved from Kyoto at the end of Sengoku period, genealogy began from Nakahyoe who moved to Shiraigokawakami in Jokyo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they say that their ancestors moved from Kyoto at the end of the Sengoku period, the genealogy begins from Nakahyoe, who moved to Shiraigokawakami in the Jokyo era.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they say that their ancestors moved from Kyoto at the end of the Sengoku period, the genealogy begins from Nakabei, who moved to Ichikigo Kawakami in the Jokyo era.</e>
<cmt>NakahyoueをNakabeiに修正し、ShiraigokawakamiをIchikigo Kawakamiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>官位及び栄典の履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO&apos;s personal history of official rank and honor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimichi OKUBO&apos;s personal history of official ranks and honors</e>
<cmt>Wording. Not sure if &quot;merits&quot; is better than &quot;honors&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO&apos;s personal history of official ranks and honors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>明治元年閏月4月21日 (旧暦)（1868年6月11日）：従四位（辞退）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junior Fourth Rank in 1868: declined</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junior Fourth Rank in 1868: declined</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junior Fourth Rank in 1868: declined</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>明治2年6月2日 (旧暦)（1869年7月10日）：従三位、永世賞典禄1,800石</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junior Third Rank, eternal premium 18,000 koku in 1869,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junior Third Rank, eternal premium 18,000 koku in 1869.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junior Third Rank, eternal premium 18,000 goku in 1869.</e>
<cmt>石の読みkokuをgokuに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>明治10年（1877年）11月2日：勲一等旭日大綬章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun in 1877</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun in 1877</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun in 1877</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>明治11年（1878年）5月15日：贈位正二位右大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conferral of a posthumous rank: Senior Second Rank, Chief of an Imperial Japanese Council of State in 1878</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conferral of a posthumous rank: Senior Second Rank, Chief of the Imperial Japanese Council of State in 1878</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conferral of a posthumous rank: Senior Second Rank, Chief of the Imperial Japanese Council of State in 1878</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>明治17年（1884年）7月7日：継嗣利和が侯爵に叙爵される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heir Toshikazu was conferred a marquis in 1884</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heir Toshikazu was conferred a marquis in 1884.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heir Toshikazu was conferred a marquis in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="107">
<j>明治34年（1901年）5月22日：贈従一位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Postmortem promotion to Junior First Rank in 1901</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Postmortem promotion to Junior First Rank in 1901</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Postmortem promotion to Junior First Rank in 1901</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), 戊辰龍馬(id:10371), CHISC(id:108483), KAZUI(id:46122), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Krypton(id:150926), Lupinoid(id:68), Tribot(id:186681), Greenland4(id:114494), Zepher(id:23663), Arpeggio(id:9385), でここ(id:9565), 継之助(id:39352), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), 茶太郎(id:16870), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), 海獺(id:153448), Pakupaku(id:115950), Knua(id:66861), Kanoe(id:17203), 木戸信長(id:23914), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), たーじゃん(id:80884), 修一(id:38717), DumZiBoT(id:230315), DCyokohama(id:26779), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Lemon pie(id:66842), 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), Kurayamizaka(id:7150), Moltke(id:17553), 松茸(id:27535), 砂場(id:27896), Complex01(id:10454), L III (N)(id:72793), 山岡鉄人(id:99343), よもすがら(id:212112), 樒(id:35770), Kagetudo(id:163875), Tietew(id:4054), 総督(id:124846), トホホ川(id:50502), Andrewsbar(id:268701), Junger(id:10282), Mameneko(id:785), ツナマヨ(id:40302), みょうじ(id:124419), Hatabon(id:146971), Deewell(id:22093), Resto1578(id:168692), Tomzo(id:16777), Miuharehareyukai(id:172205), Reggaeman(id:6214), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), ぎぶそん(id:261394), Tom-spring(id:42457), ロナルド(id:9943), 陽一(id:92099), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Ohura(id:5986), Spothit(id:217246), トッキッキ2009(id:250957), 伊勢佐木町メランコリー(id:304952), Tomo suzuki(id:11928), Goki(id:7107), Rei-bot(id:94097), 盛風力(id:54988), 寂華(id:83725), こぶまき(id:38278), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), TARBOT(id:73059), Juqipedia(id:188816), J-ishikawa(id:74471), Race(id:131322), 東京外国語大学生(id:70622), 水野白楓(id:22811), Inukawa(id:842), つきみ(id:91808), Gainax(id:172075), Hadge(id:9555), YurikBot(id:18605), Miya(id:1881), 上田隼人(id:23104), Nonnonba(id:124424), シャさん(id:43303), AEONseven&amp;i(id:89677), じゃんもどき(id:251238), 江戸ラー(id:30154), Muyo(id:14948), Falcosapiens(id:221), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>