<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千覚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千覚（せんがく、生没年未詳）は平安時代末期の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengaku (year of birth and death unknown) was a Buddhist monk who lived in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengaku (year of birth and death unknown) was a Buddhist monk who lived during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengaku (year of birth and death unknown) was a Buddhist monk during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと表現を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家勧修寺流、土佐守藤原盛実の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Morizane from the Kanjuji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, who held the position of Tosa no kuni no kami (the governor of Tosa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Morizane from the Kanjuji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, who held the position of Tosa no kuni no kami (governor of Tosa Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Kajuji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and he was a son of FUJIWARA no Morizane who held the position of Tosa no kami (Governor of Tosa Province).</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄弟姉妹に藤原顕憲、藤原忠実室（藤原頼長母）らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His siblings included FUJIWARA no Akinori, and a wife of FUJIWARA no Tadazane (the mother of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His siblings included FUJIWARA no Akinori, and the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadazane (the mother of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His siblings included FUJIWARA no Akinori, and the wife of FUJIWARA no Tadazane (the mother of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>興福寺に入り僧正隆覚に師事し、仁平3年（1153年）に権律師となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the Kofuku-ji Temple to study under Ryukaku Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest), and was granted the rank of Gon-Risshi (generally in Shingon sect, fifteenth-ranking Buddhist priest, literally, &quot;supernumerary master of discipline&quot;) in 1153.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the Kofuku-ji Temple to study under Ryukaku Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest), and was granted the rank of Gon-Risshi (generally in the Shingon sect, fifteenth-ranking Buddhist priest, literally, &quot;supernumerary master of discipline&quot;) in 1153.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the Kofuku-ji Temple to study under Ryukaku Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest), and was granted the rank of Gon no Risshi (a provisional rank in the lowest managerial position) in 1153.</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その三年後の保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱においては、外甥である藤原頼長に与同し崇徳上皇方に加担。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three years later, in 1156, he joined his nephew FUJIWARA no Yorinaga and fought for the Retired Emperor Sutoku in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three years later, in 1156, he joined his nephew FUJIWARA no Yorinaga and fought for Retired Emperor Sutoku during the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three years later, in 1156, he joined his nephew FUJIWARA no Yorinaga and fought for Retired Emperor Sutoku during the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>敗戦後、負傷した頼長が最後に逃れ息を引き取ったのが興福寺の千覚の房であったこと、また南都に逃れてきた頼長の父忠実を信実・尋範らとともに守護したことなどから、その関与の深さを問われ所領を没官されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Yorinaga, defeated and injured in the War, died in Sengaku&apos;s cell at the Kofuku-ji Temple, and Sengaku patronized Tadazane, who was the father of Yorinaga who had fled from Nanto (southern capital (Nara)), along with Nobuzane and Jinpan, his land was confiscated under the charge of deep involvement in the War.</e>
<cmt>その関与の深さ：保元の乱への関与として訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Yorinaga, defeated and injured in the War, died in Sengaku&apos;s cell at the Kofuku-ji Temple, and Sengaku patronized Tadazane, who was the father of Yorinaga who had fled from Nanto (southern capital - Nara), along with Nobuzane and Jinpan, his land was confiscated under the charge of deep involvement in the War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Yorinaga, defeated and injured in the War, died in Sengaku&apos;s cell at the Kofuku-ji Temple, and Sengaku patronized Tadazane, who was the father of Yorinaga and had fled from Nanto (southern capital - Nara), along with Nobuzane and Jinpan, his land was confiscated under the charge of deep involvement in the War.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>