<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平忠常</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadatsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 忠常（たいら の ただつね）は平安時代の人物、武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsune was a samurai lived during Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadatsune was a samurai lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>冠詞挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsune was a samurai lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は陸奥国介平忠頼で、房総平氏の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father TAIRA no Tadayori, who was Mutsu no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Mutsu), was an ancestor of Boso-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father TAIRA no Tadayori, who was Mutsu no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Mutsu), was the ancestor of Boso-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father TAIRA no Tadayori, who was Mutsu no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Mutsu), was the ancestor of Boso-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>祖父の平良文は武蔵国村岡に土着して村岡五郎と称して、下総国相馬郡 (下総国)の大半を所領とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather TAIRA no Yoshifumi settled in Muraoka, Musashi Province and called himself Goro MURAOKA, who possessed shoryo (territory) in the greater part of Soma County, Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather TAIRA no Yoshifumi settled in Muraoka, Musashi Province and called himself Goro MURAOKA, who possessed shoryo (territory) in the greater part of Soma County, Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather TAIRA no Yoshifumi settled in Muraoka, Musashi Province and called himself Goro MURAOKA, who possessed shoryo (territory) in the greater part of Soma County, Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父の忠頼も関東で有力な武士として名をはせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Tadayori was also renowned as a powerful samurai in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Tadayori was also renowned as a powerful samurai in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Tadayori was also renowned as a powerful samurai in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>忠常は祖父と父の地盤を引き継ぎ、常陸国、上総国、下総国に広大な所領を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune took over the sphere of influence built by his grandfather and father and possessed a vast shoryo in Hitachi Province, Kazusa Province and Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>原文が、括弧内の途中で分割されていたため、区切りの良いところで分割しなおしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune took over the sphere of influence built by his grandfather and father and possessed vast shoryo in Hitachi Province, Kazusa Province and Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune took over the sphere of influence built by his grandfather and father and possessed vast shoryo in Hitachi Province, Kazusa Province and Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>上総介（『日本紀略』による。『応徳元年皇代記』には下総権介）、武蔵押領使に任官されている（これらの官に任官はされず自称という説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province) (accorging to &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; [Summary of Japanese Chronologies]. It was Shimousa no gonsuke [officer of regional administration in Shimousa] according to &quot;Otoku Gannen Kodaiki&quot; [The Chronicle of the Emperors in Otoku era]) and Oryoshi (government official of police and military affairs) in Musashi Province (there is another theory that he was not appointed to these posts and described himself).</e>
<cmt>「応徳元年皇代記」、「押領使」の定訳不明です。それぞれローマ字表記の後に括弧で説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province) (this is accorging to &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; [Summary of Japanese Chronologies] and it was Shimousa no gonsuke [officer of regional administration in Shimousa] according to &quot;Otoku Gannen Kodaiki&quot; [The Chronicle of the Emperors in Otoku era]) and Oryoshi (government official of police and military affairs) in Musashi Province (there is another theory that he was not appointed to these posts and professed to be appointed).</e>
<cmt>that is挿入、ピリオドをコンマに変更、自称の表現変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province) (this is accorging to &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; [Summary of Japanese Chronologies] and it was Shimousa no gonsuke [officer of regional administration in Shimousa] according to &quot;Otoku Gannen Kodaiki&quot; [The Chronicle of the Emperors in Otoku era]) and Oryoshi (government official of police and military affairs) in Musashi Province (there is another theory that he was not appointed to these posts and professed to be appointed).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>諸系図では下総国千葉郡にて千葉小次郎と称したと言うが、不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although several genealogies show that he called himself Kojiro CHIBA in Chiba County, Shimousa Province, the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although several genealogies show that he called himself Kojiro CHIBA in Chiba County, Shimousa Province, the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although several genealogies show that he called himself Kojiro CHIBA in Chiba County, Shimousa Province, the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>京に上り藤原教通（藤原道長の次男）に仕えていた形跡がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a trace that he left for the capital to serve FUJIWARA no Norimichi (the second son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a trace that he left for the capital to serve FUJIWARA no Norimichi (the second son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a trace that he left for the capital to serve FUJIWARA no Norimichi (the second son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>忠常は強大な武力を背景に傍若無人に振る舞い、国司の命に従わず租税も納めなかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune behaved outrageously against the background of the mighty military power and it is said he did not even pay his taxes, disobeyed kokushi (provincial governors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune behaved outrageously with backing of the mighty military power and it is said he did not pay his taxes and disobeyed kokushi (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>「背景に」の部分変更、and挿入、単数化、even削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune behaved outrageously with backing of the mighty military power and it is said he did not pay his taxes and disobeyed kokushi (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>官軍との戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle with Government Army</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle with government army</e>
<cmt>小文字化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle with government army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>長元元年（1028年）6月、忠常は安房国の国府を襲い、安房守平惟忠を焼き殺す事件を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune raised an event that he attacked kokufu (provincial office) in Awa Province in June, 1028, and burned to murder Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) TAIRA no Koretada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune caused an event that he attacked kokufu (provincial office) in Awa Province in June, 1028 and burned to murder Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) TAIRA no Koretada.</e>
<cmt>動詞変更、コンマ削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune caused an event that he attacked kokufu (provincial office) in Awa Province in June, 1028 and burned to murder Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) TAIRA no Koretada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>原因は不明だが受領との対立が高じたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the origin of the event is unknown, it could be the rising antagonism against Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the origin of the event is unknown, it could be the rising antagonism to Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>前置詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the origin of the event is unknown, it could be the rising antagonism to Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>朝廷は忠常追討を命じ、追討使平直方が派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Court commanded and dispatched TAIRA no Naokata as an envoy to search and kill Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court commanded to hunt down and kill Tadatsune and dispatched TAIRA no Naokata as an envoy to search and kill him.</e>
<cmt>冠詞挿入、目的語の挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court commanded to hunt down and kill Tadatsune and dispatched TAIRA no Naokata as an envoy to search and kill him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>官軍を相手に忠常は頑強に抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune put up stubborn resistance to the government army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune put up stubborn resistance to the government army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune put up stubborn resistance to the government army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>乱は房総三カ国に広まり、合戦の被害と官軍による強引な徴発により大いに疲弊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle had spread throughout three provinces in Boso, where became impoverished terribly due to the damage of the battle and a forcible requisition by the government army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle had spread throughout three provinces in Boso, which became impoverished terribly due to the damage of the battle and forcible requisitions by the government army.</e>
<cmt>whereを訂正、複数化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle had spread throughout three provinces in Boso, which became impoverished terribly due to the damage of the battle and forcible requisitions by the government army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>（平忠常の乱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The TAIRA no Tadatsune War)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The TAIRA no Tadatsune War)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The TAIRA no Tadatsune War)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>長元3年（1030年）9月、平直方が解任され、甲斐国守源頼信が追討使に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Naokata was dismissed and MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, Kai no kuni no Kami (officer in charge of regional administration in Kai), was appointed to be an envoy to search and kill instead in September, 1030.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Naokata was dismissed and MINAMOTO no Yorinobu in the position of Kai no kuni no Kami (officer in charge of regional administration in Kai) was appointed to be the envoy instead in September, 1030.</e>
<cmt>in the position ofを挿入、前列と重複となる部分を削除、コンマ削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Naokata was dismissed and MINAMOTO no Yorinobu in the position of Kai no kuni no Kami (officer in charge of regional administration in Kai) was appointed to be the envoy instead in October, 1030.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>長期にわたる合戦で忠常の軍は疲弊しきっており、長元4年（1031年）春に忠常は出家して常安と称し、子2人と従者をつれて頼信のもとへ出頭して降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Tadatsune&apos;s troops had been exhausted from a long battle, he entered into priesthood with a posthumous Buddhist name Tsuneyasu in Spring of 1031, and then went before Yorinobu to surrender taking his two children and his followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Tadatsune&apos;s troops had been exhausted from the long battle, he entered into priesthood with a posthumous Buddhist name Tsuneyasu in Spring of 1031, and then surrendered himself to Yorinobu with his two children and his followers.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、takingを変更、出頭するの表現変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Tadatsune&apos;s troops had been exhausted from the long battle, he entered into priesthood with a posthumous Buddhist name Tsuneyasu in Spring of 1031, and then surrendered himself to Yorinobu with his two children and his followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同年6月、京へ連行される途上の美濃国野上で病没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year, he was died of disease in Nogami, Mino Province on the way to being taken to the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, he was died of disease in Nogami, Mino Province on the way to being taken to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year, he was died of disease in Nogami, Mino Province on the way to being taken to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>忠常の首ははねられ、京都で梟首とされたが、後に首は親族へ返されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tadatsune had been beheaded to expose a severed head in Kyoto, his head was returned to his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tadatsune had been beheaded to expose his severed head in Kyoto, his head was returned to his family.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tadatsune had been beheaded to expose his severed head in Kyoto, his head was returned to his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>子の平常将と平常近も罪を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of his children, TAIRA no Tsunemasa and TAIRA no Tsunechika were forgiven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children, TAIRA no Tsunemasa and TAIRA no Tsunechika were forgiven.</e>
<cmt>Both ofを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children, TAIRA no Tsunemasa and TAIRA no Tsunechika were forgiven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>忠常の子孫は房総半島の有力武士として残り、後に鎌倉幕府の御家人となる上総氏、千葉氏が出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune&apos;s descendants had remained as powerful samurai in Boso peninsula and formed the Kazusa clan and the Chiba clan which became gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) at Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune&apos;s descendants remained as powerful samurai in Boso Peninsula and formed the Kazusa clan and the Chiba clan which became gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate) in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) afterwards.</e>
<cmt>had削除、大文字化、「in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods」削除、冠詞挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune&apos;s descendants remained as powerful samurai in Boso Peninsula and formed the Kazusa clan and the Chiba clan which became gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate) in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 梟(id:117930), Horlicks(id:62133), 出羽卒族(id:283926), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 米栂(こめつが)(id:82593), Eskimbot(id:29676), 味っ子(id:17086), Yanahan(id:2437), Bonten2007(id:156965), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>