<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三淵藤英</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujihide MITSUBUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujihide MITSUBUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujihide MITSUBUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三淵 藤英（みつぶち ふじひで、？ - 天正2年7月6日 (旧暦)（1574年7月23日））は、室町幕府末期の幕臣（奉公衆）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujihide MITSUBUCHI [date of birth unknown - July 6, 1574 on lunar calendar (July 23, 1574)] was a direct vassal of shogun (military official) in the end of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujihide MITSUBUCHI [date of birth unknown - July 6, 1574 on lunar calendar (July 23, 1574)] was a direct vassal of shogun (military official) during the end of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujihide MITSUBUCHI (date of birth unknown - July 6, 1574) was a direct vassal of shogun (military official) during the end of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三淵晴員の長男で異母弟には細川幽斎（伯父の和泉国半国守護細川元常養子）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of Harukazu MITSUBUCHI, his half brother was Yusai HOSOKAWA [adopted son of Mototsune HOSOKAWA, hankoku shugo (military governor in charge of the half area of the Province) of Izumi Province.]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of Harukazu MITSUBUCHI, his half brother was Yusai HOSOKAWA [adopted son of Mototsune HOSOKAWA, hankoku shugo (military governor in charge of the half area of the Province) of Izumi Province.]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of Harukazu MITSUBUCHI, his half brother was Yusai HOSOKAWA (adopted son of Mototsune HOSOKAWA, hankoku shugo [military governor in charge of the half area of the Province] of Izumi Province.)</e>
<cmt>[()]→([])に整理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>永禄8年（1565年）に第13代征夷大将軍足利義輝が松永久秀・三好三人衆に暗殺されると（永禄の変）、藤英は弟の藤孝とともに一乗院覚慶（後の足利義昭）を擁立して越前国朝倉氏を頼る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1565, when the thirteenth seii taishogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was assassinated by Miyoshi sannin shu (Three subordinates of the Miyoshi clan: Nagayasu MIYOSHI, Masayasu MIYOSHI, and Tomomichi IWANARI) in the Eiroku Incident, Fujihide and his brother Fujitaka enthroned Kakukei ICHIJOIN (later, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA) and asked the Asakura clan in Echizen Province for help.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1565, when the thirteenth seii taishogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was assassinated by Miyoshi sannin shu (Three subordinates of the Miyoshi clan: Nagayasu MIYOSHI, Masayasu MIYOSHI, and Tomomichi IWANARI) in the Eiroku Incident, Fujihide and his brother Fujitaka enthroned Kakukei ICHIJOIN (later, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA) and asked the Asakura clan in Echizen Province for help.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1565, when the thirteenth Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and Miyoshi sannin shu (Three subordinates of the Miyoshi clan: Nagayasu MIYOSHI, Masayasu MIYOSHI, and Tomomichi IWANARI) in the Eiroku Incident, Fujihide and his brother Fujitaka enthroned Kakukei ICHIJOIN (later, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA) and asked the Asakura clan in Echizen Province for help.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一（征夷大将軍）Hisahide MATSUNAGAを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に織田信長に擁立されて義昭が第15代将軍となると、山城国伏見城が与えられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshiaki became the fifteenth Shogun enthroned by Nobunaga ODA, Fujihide was given the Fushimi-jo Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshiaki became the fifteenth Shogun enthroned by Nobunaga ODA, Fujihide was given the Fushimi-jo Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshiaki became the fifteenth Shogun enthroned by Nobunaga ODA, Fujihide was given the Fushimi-jo Castle in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後も和田惟政・伊丹親興とともに三好氏との戦いに参加する一方、行政官僚としての手腕を発揮して義昭の側近の一人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Koremasa WADA, Chikafusa ITAMI and Fujihide fought against the Miyoshi clan, Fujihide became one of Yoshiaki&apos;s close advisors, showing his administrative ability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Koremasa WADA, Chikafusa ITAMI and Fujihide fought against the Miyoshi clan, Fujihide became one of Yoshiaki&apos;s close advisors, showing his administrative ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Koremasa WADA, Chikafusa ITAMI and Fujihide fought against the Miyoshi clan, Fujihide became one of Yoshiaki&apos;s close advisors, showing his administrative ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、義昭と信長が対立したときに弟・藤孝が信長方に付いたことを知って激怒した藤英は藤孝襲撃を計画するが失敗に終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his brother Fujitaka took sides with Nobunaga in the event of conflict between Yoshiaki and Nobunaga, Fujihide got furious at Fujitaka and planned the attack against him, but it failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his brother Fujitaka took sides with Nobunaga in the conflict between Yoshiaki and Nobunaga, Fujihide became furious at Fujitaka and planned an attack against him, but failed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his brother Fujitaka took sides with Nobunaga in the conflict between Yoshiaki and Nobunaga, Fujihide became furious at Fujitaka and planned an attack against him, but failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天正元年（1573年）に義昭が山城槇島城に籠城すると、藤英は二条城の城代となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, when Yoshiaki was besieged in the Makishima-jo Castle in Yamashiro, Fujihide became a jodai (substitute lord of castle) of Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, when Yoshiaki was besieged in the Makishima-jo Castle in Yamashiro, Fujihide became a jodai (substitute lord of castle) of Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, when Yoshiaki was besieged in the Makishima-jo Castle in Yamashiro, Fujihide became a Jodai (the keeper of castle) of Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、信長の大軍に囲まれて軍は潰走したため、藤孝と柴田勝家の説得を受けて降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshiaki&apos;s army was besieged by Nobunaga&apos;s large army and fled in disorderly retreat, therefore, Fujihide surrendered by persuasion of Fujitaka and Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshiaki&apos;s army was besieged by Nobunaga&apos;s large army and fled in a disorderly retreat, therefore, Fujihide surrendered after being persuaded by Fujitaka and Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshiaki&apos;s army was besieged by Nobunaga&apos;s large army and fled in a disorderly retreat, therefore, Fujihide surrendered after being persuaded by Fujitaka and Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>間もなく、義昭は信長によって追放されて室町幕府は事実上滅亡してしまい藤英も信長に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after that, Yoshiaki was expelled by Nobunaga and the Muromachi bakufu was practically over, thus Fujihide served for Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, Yoshiaki was expelled by Nobunaga and the Muromachi bakufu was practically over, thus Fujihide served Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>FLow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, Yoshiaki was expelled by Nobunaga and the Muromachi bakufu was practically over, thus Fujihide served Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、翌年になって信長によって突如所領を没収されて明智光秀の元に預けられて、嫡男・三淵秋豪とともに自害を命じられるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the next year, his territory was suddenly confiscated by Nobunaga and after he was sent to Mitsuhide AKECHI, he was ordered to commit suicide including his son and heir Shugo MITSUBUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the next year, his territory was suddenly confiscated by Nobunaga and afterwards he was sent to Mitsuhide AKECHI, and ordered to commit suicide together with his son and heir Shugo MITSUBUCHI.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the next year, his territory was suddenly confiscated by Nobunaga and afterwards he was sent to Mitsuhide AKECHI, and ordered to commit suicide together with his son and heir Shugo MITSUBUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、幼い末子は藤孝に預けられてそのまま叔父に仕えて三淵光行と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His youngest son was taken care by his uncle Fujitaka, and served for him, called Mitsuyuki MITSUBUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His youngest son was taken care by his uncle Fujitaka, and served him, called Mitsuyuki MITSUBUCHI.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His youngest son was taken care by his uncle Fujitaka, and served him, called Mitsuyuki MITSUBUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後に関ヶ原の戦いに付随して生じた丹後国田辺城 (丹後国)の戦い（田辺城の戦い）において、光行はよく叔父を助けたことを知った徳川家康に高く評価されて旗本として召しだされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing that Mitsuyuki helped his uncle in the battle of Tanabe-jo Castle which was accompanied by the Battle of Sekigahara in Tanabe-jo Castle, Tango Province, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA thought highly of Mitsuyuki and hired him as hatamoto (direct vassal of the shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing that Mitsuyuki helped his uncle in the battle of Tanabe-jo Castle which was accompanied by the Battle of Sekigahara in Tanabe-jo Castle, Tango Province, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA thought highly of Mitsuyuki and hired him as hatamoto (direct vassal of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing that Mitsuyuki helped his uncle in the battle of Tanabe-jo Castle (Tango Province) which was accompanied by the Battle of Sekigahara in Tanabe-jo Castle, Tango Province, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA thought highly of Mitsuyuki and hired him as hatamoto (direct vassal of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>(Tango Province)を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 前田左衛門佐(id:194701), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>