<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土御門晴雄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土御門 晴雄（つちみかど はるお/はれお/はれたけ、文政10年6月5日 (旧暦)（1827年6月28日） - 明治2年10月6日 (旧暦)（1869年11月9日））は、幕末の公卿で阿倍氏陰陽道の事実上の最後の当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO (June 28, 1827 to November 9, 1869) was a Kugyo (high court noble) at the end of shogunate period and he was in reality the last headmaster of the ABE family&apos;s Onmyo Sect.(the way of positive and negative).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO (June 28, 1827 to November 9, 1869) was a Kugyo (high court noble) at the end of shogunate period and he was in reality the last headmaster of the Abe family&apos;s Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements).</e>
<cmt>家名は頭文字のみ大文字で表記します。「陰陽道」の訳語は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO (June 28, 1827 to November 9, 1869) was a Kugyo (high court noble) at the end of shogunate period and he was in reality the last headmaster of the Abe family&apos;s Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は土御門晴親、子は土御門晴栄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Harechika TSUCHIMIKADO and his son was Haruei TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Harechika TSUCHIMIKADO, and Haruei TSUCHIMIKADO was his son.</e>
<cmt>「子」は1人とは限りません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Harechika TSUCHIMIKADO, and Haruei TSUCHIMIKADO was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>妹に土御門藤子がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger sister was Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO was his younger sister.</e>
<cmt>「妹」は1人とは限りません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiko TSUCHIMIKADO was his younger sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家禄は183石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 183 koku of of crop yield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 183 koku of crop yield.</e>
<cmt>ofが重複していました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 183 koku of crop yield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>天保4年（1833年）に従五位上に叙されて、同10年（1839年）に元服して従五位上大膳大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1833, he was appointed Junior Fifth Rank Upper and in 1839, he was appointed Junior Fifth Rank Superior Cook.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1833, he was appointed Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and in 1839, he reached the manhood and became a Jugoinojo Daizen no daibu (Master of the Palace Table).</e>
<cmt>「元服して」の訳漏れ。「従五位上」の訳出を用語統一リストに従って修正しました。「大膳大夫」の訳語は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1833, he was appointed Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and in 1839, he reached the manhood and became a Jugoinojo Daizen no daibu (Master of the Palace Table).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同13年（1842年）に陰陽頭となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1842, he became the headmaster of Onmyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1842, he became the Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Buereau of Divination).</e>
<cmt>「陰陽頭」の訳語は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1842, he became the Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Buereau of Divination).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>嘉永2年（1849年）に右兵衛佐を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1849, he also served as the Right Guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1849, he also served as the Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>「右兵衛佐」の訳語は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1849, he also served as the Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>安政2年（1855年）には正四位下となり、安政5年（1858年）の廷臣八十八卿列参事件に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1855, he became Senior Fourth Rank Lower, and in 1858, he participated in the Teishin 88 Kyoressan Jiken (Demonstration by 88 Courtiers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1855, he became Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and in 1858, he participated in the Teishin 88-kyo Ressan Jiken (Incident of Demonstration by 88 Courtiers).</e>
<cmt>「正四位下」の訳出を用語統一リストに従って修正しました。「廷臣八十八卿列参事件」のローマ字表記の語句の切れ目が不自然です。また英語での説明にincidentを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1855, he became Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and in 1858, he participated in the Teishin 88-kyo Ressan Jiken (Incident of Demonstration by 88 Courtiers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年12月1日に行われた江戸幕府14代征夷大将軍徳川家茂の就任式に際して侍従高倉永祐とともに勅使として江戸城に派遣されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the inauguration ceremony of the 14th generation conquest barbarian general Iemochi TOKUGAWA of the Edo Shogunate held on December 1 of the same year, he was sent to the Edo-jo Castle as envoys with his attendant Nagasachi TAKAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the inauguration ceremony of the 14th seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Edo Shogunate Iemochi TOKUGAWA held on December 1 of the same year, he was sent to the Edo-jo Castle as an envoy with his attendant Nagasachi TAKAKURA.</e>
<cmt>「江戸幕府14代征夷大将軍」の訳出が不自然です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the inauguration ceremony of the 14th seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Edo Shogunate Iemochi TOKUGAWA held on December 1 of the same year, he was sent to the Edo-jo Castle as an envoy with his attendant Nagasachi TAKAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌年には民部卿に転じて、元治元年（1864年）には従三位となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to Minbukyo (Civic Ministry) the next year, and in 1864, he became Junior Third Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs) the next year, and in 1864, he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>「民部卿」の訳出が不自然です。「従三位」の訳出を用語統一リストに従って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs) the next year, and in 1864, he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>明治元年（1868年）民部卿を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868, he was resigned from Minbukyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1868, he resigned from Minbukyo.</e>
<cmt>「を辞任する」はresign from。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1868, he resigned from Minbukyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>明治維新によって江戸幕府が崩壊すると、新政府に働きかけて旧幕府の天文方を廃止に追い込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Edo Shogunate was collapsed by Meiji Restoration, he appealed to the new government to urge the abolition of the astronomical officials of the old shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Edo Shogunate was collapsed by Meiji Restoration, he appealed to the new government to urge the abolition of the astronomical officials of the old shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Edo Shogunate was collapsed by Meiji Restoration, he appealed to the new government to urge the abolition of the astronomical officials of the old shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>編暦・頒暦といった暦の権限のみならず、測量・天文などの管轄権を陰陽寮が掌握する事に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only did he succeed in grasping the authority in making and announcing the calendar, he also succeeded in making Onmyo Ryo seize the jurisdiction such as measurements and observations of heavenly phenomena.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only did he succeed in grasping the authority in making and announcing the calendar, he also succeeded in making Onmyoryo (a government office that had jurisdiction over calendar preparation, astronomy, divination, etc.) seize the jurisdiction over measurements and astronomy.</e>
<cmt>「陰陽寮」の訳出は用語集を参照しました。「などの管轄権」の「などの」を直訳しても意味をなさないので言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only did he succeed in grasping the authority in making and announcing the calendar, he also succeeded in making Onmyoryo (a government office that had jurisdiction over calendar preparation, astronomy, divination, etc.) seize the jurisdiction over measurements and astronomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>当時の新政府の中においては、富国強兵や殖産興業に直接つながらない天文学や暦法に関する関心が極端に低かったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the new government at that time, the concern about astronomy or the calender, which was not related directly to &apos;wealthy nation and strong army&apos; and &apos;encouragement of new industries&apos;, was extremely low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the new government at that time, the concern about astronomy or calendars, which was not related directly to &apos;wealthy nation and strong army&apos; and &apos;encouragement of new industries&apos;, was extremely low.</e>
<cmt>calendarのスペリングミス。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the new government at that time, the concern about astronomy or calendars, which was not related directly to &apos;wealthy nation and strong army&apos; and &apos;encouragement of new industries&apos;, was extremely low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>更に洋学者の間で高まりつつあった太陽暦導入に反対して、天保暦を改暦して太陰太陽暦の継続を図るように提案した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, as opposite to the introduction of solar calendar by the western scholars, he proposed to attempt the continuance of the calendar amendment; namely changing Tempo calendar to lunisolar calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, objecting the introduction of the solar calendar by the western scholars, he proposed to continue the use of the lumar-solar calendar by revising Tenpo reki (Tenpo calendar).</e>
<cmt>as opposed toは「～に対して」であり、ここで言う「反対する」とは異なります。また「天保暦を改暦して太陰太陽暦を継続する」の訳出がうまくできていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, objecting the introduction of the solar calendar by the western scholars, he proposed to continue the use of the lumar-solar calendar by revising Tenpo reki (Tenpo calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、今度は逆に新政府の関心の低さが災いして、改暦は見送られる事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However on the contrary, the low degree of the concern of the new government did harm this time, and the calendar amendment was not passed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on the contrary, the low degree of the concern of the new government did harm this time, and the revision of the calendar was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>passedでは意味が不明確です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on the contrary, the low degree of the concern of the new government did harm this time, and the revision of the calendar was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>晴雄はなおも改暦を要求したが、病に倒れ43歳の若さで病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Haruo still demanded the calendar amendment, he collapsed and died of sickness at a young age of 43.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Haruo still demanded the revision of the calendar, he was taken with illness and died young at an age of 43.</e>
<cmt>collapse of sicknessでは意味をなしません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Haruo still demanded the revision of the calendar, he was taken with illness and died young at an age of 43.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>後を継いだ嫡男・和丸（後の晴栄）はまだ幼かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His heiress son Kazumaru (the later Haruei) who succeeded after him were still young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His heiress son Kazumaru (the later Haruei), who succeeded him, was still young.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文例外対処」のコメントが漏れています。「後を継ぐ」の意のsucceedは他動詞なので前置詞は不要です。主語は単数なので動詞はwas。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His heiress son Kazumaru (the later Haruei), who succeeded him, was still young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>更に新政府内部でも陸海軍の円滑な運営に欠かせない天文や測量が古い陰陽寮に縛られる事への危惧や、非科学的な陰陽道が日本の近代科学導入の障害になる事が指摘されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, even within the new government, it became that people started pointing out the risk that the army and navy, whose smooth operations for which heavenly phenomena and measurement were indispensable, might be bounded by the old Onmyo Ryo, and unscientific Onmyo method became an obstacle against the introduction of modern science to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, even within the new government, some people started to point out the risk associated with the fact that astronomy and measurements, which were indispensable to smooth operations of the army and the navy, were controlled by the old Onmyoryo, and others pointed out that unscientific Onmyodo might become an obstacle to the introduction of modern science into Japan.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文例外対処」のコメントが漏れています。また、文構造が不自然です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, even within the new government, some people started to point out the risk associated with the fact that astronomy and measurements, which were indispensable to smooth operations of the army and the navy, were controlled by the old Onmyoryo, and others pointed out that unscientific Onmyodo might become an obstacle to the introduction of modern science into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>新政府は晴雄の死の翌年の明治3年（1870年）、陰陽寮の解体を断行するのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1870, the next year of Haruo&apos;s death, the new government carried out resolutely the dismantlement of Onmyo Ryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870, the next year of Haruo&apos;s death, the new government resolutely carried out the dismantlement of Onmyoryo.</e>
<cmt>副詞resolutelyを動詞と目的語の間に入れるのは不可。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1870, the next year of Haruo&apos;s death, the new government resolutely carried out the dismantlement of Onmyoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), ととりん(id:31982), 下総大納言(id:43461), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>