<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐伯葛城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki no Kazuragi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAEKI no Kazuragi</e>
<cmt>・「佐伯」を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAEKI no Kazuragi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐伯 葛城（さえき の かずらぎ）は、奈良時代の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki no Kazuragi is a court noble in the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAEKI no Kazuragi is a court noble in the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>・「佐伯」を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAEKI no Kazuragi is a court noble in the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は佐伯宿祢。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His main name is Saeki no Sukune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His main name is SAEKI no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>・「佐伯」を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His main name is SAEKI no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>在京官人時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The phase of government official in Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phase of government official in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phase of government official in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>延暦3年（784年）11月11日 (旧暦)、時の天皇桓武天皇は従前の平城京から長岡京に遷都された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 31, December, 784, Emperor Kanmu at that time transferred the capital from Heijyo-kyo, which was the prior and existing capital, to Nagaoka-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 11, 784 on the old calendar, Emperor Kanmu at that time transferred the capital from Heijyo-kyo to Nagaoka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>・原文と日付が異なっていたので削除し、旧暦を追加しました。・which was the prior and existing capital,の部分は冗長になるので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 11, 784 on the old calendar, Emperor Kanmu at that time transferred the capital from Heijyo-kyo to Nagaoka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>葛城は新都・長岡宮造営の功労が認められ、同年12月2日 (旧暦)、正六位上から従五位下に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 21, 785, Katsuragi was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as his achievement in establishing and operating Nagaoka palace in the new capital was recognized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21, 785 or December 2, 784 on the old calendar, Kazuragi was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as his achievement in establishing and operating Nagaoka palace in the new capital was recognized.</e>
<cmt>・原文が旧暦表記なので訳文にも念のため旧暦を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 21, 785 or December 2, 784 on the old calendar, Kazuragi was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as his achievement in establishing and operating Nagaoka palace in the new capital was recognized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この時一族の佐伯今毛人は参議になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAEKI no Imaemishi, a member of this family became Sangi (councilor) at this ime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAEKI no Imaemishi, a member of this family became Sangi (councilor) at that time.</e>
<cmt>・スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAEKI no Imaemishi, a member of this family became Sangi (councilor) at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>葛城は翌年3月11日 (旧暦)に近衛兵令外官に、また同年9月29日 (旧暦)には左少弁を命じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 28, 785, Katsuragi was assigned to Konoehei Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts), and on November 9, 785, he was assigned to Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 28, 785 or March 11 on the old calendar, Kazuragi was assigned to Konoehei Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts), and on November 9, 785 or September 29 on the old calendar, he was assigned to Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left).</e>
<cmt>・原文が旧暦表記なので訳文にも念のため旧暦を追加しました。・「葛城」がKatsuragiになっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 28, 785 or March 11 on the old calendar, Kazuragi was assigned to Konoehei Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts), and on November 9, 785 or September 29 on the old calendar, he was assigned to Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>征東副将軍時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Phase of seito vice-shogun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Phase of seito vice-shogun</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Phase of seito vice-shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>延暦5年（786年）8月8日 (旧暦)、葛城は蝦夷征伐の準備の閲兵と武具点検ため、判官1名、主典1名とともに東海道に遣わされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 8, 786, Katsuragi, together with a member of hangan (judge, magistrate), a member of sakan, were dispatched to Tokaido region to review the prepared army and to check arms for conquest of ezo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 8, 786 or August 8 on the old calendar, Kazuragi, together with a member of hangan (judge, magistrate), a member of sakan, was dispatched to Tokaido region to review the prepared army and to check arms for conquest of ezo.</e>
<cmt>・原文が旧暦表記なので訳文にも念のため旧暦を追加しました。・「葛城」がKatsuragiになっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 8, 786 or August 8 on the old calendar, Kazuragi, together with a member of hangan (judge, magistrate), a member of sakan, was dispatched to Tokaido region to review the prepared army and to check arms for conquest of ezo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この時東山道には紀楫長が遣わされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">紀楫長 was dispatched to Tosan-do Road at this time.</e>
<cmt>紀楫長→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">紀楫長 was dispatched to Tosan-do Road at this time.</e>
<cmt>・「紀楫長」が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">紀楫長 was dispatched to Tosan-do Road at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>その翌年2月5日 (旧暦)、葛城は陸奥国介と鎮守府将軍の兼任を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 3, 787, Katsuraki was assigned to Mutsu no suke (assistant governor of Mutsu Province) and to Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 3, 787 or February 5 on the old calendar, Kazuragi was assigned to Mutsu no kuni no suke (assistant governor of Mutsu Province) and to Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North).</e>
<cmt>・原文が旧暦表記なので訳文にも念のため旧暦を追加しました。・「陸奥国介」の読み方を修正しました。・「葛城」がKatsuragiになっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 3, 787 or February 5 on the old calendar, Kazuragi was assigned to Mutsu no kuni no suke (assistant governor of Mutsu Province) and to Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>すぐ後の2月25日 (旧暦)、陸奥介は藤原葛野麻呂に、また鎮守副将軍は池田眞枚に交代して葛城は下野守となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 23, just after that, Katsuragi became Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province) while Mutsu no suke was replaced by FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro, and Chinju-fu shogun was replaced by 池田眞枚.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処池田眞枚→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 23 or February 25 on the old calendar, Kazuragi became Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province) while Mutsu no suke was replaced by FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro, and Chinju-fu shogun was replaced by IKEDA no Mahira.</e>
<cmt>・「池田眞枚」は下記サイトより。http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%B1%A0%E7%94%B0%E7%9C%9F%E6%9E%9A・「葛城」がKatsuragiになっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 23 or February 25 on the old calendar, Kazuragi became Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province) while Mutsu no suke was replaced by FUJIWARA no Kadonomaro, and Chinju-fu shogun was replaced by IKEDA no Mahira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その10月24日 (旧暦)には民部少輔を命ぜられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 11, he was assigned to Minbu shoyu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 11 or October 24 on the old calendar, he was assigned to Minbu shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>・原文が旧暦表記なので訳文にも念のため旧暦を追加しました。・「民部少輔」がこのファイルでは初出なので、用語集に合わせて英訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 11 or October 24 on the old calendar, he was assigned to Minbu shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この時点では在京であったと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that he was in Kyoto at this time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that he was in Kyoto at this time.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that he was in Kyoto at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし翌年の延暦7年（788年）3月21日 (旧暦)、葛城は入間廣成および紀真人とともに征夷大将軍奈良・平安時代に任ぜられ、軍を率いて入征する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 5, 788, in the following year, Katsuragi, together with 入間廣成 and KI no Mahito, were ordered by seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Nara and Heian Period to go on a conquest leading the army.</e>
<cmt>入間廣成→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 5, 788 or March 21 on the old calendar, in the following year, Kazuragi, together with 入間廣成 and KI no Mahito, were ordered by seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Nara and Heian Period to go on a conquest leading the army.</e>
<cmt>・「入間廣成」が確認できませんでした。・原文が旧暦表記なので訳文にも念のため旧暦を追加しました。・「葛城」がKatsuragiになっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 5, 788 or March 21 on the old calendar, in the following year, Kazuragi, together with 入間廣成 and KI no Mahito, were ordered by seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Nara and Heian Period to go on a conquest leading the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この時の征夷大将軍奈良・平安時代は正四位下紀古佐美、征東副将軍は葛城と入間廣成および紀真人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Nara and Heian Period was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), KI no Kosami, and the seito vice-shogun were Katsuragi, 入間廣成, and KI no Mahito.</e>
<cmt>入間廣成→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Nara and Heian Period was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), KI no Kosami, and the seito vice-shogun were Katsuragi, 入間廣成, and KI no Mahito.</e>
<cmt>・「入間廣成」が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Nara and Heian Period was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), KI no Kosami, and the seito vice-shogun were Katsuragi, 入間廣成, and KI no Mahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>前軍別将は安倍媛嶋墨縄、左中軍別将は池田眞枚、後軍別将は丈部善理で、その兵数は27,470人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">別将 of the front guard was 安倍媛嶋墨縄, 別将 of the left-middle guard was 池田眞枚, and 別将 of the rear guard was 丈部善理, and the number of solders was 27,470.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処別将, 安倍媛嶋墨縄, 池田眞枚, 丈部善理,</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An impromptu officer of the front guard was ABE no Sashima no Suminawa, an impromptu officer of the left-middle guard was IKEDA no Mahira, and an impromptu officer of the rear guard was HASETSUKABE no Yoshimaro, and the number of solders was 27,470.</e>
<cmt>・「安倍媛嶋墨縄」は「あべのさしまのすみなわ」と読むようです。http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%AE%89%E5%80%8D%E7%8C%A8%E5%B6%8B%E5%A2%A8%E7%B8%84・「池田眞枚」は下記サイトより。http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%B1%A0%E7%94%B0%E7%9C%9F%E6%9E%9A・「丈部善理」は「はせつかべのよしまろ」と読むようです。http://www5d.biglobe.ne.jp/~hisaya/kodai.htm・「別将」とは、あるサイトによると、「正規軍とは別の目的で編制された軍隊を率いる将校」のことをいうそうです。impromptu officerとしました。http://blog.canpan.info/kohm-blog/archive/29</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officers of the irregular forces were as follows: that of the front guard was ABE no Sashima no Suminawa, that of the left-middle guard was IKEDA no Mahira, and that of the rear guard was HASETSUKABE no Yoshimaro, while the total number of solders was 27,470.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし征討軍は胆沢城のアテルイほか紫波郡、和賀郡の蝦夷勢に対し攻めあぐねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the seitogun (expeditionary force) struggled to find an efficient attack against Aterui in Isawa-jo Castle,the force of Ezo (the Early Modern Japanese to describe the island of Hokkaido and the people who lived there) of Shiwa Country and Waga Country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the seitogun (expeditionary force) struggled to find an efficient attack against Aterui in Isawa-jo Castle, the force of Ezo (the Early Modern Japanese to describe the island of Hokkaido and the people who lived there) of Shiwa County and Waga County.</e>
<cmt>・「郡」はcountyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the seitogun (expeditionary force) struggled to find an efficient attack against Aterui in Isawa-jo Castle, the force of Ezo (the Early Modern Japanese to describe the island of Hokkaido and the people who lived there) of Shiwa County and Waga County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その衣川の陣営で葛城は没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">katsuragi passed away at the camps of Koromogawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuragi passed away at the camps of Koromogawa.</e>
<cmt>・文頭は大文字としました。・「葛城」がKatsuragiになっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuragi passed away at the camps of Koromogawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>延暦8年（789年）5月26日 (旧暦)、陣没した征東副将軍民部少輔兼下野守勲八等の葛城に 正五位下が贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 27, 689, Katsuragi, who passed away in the positions of seito vice-shogun, Minbu shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs), Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province), Kun hachito, was granted Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 27, 789 or May 26 on the old calendar, Katsuragi, who passed away in the positions of seito vice-shogun, Minbu shoyu, Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province), Kun hachito, was granted Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>・原文が旧暦表記なので訳文にも念のため旧暦を追加しました。・年号が原文と異なったので修正しました。・民部少輔は既出なので（）内の説明は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 27, 789 or May 26 on the old calendar, Katsuragi, who passed away in the positions of seito vice-shogun, Minbu shoyu, Shimotsuke no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province), Kun hachito, was granted Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 FCTR2(id:213046), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>