<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>永谷宗円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen NAGATANI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen NAGATANI</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen NAGATANI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>永谷 宗円（ながたに そうえん、天和 (日本)元年（1681年） - 安永7年（1778年））は山城国宇治田原郷湯屋谷村（現京都府綴喜郡宇治田原町湯屋谷）の農家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen NAGATANI (1681 -1778) was a farmer who lived in Yuyatani Village in Ujitawarago (present Yuyatani, Ujitawara Town, Tsuzuki District, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen NAGATANI (1681 -1778) was a farmer who lived in Yuyatani Village in Ujitawarago (present Yuyatani, Ujitawara Town, Tsuzuki District, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen NAGATANI (1681 -1778) was a farmer who lived in Yuyatani Village, Ujitawarago, Yamashiro Province (present Yuyatani, Ujitawara-cho, Tsuzuki-gun, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「山城国」を訳出、住所表記を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>永谷家の先祖は同じ宇治田原の糠塚村の土豪で、文禄元年（1592年）に湯屋谷に移り住んで農業に携わる一方、湯山社を祀っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancestor of the Nagatani family was a local clan in Nukazuka Village in Ujitawara and moved to Yuyatani in 1592 and while engaged in faming, worshipped the Yuyama-sha Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancestor of the Nagatani family was a local clan in Nukazuka Village in Ujitawara and moved to Yuyatani in 1592 and while he was engaged in farming, worshipped the Yuyama-sha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancestor of the Nagatani family was a local clan in Nukazuka Village in Ujitawara and moved to Yuyatani in 1592 and while he was engaged in farming, worshipped the Yuyama-sha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>もともと名は宗七郎義弘といい、入道して宗円と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Soshichiro Yoshihiro and, when he entered the priesthood, named himself Soen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Soshichiro Yoshihiro and, when he entered the priesthood, named himself Soen.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Soshichiro Yoshihiro and, when he entered the priesthood, named himself Soen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三之丞ともいい、直系の子孫は代々「三之丞」を襲名していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Sannojo and his direct descendants succeeded the name &quot;Sannojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Sannojo and his direct descendants also inherited the name &quot;Sannojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Sannojo and his direct descendants also inherited the name &apos;Sannojo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>湯屋谷では茶業のみならず、湿田改良などの事業を行い、村人を指導する立場であったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yuyatani, he not only produced tea but also carried out improvement of wet fields and other operations and he was in a position to guide village people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yuyatani, he not only produced tea but also carried out improvements of wet fields and other operations and he was in a position to guide village people.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yuyatani, he not only produced tea but also carried out improvements of wet fields and other operations and he was in a position to guide village people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>宗円の功績にまつわる伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditions Concerning Soen&apos;s Achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditions Concerning Soen&apos;s Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditions Concerning Soen&apos;s Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中国から日本にもたらされた茶は、南宋に渡った栄西が「喫茶養生記」で茶の効能を説いたように、当初は寺院での修行や薬用として飲用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tea brought from China to Japan was drunk for medical purpose as Eisai, who had been to Southern Song (dynasty of China) explained effects of tea in his &quot;Kissa Yojoki&quot;(Drink Tea and Prolong Life, a Note on Drinking Green Tea for Good Health).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tea brought from China to Japan was drunk for medical purpose as Eisai, who had been to Southern Song (dynasty of China) and explained the effects of tea in his &quot;Kissa Yojoki&quot;(Drink Tea and Prolong Life, a Note on Drinking Green Tea for Good Health).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tea brought from China to Japan was drunk for medical purpose as Eisai, who had been to Southern Song (dynasty of China) and explained the effects of tea in his &apos;Kissa Yojoki&apos; (Drink Tea and Prolong Life, a Note on Drinking Green Tea for Good Health).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>やがて各地で栽培が広がるが、宇治の特定の茶師は、幕府の許可を得て高品質の碾茶の製造を独占していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, tea cultivation spread to various place, but certain chashi (tea grower) obtained a permission from bakufu and monopolized production of high-quality powdered green tea (steamed and dried before being stone-ground).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, tea cultivation spread to various places, but certain chashi (tea growers) obtained permission from the bakufu and monopolized the production of high-quality powdered green tea (steamed and dried before being stone-ground).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, tea cultivation spread to various places, but certain chashi (tea growers) obtained permission from the bakufu and monopolized the production of high-quality powdered green tea (steamed and dried before being stone-ground).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>富裕層が好んだ抹茶とはちがい、庶民は色が赤黒く味も粗末な「煎じ茶」を飲んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different from powdered tea which had been loved by rich people, ordinary people used senjicha (decoction of tea) which was red in color and tasted poor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ordinary people used senjicha (decoction of tea) which was red in color and tasted poor, which differed from powdered tea which had been loved by rich people,</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ordinary people used &apos;senjicha&apos; (decoction of tea) which was red in color and tasted poor, which differed from powdered tea which had been loved by rich people.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加、カンマ→ピリオドに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そんな中、宗円は15年の歳月をかけて製茶法を研究し、味もすぐれた緑の新しい煎茶（正確には「だし茶」である）を作り上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the circumstances, Soen studied the method of producing tea for fifteen years and succeeded to make new sencha that is rich in taste and green in color (to be correct, it was dashicha (a type of tea used by making infusion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the circumstances, Soen studied the method of producing tea for fifteen years and succeeded in making a new type of sencha which was rich in taste and green in color (to be correct, it was dashicha (a type of tea used by making an infusion).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the circumstances, Soen studied the method of producing tea for fifteen years and succeeded in making a new type of sencha which was rich in taste and green in color (to be correct, it was &apos;dashicha,&apos; a type of tea used by making an infusion).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加、カッコ内を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この宗円が発明した「青製煎茶製法」はその後の日本緑茶の主流となる製法となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;aoseisencha seiho&quot; invented by Soen became the mainstream of Japanese green tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;aoseisencha seiho&quot; invented by Soen became the mainstream Japanese green tea.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;aoseisencha seiho&apos; invented by Soen became the mainstream Japanese green tea.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>宗円は完成した茶を携えて江戸に赴き、茶商の山本嘉兵衛に販売を託したところ、たちまち評判となり、以後「宇治の煎茶」は日本を代表する茶となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen visited Edo with completed tea and consigned the sale of the tea to a tea dealer, Kahei YAMAMOTO and the tea immediately became popular and, since then, &quot;Uji no sencha&quot; (green tea from Uji) became to represent Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen visited Edo with the completed tea and consigned the sale of the tea to a tea dealer, Kahei YAMAMOTO and the tea immediately became popular and, since then, &quot;Uji no sencha&quot; (green tea from Uji) came to represent Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen visited Edo with the completed tea and consigned the sale of the tea to a tea dealer, Kahei YAMAMOTO and the tea immediately became popular and, since then, &apos;Uji no sencha&apos; (green tea from Uji) came to represent Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>宗円の煎茶を販売し大きく利益をた「山本山」では、明治8年（1875年）まで永谷家に毎年小判二十五両を贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yamamotoyama&quot; that sold Soen&apos;s green tea and earned a lot donated koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) for twenty-five ryo every year until 1875.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yamamotoyama&quot; that sold Soen&apos;s green tea earned a lot of donated koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) for twenty-five ryo every year until 1875.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamamotoyama,&apos; that sold Soen&apos;s green tea and earned a lot, donated koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) for twenty-five ryo to the Nagatani family every year until 1875.</e>
<cmt>「永谷家に」を訳出、シングルクォーテーションに変更、原文の内容に沿うよう訳文を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宗円は自身が発明した製茶法を近隣にも惜しみなく伝えたため、「永谷式煎茶」「宇治製煎茶」は全国に広がることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Soen did not hesitate to teach the method of producing tea that he invented to neighbors, &quot;Nagatanishiki sencha (sencha by Nagatani method)&quot; and &quot;Ujisei sencha (sencha made in Uji)&quot; spread over nationwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Soen did not hesitate to teach the method for producing tea that he invented to neighbors, &quot;Nagatanishiki sencha (sencha by Nagatani method)&quot; and &quot;Ujisei sencha (sencha made in Uji)&quot; spread nationwide.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Soen did not hesitate to teach the method for producing tea that he invented to neighbors, &apos;Nagatanishiki sencha&apos; (sencha by Nagatani method) and &apos;Ujisei sencha&apos; (sencha made in Uji) spread nationwide.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテションに変更、位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>実際の姿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">True Situations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">True Situations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">True Situations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>上記の宗円の事跡は地元や茶業者を中心に根強く信じられているが、近年の研究では、それは伝承の域を出ないことが明らかになってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Above-explained achievements by Soen have been deeply believed in the region and people involved in tea business, but thanks to studies in recent years, it became clear that such stories do no pass the bound of traditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above-explained achievements by Soen were deeply believed in the region and people involved in the tea business, but thanks to studies in recent years, it became clear that such stories do no pass the bounds of tradition.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above-explained achievements by Soen were deeply believed in the region and people involved in the tea business, but thanks to studies in recent years, it became clear that such stories do no pass the bounds of tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>まず、中国から当初もたらされた茶は「抹茶」ではなく、「煎じ茶」と「挽き茶」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, the tea brought from China at the beginning was not &quot;maccha&quot; but &quot;senjicha&quot; and &quot;hikicha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「抹茶」、「煎じ茶」、「挽き茶」の違いについては以下に詳細な説明があるため、この文でそれぞれの後ろにカッコ書きすることは省きました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, the tea brought from China at the beginning was not &quot;maccha&quot; but &quot;senjicha&quot; and &quot;hikicha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, the tea brought from China at the beginning was not &apos;matcha&apos; but &apos;senjicha&apos; and &apos;hikicha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>maccha→matchaに修正、シングルクォーテションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「煎じ茶」は乾燥させた茶葉を煮出したもので、「煎茶」とはもともとこれを意味していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Senjicha&quot; means tea obtained by decocting tried tea leave and &quot;sencha&quot; originally meant this type of tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Senjicha&quot; means tea obtained by decocting tried tea leave and &quot;sencha&quot; originally meant this type of tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senjicha&apos; means tea obtained by decocting tried tea leave and &apos;sencha&apos; originally meant this type of tea.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「水色（すいしょく）」は黄色系で、保存状態が悪いと赤黒くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The color of water is yellowish and, if poorly preserved, reddish black.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color of water is yellowish and, if poorly preserved, reddish black.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color of water is yellowish and, if poorly preserved, reddish black.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一方の「挽き茶」は乾燥させた茶葉を臼や薬研ですりつぶしたものを湯で溶いたもので、「抹茶」の原型といえるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;hikicha&quot; is prepared by dissolving tea powder, which is produced by grinding dried tea leaves with a mill-stone or a druggist&apos;s mortar and we can call it the prototypical form of &quot;maccha.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, &quot;hikicha&quot; is prepared by dissolving tea powder, which is produced by grinding dried tea leaves with a mill-stone or a druggist&apos;s mortar and we can call it the prototypical form of &quot;maccha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, &apos;hikicha&apos; is prepared by dissolving tea powder, which is produced by grinding dried tea leaves with a mill-stone or a druggist&apos;s mortar and we can call it the prototypical form of &apos;matcha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>maccha→matchaに修正、シングルクォーテションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>水色は緑系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The color of water is greenish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color of water is greenish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color of water is greenish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後の抹茶との違いは煎茶と同じく露天の茶園で栽培されたことで、戦国時代 (日本)になってから宇治で「覆下茶園」が発明され、茶臼の改良などにより現在の抹茶となっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The difference to the later maccha is that tea leaves for hikicha were grown in open-air tea plantation, and, in the Warring States Period in Japan, &quot;oishita chaen (tea field covered wit shade to harvest good leaves) was invented and through improvement of mill-stone, etc. it was developed to the present maccha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The difference between this tea and the later maccha is that the tea leaves for hikicha were grown in open-air tea plantations, and, in the Warring States Period in Japan, &quot;oishita chaen (tea field covered wit shade to harvest good leaves) was invented and through improvement in mill-stone, etc. it was developed to the present maccha.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The difference between this tea and the later maccha is that the tea leaves for hikicha were grown in open-air tea plantations, and, in the Warring States Period in Japan, &apos;oishita chaen&apos; (tea field covered wit shade to harvest good leaves) was invented and through improvement in mill-stone, etc. it was developed to the present maccha.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテションに変更、クォーテーションの片方を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、従来は庶民は煎じ茶、富裕層は抹茶を飲んでいたとされていたが、中世では庶民層も挽き茶を飲んでいたことが明らかになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, it was told that ordinary people used senjicha and rich people maccha, but it revealed that ordinary people also used hikicha in the middle ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, it was said that ordinary people used senjicha and rich people maccha, but it became clear that ordinary people also used hikicha in the middle ages.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, it was said that ordinary people used senjicha and rich people maccha, but it became clear that ordinary people also used hikicha in the middle ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>「宗円が発明した技法の特徴」は「それまで中国のような釜炒り茶が主流な中、良質な茶葉を蒸して、「ほいろ」で揉み上げて乾燥せた」こととされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was told that &quot;features of the technique invented by Soen&quot; was &quot;while kamairicha (green tea processed by parching in a caldron) same as in Chine was the mainstream, steaming high quality tea leaves and drying them by crumpling them in &apos;hoiro (a tool used for producing tea, etc.).&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文を二つに分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that &quot;features of the technique invented by Soen&quot; was &quot;while kamairicha (green tea processed by parching in a caldron) same as in Chine was the mainstream, steaming high quality tea leaves and drying them by crumpling them in &apos;hoiro (a tool used for producing tea, etc.).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that &apos;features of the technique invented by Soen&apos; was &apos;while kamairicha (green tea processed by parching in a caldron) same as in Chine was the mainstream, steaming high quality tea leaves and drying them by crumpling them in &apos;hoiro&apos; (a tool used for producing tea, etc.).&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテションに変更、クォーテーションの片方を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、世以降、全国各地では多様な製法による茶が生産されており、茶葉を蒸したり、湯がいたものを、日光や「ほいろ」で乾燥させ、近世には「揉む」工程が加わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the middle ages, however, teas were produced with various methods in various place in Japan including the method to steam or boil tea leaves, and dry them by sunlight or using &quot;hoiro&quot; and in the early-modern times, crumpling process was added.</e>
<cmt>原文を二つに分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the middle ages, however, teas were produced with various methods in various places in Japan including the method in which the leaves were steamed or boiled, then dried with sunlight, or using &quot;hoiro,&quot; while in the early-modern times, the crumpling process was added.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the middle ages, however, teas were produced with various methods in various places in Japan including the method in which the leaves were steamed or boiled, then dried with sunlight, or using &apos;hoiro,&apos; while in the early-modern times, the crumpling process was added.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>こうした製茶法の変化については中世〜近世の当時の文献資料などから明らかになってきたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such changes in the method of producing teas have been made clear with literatures and materials of the middle ages and early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such changes in the tea production methods were made clear through literature and material from the middle ages and early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such changes in the tea production methods were made clear through literature and material from the middle ages and early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>宗円の功績の伝承で語られる「釜炒りから蒸し製へ」「茶葉を揉み乾かす工程」を宗円がはじめて導入したわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen was not the first introducer of the change &quot;from kamairicha to steaming method &quot; and &quot;method to dry tea leaves by crumpling&quot; as told in traditions on Soen&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen was not the first person to introduce a change &quot;from kamairicha to steaming method &quot; and &quot;method to dry tea leaves by crumpling&quot; as is said according to the lore on Soen&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen was not the first person to introduce a change &apos;from kamairicha to steaming method&apos; and &apos;method to dry tea leaves by crumpling&apos; as is said according to the lore on Soen&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、資料から伺える「ほいろ」の構造からは、明治までは現在のようにほいろの上で茶葉を終始一貫して揉みながら乾かすという作業を行うことができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the structure of &quot;hoiro&quot; which we can imagine from materials, up until Meiji Period, it was impossible to carry out the present method in which tea leaves are dried while continuously kneaded on a hoiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from the structure of &quot;hoiro&quot; which we can imagine from materials, up until the Meiji Period, it was impossible to carry out the present method in which tea leaves are dried while continuously kneaded on a hoiro.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from the structure of &apos;hoiro&apos; which we can imagine from materials, up until the Meiji period, it was impossible to carry out the present method in which tea leaves are dried while continuously kneaded on a hoiro.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、Periodの頭文字を小文字に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>江戸時代までのほいろは、竹の骨組みに和紙を貼り付けたもので、耐久力の面から、その上で強い力をもって揉み通すということが不可能であったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up until Edo Period, hoiro was produced by sticking Japanese paper to a frame made with bamboo, and, therefore, it is said that it was impossible to continue to knead with strong force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up until the Edo Period, hoiro was produced by sticking Japanese paper to a frame made with bamboo, and, therefore, it is said that it was impossible to be continuously knead through the use of strong pressure.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up until the Edo period, hoiro was produced by sticking Japanese paper to a frame made with bamboo, and, therefore, it is said that it was impossible to be continuously knead through the use of strong pressure.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>明治になり、鉄の骨組みを持つほいろが登場し、ほいろの上で揉み乾かす手揉みの技法が発達して、様々な流派が生まれていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji Period, hoiro with iron framework appeared and technique to dry on hoiro by kneading was advanced and various schools were generated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Period, hoiro with iron framework appeared and a technique to dry the leaves on hoiro by kneading them was advanced and various schools were generated.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, hoiro with iron framework appeared and a technique to dry the leaves on hoiro by kneading them was advanced and various schools were generated.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>このように、長い年月を経て製茶法は改良を重ねられたのであり、決して一人の人間によって発明されたものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As describe above, the method for producing tea has been continuously improved and it was not invented by a single person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As describe above, the method for producing tea has been continuously improved and it was not invented by a single person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As describe above, the method for producing tea has been continuously improved and it was not invented by a single person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>江戸時代には中国文化の影響を受けた文人趣味の中で煎茶をたしなむことが流行し、「青製煎茶製法」はそうした文化的・経済的需要の中で到達した日本茶の製法のひとつの頂点であるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo Period, it was widely liked to enjoy sencha in tastes of literary men influenced by Chinese culture and we can say that &quot;aoseisencha seiho&quot; in a peak of manufacturing method for Japanese tea reached in such cultural and economical demands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Edo Period, sencha was widely enjoyed by literary men influenced by Chinese culture and we can say that &quot;aoseisencha seiho&quot; in a peak of manufacturing method for Japanese tea reached in such cultural and economical demands.</e>
<cmt>Robert: This doesn&apos;t make much sense &quot;in a peak of manufacturing method for Japanese tea reached in such cultural and economical demands.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, sencha was widely enjoyed by literary men influenced by Chinese culture and we can say that &apos;aoseisencha seiho&apos; was a peak of manufacturing method for Japanese tea reached in such cultural and economical demands.</e>
<cmt>In Edo Period→In the Edo periodとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更、in a peak→was a peakとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>では実際の宗円の功績は何であるかというと、「宇治茶の産地」であった宇治田原の茶を、当時の大消費地であった江戸での直販ルートを開拓したことであり、それが現在の通信販売を中心とした全国展開される茶の販売網の礎を築くことになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen&apos;s actual achievement was the pioneering of direct sales route for tea of Ujitawara, which was a &quot;place of production of Uji tea&quot; to Edo, which was a great consumption place at that time and it led to establishment of the foundation of nationwide sales network for tea centering on mail order system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen&apos;s actual achievement was the pioneering of a direct sales route for tea of Ujitawara, which was a &quot;place of production of Uji tea&quot; to Edo, which was a great consumption place at that time and led to establishment of the foundation of nationwide sales network for tea centering upon a mail order system.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen&apos;s actual achievement was the pioneering of a direct sales route for tea of Ujitawara, which was a &apos;place of production of Uji tea&apos; to Edo, which was a great consumption place at that time and led to establishment of the foundation of nationwide sales network for tea centering upon a mail order system.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>ただ、宇治を中心とする茶業者や地元では宗円の功績を顕彰する気持ちが強いため、こうした研究成果を受け入れたがらない傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among people involved in tea business centering on Uji and people in the region, as they strongly wish to publicly honor Soen&apos;s achievement, they tend to refuse to accept such results of research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most people involved in the tea business in Uji, as well as people in the region tend to refuse to accept the results of such research, due to their strong wish to publicly honor Soen&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most people involved in the tea business in Uji, as well as people in the region tend to refuse to accept the results of such research, due to their strong wish to publicly honor Soen&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>「宗円の功績」について後年になって当事者である永谷家や山本家（山本山）の記した文献以外に、当時の客観的資料が見いだせない以上、業界の宣伝のためとはいえ、伝承を安易に史実としてしまうことはさけるべきであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As far as we cannot find any objective materials at that time on &quot;Soen&apos;s achievement&quot;other than recorded later by the Nagatani family or the Yamamoto family (Yamamotoyama), it should be avoided to make mere tradition as the historical fact even for propaganda for the industry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As far as we cannot find any objective materials at that time on &quot;Soen&apos;s achievement&quot;other than what was recorded later by the Nagatani family or the Yamamoto family (Yamamotoyama), taking mere lore as historical fact should be avoided, even to be used as propaganda for industrial purposes.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As far as we cannot find any objective materials at that time on &apos;Soen&apos;s achievement&apos; other than what was recorded later by the Nagatani family or the Yamamoto family (Yamamotoyama), taking mere lore as historical fact should be avoided, even to be used as propaganda for industrial purposes.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>宗円と永谷家のその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen and the Nagatani Family Thereafter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen and the Nagatani Family Thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen and the Nagatani Family Thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>宗円は安永7年（1778年）に98歳で天寿を全うした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1778, Soen lived out his natural life at the age of ninety-eight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1778, Soen lived out his natural life at the age of ninety-eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1778, Soen lived out his natural life at the age of ninety-eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="38">
<j>宗円の子孫のひとりは東京で「永谷園」を創業した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of Soen&apos;s descendant established &quot;Nagatanien&quot; in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of Soen&apos;s descendant established &quot;Nagatanien&quot; in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of Soen&apos;s descendant established &apos;Nagatanien&apos; in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="39">
<j>直系の子孫である三之丞家は明治に宇治市六地蔵に移転し、現在９代目が茶問屋「永谷宗園」を継いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sannojo family, which is the direct descendant, moved to Rokujizo, Uji City in Meiji era and, at present, the ninth family head inherited the tea wholesaler &quot;Nagatani Soen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sannojo family, which is a direct descendant, moved to Rokujizo, Uji City in Meiji era and, at present, the ninth family head inherited the tea wholesaler &quot;Nagatani Soen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sannojo family, which is a direct descendant, moved to Rokujizo, Uji City in the Meiji period and, at present, the ninth family head inherited the tea wholesaler &apos;Nagatani Soen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、in Meiji era→in the Meiji periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="40">
<j>宇治田原町湯屋谷の、永谷家のあった場所には製茶道具やほいろ跡を保存する施設「永谷宗円生家」が昭和35年に建てられ、それに隣接する大神宮神社には昭和29年、宗円が「茶宗明神」として祀られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the place where the Nagatani family existed in Yuyatani, Ujitawara Town, &quot;Nagatani Soen Seika (literally, the house where Soen Nagatani was born)&quot;, which tools for producing tea and the trace of hoiro, was built in 1960 and, in 1944, Soen was enshrined as &quot;Chasomyoujin (literally, god of tea)&quot; in neighboring Dai-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In place of where the Nagatani family existed in Yuyatani, Ujitawara Town, &quot;Nagatani Soen Seika (literally, the house where Soen Nagatani was born)&quot;, has tools for producing tea and has a trace of hoiro, which was built in 1960 and, in 1944, Soen was enshrined as &quot;Chasomyoujin (literally, god of tea)&quot; in the neighboring Dai-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In place of where the Nagatani family existed in Yuyatani, Ujitawara-cho, &apos;Nagatani Soen Seika&apos; (literally, the house where Soen Nagatani was born), has tools for producing tea and has a trace of hoiro, which was built in 1960 and, in 1944, Soen was enshrined as &apos;Chasomyoujin&apos; (literally, god of tea) in the neighboring Dai-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>現住所のため、Ujitawara Town→Ujitawara-choとし、シングルクォーテションに変更、位置を移動、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 細川右馬守(id:64654), TAMA(id:25299), 茶味(id:123295), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>