<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Sadamu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Sadamu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Sadamu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 定（みなもと の さだむ、弘仁5年（816年） - 貞観_(日本)5年1月3日 (旧暦)（863年1月25日））は平安時代前期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Sadamu (816 to January 25, 863) was a court noble in the early part of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Sadamu (816 to January 25, 863) was a court noble who lived in the early part of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>removed double-byte parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Sadamu (816 to January 25, 863) was a court noble who lived in the early part of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は嵯峨天皇、母は内侍司百済王慶命。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Saga, and his mother Kudara no Konikishi Kyomyo, a member of the Naishi-no-tsukasa (Handmaids&apos; Office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Saga, and his mother Kudara no Konikishi Kyomyo, a member of the Naishi-no-tsukasa (Handmaids&apos; Office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Emperor Saga, and his mother Kudara no Konikishi Kyomyo, a member of the Naishi no tsukasa (female palace attendants).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>淳和天皇の猶子になったが、父嵯峨天皇からも特に寵愛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was later adopted by Emperor Junna, he was still very much loved by his biological father Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was later adopted by Emperor Junna, he was still very much loved by his biological father Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was later adopted by Emperor Junna, he was still very much loved by his biological father Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>四条大納言または賀陽院大納言（陽院大納言とも）とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called as Shijo Dainagon or Kayoin Dainagon (or Yoin Dainagon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Shijo Dainagon or Kayoin Dainagon (also Yoin Dainagon).</e>
<cmt>removed “as”, or-&gt;also</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Shijo Dainagon or Kayoin Dainagon (also Yoin Dainagon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に源包・源宥・源至・源精・源唱らがいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children include MINAMOTO no Tsutsumi, MINAMOTO no Nadamu, MINAMOTO no Itaru, MINAMOTO no Kuwashi, and MINAMOTO no Tonau.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children include MINAMOTO no Tsutsumi, MINAMOTO no Nadamu, MINAMOTO no Itaru, MINAMOTO no Kuwashi, and MINAMOTO no Tonau.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children include MINAMOTO no Tsutsumi, MINAMOTO no Nadamu, MINAMOTO no Itaru, MINAMOTO no Kuwashi, and MINAMOTO no Tonau.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>天長5年（828年）、源朝臣の姓を賜った（嵯峨第六源氏と呼ばれた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 828, he was granted the asomi of Minamoto (and came to be called Sagadairoku-Genji, lit. Saga&apos;s sixth Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 828, he was granted the title of Asomi of the Minamoto (and came to be called Sagadairoku-Genji, meaning the sixth Minamoto clan of Saga).</e>
<cmt>added “title of”, edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 828, he was granted the title of Asomi of the Minamoto (and came to be called Sagadairoku-Genji, meaning the sixth Minamoto clan of Saga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、同9年（832年）には従三位に直叙されるという、特別な待遇がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 832, he was given special treatment by being promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 832, he was given special treatment by being promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 832, he was given special treatment by being promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌年の天長10年（833年）に参議になり、治部卿・中務卿を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 833, he became a sangi councillor and took office as Jibu Kyo (Chief Minister of Ceremonies) and Nakatsukasa Kyo (Chief Administrator of the Ministry of the Center).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 833, he became a sangi councilor and took office as Jibu Kyo (Chief Minister of Ceremonies) and Nakatsukasa Kyo (Chief Administrator of the Ministry of the Center).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 833, he became a Sangi (councilor) and took office as Jibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) and Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>承和 (日本)7年（840年）に淳和上皇の服喪のため、同9年（842年）に嵯峨上皇の服喪のため、それぞれ官を辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned as each of the position in mourning the death of the retired Emperor Junna in 840 and the retired Emperor Saga in 842.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned both positions in mourning for the deaths of the retired Emperor Junna in 840 and the retired Emperor Saga in 842.</e>
<cmt>each-&gt;both</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned both positions in mourning for the deaths of the retired Emperor Junna in 840 and the retired Emperor Saga in 842.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後復官して嘉祥2年（849年）中納言になり、貞観元年（859年）には大納言に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he was again reinstated and became Chunagon in 849 and Dainagon in 859.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he was reinstated and became Chunagon in 849 and Dainagon in 859.</e>
<cmt>deleted “again”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he was reinstated and became Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) in 849 and Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 859.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし「深宮の内に養長して未だ嘗て世俗の艱難を知らず」と評され、性格は温雅で音楽を愛好し、座右に鼓鐘を置いて、退庁の後は自ら弾じて楽しんだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was reputed to be mild-mannered, loved music, had a hand drum and a bell on his desk at office and played them himself after work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was reputed to be mild-mannered, loved music, had a hand drum and a bell on his desk at office and played them himself after work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people criticized him as a spoiled man who was ignorant of the real world hardships, however he was also reputed to be mild-mannered, loved music, had a hand drum and a bell on his desk at office and played them himself after work.</e>
<cmt>「甘やかされて世間の苦労を知らない人」としてみました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>貞観5年正月3日、正三位大納言兼右大将で薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the third of January (lunar calendar) in 861, he died holding a court rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and a title of Udaisho (Right Side General).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the third of January (lunar calendar) in 861, he died holding the court rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and the title of Udaisho (Right Side General).</e>
<cmt>a-&gt;the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the third of January (lunar calendar) in 861, he died holding the court rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and the title of Dainagon and Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>Dainagonを追加用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>没後従二位を追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was posthumously given Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously given Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously given Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>彼は彼の兄たち（源信 (公卿)、源弘、源常）同様嵯峨源氏と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Saga-Genji like his brothers (MINAMOTO no Makoto, MINAMOTO no Hiromu and MINAMOTO no Tokiwa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Saga-Genji like his brothers (MINAMOTO no Makoto, MINAMOTO no Hiromu and MINAMOTO no Tokiwa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Saga-Genji (Minamoto clan) like his brothers (MINAMOTO no Makoto, MINAMOTO no Hiromu and MINAMOTO no Tokiwa).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Andee(id:20421), Y.Sanada(id:36926), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>