<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鷹見泉石</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>鷹見 泉石（たかみ せんせき、天明5年6月29日 (旧暦)（1785年8月3日） - 安政5年7月16日 (旧暦)（1858年8月24日））は、江戸時代の蘭学者であり、下総国古河藩の家老。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senseki TAKAMI (August 3, 1785 to August 24,1858) was a Dutch scholar (a person who studied Western sciences by means of the Dutch language) in Edo period, and he was a principal retainer in the Koga clan of Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senseki TAKAMI (August 3, 1785 to August 24,1858) was a Dutch scholar (a person who studied Western sciences by means of the Dutch language) in the Edo period and principal retainer in the Koga clan of Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senseki TAKAMI (August 3, 1785 to August 24,1858) was a Dutch scholar (a person who studied Western sciences by means of the Dutch language) in the Edo period and principal retainer in the Koga clan of Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名を忠常、通称を又蔵、十郎左衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Tadatsune, but he was commonly called Matazo, Jurozaemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was Tadatsune, but he was commonly called Matazo, Jurozaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was Tadatsune, but he was commonly called Matazo, Jurozaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>字を伯直（はくちょく）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characters were Hakuchoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His azana (adult male&apos;s nickname) was Hakuchoku.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His azana (adult male&apos;s nickname) was Hakuchoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は泉石の他に、楓所（ふうしょ）、泰西堂（たいせいどう）、可琴軒（かきんけん）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Senseki, his titles were Husho, Taiseido, and Kakinken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (pen name) was Senseki, Fusho, Taiseido, Kakinken.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Senseki, Fusho, Taiseido, Kakinken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、ヤン・ヘンドリック・ダップル（Jan Hendrik Daper）という蘭名も署名に用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also used the Dutch name Jan Hendrik Daper in signature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also used the Dutch name Jan Hendrik Daper as his signature.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also used the Dutch name Jan Hendrik Daper as his signature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>1785年、古河藩の御使番役・鷹見忠徳（250石）の嫡男として古河城下に誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1785, he was born in Koga-jo Castle as the heiress of Tadanori TAKAMI (250 Koku of crop yield), who was the Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) of the Koga clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1785, he was born near Koga-jo Castle as the eldest son to Tadanori TAKAMI (250 Koku of crop yields), who was working as Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) of the Koga clan.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1785, he was born near Koga-jo Castle as the eldest son to Tadanori TAKAMI (250 Koku of crop yields), who was working as Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) of the Koga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1797年、調役給仕として出仕して以降、目付、用人上席、番頭格などを経、1831年には280石の家老（役高500石）に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his serving as an investigator in 1797, he became inspector of foot soldiers, superior lord chamberlain, head clerk, etc, and got promoted to the chief retainer of 280 Koku of crop yield (high post 500 Koku) in 1831.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting to serve as shirabeyaku kyuji (investigating assistant) in the domain in 1797, he served in a variety of posts including metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers), yonin joseki (senior officer handling domestic economy), bantokaku (head of security guard) and got promoted to karo (chief retainer) with 280 Koku of crop yield (500 Koku paid for his post) in 1831.</e>
<cmt>・「調役給仕」は「調役補助」としました。・「番頭格」は「警備の長」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting to serve as shirabeyaku kyuji (investigating assistant) in the domain in 1797, he served in a variety of posts including metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers), yonin joseki (senior officer handling domestic economy), bantokaku (head of security guard) and got promoted to karo (chief retainer) with 280 Koku of crop yield (500 Koku paid for his post) in 1831.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>譜代大名の土井氏は代々幕府の要職を歴任しておる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Doi clan, who were fudai daimyo (a feudal lord in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), held the important position of the shogunate successively for generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Doi clan, one fudai daimyo (a feudal lord in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), held the important posts of the Tokugawa shogunate for generations.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Doi clan, one fudai daimyo (a feudal lord in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), held the important posts of the Tokugawa shogunate for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>土井利厚・土井利位父子もまた、寺社奉行や大坂城代、京都所司代、老中などの要職を務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiatsu DOI and Toshitsura DOI (father and son) also were serving as important positions such as the magistrate of temples and shrines, the keeper of Osaka Castle, the Kyoto deputy, and member of shogun&apos;s council of elders.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiatsu DOI and Toshitsura DOI (father and son) also held important posts such as jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines), Osaka jodai (the keeper of Osaka Castle), Kyoto shosidai (the Kyoto deputy), and roju (senior councillor of the Tokugawa shogunate).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiatsu DOI and Toshitsura DOI (father and son) also held important posts such as jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines), Osaka jodai (the keeper of Osaka Castle), Kyoto shosidai (the Kyoto deputy), and roju (senior councillor of the Tokugawa shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>泉石は藩主に近侍して全国各地へ同行し、これら職務の補佐に務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senseki waited on the feudal lords closely, accompanied them to various places over the whole country, and served as assistant to their duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanseki accompanied the lords of the domain on their visits to various places throughout the country to help them do their duties.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanseki accompanied the lords of the domain on their visits to various places throughout the country to help them do their duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「土井の鷹見か，鷹見の土井か」といわれるほどに，その能力は賞賛を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ability was highly praised by comments such as &quot;Is it TAKAMI of Doi or Doi of TAKAMI?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His ability was highly praised as represented by the comment, &apos;Doi for Takami or Takami for Doi?&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ability was highly praised as represented by the comment, &apos;Doi for Takami or Takami for Doi?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1845年、加増をうけ330石となるが、翌1846年に免職となって古河に隠居している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1845, his salary was increased to 330 Koku crop of yield, but he became dismissed in the next year 1846, and he retired in Koga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1845, his salary increased to 330 Koku crop of yield, but he was dismissed from the office in 1846 and retired in Koga.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1845, his salary increased to 330 Koku crop of yield, but he was dismissed from the office in 1846 and retired in Koga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1858年、古河長谷町の隠居屋敷（現古河歴史博物館の鷹見泉石記念館）にて死没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1858, he died in the retirement residence (present Koga Historical Museum) in Hase-cho Town of Koga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1858, he died in the retirement residence (present Takami Senseki Memorial Hall in Koga Historical Museum) in Hasemachi, Koga City,</e>
<cmt>「古河歴史博物館」、「鷹見泉石記念館」は定訳はないようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1858, he died in the retirement residence (present Takami Senseki Memorial Hall in Koga Historical Museum) in Hasemachi, Koga City,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>享年74。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>対外危機意識の高まるなか、幕政に当たる譜代大名の重臣という立場から早くから海外事情に関心を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the increasing consciousness of foreign crisis, from the standpoint of a feudal lord who was an important statesman in charge of the shogunate administration, he had much interest in overseas affairs from early time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the increasing crisis awareness of foreign countries, he, as a major feudal lord who was in charge of the shogunate administration, had interest in foreign affairs at early stage.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the increasing crisis awareness of foreign countries, he, as a major feudal lord who was in charge of the shogunate administration, had interest in foreign affairs at early stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>地理、歴史、兵学、天文学、暦数などの文物の収集に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried to collect the cultural items of geography, history, military science, astronomy, and calendar, etc. of calendars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He tried to collect various literature covering geography, history, military science, astronomy, calendar system etc.</e>
<cmt>「文物」は「文献」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He tried to collect various literature covering geography, history, military science, astronomy, calendar system etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、川路聖謨、江川英龍などの幕府要人、渡辺崋山、桂川甫周などの蘭学者、箕作省吾などの地理学者、司馬江漢、谷文晁ら画家、砲術家　高島秋帆、海外渡航者の大黒屋光太夫、足立左内、潁川君平、中山作三郎ら和蘭通詞、オランダ商館長（カピタン）のスチュルレ（Johan Willem de Sturler）など、当時の政治、文化、外交の中枢にある人々と広く交流を持って洋学界にも大きく寄与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also greatly contributed to the section of western studies by his wide exchange with the central people existing at that time in the sectors of politics, cultures, diplomatic relations, ranging from shogunate&apos;s important people such as Toshiakira KAWAJI and Hidetatsu EGAWA, Dutch scholars such as Kazan WATANABE, Hoshu KATSURAGAWA, geographers such as learning people and Shogo MITSUKURI, painters such as Kokan SHIBA, Buncho TANI, ballistic specialists, Shuhan TAKASHIMA, overseas navigator such as Kodayu DAIKOKUYA, Japanese-Dutch translators such as Sanai ADACHI, Kunpei EGAWA, Sakusaburo NAKAYAMA, to the curator of Dutch trading house Johan Willem de Sturler.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also greatly contributed to the development of western studies by his wide-ranging exchanges with the central people of that time in politics, culture, diplomacy such as Toshiakira KAWAJI and Hidetatsu EGAWA (key Edo shogunate figures), Kazan WATANABE and Hoshu KATSURAGAWA (Dutch scholars), Shogo MITSUKURI (geographer), Kokan SHIBA and Buncho TANI (painters), Shuhan TAKASHIMA (ballistic specialist), Kodayu DAIKOKUYA (returnee from Russia), Sanai ADACHI, Kunpei EGAWA, Sakusaburo NAKAYAMA (Japanese-Dutch translator), Johan Willem de Sturler (curator of Dutch trading house).</e>
<cmt>・表現の修正・「海外渡航者の大黒屋光太夫」は「ロシアからの帰国者」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also greatly contributed to the development of western studies by his wide-ranging exchanges with the central people of that time in politics, culture, diplomacy such as Toshiakira KAWAJI and Hidetatsu EGAWA (key Edo shogunate figures), Kazan WATANABE and Hoshu KATSURAGAWA (Dutch scholars), Shogo MITSUKURI (geographer), Kokan SHIBA and Buncho TANI (painters), Shuhan TAKASHIMA (ballistic specialist), Kodayu DAIKOKUYA (returnee from Russia), Sanai ADACHI, Kunpei EGAWA, Sakusaburo NAKAYAMA (Japanese-Dutch translator), Johan Willem de Sturler (curator of Dutch trading house).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>鷹見泉石像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait of Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portrait of Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portrait of Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>渡辺崋山の描いた「鷹見泉石像（東京国立博物館蔵）」は、西洋の画法も取り入れた近世画の傑作として、国宝に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait of Senseki TAKAMI (a property of Tokyo National Museum) drawn by Kazan WATANABE, which was a masterpiece of picture at the early modern age that incorporated the Western style of painting, was designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan WATANABE&apos;s &apos;Portrait of Senseki Takami (housed in Tokyo National Museum)&apos;, appreciated as a masterpiece of the early-modern picture that incorporated the Western painting style, is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE&apos;s &apos;Portrait of Senseki Takami (housed in Tokyo National Museum)&apos;, appreciated as a masterpiece of the early-modern picture that incorporated the Western painting style, is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>烏帽子と服は線描を使った東洋の伝統的な画法、相貌は西洋の陰影法や彩色法を使うという対照的な技法を用いながら、全く違和感なく融合させ人物の内面まで感じさせる高い完成度をもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was using the Oriental traditional painting technique of outlining the black-lacquered headgear (formal headwear for court nobles) and clothes, and the western coloring technique and shading technique of the face together, his work had a high level of completion revealing the inside character of the person without any feeling of incompatibility of Oriental and Western styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blending two different painting style perfectly - the Oriental traditional painting one using drawing technique for describing eboshi (formal headwear for court nobles) and clothes and the Western style of shadowing and coloring methods for describing facial expression - succeeded in producing a high-quality picture that also expressed the inside of the character.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blending two different painting style perfectly - the Oriental traditional painting one using drawing technique for describing eboshi (formal headwear for court nobles) and clothes and the Western style of shadowing and coloring methods for describing facial expression - succeeded in producing a high-quality picture that also expressed the inside of the character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天保9年（1838年）、泉石54歳の時のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was belonged to Senseki TAKAMI at the age of 54, in1838.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The picture was drawn in 1838 when Senseki was 54 years old.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The picture was drawn in 1838 when Senseki was 54 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ちなみに絵画の部門では最も時代が新しい国宝である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, it was the national treasure of the latest age in the section of paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the most recent national treasure in the category of paintings.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the most recent national treasure in the category of paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>鷹見泉石日記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diary of Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diary of Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diary of Senseki TAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>『鷹見泉石日記』は、彼が職に就いた12歳から、60年間にもわたった自らの公務を中心に書き留められたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diary of Senseki TAKAMI was a work written about his own official duties for as many as 60 years since he was 12 when he got the employment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diary of Senseki TAKAMI mainly describes about his own official duties for 60 years since he started to work at the age of 12.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diary of Senseki TAKAMI mainly describes about his own official duties for 60 years since he started to work at the age of 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>彼の交友の広さと、客観に徹した文章のために史料価値は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his circle of friends was wide and his essays were objective, the historical information value was high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of his wide circle of friends and his objective description, the diary is appreciated as a historical material.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of his wide circle of friends and his objective description, the diary is appreciated as a historical material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>特に、藩主利位の大坂城代在職中に起こった大塩平八郎の乱については、彼自身が鎮圧に当たったこともあって詳しく記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, about the Rebellion of Heihachiro Oshima which happened while he was serving for the feudal lord Toshitsura as the keeper of Osaka Castle, he himself undertook the repression and it was described in detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diary describes in detail about the Rebellion of Heihachiro Oshio that broke out when the then lord of the domain, Toshitsura DOI, was working as Osaka jodai (the keeper of Osaka Castle) partly because Senseki himself suppressed the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diary describes in detail about the Rebellion of Heihachiro Oshio that broke out when the then lord of the domain, Toshitsura DOI, was working as Osaka jodai (the keeper of Osaka Castle) partly because Senseki himself suppressed the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>蘭学者らしく、日記中に各所へカステラを贈答する記事が記載されているが、どこで製造されたものか詳細不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just like a Dutch scholar, it was described in many articles in his diary about castella sponge cake, but the place where the cake was made was uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unsurprisingly for a Dutch scholar, the diary indicates that he gave castella sponge cake to those concerned as gift, but it is unclear where the cake was made.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unsurprisingly for a Dutch scholar, the diary indicates that he gave castella sponge cake to those concerned as gift, but it is unclear where the cake was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 パの字(id:34188), Kurayamizaka(id:7150), Foldingfan(id:234775), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Goki(id:7107), Cprobot(id:97843), Urania(id:7213), Humpty Dumpty書記官(id:155033), Seibuabina(id:37532), 下総赤堀川(id:43839), こいつぅ(id:2105), Kaznov17(id:68122), Aboshi(id:9318), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>