<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源宗綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Munetsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Munetsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Munetsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源宗綱（みなもと の むねつな、生年未詳 － 1180年6月20日（治承4年5月26日 (旧暦)））は、平安時代末期の摂津源氏の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Munetsuna (date of birth unknown - June 20, 1180) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Munetsuna (date of birth unknown - June 20, 1180) was a busho (Japanese military commander) from Settsu-Genji (the Minamoto clan of Settsu Province) and active during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ、訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Munetsuna (date of birth unknown - June 20, 1180) was a busho (Japanese military commander) from Settsu-Genji (the Minamoto clan of Settsu Province) and active during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源仲綱の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>源頼政の嫡孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a legitimate grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a legitimate grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a legitimate grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官職は従五位下・左衛門尉・肥後守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His government post was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Higo no kami (governor of Higo Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His government post was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Higo no kami (governor of Higo Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His government post was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Higo no kami (governor of Higo Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1180年、祖父・頼政、父・仲綱らは以仁王を擁して平家に叛旗を翻す（宇治川の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grandfather Yorimasa and father Nakatsuna supported Prince Mochihito and raised the standard of revolt against Heike (The battle of Uji-gawa River) in 1180.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1180, his grandfather Yorimasa and father Nakatsuna supported Prince Mochihito and raised an army to revolt against the Taira family (the battle of Uji-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1180, his grandfather Yorimasa and father Nakatsuna supported Prince Mochihito and raised an army to revolt against the Taira family (the battle of Uji-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>宗綱はこの戦いに一家の嫡男として参加し奮戦するが、やがて衆寡敵せず敗北し、宇治平等院にて一族もろとも自害して果てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetsuna participated in this battle as a legitimate son of his clan and fought bravely, but his army was hopelessly outnumbered and defeated, and he and his family committed suicide in Uji-byodoin Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetsuna participated in this battle as the heir of the family and fought bravely, however his army was too small to fight against the enemy&apos;s much larger army, so soon they were defeated, and he and his family committed suicide in Uji-byodoin Temple.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ、訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetsuna participated in this battle as the heir of the family and fought bravely, however his army was too small to fight against the enemy&apos;s much larger army, so soon they were defeated, and he and his family committed suicide in Uji-byodoin Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>宗綱本人は若くして死去したが、孫の下間宗重（蓮位）が親鸞の弟子となったことを契機に、その子孫は本願寺の重臣下間氏として発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetsuna himself died young, but when his grandson Muneshige SHIMOTSUMA (Reni) became a disciple of Shinran, his descendants flourished as senior vassals of the Hongan-ji Temple, the Shimotsuma clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Munetsuna himself died young, his grandson Muneshige SHIMOTSUMA (Reni SHIMOTSUMA or Reni SHIMOZUMA) became a disciple of Shinran, which led to his descendants&apos; development as the Shimotsuma clan (the Shimozuma clan) as senior vassals of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Munetsuna himself died young, his grandson Muneshige SHIMOTSUMA (Reni SHIMOTSUMA or Reni SHIMOZUMA) became a disciple of Shinran, which led to his descendants&apos; development as the Shimotsuma clan (the Shimozuma clan) as senior vassals of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)には一向一揆において中心的役割を果たし、さらに降って江戸時代には一族から池田重利が出て一万石を領し、大名に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan played a central part in an uprising of Ikko sect followers in the Sengoku period (Japan) and Shigetoshi IKEDA of the clan became a daimyo with a fief of 10000 koku in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan played a central part in uprisings of the followers of the Ikko sect in the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States, Japan), and later, in the Edo period, Shigetoshi IKEDA from the clan produced some achievements, he was given rice stipend of 10,000 koku (1,803,900 cubic decimeters) and became daimyo (Japanese territorial lord).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan played a central part in uprisings of the followers of the Ikko sect in the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States, Japan), and later, in the Edo period, Shigetoshi IKEDA from the clan produced some achievements, he was given rice stipend of 10,000 koku (1,803,900 cubic decimeters) and became daimyo (Japanese territorial lord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Izayohi(id:13095), Andee(id:20421), Junger(id:10282), 代言人(id:33675), 豊田充(id:58694), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>