<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>前田利益</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimasu MAEDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimasu MAEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimasu MAEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>戦国時代の武将であり、慶次郎などの通称を持つ前田利久の養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a warlord of the Sengoku period, was an adopted son of Toshihisa MAEDA, and had multiple nicknames such as Keijiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a warlord of the Sengoku period, was an adopted son of Toshihisa MAEDA, and had various nicknames such as Keijiro.</e>
<cmt>&quot;multiple&quot;→&quot;various&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a warlord of the Sengoku period, was an adopted son of Toshihisa MAEDA, and had various nicknames such as Keijiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この項で記す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Information about him is provided in this section.</e>
<cmt>「前田利益の情報がこの項にて提供される」の意と解釈し訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Information about him is provided in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Information about him is provided in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>大聖寺藩藩主前田利鬯の前名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimasu MAEDA was the name formerly used by Toshika MAEDA who was the lord of the Daishoji domain.</e>
<cmt>「前田利益は」を文の主語として追加した上で訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimasu MAEDA was the name formerly used by Toshika MAEDA, who was the lord of Daishoji Domain.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;d&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimasu MAEDA was the name formerly used by Toshika MAEDA, who was the lord of Daishoji Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>前田 利益（まえだ とします、天文 (元号)12年（1533年？1543年？） - 慶長17年（1612年）？）は、戦国時代 (日本)末期から江戸時代初期にかけての武将で、前田利家の義理の甥。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimasu MAEDA (1553 or 1543? - 1612?) was a warlord from the end of the Sengoku period (Japan) to the beginning of the Edo period, and was also a nephew-in-law of Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimasu MAEDA (1553 or 1543? - 1612?) was a warlord from the end of the Sengoku period to the beginning of the Edo period, and was also a nephew-in-law of Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;(Japan)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimasu MAEDA (1553 or 1543? - 1612?) was a warlord from the end of the Sengoku period to the beginning of the Edo period, and was also a nephew-in-law of Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>武勇に優れ、古今典籍にも通じた文武両道の将だったが、奇矯な振る舞いを好むカブキ者としても知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was both a good warrior and a respected scholar as he was very brave and also was knowledgeable in the fields of ancient and modern literature, but at the same time, he was known as an eccentric person who liked to behave in a bizarre way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an accomplished warrior and scholar, being both brave and knowledgeable in the fields of ancient and contemporary literature but, at the same time, he was known as an eccentric person who liked to behave in a bizarre way.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;both&quot;&quot;a good&quot;→&quot;an accomplished&quot;Deleted &quot;a respected&quot;&quot;as he was very&quot;→&quot;, being both&quot;Deleted &quot;also was&quot;&quot;modern&quot;→&quot;contemporary&quot;Moved comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an accomplished warrior and scholar, being both brave and knowledgeable in the fields of ancient and contemporary literature but, at the same time, he was known as an eccentric person who liked to behave in a bizarre way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>なお利益に関する一次史料はほとんど存在しないため、歴史学などの学術的視点からの研究はあまり行われておらず、事跡に不明な点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there are few materials left from the subject time of history there have not been many studies on him from academic perspectives such as historiology; therefore facticity of the events that were supposed to have occurred is often questionable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since not many primary materials relating to Toshimasu are in existence, he has not been studied much and there are lots of gaps in what is known about him.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since not many primary materials relating to Toshimasu are in existence, he has not been studied much and there are lots of gaps in what is known about him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>現代の知名度・評価は後述のとおり小説やマンガ等の影響が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described later, the current recognition and reputation of him are greatly attributed to novels or comics featuring him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described later, his current popularity and reputation are largely due to novels or manga featuring him.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;&quot;his&quot;&quot;recognition&quot;→&quot;popularity&quot;Deleted &quot;of him&quot;&quot;greatly attributed to&quot;→&quot;largely due&quot;&quot;comics&quot;→&quot;manga&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described later, his current popularity and reputation are largely due to novels or manga featuring him.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>通称は宗兵衛、慶次郎、慶二郎、啓次郎など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His nick names were Shube and Keijiro, and Keijiro was written in various combinations of Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His nick names were Shube and Keijiro, with Keijiro being written in various combinations of Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot;→&quot;with&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His nick names were Sobe and Keijiro, with Keijiro being written in various combinations of Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>宗兵衛→Sobe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>彼を題材とした漫画「花の慶次」の影響で前田慶次という名前で呼ばれることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being influenced by the comic &apos;Hana no Keiji&apos; featuring him, he quite often is called Keiji MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the influence of the manga &apos;Hana no Keiji&apos; featuring him, he is quite often called Keiji MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Being influenced by&quot;→&quot;Due to the influence of&quot;&quot;comic&quot;→&quot;manga&quot;Moved &quot;is&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the influence of the manga &apos;Hana no Keiji&apos; featuring him, he is quite often called Keiji MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>諱は利益の他、利太（としたか）あるいは利大（としひろ、としおき）、利貞（としさだ）、利卓（としたか）など複数伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Toshimasu, he supposedly had multiple real names such as Toshitaka, Toshihiro (or Toshioki), Toshisada, and Toshitaka (using a different Chinese character).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Toshimasu, he supposedly had several real names such as Toshitaka, Toshihiro (or Toshioki), Toshisada, and Toshitaka (using a different Chinese character).</e>
<cmt>&quot;multiple&quot;→&quot;several&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Toshimasu, he supposedly had several real names such as Toshitaka, Toshihiro (or Toshioki), Toshisada, and Toshitaka (using a different Chinese character).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また浪人時代は穀蔵院飄戸斎（こくぞういん・ひょっとさい）と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also called himself Hyottosai KOKUZOIN while he was a ronin, a masterless samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also called himself Hyottosai KOKUZOIN while he was a ronin, or masterless samurai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot;→&quot;or&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also called himself Hyottosai KOKUZOIN while he was a ronin, or masterless samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>妻は前田安勝の娘で、間に一男三女をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of Yasukatsu MAEDA, and they had one son and three daughters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was a daughter of Yasukatsu MAEDA, and they had one son and three daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of Yasukatsu MAEDA, and they had one son and three daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>嫡男の前田正虎は従兄弟の前田利常に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first son of the legal wife Masatora MAEDA served his cousin Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eldest son, Masatora MAEDA, served his cousin Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The first son of the legal wife&quot;→&quot;His eldest son,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eldest son, Masatora MAEDA, served his cousin Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>娘は、戸田方勝の妻、北条庄三郎（北条氏邦末子）の妻など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The daughters became a wife of, for example, Kata TODA or Shozaburo HOJO (Ujikuni HOJO&apos;s youngest son).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The daughters became wives of, for example, Kata TODA or Shozaburo HOJO (Ujikuni HOJO&apos;s youngest son).</e>
<cmt>&quot;a wife&quot;→&quot;wives&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The daughters became wives of, for example, Kata TODA or Shozaburo HOJO (Ujikuni HOJO&apos;s youngest son).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;His&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Life→Biographyに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>生年に関しては1533年、1540年、1541年、1542年、1543年、1552年、1555年など様々な説があるが1533年説・1541年説が主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was born in one of 1533, 1540, 1541, 1542, 1543, 1552, and 1555, and the theories claiming that he was born in 1533 or 1541 are now widely accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was born in 1533, 1540, 1541, 1542, 1543, 1552, or 1555, but the theories claiming that he was born in 1533 or 1541 are now widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;one of&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;or&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;but&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was born in 1533, 1540, 1541, 1542, 1543, 1552, or 1555, but the theories claiming that he was born in 1533 or 1541 are now widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>養父の前田利久は、前田利家の長兄で、尾張国荒子城主（愛知県名古屋市中川区）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshihisa MAEDA, his adoptive father, was the eldest son of Toshiie MAEDA as well as the lord of Arako Castle, the Province of Owari (Nakagawa Ward, Nagoya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshihisa MAEDA, his adoptive father, was the eldest brother of Toshiie MAEDA and the Lord of Arako Castle in the Province of Owari (Nakagawa Ward, Nagoya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>&quot;son&quot;→&quot;brother&quot;&quot;as well as the lord&quot;→&quot;and the Lord&quot;comma→&quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshihisa MAEDA, his adoptive father, was the eldest brother of Toshiie MAEDA and the Lord of Arako Castle in the Province of Owari (Nakagawa Ward, Nagoya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>利益の実父は織田信長の重臣滝川一益の一族（従兄弟あるいは甥）である滝川益氏（たきがわますうじ）か滝川益重（たきがわますしげ）とされ、実母が利久に再婚したためその養子になったのだとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biological father of Toshimasu is considered to be either Masuuji TAKIGAWA, a member of the clan led by Kazumasu TAKIGAWA who was the main vassal of Nobunaga ODA, or Masushige TAKIGAWA, and it is said that he was adopted because his biological mother re-married to Toshihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biological father of Toshimasu is considered to be either Masuuji TAKIGAWA, a member of the clan led by Kazumasu TAKIGAWA who was the main vassal of Nobunaga ODA, or Masushige TAKIGAWA, and it is said that he was adopted because his biological mother re-married to Toshihisa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biological father of Toshimasu is considered to be either Masuuji TAKIGAWA, a member of the clan led by Kazumasu TAKIGAWA who was the main vassal of Nobunaga ODA, or Masushige TAKIGAWA, and it is said that he was adopted because his biological mother re-married to Toshihisa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、1567年に信長の命令により、養子の利益が荒子城を継ぐよりも実弟の前田利家が継ぐべきであるという名目によって利久は隠居させられ、利家が荒子城を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1567, Nobunaga issued an ordinance, and this made Toshihisa retire on the grounds that Arako Castle should be taken over by Toshiie MAEDA who was the real younger brother instead of Toshimasu the adopted son, and as a result, Toshiie took over Arako Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1567, following Nobunaga&apos;s order that Toshihisa should give Arako Castle to his biological brother, Toshiie MAEDA, rather than the adopted Toshimasu, Toshihisa retired and Toshiie took over the castle.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1567, following Nobunaga&apos;s order that Toshihisa should give Arako Castle to his biological brother, Toshiie MAEDA, rather than the adopted Toshimasu, Toshihisa retired and Toshiie took over the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このため利益ははじめ養父に従って荒子を離れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimasu therefore followed his adoptive father&apos;s advice and left Arako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Toshimasu followed his adoptive father&apos;s advice and left Arako.</e>
<cmt>&quot;therefore&quot;→&quot;As a result,&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Toshimasu followed his adoptive father&apos;s advice and left Arako.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後に累進して能登国一国を得た利家を頼り、義理の叔父にあたる利家に仕えた（1580年頃）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then counted on and served his uncle-in-law Toshiie who later got promoted and became in charge of the Province of Noto (around 1580).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then relied on and served his uncle-in-law Toshiie, who later got promoted and was given control of the Province of Noto (around 1580).</e>
<cmt>&quot;counted&quot;→&quot;relied&quot;Added comma&quot;became in charge&quot;→&quot;was given control&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then relied on and served his uncle-in-law Toshiie, who later got promoted and was given control of the Province of Noto (around 1580).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>石山軍記に、石山本願寺攻めの際に、信長の大旗を奪い返すとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Ishiyama War Story, Toshimasu regained Nobunaga&apos;s large flag at the time of the seige of the Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Ishiyama War Chronicles, Toshimasu regained Nobunaga&apos;s standard during the seige of Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Story&quot;→&quot;Chronicles&quot;&quot;large flag&quot;→&quot;standard&quot;&quot;at the time of&quot;→&quot;during&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Ishiyama War Chronicles, Toshimasu regained Nobunaga&apos;s standard during the siege of Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペル’→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>（その間10年ほどの消息は全く不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(For about 10 years before that event no one knows where he was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For about 10 years before that event no one knows where he was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For about 10 years before that event no one knows where he was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>隆慶一郎の小説「一夢庵風流記」では、滝川一益に仕えていたとするが、あくまで作者の推測および創作である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The novel &apos;Ichimuan Furyuki&apos; by Keiichiro RYU has it that he was serving Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, but it is only the imagination and creation of the author.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The novel &apos;Ichimuan Furyuki&apos; by Keiichiro RYU has it that he was serving Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, but it is only the imagination and creation of the author.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;it&quot;→&quot;this&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The novel &apos;Ichimuan Furyuki&apos; by Keiichiro RYU has it that he was serving Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, but it is only the imagination and creation of the author.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1584年の小牧・長久手の戦いでは佐々成政に攻められた末森城の救援に向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he went to guard Suemori Castle which was under attack by Shigemasa SASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he went to guard Suemori Castle, which was under attack by Shigemasa SASA.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the battle of Komaki-Nagakute in 1584, he went to guard Suemori Castle, which was under attack by Shigemasa SASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その後、佐々方から寝返った阿尾城の城代に任じられ、同城奪還に向かった神保氏張らの軍勢と交戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, following the order issued by the chief vassal of Ao Castle, who left the Sasa side, he fought against the force led by Ujiharu JIMBO who went to regain control of the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, following orders issued by the chief vassal of Ao Castle, who had left the Sasa side, he fought against forces led by Ujiharu JIMBO, who was on his way to regain control of the castle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the order&quot;→&quot;orders&quot;Added &quot;had&quot;&quot;the force&quot;→&quot;forces&quot;&quot;went&quot;→&quot;was on his way&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, following orders issued by the chief vassal of Ao Castle, who had left the Sasa side, he fought against forces led by Ujiharu JIMBO, who was on his way to regain control of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>利久死後の1590年頃、利家と仲違いして前田氏を出奔する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Toshihisa died, around 1590, he had a disagreement with Toshiie and left the Maeda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Toshihisa died, around 1590, he had a disagreement with Toshiie and left the Maeda Clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Toshihisa died, around 1590, he had a disagreement with Toshiie and left the Maeda Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このとき、利家をだまして水風呂に入れ、名馬一覧松風（利家の愛馬「谷風」とも）を奪って出奔したという逸話が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There has been an anecdote that Toshimasu tricked Toshiie into taking a water bath, and while he was in the bath, Toshimasu stole Matsukaze (or &apos;Tanikaze&apos; that was the horse of Toshiie) on the Historical Horse List and left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a story that Toshimasu tricked Toshiie into taking a cold bath, and while he was in the bath, Toshimasu stole the famous horse, Matsukaze (or Toshiie&apos;s favorite horse, &apos;Tanikaze&apos;) and left.</e>
<cmt>&quot;has been an anecdote&quot;→&quot;is a story&quot;&quot;water&quot;→&quot;cold&quot;&quot;on the Historical Horse List&quot;→&quot;the famous horse&quot;&quot;‘Tanikaze’ that was the horse of Toshiie&quot;→&quot;Toshiie&apos;s favorite horse, Tanikaze&apos;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a story that Toshimasu tricked Toshiie into taking a cold bath, and while he was in the bath, Toshimasu stole the famous horse, Matsukaze (or Toshiie&apos;s favorite horse, &apos;Tanikaze&apos;) and left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>出奔後は京都で浪人生活を送りながら、里村紹巴・里村昌叱父子や九条稙道・古田重然ら多数の文人と交流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After leaving the family, he was leading a ronin life in Kyoto, and meanwhile, he interacted with a large number of writers such as Jyoha and Shoshitsu SATOMURA, a father and a son, Tanemichi KUJO, and Shigeteru FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After leaving the family, while leading the life of a ronin in Kyoto, he interacted with a large number of writers such as the father and son, Jyoha and Shoshitsu SATOMURA, Tanemichi KUJO, and Shigeteru FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was leading a ronin life&quot;→&quot;while leading the life of a ronin&quot;Deleted &quot;and meanwhile,&quot;&quot;a father and a son&quot;→&quot;the father and son,&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After leaving the family, while leading the life of a ronin in Kyoto, he interacted with a large number of writers such as the father and son, Joha and Shoshitsu SATOMURA, Tanemichi KUJO, and Shigeteru FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>Jyoha→Johaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>後に上杉景勝とその重臣直江兼続の知遇を得て、景勝が越後国から会津藩120万石に移封された1598年から関ヶ原の戦いが起こった1600年のまでの間に上杉氏に仕官し、兼続の与力として1000石を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he was recognized and treated with respect by Kagekatsu UESUGI and his senior statesman Kanetsugu NAOE, and he then therefore served the Uesugi family from 1590, when the territory of Kagekatsu was transferred from the Province of Echigo to the domain of Aizu with 1.2 million koku, to 1600 when the battle of Seigahara starts, and thereafter received 1,000 koku as an assistant of Kanetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Toshimasu gained favor with Kagekatsu UESUGI and his chief vassal, Kanetsugu NAOE, he served the Uesugi Clan from 1590, when Kagekatsu was transferred from the Province of Echigo to the 1.2 million koku Domain of Aizu, until the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and thereafter received 1,000 koku as an assistant of Kanetsugu.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Toshimasu gained favor with Kagekatsu UESUGI and his chief vassal, Kanetsugu NAOE, he served the Uesugi Clan from 1598, when Kagekatsu was transferred from the Province of Echigo to the 1.2 million koku Domain of Aizu, until the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and thereafter received 1,000 koku as an assistant of Kanetsugu.</e>
<cmt>1590→1598</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>関ヶ原の役に際しては、上杉景勝が東軍についた最上義光と戦った長谷堂城の戦いに出陣して功を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Sekigahara conflict, he participated in the battle of Hasedo-jyo where Kagekatsu UESUGI fought against Yoshimitsu MOGAMI who belonged to the East force and distinguished himself there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sekigahara conflict, he fought with distinction in the battle for Hasedo-jyo Castle, where Kagekatsu UESUGI fought against Yoshimitsu MOGAMI of the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>&quot;participated&quot;→&quot;fought with distinction&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;for&quot;Added &quot;Castle,&quot;&quot;who belonged to the East force&quot;→&quot;of the Eastern Army&quot;Deleted &quot;and distinguished himself there&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sekigahara conflict, he fought with distinction in the battle for Hasedo-jo Castle, where Kagekatsu UESUGI fought against Yoshimitsu MOGAMI of the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>jyo→jo に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>西軍敗退により上杉氏が30万石に減封され米沢藩に移されると、これに従って米沢藩に仕え、米沢近郊の堂森（現、米沢市万世町堂森で慶次清水と呼ばれる）に隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the West force lost the battle and the territory of the Uesugi family was reduced to 300,000 koku and relocated to the domain of Yonezawa, Toshimasu served the domain of Yonezawa and retired in Domori near Yonezawa (currently known as Keijisimizu in Domori, Bansei-Town, Yonezawa-City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Western Army lost the battle and the territory of the Uesugi Clan was reduced to 300,000 koku and relocated to the Domain of Yonezawa, Toshimasu served the Domain of Yonezawa and retired to Domori near Yonezawa (currently known as Keijisimizu in Domori, Bansei-Town, Yonezawa-City).</e>
<cmt>&quot;West force&quot;→&quot;Western Army&quot;&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;Capitalized &apos;d&apos;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Western Army lost the battle and the territory of the Uesugi Clan was reduced to 300,000 koku and relocated to the Domain of Yonezawa, Toshimasu served the Domain of Yonezawa and retired to Domori near Yonezawa (currently known as Keijisimizu in Domori, Bansei-Town, Yonezawa-City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>隠棲後は兼続とともに「史記」に注釈を入れたり（ちなみに直江兼続が所有していた「史記」は今現在国宝に指定されているが、こちらに注釈を入れていたかについては不明）、和歌や連歌を詠むなど自適の生活を送ったと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Toshimasu is said to have led a leisurely life annotating &apos;Shiki&apos; with Kanetsugu (note that although &apos;Shiki&apos; owned by Kanetsugu NAOE is now designated as national treasure, it is not clear if that was the one that they annotated) or creating waka poems and linked verses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Toshimasu is said to have led a leisurely life, annotating the &apos;Shiki (historical records)&apos; with Kanetsugu (although it is not clear if the &apos;Shiki&apos; owned by Kanetsugu NAOE and now designated as a national treasure is the one that they annotated) or creating waka poems and linked verses.</e>
<cmt>Added comma- I&apos;m not sure if the &quot;史記&quot; is the Chinese one (in which case it would be &apos;Shiji&apos; in English) or a Japanese versionReworded section in brackets for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retired Toshimasu is said to have led a leisurely life, annotating the &apos;Shiki (historical records)&apos; with Kanetsugu (although it is not clear if the &apos;Shiki&apos; owned by Kanetsugu NAOE and now designated as a national treasure is the one that they annotated) or creating waka poems and linked verses.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>1612年に堂森で没したとされ、同地に供養塔が残るが、一方で加賀藩藩主前田利長の命によって大和国刈布に隠棲し、1605年にその地で生涯を終えたなどの異説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he died in Domori in 1612 and there is a memorial tower there, but meanwhile, there is a different theory that he was retired in Karifu in the Province of Yamato following the order of Toshinaga MAEDA, a lord of the domain of Kaga, and ended his life there in 1605.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he died in Domori in 1612 and there is a memorial tower there, but there is also a different theory that he retired to Karifu in the Province of Yamato on the orders of Toshinaga MAEDA, the lord of the Domain of Kaga, and died there in 1605.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;meanwhile,&quot;Added &quot;also&quot;&quot;was retired in&quot;→&quot;retired to&quot;&quot;following the order&quot;→&quot;on the orders&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;d&apos;&quot;ended his life&quot;→&quot;died&quot; - he didn&apos;t kill himself</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he died in Domori in 1612 and there is a memorial tower there, but there is also a different theory that he retired to Karifu in the Province of Yamato on the orders of Toshinaga MAEDA, the lord of the Domain of Kaga, and died there in 1605.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>後世の評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Reputation in Later Generations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reputation in Later Generations</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;His&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reputation in Later Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>隆慶一郎の時代小説「一夢庵風流記」およびそのコミカライズ作品である「花の慶次 ―雲のかなたに―」などから影響を受け、人々に豪腕な武人・超一級の戦人のように印象づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influenced by the novel &apos;Ichimuan Furyuki&apos; by Keiichiro RYU and its comic version &apos;Hana no Keiji: Kumo no Kanata ni,&apos; he is portrayed as a strong warrior or a battle master of the highest level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influenced by Keiichiro RYU&apos;s novel &apos;Ichimuan Furyuki&apos; and its comic version &apos;Hana no Keiji: Kumo no Kanata ni,&apos; he is seen as a strong warrior and a battle master of the highest level.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;Keiichiro RYU&apos;s&quot;&quot;portrayed&quot;→&quot;seen&quot;&quot;or&quot;→&quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influenced by Keiichiro RYU&apos;s novel &apos;Ichimuan Furyuki&apos; and its comic version &apos;Hana no Keiji: Kumo no Kanata ni,&apos; he is seen as a strong warrior and a battle master of the highest level.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>平成以降における「傾奇者」という言葉とこの歴史上の人物の知名度・イメージについては、これら作品群の存在が過半を担っているといっても過言ではない程である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s not an exaggeration to say that he has been considered to be an &apos;eccentric person&apos; since the Heisei period and also as a historical figure had gained a certain level of recognition and type of image mostly because of the pieces of work mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s not an exaggeration to say that, since the early 1990s, he has been considered an &apos;eccentric person&apos; and that his popularity and image as a historical figure come mainly from the pieces of work mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;to be&quot;&quot;since the Heisei period&quot;→&quot;since the early 1990s,&quot; and movedDeleted &quot;also&quot;&quot;as a historical figure had gained a certain level of recognition and type of image&quot;→&quot;his popularity and image as a historical figure come mainly from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s not an exaggeration to say that, since the early 1990s, he has been considered an &apos;eccentric person&apos; and that his popularity and image as a historical figure come mainly from the pieces of work mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>この影響があり、更に近年、シミュレーションゲームやアクションゲームでは、武芸に精通したサムライ、あるいは敏腕なる剣豪などとして登場することが多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These influences have resulted in him being featured as a samurai who has mastered the military arts or a great swordsman in recent simulation or action games.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These influences have resulted in him being featured as a samurai who has mastered the military arts or a great swordsman in recent simulation or action games.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These influences have resulted in him being featured as a samurai who has mastered the military arts or a great swordsman in recent simulation or action games.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>上述した通り利益に関する一次史料はほとんど存在しない事もあって、恵まれた体格と優れた槍術があったと、長谷堂の戦いで伝えられている活躍の話が誇張されている節はある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, since there are few materials about Toshimasu left from the subject time of history, it seems that the stories about his actions in the battle of Hasedo have been exaggerated to create an impression that he was well built and was excellent in spearmanship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, since there are few original materials about Toshimasu left, it seems that the stories about his actions in the Battle of Hasedo have been exaggerated to create an impression that he was well built and excelled in spearmanship.</e>
<cmt>&quot;from the subject time of history&quot;→&quot;original&quot; and movedCapitalized &apos;b&apos;&quot;was excellent&quot;→&quot;excelled&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, since there are few original materials about Toshimasu left, it seems that the stories about his actions in the Battle of Hasedo have been exaggerated to create an impression that he was well built and excelled in spearmanship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、現在の創作物での描写には明らかに誇大表現といえる部分も無くはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some descriptions about him in current fictional works are clearly exaggerated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some descriptions about him in current fictional works are clearly exaggerated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some descriptions about him in current fictional works are clearly exaggerated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>だが、戦場にあっては長谷堂の戦いの様な逸話を残し、一方で古今典籍に通じ文人との交流を好んだ文武両道の人物というイメージは、その戦歴や『前田慶次道中日記』などの数少ない資料から得られる人物像と照らし合わせて見る限りでは、極端に外れてはいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, images of him that he left heroic war stories such as the stories of the battle of Hasedo while he was both a good warrior and a respected scholar having extensive knowledge in old and new literature and enjoying interacting with writers would not be too far from the truth when referring to his character built based on his war history and little historic information currently available such as the &quot;Maeda Keiji Dochu Nikki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, based on his war history and the little historic information currently available, such as the &quot;Maeda Keiji Dochu Nikki (Diary of the Travels of Keiji Maeda)&quot;, the stories of his actions at the Battle of Hasedo and the image of him as both a good warrior and a respected scholar of old and new literature who enjoyed the company of writers, is probably not be too far from the truth.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, based on his war history and the little historic information currently available, such as the &quot;Maeda Keiji Dochu Nikki (Diary of the Travels of Keiji Maeda)&quot;, the stories of his actions at the Battle of Hasedo and the image of him as both a good warrior and a respected scholar of old and new literature who enjoyed the company of writers, is probably not be too far from the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>山形県米沢市にある宮坂考古館に甲冑等の遺品が展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His personal belongings such as armor are exhibited at the Miyasaka Archaeology Museum in Yonezawa-City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His personal belongings, such as his armor, are exhibited at the Miyasaka Archaeology Museum in Yonezawa-City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Added commas and &quot;his&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His personal belongings, such as his armor, are exhibited at the Miyasaka Archaeology Museum in Yonezawa-City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>著書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Book</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary Works</e>
<cmt>&quot;His Book&quot;→&quot;Literary Works&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>『前田慶次道中日記』（米沢市指定文化財、市立米沢図書館所蔵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Maeda Keiji Dochu Nikki&quot; (Yonezawa city designated cultural property, owned by Yonezawa Library)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Maeda Keiji Dochu Nikki&quot; (Yonezawa city designated cultural property, owned by Yonezawa Library)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Maeda Keiji Dochu Nikki&quot; (Yonezawa city designated cultural property, owned by Yonezawa Library)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>慶長6年（1601年）10月15日 (旧暦)に京都を発ってから同年11月19日 (旧暦)に米沢へ着くまでを記した道中日記で、文中には本人が詠んだ俳句・和歌なども挿入しつつ、道中の風俗を詳しく書き残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a diary that he wrote from October 15, 1601 (lunar calendar), the day that he left Kyoto, to November 19, 1601, the day that he arrived in Yonezawa, and in this diary, he made a detailed record of the customs that he encountered during his trip while introducing his own waka and haiku poems from time to time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a diary that he wrote from October 15, 1601 (lunar calendar), the day that he left Kyoto, to November 19, 1601, the day that he arrived in Yonezawa, in which he made a detailed record of the customs that he encountered during his trip while introducing his own waka and haiku poems.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It&quot;→&quot;This&quot;&quot;and in this diary&quot;→&quot;in which&quot;Deleted &quot;from time to time&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a diary that he wrote from October 15, 1601 (lunar calendar), the day that he left Kyoto, to November 19, 1601, the day that he arrived in Yonezawa, in which he made a detailed record of the customs that he encountered during his trip while introducing his own waka and haiku poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この日記は当時の風俗を伺う史料として、また利益の教養の高さを示す史料として評価されており、米沢図書館より関連資料・活字を併録した影印本が出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This diary is highly valued as historical information that described the customs of that time and that showed how educated Toshimasu was, and a printing of photograph of this diary also containing relevant data has been published by Yonezawa Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This diary is highly valued as a historical document that describes the customs of the time and that shows how educated Toshimasu was, and a printing of a photograph of the diary also containing relevant data has been published by Yonezawa Library.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as historical information&quot;→&quot;as a historical document&quot;Made &quot;described&quot;, &quot;showed&quot; present tenseAdded &quot;a&quot;&quot;this&quot;→&quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This diary is highly valued as a historical document that describes the customs of the time and that shows how educated Toshimasu was, and a printing of a photograph of the diary also containing relevant data has been published by Yonezawa Library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>なお三一書房の「日本庶民生活史料集成」にも翻刻文が所収されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reproduction of that diary is also included in the &apos;Nihon Shomin Seikatsu Shiryo Shusei&apos; published by San&apos;itsu Shobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A reproduction of the diary is also included in the &apos;Nihon Shomin Seikatsu Shiryo Shusei&apos;, published by San&apos;itsu Shobo.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;A&quot;&quot;that&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A reproduction of the diary is also included in the &apos;Nihon Shomin Seikatsu Shiryo Shusei&apos;, published by Sanitsu Shobo.</e>
<cmt>San&apos;itsu→Sanitsu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), 田無稲子(id:63575), SINOBU(id:28887), Dummyoscar(id:26399), Carbuncle(id:346), 0null0(id:582), Bright Long(id:39135), Sheepech(id:111676), Jidaigeki.db(id:197318), Harupri(id:133581), 無苦斎(id:179040), 立つのかよ(id:111350), Kamakura(id:472), Yhiroyuki(id:84500), Hrs885(id:104160), Gnsin(id:12351), 未完(id:84727), 百人(id:16483), 山県昌景(id:60872), VolkovBot(id:105371), アンサイクロペディアン(id:89886), 魔都レイ(id:29665), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Rei-bot(id:94097), KSKS(id:97637), Akimoto(id:6951), Safkan(id:423), ５１６(id:45205), Ebimu-man(id:70113), King-wise(id:19033), V-ＳＳＫ(id:29127), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>