<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤崎吉五郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kichigoro FUJISAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kichigoro FUJISAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichigoro FUJISAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤崎吉五郎（ふじさき きちごろう、?－慶応2年9月12日 (旧暦)(1866年10月20日)）は、幕末の土佐藩士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kichigoro FUJISAKI (male, ? to October 20, 1866) was a warrior of Tosa clan at the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kichigoro FUJISAKI (male, ? to October 20, 1866) was a warrior of Tosa clan at the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichigoro FUJISAKI (date of birth unknown - October 20, 1866) was a warrior of Tosa clan at the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>male, ?削除date of birth unknown補足しました。ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元治元年(1864年)6月5日の池田屋事件に巻き込まれて死亡した藤崎八郎の弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kichigoro FUJISAKI was a younger brother of Hachiro FUJISAKI who was involved and killed in Ikedaya incident on June 5, 1864.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kichigoro FUJISAKI was a younger brother of Hachiro FUJISAKI who was involved and killed during the Ikedaya incident on June 5, 1864.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichigoro FUJISAKI was a younger brother of Hachiro FUJISAKI who was involved and killed during the Ikedaya Incident on July 8, 1864.</e>
<cmt>Incident大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>慶応2年の長州征伐が一段落した際、徳川幕府が三条大橋に掲げた高札が抜き取られて川に投げ捨てられると言う事態がたびたび起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the conquest of Choshu clan was almost finished in 1866, such an event often happened as that a temporary notice board held up by the Tokugawa shogunate at Sanjo-ohashi bridge was pulled out and thrown into the river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the conquest of Choshu clan was almost finished in 1866, an event often happened such that a temporary notice board held up by the Tokugawa shogunate at Sanjo-ohashi bridge was pulled out and thrown into the river.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the conquest of Choshu clan was almost finished in 1866, an event often happened such that a temporary notice board held up by the Tokugawa shogunate at Sanjo-ohashi bridge was pulled out and thrown into the river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そこで幕府は新選組に高札場の警備を依頼する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the shogunate requested Shinsengumi to guard the site for the notice board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate then requested the Shinsengumi to guard the site of the notice board.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate then requested the Shinsengumi to guard the site of the notice board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その9月12日、藤崎は松島和助、宮川助五郎、沢田甚兵衛、安藤鎌次、岡山禎六、早川安太郎、中山謙太郎などと共に三条大橋を訪れて高札を引き抜こうとしたため、見張りについていた新選組の原田左之助・新井忠雄らから襲撃を受け、長剣を振るって応戦したが死亡した（三条制札事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 12 of the same year, FUJISAKI along with his fellows including Kazusuki MATSUSHIMA, Sukegoro MIYAGAWA, Jinbee SAWADA, Kanetsugu ANDO, Sadaroku OKAYAMA, Yasutaro HAYAKAWA, and Kentaro NAKAYAMA visited Sanjo-ohashi bridge and tried to pull out the notice board and, therefore, they were attacked by Shinsengumi members who were watching the notice board including Sanosuke HARADA and Tadao ARAI, and fight back using their long swords, however, FUJISAKI was killed (Sanjo notice board incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 12 of the same year, FUJISAKI along with his fellows including Kazusuki MATSUSHIMA, Sukegoro MIYAGAWA, Jinbee SAWADA, Kanetsugu ANDO, Sadaroku OKAYAMA, Yasutaro HAYAKAWA, and Kentaro NAKAYAMA visited Sanjo-ohashi bridge and tried to remove the notice board and, therefore, they were attacked by Shinsengumi members who were watching the notice board including Sanosuke HARADA and Tadao ARAI, who fought back using their long swords, however, FUJISAKI was killed (Sanjo notice board incident).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 20 of the same year, Kichigoro along with his fellows including Kazusuke MATSUSHIMA, Sukegoro MIYAGAWA, Jinbe SAWADA, Kanetsugu ANDO, Sadaroku OKAYAMA, Yasutaro HAYAKAWA, and Kentaro NAKAYAMA visited Sanjo-ohashi bridge and tried to remove the notice board and, therefore, they were attacked by Shinsengumi members who were watching the notice board including Sanosuke HARADA and Tadao ARAI, who fought back using their long swords, however, Kichigoro was killed (Sanjo notice board incident).</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。兄がいるため、混乱を避けて主語をKichigoroとしました。KazusukiをKazusukeに訂正しました。JinbeeをJinbeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>高札を棄てたのが全て藤崎らの仕業だったかどうかは不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is still unknown whether or not all the cases of throwing away the notice board were commited by FUJISAKi and his fellows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is still unknown whether or not all the cases involving removal of the notice board were commited by FUJISAKi and his fellows.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is still unknown whether or not all the cases involving removal of the notice board were committed by Kichigoro and his fellows.</e>
<cmt>committedスペル訂正しました。主語をKichigoroとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>明治以後、従五位を贈られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji period, FUJISAKI was given Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, FUJISAKI was given Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, Kichigoro was given Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>主語をKichigoroとしました。従五位→Jugoiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fryed-peach(id:63402), たとゥ(id:25557), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>