<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源仲綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 仲綱（みなもと の なかつな、大治元年（1126年）？ － 治承4年5月26日 (旧暦)（1180年6月20日）は、平安時代末期の摂津源氏の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna (1126? - June 20, 1180) was a military commander of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan) who lived in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna (1126? - June 20, 1180) was a military commander of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan) who lived in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna (1126? - June 27, 1180) was a military commander of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan) who lived in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源頼政の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は源斉頼の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Masayori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Masayori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Masayori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は正五位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank was Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>隠岐受領。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Zuryo (the highest rank provincial governor) of Oki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the Zuryo (the highest rank provincial governor) of Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the Zuryo (the highest rank provincial governor) of Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>伊豆守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also the director of Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also the director of Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also the director of Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仲綱は源頼光の系統の摂津源氏で、代々大内守護（内裏の警護）の任にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakatsuna was a Settsu-Genji member in the family line of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, and the family members were for generations appointed to Ouchi shugo (guards of the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakatsuna was a Settsu-Genji member in the family line of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, and for generations the family members were appointed to Ouchi shugo (guards of the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakatsuna was a Settsu-Genji member in the family line of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, and for generations the family members were appointed to Ouchi shugo (guards of the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）守仁親王（後の二条天皇）が立太子されると蔵人に補され、東宮（皇太子）に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Imperial Prince Morihito (later to become Emperor Nijo) became Crown Prince, Nakatsuna was appointed to Kurodo (sovereign&apos;s secretary) and served for Togu (the Prince).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Imperial Prince Morihito (later to become Emperor Nijo) became Crown Prince, Nakatsuna was appointed to Kurodo (sovereign&apos;s secretary) and served Togu (the Prince).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Imperial Prince Morihito (later to become Emperor Nijo) became Crown Prince in 1155, Nakatsuna was appointed to Kurodo (sovereign&apos;s secretary) and served Togu (the Prince).</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたので補う</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>父の頼政は平治の乱では平清盛に味方し、その結果、源義朝の河内源氏（源頼信の系統）は没落するが、摂津源氏は平氏政権下の中央に留まることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Yorimasa, supported TAIRA no Kiyomori in the Heiji Rebellion, and as a result, the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) led by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (in the family line of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu) was destroyed while the Settsu Genji remained as an important family under the Taira administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Yorimasa, supported TAIRA no Kiyomori in the Heiji Rebellion, and as a result, the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) led by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (in the family line of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu) was destroyed while the Settsu Genji remained an important family under the Taira administration.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Yorimasa, supported TAIRA no Kiyomori in the Heiji Rebellion, and as a result, the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) led by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo (in the family line of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu) was destroyed while the Settsu Genji remained an important family under the Taira administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>義朝の三男の頼朝が伊豆国蛭ヶ小島に流罪になっていた時期、仲綱は伊豆守だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitomo&apos;s third son, Yoritomo, was on Hiruga-kojima Island in Izu Province because of deportation, Nakatsuna was the director of that province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitomo&apos;s third son, Yoritomo, was on Hiruga-kojima Island in Izu Province because of deportation, Nakatsuna was the director of that province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitomo&apos;s third son, Yoritomo, was on Hiruga-kojima Island in Izu Province because of deportation, Nakatsuna was the director of that province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一説では流罪の身となった頼朝を伊豆へ運んだのは、頼政の配下の摂津国の渡辺氏だとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There has been a theory that the deported Yoritomo was transported to Izu by the Watanabe clan of Settsu Province which was at that time controlled by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a theory that the deported Yoritomo was transported to Izu by the Watanabe clan of Settsu Province which was at that time was controlled by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a theory that the deported Yoritomo was transported to Izu by the Watanabe clan of Settsu Province which was at that time was controlled by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>平氏政権下での仲綱の動向としては仁安 (日本)3年（1168年）、伊豆守だった仲綱が伊豆が不作なため朝廷に献じる五節舞の舞姫の費用を弁じることができない旨の請文が現存しており、頼政・仲綱の動向を知る数少ない史料になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There have only been a few historical materials introducing Yorimasa and Nakatsuna&apos;s behavior under the Taira administration, and one of them was a report written by Nakatsuna in 1168 saying that he could not afford hiring dancers for Gosechi-mai (dance performance as part of a harvest festival) to be held at the Imperial Court due to the poor rice harvest in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have only been a few historical materials introducing Yorimasa and Nakatsuna&apos;s behavior under the Taira administration, and one of them was a report written by Nakatsuna in 1168 saying that he could not afford to hire dancers for Gosechi-mai (dance performance as part of a harvest festival) to be held at the Imperial Court due to the poor rice harvest in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have only been a few historical materials introducing Yorimasa and Nakatsuna&apos;s behavior under the Taira administration, and one of them was a report written by Nakatsuna in 1168 saying that he could not afford to hire dancers for Gosechi-mai (dance performance as part of a harvest festival) to be held at the Imperial Court due to the poor rice harvest in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>大内守護の任にある仲綱は頼政とともに天皇や法皇に仕え諸行事に供奉している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ouchi shugo Nakatsuna, together with Yorimasa, served the Emperor and the Cloistered Emperor, and participated in a various types of events.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ouchi shugo Nakatsuna, together with Yorimasa, served the Emperor and the Cloistered Emperor, and participated in various types of events.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ouchi shugo Nakatsuna, together with Yorimasa, served the Emperor and the Cloistered Emperor, and participated in various types of events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>父の頼政は家門の誉まれとして従三位（公卿）に昇ることに望みをつなぎ続け、70歳を過ぎても家督を仲綱に譲らずにいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakatsuna&apos;s father, Yorimasa, kept his hope to be promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) (Court noble) as an honor to his family, and he therefore did not let Nakatsuna succeed the headship of the family even after he was well passed 70 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakatsuna&apos;s father, Yorimasa, kept his hope to be promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) (Court noble) as an honor to his family, and therefore did not let Nakatsuna succeed the headship of the family even after he was well past 70 years of age.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakatsuna&apos;s father, Yorimasa, kept his hope to be promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) (Court noble) as an honor to his family, and therefore did not let Nakatsuna succeed the headship of the family even after he was well past 70 years of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その願いが叶い治承2年（1178年）12月、清盛の推挙により頼政は従三位に叙され、翌治承3年（1179年）11月、頼政は家督を仲綱に譲って出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1178, owing to Kiyomori&apos;s recommendation, Yorimasa&apos;s wish came true and he was appointed to Jusanmi, and so in November of the following year, he transferred the family headship to Nakatsuna and entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1178, owing to Kiyomori&apos;s recommendation, Yorimasa&apos;s wish came true and he was appointed to Jusanmi, and so in November of the following year, he transferred the family headship to Nakatsuna and entered priesthood.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, 1178, owing to Kiyomori&apos;s recommendation, Yorimasa&apos;s wish came true and he was appointed to Jusanmi, and so in November of the following year, he transferred the family headship to Nakatsuna and entered priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>以仁王の挙兵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raising of an Army by Prince Mochihito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raising of an Army by Prince Mochihito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raising of an Army by Prince Mochihito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>治承4年（1180年）4月、頼政・仲綱父子は後白河法皇の第三皇子以仁王と平家打倒を謀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1180, Yorimasa and his son Nakatsune made a plan with Prince Mochihito who was the third son of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakwa to destroy the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1180, Yorimasa and his son Nakatsune made a plan with Prince Mochihito who was the third son of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakwa to destroy the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1180, Yorimasa and his son Nakatsune made a plan with Prince Mochihito who was the third son of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakwa to destroy the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その動機について、『平家物語』では、仲綱が所有していた「木の下」（または「九重」）という名馬を清盛の三男の平宗盛が権勢を傘に強引に奪い、しかもその馬に「仲綱」という名をつけて侮辱したのがきっかけだったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; they made that plan because TAIRA no Munemori, who was the third son of Kiyomori, seized Nakatsune&apos;s fine horse called &apos;Kinoshita (or Kokonoe)&apos; using his political power, and then he insulted Nakatsune by naming the horse &apos;Nakatsune.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; the plan was created because TAIRA no Munemori, who was the third son of Kiyomori, seized Nakatsune&apos;s fine horse called &apos;Kinoshita (or Kokonoe)&apos; using his political power, and then insulted Nakatsune by naming the horse &apos;Nakatsune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; the plan was created because TAIRA no Munemori, who was the third son of Kiyomori, seized Nakatsuna&apos;s fine horse called &apos;Kinoshita (or Kokonoe)&apos; using his political power, and then insulted Nakatsuna by naming the horse &apos;Nakatsuna.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>暗愚の武将・宗盛という人物像を印象づける逸話であるが、事実かどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This episode gave audience an impression that Munemori was a benighted military commander, but it is not certain if it was based on the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This episode gave the audience an impression that Munemori was a benighted military commander, but it is not certain if this was based on the truth.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This episode gave the audience an impression that Munemori was a benighted military commander, but it is not certain if this was based on the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>挙兵計画は以仁王の名で平家追討の令旨を大寺社や諸国に雌伏する源氏に下し、その蜂起の呼びかけの名義人が「前伊豆守源仲綱」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plan to raise an army was communicated in the form of Prince Mochihito&apos;s Imperial order to the priests of the Daiji-sha Temple and the Minamoto clan who had yielded to power in various provinces across Japan to destroy the Taira clan, and &apos;MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna, the former Director of Izu Province&apos; was listed as the leader of the plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan to raise an army was communicated in the form of Prince Mochihito&apos;s Imperial order to the priests of the Daiji-sha Temple and the Minamoto clan who had yielded to power in various provinces across Japan to destroy the Taira clan, and &apos;MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna, the former Director of Izu Province&apos; was listed as the leader of the plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan to raise an army was communicated in the form of Prince Mochihito&apos;s Imperial order to the priests of the large-scale temples and shrines and the Minamoto clan who had yielded to power in various provinces across Japan to destroy the Taira clan, and &apos;MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna, the former Director of Izu Province&apos; was listed as the leader of the plan.</e>
<cmt>大寺社の訳語を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>5月になって挙兵計画は準備不足の段階で漏洩してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, however, the plan was discovered before it was ready to be executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, however, the plan was discovered before it was ready to be executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, however, the plan was discovered before it was ready to be executed.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>同年5月21日夜に父頼政、弟の兼綱らとともに自邸を焼いて京を退去し、園城寺に逃れていた以仁王と合流し挙兵の意思を明らかにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the night of May 21, Nakatsuna, together with his father Yorimasa and his younger brother Kanetsuna, set fire to his own residence and left the capital, met with Prince Mochihito at the Onjo-ji Temple where he had escaped to, and made clear his intention to raise an army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the night of May 21, Nakatsuna, together with his father Yorimasa and his younger brother Kanetsuna, set fire to his own residence and left the capital, met with Prince Mochihito at the Onjo-ji Temple where he had escaped, and made clear his intention to raise an army.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the night of June 22, Nakatsuna, together with his father Yorimasa and his younger brother Kanetsuna, set fire to his own residence and left the capital, met with Prince Mochihito at Onjo-ji Temple where he had escaped, and made clear his intention to raise an army.</e>
<cmt>theを省くグレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>だが、平家の調略で延暦寺は動かず、園城寺も危険になったため、奈良興福寺へ向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Taira family had prevented the priests of the Enryaku-ji Temple from following Nakatsuna, and also they were no longer safe at the Onjo-ji Temple; therefore, they left for the Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Taira family had prevented the priests of the Enryaku-ji Temple from following Nakatsuna, and also they were no longer safe at the Onjo-ji Temple; therefore, they left for Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Taira family had prevented the priests of Enryaku-ji Temple from following Nakatsuna, and also they were no longer safe at Onjo-ji Temple; therefore, they left for Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara.</e>
<cmt>寺院名のtheを省くCityを省く</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>26日に平知盛率いる追討軍に追いつかれ宇治川をはさんで平家方の大軍と合戦になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 26th, they were caught by the subjugation force led by TAIRA no Tomomori, and finally they entered a battle with the large Taira army with the Uji-gawa River as the frontline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 26th, they were caught by a subjugation force led by TAIRA no Tomomori, and finally entered into battle with the large Taira army with the Uji-gawa River as the frontline.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 27th, they were caught by a subjugation force led by TAIRA no Tomomori, and finally entered into battle with the large Taira army with the Uji-gawa River as the frontline.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>頼政と仲綱が大将となって防戦するが、平家方に強攻渡河されて防御陣は崩れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yorimasa and Nakatsune served as taisho to defend their army, the Taira army crossed the river to destroy the defending force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yorimasa and Nakatsune served as taisho to defend their army, the Taira army crossed the river to destroy the defending force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yorimasa and Nakatsuna served as taisho to defend their army, the Taira army crossed the river to destroy the defending force.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>仲綱らは以仁王を逃すべく平等院に籠って必死で戦い、仲綱はさんざんに戦い満身創痍になって平等院釣殿で自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakatsune fought hard inside the Byodo-in Temple to let Prince Mochihito escape, and after fighting and being wounded, he killed himself in the Tsuridono fishing pavilion of the Byodo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakatsune fought hard inside the Byodo-in Temple to let Prince Mochihito escape, and after fighting and being wounded, he killed himself in the Tsuridono fishing pavilion of the Byodo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakatsuna fought hard inside Byodo-in Temple to let Prince Mochihito escape, and after fighting and being wounded, he killed himself in the Tsuridono fishing pavilion of Byodo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス寺院名のtheを省く</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="28">
<j>老齢の父頼政は腹を切って自害し、頼政養子の源兼綱、源仲家（源義仲の兄）、仲綱嫡男・源宗綱らも最期をともにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Yorimasa committed hara-kiri, and MINAMOTO no Kanetsune who was an adopted son of Yorimasa, MINAMOTO no Nakaie (older brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka), and MINAMOTO no Munetsuna all died together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old Yorimasa committed hara-kiri, and MINAMOTO no Kanetsune who was an adopted son of Yorimasa, MINAMOTO no Nakaie (older brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka), and MINAMOTO no Munetsuna all died together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old Yorimasa committed seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), and MINAMOTO no Kanetsuna who was an adopted son of Yorimasa, MINAMOTO no Nakaie (older brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka), and MINAMOTO no Munetsuna all died together.</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストにhara-kiriは不可とあります。スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="29">
<j>仲綱の次男の源有綱は知行国の伊豆にいたため生き残り、伊豆での源頼朝の挙兵に参加、のち源義経の女婿となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Aritsuna, the second son of Nakatsuna, who had survived because he was in his chigyokoku (province that he was in charge of) Izu Province, joined MINAMOTO no Yoritomo when he raised an army in Izu Province, and later married a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Aritsuna, the second son of Nakatsuna, who had survived because he was in his chigyokoku (province that he was in charge of) Izu Province, joined MINAMOTO no Yoritomo when he raised an army in Izu Province, and later married a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Aritsuna, the second son of Nakatsuna, who had survived because he was in his chigyokoku (province that he was in charge of) Izu Province, joined MINAMOTO no Yoritomo when he raised an army in Izu Province, and later married a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), やりたこ(id:113528), 地図帳(id:122587), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), NPD(id:58640), 味っ子(id:17086), トホホ川(id:50502), Andee(id:20421), NDR(id:5500), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), 三郎太(id:172498), Sumaru(id:20609), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>