<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長嶺諸近</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAMINE no Morochika</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAMINE no Morochika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAMINE no Morochika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長嶺 諸近（ながみね の もろちか、生没年不詳）は、平安時代の対馬国の役人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAMINE no Morochika (year of birth and death unknown) was a government official of Tsushima Province in Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAMINE no Morochika (year of birth and death unknown) was a government official for Tsushima Province who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>コメント欄は空欄になっていましたが、ネイティブチェック済のようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAMINE no Morochika (year of birth and death unknown) was a government official for Tsushima Province who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>対馬国四等官代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Tsushima no kuni shitokandai.</e>
<cmt>「四等官代」の読み方は判明しましたが、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a fourth-ranked government official for the Province.</e>
<cmt>Please remind the translator that they need to translate this into meaningful English. A native speaker of English reading &quot;Tsushima no kuni shitokandai&quot; would have no idea what this is supposed to mean. I&apos;ve tried to track down an established translation for &quot;四等官代&quot; but have been unable to find one.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a fourth-ranked government official for the Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>刀伊の入寇の正体と、その賊船に連れ去られた日本人捕虜の消息を独自に調査し、大宰府に報告したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he did his own investigation of who the Toi was and whereabouts of Japanese captives kidnapped by the Toi&apos;s ship, and reported the findings to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>「刀伊の入寇の正体」の部分ですが、「刀伊の入寇」とは事件の名のため、「刀伊の正体」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he conducted his own investigation into who was behind the Toi invasion (the invasion of northern Kyushu by Jurchen pirates) and the whereabouts of the Japanese captives that were kidnapped and put aboard Toi ships, after which he reported his findings to the Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>The translation doesn&apos;t seem to include the nuance of &quot;入寇&quot; and gives no indication of what Toi is supposed to mean. You have to give the English speaker reading this at least some idea of what is being discussed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he conducted his own investigation into who was behind the Toi invasion (the invasion of northern Kyushu by Jurchen pirates) and the whereabouts of the Japanese captives that were kidnapped and put aboard Toi ships, after which he reported his findings to the Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>寛仁3年（1019年）刀伊の入寇の際に、諸近は、母、妻、妹、伯母、従者などと共に刀伊の賊船に連れ去られてしまうが、賊船が帰る途中に一人で脱出に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Toi invasion in 1019, Morochika was kidnapped by the Toi&apos;s ship with his mother, wife, sister, aunt, followers and so on, however, he won free from the ship by himself on the ship&apos;s way back to home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Toi invasion in 1019, Morochika was kidnapped by Toi&apos;s ship with his mother, wife, sister, aunt, followers and many others; but he broke free from the ship by himself on the ship&apos;s way back home.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため、一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Toi invasion in 1019, Morochika was kidnapped by Toi&apos;s ship with his mother, wife, sister, aunt, followers and many others; but he broke free from the ship by himself on the ship&apos;s way back home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、連れ去られた家族などを探すため、渡海の禁を破って高麗に密出国し、そこで、刀伊の賊の正体と賊に捕らわれた日本人の消息に付いて聞いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Morochika smuggled himself out of Japan to Goryeo breaking the prohibition against crossing across the sea to search for his kidnapped family and others, and asked there about who the Toi was and whereabouts of Japanese caught by the Toi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Morochika smuggled himself out of Japan to Goryeo, breaking the prohibition against crossing across the sea to search for his kidnapped family and the others, and asked who Toi was and the whereabouts of the Japanese caught by Toi.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞が一部抜けています。不要な箇所は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Morochika smuggled himself out of Japan to Goryeo, breaking the prohibition against crossing across the sea to search for his kidnapped family and the others, and asked who Toi was and the whereabouts of the Japanese caught by Toi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>すると、刀伊は服装や使う武器などから女真族ではないかと見られていて、最初に高麗の海岸付近の村々を襲って暴れまわり、その後、日本へ向って行ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, it was estimated that the Toi was the Joshin tribe judging from their costume and weapons, and after first they attacked villages near the coast of Goryeo and rampaged around there, they left for Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then found that Toi was assumed to have been the Joshin tribe judging from their costume and weapons, and that they had left for Japan after attacking villages near the coast of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため、全体を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then found that Toi was assumed to have been the Joshin tribe judging from their costume and weapons, and that they had left for Japan after attacking villages near the coast of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこで高麗軍は、刀伊がそのうち日本から戻って来るだろうと考えて待ち伏せしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goryeo Army ambushed the Toi because they thought that the Toi would have come back from Japan soon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Goryeo Army ambushed Toi because they believed that Toi would have returned from Japan soon.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため、一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Goryeo Army ambushed Toi because they believed that Toi would have returned from Japan soon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>すると、ほどなくして刀伊の船がやって来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, the Toi&apos;s ship was coming back, so the Goryeo Army engaged and wiped them out, and could save all Japanese caught by the Toi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, the Toi&apos;s ship came back.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, the Toi&apos;s ship came back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>高麗軍は、これを迎え撃って全滅させ、捕らわれていた日本人を全員救助したという事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Goryeo Army engaged and destroyed them, saving the Japanese caught by Toi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Goryeo Army engaged and destroyed them, saving the Japanese caught by Toi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、救助された人達の中には、悲しくも母、妻、妹、の姿は無く、家族は刀伊によって殺されてしまっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, tragically, Morochika could not find his mother, wife and sister in the people who were saved by the Goryeo Army and found that they were killed by Toi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tragically, however, Morochika could not find his mother, wife and sister in the people saved by the Goryeo Army and found that they were killed by Toi.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため、一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tragically, however, Morochika could not find his mother, wife and sister in the people saved by the Goryeo Army and found that they were killed by Toi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、さいわいにも伯母だけは殺されずに生き残っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But fortunately, only his aunt was alive without being killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But fortunately, his aunt was alive.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため、一部削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But fortunately, his aunt was alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>諸近は、救助された日本人の、内蔵石女と、多治見阿古見という二人の女の報告を添えて、事件の詳細を大宰府の太政官に提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morochika reported details of the invasion to Daijokan (Grand Council of State) of Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) with reports from two ladies; 石女 UCHIKURA and Akomi TAJIMI who were rescued from the Toi.</e>
<cmt>「石女」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morochika reported details of the invasion to the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) of Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) with reports from the two ladies; 石女 UCHIKURA and Akomi TAJIMI who were rescued from the Toi.</e>
<cmt>「石女」の読み方が不明です。定冠詞が抜けていたので、追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morochika reported details of the invasion to the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) of Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) with reports from the two ladies; 石女 UCHIKURA and Akomi TAJIMI who were rescued from the Toi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これによって大宰府は、刀伊の賊の正体と捕虜の消息を知る事が出来たのだが、渡海の禁を破って密出国した諸近は、罪人として禁固刑に処されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reports enabled the Dazai-fu to know what the Toi was and whereabouts of Japanese captives, but Morochika was sentenced to imprisonment as a violator who smuggled himself out of Japan by breaking the prohibition against crossing across the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reports enabled Dazai-fu to know who Toi was and the whereabouts of Japanese captives, but Morochika was sentenced to imprisonment as a violator who smuggled out of Japan, breaking the prohibition against crossing across the sea.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reports enabled the officials at Dazai-fu to learn who Toi was and the whereabouts of the Japanese captives, but Morochika, who had broken the prohibition against overseas travel, was imprisoned as a criminal.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後の事に付いては資料が何も残っていないため不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown what happened to him after that due to no record about him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since there is no record of what happened to him after that, his whereabouts are unknown.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため、全体を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there is no record of what happened to him after that, his whereabouts are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MioUzaki(id:89034), Nekomiminarikin(id:199247), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>