<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利義晴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 義晴（あしかが よしはる）は、室町幕府の第12代征夷大将軍（将軍在位：大永元年（1521年） - 天文15年（1546年））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA was the 12th Seii Taishogun (Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo) of the Muromachi Shogunate (shogunship from 1521 to 1546).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA was the 12th Seii Taishogun (Barbarian Subduing Generalissimo) of the Muromachi Shogunate (shogunship from 1521 to 1546).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA was the 12th Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi Shogunate (shogunship from 1521 to 1546).</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍、説明補足→(literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第11代将軍・足利義澄の長男、母は日野永俊の娘で日野富子の姪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of the 11th Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, and his mother was a daughter of Nagatoshi HINO, who was a niece of Tomiko HINO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of the eleventh shogun, Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, and his mother was a daughter of Nagatoshi HINO, who was a niece of Tomiko HINO.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of the eleventh shogun, Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, and his mother was a daughter of Nagatoshi HINO, who was a niece of Tomiko HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>弟に足利義維がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother was Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother was Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother was Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Personal History→Biographyに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>将軍就任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Installation as a Shogun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Installation as the Shogun</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Installation as the Shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>義晴の父・義澄は大内義興によって第10代将軍・足利義稙が擁立されて上洛してきた時、近江の六角高頼を頼って落ち延びていたが、その最中の永正8年（1511年）3月5日、義澄の長男として近江朽木で生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was enthroned by Yoshioki OUCHI as the 10th Shogun and entered Kyoto, Yoshiharu&apos;s father Yoshizumi fled from Kyoto to find shelter under Takayori ROKKAKU in Omi, and Yoshiharu was born as Yoshizumi&apos;s first son in Omi Kutsuki on March 5, 1511, on their flight to Omi.</e>
<cmt>「その最中」は on their flight to としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was enthroned by Yoshioki OUCHI as the tenth shogun and entered Kyoto, Yoshiharu&apos;s father Yoshizumi fled from Kyoto to find shelter under Takayori ROKKAKU in Omi, and Yoshiharu was born as Yoshizumi&apos;s first son in Omi Kutsuki on March 5, 1511, while en route to Omi.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was enthroned by Yoshioki OUCHI as the tenth shogun and entered Kyoto, Yoshiharu&apos;s father Yoshizumi fled from Kyoto to find shelter under Takayori ROKKAKU in Omi, and Yoshiharu was born as Yoshizumi&apos;s first son in Omi Kutsuki on March 5, 1511, while en route to Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、父は義晴が誕生した年の8月14日に朽木で死去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Yoshiharu&apos;s father died on August 14 in Kutsuki in the year he was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on August 14 in the year of his birth, Yoshiharu&apos;s father died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on August 14 in the year of his birth, Yoshiharu&apos;s father died in Kutsuki.</e>
<cmt>「朽木で」訳抜け</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>このため、永正11年（1514年）、義晴は播磨国に下向し、赤松義村の庇護を受けて養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Yoshiharu was brought to the Province of Harima in 1514 and raised under the protection of Yoshimura AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Yoshiharu was brought to the Province of Harima in 1514 and was raised under the protection of Yoshimura AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Yoshiharu was brought to the Province of Harima in 1514 and was raised under the protection of Yoshimura AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>大永元年（1521年）、父と対立して将軍職に再任していた足利義稙が、管領の細川高国と対立して京都から追放されたため、高国に擁立されて第12代将軍に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, who had opposed his father and reassumed the shogunship, was driven out from Kyoto as a result of his confrontation with Takakuni HOSOKAWA, kanrei or shogunal deputy, in 1521, Yoshiharu was supported by Takakuni to become the 12th Shogun.</e>
<cmt>「父と対立して」を読んだだけでは読者は何のことかよくわからないと思いますが、そのまま訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, who had opposed his father and reassumed the shogunship, had been driven out from Kyoto as a result of his confrontation with Takakuni HOSOKAWA, the kanrei (shogunal deputy), in 1521, Yoshiharu was supported by Takakuni to become the twelfth shogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, who had opposed his father and reassumed the shogunship, had been driven out from Kyoto as a result of his confrontation with Takakuni HOSOKAWA, the kanrei (shogunal deputy), in 1521, Yoshiharu was supported by Takakuni to become the twelfth shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>京都と近江の往復</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuttling between Kyoto and Omi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuttling Between Kyoto and Omi</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuttling Between Kyoto and Omi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>大永6年（1526年）、高国が家臣の香西元盛を殺害して細川氏で内紛が起こると、高国と対立していた細川晴元は、三好元長の援助を受けて義晴の弟・足利義維を擁立して高国と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takakuni killed one of his subordinates Motomori KOZAI to cause an internal strife in the Hosokawa Clan in 1526, Harumoto HOSOKAWA, who confronted with Takakuni, fought against Takakuni with the assistance of Motonaga MIYOSHI in order to try to enthrone Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, younger brother of Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takakuni killed one of his subordinates, Motomori KOZAI, in order to cause internal strife in the Hosokawa clan in 1526, Harumoto HOSOKAWA, who confronted Takakuni, fought against Takakuni with the assistance of Motonaga MIYOSHI in order to enthrone Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, the younger brother of Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takakuni killed one of his subordinates, Motomori KOZAI, in order to cause internal strife in the Hosokawa clan in 1526, Harumoto HOSOKAWA, who confronted Takakuni, fought against Takakuni with the assistance of Motonaga MIYOSHI in order to enthrone Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, the younger brother of Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>さらに元盛を殺したことで波多野稙通や柳本賢治らも挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni&apos;s murder of Motomori made Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO decide to stand against Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni&apos;s murder of Motomori made Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO decide to stand against Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni&apos;s murder of Motomori made Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO decide to stand against Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大永7年（1527年）に桂川の戦いで細川高国が破れると、実権を掌握した阿波国の国人・三好元長や細川晴元らによって京を追われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Takakuni HOSOKAWA lost in the Battle of Katsuragawa in 1527, and Yoshiharu was ousted from Kyoto by the new power holders such as Motonaga MIYOSHI, native bushi of the Province of Awa, and Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Takakuni HOSOKAWA lost the Battle of Katsuragawa in 1527, and Yoshiharu was ousted from Kyoto by those who were newly empowered, such as Motonaga MIYOSHI, a native bushi of Awa Province, and Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Takakuni HOSOKAWA lost the Battle of Katsuragawa in 1527, and Yoshiharu was ousted from Kyoto by those who were newly empowered, such as Motonaga MIYOSHI, a native bushi of Awa Province, and Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>享禄元年（1528年）には朽木稙綱 (戦国武将)を頼って近江国（現滋賀県）に落ち延び、元長らが擁立した堺公方・足利義維と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1528, Yoshiharu fled to the Province of Omi (present Shiga Prefecture) to seek shelter under Tanetsuna KUTSUKI, general of Sengoku period, and stood against Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, who was then called Sakai Kubo, head of Sakai-based municipal government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処堺公方の説明文を付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1528, Yoshiharu fled to Omi Province (present-day Shiga Prefecture) to seek shelter under Tanetsuna KUTSUKI, a general of Sengoku period, and stood against Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, who was then called Sakai Kubo, who was the head of the Sakai-based municipal government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1528, Yoshiharu fled to Omi Province (present-day Shiga Prefecture) to seek shelter under Tanetsuna KUTSUKI, a general of Sengoku period, and stood against Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, who was then called Sakai Kubo, who was the head of the Sakai-based municipal government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>享禄4年（1531年）、高国は天王寺の戦いに敗れて自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1531, Takakuni lost the Battle of Ten&apos;noji and killed himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1531, Takakuni lost the Battle of Ten&apos;noji and killed himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1531, Takakuni lost the Battle of Tennoji and killed himself.</e>
<cmt>Ten&apos;noji→&apos;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>戦後、今度は細川晴元と三好元長が対立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that battle, Harumoto HOSOKAWA and Motonaga MIYOSHI became antagonistic to each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the battle, Harumoto HOSOKAWA and Motonaga MIYOSHI became antagonistic toward one another.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the battle, Harumoto HOSOKAWA and Motonaga MIYOSHI became antagonistic toward one another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして、天文元年（1532年）に元長が細川晴元によって討たれた後、天文3年（1534年）には六角定頼・六角義賢父子の後援を得て晴元と和解し、帰京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, Motonaga was defeated by Harumoto HOSOKAWA in 1532, and Yoshiharu won the support of Sadayori ROKKAKU and his son Yoshitaka ROKKAKU, made peace with Harumoto and returned to Kyoto in 1534.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Motonaga was defeated by Harumoto HOSOKAWA in 1532, but Yoshiharu won the support of Sadayori ROKKAKU and his son Yoshitaka ROKKAKU, made peace with Harumoto and returned to Kyoto in 1534.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Motonaga was defeated by Harumoto HOSOKAWA in 1532, but Yoshiharu won the support of Sadayori ROKKAKU and his son Yoshitaka ROKKAKU, made peace with Harumoto and returned to Kyoto in 1534.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、その後も晴元と対立して敗れたのち、和解して帰京するといった行動を繰り返しており、天文10年（1541年）には近江坂本に逃れ、天文11年（1542年）には京都へ帰還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Yoshiharu&apos;s relationship with Harumoto never stayed calm; on the contrary it was always unstable as the shogun confronted his greatest supporter, lost in a battle against him, escaped to Omi Sakamoto in 1541, made peace with him and returned to Kyoto in 1541.</e>
<cmt>「行動を繰り返す」については、「関係は決して落ち着いたものではなかった。その逆で将軍は・・・・するなど、常に不安定だった」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshiharu&apos;s relationship with Harumoto never stayed calm; on the contrary, it was always unstable as the shogun confronted his greatest supporter, lost in a battle against him, escaped to Omi Sakamoto in 1541, made peace with him and returned to Kyoto in 1541.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshiharu&apos;s relationship with Harumoto never stayed calm; on the contrary, it was always unstable as the shogun confronted his greatest supporter, lost in a battle against him, escaped to Omi Sakamoto in 1541, made peace with him and returned to Kyoto in 1541.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天文12年（1543年）には近江に再び逃れるなどしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But then again he fled to Omi in 1543.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, he fled to Omi again in 1543.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, he fled to Omi again in 1543.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>将軍職譲渡と最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transfer of Shogunship and Death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transfer of Shogunship and Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transfer of Shogunship and Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>天文15年（1546年）、義晴は晴元と対立して敗れ（江口の戦い）、近江坂本に避難したが、このときに嫡男・足利義輝に将軍職を譲り、以後は幼少の義輝の後見人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1546, Yoshiharu fought Harumoto (in the Battle of Eguchi), lost and escaped to Omi Sakamoto, during which time he gave shogunship to his son and heir to throne Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA and helped the still juvenile Shogun as his guardian.</e>
<cmt>「嫡男」を「息子であり王座の継承者である」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1546, Yoshiharu fought Harumoto (in the Battle of Eguchi), lost and escaped to Omi Sakamoto, during which time he gave the shogunship to his son and heir to the throne, Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and helped the still juvenile shogun as his guardian.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1546, Yoshiharu fought Harumoto (in the Battle of Eguchi), lost and escaped to Omi Sakamoto, during which time he gave the shogunship to his son and heir to the throne, Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and helped the still juvenile shogun as his guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、晴元と和睦して義輝と共に京都に戻るが、天文18年（1549年）には晴元と晴元の重臣・三好長慶が対立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Yoshiharu came to terms with Harumoto and returned to Kyoto together with Yoshiteru, but Harumoto came to antagonize one of his senior vassals, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, Yoshiharu came to terms with Harumoto and returned to Kyoto together with Yoshiteru, but Harumoto became antagonistic toward one of his senior vassals, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, Yoshiharu came to terms with Harumoto and returned to Kyoto together with Yoshiteru, but Harumoto became antagonistic toward one of his senior vassals, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>晴元は敗れ、義晴は義輝と共に近江朽木谷に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto was defeated by Nagayoshi, and Yoshiharu fled to Omi Kutsuki-dani together with Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto was defeated by Nagayoshi, and Yoshiharu fled to Omi Kutsuki-dani together with Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto was defeated by Nagayoshi, and Yoshiharu fled to Omi Kutsuki-dani together with Yoshiteru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>天文19年（1550年）5月4日、近江穴太（現在の滋賀県大津市穴太 (大津市)）にて死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 4, 1550, Yoshiharu died at Omi Anou (present Anou, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>穴太は「あのう」http://www.shipping.jp/zipcode/zip/5200114.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 4, 1550, Yoshiharu died at Omi Anou (the present-day Anou, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 4, 1550, Yoshiharu died at Omi Ano (the present-day Anou, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Anou→Ano</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomb</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomb</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomb</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>義晴地蔵寺（現在の大阪府交野市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu Jizo-ji Temple (present Katano City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu Jizo-ji Temple (in the present-day Katano City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu Jizo-ji Temple (in the present-day Katano City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、「近江國滋賀郡誌」（明治14年（1881年））には、「頼珍逆修」と刻まれた彼の墓が穴太に現存すると記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Accounts on Shiga District of the Province of Omi published in 1881, however, mentions his tomb with an inscription of &quot;Raichin-gyakushu&quot; exists at Anou.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Accounts of the Shiga District in the Province of Omi,&quot; published in 1881, states that his tomb with tthe inscription &quot;Raichin-gyakushu&quot; exists at Anou.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Accounts of the Shiga District in the Province of Omi,&apos; published in 1881, states that his tomb with tthe inscription &apos;Raichin-gyakushu&apos; exists at Ano.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にAnou→Ano</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Record of Official Title and Rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Record of Official Titles and Ranks</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of Official Titles and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*Dates are all based on the lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>訳抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1521年（大永元年）7月28日、従五位下に叙す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 28, 1521, Yoshiharu was given the rank of Jugoi-ge (Junior Fifth Low Court Rank).</e>
<cmt>北条時政の説明では「下」は 最後ではなく、Low Court Rank とあり、こちらのほうが自然だと思いますので、こちらに統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 28, 1521, Yoshiharu was given the rank of Jugoi-ge (junior fifth court low rank).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 28, 1521: Yoshiharu was given the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>従五位下→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)On July 28, 1521,→July 28, 1521:に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>11月24日、元服し、義晴と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was renamed as Yoshiharu upon his coming of age on November 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was renamed as Yoshiharu upon his coming of age on November 24.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 24: He was renamed as Yoshiharu upon his coming of age.</e>
<cmt>November 24: He was renamed as Yoshiharu upon his coming of age.に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>11月25日、正五位下に昇叙し、左馬頭に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Shogoi-ge (Senior Fifth Low Court Rank) and assumed Samanokami (Minister of the Horse Office of the Left) on November 25.</e>
<cmt>官位については、最初にローマ字読みをしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Shogoi-ge (senior fifth low court rank) and assumed Samanokami (the minister of the Horse Office of the Left) on November 25.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 25: He was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assumed Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>正五位下→Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)左馬頭→Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses)November 25: を前に出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>併せて征夷大将軍宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he was appointed Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concurrently, he was appointed Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concurrently, he was appointed Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>1522年（大永2年）2月17日、従四位下に昇叙し、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 17, 1522, he was promoted to Jushimi-ge (Junior Fourth Low Court Rank) and became a sangi (Councillor).</e>
<cmt>従は「じゅ」とよみ、四位は「しみ」、三位は「さんみ」と読むそうです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 17, 1522, he was promoted to Jushimi-ge (junior fourth low court rank) and became a sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 17, 1522: He was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) and became a sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>従四位下→Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade)On February 17, 1522, he→February 17, 1522: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>左近衛中将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also assumed Sakon&apos;e-no-Chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also assumed Sakon&apos;e-no-Chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also assumed Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>左近衛中将→Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>1530年（享禄3年）1月20日、従三位に昇叙し、権大納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 20, 1530, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Court Rank) and transferred to the title of Gon-Dainagon (Deputy Chief of the Councillor of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 20, 1530, he was promoted to Jusanmi (junior third court rank) and transferred to the title of Gon-Dainagon (the deputy chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 20, 1530: He was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and transferred to the title of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>従三位→Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)権大納言→Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor)On January 20, 1530, he→January 20, 1530: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>1546年（天文 (元号)15年）12月20日、右近衛大将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 20, 1546, he also assumed Ukon&apos;e-no-Daisho (General of Imperial Guard of the Right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 20, 1546, he also assumed Ukon&apos;e-no-Daisho (general of Imperial Guard of the Right).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 20, 1546: He also assumed Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>右近衛大将→Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)On December 20, 1546, he→December 20, 1546: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>同日、征夷大将軍を辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned Seii Taishogun on the same day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from the post of Seii Taishogun on the same day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from the post of Seii Taishogun on the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>1550年（天文19年）4月4日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on April 4, 1550.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on April 4, 1550.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 4, 1550: He died.</e>
<cmt>He died on April 4, 1550.→April 4, 1550: He died.に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>5月7日、贈従一位、左大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 7, he was posthumously raised to Juichi&apos;i (Junior First Court Rank) and Sadaijin (Ministry of the Left).</e>
<cmt>文語、ということで、posthumously を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 7, he was posthumously elevated to Juichi&apos;i (junior first court rank) and Sadaijin (Ministry of the Left).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 7, he was posthumously elevated to Juichii (Junior First Rank) and Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>従一位→Juichii (Junior First Rank)左大臣→Sadaijin (minister of the left)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>義晴の偏諱を受けた人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Persons who were granted the use of part of the characters of Yoshiharu&apos;s name</e>
<cmt>「偏諱を受けた」は、termsのところの定義をもとにわかりやすく変えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Persons who were granted the use of characters from Yoshiharu&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Persons who were granted the use of characters from Yoshiharu&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>北畠晴具</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harutomo KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harutomo KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harutomo KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>近衛前久（晴嗣）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakihisa (Harutsugu) KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakihisa (Harutsugu) KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakihisa (Harutsugu) KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>二条晴良</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haruyoshi NIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haruyoshi NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruyoshi NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>尼子晴久</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haruhisa AMAKO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haruhisa AMAKO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruhisa AMAGO</e>
<cmt>尼子晴久→Haruhisa AMAGO</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>伊達晴宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumune DATE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>武田信玄（晴信）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingen (Harunobu) TAKEDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingen (Harunobu) TAKEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingen (Harunobu) TAKEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>長尾晴景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harukage NAGAO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harukage NAGAO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harukage NAGAO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>南部晴政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumasa NAMBU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumasa NAMBU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumasa NANBU</e>
<cmt>南部晴政→Harumasa NANBU</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>細川晴元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 花蝶風月雪月花警部(id:163674), 諏訪太郎頼光(id:98476), ドルチェット(id:46458), Ittyon(id:1348), Nnh(id:474), 瑞雲(id:27410), Cprobot(id:97843), 麝香(id:89874), Eskimbot(id:29676), Rai koku(id:1661), Ash Crow(id:26765), Kamakura(id:472), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Alex K(id:86829), Joney john j(id:42271), でここ(id:9565), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), Sho-gun(id:74168), Kouko0515(id:100370), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Carbuncle(id:346), Lombroso(id:20212), たね(id:10372), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Daranome(id:1429), Yanahan(id:2437), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Escarbot(id:59151), Tanuki Z(id:612), ひろくん(id:79638), BrevamBot(id:29583), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>