<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中山忠親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadachika NAKAYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadachika NAKAYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadachika NAKAYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中山 忠親（なかやま ただちか、天承元年（1131年）頃 － 建久6年3月12日 (旧暦)（1195年4月23日））は平安時代の公卿、通称を中山内大臣といい、中山家の始祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadachika NAKAYAMA (around 1131 - April 23, 1195) was a court noble who lived in the Heian period, was commonly called Nakayama Naidaijin (Nakayama, the minister of the center) and was the founder of the Nakayama family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadachika NAKAYAMA (around 1131 - April 23, 1195) was a court noble who lived in the Heian period, was commonly called Nakayama Naidaijin (Nakayama, the minister of the center) and was the founder of the Nakayama family.</e>
<cmt>Capital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadachika NAKAYAMA (around 1131 - April 30, 1195) was a court noble who lived in the Heian period, was commonly called Nakayama Naidaijin (Nakayama, the minister of the center) and was the founder of the Nakayama family.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原忠宗の三男で、母は藤原家保の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Tadamune and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Tadamune and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Tadamune and his mother was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>太政大臣の花山院忠雅は同母兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamasa KAZANIN, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state), was his elder brother from the same mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamasa KAZANIN, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state), was his elder brother from the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamasa KAZANIN, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state), was his elder brother from the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>室に藤原光房女・平時忠女らがおり、子に中山兼宗・中山忠季・中山兼季・中山忠明・親覚・雅明・覚敒・親慶・三条公房室らがいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A FUJIWARA no Mitsufusa&apos;s daughter and a TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s daughter were his wives, and Kanemune NAKAYAMA, Tadasue NAKAYAMA, Kanesue NAKAYAMA, Tadaaki NAKAYAMA, Shinkaku, Masaaki, Kakujo, Shinkei and a concubine of Kinfusa SANJO were his children.</e>
<cmt>親覚・雅明・覚敒：　これらの正確な読みは、確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wives were FUJIWARA no Mitsufusa&apos;s daughter and a daughter of TAIRA no Tokitada, and his children were Kanemune NAKAYAMA, Tadasue NAKAYAMA, Kanesue NAKAYAMA, Tadaaki NAKAYAMA, Shinkaku, Masaaki, Kakujo, Shinkei and a concubine of Kinfusa SANJO.</e>
<cmt>GrammarChanged word order- I think FUJIWARA no Mitsufusa only had one daughter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wives were FUJIWARA no Mitsufusa&apos;s daughter and a daughter of TAIRA no Tokitada, and his children were Kanemune NAKAYAMA, Tadasue NAKAYAMA, Kanesue NAKAYAMA, Tadaaki NAKAYAMA, Shinkaku (親覚), Masaaki (雅明), Kakujo (覚敒), Shinkei and a concubine of Kinfusa SANJO.</e>
<cmt>読みが不確かなため、Shinkaku (親覚), Masaaki (雅明), Kakujo (覚敒) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『山槐記』の作者として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known as the writer of &quot;Sankaiki (a diary).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is known for his diary &quot;Sankaiki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordyPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is known for his diary &quot;Sankaiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また『水鏡』の作者にも擬せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he might be the writer of &quot;Mizu Kagami (literally, water mirror: a book on historical stories)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he might be the writer of the historical tale &quot;Mizu Kagami (literally, water mirror)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he might be the writer of the historical tale &quot;Mizu Kagami&quot; (literally, water mirror).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>保延6年（1140年）従五位下となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given Jugoinoge (junior fifth rank,lower grade) in 1140.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given Jugoinoge (junior fifth rank,lower grade) in 1140.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1140.</e>
<cmt>「従五位下」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>蔵人、近衛府・中将、蔵人頭を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed the posts of Kurodo (chamberlain), Chujo (middle captain) at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) and Kurodo no to (head chamberlain) in succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was successively Kurodo (Chamberlain), Chujo (Middle Captain) at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) and Kurodo-no-to (Head Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>HyphensRevised for clarityCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was successively Kurodo (Chamberlain), Chujo (Middle Captain) at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、ハイフンをとり、Kurodo no toとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）参議、仁安 (日本)2年（1167年）従三位権中納言、さらに右衛門督・検非違使別当となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Sangi (councilor) in 1164, Gon Chunagon (provisional middle counselor) at Jusani (junior third rank) in 1167 and later, Uemon no kami (captain of the right division of outer palace guards) and then Kebiishi no betto (superintendent of the imperial police).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Sangi (councilor) in 1164, Gon-Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) at Jusani (junior third rank) in 1167 and later, Uemon-no-kami (Captain of the right division of the outer palace guards) and then Kebiishi-no-betto (Superintendent of the imperial police).</e>
<cmt>HyphensCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Sangi (councilor) in 1164, Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state) at Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1167 and later, Uemon no kami (Captain of the right division of the outer palace guards) and then Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the imperial police).</e>
<cmt>「権中納言」「従三位」→統一リストの表記に修正、Uemon-no-kami、Kebiishi-no-bettoのハイフン消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>兄と同様に平氏一門と親しく、平徳子に中宮権大夫・建礼門院別当として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being also intimate with members of the Taira clan, like his elder brothers, he attended Taira no Tokuko as Chugu Gon no daibu (provisional master of the consort&apos;s household) or as Kenreimonin no Betto (chief officer serving to Kenreimonin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like his elder brothers, he was intimate with members of the Taira clan and he served Taira no Tokuko as Chugu-Gon-no-daibu (provisional master of the consort&apos;s household) and later as Kenreimonin-no-Betto (chief officer serving Kenreimonin).</e>
<cmt>HyphensPrepostion</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like his elder brothers, he was intimate with members of the Taira clan and he served TAIRA no Tokuko as Chugu Gon no daibu (provisional master of the consort&apos;s household) and later as Kenreimonin no Betto (chief officer serving Kenreimonin).</e>
<cmt>Taira no Tokuko→TAIRA no Tokukoに修正、Chugu-Gon-no-daibu、Kenreimonin-no-Bettoのハイフン消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後白河法皇の院庁別当にも名を連ね、「年来礼儀作法の道を営む、当時頗るその褒（ほまれ）あり」（『玉葉』）と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also became Innocho Betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) for Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and his behavior is described in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (a diary of Kanezane KUJO) that he was engaged in the ways of etiquette for years and was praised extensively then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also became Innocho-Betto (Chief Administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) for Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and his behavior is described in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary) as having &quot;engaged in the ways of etiquette for years and he now receives great praise&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also became Innocho-Betto (Chief Administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) for Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and his behavior is described in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary) as having &apos;engaged in the ways of etiquette for years and he now receives great praise.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>治承三年の政変では、解官された甥・花山院兼雅に代わって春宮大夫となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the coup in 1179, he was appointed to Togu no daibu (the master of the crown prince&apos;s quarters), replacing Kanemasa KAZANIN, his nephew, who was dismissed from the post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a coup in 1179, he was appointed to Togu-no-daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters), replacing his dismissed nephew, Kanemasa KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt>ArticleHyphensCapital lettersRevised for brevity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a coup in 1179, he was appointed to Togu no daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters), replacing his dismissed nephew, Kanemasa KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt>Togu-no-daibuのハイフン消去、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）正月に正二位権大納言となるが、同年7月に平氏一門が都落ちした後は昇進が停滞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) at Shonii (senior second rank) in early January of 1183, but after the Taira clan escaped from the capital in July of the same year, his ascendancy in the government rank became sluggish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Gon-Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) at Shonii (senior second rank) in early January 1183, but after the Taira clan fled the capital in July of the same year, his rise came to a halt.</e>
<cmt>HyphensCapital lettersPrepositionRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) at Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in early February 1183, but after the Taira clan fled the capital in July of the same year, his rise came to a halt.</e>
<cmt>「正二位」「権大納言」→統一リストに基づき表記を修正、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>文治元年（1185年）12月、頼朝から有職の公卿であることを評価されて、議奏公卿に推挙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting Yoritomo&apos;s evaluation of being a court noble with a government position, he was recommended for Giso kugyo (noble council) in December of 1185.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December of 1185, after being evaluated by Yoritomo as a court noble wotrhy of a government position, he was recommended for the Giso-kugyo (Council of Nobles) in December of 1185.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of 1185, after being evaluated by Yoritomo as a court noble wotrhy of a government position, he was recommended for the Giso-kugyo (Council of Nobles).</e>
<cmt>In December of 1185→重複しているため文末の表記を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>建久2年（1191年）に内大臣に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1191, he was appointed to Naidaijin (the minister of the center).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1191, he was appointed to Naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt>Capital lettersPreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1191, he was appointed to Naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>建久5年（1194年）に出家して静和と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1194, he became a priest and called himself Seiwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1194, he became a priest and took the name Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1194, he became a priest and took the name Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>翌年3月に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was died in March of the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in March of the next year.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in April of the next year.</e>
<cmt>冒頭の日付(新暦)に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 松茸(id:27535), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>