<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源義光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 義光（みなもと の よしみつ）は、平安時代後期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu was busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu was a late Heian-period military commander.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>河内源氏の二代目棟梁である源頼義の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, the head (second generation) of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, the head (second generation) of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, who was the second-generation leader of the Kawachi-Genji (of the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>源義家や源義綱の弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the younger brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the younger brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the younger brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>近江国の新羅明神（大津園城寺）で元服したことから新羅三郎（しんらさぶろう）と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Shinra-Saburo because he celebrated his coming of age at Shinra Myojin (Onjo-ji Temple in Otsu) in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Shinra-Saburo because he celebrated his coming of age at Shinra Myojin (Onjo-ji Temple in Otsu) in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Shinra-Saburo because he celebrated his coming of age at Shinra Myojin (Onjo-ji Temple in Otsu) in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>後三年の役の時に苦戦する兄の源義家を助けるため都での官位を捨てて奥州へ向った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He discarded his official rank in the capital and went to Oshu to help his older brother MINAMOTO no Yoshiie who was having a hard battle in Gosannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He discarded his official rank in the capital and went to Oshu to help his older brother MINAMOTO no Yoshiie who was facing hard times in his battle in Gosannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his older brother MINAMOTO no Yoshiie became hard-pressed during the Gosannen no Eki (The Latter Three Years&apos; War), Yoshimitsu, who was in the capital, renounced his court rank and headed for Oshu (Mutsu province) in order to help.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>役の後、常陸国の有力豪族の常陸平氏（吉田一族）から妻を得て、その勢力を自らの勢力としていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, he got a wife from Hitachi-Heishi (Taira clan) (Yoshida family), influential Gozoku (local ruling family) of Hitachi Province, and incorporated its power into his own power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, he married his wife from Hitachi-Heishi (Taira clan) (Yoshida family),an influential Gozoku (local ruling family) of Hitachi Province, and incorporated its power into his own power.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, he was able to marry a daughter of the Hitachi Taira clan (specifically, the Yoshida family), thereby making their strength his own.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に遅れて常陸に進出してきた甥の源義国（足利氏や新田氏の祖）と争って合戦に及び勅勘を蒙る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He battled against his nephew MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni (ancestor of Ashikaga clan and Nitta clan), who extended himself into Hitachi after Yoshimitsu, and was punished by Imperial order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He battled his nephew MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni (ancestor of Ashikaga clan and Nitta clan), who had pushed into Hitachi after Yoshimitsu, and was punished by Imperial decree.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought with his nephew MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni (the ancestor of both the Ashikaga and Nitta clans), who had advanced into Hitachi well after Yoshimitsu, but was punished by imperial decree for fighting this battle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>義家の没後に野心をおこし、河内源氏の棟梁の座を狙った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Yoshiie, he became highly ambitious to obtain the position of the head of Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Yoshiie, he became ambitious, trying to obtain a position as head of Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshiie died, Yoshimitsu&apos;s ambitions grew, and he started aiming to become the head of the Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その手段として、弟の快誉と共謀し、義家の後継者として源氏の棟梁となっていた甥の源義忠、及び次兄の源義綱の両者を滅ぼす算段を練った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To obtain the position of the head, he colluded with his younger brother Kaiyo and worked out to kill his nephew MINAMOTO no Yoshitada, who was the head of the Minamoto clan as a successor of Yoshiie, and his older brother MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to obtain this position, he colluded with his younger brother Kaiyo and sought to kill his nephew MINAMOTO no Yoshitada, who was the head of the Minamoto clan and a successor of Yoshiie, together with his older brother MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to accomplish this, he plotted with his younger brother Kaiyo to destroy both his nephew MINAMOTO no Yoshitada, who as Yoshiie&apos;s successor had become the leader of the Minamoto clan, and his older brother MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>まず郎党の藤原季方を義綱の子の源義明の郎党として送り込み、次いで妻方の縁戚の平成幹（鹿島三郎）を義忠の郎党として送り込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, he sent out his retainer FUJIWARA no Suekata as a retainer of MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki, Yoshitsuna&apos;s child, and then TAIRA no Narimoto (Saburo KASHIMA), a relative of Yoshimitsu&apos; wife, as a retainer of Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, he sent out his retainer FUJIWARA no Suekata as a retainer of MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki, Yoshitsuna&apos;s child, and then TAIRA no Narimoto (Saburo KASHIMA), a relative of Yoshimitsu&apos; wife, as a retainer of Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First he dispatched his retainer FUJIWARA no Suekata to serve as a retainer to MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki, who was Yoshitsuna&apos;s son, and next sent TAIRA no Narimoto (also known as Saburo KASHIMA), a relative of Yoshimitsu&apos;s wife, to serve as a retainer to Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>そして1109年の春、義光は藤原季方に義明の刀を奪うように命じ、その刀を成幹に与え、義忠暗殺の密命を下したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the spring of 1109, Yoshimitsu ordered FUJIWARA no Suekata to deprive Yoshiaki of his sword, gave the sword to Narimoto to secretly order him to assassinate Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the spring of 1109, Yoshimitsu ordered FUJIWARA no Suekata to deprive Yoshiaki of his sword, giving the sword to Narimoto to secretly order him to assassinate Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, in the spring of 1109, Yoshimitsu ordered FUJIWARA no Suekata to steal Yoshiaki&apos;s sword and give it to Narimoto, secretly ordering him to assassinate Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その結果、義忠は闘死（いわゆる「源義忠暗殺事件」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Yoshitada was killed (the so-called &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshitada assassination&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Yoshitada was killed (the so-called &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshitada assassination&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this plot, Yoshitada was killed (in what is known as &quot;The Assassination of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>その現場に残された刀が源義明のものであることから、義忠暗殺の嫌疑は義明とその父である義綱に向けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the fact that the sword left at the site was MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki&apos;s sword, Yoshiaki and his father Yoshitsuna were suspected of the assassination of Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the fact that the sword left at the site was MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki&apos;s sword, Yoshiaki and his father Yoshitsuna were suspected of the assassination of Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the sword left lying next to where the assassination had occurred was MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki&apos;s, Yoshiaki and his father Yoshitsuna fell under suspicion of having assassinated Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして、義綱一族は、義光の勢力圏である甲賀山で義忠の養子である源為義によって討たれるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, Yoshitsuna&apos;s family were killed by MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, the adopted child of Yoshitada, in Mt. Koka, the Yoshimitsu&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, Yoshitsuna&apos;s family were killed by MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, the adopted child of Yoshitada, in Mt. Koka, the Yoshimitsu&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, Yoshitsuna&apos;s whole family was killed at Mt. Koka, which was inside Yoshimitsu&apos;s sphere of influence, by MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, the adopted son of Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>だが、実際に若年の為義が指揮をとっていたわけではなく、その背後には義光がいた（いわゆる「源義綱冤罪事件」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in fact young Tameyoshi did not lead the assassination but Yoshimitsu controlled Tameyoshi from behind the scenes (the so-called &quot;a case of false accusation of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in fact young Tameyoshi did not lead the assassination but was controlled from behind the scenes (the so-called &quot;a case of false accusation of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna&quot;) by Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In actuality, however, it was not Tameyoshi who orchestrated the massacre of Yoshitsuna&apos;s family (in what became known as the &quot;False Accusation of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna&quot;) but Yoshimitsu, who was directing everything behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、義綱の郎党の藤原季方、鹿島三郎も義光（及びその指示を受けた園城寺の僧で義光の実弟の快誉）らの手によって殺害され、事件の真相は闇の中へ消え行くはずであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, FUJIWARA no Suekata, the retainer of Yoshitsuna, and Saburo KASHIMA were also killed by Yoshimitsu (and Kaiyo, the priest of Onjo-ji Temple and the younger brother of Yoshimitsu upon order) and the fact of the assassination was thus going to be hushed up.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, FUJIWARA no Suekata, the retainer of Yoshitsuna, and Saburo KASHIMA were also killed by Yoshimitsu (and Kaiyo, the priest of Onjo-ji Temple and the younger brother of Yoshimitsu upon order) afterwhich the assassination was covered up.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, FUJIWARA no Suekata, Yoshitsuna&apos;s retainer, and Saburo KASHIMA were also murdered on Yoshimitsu&apos;s orders (as was Kaiyo, a monk of Onjo-ji Temple who was also Yoshimitsu&apos;s biological younger brother) in order to ensure that the plot would never come to light.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>だが、その真相が発覚し、義光は勢力の強い常陸国に逃亡せざるを得なくなり、源氏の棟梁への野望は潰えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the truth was revealed and therefore Yoshimitsu was forced to expel to Hitachi Province, where his influence was strong, and to discard his ambition of becoming the head of Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the truth was revealed and therefore Yoshimitsu was expelled to Hitachi Province, where his influence was strong. As a result he had to discard his ambition of becoming the head of Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the truth came out, and Yoshimitsu was forced to flee to Hitachi province (where his power and influence remained strong), his dream of becoming the head of the Minamoto clan in tatters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>その最期については、三井寺で死去したとする説が有力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is widely believed that Yoshimitsu died at Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is widely believed that Yoshimitsu died at Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is widely believed that Yoshimitsu died at Mii-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>病死とする説と、殺害説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that he died of disease or he was killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that he died of disease or he that he was killed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other theories claim that he died of disease or was murdered.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>殺害説では、自身が暗殺した源義忠の遺児、河内経国に討たれたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the theory that he was killed, he was killed by Tsunekuni KAWACHI, the bereaved child of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada who Yoshimitsu assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory that says he was killed, it was done by Tsunekuni KAWACHI, the bereaved child of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada who Yoshimitsu assassinated.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one such theory which claims he was murdered, the killer is believed to have been Tsunekuni KAWACHI, the bereaved son of MINAMOTO no Yoshitada, whose assassination had been orchestrated by Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>義光の甥義忠の暗殺は源氏の凋落を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The assassination of Yoshimitsu&apos;s nephew Yoshitada led to the fall of Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The assassination of Yoshimitsu&apos;s nephew Yoshitada led to the fall of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The assassination of Yoshimitsu&apos;s nephew Yoshitada led to the fall of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>源氏の凋落は院政の陰謀も原因であるが、源氏内部での暗闘も衰退の原因であり、その内部の暗闘の中心人物は義光であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the causes of the fall of Minamoto clan was a conspiracy by the cloister government, as well as the behind-the-scenes battle inside the Minamoto clan; Yoshimitsu was the key figure of the behind-the-scenes battle inside the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the causes of the fall of the Minamoto clan was a conspiracy by the cloister government, as well as the behind-the-scenes battle inside the Minamoto clan; Yoshimitsu was a key figure in the behind-the-scenes battle inside the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One cause of the downfall of the Minamoto clan was the conspiracy in the cloister government, while another was the secret infighting going on within the Minamoto clan; in such infighting among the Minamoto clan, the major figure was Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、義光の子孫が、武田氏、佐竹氏、小笠原氏、南部氏と発展していったことを考えると一族の繁栄に対する義光の功績は偉大である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in view of the fact that the prosperity of the descendants of Yoshimitsu continued as Takeda clan, Satake clan, Ogasawara clan, and Nanbu clan, the achievements made by Yoshimitsu for the prosperity of the family were significant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in view of the fact that the descendants of Yoshimitsu prospered as the Takeda clan, Satake clan, Ogasawara clan, and Nanbu clan, his achievements for the family could be said to be significant.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, since Yoshimitsu&apos;s descendants--which include the Takeda, Satake, Ogasawara, and Nanbu clans--ended up flourishing, Yoshimitsu&apos;s contributions to the family&apos;s prosperity could actually be seen as quite significant.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>兄の義家が河内源氏の棟梁として河内源氏全体の利益を図ったのに対して、義光は自身の利益を優先し、結果的に地方に所領を拡大することで、勢力を扶植していったともいえ、対照的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to Yoshimitsu&apos;s older brother Yoshiie who, as a head of Kawachi-Genji, attempted to benefit the entire Kawachi-Genji, Yoshimitsu focused more on his own benefits, resulting in the expansion of his territories in the provinces to establish his influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to Yoshimitsu&apos;s older brother Yoshiie who, as head of Kawachi-Genji, attempted to benefit the entire Kawachi-Genji, Yoshimitsu focused more on his own benefits, resulting in the expansion of his territories in the provinces, establishing his influence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In stark contrast to his older brother Yoshiie, who used his position as head of the Kawachi-Genji to benefit the entire clan, Yoshimitsu&apos;s first priority was benefiting himself, and as a result he greatly expanded the amount of territory under his control, thereby magnifying his own power and influence.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その結果、河内源氏の嫡流が衰退した時期やその後の復興の過程（源頼朝の鎌倉幕府の成立）でも、義光系の一族の帰趨が大きな影響を与えており、義光の施策は源氏の復興に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, even in the decline of the direct descendants of Kawachi-Genji or in the subsequent recovery processes (i.e., Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) established by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo), the outcome of the family line of Yoshimitsu had a great impact: therefore, the measures took by Yoshimitsu contributed to the recovery of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, even in the decline of the direct descendants of Kawachi-Genji or in the subsequent recovery (i.e., Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) established by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo), the outcome of the family line of Yoshimitsu had a great impact: therefore, it can be said that the measures took by Yoshimitsu contributed to the recovery of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, even in the period during which the main lineage of the Kawachi-Genji fell into decline, and during its subsequent revitalization (with the establishment of the Kamakura shogunate by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo), Yoshimitsu&apos;s own lineage continued to have enormous influence over the clan at large, and Yoshimitsu&apos;s policies contributed to the revival of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>また古武道の大東流合気柔術では、義光を開祖としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Daito-ryu Aikijujutsu, the old Japanese martial arts, Yoshimitsu is considered to be a founder of the school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu is considered to be a founder of the school of Daito-ryu Aikijujutsu, an old Japanese martial art..</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu is also considered the founder of the Daito-ryu Aikijujutsu (a type of Jujutsu), an ancient Japanese martial art style.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>音楽を好み、笙を豊原時元に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu was fond of music and was taught Sho (Japanese flute) by TOYOHARA no Tokimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu was fond of music and was taught Sho (Japanese flute) by TOYOHARA no Tokimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu was fond of music and was taught Sho (Japanese flute) by TOYOHARA no Tokimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>後三年の役で兄義家の救援に赴く際、相模国足柄峠で笙を吹き、時元の遺子である豊原時秋に学びし所を尽く授けて訣別したという逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote that, when Yoshimitsu went to help his older brother Yoshiie in the Gosannen no Eki, he played Sho on Ashigara-toge Path in Sagami Province and taught TOYOHARA no Tokiaki, a bereaved child of Tokimoto, what he had learned from Tokimoto, in parting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote that, when Yoshimitsu went to help his older brother Yoshiie in the Gosannen no Eki, he played Sho on Ashigara-toge Path in Sagami Province and taught TOYOHARA no Tokiaki, a bereaved child of Tokimoto, what he had learned from Tokimoto, in parting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One anecdote holds that when Yoshimitsu went to help his older brother Yoshiie in the Gosannen no Eki, he played the Sho (a type of flute) on the Ashigara-toge Pass in Sagami province, and taught TOYOHARA no Tokiaki, the orphaned son of Tokimoto, everything he had learned from Tokimoto as a parting gift.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>墓所は滋賀県大津市園城寺町。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is in Onjoji-cho, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is in Onjoji-cho, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is in Onjoji-cho, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>また、生誕地と思われる河内源氏の本拠地の河内国石川郡 (大阪府)壷井（現在の大阪府羽曳野市壷井）にある河内源氏の氏神の壷井八幡宮と並ぶ壷井権現に、祖父源頼信、父源頼義、兄源義家、兄源義綱と共に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tsuboi-gongen, next to Tsuboi Hachiman-gu Shrine which enshrines ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) of Kawachi-Genji, located in Tsuboi, Ishikawa Country, Kawachi Province (present-day Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture), where Yoshimitsu was believed to be born and Kawachi-Genji was based, Yoshimitsu is enshrined with his grandfather MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, father MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, older brothers MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tsuboi-gongen, next to Tsuboi Hachiman-gu Shrine which enshrines ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) of Kawachi-Genji, located in Tsuboi, Ishikawa Country, Kawachi Province (present-day Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture), where Yoshimitsu was believed to be born and Kawachi-Genji was based, Yoshimitsu is enshrined with his grandfather MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, father MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, older brothers MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu is enshrined with his grandfather MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, his father MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, and his older brothers MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna at Tsuboi-gongen, which is next to Tsuboi Hachiman-gu shrine, where the ujigami (the guardian deity) of the Kawachi-Genji is enshrined; Tsuboi-gongen is located in Tsuboi in Ishikawa county of Kawachi province (present-day Tsuboi in the city of Habikino in Osaka Pref.), which was the seat of the Kawachi-Genji&apos;s power as well as where Yoshimitsu is believed to have been born.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>なお、戒名は佐竹家の伝承によれば崇源院殿義光尊了。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the oral tradition of Satake family, Yoshimitsu&apos;s posthumous Buddhist name is Sugen-in dono Yoshimitsu Sonryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the oral tradition of the Satake family, Yoshimitsu&apos;s posthumous Buddhist name is Sugen-in dono Yoshimitsu Sonryo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the orally transmitted legends of the Satake family, Yoshimitsu&apos;s posthumous Buddhist name was &quot;Sugen-in dono Yoshimitsu Sonryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 阿波座行広(id:39667), やりたこ(id:113528), 諏訪太郎頼光(id:98476), 与左衛門(id:159462), Stanislaus(id:1806), 花いちもんめ(id:39081), 表現等規制委員会(id:61918), 味っ子(id:17086), Yanahan(id:2437), 葉月(id:25674), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), Masyu(id:31065), Carkuni(id:79281), １３２人目(id:18687), JOKER(id:22180), Otoshigo(id:80102), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 木林森(id:10796), 代言人(id:33675), Point136(id:211299), ASAMA501(id:91947), Junger(id:10282), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>