<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原保忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasutada</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasutada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasutada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原保忠（ふじわらのやすただ、寛平2年（890年） - 承平 (日本)6年7月14日 (旧暦)（936年8月3日））は平安時代前・中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasutada (890- August 3, 936) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) in the early part and middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasutada (890- August 3, 936) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) in the early part and middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasutada (890- August 8, 936) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) in the early part and middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原時平の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Tokihira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Tokihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Tokihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄弟に藤原顕忠、藤原敦忠がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akitada and FUJIWARA no Atsutada were his brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akitada and FUJIWARA no Atsutada were his brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akitada and FUJIWARA no Atsutada were his brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>八条大納言と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the name Hachijo Dainagon as his go (byname).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the name Hachijo Dainagon as his go (byname).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the name Hachijo Dainagon as his go (byname).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>笙の名手だったが、父時平の早世で藤原氏の嫡流が叔父の藤原忠平に移ったため、大納言に出世したのは930年(延長 (日本)8年)12月の事であり、忠平や従兄弟の藤原実頼、藤原師輔に比べやや遅れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a master of Sho (Japanese flute) and assigned to Dainagon (Major Counselor) on December 930, which was a little later than FUJIWARA no Tadahira, his uncle, and FUJIWARA no Saneyori and FUJIWARA no Morosuke, his cousins, because his father Tokihira died early and Tadahira succeeded the family estates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a master of Sho (Japanese flute) and assigned to Dainagon (Major Counselor) on December 930, which was a little later than FUJIWARA no Tadahira, his uncle, and FUJIWARA no Saneyori and FUJIWARA no Morosuke, his cousins, because his father Tokihira died early and Tadahira succeeded the family estates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a master of Sho (Japanese flute) and assigned to Dainagon (chief councilor of state) on December 930, which was a little later than FUJIWARA no Tadahira, his uncle, and FUJIWARA no Saneyori and FUJIWARA no Morosuke, his cousins, because his father Tokihira died early and Tadahira succeeded the family estates.</e>
<cmt>Dainagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>右大将も兼任したが、一生の大半を父に讒言され、大宰府に左遷された菅原道真の怨霊に怯えながら過ごす事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also assigned to Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), but he had been slandered by his father during almost all his life and had lived with scaring the vengeful ghost of SUGAWARA no Michizane, who had been relegated to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also assigned to Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), but he had been slandered by his father almost all his life and had lived with under the fear of being haunted by the vengeful ghost of SUGAWARA no Michizane, who had been relegated to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also assigned to Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), but he had been slandered by his father almost all his life and had lived with under the fear of being haunted by the vengeful ghost of SUGAWARA no Michizane, who had been relegated to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>保忠が病床に伏せ、祈祷のため僧侶に薬師如来の読経をさせた途中、金毘羅の名前が出た事を聞いた途端に発狂し（近衛大将である自分を縊るのだと思ったという）、まもなく絶命した（『大鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yasutada was sick in bed and made a monk chant the sutra of Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha) for prayer, as soon as he heard the name of kompira (guardian deity of seafaring), he went mad (it is said that he, Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards), thought to be killed) and died in a short time (&quot;Okagami&quot; (the Great Mirror)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yasutada was sick in bed, he chanted a sutra of Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha) as a prayer, as soon as he heard the name of kompira (guardian deity of seafaring), he went mad (it is said that he, Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards), thought to be killed) and died a short time later (&quot;Okagami&quot; (the Great Mirror)).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yasutada was sick in bed, he chanted a sutra of Yakushi Nyorai (the Healing Buddha) as a prayer, as soon as he heard the name of konpira (guardian deity of seafaring), he went mad (it is said that he, Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards), thought to be killed) and died a short time later (&quot;Okagami&quot; (the Great Mirror)).</e>
<cmt>kompira→konpiraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Yonoemon(id:55450), Snap55(id:89773), Cprobot(id:97843), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>