<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上杉重房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigefusa UESUGI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigefusa UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigefusa UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上杉重房（うえすぎ しげふさ、生没年不詳）は鎌倉時代中期の公家、武士である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigefusa UESUGI (it is unknown when he was born and when he died) was a court noble and samurai who lived in the middle of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigefusa UESUGI (dates of birth and death unknown) was a court noble and samurai who lived in the middle of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigefusa UESUGI (dates of birth and death unknown) was a court noble and samurai who lived in the middle of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>上杉氏の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uesugi clan started from him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the founder of the Uesugi Clan.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the founder of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>Clanの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>別称を式乾門院蔵人、官位は修理大夫・左衛門督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Shikikenmonin Kurodo (the chamberlain of shikikenmonin), and his government positions were Shuri no daibu (the master of the office of palace repairs) and Saemon no kami (the captain of the left division of outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Shikikenmonin Kurodo (the chamberlain of Shikikenmonin), and his government positions were Shuri-no-daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs) and Saemon-no-kami (Captain of the Left Division of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>HyphensCapital LettersArticles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Shikikenmonin Kurodo (the chamberlain of Shikikenmonin), and his government positions were Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs) and Saemon no kami (Captain of the Left Division of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、Shuri-no-daibu、Saemon-no-kamiのハイフン消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子は上杉頼重、山名政氏室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorishige UESUGI and a concubine of Masauji YAMANA were his children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorishige UESUGI and a concubine of Masauji YAMANA were his children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorishige UESUGI and a wife of Masauji YAMANA were his children.</e>
<cmt>a concubine of Masauji YAMANA→「室」のみの表記であるため、a wife of Masauji YAMANAとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal history</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;His&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>京都の中級公家であった、左衛門尉勧修寺清房（藤原北家藤原高藤流）の二子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the second child of Kiyofusa KAJUJI (originated in FUJIWARA no Takafuji of Hokke (the northen house) of the Fujiwara clan) who was a middle-class court noble in Kyoto and assumed Saemon no jo (a third-ranked officer of the left Division of outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second child of Kiyofusa KAJUJI (a descendant of FUJIWARA no Takafuji of the Northern House (Hokke) of Fujiwara), a mid-ranking court noble from Kyoto who held the position of Saemon-no-jo (Lieutenant of the Left Division of the Outer Palace guards).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second child of Kiyofusa KAJUJI (a descendant of FUJIWARA no Takafuji of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan), a mid-ranking court noble from Kyoto who held the position of Saemon no jo (Lieutenant of the Left Division of the Outer Palace guards).</e>
<cmt>「藤原北家」→統一リストの表記に修正、Saemon-no-joのハイフン消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1252年（建長4年）、後嵯峨天皇の皇子宗尊親王が鎌倉幕府第6代征夷大将軍に就任するが、重房はその介添えとして共に鎌倉へ下向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Prince Munetaka, a son of Emperor Gosaga assumed the sixth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general for subduing the barbarians&quot;) in 1252, Shigefusa moved to Kamakura together with the prince as his attendant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Prince Munetaka, a son of Emperor Gosaga, became the sixth Shogun in 1252, Shigefusa moved to Kamakura together with the prince to be his attendant.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationRevised for brevity, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Imperial Prince Munetaka, a son of Emperor Gosaga, became the sixth Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in 1252, Shigefusa moved to Kamakura together with the prince to be his attendant.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Munetakaとし、「鎌倉幕府第6代征夷大将軍」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>丹波国何鹿郡上杉庄（京都府綾部市上杉町周辺）を賜り、以後あらたに上杉氏を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded Uesugi-sho, Ikaruga County, Tanba Province (around present Uesugi-cho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), and thereafter he used Uesugi as his family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded Uesugi-sho, Ikaruga County, Tanba Province (around present-day Uesugi-cho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), and thereafter he used Uesugi as his family name.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;-day&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded Uesugi-sho, Ikaruga County, Tanba Province (around present-day Uesugi-cho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), and thereafter he used Uesugi as his family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>1266年（文永3年）、宗尊親王は謀反の疑いにより帰京させられるが、重房はそのまま鎌倉にとどまって武士となり、幕府に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Munetaka was forced to return to the capital on suspicion of a rebellion in 1266, but he remained in Kamakura to become a samurai and worked for the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Munetaka was forced to return to the capital on suspicion of rebellion in 1266, but Shigefusa remained in Kamakura, becoming a samurai and working for the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Article&quot;he&quot;→&quot;Shigefusa&quot;Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Munetaka was forced to return to the capital on suspicion of rebellion in 1266, but Shigefusa remained in Kamakura, becoming a samurai and working for the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Munetakaとし、the shogunate→the bakufuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>やがて有力御家人足利泰氏に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he became to work for Yasuuji ASHIKAGA, a powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he served Yasuuji ASHIKAGA, a powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he served Yasuuji ASHIKAGA, a powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>the shogunate→the bakufuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>重房の妹（娘？）が足利頼氏の家女房となり、以後、上杉氏は姻戚関係を通じて足利家中で権勢を得るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger sister (or his daughter?) became Yoriuji ASHIKAGA&apos;s Ie no Nyobo (a lady-in-waiting), and after that, the Uesugi clan became to be dominant in the Ashikaga family through marriage relationships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger sister (or his daughter?) became Yoriuji ASHIKAGA&apos;s Ie-no-Nyobo (lady-in-waiting), and after that, through inter-marriage, the Uesugi Clan became very influential in the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger sister (or his daughter?) became Yoriuji ASHIKAGA&apos;s Ie no Nyobo (lady-in-waiting), and after that, through inter-marriage, the Uesugi clan became very influential in the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>Ie-no-Nyoboのハイフン消去、Clanの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この婚姻は、足利氏が、もともと公家で朝廷とのコネクションがあった上杉氏を重要視した結果といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uesugi clan came from a court noble, and it is said that these marriages were made because the Ashikaga clan put importance on the Uesugi clan&apos;s connections with the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that these marriages were made because the Ashikaga Clan valued the connections the Uesugi Clan, as former court nobles, had with the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that these marriages were made because the Ashikaga clan valued the connections the Uesugi clan, as former court nobles, had with the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Clanの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>また、重房の孫娘上杉清子は、足利貞氏に嫁して後の征夷大将軍足利尊氏やその弟の足利直義を産んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyoko UESUGI, his granddaughter, married Sadauji ASHIKAGA and gave birth to Takauji ASHIKAGA, later Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general for subduing the barbarians&quot;) and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyoko UESUGI, his granddaughter, married Sadauji ASHIKAGA and gave birth to Takauji ASHIKAGA, who later becmae Shogun, and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>SpaceRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoko UESUGI, his granddaughter, married Sadauji ASHIKAGA and gave birth to Takauji ASHIKAGA, who later became Seii Taishogun, and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>becameのスペルミス修正、Shogun→Seii Taishogunとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、その清子の弟は題目宗の僧となって日静と名乗り、京本圀寺や越後国三条本成寺（新潟県三条市）の住職となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A younger brother of Kiyoko became a priest of Daimokushu (a Nichiren sect), called himself Nichijo, and became the chief priest of Honkoku-ji Temple in Kyoto and that of Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province (present Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A younger brother of Kiyoko became a priest of Daimokushu (a Nichiren sect), called himself Nichijo, and became the chief priest of Honkoku-ji Temple in Kyoto and Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province (present Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;that of&quot;Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A younger brother of Kiyoko became a priest of Daimokushu (a Nichiren sect), called himself Nichijo, and became the chief priest of Honkoku-ji Temple in Kyoto and Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province (present Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>師の名僧日印が幕府の殿中で全宗派を論破したことについて「鎌倉殿中問答」として書き残すことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he wrote &quot;Kamakura denchu mondo (literally, questions and answers in a hall of the Kamakura bakufu)&quot; describing how Nichiin, his mentor and a great priest, refuted arguments of all of the other Buddhist sects in a hall of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he wrote &quot;Kamakura denchu mondo (literally, questions and answers in a hall of the Kamakura Shogunate)&quot;, describing how his mentor, the great priest Nichiin, refuted arguments of all of the other Buddhist sects in a hall of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>&quot;bakufu&quot;→&quot;Shogunate&quot;PunctuationRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he wrote &apos;Kamakura Denchu Mondo&apos; (literally, questions and answers in a hall of the Kamakura bakufu), describing how his mentor, the great priest Nichiin, refuted arguments of all of the other Buddhist sects in a hall of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Kamakura Denchu Mondoとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更、位置を移動、Shogunate→bakufuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>墓所・法名 不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Where he was buried and what was his posthumous Buddhist name were unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Where he was buried and what his posthumous Buddhist name was are unknown.</e>
<cmt>Word orderTense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Where he was buried and what his posthumous Buddhist name was are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>鎌倉明月院に木造上杉重房坐像（国の重要文化財）が所蔵されている（鎌倉国宝館に寄託）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sitting statue of Shigefusa UESUGI is kept at Meigetsu-in Temple in Kamakura (a national important cultural property) (is entrusted to Kamakura Museum of National Treasures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sitting statue of Shigefusa UESUGI (a national important cultural property) is owned by Meigetsu-in Temple in Kamakura (entrusted to Kamakura Museum of National Treasures)</e>
<cmt>Word orderRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A seated statue of Shigefusa UESUGI (a national important cultural property) is owned by Meigetsu-in Temple in Kamakura (entrusted to Kamakura Museum of National Treasures).</e>
<cmt>「坐像」→統一リストの表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Wikipediasherpa(id:97571), 伏儀(id:142093), Urania(id:7213), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>