<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉良義信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu KIRA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉良 義信（きら よしのぶ、生没年不詳）は室町時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu KIRA, whose birth and death year is unknown, was a &quot;busho&quot; (Japanese military commander) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu KIRA, whose birth and death year is unknown, was a &quot;busho&quot; (Japanese military commander) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu KIRA, whose birth and death year is unknown, was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>吉良義真の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the heir of Yoshizane KIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the heir of Yoshizane KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the heir of Yoshizane KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>西条城主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he was the chatelain of Saijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he was the chatelain of Saijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he was the chatelain of Saijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>西条吉良氏（上吉良）5代目。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fifth heir of the Saijo Kira clan (the Kami Kira family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fifth heir of the Saijo Kira clan (the Kami Kira family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fifth heir of the Saijo Kira clan (the Kami Kira family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幼名は三郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was &quot;Saburo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was &quot;Saburo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Saburo.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>官途は従四位下、左兵衛佐、治部大輔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank and title in the Imperial Court reached &quot;Jushiinoge&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), &quot;Sahyoe no suke&quot; (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), and &quot;Jibu taifu&quot; (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of the Civil Administration).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank and title in the Imperial Court reached &quot;Jushiinoge&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), &quot;Sahyoe no suke&quot; (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), and &quot;Jibu taifu&quot; (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of the Civil Administration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank and title in the Imperial Court reached Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), and Jibu taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of the Civil Administration).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子は吉良義元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son was Yoshimoto KIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son was Yoshimoto KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son was Yoshimoto KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>応仁の乱が起こると、父吉良義真は三河国の本領を攻撃し始めた東条吉良氏の吉良義藤の後を追って、応仁元年（1467年）5月18日に京都を発ち三河へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Onin War broke out, Yoshinobu&apos;s father Yoshizane KIRA left Kyoto for Mikawa Province on June 28, 1467, chasing Yoshifuji KIRA of the Tojo Kira clan who began to attack Yoshizane&apos;s fief in Mikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Onin War broke out, Yoshinobu&apos;s father Yoshizane KIRA left Kyoto for Mikawa Province on June 28, 1467, chasing Yoshifuji KIRA of the Tojo Kira clan who began to attack Yoshizane&apos;s fief in Mikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Onin War broke out, Yoshinobu&apos;s father Yoshizane KIRA left Kyoto for Mikawa Province on June 28, 1467, chasing Yoshifuji KIRA of the Tojo Kira clan who began to attack Yoshizane&apos;s fief in Mikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その際、子の義信は同行させず、将軍足利義政に近侍させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Yoshizane made his son Yoshinobu attend to the shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, instead of allowing to come with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Yoshizane made his son Yoshinobu attend the shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, instead of allowing him to come with him.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Yoshizane made his son Yoshinobu attend the shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, instead of allowing him to come with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>応仁元年8月18日、細川勝元は将軍に近侍する奉公衆の中に西軍に味方する者がいるとして、将軍御所を囲み人の出入りを厳重に調べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 25, 1467, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA laid siege to the Shogun&apos;s palace and checked the people coming in and out of the palace, saying some busho in &quot;Hokoshu&quot; (Shogun&apos;s direct controlled army) took the side of the western camp in the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 25, 1467, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA laid siege to the Shogun&apos;s palace and checked people coming in and out of the palace, saying some busho in &quot;Hokoshu&quot; (Shogun&apos;s direct controlled army) took the side of the western camp in the war.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 25, 1467, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA laid siege to the Shogun&apos;s palace and checked people coming in and out of the palace, saying some busho in Hokoshu (Shogun&apos;s direct controlled army) took the side of the western camp in the war.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>勝元が後土御門天皇にこのことを奏上すると、天皇は大納言三条公春と吉良義信を使いとして勝元に対し、西軍与同の者の姓名を記し追放するよう命令する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Katsumoto&apos;s reporting about this, Emperor Gotsuchimikado ordered him through messengers, Yoshinobu KIRA &amp; &quot;Dainagon&quot; (Major Counselor) Kimiharu SANJO, to make clear the name of busho taking the western side and to expel them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Katsumoto&apos;s reporting about this, Emperor Gotsuchimikado ordered him through messengers, Yoshinobu KIRA &amp; &quot;Dainagon&quot; (Major Counselor) Kimiharu SANJO, to clearly announce the name of busho while taking the western side and to expelling them.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Katsumoto&apos;s reporting about this, Emperor Gotsuchimikado ordered him through messengers, Yoshinobu KIRA and Dainagon (chief councilor of state) Kimiharu SANJO, to clearly announce the name of busho while taking the western side and to expelling them.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除、&amp;→andに修正、Dainagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして調査の結果、23日に12名の名を書いた名簿が将軍義政に提出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And on investigation, twelve names of busho were listed, and the list was handed in to the shogun Yoshimasa on September 30.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And on investigation, twelve names of busho were listed, and the list was handed in to the shogun Yoshimasa on September 30.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And on investigation, twelve names of busho were listed, and the list was handed in to the shogun Yoshimasa on September 30.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>義政は天皇と同様に三条公春と吉良義信の二人を使いにして、名簿に挙がった12名の者に対し御所を退出するよう命令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just like the emperor, Yoshimasa ordered the listed twelve busho to leave the Shogun palace through messengers Kimiharu SANJO &amp; Yoshinobu KIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just like the emperor, Yoshimasa ordered the listed twelve busho to leave the Shogun palace through messengers Kimiharu SANJO &amp; Yoshinobu KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just like the emperor, Yoshimasa ordered the listed twelve busho to leave the Shogun palace through messengers Kimiharu SANJO and Yoshinobu KIRA.</e>
<cmt>&amp;→andに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>が、12名は憤りが収まらずその場で合戦の支度を始めてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the twelve busho got furious at the list, and they began to prepare for the battle on the spot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelve busho became furiou, and they prepared for battle on the spot.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelve busho became furious, and they prepared for battle on the spot.</e>
<cmt>furiou→furiousに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同じ日に山名宗全の兵が内裏へ乱入し天皇・太上天皇を拉致するという噂が流れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day, it was rumored that the forces of Sozen YAMANA would break into &quot;Dairi&quot; (the Imperial Palace) and abduct Emperor and &quot;Daijo tenno&quot; (the Retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same day, it was rumored that the forces of Sozen YAMANA would break into &quot;Dairi&quot; (the Imperial Palace) and abduct Emperor and &quot;Daijo tenno&quot; (the Retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same day, it was rumored that the forces of Sozen YAMANA would break into Dairi (the Imperial Palace) and abduct Emperor and Daijo tenno (the Retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そこで義信は武者頭として禁中警護に当り、再度、三条とともに名簿の12名に対し、天皇・将軍の命令として御所退出を促し、説得に成功、御所から脱出させている（『応仁記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So Yoshinobu guarded the Imperial Palace as the top-ranking warrior, and he urged the listed 12 once again with Sanjo to go out of the Shogun&apos;s palace in the name of the Emperor &amp; the Shogun, and he at last persuaded them into going out (cf. &quot;Oninki&quot; [The Record of the Onin War]).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So Yoshinobu guarded the Imperial Palace as the top-ranking warrior, and he urged the listed 12 once again with Sanjo leave the Shogun&apos;s palace in the name of the Emperor &amp; the Shogun, and he at last persuaded them into exiting the premises (cf. &quot;Oninki&quot; [The Record of the Onin War]).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So Yoshinobu guarded the Imperial Palace as the top-ranking warrior, and he urged the listed 12 once again with Sanjo leave the Shogun&apos;s palace in the name of the Emperor and the Shogun, and he at last persuaded them into exiting the premises (cf. &quot;Oninki&quot; [The Record of the Onin War]).</e>
<cmt>&amp;→andに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>9月1日、西軍の攻撃により多くの武家の邸宅が炎上したが、吉良邸はその筆頭に挙げられている（『応仁記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oninki says the western camp burned down many samurai residences on October 8, and Kira&apos;s one was mentioned on its top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oninki says the western camp burned down many samurai residences on October 8, and Kira&apos;s one was mentioned on its top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oninki says the western camp burned down many samurai residences on October 8, and Kira&apos;s one was mentioned on its top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>10月、義信には伯父に当る先代吉良義尚が京に於いて病没している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November (or December), Yoshinobu&apos;s uncle &quot;Yoshinao KIRA&quot; died from a disease in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November (or December), Yoshinobu&apos;s uncle &quot;Yoshinao KIRA&quot; died from a disease in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November (or December), Yoshinobu&apos;s uncle Yoshinao KIRA died from a disease in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>応仁の乱が終結すると、義信は父義真とともに近衛政家ら公家との交際を積極的に展開、政家の日記『後法興院記』に度々名前が表れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Onin War ended, Yoshinobu actively developed the association with court nobles including &quot;Masaie KONOE&quot; along with his father Yoshizane, so the name of Noshinobu frequently appeared in &quot;Gohokoinki&quot; (Diary of Masaie KONOE).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Onin War ended, Yoshinobu actively developed an association with court nobles including &quot;Masaie KONOE&quot; along with his father Yoshizane, so the name of Noshinobu frequently appeared in &quot;Gohokoinki&quot; (Diary of Masaie KONOE).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Onin War ended, Yoshinobu actively developed an association with court nobles including Masaie KONOE along with his father Yoshizane, so the name of Noshinobu frequently appeared in &quot;Gohokoinki&quot; (Diary of Masaie KONOE).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Masaie KONOE&quot;のクォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>文明 (日本)13年（1481年）7月21日に義真が没するとしばらく喪に服し、同年12月26日に家督相続後初めて幕府に出仕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshizane died on August 25, 1481, Yoshinobu was in mourning for some time, and on January 24, 1482, he went to work for the Muromachi shogunate for the first time after his succession to the family headship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshizane died on August 25, 1481, Yoshinobu was in mourning for some time, and on January 24, 1482, he went to work for the Muromachi shogunate for the first time after his succession to the family headship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshizane died on August 25, 1481, Yoshinobu was in mourning for some time, and on January 24, 1482, he went to work for the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) for the first time after his succession to the family headship.</e>
<cmt>the Muromachi shogunate→the Muromachi bakufuとし、初出のためbakufuの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>長享元年（1487年）の足利義尚による近江国六角高頼攻めに従軍、延徳3年（1491年）の足利義稙による再度の六角攻めにも従軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1487, Yoshinobu served in a war waged by &quot;Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA&quot; against &quot;Takayori ROKKAKU&quot; in Omi Province, and in 1491, Yoshinobu served again in a war waged by &quot;Yoshitane ASHIKAGA&quot; against the same enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1487, Yoshinobu served in a war waged by &quot;Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA&quot; against &quot;Takayori ROKKAKU&quot; in Omi Province, and in 1491, Yoshinobu served again in a war waged by &quot;Yoshitane ASHIKAGA&quot; against the same enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1487, Yoshinobu served in a war waged by Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA against Takayori ROKKAKU in Omi Province, and in 1491, Yoshinobu served again in a war waged by Yoshitane ASHIKAGA against the same enemy.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>明応2年（1493年）、明応の政変で義材が失脚、足利義澄が新将軍となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1493, Yoshiki (Yoshitane) lost his position in Coup of Meio, and Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA became the new shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1493, Yoshiki (Yoshitane) lost his position in the Coup of Meio, and Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA became the new shogun.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1493, Yoshiki (Yoshitane) lost his position in the Coup of Meio, and Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA became the new shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この後も義信はしばらくの間、幕府出仕を続けるが、明応7年（1498年）12月に至り病と称して出仕を止め、以後明応10年（1501年）までの3年間屋敷に引き篭っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For some time after that, Yoshinobu continued to work for the Muromachi shogunate, but in December 1498 (by the lunar calendar), he pretended to be sick and stopped working for the shogunate, and thereafter until 1501, he stayed in his residence for three years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For some time after that, Yoshinobu continued to work for the Muromachi shogunate, but in December 1498 (by the lunar calendar), he pretended to be sick and stopped working for the shogunate, and thereafter until 1501, he stayed in his residence for three years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For some time after that, Yoshinobu continued to work for the Muromachi bakufu, but in January and February of 1499, he pretended to be sick and stopped working for the bakufu, and thereafter until 1501, he stayed in his residence for three years.</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、December 1498 (by the lunar calendar)→January and February of 1499とし、the Muromachi shogunate→the Muromachi bakufu、およびthe shogunate→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この間、西国に走った前将軍義材（義尹）と連絡をとっていたのかも知れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presumably, he might keep contact during the period with the former shogun Yoshiki (Yoshitada) who fled to a province lying to the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presumably, he might have kept contact during this period with the former shogun Yoshiki (Yoshitada) who had fled to a province lying to the west.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presumably, he might have kept contact during this period with the former shogun Yoshiki (Yoshitada) who had fled to a province lying to the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>永正4年（1507年）6月、細川政元が養子細川澄之の手の者に殺害され、澄之ともう一人の養子細川澄元との間で合戦が起きると、義信は30人程の手勢で禁中警護に当っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1507 (by the lunar calendar), &quot;Masamoto HOSOKAWA&quot; was killed by men of his adopted child &quot;Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA,&quot; and a fight broke out between Sumiyuki and Masamoto&apos;s another adopted child &quot;Sumimoto HOSOKAWA,&quot; so Yoshinobu guarded the Imperial Palace with about 30 soldiers under his command.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1507 (by the lunar calendar), &quot;Masamoto HOSOKAWA&quot; was killed by men of his adopted child &quot;Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA,&quot; and a fight broke out between Sumiyuki and Masamoto&apos;s another adopted child &quot;Sumimoto HOSOKAWA,&quot; so Yoshinobu guarded the Imperial Palace with about 30 soldiers under his command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between July and August of 1507, Masamoto HOSOKAWA was killed by men of his adopted child Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, and a fight broke out between Sumiyuki and Masamoto&apos;s another adopted child Sumimoto HOSOKAWA, so Yoshinobu guarded the Imperial Palace with about 30 soldiers under his command.</e>
<cmt>In June 1507 (by the lunar calendar)→Between July and August of 1507に修正、クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>永正5年（1508年）6月8日、前将軍義尹（義稙）が入京すると、義信は一条室町の自邸を将軍の仮御所として提供、将軍に復位した義尹はここで犬追物や能を開催している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 15, 1508, the former shogun Yoshitada (Yoshitane) entered Kyoto, when Yoshinobu provided Yoshitada with his own residence in Ichijo Muromachi as the temporary shogun&apos;s palace, and Yoshitada held &quot;inuoumono&quot; (a dog-hunting event) and &quot;noh&quot; (a Japanese musical dance drama) there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 15, 1508, the former shogun Yoshitada (Yoshitane) entered Kyoto, when Yoshinobu provided Yoshitada with his own residence in Ichijo Muromachi as the temporary shogun&apos;s palace, and Yoshitada held &quot;inuoumono&quot; (a dog-hunting event) and &quot;noh&quot; (a Japanese musical dance drama) there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 15, 1508, the former shogun Yoshitada (Yoshitane) entered Kyoto, when Yoshinobu provided Yoshitada with his own residence in Ichijo Muromachi as the temporary shogun&apos;s palace, and Yoshitada held Inuoumono (a dog-hunting event) and Noh (a Japanese musical dance drama) there.</e>
<cmt>Inuoumono、Nohとし、クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="27">
<j>永正8年（1511年）8月16日、細川澄元の京都侵攻により将軍義尹は丹波国に逃げるが、義信はこれに随行、同日将軍仮御所であった吉良邸は焼き討ちにあい焼亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 18, 1511, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA advanced into Kyoto, so Shogun Yoshitada fled to Tanba Province and Yoshinobu accompanied Yoshitada, and on the same day, Kira&apos;s residence, used as the temporary shogun&apos;s palace, was set on fire and was burned down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 18, 1511, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA advanced into Kyoto, so Shogun Yoshitada fled to Tanba Province and Yoshinobu accompanied Yoshitada, and on the same day, Kira&apos;s residence, which was being used as a temporary palace for the shogun, was set on fire and burned down.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 18, 1511, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA advanced into Kyoto, so Shogun Yoshitada fled to Tanba Province and Yoshinobu accompanied Yoshitada, and on the same day, Kira&apos;s residence, which was being used as a temporary palace for the shogun, was set on fire and burned down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>船岡山合戦により澄元の兵は敗走、義信は義尹とともに帰洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the forces of Sumimoto was routed in &quot;Funaokayama-no-kassen&quot; (the Battle at Mt. Funaoka), so Yoshinobu returned to Kyoto with Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the forces of Sumimoto were routed in &quot;Funaokayama-no-kassen&quot; (the Battle at Mt. Funaoka), so Yoshinobu returned to Kyoto with Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the forces of Sumimoto were routed in the Battle at Mt. Funaoka, so Yoshinobu returned to Kyoto with Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Funaokayama-no-kassen&quot; (the Battle at Mt. Funaoka)→the Battle at Mt. Funaokaのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>翌永正9年（1512年）2月24日、新装成った吉良邸に大内義興らを招いて酒宴が催される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 22, 1512, a banquet was held in the reconstructed Kira&apos;s residence, inviting &quot;Yoshioki OUCHI&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 22, 1512, a banquet was held in the reconstructed Kira&apos;s residence, where &quot;Yoshioki OUCHI&quot; and others were invited.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 22, 1512, a banquet was held in the reconstructed Kira&apos;s residence, where Yoshioki OUCHI and others were invited.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション、スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>永正13年（1516年）10月4日、嫡子吉良義元に先立たれた義信は嫡孫吉良義尭に家督を譲る（『室町家御内書案』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outliving his heir Yoshimoto KIRA, Yoshinobu transferred his family headship to his legitimate grandson Yoshitaka KIRA on November 8, 1516 (cf. &quot;Muromachike Gonaishoan&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outliving his heir Yoshimoto KIRA, Yoshinobu transferred his family headship to his legitimate grandson Yoshitaka KIRA on November 8, 1516 (cf. &quot;Muromachike Gonaishoan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outliving his heir Yoshimoto KIRA, Yoshinobu transferred his family headship to his legitimate grandson Yoshitaka KIRA on November 8, 1516 (cf. &quot;Muromachike Gonaishoan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>義信の没年月日は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu&apos;s death date is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu&apos;s death date is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu&apos;s death date is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>法名は常楽院殿峻山棟公大禅定門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name is &quot;Jorakuinden shunzantoko daizenteimon.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name is &quot;Jorakuinden shunzantoko daizenteimon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name is Jorakuinden Shunzantoko Daizenteimon (常楽院殿峻山棟公大禅定門).</e>
<cmt>Jorakuinden Shunzantoko Daizenteimon (常楽院殿峻山棟公大禅定門) とし、クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), Oxhop(id:2551), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), GAVVA(id:47103), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>