<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平貞盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Sadamori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Sadamori</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペースになっていました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Sadamori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 貞盛（たいら の さだもり、生年不詳 - 永祚 (日本)元年10月15日 (旧暦)（989年11月16日）？）は、平安時代中期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Sadamori (year of birth unknown - November 16, 989) was Busho (a military commander) in mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Sadamori (year of birth unknown - November 16, 989) was a Busho (Japanese military commander) in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペースになっていました。武将，時代に冠詞を追加しました。武将の説明を用語集に基づいて訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Sadamori (year of birth unknown - November 16, 989) was a Busho (Japanese military commander) in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平国香の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of TAIRA no Kunika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of TAIRA no Kunika.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of TAIRA no Kunika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平維叙、平維将、平維敏、平維衡らの父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of TAIRA no Korenobu,TAIRA no Koremasa, TAIRA no Korehira and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of TAIRA no Korenobu, TAIRA no Koremasa, TAIRA no Korehira and so on.</e>
<cmt>平維叙の後をコロンに直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of TAIRA no Korenobu, TAIRA no Koremasa, TAIRA no Korehira and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「常平太」と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was referred to as &quot;常平太&quot;.</e>
<cmt>常平太→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was referred to as &apos;常平太.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」なので，&apos;・・&apos;に訂正，ピリオドの位置も&apos;・・&apos;内に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was referred to as &apos;常平太.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従四位下、馬寮、馬寮、常陸国大掾。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and he worked for Meryo (Bureau of Horses), then he became Daijo (the third rank official of a province) in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the official court rank of Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, he assumed the post of Meryo (an government official of the Bureau of Horses) and Daijo (the third rank official of a province) of Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペースになっていました。馬寮は官司の一つなので，書き換えました。従四位下の日本語読みをつける意味は少ないと考え省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the official court rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), he assumed the post of Meryo (an government official of the Bureau of Horses) and Daijo (the third rank official of a province) of Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに従い、Jushiinogeを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>平将軍、平将軍貞盛と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called TAIRA Shogun or TAIRA Shogun Sadamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called &quot;TAIRA no Shogun&quot; or &quot;TAIRA no Shogun Sadamori.&quot;</e>
<cmt>名前が二つ並び，わかりづらいので&quot;&quot;を使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called &quot;TAIRA no Shogun&quot; or &quot;TAIRA no Shogun Sadamori.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>承平 (日本)5年（935年）父国香が従兄弟の平将門に討たれた際は平安京で馬寮在任中であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his father TAIRA no Kunika was killed by his male cousin TAIRA no Masakado, Sadamori was in charge of Meryo in Heian-Kyo (ancient capital in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Sadamori served as Meryo in Heian-Kyo (ancient capital in current Kyoto), his father TAIRA no Kunika was killed by his male cousin TAIRA no Masakado.</e>
<cmt>in charge ofでは在任中のイメージに足りないと考え，書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Sadamori served as Meryo in Heian-Kyo (ancient capital in current Kyoto), his father TAIRA no Kunika was killed by his male cousin TAIRA no Masakado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>休暇を申請して急遽帰国し、焼失した自宅から父国香の屍を探し、山中に避難した母と妻を探し出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After taking a leave of absence then hastely going back to his province, he looked for the dead body of his father Kunika in his burnt residence, and found out his mother and wife who had evacuated in the mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hastily returning home after taking a leave of absence, he searched out the corpse of his father Kunika at his house burnt down, and found out his mother and his wife both of whom had evacuated in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>文がわかりづらいので書き換えました。hastilyにスペルミスがありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hastily returning home after taking a leave of absence, he searched out the corpse of his father Kunika at his house burnt down, and found out his mother and his wife both of whom had evacuated in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>今回の事件を「源氏の縁座」であったことにより巻き込まれたと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadamori thought that his family members had been involved in the incidents due to the crime committed by their relatives (He also thought that he would prefer promotion as a government official in Kyoto to taking revenge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadamori thought that his family members were involved in the incidents as a penalty for the crime committed by their relatives in line with the rule of those days (the rule indicated that not only a criminal but also his or her relatives are punished).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。縁座のイメージが不足していると考え追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadamori thought that his family members were involved in the incidents as a penalty for the crime committed by their relatives in line with the rule of those days (the rule indicated that not only a criminal but also his or her relatives are punished).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（または、仇討よりも京で官人としての昇進を望んだとも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Another theory suggests that Sadamori chose winning a promotion as a government official in capital rather than taking revenge).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Another theory suggests that Sadamori chose winning a promotion as a government official in capital rather than taking revenge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>貞盛は仇敵である平将門に「互いに親睦をはかるのが最も良策である」という態度をみせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadamori showed TAIRA no Masakado his stance that promoting friendly relationships with each other would be the best way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadamori showed TAIRA no Masakado his stance that promoting friendly relationships with each other would be the best way.</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペースになっていました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadamori showed TAIRA no Masakado his stance that promoting friendly relationships with each other would be the best way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、叔父の平良兼・平良正らが将門を攻めると誘われ、これに加わり将門と対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when his uncles TAIRA no Yoshikane and TAIRA no Yoshimasa attacked Masakado, Sadamori was asked to join them and fought against Masakado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, induced by his uncles TAIRA no Yoshikane and TAIRA no Yoshimasa, who had been plotting an attack on Masakado, Sadamori joined them to fight against Masakado.</e>
<cmt>文がわかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, induced by his uncles TAIRA no Yoshikane and TAIRA no Yoshimasa, who had been plotting an attack on Masakado, Sadamori joined them to fight against Masakado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天慶元年（938年）2月29日、密かに上洛を企てるも将門に察知された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he secretly planned to go to the capital on February 29, 989, his intention was detected by Masakado, so he was chased and attacked near Shinano Kokubun-ji Temple in Chiisagata-gun, Shinano Province, which was under the control of Masakado, where he managed to escape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A secret plot to go to the capital on April 6, 989 was found out by Masakado.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。天慶元年（938年）2月29日は旧暦と考え変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A secret plot to go to the capital on April 6, 989 was found out by Masakado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>将門勢力下の信濃国小県郡の信濃国分寺付近で追撃を受けるも脱出に成功。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chased by Masakado troops, he was attacked at the neighborhood of Shinano Kokubun-ji Temple in Chiisagata-gun, Shinano Province, which was under the control of Masakado, but he managed to escape.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chased by Masakado troops, he was attacked at the neighborhood of Shinano Kokubun-ji Temple in Chiisagata-gun, Shinano Province, which was under the control of Masakado, but he managed to escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>良兼の死後、将門追捕の官符を持って帰国するが将門に一蹴された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Yoshikane, Sadamori went back to his provinve with Kanpu (official documents from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) to search and capture Masakado, but his troop was swept aside by Masakado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Yoshikane, Sadamori returned home with Kanpu (official documents from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) to search and capture Masakado, but his troops were easily beaten by Masakado.</e>
<cmt>一蹴のニュアンスはsweep asideとは少し異なるのではと考え書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Yoshikane, Sadamori returned home with Kanpu (official documents from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) to search and capture Masakado, but his troops were easily beaten by Masakado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同年10月、陸奥国平維扶の赴任に従って陸奥に入らんとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Sadamori tried to enter Mutsu Province in October of that year, he was chased and attacked by Masakado again, then he barely escaped alive and hid himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When TAIRA no Koresuke left for Mutsu Province to assume a new post, Sadamori accompanied him and tried to enter Mutsu Province in October of that year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。訳漏れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When TAIRA no Koresuke left for Mutsu Province to assume a new post, Sadamori accompanied him and tried to enter Mutsu Province in October of that year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし再び将門の追撃を受け、辛くも逃げきり身を隠す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, chased by Masakado again, he barely escaped and hid himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, chased by Masakado again, he barely escaped and hid himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>11月常陸国の紛争を利用して将門を討たんとするも再び失敗、藤原為憲と共に再び身を隠した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried to kill Masakado, taking advantage of the conflict in Hitachi Province in November, but he faild it again and hide himself again with FUJIWARA no Tamenori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of the conflict in Hitachi Province in November, he plotted to kill Masakado only to fail again and hid himself again along with FUJIWARA no Tamenori.</e>
<cmt>文がわかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of the conflict in Hitachi Province in November, he plotted to kill Masakado only to fail again and hid himself again along with FUJIWARA no Tamenori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>天慶3年（940年）、藤原秀郷と協力して将門を攻め、2月14日「北山の決戦」にてこれを滅ぼす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 940, he attacked Masakado in cooperation with FUJIWARA no hidesato, and he killed Masakado in the decisive battles of Kitayama on February 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 940, in cooperation with FUJIWARA no Hidesato, he attacked and killed Masakado in &apos;Kitayama no Kessen&apos; (the decisive battles of Kitayama) on February 14.</e>
<cmt>文が多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。「北山の決戦」は名称のまま書きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 940, in cooperation with FUJIWARA no Hidesato, he attacked and killed Masakado in &apos;Kitayama no Kessen&apos; (the decisive battles of Kitayama) on February 14.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>将門討伐後、将門ら謀反人を討つことができたのも、多年の苦難を経て努力した貞盛の為すところも大きいとして、従五位上（正五位上とも）に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After subduing Masakado, Sadamori was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) (or Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) as a reward for his great effort and struggle of many years to defeat rebels such as Masakado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After subduing Masakado, Sadamori was awarded Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade (other theory suggests that he was awarded Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) for his great efforts to defeat rebels such as Masakado, while overcoming hardships for many years.</e>
<cmt>従五位上，正五位上の日本語読みをつける意味は少ないと考え省きました。文が多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After subduing Masakado, Sadamori was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) (other theory suggests that he was awarded Shogoinojo [Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)] for his great efforts to defeat rebels such as Masakado, while overcoming hardships for many years.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに従い、従五位上，正五位上の日本語読みをつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>のちに鎮守府将軍となり、陸奥国・丹波国を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Sadamori became Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) and successively worked in Mutsu and Tanba Provinces, then he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) and was called &quot;TAIRA Shogun&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, promoted to Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North), Sadamori worked successively in Mutsu and then Tanba Provinces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, promoted to Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North), Sadamori worked successively in Mutsu and then Tanba Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>従四位下に叙せられ「平将軍」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade to be called &apos;TAIRA Shogun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。従四位下の日本語読みをつける意味は少ないと考え省きました。「」なので，&apos;・・&apos;に訂正，ピリオドの位置も&apos;・・&apos;内に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded Jushiinoge to be called &apos;TAIRA Shogun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>統一リストに従い、従四位下は既出のため補足は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>今昔物語集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konjaku monogatari shu (The Tale of Times Now Past)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konjaku monogatari shu (The Tale of Times Now Past)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konjaku monogatari shu (The Tale of Times Now Past)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>『将門記』では将門と親睦をはかろうとする態度を見せたり、たびたび将門に敗れて追われる様の多い貞盛である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Shomonki (Tale of Masakado), Sadamori tried to build up a friendly relationship with Masakado, but he was often defeated and chased by Masakado.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shomonki&quot; (Tale of Masakado), Sadamori was often defeated and chased by Masakado despite showing a friendly attitude to him.</e>
<cmt>Shomonkiの後の&quot;が抜けていました。文が多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shomonki&quot; (Tale of Masakado), Sadamori was often defeated and chased by Masakado despite showing a friendly attitude to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、『今昔物語集』巻第二十九・本朝付悪行では、第五話「平貞盛朝臣、法師ノ家ニ於テ盗人ヲ射取リシ語」の、陸奥から帰京の途中に知人の法師の家に宿った際、盗人相手に振るった武勇の逸話が述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his brave character was described in Konjyaku Monogatari Shu, vol.29 本朝付悪業, episode 5 titled &quot;The story of Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) TAIRA no Sadamori, who shot out a robber in the house of a Buddhist priest,&quot; where Sadamori performed a hiroic act against a robber when he stayed in a house of the Buddhist priest on his way back to Kyoto,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処 本朝付悪業→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Konjyaku Monogatari Shu&quot; vol.29 &quot;This land with evil&quot; (本朝付悪業), the episode fifth titled &quot;The story of Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) TAIRA no Sadamori, who shot a robber at the house of a Buddhist priest&quot; introduces his heroic exploit against a robber at the house of a Buddhist priest of his acquaintance, where he stayed on his way back to the capital from Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペースになっていました。本朝付悪業に訳をつけました。文が多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;Konjyaku Monogatari Shu&quot; vol.29 &quot;This land with evil&quot; (本朝付悪業), the episode fifth titled &quot;The story of Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) TAIRA no Sadamori, who shot a robber at the house of a Buddhist priest&quot; introduces his heroic exploit against a robber at the house of a Buddhist priest of his acquaintance, where he stayed on his way back to the capital from Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>at→inに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、第二十五話「丹波守平貞盛、児ノ肝ヲ取リシ語」の、妊婦の腹を裂き胎児の肝を得て自分の矢傷の治療をし、その秘密を守るため治療法を伝授した医師の殺害を企てた、という逸話とが述べられ、豪胆な人物に記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In adittion, his daring chracter was also described in episode 25 titled &quot;The story of Tanba no Kami (the governor of Tanba Province) TAIRA no Sadamori, who gutted a preborn baby&quot;, where Sadamori cut open the belly of a pregnant woman to get her preborn baby&apos;s gut for the treatment of his injury by an arrow, and he plotted to kill the doctor who taught him how to cure the injury to keep it a secret.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, his daring character is also introduced in the episode 25th titled &quot;The story of Tanba no Kami (the governor of Tanba Province) TAIRA no Sadamori, who extracted the internal organs of an unborn baby&quot; by a story that Sadamori not only cut open the belly of a pregnant woman to get her unborn baby&apos;s internal organs for the treatment of his arrow wound, but also plotted to kill the doctor who taught him the remedy for fear that such a cruel conduct would come to light.</e>
<cmt>文が多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, his daring character is also introduced in the episode 25th titled &quot;The story of Tanba no Kami (the governor of Tanba Province) TAIRA no Sadamori, who extracted the internal organs of an unborn baby&quot; by a story that Sadamori not only cut open the belly of a pregnant woman to get her unborn baby&apos;s internal organs for the treatment of his arrow wound, but also plotted to kill the doctor who taught him the remedy for fear that such a cruel conduct would come to light.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Masyu(id:31065), ファービィ(id:129184), 梟(id:117930), 海衛士(id:19229), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Law soma(id:45202), 相馬小次郎(id:188976), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>