<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤堂家信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienobu TODO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienobu TODO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienobu TODO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤堂 式部 家信（とうどう しきぶ　いえのぶ）、天正6年（1578年） - 寛永13年2月19日 (旧暦)（1636年3月26日））は安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期の藤堂氏の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienobu TODO (1578-March 26, 1636) was a vassal of the Todo clan over the period ranging from the Azuchi- Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienobu TODO (1578-March 26, 1636) was a vassal of the Todo clan over the period ranging from the Azuchi- Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienobu Shikibu TODO (1578 - March 26, 1636) was a vassal of the Todo clan over the period ranging from the Azuchi- Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Ienobu Shikibu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称は式部。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His popular name was Shikibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was popularly known as Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was popularly known as Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近江の磯の出身であり、元は礒崎金七といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Iso, Omi Province and his original name was Kinshichi ISOZAKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Iso, Omi Province and his original name was Kinshichi ISOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in the town of Iso in Omi Province; his birth name was Kinshichi ISOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天正6年（1578年）の生まれで、米原磯村の磯崎氏の系図によれば、礒崎刑部佐衛門の六男という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the Isozaki clan&apos;s family trees in Maibara Iso village (米原磯村,) he was born in 1578 as the sixth son of Gyobuzaemon ISOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>米原磯村 - 読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the Isozaki clan&apos;s family trees in Maibara Iso village (米原磯村,) he was born in 1578 as the sixth son of Gyobuzaemon ISOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1578, and according to the Isozaki clan&apos;s family genealogy, he was the sixth son of Gyobuzaemon ISOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『宋国史』によれば原姓は蒲生となっており、武内家の系図に蒲生と名のっている時期がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Sokokushi,&quot; his original family name was Gamo and the Takenouchi family&apos;s family trees show that there was a period when he identified himself as named Gamo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Sokokushi,&quot; his original family name was Gamo and the Takenouchi family&apos;s family trees show that there was a period where he identified himself as named Gamo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Sokoku shi&quot; (The History of the Todo clan), his family name was Gamo at birth, and the Takenouchi family&apos;s genealogy shows that there was a period where he identified himself as Gamo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは蒲生氏郷の三代前の礒崎家郷と蒲生定秀兄弟の時代から礒崎姓と蒲生姓を両家で使用するようになったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both families began to use a family name of Isozaki and a family name of Gamo during the time when two brothers Iesato ISOZAKI and Sadahide GAMO were the family heads three generations ago from Ujisato GAMO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both families began to use the family name of Isozaki and a family name of Gamo during the time when two brothers Iesato ISOZAKI and Sadahide GAMO were the family heads three generations ago from Ujisato GAMO.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three generations before Ujisato GAMO, from the time when two brothers, Iesato ISOZAKI and Sadahide GAMO, were heads of their respective families, each family began using both the Isozaki and Gamo surnames.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>この礒崎家は日本武尊の埋葬地と言われる近江の礒崎神社に神官として武内宿禰の後裔、武内信實が京都より派遣され、蒲生姓を名のる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Yamato Takeru no Mikoto is thought to have been buried in Isozaki Shrine in Omi, and TAKENOUCHI no Nobuzane (武内信實,) a descendant of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, was sent from Kyoto to Isozaki Shrine in Omi to take the post of Shinto priest and began to use a family name of Gamo, that was the beginning of the Isozaki family.</e>
<cmt>日本語原文は、極めて理解しづらい文章です。武内信實 - 読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Yamato Takeru no Mikoto is thought to have been buried in Isozaki Shrine in Omi, and TAKENOUCHI no Nobuzane (武内信實,) a descendant of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, was sent from Kyoto to Isozaki Shrine in Omi to take the post of Shinto priest and began to use a family name of Gamo, that was the beginning of the Isozaki family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Yamato Takeru no Mikoto is thought to have been buried in Isozaki-jinja Shrine in Omi, and TAKENOUCHI no Nobuzane (武内信實,) a descendant of TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, was sent from Kyoto to Isozaki-jinja Shrine in Omi to take the post of Shinto priest and began to use a family name of Gamo; that was the beginning of the Isozaki family.</e>
<cmt>Isozaki-jinja Shrine としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、礒崎を名乗ったのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a later year, he started using Isozaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a later year, his name started with Isozaki.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a later year, he started using Isozaki as the family name.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>礒崎金七は藤堂高虎に従い、豊臣秀吉の文禄元年（1592年）の文禄・慶長の役に参加し、南原の戦いで得た敵将の衣服が遺されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinshichi ISOZAKI joined Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to fight the Bunroku-Keicho War in 1592 following Takatora TODO and got the clothes the enemy&apos;s head wore in the Nangen War, that have been retained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinshichi ISOZAKI joined Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to fight the Bunroku-Keicho War in 1592 following Takatora TODO and retrieving the clothes that adorned the enemy&apos;s during the Nangen War.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinshichi ISOZAKI followed Takatora TODO in joining Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s army during the Bunroku-Keicho War of 1592, and collecting the clothes taken from the bodies of the enemy during the Nangen War.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、関ヶ原の戦いにも参加、大坂夏の陣では長宗我部氏の吉田重親、横山将監を討つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he joined the Battle of Sekigahara, and in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka,) put down Shigechika YOSHIDA and Shogen YOKOYAMA of the Chosokabe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he joined the Battle of Sekigahara, and in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka,) put down Shigechika YOSHIDA and Shogen YOKOYAMA of the Chosokabe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he also fought in the Battle of Sekigahara, and struck down Shigechika YOSHIDA and Shogen YOKOYAMA of the Chosokabe clan during the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これはその日一番（5月6日）の手柄ということで家康公から（一ニ）の紋をいただき、代々、式部家では惣領の当主が男紋として使用することになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu appreciated his act was the most extinguished achievement for that day (May 6) and gave a crest of (一二) to him, and in the Shikibu family, its family head as Soryo (heir) has to use the crest as Otokomon (crest for male family heads) for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu appreciated his act and recognized it as the most distinguished achievement for that day (May 6) and gave him a crest of (一二), and in the Shikibu family, its family head as Soryo (heir) used the crest as Otokomon (crest for male family heads) for generations.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu honored his deed as the most distinguished achievement for that day (June 2, 1615), granting him the (一二) crest, which was used by each successive Shikibu family head as the Otokomon (the crest for the male family head).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>系図によれば一時は2万石を拝領し、慶長12年（1607年）に藤堂姓を賜り、藤堂式部を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the family trees, he had territories which yielded 20,000 koku in rice (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter) for a while, and as he was conferred a family name of Todo in 1607, he started identifying himself as Shikibu TODO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the family trees, he had territories which yielded 20,000 koku in rice (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter) for a while, and as he was conferred a family name of Todo in 1607, he started identifying himself as Shikibu TODO.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on genealogies, at one time he controlled a territory of 20,000 koku (a volume measurement for rice), and after being granted the family name of Todo in 1607, he started identifying himself as Shikibu TODO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、大坂夏の陣の時で受けた傷に徳川家康からいただいた「権現様頂戴之御軟膏」が現在でも伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a known anecdote that he applied Gongen-sama chodai no gonanko (ointment given from Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) to the injuries he got in the Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt>原文全体が下足らずで、何が（軟膏あるいはこの逸話？）現在でも伝わっているのか、不明です。一応、”この逸話”としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a known anecdote that he applied Gongen-sama chodai no gonanko (ointment given from Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) to the injuries he recieved in the Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One legend about him that has continued to be passed down to today is that he applied a healing salve given to him by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to the wounds he had suffered during the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>松尾芭蕉は藤堂新七郎家の家来であったが、式部家の組下ということになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basho MATSUO was a retainer of the Shinshichiro Todo family, but he is thought to have been Kumishita (a person who serves under a Japanese military commander) of the Shikibu family.</e>
<cmt>組下 - 定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basho MATSUO was a retainer of the Shinshichiro Todo family, but he is thought to have been Kumishita (a person who serves under a Japanese military commander) of the Shikibu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basho MATSUO was one of the Shinshichiro Todo family&apos;s retainers; he is thought to have served as a Kumishita (a person who serves under a Japanese military commander) of the Shikibu family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>さらに、家信の在世中に荒木又右衛門、河合又五郎の鍵屋の辻の決闘があり、敵討ちが終わった後、式部家にお預けとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, there was a battle of Ketto Kagiya no Tsuji (the Duel at the Key-Maker&apos;s Corner) by Matagoro KAWAI, and after the vengeance was finished, Mataemon ARAKI was placed in the custody of the Shikibu family while Ienobu was alive.</e>
<cmt>”お預けとなっていた”の意味がよく分かりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, there was a battle of Ketto Kagiya no Tsuji (the Duel at the Key-Maker&apos;s Corner) by Matagoro KAWAI, and after the act of revenge finished, Mataemon ARAKI was placed in the custody of the Shikibu family while Ienobu was alive.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, while Ienobu was still alive, a duel called &quot;Kagiya no Tsuji no Ketto&quot; (the Duel at the Key-Maker&apos;s Corner) was fought between Mataemon ARAKI and Matagoro KAWAI; after Mataemon struck down his enemy, he was was placed in the custody of the Shikibu family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>藤堂式部家信は寛永13年（1636年）2月19日に京都で没し、藤堂式部家の５代までの墓が紫野の大徳寺大光院に墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienobu Shikibu TODO died on February 19, 1636 in Kyoto, and the five generations&apos; graves of Todo Shikibu family are in Daitoku-ji Daiko-in Temple in Murasakino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienobu Shikibu TODO died on February 19, 1636 in Kyoto, and the five generations&apos; graves of Todo Shikibu family are in Daitoku-ji Daiko-in Temple in Murasakino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienobu Shikibu TODO died on March 26, 1636 in Kyoto; the ancestral tombs for the first five generations of the Todo Shikibu family are located in Daitoku-ji Daiko-in Temple in Murasakino.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは『宋国史』下巻（482~483頁）にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is stated in the last volume (pages 482-483) of Sokokushi.</e>
<cmt>日本語が分かりにくいです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is stated in the last volume (pages 482-483) of Sokokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is stated in the pages 482-483 of the last volume of &quot;Sokokushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、伊賀市朝屋の龍王寺が式部家の菩提寺である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shikibu family&apos;s family temple is Ryuo-ji Temple in Choya, Iga City.</e>
<cmt>日本語が分かりにくいです。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shikibu family&apos;s family temple is Ryuo-ji Temple in Choya, Iga City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family temple of the Shikibu family is Ryuo-ji Temple, which is located in the town of Choya in the city of Iga.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>三代将軍徳川家光時代の紫衣事件によって大徳寺から追放になった沢庵宗彭の高弟、藤堂家が清巌和尚をお預かりし、同寺は清巌和尚の開山となっている（『宋国史』下巻590頁）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seigan Osho (priest Seigan,) a high-caliber disciple of Takuan SOHO, who was expelled from Daitoku-ji Temple because of the Shie Incident occurred in the years of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, was allowed to stay with the Todo family, and Ryuo-ji Temple was founded by Seigan Osho (See page 590 of &quot;Sokokushi&quot; the last volume.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seigan Osho (priest Seigan,) a high-caliber disciple of Takuan SOHO, who was expelled from Daitoku-ji Temple because of the Shie Incident which occurred in the years of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, was allowed to stay with the Todo family, and Ryuo-ji Temple was founded by Seigan Osho (See page 590 of &quot;Sokokushi&quot; the last volume.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seigan Osho (high priest Seigan), a high-ranking disciple of Takuan SOHO who was expelled from Daitoku-ji Temple due to the Shie Incident--which occurred during the reign of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA--was handed over to the Todo family, and Ryuo-ji Temple was founded by Seigan Osho (See page 590 of &quot;Sokokushi&quot; the last volume).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>明治13年（1880年）に藤堂姓を返還し、元の武内（タケノウチ）に戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They returned the family name of Todo in 1880 and got back to their original family name, Takenouchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They returned the family name of Todo in 1880 and returned to their original family name, Takenouchi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family gave up the surname Todo in 1880, returning to their original surname of Takenouchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、2008年は藤堂高虎が四国今治から伊賀伊勢に入府して400年になり、上野城では入府400年祭を開催し、高虎公直筆の古文書の展示を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year 2008 has been the 400th year since Takatora TODO got into Iga Ise from Shikoku Imabari and Nyufu 400 Nensai (the 400th anniversary for entering the metropolitan area) was held at Ueno-jo Castle, and the ancient documents written by Takatora were displayed for visitors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 2008 has been the 400th year since Takatora TODO came to Iga Ise from Shikoku Imabari and Nyufu 400 Nensai (the 400th anniversary for entering the metropolitan area) was held at Ueno-jo Castle, and the ancient documents written by Takatora were displayed for visitors.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2008 was the 400th anniversary of Takatora TODO&apos;s relocation from Imabari in Shikoku to Iga Ise, which is part of the capital&apos;s metropolitan area, and so a commemorative celebration of the 400-year anniversary of his entry into the capital area was held at Ueno-jo Castle, during which ancient documents written by Takatora were put on display.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これには藤堂本家、同玄蕃家、同新七郎家、同釆女家、同式部家（武内家）、その他が参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main Todo family, the Genba family, the Shinshichiro family, the Uneme family, the Shikibu family and the Takeuchi family (Takenouchi family) of the Todo family, etc. joined the anniversary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main Todo family, the Genba family, the Shinshichiro family, the Uneme family, the Shikibu family and the Takeuchi family (Takenouchi family) of the Todo family, etc. joined the anniversary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main Todo family line as well as the Genba, Shinshichiro, Uneme, and Shikibu (Takenouchi) branch families all took part in the anniversary celebration.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Haeha(id:9372), FREEZA(id:68069), しちしとう(id:180831), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>