<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鳥居元忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada TORII</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada TORII</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada TORII</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鳥居 元忠（とりい もとただ）は、安土桃山時代の徳川家康の家臣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada TORII was a vassal of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s in the Azuchi Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada TORII was a vassal of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s in the Azuchi Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada TORII was a vassal of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s in the Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三河国渡村（現在の愛知県岡崎市）出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Watari village of Mikawa Province (present- day, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Watari village in Mikawa Province (present- day, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「of」→「in」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Watari-mura in Mikawa Province (present- day, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>父の鳥居忠吉は岡崎奉行などを務めた松平氏以来の老臣で、元忠も家康がまだ「松平竹千代」と呼ばれて今川氏の人質だった頃からの側近の一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Tadayoshi TORII, had served for the TOKUGAWA clan since TOKUGAWAs called themselvwas MATSUDAIRA clan and he once worked as Okazaki bugyo. Motonaga had served as one of Ieyasu&apos;s aides since Ieyasu was Imagawa&apos;s hostage and called Takechiyo MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Tadayoshi TORII, had served the TOKUGAWA clan since the TOKUGAWAs called themselves the MATSUDAIRA clan and he once worked as Okazaki bugyo. Mototada had served as one of Ieyasu&apos;s aides since the time when Ieyasu was Imagawa&apos;s hostage and called Takechiyo MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>「for」削除, 「the」挿入x2, 「themselvwas」→「themselves」,「Motonaga」→「Mototada」, 「the time when」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Tadayoshi TORII, had served the TOKUGAWA clan since the clan called itself the MATSUDAIRA clan and he once worked as Okazaki magistrate and the like; Mototada had served as one of Ieyasu&apos;s aides since Ieyasu was Imagawa&apos;s hostage and called Takechiyo MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家康の三河統一後、旗本先手役となり旗本部隊の将として戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ieyasu united Mikawa Province, Mototada became Hatamoto sakiteyaku (a hatamoto vassal of the shogun, who leads the way) and fought as the leader of Hatamoto troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Ieyasu united Mikawa Province, Mototada became Hatamoto sakiteyaku (a hatamoto vassal of the shogun, who leads the way in battle) and fought as the leader of Hatamoto troops.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Ieyasu united Mikawa Province, Mototada became a bodyguard of Ieyasu and fought as the leader of the troop under the direct control of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>元亀3年（1572年）、父の死により家督を相続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1572, he inherited the headship of his family due to his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1572, he inherited the headship of his family due to his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1572, he inherited the headship of his family due to his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同年の三方ヶ原の戦いや諏訪原城合戦で足に傷を負い、以後は歩行に多少の障害を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he got his leg hurt in the Battle of Mikatagahara and the Battle of Suwahara-jo Castle, and after that had some difficulty in walking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year he injured his leg in the Battle of Mikatagahara and the Battle of Suwahara-jo Castle, and after that had some difficulty in walking.</e>
<cmt>「,」削除, 「got his leg hurt」→「injured his leg」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, as he injured his leg in the Battle of Mikatagahara and in the Battle of Suwahara-jo Castle, he had some difficulty in walking thereafter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、天正壬午の乱で家康の背後を襲おうとした北条勢の別働隊10,000を鳥居元忠ら2,000が撃退し北条勢約300を討ち取り（黒駒合戦）、その後甲斐国郡内地方を家康より与えられ、谷村城の城主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, in Tenshojingo Rebellion, Hojo&apos;s detachment force consisting of 10,000 was going to attack Ieyas in the rear. However, Ieysuzu&apos;s 2000 men, including Mototada, drove them back and killed 300 of Hojo&apos;s force (the Battle of Kurokoma). Mototada was given 郡内地方 of Kai Province by Ieyasu, and became the lord of Tanimura Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, during the Tenshojingo Rebellion, Hojo&apos;s detachment force consisting of 10,000 men planned to attack Ieyasu from the rear. However, Ieyasu&apos;s 2000 men, containing Mototada, drove them back and killed 300 of the Hojo force (the Battle of Kurokoma). Mototada was given land within Kai Province by Ieyasu, and became the lord of Tanimura Castle.</e>
<cmt>「in」→「during the」, 「men」挿入,「was going」→「planned」, 「Ieyas」→「Ieyasu」,「in」→「from」, 「Ieysuzu&apos;s」→「Ieyasu&apos;s」, 「including」→「containing」,「Hojo&apos;s force」→「the Hojo force」.「郡内地方 of」→「land within」 (suggestion).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, during the Tenshojingo War, Hojo&apos;s detached force consisting of 10,000 men planned to attack Ieyasu from the rear, however, Ieyasu&apos;s 2,000 men, containing Mototada, drove them back and killed 300 of the Hojo force (the Battle of Kurokoma), and Mototada was given Gunnai region in Kai Province by Ieyasu, and became the lord of Tanimura-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、天正13年（1585年）に上杉景勝へ通じた真田昌幸を討伐しようとした上田合戦では大久保忠世、平岩親吉と共に兵7,000を率いて上田城を攻撃するものの大きな損害を受け撃退される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, in the Battle of Ueda, Mototada tried to put down Masayuki SANADA, who communicated with Kagekatsu UESUGI, and attacked Ueda Castle with Tadayo OKUBO and Chikayoshi HIRAIWA, leading 7,000 soldiers. However they were greatly damaged and repelled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, in the Battle of Ueda, Mototada tried to put down Masayuki SANADA, who communicated with Kagekatsu UESUGI, and attacked Ueda Castle with Tadayo OKUBO and Chikayoshi HIRAIWA, leading 7,000 soldiers. However they were greatly damaged and were repelled.</e>
<cmt>「were」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, in the Battle of Ueda, Mototada tried to defeat Masayuki SANADA, who communicated with Kagekatsu UESUGI, and attacked Ueda-jo Castle with Tadayo OKUBO and Chikayoshi HIRAIWA, leading 7,000 soldiers; however, they were repelled with great casualties.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>家康が豊臣秀吉に帰服して関東に移封されたとき、下総国矢作に4万石を与えられる（矢作藩）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ieyasu surrendered to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was transferred to Kanto region, Mototada was given 40,000 koku in Yahagi, Shimosa Province (Yahagi Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ieyasu surrendered to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was transferred to the Kanto region, Mototada was given 40,000 koku in Yahagi, Shimosa Province (Yahagi Domain).</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ieyasu surrendered to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was transferred to the Kanto region, Mototada was given 40,000 koku in Yahagi, Shimosa Province (Yahagi Domain).</e>
<cmt>イタリックをとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）には秀吉死後の豊臣政権において、五大老となっていた家康は会津の上杉景勝の征伐を主張し、諸将を率いて出兵すると、伏見城を預けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1600, Ieyasu, who had become one of Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) in the Toyotomi government after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, insisted on the conquest of Kagekatsu UESUGI. Ieyasu led troops and was asked to be in charge of Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600, Ieyasu, who had become one of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) in the Toyotomi government after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, insisted on the subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI. Ieyasu led the troops and was asked to be in charge of Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「conquest」→「subjugation」,「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600, Ieyasu, who had become one of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) in the Toyotomi government after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, led the troops as the head of warlords, insisting on the subjugation of Kagekatsu UESUGI, then was asked to be in charge of Fushimi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>家康らの出陣中に五奉行の石田三成らが家康に対して挙兵すると、伏見城は前哨戦の舞台となり、元忠は1800人の兵力で立て籠もる（伏見城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Ieyasu&apos;s departure, Mitsunari ISHIDA and others raised an army against Ieyasu. Fushimi-jo Castle was the stage for the fire fight and Mototada held up in the castle with 1,800 soldiers (the Battle of Fushimi-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Ieyasu&apos;s absence, Mitsunari ISHIDA and others raised an army against Ieyasu. Fushimi-jo Castle was the stage for the fire fight and Mototada was confined in the castle with 1,800 soldiers (the Battle of Fushimi-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>「departure」→「absence」, 「held up」→「was confined」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Ieyasu&apos;s absence, Mitsunari ISHIDA of Gobugyo (five major magistrates) and others raised an army against Ieyasu and fought a skirmish at Fushimi-jo Castle where Mototada held in with 1,800 soldiers (the Battle of Fushimi-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>元忠は最初から玉砕を覚悟で戦い続け、鈴木重朝と一騎打ちの末に討ち死にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada, prepared to die in the battle, continued fighting and wad killed in the one-on-one battle against Shigetomo SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada, prepared to die in the battle, continued fighting and was killed in a one-on-one battle against Shigetomo SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>「wad」→「was」, 「the」→「a」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having prepared to die in the battle, Mototada continued fighting and was killed in a one-on-one battle against Shigetomo SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>享年62。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その忠節は「三河武士の鑑」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His loyalty was honored as &apos;the paragon of the warrior in Mikawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His loyalty was honored as &apos;the paragon of all warriors in Mikawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「the warrior」→「all warriors」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His loyalty was honored as &apos;the paragon of all warriors in Mikawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このときの伏見城の床板は、「血天井」として京都市の養源院をはじめ、宝泉院、正伝寺、源光庵、宇治市の興聖寺 (宇治市)に今も伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The floor board of the Fushimi-jo Castle is described as the &apos;bloody ceiling&apos; in the following temples: Yogen-in Temple, Hosen-in Temple, and Genko-an Temple in Kyoto city, and Kosho-ji Temple in Uji city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The floor boards of Fushimi-jo Castle are described as the &apos;bloody ceiling&apos; in the following temples: Yogen-in Temple, Hosen-in Temple, and Genko-an Temple in Kyoto city, and Kosho-ji Temple in Uji city.</e>
<cmt>「board of the」→「boards of」,「is」→「are」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The floorboards of Fushimi-jo Castle have been kept in the following temples as the &apos;bloody ceiling&apos;: Yogen-in Temple, Hosen-in Temple, and Genko-an Temple in Kyoto City, and Kosho-ji Temple in Uji City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>家康は忠実な部下の死を悲しみ、その功績もあって嫡男の鳥居忠政は後に山形藩24万石の大名に昇格している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu lamented over that faithful vassal. Partly because of Mototada&apos;s achievements, hiseldest son and heir, Tadamasa TORII was promoted to the Yamagada domain 240,000-koku daimyo (feuderal lord of 240,000-koku class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu lamented over his faithful vassal. Partly because of Mototada&apos;s achievements, his eldest son and heir, Tadamasa TORII was promoted to the Yamagada domain 240,000-koku daimyo (a feudal lord of 240,000-koku class).</e>
<cmt>「that」→「his」, 「hiseldest」→「his eldest」,「feuderal」→「a feudal」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu, lamented over his faithful vassal and also recognized Mototada&apos;s achievements, promoted Mototada&apos;s eldest son and heir Tadamasa TORII to the Yamagata domain 240,000-koku feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>Made plural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>元忠は幼少の頃から徳川家康に仕えて幾度となく功績を挙げたが、感状をもらうことは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada had served for Ieyasu Tokugawa since his childhood and rendered more distinguished service than anyone else. However he had never received any awarding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada served Ieyasu Tokugawa since his childhood and rendered more distinguished service than anyone else, although he never received any significant reward.</e>
<cmt>Changed to single sentence.「had」削除,「for」削除,「. However he had」→「, although he」, 「awarding」→「significant reward」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada served Ieyasu Tokugawa from his childhood and rendered a lot of distinguished services but never received a citation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>家康が感状を与えようとしたが、元忠は感状などは別の主君に仕えるときに役立つものであり、家康しか主君を考えていない自分には無用なものであると答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ieyasu tried to give him an awarding, Mototada refused it. Mototada said an awarding was useful only when he served for anybody but Ieyasu and that it was useless since he could only think of Ieyasu as his master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ieyasu tried to give him a reward, Mototada refused it, saying a reward would be useful only if he served anybody but Ieyasu, but that it was useless since he could only think of Ieyasu as his master.</e>
<cmt>Changed to single sentence. 「an awarding」→「a reward」x2, 「. Mototada said」→「, saying」「was」→「would be」, 「when」→「if」,「and」→「, but」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ieyasu tried to give him a citation, Mototada refused it, saying a citation would be useful if only he served another lord, but as he could not think of any lord but Ieyasu, a citation was useless.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>絶対の忠臣であったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada was called an absolute loyal subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada was called an absolutely loyal subject.</e>
<cmt>「absolute」→「absolutely」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Mototada was a subject of firm loyality.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、秀吉からの官位推挙の話が度々あったものの、主君以外の人間から貰う言われはないと断ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that although Hideyoshi several times offered to say a good word for him to get an official rank, Mototada refused the offer, by saying that he had no reason to receive any prize from anybody else except his master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that although Hideyoshi offered several times to say a good word in order for him to get an official rank, Mototada refused the offer, saying that he had no reason to receive any prize from anybody else except his master.</e>
<cmt>「offered」箇所異動,「in order」挿入,「by」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that although Hideyoshi offered several times to say a good word in order for him to get an official rank, Mototada refused the offer, saying that he had no reason to receive any prize from anybody else except his master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>武田氏の滅亡後、重臣である馬場信房の娘の情報が家康に届き、元忠に捜索を命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the downfall of the Takeda clan, Ieyasu heard about a daughter of Nobufusa BABA, a senior vassal of the Takeda clan, and ordered Mototada to find her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the downfall of the Takeda clan, Ieyasu heard about a daughter of Nobufusa BABA, a senior vassal of the Takeda clan, and ordered Mototada to find her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the downfall of the Takeda clan, Ieyasu heard about a daughter of Nobufusa BABA, a senior vassal of the Takeda clan, and ordered Mototada to find her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし元忠は娘は見つからないと報告し、捜索は打ち切られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada reported Iyeasu that the daughter was not found, and the search was stopped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada reported to Ieyasu that the daughter could not be found, and the search was stopped.</e>
<cmt>「to」挿入, 「Iyeasu」→「Ieyasu」, 「was not」→「could not be」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada reported to Ieyasu that the daughter could not be found, and he called off the investigation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しばらくして、馬場の娘が元忠の本妻になったという話を聞き、家康は高笑いで許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, when Ieyasu heard the daughter became Mototada&apos;s wife, he gave a loud laugh and permitted their marriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, when Ieyasu heard that the daughter had become Mototada&apos;s wife, he gave a hearty laugh and permitted their marriage.</e>
<cmt>「that」挿入, 「became」→「had become」, 「loud」→「hearty」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, when Ieyasu heard that the daughter had become Mototada&apos;s wife, he gave a hearty laugh and permitted their marriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>子のひとり鳥居忠勝（水戸藩士）の娘が赤穂藩の家老大石良欽に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A daughter of one of Mototada&apos;s sons, Tadakatsu TORII married into Yoshitaka OISHI, a chief vassal of the domain of Ako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A daughter of one of Mototada&apos;s sons, Tadakatsu TORII, married Yoshitaka OISHI, a chief vassal of the domain of Ako.</e>
<cmt>「,」挿入,「into」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A daughter of one of Mototada&apos;s sons, Tadakatsu TORII, married Yoshitaka OISHI, a chief vassal of the Ako Domain.</e>
<cmt>赤穂藩の表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その夫婦の孫が元禄赤穂事件において主君に忠死した大石良雄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A grandson of the couple was Yoshio OISHI, who died for his master at Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A grandson of the couple was Yoshio OISHI, who died for his master in the Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt>「at」→「in the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A grandson of the couple was Yoshio OISHI, who died for his master in the Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>元忠の出生地は愛知県岡崎市渡町（元の矢作町）という所で鳥居氏発祥の地 として碑が建っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada&apos;s birthplace was Watari town, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture (former, Yahagi town). A monument as the Torii clan&apos;s birthplace stands there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada&apos;s birthplace was Watari town, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture (formerly Yahagi town), where a monument to the Torii clan&apos;s birthplace stands.</e>
<cmt>Reverted into a single sentence. 「former,」→「formerly」, 「. A monument as the Torii clan&apos;s birthplace stands there.」→「, where a monument to the Torii clan&apos;s birthplace stands.」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada&apos;s birthplace was Watari-cho town, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture (formerly Yahagi-cho town), where a monument marking the Torii clan&apos;s birthplace stands.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その碑を管理しているのが鳥居元忠の生家で、今では鳥居家の本家として受け継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada&apos;s descendents have been in charge of the monument. Nowadays the head family of the Torii clan is charge of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada&apos;s descendents have been in charge of the monument, and even now the head family of the Torii clan has charge of it.</e>
<cmt>「. Nowadays」→「, and even now」, 「is」→「has」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada&apos;s descendents, currently as the head family of the Torii clan, have been in charge of the monument.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>鳥居元忠の関係の子孫の多くは関東を中心に東京、栃木、神奈川、千葉、岩手、群馬、茨城、長野等に散らばっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of Mototada&apos;s descendents mainly live in Kanto area and also in various places such as Tokyo, Tochigi, Kanagawa, Chiba, Iwate, Gunma, Ibaraki, Nagano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of Mototada&apos;s descendents live in the Kanto area, in various places such as Tokyo, Tochigi, Kanagawa, Chiba, Iwate, Gunma, Ibaraki and Nagano.</e>
<cmt>「mainly」削除, 「the」挿入, 「and also」→「,」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of Mototada&apos;s descendents live centering on the Kanto region, and in various places such as Tokyo, Tochigi, Kanagawa, Chiba, Iwate, Gunma, Ibaraki and Nagano.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>400年以上過ぎた今でも、元大名の鳥居家や本家を中心とした鳥居家一族の会（鳥居会）を作って時代の検証を続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even 400 years after Mototada&apos;s death, the Torii clans form their family meeting (the Torii meeting) and continue studying the historical aspects related with Mototada TORII. The main members are the former-daimyo Torii family and the head family of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even 400 years after Mototada&apos;s death, the Torii clans hold a family meeting (the Torii meeting) and continue studying historical aspects related to Mototada TORII. The main members are the former-daimyo Torii family and the head family of the clan.</e>
<cmt>「form their」→「hold a」,「the」削除, 「with」→「to」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even 400 years after Mototada&apos;s death, the Torii clans hold a family meeting called &apos;Torii-kai&apos;, which consists mainly of the former-daimyo Torii family and the head family of the clan, and continue studying historical aspects related to Mototada TORII.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), いいすく(id:136753), YonaBot(id:125006), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), HI(id:72996), ＤＦ．Ｋｉｎｇ(id:48817), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Sutou(id:32), Chocoyoshi(id:170796), 酒井貴広(id:52017), PipepBot(id:146181), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), D5(id:60352), VolkovBot(id:105371), 玄史生(id:43670), 下総大納言(id:43461), Arawodas(id:213174), こいつぅ(id:2105), NDR(id:5500), はぐれ風(id:53189), Kouko0515(id:100370), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>