<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原穆子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Bokushi (Atsuko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Bokushi (Atsuko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Bokushi</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 穆子（ふじわら の ぼくし/あつこ、承平 (日本)元年（931年）－長和5年7月26日 (旧暦)（1016年8月31日））は、平安時代の左大臣・源雅信の正室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Bokushi (Atsuko) (931 - August 31, 1016) was the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, Sadaijin (minister of the left) during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Bokushi (Atsuko) (931 - August 31, 1016) was the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, Sadaijin (minister of the left) during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Bokushi (also known as Atsuko) (931 - September 6, 1016) was the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, Sadaijin (minister of the left) during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中納言藤原朝忠の娘で、藤原道長正室である源倫子や源時通、源時叙、藤原道綱正室の母となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Asatada who served as Chunagon (middle councilor), and the mother of MINAMOTO no Tokimichi, MINAMOTO no Tokinobu, MINAMOTO no Rinshi who was the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and another daughter who was the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michitsuna.</e>
<cmt>混乱を避けるためanother daughterを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Asatada who served as Chunagon (middle councilor), and the mother of MINAMOTO no Tokimichi, MINAMOTO no Tokinobu, MINAMOTO no Rinshi who was the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and another daughter who was the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michitsuna.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Asatada who served as Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), and the mother of MINAMOTO no Tokimichi, MINAMOTO no Tokinobu, MINAMOTO no Rinshi who was the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and another daughter who was the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michitsuna.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原道長が源倫子に求婚した折に夫の雅信は倫子を一条天皇の妃にしようと画策しており、これを断ろうとしたが、穆子が倫子と天皇とでは年齢的に不釣合いであるとしてこれに反対し、道長を婿に迎え入れさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Michinaga proposed MINAMOTO no Rinshi, Bokushi&apos;s husband Masanobu was planning to make Rinshi the Empress of Emperor Ichijo and tried to refuse the proposal, but Bokushi (Atsuko) was against her husband because of the big age gap between Rinshi and the Emperor, and let Michinaga marry into her family as her son-in-law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When FUJIWARA no Michinaga proposed to MINAMOTO no Rinshi, Bokushi&apos;s husband Masanobu was planning to make Rinshi the Empress of Emperor Ichijo and tried to refuse the proposal, but Bokushi (Atsuko) was against her husband because of the big age gap between Rinshi and the Emperor, and let Michinaga marry into her family as her son-in-law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Michinaga proposed to MINAMOTO no Rinshi, Bokushi&apos;s husband Masanobu was planning to make Rinshi the Empress of Emperor Ichijo and tried to refuse the proposal, but Bokushi was against her husband because of the big age gap between Rinshi and the Emperor, and let Michinaga marry into her family as her son-in-law.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このため、道長もこの義母には頭が上がらなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this Michinaga was said to be deeply indebted to his mother-in-law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this Michinaga was said to be deeply indebted to his mother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this Michinaga was said to be deeply indebted to his mother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>夫の死後、出家したため、「一条尼（いちじょうのあま）」と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After her husband&apos;s death Bokushi became a nun and was called as &quot;Ichijo no ama (nun).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her husband&apos;s death Bokushi became a nun and was called &quot;Ichijo no ama (nun).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her husband&apos;s death Bokushi became a nun and was called &apos;Ichijo no ama&apos; (nun of Ichijo).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、道長の昇進、孫娘の藤原彰子の入内などが続き、長保3年（1001年）の穆子の七十算の修法（70歳を祝う加持祈祷）は、道長夫妻の主催によって大規模に行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, glorious events such as Michinaga&apos;s promotion and her granddaughter FUJIWARA no Shoshi&apos;s Judai (marriage to the emperor) followed, and Bokushi&apos;s Shichi-ju san no shuho (incantation and prayers to celebrate her becoming seventy years old) was held on a large scale by Michinaga and Rinshi in 1001.</e>
<cmt>「などが続き」は(輝かしいできごと）などであるとして、glorious eventsを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, glorious events such as Michinaga&apos;s promotion and her granddaughter FUJIWARA no Shoshi&apos;s Judai (marriage to the emperor) followed, and Bokushi&apos;s Shichi-ju san no shuho (incantation and prayers to celebrate her becoming seventy years old) was held on a large scale by Michinaga and Rinshi in 1001.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, glorious events such as Michinaga&apos;s promotion and her granddaughter FUJIWARA no Shoshi&apos;s judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) followed, and Bokushi&apos;s Shichi-ju san no shuho(Rituals of exorcism or removing evil influences at 70 years old) was held on a large scale by Michinaga and Rinshi in 1001.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>晩年は観音寺 (京都市)にしばしば籠ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In her last years she was said to often confine herself in Kannonn-ji Temple (Kyoto City) for prayer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In her last years she was said to often confine herself in Kannonn-ji Temple (Kyoto City) for prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In her last years she was said to often confine herself in Kannon-ji Temple (Kyoto City) for prayer.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>長和元年（1016年）、曾孫に当たる後一条天皇が即位するが、間もなく病状が悪化し、道長夫妻も看病にあたったものの、同年7月に86歳で病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1016 soon after her great-grandson was enthroned to become Emperor Goichijo, she became seriously ill, and despite the care of Michinaga and Rinshi, she died of an illness in July of the same year at the age of 86.</e>
<cmt>「病状が悪化し」を直訳するとher condition became worseですが、この前に彼女が病気であるという話がでてきていませんので、流れとして自然になるようshe became seriously ill としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1016 soon after her great-grandson was enthroned to become Emperor Goichijo, she became seriously ill, and despite the care from Michinaga and Rinshi, she died of an illness in July of the same year at the age of 86.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1016 soon after her great-grandson was enthroned to become Emperor Goichijo, she became seriously ill, and despite the care from Michinaga and Rinshi, she died of an illness in August of the same year at the age of 86.</e>
<cmt>「長和元年」はグレゴリオ暦では1013年で原文表記に相違がありますが、前出で死亡年が「長和5年（1016年）」となっているため、西暦表示（1016年）を採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), Point136(id:211299), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>