<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原実資</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 実資（ふじわら の さねすけ、天徳 (日本)元年（957年） - 永承元年1月18日 (旧暦)（1046年2月26日））は、平安時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke (957 - February 26, 1046) was a high court official during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke (957 - February 26, 1046) was a high court official during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke (957 - March 4, 1046) was a high court official during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家の一流・小野宮流の藤原斉敏の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Tadatoshi, who belonged to the house of Ononomiya, one of the northern houses of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Tadatoshi, who belonged to the house of Ononomiya, one of the northern houses of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the fourth son of FUJIWARA no Tadatoshi, who belonged to the house of Ononomiya, one of the northern houses of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に祖父藤原実頼の養子となり小野宮流を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was later adopted by his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Saneyori, to succeed him as the head of the house of Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was later adopted by his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Saneyori, to succeed him as the head of the house of Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was later adopted by his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Saneyori, to succeed him as the head of the house of Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>養子に藤原資高、藤原資平。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had two adopted sons, FUJIWARA no Suketaka and FUJIWARA no Sukehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had two adopted sons, FUJIWARA no Suketaka and FUJIWARA no Sukehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had two adopted sons, FUJIWARA no Suketaka and FUJIWARA no Sukehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>実子に藤原資頼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sukeyori was his own son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sukeyori was his own son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sukeyori was his own son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼名は大学丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a child he was called Daigakumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a child he was called Daigakumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a child he was called Daigakumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>小野宮実資とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as Sanesuke ONONOMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as Sanesuke ONONOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Sanesuke ONONOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>藤原北家嫡流の小野宮流の膨大な家領を継ぎ、また有職故実に精通した当代一流の学識人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, who inherited the enormous family territory of the house of Ononomiya, a major branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, was one of the most outstanding scholars during his period, who had an intimate knowledge of traditional court customs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, who inherited the enormous family territory of the house of Ononomiya, a major branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, was one of the most outstanding scholars during his period, and had intimate knowledge of traditional court customs.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, who inherited the enormous family territory of the house of Ononomiya, a major branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, was one of the most outstanding scholars during his period, and had intimate knowledge of traditional court customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原道長が権勢を振るった時代に筋を通した態度を貫き、権貴に阿らぬ人との評価を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued to take a principled stand in the period when FUJIWARA no Michinaga wielded power and was highly regarded as a person who did not kneel before those in power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to take a principled stand in the period when FUJIWARA no Michinaga wielded power and was highly regarded as a person who did not kneel before those in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to take a principled stand in the period when FUJIWARA no Michinaga wielded power and was highly regarded as a person who did not kneel before those in power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>最終的に従一位右大臣に昇り、「賢人右府」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He rose to the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and was appointed as Udaijin (Minister of the Right), being also known as &quot;the wisest person in the court.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He rose to the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and was appointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right), being also known as &quot;the wisest person in the court.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He rose to the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and was appointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right), being also known as &apos;the wisest person in the court.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>実資の残した日記『小右記』はこの時代を知る貴重な資料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His diary, &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; provides valuable material for understanding this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His diary, &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; provides valuable material for understanding this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His diary, &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; provides valuable material for understanding this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>祖父の実頼は摂政関白を歴任した藤原忠平の長男で、村上天皇のときに左大臣、冷泉天皇のときに関白、円融天皇のときに摂政を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke&apos;s grandfather, Saneyori, was the eldest son of FUJIWARA no Tadahira, who served as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) during Emperor Murakami&apos;s reign, as Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) during Emperor Reizei&apos;s reign and as the Regent during Emperor Enyu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke&apos;s grandfather, Saneyori, was the eldest son of FUJIWARA no Tadahira, who served as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) during Emperor Murakami&apos;s reign, as Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) during Emperor Reizei&apos;s reign, and as the Regent during Emperor Enyu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke&apos;s grandfather, Saneyori, was the eldest son of FUJIWARA no Tadahira, who served as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) during Emperor Murakami&apos;s reign, as Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) during Emperor Reizei&apos;s reign, and as Sessho (Regent) during Emperor Enyu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>Sessho を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>実頼の二男の藤原頼忠も円融天皇、花山天皇の関白を務め朝政を指導したが、小野宮流は天皇との外戚関係を結べなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Saneyori&apos;s second son, FUJIWARA no Yoritada, also served as Chief Advisor to Emperor Enyu and Emperor Kazan, leading the imperial court, the house of Ononomiya was unable to develop a marriage relationship with the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Saneyori&apos;s second son, FUJIWARA no Yoritada, also served as Chief Advisor to Emperor Enyu and Emperor Kazan, leading the imperial court, the house of Ononomiya was unable to develop a marriage relationship with the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Saneyori&apos;s second son, FUJIWARA no Yoritada, also served as Kanpaku to Emperor Enyu and Emperor Kazan, leading the Imperial Court, the house of Ononomiya was unable to develop a marriage relationship with the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>Kanpaku としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>一方、天皇との外戚関係を巧みにつくった実頼の弟の藤原師輔（九条流）の子の藤原伊尹、藤原兼通、藤原兼家が台頭して摂関を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Saneyori&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Morosuke (house of Kujo), was cunning enough to marry his daughters into the imperial family, and his sons, FUJIWARA no Koretada, FUJIWARA no Kanemichi and FUIWARA no Kaneie rose to power, successively assuming the positions of Chief Adviser to the Emperor and Regent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Saneyori&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Morosuke (house of Kujo), was cunning enough to marry his daughters into the imperial family, and his sons, FUJIWARA no Koretada, FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, and FUIWARA no Kaneie rose to power, successively assuming the positions of Chief Adviser to the Emperor and Regent.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Saneyori&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Morosuke (house of Kujo), was cunning enough to marry his daughters into the Imperial family, and his sons, FUJIWARA no Koretada, FUJIWARA no Kanemichi, and FUJIWARA no Kaneie rose to power, successively assuming the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>Sessho and Kanpaku としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一条天皇が即位すると強い外戚関係を持つ兼家が摂政に任じられ、彼の系統が政治の主導権を握るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Ichijo succeeded to the throne, Kaneie, who had great influence over the imperial family as its maternal relative, was appointed as the Regent, with his lineage members taking the leading part in the imperial government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Ichijo succeeded to the throne, Kaneie, who had great influence over the imperial family as its maternal relative, was appointed the Regent, with his lineage members taking the leading part in the imperial government.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Ichijo succeeded to the throne, Kaneie, who had great influence over the Imperial family as its maternal relative, was appointed as Sessho, with his lineage members taking the leading part in the Imperial government.</e>
<cmt>Sessho としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>実資は参議斉敏の四男に生まれ、後に祖父の実頼の養子となり、非常に愛されて家領の多くを相続し、小野宮流を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born as the fourth son of Tadatoshi, who served as a vice-minister of the imperial government, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke was later adopted by his grandfather, Saneyori, as his son; and adored by Saneyori, he inherited the bulk of Saneyori&apos;s family territory, succeeding Saneyori as the head of the house of Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born the fourth son of Tadatoshi, who served as a vice-minister of the imperial government, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke was later adopted by his grandfather, Saneyori, as his son; and adored by Saneyori, he inherited the bulk of Saneyori&apos;s family territory, succeeding Saneyori as the head of the house of Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born the fourth son of Tadatoshi, who served as Sangi (Councilor) of the Imperial government, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke was later adopted by his grandfather, Saneyori, as his son; and adored by Saneyori, he inherited the bulk of Saneyori&apos;s family territory, succeeding Saneyori as the head of the house of Ononomiya.</e>
<cmt>参議→ Sangi (Councilor) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>小野宮流は藤原北家嫡流でありながら、分派であるはずの九条流に摂家の主導権を奪われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the house of Ononomiya was a major branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, it lagged behind the house of Kujo, a minor Fujiwara branch, in the struggle for leadership between the two Sekke regent families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the house of Ononomiya was a major branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, it lagged behind the house of Kujo, a minor Fujiwara branch, in the struggle for leadership between the two Sekke regent families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the house of Ononomiya was a major branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, it lagged behind the house of Kujo, a minor Fujiwara branch, in the struggle for leadership between the two Sekke regent families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかしながら、九条流に対して記録資料の面で優れ、故実に通じる家として著名であり、実資は膨大な記録資料を実頼より継承したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the house of Ononomiya, which was more skilled in collecting records and documents and was celebrated as a house well versed in traditional court customs, is believed to have inherited an enormous number of old records and documents from Saneyori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, the house of Ononomiya, which was more skilled in collecting records and documents and was celebrated as a house well versed in traditional court customs, is believed to have inherited an enormous number of old records and documents from Saneyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the house of Ononomiya, which was more skilled in collecting records and documents and was celebrated as a house well versed in traditional court customs, is believed to have inherited an enormous number of old records and documents from Saneyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その膨大な家領については未だ不明な部分も多いが、相当な財力を有していたことは、当該期史料から判明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While little is known about its vast family territory, it is clear from various historical materials of the period that it had considerable wealth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While little is known about its vast family territory, it is clear from various historical materials of the period that it had considerable wealth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While little is known about its vast family territory, it is clear from various historical materials of the period that it had considerable wealth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>実資は故実家・資産家としても知られたが、物事の要点を押さえ、個人の利得や名声のために真実を覆さないという良識人でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke was known as a scholar with an intimate knowledge of traditional court customs and a man of wealth, but he was also a person with common sense, who was able to capture the essence of things and never concealed the truth to protect his personal interests or reputation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke was known as a scholar with an intimate knowledge of traditional court customs and a man of wealth, but he was also a person with common sense, who was able to capture the essence of things and never concealed the truth to protect his personal interests or reputation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke was known as a scholar with an intimate knowledge of traditional court customs and a man of wealth, but he was also a person with common sense, who was able to capture the essence of things and never concealed the truth to protect his personal interests or reputation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>円融天皇のときの天元 (日本)4年（981年）蔵人頭に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke was appointed as Kurodo no to (Chief Imperial Secretary) in 981, during Emperor Enyu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke was appointed Kurodo no to (Chief Imperial Secretary) in 981, during Emperor Enyu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke was appointed Kurodo no to (Chief Imperial Secretary) in 981, during Emperor Enyu&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一条天皇のときの永祚 (日本)元年（989年）に参議となり公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 989, he became a vice minister of the imperial government and assumed a high court official position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 989, he became a vice minister of the imperial government and assumed a high court official position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 989, he was appointed during the Emperor Ichijo&apos;s reign and assumed a high court official position.</e>
<cmt>一条天皇の時に　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>正暦元年（990年）に兼家が没すると、子の藤原道隆が関白となり、次いで藤原道兼を経て、道長が左大臣となり内覧を許され、藤原伊周（道隆の嫡子）との政争の末に主導権を握り、権勢を振るうようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of FUJIWARA no Kaneie in 990, his son, FUJIWARA no Michitaka became the Chief Adviser to the Emperor, while Michinaga succeeded FUJIWARA no Michikane as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left); and allowed to audit documents submitted to the emperor, Michinaga established his control of the imperial government after the political struggle with FUJIWARA no Korechika (Michitaka&apos;s legitimate son) and rose to power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of FUJIWARA no Kaneie in 990, his son, FUJIWARA no Michitaka, became the Chief Adviser to the Emperor, while Michinaga succeeded FUJIWARA no Michikane as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left); and, allowed to audit documents submitted to the emperor, Michinaga established his control of the imperial government after a political struggle with FUJIWARA no Korechika (Michitaka&apos;s legitimate son) and rose to power.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of FUJIWARA no Kaneie in 990, his son, FUJIWARA no Michitaka, became Kanpaku, while FUJIWARA no Michinaga succeeded FUJIWARA no Michikane as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) and was allowed to audit documents submitted to the emperor; Michinaga established his control of the Imperial government after a political struggle with FUJIWARA no Korechika (Michitaka&apos;s legitimate son) and rose to power.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>長保元年（999年）道長の娘の藤原彰子が入内することになり、その調度品のひとつとして四尺の屏風をつくらせ、それは当時の公卿名士たちから和歌を募り、藤原公任が選首となり、書家の藤原行成に筆を入れさせる趣向であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Akiko, was wedded to the emperor in 999, Michinaga had a folding screen four shaku (approximately 120 cm) wide created as a bridal gift, which was designed in such a way that Japanese waka poems, collected from well-known high court officials at the time and selected by FUJIWARA no Kinto, would be written onto it by a famous calligrapher, FUJIWARA no Yukinari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Akiko, was wedded to the emperor in 999, Michinaga had a folding screen four shaku (approximately 120 cm) wide created as a bridal gift, which was designed in such a way that Japanese waka poems, collected from well-known high court officials at the time and selected by FUJIWARA no Kinto, would be written onto it by a famous calligrapher, FUJIWARA no Yukinari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Akiko, was wedded to the emperor in 999, Michinaga had a folding screen of four shaku (approximately 120 cm) wide created as a bridal gift, which was designed in such a way that Japanese waka poems, collected from well-known high court officials at the time and selected by FUJIWARA no Kinto, would be written onto it by a famous calligrapher, FUJIWARA no Yukinari.</e>
<cmt>イタリックを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これには公卿たちだけでなく、花山法皇までも御製の歌を贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only high court officials but even Cloistered Emperor Kazan sent his own poem for the folding screen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only high court officials but even Cloistered Emperor Kazan sent his own poem for the folding screen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only high court officials but even Cloistered Emperor Kazan sent his own poem for the folding screen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このとき、中納言であった実資だけは「大臣の命を受けて、その屏風に歌をつくるなぞ、未だに前聞なし」と言って、道長から何度催促されても歌を献じるのを拒んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sanesuke, who served as Chunagon (Junior Councillor of State), alone refused to make a poem despite repeated requests by Michinaga, claiming that it was unheard-of for a court official to be ordered by a minister to make a poem for a folding screen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sanesuke, who served as Chunagon (Junior Councillor of State), alone refused to write a poem despite repeated requests by Michinaga, claiming that it was unheard-of for a court official to be ordered by a minister to write a poem for a folding screen.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sanesuke, who served as Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), alone refused to write a poem despite repeated requests by Michinaga, claiming that it was unheard-of for a court official to be ordered by a minister to write a poem for a folding screen.</e>
<cmt>中納言→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>長保3年（1001年）権大納言に任じられ、右近衛大将を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1001, Sanesuke was appointed as Gon no dainagon (Deputy Chief Councillor of State), serving also as Ukone no taisho (commander of the right inner palace guard division).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1001, Sanesuke was appointed Gon no dainagon (Deputy Chief Councillor of State), serving also as Ukone no taisho (commander of the right inner palace guard division).</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1001, Sanesuke was appointed Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state), serving also as Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>権大納言→Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>寛弘8年（1011年）一条天皇が崩御して三条天皇が即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1011, Emperor Sanjo ascended the throne after the death of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1011, Emperor Sanjo ascended the throne after the death of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1011, Emperor Sanjo ascended the throne after the death of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>三条天皇と道長は不仲で、やがてことごとに対立するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being at odds with Michinaga, Emperor Sanjo came to disagree with him on every occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being at odds with Michinaga, Emperor Sanjo came to disagree with him on every occasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being at odds with Michinaga, Emperor Sanjo came to disagree with him on every occasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>ところが朝臣の多くは権勢家の道長に阿り、天皇は孤立し、朝廷の綱紀は日々弛緩するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, most of the court retainers sided with Michinaga, who wielded great political power, isolating the emperor from politics and disrupting the official disciple of the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, most of the court retainers sided with Michinaga, who wielded great political power, isolating the emperor from politics and disrupting the official disciple of the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, most of the court retainers sided with Michinaga, who wielded great political power, isolating the emperor from politics and disrupting the official disciple of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この時も実資は敢然として公平な立場に努め、天皇も密かに実資に頼るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On these occasions also, Sanesuke steadfastly maintained an impartial attitude, causing the emperor to secretly depend on his support in consequence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On these occasions also, Sanesuke steadfastly maintained an impartial attitude, causing the emperor to secretly depend on his support in consequence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On these occasions also, Sanesuke steadfastly maintained an impartial attitude, causing the emperor to secretly depend on his support in consequence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="33">
<j>三条天皇には東宮（皇太子）時代からの女御に道長の娘の藤原妍子と藤原済時の娘の藤原せい子がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the court ladies Emperor Sanjo had frequented since he was the Crown Prince, there were Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Seishi, and FUJIWARA no Naritoki&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kenshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the court ladies Emperor Sanjo had frequented since he was the Crown Prince, there were Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Seishi, and FUJIWARA no Naritoki&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kenshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the court ladies Emperor Sanjo had frequented since he was the Crown Prince, there were Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kenshi, and FUJIWARA no Naritoki&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Seishi.</e>
<cmt>名前を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>即位とともに妍子は中宮とされたが子はなく、一方、娍子は敦明親王を生んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Sanjo succeeded to the throne, Kenshi was made his Chugu (empress), who however had no child, while Seishi had born Imperial Prince Atsuakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Sanjo succeeded to the throne, Kenshi was made his Chugu (empress), but had no child, while Seishi had borne Imperial Prince Atsuakira.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Sanjo succeeded to the throne, Kenshi was made his Chugu (empress), but had no child, while Seishi had borne Imperial Prince Atsuakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>長和元年（1012年）、天皇は娍子を皇后に立てるよう欲するが、道長に憚って決しかねていたところ、道長から立后の提案があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1012, wishing to make Seishi his empress, the emperor was still unable to make up his mind, worried about what Michinaga would think about his decision, whereupon Michinaga suggested that Seishi be officially invested as the Empress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1012, wishing to make Seishi his empress, the emperor was still unable to make up his mind, worried about what Michinaga would think about his decision, whereupon Michinaga suggested that Seishi be officially invested as the Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1012, wishing to make Seishi his empress, the emperor was still unable to make up his mind, worried about what Michinaga would think about his decision, whereupon Michinaga suggested that Seishi be officially invested as the Empress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>ところが立后の儀式の日になると道長は嫌がらせを行い、同日を中宮妍子の参内の日として出席せず、諸公卿もこれに同調して皆中宮の東三条第へ行ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the day of the investiture of the empress, Michinaga refused to attend the ceremony in order to offend the emperor, on the pretext that it was the day to visit the Empress Kenshi, and went off to the palace of the Empress, accompanied by other high court officials, who all agreed with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on the day of the investiture of the empress, Michinaga refused to attend the ceremony in order to avoid offending the emperor, on the pretext that it was the day to visit the Empress Kenshi, and went off to the palace of the Empress, accompanied by other high court officials, who all agreed with him.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on the day of the investiture of the empress, Michinaga refused to attend the ceremony in order to offend the emperor, on the pretext that it was the day to visit the Chugu Kenshi, and went off to Hisashisanjo-tei (the palace of the Chugu), accompanied by other high court officials, who all agreed with him.</e>
<cmt>嫌がらせ→in order to offend としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>天皇は勅使を東三条第へ送って出席を命じるが、諸公卿には勅使を嘲り、参議藤原正光に至っては瓦礫を投げつける始末だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor sent an imperial messenger to Higashi-Sanjo dai and ordered all court officials to attend the investiture ceremony, but officials jeered at the messenger, and FUJIWARA no Masamitsu, one of the vice-ministers of the imperial government, even went so far as to throw stones at him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor sent an imperial messenger to Higashi-Sanjo dai and ordered all court officials to attend the investiture ceremony, but officials jeered at the messenger, and FUJIWARA no Masamitsu, one of the vice-ministers of the imperial government, even went so far as to throw stones at him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor sent an imperial messenger to Hisashisanjo-tei and ordered all court officials to attend the investiture ceremony, but officials jeered at the messenger, and FUJIWARA no Masamitsu, one of the Sangi of the Imperial government, even went so far as to throw stones at him.</e>
<cmt>Higashisanjo-tei としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>実資はこの日は病身であったが「天に二日なし、土に両主なし」と言うや中納言藤原隆家とともに参内して、儀式を取り仕切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Sanesuke was sick on that day, he visited the imperial palace together with Chunagon (Junior Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Takaie, saying that there were no two lords in a country just as there were no two suns in heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Sanesuke was sick on that day, he visited the imperial palace together with Chunagon (Junior Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Takaie, saying that there were no two lords in a country just as there were no two suns in heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Sanesuke was sick on that day, he visited the Imperial Palace together with Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Takaie, saying that there were no two lords in a country just as there were no two suns in heaven.</e>
<cmt>中納言→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="39">
<j>三条天皇は実資の態度を徳として感謝し、実資の子の資平に「朕は長く東宮にあって物情を知らず、一旦登極すれば全て意のままになると思っていたのに、后を立てるにも皆左大臣（道長）を憚り、勅命に応じようともしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feeling grateful for Sanesuke&apos;s virtuous behavior, Emperor Sanjo told him that he grew up as the Crown Prince without understanding worldly affairs and that although he had thought he would be able to control everything as he wished once he succeeded to the throne, he found himself powerless before his men, who did not obey his order to attend the investiture ceremony in fear of the Minister of the Left (Michinaga).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feeling grateful for Sanesuke&apos;s virtuous behavior, Emperor Sanjo told him that he grew up as the Crown Prince without understanding worldly affairs and that although he had thought he would be able to control everything as he wished once he succeeded to the throne, he found himself powerless before his men, who did not obey his order to attend the investiture ceremony in fear of the Minister of the Left (Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feeling grateful for Sanesuke&apos;s virtuous behavior, Emperor Sanjo told Sukehira, Sanesuke&apos;s son, that he grew up as the Crown Prince without understanding worldly affairs and that although he had thought he would be able to control everything as he wished once he succeeded to the throne, he found himself powerless before his men, who did not obey his order to attend the investiture ceremony in fear of Sadaijin (Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>実資の子の資平　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>（実資の）忠懇を嘉とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor then thanked Sanesuke for his loyalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor then thanked Sanesuke for his loyalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor then thanked Sanesuke for his loyalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これからは諸事、大将と議したい」と伝え、これを聞いた実資は歓喜した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke rejoiced to hear the emperor&apos;s words that he wished to consult him about all matters from then onward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke rejoiced to hear the emperor&apos;s words that he wished to consult him about all matters from then onward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke rejoiced to hear the emperor&apos;s words that he wished to consult him about all matters from then onward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>もっとも、賢明な実資は道長と正面から対決するようなことはせず、あくまで筋を通す態度を貫き、また、三条天皇も資平を蔵人頭に任じると約束しながら、道長を憚って止み沙汰にしてしまうなど、あまり頼りにはならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sanesuke was wise enough not to directly confront Michinaga and simply maintained principled behavior, while Emperor Sanjo himself was also not very trustworthy, breaking his promise to appoint Sanesuke as Kurodo no to (Chief Imperial Secretary) in fear of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sanesuke was wise enough not to directly confront Michinaga and simply maintained principled behavior, while Emperor Sanjo himself was also not very trustworthy, breaking his promise to appoint Sanesuke Kurodo no to (Chief Imperial Secretary) in fear of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sanesuke was wise enough not to directly confront Michinaga and simply maintained principled behavior, while Emperor Sanjo himself was also not very trustworthy, breaking his promise to appoint Sanesuke Kurodo no to in fear of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>蔵人の頭　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="43">
<j>道長と対立を続けた三条天皇だが、やがて失明寸前の眼病となり、道長から強く退位を迫られ、結局、長和5年（1016年）に皇子の敦明親王を東宮とすることを条件に後一条天皇に譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Emperor Sanjo continued to confront Michinaga, he later contracted an eye disease that nearly made him lose his eyesight; and repeatedly urged by Michinaga to resign from his office, he finally agreed to hand over the throne to Emperor Goichijo in 1016, on condition that his son, Imperial Prince Atsuakira, be made the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Emperor Sanjo continued to confront Michinaga, he later contracted an eye disease that nearly made him lose his eyesight; and repeatedly urged by Michinaga to resign from his office, he finally agreed to hand over the throne to Emperor Goichijo in 1016, on condition that his son, Imperial Prince Atsuakira, be made the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Emperor Sanjo continued to confront Michinaga, he later contracted an eye disease that nearly made him lose his eyesight; he was repeatedly urged by Michinaga to resign from his office, and he finally agreed to hand over the throne to Emperor Goichijo in 1016, on condition that his son, Imperial Prince Atsuakira, be made the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>he was repeatedly urged としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>春宮大夫には実資が推薦されたが、実資は老衰の身であるとして固辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though recommended as Shungu no daibu (Chief Officer of the Crown Prince&apos;s palace), Sanesuke declined the offer for the reason that he was getting too old for the job.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though recommended as Shungu no daibu (Chief Officer of the Crown Prince&apos;s palace), Sanesuke declined the offer for the reason that he was getting too old for the job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although recommended as Shungu no daibu (Chief Officer of the Crown Prince&apos;s palace), Sanesuke declined the offer for the reason that he was getting too old for the job.</e>
<cmt>Although としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>翌寛仁元年（1017年）に三条上皇が崩御すると、約束は反故とされ、道長の画策で敦明親王は東宮を辞退している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Sanjo died in 1017, Michinaga broke his promise and plotted a scheme to make Imperial Prince Atsuakira decline the offer to be appointed as the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Sanjo died in 1017, Michinaga broke his promise and plotted a scheme to make Imperial Prince Atsuakira decline the offer to be appointed the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Sanjo died in 1017, Michinaga broke his promise and plotted a scheme to make Imperial Prince Atsuakira decline the offer to be appointed the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="46">
<j>寛仁3年（1019年）、刀伊の入寇を撃退した大宰権帥藤原隆家が部下らに対する恩賞を懇請し、これに対して諸国申請雑事定が公卿らによって行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1019, FUJIWARA no Takaie, the Viceroy of the Dazaifu government in Kyushu, who fought off the attack of foreign pirates, requested that his men be given rewards for their military contributions, and in response to his request, rules regarding local governments were discussed among high court officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1019, FUJIWARA no Takaie, the Viceroy of the Dazaifu government in Kyushu, who fought off the attack of foreign pirates, requested that his men be given rewards for their military contributions, and in response to his request, rules regarding local governments were discussed among high court officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1019, FUJIWARA no Takaie, who served as Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu office in Kyushu) and fought off the attack of foreign pirates in Toi invasion, requested that his men be given rewards for their military contributions, and in response to his request, rules regarding local governments were discussed among high court officials.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>大納言藤原公任と中納言藤原行成は、「彼らは追討の勅符が到達する以前に戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainagon (Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Kinto, and Chunagon (Junior Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Yukinari argued that Takaie&apos;s army fought before receiving the imperial charter to fight off the pirates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainagon (Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Kinto, and Chunagon (Junior Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Yukinari argued that Takaie&apos;s army fought before receiving the imperial charter to fight off the pirates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainagon (chief councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Kinto, and Chunagon FUJIWARA no Yukinari argued that Takaie&apos;s army fought before receiving the imperial charter to fight off the pirates.</e>
<cmt>中納言　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>故に私闘であるから賞するには及ばない」と主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They maintained that for that reason, their battle was a private battle and that they did not deserve to be given rewards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They maintained that for that reason, their battle was a private battle and they did not deserve to be given rewards.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They maintained that for that reason, their battle was a private battle and they did not deserve to be given rewards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>貴族らは文官統治を維持するために軍事を軽く見る傾向にあり、また、隆家は道長の政敵であった伊周の弟でもあり、道長に追従したためでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Court nobles, who represented civilian rule, were likely to underestimate the importance of military affairs and they also tried to flatter Michinaga by downgrading Takaie, who was a younger brother of Korechika, Michinaga&apos;s political enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Court nobles, who represented civilian rule, were likely to underestimate the importance of military affairs and they also tried to flatter Michinaga by downgrading Takaie, who was a younger brother of Korechika, Michinaga&apos;s political enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Court nobles, who represented civilian rule, were likely to underestimate the importance of military affairs and they also tried to flatter Michinaga by downgrading Takaie, who was a younger brother of Korechika, Michinaga&apos;s political enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="50">
<j>これに対し実資は勅符が到達する以前に戦った点には問題があることを認めつつも、「勅符が到達したかどうかは問題ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Sanesuke, admitting that there were issues to be discussed about fighting the battle before receiving the imperial charter, argued that the question was not whether they received the charter or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Sanesuke, admitting that there were issues to be discussed about fighting the battle before receiving the imperial charter, argued that the question was not whether they received the charter.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;or not&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Sanesuke, admitting that there were issues to be discussed about fighting the battle before receiving the imperial charter, argued that the question was not whether they received the charter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>たとえ勅がなかったとしても、勲功ある者を賞する例は何事にもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went on to argue that there were many examples where soldiers were awarded for their military contributions they made without imperial charters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went on to argue that there were many examples where soldiers were awarded for their military contributions they made without imperial charters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went on to argue that there were many examples where soldiers were awarded for their military contributions they made without imperial charters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>寛平6年（894年）に新羅の凶賊が対馬を襲撃したとき、島司文室善友は直ちにこれを撃退し、賞を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, when the barbarians of Shiragi attacked Tsushima in 894, BUNYA no Yoshitomo, the governor of Tsushima, was highly rewarded for fighting off those barbarians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, when the barbarians of Shiragi attacked Tsushima in 894, BUNYA no Yoshitomo, the governor of Tsushima, was highly rewarded for fighting off those barbarians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, when the barbarians of Shiragi attacked Tsushima in 894, BUNYA no Yoshitomo, the governor of Tsushima, was highly rewarded for fighting off those barbarians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これと同じことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Sanesuke, there was no difference between Takaie and his men&apos;s behavior and BUNYA no Yoshitomo&apos;s behavior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Sanesuke, there was no difference between Takaie and his men&apos;s behavior and BUNYA no Yoshitomo&apos;s behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Sanesuke, there was no difference between Takaie and his men&apos;s behavior and BUNYA no Yoshitomo&apos;s behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>特に今回の事件は、外敵が警固所に肉薄し、各島人が一千人余りも誘拐され、数百人が殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he pointed out in his argument, during the attack, pirates came close to the guard station, abducting more than 1,000 residents of the island and killing several hundreds of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he pointed out in his argument, during the attack, pirates came close to the guard station, abducting more than 1,000 residents of the island and killing several hundred of them.</e>
<cmt>&quot;hundreds&quot; to &quot;hundred&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he pointed out in his argument, during the attack, pirates came close to the guard station, abducting more than 1,000 residents of the island and killing several hundred of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>壱岐国受領藤原理忠も戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masatada, the Governor of Iki Province, was also killed in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Masatada, the Governor of Iki Province, was also killed in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Masatada, the Governor of Iki Province, was also killed in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>しかし、大宰府は直ちに軍を動かしてこれを撃攘せしめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dazaifu government immediately organized its army to fight off the pirates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dazaifu government immediately organized its army to fight off the pirates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dazaifu government immediately organized its army to fight off the pirates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>何故に賞さないことがあろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And that was well worthy of reward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And that was well worthy of reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And that was well worthy of reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>もし賞さないならば、今後進んで事に当たる勇士はいなくなってしまうであろう」と弁じ立てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If their behavior were not rewarded, there would be no brave soldiers left in the imperial army - Sanesuke argued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If their behavior were not rewarded, there would be no brave soldiers left in the imperial army - Sanesuke argued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If their behavior were not rewarded, there would be no brave soldiers left in the imperial army - Sanesuke argued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="59">
<j>まず、大納言藤原斉信がこれに同意し、続いて公任・行成も翻意、ついに公卿ら皆意見を同じくして褒賞は決議された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke&apos;s argument was supported first by Dainagon FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, after whom Kinto and Yukinari also changed their decision, with all high court officials finally agreeing on giving reward to the soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke&apos;s argument was supported first by Dainagon FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, after whom Kinto and Yukinari also changed their decision, with all high court officials finally agreeing on giving reward to the soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke&apos;s argument was supported first by Dainagon FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, after whom Kinto and Yukinari also changed their decision, with all high court officials finally agreeing on giving reward to the soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また、当時政治の一線から退いていた道長もこれを是としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga, who had already been retired from the frontline politics, also agreed with Sanesuke&apos;s opinion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga, who had already retired from frontline politics, also agreed with Sanesuke&apos;s opinion.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga, who had already retired from frontline politics, also agreed with Sanesuke&apos;s opinion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>このとき実資は右大臣に任ぜられるか否かで同僚らの歓心を買わなければいけない時期だったが、それでも付和雷同・阿諛追従することなく、ものごとの道理を滔々と陳述している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Sanesuke, who was about to be appointed as the next Udaijin (Minister of the Right), was faced with the need to curry favor with his colleagues, but he made his statements to reach an impartial decision without siding with, or flattering other people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Sanesuke, who was about to be appointed the next Udaijin (Minister of the Right), was faced with the need to curry favor with his colleagues, but he made his statements to reach an impartial decision without siding with or flattering other people.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Sanesuke, who was about to be appointed the next Udaijin, was faced with the need to curry favor with his colleagues, but he made his statements to reach an impartial decision without siding with or flattering other people.</e>
<cmt>右大臣　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="62">
<j>治安 (元号)元年（1021年）右大臣を拝し、皇太弟傅を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1021, he was appointed as Udaijin and also as the Educational Adviser to the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1021, he was appointed Udaijin and the Educational Adviser to the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1021, he was appointed Udaijin and Kotaitei no fu (the Educational Adviser to the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>Kotaitei no fu を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>長暦元年（1037年）従一位に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1037.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1037.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1037.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="64">
<j>常に九条流に対抗する家の当主として活躍したが、晩年は子の資平への家督継承と家領温存のため、道長・藤原頼通親子に口入を申し出るなど、九条流への柔軟な行動も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Sanesuke always acted as the head of a family opposed to the house of Kujo, he also exhibited flexible behavior toward the Kujo family, especially in his later years, requesting Michinaga and his son, FAIRWARA no Yorimichi, to help his adopted son, Sukehira, to succeed him as the head of the family and to inherit the family property intact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Sanesuke always acted as the head of a family opposed to the house of Kujo, he also exhibited flexible behavior toward the Kujo family, especially in his later years, requesting Michinaga and his son, FAIRWARA no Yorimichi, to help his adopted son, Sukehira, to succeed him as the head of the family and to inherit the family property intact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Sanesuke always acted as the head of a family opposed to the house of Kujo, he also exhibited flexible behavior toward the Kujo family, especially in his later years, requesting Michinaga and his son, FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, to help his adopted son, Sukehira, to succeed him as the head of the family and to inherit the family property intact.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>一方、頼通の方も政界の長老である実資への敬意を怠らなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimichi also never failed to show respect to Sanesuke as an elderly statesman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimichi also never failed to show respect to Sanesuke as an elderly statesman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimichi also never failed to show respect to Sanesuke as an elderly statesman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>その一方で、当時の慣例に反して頼通が関白のまま実資と共同で一上の職務を行い、藤原公季の死去により空席になった太政大臣への昇進を頼通が実資の死後まで控えたのは、実資が頼通の後任の左大臣に昇進することで、一上として太政官を率いて頼通と対抗することを恐れたからだとも言われている（一上には通常左大臣が就任して、関白及び太政大臣はその職務には携わらず、左大臣が関白を兼ねる場合には右大臣が一上となる慣例であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, it is believed that the reason why Yorimichi fulfilled his duty as Ichi no kami (the head of high court officials) jointly with Sanesuke without leaving the position of Kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor) against the court custom of the time and declined to be promoted to the office of Dajodaijin (Prime Minister), which had remained vacant after the death of FUJIWARA no Kinsue, until after the death of Sanesuke was that he was afraid of the possibility that Sanesuke, promoted to the office of Sadaijin after Yorimichi, might come into conflict with Yorimichi and lead all ministers as Ichi no kami (the office of Ichi no kami was normally assumed by the Sadaijin, while the Chief Advisor to the Emperor and cabinet ministers did not perform the duty as Ichi no kami, and if the Sadaijin also served as Kanpaku, Udaijin was normally appointed as Ichi no kami).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, it is believed that the reason why Yorimichi fulfilled his duty as Ichi no kami (the head of high court officials) jointly with Sanesuke without leaving the position of Kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor) against the court custom of the time and declined to be promoted to the office of Dajodaijin (Prime Minister), which had remained vacant after the death of FUJIWARA no Kinsue, until after the death of Sanesuke, was that he was afraid of the possibility that Sanesuke, promoted to the office of Sadaijin after Yorimichi, might come into conflict with Yorimichi and lead all ministers as Ichi no kami (the office of Ichi no kami was normally assumed by the Sadaijin, while the Chief Advisor to the Emperor and cabinet ministers did not perform the duty as Ichi no kami, and if the Sadaijin also served as Kanpaku, Udaijin was normally appointed as Ichi no kami).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, it is believed that the reason why Yorimichi fulfilled his duty as Ichi no kami (the head of high court officials) jointly with Sanesuke without leaving the position of Kanpaku against the court custom of the time and declined to be promoted to the office of Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), which had remained vacant after the death of FUJIWARA no Kinsue, until after the death of Sanesuke, was that he was afraid of the possibility that Sanesuke, promoted to the office of Sadaijin after Yorimichi, might come into conflict with Yorimichi and lead all ministers as Ichi no kami (the office of Ichi no kami was normally assumed by the Sadaijin, while Kanpaku and Daijo-daijin did not perform the duty as Ichi no kami, and if the Sadaijin also served as Kanpaku, Udaijin was normally appointed as Ichi no kami).</e>
<cmt>関白　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="67">
<j>花山天皇の女御・婉子女王と大恋愛して結婚したが子供に恵まれず、晩年アルツハイマー型認知症が進行してからは焦りのために手当たり次第に手を出し、政治上の弟子である宇治関白頼通（彼は妻が非常に少ない）を嘆かせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke fell passionately in love with Princess Enshi, who was Emperor Kazan&apos;s court lady, but had no child of his own born by Enshi, and in his later years, suffering from Alzheimer&apos;s disease, he had relationships with women at random, making his political disciple, Uji Kanpaku Yorimichi (who had a very small number of wives) lament about his love affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke fell passionately in love with Princess Enshi, who was Emperor Kazan&apos;s court lady, but had no child of his own born by Enshi, and in his later years, suffering from Alzheimer&apos;s disease, he had relationships with women at random, making his political disciple, Uji Kanpaku Yorimichi (who had a very small number of wives) lament about his love affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke fell passionately in love with Princess Enshi, who was Emperor Kazan&apos;s court lady, but had no child of his own born by Enshi, and in his later years, suffering from Alzheimer&apos;s disease, he had relationships with women at random, making his political disciple, Uji Kanpaku Yorimichi (who had a very small number of wives) lament about his love affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>弟・権中納言藤原懐平の子である資平を養子としたが、最愛の子は実女・藤原千古（ちこ、ちふる）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He adopted Sukehira, a son of his younger brother, FUJIWARA no Kanehira, who served as the Deputy Junior Councillor of State, as his son, but his dearest child was his real daughter, FUJIWARA no Chifuru (Chiko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He adopted Sukehira, a son of his younger brother, FUJIWARA no Kanehira, who served as the Deputy Junior Councillor of State, as his son, but his dearest child was his real daughter, FUJIWARA no Chifuru (Chiko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He adopted Sukehira, a son of his younger brother, FUJIWARA no Kanehira, who served as Gon Chunagon, as his son, but his dearest child was his real daughter, FUJIWARA no Chifuru (Chiko).</e>
<cmt>中納言　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="69">
<j>永承元年（1046年）に90歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke died in 1046 at the age of 90.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke died in 1046 at the age of 90.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke died in 1046 at the age of 90.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>信仰厚い仏教であったが、今はの際まで現実社会で活躍することを好み、その死に臨んでも出家することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was a devout Buddhist, he preferred to be active in the secular world until his death, refusing to become a priest even on the verge of death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was a devout Buddhist, he preferred to be active in the secular world until his death, refusing to become a priest even on the verge of death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was a devout Buddhist, he preferred to be active in the secular world until his death, refusing to become a priest even on the verge of death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>天寿を全うするとき、彼の小野宮第には朝野上下の人々が参集し、声を放って慟哭したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People from all walks of life are believed to have attended his funeral held in Ononomiyadai and cried over his death out loud.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People from all walks of life are believed to have attended his funeral held in Ononomiyadai and cried over his death out loud.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People from all walks of life are believed to have attended his funeral held in Ononomiyadai and cried over his death out loud.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="72">
<j>実資は小野宮家の財産を多く、息女に継承させ、一子資平には一部しか継承させなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke bequeathed the bulk of the Ononomiya family&apos;s property to his daughters, leaving only a small part to his son, Sukehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke bequeathed the bulk of the Ononomiya family&apos;s property to his daughters, leaving only a small part to his son, Sukehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke bequeathed the bulk of the Ononomiya family&apos;s property to his daughters, leaving only a small part to his son, Sukehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>このためか、実頼から継承したと思われる家領は分散継承され、院政期には空中分解を遂げることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is perhaps for this reason that family property estimated to have been inherited from Sanesuke was dispersed among a number of families and was dissolved into pieces during the reign of retired emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is perhaps for this reason that family property estimated to have been inherited from Sanesuke was dispersed among a number of families and was dissolved into pieces during the reign of retired emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is perhaps for this reason that family property estimated to have been inherited from Sanesuke was dispersed among a number of families and was dissolved into pieces during the reign of retired emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また、男系子孫に財産が渡らなかったことによって同家の経済的な衰微を招き、小野宮家没落の原因を作ったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed that Sanesuke caused the economic decline of his family by not leaving property to descendants in the male line, which led finally to the downfall of the Ononomiya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also believed that Sanesuke caused the economic decline of his family by not leaving property to descendants in the male line, which eventually led to the downfall of the Ononomiya family.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also believed that Sanesuke caused the economic decline of his family by not leaving property to descendants in the male line, which eventually led to the downfall of the Ononomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="75">
<j>実資は日記史料として後年、故実に必携の書となる『小右記』（小野宮右大臣家記の略）を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanesuke left his diary, &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (Family Record of Udaijin Ononomiya), which provides indispensable material for understanding ancient court customs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanesuke left his diary, &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (Family Record of Udaijin Ononomiya), which provides indispensable material for understanding ancient court customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanesuke left his diary, &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (Family Record of Udaijin Ononomiya), which provides indispensable material for understanding ancient court customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>ここで実資は、現存する限り蔵人頭から右大臣近衛左大将を兼任するまで日記を残し、膨大な儀礼の記述を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His diary covers the period from the time when he became Kurodo no to until the time when he was appointed as Udaijin and Kone sadaisho (commander of the left inner palace guard division), providing descriptions of an enormous number of court rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His diary covers the period from the time when he became Kurodo no to until the time when he was appointed Udaijin and Kone sadaisho (commander of the left inner palace guard division), providing descriptions of an enormous number of court rituals.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His diary covers the period from the time when he became Kurodo no to until the time when he was appointed Udaijin and Kone no Sadaisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), providing descriptions of an enormous number of court rituals.</e>
<cmt>近衛左大将 の補足を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>また、個人的見解を記したことでも著名で、有名な藤原道長の「この世をば…」の和歌は実資の『小右記』から現代に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also well known for his personal comments on other people, and FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s famous waka poem, &quot;Kono yo o ba… (I have always been able to control this world as I wished)&quot; was made known to the later periods through his &quot;Shoyuki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also well known for his personal comments on other people, and FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s famous waka poem, &quot;Kono yo o ba… (I have always been able to control this world as I wished)&quot; was made known to the later periods through his &quot;Shoyuki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also well known for his personal comments on other people, and FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s famous waka poem, &apos;Kono yo o ba… (I have always been able to control this world as I wished)&apos; was made known to the later periods through his &quot;Shoyuki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Kitakyushu(id:47491), Novo(id:87875), Cprobot(id:97843), Hannah(id:15935), 水野白楓(id:22811), VoidAimai(id:212464), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), BAKU(id:55205), Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), 秋友良哉(id:50157), Point136(id:211299), Qaz(id:46297), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>