<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三好長逸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayasu MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三好長逸（みよしながやす、？ － 天正元年（1573年？））は戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayasu MIYOSHI was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Japan) (his dates of birth and death are unknown though he was believed to be dead in 1573.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu MIYOSHI was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Japan) (his dates of birth and death are unknown, although he was believed to have died in 1573).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu MIYOSHI was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (his dates of birth and death are unknown, although he was believed to have died in 1573).</e>
<cmt>戦国時代、説明補足。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三好氏の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日向守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Hyuga-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Hyuga-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Hyuga no kami (the governor of Hyuga Province).</e>
<cmt>日向守→Hyuga no kami (the governor of Hyuga Province)、ハイフン削除、説明補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称は孫四郎、別名として長縁ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known as Magoshiro and seemed to have another name, Nagayori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as Magoshiro and may have had another name--Nagayori.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as Magoshiro and may have had another name, Nagayori.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、コンマ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>三好三人衆の一人で、その筆頭格であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a member of the Miyoshi Sannin-shu (three elite retainers of Miyoshi) and played the role of a leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of the Miyoshi Sannin-shu (three elite retainers of Miyoshi) and played the role of a leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of the Miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan) and played the role of a leader.</e>
<cmt>三好三人衆→miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan)　用語集より</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>三好一族の一人で、三好之長の孫で、三好長光（芥川長光）の子にあたるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was believed to be from the Miyoshi family and a grandson of Yukinaga MIYOSHI and a son of Nagamitsu MIYOSHI (Nagamitsu AKUTAGAWA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was believed to be from the Miyoshi family and a grandson of Yukinaga MIYOSHI as well as a son of Nagamitsu MIYOSHI (Nagamitsu AKUTAGAWA).</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was believed to be from the Miyoshi family and a grandson of Yukinaga MIYOSHI as well as a son of Nagamitsu MIYOSHI (Nagamitsu AKUTAGAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に三好久助（久介、長将とも）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a son, Hisasuke MIYOSHI (三好久助) (also called Hisasuke (久介) and Nagamasa (長将).)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a son, Hisasuke MIYOSHI (三好久助), who was also known as Hisasuke (久介) and Nagamasa (長将).</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a son, Hisasuke MIYOSHI (三好久助), who was also known as Hisasuke (久介) and Nagamasa (長将).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>生年は不明だが、永正12年（1520年）、祖父とされる之長と父とされる長光が戦死しており、長光の子だとすれば出生はそれ以前ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His date of birth is unknown, but Yukinaga who was believed to be his grandfather and Nagamitsu who was believed to his father were killed in war in 1520 and if he was Nagamitsu&apos;s son, his date of birth would have been earlier than the date of his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His date of birth is unknown, but Yukinaga, who was believed to be his grandfather, and Nagamitsu, who was believed to his father, were killed in war in 1520. If he was Nagamitsu&apos;s son, his date of birth would have been earlier than the date of his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His date of birth is unknown, but Yukinaga, who was believed to be his grandfather, and Nagamitsu, who was believed to his father, were killed in war in 1520, so his date of birth would have been earlier than the date of his father&apos;s death if he was Nagamitsu&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>三好長慶に仕える三好一族の一人として、有馬重則の要請に応じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the request of Shigenori ARIMA, he, one from the Miyoshi clan who serving Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, was involved in attacking Harima-no-kuni and also subduing Harumichi HATANO in Tanba-no-kuni (Nagayasu lost the war and Nagayori MATSUNAGA took his place) to contribute to the expansion of Nagayoshi&apos;s power of influence, and also combated against the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA who was defying Nagayoshi at Nagayoshi&apos;s direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu MIYOSHI accepted Shigenori ARIMA&apos;s request from the position of a member of the Miyoshi clan who served Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu MIYOSHI accepted Shigenori ARIMA&apos;s request from the position of a member of the Miyoshi clan who served Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>播磨国攻めや、丹波国の波多野晴通討伐（これは敗北し、松永長頼に代わった）など長慶の勢力拡大に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu attacked Harima-no-kuni and subdued Harumichi HATANO in Tanba-no-kuni (Nagayasu lost the war and Nagayori MATSUNAGA took his place), and also contributed to the expansion of Nagahoshi&apos;s sphere of influence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu attacked Harima Province and subdued Harumichi HATANO in Tanba Province (Nagayasu lost the war and Nagayori MATSUNAGA took his place), and also contributed to the expansion of Nagahoshi&apos;s sphere of influence.</e>
<cmt>播磨国/丹波国、－Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>長慶に反発する13代将軍・足利義輝とも長慶の命令で戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following Nagayoshi&apos;s orders, he also fought against the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, who was defying Nagayoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Nagayoshi&apos;s orders, he also fought against the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, who was defying Nagayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>長逸は三好一族の中でも、長慶に最も信頼されて、1558年頃までには山城国の飯岡城主を任ぜられ、山城国南半分の統治を任されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayasu who was most relied upon by Nagayoshi in the Miyoshi clan was appointed as the castellan of Ioka Castle in Yamashiro-no-kuni to govern the southern half of Yamashiro-no-kuni in around 1558.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1558, Nagayasu, who was most relied upon by Nagayoshi in the Miyoshi clan, was appointed as the castellan of Ioka Castle in Yamashiro-no-kuni to govern the southern half of Yamashiro-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1558, Nagayasu, who was most relied upon by Nagayoshi in the Miyoshi clan, was appointed as the castellan of Ioka Castle in Yamashiro Province to govern the southern half of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>Yamashiro Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、同名衆にも列せられ、三好義賢や松永久秀よりも先に従四位に叙せられるなど、非常に三好家の中で重要な地位を占めていたことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was included in the Domei-shu (family of Miyoshi) and promoted to the Jushi rank (senior fourth rank) earlier than Yoshitaka MIYOSHI and Hidehisa MATSUNAGA, and it is understood that he assumed a very important role in the Miyoshi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was included in the Domei-shu (family of Miyoshi) and promoted to the rank of Jushi (senior fourth rank) sooner than Yoshitaka MIYOSHI and Hidehisa MATSUNAGA. It is understood that he assumed a very important role in the Miyoshi family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was included in the Domei-shu (family of Miyoshi) and promoted to the rank of Jushii (Senior Fourth Rank) sooner than Yoshitaka MIYOSHI and Hidehisa MATSUNAGA, so it is understood that he assumed a very important role in the Miyoshi family.</e>
<cmt>Jushii に訂正しました。 (Senior Fourth Rank)大文字にしました。一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>長慶の死後は幼少の当主・三好義継を他の三人衆や松永久秀らと共に補佐し、永禄8年（1565年）にはついに足利義輝を暗殺した（永禄の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nagayoshi died, he supported a young head of the family, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI in cooperation with other Miyoshi sannin-shu and Hisahide MATSUNAGA, and assassinated Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA in 1565 at the end (the Eiroku no Hen (Conspiracy of Eiroku.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nagayoshi died, he supported the young head of the family, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI allied with other Miyoshi sannin-shu and Hisahide MATSUNAGA, and ultimately assassinated Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA in 1565 (the Eiroku no Hen) (Conspiracy of Eiroku).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nagayoshi died, he supported the young head of the family, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI allied with other Miyoshi sanninshu and Hisahide MATSUNAGA, and ultimately assassinated Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA in 1565 (the Eiroku no Hen) (Conspiracy of Eiroku).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、三好家中における主導権争いから三好義継や松永久秀とは次第に対立を深め、永禄9年（1566年）に入ると両者は交戦状態に突入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, he was gradually suffering bad relations with Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA as a result of the leadership struggles in the Miyoshi family, and they went into war in 1566.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his relations with Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA gradually worsened as a result of the leadership struggles in the Miyoshi family. They went to war in 1566.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his relations with Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA gradually worsened as a result of the leadership struggles in the Miyoshi family, and they went to war in 1566.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>この過程で永禄10年（1567年）、三人衆の軍勢が陣取った奈良東大寺を松永軍が攻撃、焼亡する事件が起きている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the development of this battle, Todai-ji Temple which was occupied by the Miyoshi Sannin-shu&apos;s army to use it for their post was attacked by Matsunaga&apos;s soldiers and burnt down in 1567.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During battle, Todai-ji Temple, which was occupied by the Miyoshi Sannin-shu&apos;s army for use as an outpost, was attacked by Matsunaga&apos;s soldiers and burnt down in 1567.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the battle, Todai-ji Temple, which was occupied by the Miyoshi sanninshu&apos;s army for use as an outpost, was attacked by Matsunaga&apos;s soldiers and burnt down in 1567.</e>
<cmt>the補足しました。S小文字にしました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、その十日後には長逸の嫡男久助が山城国普賢谷で松永方の軍勢に討ち取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten days later from the above incident, Nagayasu&apos;s progeny, Hisasuke was killed in Yamashiro-no-kuni Fugendani by Matsunaga&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten days later, Nagayasu&apos;s son, Hisasuke was killed in Yamashiro-no-kuni Fugendani by Matsunaga&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten days later, Nagayasu&apos;s son, Hisasuke was killed in Fugendani, Yamashiro Province by Matsunaga&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt>Fugendani, Yamashiro Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>だが義継・松永方にこのような抵抗を受けつつも、戦局は全般的に長逸ら三人衆方の優勢で進んでいたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was encountering such resistance from the soldiers on the Yoshitugu and Matsunaga side, the war situation overall seemed to be continuously favorable for Miyoshi Sannin-shu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he encountered resistance from the soldiers on the Yoshitsugu and Matsunaga side, the war seemed to go overall favorably for Miyoshi Sannin-shu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he encountered resistance from the soldiers on the Yoshitsugu and Matsunaga side, the war seemed to go overall favorably for the Miyoshi sanninshu.</e>
<cmt>the補足しました。S小文字にし、ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）、織田信長が六万と号する大軍を擁し、永禄の変で三好方が取り逃がした足利義昭を押し立てて上洛を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1568, Nobunaga ODA collected a large army of 60,000 soldiers and began the Joraku (going to Kyoto) together with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA declared as a leader, whom the Miyoshi army had failed to grab in the Eiraku no Hen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1568, Nobunaga ODA collected a large army of 60,000 soldiers and travelled to Kyoto. Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, whom the Miyoshi army had failed to grab in the Eiraku no Hen, was declared leader.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1568, Nobunaga ODA collected a large army of 60,000 soldiers and travelled to Kyoto, and he declared Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, whom the Miyoshi army had failed to grab in Eiroku Incident, as a leader.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。永禄の変→Eiroku Incident 用語集より</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この動きに対し、三人衆がかつての宿敵である六角義賢や紀伊国の国人衆、高野山等と結んでこれに徹底して対立する姿勢を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyoshi Sannin-shu showed their attitudes to completely hinder their moves in partnership with Yoshitaka ROKKAKU, the Kuniudo-shu (Kokujin-shu) in Ki-no-kuni and Koya-san who had been long-time enemies, while Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA immediately displayed an obedience to Nobunaga because of the worsening situation caused by attacks from Miyoshi Sannin-shu.</e>
<cmt>リサーチしますと、高野山という山はないようで、従ってKoya-san Mountain は誤りと思います。Koya-sanという記述が大方で、 Mt.Koyaとするものもあります。ここでは山を意味してるのでなく、神社等の建物を含めた仏教の宗派等を意味していると判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyoshi Sannin-shu took a confrontational stance against these movements together with Yoshitaka ROKKAKU, the Kuniudo-shu (Kokujin-shu) in Ki-no-kuni and Koya-san who had been long-time enemies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyoshi sanninshu took a confrontational stance against these movements together with Yoshitaka ROKKAKU, the Kokujin-shu (local samurais) in Ki Province and Koya-san who had been long-time enemies.</e>
<cmt>S小文字にし、ハイフン削除。国人衆→Kokujin-shu (local samurais)　用語集より-no-kuniをProvinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一方で、三人衆の攻撃を受け劣勢に立っていた三好義継、松永久秀はいち早く信長に恭順する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA were in a worsening situation because of an attack from Miyoshi Sannin-shu; thus, they soon capitulated to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA were in a worsening situation because of an attack from the Miyoshi sanninshu; thus, they soon capitulated to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>the補足しました。S小文字にし、ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>三好長慶没後の三好家内紛の悪影響は甚大であり、織田信長の上洛を受けて三人衆方の国人衆や幕府奉公衆らからも織田方への寝返りが続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battles which broke out in the Miyoshi family after Nagayoshi&apos;s death seemed to very adversely influence the family, and given the Joraku (going to Kyoto) of Nobunaga ODA, the Kuniudo-shu (Kokujin-shu) and the Bakufu-Hoko-shu on the side of Miyoshi Sanni-shu switched to the Nobunaga side one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battles which broke out in the Miyoshi family after Nagayoshi&apos;s death seemed to have an adverse effect on the family. After Nobunaga ODA&apos;s journey to Kyoto, the Kuniudo-shu (Kokujin-shu) and the Bakufu-Hoko-shu, who sided with Miyoshi Sanni-shu, switched to the Nobunaga&apos;s side one after another.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battles which broke out in the Miyoshi family after Nagayoshi&apos;s death seemed to have an adverse effect on the family; after Nobunaga ODA&apos;s journey to Kyoto, the Kokujin-shu and the bakufu&apos;s hokoshu (a military post in Muromachi Shogunate), who sided with the Miyoshi sannishu, switched to the Nobunaga&apos;s side one after another.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。国人衆→Kokujin-shu幕府奉公衆→bakufu&apos;s hokoshu (a military post in Muromachi Shogunate)the補足しました。S小文字にし、ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>永禄12年（1569年）の本圀寺襲撃（本圀寺の変）において、三好長逸は兵三千を率いて摂津国池田方面から来援する織田方の池田勝正、細川幽斎、三好義継らの軍勢を桂川で迎撃したが激戦の末に敗北し（桂川の戦い）、これにより三好三人衆の勢力は本国阿波国まで後退してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Honkoku-ji no Hen (Conspiracy of Honkoku-ji Temple) in 1569, Nagayasu MIYOSHI ambushed Katsumasa IKEDA, Yusai HOSOKAWA and Yoshitugu MIYOSHI&apos;s troops of 3,000 soldiers coming from Settsu-no-kuni Ikeda to support the Oda side near Katsura-gawa River, but he lost the battle after the fierce fighting (the Battle of Katsura-gawa), diminishing the Miyoshi Sannin-shu&apos;s power of influence up to Hongoku Awa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Honkoku-ji no Hen (Conspiracy of Honkoku-ji Temple) in 1569, Nagayasu MIYOSHI ambushed Katsumasa IKEDA, Yusai HOSOKAWA and Yoshitugu MIYOSHI&apos;s force of 3,000 soldiers coming from Settsu-no-kuni Ikeda to support the Oda side near the Katsura-gawa River. However, he lost the battle after fierce fighting (the Battle of Katsura-gawa), reducing the Miyoshi Sannin-shu&apos;s sphere of influence up to Hongoku Awa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Honkoku-ji no Hen (Conspiracy of Honkoku-ji Temple) in 1569, Nagayasu MIYOSHI ambushed Katsumasa IKEDA, Yusai HOSOKAWA and Yoshitugu MIYOSHI&apos;s force of 3,000 soldiers coming from Ikeda, Settsu Province to support the Oda side near the Katsura-gawa River; however, he lost the battle after fierce fighting (the Battle of Katsura-gawa), reducing the Miyoshi sanninshu&apos;s sphere of influence up to the home country, Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>-no-kuniをProvinceに訂正しました。一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。S小文字にし、ハイフン削除。本国→home country</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし翌元亀元年（1570年）、長逸は篠原長房らと共に四国における三好軍をまとめあげ再度の反攻を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1570, however, Nagayasu structured Miyoshi&apos;s troops in Shikoku in cooperation with Nagafusa SHINOHARA and attempted to fight them back again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1570, however, Nagayasu organized Miyoshi&apos;s troops in Shikoku along with Nagafusa SHINOHARA and attempted to fight them back again.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1570, however, Nagayasu organized Miyoshi&apos;s troops in Shikoku along with Nagafusa SHINOHARA and attempted to fight them back again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>同年6月、摂津池田城で謀反を起こして城主池田勝正を追放した荒木村重ら池田二十一人衆に呼応して摂津国に軍を進めた（野田・福嶋の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year, at the request of Ikeda Nijuichinin-shu (Twenty-one elite retainers of Miyoshi) including Murashige ARAKI who had ousted the castellan of Settsu Ikeda Castle due to a rebellion there, he advanced his troops to Settsu-no-kuni (the Battle of Noda and Fukushima.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year he advanced his troops to Settsu-no-kuni (the Battle of Noda and Fukushima) at the request of Ikeda Nijuichinin-shu (Twenty-one elite retainers of Miyoshi), including Murashige ARAKI, who had ousted the castellan of Settsu Ikeda Castle due to a rebellion there.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year he advanced his troops to Settsu Province (the Battle of Noda and Fukushima) at the request of Ikeda Nijuichininshu (Twenty-one elite retainers of Miyoshi), including Murashige ARAKI, who had ousted the castellan of Settsu Ikeda Castle due to a rebellion there.</e>
<cmt>-no-kuniをProvinceに訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>「元亀争乱」と呼ばれる一連の動乱において、野田城及び福島城を根拠地とする長逸ら三好軍の抵抗は激しかったが、これに対する信長の攻撃は苛烈なものであり、同じく信長と不仲な摂津に本拠をもつ石山本願寺の危機感を煽ることになり、ついには本願寺の反信長陣営への参加を促すことになる（石山合戦の勃発）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayasu and the Miyoshi army whose home bases were Noda Castle and Fukushima Castle fiercely resisted in the continuous battles called &apos;Genki Soran&apos;, and meanwhile, Nobunaga&apos;s attacks were so relentless that they triggered a sense of crisis in Ishiyama Hongwan-ji Temple with their main base in Settsu which was also against Nobunaga and at last, prompted them to join the anti-Nobunaga armies (outbreak of Ishiyama Gassen.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu and the Miyoshi army, whose home bases were Noda Castle and Fukushima Castle, fiercely resisted in the continuous battles known as &apos;Genki Soran&apos;. Nobunaga&apos;s attacks were so relentless that they triggered a sense of crisis in Ishiyama Hongwan-ji Temple, with their main base in Settsu, which was also opposed Nobunaga. The were finally prompted to join the anti-Nobunaga armies (outbreak of Ishiyama Gassen).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu and the Miyoshi army, whose home bases were Noda Castle and Fukushima Castle, fiercely resisted in the continuous battles known as &apos;Genki Soran,&apos; however, Nobunaga&apos;s attacks were so relentless that they triggered a sense of crisis in Ishiyama Hongwan-ji Temple, with their main base in Settsu, which was also opposed Nobunaga; finally they were prompted to join the anti-Nobunaga armies (outbreak of Ishiyama Gassen).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>三好軍は紀州勢や一向一揆の参戦、さらに織田方にとっての後方である近江国での浅井氏・朝倉氏連合軍の攻勢に助けられ、一時的に織田軍を摂津・河内国から駆逐する成果を上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supported by the join of the Kishu force and Ikko-Ikki riot and taking advantage of offensive actions taken by the allied Asai clan and Asakura clan forces which were serving as back forces for the Oda side in Omi-no-kuni, the Miyoshi army was successful in temporarily expelling the Oda army from Settu-no-kuni and Kawachi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supported by the join of the Kishu force and Ikko-Ikki riot and taking advantage of offensive actions taken by the allied Asai clan and Asakura clan forces which were serving as back forces for the Oda side in Omi-no-kuni, the Miyoshi army was successful in temporarily expelling the Oda army from Settu-no-kuni and Kawachi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supported by the join of the Kishu force and Ikko-Ikki riot and taking advantage of offensive actions taken by the allied Asai clan and Asakura clan forces which were serving as back forces for the Oda side in Omi Province, the Miyoshi army was successful in temporarily expelling the Oda army from Settu Province and Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>-no-kuniをProvinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>だが三好軍にも追撃の余力はなく、同年11月には反織田の諸勢力と共に信長との間に和議が結ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, the Miyoshi army had no additional energies to fight more wars, and the Miyoshi army and other anti-Oda forces reached a reconciliation arrangement with Nobunaga in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, the Miyoshi army had no additional energies to fight more wars, and the Miyoshi army and other anti-Oda forces reached a reconciliation arrangement with Nobunaga in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, the Miyoshi army had no additional energies to fight more wars, and the Miyoshi army and other anti-Oda forces reached a reconciliation arrangement with Nobunaga in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>この和議は翌年早くも破られ、長逸らは摂津・河内を拠点に石山本願寺と連携しつつ信長包囲網の一角を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That reconciliation arrangement was broken as early as the next year, and Nagayoshi put his base in Settsu and Kawachi and played a role to establish an encirclement against Nobunaga in cooperation with Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That reconciliation arrangement was broken as early as the next year, and Nagayoshi put his base in Settsu and Kawachi and played a role to establish an encirclement against Nobunaga in cooperation with Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That reconciliation arrangement was broken as early as the next year, and Nagayoshi put his base in Settsu and Kawachi and played a role to establish an encirclement against Nobunaga in cooperation with Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、本国阿波で三好長治が篠原長房を殺害し、家中の不和を招くなどの混乱もあり、積極策を取れないまま三好軍は徐々に衰えていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his home country, Awa, the whole Miyoshi family was facing conflicts and confusions due to the murder of Nagafusa SHINOHARA by Nagaharu MIYOSHI, and the Miyoshi army was gradually losing power and strength without taking any positive measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his home country, Awa, the whole Miyoshi family faced conflicts and confusion after the murder of Nagafusa SHINOHARA by Nagaharu MIYOSHI. The Miyoshi army gradually lost power and strength without being able to take any positive measures.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his home country, Awa, the whole Miyoshi family faced conflicts and confusion after the murder of Nagafusa SHINOHARA by Nagaharu MIYOSHI, so the Miyoshi army gradually lost power and strength without being able to take any positive measures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="31">
<j>元亀4年（1573年）、足利義昭自身が決起し、これに三好義継、松永久秀らが呼応してはじめて三好一族の足並みが反織田で一致した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA stood against Oda by himself and Yoshitugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA followed him, and the whole Miyoshi clan for the first time got to be united in anti-Oda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA stood against Oda by himself and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA soon followed him. This marked the first time for the entire Miyoshi clan to come together against Oda.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA stood against Oda by himself and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI and Hisahide MATSUNAGA soon followed him, and this marked the first time for the entire Miyoshi clan to come together against Oda.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>だが同年の武田信玄の病死が反織田方にとって致命的な一撃となり、三好一族を含めた畿内の反織田勢力も一気に瓦解に突き進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, Singen TAKEDA&apos;s death of illness in the same year was a fatal blow for the anti-Oda side, and all anti-Oda forces in the Kinai including the Miyoshi clan began to fall apart all at once, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s death from illness in the same year struck a fatal blow to the side opposed to Oda. All forces opposed to Oda in the Kinai, including the Miyoshi clan, soon fell apart also.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s death from illness in the same year struck a fatal blow to the side opposed to Oda, all forces opposed to Oda in the Kinai, including the Miyoshi clan, soon fell apart also.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="33">
<j>摂津中島城にて信長が派遣してきた軍勢と戦い、敗北して城を逃れたのが三好長逸の確認できる最後の事跡である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lost a battle against the forces sent by Nobunaga in Settsu Nakashima Castle and escaped from the castle, that is the last occasion to know the track of Nagayasu MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost a battle against the forces sent by Nobunaga in Settsu Nakashima Castle. His escape from the castle marked the last that was ever heard from Nagayasu MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost a battle against the forces sent by Nobunaga in Settsu Nakashima Castle, and his escape from the castle marked the last that was ever heard from Nagayasu MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>一説にはこの合戦で討ち死にしたともされるが、その死を確認できる史料はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed that he was killed in that battle, but there are no historical sources to ascertain the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also believed that he was killed in that battle, but there are no historical sources to ascertain the truth.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also believed that he was killed in that battle, but there are no historical sources to ascertain the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>同時に史料から姿を消し、四十年後に唐突に登場した三好政康の例もあり、長逸のその後については隠居・幽閉説など各種の説が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, there is a case in which Masayasu MIYOSHI disappeared from any historical materials and abruptly appeared in such materials in forty years, and there exist several stories about his later days that he retired or was confined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, there is a case in which Masayasu MIYOSHI disappeared from any historical materials for forty years only to abruptly appear again in the same materials. There also exist several stories about his later days where he was said to have retired or been confined.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There also exist several stories about his later days where he was said to have retired or been confined; at the same time, there is a case in which Masayasu MIYOSHI disappeared from any historical materials for forty years only to abruptly appear again in the same materials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 らりた(id:1327), 寮チョ(id:157004), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Cprobot(id:97843), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Orihakat(id:99279), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>