<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利持氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 持氏（あしかが もちうじ、応永5年（1398年） - 永享11年2月10日 (旧暦)（1439年3月24日）、在位1409年 - 1439年）は第四代鎌倉公方。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA 1398-March 24, 1439, was the fourth Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) from 1409 to 1439.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA (1398-April 2, 1439), was the fourth Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) from 1409 to 1439.</e>
<cmt>カッコ追加、ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA (1398-April 2, 1439), was the fourth Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) from 1409 to 1439.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>足利満兼の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Mitsukane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Mitsukane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Mitsukane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>家系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real family name was Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real family name was the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Genji→the Minamoto clanに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real family name was the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一家系　河内源氏の棟梁　鎮守府将軍源義家の子　源義国を祖とする足利氏の嫡流 足利将軍家の分家　鎌倉公方足利家の四代の後胤にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family line was Seiwa-Genji, the head of the Kawachi-Genji, a direct descendant of Ashikaga clan whose ancestor was MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni whose father was MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North), a branch family of Ashikaga shogunal family and a descendant of the fourth of Kamakura kubo Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family line was Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), the head of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), a direct descendant of the Ashikaga clan whose ancestor was MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni whose father was MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North), a branch family of the Ashikaga shogunal family and a descendant of the fourth of the Kamakura kubo Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan)、Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)、the Ashikaga clan、the Ashikaga shogunal family、the Kamakura kubo Ashikaga familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family line was Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), the head of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), a direct descendant of the Ashikaga clan whose ancestor was MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni whose father was MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North), a branch family of the Ashikaga shogunal family and a descendant of the fourth of the Kamakura kubo Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>（詳細は足利氏及び足利将軍家の項を参照のこと。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Please refer to items about Ashikaga clan and Ashikaga shogun family for details.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Please refer to items about the Ashikaga clan and Ashikaga shogun family for details.)</e>
<cmt>the Ashikaga clan and Ashikaga shogun familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Please refer to items about the Ashikaga clan and Ashikaga shogun family for details.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>足利尊氏 - 足利基氏 - 足利氏満 - 足利満兼 - 足利持氏 - 足利成氏 --- 古河公方へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA-Motouji ASHIKAGA-Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA-Mitsukane ASHIKAGA-Mochiuji ASHIKAGA-Shigeuji ASHIKAGA---to Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA - Motouji ASHIKAGA - Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA -Mitsukane ASHIKAGA - Mochiuji ASHIKAGA - Shigeuji ASHIKAGA --- to Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの前後にスペース追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA - Motouji ASHIKAGA - Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA -Mitsukane ASHIKAGA - Mochiuji ASHIKAGA - Shigeuji ASHIKAGA --- to Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>1409年、父・満兼の死去によって鎌倉公方となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his farther, Mitsukane&apos;s death he became Kamakura kubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1409, after his farther, Mitsukane&apos;s death he became the Kamakura kubo.</e>
<cmt>「1409年」→訳漏れのため訳出、the Kamakura kuboとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1409, after his farther, Mitsukane&apos;s death he became the Kamakura kubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし関東管領であった上杉禅秀（上杉氏憲）や叔父の足利満隆と不仲で、次第に対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he didn&apos;t get along with Zenshu UESUGI (Ujinori UESUGI), Kanto kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and Mitsutaka ASHIKAGA, his uncle and became opposed to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he did not get along with Zenshu UESUGI (Ujinori UESUGI), the Kanto kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and Mitsutaka ASHIKAGA, his uncle and became opposed to them.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t→did not、the Kanto kanreiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he did not get along with Zenshu UESUGI (Ujinori UESUGI), the Kanto kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and Mitsutaka ASHIKAGA, his uncle and became opposed to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1416年、禅秀と満隆にクーデターを起こされて一時、駿河国に追放された（上杉禅秀の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1416 Zenshu and Mitsutaka plotted a coup and he was temporarily exiled to Suruga Province (War of Zenshu UESUGI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1416 Zenshu and Mitsutaka plotted a coup and he was temporarily exiled to Suruga Province (The War of Zenshu UESUGI).</e>
<cmt>The War of Zenshu UESUGIとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1416 Zenshu and Mitsutaka plotted a coup and he was temporarily exiled to Suruga Province (The War of Zenshu UESUGI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかしこの反乱は、翌年に越後国の上杉房方らの助力を得て鎮圧している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the next year, he suppressed the rebellion in cooperation with Fusakata UESUGI in Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the next year, he suppressed the rebellion in cooperation with Fusakata UESUGI in Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the next year, he suppressed the rebellion in cooperation with Fusakata UESUGI in Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>将軍との対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confrontation with Shogun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confrontation with Shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confrontation with Shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>京都の将軍と鎌倉公方の対立は、持氏の祖父・足利氏満の時代にすでに始まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The confrontation between Shogun in Kyoto and Kamakura kubo continued from the generation of Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, his grand father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The confrontation between the Shogun in Kyoto and the Kamakura kubo continued from the generation of Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, his grand father.</e>
<cmt>the Shogun, the Kamakura kuboとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The confrontation between the Shogun in Kyoto and the Kamakura kubo continued from the generation of Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA, his grand father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この時は関東管領上杉憲春の諫死で対立は未然に防がれたが、関東に支配権を延ばそうとする将軍と、それに抗する鎌倉公方の衝突は宿命的なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, because Noriharu UESUGI committed suicide to stop Ujimitsu, a conflict was avoided but conflict between Shogun who wanted to gain control of Kanto region and Kamakura kubo who resisted to Shogun was fateful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, because the Kanto kanrei Noriharu UESUGI committed suicide to stop Ujimitsu, a conflict was avoided but conflict between the Shogun who wanted to gain control of the Kanto region and the Kamakura kubo who resisted to the Shogun was fateful.</e>
<cmt>「関東管領」→訳漏れのため訳出、the Shogun、the Kanto region、the Kamakura kuboとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, because the Kanto kanrei Noriharu UESUGI committed suicide to stop Ujimitsu, a conflict was avoided but conflict between the Shogun who wanted to gain control of the Kanto region and the Kamakura kubo who resisted to the Shogun was fateful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>1423年に京都御扶持衆の小栗満重が室町幕府の命令を受けて反持氏反乱を企てたとしてこれを攻め滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1423, he destroyed Mitsushige OGURI who was one of Kyoto fuchishu (samurais directly subjected to Shogun) was ordered by Muromachi bakufu to plot a rebellion against Mochiuji and continuously conquered Mochitsuna UTSUNOMIYA and Nobuyoshi MOMOI who were members of Kyoto fuchishu to wipe out groups which supported Muromachi bakufu (War of Mitsushige OGURI or Oei War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1423, he destroyed Mitsushige OGURI who was one of the Kyoto fuchishu (samurais directly subjected to Shogun) on the ground that Mitsushige was ordered by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to plot a rebellion against Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」was ordered→on the ground that Mitsushige was orderdに修正、the Kyoto fuchishu、the Muromachi bakufuとし、bakufuの補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1423, he destroyed Mitsushige OGURI who was one of the Kyoto fuchishu (samurais directly subjected to Shogun) on the ground that Mitsushige was ordered by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to plot a rebellion against Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>続いて同じく扶持衆の宇都宮持綱・桃井宣義を倒して関東から親幕府勢力の一掃を図った（小栗満重の乱または応永の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiuji continuously conquered Mochitsuna UTSUNOMIYA and Nobuyoshi MOMOI who were also members of the Kyoto fuchishu to wipe out groups which supported the Muromachi bakufu (The War of Mitsushige OGURI or The Oei War).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」文頭にMochiujiを追加、who were members→who were also membersとし、the Muromachi bakufu、The War of Mitsuhide OGURI、The Oei Warとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiuji continuously conquered Mochitsuna UTSUNOMIYA and Nobuyoshi MOMOI who were also members of the Kyoto fuchishu to wipe out groups which supported the Muromachi bakufu (The War of Mitsushige OGURI or The Oei War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これに対して室町幕府4代将軍足利義持は持氏討伐を計画するが、持氏の謝罪によって討伐は中止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, the fourth Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA plotted to put down Mochiuji, but the suppression was canceled because of Mochiuji&apos;s apology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, the fourth Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA plotted to put down Mochiuji, but the suppression was canceled because of Mochiuji&apos;s apology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, the fourth Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA plotted to put down Mochiuji, but the suppression was canceled because of Mochiuji&apos;s apology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>だが、関東御扶持衆を用いて持氏の勢力拡大を牽制しようとする幕府側とそれに対抗しようとする持氏の対立は深刻化する一方であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the confrontation between bakufu side who plotted to use Kanto huchishu to prevent Mochiuji from gaining power and Mochiuji who resisted this became worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the confrontation between the bakufu side who plotted to use the Kanto fuchishu to prevent Mochiuji from gaining power and Mochiuji who resisted this became worse.</e>
<cmt>the bakufu sideとし、Kanto huchishu→the Kanto fuchishuに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the confrontation between the bakufu side who plotted to use the Kanto fuchishu to prevent Mochiuji from gaining power and Mochiuji who resisted this became worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>1425年、5代将軍であった足利義量が病死し、1428年に前将軍であった足利義持も病死して将軍職が空位となると、持氏は自身が足利氏の一族であるという名分から6代将軍の座を望んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1425, the fifth Shogun Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA died of illness and former Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA died of illness in 1428, the shogunate was vacant and Mochiuji wished for the sixth Shogun position because he belonged to Ashikaga clan, however Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, Kanrei and Mansai, the monzeki (successor of a temple) of Sanbo-in Temple discussed and decided to choose a successor from four younger brothers of Yoshimochi by drawing lots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1425, the fifth Shogun Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA died of illness and the former Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA died of illness in 1428; the shogunate was vacant and Mochiuji wished for the sixth Shogun position because he belonged to the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」the former Shogun、the Ashikaga clanとし、カンマ→セミコロンに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1425, the fifth Shogun Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA died of illness and the former Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA died of illness in 1428; the shogunate was vacant and Mochiuji wished for the sixth Shogun position because he belonged to the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>が、管領の畠山満家や三宝院門跡満済らの協議によって、6代将軍は義持の弟4人のうちから籤引きで選ばれることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) and Mansai, the monzeki (successor of a temple) of Sanbo-in Temple discussed and decided to choose a successor from four younger brothers of Yoshimochi by drawing lots.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」the Kanreiとし、補足追加しました。(用語集参照)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) and Mansai, the monzeki (successor of a temple) of Sanbo-in Temple discussed and decided to choose a successor from four younger brothers of Yoshimochi by drawing lots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>結果、天台座主義円が還俗して足利義教として将軍職を継承することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, Gien who was Tendai-Zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) quitted the priesthood and became successor of shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Gien who was Tendai-Zasu (head priest of the Tendaishu sect) quitted the priesthood and became the successor to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>As the result→As a result、Tendaishu sect、successor of shogunate→the successor to the shogunateとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Gien who was Tendai-Zasu (head priest of the Tendaishu sect) quitted the priesthood and became the successor to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この将軍職相続に義持の猶子となっていた持氏は不満を持ち、新将軍の義教を『還俗将軍』と軽んじ、義教の将軍襲職祝いの使者を送らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiuji who was an adopted child of Yoshimochi was not satisfied with the result and called new Shogun Yoshinori &quot;shogun returned to secular life&quot; and didn&apos;t even send a envoy to celebrate Yoshinori&apos;s inauguration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiuji who was an adopted child of Yoshimochi was not satisfied with the result and called new Shogun Yoshinori &quot;shogun returned to secular life&quot; and did not even send an envoy to celebrate Yoshinori&apos;s inauguration.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t→did not、a envoy→an envoyに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiuji who was an adopted child of Yoshimochi was not satisfied with the result and called new Shogun Yoshinori &quot;shogun returned to secular life&quot; and did not even send an envoy to celebrate Yoshinori&apos;s inauguration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに元号が永享に改元されても前年号の正長を使い続け、本来ならば将軍が決定する鎌倉五山の住職を勝手に取り決めるなど、幕府と対立する姿勢を見せ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he continued to use former era name, Shocho after the era name was changed to Eikyo, then assigned the chief priest of Kamakura Gozan Temples which was usually assigned by Shogun, the behavior was to show his attitude against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he continued to use the former era name, Shocho after the era name was changed to Eikyo, then assigned the chief priests of Kamakura Gozan Temples who were usually assigned by the Shogun; the behavior was to show his attitude against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the former era name、the Shogunとし、the chief priest→the chief priests、which was→who wereに修正、カンマ→セミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he continued to use the former era name, Shocho after the era name was changed to Eikyo, then assigned the chief priests of Kamakura Gozan Temples who were usually assigned by the Shogun; the behavior was to show his attitude against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>関東管領・上杉憲実は、持氏と義教の融和を懸命に努めたが、持氏は応じなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norizane UESUGI, Kanto kanrei tried to maintain harmonious relation between Mochiuji and Yoshinori but Mochiuji didn&apos;t accept this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norizane UESUGI, the Kanto kanrei tried to maintain harmonious relation between Mochiuji and Yoshinori but Mochiuji did not accept this.</e>
<cmt>the Kanto kanrei、didn&apos;t→did notとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norizane UESUGI, the Kanto kanrei tried to maintain harmonious relation between Mochiuji and Yoshinori but Mochiuji did not accept this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>憲実が持氏に討たれるという噂が流れ、徐々に両者の溝は広がっていき、1437年には憲実が関東管領を辞職している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition there was a rumor that Norizane will be destroyed by Mochiuji, so a gap between Norizane and Mochiuji gradually became bigger, finally in 1437, Norizane resigned Kanto kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there was a rumor that Norizane will be destroyed by Mochiuji, so a gap between Norizane and Mochiuji gradually became bigger, finally in 1437, Norizane resigned the Kanto kanrei.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加、the Kanto kanreiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there was a rumor that Norizane will be destroyed by Mochiuji, so a gap between Norizane and Mochiuji gradually became bigger, finally in 1437, Norizane resigned the Kanto kanrei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一方、幕府においても宥和派の管領・畠山満家が永享5年（1433年）に、満済が永享7年（1435年）に没すると義教を止めることのできる人間は存在しなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, Kanrei (shogunal deputy) died in 1433, and Mansai died in 1435, after the death of two persons who wished for harmonious relations between Shogun and Mochiuji at the bakufu side, there was no person who could stop Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, the Kanrei died in 1433, and Mansai died in 1435; after the death of two persons who wished for harmonious relations between the Shogun and Mochiuji at the bakufu side, there was no person who could stop Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt>the Kanreiとし、既出のため補足削除、カンマ→セミコロンに変更、the Shogunとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, the Kanrei died in 1433, and Mansai died in 1435; after the death of two persons who wished for harmonious relations between the Shogun and Mochiuji at the bakufu side, there was no person who could stop Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>永享の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eikyo War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eikyo War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eikyo War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>永享10年6月（1438年）、持氏の嫡子足利義久が元服を迎えて名を改める際、本来ならば将軍に一字を拝領する慣例であったが、それを行わず「義久」と名付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1438, a legitimate child of Mochiuji had genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) and there was a custom that a name will be given to the child taking a character which given by Shogun, but Mochiuji didn&apos;t follow the tradition and named him Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1438, a legitimate child of Mochiuji, Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA had genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) and there was a custom that a name would be given to the child taking a character given by the Shogun, but Mochiuji did not follow the tradition and named him Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt>「足利義久」→訳漏れのため訳出、will be→would be、which given→given、didn&apos;t→did notに修正、the Shogunとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1438, a legitimate child of Mochiuji, Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA celebrated genpuku (one&apos;s coming of age); it was a common practice that a name would be given to the child taking one character given by the Shogun, but Mochiuji did not follow the tradition and named him Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt>edited for natural English and to avoid a run-on sentence by adding a semicolon.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>憲実はこの元服式に出席せず、憲実と持氏の対立は決定的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norizane didn&apos;t attend the ceremony, so the confrontation between Norizane and Mochiuji became clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norizane did not attend the ceremony, so the confrontation between Norizane and Mochiuji became clear.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t→did notとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norizane did not attend the ceremony, so the confrontation between Norizane and Mochiuji became clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>8月、憲実は鎌倉市を去り、領国の上野国へ下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, Norizane left Kamakura to go back to his territory in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, Norizane left Kamakura to go back to his territory in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, Norizane left Kamakura to go back to his territory in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これを憲実の反逆と見た持氏は討伐の兵を差し向け、自らも武蔵国府中高安寺に出陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiuji understand this as Norizane&apos;s rebellion, so he sent army to put down Norizane and he led army to Fuchu, Musashi Province by his own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiuji understood this as Norizane&apos;s rebellion, so he sent army to put down Norizane and he led army to Koan-ji Temple, Fuchu, Musashi Province by his own.</e>
<cmt>understand→understoodに修正、「高安寺」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiuji understood this as Norizane&apos;s rebellion, so he sent army to put down Norizane and he led army to Koan-ji Temple, Fuchu, Musashi Province by his own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>将軍・義教は憲実の救援のため、篠川御所足利満直や駿河守護今川範忠の出兵を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun Yoshinori ordered Mitsunao ASHIKAGA at Sasagawa Palace and Noritada IMAGAWA, Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga Province) to dispatch of troops to save Norizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun Yoshinori ordered Mitsunao ASHIKAGA at Sasagawa Palace and Noritada IMAGAWA, the Governor of Suruga Province to dispatch troops to save Norizane.</e>
<cmt>Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga Province)→the Governor of Suruga Province、to dispatch of troops→to dispatch troopsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun Yoshinori ordered Mitsunao ASHIKAGA at Sasagawa Palace and Noritada IMAGAWA, the Governor of Suruga Province to dispatch troops to save Norizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>さらに禅秀の子上杉持房・上杉教朝らを含む幕府軍を派遣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a force of bakufu including Zenshu&apos;s sons, Mochifusa UESUGI and Noritomo UESUGI was sent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the bakufu force including Zenshu&apos;s sons, Mochifusa UESUGI and Noritomo UESUGI was sent.</e>
<cmt>a force of bakufu→the bakufu forceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the bakufu force including Zenshu&apos;s sons, Mochifusa UESUGI and Noritomo UESUGI was sent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>同時に持氏追討の治罰綸旨の発給を求め、持氏は朝敵となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Jibatsu Rinji (a permission to destroy Emperor&apos;s enemy) was given and Mochiuji became an Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>Jibatsu Rinjiは定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Jibatsu Rinji (a permission to destroy Emperor&apos;s enemy) was given and Mochiuji became an Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Jibatsu Rinji (a permission to destroy Emperor&apos;s enemy) was given and Mochiuji became an Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>9月27日には持氏軍は破れて相模の海老名まで引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 27, Mochiuji was defeated and withdraw his force to Ebina in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 25, Mochiuji was defeated and withdrew his force to Ebina in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正、withdraw→withdrewに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 25, Mochiuji was defeated and withdrew his force to Ebina in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし鎌倉を守護していた三浦時高等武将の裏切りが相次いだうえに兵は逃亡し、持氏は孤立無援となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some busho who guarded Kamakura including Tokitaka MIURA continuously betrayed Mochiuji and soldiers run away, so Mochiuji was isolated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some busho who guarded Kamakura including Tokitaka MIURA continuously betrayed Mochiuji and soldiers ran away, so Mochiuji was isolated.</e>
<cmt>run→ranに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some busho who guarded Kamakura including Tokitaka MIURA continuously betrayed Mochiuji and soldiers ran away, so Mochiuji was isolated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>持氏は鎌倉に引く途中で憲実の家宰・長尾忠政と出会い、憲実に義教との折衝を依頼する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During going back to Kamakura, Mochiuji met Tadamasa NAGAO, a Kasai (main retainer) of Norizane and asked him to tell his request to Norizane, his request was to ask Norizane to negotiate with Yoshinori for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way back to Kamakura, Mochiuji met Tadamasa NAGAO, a Kasai (main retainer) of Norizane and asked him to tell his request to Norizane; his request was to ask Norizane to negotiate with Yoshinori for him.</e>
<cmt>During going back to→On the way back toとし、カンマ→セミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way back to Kamakura, Mochiuji met Tadamasa NAGAO, a Kasai (main retainer) of Norizane and asked him to tell his request to Norizane; his request was to ask Norizane to negotiate with Yoshinori for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その後鎌倉称名寺で出家し、永安寺に幽閉された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he became a priest in Shomyo-ji Temple and was confined in Yoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he became a priest in Shomyo-ji Temple in Kamakura and was confined in Yoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「鎌倉」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he became a priest in Shomyo-ji Temple in Kamakura and was confined in Yoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>憲実は持氏の助命と義久の公方就任を懇願したが、義教は許さず、憲実に持氏の追討を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norizane implored Yoshinori to save Mochiuji&apos;s life and give a kubo position to Yoshihisa, Yoshinori didn&apos;t granted his wishes and ordered him to hunt down and kill Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norizane implored Yoshinori to save Mochiuji&apos;s life and give a kubo position to Yoshihisa, Yoshinori did not grant his wishes and ordered him to hunt down and kill Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t granted→did not grantに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norizane implored Yoshinori to save Mochiuji&apos;s life and give a kubo position to Yoshihisa, Yoshinori did not grant his wishes and ordered him to hunt down and kill Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>永享11年（1439年）2月10日、憲実の兵が永安寺を攻撃、持氏は自害して果てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 10, 1439 soldiers led by Norizane attacked Yoan-ji Temple and Mochiuji committed suicide and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 2, 1439 soldiers led by Norizane attacked Yoan-ji Temple and Mochiuji committed suicide and died.</e>
<cmt>In→On、旧暦→新暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 2, 1439 soldiers led by Norizane attacked Yoan-ji Temple and Mochiuji committed suicide and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>（永享の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eikyo War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Eikyo War.)</e>
<cmt>The Eikyo Warとし、カッコ表記、ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Eikyo War.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>法名は長春院陽山道純。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was 長春院陽山道純.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。：長春院陽山道純</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was 長春院陽山道純.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) was 長春院陽山道純.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>彼の自害により鎌倉公方は一旦滅亡することになるが、彼の遺児である足利春王丸、足利安王丸を担いだ結城氏朝・結城持朝が蜂起し、関東の混乱は続いた（結城合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his suicide, Kamakura kubo fell once, but Ujitomo YUKI and MochitomoYUKI supported Mochiuji&apos;s bereaved children Haruomaru ASHIKAGA and Yasuomar ASHIKAGA and raised army, so turbulence lasted for a while (Yuki War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his suicide, the Kamakura kubo fell once, but Ujitomo YUKI and MochitomoYUKI who supported Mochiuji&apos;s bereaved children Haruomaru ASHIKAGA and Yasuomaru ASHIKAGA and raised army, so turbulence in the Kanto region lasted for a while (The Battle of Yuki).</e>
<cmt>「関東の」→訳漏れのため訳出、the Kamakura kuboとし、supported→who supported、Yasuomar→Yasuomaruに修正、The Yuki War→The Battle of Yukiとしました。(参考: http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/40016935136)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his suicide, the Kamakura kubo fell once, but Ujitomo YUKI and MochitomoYUKI who supported Mochiuji&apos;s bereaved children Haruomaru ASHIKAGA and Yasuomaru ASHIKAGA and raised army, so turbulence in the Kanto region lasted for a while (The Battle of Yuki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt>統一リストの「官歴」の表記に基づき修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*the date=Japan&apos;s old lunisolar calendar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date according to old lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date according to old lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1410年（応永17年）12月22日、元服し、持氏と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 22, 1410 he reached the manhood and started to name himself Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 22, 1410 he reached the manhood and started to name himself Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt>In→Onに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 22, 1410 he reached the manhood and started to name himself Mochiuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>同日、従四位下に叙し、左馬頭に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned to Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same day, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned to Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same day, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned to Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>1420年（応永27年）12月、従三位に昇叙し、左兵衛督に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1420, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and transferred to Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1420, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and transferred to Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1420, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and transferred to Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>1438年（永享10年）10月、出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1483, he entered priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1483, he entered priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1483, he entered priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="47">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>父：足利満兼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father: Mitsukane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Father: Mitsukane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Father: Mitsukane ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>母：一色氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mother: from Isshiki clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mother: from the Isshiki clan</e>
<cmt>the Isshiki clanとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mother: from the Isshiki clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>弟：足利持仲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger brother: Mochinaka ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger brother: Mochinaka ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Younger brother: Mochinaka ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>妻：簗田満助の娘？</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wife: A daughter of Mitsusuke YANADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wife: A daughter of Mitsusuke YANADA?</e>
<cmt>?マーク追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wife: A daughter of Mitsusuke YANADA?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>子：安漬和尚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: 安漬和尚</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。：安漬和尚</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: 安漬和尚</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: 安漬和尚</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>子：足利義久（賢王丸）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA (Kenoumaru)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA (Kenomaru)</e>
<cmt>Kenoumaru→Kenomaruに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA (Kenomaru)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>子：春王丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Haruomaru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Haruomaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Haruomaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>子：安王丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Yasuomaru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Yasuomaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Yasuomaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>子：足利成氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Shigeuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Shigeuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Shigeuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>子：成潤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: 成潤</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。：成潤</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: 成潤</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: 成潤</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>子：周昉（守実）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: 周昉(Morizane)</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。：周昉　しゅうぼう？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Shubo (周昉) (Morizane)</e>
<cmt>Shubo (周昉)とし、スペース追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Shubo (周昉) (Morizane)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>子：尊敒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: 尊敒</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。：尊敒</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: 尊敒</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: 尊敒</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>子：定尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: 定尊</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。：定尊　じょうそん？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Joson (定尊)</e>
<cmt>Joson (定尊)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Joson (定尊)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>子：弘尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Hirotaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Hirotaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Hirotaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>子：蔭山広氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: 広氏 KAGEYAMA</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。：広氏</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Hirouji (広氏) KAGEYAMA</e>
<cmt>Hirouji (広氏)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Hirouji (広氏) KAGEYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), やりたこ(id:113528), 霧木諒二(id:9795), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 味っ子(id:17086), Urashimataro(id:188234), 彩華1226(id:64711), でここ(id:9565), Rusk(id:9895), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), 海衛士(id:19229), Nekosuki600(id:21263), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Nalc(id:139567), NDR(id:5500), Klesha(id:203751), Suisui(id:69), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>