<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>智鳳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ho CHI (aka Korean name Jibong)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiho</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。補足情報は削除し、後項に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>智鳳（ちほう、生没年不詳）は、奈良時代における新羅の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ho CHI (DOB unknown) was a priest in the ancient Korean Shilla priest during Japan`s Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiho (aka Jibong in Korean; years of birth and death unknown) was a priest from ancient Korean Shilla, who lived in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>用語・形式・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiho (aka Jibong in Korean; years of birth and death unknown) was a priest from ancient Korean Shilla, who lived in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>703年（大宝 (日本)3年）智鸞・智雄などとともに入唐し、慈恩大師基（或いは窺基）の法孫で法相第3祖の濮陽（ぼくよう）大師智周に師事して法相宗を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 703 visited China together with Yu CHI and Ran CHI (Korean name `Jiran`) studied the Hosso sect Tripitaka under high-priest (or possibly a priest named Kuiji) and became a pupil of high-priest Shu CHI at Puyang in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 703, he visited Tang China together with Chiran and Chiyu, studied Faxiang Buddhism (or Dharma-character school which was the Chinese equivalent of the Japanese Hosso sect) under Chishu (Zhizhou in Chinese) the Bokuyo Daishi (Master Puyang), who was a dharma-grandson of Ki (Ji in Chinese, aka Kuiji) the Jion Daishi (Master Cien) and the third generation founder of the Faxiang sect in China.</e>
<cmt>原文のリンク先表示を削除しました。用語・人名を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 703, he visited Tang China together with Chiran and Chiyu, studied Faxiang Buddhism (or Dharma-character school which was the Chinese equivalent of the Japanese Hosso sect) under Chishu (Zhizhou in Chinese) the Bokuyo Daishi (Master Puyang), who was a dharma-grandson of Ki (Ji in Chinese, aka Kuiji) the Jion Daishi (Master Cien) and the third generation founder of the Faxiang sect in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>奈良法興寺に住して法相宗を広め、日本における法相宗の第3伝とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Living at the Hoko-ji temple in Nara he propagated the Hosso sect and was the 3rd generation of the Hosso sect in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Living at the Hoko-ji Temple in Nara, Chiho propagated the Hosso sect in Japan, which was supposedly the third generation transmission of the Japanese Hosso sect.</e>
<cmt>用語・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Living at the Hoko-ji Temple in Nara, Chiho propagated the Hosso sect in Japan, which was supposedly the third generation transmission of the Japanese Hosso sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>706年（慶雲3年）藤原不比等が維摩会を復興した折にはその講師をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 706 when FUJIWARA no Fuhito revived the holding `Yuimae` religious meetings Ho CHI served as a presenter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 706, when FUJIWARA no Fuhito revived the holding known as Yuima-e religious meetings, Chiho served as a lecturer.</e>
<cmt>形式・用語・人名を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 706, when FUJIWARA no Fuhito revived the holding known as Yuima-e religious meetings, Chiho served as a lecturer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弟子に義淵がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">GI En was his pupil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gien was his pupil.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gien was his pupil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lobbyonce(id:195963), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>