<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原兼光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanemitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 兼光（ふじわら の かねみつ、久安2年（1146年） - 建久7年4月23日 (旧暦)（1196年5月22日））は、平安時代末期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemitsu (1146-May 22, 1196) was Kugyo (the top court official) in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanemitsu (1146-May 22, 1196) was Kugyo (top court official) during the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemitsu (1146 - May 29, 1196) was a Kugyo (top court official) during the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日野流権中納言藤原資長の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the child of FUJIWARA no Sukenaga, Gon Chunagon (provisional middle counselor) in Hino line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of FUJIWARA no Sukenaga, Gon Chunagon (provisional middle counselor) in Hino line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of FUJIWARA no Sukenaga, Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state) in the Hino line of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>日野流藤原氏　と補足をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は源季兼の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Suekane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Suekane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Suekane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に日野資実（日野家の祖）・広橋頼資（広橋家の祖）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Sukezane HINO (the ancestor of the Hino family) and Yorisuke HIROHASHI (the ancestor of the Hirohashi family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Sukezane HINO (the ancestor of the Hino family) and Yorisuke HIROHASHI (the ancestor of the Hirohashi family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Sukezane HINO (the ancestor of the Hino family) and Yorisuke HIROHASHI (the ancestor of the Hirohashi family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>保元元年（1156年）に勧学院学問料を支給されていることから、大学寮で紀伝道を学んでいたことが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the issuance of Gakumonryo (the scholarship for Monjosho who study at Daigaku-ryo in the Heian period) for Kangakuin (educational institutions) in 1156, he seemed to learn Kidendo (the study of the histories) in Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from the issuance of Gakumonryo (the scholarship for Monjosho who study at Daigaku-ryo in the Heian period) for Kangakuin (educational institutions) in 1156, he seemed to learn Kidendo (the study of the history) in Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from the issuance of Gakumonryo (the scholarship for Monjosho who study at Daigaku-ryo in the Heian period) for Kangakuin (educational institutions) in 1156, he seemed to learn Kidendo (the study of the history) in Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>2年後に文章得業生となり、永暦 (日本)元年（1160年）に対策に及第して従五位下修理亮兼右近衛少尉となり、使宣旨を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After becoming Monjo tokugosho (Distinguished Scholars of Letters) two years later and successfully passing taisaku (one of the examination for adopting government officials under the Ritsuryo legal codes) in 1160, he became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Shuri no suke (assistant officer of the Office of Palace Repairs) concurrently with Ukone no shojo and was conferred Shisenji (imperial decrees issued when appointing kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and Hoheishi (an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After becoming Monjo tokugosho (Distinguished Scholars of Letters) two years later and successfully passing taisaku (one of the examination for adopting government officials under the Ritsuryo legal codes) in 1160, he became Jugoinoge (Junior 5th Rank, Lower Grade), Shuri no suke (assistant officer of the Office of Palace Repairs) concurrently with Ukone no shojo and was conferred Shisenji (imperial decrees issued when appointing kebiishi - a police and judicial chief and Hoheishi - an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After becoming Monjo tokugosho (Distinguished Scholars of Letters) two years later and successfully passing taisaku (one of the examination for adopting government officials under the Ritsuryo legal codes) in 1160, he became Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Shuri no suke (assistant officer of the Office of Palace Repairs) concurrently with Ukone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and was conferred Shisenji (imperial decrees issued when appointing kebiishi [a police and judicial chief] and Hoheishi [an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine]).</e>
<cmt>右近衛少尉→Ukone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>応保3年（1163年）に治部少輔に任じられ、翌年に昇殿を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Jibushoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) in 1163, and was admitted to the access to the imperial court the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Jibushoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) in 1163, and was admitted to access to the imperial court the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Jibushoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) in 1163, and was admitted to access to the Imperial Court the next year.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）に治部少輔のまま従五位上東宮学士となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1166, he became Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince) with serving as Jibushoyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1166, he became Jugoinojo (Junior 5th Rank, Upper Grade) Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince) serving as Jibushoyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1166, he became Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince) while serving as Jibushoyu.</e>
<cmt>5th →Fifth としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>翌年正五位下に叙され、仁安3年（1168年）には蔵人兼備中権介となり東宮学士を辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After appointment to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) the next year, he became Kurodo (Chamberlain) as well as Bichu gon-no-suke (acting assistant governor of Bichu Province) in 1168 and resigned Togu gakushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After appointment to Shogoinoge (Senior 5th Rank, Lower Grade) the next year, he became Kurodo (Chamberlain) as well as Bichu gon-no-suke (acting assistant governor of Bichu Province) in 1168 and resigned Togu gakushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After appointment to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) the next year, he became Kurodo (Chamberlain) as well as Bicchu gon no suke (acting assistant governor of Bicchu Province) in 1168 and resigned Togu gakushi.</e>
<cmt>5th →Fifth としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>嘉応元年（1170年）に右少弁、承安 (日本)2年（1172年）に左少弁に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1170 and Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left) in 1172.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1170 and Sashoben (3rd-ranked officer of the left) in 1172.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1170 and Sashoben (Minor Controller of the Left) in 1172.</e>
<cmt>左少弁→Minor Controller of the Left　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>治承3年（1179年）には右中弁に勧学院弁別当を兼ね、更に造東大寺長官を兼ねて従四位下に昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also served as Ben no Betto (a second principal having a high rank in the government) of Kangakuin as well as Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right in 1179, in addition, concurrently served as Zo-Todaiji-chokan (the director for the construction of Todai-ji Temple) and then promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also served as Ben no Betto (a 2nd principal having a high rank in the government) of Kangakuin as well as Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right in 1179, in addition, concurrently served as Zo-Todaiji-chokan (the director for the construction of Todai-ji Temple) and then promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior 4th Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also served as Ben no Betto (a second principal having a high rank in the government) of Kangakuin as well as Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right) in 1179, in addition, concurrently served as Zo-Todaiji-chokan (the director for the construction of Todai-ji Temple) and then promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>養和元年（1181年）には左中弁に進み、造興福寺長官となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He promoted to Sachuben (middle controller of the left) in 1181 and became Zo Kofuku-ji chokan (the director for the construction of Kofuku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Sachuben (middle controller of the left) in 1181 and became Zo Kofuku-ji chokan (the director for the construction of Kofuku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) in 1181 and became Zo-Kofuku-ji chokan (the director for the construction of Kofuku-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>左中弁 補足を大文字にして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>寿永元年（1182年）に正四位下に昇り、翌年には安徳天皇の蔵人頭に任命される.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1182 and was appointed to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) of the Emperor Antoku the next year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior 4th Rank, Lower Grade) in 1182 and was appointed to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) for Emperor Antoku the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1182 and was appointed to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) for Emperor Antoku the next year.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、同天皇の西下には従わずに引き続き後鳥羽天皇の蔵人頭を務め、続いて参議兼右大弁に転じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he continued to serve as Kurodo no to of the Emperor Gotoba without following the Emperor Antoku to leave for the west, and became Sangi (councilor) as well as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) later.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he continued to serve as Kurodo no to for Emperor Gotoba without following Emperor Antoku to leave for the west, and became Sangi (councilor) as well as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he continued to serve as Kurodo no to for Emperor Gotoba without following Emperor Antoku to leave for the west, and became Sangi (councilor) as well as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>元暦元年（1184年）には従三位左大弁となり近江権守を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1184, he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Sadaiben (major controller of the left) with concurrently serving as Omi no gon no kami (provisional governor of Omi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1184, he became Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank) Sadaiben (major controller of the left) with concurrently serving as Omi no gon no kami (provisional governor of Omi Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1184, he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left) with concurrently serving as Omi no gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Omi Province).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>公卿昇任が間近と言われていた院近臣の藤原隆房よりも先に公卿に列したために、義母で後白河法皇の寵愛を受けた高階栄子（丹後局）の後ろ盾があったとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ranked with Kugyo earlier than FUJIWARA no Takafusa who was In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) and was said to promote to Kugyo soon, which was said to be backed by his mother-in-law, TAKASHINA no Eishi (Tango no tsubone) favored by the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ranked with Kugyo earlier than FUJIWARA no Takafusa who was In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) and was said to promote to Kugyo soon, which was said to be backed by his mother-in-law, TAKASHINA no Eishi (Tango no tsubone) favored by the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ranked with Kugyo earlier than FUJIWARA no Takafusa who was In no Kinshin (the Retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) and was said to promote to Kugyo soon; this promotion is said to be backed by his mother-in-law, TAKASHINA no Eishi (Tango no tsubone) favored by the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>文治元年（1185年）に勘解由長官、翌年に権中納言に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Kageyu no kami (chief investigator of the records of outgoing officials) in 1185, and Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Kageyu no kami (chief investigator of the records of outgoing officials) in 1185, and Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Kageyu no kami (chief investigator of the records of outgoing officials) in 1185, and Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>建久元年（1190年）に右兵衛督を、建久2年（1191年）には検非違使別当を兼務、建久4年（1193年）には右衛門督転じて、京都の治安回復に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He concurrently served as Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) in 1190 as well as Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) in 1191, and transferred to Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) to make effort to restore the security in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He concurrently served as Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of the Middle Palace Guards) in 1190 as well as Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) in 1191, and transferred to Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) to make an effort to restore the security in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He concurrently served as Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of the Middle Palace Guards) in 1190 as well as Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) in 1191, and transferred to Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) to make an effort to restore the security in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>建久5年（1194年）に右衛門督・検非違使別当を辞任、翌年に従二位に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned Uemon no kami and Kebiishi no betto in 1194 and was conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank) the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned Uemon no kami and Kebiishi no betto in 1194 and was conferred Junii (Junior 2nd Rank) the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned Uemon no kami and Kebiishi no betto in 1194 and was conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank) the next year.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>だが、建久7年（1196年）に腫物の病で4月12日に出家し間もなく死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he entered into priesthood in April 12, 1196 because of illness with tumor (indirectly referring to cancer) and died soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he entered into the priesthood in April 12, 1196 because of illness with a tumor (indirectly referring to cancer) and soon died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he entered into the priesthood in May 18, 1196 because of illness with a tumor (indirectly referring to cancer) and soon died.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>高倉天皇・後鳥羽天皇の侍読を務め、歌人としても『千載和歌集』・『新古今和歌集』など3つの勅撰和歌集に採録される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Jidoku (imperial tutor) for the Emperor Takakura and the Emperor Gotoba, while as a kajin (waka poet), his wakas were selected for 3 kinds of Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) including &quot;Senzai waka shu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) and &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as Jidoku (imperial tutor) for the Emperor Takakura and the Emperor Gotoba, while as a kajin (waka poet), his wakas were selected for three kinds of Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) including &quot;Senzai waka shu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) and &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as Jidoku (imperial tutor) for the Emperor Takakura and the Emperor Gotoba, while as a waka poet, his wakas were selected for three kinds of chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) including &quot;Senzai waka shu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) and &quot;Shinkokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>歌人→waka poet としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、日記『姉言記』（『兼光卿記』）が伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the diary &quot;姉言記&quot; (&quot;Kanemitsukyoki&quot; (a journal of Fujiwara no Kanemitsu)) were left.</e>
<cmt>読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, the diary &quot;姉言記&quot; (&quot;Kanemitsukyoki&quot; - a journal of Fujiwara no Kanemitsu) was left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, the diary &quot;姉言記&quot; (&quot;Kanemitsu-kyo ki&quot; - a journal of FUJIWARA no Kanemitsu) was left.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>学識に優れ、実務にも長けた官人として平家政権・後白河院政両方において重んじられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the excellent scholarship, he was given important positions both in the Heike government and Goshirakawa-insei (the government by the retired Emperor Goshirakawa) as a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) with rich practical experiences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the excellent scholarship, he was given important positions both in the Heike government and Goshirakawa-insei (the government of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa) as a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) with rich practical experiences.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the excellent scholarship, he was given important positions both in the Heike government and Goshirakawa-insei (the government of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa) as a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) with rich practical experiences.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>