<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>月形潔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>月形 潔（つきがた きよし、1846年（弘化3年） - 1894年（明治27年））は、明治時代の官僚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA (1846 - 1894) was a government official of Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA (1846 - 1894) was a government official of the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>theを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA (1846 - 1894) was a government official of the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北海道樺戸集治監典獄、樺戸・雨竜・上川三郡郡長として北海道開拓に携わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got involved in the reclamation of Hokkaido as Tengoku (director) of Hokkaido Kabato Shujikan (former prison) and Guncho (mayor of county) of the three counties such as Kabato, Uryu and Kamikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was involved in the reclamation of Hokkaido as Tengoku (director) of Hokkaido Kabato Shujikan (former prison) and Guncho (mayor of county) of the three counties such as Kabato, Uryu and Kamikawa.</e>
<cmt>wasにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was involved in the reclamation of Hokkaido as Tengoku (director) of Hokkaido Kabato Shujikan (former prison) and Guncho (mayor of county) of the three counties such as Kabato, Uryu and Kamikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>樺戸郡月形町の町名は彼の姓に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The town name called Tsukigata-cho, Kabato County derives from his family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town name called Tsukigata-cho, Kabato County derives from his family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town name called Tsukigata-cho, Kabato County derives from his family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>福岡藩士の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as a child of a feudal retainer of Fukushima Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as a child of a feudal retainer of the Fukushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>theを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as a child of a feudal retainer of the Fukushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1865年（慶応元年）叔父の月形洗蔵は筑前勤王党首領として江戸幕府に抗した為、一族そろって拘束され幼少の潔もまた収監されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1865, his uncle, Senzo TSUKIGATA, resisted Edo bakufu as a chieftain of Chikuzen Kinnoto (loyalist clique), so his whole family including young Kiyoshi was restrained and imprisoned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1865, his uncle, Senzo TSUKIGATA, resisted Edo bakufu as a chieftain of Chikuzen Kinnoto (loyalist clique), so his whole family including young Kiyoshi was restrained and imprisoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1865, his uncle, Senzo TSUKIGATA, resisted Edo bakufu as a chieftain of Chikuzen Kinnoto (loyalist clique), so his whole family including young Kiyoshi was restrained and imprisoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治維新の後、新政府に雇われ福岡藩権少参事として勤務する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji restoration, he was hired by the new government, and began to work as Fukuoka-han Gonnosho Sanji (Councilor of Gonnosho of Fukuoka Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji restoration, he was hired by the new government, and began to work as Fukuoka-han Gonnosho Sanji (Councilor of Gonnosho of Fukuoka Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji restoration, he was hired by the new government, and began to work as Fukuoka-han Gonnosho Sanji (Councilor of Gonnosho of Fukuoka Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>潔はこのとき藩が組織的に行っていた贋札事件の調査を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Kiyoshi was ordered the investigation of the case involving counterfeit bill systematically being committed by the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Kiyoshi was ordered to investigate the counterfeit bill case committed by the domain as an organization.</e>
<cmt>to investigateにしました。Systematicallyをかえました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Kiyoshi was ordered to investigate the counterfeit bill case committed by the domain as an organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>事件そのものは政治決着により片付けられてしまうが、この時の働きが評価され1877年（明治10年）警察の巡査隊長に任命され西南戦争の鎮圧に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The case itself was settled by a political solution, but his achievement was highly evaluated enough to be appointed as a chief patrol officer of police in 1877, and he worked on suppression of Seinan War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The case itself was settled by a political solution, but his achievement was highly evaluated enough to be appointed as a chief patrol officer of police in 1877, and he worked on the suppression of Seinan War.</e>
<cmt>theを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The case itself was settled by a political solution, but his achievement was highly evaluated enough to be appointed as a chief patrol officer of police in 1877, and he worked on the suppression of Seinan War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後司法省八等出仕、東京裁判所小検事、内務省 (日本)御用掛を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he successively worked as Hachito Shusshi (the 8th grade attendant) of Ministry of Justice, Shokenji (lower-grade prosecutor) of Tokyo Court and Goyogakari (general official) of Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he successively worked as Hachito Shusshi (the 8th grade attendant) of the Ministry of Justice, Shokenji (lower-grade prosecutor) of Tokyo Court and Goyogakari (general official) of Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt>theを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he successively worked as Hachito Shusshi (the 8th grade attendant) of the Ministry of Justice, Shokenji (lower-grade prosecutor) of Tokyo Court and Goyogakari (general official) of Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>西南戦争が終わった頃から政府は相次いで起こった内乱の逮捕者を収監する施設の建設が急務となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around the time after the end of Seinan War, the government came to have to rush the construction of facilities to detain arrestees from domestic conflict that successively occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around the time after the end of Seinan War, the government had to rush the construction of facilities to detain arrestees from domestic conflict that successively occurred.</e>
<cmt>had toにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around the time after the end of Seinan War, the government had to rush the construction of facilities to detain arrestees from domestic conflict that successively occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>本来危険分子の隔離が目的であったが、当時政府はロシアの南下に備える為に北海道の開拓を推し進め北の守りを固める方針をとっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original purpose was to isolate such dangerous elements, but the government of the times was having a policy to protect the north by encouraging reclamation of Hokkaido, in order to be ready for Russia&apos;s advancing southward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original purpose was to isolate such dangerous elements, but the government of the time had a policy to protect the north by encouraging reclamation of Hokkaido, in order to be ready for Russia&apos;s advancing southward.</e>
<cmt>timeにしました。Hadにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original purpose was to isolate such dangerous elements, but the government of the time had a policy to protect the north by encouraging reclamation of Hokkaido, in order to be ready for Russia&apos;s advancing southward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、北海道開拓は遅々として進まないことから内務卿の伊藤博文は囚人を安価で使える労働者とみたて囚人に開拓にあたらせることを発案し、監獄を北海道に建設する方針を固める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as reclamation of Hokkaido was advancing so slowly, Hirobumi ITO, Secretary of Interior, proposed to use prisoners as labors at low cost who engaged in reclamation, and determined the policy for constructing prisons in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as reclamation of Hokkaido was progressing so slowly, Hirobumi ITO, Secretary of Interior, proposed to use prisoners as labors at a low cost for the reclamation, and determined the policy for constructing prisons in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>progressingにしました。A lost cost, for the reclamationにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as reclamation of Hokkaido was progressing so slowly, Hirobumi ITO, Secretary of Interior, proposed to use prisoners as labors at a low cost for the reclamation, and determined the policy for constructing prisons in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>政府は開拓使黒田清隆に監獄候補地の推挙を求め、この現地調査にかねてから官吏として評価の高かった潔ら7人が抜擢される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government asked Kiyotaka KURODA, Hokkaido Development Commissioner, for recommendation of the candidate site where prisons would be constructed, and for the land survey, seven people including Kiyoshi who was already receiving a high public estimation were chozen as government officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government asked Kiyotaka KURODA, Hokkaido Development Commissioner, for recommendation of the candidate site where prisons would be constructed, and for the land survey, seven people including Kiyoshi, who were already evaluated highly, were chozen as government officials.</e>
<cmt>were already evaluated highlyにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government asked Kiyotaka KURODA, Hokkaido Development Commissioner, for recommendation of the candidate site where prisons would be constructed, and for the land survey, seven people including Kiyoshi, who were already evaluated highly, were chozen as government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>伊藤博文と山縣有朋が信頼してのものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was being trusted by Hirobumi ITO and Aritomo YAMAGATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was being trusted by Hirobumi ITO and Aritomo YAMAGATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was being trusted by Hirobumi ITO and Aritomo YAMAGATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>典獄として開拓を先導</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leading reclamation as Tengoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leading reclamation as Tengoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leading reclamation as Tengoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>開拓使による集治監候補地は十勝川沿岸、有珠郡奥後志山麓（羊蹄山）、石狩川上流方面の三箇所で、月形らは3班に分かれ調査を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The candidate sites for prisons selected by development commissioners were three locations such as the riverside of Tokachi River, the foot of a mountain in Okugoshi, Usu County (Mt. Yotei) and the upriver district of Ishikari River, and TSUKIGATA and others conducted land survey separated in three groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The candidate sites for prisons selected by development commissioners were three locations such as the riverside of Tokachi River, the foot of a mountain in Okugoshi, Usu County (Mt. Yotei) and the upriver district of Ishikari River, and TSUKIGATA and others conducted land survey separated in three groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The candidate sites for prisons selected by development commissioners were three locations such as the riverside of Tokachi River, the foot of a mountain in Okugoshi, Usu County (Mt. Yotei) and the upriver district of Ishikari River, and TSUKIGATA and others conducted land survey separated in three groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>月形が調査を行った石狩川沿上流は「シベツブト（上シベツ辺とも）」と呼ばれる土地で、樹木が生い茂り正に原生林そのものであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The upriver district of Ishikari River where TSUKIGATA conducted a survey was the land called &apos;Shibetsubuto (also referred to as &apos;Kami Shibetsu Atari&apos;)&apos; and it is said to have been just like a virgin forest with thick trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The upriver district of Ishikari River where TSUKIGATA conducted a survey was the land called &apos;Shibetsubuto (also referred to as &apos;Kami Shibetsu Atari&apos;)&apos; and it is said to have been just like a virgin forest with thick trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The upriver district of Ishikari River where TSUKIGATA conducted a survey was the land called &apos;Shibetsubuto (also referred to as &apos;Kami Shibetsu Atari&apos;)&apos; and it is said to have been just like a virgin forest with thick trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>他の候補地に比べ石狩川という水上交通を利用でき、札幌市に近いことからこの地と決め、1881年（明治14年）に建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the reason that it could use any water transportation with Ishikawa River and that it was close to Sapporo City compared to the other candidates, they decided there as construction site, and in 1881, the construction was launched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the reason that it could use any water transportation with Ishikawa River and that it was close to Sapporo City compared to the other candidates, they decided it to be the construction site, and in 1881, the construction was launched.</e>
<cmt>Forにしました。It to beにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the reason that it could use any water transportation with Ishikawa River and that it was close to Sapporo City compared to the other candidates, they decided it to be the construction site, and in 1881, the construction was launched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>建設された樺戸集治監の初代典獄（刑務所長）に月形が就任し、2000人もの囚人が収容された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TSUKIGATA was appointed as the 1st Tengoku (director of prison) of Kabato Shujikan which was just completed the construction, and two thousands prisoners were detained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TSUKIGATA was appointed as the 1st Tengoku (director of prison) of Kabato Shujikan where construction had just completed, and two thousands prisoners were detained.</e>
<cmt>where construction had just completedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TSUKIGATA was appointed as the 1st Tengoku (director of prison) of Kabato Shujikan where construction had just completed, and two thousands prisoners were detained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>月形はまず戸籍を福岡から樺戸に移し、率先して開拓にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TSUKIGATA began with a transfer of his family register from Fukuoka to Kabado, and took the initiative for reclamation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TSUKIGATA began with a transfer of his family register from Fukuoka to Kabado, and took the initiative for reclamation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TSUKIGATA began with a transfer of his family register from Fukuoka to Kabado, and took the initiative for reclamation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>月形の指揮する囚人達は効率よく開拓を進め、後に国道12号等北海道の主要道路とされるものの原型は彼等が作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prisoners TSUKIGATA was leading proceeded the reclamation effectively, and the prototype of the roads that later became the main roads in Hokkaido such as National Route 12 was formed by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prisoners led by TSUKIGATA proceeded the reclamation effectively, and the prototype of the roads that later became the main roads in Hokkaido such as National Route 12 was formed by them.</e>
<cmt>書き出しを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prisoners led by TSUKIGATA proceeded the reclamation effectively, and the prototype of the roads that later became the main roads in Hokkaido such as National Route 12 was formed by them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1884年（明治17年）北漸寺仮御堂等を建設する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884, Kari-mido (hall) of Hokuzen-ji Temple and others were constructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884, Kari-mido (hall) of Hokuzen-ji Temple among others were constructed.</e>
<cmt>amongにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884, Kari-mido (hall) of Hokuzen-ji Temple among others were constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>当時の樺戸集治監には官舎がなかった為月形も典獄といえども囚人と同じ場所で起居したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, as there was no official residence in Kabato Shujikan, TSUKIGATA slept in the same place as prisoners although he was Tengoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, as there was no official residence in Kabato Shujikan, TSUKIGATA slept in the same place as prisoners although he was Tengoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, as there was no official residence in Kabato Shujikan, TSUKIGATA slept in the same place as prisoners although he was Tengoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>月形が典獄を務めたこの頃集治監には｢五寸釘の寅吉｣で知られる西川寅吉や贋札作りの名人熊坂長奄等が収監されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shujikan of the times when TSUKIGATA was serving as Tengoku, Torakichi NISHIKAWA known for &apos;Torakichi handling Gosun-kugi long nail&apos; and Choan KUMASAKA, a famous creator of forfeit bills and others were detained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shujikan of the times when TSUKIGATA served as Tengoku, Torakichi NISHIKAWA known for &apos;Torakichi handling Gosun-kugi long nail&apos; and Choan KUMASAKA, a famous creator of forfeit bills and others were detained.</e>
<cmt>servedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shujikan of the times when TSUKIGATA served as Tengoku, Torakichi NISHIKAWA known for &apos;Torakichi handling Gosun-kugi long nail&apos; and Choan KUMASAKA, a famous creator of forfeit bills and others were detained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>熊坂は樺戸にいる間に村人に絵を教えていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KUMASAKA is said to have been teaching painting to village people while he was in Kabato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KUMASAKA is said to have taught painting to village people while he was in Kabato.</e>
<cmt>taughtにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KUMASAKA is said to have taught painting to village people while he was in Kabato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、新撰組の生き残りの永倉新八も剣術を教えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Shinpachi YONEKURA, a survivor of Shinsengumi, also was teaching swordplay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Shinpachi YONEKURA, a survivor of Shinsengumi, also was teaching swordplay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Shinpachi YONEKURA, a survivor of Shinsengumi, also was teaching swordplay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>村人は月形のこれらの功績を称え同地を「月形村」と提案し、内務省もまた認可を与え樺戸郡月形町となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The village people praised these TSUKIGATA&apos;s achievements and made a proposal to give the site a name of &apos;Tsukigata Village&apos;, and Ministry of Interior also approved, then it became Tsukigata Town, Kabato County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The village people praised these TSUKIGATA&apos;s achievements and made a proposal to give the site the name of &apos;Tsukigata Village&apos;, which the Ministry of Interior also approved, so it became Tsukigata Town, Kabato County.</e>
<cmt>theにしました。Which, soにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The village people praised these TSUKIGATA&apos;s achievements and made a proposal to give the site the name of &apos;Tsukigata Village&apos;, which the Ministry of Interior also approved, so it became Tsukigata Town, Kabato County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1885年（明治18年）に潔は肺を患い郷里の福岡で静養する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1885, Kiyoshi had trouble with his lungs, and took a rest cure in his hometown Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1885, Kiyoshi had trouble with his lungs, and took a rest cure in his hometown Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1885, Kiyoshi had trouble with his lungs, and took a rest cure in his hometown Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1894年（明治27年）逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1894, he passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away in 1894.</e>
<cmt>順序をかえました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away in 1894.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>樺戸集治監のその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Kabato Shujikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabato Shujikan in later years</e>
<cmt>in later yearsにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabato Shujikan in later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>月形が去った後も囚人達の開拓は進み、1886年（明治19年）には日本で初めてといわれる上水道を建設する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reclamation by prisoners proceeded even after TSUKIGATA&apos;s death, and in 1886, a water supply that is said the first in Japan was constructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reclamation by prisoners proceeded even after TSUKIGATA&apos;s death, and in 1886, a water supply that is said the first in Japan was constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reclamation by prisoners proceeded even after TSUKIGATA&apos;s death, and in 1886, a water supply that is said the first in Japan was constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これは月形水道或いは監獄水道と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is referred to as Tsukigata Suido (water supply) or Kangoku (prison) Suido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is referred to as Tsukigata Suido (water supply) or Kangoku (prison) Suido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is referred to as Tsukigata Suido (water supply) or Kangoku (prison) Suido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1896年（明治29年）には円福寺を建築する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, Enpuku-ji Temple was constructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896, Enpuku-ji Temple was constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, Enpuku-ji Temple was constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>住民と囚人との間でも交流がすすみ、囚人が住民の家を建てることもあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural exchanges between residents and prisoners proceeded, and it is said that, sometimes, prisoners built a house for local people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural exchanges between residents and prisoners proceeded, and it is said that, sometimes, prisoners built a house for the local people.</e>
<cmt>the localにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural exchanges between residents and prisoners proceeded, and it is said that, sometimes, prisoners built a house for the local people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>1909年（明治42年）には先の仮御堂建築した北漸寺本堂を完成させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1909, the main hall of Hikuzen-ji Temple which Kari-Mido had been already done was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1909, the main hall of Hikuzen-ji Temple, where Kari-Mido had been constructed, was completed.</e>
<cmt>whereにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1909, the main hall of Hikuzen-ji Temple, where Kari-Mido had been constructed, was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1919年（大正8年）に樺戸集治監は廃監となったが、その後は1973年（昭和48年）まで月形村役場として活用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, Kabato Shujikan came to close, but from the time to 1973, it was being used as Tsukigata-mura Village Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, Kabato Shujikan was closed, but it was being used as Tsukigata-mura Village Hall up to 1973.</e>
<cmt>was closedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, Kabato Shujikan was closed, but it was being used as Tsukigata-mura Village Hall up to 1973.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>月形の地には以後監獄はなくなったが1970年代に刑務所の誘致運動が興る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, there was no more prisons on the land of Tsukigata, but after 1970, a movement welcoming the construction of prisons began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, there was no more prisons on the land of Tsukigata, but after 1970, a movement welcoming the construction of prisons began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, there was no more prisons on the land of Tsukigata, but after 1970, a movement welcoming the construction of prisons began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>おりしも東京・中野刑務所の移転が検討されていた事もあり、運動の甲斐あって1983年（昭和58年）に月形刑務所が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, a relocation of Nakano Prison in Tokyo was under consideration, and also thanks to the movement, Tsukigata Prison was set up in 1983.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, a relocation of Nakano Prison in Tokyo was under consideration, and thanks to the movement, Tsukigata Prison was set up in 1983.</e>
<cmt>alsoを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, a relocation of Nakano Prison in Tokyo was under consideration, and thanks to the movement, Tsukigata Prison was set up in 1983.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>1973年（昭和48年）に月形町役場（1953年（昭和28年）に町制施行）が新庁舎に移ると旧樺戸集治監は新たに｢北海道行刑資料館｣として生まれ変わり、1996年（平成8年）同館は｢月形樺戸博物館｣と名称変更する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As in 1973, Tsukigata-cho Town Hall (back in 1953, Municipal organization was established) moved out to a new building, Old Kabato Shujikan was newly given a birth as &apos;Hokkaido Gyokei Shiryokan (Imprisonment Museum)&apos;, and in 1996, the name changed to &apos;Tsukigata Kabato Museum&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Tsukigata-cho Town Hall (back in 1953, Municipal organization was established) moved out to a new building in 1973, Old Kabato Shujikan was newly renovated as &apos;Hokkaido Gyokei Shiryokan (Imprisonment Museum)&apos;, and in 1996, the name changed to &apos;Tsukigata Kabato Museum&apos;.</e>
<cmt>in 1973の位置をかえました。renovatedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Tsukigata-cho Town Hall (back in 1953, Municipal organization was established) moved out to a new building in 1973, Old Kabato Shujikan was newly renovated as &apos;Hokkaido Gyokei Shiryokan (Imprisonment Museum)&apos;, and in 1996, the name changed to &apos;Tsukigata Kabato Museum&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>月形町には月形潔の銅像も建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tsukigata Town, the bronze statue of Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA was also built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tsukigata Town, the bronze statue of Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA was also built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tsukigata Town, the bronze statue of Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA was also built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 パの字(id:34188), 海亀(id:48936), ZassouTori(id:136771), BBG(id:124711), 代言人(id:33675), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), Complex01(id:10454), BitBucket(id:30999), Him56(id:137349), としぴい(id:161011), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>