<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原顕信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akinobu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akinobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akinobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 顕信（ふじわらの あきのぶ、正暦5年（994年） - 万寿4年（1027年）5月14日 (旧暦)）は、平安時代の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akinobu (994-May 14, 1027) was a noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akinobu (994-May 14, 1027) was a noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akinobu (994-May 14, 1027) was a noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原道長の三男、母は源明子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his mother was MINAMOTO no Akiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his mother was MINAMOTO no Akiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his mother was MINAMOTO no Akiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>法名長禅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Chozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Chozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Chozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>右馬頭の職にあった寛弘9年正月19日（1012年2月19日）、世を儚み行願寺（革堂）の行円の許を訪ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He grew weary of the world and visited Gyoen of Gyogan-ji Temple (Ko-do) on February 19, 1012 when he was on the post of Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He grew weary of the world and visited Gyoen of Gyogan-ji Temple (Ko-do) on February 19, 1012 when he was filling the post of Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He grew weary of the world and visited Gyoen of Gyogan-ji Temple (Ko-do) on February 19, 1012 when he was filling the post of Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その教えに感銘を受け、そのまま剃髪し、比叡山無動寺に出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was impressed by the teachings, immediately got his head shaved and became a priest in Mudo-ji Temple, Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was impressed by the teachings, immediately had his head shaved, and became a priest in Mudo-ji Temple, Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was impressed by the teachings, immediately had his head shaved, and became a priest in Mudo-ji Temple, Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その将来に期待していた両親は、大いに嘆き悲しんだと言われる（『大鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His parents who felt hopeful about his future are said to have been extremely disappointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His parents, who felt hopeful about his future, are said to have been extremely disappointed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His parents, who felt hopeful about his future, are said to have been extremely disappointed (&quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror)).</e>
<cmt>（『大鏡』）　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし、顕信の出家の2ヶ月前にあった事件が出家の一因であったとの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some said that his becoming a priest was caused by an incident which occurred two months before it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some said that his becoming a priest was caused by an incident which had occurred two months before.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some said that his becoming a priest was caused by an incident which had occurred two months before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>寛弘8年12月15日、藤原伊周の子藤原道雅と道長の子藤原頼宗（高松三位中将）及びその舎弟が、派遣先の北野の斎場にて他人の悪口を言い合っていたことが発覚している（『小右記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was found out that FUJIWARA no Michimasa, son of FUJIWARA no Korechika, FUJIWARA no Yorimune, son of Michinaga and his younger brother were speaking ill of others at the funeral hall in Kitano where they were sent to (&quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) on December 15, 1011.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was found out that FUJIWARA no Michimasa, son of FUJIWARA no Korechika; FUJIWARA no Yorimune, son of Michinaga; and his younger brother were speaking ill of others at the funeral hall in Kitano where they were sent to (&quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) on December 15, 1011.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was found out that FUJIWARA no Michimasa, son of FUJIWARA no Korechika; FUJIWARA no Yorimune (Takamatsu Sanmi no chujo), son of Michinaga; and his younger brother were speaking ill of others at the funeral hall in Kitano where they were sent to (&quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) on January 17, 1012.</e>
<cmt>（高松三位中将）　訳漏れ対応しました。旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『小右記』では頼宗の弟が誰であるかは明らかにはされていないものの、状況的に道雅・頼宗と居合わせられる弟は顕信以外にはいなかったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Shoyuki&quot; didn&apos;t disclose who the brother of Yorimune was, a brother who could be with Michimasa and Yorimune was considered to be only Akinobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;Shoyuki&quot; didn&apos;t disclose who the brother of Yorimune was, Akinobu was the only brother who could have been with Michimasa and Yorimune.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;Shoyuki&quot; didn&apos;t disclose who the brother of Yorimune was, Akinobu was the only brother who could have been with Michimasa and Yorimune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その4日後の19日、三条天皇から道長に対して藤原通任の参議昇進で空席となった蔵人頭に顕信を就ける意志を告げたところ、道長が顕信は「不足職之者」で「衆人之謗」を招くとして辞退を申し出ている（『権記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 19, four days after that, when Emperor Sanjo expressed to Michinaga his intention to appoint Akinobu Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) which became empty due to FUJIWARA no Michito&apos;s promotion to Sangi (councilor), Michinaga declined to accept it, saying Akinobu is &apos;lack of knowledge&apos; which would invite &apos;public censure&apos; (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary).</e>
<cmt>「不足職之者」＝「lack of knowledge」、 「衆人之謗」＝「public censure」は、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four days later, on December 19, when Emperor Sanjo expressed to Michinaga his intention to appoint Akinobu Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) which became vacant due to FUJIWARA no Michito&apos;s promotion to Sangi (councilor), Michinaga declined to accept it, saying Akinobu is &apos;lack of knowledge&apos; which would invite &apos;public censure&apos; (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four days later, on January 21, when Emperor Sanjo expressed to Michinaga his intention to appoint Akinobu Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) which became vacant due to FUJIWARA no Michito&apos;s promotion to Sangi (councilor), Michinaga declined to accept it, saying Akinobu is &apos;lack of knowledge&apos; which would invite &apos;public censure&apos; (&quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s Diary).</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦（の後のスペース短縮diary→Diary</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>道長の辞退の理由は15日の一件と考えられているが、同時に天皇の前で父親から「不足職之者」と評された顕信は、自己の将来に対する不安を抱えていたことが突然の出家につながったというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cause for Michinaga&apos;s decline is considered to have been the incident on December 15 and at the same time Akinobu who was described as &apos;lack of knowledge&apos; by his father in the presence of the Emperor was rife with anxiety about his own future, which led to his becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause for Michinaga&apos;s decline is considered to have been the incident on December 15, and at the same time Akinobu, who was described as &apos;lack of knowledge&apos; by his father in the presence of the Emperor, was rife with anxiety about his own future, which led to his becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause for Michinaga&apos;s decline is considered to have been the incident on January 17, and at the same time Akinobu, who was described as &apos;lack of knowledge&apos; by his father in the presence of the Emperor, was rife with anxiety about his own future, which led to his becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、無動寺から大原 (京都市)に移って仏道修行に励んでいた（『御堂関白記』長和3年8月9日条）が、余命短い事を悟って延暦寺の根本本堂に2週間籠った後に無動寺にて病死したという（『栄花物語』巻15）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After then, while he moved from Mudo-ji Temple to Ohara (Kyoto City) where he devoted himself to ascetic training (August 9, 1014 entry of &quot;Mido Kanpakuki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s diary), he realized he had a limited life expectancy and after he confined himself in Konpon main temple of Enryaku-ji Temple for two weeks, he died of disease in Mudo-ji Temple (Book 15 of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;, the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After then, while he moved from Mudo-ji Temple to Ohara (Kyoto City) where he devoted himself to ascetic training (August 9, 1014 entry of &quot;Mido Kanpakuki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s diary), he realized he had a limited life expectancy and after he confined himself in Konpon main temple of Enryaku-ji Temple for two weeks, he died of disease in Mudo-ji Temple (Book 15 of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;, the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After then, while he moved from Mudo-ji Temple to Ohara (Kyoto City) where he devoted himself to ascetic training (September 11, 1014 entry of &quot;Mido Kanpakuki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s Diary), he realized he had a limited life expectancy and after he confined himself in Konpon main temple of Enryaku-ji Temple for two weeks, he died of disease in Mudo-ji Temple (Vol. 15 of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;, the Tale of Glory).</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦diary→DiaryBook→Vol.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), エルシード(id:122427), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Electric goat(id:2935), 伏儀(id:142093), Snap55(id:89773), Yossie(id:121855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>