<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐々木秀綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsuna SASAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsuna SASAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsuna SASAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐々木 秀綱（ささき ひでつな）は、鎌倉時代末期から室町時代初期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsuna SASAKI was a warlord who lived in the late Kamakura Period and the beginning of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsuna SASAKI was a warlord who lived in the late Kamakura Period and the beginning of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsuna SASAKI was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived in the late Kamakura period and the beginning of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。Busho　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>足利尊氏に仕え、室町幕府の成立に大きく貢献する佐々木道誉の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Takauji ASHIKAGA and he was born as the first son of Doyo SASAKI who greatly contributed to formation of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Takauji ASHIKAGA and he was born the first son of Doyo SASAKI, who greatly contributed to formation of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the first son of Doyo SASAKI, who served Takauji ASHIKAGA and greatly contributed to formation of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>尊氏に仕えたのが道誉である、という意味にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>延元3年/暦応元年（1338年）には国司を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1338, he worked as a kokushi (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1338, he worked as a kokushi (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1338, he worked as a kokushi (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>北畠顕家が陸奥国より足利義詮の守る鎌倉を落し京へと攻め寄せた際には、これを迎え撃つべく、高師泰、高師冬、細川頼春、佐々木氏信、父の佐々木道誉らと共に近江国と美濃国の国境へと赴き、顕家の進軍を阻止する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Akiie KITABATAKE, after capturing Kamakura which was guarded by Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, closed in to Kyoto from Mutsu Province, Hidetsuna went to the border between the Omi Province and the Mino Province together with KO no Moroyasu, KO no Morofuyu, Yoriharu HOSOKAWA, Ujinobu SASAKI and his father, Doyo SASAKI, and stopped Akiie&apos;s marching.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Akiie KITABATAKE, after capturing Kamakura which was guarded by Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, closed in on Kyoto from Mutsu Province, Hidetsuna went to the border between Omi Province and Mino Province together with KO no Moroyasu, KO no Morofuyu, Yoriharu HOSOKAWA, Ujinobu SASAKI and his father, Doyo SASAKI, and stopped Akiie&apos;s march.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Akiie KITABATAKE, after capturing Kamakura which was guarded by Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, closed in on Kyoto from Mutsu Province, Hidetsuna went to the border between Omi Province and Mino Province together with KO no Moroyasu, KO no Morofuyu, Yoriharu HOSOKAWA, Ujinobu SASAKI and his father, Doyo SASAKI, and stopped Akiie&apos;s march.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>興国元年/暦応3年（1340年）、家臣が光厳天皇の弟である妙法院の御所の僧兵に殴打された事を怒り、父と共に御所に火をかけ建仁寺を延焼させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1340, he got angry when his retainer was beaten by sohei (armed priest) of the gosho (Imperial Palace) of Myohoin, who was a younger brother of the Emperor Kogon, and set fire to the palace together with his father and burnt the Kennin-ji Temple by spread fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1340, he got angry when his retainer was beaten by a sohei (armed priest) of the gosho (Imperial Palace) of Myohoin, who was a younger brother of the Emperor Kogon, and set fire to the palace together with his father and burnt Kennin-ji Temple by spread of fire.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1340, he got angry when his retainer was beaten by a sohei (armed priest) of the gosho (Imperial Palace) of Myohoin, who was a younger brother of the Emperor Kogon, and set fire to the palace together with his father and burnt Kennin-ji Temple by spread of fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>延暦寺は朝廷と幕府に二人の死罪を求めるが、幕府はこれを放置し、延暦寺がさらに強く抗議を行った結果、二人は上総国山辺郡 (上総国)へ一時流される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Enryaku-ji Temple require Imperial Court and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to sentence both of them to death, but the bakufu left the matter as it was, but after the Enryaku-ji Temple made stronger protest, both of them were temporarily exiled to Yamabe-gun Kazusa Province (Kazusa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enryaku-ji Temple required the Imperial Court and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to sentence both of them to death, but the bakufu left the matter as it was; after Enryaku-ji Temple made a stronger protest, both of them were temporarily exiled to Yamabe-gun Kazusa Province (Kazusa Province).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enryaku-ji Temple required the Imperial Court and the bakufu to sentence both of them to death, but the bakufu left the matter as it was; after Enryaku-ji Temple made a stronger protest, both of them were temporarily exiled to Yamabe-gun, Kazusa Province (Kazusa Province).</e>
<cmt>幕府　既出単語のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その道中は道々で酒席を設け宿々で美女を弄び、流人には見えなかったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On their way, they gave a drinking party in every road and played with beauty in every inn and therefore they did not look like exiles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On their way, they gave a drinking party on every road and played with beauty in every inn and therefore they did not look like exiles.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On their way, they gave a drinking party on every road and played with beauty in every inn and therefore they did not look like exiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>興国6年/康永4年（1345年）には検非違使を務めており、後醍醐天皇を弔う天龍寺の法要が行われた際に警備を担当している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1345, he served as kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and he was in charge of security when memorial service at the Tenryu-ji Temple for mourning the Emperor Godaigo was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1345, he served as kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and was in charge of security when a memorial service was held at Tenryu-ji Temple for mourning the Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1345, he served as kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and was in charge of security when a memorial service was held at Tenryu-ji Temple for mourning the Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>正平 (日本)6年/観応2年（1351年）、観応の擾乱で尊氏とその弟である足利直義が対立し、直義追討の宣旨を得て近江に布陣した三百騎に満たない尊氏の軍に、父と共に三千余騎を率いて真っ先に参じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1351, Takauji and his younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA had conflict between them, and Hidetsuna joined together with his father, leading more than three thousand horsed warriors, in the army of Takauji with less than three hundred mounted warriors, which Takauji took up their position in Omi after obtaining an Imperial order to send a punitive force against Tadayoshi,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1351, Takauji and his younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, had a conflict between them, and Hidetsuna joined together with his father, leading more than three thousand mounted warriors, in the army of Takauji with less than three hundred mounted warriors, which Takauji took up their position in Omi after obtaining an Imperial order to send a punitive force against Tadayoshi,</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1351, Takauji and his younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, had a conflict between them in the Kanno Disturbance, and Hidetsuna joined together with his father, leading more than three thousand mounted warriors, in the army of Takauji with less than three hundred mounted warriors, which Takauji took up their position in Omi after obtaining an Imperial order to send a punitive force against Tadayoshi,</e>
<cmt>観応の擾乱 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>正平8年/文和2年（1353年）6月13日、侍所司を務めており、南朝に京を追われ東近江へと逃れる後光厳天皇、足利義詮らを守っていた際に、堅田近くの真野浦にて、新田氏の残党である堀口貞祐に襲われ、戦いの末に討たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 13, 1353, when he served as Samurai-dokoro no tsukasa (the officer of the Board of Retainers) and guarding the Emperor Gokogon and Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who were forced out from Kyoto and escaping to Higashi-omi (eastern Omi), he was attacked by Sadasuke HORIGUCHI, who was the remnant of the Nitta clan, at Mano no ura near Katata and killed in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 13, 1353, when he served as Samurai-dokoro no tsukasa (officer of the Board of Retainers) and was guarding the Emperor Gokogon and Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who had been forced out from Kyoto and were escaping to Higashi-omi (eastern Omi), he was attacked by Sadasuke HORIGUCHI, who was the remnant of the Nitta clan, at Mano no ura near Katata and was killed in the battle.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 22, 1353, when he served as Samurai-dokoro no tsukasa (officer of the Board of Retainers) and was guarding the Emperor Gokogon and Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who had been forced out from Kyoto and were escaping to Higashi-omi (eastern Omi), he was attacked by Sadasuke HORIGUCHI, who was the remnant of the Nitta clan, at Mano no ura near Katata and was killed in the battle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。二バイト文字を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Oxhop(id:2551), Kinori(id:443), 俊(id:14924), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>