<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原有綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Aritsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Aritsuna</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Aritsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 有綱（ふじわら の ありつな、生年不詳 - 永保2年（1082年）または応徳3年（1086年））は、平安時代後期の廷臣、学者、漢詩人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Aritsuna (date of birth unknown -1082 or 1086) was a retainer of Imperial Court,scholar, andChinese-style poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Aritsuna (date of birth unknown -1082 or 1086) was a retainer of the Imperial Court, scholar, and Chinese-style poet.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Aritsuna (date of birth unknown -1082 or 1086) was a retainer of the Imperial Court, scholar, and Chinese-style poet in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「平安時代後期の」→訳漏れのため訳出対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家藤原真夏流（日野家流）の出身で、式部大輔・藤原実綱の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, FUJIWARA no Manatsu line (the Hino family line) and a son of Shikibu no taifu (Senior assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial) FUJIWARA no Sanetsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, FUJIWARA no Manatsu line (the Hino family line) and a son of Shikibu no taifu (Senior assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial) FUJIWARA no Sanetsuna.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, FUJIWARA no Manatsu line (the Hino family line) and a son of Shikibu no taifu (Senior assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial) FUJIWARA no Sanetsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は備後守源道成の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is a daughter of the Military Governor of Bingo, MINAMOTO no Michinar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother is a daughter of the Military Governor of Bingo, MINAMOTO no Michinari.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of the Military Governor of Bingo Province, MINAMOTO no Michinari.</e>
<cmt>is→was、Bingo→Bingo Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>弟に藤原有俊、藤原有信、藤原有定らが、子に実義、資文らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Aritoshi, FUJIWARA no Arinobu, and FUJIWARA no Arisada are his younger brothers, and Saneyoshi and Shifumi are his sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Aritoshi, FUJIWARA no Arinobu, and FUJIWARA no Arisada are his younger brothers, and Saneyoshi and Shifumi are his sons.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Aritoshi, FUJIWARA no Arinobu, and FUJIWARA no Arisada were his younger brothers, and Saneyoshi and Shifumi were his sons.</e>
<cmt>are→wereとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>天喜元年（1053年）に対策に及第し、左衛門尉となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1053 he passed Taisaku (governmental officer examination in the Heian Period) and became Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>対策→定訳不明：Taisaku (the governmental officer examination in the Heian Period)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1053 he passed Taisaku (governmental officer examination in the Heian Period) and became Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1053 he passed Taisaku (governmental officer examination in the Heian Period) and became Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以後、蔵人、左少弁、中宮亮、大学頭、文章博士等々を歴任し、その学識の高さをもって知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he served successively as Kurodo (Chamberlain), Sashoben (third ranked officer of the left), Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), Monjo hakase (professor of literature), etc., and he was distinguished for the breadth of his learning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, he served successively as Kurodo (Chamberlain), Sashoben (third ranked officer of the left), Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), Monjo hakase (professor of literature), etc., and he was distinguished for the breadth of his learning.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, he served successively as Kurodo (Chamberlain), Sashoben (third ranked officer of the left), Chugu no suke (Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household), Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education), Monjo hakase (professor of literature), etc., and he was distinguished for the breadth of his learning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>年号「応徳」の制定の勘申者でもあったことから、応徳年間のころには最も名声がある学者の一人であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was Kanjinsha (the proposer) of the name of the era Otoku as well, during the Otoku Era, he was said to be one of the most highly recognized scholars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was Kanjinsha (the proposer) of the name of the era Otoku as well, during the Otoku Era, he was said to be one of the most highly recognized scholars.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was Kanjinsha (the proposer) of the name of the era &apos;Otoku&apos; as well, during the Otoku era, he was said to be one of the most highly recognized scholars.</e>
<cmt>Eraの頭文字を小文字に変更、クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>漢詩人や歌人としても名高く、漢詩は『本朝無題詩』や『別本和漢兼作集』、和歌は『万代集』『秋風集』などにその作が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also famous as a Chinese style poet and a poet, and his Chinese poetries are included in &quot;Honchomudaishi&quot; (A collection of Chinese poems), &quot;Beppon wakan kensaku shu&quot; (Special issueof a collection of Japanese-Chinese poems) and his waka poetries are found in &quot;Mandaishu&quot; and &quot;Shufushu,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>『別本和漢兼作集』→&quot;Beppon wakan kensaku shu&quot; (Special issue of a collection of Japanese-Chinese poems) (別本和漢兼作集) [正式な読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also famous as a Chinese style poet and a poet, and his Chinese poetries are included in &quot;Honchomudaishi&quot; (A collection of Chinese poems), &quot;Beppon wakan kensaku shu&quot; (Special issue of a collection of Japanese-Chinese poems) and his waka poetries are found in &quot;Mandaishu&quot; and &quot;Shufushu,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also famous as a Chinese style poet and a poet, and his Chinese poetries are included in &quot;Honchomudaishi&quot; (A collection of Chinese poems), &quot;Beppon Wakan Kensaku Shu&quot; (Special issue of a collection of Japanese-Chinese poems) and his waka poetries are found in &quot;Mandaishu&quot; and &quot;Shufushu,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Beppon Wakan Kensaku Shu&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>承保2年（1075年）には自邸で歌合せを開催したことが記録に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a record, in 1075 he organized a utaawase (poetry contest) at his residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a record, in 1075 he organized a utaawase (poetry contest) at his residence.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a record, in 1075 he organized a utaawase (poetry contest) at his residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>その息女は源義家の室となり、源義国・源義忠兄弟の母となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter married into MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and became a mother of MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni and his younger brother MINAMOTO no Yoshitada..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter married MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and became the mother of MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni and his younger brother MINAMOTO no Yoshitada..</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter married MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and became the mother of MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni and his younger brother MINAMOTO no Yoshitada..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 阿波座行広(id:39667), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), BAKU(id:55205), Suisui(id:69), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>