<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺実通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 実通（とくだいじ さねみち、永正10年（1513年） - 天文 (元号)14年4月9日 (旧暦)（1545年5月19日））は、室町時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI (1513 - May 19, 1545) was a kugyo (top court noble) who lived in the latter half of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI (1513 - May 19, 1545) was a kugyo (top court noble) who lived during the latter half of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI (1513 - May 29, 1545) was a kugyo (court noble) who lived during the latter half of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一19→29</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後柏原天皇（104代）・後奈良天皇（105代）の二帝にわたって仕え、官位は正二位権大納言・近衛府まで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served two emperors of Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th emperor) and Emperor Gonara (the 105th emperor), and was promoted up to Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor) and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) at the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served two emperors, Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th emperor) and Emperor Gonara (the 105th emperor), and was promoted up to Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor) and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) at the rank of Shonii (Senior 2nd Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served two emperors, Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th) and Emperor Gonara (the 105th), and was promoted up to Gon Dainagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) at the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初名は実規。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His initial name was Sanenori.</e>
<cmt>実規：　読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His initial name was Sanenori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His initial name was Sanenori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は左大臣徳大寺公胤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kimitane TOKUDAIJI, Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kimitane TOKUDAIJI, Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kintane TOKUDAIJI, Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は尾張国源某の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of a Minamoto family member (his name was unknown) in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of a Minamoto family member (his name was unknown) in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of a Minamoto family member (his name was unknown) in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>養子に内大臣徳大寺公維。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinfusa TOKUDAIJI, Naidaijin (minister of the interior), was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinfusa TOKUDAIJI, Naidaijin (minister of the interior), was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinfusa TOKUDAIJI, Naidaijin (minister of the interior), was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>永正16年（1519年）に従五位上に叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1519, he was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1519, he was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior 5th Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1519, he was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>以降、侍従・近衛府などを歴任、大永7年（1527年）に従三位となり公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, he assumed a palace staff and a post at Konoefu in succession, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1527, becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, he assumed a palace staff and a post at Konoefu in succession, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank) in 1527, becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>grammr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, he assumed a palace staff and a post at Konoefu in succession, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1527, becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、中納言を経て、天文元年（1532年）に大納言に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he was appointed to Dainagon (a major counselor) in 1532 after assuming Chunagon (a middle counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was appointed to Dainagon (major counselor) in 1532 after assuming Chunagon (middle counselor).</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was appointed to Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 1532 after assuming Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>(major counselor)→(chief councilor of state)(middle counselor)→ (vice-councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>またこの年に実通と改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year, he changed his name to Sanemichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he changed his name to Sanemichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he changed his name to Sanemichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし経済的に困窮し、天文3年（1534年）に最初の北国下向。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was reduced to poverty economically, and moved for the first time to the northern region, leaving the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was reduced to poverty economically, and moved for the first time to the northern region, leaving the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was reduced to poverty economically, and moved for the first time to the northern region, leaving the capital in 1534.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天文5年（1536年）には一度帰京し、従二位・正二位と昇進し、天文11年（1542年）近衛府。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned once to Kyoto in 1536, was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) and then to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and assumed a post at Konoefu in 1542.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned once to Kyoto in 1536, was promoted to Junii (Junior 2nd Rank) and then to Shonii (Senior 2nd Rank), and assumed a post at Konoefu in 1542.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned once to Kyoto in 1536, was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) and then to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and assumed a post at Konoefu in 1542.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし天文14年（1545年）に京都で戦乱がおこった際に再び北国へ逃れ、越中国放生津城へ入ったが、同地で神保長職により殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when a battle occurred in Kyoto, he escaped again to the northern region and entered Hojozu-jo Castle in Ecchu Province, but was killed there by Nagatomo JINBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when a battle broke out in Kyoto, he escaped again to the northern region and entered Hojozu-jo Castle in Ecchu Province, but was killed there by Nagatomo JINBO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when a battle broke out in Kyoto in 1545, he escaped again to the northern region and entered Hojozu-jo Castle in Ecchu Province, but was killed there by Nagatomo JINBO.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>享年33。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 33 years old when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 33 years old when he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 33.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>これを受けて朝廷では久我家の庶子徳大寺公維をもって実通の養子となし、徳大寺家を継がせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving this information, the Imperial court made Kinfusa TOKUDAIJI, a son from an unlawful wife of the kuga family, his adopted son and made Kinfusa inherit the Daitokuji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Receiving this information, the Imperial court made Kinfusa TOKUDAIJI, a son from an unlawful wife of the kuga family, his adopted son and had Kinfusa inherit the Daitokuji family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving this information, the Imperial court made Kinfusa TOKUDAIJI, a son from an unlawful wife of the Koga family, his adopted son and had Kinfusa inherit the Tokudaiji family.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Troy3(id:259591), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>