<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長尾真墨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAO no Masumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAO no Masumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAO no Masumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長尾真墨（ながおのますみ、生没年不明）は、日本の飛鳥時代の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAO no Masumi (year of birth and death unknown) was one historical figure in the Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAO no Masumi (year of birth and death unknown) was a person from the Asuka Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>one historiacl figure in -&gt; a person from</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAO no Masumi (year of birth and death unknown) was a person from the Asuka Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧仮名遣いでの読みは「ながをのますみ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the old Japanese syllabary characters way of reading, it was read NAGAWO no Masumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old Japanese syllabary characters, his name was pronounced &apos;NAGAWO no Masumi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>read -&gt; pronounced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old Japanese syllabary characters, his name was pronounced &apos;NAGAWO no Masumi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>姓（カバネ）は直。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabane (hereditary title) was Atai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Kabane (hereditary title) was Atai.</e>
<cmt>His を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Kabane (hereditary title) was Atai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>672年の壬申の乱のとき大海人皇子（天武天皇）側につき、河内国から倭（大和国）に来る敵を防いで連戦したが、およばず退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking sides with Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) at the Jinshin War in 672 and although having many battles to defend Yamato Province against the enemy coming from Kawachi Province, NAGAO was forced to retreat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jinshin War which broke out in 672, NAGAO fought for Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) and participated in a series of wars to defend the enemy from Kawachi Province to Yamato (Yamato Province), but he was forced to retreat.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jinshin War which broke out in 672, NAGAO fought for Prince Oama (Emperor Tenmu) and participated in a series of wars to defend the enemy from Kawachi Province to Yamato (Yamato Province), but he was forced to retreat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>長尾氏は、東漢氏に属する渡来系の氏族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NAGAO Clan is one member of the immigrants coming from oversea to ancient Japan belonging to the Tokan Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nagao clan was one of the Yamatonoaya clan, the families of immigrants from overseas to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>東漢氏：やまとのあや（うじ）http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn2/222972/m0u/%E6%9D%B1%E6%BC%A2%E6%B0%8F/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nagao clan was one of the Yamatonoaya clan, the families of immigrants from overseas to ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>壬申の年（672年）の6月29日に倭で挙兵した大伴吹負は、北進して及楽（奈良市）に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 2, 672 (the year of Mizunoe-Saru, one of the Oriental Zoadic), OTOMO no Fukei took arms and they headed to Kyuraku (NARA City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 672, OTOMO no Fukei and his troops rose in arms in Yamato and headed for north, Nara (NARA City).</e>
<cmt>天武天皇元年6月29日は西暦672年8月1日です。及楽：読みは「なら」としています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, 672, OTOMO no Fukei and his troops rose in arms in Yamato and headed for north, Nara (NARA City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その途中、おそらく7月3日に、河内から大軍が来たという情報を稗田で得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way to Kyuraku (Nara City), probably July 2, 673 at Hieda OTOMO obtained information that a large forces would come from Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hieda, on his way to Nara, probably on August 4, 672, Fukei got the information of the invasion of a large enemy force coming from Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>天武天皇元年7月3日は西暦672年8月4日です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hieda, on his way to Nara, probably on August 4, 672, Fukei got the information of the invasion of a large enemy force coming from Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>吹負は数百人ずつの3隊を分派して守備につかせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukei organized three military units of some hundred members each and despatched them to defend the district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukei organized three military units comprised of some hundred members for each and dispatched them for the defense.</e>
<cmt>comprise を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukei organized three military units comprised of some hundred members for each and dispatched them for the defense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのうち、竜田に向かった300人の指揮官が、坂本財、長尾真墨、倉墻麻呂、民小鮪、谷根麻呂であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The commanders of the unit of three hundred members heading to Tatsuda were SAKAMOTO no Takara, NAGAO no Masumi, KURAKAKI no Maro, 民小鮪 and TANI no ne Maro.</e>
<cmt>民小鮪　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKAMOTO no Takara, NAGAO no Masumi, KURAKAKI no Maro, TAMI no Oshibi, and TANI no Ne Maro were involved in the troops as the commanders of the 300-member unit that headed for Tatsuta.</e>
<cmt>民小鮪：たみのおしび</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKAMOTO no Takara, NAGAO no Masumi, KURAKAKI no Maro, TAMI no Oshibi, and TANI no Ne Maro were involved in the troops as the commanders of the 300-member unit that headed for Tatsuta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼らはその日平石野に宿営したが、高安城に敵軍がいると聞いてその山に登った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they set up camp at Hiraishino on the sameday, with obtaining information that the enemy was in Takayasu Castle which was located in mountain, they climed the mountain to fight against the enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they set up camps at Hiraishino on the same day, the commanders were informed that there was the enemy in Takayasunoki Castle, so they climbed the mountain where the castle was located to attack the enemy.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。高安城：「たかやすじょう」は戦国時代の城です。原文の時代の読みは「たかやすのき」です。古代の山城のため、Castleを追記しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they set up camps at Hiraishino on the same day, the commanders were informed that there was the enemy in Takayasunoki Castle, so they climbed the mountain where the castle was located to attack the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>近江軍（弘文天皇側の軍）は税倉を焼いて逃げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi forces (the army on the Emperor Kobun&apos;s side) fled from the castle setting fire to storehouses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi forces (the army on the Emperor Kobun&apos;s side) fled from the castle after setting fire to storehouses.</e>
<cmt>after を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi forces (the army on the Emperor Kobun&apos;s side) fled from the castle after setting fire to storehouses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>翌日（3日か）の朝、彼らは、西方の大津・丹比の両道に壱伎韓国が率いる大軍を見た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next morning (6th) they saw a large force in the west in command of Repubric Korea along both Otsu and Taiji streets</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next morning (5th) they saw a large enemy force led by IKI no Karakuni approaching from both Otsu-chi Road and Tajihi-michi Road which were located on the west side of the castle.</e>
<cmt>「翌日」は「7月4日」と考え、（3日か）は割愛しています。西暦672年8月5日としています。大津・丹比：大津道、丹比道と解釈しました。壱伎韓国：いきのからくに以下「韓国」は「かんこく」ではなく人名「からくに」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next morning (5th) they saw a large enemy force led by IKI no Karakuni approaching from both Otsu-chi Road and Tajihi-michi Road which were located on the west side of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>城から下って衛我河を渡り、川の西で戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After coming down from the castle and crossing the Eiga gawa-river, they had a battle in the west of the river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They left the castle and advanced the troops across Egakawa River, and the battle broke out on the west side of the river.</e>
<cmt>衛我河：えがかわ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They left the castle and advanced the troops across Egakawa River, and the battle broke out on the west side of the river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>敗れて懼坂に用意しておいた陣営に退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they were defeated in the battle, retreating to the camp which have been arrenged in 懼坂</e>
<cmt>懼坂　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they were defeated and gathered at the camp which had been set up in Kashikosaka after the withdrawal.</e>
<cmt>懼坂：かしこさか</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they were defeated and gathered at the camp which had been set up in Kashikosaka after the withdrawal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、勝った韓国軍の側では、河内国司守来目塩籠が大海人皇子側にくみするために軍を集めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the side of the victorious Korean army however, Shiogori KUME the governor of Kawachi Province was gathering the members of the army to take Prince Oama&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the troops of Karakuni, the winner, KUME no Shioko, Kawachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Kawachi Province), was gathering the troops to take the side of Prince Oama.</e>
<cmt>来目塩籠：くめのしおこ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the troops of Karakuni, the winner, KUME no Shioko, Kawachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Kawachi Province), was gathering the troops to take the side of Prince Oama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この計画は韓国に知られ、失敗を悟った塩籠は自殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing this plot failed, Shiogori committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karakuni detected Shioko&apos;s betrayal, and Shioko committed suicide knowing that his plot was failed.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karakuni detected Shioko&apos;s betrayal, and Shioko committed suicide knowing that his plot was failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>中一日をおいて、おそらく5日に、近江軍はいくつもの道から押し寄せてきたため、退却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day after tomorrow, possibly on 8 their troops retreated without any battles, since Omi forces were surging from everywhere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two days later, probably on 7, the commanders decided to pull out their troops as they saw Omi forces attacking from every direction.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。日付は「7月6日」と考え、西暦672年8月7日としています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two days later, probably on 7, the commanders decided to pull out their troops as they saw Omi forces attacking from every direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>長尾真墨はこの後も大伴吹負のもとで戦ったと考えられるが、その様子は『日本書紀』に現れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAO no Masumi was believed to have continued fighting under OTOMO no Fukei after this war howwver, nothing of his story appered in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAO no Masumi was believed to have continued fighting for OTOMO no Fukei after this battle, but nothing was mentioned about him in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAO no Masumi was believed to have continued fighting for OTOMO no Fukei after this battle, but nothing was mentioned about him in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kinori(id:443), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>