<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一色義幸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一色 義幸（いっしき よしゆき、生没年不詳）は戦国時代 (日本)の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI (dates of birth &amp; death unknown) was a personality during Japan&apos;s Sengoku (Warring States) Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI (dates of birth &amp; death unknown) was a figure during Japan&apos;s Sengoku (Warring States) Period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;personality&quot;&quot;figure&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI (dates of birth and death unknown) was a figure during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>&amp; →and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>丹後国の大名一色氏の当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was head of the Isshiki Clan and Daimyo (lord) of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was head of the Isshiki Clan and Daimyo (lord) of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was head of the Isshiki clan and Daimyo (lord) of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一色氏庶流で伊勢国守護を務めた一色教親の末裔とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an illegitimate member of the Isshiki Clan, served as Kokushu (Governor) of Ise Province and is considered a descendant of Norichika ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an illegitimate member of the Isshiki Clan, served as Kokushu (Governor) of Ise Province and is considered a descendant of Norichika ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a descendant of Norichika ISSHIKI, who was an illegitimate member of the Isshiki clan and served as Shugo (military governor) of Ise Province</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一色義道、一色義清（吉原義清）の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father of: Yoshimichi ISSHIKI and Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI (Yoshikiyo YOSHIHARA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of Yoshimichi ISSHIKI and Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI (Yoshikiyo YOSHIHARA).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;He was the&quot;Deleted colon</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of Yoshimichi ISSHIKI and Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI (Yoshikiyo YOSHIHARA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>左京大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakyo-no-daibu (Chief Steward East Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Sakyo-no-daibu (Chief Steward of East Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;He was&quot;, &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>官職の表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>一色氏は応仁の乱において西軍に与したため、守護職を一時隣国の若狭国武田氏に奪われるなど没落し、さらに戦国時代には守護代延永氏の下克上により衰退していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the Isshiki Clan fought with the Western army in the Onin War, their governorship was for a period of time lost to the Takeda clan of neighboring Wakasa Province and, moreover, during the Sengoku (Warring States) Period, power was forcibly taken by the Nobunaga Clan, which led to a decline in fortunes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Isshiki Clan fought with the Western army in the Onin War, their governorship was for a period of time lost to the Takeda Clan of neighboring Wakasa Province and, moreover, during the Sengoku (Warring States) Period, power was forcibly taken by the Shugodai (Deputy Governor) Nobunaga Clan, which led to a decline in fortunes.</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;Shugodai (Deputy Governor)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Isshiki clan fought with the Western army in the Onin War, their position as Shugo was for a period of time lost to the Takeda clan of neighboring Wakasa Province and, moreover, during the Sengoku period, power was forcibly taken by the Shugodai (Deputy Governor) Nobunaga clan, which led to a decline in fortunes.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>先代の当主は一色氏嫡流（一色義貫の末裔）の一色義有（義道の子とは別人）か庶流（義幸の血族か）の一色義清（子の義清とは別人）と思われるが、記録が乏しいため義幸が当主に就任した前後の時代の一色氏の動向ははっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Head clansman within the Isshiki Clan during the previous period was Yoshiari ISSHIKI (different child to that of Yoshimichi) who was of eldest son lineage (descendant of Yoshitsura ISSHIKI) or possibly, the illegitimate (possibly blood relative of Yoshiyuki) Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI (the child Yoshikiyo being a different individual) it is thought. However, because records are scarce, Isshiki Clan movements and, whether or not Yoshiyuki took over the role of head clansman before or after the period are not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the previous head of the clan was either Yoshiari ISSHIKI (not to be confused with Yoshimichi&apos;s son), who as a descendant of Yoshitsura ISSHIKI was of eldest son lineage, or the illegitimate (possibly a blood relative of Yoshiyuki) Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI (not to be confused with Yoshiyuki&apos;s son) but because records are scarce, Isshiki Clan movements around the time Yoshiyuki took over as head clansman are not clear.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence - mistranslation, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the previous head of the clan was either Yoshiari ISSHIKI (not to be confused with Yoshimichi&apos;s son), who as a descendant of Yoshitsura ISSHIKI was of eldest son lineage, or the illegitimate (possibly a blood relative of Yoshiyuki) Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI (not to be confused with Yoshiyuki&apos;s son) but because records are scarce, Isshiki clan movements around the time Yoshiyuki took over as head clansman are not clear.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>若狭国の武田元光と丹後・若狭地方の支配権をめぐってたびたび争ったが、決着はつかず、かえって一色氏の勢力を衰退させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought from time to time with Motomitsu TAKEDA of Wakasa Province for control of the Tango/Wakasa region however, no settlement was reached and on the contrary, it is said that the influence of the Isshiki Clan declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought from time to time with Motomitsu TAKEDA of Wakasa Province for control of the Tango/Wakasa region although no settlement was reached; on the contrary, it is said that the influence of the Isshiki Clan declined.</e>
<cmt>&quot;however,&quot;→&quot;although&quot;&quot; and&quot;→semicolon</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought from time to time with Motomitsu TAKEDA of Wakasa Province for control of the Tango/Wakasa region although no settlement was reached; on the contrary, it is said that the influence of the Isshiki clan declined.</e>
<cmt>clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1558年に隠居し、家督を子の義道に譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retired in 1558 and role of head clansman was inherited by his son Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retired in 1558 and the role of head clansman was inherited by his son, Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;, comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retired in 1558 and the role of head clansman was inherited by his son, Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nalc(id:139567), Cprobot(id:97843), Jmho(id:10472), Dwy(id:13375), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>