<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条高能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayoshi ICHIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayoshi ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayoshi ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一条 高能（いちじょう たかよし、安元2年（1176年） - 建久9年9月17日_(旧暦)（1198年10月19日））は、鎌倉時代初期の公卿・政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayoshi ICHIJO (1176 -October 19, 1198) was a kugyo (top court officials) and politician in early days of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayoshi ICHIJO (1176 -October 19, 1198) was a kugyo (top court official) and politician during early days of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayoshi ICHIJO (1176 - October 26, 1198) was a kugyo (top court official) and politician during early days of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は一条能保、母は源義朝の娘・坊門姫 (一条能保室)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, Bomonhime (the lawful wife of Yoshiyasu ICHIJYO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, Bomonhime (the lawful wife of Yoshiyasu ICHIJYO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, Bomon-hime (the lawful wife of Yoshiyasu ICHIJO).</e>
<cmt>ICHIJO としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>源頼朝は伯父にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his uncle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his uncle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was his uncle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>元暦元年（1184年）に叙爵されると、左馬頭・右兵衛督・蔵人頭などを歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was granted a peerage in 1184, he had successively held Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses), Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was granted peerage in 1184, he had successively held Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses), Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was granted peerage in 1184, he had successively held Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses), Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>一方で鎌倉幕府からは京都守護に任じられて頼朝の娘・大姫 (源頼朝の娘)との縁談が進められた（大姫の拒絶にあい破談）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, he was appointed to the Kyoto shugo (provincial constable) by Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and had an offer of marriage to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s daughter, Ohime (however, the match was broken off by the refusal of Ohime).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, he was appointed to the Kyoto shugo (provincial constable) by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and had an offer of marriage to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s daughter, Ohime (however, the match was refused by Ohime).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, he was appointed to the Kyoto shugo (provincial constable) by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and had an offer of marriage to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s daughter, O-hime (however, the match was refused by O-hime).</e>
<cmt>大姫→O-hime としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後に松殿基房の娘を妻として一条頼氏を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he married a daughter of Motofusa MATSUDONO and had a son, Yoriuji ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he married the daughter of Motofusa MATSUDONO and had a son, Yoriuji ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he married the daughter of Motofusa MATSUDONO and had a son, Yoriuji ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>当時、朝廷の中枢にあった源通親は、政敵である九条兼実や彼と結びつく源頼朝と対立関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, MINAMOTO no Michichika was a key figure in Imperial Court and opposed to Kanezane KUJO and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was connected with Kanezane.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, MINAMOTO no Michichika was a key figure in the Imperial Court and opposed Kanezane KUJO and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who were connected to Kanezane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, MINAMOTO no Michichika was a key figure in the Imperial Court and opposed Kanezane KUJO and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who were connected to Kanezane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、兼実失脚後は頼朝の鎌倉幕府の権威の増大に対してこれと融和して政権維持を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the downfall of Kanezane, he harmonized with Yoritomo&apos;s intention to increase the authority of Kamakura bakufu and aimed to maintain the administrative power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the downfall of Kanezane, he agreed with Yoritomo&apos;s intention to increase the authority of Kamakura bakufu and aimed to maintain the administrative power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the downfall of Kanezane, he agreed with Yoritomo&apos;s intention to increase the authority of Kamakura bakufu and aimed to maintain the administrative power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>高能の急激な昇進の背景には通親が頼朝との連携を期待したものであったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Takayoshi&apos;s fast promotion was made because of Michichika&apos;s anticipation to cooperate with Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Takayoshi&apos;s fast promotion was made because of Michichika&apos;s anticipation to cooperate with Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Takayoshi&apos;s fast promotion was made because of Michichika&apos;s anticipation to cooperate with Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>建久7年（1196年）には参議昇進、翌年には従三位叙位により公卿となるが、その翌年に23歳の若さで病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was promoted to Sangi (councillor) in 1196 and became kugyo (top court officials) with the investiture as Third Rank next year, he died of an illness at age 23 in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was promoted to Sangi (councillor) in 1196 and became kugyo (top court official) with the investiture as Third Rank the next year, he died of an illness at age 23 druing the following year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was promoted to Sangi (councilor) in 1196 and became kugyo (top court official) with the investiture as Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) the next year, he died of an illness at age 23 in the following year.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), ひろくん(id:79638), ちちぶ(id:184715), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>