<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>弘瀬金蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinzo HIROSE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinzo HIROSE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinzo HIROSE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>弘瀬 金蔵（ひろせ きんぞう、文化 (元号)9年10月1日 (旧暦)（1812年11月4日） - 明治9年（1876年）3月8日）は、幕末・明治期の浮世絵師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinzo HIROSE (November 4, 1812 to March 8, 1876) was an ukiyoe artist who lived from the end of the Edo period to the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>文化 (元号)9年10月1日：西暦1812年11月4日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinzo HIROSE (November 4, 1812 - March 8, 1876) was an Ukiyo-e artist who lived from the end of the Edo period to the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>年号をtoで結んでいるところ、ハイフンとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinzo HIROSE (November 4, 1812 - March 8, 1876) was an Ukiyo-e artist who lived from the end of the Edo period to the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>本名は生前、10回以上にわたり改名しているが一般には弘瀬 金蔵の名で知られており、高知県下を中心に絵金（えきん）の愛称で親しまれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his real name was changed 10 or more times in his life, he is generally known as Kinzo HIROSE, and became popular in Kochi Prefecture and nearby areas by the nickname of Ekin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he changed his name more than 10 times throughout his life, he is generally known as Kinzo HIROSE; especially in his hometown Kochi Prefecture and nearby areas, he is affectionately called by his nickname, Ekin.</e>
<cmt>「10 or more times」など直訳的で一般的な英文ではないところがあります。修正しました。原文で「〜いるが〜」となっているためかAlthoughの接続詞で始めていますが、内容はalthoughが用いられるものではないためwhileを用いました。「改名している」と能動態の原文が「was changed」の受動態になり、本人の意思ではないところで改名されたという別の意味が入ってきてしまいますので、能動態に修正しました。改名を繰り返した場合、各名前を本名と言うかどうか疑問です。「real name」は訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he changed his name more than 10 times throughout his life, he is generally known as Kinzo HIROSE; especially in his hometown Kochi Prefecture and nearby areas, he is affectionately called by his nickname, Ekin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>文化9年、高知市に髪結い職人の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as a son of a hairdresser in 1812.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kochi City in 1812 as a son of a hairdresser.</e>
<cmt>「高知市に」という部分が約では欠落しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kochi City in 1812 as a son of a hairdresser.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼少の折から絵の才能で城下の評判となり、16歳で江戸に行き土佐江戸藩邸御用絵師・前村洞和の師事を仰ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had been renowned for his talent for drawing pictures since he was very young, and went to Edo at the age o 16 to study under Towa MAEMURA, who was a goyo eshi (a purveying painter to the government) serving for the edohantei (residence maintained by a daimyo in Edo) of Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was very young, he had been recognized for his talent of drawing in the castle town of Kochi; he went to Edo at the age of 16 to study under Towa MAEMURA, a goyo eshi serving at the Edo hantei of Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「幼少の折り」に絵の才能があったため「renowned」と訳しているようですが、この単語は実力をもって有名になった場合に用いられるのでさすがに幼少時の人物に使うべきではないと思います。単純に「known」を用いました。2. 「城下」の訳が欠落しています。追加しました。3. 前置詞「of」が「o」になっています。また、forが続けて出てきたりするなど、音読推敲すれば見落とさない問題が幾つか見受けられました。（+前置詞用法の間違い）4. 土佐藩を「Tosa Province」と訳しており、定訳ルールに従っていないため訂正しました。(土佐藩の江戸藩邸で勤めていることを考えればProvinceは自然使わないはずです）＊定訳で江戸藩邸を「edohantei」としていますが、これだと「江戸の」「藩邸」という意味に気づかない読者がいるのではないかと思われるため「Edo hantei」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was very young, he had been recognized for his talent of drawing in the castle town of Kochi; he went to Edo at the age of 16 to study under Towa MAEMURA, a goyo eshi serving at the Edo hantei of Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また江戸幕府御用絵師・狩野洞益に師事したともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he also studied under Toeki KANO, who was a goyo eshi of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he also studied under Toeki KANO, who was a goyo eshi of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he also studied under Toeki KANO, who was a goyo eshi of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>通常ならば10年はかかるとされる修行期間を足かけ3年で修了し、林 洞意（はやし とうい）の名を得て高知に帰郷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After completing his apprenticeship, which usually takes 10 years, in three years, he was given the name Toi HAYASHI and returned to Kochi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He completed his apprenticeship in total 3 years, which usually takes at least 10 years; he was given a pseudonym of Toi HAYASHI and returned to Kochi.</e>
<cmt>関係代名詞による文章挿入で文が3つに分かれており、意味のよく通らない文章になっています。文の途中に別文を挿入するのは避けました。内容が異なる複数の分節がある場合、できるだけはっきりと分けるならば分ける、つなげるならつなげるとした方がよいと思います。「;」で分割しました。足かけの意味が欠落していましたのでそれに準ずる意味の「total」を加えました。「名前を得て」については、雅号の意味を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He completed his apprenticeship in total 3 years, which usually takes at least 10 years; he was given a pseudonym of Toi HAYASHI and returned to Kochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>20歳にして土佐藩家老・桐間家の御用絵師となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a goyo eshi of the Kirima family, which was the family of a karo (chief retainer) of the Tosa Domain, at the age of 20.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only at the age of 20, he became a goyo eshi of the Kirima family, which served as a karo (chief retainer) of Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>文の各内容を細切れにつなげたという印象です。音読もしづらいので修正しました。土佐藩の訳においてルール違いを訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only at the age of 20, he became a goyo eshi of the Kirima family, which served as a karo (chief retainer) of Tosa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、狩野探幽の贋作を描いた嫌疑を掛けられたことで職を解かれ高知城下所払いの処分となり、狩野派からは破門を言い渡される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he was dismissed from his position on charge of making a counterfeit painting of Tanyu Kano, banished from the castle town of Kochi-jo Castle, and excommunicated from the Kano school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was dismissed from his position on the suspicion of counterfeiting the work of Tanyu KANO　and expelled from the castle town of Kochi-jo Castle, while Kano school expelled him from its school member list.</e>
<cmt>1. 「嫌疑をかけられた」という原文を「on charge of --」と訳しており、これだと罪を認めた場合の結果を差します。間違いではないでしょうが、実際罪は軽いものだったことを考えると、「嫌疑」と訳したほうがよいと思います。2. 通常「But」で文を始めることはないと思います。「However」を用いました。2. 「所払い」は確かに流刑に近い刑罰のようですが、そこまで厳しいものではなく中心部に住んではいけない程度のようです。「banish」は強すぎると思います。3. 「破門」ですが、excommunicationは宗教的な破門で 用いられます。師匠などから破門される場合は「explusion」を用いるのが一般的です。意味は通りますが、「神との不通」を意味するもので、これを読む外国人が宗教的背景を持つ場合も多いことを考えると修正すべきです。定訳は自動的に追加されている場合もあるため、意味を自分で確認せずそのまま用いるとこうした問題が起こります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was dismissed from his position on the suspicion of counterfeiting the work of Tanyu KANO　and expelled from the castle town of Kochi-jo Castle, while Kano school expelled him from its school member list.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その際、御用絵師として手がけた水墨画の多くが焼却された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, many of his ink-wash paintings painted during his goyo eshi career were incinerated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, many of his ink-wash paintings produced during his goyo eshi career were incinerated.</e>
<cmt>paintingsとpaintedが連続しますので、一つをproducedに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, many of his ink-wash paintings produced during his goyo eshi career were incinerated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>洞意が実際に贋作を描いたかどうか真相は明らかではないが、習作として模写したものが古物商の手に渡り、町人の身分から若くして御用絵師に取り立てられた洞意に対する周囲の嫉妬により濡れ衣を着せられたのではないかと洞意を擁護する意見も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although whether he actually made a counterfeit paintings is unknown, some vindicative opinions state that the copied pictures were etudes acquired by an antique dealer, and that he was framed up by his neighbors who were jealous of the townspeople who became a goyo eshi at a young age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether he actually produced counterfeit or not is unknown, but there are some opinions vindicating Toi that he was framed up by those who were jealous of Toi as he was promoted from a mere townspeople to a goyo eshi at such young age, by abusing Toi&apos;s reproduction for study purpose acquired by some antique dealer.</e>
<cmt>「he was framed up by his neighbors who were jealous of the townspeople who became a goyo eshi at a young age」の部分ですが、関係代名詞の二重使用で意図はわかりますが、訳は成立していません。「Although whether he actually made a counterfeit paintings」の部分ですが、althoughとwhetherの接続詞が連続するのを避けました。できるだけ問題のない部分は残しながら直しましたが、修正というより書き直しに近いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether he actually produced counterfeit or not is unknown, but there are some opinions vindicating Toi that he was framed up by those who were jealous of Toi as he was promoted from a mere townspeople to a goyo eshi at such young age, by abusing Toi&apos;s reproduction for study purpose acquired by some antique dealer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>高知城下を離れて町医者から弘瀬姓を買い取った後の足取りには不明な点が多いが、慶応年間より叔母を頼って赤岡町（現・香南市）に定住し「町絵師・金蔵」を名乗り、地元の農民や漁民に頼まれるがままに芝居絵や台提灯絵、絵馬、凧絵などを数多く描いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of his life after leaving the castle town of Kochi-jo Castle and purchased the family name of Hirose from a town doctor remains unknown, but from the Keio era on, he resorted his aunt and stayed in Akaoka town (present-day Konan City) by the name of &apos;Kinzo, the townpainter,&apos; and painted many shibai-e (pictures of kabuki plays), pictures for standing lanterns, ema (a votive horse tablet), and kites as asked by local peasants and fisherfolk.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remains many unknown points about his life after leaving the castle town of Kochi-jo Castle and changing his name to Hirose by purchasing a name from a town doctor; yet it is known that he resorted his aunt and settled down in Akaoka town (present-day Konan City) from the Keio era, called himself by the name of &apos;Kinzo the painter for townspeople,&apos; and left many paintings in the form of shibai-e (pictures of kabuki plays) or pictures for standing lanterns, ema (a votive horse tablet) or kites, whenever he was asked by local peasants or fishermen.</e>
<cmt>1. 「Most of his life after leaving the castle town of Kochi-jo Castle and purchased the family name of Hirose from a town doctor」について色分けして示しましたが、「after」でくくられた別の２文節における動詞の態が揃っておらず、これにより訳文の意味が分からなくなります。2. 町絵師を「townpainter」漁民を「fishfolk」としていますが、これらはスペルチェックをすれば単語が分離されていないために必ず引っかかるはずです。それとも訳者による造語でしょうか。推敲のみならずさらに基本のスペルチェックもされていないようで、成果物として提出できる段階に達していません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remains many unknown points about his life after leaving the castle town of Kochi-jo Castle and changing his name to Hirose by purchasing a name from a town doctor; yet it is known that he resorted his aunt and settled down in Akaoka town (present-day Konan City) from the Keio era, called himself by the name of &apos;Kinzo the painter for townspeople,&apos; and left many paintings in the form of shibai-e (pictures of kabuki plays) or pictures for standing lanterns, ema (a votive horse tablet) or kites, whenever he was asked by local peasants or fishermen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「絵金」の愛称で親しまれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became popular and gained the nickname of &apos;Ekin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called by a nickname of Ekin among those people with affection.</e>
<cmt>「親しまれた」を「人気が出た」とするのは間違いではありませんが意味が違ってきます。原文に近い意味を持つように訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called by a nickname of Ekin among those people with affection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この時期の猥雑、土俗的で血みどろの芝居絵は特に人気が高く、現在も赤岡では毎年7月に各家が屏風絵を開陳する「土佐赤岡絵金祭り」が開かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bawdy, vulgar and gory shibai-e at the time was especially popular, and today Akaoka holds &apos;Tosa Akaoka Ekin Festival&apos; every July, to exhibit paintings on folding screens owned by each house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jumbling, provincial and gory shibai-e paintings produced during this period were especially popular, and the neighbors of Akaoka still hold the &apos;Tosa Akaoka Ekin Festival&apos; every year in July, to exhibit his paintings owned by each house on folding screens.</e>
<cmt>1. 「猥雑」を「bawdy」とすると「猥褻」に近い意味になります。また「土俗的」も「vulgar」とすると「俗悪」といった意味になり強すぎます。多少意味が違うのではないでしょうか。2. 絵は複数残っているので、「shibai-e」を複数形にできないことから「paintings」を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jumbling, provincial and gory shibai-e paintings produced during this period were especially popular, and the neighbors of Akaoka still hold the &apos;Tosa Akaoka Ekin Festival&apos; every year in July, to exhibit his paintings owned by each house on folding screens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>大政奉還の後は生まれ故郷の高知に戻るが、1873年に中風を患い右手の自由が利かなくなったため左手で絵を描き続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he returned to Kochi, which was his hometown, after Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor), he had paralysis in 1873, losing control of his right hand, but continued painting with his left hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor), he returned to his hometown Kochi, but he lost control of his right hand after he suffered from paralysis in 1873; still, he continued painting with his left hand.</e>
<cmt>語順、フレーズなど含め全体修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor), he returned to his hometown Kochi, but he lost control of his right hand after he suffered from paralysis in 1873; still, he continued painting with his left hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>1876年3月8日死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on March 8, 1876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on March 8, 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on March 8, 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>享年65。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>主な作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「浮世柄比翼稲妻　鈴ヶ森」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Ukiyozuka hiyoku no inazuma Suzugamori&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukiyozuka hiyoku no inazuma Suzugamori&apos; (A scene of Kabuki theater in the same title; &quot;The scene at Suzugamori, with two swordsmen of lightning speed meeting each other for the first time)</e>
<cmt>通常は和製タイトルも英訳していました。訳者は訳していないようですし、訳していないことに対するコメントもありません。本来訳者の作業ですが、一応調べて英語による説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukiyozuka hiyoku no inazuma Suzugamori&apos; (A scene of Kabuki theater in the same title; &quot;The scene at Suzugamori, with two swordsmen of lightning speed meeting each other for the first time)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>- 寄託</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">: Bailed article</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">: The work is entrusted for museum collection at Ekingura Museum.</e>
<cmt>bailは保釈などで一般的に使われます。（寄託の意味もありますが）またこの訳では意味がわかりません。元のwikipediaページでは「絵金蔵寄託」となっていますのでそのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">: The work is entrusted for museum collection at Ekingura Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「図太平記実録代忠臣蔵」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Zu taiheiki jitsurokudai Chushingura&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zu taiheiki jitsurokudai Chushingura&apos; (The scene of Joruri theater, the spoken story of Chushingura)</e>
<cmt>通常は和製タイトルも英訳していました。訳者は訳していないようですし、訳していないことに対するコメントもありません。本来訳者の作業ですが、一応調べて英語による説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zu taiheiki jitsurokudai Chushingura&apos; (The scene of Joruri theater, the spoken story of Chushingura)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>- 高知県立美術館所蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">: Housed in the museum of art, Kochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">: The work is owned and exhibited by the museum of art, Kochi.</e>
<cmt>所蔵の意味に修正しました。文章としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">: The work is owned and exhibited by the museum of art, Kochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Akoyano(id:56905), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Tammyoku(id:256409), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>