<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>円山応挙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okyo MARUYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okyo MARUYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okyo MARUYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>円山 応挙（まるやま おうきょ、享保18年5月1日 (旧暦)（1733年6月12日） - 寛政7年7月17日 (旧暦)（1795年8月31日））は、江戸時代中期の絵師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okyo MARUYAMA, (June 12, 1733 – August 31, 1795; May 1st-August 31 in lunar calender) was a mid Edo period painter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okyo MARUYAMA, (June 12, 1733 – August 31, 1795; May 1st-August 31 in lunar calender) was a mid Edo period painter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okyo MARUYAMA, (June 12, 1733 – August 31, 1795) was a mid Edo period painter.</e>
<cmt>May 1st-August 31 in lunar calenderを削除し、西暦のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近現代の京都画壇にまでその系統が続く円山派の祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the founder of the Maruyama school which continued to the Kyoto art circles in the modern period has his approachable style of painting which attaches great importance to sketching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the founder of the Maruyama school, which continued in the Kyoto art circles up to the modern period. His approachable style of painting attaches great importance to sketching.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the founder of the Maruyama school, which continued in the Kyoto art circles up to the modern period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>写生を重視した親しみやすい画風が特色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His approachable style of painting attaches great importance to sketching.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>姓を丸山と誤表記する例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many examples that his surname is mistakenly written 丸山 instead of 円山.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many examples that his surname is mistakenly written 丸山 instead of 円山.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many examples that his surname is mistakenly written 丸山 instead of 円山.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>享保18年（1733年）、丹波国桑田郡穴太（あのお）村（現・京都府亀岡市）に農家の次男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1733 in Anoo-mura, Kuwata-gun, Tanba-no-kuni (Tanba province) (currently Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) as a farmer&apos;s second son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1733 in Anoo-mura, Kuwata-gun, Tanba-no-kuni (Tanba province) (currently Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) as the second son of a farmer.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1733 in Ano Village, Kuwata District, Tanba Province (currently Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) as the second son of a farmer.</e>
<cmt>丹波国桑田郡穴太村→Ano Village, Kuwata District, Tanba Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>穴太は、西国三十三ヵ所の札所寺院である穴太寺があることで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anoo is known for the Anoo Temple, one of the Saigoku Sanju-san-ka-sho (Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage) temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anoo is known for the Anoo Temple, one of the Saigoku Sanju-san-ka-sho (Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage) temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ano is known for the Anao-ji Temple, one of the Saigoku 33 Kannon Pilgrimage temples.</e>
<cmt>Anoo→Ano、Anoo Temple→Anao-ji Templeに修正 (参照: http://www.y-morimoto.com/saigoku/saigoku21a.html)Saigoku Sanju-san-ka-sho (Kansai Kannon Pilgrimage)→Saigoku 33 Kannon Pilgrimageとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>少年時代のことはあまり詳しくわかっていないが、遅くとも十代の後半には京へ出て、狩野探幽の流れを引く鶴沢派の画家、石田幽汀の門に入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his boyhood is not known well, he went to Kyoto from his late teens and became a disciple of Yutei ISHIDA, a painter of the TSURUSAWA school belonging to Tanyu KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his boyhood is not known well, he went to Kyoto from his late teens and became a disciple of Yutei ISHIDA, a painter of the TSURUSAWA school belonging to Tanyu KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his boyhood is not known well, he went to Kyoto from his late teens and became a disciple of Yutei ISHIDA, a painter of the Tsurusawa school belonging to Tanyu KANO.</e>
<cmt>TSURUSAWA school→Tsurusawa schoolとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>20代の頃にはいわゆる「眼鏡絵」の制作に携わっていたことが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that he was involved in making so-called &quot;megane-e (eyeglass pictures)&quot; in his twenties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that he was involved in making so-called megane-e (eyeglass pictures) in his twenties.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that he was involved in making so-called megane-e (eyeglass pictures) in his twenties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>眼鏡絵とは、風景などを西洋画の線遠近法を応用して描き、これを「覗き眼鏡」という凸レンズを嵌めた箱を通して見ると立体的に見えるというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Megane-e&quot; are pictures that use the western line perspective method to draw landscapes, etc., which appear three-dimensional when looked at through a convex lense called &quot;Nozoki megane&quot; which is put into a box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Megane-e are pictures that use the western line perspective method to draw landscapes, etc., which appear three-dimensional when looked at through a convex lense called Nozoki megane which is placed in a box.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Megane-e are pictures that use the western line perspective method to draw landscapes, etc., which appear three-dimensional when looked at through a convex lense called Nozoki megane which is placed in a box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>明和3年（1766年）から「応挙」を名乗り始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1766 on he called himself &quot;Okyo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1766 onwards he referred to himself Okyo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1766 onwards he referred to himself Okyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「応挙」の意は「銭舜挙（中国宋末 - 元初の画家）に応ずる」ということであり、中国の大家に劣らぬ水準の絵を描こうとする意が込められていると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Okyo&quot; means that he considered himself equal to &quot;Senshunkyo (Qian Xuan)[the end of the Song Dynasty-the first painter in the Yuan Dynasty], and it seems that he intended to draw pictures at the same level as the Chinese virtuoso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okyo means that he considered himself equal to Senshunkyo (Qian Xuan)[the end of the Song Dynasty-the first painter in the Yuan Dynasty], and it seems that he intended to draw pictures at the same level as the Chinese virtuoso.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okyo means that he considered himself equal to Senshunkyo (Qian Xuan) (a painter during the end of the Song Dynasty - the beginning of the Yuan Dynasty), and it seems that he intended to draw pictures at the same level as the Chinese virtuoso.</e>
<cmt>[]→()に変更、&quot;the end of the Song Dynasty-the first painter in the Yuan Dynasty&quot;→&quot;a painter during the end of the Song Dynasty - the beginning of the Yuan Dynasty&quot;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>またこの頃から園城寺円満院の祐常門主の知己を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, since around this time, he gained the friendship of Yujo Monshu of the Onjo-ji Temple Enman-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, since around this time, he gained the friendship of Yujo Monshu of the Onjo-ji Temple Enman-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, since around this time, he gained the friendship of Yujo, the chief priest of the Onjo-ji Temple Enman-in.</e>
<cmt>門主→the chief priestとし、Yujo Monshu→Yujo, the chief priestに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>祐常は公家の二条家から門跡寺院に入って僧となった人物で、『萬誌』（ばんし）という日常雑事を記録した書物を残しているが、その中に応挙の言動が詳細に書き留められており、同時代の貴重な記録となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yujo was from the NIJO family, who were court nobles, and he became a priest and disciple of the Monseki-jiin temple and left a book called &quot;Banshi&quot; which kept a record of quotidian matters, in which Okyo&apos;s speech and behavior is described in detail and is regarded as a valuable record of the same period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yujo was from the NIJO family, who were court nobles. He became a priest and disciple of the Monseki-jiin temple and left a book called Banshi which kept a record of quotidian matters, in which Okyo&apos;s speech and behavior is described in detail and is regarded as a valuable record of the same period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yujo was from the Nijo family of court nobles, and he became a priest and disciple of a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) and left a book called &quot;Banshi&quot; which kept a record of quotidian matters, in which Okyo&apos;s speech and behavior is described in detail and is regarded as a valuable record of the same period.</e>
<cmt>二文→一文になるよう修正、NIJO family→Nijo familyとし、「門跡寺院」の表記を修正、クォーテーションを付け&quot;Banshi&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>この祐常門主や豪商三井家が応挙の主要なパトロンであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Yujo Monshu and the MITSUI family, a business tycoon, were Okyo&apos;s main patrons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Yujo Monshu and the MITSUI family, a business tycoon, were Okyo&apos;s main patrons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This chief priest Yujo and the Mitsui family, a business tycoon, were Okyo&apos;s main patrons.</e>
<cmt>Yujo Monshu→chief priest Yujo、MITSUI family→Mitsui familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>代表作の《七難七福図》、《孔雀牡丹図》などは第二次大戦後まで三井寺円満院に伝来したものであり、《雪松図》は三井家に伝来したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works, &quot;Sichinan-sichifuku-zu&quot; (the Seven Misfortunes and Seven Fortunes) and &quot;Kujaku-botan-zu&quot;etc. had been kept at the Mitsui-dera Temple Enman-in until after the end of the World War Ⅱ, and &quot;Sessho-zu&quot; had been in the possession of the MITSUI family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works, Sichinan-sichifuku-zu (the Seven Misfortunes and Seven Fortunes) and Kujaku-botan-zu etc. had been kept at the Mitsui-dera Temple Enman-in until after the end of the World War II, and Sessho-zu had been in the possession of the MITSUI family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works, Sichinan-sichifuku-zu (the Seven Misfortunes and Seven Fortunes) and Kujaku-botan-zu (Peacocks and Peonies) etc. had been kept at the Mii-dera Temple (Onjo-ji Temple) Enman-in until after the end of the World War II, and Sessho-zu (Pine Tree in Snow) had been in the possession of the Mitsui family.</e>
<cmt>《孔雀牡丹図》《雪松図》の補足を追加、MITSUI family→Mitsui familyとしました。Mitsui-dera→Mii-deraに訂正、「三井寺」＝既出の「園城寺」のため、Mii-dera Temple (Onjo-ji Temple)としました。(参照: http://www.shiga-miidera.or.jp/)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、兵庫・大乗寺、郷里穴太の金剛寺の障壁画群も代表作に数えられよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, a set of pictures on partitions at the Daijo-ji Temple in Hyogo and Kongo-ji Temple in his hometown Anoo can also be counted as one of his representative works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, a set of pictures on partitions at the Daijo-ji Temple in Hyogo and Kongo-ji Temple in his hometown Anoo can also be counted as one of his representative works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, a set of pictures on partitions at the Daijo-ji Temple in Hyogo and Kongo-ji Temple in his hometown Ano can also be counted as one of his representative works.</e>
<cmt>Anoo→Anoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>応挙の画風上の特色として第一に挙げるべきことは近世の日本の画家のなかでも際立って「写生」を重視したことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most prominent feature of Okyo&apos;s painting style is his emphasis on &quot;sketching&quot; especially among early modern Japanese painters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most prominent feature of Okyo&apos;s painting style is his emphasis on sketching especially among early modern Japanese painters.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most prominent feature of Okyo&apos;s painting style is his emphasis on sketching especially among early modern Japanese painters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>前述の祐常著『萬誌』によれば、応挙は常に懐中に写生帖を忍ばせ、暇さえあればスケッチに余念がなかったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Banshi&quot; written by Yujo, as described above, it seems that Okyo always secretly carried his sketchbook with him and devoted every spare moment to sketching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Banshi written by Yujo, as described above, it seems that Okyo always secretly carried his sketchbook with him and devoted every spare moment to sketching.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Banshi&quot; written by Yujo, as described above, it seems that Okyo always secretly carried his sketchbook with him and devoted every spare moment to sketching.</e>
<cmt>Banshiにクォーテーションをつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>現存する『花鳥写生図巻』（個人蔵、重要文化財）や東京国立博物館蔵の《写生帖》などには動物、昆虫、植物などがさまざまな角度から客観的に描写されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Animals, insects and plants are depicted objectively from a variety of different angles in the still existing &quot;Kacho-shasei-zumaki&quot; (Personal Library, Important Cultural Asset) and &quot;Shasei-cho&quot; in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Animals, insects and plants are depicted objectively from a variety of different angles in the still existing Kacho-shasei-zumaki (Personal Library, Important Cultural Asset) and Shasei-cho in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Animals, insects and plants are depicted objectively from a variety of different angles in the still existing &quot;Kacho-shasei-zumaki&quot; (Personal Library, Important Cultural Asset) and Shasei-jo (Album of sketches) in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをつけ&quot;Kacho-shasei-zumaki&quot;とし、Shasei-cho→Shasei-joに修正、補足を追加 (参照:http://www.tnm.go.jp/en/servlet/Con?processId=00&amp;ref=&amp;Q1=&amp;Q2=&amp;Q3=&amp;Q4=&amp;Q5=&amp;F1=&amp;F2=&amp;pageId=E15&amp;colid=A168)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>応挙画は、こうした写生の技術を基礎としつつも、日本絵画の伝統的な画題を扱い、装飾性豊かな画面を創造しているところが特色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feature of Okyo&apos;s painting is having its basis on this sketch tecniques and dealing with the traditional subjects of the Japanese painting and creates a screen rich in decorative features.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okyo&apos;s paintings are based on these sketch techniques and deal with traditional subjects of Japanese painting and creates a screen rich in decorative features.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okyo&apos;s paintings are based on these sketch techniques and deal with traditional subjects of Japanese painting and creates a screen rich in decorative features.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一例として根津美術館蔵の《藤花図》屏風を見ると、藤の幹や枝は輪郭線を用いず、付立て（注）の技法で大胆に描き出す一方で、藤の花房は写実的かつ繊細に描かれ、全体としては琳派を思わせるような装飾性豊かな大画面をつくり出すことに成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking at the folding screen &quot;Toka-zu&quot; in the possession of Nezu Museum as an example, while Okyo does not use any outline for drawing the trunks or branches of a Japanese wisteria and depicts them boldly by using tecniques called Tsuketate (see footnote below), he depicts the wisteria&apos;s flower truss delicately and in a true-to-life way and successfully creates a decorative large screen which includes elements of the Rinpa school as a whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking as an example the folding screen Toka-zu at Nezu Museum--while Okyo does not use any outline for drawing the trunks or branches of a Japanese wisteria and depicts them boldly by using tecniques called Tsuketate (see footnote below), he depicts the wisteria&apos;s flower truss delicately and in a true-to-life way. He also successfully creates a decorative large screen which includes elements of the Rinpa school as a whole.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking as an example the folding screen Fujibana-zu (Wisteria flowers) at Nezu Museum--while Okyo does not use any outline for drawing the trunks or branches of a Japanese wisteria and depicts them boldly by using tecniques called Tsuketate (see footnote below), he depicts the wisteria&apos;s flower truss delicately and in a true-to-life way. He also successfully creates a decorative large screen which includes elements of the Rinpa school as a whole.</e>
<cmt>Toka-zu→Fujibana-zuに修正、補足を追加 (参照: http://www.nezu-muse.or.jp/jp/collection/detail.php?id=10323)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>卓越した画技と平明で親しみやすい画風から、応挙画は三井家をはじめとする富裕な町人層に好まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okyo paintings were popular among the rich townspeople including the Mitsui family due to his great art of drawing and simple and friendly paiting style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okyo paintings were popular among the rich townspeople including the Mitsui family due to his great art of drawing and simple and friendly painting style.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okyo paintings were popular among the rich townspeople including the Mitsui family due to his great art of drawing and simple and friendly painting style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>著名な弟子には呉春や長沢蘆雪、森徹山、源琦などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His famous disciples are Goshun, Rosetsu NAGASAWA, Tetsuzan MORI and Ki GEN and so forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His famous disciples are Goshun, Rosetsu NAGASAWA, Tetsuzan MORI and Ki GEN and so forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His famous disciples are Goshun, Rosetsu NAGASAWA, Tetsuzan MORI and Genki and so forth.</e>
<cmt>Ki GEN→Genkiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>応挙を祖とするこの一派は「円山四条派」と称され、現代にまでその系譜を引く京都画壇の源流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school which had Okyo as its founder was called &quot;MARUYAMA Shijo school&quot;, and has become a source of Kyoto art circles, which are in the lineage of this school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school which had Okyo as its founder was called the MARUYAMA Shijo school, and has become a source of Kyoto art circles, which are in the lineage of this school.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school which had Okyo as its founder was called the Maruyama Shijo school, and has become a source of Kyoto art circles, which are in the lineage of this school.</e>
<cmt>MARUYAMA Shijo school→Maruyama Shijo schoolとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>代表作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>雪松図屏風 （年紀を欠く） 三井記念美術館蔵（国宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessho-zu Byobu (undated) in the possession of the Mitsui Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessho-zu Byobu (undated) in the possession of the Mitsui Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessho-zu Byobu (the folding screen with the painting of the Pine Tree in Snow) (undated) in the possession of the Mitsui Memorial Museum</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、Sessho-zu Byobuの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>七難七福図巻　明和5年（1768） 萬野美術館（2004年閉館）旧蔵（重文）承天閣美術館へ寄贈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shichinan-shichifuku-zukan (1768) in the old stock of the Manno Museum (closed in 2004) (Important Cultural Asset), donated to the Jotenkaku Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichinan-shichifuku-zukan (1768) in the old stock of the Manno Museum (closed in 2004) (Important Cultural Asset), was donated to the Jotenkaku Museum.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichinan-shichifuku-zukan (1768) in the old stock of the Manno Museum (closed in 2004) (Important Cultural Asset), was donated to the Jotenkaku Museum</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>孔雀牡丹図　明和8年（1771） 萬野美術館旧蔵（重文）承天閣美術館へ寄贈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujyaku-Botan-zu (1771) in the old storage of the Manno Museum (important cultural asset) donated to the Jotenkaku Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujyaku-Botan-zu (1771) in the old storage of the Manno Museum (important cultural asset) was donated to the Jotenkaku Museum.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujaku-botan-zu (1771) in the old storage of the Manno Museum (important cultural asset) was donated to the Jotenkaku Museum</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、Kujyaku-Botan-zu→Kujaku-botan-zuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>雲龍図屏風 安永2年（1773） 岐阜・法人蔵（重文）東寺観智院伝来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unryu-zu Byobu (1773) Gifu, in the possession of a company (Important Cultural Asset), from the To-ji Temple, Kanchi-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unryu-zu Byobu (1773) Gifu, in the possession of a company (Important Cultural Asset), from the To-ji Temple, Kanchi-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unryu-zu Byobu (the folding screen with the painting of Dragon in Clouds) (1773) Gifu Prefecture, in the possession of a company (Important Cultural Asset), from the To-ji Temple, Kanchi-in</e>
<cmt>スペース、ピリオド削除、Unryu-zu Byobuの補足を追加、Gifu Prefectureとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>藤花図屏風　安永5年（1776） 根津美術館蔵（重文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toka-zu Byobu (1776) in the possession of the Nezu Art Museum (Important Cultural Asset)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toka-zu Byobu (1776) in the possession of the Nezu Art Museum (Important Cultural Asset).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujibana-zu Byobu (the folding screen with the painting of Wisteria flowers) (1776) in the possession of the Nezu Art Museum (Important Cultural Asset)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、Fujibana-zu Byobuとし、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>雨竹風竹図屏風　安永5年（1776） 京都・円光院蔵（重文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uchiku-Fuchiku-zu (1776) in the possession of the Enkoji Temple (Important Cultural Asset)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uchiku-Fuchiku-zu (1776) in the possession of the Enkoji Temple (Important Cultural Asset).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uchiku-Fuchiku-zu Byobu (the folding screens with the paintings of rainy-weather bamboo and windy-weather bamboo) (1776) in the possession of the Enko-ji Temple, Kyoto Prefecture (Important Cultural Asset)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、Uchiku-Fuchiku-zu Byobuとし、補足を追加 (参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=cyJylfoYF28C&amp;pg=RA2-PA53&amp;dq=uchiku+fuchiku&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=uchiku%20fuchiku&amp;f=false)「京都」を訳出、Enko-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大乗寺障壁画（165面） 天明7年（1787）および寛政7年（1795） 兵庫・大乗寺 (香美町)蔵（重文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pictures on partitions at the Daijyoji temple (165 murals) in 1787 and 1795 in the possession of the Daijyoji temple in Kamo-cho, Hyogo (Important Cultural Asset)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pictures on the partitions at the Daijyoji temple (165 murals) in 1787 and 1795 is in the possession of the Daijyoji temple in Kamo-cho, Hyogo (Important Cultural Asset).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Pictures on the Partitions at the Daijo-ji Temple (165 murals) in 1787 and 1795 is in the possession of the Daijo-ji Temple in Kami-cho, Hyogo Prefecture (Important Cultural Asset)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、頭文字を大文字に変更、Daijyoji temple→Daijo-ji Temple、Kamo-cho, Hyogo→Kami-cho, Hyogo Prefectureに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>金剛寺障壁画　天明8年（1788） 京都・金剛寺蔵（重文）東京国立博物館に寄託中。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pictures on partitions at the Kongoji temple in 1788 in the possession of the Kongoji temple, Kyoto (Important Cultural Asset) which have been entrusted to the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pictures on partitions at the Kongoji temple in 1788 are in the possession of the Kongoji temple, Kyoto (Important Cultural Asset) which have been entrusted to the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Pictures on Partitions at the Kongo-ji Temple in 1788 are in the possession of the Kongo-ji Temple, Kyoto Prefecture (Important Cultural Asset) which have been entrusted to the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更、Kongoji temple→Kongo-ji Templeに修正、Kyoto Prefectureとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>金刀比羅宮障壁画 天明7年（1787）および寛政6年（1794） 金刀比羅宮蔵（重文）三井家の注文で描いたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pictures on partitions at the Kotohira-gu Shrine (1787 and 1794) in the possession of the Kotohira-gu Shrine depicted on order of the Mitsui family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pictures on partitions at the Kotohira-gu Shrine (1787 and 1794) are in the possession of the Kotohira-gu Shrine depicted on order of the Mitsui family.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Pictures on Partitions at the Kotohira-gu Shrine (1787 and 1794) are in the possession of the Kotohira-gu Shrine depicted on order of the Mitsui family.</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>床（とこ）貼付絵の『瀑布図』が有名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bakufu-zu&quot;, a painting on paper is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakufu-zu, a painting on paper, has gained fame.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bakufu-zu,&quot; a painting on paper, has gained fame</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ、クォーテーション追加、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>保津川図屏風 寛政7年（1795） 個人蔵（重文）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hozugawa-zu Byobu in 1795 in the possession of an individual (important cultural asset)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hozugawa-zu Byobu in 1795 is in the possession of an individual (important cultural asset).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hozugawa-zu Byobu (the folding screen with the painting of Hozu-gawa River) in 1795 is in the possession of an individual (important cultural asset)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、Hozugawa-zu Byobuの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Reggaeman(id:6214), MIsogi(id:20599), Cprobot(id:97843), 9PgUp(id:24726), Urania(id:7213), LiDaobing(id:14511), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), Masyu(id:31065), Miya(id:1881), 663highland(id:18755), パーキングスパンク(id:172868), Yas(id:739), Okyo(id:190765), Akimoto(id:6951), Khaosan Lover(id:161770), Nopira(id:29335), Saaki(id:43602), Bsx(id:38434), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>