<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>牛原虚彦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyohiko USHIHARA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyohiko USHIHARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyohiko USHIHARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>牛原虚彦（うしはら きよひこ、本名・清彦、1897年3月22日 - 1985年5月20日）は、大正・昭和期の映画監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyohiko USHIHARA (March 22, 1897 ~ May 20, 1985) is a movie director from Taisho to Showa era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyohiko USHIHARA (March 22, 1897 ~ May 20, 1985) was a movie director from the Taisho to the Showa era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyohiko USHIHARA (March 22, 1897 - May 20, 1985) was a movie director from the Taisho to the Showa era.</e>
<cmt>~→- 他ファイルと合わせる</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>熊本県熊本市に生まれ、1920年、東京帝国大学（現・東京大学）文学部英文学科を卒業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kumamoto City, Kumamoto Prefecture, and graduated Faculty of Letters, Dept. of English and American Literature, Tokyo Imperial University (today&apos;s University of Tokyo) in 1920.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kumamoto City, Kumamoto Prefecture, and graduated Faculty of Letters, Dept. of English and American Literature, Tokyo Imperial University (today&apos;s University of Tokyo) in 1920.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kumamoto City, Kumamoto Prefecture, and graduated from the Tokyo Imperial University (now University of Tokyo) Faculty of Letters Department of English Literature in 1920.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>小山内薫の紹介で松竹蒲田撮影所に入社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Shochiku Kamata Studio with an introduction of Kaoru OSANAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Shochiku Kamata Studio with an introduction from Kaoru OSANAI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered Shochiku Kamata Studios through the introduction of Kaoru OSANAI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>新派劇出身の賀古残夢監督の助手を務めた後、1920年、小山内が松竹キネマ研究所を創立すると、そこへ移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he worked as an assistant of director Zanmu KAKO who came from Shinpa-Geki (a New-School Play), he moved to Shochiku Cinema Laboratory when Osanai established it in 1920.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he worked as an assistant of director Zanmu KAKO who came from Shinpa-Geki (a New-School Play), he moved to Shochiku Cinema Laboratory established by Osanai in 1920.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After working as an assistant to director Zanmu KAKO who came from shinpa-geki (New-School Play), he moved to the Shochiku Kinema Kenkyu-jo production company after it was established by Osanai in 1920.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>第1回作品『路上の霊魂』の脚本を書き、出演もこなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ushihara wrote the playbook of the Laboratory&apos;s first film &quot;Rojo no Reikon (Souls on The Road)&quot; and also played a role in it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ushihara wrote the playbook of the Laboratory&apos;s first film &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) and also played a role in it.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ushihara wrote the screenplay for the company&apos;s first film &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on the Road) and also played a role as an actor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>2作目の『山暮るる』で監督デビュー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He debuted as a director in the 2nd Laboratory&apos;s film &quot;Yamakururu (literally, sunset in the mountain).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He debuted as a director in the 2nd Laboratory&apos;s film &quot;Yamakururu&quot; (literally, sunset in the mountain).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He debuted as a director in the company&apos;s second film &quot;Yama Kururu&quot; (The Mountains Grow Dark).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>研究所解散後は、蒲田撮影所の監督となり、井上正夫主演の『噫無情』などを撮る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the dismissal of the laboratory, he became a director of Shochiku Kamata Studio and directed &quot;A Mujo&quot; in which Masao INOUE played a leading role, etc.</e>
<cmt>「噫無情」の内容が分からない為、意訳もできません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the dismissal from the laboratory, he became a director at Shochiku Kamata Studio and directed &quot;A Mujo&quot; in which Masao INOUE played a leading role, etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the dissolution of the company he became a director at Shochiku Kamata Studios and shot pictures including &quot;Aa Mujo&quot; (Les Miserables) starring Masao INOUE.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Shimazuをheに変え、補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1926年、ハリウッドへ渡り、チャーリー・チャップリンの『サーカス (映画)』の撮影隊の助手として研鑽を積む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1926, he went to Hollywood and practiced as an assistant of camera crews of a Charles Chaplin&apos;s film &quot;Circus.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1926, he went to Hollywood and practiced as an assistant to the camera crews of a Charles Chaplin film &quot;Circus.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1926, he went to Hollywood and worked as an assistant to the film unit on Charlie Chaplin&apos;s &quot;The Circus.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>帰国後、1926年のメロドラマ『受難華』をヒットさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he returned to Japan, he made a success in a soap opera &quot;Junanbana (Suffering Women).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he returned to Japan, he made a success in a soap opera &quot;Junanbana&quot; (Suffering Women).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to Japan, he had a success with the melodrama &quot;Junanbana&quot; (Suffering Women) in 1926.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1928年から1929年には鈴木傳明を主役に明朗快活な青年像を描いた作品を発表し、青春映画の原型を形作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1928 to 1929, he released movies, in which Denmei SUZUKI played leading roles, and depicted a cheerful and pleasant personality of youngman, and formed an archetype of so-called youth movie.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1928 to 1929, he released movies, in which Denmei SUZUKI played leading roles, and depicted the cheerful and pleasant personality of youngman, and formed an archetype of the so-called youth movie.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between 1928 and 1929, he released films portraying cheerful young people starring Denmei SUZUKI and created the forerunner of the teen movie.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>1930年、トーキー技術研究のため、2年間、欧米に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And 2 years from 1930, he visited Europe and the United States to research the talking picture technologies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And 2 years from 1930, he visited Europe and the United States to research talking picture technologies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1930, he spent two years in Europe and the United states researching talking picture technology.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>帰国後、1933年日活太秦撮影所に移り、さらに1934年、新興キネマ京都撮影所に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he returned to Japan, he moved to Nikkatsu Uzumasa movie studio in 1933, and further moved to New cinema Kyoto studio in 1934.</e>
<cmt>「新興キネマ京都撮影所」は仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he returned to Japan, he moved to Nikkatsu Uzumasa movie studio in 1933, and further moved to New cinema Kyoto studio in 1934.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to Japan, he moved to Nikkatsu Uzumasa Studios in 1933 before moving to Shinkyo Kinema Kyoto Studio in 1934.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Shimazuをheにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『南風薩摩歌』（1937年）などを発表するが、サイレント時代のような清新さは見られなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He released &quot;Hae Satsumauta,&quot; (1937) etc. however, the freshness at the time of silent movies was lost.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Hae Satsumauta,&quot;は仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He released &quot;Hae Satsumauta,&quot; (1937) etc. however, the freshness at the time of silent movies was lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He released a number of films including &quot;Nanpu Satsuma Uta&quot; (literally, South Satsuma Songs, 1937) but these did not have the freshness of the pictures he made during the silent era.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Shimazuをheにしました。用語読みを修正、年号など補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1949年、特撮映画の先駆けともいえる作品『虹男』を最後に、新興キネマの統合によって移っていた角川映画を退社する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1949, he released his last film &quot;Nijiotoko (literally, Rainbow man)&quot; which can be said a pioneer of special effects movies and quit Kadokawa Pictures Inc. where he moved from New cinema when New cinema was unified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1949, he released his last film &quot;Nijiotoko&quot; (literally, Rainbow man) which can be said to be a pioneer in special effects movies and quit Kadokawa Pictures Inc. where he moved from New cinema when New cinema was unified.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1949, he released his last film &quot;Nijiotoko&quot; (literally, Rainbow man) which can be said to be a pioneer in special effects movies and quit Kadokawa Pictures Inc. where he moved from New cinema when New cinema was unified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>1950年、日本大学芸術学部映画学科客員教授になり、1956年から同学科主任教授。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1950, he became an affiliate professor of Department of Cinema, College of Art, Nihon University, and a senior professor of the same Dept. from 1956.</e>
<cmt>「主任教授」に該当する訳語が分かりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1950, he became an affiliate professor of Department of Cinema, College of Art, Nihon University, and a senior professor of the same Dept. from 1956.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1950, he became a visiting professor at the Nihon University, College of Art Department of Cinema, and served as head of the same department from 1956.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。カンマを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1975年からは日活芸術学院院長を務めるなど一貫して後進の指導にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked as the head of Nikkatsu Visual Arts Academy from 1975 and consistently led the descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked as the head of Nikkatsu Visual Arts Academy from 1975 and consistently led the descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked tirelessly to guide his successors, serving as head of the Nikkatsu Visual Arts Academy from 1975.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Shimazuをheにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>映画監督牛原陽一は実子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A film director Yoichi USHIHARA is his real son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The film director Yoichi USHIHARA is his real son.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The film director Yoichi USHIHARA was his biological son.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。また故人のため過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Umzk555(id:33692), 雲南(id:61460), Mait(id:73947), Goki(id:7107), Bankokuya(id:91191), 松木完之(id:26818), Dream100(id:41924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>