<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>橘公頼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kimiyori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Kimiyori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kimiyori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>橘公頼（たちばなの きみより、元慶元年（877年） - 天慶4年2月20日 (旧暦)（941年3月25日））は、平安時代の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kimiyori (877-March 25, 941) was the aristocrat of the Heian era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Kimiyori (877-March 25, 941) was an aristocrat of the Heian Era.</e>
<cmt>article, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kimiyori (877 - March 25, 941) was a noble who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>貴族→noble、平安時代→Heian period　を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>従三位、中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His titles were Jusanmi rank (Junior Third Rank) and Chunagon (provisional middle councillor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His titles were Jusanmi rank (Junior Third Rank) and Chunagon (provisional middle councillor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His titles were Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>中納言→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>京職、近衛府、大宰権帥。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also held the titles of Kyoshiki (Kyoto government official), Konoe fu (the Imperial Guard Division), and Dazai gonno sochi (the governor-general).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also held the titles of Kyoshiki (Kyoto government official), Konoe fu (Imperial Guard Division), and Dazai gonno sochi (governor-general).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also held the titles of Kyoshiki (Kyoto government official), Konoe fu (Imperial Guard Division), and Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices).</e>
<cmt>大宰権帥→Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に橘敏実・橘敏仲・橘敏通・橘敏貞・橘敏延がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons were TACHIBANA no Toshizane, TACHIBANA no Toshinaka, TACHIBANA no Toshimichi, TACHIBANA no Toshisada, and TACHIBANA no Toshinobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons were TACHIBANA no Toshizane, TACHIBANA no Toshinaka, TACHIBANA no Toshimichi, TACHIBANA no Toshisada, and TACHIBANA no Toshinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons were TACHIBANA no Toshizane, TACHIBANA no Toshinaka, TACHIBANA no Toshimichi, TACHIBANA no Toshisada, and TACHIBANA no Toshinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>贈中納言橘広相の子であり、橘諸兄の6代後。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of TACHIBANA no Hiromi, who held the title of Zon Chunagon (Middle Councillor rank, given posthumously) and was the sixth generation since TACHIBANA no Moroe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimiyori was the son of TACHIBANA no Hiromi, who held the title of Zon Chunagon (Middle Councillor rank, given posthumously) and was a sixth generation descendant of TACHIBANA no Moroe.</e>
<cmt>mentioned name, wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimiyori was the son of TACHIBANA no Hiromi, who held the title of Zon Chunagon (vice-councilor of state, given posthumously) and was a sixth generation descendant of TACHIBANA no Moroe.</e>
<cmt>中納言→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は馬寮橘惟風女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Meryo, the daughter of TACHIBANA no Korekaze.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Meryo, the daughter of TACHIBANA no Korekaze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of TACHIBANA no Korekaze, who seved in Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寛平8年（896年）六位蔵人になり、昌泰2年（899年）叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Rokui no Kurodo (secretary for the emperor) in 896 and Joshaku (conferred a peerage) in 899.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Rokui no Kurodo (secretary for the emperor) in 896 and was conferred Joshaku (a peerage) in 899.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) in 896 and was conferred Joshaku (a peerage) in 899.</e>
<cmt>六位蔵人→Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>延喜19年（919年）従四位下に叙され、以後、近江国権守・伊予国権守・右京大夫・左中将・播磨国権守・備前国権守などを歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the jo (court rank) of Jushi no ge rank (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and since then, he played his role as Omi no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of the Omi Province), Iyo no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of the Iyo Province), Ukyo no daibu (chief of Ukyoshiki government agency), Sachujo (lieutenant general of left division), Harima no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of the Harima Province), and Bizen no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of the Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the jo (court rank) of Jushi no ge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and after that, he fulfilled the positions of Omi no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of Omi Province), Iyo no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of Iyo Province), Ukyo no daibu (chief of Ukyoshiki government agency), Sachujo (lieutenant general of left division), Harima no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of Harima Province), and Bizen no kuni Gon no kami (Lord of Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt>articles, wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 919 and after that, he fulfilled the positions of Omi no kuni Gon no kami (Governor of Omi Province), Iyo no kuni Gon no kami (Governor of Iyo Province), Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices), Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Harima no kuni Gon no kami (Governor of Harima Province), and Bizen no kuni Gon no kami (Governor of Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt>役職名の表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延長 (元号)3年（925年）従四位上に昇叙され、同5年に参議になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went through Shojo (promotion in Jo rank) to Jushi no jo rank (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 925 and became a Sangi (consultant) in 928.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimiyori received Shojo (promotion in Jo rank) to Jushi no jo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 925, and became a Sangi (consultant) in 928.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimiyori was promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 925, and became a Sangi (consultant) in 928.</e>
<cmt>was promoted to としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>承平 (日本)2年（932年）正四位下に昇叙され、同5年大宰権帥、同6年従三位になり、天慶2年（939年）大宰権帥のまま中納言に任ぜられ、天慶4年2月20日大宰府で薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His titles shifted from Shojo to Shoshi no ge rank (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 932, Dazai gonno sochi in 935, Jusanmi rank (Junior Third Rank) in 936, and became Chunagon while being Dazai gonno sochi in 939 before passing way on March 25, 941 in Dazai-fu (the governmental office with the jurisdiction of Kyushu, Iki, and Tsushima).</e>
<cmt>大宰府→dazai-fu (the governmental office with jurisdiction of Kyushu, Iki, and Tsushima)[http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=dazaifu%20(under%20the%20ritsuryo%20system,%20governmental%20office%20with%20jurisdiction%20over%20Kyushu,%20Iki%20and%20Tsushima)]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His titles shifted from Shojo to Shoshi no ge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 932, Dazai gonno sochi in 935, and Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 936, and he became Chunagon while serving as Dazai gonno sochi in 939 before passing way on March 25, 941 in Dazai-fu (the governmental office with the jurisdiction of Kyushu, Iki, and Tsushima).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His titles shifted from Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 932, Dazai gonno sochi in 935, and Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 936, and he became Chunagon while serving as Dazai gonno sochi in 939 before passing away on March 25, 941 in Dazai-fu (the governmental office with the jurisdiction of Kyushu, Iki, and Tsushima).</e>
<cmt>役職名の表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>享年65歳だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『後撰和歌集』（歌番号637）と『新勅撰和歌集』（歌番号1282）に1首ずつ入集する歌人でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Kajin poet who had his poem collected in &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Poem Number 637) and &quot;Chokusen Wakashu&quot; (Poem Number 1282).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Kajin poet, and his poems were collected in &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Poem Number 637) and &quot;Chokusen Wakashu&quot; (Poem Number 1282).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Kajin poet, and his poems were collected in &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later selected collection of Japanese poetry) (Poem Number 637) and &quot;Shin chokusen wakashu&quot; (A new anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) (Poem Number 1282).</e>
<cmt>歌集の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>藤原純友の乱の時、大宰府を落として柳川に迫った純友の弟の藤原純乗の軍勢を、蒲池城で迎え撃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He counter attacked at Kamachi Castle against the army of FUJIWARA no Suminori, the younger brother of Sumimoto, who destroyed Dazai-fu and invaded Yanagawa during FUJIWARA no Sumimoto no ran (Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Sumimoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimiyori counterattacked at Kamachi Castle against the army of FUJIWARA no Suminori, the younger brother of Sumimoto, who destroyed Dazai-fu and invaded Yanagawa during FUJIWARA no Sumimoto no ran (Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Sumimoto).</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimiyori counterattacked at Kamachi-jo Castle against the army of FUJIWARA no Suminori, the younger brother of Sumimoto, who destroyed Dazai-fu and invaded Yanagawa during Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Sumitomo.</e>
<cmt>Kamachi-jo Castle　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その功により橘公頼の子孫は、筑後国蒲池の領主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this deed, the descendants of TACHIBANA no Kimiyori became the lord of Kamachi, Chikugo no kuni (Chikugo Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this deed, the descendants of TACHIBANA no Kimiyori received the heriditary title of Lord of Kamachi, Chikugo no kuni (Chikugo Province).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this deed, the descendants of TACHIBANA no Kimiyori received the hereditary title of Lord of Kamachi, Chikugo Province.</e>
<cmt>Chikugo Province　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>福岡県柳川市に伝わる伝承では、蒲池城は藤原純乗が築き、橘公頼は柳川城を築いて対抗したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a tale told in Yanagawa City, Fukuoka Prefecture, Kamachi Castle was built by FUJIWARA no Suminori and TACHIBANA no Kimiyori resisted it by building Yanagawa Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a legend told in Yanagawa City, Fukuoka Prefecture, Kamachi Castle was built by FUJIWARA no Suminori, and TACHIBANA no Kimiyori resisted it by building Yanagawa Castle.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend told in Yanagawa City, Fukuoka Prefecture, Kamachi-jo Castle was built by FUJIWARA no Suminori, and TACHIBANA no Kimiyori resisted it by building Yanagawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Kamachi-jo Castle, Yanagawa-jo Castle　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そこから蒲池城に拠る蒲池の領主は藤原純乗の一族と伝えられているが、当時は柳川城はまだなく、橘公頼が子の橘敏通と共に藤原純乗を迎え撃ったのは蒲池城である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was told that the lord of Kamachi in Kamachi Castle was the family of FUJIWARA no Suminori, but there was no Yanagawa Castle present at that time, and it was Kamachi Castle that TACHIBANA no Kimiyori and his son TACHIBANA no Toshimichi made a counter attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was told that the lord of Kamachi in Kamachi Castle was from the family of FUJIWARA no Suminori, but Yanagawa Castle did not exist at that time, and it was at Kamachi Castle that TACHIBANA no Kimiyori and his son TACHIBANA no Toshimichi made a counterattack.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was told that the lord of Kamachi in Kamachi-jo Castle was from the family of FUJIWARA no Suminori, but Yanagawa-jo Castle did not exist at that time, and it was at Kamachi-jo Castle that TACHIBANA no Kimiyori and his son TACHIBANA no Toshimichi made a counterattack.</e>
<cmt>Kamachi-jo Castle, Yanagawa-jo Castle　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また近隣一帯は、田尻氏など純友追討に功のあった大蔵春実の子孫が土着しており、藤原純友一族の子孫が勢力を持ったとは見なしがたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were the Tajiri clan, native to the surrounding area, who were the descendants of Haruzane OKURA, who showed fine performances during the subjugation of Sumitomo, and it seems unlikely that the descendants of the family of FUJIWARA no Sumimoto controlled the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tajiri clan, native to the surrounding area, who were the descendants of Haruzane OKURA, showed fine performances during the subjugation of Sumitomo, and it seems unlikely that the descendants of the family of FUJIWARA no Sumimoto controlled the area.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tajiri clan, native to the surrounding area, who were the descendants of Haruzane OKURA, showed fine performances during the subjugation of Sumitomo, and it seems unlikely that the descendants of the family of FUJIWARA no Sumitomo controlled the area.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>蒲池の領主もまた藤原純友追討に功のあった橘公頼の子孫であり、鎌倉時代に嵯峨源氏の源久直が蒲池の地頭職になって赴任し、橘公頼の子孫の筑後の橘氏の娘婿となり、その勢力を背景にして蒲池氏を名のる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of Kamachi estate was the descendant of TACHIBANA no Kiyomori, who showed fine performances during the subjugation of FUJIWARA no Sumimoto, and MINAMOTO no Hisanao of Saga-Genji (the Saga-Minamoto clan) became the Jitoshiki (steward) of Kamachi in Kamakura era and left for the new post, and became the husband to the daughter of the Tachibana clan, the descendants of TACHIBANA no Kiyomori, and named themselves as the Kamachi clan with power in hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of Kamachi estate, a descendant of TACHIBANA no Kiyomori, showed fine performance during the subjugation of FUJIWARA no Sumimoto; MINAMOTO no Hisanao of Saga-Genji (the Saga-Minamoto clan) became the Jitoshiki (steward) of Kamachi in the Kamakura Era and when leaving for this new post, married the daughter of the Tachibana clan, a descendant of TACHIBANA no Kiyomori; their family named themselves the Kamachi clan and wielded power.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of Kamachi area was also a descendant of TACHIBANA no Kiyomori, who showed fine performance during the subjugation of FUJIWARA no Sumitomo; when MINAMOTO no Hisanao of Saga-Genji (Minamoto clan) became the Jitoshiki (steward) of Kamachi in the Kamakura period, he married the daughter of the Tachibana clan of the Chikugo Province, a descendant of TACHIBANA no Kiyomori; their family named themselves the Kamachi clan and wielded power.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 亜麻(id:64477), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 代言人(id:33675), Auf(id:633), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 味っ子(id:17086), YOSHI438(id:174755), Junger(id:10282), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>