<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>渡辺了</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satoru Watanabe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satoru WATANABE</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satoru WATANABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>渡辺 了（わたなべ さとる、永禄5年（1562年） - 寛永17年（1640年））は安土桃山時代から江戸時代の武士である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satoru WATANABE (1562-1640) was a samurai warrior during Azuchi-Momoyama period to Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satoru WATANABE (1562-1640) was a samurai warrior during Azuchi-Momoyama period to Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satoru WATANABE (1562-1640) was a samurai warrior during Azuchi-Momoyama period to Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称は勘兵衛（かんべえ）で、「渡辺勘兵衛」の名で有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Kanbei but more well known by the name Kanbei WATANABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Kanbe but he was more well known by the name Kanbe WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>Kanbei → Kanbe に訂正しました。 more well known の前に主語がなかったので、he was を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Kanbe but he was more well known by the name Kanbe WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名は初め「吉光」と伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was handed down as &quot;Yoshimitsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his original name was Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>誤訳でしたので、訂正して訳しなおしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his original name was Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>近江国浅井郡の土豪、渡辺右京の子として生まれ、同族の渡辺任の養子となったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born to the local ruling family in Asai-gun, Omi Province of Ukyo WATANABE was said to be adopted to Nin WATANABE of the same clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born to Ukyo WATANABE who was a member of the local ruling family in Asai-gun, Omi Province, and is said to have been adopted by Tamotsu WATANABE of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>born と to の間の空白を半角分削除しました。 文の構成が正しくありませんでしたので、大幅に訂正しました。 to be adopted → to have been adopted に時制を訂正しました。 adopted to → adopted by に訂正しました。 「渡辺任」の読みは「わたなべたもつ」で、「わたなべにん」ではないので訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born to Ukyo WATANABE who was a member of the local ruling family in Asai-gun, Omi Province, and is said to have been adopted by Tamotsu WATANABE of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に渡辺宗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a child named So WATANABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a child named So WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a child named So WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>睡庵（水庵）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suian</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suian</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suian</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>初め浅井氏麾下の将阿閉貞征家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, he was a vassal to Sadayuki ATSUJI who was under the general&apos;s command of Asai clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, he was a vassal to Sadayuki ATSUJI who was under the general&apos;s command of Asai clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, he was a vassal to Sadayuki ATSUJI who was under the general&apos;s command of Asai clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>貞征の娘を妻としてもらい受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He married to the daughter of Sadayuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married to a daughter of Sadayuki.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married to a daughter of Sadayuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>のちに「槍の勘兵衛」と称されるように槍の名手であり、摂津吹田城攻めで一番首を挙げ、織田信長から直接称賛されたほどだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was known later as &quot;spearman Kanbei&quot;, he was a master spearman and was the first to get an enemy head during the attack on Settsu Suita-jo Castle and praised by Nobunaga ODA firsthand and he was one of the elite body guard unit members of ATSUJI clan however he later resigned from the position and began serving to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI around 1582 and he was assigned to Hideyoshi&apos;s adopted son Hidekatsu HASHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was known later as &quot;spearman Kanbe,&quot; he was a master spearman and was the first to get an enemy head during the attack on Settsu Suita-jo Castle and was praised by Nobunaga ODA firsthand.</e>
<cmt>非常に一文が長く、分かりづらいので分割しました。　一原文一訳文の例外対処　Kanbei → Kanbe に訂正しました。また、その直後のコンマをクオーテーションの中に納めました。　　　praised の前にwas を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was known later as &quot;spearman Kanbe,&quot; he was a master spearman and was the first to get an enemy head during the attack on Settsu Suita-jo Castle and was praised by Nobunaga ODA firsthand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>阿閉家の精鋭であった母衣衆の一人であったが、後に辞して天正10年（1582年）ごろより豊臣秀吉に仕え、2,000石の扶持をもって、秀吉の養子である羽柴秀勝付きとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the elite body guard unit members of ATSUJI clan, however, he later resigned from the position to serve Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI around 1582 and he was assigned to escort Hideyoshi&apos;s adopted son Hidekatsu HASHIBA with 2,000 koku (360.78 cubic meters) of fuchi (stipend).</e>
<cmt>however の前後にコンマを入れました。　　「付き」のニュアンスを入れるため、to の後にescort を加えました。 And で結ぶ並列を減らすために、and began serving → to serve に変更しました。さらにその後のto は不必要なので削除しました。　　訳漏れ：「2,000石の扶持をもって」の部分が訳されていませんでしたので、訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the elite body guard unit members of ATSUJI clan, however, he later resigned from the position to serve Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI around 1582 and he was assigned to escort Hideyoshi&apos;s adopted son Hidekatsu HASHIBA with 2,000 koku (360.78 cubic meters) of fuchi (stipend).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>山崎の戦いや賤ヶ岳の戦いでも活躍し、石田三成家臣の杉江勘兵衛、田中吉政家臣の辻勘兵衛と並んで「三勘兵衛」と評されたものの、天正13年（1585年）に秀勝が没してしまうと、それに伴い浪人する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made the big impact during the Battle of Yamazaki and the Battle of Shizugatake and he was called &quot;Sankanbei&quot; along with Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s vassal Kanbei Sugie and Yoshimasa TANAKA&apos;s vassal Kanbei TSUJI however he became unemployed when Hidekatsu died in 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made the big impact during the Battle of Yamazaki and the Battle of Shizugatake and he was called &quot;Sankanbe&quot; along with Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s vassal Kanbe Sugie and Yoshimasa TANAKA&apos;s vassal Kanbe TSUJI, however, he became unemployed when Hidekatsu died in 1585.</e>
<cmt>kanbei → kanbe に訂正しました。 however の前後にコンマを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made the big impact during the Battle of Yamazaki and the Battle of Shizugatake and he was called &quot;Sankanbe&quot; along with Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s vassal Kanbe Sugie and Yoshimasa TANAKA&apos;s vassal Kanbe TSUJI, however, he became unemployed when Hidekatsu died in 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>次に中村一氏に3,000石で仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Kazuuji NAKAMURA next for 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Kazuuji NAKAMURA next for 3,000 koku (541.17 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>3000石の注釈を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Kazuuji NAKAMURA next for 3,000 koku (541.17 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>小田原の役において中村勢の先鋒として働き、伊豆山中城攻めにおいて一番乗りを果たす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Odawara conflict, he spearheaded the Nakamura troops and he was the first to enter the enemy castle during the attack on Izu-Yamanaka castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Siege of Odawara, he spearheaded the Nakamura troops and he was the first to enter the enemy castle during the Siege of Izu Yamanaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>「小田原の役」と「伊豆山中城攻め」を定訳に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Siege of Odawara, he spearheaded the Nakamura troops and he was the first to enter the enemy castle during the Siege of Izu Yamanaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>秀吉から「捨てても一万石は取るべき」と賞賛されるが、一氏からの恩賞（倍の6,000石）に不満を持ち、再び浪人する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was applauded by Hideyoshi as worthy of at least 10,000 koku, his dissatisfaction to Onsho (6000 koku that was double of his salary) (grants) offered by Ichiuji led him to leave and became ronin (unemployed) once again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was applauded by Hideyoshi as worthy of at least 10,000 koku (approximately 1.8 million liters of crop yield), his dissatisfaction to Onsho (6000 koku that was double of his salary) offered by Kazuuji led him to leave and became ronin (unemployed) once again.</e>
<cmt>10,000石の注釈をカッコ書きで入れました。　 一氏を Ichiuji → Kazuuji に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was praised by Hideyoshi, who said that he was worthy of at least 10,000 koku (a measurement of crop yield, putatively in rice, equal to about 1.8 million liters), he was dissatisfied with the reward (6,000 koku, or double his salary) offered him by Kazuuji, so he left and became a ronin (unemployed warrior) once again.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>続けて増田長盛に4,000石で仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served under Nagamori MASUDA for 4000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served under Nagamori MASUDA for 4000 koku next.</e>
<cmt>「続けて」の部分に相当する訳がないので、最後にnext を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served under Nagamori MASUDA for 4,000 koku next.</e>
<cmt>4,000 kokuとカンマを入力しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いで西軍についた長盛の出陣中に、居城の郡山城 (大和国)を任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Nagamori was gone for the front of the Battle of Sekigahara to aid the Western Troop, he was left to protect his castle Koriyama-jo Castle (Yamato province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Nagamori was gone for the front of the Battle of Sekigahara to aid the Western Troop, he was left to protect his castle Koriyama-jo Castle (Yamato province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Nagamori was gone for the front of the Battle of Sekigahara to aid the Western Troop, he was left to protect his castle Koriyama-jo Castle (Yamato province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>戦後、既に長盛が所領を没収されて高野山に蟄居していたにも関わらず、「主君長盛からの命で城を守っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, he continued to remain in the castle to protect it under the order of his lord Nagamori despite the fact that Nagamori&apos;s shoryo (territory) was confiscated after the war and Naganori was staying in Koyasan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, he continued to remain in the castle to protect it under the order of his lord Nagamori despite the fact that Nagamori&apos;s shoryo (territory) was confiscated after the war and Nagamori was staying in Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>最後に出てくる「長盛」の訳が&quot;Naganori&quot;になっていたので訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, he continued to remain in the castle to protect it under the order of his lord Nagamori despite the fact that Nagamori&apos;s shoryo (territory) was confiscated after the war and Nagamori was staying in Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>それ以外の命によって開城はできない」と、城接収の藤堂高虎、本多正純らにあくまで抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fiercely resisted to surrender the castle to the enemy representatives Takotora TODO and Masazumi HONDA without an order from his lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fiercely resisted to surrender the castle to the enemy representatives Takatora TODO and Masazumi HONDA without an order from his lord.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス： Takotora → Takatora に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fiercely resisted to surrender the castle to the enemy representatives Takatora TODO and Masazumi HONDA without an order from his lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>徳川家康らによって、長盛に書状を書かせるまで城を守り通した後に、無事に開城もすませ、その忠義と力量に仕官の誘いが相次いだが、同郷でもあった藤堂高虎に2万石の破格の待遇で仕えることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His effort of protecting the castle that compeled Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and others to write to Nagamori to surrender and he finally surrendered the castle to the enemy without incident, and as a result there were many offers to retain him because of his loyalty and competency however he decided to serve under Takatora TODO who was from the same village for an extraordinary pay of 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His effort of protecting the castle compelled Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and others to write to Nagamori to surrender and he finally surrendered the castle to the enemy without incident, and as a result there were many offers to retain him because of his loyalty and competency however he decided to serve under Takatora TODO who was from the same village for an extraordinary pay of 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>不必要なのでthat を削除しました。 スペルミス： compeled → compelled に訂正しました。 Because of の後の空白を半角分削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His effort of protecting the castle compelled Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and others to write to Nagamori to surrender and he finally surrendered the castle to the enemy without incident, and as a result there were many offers to retain him because of his loyalty and competency however he decided to serve under Takatora TODO who was from the same village for an extraordinary pay of 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>新たに高虎の居城となった伊予国の今治城の普請奉行を務めるなど、槍働き以外の才能を見せ、その後藤堂家が伊勢国に移封となると、上野城代にまでなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He demonstrated his talent over and above yaribataraki (spear works) by assuming the position of Fushin Bugyo (the Minister of Civil Engineering &amp; Construction Office) and other duties and later he ascended to become a head administrator of Ueno-jo Castle after Todo clan was transferred to Iyo province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He demonstrated his talent over and above yaribataraki (spear works) by assuming the position of Fushin Bugyo (the Minister of Civil Engineering &amp; Construction Office) and other duties and later he ascended to become a head administrator of Ueno-jo Castle after Todo clan was transferred to Iyo province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He demonstrated his talent over and above yaribataraki (spear works) by assuming the position of Fushin Bugyo (the Minister of Civil Engineering &amp; Construction Office) and other duties and later he ascended to become a head administrator of Ueno-jo Castle after Todo clan was transferred to Iyo province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>大坂の役では藤堂勢の先鋒を務めるが、冬の陣にて、戦い方で主君高虎と衝突。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Siege of Osaka, he spearheaded TODO&apos;s troops however he had a conflict with his lord Takatora over the war tactics during Fuyuno-jin (winter battle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Siege of Osaka, he spearheaded TODO&apos;s troops however he had a conflict with his lord Takatora over the war tactics during Fuyu no jin (winter battle).</e>
<cmt>「冬の陣」の表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Siege of Osaka, he spearheaded TODO&apos;s troops however he had a conflict with his lord Takatora over the war tactics during Fuyu no jin (winter battle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>谷町口の攻防戦において長宗我部盛親の部隊に蹴散らされて、落馬して負傷するなど大敗してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was injured by thrown off his horse and was badly defeated in the Tanimachiguchi battle by the troops commanded by Morichika CHOSOKABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was injured from falling off his horse and was badly defeated in the battle at the Tanimachiguchi gate by the troops commanded by Morichika CHOSOKABE.</e>
<cmt>「落馬する」の表現を訂正しました。 was と badly の間の空白を半角分削除しました。 「谷町口の」の部分を定訳に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was injured from falling off his horse and was badly defeated in the battle at the Tanimachiguchi gate by the troops commanded by Morichika CHOSOKABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>夏の陣の八尾の戦いにおいては名誉挽回とばかりに再び長宗我部盛親・増田盛次の部隊に襲い掛かり300余人を討ち取る活躍をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Natsunojin (summer battle), in Yao, he pounced again on the troops headed by Morichika CHOSOKABE and Moritsugu MASUDA to retrieve his honor and killed over 300 warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Natsu no jin (summer battle) in Yao, he pounced again on the troops headed by Morichika CHOSOKABE and Moritsugu MASUDA to retrieve his honor and killed over 300 warriors.</e>
<cmt>「夏の陣」の表記を訂正しました。　　in Yao の前のコンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Natsu no jin (summer battle) in Yao, he pounced again on the troops headed by Morichika CHOSOKABE and Moritsugu MASUDA to retrieve his honor and killed over 300 warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、この活躍も独断専行甚だしく、7回にも及ぶ撤退命令を無視して追撃して得たもので、戦いには勝ったものの損害もまた大きく、高虎や他の重臣たちから疎まれる原因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However such victory was achieved only by acting his own authority for disobeying the retreat order seven times in pursuit of the fleeing enemy and such puerile victory led Takatora and his vassals to give him a cold shoulder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However such victory was achieved only by acting on his own authority disobeying the retreat order seven times in pursuit of the fleeing enemy and such puerile victory led Takatora and his vassals to give him a cold shoulder.</e>
<cmt>acting と his の間に on を加えました。 authority の後のfor を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However such victory was achieved only by acting on his own authority disobeying the retreat order seven times in pursuit of the fleeing enemy and such puerile victory led Takatora and his vassals to give him a cold shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そのため戦後出奔して再び浪人となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that reason, he became ronin by leaving the officer&apos;s position after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, he became ronin again by leaving the officer&apos;s position after the war.</e>
<cmt>Because of that reason → For that reason に訂正しました。 「再び」に相当する訳がないので、again を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, he became ronin again by leaving the officer&apos;s position after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>再び仕官の道を探すものの、藤堂家から「奉公構」の触れ（仕官を他の家にさせないようにする願い）が出ており、幕府などからも誘われるものの、適うことはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he looked for another opportunity to serve a master, and Bakufu and others courted him, it wasn&apos;t successful because of hokokamae (a petition to other clans for not to hire him) was circulated by TODO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he looked for another opportunity to serve a master, and Bakufu and others courted him, it wasn&apos;t successful because hokokamae (a petition to other clans for not to hire him) was circulated by TODO clan.</e>
<cmt>because of の of を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he looked for another opportunity to serve a master, and Bakufu and others courted him, it wasn&apos;t successful because hokokamae (a petition to other clans for not to hire him) was circulated by TODO clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>高虎は「奉公したければ（姻戚関係のある）会津の蒲生氏に仕えよ」と命じたものの、これを彼は承知しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatora ordered him to serve Gamoo clan in Aizu (related by marriage) if he wanted to serve but he never agreed to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatora ordered him to serve Gamo clan in Aizu (related by marriage) if he wanted to serve but he never agreed to it.</e>
<cmt>Gamoo → Gamo に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatora ordered him to serve Gamo clan in Aizu (related by marriage) if he wanted to serve but he never agreed to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>寛永5年（1628年）には天海を仲裁役にして奉公構の解除を願ったが、藤堂家から出された一方的な和解の条件に承知せず、逆に高虎への不平不満を申し立てたため、交渉は決裂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1628, he appealed a withdrawal of hokokamae thru the mediator Tenkai however he did not agree to the unilateral conditions proposed by TODO clan and the negotiation was broken off after he expressed his complaint and discontent toward Takatora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1628, he appealed a withdrawal of hokokamae through the mediator Tenkai, however, he did not agree to the unilateral conditions proposed by TODO clan and the negotiation was broken off after he expressed his complaint and discontent toward Takatora.</e>
<cmt>thru → through に訂正しました。 however の前後にコンマを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1628, he appealed a withdrawal of hokokamae through the mediator Tenkai, however, he did not agree to the unilateral conditions proposed by TODO clan and the negotiation was broken off after he expressed his complaint and discontent toward Takatora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>高虎の死後も、子の藤堂高次が引き続き奉公構の方針を維持したため仕官はかなわず、その才を惜しんだ細川忠興や徳川義直らの捨扶持を細々と受けながら、「睡庵」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatora&apos;s son Takatsugu TODO continued a policy of hokokamae that was imposed by his father after Takatora&apos;s death and as a result there was no chance to serve a master again, and he lived thru the rest of his life as &quot;Suian&quot; on meager alms from Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Yoshinao TOKUGAWA who valued his talent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatora&apos;s son Takatsugu TODO continued a policy of hokokamae that was imposed by his father after Takatora&apos;s death and as a result there was no chance for him to serve a master again, and he lived through the rest of his life as &quot;Suian&quot; on meager alms from Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Yoshinao TOKUGAWA who valued his talent.</e>
<cmt>主語を明確にするため、no chance の後にfor him を入れました。 thru → through に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatora&apos;s son Takatsugu TODO continued a policy of hokokamae that was imposed by his father after Takatora&apos;s death and as a result there was no chance for him to serve a master again, and he lived through the rest of his life as &quot;Suian&quot; on meager alms from Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Yoshinao TOKUGAWA who valued his talent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>京で没したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be died in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have died in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス：時制を整えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have died in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nalc(id:139567), ナツメグ(id:112775), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), Jmho(id:10472), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>