<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>渡辺崋山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan WATANABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>渡辺 崋山（わたなべ かざん、寛政5年9月16日 (旧暦)（1793年10月20日） - 天保12年10月11日 (旧暦)（1841年11月23日））は、江戸時代後期の政治家・画家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE (Oct. 20, 1793, to Nov. 23, 1841) was a politician and painter in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan WATANABE (Oct. 20, 1793 to Nov. 23, 1841) was a politician and painter in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE (October 20, 1793 to November 23, 1841) was a politician and painter who lived during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Oct.をOctoberに、Nov.をNovemberに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>40歳の時、三河国田原藩（現在の愛知県田原市域にほぼ当たる）家老。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a senior retainer of Tahara Domain of the Mikawa Province (almost equal to today&apos;s city area of Tahara, Aichi prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a senior retainer of the Tahara Domain of Mikawa Province (roughly equivalent to today&apos;s city area of Tahara, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a senior retainer of the Tahara Domain of Mikawa Province (roughly equivalent to today&apos;s city area of Tahara, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は登（のぼり・ただし一部の絵には「のぼる」と揮毫）、諱は定静（さだやす）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name is Nobori (or Tadashi) (&quot;Noboru&quot; is also written in some of his works), and his personal name is Sadayasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Nobori (or Tadashi) (&quot;Noboru&quot; is also written in some of his works), and his personal name was Sadayasu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Nobori (or Tadashi) (&apos;Noboru&apos; is also written in some of his works), and his personal name was Sadayasu.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号ははじめ華山で、35歳ころに崋山と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first pen name was 華山 (Kazan), but the kanji characters were changed to 崋山 at around the age of 35.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first pen name was 華山 (Kazan), but the kanji characters were changed to 崋山 when he was about 35 years of age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first pen name was 華山 (Kazan), but the kanji characters were changed to 崋山 when he was about 35 years of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>誕生と苦難の幼少時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His birth and childhood days in distress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His birth and childhood days in distress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His birth and childhood days in distress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>田原藩士である父・渡辺定通と母・栄の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born to a father, feudal retainer of Tahara Domain, Sadamichi WATANABE, and a mother Sakae as their first son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was a feudal retainer of the Tahara Domain, Sadamichi WATANABE, and his mother was Sakae; he was their first son.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was a feudal retainer of the Tahara Domain, Sadamichi WATANABE, and his mother was Sakae; he was their first son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>渡辺家は田原藩の中でも上士の家格を持ち、代々100石の禄を与えられていたが、父定通は養子であったために15人扶持（石に直すと田原藩では27石）に削られ、加えて折からの藩の財政難による減俸で実収入はわずか12石足らずであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Watanabe family maintained a family status of joshi (superior samurai) in the Tahara Domain and was granted 100 goku through generations, but since his father Sadamichi was an adopted son, his salary was reduced to 15-people buchi (or 27 goku when converted to koku in Tahara Domain), and the actual income was only 12 goku because of the financial difficulty of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Watanabe family maintained the family status of joshi (superior samurai) in the Tahara Domain and was granted 100 goku through generations, but since his father Sadamichi was an adopted son, his salary was reduced to 15-people buchi (or 27 goku when converted to koku in the Tahara Domain) and the actual income was only 12 goku because of the financial difficulties of the domain.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Watanabe family maintained the family status of joshi (superior samurai) in the Tahara Domain and was granted 100 koku through generations, but since his father Sadamichi was an adopted son, his salary was reduced to 15-people buchi (or 27 koku when converted to koku in the Tahara Domain) and the actual income was only 12 koku because of the financial difficulties of the domain.</e>
<cmt>gokuをkokuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>さらに父定通が病気がちであったために医薬に多くの費用がかかったこともあり、幼少期は極端な貧窮の中に送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his father Sadamichi was prone to illness, the family&apos;s money was very much spent on the cost of Sadamichi&apos;s medicine, and therefore he spent his childhood days in extreme poverty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his father Sadamichi was prone to illness, the family&apos;s money was very much spent on the cost of Sadamichi&apos;s medicine, and therefore he spent his childhood in extreme poverty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his father Sadamichi was prone to illness, the family&apos;s money was very much spent on the cost of Sadamichi&apos;s medicine, and therefore he spent his childhood in extreme poverty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日々の食事にも事欠き、弟や妹は次々に奉公に出されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were so poor that they even couldn&apos;t have meals everyday, and Kazan&apos;s younger brothers and sisters left their home to work for someone else&apos;s servants one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were so poor that they even couldn&apos;t have meals each day, and one after another Kazan&apos;s younger brothers and sisters left their home to work as someone else&apos;s servants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were so poor that they even couldn&apos;t have meals each day, and one after another Kazan&apos;s younger brothers and sisters left their home to work as someone else&apos;s servants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このありさまは、崋山が壮年期に書いた『退役願書之稿』に詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those hard days are depicted in detail in one of his works in his older days, &quot;Taieki Gansho no Ko.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those hard days are depicted in detail in one of his works in his older days, &quot;Taieki Gansho no Ko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those hard days are depicted in detail in one of his works in his older days, &quot;Taieki Gansho no Ko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この悲劇が、のちの勉学に励む姿とあわせて太平洋戦争以前の修身の教科書に掲載されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These descriptions of suffering were used in an ethics textbook before the Pacific War together with the descriptions of his dedication to study in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These descriptions of suffering were used in an ethics textbook before the Pacific War, together with the descriptions of his dedication to study in later years.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These descriptions of suffering were used in an ethics textbook before the Pacific War, together with the descriptions of his dedication to study in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>こうした中、まだ少年の崋山は生計を助けるために得意であった絵を売って、生計を支えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under those circumstances, Kazan, young as he was, came to support the family by selling his drawings he was good at.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the circumstances as well as his talent, Kazan, young as he was, came to support the family by selling his drawings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the circumstances as well as his talent, Kazan, young as he was, came to support the family by selling his drawings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>のちに谷文晁（たにぶんちょう）に入門し、絵の才能は大きく花開くこととなり、20代半ばには画家として著名となり、生活にも苦労せずにすむようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he became a student of Buncho TANI, which led to the great leap in his painting talent, and he made a successful painter in the middle of his 20s, which lifted his family&apos;s life from financial misery to modesty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he became a student of Buncho TANI, which led to a great leap in his abilities as a painter; he achieved success in his mid-twenties, which lifted his family&apos;s life from financial misery to modesty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he became a student of Buncho TANI, which led to a great leap in his abilities as a painter; he achieved success in his mid-twenties, which lifted his family&apos;s life from financial misery to modesty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>一方で学問にも励み、鷹見星皐、後に松崎慊堂から儒学（朱子学）を学び、昌平坂学問所に通い佐藤一斎からも学んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also dedicated to learning; he learned Confucianism (Neo-Confucianism) from Seiko TAKAMI and later from Kodo MATSUZAKI and also from Issai SATO while he attended Shoheizaka Gakumonjo (Shoheizaka School).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also dedicated to learning; he studied Confucianism (Neo-Confucianism) under Seiko TAKAMI and later under Kodo MATSUZAKI and eventually under Issai SATO while he attended Shoheizaka Gakumonjo (Shoheizaka School).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also dedicated to learning; he studied Confucianism (Neo-Confucianism) under Seiko TAKAMI and later under Kodo MATSUZAKI and eventually under Issai SATO while he attended Shoheizaka Gakumonjo (Shoheizaka School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、佐藤信淵からは農学を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned agriculture from Nobuhiro SATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied agriculture with Nobuhiro SATO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied agriculture with Nobuhiro SATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>田原藩士として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Days as a Retainer of Tahara Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Days as a Retainer of the Tahara Domain</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Days as a Retainer of the Tahara Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>藩士としては、8歳で時の藩主三宅康友の嫡男・亀吉の伽役を命じられ、亀吉の夭折後もその弟・元吉（後の藩主・三宅康明）の伽役となり、藩主康友からも目をかけられるなど、幼少時から藩主一家にごく近い位置にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned as an attendant to Kamekichi, an heir of the domain lord Yasutomo MIYAKE at the age of 8 as well as Kamekichi&apos;s younger brother Motokichi (who later became the lord of domain Yasuaki MIYAKE) after Kamekichi&apos;s early death, and because of this assignment, Kazan was well remembered by his master Yasutomo, which means he was very close to the lord family from his childhood days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At eight years of age he was assigned to serve as an attendant to Kamekichi, an heir of the domain lord Yasutomo MIYAKE, as well as Kamekichi&apos;s younger brother Motokichi (who later became the domain lord Yasuaki MIYAKE) after Kamekichi&apos;s early death, and because of this assignment Kazan was well remembered by his master Yasutomo, which means he was very close to the lord family from his childhood days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At eight years of age he was assigned to serve as an attendant to Kamekichi, an heir of the domain lord Yasutomo MIYAKE, as well as Kamekichi&apos;s younger brother Motokichi (who later became the domain lord Yasuaki MIYAKE) after Kamekichi&apos;s early death, and because of this assignment Kazan was well remembered by his master Yasutomo, which means he was very close to the lord family from his childhood days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>こういった生い立ちが崋山の藩主一家への親近感や一層の忠誠心につながっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those memories of his in his younger days created in him a sense of familiarity and a high level of royalty to the lord family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The memories of his younger days created in him a sense of familiarity and a high degree of loyalty to the lord family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The memories of his younger days created in him a sense of familiarity and a high degree of loyalty to the lord family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>16歳で正式に藩の江戸屋敷に出仕するが、納戸役・使番等など、藩主にごく近い役目であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 16, he was officially ordered to work at the Edo residence of the Tahara Domain, and the roles he was assigned were those very close to the lord, such as Nando-yaku (role in charge of the lord&apos;s personal care) or Tsukaiban (a role similar to liaison).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 16 years of age he was officially ordered to work at the Edo residence of the Tahara Domain, where the roles he was assigned were those very close to the lord, such as Nando-yaku (being in charge of the lord&apos;s personal care) or Tsukaiban (a role similar to that of a liaison).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 16 years of age he was officially ordered to work at the Edo residence of the Tahara Domain, where the roles he was assigned were those very close to the lord, such as Nando-yaku (being in charge of the lord&apos;s personal care) or Tsukaiban (a role similar to that of a liaison).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>文政6年（1823年）、田原藩の和田氏の娘・たかと結婚し、同8年（1825年）には父の病死のため32歳で家督を相続し、80石の家禄を引き継いだ（父の藩内の出世に合わせて、禄は復帰していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He married Taka, a daughter of the Wada family of Tahara Domain, in 1823 and inherited the Watanabe family following the death of his father to take over the karoku (hereditary stipend) of 80 goku (the stipend returned to the original level with promotion of his father in the domain administration) in 1825.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1823 he married Taka, a daughter of the Wada family of the Tahara Domain, and inherited the Watanabe family following the death of his father, whereupon he took over the karoku (hereditary stipend) of 80 goku (the stipend returned to the original level with his father&apos;s promotion in the domain administration) in 1825.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1823 he married Taka, a daughter of the Wada family of the Tahara Domain, and inherited the Watanabe family following the death of his father, whereupon he took over the karoku (hereditary stipend) of 80 koku (the stipend returned to the original level with his father&apos;s promotion in the domain administration) in 1825.</e>
<cmt>gokuをkokuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同9年には取次役となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1826, he was appointed as Toritsugiyaku (liaison).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1826, he was appointed as Toritsugiyaku (liaison).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1826, he was appointed as Toritsugiyaku (liaison).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>ところが、翌10年に藩主康明は28歳の若さで病死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1827, the lord of Tahara Domain Yasuaki died young at the age of 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1827, Yasuaki, the lord of the Tahara Domain, died at just 28 years of age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1827, Yasuaki, the lord of the Tahara Domain, died at just 28 years of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>藩首脳部は貧窮する藩財政を打開するため、当時比較的裕福であった姫路藩から持参金つき養子を迎えようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leaders of the domain administration intended to adopt a member of the Himeji Domain&apos;s lord family, who was relatively rich in those days, with a dowry in order to solve the domain&apos;s financial distress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leaders of the domain administration intended to adopt a member of the Himeji Domain&apos;s lord family, which was relatively rich in those days, with a dowry in order to solve the domain&apos;s financial distress.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leaders of the domain administration intended to adopt a member of the Himeji Domain&apos;s lord family, which was relatively rich in those days, with a dowry in order to solve the domain&apos;s financial distress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>崋山はこれに強く反発し、用人の真木定前らとともに康明の異母弟・三宅友信の擁立運動を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan strongly opposed their plan and conducted a movement, together with Sadachika MAKI, one of the lord chamberlains, demanding that Yasuaki&apos;s half-brother Tomonobu MIYAKE be made the next lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan strongly opposed their plan and conducted an effort, together with Sadachika MAKI, one of the lord chamberlains, demanding that Yasuaki&apos;s half-brother Tomonobu MIYAKE be made the next lord.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan strongly opposed their plan and conducted an effort, together with Sadachika MAKI, one of the lord chamberlains, demanding that Yasuaki&apos;s half-brother Tomonobu MIYAKE be made the next lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>結局藩上層部の意思がとおって養子・三宅康直が藩主となり、崋山は一時自暴自棄となって酒浸りの生活を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The top management of the domain administration finally governed the decision, and Yasunao MIYAKE, adopted from the Himeji Domain, became the new lord, which made Kazan lead a desperate and drunkard&apos;s life for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The top management of the domain administration finally governed the decision, and Yasunao MIYAKE, adopted from the Himeji Domain, became the new lord; consequently, Kazan led the desperate life of a drunkard for a while.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The top management of the domain administration finally governed the decision, and Yasunao MIYAKE, adopted from the Himeji Domain, became the new lord; consequently, Kazan led the desperate life of a drunkard for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、一方で藩首脳部と姫路藩と交渉して後日に三宅友信の男子と康直の娘を結婚させ、生まれた男子（のちの三宅康保）を次の藩主とすることを承諾させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Kazan negotiated with the domain administration and the Himeji Domain and had them approve that a son of Tomonobu MIYAKE marry a daughter of Yasunao and that their son be the next domain lord (this arrangement was later realized as their son Yasuyoshi MIYAKE).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kazan negotiated with the domain administration and the Himeji Domain; he had them approve that a son of Tomonobu MIYAKE would marry a daughter of Yasunao and that their son would be the next domain lord (an arrangement that was later realized as their son, Yasuyoshi MIYAKE).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kazan negotiated with the domain administration and the Himeji Domain; he had them approve that a son of Tomonobu MIYAKE would marry a daughter of Yasunao and that their son would be the next domain lord (an arrangement that was later realized as their son, Yasuyoshi MIYAKE).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また藩首脳部は、崋山ら反対派の慰撫の目的もあって、友信に前藩主の格式を与え、巣鴨に別邸を与えて優遇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The top management of the domain also granted the status of former domain lord to Tomonobu and gave him preferential treatment by giving him a separate residence at Sugamo partly for the purpose of soothing the opposition group including Kazan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The top management of the domain also granted the status of former domain lord to Tomonobu and gave him preferential treatment by giving him a separate residence at Sugamo, partly for the purpose of soothing the opposition group, including Kazan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The top management of the domain also granted the status of former domain lord to Tomonobu and gave him preferential treatment by giving him a separate residence at Sugamo, partly for the purpose of soothing the opposition group, including Kazan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>崋山は側用人として親しく友信と接することとなり、こののちに崋山が多くの蘭学書の購入を希望する際には友信が快く資金を出すこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan came to be in good terms with Tomonobu as one of his chamberlains, and this close relationship led to Tomonobu&apos;s willing provision of fund when Kazan wished to purchase foreign books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan came to be on good terms with Tomonobu as one of his chamberlains, and this close relationship led to Tomonobu&apos;s willing provision of funds when Kazan wanted to purchase foreign books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan came to be on good terms with Tomonobu as one of his chamberlains, and this close relationship led to Tomonobu&apos;s willing provision of funds when Kazan wanted to purchase foreign books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>友信は崋山の死後の明治14年（1881年）に「崋山先生略伝」として崋山の伝記を書き残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonobu authored a biography of Kazan &quot;Kazan Sensei Ryakuden&quot; (Brief History of Teacher Kazan) in 1881 after the death of Kazan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonobu authored a biography of Kazan titled &quot;Kazan Sensei Ryakuden (Brief History of Teacher Kazan)&quot; in 1881, after the death of Kazan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonobu authored a biography of Kazan titled &apos;Kazan Sensei Ryakuden&apos; (Brief History of Teacher Kazan) in 1881, after the death of Kazan.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更し、()を&apos; &apos;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>天保3年（1832年）5月、崋山は田原藩の年寄役末席（家老職）に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1832, Kazan assumed Toshiyori-yaku Masseki (the lowest position of executive retainer, which is a position of Karo, or chief retainer) of the Tahara Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1832, Kazan assumed Toshiyori-yaku Masseki (the lowest position of executive retainer, which is a position of Karo, or chief retainer) of the Tahara Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1832, Kazan assumed Toshiyori-yaku Masseki (the lowest position of executive retainer, which is a position of Karo, or chief retainer) of the Tahara Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>20代半ばから絵画ですでに名を挙げていた崋山は、藩政の中枢にはできるだけ近よらずに画業に専念したかったようだが、その希望はかなわなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Already a renowned painter since the middle of his 20s, Kazan seemed to dedicate himself to painting away from the important positions of the domain administration, but his wish was not honored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Already a renowned painter since his mid-twenties, Kazan seemed to dedicate himself to painting away from the important positions of the domain administration, but his wish wasn&apos;t honored.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Already a renowned painter since his mid-twenties, Kazan seemed to dedicate himself to painting away from the important positions of the domain administration, but his wish wasn&apos;t honored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>こうして崋山は、藩政改革に尽力する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus he was determined to do his best to reform the domain government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus he was determined to do his best to reform the domain government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus he was determined to do his best to reform the domain government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>優秀な藩士の登用と士気向上のため、B16を導入し、家格よりも役職を反映した俸禄形式とし、合わせて支出の引き締めを図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He introduced the merit system, in which the stipend is determined based on the rank of role, not the status of family, to promote employment of excellent people and improve the retainers&apos; morale and took measures to reduce the expenditure of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He introduced the merit system, in which the stipend was determined based on the rank of one&apos;s role instead of the status of family, in order to promote the employment of excellent people and improve the retainers&apos; morale; he also took measures to reduce the expenditures of the domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He introduced the merit system, in which the stipend was determined based on the rank of one&apos;s role instead of the status of family, in order to promote the employment of excellent people and improve the retainers&apos; morale; he also took measures to reduce the expenditures of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>さらに農学者大蔵永常を田原に招聘して殖産興業を行おうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also attempted to encourage new industries by inviting agriculturist Nagatsune OKURA to Tahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he attempted to encourage new industries by inviting the agriculturist Nagatsune OKURA to Tahara.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he attempted to encourage new industries by inviting the agriculturist Nagatsune OKURA to Tahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>永常はまず田原で稲作の技術改良を行い、特に鯨油によるイネの害虫駆除法の導入は大きな成果につながったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagatsune first conducted technical improvement of rice cultivation in Tahara, and among the measures taken by him, introduction of removal of pest from rice fields with whale oil is believed to have brought a great success.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagatsune first conducted the technical improvement of rice cultivation in Tahara, and among the measures taken by him the introduction to remove pests from rice fields with whale oil is believed to have brought great success.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagatsune first conducted the technical improvement of rice cultivation in Tahara, and among the measures taken by him the introduction to remove pests from rice fields with whale oil is believed to have brought great success.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>さらに当時諸藩の有力な財源となりつつあった商品作物の栽培を行い、特に温暖な渥美半島に着目してサトウキビ栽培を同地に定着させようとしたが、これはあまりうまくいかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also promoted cultivation of commercial crops, which had come to be a major source of income for the domain, and particularly attempted to settle sugar cane in Atsumi Peninsula, which is particularly warm in climate, but this trial didn&apos;t succeed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also promoted the cultivation of commercial crops, which had come to be a major income source for the domain, and particularly he attempted to establish sugar cane in Atsumi Peninsula, which is particularly warm in climate, but that effort didn&apos;t succeed.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also promoted the cultivation of commercial crops, which had come to be a major income source for the domain, and particularly he attempted to establish sugar cane in Atsumi Peninsula, which is particularly warm in climate, but that effort didn&apos;t succeed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>このほか、ハゼノキ・コウゾの栽培や蠟絞りの技術や、藩士の内職として土焼人形の製造法なども伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other achievements of Nagatsune include successful cultivation of Hazenoki (Rhus succedanea, a kind of wax tree) and Kozo (a mixture of Broussonetia kazinoki and B. papyrifera, a material for Japanese paper), mastery of wax extraction technique, and settlement of production of unglazed earthenware as samurai&apos;s side job.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other achievements of Nagatsune include the successful cultivation of Hazenoki (Rhus succedanea, a kind of wax tree) and Kozo (a mixture of Broussonetia kazinoki and B. papyrifera, a material for Japanese paper), mastery of the wax extraction technique, and the settlement of production of unglazed earthenware as a samurai&apos;s side job.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other achievements of Nagatsune include the successful cultivation of Hazenoki (Rhus succedanea, a kind of wax tree) and Kozo (a mixture of Broussonetia kazinoki and B. papyrifera, a material for Japanese paper), mastery of the wax extraction technique, and the settlement of production of unglazed earthenware as a samurai&apos;s side job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>天保7年（1836年）から翌年にかけての天保の大飢饉の際には、あらかじめ食料備蓄庫（報民倉と命名）を築いておいたことや『凶荒心得書』という対応手引きを著して家中に綱紀粛正と倹約の徹底、領民救済の優先を徹底させることなどで、貧しい藩内で誰も餓死者を出さず、そのために全国で唯一幕府から表彰を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Tempo Famine hit the domain from 1836 to 1837, Kazan helped the domain survive it without any deaths from starving by taking various precautions including construction of food storages (named &quot;Homin-kura&quot;), education of strict compliance with the law and order and the importance of saving by means of a handbook named &quot;Kyoko Kokoroe-sho&quot; (Handbook for Disaster Preparedness), and imparting the principle of priority on survival of the domain people to the samurai retainers of the domain, and Tahara Domain was the only domain that was awarded by the Tokugawa Shogunate for their great feat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Tempo Famine struck the domain from 1836 to 1837, Kazan helped the domain survive without any deaths due to starvation by taking various precautions, including the construction of food storages (named &quot;Homin-kura&quot;), education on strict compliance with the law and order, the importance of saving by means of a handbook called &quot;Kyoko Kokoroe-sho (Handbook for Disaster Preparedness),&quot; and imparting the principle of priority on the survival of the domain&apos;s people to the samurai retainers of the domain; consequently, the Tahara Domain was the only domain that was awarded by the Tokugawa shogunate for its great feat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Tempo Famine struck the domain from 1836 to 1837, Kazan helped the domain survive without any deaths due to starvation by taking various precautions, including the construction of food storages (named &quot;Homin-kura&quot;), education on strict compliance with the law and order, the importance of saving by means of a handbook called &quot;Kyoko Kokoroe-sho&quot; (Handbook for Disaster Preparedness), and imparting the principle of priority on the survival of the domain&apos;s people to the samurai retainers of the domain; consequently, the Tahara Domain was the only domain that was awarded by the Tokugawa shogunate for its great feat.</e>
<cmt>surviveの後の余分なスペースを除去しました。&quot; &quot;の外に()を移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>「蘭学にて大施主」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Great Donor in Rangaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Great Donor in Rangaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Great Donor in Rangaku&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>また、紀州藩儒官遠藤勝助が設立した尚歯会に参加し、高野長英などと飢饉の対策について話し合った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan participated in Shoshikai (a kind of think tank) established by Confucian official of Kishu Domain, Katsusuke ENDO, and exchanged notes with many people including Choei TAKANO about measures against famine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan participated in Shoshikai (a kind of think tank) established by a Confucian official of Kishu Domain, Katsusuke ENDO, and exchanged notes with many people (including Choei TAKANO) regarding measures to be taken against famine.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan participated in Shoshikai (a kind of think tank) established by a Confucian official of Kishu Domain, Katsusuke ENDO, and exchanged notes with many people (including Choei TAKANO) regarding measures to be taken against famine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この成果として長英はジャガイモ（馬鈴薯）とソバ（早ソバ）を飢饉対策に提案した『救荒二物考』を上梓するが、絵心のある崋山がその挿絵を担当している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this discussion, Choei authored &quot;Kyuko Nibutsu-ko&quot; (Two Crops for Disaster Restoration), in which potato and soba (buckwheat noodle) should be prepared for solution to famine, and Kazan, an expert of painting, provided illustrations to the book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of such discussion, Choei authored &quot;Kyuko Nibutsu-ko (Two Crops for Disaster Restoration),&quot; in which potatoes and soba (buckwheat noodle) should be prepared as a solution to famine, and Kazan, an expert painter, provided illustrations for the book.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of such discussion, Choei authored &quot;Kyuko Nibutsu-ko&quot; (Two Crops for Disaster Restoration), in which potatoes and soba (buckwheat noodle) should be prepared as a solution to famine, and Kazan, an expert painter, provided illustrations for the book.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;の外に()を移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その後この学問サークルはモリソン号事件とともにさらに広がりを見せ、蘭学者の長英や小関三英、幡崎鼎、幕臣の川路聖謨、羽倉簡堂、江川英龍（太郎左衛門）などが加わり、海防問題などで深く議論するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their study circle further grew with the occurrence of the Morrison Incident, involving Dutch scholars (a person who studied Western sciences by means of the Dutch language) Choei, Sanei KOSEKI, and Kanae HATAZAKI, a shogunate retainer Toshiakira KAWAJI, Kando HAKURA, and Hidetatsu EGAWA (Tarozaemon) being members, with a range of themes to discuss in detail extending to naval defense issues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their study circle further grew with the occurrence of the Morrison Incident, involving Dutch scholars (a person who studied Western sciences by means of the Dutch language), with Choei, Sanei KOSEKI and Kanae HATAZAKI, the shogunate retainer Toshiakira KAWAJI, Kando HAKURA and Hidetatsu EGAWA (Tarozaemon) being members, covering a range of themes to discuss in detail, even extending to issues of naval defense.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their study circle further grew with the occurrence of the Morrison Incident, involving Dutch scholars (a person who studied Western sciences by means of the Dutch language), with Choei, Sanei KOSEKI and Kanae HATAZAKI, the shogunate retainer Toshiakira KAWAJI, Kando HAKURA and Hidetatsu EGAWA (Tarozaemon) being members, covering a range of themes to discuss in detail, even extending to issues of naval defense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>特に江川は崋山に深く師事するようになり、幕府の海防政策などの助言を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Egawa in particular became a devoted disciple of Kazan and received advice from him on the naval defense policy for the Shogunate government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Egawa, in particular, became a devoted disciple of Kazan and received advice from him on the naval defense policy for the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Egawa, in particular, became a devoted disciple of Kazan and received advice from him on the naval defense policy for the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>こうした崋山の姿を、この会合に顔を出したこともある藤田東湖は、「蘭学にて大施主」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toko FUJITA, who attended those sessions, remembered the enthusiastic Kazan and described him &quot;the Great Donor in Rangaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toko FUJITA, who attended those sessions, remembered the enthusiastic Kazan and described him as &quot;the Great Donor in Rangaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toko FUJITA, who attended those sessions, remembered the enthusiastic Kazan and described him as &apos;the Great Donor in Rangaku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>崋山自身は蘭学者ではないものの、時の蘭学者たちのリーダー的存在であるとみなしての呼び名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kazan himself was not a Dutch scholar, Fujita&apos;s description came from his status as the leader of Dutch scholars in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kazan himself was not a Dutch scholar, Fujita&apos;s description came from his status as the leader of Dutch scholars in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kazan himself was not a Dutch scholar, Fujita&apos;s description came from his status as the leader of Dutch scholars in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>蛮社の獄とその最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of Scholars of Western Learning) and His Last</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of Scholars of Western Learning) and His Last</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bansha no goku (Imprisonment of Scholars of Western Learning) and His Last</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし幕府の保守派、特に幕府目付鳥居耀蔵らはこれらの動きを嫌っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those activities, however, were recognized unfavorably by the conservatives of the Shogunate, particularly Yozo TORII, metsuke (inspectors of the Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those activities, however, were viewed unfavorably by the conservatives of the shogunate, particularly Yozo TORII, the metsuke (inspector of the Tokugawa shogunate).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those activities, however, were viewed unfavorably by the conservatives of the shogunate, particularly Yozo TORII, the metsuke (inspector of the Tokugawa shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>鳥居は元々幕府の儒学（朱子学）を担う林家の出であり、蘭学者が幕府の政治に介入することを好まなかったし、加えてそもそも崋山や江川も林家（昌平坂学問所）で儒学を学んだこともあり、鳥居からすれば彼らを裏切り者と感じていたともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torii was originally from the Hayashi family who traditionally served the Shogunate as Confucianist (New-Confucianist) and, because of this background, did not like interference of Dutch scholars with the politics of the Shogunate in the first place and, according to some interpretation, considered Kazan and Egawa as traitors of Confucianism as they once learned Confucianism at the Hayashi family (Shoheizaka School).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torii was originally from the Hayashi family, which traditionally served the shogunate as Confucianist (New-Confucianist) and, given that background, did not like the interference of Dutch scholars in the politics of the shogunate and, according to some interpretations, considered Kazan and Egawa as traitors of Confucianism because they had once studied Confucianism under the Hayashi family (Shoheizaka School).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torii was originally from the Hayashi family, which traditionally served the shogunate as Confucianist (New-Confucianist) and, given that background, did not like the interference of Dutch scholars in the politics of the shogunate and, according to some interpretations, considered Kazan and Egawa as traitors of Confucianism because they had once studied Confucianism under the Hayashi family (Shoheizaka School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>天保10年（1839年）5月、鳥居はついにでっちあげの罪を設けて江川や崋山を罪に落とそうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torii finally attempted to make Egawa and Kazan criminals by false charge in May 1839.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torii finally attempted to make Egawa and Kazan criminals based on a false charge in May 1839.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torii finally attempted to make Egawa and Kazan criminals based on a false charge in June 1839.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>江川は老中水野忠邦にかばわれて無事だったが、崋山は家宅捜索の際に幕府の保守的海防方針を批判し、そのために発表を控えていた『慎機論』が発見されてしまい、幕政批判で有罪となり、国元田原で蟄居することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Egawa was safe as he was harbored by roju (Shogun&apos;s council member) Tadakuni MIZUNO, but Kazan criticized the Shogunate&apos;s conservative naval defense policy while his house was being searched, and, because of that agitation, his personal paper &quot;Shinkiron,&quot; which he refrained from publishing, was found by house researchers, which ended up his being guilty of blaming the Shogunate&apos;s policy and his home confinement in his hometown Tahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Egawa was safe, as he was harbored by roju (Shogun&apos;s council member) Tadakuni MIZUNO, but Kazan criticized the shogunate&apos;s conservative naval defense policy while his house was being searched and, because of that agitation, his personal paper &quot;Shinkiron,&quot; which he had refrained from publishing, was found by house researchers, whereupon he was deemed guilty of blaming the shogunate&apos;s policy; consequently, he was placed under house arrest in his hometown of Tahara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Egawa was safe, as he was harbored by roju (Shogun&apos;s council member) Tadakuni MIZUNO, but Kazan criticized the shogunate&apos;s conservative naval defense policy while his house was being searched and, because of that agitation, his personal paper &quot;Shinkiron,&quot; which he had refrained from publishing, was found by house researchers, whereupon he was deemed guilty of blaming the shogunate&apos;s policy; consequently, he was placed under house arrest in his hometown of Tahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>翌々年、田原の池ノ原屋敷で謹慎生活を送る崋山一家の貧窮ぶりを憂慮した門人福田半香の計らいで江戸で崋山の書画会を開き、その代金を生活費に充てることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two years later, one of Kazan&apos;s disciples, Hanko FUKUDA felt sorry for the miserable life of the Kazan family living in confinement in Ikenohara Residence in Tahara and planned an exhibition of his painting works in Edo so as to apply the profits to the Kazan family&apos;s living expenses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two years later, one of Kazan&apos;s disciples, Hanko FUKUDA, felt sorry for the miserable life of the Kazan family living in confinement in the Ikenohara residence of Tahara and planned an exhibition of his paintings in Edo so as to apply the profits to the Kazan family&apos;s living expenses.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two years later, one of Kazan&apos;s disciples, Hanko FUKUDA, felt sorry for the miserable life of the Kazan family living in confinement in the Ikenohara residence of Tahara and planned an exhibition of his paintings in Edo so as to apply the profits to the Kazan family&apos;s living expenses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>ところが、生活のために絵を売っていたことが幕府で問題視されたとの風聞が立ち（一説には藩内の反崋山派による策動とされている）、藩に迷惑が及ぶことを恐れた崋山は「不忠不孝渡辺登」の絶筆の書を遺して、池ノ原屋敷の納屋にて切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the rumor came to have it that the Shogunate considered the sale of Kazan&apos;s works to support his life as a problem (one theory says that this was a scheme attempted by the anti-Kazan group in the Tahara Domain), and since Kazan was afraid that it would damage the domain, he killed himself by seppuku in the barn of the Ikenohara Residence after leaving his farewell words &quot;Fuchu Fuko Watanabe Nobori&quot; (Disloyal, Unfilial, Watanabe Nobori).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the rumor emerged that the shogunate viewed the sale of Kazan&apos;s works to support his life as a problem (one theory says this was a scheme attempted by an anti-Kazan group in the Tahara Domain), and since Kazan was afraid it would damage the domain, he killed himself by seppuku in the barn of the Ikenohara residence, having left the farewell words &quot;Fuchu Fuko Watanabe Nobori&quot; (Disloyal, Unfilial, Watanabe Nobori).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the rumor emerged that the shogunate viewed the sale of Kazan&apos;s works to support his life as a problem (one theory says this was a scheme attempted by an anti-Kazan group in the Tahara Domain), and since Kazan was afraid it would damage the domain, he killed himself by seppuku in the barn of the Ikenohara residence, having left the farewell words &apos;Fuchu Fuko Watanabe Nobori&apos; (Disloyal, Unfilial, Watanabe Nobori).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>崋山に対する反崋山派の圧力はその死後も強く、また幕府の手前もあり、息子の渡辺小崋が家老に就任して家名再興を果たした後も墓を建立することが許されなかったという（江戸幕府が崋山の名誉回復と墓の建立を許可したのは、江戸幕府滅亡直前の明治元年3月15日 (旧暦)（1868年4月7日）のことであった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pressure of the anti-Kazan group still remained so strong even after his death that, according to some record, they did not allow establishment of Kazan&apos;s tomb even after his son Shoka WATANABE assumed karo (chief retainer) of the Tahara Domain to restore his family&apos;s impaired reputation (it was in April 7, 1868, immediately before the collapse of the Edo Shogunate that the Shogunate allowed rehabilitation of Kazan&apos;s honor and construction of his tomb).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pressure of the anti-Kazan group remained so strong even after his death that, according to some records, they didn&apos;t allow the establishment of Kazan&apos;s tomb even after his son, Shoka WATANABE, assumed the post of karo (chief retainer) of the Tahara Domain in order to restore his family&apos;s impaired reputation (it was in April 7, 1868, immediately before the collapse of the Edo shogunate, that the shogunate allowed the rehabilitation of Kazan&apos;s honor and the construction of his tomb).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pressure of the anti-Kazan group remained so strong even after his death that, according to some records, they didn&apos;t allow the establishment of Kazan&apos;s tomb even after his son, Shoka WATANABE, assumed the post of karo (chief retainer) of the Tahara Domain in order to restore his family&apos;s impaired reputation (it was in April 7, 1868, immediately before the collapse of the Edo shogunate, that the shogunate allowed the rehabilitation of Kazan&apos;s honor and the construction of his tomb).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>なお、小崋をはじめとする崋山の子女はいずれも子供に恵まれなかったために、明治期にその家系は断絶することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Shoka and all the children of Kazan did not have children, Kazan&apos;s family line extinguished in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Shoka and all the children of Kazan did not have children of their own, Kazan&apos;s family line was extinguished in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Shoka and all the children of Kazan did not have children of their own, Kazan&apos;s family line was extinguished in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>著書に『西洋事情書』など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His works include &quot;Seiyo Jijosho&quot; (Affairs in the Western Countries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His works include &quot;Seiyo Jijosho (Affairs in the Western Countries).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His works include &quot;Seiyo Jijosho&quot; (Affairs in the Western Countries).</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>画家・文人としての崋山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan as Painter and Literati</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan as Painter and Literati</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan as Painter and Literati</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>華山は年少の頃より生計を支える為に画業を志した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan wanted to become a professional painter to support his family when he was a child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a child, Kazan wanted to become a professional painter in order to support his family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a child, Kazan wanted to become a professional painter in order to support his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>最初、大叔父の平山文鏡に画の手ほどきを受け、続いて白川芝山に師事したが付届けができないことを理由に破門された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first he learned painting from his grand-uncle Bunkyo HIRAYAMA, and then he learned from Shizan SHIRAKAWA, but he was excommunicated by Shirakawa because his family could not send him gifts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first he studied painting under his great-uncle Bunkyo HIRAYAMA, and then he studied with Shizan SHIRAKAWA, but eventually Kazan was excommunicated by Shirakawa because his family could not send him gifts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first he studied painting under his great-uncle Bunkyo HIRAYAMA, and then he studied with Shizan SHIRAKAWA, but eventually Kazan was excommunicated by Shirakawa because his family could not send him gifts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>これを憐れんだ父は、藩主の姻戚の家来というつてを頼って金子金陵に崋山の弟子入りを頼み、受け入れられた（崋山16歳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feeling sorry for him, his father found that professional painter Kinryo KANEKO was a retainer of a relative of the Tahara Domain&apos;s lord family and asked Kaneko to take Kazan as his student based on that connection, and Kaneko accepted it (Kazan was 16 years old).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feeling sorry for him, his father found that the professional painter Kinryo KANEKO was a retainer of a relative of the Tahara Domain&apos;s lord family and asked Kaneko to take Kazan as his student based on that connection, whereupon Kaneko accepted it (Kazan was then 16 years old).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feeling sorry for him, his father found that the professional painter Kinryo KANEKO was a retainer of a relative of the Tahara Domain&apos;s lord family and asked Kaneko to take Kazan as his student based on that connection, whereupon Kaneko accepted it (Kazan was then 16 years old).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>金陵は崋山に眼をかけ、崋山の画力は向上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinryo took a good care of Kazan and helped him greatly improve his painting capability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinryo took good care of Kazan and helped him achieve great improvements in his painting ability.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinryo took good care of Kazan and helped him achieve great improvements in his painting ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>このころ、初午灯篭の絵を描く内職を手がけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, Kazan did a side job of drawing Hatsu-uma lanterns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, Kazan had the side job of drawing Hatsu-uma lanterns.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, Kazan had the side job of drawing Hatsu-uma lanterns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>崋山によれば百枚書いて、銭一貫だったというが、このときに絵を速く描く技術を身につけたことは、後年の紀行文中のスケッチなどに大きく役立ったであろうことがうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kazan, he was paid one kan (one of the monetary units in the Edo period) for 100 paintings drawn, but he acquired a technique of fast drawing from this side job, and it seems apparent that this technique was very helpful when he drew sketches as he wrote travel essays in his later life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kazan, he was paid one kan (a monetary unit of the Edo period) for 100 paintings drawn, but he had acquired a rapid drawing technique from his side job; it seems apparent that this technique was very helpful when he drew sketches to accompany the travel essays he wrote in later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kazan, he was paid one kan (a monetary unit of the Edo period) for 100 paintings drawn, but he had acquired a rapid drawing technique from his side job; it seems apparent that this technique was very helpful when he drew sketches to accompany the travel essays he wrote in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>さらに、金陵の師である谷文晁にも教えを受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also learned from Kinryo&apos;s master Buncho TANI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also studied under Kinryo&apos;s master, Buncho TANI.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also studied under Kinryo&apos;s master, Buncho TANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>文晁は華山の才能を見抜き、画技のみならず文人画としての手本となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buncho knew that Kazan had a great potential; not only he taught him the painting techniques but also his works became role models of literati painting for Kazan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buncho knew that Kazan had great potential; not only did he teach him the painting techniques but his works also served as the role models of literati painting for Kazan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buncho knew that Kazan had great potential; not only did he teach him the painting techniques but his works also served as the role models of literati painting for Kazan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>師の文晁に倣って南画のみならず様々な系統の画派を広く吸収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the example of Buncho, Kazan learned not only the technique of nanga (a school of painting originating in China) but also various schools of painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the example of Buncho, Kazan acquired the technique of nanga (a school of painting originating in China) and also learned about various schools of painting.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the example of Buncho, Kazan acquired the technique of nanga (a school of painting originating in China) and also learned about various schools of painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>文人画は清の惲南田に強く影響されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His literati painting was strongly influenced by Yun Nantian of Qing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His literati painting was strongly influenced by Yun Nantian, of Qing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His literati painting was strongly influenced by Yun Nantian, of Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また肖像画は陰影を巧みに用いて高い写実表現に成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For portrait paintings, Kazan successfully acquired a technique of naturalistic painting dexterously using shades.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For portrait paintings, Kazan successfully acquired the technique of painting naturalistically, which he performed with great dexterity using shades.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For portrait paintings, Kazan successfully acquired the technique of painting naturalistically, which he performed with great dexterity using shades.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>西洋画の影響があったことは間違いないがかつて例のない独自の画法を確立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was definitely influenced by Western painting, he established an unprecedented style of painting of his own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was certainly influenced by Western painting, he established his own unprecedented style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was certainly influenced by Western painting, he established his own unprecedented style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>当時から華山の肖像画は人気があり多くの作品を画いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His portrait paintings won a high reputation in those days and he drew a lot of portraits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His portrait paintings won a high reputation in those days, and he drew many of them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His portrait paintings won a high reputation in those days, and he drew many of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>代表作としては、「鷹見泉石像」・「佐藤一斎像」・「市河米庵像」などが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative portrait works include &quot;Portrait of Takami Senseki,&quot; &quot;Portrait of Sato Issai,&quot; and &quot;Portrait of Ichikawa Beian.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative portrait works include &quot;Portrait of Takami Senseki,&quot; &quot;Portrait of Sato Issai&quot; and &quot;Portrait of Ichikawa Beian.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative portrait works include &apos;Portrait of Takami Senseki,&apos; &apos;Portrait of Sato Issai&apos; and &apos;Portrait of Ichikawa Beian.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>弟子に椿椿山・福田半香などが育った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He developed such disciples as Chinzan TSUBAKI and Hanko FUKUDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He developed such disciples as Chinzan TSUBAKI and Hanko FUKUDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He developed such disciples as Chinzan TSUBAKI and Hanko FUKUDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>こうした崋山の写実性へのこだわりを示すエピソードがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an episode that describes how keenly he was after photorealistic depiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an episode that describes how keenly he sought photorealistic depiction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an episode that describes how keenly he sought photorealistic depiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>1835年（天保6）、画家友達であった滝沢琴嶺が没し、崋山は葬儀の場で琴嶺の父・曲亭馬琴にその肖像画の作成を依頼された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1835, one of his painter friends Kinrei TAKIZAWA died, and Kazan was asked by Kinrei&apos;s father Kyokutei Bakin to draw Kinrei&apos;s portrait at the funeral.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1835, one of his painter friends Kinrei TAKIZAWA died, and Kazan was asked by Kinrei&apos;s father Kyokutei Bakin to draw Kinrei&apos;s portrait at the funeral.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1835, one of his painter friends Kinrei TAKIZAWA died, and Kazan was asked by Kinrei&apos;s father Kyokutei Bakin to draw Kinrei&apos;s portrait at the funeral.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>当時、肖像画は当人の没後に描かれることが多く、画家はしばしば実際に実物を見ることなく、やむを得ず死者を思い出しながら描くことがしばしばあり、崋山の琴嶺像執筆もそうなる予定だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, the portrait of a person was generally drawn often after his death, and painters had to draw the portraits without actually seeing the models and therefore needed to imagine them to draw, and that should also be the case of Kazan&apos;s drawing of Kinrei&apos;s portrait.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, a person&apos;s portrait was often drawn often after death, so the painter had to draw the portraits without actually seeing the model and therefore needed to imagine in order to draw, which should also have been the case with Kazan&apos;s drawing of Kinrei&apos;s portrait.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, a person&apos;s portrait was often drawn often after death, so the painter had to draw the portraits without actually seeing the model and therefore needed to imagine in order to draw, which should also have been the case with Kazan&apos;s drawing of Kinrei&apos;s portrait.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>ところが崋山はそれを受け入れず、棺桶のふたを開けて琴嶺を覗き込んでスケッチし、さらに顔に直接触れたという（馬琴『後の為の記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Kazan did not accept that approach, opened the lid of the coffin, had a look of Kinrei&apos;s face, sketched it, and touched his face (according to Bakin&apos;s book &quot;Nochino tameno ki&quot; (Records for the Future).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan, however, didn&apos;t accept that approach; instead he opened the lid of the coffin, took a look of Kinrei&apos;s face, sketched it and touched his face (according to Bakin&apos;s book, &quot;Nochino tameno ki (Records for the Future).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan, however, didn&apos;t accept that approach; instead he opened the lid of the coffin, took a look of Kinrei&apos;s face, sketched it and touched his face (according to Bakin&apos;s book, &quot;Nochino tameno ki&quot; (Records for the Future).</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>これらは当時の価値観や風習から大きく外れた行動であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those actions of his were formidably deviated from the sense of value or custom in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actions such as those represented a significant departure from the sense of protocol in those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actions such as those represented a significant departure from the sense of protocol in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="72">
<j>元々崋山は貧しさをしのぐ目的もあり画業を始めたのだが、それが大きく花開き、また画業を習得する際に得た視野や人脈は、崋山の発想を大きくするために得がたいものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan originally started painting partly for the purpose of supporting his family, but his talent brought a great success, and the frame of reference and personal connections he obtained as he mastered painting were indispensable for enhancing his sense of original thinking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan had originally started painting partly for the purpose of supporting his family, but his talent brought great success, and the frame of reference and personal connections he obtained as he mastered painting were indispensable for enhancing his very original manner of thinking.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan had originally started painting partly for the purpose of supporting his family, but his talent brought great success, and the frame of reference and personal connections he obtained as he mastered painting were indispensable for enhancing his very original manner of thinking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>代表作に当時の風俗を写生した「一掃百態図」など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Isso Hyakutai Zu&quot; that depicts the manners and customs of those days is one of the portrait masterpieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Isso Hyakutai Zu,&quot; which depicts the manners and customs of those days, is one of the portrait masterpieces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isso Hyakutai Zu,&apos; which depicts the manners and customs of those days, is one of the portrait masterpieces.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また、文人としては随筆紀行文である『全楽堂日録』『日光紀行』などを残し、文章とともに多く残されている挿絵が旅の情景を髣髴させるとともに、当時を文化・風俗を知る重要な資料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a man of literature, Kazan produced travel writings and essays including &quot;Zengakudo Hiroku&quot; and &quot;Nikko Kiko,&quot; and his writings as well as abundant illustrations vividly depict the scenes of his travels and serve as important materials to tell the then culture and local manners and customs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a man of literature, Kazan produced travel writings and essays including &quot;Zengakudo Hiroku&quot; and &quot;Nikko Kiko&quot;; his writings, like his abundant illustrations, vividly depict the scenes of his travels and serve as important materials to depict the culture, local manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a man of literature, Kazan produced travel writings and essays including &quot;Zengakudo Hiroku&quot; and &quot;Nikko Kiko&quot;; his writings, like his abundant illustrations, vividly depict the scenes of his travels and serve as important materials to depict the culture, local manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Nnh(id:474), 宗純(id:232846), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), KurmUmy(id:202680), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Mishika(id:276), Greenland4(id:114494), パの字(id:34188), 下総大納言(id:43461), Goki(id:7107), TY(id:1386), Niohe(id:82143), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), Bow(id:16755), Non2non(id:190118), Klesha(id:203751), ウィキ豊(id:82961), M-sho-gun(id:88956), GoGoDoll(id:131511), STBot(id:137943), Kaznov17(id:68122), Inukawa(id:842), Aboshi(id:9318), Hatsune(id:26654), Carkuni(id:79281), ヤマト(id:8425), 松浪ケンシロウ(id:25283), R28Bot(id:177951), Nekosuki600(id:21263), DSisyphBot(id:262306), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), 月臣くにひと(id:3159), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>