<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今出川公彦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinhiko IMADEGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinhiko IMADEGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinhiko IMADEGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今出川 公彦（いまでがわ きんひこ、永正3年（1506年） - 天正6年1月23日 (旧暦)（1578年3月1日））は、室町時代後期（戦国時代 (日本)）の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinhiko IMADEGAWA (1506 - March 1, 1578) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived in the latter half of the Muromachi period (Sengoku period (period of warring states) in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinhiko IMADEGAWA (1506 - March 1, 1578) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived during the latter half of the Muromachi period (Sengoku period - period of warring states in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinhiko IMADEGAWA (1506 - March 11, 1578) was a kugyo (court noble) who lived during the latter half of the Muromachi period (Sengoku period - period of warring states in Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後柏原天皇（104代）・後奈良天皇（105代）・正親町天皇（106代）の三帝にわたり仕え、官位は従一位左大臣まで昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He serve the three emperors of Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th emperor), Emperor Gonara (the 105th emperor) and Emperor Ogimachi (the 106th emperor), and advanced up to Sadaijin (minister of the left) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He serve the three emperors, Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th emperor), Emperor Gonara (the 105th emperor), and Emperor Ogimachi (the 106th emperor), and advanced to Sadaijin (minister of the left) at the rank of Juichii (Junior 1st Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He serve the three emperors, Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th), Emperor Gonara (the 105th), and Emperor Ogimachi (the 106th), and advanced to Sadaijin (minister of the left) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は権大納言今出川季孝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Suetaka IMADEGAWA, Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Suetaka IMADEGAWA, Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Suetaka IMADEGAWA, Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に右大臣今出川晴季、興福寺大僧正空慶がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harusue IMADEGAWA, Udaijin (minister of the right), and Kukei, daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) at Kofukuji Temple, were his sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harusue IMADEGAWA, Udaijin (minister of the right), and Kukei, daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) at Kofukuji Temple, were his sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harusue IMADEGAWA, Udaijin (minister of the right), and Kukei, daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) at Kofuku-ji Temple, were his sons.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>永正4年（1507年）に叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ennobled in 1507.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ennobled in 1507.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred to a peerage in 1507.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以降累進して、侍従・近衛府を経て、永正15年（1518年）に従三位・参議となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continued being promoted after that, he was appointed to Sangi (a councilor) at the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1518, becoming a kugyo, after assuming jiju (a chamberlain) and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Continued being promoted after that, he was appointed to Sangi (a councilor) at the rank of Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank) in 1518, becoming a kugyo, after assuming jiju (a chamberlain) and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Continued being promoted after that, he was appointed to Sangi (a councilor) at the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1518, becoming a kugyo, after assuming jiju (a chamberlain) and a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中納言・踏歌節会外弁を経て、大永5年（1525年）大納言に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After assuming Chunagon (a middle counselor) and Toka no sechie Geben (a kugyo who supervised many matters outside Jomei Gate at Toka no sechi-e (Imperial Court ceremonies where many persons danced while singing)), he was appointed to Dainagon (a major counselor) in 1525.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After assuming Chunagon (a middle counselor) and Toka no sechie Geben (a kugyo who supervised many matters outside Jomei Gate at Toka no sechi-e (Imperial Court ceremonies where many persons danced while singing), he was appointed to Dainagon (a major counselor) in 1525.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After assuming Chunagon (a vice-councilor of state) and Toka no sechie Geben (a kugyo who supervised many matters outside Jomei Gate at Toka no sechi-e (Imperial Court ceremonies where many persons danced while singing), he was appointed to Dainagon (a chief councilor of state) in 1525.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大永6年（1526年）から天文 (元号)元年（1532年）まで神宮伝奏を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period from 1526 to 1532, he assumed Jingutenso (a shrine messenger to the emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period from 1526 to 1532, he assumed Jingutenso (shrine messenger to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period from 1526 to 1532, he assumed Jingutenso (shrine messenger to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天文8年（1539年）に近衛府、さらに天文11年（1542年）には近衛府へと昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to a post at Konoefu in 1539 and to another post at Konoefu in 1542.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to a post at Konoefu in 1539 and to another post at Konoefu in 1542.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to a post at Konoefu in 1539 and to another post at Konoefu in 1542.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天文12年（1543年）内大臣に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior) in 1543.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior) in 1543.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior) in 1543.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年に左近衛大将を辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he resigned Sakonoe no daisho (the major captain of the left division of inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he resigned Sakonoe no daisho (the major captain of the left division of the inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he resigned Sakonoe no daisho (the major captain of the left division of the inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天文14年（1545年）には右大臣、天文15年（1546年）には左大臣を拝命するも翌年に辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) in 1545 and to Sadaijin (minister of the left)5 and in 1546, but regsigned the post in the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) in 1545 and to Sadaijin (minister of the left) and in 1546, but regsigned the post in the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) in 1545 and to Sadaijin (minister of the left) and in 1546, but resigned the post in the next year.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天文16年（1547年）に従一位を授与された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1547, he was awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1547, he was awarded Juichii (Junior 1st Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1547, he was awarded Juichii (Junior first Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>永禄2年（1559年）に出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest in 1559.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a priest in 1559.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a priest in 1559.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>