<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原通季</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michisue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michisue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michisue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 通季（ふじわら の みちすえ、寛治4年（1090年） - 大治 (日本)4年6月17日 (旧暦)（1128年7月16日））は平安時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michisue (1090 - July 16, 1128) was the Court noble in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michisue (1090 - July 16, 1128) was a Court noble in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michisue (1090 - July 12, 1128) was a Kugyo (top court official) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家閑院流、大納言藤原公実の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was originally from Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and the child of FUJIWARA no Kinzane, Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The son of Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) FUJIWARA no Kinzane, he was descended from the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The son of Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) FUJIWARA no Kinzane, he was descended from the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>clan　を小文字で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正三位・中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Chunagon (middle counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attained the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and the post of Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attained the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and the post of Chunagon (Vice-Councilor of State).</e>
<cmt>中納言　補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大宮を号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called himself Omiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Omiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Omiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>西園寺家初代で、西園寺通季と表記する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first generation of the Saionji family and described as Michisue SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the forefather of the Saionji family, he sometimes appears as Michisue SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the forefather of the Saionji family, he sometimes appears as Michisue SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>承徳3年（1099年）に越中国国司、康和2年（1100年）に右兵衛佐、康和4年（1102年）に従五位、康和5年（1103年）に正五位、康和6年（1104年）に左少将、美作守、長治2年（1105年）に従四位、嘉承2年（1107年）に従四位上、天仁元年（1108年）に正四位、天永2年（1111年）に左中将、蔵人頭、天永3年（1112年）に備前権守、永久 (元号)3年（1115年）に参議となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became kokushi (provincial governors) of Ecchu Province in 1099, Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) in 1100, Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 1102, Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) in 1103, Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Mimasaka no kami (the governor of Mimasaka Province) in 1104, Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in 1105, Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 1107, Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) in 1108, Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1111, Bizen gon no kami (provisional governor of Bizen Province) in 1112, and Sangi (councilor) in 1115.</e>
<cmt>下記用語については、ウェブの用語を使用して訳出しました。兵衛府→右兵衛佐近衛府→左少将（1104年）美作国→美作守近衛府→左中将（1111年）備前国→備前権守「正五位」は、ウェブの用語と異なります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Kokushi (Governor) of Ecchu Province in 1099, Uhyoe no Suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) in 1100, Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 1102, Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) in 1103, Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Kami (Governor) of Mimasaka Province in 1104, Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in 1105, Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 1107, Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) in 1108, Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1111, Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor) of Bizen Province in 1112, and Sangi (Councilor) in 1115.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Ecchu no kuni kokushi (Provincial Governor of Ecchu Province) in 1099, Uhyoe no Suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) in 1100, Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 1102, Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) in 1103, Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Mimasaka no kami (Governor of Mimasaka Province) in 1104, Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in 1105, Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 1107, Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) in 1108, Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1111, Bizen gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Bizen Province) in 1112, and Sangi (Councilor) in 1115.</e>
<cmt>役職名などの表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>蔵人頭、参議への補任はともに異母兄の実行と同時であったが、父公実があらかじめ定めていた嫡庶の順により通季が上首とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the appointment of Kurodo no to and Sangi at the same time with his half brother Saneyuki, but Michisue became the head according to Chakusho-no-jun (the order of legal wife&apos;s child and concubine&apos;s child) that his father Kinzane had already established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He shared the positions of Kurodo no to and Sangi with his half brother, Saneyuki, but Michisue had superiorty due the policy of Chakusho-no-jun (where children of a legal wife have precedence over the children of concubines) that had been established by his father, Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He shared the positions of Kurodo no to and Sangi with his elder paternal half-brother, Saneyuki, but Michisue had superiority due the policy of Chakusho-no-jun (where children of a legal wife have precedence over the children of concubines) that had been established by his father, Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>異母兄　の表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>代々、閑院流の正嫡に伝えられる牛車を公実から相続したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded gissha (ox-drawn carriage) from Kinzane that was transmitted to a legal child of Kanin line for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kinzane, he inherited the &apos;gissha&apos; (ox-drawn carriage) that had been handed down to legitimate children of the Kanin line for generations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kinzane, he inherited the &apos;gissha&apos; (ox-drawn carriage) that had been handed down to legitimate children of the Kanin line for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>永久4年（1116年）に兼近江権守、永久5年（1117年）に従三位、永久6年（1118年）に兼中宮権大夫、さらに、保安 (元号)3年（1122年）に中納言、左衛門督、大治3年（1128年）に正三位に進むが、同年39歳にして早世した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Omi no gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Omi Province) in 1116, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1117, Chugu-shiki daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) in 1118, Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) and Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in 1122, and proceeded to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1128 but had a premature death at the age of thirty nine in the same year.</e>
<cmt>下記用語については、ウェブの用語を使用して訳出しました。兼近江国→兼近江権守兼中宮職→兼中宮権大夫衛門府→左衛門督「中納言」は、ウェブの用語と異なります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Kami (Provisional Governor) of Omi Province in 1116, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1117, Chugu-shiki daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) in 1118, Chunagon (Vice-Councilor of State) and Saemon no Kami (Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in 1122, and was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1128 but died at the young age of thirty-nine that same year.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Omi no gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Omi Province) in 1116, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1117, Chugu-shiki daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s Household) in 1118, Chunagon (Vice-Councilor of State) and Saemon no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in 1122, and was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1128 but died at the young age of 39 that same year.</e>
<cmt>役職名などの表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>通季の死後、閑院流の中では暫く実行、実能の子孫が権勢を強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Michisue&apos;s death, Saneyuki and the descendant of Saneyoshi strengthened their influence for a while within the Kanin line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Michisue&apos;s death, the descendants of Saneyuki and Saneyoshi strengthened their influence within the Kanin line for a while.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Michisue&apos;s death, the descendants of Saneyuki and Saneyoshi strengthened their influence within the Kanin line for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、通季の曾孫に当たる西園寺公経が鎌倉時代初期に太政大臣に昇り、西園寺家を創始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Michisue&apos;s great-grandchild, Kintsune SAIONJI, moved up to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) in the early Kamakura period and originated the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Michisue&apos;s great-grandson, Kintsune SAIONJI, was promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State) in the early Kamakura period and founded the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Michisue&apos;s great-grandson, Kintsune SAIONJI, was promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State) in the early Kamakura period and founded the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>以後その子孫は清華家の一つとして繁栄し、公卿や女院を輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the descendant was flourished as one of Seiga family (one of the highest court noble families in Japan at that time) and produced a Court noble and nyoin (a close female relative of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, his descendants flourished as one of Seiga families (one of the highest ranks for noble families) and produced many Court nobles and nyoin (female relatives of the Emperor or women of comparable standing).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, his descendants flourished as one of Seiga families (one of the highest ranks for noble families) and produced many Kugyo and Nyoin (female relatives of the Emperor or women of comparable standing).</e>
<cmt>Kugyo を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まさふゆ(id:232040), Point136(id:211299), Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), Snap55(id:89773), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>