<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原致忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Munetada</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Munetada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Munetada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 致忠（ふじわら の むねただ、生没年未詳）は、平安時代中期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Munetada (date of birth and death unknown) was a court noble during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Munetada (year of birth and death unknown) was a court noble during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>fixed year details to match the word list</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Munetada (year of birth and death unknown) was a court noble during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大納言藤原元方の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of FUJIWARA no Motokata, who was a dainagon (a chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of FUJIWARA no Motokata, who was a Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Dainagon&quot; and fixed to match the word list</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of FUJIWARA no Motokata, who was a Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>従四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;He held the rank of&quot; to make this a sentence and added a period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>蔵人、備後国守、右馬頭、京職などを歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Kurodo (Chamberlain), Governor of Bingo Province, Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses), Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau) among others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among other posts, Munetada served as Kurodo (Chamberlain), Governor of the Bingo Province, Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses), and Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;among others&quot; to the beginning of the sentence; changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Munetada&quot; since this is a new paragraph</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among other posts, Munetada served as Kurodo (Chamberlain), Governor of Bingo Province, Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses), and Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt>Governor of the Bingo Province の the を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>永延2年（988年）、息子の保輔が強盗の首領として朝廷から追捕宣旨を下された際、父親である致忠も拘禁された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 988, when his son, Yasusuke, was captured by the Imperial court for being the chieftain of a group of robbers, Munetada, being his father, was also arrested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his son, Yasusuke, was captured by the Imperial court in 988 for being the chieftain of a group of thieves, as his father, Munetada was also arrested.</e>
<cmt>robbers→thieves; changed position of the year and fixed grammar to sound more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his son, Yasusuke, was captured by the Imperial court in 988 for being the chieftain of a group of thieves, as his father, Munetada was also arrested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>長保元年（999年）橘惟頼及びその郎等を殺害した罪で佐渡国に流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 999, he was exile to Sado Province being charged with murder of Koreyori TACHIBANA and his followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 999, Munetada was exiled to Sado Province after being charged with the murder of Koreyori TACHIBANA and his followers.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;he&quot; to &quot;Munetada&quot; since it was potentially ambiguous; exile→exiled; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 999, Munetada was exiled to Sado Province after being charged with the murder of Koreyori TACHIBANA and his followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>薫物の名手としても知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known for his expertise in blending incense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known for his expertise in blending incense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known for his expertise in blending incense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>