<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大島友之允</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonojo OSHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonojo OSHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonojo OSHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大島 友之允（おおしま とものじょう、文政9年6月23日 (旧暦)（1826年7月27日） - 明治15年（1882年）8月9日）は日本の武士・対馬府中藩士・外交官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonojo OSHIMA (July 27, 1826-August 9, 1882) was a samurai warrior, a feudal retainer and a diplomat of the Tsushimafuchu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonojo OSHIMA (July 27, 1826-August 9, 1882) was a samurai warrior, a feudal retainer and a diplomat of the Tsushimafuchu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonojo OSHIMA (July 27, 1826-August 9, 1882) was a samurai warrior, a feudal retainer and a diplomat of the Tsushimafuchu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治維新直後の日朝交渉に参画した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately, after the Meiji restoration OSHIMA had a part in a Japan-Korea negotiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the Meiji restoration, OSHIMA had a part in a Japan-Korea negotiation.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the Meiji restoration, OSHIMA had a part in a Japan-Korea negotiation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は正朝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Real name was Masatomo (it was not used in daily life)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Real name was Masatomo (it was not used in daily life)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Real name was Masatomo (it was not used in daily life)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幕末期の対馬藩は財政難に苦しんでおり、大島は援助を求めて奔走していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Tsushima clan having financial difficulties in the last days of Tokugawa shogunate, OSHIMA made every effort at monetary support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Tsushima Domain having financial difficulties during the last days of Tokugawa shogunate, OSHIMA made every effort at monetary support.</e>
<cmt>clan → Domainin → during</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Tsushima Domain having financial difficulties during the last days of Tokugawa shogunate, OSHIMA made every effort at monetary support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その中で文久3年（1863年）5月、老中・板倉勝静の顧問であった山田方谷と会見する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the course of his attempt, in may 1863 he had an interview with Hokoku YAMADA the adviser of Katsukiyo ITAKURA the senior councilor of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the course of his attempt, in may 1863, he had an interview with Hokoku YAMADA, an adviser of Katsukiyo ITAKURA who was a senior councilor of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>カンマを増やしました。The adviser → an adviserthe senior → who was an senior</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the course of his attempt, in may 1863, he had an interview with Hokoku YAMADA, an adviser of Katsukiyo ITAKURA who was a senior councilor of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この時、中国大陸進出を唱えていた山田に「貴藩困乏斯の如し、何ぞ李氏朝鮮違約の罪を鳴らして、之を征服する策に出でざるか」と説かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YAMADA had advocated expanding military activities to the Chinese continent, so at this interview he preached to OSHIMA that &apos;you should blame Joseon Dynasty for their breach of contract to conquer them&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YAMADA had advocated expanding military activities to the Chinese continent, so at this interview he preached to OSHIMA that &apos;you should blame Joseon Dynasty for their breach of contract to conquer them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YAMADA had advocated expanding military activities to the Chinese continent, so at this interview he preached to OSHIMA that &apos;you should blame Joseon Dynasty for their breach of contract to conquer them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに感化された大島は征韓論を唱えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under YAMADA&apos;s influence, OSHIMA began to advocated Seikanron (an opinion to dispatch military forces to Korea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under YAMADA&apos;s influence, OSHIMA began to advocate Seikanron (an opinion to dispatch military forces to Korea).</e>
<cmt>advocated → advocate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under YAMADA&apos;s influence, OSHIMA began to advocate Seikanron (an opinion to dispatch military forces to Korea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして元治元年（1864年）には、朝鮮進出の建白書を提出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864 OSHIMA submitted a petition to expand military activities to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864 OSHIMA submitted a petition to expand military activities to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864 OSHIMA submitted a petition to expand military activities to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この大島の感化を受けたのが友人である桂小五郎（木戸孝允）であり、後に桂が新政府の高官となるに至って、大島の論は政局に重大な影響を与えることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And OSHIMA influenced his friend Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO), so as KATSURA rose up to a high official officer, as a result, Oshima&apos;s opinion came to have greater influence on the political situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And OSHIMA influenced his friend Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO), and later as KATSURA rose up to a high-ranking officer, as a result, Oshima&apos;s opinion came to have greater influence on the political situation.</e>
<cmt>so → and laterhigh official officer → high-ranking officer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And OSHIMA influenced his friend Kogoro KATSURA (Takayoshi KIDO), and later as KATSURA rose up to a high-ranking officer, as a result, Oshima&apos;s opinion came to have greater influence on the political situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）10月14日 (旧暦)、大政奉還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 9, 1867 Taisei Hokan (restoration of imperial rule).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 9, 1867 Taisei Hokan (restoration of imperial rule).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 9, 1867 Taisei Hokan (restoration of imperial rule).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これより先、江戸幕府は朝鮮とイギリス・フランス間の紛争を調停するための、使節派遣を決定していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Taisei Hokan, the Edo shogunate had decided to dispatch an envoy to mediate the dispute between Korea-Britain and France.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Taisei Hokan, the Edo bakufu had decided to dispatch an envoy to mediate the dispute between Korea and Britain/France.</e>
<cmt>Edo shogunate → Edo bakufuKorea-Britain and France → Korea and Britain/France</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Taisei Hokan, the Edo bakufu had decided to dispatch an envoy to mediate the dispute between Korea and Britain/France.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>10月25日 (旧暦)、大島は、京都留守居の任にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshima was at the post of Kyoto rusui-yaku officer (a post representing the master during his absence).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 26, Oshima was at the post of Kyoto rusui-yaku officer (a post representing the master during his absence).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ（日付を補足しました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 26, Oshima was at the post of Kyoto rusui-yaku officer (a post representing the master during his absence).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>徳川慶喜から「予定どおり使節を派遣させるべき」という上申を託され、その旨を正親町三条実愛に伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After entrusted by Yoshinobu TOKIGAWA with the paper that said &apos;dispatch the mission as scheduled&apos; OSHIMA conveyed the effect to Sanenaru Ogimachi-SANJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After entrusted by Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA with the paper that said &apos;dispatch the mission as scheduled&apos; OSHIMA conveyed the effect to Sanenaru Ogimachi-SANJO.</e>
<cmt>TOKIGAWA → TOKUGAWA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After entrusted by Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA with the paper that said &apos;dispatch the mission as scheduled&apos; OSHIMA conveyed the effect to Sanenaru Ogimachi-SANJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>明治元年（1868年）閏4月6日、対馬藩主・宗義達は政府に上申書を提出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 27,1868 Yoshitatsu MUNE the lord of Tsushima domain and the local doctrinaires submitted a paper to the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 27,1868 Yoshiakira SO, the lord of Tsushima domain, submitted a petition to the government.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一しました。Yoshitatsu MUNE → Yoshiakira SOand the local doctrinairesは意味不明なので削除しました。Paper → petition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 27,1868 Yoshiakira SO, the lord of Tsushima domain, submitted a petition to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>対馬藩と朝鮮との関係を説明した上で、日朝関係の刷新と対馬藩救済を訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After explained their relationship to Korea, they made an appeal to the government for reforms of relationship between Japan and Korea and supports for Tsushima clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After explained their relationship to Korea, they made an appeal to the government for reforms in relationship between Japan and Korea and supports for Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>reforms of → reforms inclan → Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After explained their relationship to Korea, they made an appeal to the government for reforms in relationship between Japan and Korea and supports for Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これに伴い大島は、外国官判事・小松清廉らと会見、外交刷新について協議するとともに、対馬藩への援助を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having an interview with Kiyokado KOMATSU the officer of Foreign Affairs Council, OSHIMA discussed diplomacy reforms and requested monetary support for Tsushima clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having an interview with Kiyokado KOMATSU the officer of Foreign Affairs Council, OSHIMA discussed diplomacy reforms and requested monetary support for Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>clan → Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having an interview with Kiyokado KOMATSU the officer of Foreign Affairs Council, OSHIMA discussed diplomacy reforms and requested monetary support for Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この際の要望は却下されたが、後に大島が再度請願した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his all requests were rejected at this time, OSHIMA remade the petition to the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his all requests were rejected at the time, OSHIMA remade the petition to the government.</e>
<cmt>at this time → at the time</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his all requests were rejected at the time, OSHIMA remade the petition to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その要望の一部である太政官札の貸付が認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, loan of daijokansatsu (the first Japanese paper money) were approved which was a part of their requests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a part of their requests, loan of daijokan-satsu (the first Japanese paper money issued during the early Meiji period) was approved.</e>
<cmt>a part of their requestsを冒頭に移動しました。issued during the early Meiji period を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a part of their requests, loan of daijokan-satsu (the first Japanese paper money issued during the early Meiji period) was approved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、この時の大島は既に征韓論者ではなく、交渉による外交関係の樹立を主張するようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since OSHIMA at this time was no longer an advocate for the Seikanron, he maintained establishment of diplomatic relations without military action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since OSHIMA at this time was no longer an advocate for the Seikanron, he maintained establishment of diplomatic relations without military action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since OSHIMA at this time was no longer an advocate for the Seikanron, he maintained establishment of diplomatic relations without military action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>明治2年（1869年）2月上旬、対馬藩職制改革により参政に転じていた大島は、朝鮮事情視察のため倭館草梁倭館に派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">early in February 1869 OSHIMA (he had been assigned to the office of an administrator due to Tsushima clan administration reform) was dispatched to Choryang-dong Wakan (consular office in Korea) to inspect the situation of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early February 1869, OSHIMA (he had been assigned to the senior officer of Tsushima Domain due to the office organization reform) was dispatched to Choryang-dong Wakan (consular office in Korea) to inspect the situation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>early in February 1869 → In the early February 1869,the office of an administrator due to Tsushima clan administration reform → the senior officer of Tsushima Domain due to the office organization reform</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early February 1869, OSHIMA (he had been assigned to the senior officer of Tsushima Domain due to the office organization reform) was dispatched to Choryang-dong Wakan (consular office in Korea) to inspect the situation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ここで日朝修好条規日朝間の懸案：書契問題により膠着状態に陥っていた日朝交渉に参画することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OSHIMA took part in the Japan-Korea negotiation which had come to an impasse due to the issues on hold and shokei (form of the letters used in negotiations) problems laid down Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt>書契　「交渉等で使われる書簡の形式」　で処理しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OSHIMA took part in the Japan-Korea negotiation which had come to an impasse due to the issues on hold and shokei (form of the letters used in negotiations) problems laid down Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OSHIMA took part in the Japan-Korea negotiation which had come to an impasse due to the issues on hold and shokei (form of the letters used in negotiations) problems laid down Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大島は朝鮮側の安東晙と会見し、日本の国書を受理するよう求めたが、安東晙は頑として受理を拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although OSHIMA had an interview with 安東晙 requesting him to accept sovereign&apos;s message, 安東晙 firmly rejected the acceptance.</e>
<cmt>安東晙　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although OSHIMA had an interview with Dong-Jun AHN (安東晙), Korean counterpart, requesting him to accept sovereign&apos;s message, Dong-Jun AHN firmly rejected the acceptance.</e>
<cmt>Dong-Jun AHN (安東晙)としました。korean counterpartを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although OSHIMA had an interview with Dong-Jun AHN (安東晙), Korean counterpart, requesting him to accept sovereign&apos;s message, Dong-Jun AHN firmly rejected the acceptance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>3月11日 (旧暦)、大島は倭館を去って対馬に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 22, 1869 OSHIMA returned Tsushima from Choryang-dong Wakan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 22, 1869 OSHIMA returned Tsushima from Choryang-dong Wakan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 22, 1869 OSHIMA returned Tsushima from Choryang-dong Wakan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>5月13日 (旧暦)、日朝交渉の停頓に痺れを切らした政府は、対馬藩に対し、対朝鮮交渉権の接収を示唆した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 22, 1869 due to a standstill in the Japan-Korea negotiation, the government became impatient and suggested the requisition for the negotiation rights to Tsushima clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 22, 1869 due to a standstill in the Japan-Korea negotiation, the government became impatient and suggested the requisition for the negotiation rights to Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>clan → Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 22, 1869 due to a standstill in the Japan-Korea negotiation, the government became impatient and suggested the requisition for the negotiation rights to Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これが実行されれば、すなわち対馬藩による日朝関係の刷新は失敗に終わったということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If carried out, that is to say, the reform of the relationship between Japan-Korea by Tsushima clan would be concluded as a failure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If carried out, that is to say, the reform of the relationship between Japan-Korea by Tsushima Domain would be concluded as a failure.</e>
<cmt>clan → Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If carried out, that is to say, the reform of the relationship between Japan-Korea by Tsushima Domain would be concluded as a failure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>それを理由に財政救済も拒否される恐れがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And for this reason, the government might reject financial support for Tsushima clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And for this reason, the government might reject financial support for Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>clan → Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And for this reason, the government might reject financial support for Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そこで大島は、今日までの交渉の経過を説明し、交渉停頓の責は対馬藩ではなく朝鮮の側にあることを強調した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To avoid this, with accounting for the course of the negotiation, OSHIMA emphasized that the blame for the standstill in the negotiation rested with Korea not Tsushima clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To avoid this, with accounting for the course of the negotiation, OSHIMA emphasized that the blame for the standstill in the negotiation rested with Korea rather than Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>not Tsushima clan → rather than Tsushima Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To avoid this, with accounting for the course of the negotiation, OSHIMA emphasized that the blame for the standstill in the negotiation rested with Korea rather than Tsushima Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>かつ朝鮮の政情は外国官には想像し難い複雑なもので、対馬藩を経由しなければ条約締結の見込みはない、とする上申書を提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He submitted a paper that said Korean political situation was so hard to predict and very complicated that there was no chance to conclude the treaty unless Tsushima clan took charge of.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He submitted a paper that said Korean political situation was so hard to predict and very complicated that there was no chance to conclude the treaty unless Tsushima Domain took charge of.</e>
<cmt>clan → Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He submitted a paper that said Korean political situation was so hard to predict and very complicated that there was no chance to conclude the treaty unless Tsushima Domain took charge of.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その後まもなく版籍奉還、並びに外務省の設置が行われ、対馬藩はさらに交渉権接収の危機に立たされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward since the government conducted hanseki hokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) and formation of Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Tsushima clan was confronted with the requisition for the negotiation right again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward since the government conducted hanseki hokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) and formation of Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Tsushima Domain was confronted with the requisition for the negotiation right again.</e>
<cmt>clan → Domain</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward since the government conducted hanseki hokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) and formation of Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Tsushima Domain was confronted with the requisition for the negotiation right again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>抗議の結果、今後も日朝交渉は対馬藩（8月7日 (旧暦)に厳原藩に改称）に委ねられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, as a result of complaint, on September 12,1869 Tsushima clan was entrusted with the Japan-Korea negotiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, as a result of complaint, Tsushima Domain (on September 12,1869, changed its name to &quot;Izuhara Domain&quot;) was continuously entrusted with the Japan-Korea negotiation.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ(on September 12,1869, changed its name to &quot;Izuhara Domain&quot;)　と　continuously を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, as a result of complaint, Tsushima Domain (on September 12,1869, changed its name to &quot;Izuhara Domain&quot;) was continuously entrusted with the Japan-Korea negotiation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>明治3年（1870年）5月、大島は同藩の通詞・浦瀬裕に対し『等対論』を内示する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1870 OSHIMA notified Yu URASE (translator) &quot;totai ron&quot; informally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1870, OSHIMA informally notified &quot;totai ron (literally, theory of equivalent)&quot; to Yu URASE (translator).</e>
<cmt>(literally, theory of equivalent)を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1870, OSHIMA informally notified &quot;totai ron (literally, theory of equivalent)&quot; to Yu URASE (translator).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これは書契問題に関し、一旦は朝鮮側の主張を認め、旧来の体式の書契で国交調整の目的を達してから、また協議すれば良いというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Totai ron&quot; had content that was that once accept Korean&apos;s claim, accomplishing the purpose of diplomatic relations in the form of old shokei then restart discussion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Totai ron&quot; had content that was that once accept Korean&apos;s claim, accomplishing the purpose of diplomatic relations in the form of old shokei then restart discussion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Totai ron&quot; had content that was that once accept Korean&apos;s claim, accomplishing the purpose of diplomatic relations in the form of old shokei then restart discussion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>浦瀬はこれに従って交渉を行い、朝鮮側の安東晙から好意的な感触を掴むに至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">carrying out negotiation as he notified informally Urase came to grasp a feeling that he was in favor of Tsushima clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using the paper as a guidance, Urase negotiated with the Korean side and grasped a feeling that he was in favor of Dong-Jun AHN.</e>
<cmt>訳が完全に間違っているので再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using the paper as a guidance, Urase negotiated with the Korean side and grasped a feeling that he was in favor of Dong-Jun AHN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし同時期、ヘルタ号事件が発生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, Helta Incident occurred at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, Helta Incident occurred at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, Helta Incident occurred at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>交渉はまたも暗礁に乗り上げてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiation came to a deadlock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiation came to a deadlock again.</e>
<cmt>againを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiation came to a deadlock again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>明治4年（1871年）7月14日 (旧暦)、廃藩置県が布告され、知藩事・宗重正（義達から改名）の家役も罷免されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29, 1871 government decreed Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), as a result OSHIMA was dismissed 家役 of Chihanji Shigemasa MUNE (Yoshitatsu&apos;s new name).</e>
<cmt>家役　意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29, 1871, as the government decreed Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), Ieyaku (low-ranking farmer or apprentice) of governor Shigemasa MUNE (Yoshitatsu&apos;s new name) were to be dismissed.</e>
<cmt>家役は中下級の農民または奉公人のことのようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 29, 1871, as the government decreed Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), Ieyaku (low-ranking farmer or apprentice) of governor Shigemasa MUNE (Yoshitatsu&apos;s new name) were to be dismissed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これに不満を抱いた大島は7月23日 (旧暦)、外務省の広津弘信（作家広津柳浪の父）と懇談した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since dissatisfied with the dismissal, on September 7 OSHIMA had a talk with Hironobu HIROTSU of Ministry of Foreign Affairs (father of 広津柳浪 a writer).</e>
<cmt>広津柳浪 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since dissatisfied with the dismissal, on September 7 OSHIMA had a talk with Hironobu HIROTSU of Ministry of Foreign Affairs (father of 広津柳浪 a writer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since dissatisfied with the dismissal, on September 7 OSHIMA had a talk with Hironobu HIROTSU of Ministry of Foreign Affairs (father of 広津柳浪 a writer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>広津は重正を外務大丞に任じて朝鮮に派遣することを提案、大島もこれに同意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIROTSU proposed that we appoint Shigemasa to be Minister of Foreign Affairs and dispatch him to Korean, OSHIMA assented to the proposal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIROTSU proposed to appoint Shigemasa to be Gaimu-taijo (post of Foreign Ministry) and dispatch him to Korea, OSHIMA assented to the proposal.</e>
<cmt>外務大丞は外務大臣とは違うようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIROTSU proposed to appoint Shigemasa to be Gaimu-taijo (post of Foreign Ministry) and dispatch him to Korea, OSHIMA assented to the proposal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>そして、重正が外務大丞に、大島が外務省准奏任出仕に任じられ、朝鮮派遣を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemasa to be Minister of Foreign Affairs, OSHIMA to be 外務省准奏任出仕, they were both appointed the posts, and were ordered to go to Korea.</e>
<cmt>外務省准奏任出仕 読み方意味不明 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemasa to be Gaimu-taijo (post of Foreign Ministry), OSHIMA to be an Official of Foreign Ministry, they were both appointed the posts, and were ordered to go to Korea.</e>
<cmt>准奏任出仕は、役人の位のようですが、よくわからないので、Official of Foreign Ministryとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemasa to be Gaimu-taijo (post of Foreign Ministry), OSHIMA to be an Official of Foreign Ministry, they were both appointed the posts, and were ordered to go to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし実際に、大島らが朝鮮に派遣されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, they would never actually be dispatched to Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, they never dispatched to Korea.</e>
<cmt>断定されているのでwouldを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, they never dispatched to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>外務大臣 (日本)の相次ぐ交代により朝鮮問題は放置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to successive replacement of Minister of Foreign Affairs, the Korean issue was left on hold for while.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to successive replacement of Minister of Foreign Affairs, the Korean issue was left on hold for while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to successive replacement of Minister of Foreign Affairs, the Korean issue was left on hold for while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>そしてようやく顧みられた時には、宗氏派遣に対する反対意見が出て、派遣は中止させられるに至ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while the dispatch was canceled due to objections against the plan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while the dispatch was canceled due to objections against the plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while the dispatch was canceled due to objections against the plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>重正の代理として、旧厳原藩の相良正樹が派遣された一方、12月28日 (旧暦)、大島は外務省の職を免じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaki AIRA was sent to Korea in place of Shigemasa on the other hand, on February 6 1872 OSHIMA was dismissed the post in Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaki AIRA was sent to Korea in place of Shigemasa on the other hand, on February 6 1872 OSHIMA was dismissed the post in Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaki AIRA was sent to Korea in place of Shigemasa on the other hand, on February 6 1872 OSHIMA was dismissed the post in Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Tomo suzuki(id:11928), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Straysheep(id:42448), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 鳴海(id:37850), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>