<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺公清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinkiyo TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinkiyo TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinkiyo TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 公清（とくだいじ きんきよ、正和元年（1312年） - 正平 (日本)15年/延文5年6月8日 (旧暦)（1360年7月21日））は、鎌倉時代から南北朝時代 (日本)の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinkiyo TOKUDAIJI (1312 - July 21, 1360) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived in the era from the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinkiyo TOKUDAIJI (1312 - July 21, 1360) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived from the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinkiyo TOKUDAIJI (1312 - July 29, 1360) was a kugyo (court noble) who lived from the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan).</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は中納言徳大寺実孝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sanetaka TOKUDAIJI, Chunagon (a middle counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sanetaka TOKUDAIJI, Chunagon (a middle counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Sanetaka TOKUDAIJI, Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は太政大臣西園寺公相の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Kinsuke SAIONJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Kinsuke SAIONJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Kinsuke SAIONJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に太政大臣徳大寺実時。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetoki TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin, was his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetoki TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin, was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetoki TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin, was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>娘に太政大臣久我具通室がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wife of Tomomichi KOGA, Daijo-daijin, was his daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wife of Tomomichi KOGA, Daijo-daijin, was his daughter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wife of Tomomichi KOGA, Daijo-daijin, was his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>正和5年（1316年）に叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ennobled in 1316.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ennobled in 1316.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred to a peerage in 1316.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以降美作国・近衛府・近衛府などを経て、正中 (元号)3年（1326年）には後醍醐天皇中宮西園寺禧子の中宮権大夫となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he became, in 1326, Chugu Gon no daibu (a provisional master of the consort&apos;s household) to Kishi SAIONJI, chugu (the second consort) of Emperor Godaigo, after assuming a post in Mimasaka Province, a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) and another post at Konoefu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in 1326 he became Chugu Gon no daibu (a provisional master of the consort&apos;s household) to Kishi SAIONJI, chugu (the 2nd consort) of Emperor Godaigo, after assuming a post in Mimasaka Province, a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) and another post at Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in 1326 he became Chugu Gon no daibu (a provisional master of the consort&apos;s household) to Kishi SAIONJI, chugu (the 2nd consort) of Emperor Godaigo, after assuming a post in Mimasaka Province, a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards) and another post at Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>嘉暦2年（1327年）に参議となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1327, he was appointed to Sangi (a councilor), becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1327, he was appointed to Sangi (councilor), becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1327, he was appointed to Sangi (councilor), becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>正慶2年（1333年）に西園寺禧子が皇太后となるとそのまま皇太后権大夫となるも、同年に禧子皇太后の崩御に伴い、辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kishi SAIONJI became Empress Dowager in 1333, he became Kotaigo Gon no daibu (a provisional master of the Kotaigo&apos;s household), but resigned the post when she died in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kishi SAIONJI became Empress Dowager in 1333, he became Kotaigo Gon no daibu (provisional master of the Kotaigo&apos;s household), but resigned the post when she died in the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kishi SAIONJI became Empress Dowager in 1333, he became Kotaigo Gon no daibu (provisional master of the Kotaigo&apos;s household), but resigned the post when she died in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>延元元年/建武 (日本)3年（1336年）皇太子恒良親王の春宮大夫となったが翌年に辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, he became Togu no daibu (the master of the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters) to Imperial Crown Prince Tsuneyoshi, but resigned the post in the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, he became Togu no daibu (master of the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters) to Imperial Crown Prince Tsuneyoshi, but resigned the post in the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, he became Togu no daibu (master of the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters) to Imperial Crown Prince Tsuneyoshi, but resigned the post in the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>延元3年/暦応元年（1338年）に大納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1338, he became Dainagon (a major counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1338, he became Dainagon (major counselor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1338, he became Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>興国4年/康永2年（1343年）に近衛府・馬寮・大納言に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1343, he was appointed to a post at Konoefu and a post at Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses) and to Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1343, he was appointed to a post at Konoefu and a post at Meryo (the section that takes care of the imperial horses) and to Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1343, he was appointed to a post at Konoefu and a post at Meryo (the section that takes care of the imperial horses) and to Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>正平元年/貞和2年（1346年）内大臣に任じられるも、同年右近衛大将と内大臣を辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1346, he was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior, but resigned Ukone no daisho (the major captain of the right division of inner palace guards) and Naidaijin in the same year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1346, he was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior, but resigned Ukone no daisho (major captain of the right division of inner palace guards) and Naidaijin in the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1346, he was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior), but resigned Ukone no daisho (major captain of the right division of inner palace guards) and Naidaijin in the same year.</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>正平11年/延文元年（1356年）従一位を授与される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1356.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded Juichii (Junior 1st Rank) in 1356.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1356.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>