<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原敏行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshiyuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Toshiyuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshiyuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 敏行（ふじわら の としゆき、生年不詳 - 延喜7年（907年））は、平安時代初期の歌人、書家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshiyuki (year of birth unknown-907) was a Kajin poet and Shoka who lived in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Toshiyuki (year of birth unknown) was a Kajin (a waka poet) and Shoka (a calligraphy artist) who lived in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, contradiction with the date in the following entry</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshiyuki (year of birth unknown - 907) was a Kajin (a waka poet) and Shoka (a calligraphy artist) who lived in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「907年」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>没年は延喜元年（901年）説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of death is said to be 901.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is thought to have died in the year 901.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that he died in the year 901.</e>
<cmt>(907年の他に) 901年説もあるという内容に沿うよう訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>父は藤原富士麿（陸奥出羽按察使）、母は紀名虎の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Fujimaro (a Mutsudewa-azechi) and his mother was a daughter of KI no Natora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Fujimaro (a Mutsudewa-azechi) and his mother was a daughter of KI no Natora.</e>
<cmt>grammar, need English explanation of Mutsuwa-azechi.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Fujimaro (a Mutsu-Dewa Azechi (local inspector of Mutsu and Dewa Provinces)) and his mother was a daughter of KI no Natora.</e>
<cmt>「陸奥出羽按察使」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>妻は紀有常の娘(在原業平室の姉妹)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of KI no Aritsune (a sister of ARIHARA no Narihira&apos;s wife)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was a daughter of KI no Aritsune (a sister of ARIHARA no Narihira&apos;s wife)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of KI no Aritsune (a sister of ARIHARA no Narihira&apos;s wife)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に藤原季方、藤原有快、藤原伊辛、藤原伊衡、藤原伊望など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had children including FUJIWARA no Suekata, FUJIWARA no Arikai, FUJIWARA no Koreshin, FUJIWARA no Korehira and FUJIWARA no Koremochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children include FUJIWARA no Suekata, FUJIWARA no Arikai, FUJIWARA no Koreshin, FUJIWARA no Korehira and FUJIWARA no Koremochi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children include FUJIWARA no Suekata, FUJIWARA no Ariyoshi (藤原有快), FUJIWARA no Koretsura (藤原伊辛), FUJIWARA no Korehira and FUJIWARA no Koremochi.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA no Arikai→FUJIWARA no Ariyoshi (藤原有快)、FUJIWARA no Koreshin→FUJIWARA no Koretsura (藤原伊辛) としました。(それぞれ読み不明のため)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原南家に生まれ、官位は従四位上右兵衛督に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in the Fujiwara Nanke and finally promoted to the rank of Jushi-no-jo and assumed the position of Uhyoe-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in the Fujiwara Nanke (the southern branch of the Fujiwara clan) and eventually attained the rank of Jushi-no-jo, assuming the position of Uhyoe-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan and eventually attained the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), assuming the position of Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>「藤原南家」「従四位上」→統一リストの表記に修正、Uhyoe-no-kamiのハイフン消去、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>三十六歌仙の一人で、家集に「敏行集」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the Thirty-six Master Poets and a collection of his poems was called &quot;Toshiyuki-shu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was numbered among the Thirty-six Master Poets of his time, and there is a collection of his poems called &quot;Toshiyuki-shu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar, time frame</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was numbered among the Thirty-six Master Poets of his time, and there is a collection of his poems called &apos;Toshiyuki-shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>三絶の鐘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanzetsu no kane (bell of three masters)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanzetsu no kane (bell of the three masters)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanzetsu no Kane (bell of the three masters)</e>
<cmt>kaneの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>当時、空海とともに能書家として有名であるが、現存する書跡は、署名のある次のものだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, he was famous as an excellent chirographer along with Kukai, however the following ones are the only existing calligraphy works with his signature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with Kukai, he was a renowned calligrapher in his day; however, only the following signed examples of his works have been preserved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with Kukai, he was a renowned calligrapher in his day; however, only the following signed examples of his works have been preserved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>神護寺鐘銘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomei (inscription on the bell) of Jingo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomei (temple bell inscription), Jingo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomei (temple bell inscription), Jingo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この銘は、禅林寺の真紹の発願によるものであるが、鋳型が出来上がる前に真紹が歿したので、和気彝範が遺志を継ぎ、貞観 (日本)17年（875年）8月23日、志我部海継を雇い鋳成したことが序文に示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the construction of this inscripition was started by Shinsho, he passed away before the completion of the mold, then Tsunenori WAKI followed his wish and hired Umitsugu SHIKABE to complete the mold on August 23, 875.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although work on this inscripition was started at the behest of Shinsho, of the Zenin-ji Temple, he passed away before the mold was completed, bequeathing the task to Tsunenori WAKI, who then hired Umitsugu SHIKABE on August 23, 875 to complete the mold.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although work on this inscripition was started at the behest of Shinsho, of the Zenrin-ji Temple, he passed away before the mold was completed, bequeathing the task to Tsunenori WAKI, who then hired Umitsugu SHIKABE on September 30, 875 to complete the mold.</e>
<cmt>Zenin-ji Temple→Zenrin-ji Templeに修正August 23→September 30に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>全文32行で、字数は245字である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The total number of lines was 32 and characters was 245.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inscription includes a total of 32 lines, with a total of 245 characters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inscription includes a total of 32 lines, with a total of 245 characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>謹厳な楷書で陽鋳（ようちゅう、浮き彫り）されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was solemnly written in standard style using relief engraving.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a solemn inscription, which was written in the standard script, rendered as a relief engraving.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a solemn inscription, which was written in the standard script, rendered as a relief engraving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>隷書をよくした小野篁および紀夏井の流れを汲んだ勁健な書法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a dynamic style descended from ONO no Takamura and KI no Natsui who often wrote in clerical script.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style of the calligraphy is dynamic, showing the influence of the work of ONO no Takamura and KI no Natsui, who were often commissioned to write inscriptions by the Buddhist clergy.</e>
<cmt>unclear, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style of the calligraphy is dynamic, showing the influence of the work of ONO no Takamura and KI no Natsui, who were often commissioned to write inscriptions by the Buddhist clergy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、この銘文の序は橘広相、銘は菅原是善、書は敏行と、当時の三名家がそれぞれ成したので、古来「三絶の鐘」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this inscription is composed of the works of three masters at that time: the preface by TACHIBANA no Hiromi, the inscription by SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi and the calligraphy by Toshiyuki, the bell has been called &quot;Sanzetsu no kane (bell of three masters)&quot; since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that the reason this this been called &quot;Sanzetsu no kane (bell of the three masters)&quot; since ancient times is because the inscription comprises the work of three masters active at that time: the preface was composed by TACHIBANA no Hiromi; the text of the inscription by composed by SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi; and the calligraphy by done by Toshiyuki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that the reason this this been called &apos;Sanzetsu no Kane&apos; (bell of the three masters) since ancient times is because the inscription comprises the work of three masters active at that time: the preface was composed by TACHIBANA no Hiromi; the text of the inscription by composed by SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi; and the calligraphy by done by Toshiyuki.</e>
<cmt>kaneの頭文字を大文字に変更、シングルクォーテーションに変更、位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この神護寺の梵鐘は国宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This temple bell of Jingo-ji Temple is a national treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This temple bell of Jingo-ji Temple has been designated a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This temple bell of Jingo-ji Temple has been designated a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>『宇治拾遺物語』によれば、敏行は、多くの人から法華経の書写を依頼され、200部余りも書いたが、魚を食うなど、不浄の身のまま書写したので、地獄に落ちて苦しみを受けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Uji-Shui Monogatari&quot;, Toshiyuki was asked to transcribe the scripture of Hoke-kyo by many people and he made over 200 copies, but he did that work in unclean condition such as eating fish, thus he went to hell and suffered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Uji-Shui Monogatari&quot;, Toshiyuki was asked often asked to transcribe text of the Hoke-kyo Sutra, and is said to have made over 200 copies; however, because he did such work under impure conditions, such as consuming fish, and hte like, it is also said that he went to hell and suffered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot;(a collection of the Tales from Uji), Toshiyuki was asked often asked to transcribe text of the Hoke-kyo Sutra, and is said to have made over 200 copies; however, because he did such work under impure conditions, such as consuming fish, and hte like, it is also said that he went to hell and suffered.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot;とし、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>代表歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative Poems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative Poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative Poems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>すみの江の岸による浪よるさへや夢のかよひぢ人目よくらむ（古今和歌集、百人一首18、）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The waves are gathered on the shore of Sumi Bay, and in the gathered night, when in dreams I go to you, I hide from people&apos;s eyes (Kokin Wakashu,Hyakunin Isshu18).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The waves are gathered on the shore of Sumi Bay, and in the gathered night, when in dreams I go to you, I hide from people&apos;s eyes (Kokin Wakashu,Hyakunin Isshu18).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The waves are gathered on the shore of Sumi Bay, and in the gathered night, when in dreams I go to you, I hide from people&apos;s eyes (Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), Hyakunin Isshu (one hundred waka poems by one hundred poets) 18).</e>
<cmt>Kokin Wakashu、Hyakunin Isshuの補足追加、スペース追加、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>秋来ぬと目にはさやかに見えねども風の音にぞおどろかれぬる（古今和歌集、秋歌上、169）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nothing meets the eye to demonstrate beyond doubt that autumn has come - yet suddenly we are struck just by the sound of the wind (Kokin Wakashu, Aki no uta Jo, 169).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nothing meets the eye to demonstrate beyond doubt that autumn has come - yet suddenly we are struck just by the sound of the wind (Kokin Wakashu, Aki no uta Jo, 169).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nothing meets the eye to demonstrate beyond doubt that autumn has come - yet suddenly we are struck just by the sound of the wind (Kokin Wakashu, Aki no Uta Jo (the first volume of Autumn Poems), 169).</e>
<cmt>Aki no Uta Joとし、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>白露の色はひとつをいかにして秋の木の葉をちぢに染むらん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How might it happen that dewdrops of purest white, all single colored, bring forth a myriad hues in the leaves of autumn trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How might it happen that dewdrops of purest white, all single colored, bring forth a myriad hues in the leaves of autumn trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How might it happen that dewdrops of purest white, all single colored, bring forth a myriad hues in the leaves of autumn trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), さららゆら(id:12274), Goodmoon(id:1219), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Point136(id:211299), 岡部碩道(id:182846), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Zippin(id:9885), Yuming(id:17854), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>